<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay on the nature and cure of the king's evil: deduced from observations and practice. The second edition: with an addition of remarkable cases of poor sufferers, cured by the author. ...</title>
            <author>Morley, John, d. 1776.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>67 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-11">2012 November</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004773729</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">N1487</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW109392492</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K000923.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3309392492</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECMS</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">1238900400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay on the nature and cure of the king's evil: deduced from observations and practice. The second edition: with an addition of remarkable cases of poor sufferers, cured by the author. ...</title>
                  <author>Morley, John, d. 1776.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6],63,[1]p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for James Buckland; and sold by T. Toft, in Chelmsford,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1763.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: John Morley.</note>
                  <note>With a half-title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCN1487.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:1238900400:1"/>
            <p>ESSAY ON THE NATURE and CURE OF THE KING's EVIL; DEDUCED FROM OBSERVATIONS and PRACTICE.</p>
            <p>[Price One Shilling.]</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1238900400:2"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY ON THE NATURE and CURE OF THE KING's EVIL; DEDUCED FROM OBSERVATIONS and PRACTICE.</p>
            <p>The SECOND EDITION: With an ADDITION of REMARKABLE CASES of poor Sufferers, cured by the Author.</p>
            <p>Seriouſly recommended to the Peruſal of all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Perſons and Families labouring under any Scrophulous Complaints, which have hitherto eluded all Attempts to remove them.</p>
            <q>Facts are ſtubborn Things.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for JAMES BUCKLAND, at the Buck, in Pater-Noſter-Row; and Sold by T. TOFT, in Chelmsford. M.DCC.LXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:1238900400:3"/>
            <head>INTRODUCTION TO THIS SECOND EDITION.</head>
            <p>IT is not from any Vanity of appearing in Print, eſpecially a ſecond time, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch ungenerous Uſage as I have met with from Perſons calling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Reviewers, but to make myſelf uſeful in my Generation to unhappy Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers, as far as I am able. I refuſe not the pooreſt Perſon my Aſſiſtance (as well as the Rich) if they come to my Houſe. The Pleaſure I feel by relieving the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, overbalances all the Cavillings,
<pb facs="tcp:1238900400:4"/>Sneers, and ill-natured Reflections of Reviewers, or any other Writers for Bread, who ſpeak Evil of the Things that they underſtand not. Let them an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer me by ſolid Arguments, confirmed by as many real Cures as I have done; then I ſhall rejoice to hear ſo many more miſerable Objects have been relieved from their Diſorders by my ſtirring up the Attention or Ambition of others to Practice with more Succeſs.</p>
            <p>As the King's Evil is a Diſeaſe few of the better Sort care to own, I muſt beg to be excuſed from naming ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but only ſome few of their Caſes. As to the lower Sort, I ſhall give their Caſes in the plaineſt Manner I can, that the People of common Underſtanding,
<pb facs="tcp:1238900400:5"/>without any Phyſical Knowledge, may in a great Meaſure judge whether their Complaints are Scrophulous or not. I have alſo inſerted the Names, and Places of Abode, of ſuch Perſons, that by diſcourſing with the Parties them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their Friends or Neighbours, they may be ſatisfied of the Truth of the Matters of Fact, and receive far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Information as to their own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints. And as I make no Profit by my Practice, it is evident, I need no Arts to influence People to declare Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths in my Favour. Greater Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Cures I might have added, but hope theſe will be ſufficient, to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy any unprejudiced Perſon, that the King's Evil, or other Scrophulous Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, may be relieved much oftener,
<pb facs="tcp:1238900400:6"/>and with more Eaſe and Safety, as well as with leſs Charge to the Patients, than the Generality of Practitioners are willing to allow, or the unhappy Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers have hitherto experienced.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:1238900400:7"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> LADY of my Family having many Years made it her Pleaſure, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the Relief of all ſuch poor Perſons as were afflicted with ſcro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phulous Diſorders, or the King's Evil, and were recommended to her by Surgeons, or other Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners; and having been very ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful in curing many ſuch Caſes, as they had given up and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to her, made me very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite with her after her Method of Practice. She very readily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed me of the Nature and Way of applying her Remedies, but would never (during her Life) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to me the Names of the Things ſhe made uſe of, or the Method of Preparation, but always told me
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:1238900400:8"/>I ſhould find a full Account amongſt her Papers after her Death, which I did (being her ſole Executor.) With other Things, I found the following Letter to her, from an eminent Surgeon.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MADAM,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I ONCE more ſollicit your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Benediction, and the ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Effects of your renowned Secret, which the World is from God and yourſelf, greatly obliged for, in Behalf of this poor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Lad (<hi>B. P.</hi> by Name) who is attended with the King's Evil in his Foot, and has been ſo for eleven Months; who I entirely ſubmit to your Care (Providence being your peculiar Guide) in the mean while, I remain in Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to Facts,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your ſincere Convert, And a Public Well-wiſher, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="v" facs="tcp:1238900400:9"/>
            <p>THIS Letter, among many others, from Surgeons and Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, together with the great Cures which ſhe daily did, made me very ſeriouſly reflect, how uſeful a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhe had been to all the human Species, which had applied to her in Time, being chiefly of the loweſt Claſs of Mankind, whoſe Health and Limbs were their only Liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: Theſe were often relieved with her Purſe, and always with her Medicines, and Advice Gratis; as alſo all others, who applied to her for Relief in this deplorable Malady. Theſe Conſiderations, and the great Number of unhappy Poor, (unable to pay a Surgeon or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary) daily preſenting themſelves to me; and I knowing the Safety of the Method, and Medicines uſed in this Diſorder, was imboldened to endeavour the Relief of my Fellow-Creatures, by following the Lady's
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:1238900400:10"/>Rules of doing good, for Charity Sake; which I have followed ſome Years, with ſuch Succeſs (for which I thank God) as ſurprizes even my own ſelf. Such Objects of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion having been relieved, as paſs all Belief of any, but ſuch as have been Eye-witneſſes of the Facts, from firſt to laſt. Since I have been in Poſſeſſion of the deceaſed Lady's Notes and Memorandums, I have read over many Authors who have treated of this Diſorder. <hi>Dr. Gibbs</hi> on this Subject, writes, "That if we take a View of what the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Authors have ſaid of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, we ſhall find their Notions of it to be of little Uſe, and very few Accounts of their Succeſs in curing Diſorders of this Nature." And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I am much of the ſame Opinion. But this great Good have I learnt by reading their Works, and from thence obſerving the Operations of
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:1238900400:11"/>my own Preſcriptions, that I have much improved both the Method and Medicines I at firſt uſed. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe no painful Applications, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or cauterizing, bliſtering, or nauſeous Loads of Phyſick, but ſuch Things only, as Children of half a Year old, to the Aged of Seventy, may have without the leaſt Hurt or Pain, and with great Safety be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to them. And I can iuſtly challenge any Perſon that has been under my Care, and followed my very eaſy Directions only, to allege the contrary. So that I can, with great Truth aſſert, That I have done ſome Good, and no Harm. The Cure of this Diſtemper by the Lady's Method, is no new Thing, but has been in ſome Meaſure uſed one hundred and fifty Years ago, as I have met with in an old Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; and having ſeen ſuch won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Effects from it, admire what
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:1238900400:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>can be the Reaſon of its being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, ſhall I ſay, or not uſed by the Gentlemen of the Faculty: But it is not according to their Method of Practice. That I am no Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, Surgeon, or Apothecary, the Reader will eaſily ſee, by my not uſing hard Words, or technical Terms of Art, to puzzle and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found him; and my Patients all know I am none of the Faculty, by refuſing Fees. All that come to me, are welcome to my Advice and Aſſiſtance Gratis. What Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries are wanted, they may buy of whom, and where they pleaſe. The inward Pleaſure I enjoy on ſeeing any poor Sufferers relieved by my Means, makes me very ample Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for all the Pains I can take for their Recovery.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Auguſt 28, 1760.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>JOHN MORLEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="medical_tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:1238900400:13"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="tract_proper">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Scrophula, or what is vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly called the King's Evil, I ſhall now conſider. The Word Scrophula (ſays a learned Writer) ſignifies a praeternatural Tumour or Humour, produced by a particular Acidity of the Serum of the Blood, either in Gland, Muſcle, or Membrane, which it both coagulates and indurates, or in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, which it always diſſolves, and alſo putrifies the Bone. Let us conſider a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle this Definition: It ſays, it is a prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural Tumour, or Humour; who doubts the Truth of the King's Evil, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and Ulcers being contrary to the Intention and Deſign of Nature, and conſequently are praeternatural? Next it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1238900400:14"/>ſays, it is produced (that is, a Tumour or Humour) by a particular Acidity of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum of the Blood. This ſeems indeed to be the general Opinion of moſt Authors I have met with on this Subject, who uſually follow each other, like Pack-Horſes in the ſame Track: But that other Cauſes may have the ſame Effects, I ſhall by and by endeavour to demonſtrate. The Nature of Acidity, according to this Definition, both coagulates and indurates. Coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is performed on Milk by Acids, that is, turning the Milk into a Curd, it ſuppoſes the Acidity, or Sourneſs of the Serum of the Blood does the ſame, that is, curdles in the fine Veſſels it enters into. But becauſe Vinegar, Lemon Juice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are acid on the Tongue, muſt they be ſo in the Blood? What mad Work muſt Vinegar, or other Acids produce, mixt with it, let every one judge? Pray think what Quantities of Vinegar <hi>Newmarket</hi> Jockeys drink for a Month or two toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to reduce themſelves to a proper Weight for Riding Races, and then tell me of any Inſtance of the Scrophula be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing produced by that Regimen. Beſides,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1238900400:15"/>if this was the Caſe, why ſhould not the Serum be as ſoon coagulated or curdled in the large Veſſels as in the finer? which we ſee it is not, though the Serum of the Blood contains a proportional Quantity of this particular Acidity in the large Veſſels, as well as in the ſmall: And I am apt to think, that the larger the Quantity of Liquor, the ſooner it will turn ſour, and more ſharp the Acidity; which I take to be the Reaſon, why the Vinegar Makers uſe ſuch large Caſks, even to the holding a hundred Barrels of Liquor in one Body.</p>
               <p>I HAVE obſerved my Patients that have had Sores or Ulcers in their Mouths or Throats, have never complained of, or perceived any Sourneſs or Acidity of Taſte, from the purulent Matter they have ſpit out, though I have been very inquiſitive in that Particular, but they have always de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared they had a very ſalt Taſte from the Matter diſcharged by Spittle.</p>
               <p>THAT there is in the Spirit of human Blood a great Hoſtility (according to Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>) or an Antipathy in reference to Acids, has been plainly intimated, and likewiſe to many Sorts of Acid Spirits,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1238900400:16"/>as of Spirit of Salt, Spirit of Nitre, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Oil of Vitriol, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and not only againſt factitious Acids, but natural ones too, which he proves by many Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the Curious may ſee in his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Hiſtory of human Blood, where he alſo ſays, as far as he has been able to obſerve, the Spirit of human Blood is manifeſtly preferable to that Claſſis, that many call Volatile Alcalies, becauſe it makes ſuch great Conflicts with divers Acid Spirits, as Spirit of Salt, Aqua For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and it will immediately turn Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup of Violets from blue to green, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> performing ſuch other Things, that may be expected from Volatile Alcalies as ſuch. And he ſeems ſtrongly to intimate, that there are very few (if any Acid Particles at all) in the Blood, or even in the digeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Ferment of the Stomach. But that great Quantities of Volatile alcalious Salts are contained in the Spirit of human Blood, he proves by many undeniable Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which if true, muſt naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all Acidity in the Blood itſelf; ſo that conſequently, it cannot be a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, or any Acidity at all in the Blood, that produces the Scrophula.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:1238900400:17"/>
               <p>THOUGH Spirit of Salt and Oil of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol (which are ſtrong Acids) will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a Curd-like Subſtance dropped into the Serum of the Blood, ſo will Oil of Tartar per Deliquium (which is a ſtrong alcalizate Salt) and alſo highly rectified Spirit of Wine, and many other alcalious Subſtances, do the like.</p>
               <p>FROM what has been ſaid, it appears, that there can be no Acidity at all in the Blood: But much Alcaline Salt there is very capable of producing all the Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms and ſcrophulous Complaints attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Diſorder.</p>
               <p>THE Induration ſpoken of in the ſame Definition, I take to be only the Curd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Matter, hardned by Length of Time, and thruſt or ſqueezed cloſer together by the Addition of more of the ſame Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. That the Marrow in the Bones is diſſolved, I have had no Opportunity to obſerve, by not ſeeing any Amputation performed in this Diſorder. That the Bones often ſcale, and throw off Honey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb-like Exfoliations, or Pieces, and are alſo much corroded, I have frequently met with. But why will not a ſharp
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1238900400:18"/>coroſive Salt cauſe this Corroſion on hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Bones, as well as common Sea Salt on the ſofter Bones and Griſtle-like Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of raw Beef, when long ſalted in the Pickling-Tub? I make no doubt but it will.</p>
               <p>THE Reaſon why this Diſeaſe is called the King's Evil, as I apprehend, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it has been often cured by the Royal Touch of our Kings in this Iſland, from <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor's Time (and how long before I have ſeen no Account) down to the late Queen <hi>Anne</hi>'s Reign. This has been the Subject of much debate amongſt the Learned, becauſe great Cures have been ſometimes effected that Way, when other Means have miſcarried; and other Means have often ſucceeded, when the Royal Touch has failed. What then ſhall we ſay? In my humble Opinion, there is ſomething in the Nature of Gold itſelf very beneficial in this Diſorder, I don't mean laid into the Hand of the Phyſician by Way of Fee, or pocketed by a Surgeon or Apothecary, but worn about the Patient's Neck, by a white Sat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Ribband, hanging down to the Pit of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1238900400:19"/>the Stomach. How often are Gold Ear-rings and Gold Beads for Necklaces worn for what People call Kernels, in and about the Neck and Throat, and for ſore Eyes, which are all common Appearances in this Diſtemper, and not without ſome Benefit, as I believe many young Women can teſtify?</p>
               <p>I VERILY believe that Gold being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually worn at the Pit of the Stomach, next the Skin, has often had great and good Effects, but then People will not attend with Patience enough the Succeſs of ſuch a gentle operating Remedy; for no doubt, but the fine Effluvia of the Gold being conſtantly heated by the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and continually rubbed againſt it, will inſinuate many of its fine Particles through the Pores of the Skin into the Blood and Spirits, and mixing in Time with the Juices of the Body, have very ſalutary Effects. But then I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend a Piece of fine Gold, without alloy, as large as a 36 <hi>s.</hi> Piece, to be uſed for that Purpoſe. But this is too charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able an Application for my poor Patients Uſe, though I ſincerely think in many
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1238900400:20"/>Caſes it would be very beneficial, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to young Subjects, whoſe Stomachs are warm, and the Diſeaſe in its Infancy. Scrophulous Caſes, ſays Dr. <hi>Leigh,</hi> may be ranked amongſt the <hi>opprobria Medico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> or Scandal of Phyſicians; and after his Deſcription of the Diſtemper in its various Appearances and Effects, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes; I could wiſh our learned Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons in this Caſe, would make their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Applications, for the Diſcovery of ſome Specifick, to correct this Humour. You ſee, this learned Gentleman ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly owns, the Nature and Cure of this Diſeaſe was very little known by any of the Faculty in his Time.</p>
               <p>SIR <hi>Richard Blackmore</hi> ſays it exceeds the Penetration and Capacity of human Underſtanding, to unravel and diſplay thoſe anomalous Clues and Convolutions proper to ſtrumous Swellings, and to ſet their Nature and Conſtitution in a clear and diſtinct View; and that the acuteſt Men cannot penetrate and clearly unfold the eſſential Difference of this Diſeaſe. This, I think, ſufficiently ſtrengthens Dr. <hi>Leigh</hi>'s Obſervations of the ſmall Progreſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1238900400:21"/>that has been made in the Nature and Cure of the King's Evil. Having but juſt mentioned the Opinions of theſe two learned Phyſicians, for more particular Accounts I refer the Reader to their Works, and ſhall proceed with my own Thoughts and Obſervations.</p>
               <p>SETTING aſide then the Doctrine of Acid and Alcaly, let us conſider the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Salts, and whether they are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of producing the Complaints and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances appendent to ſcrophulous Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. That human Blood abounds with great Quantities of Volatile Salts (is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently demonſtrable by obſerving only the Sweat and Urine) which are compoſed of Corpuſcules, or Particles of very differing Shapes and Sizes, as Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> clearly proves, who after many Experiments, has found, that theſe ſaline Concretions exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit very different Appearances; ſome are ſtrait, ſome crooked, with various Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, repreſenting Branches of Trees, Hartſhorn, Feathers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet, ſays he, theſe ſeem not to be conſtant Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions depending upon the particular Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of human Blood, but caſual Figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that depend upon ſeveral accidental Cauſes and Circumſtances. Now this Scrophula is very often an hereditary Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and conveyed by Parents: How fine then muſt the Seeds (if I may ſo call
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1238900400:22"/>them) of this Diſtemper be? yet ſo it is. As every Acorn contains an Oak rapt up within its Surface, till Time and Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation diſcover its Trunk and ſpreading Branches; ſo is it with this Diſorder. If the Seeds are born with us, they lie dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant in our Blood till a proper Time and a convenient Diſpoſition of that Liquor, and the nervous Juices of the Body, cauſe them to grow and expand into grievous Complaints, and terrible Symptoms.</p>
               <p>THE Blood, which ſeems to be the principal Seat of this Diſorder, is divided into two Parts; the one called the Fibrous, conſiſting of great Numbers of fine ſmooth red Globules, continually floating in the other, which is a clear lympid Liquor, called the Serum, or ſerous Part, which conveys theſe fine Globules to all Parts of the human Fabrick, in ſome Degree or other. Now if any of theſe red Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bules are broken change their Figure, or are obſtructed in their Paſſage by the Serum becoming glutinous, or being in too ſmall or too large a Quantity, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered by any praeternatural Commotion or Ferment, the Circulation through the fineſt Veſſels will be the firſt impeded and hindered, as in the Glands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now think, if it is not agreeable to Reaſon, that as the Globules and Serum of the Blood may both contain a larger Portion
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1238900400:23"/>of theſe Volatile Salts when the Blood is diſordered by any praeternatural Cauſe; and may not theſe Salts ſhoot into very different Figures and Sizes from what they were in their natural State, according to the Nature of the Humours or Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers that are latent in the Blood? And as theſe Salts are frequently of very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexing and entangling Figures, may we not reaſonably ſuppoſe, that thoſe irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular figur'd Bodies (carried along in the Road of Circulation) by croſſing and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangling each other, may cauſe Stoppages and Obſtructions in the fine Tubes and Strainers of the Body, as the Glands par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly are? And by a continual Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theſe perplexing Bodies, diſtend the obſtructed Veſſels (by Length of Time) into Tumours, which are often indurated or hardened, till ſometimes by their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive Quality they fret their Way through the Skin, and break into Ulcers. What can this proceed from, but the red glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bular Particles, or fibrous Part of Blood, being ſtopped by the figur'd Salts, and the ſerous Part ſtrain'd as through a Net or Sieve from the fibrous? The Serum for want of theſe ſmooth red globular Particles being mixed with it, becomes clear, tenacious, and ſizey, the minute Parts of the Serum not being ſufficiently ſeparated and divided by thoſe ſmooth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1238900400:24"/>Globules as before, and rubbing againſt each other, are thereby rendered acrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and fretting, and become produc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of grievous Complaints, hard to be removed. Tumours and Ulcers gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by theſe or the like Means, are brought to a good Digeſtion with great Difficulty, and very probably not till the remaining red globular Particles of the Blood can be again mixed in ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the clear Serum, and form one circulating Fluid of Blood and Spirits as before, which I ſuppoſe to be effected by melting, abſorbing, altering or removing thoſe ſaline acrimonious Particles that formed the Obſtructions.</p>
               <p>Now let us conſider likewiſe the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brous Part of the Blood, or red Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bules, which being unable to pervade or paſs this Rete or Strainer produced by theſe irregular figur'd Salts, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the Serum in its Progreſs, are there ſtopped, and being ſpqueezed and crowded cloſe together for want of this Liquor to float them forward through the fine Veſſels, obſtruct the Spirits, putrify and turn into a Curd-like Subſtance, till it is digeſted by Art or Nature into a ſoft Pus or Matter, and ſo expelled its Neſt. What is more common than to ſee large ſcrophulous Ulcers (eſpecially in the more fleſhy Parts) look of a deep red Colour
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1238900400:25"/>far round their Lips or Edges, which I apprehend to proceed from theſe red Globules being ſeparated from the Serum, and ſtagnating in thoſe Parts, until a proper Digeſtion is procured, and then the Redneſs gradully diſappears, and at the ſame Time you may often obſerve a clear tranſparent Liquor ſtand in dewy Drops on that red Surface of the Skin through which it has exudated? Which I think a ſufficient Demonſtration that the ſerous Part of the Blood is in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order ſtrained or ſeparated from the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brous, and viſible even to the naked Eye. And I have always found by Experience, that as the Quantity of this clear limpid Liquor has decreaſed, the Ulcer has diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged a more laudable Pus, the Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs inſenſibly worn off, and then the Ulcer has healed up with very little Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication more than dry Lint.</p>
               <p>SHOULD I attempt to mention all Parts ſubject to this Diſorder, I muſt name every individual of the human Fabrick, for I know of none exempt from this ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Malady, no not even the Bones themſelves; for in my Courſe of Practice I have had this verified by repeated Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations: I have had a Patient afflicted with Tumours and Ulcers from the Crown of the Head to the Sole of the Foot, and in above twenty different Places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1238900400:26"/>at once, the major Part of which have been cured by the Application of dry Lint only, and the Remainder by very ſimple Applications, and but very little Phyſick. But ſuch bad Caſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire much Time to make a perfect Cure. For any-body muſt think, that a Diſeaſe brought into the World with one, and ſo interwoven with the Conſtitution, and grown up with it, muſt have much Time and Patience ere it can be totally ſubdued and eradicated from the Blood and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. Though I have never ſeen any Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſections of the human Body, yet I may gueſs from what I obſerve without, that the Stomach, Bowels, and Inteſtines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are no leſs diſordered within, which muſt infallibly be the Source of many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Conſequences, unleſs removed by Art or Nature, as ſometimes may be the Caſe. Every the leaſt Tube or Strainer in the whole human Frame may poſſibly be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by the Seeds of this Diſorder, as they begin to expand, and long before they arrive to a Bulk perceiveable by the Eye or Touch. Unuſual Prickings and Daſhings, and Sickneſs at the Stomach, and Uneaſineſs in many Parts, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Complaints in the beginning of this Diſeaſe: What can theſe proceed from, but the Aſſemblage of ſharp, ſaline, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfering Particles, endeavouring to force
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1238900400:27"/>their Way through theſe fine Strainers by Stops and Starts. The upper Lip ſwelled, Eyes inflamed, the Glands about the Jaws, Neck, Throat, and Shoulders, tumified, ſhow this Diſorder rather ſooner (though not always) than moſt other Parts. The Backs of the Hands, Elbows, Arm-Pits, Ribs and Ancles, are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently affected, and as the Diſorder en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes, the ſofter Bones feel its Effects, which if they exfoliate, are often cured, if not, uſually terminate in malignant Ulcers of a cancerous Nature, and bring the Patient at Length to an End.</p>
               <p>THAT the King's Evil is a Diſeaſe, <hi>ſui Generis,</hi> or after its own Kind, I can readily admit. But then how often is it complicated and blended with others, as the Gout, Venereal Evil, White Swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in the Knees, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſeem to have a near Affinity with it, by affecting the Bones and Joints much in the ſame Manner? But the various Combinations and Degrees of each particular Malady that may at the ſame Time ſeize on the human Syſtem, I believe is impoſſible to be diſtinguiſhed and aſcertained. Then how can we range the various Swellings common or extraordinary, that ariſe on the Surface of the Body, or lie almoſt concealed among the Muſcles, and are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſuch novel Appearances every
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1238900400:28"/>Day, without knowing every particular Degree, of every particular Diſeaſe, and their Conſequences, that may poſſibly be at once uniting in the ſame Body and its Members? What may probably be the immediate Cauſe of this Diſtemper, I have already hinted at; but the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote ones, I may venture to aſſert, are as numerous as the different Appearances of Tumours and Ulcers in all Parts of the Body put together. I ſhould ſoon wade out of my Depth, if I attempted to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſuch intricate and perplexing Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, or the Forms and eſſential Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of thoſe fine Particles of hidden Matter, as may contribute to the Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the King's Evil, and have puzzled ſo many judicious and learned Phyſicians, and may ſtill do ſo for Ages to come.</p>
               <p>I SHALL now proceed to ſay ſomething relative to the Cure of this obſtinate Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. If we ſearch the moſt eminent Authors in purſuit of a Cure for this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper, we ſhall find ourſelves miſerably diſappointed, ſays a late Writer: I ſay ſo too. Therefore as their Preſcriptions ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom anſwer the deſired End, I ſhall take no Notice of them, but purſue my own Way of Thinking. I have no great Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of diſcuſſing of Tumours (unleſs the Face is likely to be much deformed by them, eſpecially of the Female Sex; or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1238900400:29"/>when the Eyes are inflamed, and very troubleſome, then I think ſuch a Remedy is juſtifiable) becauſe the peccant Matter is only removed from one Part to another, and not cured, but ſtill ſubſiſts in the Blood and Spirits, and may poſſibly be thrown on a more noble and dangerous Part, and do much more Harm than can be eaſily imagined.</p>
               <p>MY Patients have often told me (to uſe their own Way of Expreſſion) that they have had Swellings in their Necks, or other Places, and Neighbour ſuch a one told 'um, if they did them with Vinegar, 'twould put them away, which it ſometimes did, but in a little Time others aroſe in their Stead in other Parts, that would not yield to their old Remedy. If they were Pariſh Poor, and looked af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the Year, they fell to my Share, becauſe nothing was to be got by them, and 'twould coſt a deal of Trouble and Expence for Phyſick for ſuch poor Wretches, who were better out of the Way. How unhappy are poor People, to be thus cruelly uſed by ſome mercenary Phyſick-Mongers? How many funeſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are in every one's Memory (if they would recollect a little) of ſome Neighbours, or Acquaintance, that have even deſtroyed themſelves, by backing or ſtriking in Humours (as it is called)
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1238900400:30"/>and repelling them to ſome mortal Part? This Practice is too frequent with the Fair Sex; I hope they will think ſeriouſly for the future, and do ſo no more. If any Reaſons occur to make Repellents neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, I then order proper Purgatives to carry off the morbifick Matter, cleanſe the Blood, and prevent any Danger from ſuch a Revulſion. Iſſues or Setons I never uſe, and often dry them up, for I could never perceive any Benefit accrue to the Patient from them. If Ulcers diſcharge the offending Matter lodged in or near them, why ſhould we invite it another Way, and not follow the Road Nature has pointed out? What are Ulcers, but ſo many natural Iſſues, which will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge themſelves, if a good Digeſtion is procured, as long as any offending Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſubſiſts in or near them, and then dry up of courſe, unleſs hindred by Art? Why then ſhould we make an artificial Ulcer that Nature wants not? Nay, is even detrimental to it, by encreaſing a Diſcharge, which we are endeavouring to diminiſh, and wholly ſubdue.</p>
               <p>SALT Water being much in Vogue, I ſhall give my Thoughts on it as a Remedy for the King's Evil. I had a Patient troubled with a very painful Inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Eyes, which had baffled the Skill of all ſhe had applied to in <hi>London,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:1238900400:31"/>(and being a Perſon of Fortune, be ſure no Advice was wanting) ſhe was ſent to the Sea Side to drink the Salt Water, which ſhe did for a Month, and returned much worſe: When I ſaw her, I ſoon perceived the Diſorder to be ſcrophulous; ſhe kept in a dark Room, not being able to abide the leaſt Gleam of Light, complained of intolerable daſhing Pains in her Forehead, and Eyes, which diſcharged great Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of clear Water, ſo ſcalding and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive, that it excoriated the Skin where it flowed down the Cheeks. This Lady's Complaints were afterwards removed by a moſt ſimple and eaſy Remedy, which I apply in thoſe Caſes, and ſeldom miſs of a Cure. What I would obſerve from this is, that the ſaline Particles of the Water, which ſhe drank ſo long, added more Matter of a ſimilar Nature to what was too abundant in the Blood and Spirits al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, which entirely convinces me that drinking Salt Water is wrong in ſcrophu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Caſes of the Eyes; and bathing for them, I believe, to be equally hurtful, for we know many ſaline Particles may in bathing be abſorbed through the Pores of the Skin by the Blood, and ſo unite with thoſe already there. Obſerve what Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> ſays, <q rend="margQuotes">"As it ſeemeth Salt draweth Blood, as well as Blood draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Salt."</q> That is, they reciprocally
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1238900400:32"/>attract each other. Extirpating of tumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Glands (which is no unfrequent Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice) I have never uſed, either by the Knife, or Cautery, actual or potential; neither can I approve the Method, though I own its the moſt painful. I have had ſome Patients with me, whoſe Glands have been thus treated, and to all Appearance quite cured, and for a Time well; but as the Humour was not thereby eradicated out of the Blood and Spirits, it broke out again in freſh Places, which brought them to me. Theſe freſh Complaints I have afterwards cured with eaſy and gentle Applications. Sometimes indeed, where the Diſorder has been mild, and invaded but few Glands, and the Seeds of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe wholly contained in them, Extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion has done the Deed. But if theſe tumified Glands can be reduced to their natural State by a leſs dangerous and painful Way (though indeed not ſo quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) and no Danger of any Tumours ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing elſewhere: Which ſhall we chooſe, the more quick, painful, and uncertain, or the more ſlow, eaſy, and ſure Method of Cure? How many have been ſalivated without receiving any Good? Inſtances of this Kind I have met with in my Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, more than once. A learned Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian writes, <q rend="margQuotes">"A Salivation is found by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1238900400:33"/>Experience incapable of eradicating this obſtinate Diſeaſe, notwithſtanding it has ſuch peculiar Specifick, and almoſt certain Virtue to remove the Venereal Evil.</q> Which plainly proves (as I think) the Seeds or Cauſes of the two Diſtempers to be very different; and confutes the vulgar Notion, that the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nereal Evil is the Parent of the King's Evil; for if they both ſpring from the ſame Original, why are they not removed by the ſame Means? Which we find they are not; but when united in the ſame Subject, its rational to think they encreaſe each others Malignity, and render the Cure more uncertain and difficult.</p>
               <p>MOST People afflicted with ſcrophu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Diſorders in their Eyes, are very fond of hood-winking or covering them from the Light and Air, which is the worſt Method they can take, for it not only encreaſes the Inflammation, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites the Humour that Way, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently occaſions a greater Diſcharge from them, which ſhould be carried off ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Way, and which is often of ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive a Nature, as to excoriate and fret the Skin of the Face, as it diſtils down the Cheeks: I always make them throw away their Coverings, either going to Bed, or riſing in the Morning, to prevent tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cold, by too ſuddenly expoſing their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1238900400:34"/>Eyes; and my Succeſs has always war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted this Practice. After diſapproving others Proceedings in the Cure of this Diſorder, it may be aſked, why I don't publiſh my own, which I think ſo much better? To ſuch Enquirers I anſwer: The Medicines I uſe are very innocent and common Things, but the Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is curious and difficult, and takes much Time to compleat. Should I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulge it, very few People (except the Compounders of Medicine) would attend the Proceſs, or take the Trouble of it; and how little Good will a vitiouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Medicine do, is obvious to any one: And as the common Labourers, and Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicraftſmen, their Wives and Children, make the Bulk of my Patients, it is above their Capacity, and of no Uſe to tell them any Thing about it, more than what is neceſſary to their right managing themſelves under the Regimen I direct, and to give them the plaineſt and ſimpleſt Directions poſſible, as well as to uſe the eaſieſt Means for their Recovery. As to the Sellers of Medicines, I think they can have no claim to reap any Advantage from my Labour and Experience. The better Sort of Families infected by this Diſeaſe are really more to be pitied, than the very loweſt Claſs of the People, for they are but too often amuſed with falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1238900400:35"/>and flattering Accounts of their own real Diſorders (of this in particular, and as Dr. <hi>Radcliff</hi> truly obſerved) kept in Miſery for their Money. And to every one in general I ſay, nobody has any Cauſe to complain of keeping the Thing to myſelf, for every one that pleaſes, and has the King's Evil, may apply to me, and reap the ſame Benefit, as well as if they knew the whole Proceſs. (Great I know) is the general Clamour againſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, Noſtrums, and old Wives Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, as ſome pleaſe to call them; but I would fain know, if any prudent Perſon would refuſe to be cured by a ſafe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Medicine, unleſs he knew the whole particular Preparation and Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; or becauſe I don't chooſe to make that Diſcovery of my Methods that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Curioſity or Cenſure may expect? Did Dr. <hi>James</hi> publiſh the Preparation of his Fever Powder, yet I believe few Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their Senſes would ſcruple the Uſe of it? If the candid, humane, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Phyſicians an Surgeons ſmile on my Endeavours for the Publick Good, let the envious, ſnarling, and covetous Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners blame me if they pleaſe, for not treating my Patients <hi>Secundum Artem</hi> (as they term it) that is, by not making long Bills.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:1238900400:36"/>
               <p>I SHALL mention but one Thing more: Many People who have ſeen the amazing Effects of my Applications, often tell me, they hope I will not let the Secret, and its Improvements, die with me; I do not intend it ſhall; for I carefully write down every Patient's Complaints, the Methods I uſe, and the Succeſs that follows, as far as I can be informed by themſelves or Neighbours, who come to me on their Recommendation, by which Means I frequently hear of People I have cured, who living at a Diſtance, and being free from their Complaints, take no further Notice of me; though all I deſire for my Trouble is, to hear from themſelves, either by Letter, or Word of Mouth, when they are well: But all my Patients are not ſo forgetful of their Benefactor. My Papers and Obſervations relating to the Cure of the King's Evil, I hope will fall into the Hands of my Executor: And may he uſe them to the Benefit of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in general, an the Poor in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, with the ſame Succeſs, and charitable Intentions, as I have done.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="case_studies">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:1238900400:37"/>
               <p>PHILIP WINTERFLOOD, late of Halſted in Eſſex, a Journeyman Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, aged 35, now living at the Sign of the Periwig over againſt the White Horſe at Mile-End near London, was about Eight Years ago miſerably afflicted with ſeveral ſtrenuous Ulcers under both Breaſts; and being a fat Man ſome of them were above an Inch deep and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged much foul corrupted Matter, and had done ſo a long Time, had evaded all Methods of Cure, and when I ſaw him was a very deplorable Object. This Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon had the Diſorder hereditary, many of his Family having been greatly afflicted with it. He has travelled many Parts of England ſince, and been ſeen with much Admiration by many Perſons who have talked with him. I cured him in about Six Months, and he continues well to this Day, and has ſent me ſeveral poor Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients who have travelled on Foot near Fifty Miles to my Houſe, who I believe don't repent their Journeys.</p>
               <p>WIDOW of Joſeph Prentice of Halſted, aged 70 Years, ſome Years ago had the Evil in her Eyes, and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1238900400:38"/>and held well ſeveral Years, but her Eyes growing very bad again with great daſhing Pains in her Head, and a ſmall Tumor ariſing on her Shoulder, ſhe applied to me; I cured her Eyes and the Tumor ſubſided with very little Trouble, and ſhe remained perfectly free from her Complaints, till her Death, ſome Years after.</p>
               <p>JACOB HOGYOTT, Son of Samuel Hogyott, Huſbandman, of Grinſted-Green in Halſted, aged 18, had a large Scropho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Swelling under his Chin, and many Scropholous Tumors and Ulcers on each Side the Neck; ſome broke and run clear Water, and ſome good Matter. This Lad I cured in Nine Months, and is now gone to Service and capable to earn his Living as a Huſbandman; was recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by Mr. Vaughan, a very eminent Surgeon, who could do him no Service.</p>
               <p>REBECCA BROWN, Daughter of Jerry Brown of Coln Engain, Eſſex, Huſbandman, aged 12 Years, had ſeveral running Scropholous Sores about her Neck and Shoulders, otherwiſe a florid well looking Girl; my very eaſy Methods cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her in about Four Month.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:1238900400:39"/>
               <p>JONATHAN WADE, of Braintree, recommended to me for the King's Evil by Mr. Stapletyon Surgeon, of Braintree, Eſſex. When he came to me, he had two large running Sores near the Elbow on the left Arm, and one about an Inch above the Ancle on the left Leg, and a Sore in the Palm of his left Hand; had all the Sores Six Months before I ſaw him; moſt of his Relations had the Evil. About a Year after his Brother came and told me he was quite cured.</p>
               <p>WILLIAM BROWN, belongs to Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feld in Eſſex, aged 19, had the Evil much in both Eyes, very much inflamed with great Pains in the Fore-part of his Head; run ſometimes clear Water very ſalt, and ſometimes Corruption from the Corners of his Eyes, and very impatient of Light. His Mother had the Evil in her Family, and came to tell me her Son was now quite well by my Means.</p>
               <p>SARAH NORMAN, Daughter of Francis Brewer, on the Burr-Walls at Bath in Somerſetſhire, aged 14 Years. Her Upper-lip much ſwelled, and both Eyes much inflamed; theſe Diſorders I ſoon cured by a very eaſy Method.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:1238900400:40"/>
               <p>EDWARD POTTER, Son of Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Potter of Pedmarſh in Eſſex, aged 12 Years, ſent by Mr. Maniſtree, Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary of Halſted, had when he came to me a Sore on the Back of both Hands and four running Ulcers in the Calf of his left Leg; he is now quite well, and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has got him out to Service, and came to thank me for the Cure of his Son.</p>
               <p>ROBERT WADE, of Bocking in Eſſex, Shoemaker, aged 15 Years. A Sore on the Inſide of the right Knee, and a large Swelling (broke about a Week be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came to me, and run clear Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) on the Outſide the left Thigh, from a ſmall Orifice, and very hollow for two or three Inches above and below. About eight Months after his firſt coming to me, he came to thank me being quite well.</p>
               <p>SARAH EVERITT, Daughter of John Everitt of Earl's Coln, Huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, aged 19 Years; ſhe had a large Swelling on the left Side the Neck, and the ſame Side of the Face and under the Chin much ſwelled, had this Complaint four Years before ſhe came to me; ſhe had been with a Surgeon, who tried to cure her, but not ſucceeding, pronounced
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1238900400:41"/>it the King's Evil, gave her up, and then ſhe came to me, and is now well.</p>
               <p>ANN MEAD, Wife of Samuel Mead, of Great Wrating in Suffolk, Huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, aged 34, came recommended to me by Mr. John Smith, Surgeon of Little Theorloe, for the Evil very bad in her Eyes, in November 1757; and in April 1758, I received the following Letter from her.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>SIR, This comes to acquaint you, that by God's Bleſſing and your Kindneſs to me, I am quite reſtored to Sight. I am ſo well recovered that at preſent I have not the leaſt Diſorder in my Eyes. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn you my ſincere Thanks for the Trouble you gave yourſelf on my Behalf, having received that Benefit from you which I could not find from ſeveral Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors I applied to, which was very charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to me. That Almighty God will be pleaſed to ſhower down his Bleſſings upon you, both temporal and ſpiritual, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending your Charity to the Diſtreſſed, is and ſhall be the conſtant Prayer of,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                        <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>Ann Mead.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>April</hi> 23, 1758.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:1238900400:42"/>
               <p>TITUS WELLS, Son of John Wells of Sudbury in Suffolk, aged 14 Years, ſent to me by Mr. E. Grove Surgeon; when he came to me, he had a large running Sore on the left Side his Neck, had been ſo about a Year, and a very bad Ulcer on the left Thigh, a Sore on the Back of his left Hand, and ſeveral ſmall Swellings about the Neck and left Elbow; was with me about a Twelvemonth after, all his Sores quite well.</p>
               <p>SIMON SMITH, of Great Wading<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild in Suffolk, was recommended to me by Mr. Robert Upcher, Surgeon of Sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, being greatly afflicted with the King's Evil in his Eyes; he had ſome Swellings under his Chin, upon remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which, the Humor fell into both his Eyes, and reſiſted all Endeavours to remove it, till he came to me; he is now very well by my Aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>JOHN TUFF, of Stebing in Eſſex, aged 14, came to me with a ſcropholous running Sore on the Side of the left Foot, and a ſmall Sore on each Groin, his Noſe inflamed and run much clear Water and very ſcabbed; his Brother Thomas Tuff, aged 11 Years, had ſeveral Sores broke
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1238900400:43"/>on the right Side his Neck. The above Brothers were ſent to me by Mr. Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Surgeon of Braintree, I have cured them both.</p>
               <p>CATHERINE ANDERSON, aged 11 Years, living with Mrs Whitting in Cullum-ſtreet, London, had the King's Evil very much in both Eyes, had Advice to no Purpoſe. I was then deſired to ſee her. I ſoon removed the Diſorder and cured der Eyes.</p>
               <p>MARY PRENTICE, of Coln En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, Eſſex, ſingle Woman, aged 50. This Woman was cured about 30 Years ago of the King's Evil with many bad Sores all over her, held well till within ſix Months, when a large Sore broke out on the Outſide of the left Leg a little above the Ancle and greatly inflamed; I remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Complaint entirely in a few Months.</p>
               <p>Let the following ſpeak for itſelf; the Lad is quite well by my Endeavours.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>SIR, ſonce more offer my Solicitations in Behalf of a poor Lad belonging to Great Waldingfield (Tho. Newton), who has laboured under the King's Evil, for twelve
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1238900400:44"/>Months paſt, in his Eyes. I hope your Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to the above Subject, which I know will be gratefully acknowledged, and may the Almighty grant you Succeſs in this and all others, and great may be your Reward both here and hereafter, which are the hearty Prayers of,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                        <signed>Your humble Servant (tho' unknown) <hi>Robert Upcher,</hi> Surgeon in Sudbury.</signed>
                        <dateline>Sudbury, <date>
                              <hi>Jan.</hi> 31, 1759.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>ELIZ. BAYLEY, Daughter of Mr. Robert Bayley, Baker at Chelmsford, aged 10 Years, had a Scropholous Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fell into her left Eye after the Small Pox, with a large white Speck on the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pil, which continued ſeven Years before I ſaw it. Her Father and Mother both joined in a genteel Letter of Thanks, to acquaint me that her Sight was perfectly well, and ſhe returns me all the Thanks ſhe can poſſibly give.</p>
               <p>ANN GAY, Daughter of George Gay Soldier, of Bocking Church-ſtreet in Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex, aged 6 Years. A ſmall running Sore on the right Arm and one under the left Ear, and a large Tumor gathering under
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1238900400:45"/>the left Eye, and very bad in her Health; the Tumor afterwards broke withinſide of the lower Eyelid, and diſcharged a great Quantity of thick Matter; is now perfectly recovered by my Methods, and in a very good State of Health; her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brought her to ſhow me, and thank'd me.</p>
               <p>MARY ANN ALSTONE lived at Mrs. Hancock's, on the Burr-Walls at Bath in Somerſetſhire, aged ſeven Years and a half, had her upper Lip greatly ſwelled, and ſome ſmall Tumors in her Neck. I was at Bath ſome time after, and found her perfectly well by my Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections. Her Mother went a nurſing, and was removed to one Mattins a Scourer in Horſe-ſtreet, Bath.</p>
               <p>MARY, Daughter of Geo. Newman, Gardener in the Hollow Way, over the Bridge in Bath, aged 10 Years, had a Scropholous Ulcer on the Point of her right Elbow, and one on the Back of her right Hand; on my next being at Bath, her Mother brought her to me quite well, and ſhowed me a large Piece of Bone that had ſeparated from her Elbow, all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſound.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:1238900400:46"/>
               <p>SARAH LAMB, of Booking Church-ſtreet, aged 31 Years, ſent by Mr. Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton Surgeon, Jo. Blawer Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and Tho. Chandler Overſeer; had many Tumors and Ulcers on her Arms, and Legs, and Face, ſome opened by a Surgeon, ſeveral Sores in her Mouth and Throat, with great Difficulty of Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and great Heat in her Throat and Stomach, and raiſed much corrupt Matter by Spit, which ſhe told me always taſted very ſalt, but not ſour, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſweet, or acid like Vinegar. This Woman came to me about a Year after, to thank me for the Benefit ſhe had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; the Tumors all gone, the Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers healed up, raiſes no putrid Matter, and has no Complaint, but a very little Stiffneſs ſometimes in the Throat, after ſwallowing a large Morſel. Her Mother died of the King's Evil.</p>
               <p>WILLIAM BURGETT, aged Eight Years, Son of William Burgett, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Cripplegate Pariſh, London, works with Mr. Aſhmole at Holloway Mount, helps to make Lamp-black. This Boy had the King's Evil very bad in both Eyes, and the upper Lip much ſwelled, about three Months. After he was with me, I
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1238900400:47"/>received a Meſſage from his Father, to thank me, for curing his Son, who was now very well by my Directions.</p>
               <!-- stopped here -->
               <p>MABLE BULLINGBROOKE, Daughter of John Bullingbrooke, Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Long Melford in Suffolk, aged 16 Years, ſent by Mr. Fairfax, Surgeon: Both her Eyes much inflamed, upper Lip ſwelled, and the Noſe diſcharged much clear Water. This Diſorder had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing four Years ſince it firſt appeared; ſhe is now well, as I have heard from many People that know her, but never heard from herſelf, according to Promiſe.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>Mr. AMBROSE DEATH the Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is troubled with an Opthalmy, which from its Stubborneſs in not yielding to the uſual Evacuations in that Caſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, I do imagine to be ſtrumous, and upon that Account do recommend him as a King's Evil Patient.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>John Burch, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon in Lavenham, Suffolk,</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>Nov. 5, 1759.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Perſon I cured in a little Time, and he has remained very well, without the leaſt Complaint to this Day.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:1238900400:48"/>
               <p>ROBERT HEATHERLY, Son of the Reverend Mr. Heatherly, late Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Clavering in Eſſex, formerly Maſter of the School in St. Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew's Hoſpital, London, aged 23 Years, had been an Out-patient there, for the King's Evil, had the ſecond Joint of his Thumb ſo affected that the Bone was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted out, and had ſeveral other Places healed up. Not long after, the Diſorder fell into both his Eyes with ſome ſmall unbroken Tumors in the Neck, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both Ears, and had been blind ſome Months, and thus came to me with both Eyes covered over, unable to do any Thing. He had a Brother a Surgeon, whoſe Endeavours with the Hoſpital Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons proving ineffectual, he came to me. I have reſtored his Sight ſo well that he kept a Writing School ſince, and afterwards went a Privateering, and told me himſelf that he was quite well, and had not the leaſt Scropholous Complaint, and was two or three Days at my Houſe after his Cure.</p>
               <p>ANN NUNN, Daughter of John Nunn, Farmer, of Laindon Hills in Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1238900400:49"/>aged 21 Years, had a large Scro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pholous Tumor on the right Side of the Jawbone, opened by Mr. Earl of Horn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, but as he could not heal it up, ſhe came to me; I perfected the Cure, and ſhe was well, at Service, when I heard of her ſome time after.</p>
               <p>I was deſired to ſee a young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in London, aged 26 Years, about a Year after he had fell down on both his Knees, a white lymphatick Swelling had been increaſing on his right Knee, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the following Means had been uſed, as he himſelf told me; firſt the Knee was treated as a common Bruiſe, and rub'd with Oils, to no Effect; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards poulticed with white Bread and Milk, Lees of Beer near a Month, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Advantage; then fomented with an Infuſion of Camomile, to no Purpoſe; then a Bliſter, (run but little) no Benefit; then Leeches applied twice, ſix at a Time, ſignified nothing; was at Bath, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards at Southampton, and uſed the uſual Methods at both Places, and all theſe Trials had no Effect on the Swelling. He had alſo a ſmall Scropholous Tumor,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1238900400:50"/>red and inflamed, on the Point of the Breaſt-bone. Some Months after he had been under my Care, he wrote me as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <p>I am ſure all the Pleaſure I enjoy this Summer is totally to be attributed to your Kindneſs; for had I not been ſo happy as to have been under your Direction, moſt likely I ſhould not have gained the Uſe of my Limbs ſo ſoon, if ever, which lays an everlaſting Obligation on your very humble Servant. </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText> And afterwards, in another Letter, he ſays, I am ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizingly recovered in regard to my Knee. Theſe, I hope, will ſatisfy any reaſonable Perſon of the Benefit this Gentleman re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by my Means.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>Great Stambridge, near Rochford in <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi> 
                           <date>October 5, 1762.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <salute>Mr. Morley, Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I JOSEPH LAMBERT return you kind Thanks for curing my Daughter Ann Lambert of the King's Evil. She is as well as ever. Sir, I can but love and thank you for your Civility.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This little Girl was ſix Years old, had her upper Lip very much ſwelled three
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1238900400:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>Quarters of a Year. Mr. Swain, an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary at Rochford, judged it Scropho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</p>
               <p>The following Letter I received July the 17th, 1762, from PHILIP SHELLY, Weaver at Clove <add>Clare</add> in Suffolk.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Mr. Morley, Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I ſend to you, returning many humble and hearty Thanks for the great Benefits I have received by you, being at your Houſe, May the 28, 1762, having the Evil in my Eyes, and not able to bear the Light in the Houſe, and by your Help and God's Mercy, is able to work abroad; Thanks be to God and you for it; I being a poor Man, am not able to make you any other Amends. If I was, I ſhould not think any Thing too much for you, for the great Benefits I have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by you; but I hope you will accept the ſame as if I ſent you a Preſent, ſo I remain</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>your humble Servant, <hi>Philip Shelly.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>I give the Reader his Letter verbatim, as I do all others that I quote. This Man's Eyes had been much diſorder'd ſix
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1238900400:52"/>Months, run hot ſcalding Water, and much white Matter from the Corner of his left Eye, and his upper Lip ſwelled.</p>
               <p>SUSANNA SPOWERS, Wife of Martin Spowers, Mariner, aged 26, lately living at Mr. Vines's near Sir William Warron's Square in Wapping, London, had a large Tumor, very hard and livid, on the lower Part of the left Breaſt next the Arm, which had been extirpated by Mr. Caywood, Surgeon and Apothecary, near by, judged to be a Cancer; but as he did not cure it, about a Month after, ſhe came to me. Then the whole Breaſt was inflamed, with two more Tumors riſing on the lower Part, and ſome ſmall Scropholous Complaints running about. Theſe Tumors afterwards broke, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged Matter as the other, which are all now well; and one other large Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, about the Middle of the Breaſt, I diſperſed without breaking. The whole Breaſt is now quite firm and well, ſmooth, ſoft, and of its natural Colour and Size, as before, except the Sear, which ſtill remains as a Proof the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon had been there. Whilſt in the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1238900400:53"/>Country under my Care, the Surgeon let her know, ſhe had better come to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and he would go with her to an Hoſpital, to have her Breaſt taken off, before the Cancer ſhould be fixt, for then it would be incurable. Note; Many ſcro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phulated Breaſts are miſtaken for Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and have been treated as ſuch, to the irreparable Damage of the poor Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers.</p>
               <p>A young Lady in London, at the Age of 4 Years, had two Scrophulous Ulcers, on each Arm one, both dried up by the Uſe of the Bark, by Order of one of the principal Phyſicians in London; but ſoon after the Diſorder broke out, with a deep Ulcer on the Calf of each Leg. Then I was applied to, and healed them up, but ſoon after neglecting my Direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Humor fell into both Eyes; then I was again applied to, and remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Diſorder; and ſhe is now free from any Scrophulous Complaints what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
               <p>Mr. John Joſeph, Surgeon at Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham in Eſſex, recommended to my Care
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1238900400:54"/>Suſanna Milbanks, aged 18 Years, for the King's Evil. She had ſix or ſeven Tumors opened by him, and healed, and kept well ſix Months: then the Diſorder fell into both her Eyes. Her right Eye had been burnt when a Child very much, ſo will never be otherwiſe, the left Eye perfectly clear and well, and all her Sores perfectly well and ſound, and herſelf in good Health.</p>
               <p>JOHN BUTCHER, of the Pariſh of Booking in Eſſex, Bayweaver, aged 30 Years, came to me from Bugden in Huntingtonſhire, being quartered there, and belonging to Captain Carter's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the Eſſex Militia. He firſt felt a daſhing Pain ſuddenly ſtrike into the lower Joint of the Forefinger of his right Hand, and in about a Month all the other Fingers and Thumb were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in the ſame Manner, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, that he could not ſtir them even with the other Hand, without great Pain, and then but very little. No Diſcolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or any perceivable Tumor, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural Heat to the Touch of himſelf, or others. His Captain who was a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, and knowing ſeveral of his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1238900400:55"/>were greatly afflicted with the King's Evil, pronounced it ſuch; he ſoon after was diſcharged as uncapable of Service. I reſtored this Man to the full Uſe of his Hand, Fingers and Thumb, by the Means I make uſe of in Scrophulous Caſes; which I think is a Proof this was a Species of the King's Evil. He was afterwards again admitted as a Militia Man in Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Mayhews Company, being perfectly well, having the Uſe of his Hand as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly.</p>
               <p>ELIZ. REYNOLD, Wife of Jo. Reynold of Halſted, Farmer, aged 25 Years, came with her Lips much ſwoln, the Inſide of the Noſe and upper Lip broke out, and very ſcabby, a large con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glomerated Tumor being increaſing three Quarters of a Year, under the right Ear, and ſeveral ſmall Tumors on the left Side the Neck. She told me ſome Months after, that all the Swellings were entirely gone, her Health never better, and not the leaſt Complaint. Note; I diſperſed all the Tumors, ſo that no viſible Signs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main to ſhow ſhe ever had the King's Evil.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:1238900400:56"/>
               <p>MARY COOK, Wife of Ed. Cook, Huſbandman of Coln Earls in Eſſex, aged 27 Years. Ten Years before ſhe came to me, a large Stick fell on the Middle of the Outſide of her right Thigh, and bruiſed it much, and was very pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful at times for five Years; then a large Swelling aroſe where 'twas bruiſed, broke and run above a Quart of white Matter, and now diſcharges chiefly Water, ſcald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and corroſive. The Orifice ſmall as a Pea, the Diſcharge very great, and a Surgeon having probed the Ulcer and found it very hollow, ſeveral Inches both above and below the Orifice. About four Months after, her Huſband came and told me, his Wife was twenty Pound bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſome Months after that her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther came and told me, ſhe was quite well.</p>
               <p>MARY PRENTICE, Daughter of Abraham Prentice, Jun. of Coln Engain, aged a Year and a half, had a Tumor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the left Ear, and ſeveral ſmall Swell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ariſing in divers Parts, inherited this Scrophulous Diſorder from her Father's Family, who came to thank and tell me, the Child was quite cured.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:1238900400:57"/>
               <p>BENJ. REED of Gosfeild in Eſſex, Huſbandman, aged 35, recommended by Mr. Maniſtree, Apothecary, both his Eyes much inflamed, and diſcharged ſome very ſcalding Water, and was ſo blind he had not ſeen the Sun or any Object for two Months before he came to me, and had a ſmall Tumor under his left Ear, and is now well by my Remedies.</p>
               <p>JOHN DRINKMILK, Son of Adam Drinkmilk of Barrow in Suffolk, Farmer, aged 24 Years, had about a Year ago a large Swelling under the left Arm diſperſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Surgeon, and afterwards the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor fell into the left Wriſt and Hand, which were much ſwelled, and growing uſeleſs. His Father had the King's Evil help'd thirty Years ago, and now I have removed the Son's Complaints.</p>
               <p>WILL. ARDLEY, Weaver of Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſhall in Eſſex, aged 40 Years, had been much troubled with the Tooth-ach and Ear-ach; then a Sore broke Withinſide the left Cheek, and diſcharged near a Pint of ſtinking Matter at ſeveral times; then a large Tumor aroſe on the left under Jaw-bone, and broke into three Ulcers, and diſcharged much Matter; then the Ulcer within the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1238900400:58"/>Mouth healed up, and it was with ſome Difficulty he could open his Mouth. All theſe running Sores I quite cured in about five Months, with the perfect Uſe of his Jaw-bones, and has no Complaints what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever remaining, and came to thank me for the Cure.</p>
               <p>SARAH ROWLAND, of Wickham Brooke in Suffolk, aged 18 Years, had a very large ſoft Tumor under the right Ear, been four Months increaſing, and pronounced ſcrophulous by Mr. Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne Surgeon of Lidgate in Suffolk, ſome of her Family having had the King's Evil; ſhe is now well by my Means.</p>
               <p>ANN BAKER, of Braintree in Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex, Widow, aged 45 Years, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by the Rev. Mr. Morgan the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car. She had ſeveral Holes in her Toes, with an Appearance like the St. Anthony Fire, on both Arms, Neck, Breaſt and Face, and very hot, and many ſmall Water-bladers and running Pains about her Joints, and ſome ſmall Swellings about the Neck and Throat, but none broke; ſeveral of her Relations had the King's Evil. She came to thank me ſometime after, being quite well.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:1238900400:59"/>
               <p>A little Miſs in London, aged 5 Years, had a troubleſome Scurfineſs on her Head, which made it very difficult to be kept clean, and ſmall Eruptions often appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſappearing on divers Parts, leaving a dry Scurf, and many ſmall Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors like Peas about the Neck. She is now very well by my Directions.</p>
               <p>WILL. FIELD, Serjeant in the 109th Company of Marines, belongs to Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham in Kent, aged 23 Years; he came to me with a Tumor riſing under each lower Jaw-bone. He is now well; and brought his Wife afterwards, with a bad Scropholous Complaint; but are both gone from my Neighbourhood, ſo I can ſay nothing as to her.</p>
               <p>A Lady in Norfolk, about 25, had a large Scrophulous Ulcer near the left Ancle, and pricking daſhing Pains in her Joints. When I firſt ſaw her, ſhe bathed daily in the Salt-water, which had ſo ſwelled and inflamed her Leg, ſhe could hardly ſtand. I begg'd her to leave off Bathing, which ſhe did, and in forty-eight Hours ſhe found Eaſe; and in ſome Months after I had a Letter from her,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1238900400:60"/>that her Complaints were by my Direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions entirely removed.</p>
               <p>A young Lady in Norfolk, aged 12 Years, about three Years ago had a ſmall hard Tumor under the left Nipple, which ſeems now no more; but when ſhe came to me, had a ſmooth, flatiſh, ſoft Tumor about the Bigneſs of half a Crown, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering above the Nipple of the ſame Breaſt, which had been under the Management of a regular Phyſician ſometime without any apparent Advantage; but is now by my Aſſiſtance entirely removed.</p>
               <p>Mrs. BROWN, Wife of Mr. Brown at the Bell in Clare Suffolk, aged 27 Years, brought me the following from Mr. Hawes a Surgeon.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Mrs. Brown, the Bearer hereof, hath for ſome Months laboured under a Diſeaſe in her Breaſt, which the Surgeons term a Schirrhus. Various Applications hath been tried, and many Medicines taken, which have only ſerved to alleviate her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, without laying a Foundation for healing. This Diſeaſe hath ſo near an Affinity with the Evil, that I do not think but it may be really called ſuch. I
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1238900400:61"/>wiſh you may be ſo fortunate as to direct ſomewhat that may be ſerviceable, and am,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                        <signed>Your humble Servant, <hi>Rich. Hawes.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>Cavendiſh, <date>Aug. 23, 1761.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Mrs. Brown was a fat luſty Woman: About a Year ago had a large Tumor roſe in her right Breaſt, and gathered in nine ſeveral Places, and opened by a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, and diſcharged much, but that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing though inſufficient to leſſen the Breaſt, two Setons were made quite thro' the Breaſt, (which was very large) cloſe to the Ribs, in the Form of a Croſs, and as the Silk rotted out, in ten or twelve Days, more Silk was put in, and ſhe had ſeven or eight Ulcers in other Parts of the Breaſt. Several Surgeons met, to take off the Breaſt, and told her if it was not taken off ſhe could not live to Michaelmas Day following; that her Breaſt would rot off in a Week or two, if not cut off. This was the State of the Breaſt when I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took it. November the 30th following, I ſaw this Woman; all the Ulcers well healed, and the Breaſt firm, and the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in good Health a Spirits, without any Complaints whatever. Feb. 27, 1762,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1238900400:62"/>ſhe was with me again, and ſhow'd me her right Breaſt ſound and firm, but told me that about three Weeks before, on taking Cold, ſhe felt a daſhing Pain in her left Breaſt, which ſhe ſhewed me. There was a ſmooth ſoft Tumor riſing on the upper Part, above the Nipple, which had encreaſed faſt, with ſome daſhing Pains. I ordered her proper Remedies for this new Complaint. April the 4th, her Huſband came to tell me the Tumor was broke, and diſcharged in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Places round the Nipple. I ordered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and Sept. the 6th, 1762, her Huſband came again and told me her Breaſt had been quite well 2 Months paſt, and his Wife in good Health a Spirits, no Complaint at all, and that the Day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came ſhe was brought to-bed of a fine Girl, and both like to do very well. I ſaw her ſome Days after, examined her right Breaſt, which had loſt the Nipple, all continued firm, and alſo her left Breaſt, but ſhe had no Milk in it, but no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint whatever. Note, it is very eaſy to obſerve from this Caſe that if Mrs. Brown's right Breaſt had been taken off, it would have avail'd nothing, from the other being diſordered in the like Manner. After hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cured Mrs. Brown's right Breaſt, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1238900400:63"/>from the before-mentioned Mr. Hawes the following.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I muſt now congratulate your Succeſs in curing this Diſeaſe, which is more rife by far than uſed to be, and likely to make ſad Ravages among Mankind. Mrs. Brown I hear is purely. I am,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Worthy Sir, </salute>
                        <signed>Your moſt obedient humble Servant, <hi>R. Hawes.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>Cavendiſh, <date>Nov. 26, 1761.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Febr. The 17th, 1763, her Huſband came to my Houſe, told me his Wife was in all reſpects perfectly well, and his little Girl a fine thrifty Child.</p>
               <p>A young Woman unmarried, aged 26, had a large Tumor on the left Buttock, had been opened four times by a Surgeon, at leaſt ſix Inches in Length, who told her he durſt not cut any more, but muſt apply Cauſticks. She had two ſmall Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers on the Small of her Back, and her Eyes greatly inflamed. The Buttock ſeemed almoſt divided into two. About eight Months after, this young Woman came to thank me, being well, without any Remains of her Diſorder, and uſed
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1238900400:64"/>no other Means for her Recovery than I had directed.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>To Mr. Morley,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>SIR, I ſend you a Man from Bradfield Mainger, afflicted with the running Evil, owing in my Opinion to the ill Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Apothecary, when ill with the Fever; if you can poſſibly aſſiſt him, hope your good Endeavours will not be wanting,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>from yours, &amp;c. R. R. Cox, a Surgeon at Great Welnetham, Suffolk.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Man was Rob. London, Son of Rob. London of Bradfield in Suffolk, aged 32 Years. About twelve Weeks after hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had this Fever, thirteen Tumors roſe about the Legs, Thighs and Buttocks, and had been all opened by Mr. Cox, and had diſcharged monſtrouſly, which had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced him to a meer Skeleton: he was brought to me in a Cart with a Bed made in it, being unable to move Hand or Foot, or to be moved without great Trouble. I went out to ſee this poor Man in the Cart: he looked ſo like a dead Corps, that People that ſaw him ſet out from home never expected to ſee him return alive, his Stomach gone, and Viſage ſo ghaſtly. This was Aug. 31, 1761: and Sept. the 10th, I received the following from Mr. Cox the Surgeon.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:1238900400:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>According to your Orders, have made uſe of the Medicines, but have ſince been obliged to open three more Abſceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, from which found a Sanguinous Matter, filled with a corrupted, from each Sore a large Quantity. Think the others begin to heal, excepting two, which are in the Calf, the other in the muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Part of the Thigh: the Stomach holds well, and cannot find by the Face and Pulſe, he is ſo much exhauſted, as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would be thought to be under his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The 23d of October following, Mr. Cox wrote me Word my Patient at Bradfeild was well, and in October 1762, I ſaw his Father, who told me his Son held well, and went to London every Week with Carrier's Waggon from Bury in Suffolk.</p>
               <p>Mr. HARRISON, Apothecary, ſent me Suſan Ottley of Barking in Eſſex, ſingle Woman, aged 26 Years. She came to me with almoſt numberleſs Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and fungous Excreſcencies, extended from the Top of the right Shoulder, quite down to the Nipple of her right Breaſt, which diſcharged a moſt foul and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1238900400:66"/>ſtinking Matter. She had an Ulcer on the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Arm, cloſe to her Arm-pit, and a deep one on the Shoulder almoſt by her Arm-pit, and one withinſide the Arm, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 3 Inches above the Elbow, and one almoſt under the right Buttock, a bad Stomach, and very had State of Health; had the Evil hereditarily, having a Siſter died of it, and another Siſter who had it much in her Eyes, which I cured. This Woman has now all her Ulcers entirely well, the fungous Excreſcences all healed up, ſmooth and ſound, has recovered a good Stomach, a florid well-looking Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and perfect good State of Health, by my Endeavours only; but this Subject was many Months under my Care, ſo that I uſually ſaw her every eight or ten Days, or I could have been of little Service in ſuch a bad Caſe.</p>
               <p>MARY BINGHAM, Wife of Adam Bingham, Huſbandman, late of Craſſing, now living at Patiſwick in Eſſex, aged 28 Years, was led to me, being totally deprived of her Sight. She told me ſhe had not ſeen her Hand or Child for 12 Months paſt. Both her Eyes looked al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as covered over with Cobwebs of a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1238900400:67"/>leaden dead Colour, run much ſcalding Water, mixt with thick white Matter from the Corners of her Eyes, and almoſt continually daſhing Pains about her Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and many Scrophulous Breakings out, about the Corners of her Mouth, and ſeveral other Places. I bleſs God, I have reſtored this poor Woman to her Sight, ſo well as to dreſs her Children, and ſpin, which ſhe does for her Liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood daily, as ſhe did before ſhe was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
