<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The golden age, a poetical epistle: from Erasmus D-n, M.D. to Thomas Beddoes, M.D.</title>
            <author>Darwin, Erasmus, 1731-1802.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>14 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007 January</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004787540</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">N7154</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW116871934</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K004299.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3316871934</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECLL</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">1234500700</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The golden age, a poetical epistle: from Erasmus D-n, M.D. to Thomas Beddoes, M.D.</title>
                  <author>Darwin, Erasmus, 1731-1802.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15,[1]p. ; 4⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for F. and C. Rivington; and J. Cooke, Oxford,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1794.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Erasmus D-n = Erasmus Darwin.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the Countway Library of Medicine.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCN7154.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1234500700:1"/>
            <p>THE GOLDEN AGE, A POETICAL EPISTLE FROM ERASMUS D<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>_…</desc>
               </gap>N, M. D. TO THOMAS BEDDOES, M. D.</p>
            <q>The French, that moſt injured and moſt enlightened people upon Earth, within theſe few years (ſince Deſpotiſm has been overawed by Liberty) have improved Science more than all other Nations put together. <bibl>BEDDOES'S REASONS, &amp;c.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>May we not, by regulating the vegetable functions, teach our Woods and Hedges to ſupply us with Butter and Tallow? <bibl>BEDDOES'S OBSERVATIONS ON CALCULUS, SCURVY, &amp;c. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, PRINTED FOR F. AND C. RIVINGTON; AND J. COOKE, OXFORD. MDCCXCIV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1234500700:2"/>
            <head>THE GOLDEN AGE,</head>
            <head>A POETICAL EPISTLE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BOAST of proud Shropſhire, Oxford's laſting ſhame,</l>
               <l>Whom none but Coxcombs ſcorn, but Fools defame,</l>
               <l>Eternal war with dulneſs born to wage,</l>
               <l>Thou Paracelſus of this wondrous age;</l>
               <l>BEDDOES, the philoſophic Chymiſt's Guide,</l>
               <l>The Bigot's Scourge, of Democrats the Pride;</l>
               <l>Accept this lay; and to thy Brother, Friend,</l>
               <l>Or name more dear, a Sans Culotte attend,</l>
               <l>While in Rhyme's Galligaſkins I encloſe</l>
               <l>The broad poſteriors of thy brawny proſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:1234500700:3"/>
And ſing, by thee inſpir'd, in tuneful ſtrain,</l>
               <l>The bleſt return of Saturn's golden reign!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh had I, ſilly ſwain, the force and fire</l>
               <l>Of ſome, whom Frenchmen's bloody deeds inſpire;</l>
               <l>Could I, aſcending on the wing of ſound,</l>
               <l>Pleas'd with the grand, the lofty and profound,</l>
               <l>Riſe above mortal ken in rapturous glow,</l>
               <l>Leaving poor purſy Senſe to pant below;</l>
               <l>Could I, for ever ſtudious to refine,</l>
               <l>Prank with my pearly phraſe each pretty line,</l>
               <l>Or like an empty Bottle, deep immers'd,</l>
               <l>Whence Bubbles after Bubbles buſtling burſt,</l>
               <l>Amus'd to view my noiſy nothings ſwell,</l>
               <l>In the ſweet vanity of thought excel;</l>
               <l>Now burſting o'er the bounds of vulgar Rhyme,</l>
               <l>Gracefully great and terribly ſublime;</l>
               <l>Trolling in full-toned melody along</l>
               <l>With all the clattering clang of modern ſong;</l>
               <l>I'd hail the progreſs of thoſe bliſsful days,</l>
               <l>When fair Philoſophy's meridian rays</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:1234500700:4"/>
Shall brighten Nature's face, ſhall drive the Moles</l>
               <l>Of blinking Error to their ſecret holes,</l>
               <l>Diſperſe the darkneſs of primaeval Night,</l>
               <l>And bid a new Creation riſe to light!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Proceed, great days! and bring, oh! bring to view</l>
               <l>Things ſtrange to tell! Incredible, but true!</l>
               <l>Behold, behold, the Golden Age appears:</l>
               <l>Skip, ſkip, ye Mountains! Foreſts lend your Ears!</l>
               <l>See red-capt Liberty from heaven deſcend,</l>
               <l>And real Prodigies her ſteps attend!</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nec <hi>varios</hi> diſcet <hi>mentiri</hi> lana <hi>colores:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Ipſe ſed in pratis <hi>Aries</hi> jam <hi>ſuavè rubenti</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Murice,</hi> jam <hi>croceo</hi> mutabit vellera luto:</l>
                        <l>Sponte ſuâ <hi>ſandyx</hi> paſcentes veſtiet agnos.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <bibl>VIRGIL.</bibl>
                  </note> No more immers'd in many a foreign dye</l>
               <l>Shall Britiſh wool be taught to bluſh and lie;</l>
               <l>But all our paſtures glow with purple Rams,</l>
               <l>With ſcarlet Lambkins, and their yellow Dams!</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">The renovation of the world under the benign influence of French Freedom has been long foretold by prophets of every deſcription, by ſome who manufacture verſes, others who manufacture cotton, by maudling Mrs's, and mincing Miſſes, by enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened Lawyers and more enlightened Phyſicians; but by none more fully expected, more ardently longed for, than by <hi>Dr. Beddoes</hi> and <note n="*" place="bottom">A Gentleman of Pembroke College, Oxford, to whom Dr. Beddoes addreſſes a late elaborate work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> appellation</note> his "<hi>Dear Giddy!</hi>" The great Dr. aſſures us, that not only ſcience in general will ſhortly advance towards perfection, but that in particular "a new Medicine will ariſe from the aſhes of the old with healing in its wings." How this revolution is to be effected we are informed in the dedication of his Obſervations on Calculus, &amp;c. p. 4. "We are juſt beginning to catch a glimpſe of the laws of animal Nature; <hi>and now when the human mind ſeems in ſo many countries <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> be rouſed from that torpor, by which it has ſo long been benumbed, we may reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably indulge the expectation of a rapid progreſs in this the moſt beneficial of all the ſciences.</hi> An infinitely ſmall portion of genius has hitherto been exerted to diminiſh the ſum of our painful ſenſations; <hi>and the force of ſociety has been excluſively at the diſpoſal of Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pots and Juntos, the great Artificers of human Evil. Should an entire change in theſe two reſpects any where take place, every member of ſociety might ſoon expect to experience in his own perſon the conſequence of ſo happy an innovation; and ſhould the example be generally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, there is no improvement in the condition of the World, for which we might not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> from the bloodleſs rivalſhip of Nations.</hi>" But we are told, that the ſame influence of Liberty and Genius will not only in other reſpects effect equal wonders, but produce greater bleſſings. "We know," exclaims this egregious Chymiſt, "that vegetables are capable of forming oils either exactly the ſame as thoſe of Animals, or very nearly reſembling them. Thus we have the ſuet of the Croton Sebiferum, the butter of the Phoenix Dactylifera and of the Butyrum Cacao. <hi>When, from a more intimate acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with them, we ſhall be better able to apply the Laws of organic bodies to the accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation as well as preſervation of Life, may we not, by regulating the vegetable functions, teach our woods and hedges to ſupply us with Butter and Tallow?</hi>" Obſervations on Calculus, &amp;c. p. 109.</note> No more the lazy Ox ſhall gormandize,</l>
               <l>And ſwell with fattening graſs his monſtrous ſize;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:1234500700:5"/>
No more trot round and round the groaning field,</l>
               <l>But tons of Beef our loaded Thickets yield!</l>
               <l>The patient Dairy-Maid no more ſhall learn</l>
               <l>With tedious toil to whirl the frothy Churn;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:1234500700:6"/>
But from the Hedges ſhall her Dairy fill,</l>
               <l>As pounds of Butter in big drops diſtil!</l>
               <l>The ſottiſh Jews, who in a God believ'd,</l>
               <l>And ſometimes bleſſings, oftener plagues receiv'd,</l>
               <l>Shouted a Miracle, when on the ground</l>
               <l>Their boaſted bread the greedy grumblers found:</l>
               <l>By no dry cruſts ſhall Infidels be fed,</l>
               <l>Our ſoil producing Butter to our Bread!</l>
               <l>See reverend Thames, who God of Rivers reigns,</l>
               <l>And winds meand'ring through our richeſt plains,</l>
               <l>To treat the Cits, that many a ſixpence give</l>
               <l>Once in a week like Gentlemen to live,</l>
               <l>Reſign his majeſty of mud, and ſtream</l>
               <l>O'er ſtrawberry beds in deluges of <hi>Cream!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>See Tallow Candles tip the modeſt Thorn,</l>
               <l>Candles of Wax the prouder Elm adorn!</l>
               <l>See the dull Clown ſurvey with ſtupid ſtare</l>
               <l>Where Leaves once grew, now periwigs of Hair!</l>
               <l>While fluids, which a wondrous change betray,</l>
               <l>Ooze from the vernal bud, the ſummer ſpray,</l>
               <l>Differing from animals alone in name,</l>
               <l>(As Botaniſts already half exclaim).</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:1234500700:7"/>
See plants, ſuſceptible of joy and woe,</l>
               <l>Feel all we feel, and know whate'er we know!</l>
               <l>View them like us inclin'd to watch or ſleep,</l>
               <l>Like us to ſmile, and, ah! like us to weep!</l>
               <l>Like us behold them glow with warm deſire,</l>
               <l>And catch from Beauty's glance celeſtial fire!</l>
               <l>Then, oh! ye fair, if through the ſhady grove</l>
               <l>Muſing on abſent Lovers you ſhould rove,</l>
               <l>And there with tempting ſtep all heedleſs bruſh</l>
               <l>Too near ſome wanton metamorphos'd Buſh,</l>
               <l>Or only hear perchance the weſtern breeze</l>
               <l>Steal murmuring through the animated Trees,</l>
               <l>Beware, beware, leſt to your coſt you find</l>
               <l>The Buſhes dangerous, dangerous too the Wind,</l>
               <l>Leſt, ah! too late with ſhame and grief you feel</l>
               <l>What your fictitious Pads would ill conceal!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>While Plants turn Animals, Man, happy Man,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">"If this ſuppoſition were juſt, might not ſome means be diſcovered to protract the period of Youth and Vigour <hi>indefinitely?</hi> Whether true or falſe, and even though we ſhould never be able to reſtore new excitability to the ſyſtem, there can be no doubt of the immediate practicability of prolonging Life conſiderably; and what is much more deſirable, of maintaining a firmer ſtate of Health." <hi>Obſervations on Calculus,</hi> &amp;c. p. 106. "Nor, however remote Medicine may be at preſent from ſuch perfection, do I ſee any reaſon to doubt, that by taking advantage of various and continual acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as they accrue to Science, the ſame power may be acquired over living as is at preſent exerciſed over ſome inanimate bodies; and that not only the cure and preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of diſeaſes, but <hi>the art of protracting the faireſt ſeaſon of Life, and rendering Health more vigorous,</hi> will one day half realize the dream of Alchemy!" <hi>Beddoes's Letter to Darwin,</hi> p. 29.</note> To ages ſhall extend Life's lengthen'd ſpan.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1234500700:8"/>
Bane to our bliſs, no more the wrinkled face</l>
               <l>Beauty's bewitching circles ſhall diſgrace;</l>
               <l>But ſee the reigning Toaſt half kind, half coy,</l>
               <l>Her Rivals' envy, and her Lover's Joy,</l>
               <l>Skill'd to allure, to charm us, and beguile,</l>
               <l>In all the bloom of Eighty ſit and ſmile!</l>
               <l>Thus ſhall each Belle a lovely L'ENCLOS prove,</l>
               <l>Drive Boys of future Cent'ries mad with love;</l>
               <l>The Marriage Table its degrees extend,</l>
               <l>And to our great, great Grandmother aſcend.</l>
               <l>Poor POPE, who griev'd "that Life could ſcarce ſupply</l>
               <l>"More than to look about him, and to die,"</l>
               <l>Had he but flouriſh'd in theſe Halcyon days,</l>
               <l>Might long have bid Life's little Candle blaze,</l>
               <l>Have grown ſtrait, handſome, briſk and debonnair,</l>
               <l>The Muſes' favourite, favourite of the Fair!</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:1234500700:9"/>
Happy the Poet's lot, who can prolong,</l>
               <l>Till time ſhall be no more, his deathleſs ſong;</l>
               <l>And live himſelf to ſee his ſwelling name</l>
               <l>Roll, like a Snowball, gathering all its fame!</l>
               <l>Happy, thrice happy he, who at his will</l>
               <l>Can drink of Life's ſweet cup his conſtant fill;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Dr. Beddoes, in a little tract addreſſed to the Author of this Epiſtle, entertains us with a long hiſtory of how he made himſelf very lean, very fair (his complexion having been before of an uniform brown), very pretty, and very conſumptive, by the uſe of a certain "Coſmetic" called <hi>Oxygenous Air</hi>; and how he afterwards cured himſelf of the ſaid Leanneſs and Conſumption at his Friend's, Quaker Reynolds's, in Colnbrook Dale, by a diet in which <hi>Butter and Cream</hi> bore the largeſt proportions. See pages 50, 51, 52, 53, 54, and 55.</note> Who, if exceſs of Oxygene create</l>
               <l>Symptoms, which lean Conſumption indicate,</l>
               <l>A ſure ſpecific can procure with eaſe,</l>
               <l>Rich Cream and Butter from his herd of Trees:</l>
               <l>Or if he find exceſs of <note n="†" place="bottom">To prevent our Sailors from growing fat, and afterwards falling into the Scurvy (of which Obeſity, we are informed, is the firſt ſymptom), Dr. Beddoes propoſes that the jolly Tars ſhould eat their food <hi>raw! Obſervations,</hi> p. 60.</note> Hydrogene</l>
               <l>His body load with fat, his mind with ſpleen,</l>
               <l>True health and vigour to reſtore, can take</l>
               <l>From ſome regenerate Oak a ſavoury ſteak,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:1234500700:10"/>
Sliced off the ſlaughter'd Monſter's quondam ſtump,</l>
               <l>Converted now into a real Rump,</l>
               <l>And, bleſt with an accommodating maw,</l>
               <l>Devour the luſcious bit, red, recent, raw!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now riſe, my Muſe, and, warm with rapture, dart</l>
               <l>From Men to Manners, "Fancy to the Heart."</l>
               <l>Tranſporting ſight! to view the Sons of Pride</l>
               <l>Their little heads with ſhame and ſorrow hide,</l>
               <l>Ranks and Diſtinctions ceaſe, all reeking lie</l>
               <l>In the mean muck of low Equality!</l>
               <l>Favourites of freedom, Sons of friſky France,</l>
               <l>Who never learnt like Britiſh Bears to dance,</l>
               <l>And, while their Premier's humdrum Bagpipes ſound,</l>
               <l>Led by the noſe, jog growling round and round;</l>
               <l>But more like Monkeys, airy, light, and gay,</l>
               <l>Pleas'd on your Maſter's head to ſkip and play;</l>
               <l>Ye pious Atheiſts, Moraliſts, who deem</l>
               <l>The Chriſtian's Heaven and Hell an idle Dream,</l>
               <l>Delighted to deride all vulgar fears</l>
               <l>Of Beelzebub's black Claws, cropt Tail, and Ears,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:1234500700:11"/>
With manly Scorn and Dignity to tread</l>
               <l>On proſtrate Superſtition's hoary head;</l>
               <l>Who, foes to Power Deſpotic, dare defy</l>
               <l>The King of Kings, that Bugbear of the ſky;</l>
               <l>Dreading for preſent crimes no future rod,</l>
               <l>Self-praiſe your worſhip, Vanity your God:</l>
               <l>Oh how my Eyes with tears ecſtatic fill,</l>
               <l>What new felt tranſports through my boſom thrill,</l>
               <l>When I behold you with gigantic blow</l>
               <l>The pigmy pride of Royalty lay low,</l>
               <l>With pikes and guns this moral dogma teach—</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Virtue conſiſts in nudity of Breech!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Soon ſhall we view no more the glittering Things</l>
               <l>Beſtarr'd, begarter'd, and befool'd by Kings;</l>
               <l>The pretty Twinklers that ſo ſweetly ſhone,</l>
               <l>And deem'd their lovely luſtre all their own!</l>
               <l>No more the Deſpot view, whoſe mighty nods</l>
               <l>Shook nature, and proclaim'd him God of Gods;</l>
               <l>Drunk with applauſe who rais'd his rolling Eyes,</l>
               <l>And ſeem'd, whene'er he mov'd, to tread the ſkies!</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:1234500700:12"/>
Deſpis'd, deteſted, all ſhall wing their flight,</l>
               <l>And ſink, no more to riſe, in endleſs night!</l>
               <l>Arm'd with a briſtled End and glittering Awl,</l>
               <l>Behold a minor Monarch in his Stall!</l>
               <l>No circling Gold his royal brow ſurrounds,</l>
               <l>A Yard of Room his ſphere of Action bounds;</l>
               <l>His ſole ambition and his prime purſuit,</l>
               <l>With ſkill a Shoe to patch, to ſtitch a Boot!</l>
               <l>Nor deem his fate ſevere! The time may come</l>
               <l>When many a pious King in Chriſtendom,</l>
               <l>Daſh'd from his throne, and made Dame Fortune's Fool,</l>
               <l>Shall envy little Capet's cobbling ſtool!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mark with the Peer and Prince the * canting Prieſt,</l>
               <l>Forbidden on his Country's fat to feaſt, <note n="*" place="bottom">"It is a law of human Nature, the leſs of eccleſiaſtical influence, the leſs of deadly animoſity among Men."—"It is reaſonable to preſume that the majority of French Prieſts in England partake of the Spirit of their Brethren; and to a large portion of the popiſh Prieſthood, Chriſtianity is believed, <hi>upon good grounds,</hi> to be as much <hi>fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> as it was to the Greeks. Their faith in the advantages of the immenſe emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which thoſe <hi>Reverend Robbers,</hi> their predeceſſors, had extorted from ſuperſtitious Barbarians, never ſuffered any abatement; hence probably that conduct to which their ſufferings are to be imputed."—"Through all the calumny that has been vomited forth againſt the French, the moſt injured and moſt enlightened people upon Earth, it is eaſy to diſcern <hi>ſome</hi> advantages which the Nation owes to Liberty—Tythes, <hi>the accurſed relic of Popery,</hi> have been aboliſhed.—France is purged not only from <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Drones,</hi> which conſumed the ſweeteſt honey of the hive, but alſo from the monſtrous debauchery of the richer, and the beggarly inſolence of the poorer Nobleſſe."—Dr. Beddoes's admirable <hi>Reaſons for believing the friends of Liberty in France not to be the Authors or Abettors of the crimes committed in that Country; humbly addreſſed to thoſe who from time to time conſtitute themſelves Judges and Jury upon affairs public and private and, without admitting any teſtimony but the groſs lies of Beldame Rumour, damn their Neighbours individually, and the reſt of the World by the Lump</hi>; the celebrated Hand bill circulated in Shropſhire, which eventually occaſioned his reſignation of the Chemical Chair in the Univerſity of Oxford.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:1234500700:13"/>
While peace looks down ſweet ſmiling on the ſwains,</l>
               <l>And untax'd Plenty crowns the fruitful plains!</l>
               <l>No more that lazy Lubbard ſhall we pay,</l>
               <l>With phiz ſo farcical to preach and pray;</l>
               <l>No more behold that Harpy of the land</l>
               <l>Lay on our largeſt ſheaves his greedy hand;</l>
               <l>With Bigotry's black banner wide unfurl'd,</l>
               <l>Fright into Gothic Ignorance the world:</l>
               <l>But Truth and Light ſhall come, with hoſtile rage,</l>
               <l>"To drive the holy Vandal off the ſtage."</l>
               <l>See Tythes expire, and ancient Slavery fail;</l>
               <l>Proud Superſtition turn her vanquiſh'd tail;</l>
               <l>No zealous Miniſter the Church befriend,</l>
               <l>But all her ſorceries with the Beldame end:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:1234500700:14"/>
Lo! Babylon is fallen! That myſtic —</l>
               <l>That Sink of Wickedneſs, is now no more!</l>
               <l>Great Babylon is fallen! Shout, ſhout, ye Meads!</l>
               <l>And, oh! ye Corn-fields, wave your happy heads!</l>
               <l>Ye lovely Lambkins, ſtrain your feeble voice,</l>
               <l>And with your Dams in loudeſt Baas rejoice!</l>
               <l>Calves, join your notes to ſwell the gladdening ſound!</l>
               <l>Cows, let your lowings from the ſkies rebound!</l>
               <l>Prolific Ducks, quack mid the mighty noiſe!</l>
               <l>Hens, more prolific, cackle out your joys!</l>
               <l>And ye, oh! Swine, lift up your little Eyes,</l>
               <l>With rapture riot round your rotten Styes!</l>
               <l>Stretch your triumphant throats, and ſtrive to make</l>
               <l>The frighten'd welkin with your Gruntings ſhake!</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
