<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The shadows of Shakespeare: a monody, occasioned by the death of Mr. Garrick. Being a prize poem, written for the vase at Bath-Easton. The second edition. By Courtney Melmoth.</title>
            <author>Pratt, Mr. (Samuel Jackson), 1749-1814.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>22 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009 October</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004778005</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">N22364</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW112079756</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K013036.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3312079756</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECLL</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">0302201700</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The shadows of Shakespeare: a monody, occasioned by the death of Mr. Garrick. Being a prize poem, written for the vase at Bath-Easton. The second edition. By Courtney Melmoth.</title>
                  <author>Pratt, Mr. (Samuel Jackson), 1749-1814.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2],5-24p. ; 4⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and sold by R. Cruttwell: sold also by Messrs. Bull, Taylor, Sheldon, Tennent, and Shrimpton, in Bath; and by E. and C. Dilly, London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Bath :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1780?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Courtney Melmoth = Samuel Jackson Pratt.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the Harvard University Houghton Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCN22364.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:0302201700:1"/>
            <p>THE SHADOWS of SHAKESPEARE: A MONODY, OCCASIONED BY THE <hi>DEATH of Mr. GARRICK.</hi> BEING APRIZE POEM, WRITTEN FOR THE VASE AT BATH-EASTON. THE SECOND EDITION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY COURTNEY MELMOTH.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>That you may ſee</l>
               <l>His Shadows, as they paſs.</l>
            </q>
            <bibl>SHAKESPEARE.</bibl>
            <p>BATH: Printed and Sold by R. CRUTTWELL: Sold alſo by Meſſrs, BULL, TAYLOR, SHELDON, TENNENT, and SHRIMPTON, Bookſellers, in Bath; and by E. and C. DILLY, in the Poultry, London.</p>
            <p>[PRICE ONE SHILLING.]</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:0302201700:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Juſt Publiſhed, <hi>By the ſame AUTHOR,</hi> In THREE POCKET VOLUMES, Price 7s. 6d. ſew'd, Embelliſhed with a beautiful FRONTISPIECE, SHENSTONE-GREEN: OR, THE NEW PARADISE LOST. BEING <hi>A HISTORY of HUMAN NATURE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Had I a Fortune of Eight or Ten Thouſand Pounds a Year, I would build myſelf a Neighbourhood.</q>
            <bibl>SHENSTONE.</bibl>
            <p>Printed for R. BALDWIN, No. 47, in Pater-noſter-Row, LONDON; and to be had of the BATH BOOKSELLERS.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:0302201700:3"/>
            <head>THE SHADOWS OF SHAKESPEARE.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>SOON as the breath of Rumour blew</l>
               <l>This ſolemn theme into the general ear,</l>
               <l>To holy Solitude I flew,</l>
               <l>And bade the Muſe her ſympathy prepare!</l>
               <l>There cloſeted with <hi>Thought,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The brain its ſhapeleſs travail wrought!</l>
               <l>The ſeaſon to the ſubject ſolemnly did ſuit:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:0302201700:4"/>
Day's dazzling orb was wholly down;</l>
               <l>Pale Cynthia ſat upon her ſilver throne;</l>
               <l>Th' obtruſions of the light were clos'd</l>
               <l>It ſeem'd, as SILENCE <hi>ſelf</hi> repos'd,</l>
               <l>For with the Air, the Earth and all her ſons were mute:</l>
               <l>All but the <hi>wretched,</hi> who like me,</l>
               <l>The gentle vigils kept of ſympathy.</l>
               <l>With cordial awe I hail'd the ſhading night,</l>
               <l>And kiſs'd her duſky robe which muffled thus the light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Baſe buſy World, begone, <hi>begone,</hi> I ſaid,</l>
               <l>To mighty GARRICK yield the ſerious mind,</l>
               <l>This awful <hi>Now</hi> be ſacred to the dead,</l>
               <l>And turn the cautious key on human kind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:0302201700:5"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>The Dead—ah, me!—<hi>what</hi> dead?—Here it began</l>
               <l>The florid Poet felt himſelf a Man.</l>
               <l>And is <hi>he</hi> dead, whoſe wonder-working art</l>
               <l>So often <hi>tore,</hi> and <hi>touch'd,</hi> and <hi>tun'd</hi> the heart?</l>
               <l>Whoſe piercing <hi>eye</hi> intelligence could give,</l>
               <l>And bid <hi>long-buried</hi> beings look and live?</l>
               <l>Whoſe voice enrich'd the verſe <hi>his Shakeſpeare</hi> writ,</l>
               <l>And gave to every word its weight of wit;</l>
               <l>No ſentence blemiſh'd, marr'd no golden line,</l>
               <l>But <hi>poliſh'd,</hi> as he drew it from the mine;</l>
               <l>Whoſe tongue grew wanton in his Shakeſpeare's cauſe,</l>
               <l>And gave to crowded Theatres their laws;</l>
               <l>Whoſe powerful accents, ſoften'd or ſublime,</l>
               <l>Free from all frippery, falſe pauſe, falſe chime,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:0302201700:6"/>
Chain'd, as to th' attracting centre, every ear;</l>
               <l>And, all commanding, ſawy'd the ſmile and tear:</l>
               <l>Is it to Him the Muſe muſt pay</l>
               <l>Her tributary lay?</l>
               <l>For <hi>him,</hi> muſt aching Memory pour the ſtrain,</l>
               <l>Muſt ſhe her darling GARRICK'S loſs complain?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>The heart was hurt—It could no more—</l>
               <l>Along each finer nerve ſwift ſhot the miſery,</l>
               <l>Even <hi>Nature</hi> ſhed her penſive ſhower;</l>
               <l>The mighty Mother wept, alas! with me:</l>
               <l>Th' imperial Goddeſs mourn'd her own decay,</l>
               <l>(Mix'd univerſal with our human clay)</l>
               <l>And wiſh'd ſhe could a <hi>ſecond</hi> birth beſtow</l>
               <l>On this her <hi>Repreſentative below.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:0302201700:7"/>
But, ah! it cannot be,</l>
               <l>So the rich debt was paid, to poor <hi>Humanity.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Then in the ſable ſtole of woe,</l>
               <l>All conſcious of the blow,</l>
               <l>Pale her cheek, her eye declining,</l>
               <l>Half obedient, half repining;</l>
               <l>Her viſage mark'd by many a tear,</l>
               <l>(Pour'd from the cryſtal ſource of grief ſincere)</l>
               <l>In awful ſtate,</l>
               <l>Unfortunate and great,</l>
               <l>MELPOMENE came on,</l>
               <l>Afflicted for her Son,</l>
               <l>And thrice, methought, the BOWL ſhe lifted high,</l>
               <l>And thrice ſhe threw on Heaven the pity-moving eye;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:0302201700:8"/>
Then, like the ſtatue of Deſpair,</l>
               <l>Stood fix'd—her DAGGER pois'd in air.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>Now 'twas THALIA firſt conceiv'd a <hi>pain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Twas now ſhe echo'd back her ſiſter's ſighs again;</l>
               <l>The jeſt, the laugh, the look, were o'er,</l>
               <l>Her cunning was no more;</l>
               <l>The comic mirth, the comic pride,</l>
               <l>Her wit, her whim, with GARRICK dy'd;</l>
               <l>Diſdainful then the maſk ſhe flung</l>
               <l>To vacant air—and thus forlorn ſhe ſung:</l>
               <l>And ah! away with random rhyme,</l>
               <l>Tinſel, ill-ſuited to the time;</l>
               <l>Away with leiſure's coxcomb line,</l>
               <l>The couplet quaint, the ſtanza fine;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:0302201700:9"/>
Far from <hi>our</hi> verſe be now the pun, the point,</l>
               <l>The period meaſured joint by joint;</l>
               <l>Th' elaborate <hi>trade</hi> of poeſy forbear—</l>
               <l>Or rather paint the workings of deſpair;</l>
               <l>Scorn the vain edging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able Verſe aſſumes,</l>
               <l>And let dark <hi>Elegy</hi> paſs on, in all her pompous plumes.</l>
               <l>The honour of the Dead in view,</l>
               <l>A juſter path will we purſue;</l>
               <l>SHAKESPEARE HIMSELF, who beſt our ſtate can feel,</l>
               <l>Shall the ſad tale in his <hi>own language</hi> tell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>Th' inſpiring Goddeſs, mortals FANCY name,</l>
               <l>With all her magic arm'd, now near me came</l>
               <l>Her waving wand, deep midnight deeper made,</l>
               <l>With her I went—to where our GARRICK laid.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:0302201700:10"/>
Cynthia lent a feeble ray,</l>
               <l>To light us on our way!</l>
               <l>FANCY with printleſs footſteps trod,</l>
               <l>As if advancing towards a GOD!</l>
               <l>Methought we eaſy entrance found,</l>
               <l>And the drear Abbey walk'd around.</l>
               <l>How fearful thus, ye Heavens! to tread,</l>
               <l>The dampſome vaults which cloſe the dead!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>But ſoft—</l>
               <l>As at the foot of mighty SHAKESPEARE'S tomb</l>
               <l>I kneel—ſudden along the fretted ailes</l>
               <l>Innumerous SHADY FORMS, by the pale moon's</l>
               <l>Imperfect beam beheld, — in various guiſe—</l>
               <l>(Each in the habit worn in days of Nature)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:0302201700:11"/>
Appear, and pour their potent ſpells upon me!</l>
               <l>Aw'd by a ſight ſo ſtrange, aloft I ſtood,</l>
               <l>And wiſt not what to do:—the figures <hi>mov'd!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>On near approach I knew them for the TRAIN</l>
               <l>Of SHAKESPEARE: In proceſſion ſad,</l>
               <l>Strait, one by one his hallow'd homage paid</l>
               <l>O'er GARRICK'S grave all bending.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <l>ARIEL firſt,</l>
               <l>(Not ſight-deceiving, as her cuſtom was,</l>
               <l>When in the bowels of the earth ſhe div'd;</l>
               <l>"Or mounted on the ſharp wind of the North,</l>
               <l>"Or on the curling clouds, or ſunny ray,</l>
               <l>"Nor like a ſpirit at eaſe") but with ſtep</l>
               <l>Deliberate—She, and her fellow-miniſters,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:0302201700:12"/>
("Brimful of ſorrow and diſmay") ſtood mute,</l>
               <l>Then gaz'd upon the grave, — then ſunk in ſighs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>X.</head>
               <l>PROSPERO,</l>
               <l>The great magician, next—(whoſe high command</l>
               <l>"Wak'd ſleepers in their graves, and let them forth")</l>
               <l>Beheld the vaniſhing inſtruments of 's art,</l>
               <l>And ſpake—</l>
               <l>"Have <hi>ye,</hi> which are but <hi>air,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"A touch, a feeling of our loſs extreme;</l>
               <l>"And ſhall not <hi>I,</hi> one of his <hi>kind,</hi> be <hi>kindlier?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Our revel then is done; and this our <hi>Actor</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Is no more! Loſt is the book of Conjuration:—</l>
               <l>"He regulated all our myſtic charms:—He's dead!</l>
               <l>"The cloud-capt tow'rs, the gorgeous palaces,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:0302201700:13"/>
"The ſolemn temples, the great globe itſelf;</l>
               <l>"Yea, all which it inherit, ſhall diſſolve,</l>
               <l>"And, like the baſeleſs fabrick of a viſion,</l>
               <l>"Leave not a wreck behind."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <l>He ſaid, and paſs'd.</l>
               <l>The <hi>weir'd Siſters</hi> then, hag-born and horrid,</l>
               <l>Mutter'd <hi>their</hi> melancholy homage hoarſe;</l>
               <l>Cold diſtillations of diſtreſs extreme</l>
               <l>Fell down the furrows of each wint'ry cheek:</l>
               <l>Thrice pac'd they piteous round the hallow'd earth,</l>
               <l>Acknowledging their Lord. To GARRICK'S grave,</l>
               <l>Bow'd every <hi>ſwarthy She.</hi>—To end their rites,</l>
               <l>Imagination's OWL flapp'd her fell wing,</l>
               <l>And, wailing, ſhriek'd as 'croſs the dome ſhe ſlew:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:0302201700:14"/>
Sudden, the whirring wizards diſappear,</l>
               <l>And <hi>horſe</hi> themſelves upon the viewleſs winds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <l>The gentle ROMEO was the third which came;</l>
               <l>And oh! he ſaid, "Turn back dull Earth—ah, me!</l>
               <l>"Can I go forward when my <hi>friend</hi> is here?</l>
               <l>"It is even ſo—Then I defy you ſtars!</l>
               <l>"Romeo ſhall never <hi>more</hi> be Romeo now</l>
               <l>"His occupation's gone."—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <l>The noble CORIOLANUS was the fourth,</l>
               <l>Whoſe very ſhade look'd martial—firm he ſtrode,</l>
               <l>And thus with Roman dignity exclaim'd,</l>
               <l>In honour of the Dead:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:0302201700:15"/>
"<hi>My</hi> fame like <hi>thine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Demands an equal voice, an equal tongue:</l>
               <l>"All eyes ſpoke of thee, and the bleared ſights</l>
               <l>"Were ſpectacled to ſee thee—the veil'd dames</l>
               <l>"Commit the wave of white and damaſk, in</l>
               <l>"Their nicely gauded cheeks, to th'wanton ſpoil</l>
               <l>"Of Phoebus' burning kiſſes: ſuch a pother,</l>
               <l>"As if that whatſoever God that tun'd thy throat</l>
               <l>"Were ſlyly crept into thy human powers,</l>
               <l>"To give thee grace and poſture. Oft, great ſhade!</l>
               <l>"The dumb men throng'd to <hi>ſee</hi> thee, and the blind</l>
               <l>"To <hi>hear</hi> thee ſpeak. To thee have Nobles bended,</l>
               <l>"As to Jove's Statue; and the Commons made</l>
               <l>"A ſhower and thunder with their caps and ſhouts</l>
               <l>"As ne'er were ſeen the like."—The ſoldier paſs'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:0302201700:16"/>
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <l>The fifth ſad ſpirit that ſtalk'd by was LEAR'S,</l>
               <l>Mad as the vext ſea ſtill; and ſinging oft;</l>
               <l>Crown'd, as of old, by Shakeſpeare's hand; with fumiter,</l>
               <l>With hardocks, hemlocks, nettles, cuckoo flowers,</l>
               <l>Darnel, and all the idle weeds that grow</l>
               <l>In the ſuftaining corn—</l>
               <l>At ſight of GARRICK'S tomb his wounds again</l>
               <l>Bled freſh. Tottering he mov'd; his words were wild.</l>
               <l>"You do me wrong to call me out o' th' grave!</l>
               <l>"And yet I know thee, Man!—Heav'n has thee now!</l>
               <l>"Thou wer't Lear's friend.—In faith I do remember.—</l>
               <l>"Yes, we were both as ſtout a pair:—but why</l>
               <l>"This truant diſpoſition? Is the <hi>greateſt</hi> man</l>
               <l>"So poor and forked an animal in death?—</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:0302201700:17"/>
"Off, off, you lendings, come unbutton here—Poor ſhade!</l>
               <l>"No more of that, no more of that.—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <l>The figure ſwift ſucceeding was the THANE'S,</l>
               <l>Languid and penitent.—His hand he wav'd</l>
               <l>As 'twere in honour of the man, whoſe voice</l>
               <l>Did blow his baſe deſign in every ear:</l>
               <l>Malice was dead within him, and he wept;</l>
               <l>Then ſtriking thrice his boſom, <hi>thus</hi> he cried:</l>
               <l>"Oh Nature! how thyſelf thou blazon'dſt</l>
               <l>"In this thy Son; form'd in thy prodigality</l>
               <l>"To hold <hi>thy</hi> mirror up, and give the time</l>
               <l>"Its very <hi>form</hi> and <hi>preſſure:</hi>—when he ſpoke</l>
               <l>"Each <hi>aged</hi> ear play'd truant at his tales,</l>
               <l>"And <hi>younger</hi> hearers were quite raviſh'd;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:0302201700:18"/>
"So valuable was his diſcourſe.—Yet, being dead,</l>
               <l>"I am a man again!"—He ruſh'd along.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <l>The gallant ANTHONY then onward ſtrode</l>
               <l>And paus'd—as 'erſt o'er Caeſar's corſe:—then ſpake:</l>
               <l>"Thou art the ruins of the nobleſt man</l>
               <l>"That ever liv'd in the tide of Times!</l>
               <l>"Here was an Actor—when comes ſuch ANOTHER?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <l>The next a <hi>female</hi> form, of PERCY's line,</l>
               <l>A race for ever noble—thus <hi>her</hi> tribute gave:</l>
               <l>—"Thou wert the very glaſs</l>
               <l>"Wherein the nobleſt youth did <hi>dreſs</hi> themſelves;</l>
               <l>"There were no <hi>legs</hi> that practis'd not <hi>thy gait;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:0302201700:19"/>
"There were no <hi>eyes</hi> that practis'd not thy looks;</l>
               <l>"Even thoſe that ſpoke but low and tardily</l>
               <l>"Would turn their own <hi>perfections</hi> to abuſe,</l>
               <l>"To ſeem like Thee: So that in ſpeech, in gait,</l>
               <l>"In accents, and affections of delight,</l>
               <l>"Thou wert the mark and glaſs, copy and book,</l>
               <l>"To faſhion others; and on <hi>thee,</hi> as on</l>
               <l>"<hi>My</hi> Harry and the Sun, bright <hi>Honour</hi> ſtuck,</l>
               <l>"As ſticks the Sun in the grey vault of Heaven."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <l>And now, the melancholy JAQUES advanc'd,</l>
               <l>And, full of matter, thus in few, exclaim'd:</l>
               <l>"Why all the World's a ſtage,</l>
               <l>"And all the Men and Women merely players:</l>
               <l>"They have their <hi>exits</hi> and their entrances;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:0302201700:20"/>
"And THIS MAN, in his time, play'd many parts.</l>
               <l>"<hi>Life!</hi> No more on't; it is a tale, told</l>
               <l>"By an idiot, ſignifying nothing."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="19">
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <l>At laſt, with philoſophic ſtep,</l>
               <l>Swift-ſtreaming eye, and arms entwined cloſe,</l>
               <l>The ſacred ſhade of his OWN HAMLET came:</l>
               <l>Long time he paus'd—long time around he look'd,</l>
               <l>Then fix'd his view upon the grave, and ſpoke:</l>
               <l>"'Tis not <hi>now, ſeems;</hi> in verity, it <hi>is;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Oh, what a grace was ſeated on that brow!</l>
               <l>"An <hi>eye,</hi> like Mars, to threaten or command;</l>
               <l>"A combination and a form indeed,</l>
               <l>"Where every God did ſeem to ſet his ſeal,</l>
               <l>"To give the world aſſurance of a Man!</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:0302201700:21"/>
"And is it come to this?—but huſh, my heart!</l>
               <l>"He was a Man, take him for all in all,</l>
               <l>"We may not look upon his like aga</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <l>While wrapt in wonder of theſe various ſhews</l>
               <l>The ſovereign ſhade of SHAKESPEARE awful roſe,</l>
               <l>His many-colour'd wand he wav'd,</l>
               <l>And ſoon the mournful train again were grav'd.</l>
               <l>(Now was His genius even more divine,)</l>
               <l>And all <hi>alone</hi> he ſtood before <hi>his</hi> GARRICK'S ſhrine.</l>
               <l>Reſt, reſt, perturbed ſpirits, then, he ſaid,</l>
               <l>To <hi>me</hi> belongs th'ineſtimable dead;</l>
               <l>To each 'tis given to breathe, to fall;</l>
               <l>'Tis the fix'd lot of all that ſoar or crawl.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:0302201700:22"/>
For <hi>Thee,</hi> much honour'd friend,</l>
               <l>What glories mark'd thy end!</l>
               <l>Applauding nations own thy fame,</l>
               <l>And, with their SHAKSPEARE'S, blend their GARRICK'S name.</l>
               <l>Together then we mount on high,</l>
               <l>'Tis OUR'S to TRIUMPH, 'tis the WORLD'S to SIGH.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
