<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>One thousand seven hundred and thirty eight. Dialogue II. By Mr. Pope</title>
            <author>Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>15 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007 January</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004809310</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T5725</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW111252252</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K023175.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3311252252</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECLL</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">0277200200</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>One thousand seven hundred and thirty eight. Dialogue II. By Mr. Pope</title>
                  <author>Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R. Reilly. For G. Risk, G. Ewing, W. Smith, and G. Faulkner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1738.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Foxon, P940</note>
                  <note>Griffith, 496</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT5725.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:0277200200:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ONE THOUSAND
SEVEN HUNDRED
AND
THIRTY EIGHT.</p>
            <p>DIALOGUE II.</p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>POPE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>DUBLIN:</hi>
Printed by R. REILLY. For G. RISK, G. EWING, W. SMITH, and
G. FAULKNER, Bookſellers. MDCCXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:0277200200:2"/>
            <head>ONE THOUSAND
SEVEN HUNDRED
AND
THIRTY EIGHT.</head>
            <head>DIALOGUE II.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> TIS IS all a Libel—<hi>P<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>_…</desc>
                     </gap>xt<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>_…</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> (Sir) will ſay.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> Not' yet, my Friend! to-morrow
'faith it may;</l>
               <l>And for that very cauſe I print to day.</l>
               <l>How ſhou'd I fret, to mangle ev'ry line,</l>
               <l>In rev'rence to the Sins of <hi>Thirty-nine!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vice with ſuch Giant-ſtrides comes on amain,</l>
               <l>Invention ſtrives to be before in vain;</l>
               <l>Feign what I will, and paint it e'er ſo ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Some riſing Genius ſins up to my Song.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:0277200200:3"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yet none but you by Name the Guilty laſh;</l>
               <l>Ev'n <note n="*" place="bottom">The Ordinary of <hi>Newgate,</hi> who publiſhes the Memoirs of the Malefactors</note>
                  <hi>Guthry</hi> ſaves half <hi>Newgate</hi> by a Daſh.</l>
               <l>Spare then the Perſon, and expoſe the Vice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> How Sir! not damn the Sharper, but the Dice?</l>
               <l>Come on then Satire! gen'ral, unconfin'd,</l>
               <l>Spread thy broad wing, and ſowze on all the Kind.</l>
               <l>Ye Stateſmen, Prieſts, of one Religion all!</l>
               <l>Ye Tradeſmen vile, in Army, Court, or Hall!</l>
               <l>Ye Rev'rend Atheiſts!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Scandal! name them, Who?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> Why that's the thing you bid me not to do.</l>
               <l>Who ſtarv'd a Mother, who forſwore a Debt,</l>
               <l>I never nam'd—the Town's enquiring yet.</l>
               <l>The pois'ning Dame—<hi>A.</hi> You mean—<hi>B.</hi> I don't. <hi>A.</hi> You do.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> See! now I keep the Secret, and not you.</l>
               <l>The bribing Stateſman—<hi>A.</hi> Hold! too high you go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> The brib'd Elector—<hi>A.</hi> There you ſtoop too low.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> I fain wou'd pleaſe you, if I knew with what:</l>
               <l>Tell me, which Knave is lawful Game, which not?</l>
               <l>Muſt great Offenders, once eſcap'd the Crown,</l>
               <l>Like Loyal Harts, be never more run down?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:0277200200:4"/>
Admit your Law to ſpare the Knight requires;</l>
               <l>As Beaſts of Nature may we hunt the Squires?</l>
               <l>Suppoſe I cenſure—you know what I mean—</l>
               <l>To ſave a Biſhop, may I name a Dean?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Dean, Sir? no: his Fortune is not made,</l>
               <l>You hurt a man that's riſing in the Trade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> If not the Tradeſman who ſets up to day,</l>
               <l>Much leſs the 'Prentice who to morrow may.</l>
               <l>Down, down, proud Satire! tho' a Land be ſpoil'd,</l>
               <l>Arraign no mightier Thief than wretched <note n="*" place="bottom">Jonathan Wild.</note>
                  <hi>Wild,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or if a Court or Country's made a Job,</l>
               <l>Go drench a Pick-pocket, and join the Mob.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But Sir, I beg you, for the Love of Vice!</l>
               <l>The matter's weighty, pray conſider twice:</l>
               <l>Have you leſs Pity for the needy Cheat,</l>
               <l>The poor and friendleſs Villian, than the Great?</l>
               <l>Alas! the ſmall Diſcredit of a Bribe</l>
               <l>Scarce hurts the Lawyer, but undoes the Scribe.</l>
               <l>Then better ſure it Charity becomes,</l>
               <l>To tax Directors, who (thank God) have Plums;</l>
               <l>Still better, Miniſters; or if the thing</l>
               <l>May pinch ev'n there—why lay it on a King.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:0277200200:5"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Stop! ſtop!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> Muſt Satire, then, nor <hi>riſe,</hi> nor <hi>fall</hi>?</l>
               <l>Speak out, and bid me blame no Rogues at all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, ſtrike that <hi>Wild,</hi> I'll juſtify the blow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> Strike? why the man was hang'd ten years ago:</l>
               <l>Who now that obſolete Example fears?</l>
               <l>Ev'n <hi>Peter</hi> trembles only for his Ears.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> What always <hi>Peter? Peter</hi> thinks you mad,</l>
               <l>You make men deſp'rate if they once are bad:</l>
               <l>Elſe might he take to Virtue ſome years hence—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> As <hi>S<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>_…</desc>
                     </gap>k,</hi> if he lives, will love the PRINCE.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Strange ſpleen to <hi>S<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>_…</desc>
                     </gap>k</hi>!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> Do I wrong the Man?</l>
               <l>God knows, I praiſe a Courtier where I can.</l>
               <l>When I confeſs, there <hi>is</hi> who feels for Fame,</l>
               <l>And melts to Goodneſs, need I SCARBROW name?</l>
               <l>Pleas'd let me own, in <hi>Eſher</hi>'s peaceful Grove<note n="*" place="bottom">The Houſe and Gardens of <hi>Eſher</hi> in <hi>Surry,</hi> deſign'd by Mr. <hi>Kent.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>(Where <hi>Kent</hi> and Nature vye for PELHAM's Love)</l>
               <l>The Scene, the Maſter, opening to my view,</l>
               <l>I fit and dream I ſee my CRAGS anew!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:0277200200:6"/>
               <l>Ev'n in a Biſhop I can ſpy Deſert;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Secker</hi> is decent, <hi>Rundel</hi> has a Heart,</l>
               <l>Manners with Candour are to <hi>Benſon</hi> giv'n,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Berkley,</hi> ev'ry Virtue under Heav'n.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But does the Court a worthy Man remove?</l>
               <l>That inſtant, I declare he has my Love:</l>
               <l>I ſhun his Zenith, court his mild decline;</l>
               <l>Thus SOMMERS once, and HALIFAX were mine.</l>
               <l>Oft in the clear, ſtill Mirrour of Retreat,</l>
               <l>I ſtudy'd SHREWSBURY, the wiſe and great:</l>
               <l>CARLETON's calm Senſe, and STANHOPE's noble Flame</l>
               <l>Compar'd, and knew their gen'rous End the ſame:</l>
               <l>How pleaſing ATTERBURY's ſofter hour!</l>
               <l>How ſhin'd the Soul, unconquer'd in the Tow'r!</l>
               <l>How can I PULT'NEY, CHESTERFIELD forget,</l>
               <l>While <hi>Roman</hi> Spirit charms, and <hi>Attic</hi> Wit:</l>
               <l>ARGYLE, the States whole Thunder born to wield,</l>
               <l>And ſhake alike the Senate and the Field:</l>
               <l>Or WYNDHAM, arm'd for Freedom and the Throne,</l>
               <l>The Maſter of our Paſſions, and his own.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:0277200200:7"/>
Names, which I long have lov'd, nor lov'd in vain,</l>
               <l>Rank'd with their Friends, not number'd with their Train;</l>
               <l>And if yet higher the proud Liſt ſhould end,</l>
               <l>Still let me ſay! No Follower, but a Friend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet think not Friendſhip only prompts my Lays;</l>
               <l>I follow <hi>Virtue,</hi> where ſhe ſhines, I praiſe,</l>
               <l>Point ſhe to Prieſt or Elder, Whig or Tory,</l>
               <l>Or round a Quaker's Beaver caſt a Glory.</l>
               <l>I never (to my ſorrow I declare)</l>
               <l>Din'd with the MAN of ROSS, or my <note n="*" place="bottom">Sir John Barnard.</note>LORD MAY'R.</l>
               <l>Some, in their choice of Friends (nay, look not grave)</l>
               <l>Have ſtill a ſecret Byaſs to a Knave:</l>
               <l>To find an honeſt man, I beat about,</l>
               <l>And love him, court him, praiſe him, in or out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Then why ſo few commended?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> Not ſo fierce;</l>
               <l>Find you the Virtue, and I'll find the Verſe.</l>
               <l>But random Praiſe—the Taſk can ne'er be done,</l>
               <l>Each Mother aſks it for her Booby Son,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:0277200200:8"/>
Each Widow aſks it for the Beſt of Men,</l>
               <l>For him ſhe weeps, and him ſhe weds again.</l>
               <l>Praiſe cannot ſtoop, like Satire, to the Ground;</l>
               <l>The Number may be hang'd, but not be crown'd.</l>
               <l>Enough for half the Greateſt of theſe days</l>
               <l>To 'ſcape my Cenſure, not expect my Praiſe:</l>
               <l>Are they not rich? what more can they pretend?</l>
               <l>Dare they to hope a Poet for their Friend?</l>
               <l>What <hi>Richlieu</hi> wanted, <hi>Louis</hi> ſcarce could gain,</l>
               <l>And what young <hi>Ammon</hi> wiſh'd, but wiſh'd in vain.</l>
               <l>No Pow'r the Muſe's Friendſhip can command;</l>
               <l>No Pow'r, when Virtue claims it, can withſtand:</l>
               <l>To <hi>Cato, Virgil</hi> pay'd one honeſt line;</l>
               <l>O let my Country's Friends illumin mine!</l>
               <l>—What are you thinking? <hi>A.</hi> Faith, the thought's no Sin,</l>
               <l>I think your Friends are out, and would be in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> If merely to come in, Sir, they go out,</l>
               <l>The way they take is ſtrangely round about.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They too may be corrupted, you'll allow?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> I only call thoſe Knaves, who are ſo now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:0277200200:9"/>
               <l>Is that too little? Come then, I'll comply—</l>
               <l>Spirit of <hi>Arnall!</hi> aid me while I lye.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cobbam</hi>'s a Coward, <hi>Polwarth</hi> is a Slave,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Lyttleton</hi> a dark, deſigning Knave,</l>
               <l>St. <hi>John</hi> has ever been a wealthy Fool—</l>
               <l>But let me add, Sir <hi>Robert</hi>'s mighty dull,</l>
               <l>Has never made a Friend in private life,</l>
               <l>And was, beſides, a Tyrant to his Wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But pray, when others praiſe him, do I blame?</l>
               <l>Call <hi>Clodius, Wolſey,</hi> any odious name?</l>
               <l>Why rail they then, if but a Wreath of mine</l>
               <l>Oh All-accompliſh'd St. <hi>John!</hi> deck thy Shrine?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What? ſhall each ſpur-gall'd Hackney of the Day,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Pax<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>_…</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> gives him double Pots and Pay,</l>
               <l>Or each new-penſion'd Sycophant, pretend</l>
               <l>To break my Windows, if I treat a Friend;</l>
               <l>Then wiſely plead, to me they meant no hurt,</l>
               <l>But 'twas my Gueſt at whom they threw the dirt?</l>
               <l>Sure, if I ſpare the Miniſter, no rules</l>
               <l>Of Honour bind me, not to maul his Tools;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:0277200200:10"/>
Sure, if they cannot cut, it may be ſaid</l>
               <l>His ſaws are toothleſs, and his Hatchets Lead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It anger'd <hi>Turenne,</hi> once upon a day,</l>
               <l>To ſee a Footman kick'd that took his pay:</l>
               <l>But when he heard th'Affront the Fellow gave,</l>
               <l>Knew one a Man of Honour, one a Knave;</l>
               <l>The prudent Gen'ral turn'd it to a jeſt,</l>
               <l>And begg'd, he'd take the pains to kick the reſt.</l>
               <l>Which not at preſent having time to do—</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Hold Sir! for God's ſake, where's th' Affront to you?</l>
               <l>Againſt your worſhip what has <hi>S<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>_…</desc>
                     </gap>k</hi> writ?</l>
               <l>When did <hi>Ty<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>_…</desc>
                     </gap>l</hi> hurt you with his Wit?</l>
               <l>Or grant, the Bard whoſe Diſtich all commend,</l>
               <l>[<hi>In Pow'r a Servant, out of Pow'r a Friend.</hi>]</l>
               <l>To <hi>W<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>_…</desc>
                     </gap>le</hi> guilty of ſome venial Sin,</l>
               <l>What's that to you, who ne'er was out nor in?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Prieſt whoſe Flattery be-dropt the Crown,</l>
               <l>How hurt he you? he only ſtain'd the Gown.</l>
               <l>And how did, pray the Florid Youth offend,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Speech you took, and gave it to a Friend?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:0277200200:11"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> Faith it imports not much from whom it came;</l>
               <l>Whoever borrow'd, could not be to blame,</l>
               <l>Since the whole Houſe did afterwards the ſame:</l>
               <l>Let Courtly Wits to Wits afford ſupply,</l>
               <l>As Hog to Hog in Huts of <hi>Weſtphaly</hi>;</l>
               <l>If one, thro' Nature's Bounty or his Lord's,</l>
               <l>Has what the frugal, dirty ſoil affords,</l>
               <l>From him the next receives it, thick or thin,</l>
               <l>As pure a Meſs almoſt as it came in;</l>
               <l>The bleſſed Benefit, not there confin'd,</l>
               <l>Drops to the third who nuzzles cloſe behind;</l>
               <l>From tail to mouth, they feed, and they carouſe;</l>
               <l>The laſt, full fairly gives it to the <hi>Houſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This filthy Simile, this beaſtly Line,</l>
               <l>Quite turns my Stomach—<hi>B.</hi> So does Flatt'ry mine;</l>
               <l>And all your Courtly Civet-Cats can vent,</l>
               <l>Perfume to you, to me is Excrement.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But hear me further—<hi>Japhet,</hi> 'tis agreed,</l>
               <l>Writ not, and <hi>Chartres</hi> ſcarce could write or read,</l>
               <l>In all the Courts of <hi>Pindus</hi> guiltleſs quite:</l>
               <l>But Pens can ſorge, my Friend, that cannot write.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:0277200200:12"/>
And muſt no Egg in <hi>Japhet</hi>'s Face be thrown,</l>
               <l>Becauſe the Deed he forg'd was not my own?</l>
               <l>Muſt never Patriot then declaim at Gin,</l>
               <l>Unleſs, good man! he has been fairly in?</l>
               <l>No zealous Paſtor blame a failing Spouſe,</l>
               <l>Without a ſtaring Reaſon on his Brows?</l>
               <l>And each Blaſphemer quite eſcape the Rod,</l>
               <l>Becauſe the inſult's not on Man, but God?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ask you what Provocation I have had?</l>
               <l>The ſtrong Antipathy of Good to Bad.</l>
               <l>When Truth or Virtue an Affront endures,</l>
               <l>Th' Affront is mine, my Friend, and ſhould be yours.</l>
               <l>Mine, as a Foe profeſs'd to falſe Pretence,</l>
               <l>Who think a Coxcomb's Honour like his Senſe;</l>
               <l>Mine, as a Friend to ev'ry worthy mind;</l>
               <l>And mine as Man, who feel for all mankind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> You're ſtrangely proud.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> So proud, I am no Slave;</l>
               <l>So impudent, I own myſelf no Knave:</l>
               <l>So odd, my Country's Ruin makes me grave.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:0277200200:13"/>
Yes, I am proud; I muſt be proud to ſee</l>
               <l>Men not afraid of God, afraid of me:</l>
               <l>Safe from the Bar, the Pulpit, and the Throne,</l>
               <l>Yet touch'd and ſham'd by <hi>Ridicule</hi> alone.</l>
               <l>O ſacred Weapon! left for Truth's defence,</l>
               <l>Sole dread of Folly, Vice, and Inſolence!</l>
               <l>To all but Heav'n-directed hands deny'd,</l>
               <l>The Muſe may give thee, but the Gods muſt guide.</l>
               <l>Rev'rent I touch thee! but with honeſt zeal;</l>
               <l>To rowze the Watchmen of the Publick Weal,</l>
               <l>To Virtue's Work provoke the tardy Hall,</l>
               <l>And goad the Prelate ſlumb'ring in his Stall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye tinſel Inſects! whom a Court maintains,</l>
               <l>That counts your Beauties only by your Stains,</l>
               <l>Spin all your Cobwebs o'er the Eye of Day!</l>
               <l>The Muſe's wing ſhall bruſh you all away:</l>
               <l>All his Grace preaches, all his Lordſhip ſings,</l>
               <l>All that makes Saints of Queens, and Gods of Kings,</l>
               <l>All, all bat Truth, drops dead born from the Preſs,</l>
               <l>Like the laſt Gazette, or the laſt Addreſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:0277200200:14"/>
               <l>When black Ambition ſtains a Publick Cauſe,</l>
               <l>A Monarch's ſword when mad Vain-glory draws,</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Waller</hi>'s Wreath can hide the Nation's Scar,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Boileau</hi> turn the <note n="†" place="bottom">In his Ode on <hi>Namur</hi>; where (to uſe his own words) <hi>il a fait un Aſtre de la Plume blanche qui le Roy porte ordinairement a ſon Chapeau, &amp; qui eſt en effet une eſpece de Comete, fatale a nos enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis.</hi>
                  </note> Feather to a Star.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not ſo, when diadem'd with Rays divine,</l>
               <l>Touch'd with the Flame that breaks from <hi>Virtue</hi>'s Shrine,</l>
               <l>Her Prieſteſs Muſe, forbids the Good to dye,</l>
               <l>And ope's the Temple of Eternity;</l>
               <l>There other <hi>Trophies</hi> deck the truly Brave,</l>
               <l>Than ſuch as <hi>Anſtis</hi> caſts into the Grave;</l>
               <l>Far other <hi>Stars</hi> than * and * *  wear,</l>
               <l>And may deſcend to <hi>Mor<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>_…</desc>
                     </gap>ton</hi> from <hi>Stair:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such as on <note n="*" place="bottom">Dr. <hi>Hough</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
                  </note>HOUGH's unſully'd Mitre ſhine,</l>
               <l>Or beam, good DIGBY! from a Heart like thine.</l>
               <l>Let Envy howl while Heav'ns whole Chorus ſings,</l>
               <l>And bark at Honour not conferr'd by Kings;</l>
               <l>Let Flatt'ry ſickening ſee the Incenſe riſe,</l>
               <l>Sweet to the World, and grateful to the Skies:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:0277200200:15"/>
Truth guards the Poet, ſanctifies the line,</l>
               <l>And makes Immortal, Verſe as mean as mine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yes, the laſt Pen for Freedom let me draw,</l>
               <l>When Truth ſtands trembling on the edge of Law:</l>
               <l>Here, Laſt of <hi>Briton's!</hi> let your Names be read;</l>
               <l>Are none, none living? let me praiſe the Dead,</l>
               <l>And for that Cauſe which made your Fathers ſhine,</l>
               <l>Fall, by the Votes of their degen'rate Line!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Alas! alas! pray end what you began,</l>
               <l>And write next winter more <hi>Eſſays</hi> on <hi>Man.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
