<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of some of the most romantic parts of North Wales</title>
            <author>Cradock, Joseph, 1742-1826.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>154 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008 September</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004794687</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T18894</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW102436473</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K029542.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3302436473</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECHG</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">0616900400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of some of the most romantic parts of North Wales</title>
                  <author>Cradock, Joseph, 1742-1826.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>iv,147,[1]p.,plates : map ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for T. Davies; and T. Cadell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1777.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Joseph Cradock.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT18894.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="map">
            <pb facs="tcp:0616900400:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of North Wales</figDesc>
                  <head>MAP of NORTH WALES</head>
                  <p>J. Barber delin. et Sculp.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:0616900400:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF SOME OF THE MOST ROMANTIC PARTS OF NORTH WALES.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Of Antres vaſt, and Deſarts idle,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ough Quarries, Rocks, and Hills, whoſe Heads touch Heav'n,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was my Hint to ſpeak.</l>
               <bibl>SHAKESPEARE.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rinted for T. DAVIES, Ruſſel-Street Covent-Garden; and T. CADELL, in the Strand. MDCCLXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:0616900400:3"/>
            <head>TO Sir WATKIN WILLIAMS WYNNE, Bart.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>EVERY one will ſee the propriety of dedicating an Account of North Wales to You, who poſſeſs ſo conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a part of that Country, and yet, Sir, this is not the motive of my Addreſs;—it is from a
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:0616900400:4"/>
high regard to that public and private Character which has hitherto been an ornament to Society, and which I truſt will continue to adorn the Age with thoſe Virtues, of which your Anceſtors were ſuch emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Examples.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I have the Honour to be, with great reſpect, Sir, your obedient ſervant, JOSEPH CRADOCK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:0616900400:5"/>
            <head>ARMS OF THE PRINCIPALITY.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:0616900400:6"/>
            <p>BRUTE gave to CAMBER his Third ſonne, CAMBRIA with theise Armes Tres Leones Gradientes facies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ad terga uertentes in Campo Argent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. In Frenche, <hi rend="blackletterType">Iſ portoit d'Argent trois Inons paſsants regardantes de Genſes,</hi> The which Armes the Kinges and Prynces of Wales and theire ofsprynge, used for a ſong tyme after, untill the Country was deuided into three distant Pryncypalytyes viz: <hi>North Wales South Wales</hi> and <hi>Powes Lande.</hi> And then they tooke seuerall Arme.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:0616900400:7"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms of Wales</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms of North Wales</figDesc>
                  <head>North Wales.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms of South Wales</figDesc>
                  <head>South Wales.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms of Powes Land</figDesc>
                  <head>Powes Land.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:0616900400:8"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF SOME OF THE MOST ROMANTIC PARTS OF NORTH WALES.</head>
            <p>AS every one now who has either traverſed a ſteep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ountain, or croſſed a ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>annel, muſt write his Tour, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould be almoſt unpardonable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Me to be totally ſilent, who
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:0616900400:9"/>
have viſited the moſt uninhabite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> regions of North Wales—wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have ſeen lakes, rivers, ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rocks, and precipices, at unmea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſurable diſtances, and who from obſervation and experience can in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>form the world, that high hill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are very difficult of acceſs, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the tops of them generally ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cold.</p>
            <p>But ancient Britain has a kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of hereditary claim upon me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I have the honour to boaſt of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> origin from thence; and as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:0616900400:10"/>
name and exploits of my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors continually occur through the wild heroic pages of Welſh fable or hiſtory.</p>
            <p>This journey was undertaken rather late in the autumn 1776; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſeaſon proved remarkably favourable, neither rains not winds impeded my progreſs—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he air on the mountains was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ft rarified by the ſummer's heat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſun ſhone out all the day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Cader, and Snowdon had not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:0616900400:11"/>
begun to fortify himſelf againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this almoſt winter approach.</p>
            <p>I ſet out from Shrewſbury fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Welſh Poole,—the laſt eigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miles afforded a moſt beautifu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proſpect of a rich vale in Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gomeryſhire. The Vales through out this county are remarkabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſant; but they have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo frequently deſcribed, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is almoſt ſuperfluous to obſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they abound with corn, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are luxuriant in paſturage.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:0616900400:12"/>Welſh Poole is a place of ſome note—it is one of the five Boroughs in Montgomeryſhire, which jointly ſend a member to Parliament. It has a good mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, but though the Severn is navigable within two miles of it, there is ſcarce ever any fiſh—even ſalmon is never under twelve pence a pound. It takes its name from a contemptible black pool, which is ſaid to be unfathomable, and of which there is a prophecy, that it ſhall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:0616900400:13"/>
ſome time or other overflow and deluge the town. This prophecy is ſtill believed in Wales.</p>
            <p>About a mile from hence ſtands Powis caſtle, or <hi>Red</hi> caſtle, from the colour of the ſtones of which it is built. The ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it is certainly very noble, but I cannot agree with Lord Lyttelton, that three thouſand pounds would make it the moſt auguſt place in the kingdom; there is much to be done in the mere approach, and at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:0616900400:14"/>
you are obliged to aſk where the Severn runs. The ground is laid out in that formal ſtyle of gardening, that was brought in at the Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and there will be much difficulty in altering it with propriety. A common Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker in Taſte, would imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately convert the clipt hedges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd true-love-knots, into a gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and unmeaning ſhrubbery, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut to decorate this place to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dvantage, the Genius of this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:0616900400:15"/>
place only muſt be conſulted, <q rend="inline">"th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Pope.</note> parts ſhould every where b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> connected with each other, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt likewiſe bear a referenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the whole."</q> On my retur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Poole, I ordered a carriage t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> convey me to Llanvair—this wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be my laſt ſtage on know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ground,—the road was perfectl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good, the people in general ſpok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Engliſh, and their civility was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> remarkable, that the very turn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pike man was grateful for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:0616900400:16"/>
toll. I was here moſt ſtrongly recommended to a good houſe, about twelve miles diſtant, but found it only a miſerable hut; I therefore preſſed onwards as faſt as poſſible, and after ſome difficulties arrived at Dynys-Mouthy.</p>
            <p>This City (for Dynys is Welſh for City) is poſſeſſed of many and great advantages; there is no body-corporate to divide it into faction, there is not a ſingle Office that can poſſibly be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:0616900400:17"/>
for—the rent of houſes will be the ſame at all ſeaſons and even in Auguſt you are ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver incommoded by the ſun The river is not large, but it wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> never be encroached upon by the inhabitants; their ſequeſtered walks will never be injured by any freſh Dealers in Taſte,—in deed they have only one tree to cut down, an oak planted in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reign of Charles the Second; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I believe they have never hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of any King ſince.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:0616900400:18"/>As to Faſhions, they are ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to thoſe in Town—the head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs of the Females is very high, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd in a morning they generally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear the Half Paloneſe<note n="†" place="bottom">Jackets and petticoats.</note>.</p>
            <p>The Inns too, like the London <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes, are dark and dirty, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere is very little noiſe in them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d as to proviſions, the people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not attempt to make what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e has not beſtowed upon them. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey gave me whatever they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:0616900400:19"/>
had, Bread, uncontaminated wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpurious mixtures, and Milk, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was abſolutely from the cow.</p>
            <p>I did not ſee a Cathedral, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heard of either biſhop or palace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> probably he might reſide at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great diſtance, and have conſigne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his flock over to a chapel of eaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>There is no court of judica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture open here. This city is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> free from attornies as ancie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Thebes; indeed the two neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> failing ſources of litigation, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Poor laws and the Game law
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:0616900400:20"/>
are entirely unknown. There is not even a Quack; ſo that thoſe whom liquor ſpares, generally die at a very advanced age.</p>
            <p>The Theatre is held in great repute. I had the pleaſure to be preſent at one play, which is here called an <hi>Anterlute,</hi> probably a corruption from our term Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude. The piece was ſaid to have been written by a celebrated Mr. Evan ſomething, who lived at Bala; but, from the <hi>actions, geſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and <hi>emblems,</hi> I conceived it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:0616900400:21"/>
to have been modelled from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Shakeſpeare's time. The plot was in part ſimilar to a burletta, which has frequently been exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited in London, called La Serva Padrona, but the muſic was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>not</hi> Pergolen. The or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſtra, to be ſure, was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly contracted; but we muſt reflect, that ſome of our beſt, as well as earlieſt dramas, were only accompanied by a Harp. The price of admittance to this ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant entertainment, would have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:0616900400:22"/>
been termed by the Romans, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narius.</p>
            <p>The road from Dynys Mouthy afforded but little amuſement, and the firſt caſt of Cader Idris greatly diſappointed me; but I ſoon recollected, that as I was then on very high ground, it muſt have been from ſome other point of view that this mountain had rendered itſelf ſo remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. In the courſe of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, I was on a ſudden de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with the country round
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:0616900400:23"/>
Dolgelly,—woods, rocks, a ric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vale, a fine river, and, at that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the appearance of rathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a decent town, ſurrounded wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> many gentlemen's ſeats,—theſe contraſted with the barrenneſs had juſt travelled through, al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> joined to render the proſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truly delicious. But how was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſguſted on my arrival at the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terior parts of this miſerable place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there is no ſtreet in it; you paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from dungeon to dungeon through a multiplicity of hog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:0616900400:24"/>
yards;—before I reached the inn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heard a cracked trumpet ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng every where about, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately concluded that I might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee, in the evening, another farce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>anterlute</hi>; but was informed it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as only intended to call the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſtices to the quarter-ſeſſions. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the inn there was nothing to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e obtained; ſo that as ſoon as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſible I ſent out for a Guide, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at I might retire to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ns;—whilſt I was in waiting, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nquired about the only toler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:0616900400:25"/>
building I then ſaw, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was told it was for <hi>cock-match<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſuch as we had in England;—that they were juſt over, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I might go immediately and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a famous man from London ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>tricks of ſlight of hand.</hi> I chie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> wiſhed for ſome refreſhme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> having greatly ſuffered from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigue and illneſs the preced<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> day; but as I was a ſtranger, people ſhewed me little or no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vility, and on my enquiring horſes, took every advantag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:0616900400:26"/>
my diſtreſs. I was now almoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nclined to have beſtowed upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem ſome rather ungracious epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hets; but I conſidered, that as we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>emed to be teaching them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing from England but <hi>cruelty</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>fraud,</hi> I ought rather to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent the cauſe than inſult the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect of their brutality.</p>
            <p>On the arrival of the Guide, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t out immediately for Cader <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ris, and found the tract ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>edingly good, till I came to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ominent part of the mountain,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:0616900400:27"/>
and here, I muſt acknowledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my head was too giddy ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciently to admire the amazin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſcene that was opening to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> view. At length, having gaine the ſummit, (the whole aſce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> being near three miles,) on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fine piece of level ground, I cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with comfort ſurvey the ſea, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Carnarvonſhire ſhore, Snowd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> without a cloud upon his to lakes, rivers, rocks, and precipi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which were every way ſpre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> before me;—at the bottom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:0616900400:28"/>
the hill, on the oppoſite ſide, was a ſmall Village, to which ſeveral were returning heavy loaden from Dolgelly market; this Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage is remarkable for nothing but the remains of a ſmall caſtle, whoſe miſerable ſituation could not ſecure it from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>predations of Cromwell's army. In the courſe of my ſurvey of the Mountain, it ſeemed to take a thouſand capricious forms, but the moſt wonderful part of it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he tremendous peak, which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hangs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:0616900400:29"/>
the Lake of the <note n="*" place="bottom">The common people believe theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> three large craggs to have been caſt out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſhoes of the giant Idris.</note> Thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Grains,—but here I ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bear deſcription, as a fine repre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſentation of it, has been latel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> executed, by the ingenious an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accurate pencil of Mr. Wilſon.—On my return I diſcovered, fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out of any tract, on the ſteepeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part of the hill, a man gathering rock-moſs to dye baizes red,—<q rend="inline">"dreadful trade!"</q> one coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:0616900400:30"/>
only exclaim;—this excreſcence is chiefly ſold to Dublin—it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords a moſt beautiful colour at firſt, and if mixed with proper ingredients and diſtilled, will, it is ſaid, become permanent. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very thirſty from heat and fatigue, I enquired for ſome goat's milk, but to no purpoſe; the Guide, however, informed me, that he could procure me, from a neighbouring cottage, a liquor, peculiar to that part of North Wales, which infinitely
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:0616900400:31"/>
exceeded Stirom cyder—I taſted it, and found it was made of mountain-aſh berries and crabs or ſloes<note n="*" place="bottom">The following lines have ſince occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to me:<q>
                     <l>"Then ſhe deſcribes</l>
                     <l>The Scythian winter, nor diſdains to ſing</l>
                     <l>How under ground the rude Riphaean race</l>
                     <l>Mimic briſk cyder with the brake's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct wild;</l>
                     <l>Sloes pounded, hips, and ſervis' harſheſt juice."</l>
                     <bibl>PHILIPS.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </note>,—it ſhould remain at leaſt half a year in the veſſel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is bottled off, and if it were then kept to a proper age, it would not be altogether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:0616900400:32"/>
The tediouſneſs of my return to Dolgelly, was ſomewhat beguiled by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequential information of the Guide, and I muſt own he great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertained, and at the ſame time ſhocked me with the reſpect he paid me as an Engliſh gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,—whenever he replied to Me, he thought it neceſſary to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nterlard his anſwer with fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent oaths, whereas I found when he ſpoke to my ſervant only, it was entirely in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adorned
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:0616900400:33"/>
ſtyle, without the leaſt diſplay of theſe ſenſible embel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhments.</p>
            <p>The next morning being Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, I went to eight o'clock prayers here—the area of the church is ſpacious, and the pews neat—there is a coving roof of wood which is neceſſary to aid th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> voice, as the floor is only clay covered deep with ruſhes; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> congregation was large, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſervice was read with devotion and tolerable propriety.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:0616900400:34"/>My ſtay was prolonged at Dolgelly, that the maſter of the Inn, who was abſent on my firſt arrival, and who was juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to me as an intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Perſon, might attend me to ſee the three wonderful water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls in this neighbourhood—one of them is in ſo obſcure a place, that the miniſter of an adjoining Pariſh, whom I after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards met with, had never till that time even heard of it:—about five miles on the road towards
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:0616900400:35"/>
Tan y Bwlch, we turned on the left hand to ſee the firſt, which I take to be a part of the river Dery—this is not more than fifty feet in height, but you may afterwards trace it, for near a mile, through crags and trees, before it reaches its rocky bed at the bottom; the others, are falls of whole rivers, the Moth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye and the Cayne, over the tops of two rocky moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains;—the former perhaps may not be above one hundred fee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:0616900400:36"/>
in height, but the latter is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly at leaſt an hundred yards—both of them are ſhaded with beautiful woods on the ſides of hills, whoſe ſummits are in the clouds, and whoſe feet are white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the foam of theſe tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous cataracts.</p>
            <p>Before we reached Tan y Bwlch, we ſtopped to look into a ſmall church; where ſome clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly villagers were aſſembled at evening prayers,—the women were by far the handſomeſt of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:0616900400:37"/>
any I ſaw in this country; the clergyman was reading the leſſon concerning David and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines, and I could not help reflecting, that if theſe ignorant people ſhould any way confound the Old with the New Law, they might here find ſome excuſe for that Gallantry, which ſacrifices the virtue of ſo many females in this neighbourhood: to prevent ſuch a miſtake, would it not be proper to have an expoſition made of this chapter, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:0616900400:38"/>
into Welſh,—I mean only, provided the learned labour could be confined within the narrow limits of five volumes in folio.</p>
            <p>I was much ſtruck with the ſituation of Mrs. Griffith's houſe at Tan y Bwlch,—at firſt fight it ſomewhat reſembled Matlock Bath, but the hills in front are thrown to a fine diſtance, and behind the houſe they are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with wood;—through a very ſpacious valley the river Dryryd runs, and from the tops
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:0616900400:39"/>
of the mountains are frequen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and not inconſiderable cataracts—indeed moſt of the romantic proſpects of North Wales, taken ſeparately, are infinitely ſuperio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to thoſe of Derbyſhire; but where ſhall we find within the ſame diſtance, ſuch amazing contraſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as the high poliſh of Kedleſton oppoſed to the bleak horrors of the Peak.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Griffith is poſſeſſed of a conſiderable fortune,—ſhe has an only daughter, to whom a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:0616900400:40"/>
ſenſible clergyman, who reſides in the houſe, is tutor, and who, though a chaplain, is treated as independent. A lady, it is true, in ſuch a country cannot be eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day interrupted with viſitants, but Mrs. Griffith has generally a ſelect party of friends,—theſe form a rational ſociety, whereas in many places, a good neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood means little more than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeping an inn at your own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:0616900400:41"/>At the diſtance of about three miles (the road moſt beautifully diverſified) the ſcene changes on a ſudden to ſome dark and naked precipices; at the bottom is a large rocky baſon, which receive the Rhaidr-du, or Black Cataract as it is called,—this, I am con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fident, is exactly ſimilar to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpot where Hecate appointed he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſiſter-witches to aſſemble, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> offer their choiceſt incantation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to complete the ruin of Macbet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <q>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:0616900400:42"/>
                  <l>And at the pit of Acheron</l>
                  <l>Meet me i'th' morning; thither He</l>
                  <l>Shall come, to know his deſtiny.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The miſtreſs of the little inn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Tan y Bwlch, has lived many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ears ſervant in conſiderable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and from her attentive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ivility, has received great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations from the few Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhmen that have hitherto viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d this country.—Her houſe is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his year much improved;—Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>adnor, having ſtaid a day or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wo there, has made her a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:0616900400:43"/>
of the fitting up of her parlour: two ſaſh-windows add great chearfulneſs to the room and each grateful paſſenger rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dily joins with the landlady in celebrating the kindneſs of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> public-ſpirited young nobleman</p>
            <p>The road to Harlech afforde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great variety; there could ſcarc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be more within the compaſs of ten miles. For the firſt thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we ſurveyed <q rend="inline">"the Happ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Valley<note n="*" place="bottom">Vide Johnſon's Raffelas.</note>,"</q> we then paſſed b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:0616900400:44"/>
a beautiful lake, and having gained the next mountain ſaw the Caſtle, ſituated on a high rock, which projects into the Iriſh ſea. It muſt be confeſſed, however, that the laſt two miles were rather <q rend="inline">"a ſtair-caſe path;"</q> but I have frequently travelled for twenty miles together in the midland counties of England with more danger and difficulty. In Wales one has the pleaſure of ſeeing that they are making daily improvements in roads; but in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:0616900400:45"/>
England the farmers are ſo rich that, by the aid of ſome petty attorney in the neighbourhood they can generally protect per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſeneſs by knavery.</p>
            <p>Harlech ſtands on the north-weſt ſide of the county of Merio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth; its houſes are mean, and its inhabitants uncivilized. There is a good harbour for ſhips, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no ſhips for the harbour. It is remarkable only for its old de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed caſtle, which was defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Britiſh nobleman againſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:0616900400:46"/>
Edward the fourth, till an earl of Pembroke, after almoſt incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble difficulties, compelled it to ſurrender. It has been confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently aſſerted that this caſtle was built before Edward the firſt's time, and that all he did was the making ſome additions, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the fortifications; but I ſhould be rather inclined to think. that it was planned at leaſt by Edward. A tradition goes, that the workmen, after they had got to a conſiderable height, were
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:0616900400:47"/>
all taken off to build the caſtles of Aberyſtwith and Carnarvon; and indeed there are evident marks of a Separation.</p>
            <p>An unpoliſhed people, it is obſerved, have little or no curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,—I had ſeated myſelf by the fire-ſide in one of the houſes at Harlech without the inhabitants expreſſing the leaſt ſurprize at it; the Guide and attendants began to be rather clamorous for ſome refreſhment, and the people at length brought them ſome oat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:0616900400:48"/>
bread, ſour porter, and linking cheeſe. On my leaving he houſe, I believe I gave the miſtreſs of it more than ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ected, for ſhe immediately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alled me to ſhare ſome cockles with her, that were ſtewing on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he hearth, and whilſt I was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſting them, ſhe ſuper-added a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ook of ſuch native kindneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd good-will, as infinitely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſſed all the artifices of refine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:0616900400:49"/>From Harlech a freſh guid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conducted me over the top o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the mountain, and I found a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> entire good road on my retur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Tan y Bwlch.</p>
            <p>Leaving my little Inn the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with regret, I paſſed a drea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cloud-capt country, till I cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to a road which, for near a mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> was cut through a barren roo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and finely preparative for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſcene that was to open up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> me. On a ſudden I came up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:0616900400:50"/>
Pont Aberglaſlyn, the bridge that divides the counties of Merioneth and Carnarvon. It conſiſts of only one wide ſtone arch, thrown over a conſiderable water-fall, from two perpendicular pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipices; beyond it is a ſemicircle of rock, which forms a ſalmon-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eap, above which, in ſpawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time, the fiſh frequently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>empt to lodge themſelves, at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he amazing height of five or in yards; they are frequently taught here in the ſeaſon with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:0616900400:51"/>
nets, and ſometimes with ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that are barbed for the purpoſe but having paſſed the bridg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how ſhall I expreſs my feelings—the dark tremendous prec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pices, the rapid river roarin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> over disjointed rocks, blac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> caverns, and iſſuing cataracts,—all ſerve to make this the noble ſpecimen of the Finely Horri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the eye can poſſibly behold,—the Poet has not deſcribed, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Painter pictured ſo gloom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a retreat,—'tis the laſt Approa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:0616900400:52"/>
to the manſion of Pluto through the regions of Deſpair.</p>
            <p>Having ſtaid too long in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templating this amazing paſs, I poſted as faſt as poſſible over a rocky deſert to gain ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment at Bethkelert; the blackſmith's houſe appearing the neareſt, I alighted, and was able to obtain two eggs, which might here be conſidered as a moſt luxurious repaſt. At Tan y Bwlch I had been informed, that I ſhould really meet with
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:0616900400:53"/>
very decent accommodations at Bettus, and might with comfort take up my abode there for an evening. As I travelled, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected on Burnet's Deſcription of a part of Carnarvonſhire, that it was <q rend="inline">"the fragment of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed world,"</q> and on making ſome ſlight obſervation to the Guide of the drearineſs that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded me, <q rend="inline">"Aye, maſter, ſays he, this muſt have been an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient country indeed, for you ſee it is worn out to the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:0616900400:54"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ery ſtones,"</q> this remark how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, is probably rather good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han new;—but we were now arrived at Bettus, and the Guide pointed to the houſe, where I was to get lodging and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;—the violent ſtench did not prevent my looking in,—the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avages ſat lapping their oatmeal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd milk, and the ſwine were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttendant at the table. In ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſituation, only one queſtion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould properly be aſked, which was, how many miles to Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narvon?
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:0616900400:55"/>
Finding the diſtanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> only ſix miles, I determine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to hazard being loſt in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> night, rather than to be ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>focated in this nauſeous dun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geon. I muſt own I did her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> expatiate a little on recommen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dations, and ſaid it was impoſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the Guide, as well as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miſtreſs of the Inn at Tan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bwlch, could be ſo intolerabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miſtaken; the man apologize with great frankneſs, that he di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:0616900400:56"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot think the houſe altogether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o bad, as my Honour would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave been ſure to have gotten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome good ale;"—however, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt all my vexation, I could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot help doubting, whether Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ink into a Savage at Bettus, or poliſhed into an Ape at Paris, was altogether the more reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble animal.</p>
            <p>Within three miles of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narvon I was agreeably ſurpriſed with a very fine road, and a new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ridge, which will open a free
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:0616900400:57"/>
communication with theſe unfre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quented regions, and induce th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Curious to viſit the Wonders o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Britiſh Alps, in preference t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Mountains of Switzerland, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Glaciers of Savoy.—Mr. Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rington, who, to a conſummat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knowledge in the formation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Laws, adds Zeal and Propriety i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the execution of them, has now indicted all the pariſhes betwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Carnarvon and Bethkelert; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> indeed, unleſs men of great ran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or the juſtices of each diſtric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:0616900400:58"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill take upon them this office, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at Bill, which was in many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rts ſo excellently framed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r. Gilbert about two years ago, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt become totally void and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icacious;—I know that it will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> immediately ſaid, that any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ivate gentleman has the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ans within his own power; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t what private gentleman, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſake of a road, will live in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>petual warfare with five or ſix <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>iſhes around him?—Who, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> convenience of rolling his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:0616900400:59"/>
carriage a quarter of an ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſooner to ſome neighbouring m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ket-town, will endanger his pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tations being cut down, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cattle to be either maimed or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroyed?</p>
            <p>I paſſed my evening at a v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good inn at Carnarvon, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing procured an intelligent Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> returned early next morn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> through Bettus to the foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Snowdon.—Having left my h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at a ſmall hut, and hired a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taineer to carry ſome cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:0616900400:60"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d proviſions, with a ſpiked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ck, but imprudently without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ils in my ſhoes, about ten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>clock I began to aſcend the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ountain.—The two firſt miles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere rather boggy and diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble, but when the proſpect open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, I ſoon forgot all difficulties;—in the courſe of the two laſt I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſſed by ſix precipices, which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elieve were very formidable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut as I was near the brink, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e wind very high, I did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enture to examine too narrowly.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:0616900400:61"/>
—On the ſummit, which is a pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> about ſix yards in circumferen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the air was perfectly mild and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rene, and I could with pleaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> contemplate the amazing m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that was unfolded to my view.—From hence may be diſtinct <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeen, Wicklow Hills in Irelan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Iſle of Man, Cumberland, La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> caſhire, Cheſhire, Shropſhire, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part of Scotland;—all the cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties of North Wales, the Iſle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Angleſea;—rivers, plains, wood rocks, and mountains, ſix an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:0616900400:62"/>
twenty lakes, and two ſeas;—it is doubted whether there is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other circular proſpect ſo exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive in any part of the terraqueous globe.—Who could take ſuch a Survey, without perceiving his Spirits elevated in ſome propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Height?—Who could behold ſo bountiful a Diſplay of Nature without Wonder and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy?—Who but muſt feel even a Degree of Pride from having gained an eminence, from which he could with eaſe overlook the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:0616900400:63"/>
Neſt <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <p>Moel Guidon, and Moel Happo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> two mountains near Snowdon, mention<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> by Lord Lyttelton.</p>
                  <p>Vide Account of a Journey into Wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </note> of the Eagle, and the Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Hawk?</p>
            <p>But as the level walks of Lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are beſt ſuited to the generality <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mankind, it became neceſſary t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſider that this was no ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> where I could properly make an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laſting Abode, and that the Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turn would be attended with a leaſt as much difficulty as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Aſcent.—Having deſcended
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:0616900400:64"/>
mile or two, I did not think it amiſs to enquire about an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted Mine that I ſaw at a diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and I could make this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry with the better grace, as the Guides had hitherto quite won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at my proweſs;—the Mine I was informed was only Copper; and happy was it for the Welſh that their Mines did not conſiſt of choicer Metals;—had they been curſed with either Gold or Silver, Foreign Nations long ſince, in the name of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:0616900400:65"/>
God of Peace, and under pretence of teaching them an immaculate Religion<note n="*" place="bottom">The Spaniards made the Goſpel an Excuſe for all the barbarities they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the conqueſt of Peru, and when they plundered the rich mines of Potoſi, they frequently (ſays Las Caſas) erected gibbets all over the country, and hung twelve poor wretches at a time, in honour of the twelve Apoſtles.</note>, had laid waſte their country, and murdered its inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants.</p>
            <p>At the Foot of Snowdon I turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about half a mile out of the way to ſee a Water-fall;—the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:0616900400:66"/>
Side-rock was exceedingly beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, but the Cataract itſelf was rather contemptible, after the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ones I had ſeen in the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood of Dolgelly.—As the Guides ſeemed to think a floating iſland, about two miles diſtant, was a moſt wonderful phaenome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and related many ſingular and ſurpriſing tales concerning it, I indulged their credulity ſo far as to go and inſpect it;—the Lake, as they called it, was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what bigger than a common
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:0616900400:67"/>
duck-pond; and the Iſland was a knotty piece of Bog, which, after very heavy rains, might very poſſibly float in it.</p>
            <p>On my return to Carnarvon I examined the Town and Caſtle.—The town was built by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Edward the Firſt, out of the ruins of the ancient city of Segontium, that ſtood a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it;—it is ſituated between two rivers, and has a beautiful proſpect of the Iſle of Angleſea;—it was formerly of very great
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:0616900400:68"/>
account when the Princes of Wales kept their Chancery and Exchequer Courts there.—On the weſt ſide of it ſtands the Caſtle, which was built to curb the Welſh moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineers, and ſecure a paſſage to the oppoſite ſhore—In a part of it, called the Eagle Tower, you are ſhewn the remains of a chamber in which Edward the Second <note n="*" place="bottom">The Cradle of that weak, wicked, unfortunate prince is ſtill preſerved; it is now in the poſſeſſion of a clergyman in Glouceſterſhire, to whom it deſcended from one of his anceſtors, who attended the Prince in his infancy.</note> is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:0616900400:69"/>
ſaid to have been born; about ten years after his birth it was beſieged by the Welſh, but was afterwards repaired; and both the town and caſtle had divers Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges confirmed to them by different Sovereigns, down to the reign of Elizabeth; during the laſt civil war they were held for King Charles, but were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſurrendered on conditions to the Parliament. On viewing theſe ſpacious Ruins, I could
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:0616900400:70"/>
only ruminate on the Changes they had undergone;—ſtrange Reverſe!—to think that thoſe Walls, which heretofore reſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Acclamations on the Birth of the firſt Engliſh Prince of Wales, ſhould now afford Shelter only to a few miſerable Cottages, from the tempeſtuous Blaſts of the Briſtol channel!</p>
            <p>I made ſeveral Excurſions into the Iſle of Angleſea, the well-known Seat of the Druids;—
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:0616900400:71"/>
this may now be conſidered as Claſſical Ground; for though Mona is deſtroyed, and her Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars aboliſhed,—though Fires have conſumed her Groves, and her Prieſts have periſhed by the Sword, yet, like the Phoenix, ſhe riſes more glorious from Decay; her Aſhes have given Birth to the Caractacus of Maſon, and the Fate of her Bards to the Inſpiration of Gray.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:0616900400:72"/>Nothing could be more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ightful than the Ride from Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arvon to Bangor; to the right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and were Snowdon Hills, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he left the River Menai, or more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roperly ſpeaking, the Strait be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ween the Continent and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>land of Angleſea; I had now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot into Day-light and the polite World again;—there had been a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iverſion the night before at Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arvon, and the road was covered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver with Carriages.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:0616900400:73"/>Bangor lies at the north en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the ſame Frith, or arm of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sea, which is the paſſage to An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gleſea, where it has a Harbo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for Boats. It was once ſo lar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as to be called Bangor the Grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and was defended with a powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful Caſtle, built by Hugh Earl <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Cheſter, which has long ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> been demoliſhed. The Town <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now of very little Note, except f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> being the See of a Biſhop; t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Palace is neat, but deplorab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:0616900400:74"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ituated;—this is doubly morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying in a Country where every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art of the neighbourhood is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ictureſque and pleaſing; his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ordſhip however has the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of being ſo much beloved in his Dioceſe, that it would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een almoſt Treaſon there to have wiſhed him a Removal.</p>
            <p>Between Bangor and Conway I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſſed over the famous Mountain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alled Penmaen Mawr—the road <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt formerly have been very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ightful, but a Wall is now built
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:0616900400:75"/>
to the Sea ſide, to which it is ſaid the City of Dublin very largely contributed;—to form this roa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it has already coſt upwards o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> two thouſand pounds, and it ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be kept open only at a continua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> expence, for vaſt Fragments o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Rock are frequently falling fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fathom from above, which en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tirely block it up, till they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> forced through the Parapet int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Sea, which lies perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>larly full as deep below.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:0616900400:76"/>From hence the Country opens into a Plain, which extends as far as the River Conway, the eaſtern Limit of the County of Carnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>von. It riſes out of a Lake of the ſame name, and runs with a north-weſt Courſe, receiving in the ſhort ſpace of twelve miles more than as many Rivers, ſo that at Aberconway, where it diſcharges its waters into the Iriſh Sea, it is full a mile broad, and capable of bringing Ships of almoſt any Size up to the Town;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:0616900400:77"/>
at preſent Conway bears only ſome melancholy Marks of wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it once was, and to what a wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed State, by a total Decay o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Trade, it is now reduced.</p>
            <p>The Caſtle ſtill remains one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the nobleſt Monuments of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; it is built in the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Style with that of Carnarvon, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is far more regular. The Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide is the ſame as in the tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Edward the Firſt, except on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Tower, and that was not demo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhed with either battering en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gines
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:0616900400:78"/>
or cannons, but by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the place taking Stones from the foundation of it. Some Remains of the principal Rooms are ſtill to be ſeen, the Dimenſions of which have been accurately given by Lord Lyttelton, and an elegant View of them in Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by Mr. Groſe; but I had never ſeen the Outſide of this moſt venerable Ruin to advantage had I not walked over ſome po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed Ground about a quarter of a mile from it, which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:0616900400:79"/>
belongs to a Gentleman o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Conway;—there You ſee the Caſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> finely ſheltered by an Oak Wood—on one ſide <hi>the Chief of River,</hi> opening into the Iriſh Sea, and on the other the Mountains ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounding Penmaen, with a diſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Country moſt beautifully diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſified.—Art and Nature cannot combine to form a more various and more delicious Proſpect.</p>
            <p>I could not poſſibly leave this part of the Country without ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Vale of Llanryſt, the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:0616900400:80"/>
Bridge built by Inigo Jones, and the Chapel ſuppoſed to have been planned by him, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the rich monuments of the Guedir Family.—The Vale upon the whole I thought inferior to that I had ſeen in Montgomery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, but the Bridge is certainly a very elegant Structure, and ſpeaks itſelf to be the Work of a great Architect, moſt probably of Jones, for I incline to the opinion that Llanryſt was the Place of his Nativity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:0616900400:81"/>The Chapel which adjoins the Pariſh Church, was erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Sir Richard Wynne, one of the Grooms of the Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber to Charles the Firſt when Prince of Wales, and was chiefly made uſe of for the Alms-Houſe in the neighbourhood, which was endowed by the Guedir Family. I took the Pains of copying the different Inſcriptions in it, and as they are not contained in the Hiſtory of that Family lately pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:0616900400:82"/>
they may not be unaccept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the curious Antiquary.</p>
            <q>"This Cappel was erected Anno Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini 1633. By Sir Richard Wynne of Gwydir in the County of Carnavon Knight and Baronet, Treaſurer to the High and Mighty Princeſs Henrietta Maria Queen of England, Daughter to King Henery the Fourth King of France, and Wife to our Soveraing King Charles. Where lieth Buried his Father S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Wynne of Gwydir in the County of Caernarvon Knight and Baronet, Son and Heyre to Maurice Wynne, Son and Heyre to John Wynne, Son and Heyre to Meredith, Which Three lye Buried in the Church of Dolwyddelan with Tombes over them. This Meredith Son and Heyre to Evan, Son and Heyre to Robert, Son and Heyre
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:0616900400:83"/>
to Meredith, Son and Heyre to Howel, Son and Heyre to David, Son and Heyre to Griffith, Son and Heyre to Carradock, Son and Heyre to Thomas, Son and Heyre to Roderick Lord of Angleſey, Son to Owen Gwynedd Prince of Wales, and and younger to David Prince of Wales, who married Eme Plantagenet Siſter to King Henery the Second. There ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded this David Three Princes, His Nephew Leolinus Magnus, who married Jone Daughter to King John, Davil his Son, Nephew to King Henery the Third, and Leoline the Laſt Prince of Wales of that Houſe and Line who lived in King Edward the Firſt his time. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Wynne married Sydney who lieth buried here, the Daughter of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> William Gerrard Knight, Lord Chancellour of Ireland, by whom he had Iſſue S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Wynne who died att Lucca in Italy. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Richard
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:0616900400:84"/>
Wynne now living, Thomas Wynne who Lieth here, Roger Wynne who Lieth here, William Wynne now living, Maurice Wynne now living, Ellis Wynne who lieth Buried att Whitford in the County of Flint, Henery Wynne now liveing, Roger Wynne who lieth here, and Two Daughters, Mary now living married to S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Roger Moſtyn in the County of Flint Knight, and Elizabeth now liveing mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Bodvil in the County of Caernarvon Knight."</q>
            <p>On the Floor are four Braſs Plates, with Drawings of Figures upon each of them in the Dreſſes of the Times, one of Maria Moſtyn, Wife of Roger Moſtyn,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:0616900400:85"/>
another of Sir Owen Wynne, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of Sir John Wynne, and a Fourth of Lady Sydney Wynne, Wife of Sir John Wynne. And in the Corner of the Chapel a Stone Coffin, which was remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Abbey of Conway, about two miles from hence, on which is the following Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<q>"This is the Coffin of Leolinus Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Prince of Wales who was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the Abbey of Conway, and upon the Diſſolution, remov'd from thence."</q>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:0616900400:86"/>
On each Side are ſix carved Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes in the figure of Flower de Luces, which bear evident Marks of having contained Braſs Plates, and two at the bottom of the Coffin.</p>
            <p>There is now erected in the Church a Gallery of exquiſite Workmanſhip, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved likewiſe from the Abbey; and I was at the trouble of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a large quantity of Rubbiſh taken away from under an old Staircaſe, that I might inſpect a
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:0616900400:87"/>
Stone Effigy, which is ſaid to be of Hoel Coetmore, who ſold the Guedir Eſtate to the Wynne Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; the Word Gwedir is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſignify Glaſs, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Family probably was the firſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who in theſe parts had a Houſe with glazed Windows.</p>
            <p>I ought to make ſome Apology for the foregoing heavy Articles but elaborate Inſcriptions fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quently illuſtrate Hiſtory, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Theſe will at leaſt ſhew that Som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:0616900400:88"/>
of the Welſh were not totally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs of Pedigree.</p>
            <p>I made diligent enquiry through all Carnarvonſhire, and this part of Denbighſhire, for the Glyder Mountain, which Gibſon has particularly deſcribed, and which, from its ſingularity, (ſay the Authors of a Tour through Wales,) we more wiſhed to have ſeen, than the Summits of either Plinlimmon or Snow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:0616900400:89"/>
               <q rend="inline">
                  <p>"On the utmoſt top of this Mountain, according to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuator of Camden, who ſaw it, is a prodigious pile of Stones, many of which are of the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude of thoſe at Stonehenge. They lie in ſuch an irregular manner, croſſing and ſupporting each other, that ſome people have imagined them to be the remains of a vaſt building; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Gibſon more naturally ſuppoſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them to be the ſkeleton or ruin
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:0616900400:90"/>
of the Mountain; the weaker parts of which may have been worn away in a ſeries of ages, by the rains and meltings of the Snow.</p>
                  <p>"On the weſt ſide of the ſame mountain, he ſpeaks of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable precipice, adorned with numerous equidiſtant columns, formed to that ſhape by the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt continual rains, which this high rock, being expoſed to the weſterly ſea wind, is ſubject to.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:0616900400:91"/>"Notwithſtanding the ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this mountain ſeems to be pointed out by the laſt line and though its Phoenomena ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo peculiar, yet We (add the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the ſame Tour) wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> obliged to leave the Country without gaining the ſmalleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> knowledge of it."</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I was equally unfortunate i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not being able to ſee this Moun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tain, but in croſſing the wid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ferry at Conway, I by acciden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:0616900400:92"/>
gained ſuch Information, that I am confident any future Traveller may very readily ſatisfy his Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity; an old Boatman there informed me, that he had fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſeen it,—that in his younger days indeed it was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times termed the Glyder, but was now known only by the name of Wythwar,—that it was within a mile or two of a Village, called Clynog, and upon the Shore almoſt oppoſite to Carnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>von.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:0616900400:93"/>On my way to St. Aſaph, I paſſed over the top of Penmaen Roſs, a ſteep and formidable Mountain; this is by far the worſt part of the road between Holyhead and Cheſter;—a nearer Path was ſome time ſince cut along the ſide of the ſea cliff, but a Man and Horſe had lately been killed, and by order of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners it is now entirely broken up.</p>
            <p>The City of St. Aſaph is called in Britiſh Llan Elwy, on account
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:0616900400:94"/>
of its ſituation at the Conflux of the River Elwy with the Clwyd; and St. Aſaph by the Engliſh, from its Patron Aſaph, who in the year 560 erected a Biſhop's See there. The Biſhop of this Dioceſe has no entire County un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Juriſdiction, but Parts only of the Counties of Flint, Denbigh, Montgomery, Merio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and Salop. The Cathedral is a mean Structure, and the Houſes in general but ill built, St. Aſaph however may boaſt that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:0616900400:95"/>
it ſtands in the delightful Vale of Clwyd, though by no means in the fineſt part of it.</p>
            <p>About five miles from thence, near the road to Holywell, You have the beſt View I think of that fertile and delicious Vale;—it is of an oval ſhape, about 25 miles in length, and about eight miles wide in its broadeſt part; it lies open only to the Ocean, and to the clearing North Wind, being elſewhere guarded with high mountains, which towards
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:0616900400:96"/>
the Eaſt eſpecially are like Battle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Turrets, for by an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Contrivance of Nature, ſays Camden, the tops of theſe Mountains reſemble the Turrets of Walls. Upon the whole however I think that there are other cultivated Scenes in North Wales equal, if not ſuperior; in the Vale of Clwyd indeed You have the Lively and the Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but in Montgomeryſhire the Awful and Sublime.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:0616900400:97"/>Holywell, and the Hiſtory of its Virgin Saint, would require at leaſt a Folio. I ſhall only ſay that I was truly ſorry to find that blaſphemous Papers ſhould ſtill be ſuffered to be publicly ſold at the Spring there, which compare the ludicrous Legend of Winefrid with the moſt ſacred Truths of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>It was my Intention to have ſeen Winſtay, Erthig, and Chirk Caſtle<note n="*" place="bottom">Sir Watkin Wynne's, Mr. Yorke's and Mr. Middleton's.</note>,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:0616900400:98"/>
and afterwards to have traced the River Dee to Bala, but I was unexpectedly called off from my Tour; I had the good fortune however to join Party with the Biſhop of Kildare, whoſe eaſy Manners and refined Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion left me no room to regret a Diſappointment.</p>
            <p>To the foregoing Account, which was in part printed off for the Uſe and Amuſement of ſome ſelect Friends only, I ſhall now add a few general Remarks on
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:0616900400:99"/>
the Hiſtory of the Country and the Manners of its Inhabitants.</p>
            <p>The Origin of every Nation is neceſſarily obſcure, and always loſt in a pretended Antiquity. On the Authority of Bochart we may trace the Welſh from Japhet, the Son of Noah; according to Others, from Trojans and Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicians, who were the Offspring of Gods; and one Writer I think has aſſerted that a True Briton is a Compound of all Nations under Heaven. That Britain
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:0616900400:100"/>
however was peopled from Gaul 1000 years before Chriſt, appears very probable,—the arguments in favour of this opinion are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from the State of Popula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the Continent, and from the Progreſs of it in the Iſland it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. It has been well obſerved <note n="*" place="bottom">By Whitaker.</note> that Names deſcriptive of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Manners cannot be the original Appellations of any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they reſult from the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:0616900400:101"/>
and experience of the States around them, on whoſe territories they have dared to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach; the Appellation of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantes, according to Strabo, came to ſignify a turbulent and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering race, and the Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Celtae and Gael came to import, even amongſt themſelves, the Ferocious and the Stranger.</p>
            <p>The Name of Cymri appears to have been the great hereditary Diſtinction of the Gauls upon the Continent, and to have been car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:0616900400:102"/>
with them into all their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts; it was not retained in our Iſland merely by the Natives of Wales, but was equally the Appellation of a Nation in the South-Weſt of Somerſetſhire and the North-Eaſt of Cornwall.</p>
            <p>The firſt Denomination of our Iſland was certainly Albion, a name given before the Country was inhabited; it was the Celtic Term for Heights or Eminences; the Alps ſome ages before the Days of Strabo were called Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:0616900400:103"/>
and in his time there remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two tribes on the Mountains that bore the Names of Albioeci, and Albienſes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Denomination was that of Britain, derived from a Celtic Word likewiſe ſignifying <hi>Divided,</hi> not <hi>Painted</hi>; this Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy has lately been proved not to have been applied to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but beſtowed on the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; not previouſly borne on the Continent by the original Settlers of the Country, but aſſumed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:0616900400:104"/>
received at their firſt Removal into the Iſland.</p>
            <p>The Title of Welſh ſeems to ariſe from the Word Wall or Gall, an appellation which the Britons frequently gave each other; nor will this Derivation appear forced if we add, that the Channel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt France and England was denominated Sinus Vallicus, or the Gallick Strait, ſo late as the eighth Century, and that the Dutch and Germans call the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:0616900400:105"/>
French by the Name of Walls and Walloons to this very Day.</p>
            <p>The general Denomination of Wales was not impoſed on the Country by the Saxons, but was the acknowledged Appellation of the Region as early as the ſixth Century, if we may believe a Quotation from Talieſſin, as cited by Dr. Davies.</p>
            <p>Nor were ſome plain and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Derivations of Names till of late only unknown to us,—we
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:0616900400:106"/>
have not always had either juſt Ideas of Britiſh Manners or Britiſh Antiquities; this ample Field of Hiſtory has been greatly laid open by an Individual<note n="*" place="bottom">Whitaker.</note>, and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich Produce will continually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riſe from the judicious Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions of a moſt reſpectable So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iety<note n="†" place="bottom">Society of Antiquaries.</note>.</p>
            <p>Our Knowledge of the Druids <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtill vague and unſatisfying, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd muſt ever remain ſo, as they
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:0616900400:107"/>
committed few things, if any, to Writing, though they were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly not unacquainted with Let<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters; for among the Maxims col<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lected by Gollet, there is one tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forbids their Myſteries to be wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten, a Prohibition which coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> never have been given had Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters been entirely unknown; ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> curious Particulars however ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> at leaſt be traced from Traditio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and others from Specimens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Poetry that have been recit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the Natives. As Guardia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:0616900400:108"/>
of what They called True Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they of courſe poſſeſſed the greateſt authority among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; No Laws were inſtituted by the Princes without their Advice, no Plunder taken in War without their partaking of it. They held the Diſſolution of the World by Fire and Water, they taught the Immortality, and ſome ſay the Tranſmigration of the Soul, a Doctrine borrowed from the Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoreans, though Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus expreſsly aſſerts that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:0616900400:109"/>
the Pythagoreans borrowed that Doctrine from them; in my own opinion they never believed the Tranſmigration of the Soul at all; and I found this opinion on ſome late Accounts of Gauliſh Funerals, which certainly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponded with the Britiſh ones, the Cuſtoms and Ceremonials of which were abſolutely incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible with that Doctrine.</p>
            <p>They ſacrificed human Victims to propitiate the Gods; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied future Events from the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:0616900400:110"/>
falling of the Body, and the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in which the Members were convulſed;—they believed there was a divine Myſtery in Miſleto, but took their firſt Diſtinction from the Oak, to which the Jews paid the ſame regard during their Idolatry, according to a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in Ezekiel, <q rend="inline">"under every thick <hi>Oak</hi> did they offer ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to their Idols."</q> Once a, year They, with their Chief, an Arch-Druid, aſſembled at a fixed time and place to hear Cauſes,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:0616900400:111"/>
and determine all Diſputes; where their deciſive Court was held has never been determined, but moſt probably in Angleſea, as that Iſland was certainly their Metropolis. So great was the Power of the Druids, that not only the Property, but alſo the Lives of the People were entirely at their Diſpoſal, and this Power continued abſolute till the time of Tiberius;—it was afterwards ſuppreſſed by Claudius, under the fair Pretext of aboliſhing human
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:0616900400:112"/>
ſacrifices, but the Prieſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their Gods and their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars ſubſiſted, though in obſcurity, till the final Deſtruction of Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm.</p>
            <p>The Manners of the People were naturally tinged with the Diſcipline of their Teachers; in proportion to their ignorance they were ſuperſtitious, and in proportion to their zeal they committed Cruelties and Fraud; I ſhall not raiſe Diſguſt by a recital of Barbarities, but rather refer my
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:0616900400:113"/>
Readers to the Journals of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Voyages, where they will find, that there is a Sameneſs in the primaeval State of every ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage Nation: a few other Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars however may not be uninte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſting. The Britons lived in Tribes or Clans, under the Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratical rule of their ſeveral Lords; their Villages were a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Parcel of Huts placed at a ſmall diſtance from each other, and, generally ſpeaking, in the middle of a Wood, whereof the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:0616900400:114"/>
Avenues were defended with Trees, that were cut down to clear the ground.</p>
            <p>Their Trade was very inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, notwithſtanding the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient ſituation of the Iſland for carrying on an extenſive Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce; Their veſſels were very ſmall, with their Keels and Ribs made of ſlight Timber, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven with Wicker, and covered with Hides, which ſhews that they never undertook long Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, moſt probably never ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:0616900400:115"/>
to Sea beyond the Coaſts of Gaul.</p>
            <p>The Britons were not ſo total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtitute of Defence as has been imagined; the Iſland is of itſelf a Shield, and they certainly made uſe of the Battle-axe, as well as Military Chariot; theſe Chariots were drawn by Horſes, and the Axle-trees were generally furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Scythes; but the People were not united under a well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated government, or they would always have continued
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:0616900400:116"/>
formidable to their Enemies;—a number of petty Communities will never act in concert with each other; tho' Hiſtory informs us that upon great and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Dangers a Chief Commander was always choſen by common conſent; but what State or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony will acquieſce even with the Leader themſelves have choſen? and in the end, if unſucceſsful, he muſt always fall a Sacrifice to thoſe Miſeries their own Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtencies alone have occaſioned.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:0616900400:117"/>When that part of Britain which comprehends the preſent Kingdom of England and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality of Wales, was divided into ſeveral petty Kingdoms, the Inhabitants were all diſtinguiſhed by different names. The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality of Wales, formerly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the whole Country beyond the Severn, was in the Roman times occupied by the Silures, the Dimetae, and Ordo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices; to theſe belonged not only the twelve Counties of Wales,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:0616900400:118"/>
but likewiſe the two others ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beyond the Severn, Hereford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire and Monmouthſhire, which in the reign of Charles the Second were firſt reckoned amongſt the Engliſh Counties.</p>
            <p>The Country now known by the name of North Wales was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited by the Ordovices only, who held out firſt againſt the Romans, and afterwards againſt the Engliſh, after the other Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons were ſubdued; for by the Romans they were not reduced
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:0616900400:119"/>
till the time of Domitian, nor by the Engliſh till the Reign of Henry the Firſt.</p>
            <p>About forty-five years before the Chriſtian Aera, Britain was firſt invaded by the Romans un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Julius Caeſar,—afterwards by Claudius, and at length became a Province under the Roman em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; it was governed by Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, or Deputies, ſent from Rome, as Ireland is now by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties from England; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued thus under the Romans
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:0616900400:120"/>
for upwards of 400 years; till that Empire being invaded by the Goths and Vandals, the Romans were forced not only to recall their own armies, but alſo to draw from hence the braveſt of the Britons, for their aſſiſtance againſt thoſe Barbarians.</p>
            <p>The Country being left in a defenceleſs State, was invaded by the Scots, who were ſo rapacious, that the Britons ſent over a miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able application for relief to Aetius, the Roman General, who
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:0616900400:121"/>
by ſeveral famous Succeſſes, for a time, had repelled the violence of the Gothick Arms, but receiving no hopes of any Succours from that General, the South Britons invited over the Saxons, who no ſooner delivered them from their ancient Foes the Picts and Scots, than they ſtrengthened their own Numbers, turned their Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Natives, and conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, ſome few excepted, who ſecured themſelves in their Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Wales; whence their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendants
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:0616900400:122"/>
have always been diſtinguiſhed by the Title of Ancient Britons.</p>
            <p>During the Saxon Heptarchy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ived the renowed Prince Arthur, whoſe Valour would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieved the miſerable ſtate of the Britons, had Valour only been wanting; his Hiſtory has been ſo blended with Fable, that ſome have doubted the real exiſtence of ſuch a Perſon; but it ſeems ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hard becauſe Stories have been invented concerning the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:0616900400:123"/>
of his Life, that he ſhould not be allowed to have lived at all; it is true that the Saxon An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals make no mention of this King, but it was not probable that the Saxons would be fond of recording Exploits, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounded only to their own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit; an ancient Engliſh Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian ſpeaking of Cerdic, mentions his fighting ſeveral Battles with King Arthur; and William of Malmeſbury owns, that though the Britons had vented innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:0616900400:124"/>
Fables concerning this Prince, he certainly was a Hero worthy to be celebrated in True Hiſtory. The Britons bewailed <q rend="inline">"their long loſt Arthur"</q> for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ages after his Death;—they believed he was ſtill alive in Fairy Land, and that he would return once more to reign over them; nor was this notion rooted out till the reign of Henry the Second, about ſix hundred years after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when his Coffin was dug up at Glaſtenbury in Somerſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:0616900400:125"/>
with the following Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <q rend="inline">"Here lies buried the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned King Arthur in the Iſland Avalonia."</q> The Exploits of this Warrior have not only been ſung by Talieſſin and other Britiſh Bards, but have been ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated by one of the greateſt of our Engliſh Poets; it ſeems by ſome Hints given by Spenſer, that he intended a Poem whoſe title was to be expreſsly, King Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur;—Dryden tells us that he had ſome thoughts of making
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:0616900400:126"/>
choice for the ſubject of an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roic Poem, King Arthur's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts over the Saxons; Milton, in a Latin Addreſs to Manſus, has likewiſe intimated the ſame Intention.</p>
            <p>Wales was anciently bounded by the Iriſh Seas, and by the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Severn and Dee, till the Saxons became Maſters of all the level Countries over thoſe Rivers; and till Offa, king of Mercia, made the celebrated Trench, which is ſtill called by
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:0616900400:127"/>
his Name. This Trench, which extended from North to South,—from the mouth of the River Dee to that of the Wye, has been thought to have been an Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Ramparts, which were thrown up by Agricola, Adrian, and Severus, to guard the Romans againſt the Incurſions of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Barbarians; but from ſome Remains of it, as well as for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Reaſons, it ſeems more probable, that it was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by Offa as a Fortification,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:0616900400:128"/>
but rather as a Boundary betwixt his Kingdom and the Cambrian Province.</p>
            <p>When after many Events be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſeveral Races of the Heptarchy, Ecbert became the ſole King of England, as it was now diſtinguiſhed from the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality of Wales, he poſſeſſed himſelf alſo of Mona, the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of the Cambrian Province; but the Saxons ſome time after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards being driven out of it, it was from them called Angleſea,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:0616900400:129"/>
Engliſhman's Iſland, a name which it has retained ever ſince.</p>
            <p>In the year eight hundred and forty-three all Wales was united under the Dominion, of Roderic, ſurnamed the Great; who, by a teſtamentary Settlement, made a new Diviſion between three Sons into three Diſtricts, which were called Kingdoms, and diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Names of South Wales, Powis Land, and North Wales this Partition gave riſe to many Wars, which cauſed the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:0616900400:130"/>
of Powis Land to be por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned among the Conquerors, and annexed partly to South Wales, and partly to North Wales, Diviſions which ſubſiſt to this Day.</p>
            <p>No ſooner were the Saxons ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled under one Monarch, than the Danes began to trouble them, as they (the Saxons) had before done the Britons, till, after many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions, Edgar King of England ſet forth the firſt Navy, made Peace with the Danes, and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:0616900400:131"/>
them to live in his Dominions mixed with the Engliſh;—at this time we read of five Kings in Wales, who all did him Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage for their Country.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding many At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of the Engliſh, the Welſh enjoyed their own Laws, and lived under their own Princes, till in the year 1282 Llewellin loſt both his Principality and Life; in the reign of Henry the Eighth Wales was incorporated and united with England; and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:0616900400:132"/>
by a Statute of the 27th of that Reign, all Laws and Liberties of England were to take place there; from which time the Welſh have approved themſelves truly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of their high Origin, loyal and dutiful to their King, and always zealous for the Welfare of the Community.</p>
            <p>The Welſh Language is ſtill the Gomerian or Old Celtic, the ſame that was once ſpoken throughout Europe, except that through length of time, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termixture
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:0616900400:133"/>
of the people with the Scythians and other nations, it has ſplit into a variety of Dialects. No Tongue, either ancient or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern, I believe, bears greater Marks of antiquity; its ſtrong reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to the Hebrew has been generally admitted, inſomuch that one Author of great Learning has given a Specimen of a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able number of Phraſes out of the Old Teſtament, which are ſo alike in both, that they ſeem to have been originally the ſame. It is
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:0616900400:134"/>
no uncommon Error to give the Name of Mother Tongue to thoſe Languages, from which ſome known Idioms only are derived; the Hebrew has been conſidered as a Mother Tongue, but was evidently borrowed from the Phoenician; the Latin is called the Mother tongue to the Italian, the Spaniſh, and the French, but the Latin itſelf was derived from the Tuſcan, and the Tuſcan from the Celtic and the Greek. It will reaſonably be aſked, how the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merians
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:0616900400:135"/>
have preſerved their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage almoſt entire, whilſt the Jews have ſuffered theirs to be corrupted, and blended with thoſe of their Conquerors?—for this, many reaſons may be aſſigned; the Former have not been ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſubdued, and they have always preſerved a conſiderable Regard for what They conceived to be a Mother tongue; a regard greatly kept up perhaps by the Cuſtom which the Loweſt of the People had, of reciting their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogies.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:0616900400:136"/>
This ancient Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is ſpoken the neareſt to its original purity in the uncul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated parts of North Wales, but the Welſh in general ſtill retain ſo high a veneration for it, that I am confident they will never readily ſuffer the Engliſh to be entirely made uſe of in their Churches, or taught ſolely in their Schools.</p>
            <p>Much has been ſaid of thoſe Druidical Remains, which by many Authors have been indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminately
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:0616900400:137"/>
called Carns, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedds, and Cromlechs; but of their original meaning, I ſhall venture the following Conjecture,—that by the word Carn, which ſignified a Rock, the Britons ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply implied one large broad Stone, as a covering for a Grave<note n="*" place="bottom">The Word Carn was afterwards uſed in an ill ſenſe, moſt probably when the Mode of Burial came to be changed on the Introduction of Chriſtianity; ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Malefactors being thrown into holes nea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Highways, and great quantities o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Stones heaped upon them, it was no un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>common thing for a man to ſay to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> enemy; <hi>May a Carn be your Monument.</hi>
               </note>;
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:0616900400:138"/>
by a Carnedd, a heap of Stones thrown rudely together to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate an event; and by a Cromlech, an huge, broad, flat Stone raiſed high on other Stones, where the ancient Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, like the Hebrews, made Sacrifices or paid religious Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>Thoſe nice Diſtinctions that have been formed of the Druids, the Bards and the Vates, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted only, I think, in particular Societies; the Druids in general
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:0616900400:139"/>
compoſed and recited Hymns, as worſhip to their Deities; the Bards <note n="*" place="bottom">The Bards, who were inferior Druids, wore an eccleſiaſtical Ornament during the celebration of their Rites, called by the Latins Caputium, or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cullus, which is ſtill retained in our Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities; the Gauls, who borrowed this cuſtom from the Britiſh Druids, wore the Cucullus remarkably long, whence it ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, on its being made uſe of at Rome, the name of Bardo-Cucullus, or Bard's Hood. It was in alluſion to the Shape of this Hood, that Martial feared leſt a Sheet of his Book ſhould be rolled up to put Pepper or Frankincenſe in: <q>Ne Thuris Piperiſve ſit Cucullus. <bibl>VID. NICHOLLS.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </note> certainly compoſed
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:0616900400:140"/>
Hymns likewiſe; but it was in the hour of Battle that their labours were chiefly celebrated, by ſinging the Exploits of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Heroes; while the Vates were principally engaged in the Rites of Sacrifice, or the Arts of Divination.</p>
            <p>The Welſh have always laid claim to the Diſcovery of Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica, in preference to the Great Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbus, but this claim has hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to been ſupported with little more than bare Conjecture; in the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:0616900400:141"/>
twelfth Century, according to Powell, there was a War in Wales for the Succeſſion, upon the Death of Owen Guinneth; and a Baſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard having carried it from the lawful Heirs, one of the latter, called Madoc, put to Sea, and ſailing weſt from Spain, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered a new world of wonderful Fertility;—to prove that a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try was thus diſcovered, the Welſh have recourſe to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Meridith ap Rhees, who compoſed an Ode in honour
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:0616900400:142"/>
Prince Madoc and his new-found Land; and that this Country was America they have alledged on the credit of Peter Martyr, that the Natives of Virginia celebrated the memory of one Madoc, as a great and ancient Hero; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſuppoſed their Anceſtors to have come thither at firſt, from ſome very diſtant Countries on the other ſide the great Water, at the time that has been aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, and from the ſame point of the Compaſs. The af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:0616900400:143"/>
of Language has ſince been frequently urged by modern Travellers, and Biſhop Nicholſon in particular, ſpeaks confidently that the Britiſh makes a conſiderable part of ſeveral of the American Tongues; in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to theſe Aſſertions, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Dr. Robertſon has juſt now declared, that he conceives the ſkill of the Welſh in the twelfth Century, not to have been equal to ſuch a Voyage; and that the inſtances given of
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:0616900400:144"/>
the affinity of Language are ſo obſcure and fanciful, that no concluſion can be drawn from them; to theſe remarks he adds, that if the Welſh towards the Cloſe of the twelfth Century had ſettled in any part of America, ſome remains of the Chriſtian doctrine muſt have been after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards found among their Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendants, when they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered three hundred years after their migration;—but here I muſt entirely diſagree with the learned Author,—three hundred
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:0616900400:145"/>
years cannot in this caſe be called a <q rend="inline">"ſhort period;"</q>—one Century would probably have been ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to have obliterated every mark of a Religion, that had to combat with the prejudices of an unlettered people; that did not addreſs itſelf immediately to their Intereſts, and through a Mode of Civilization, teach them at firſt only, as Warburton well expreſſes it, <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <p>The Goſpel, plain and ſimple as it is, and fitted in its nature for what it was ordained to effect, requires an intellect ſomething above that of a Savage to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend. Nor is it at all to the diſhonour of our holy Faith, that ſuch a one muſt be taught a previous leſſon; and firſt of all inſtructed in <hi>the emollient Arts of Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>See the Biſhop of Glouceſter's Sermon on the Propagation of the Goſpel.</p>
               </note> the emollient Arts of Life.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:0616900400:146"/>Chriſtianity ſeems to have been introduced into Britain, as early as the firſt Century, but of this great Event our Accounts muſt neceſſarily be very imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as the Saxons deſtroyed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the Writings in which it was recorded; Mona, we read, had certainly a School of Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:0616900400:147"/>
Learning many years before 182, when there was an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of Caerleon, and Suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans under him; but the Clergy had no diſtinct Pariſhes either in Angleſea or any other part of the kingdom, till many years afterwards. About the year 600, Pope Gregory ſent Auſtin the Monk to preach the Goſpel in England to the Heathen Saxons, who was received by Ethelbert; and being admitted to explain the Doctrine and
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:0616900400:148"/>
Myſteries of it, ſo well ſucceeded that he converted great numbers, and at length the King himſelf. Thus the Chriſtian Religion came to be eſtabliſhed in England under the Rites and Authority of the Romiſh Church, by which Auſtin was inſtituted Chief Biſhop, and ſeated by the Saxon king at Canterbury; but his Juriſdiction, though admitted in all the Saxon Territories, was not received by the Britiſh Prieſts or People in Wales.—In the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:0616900400:149"/>
reign of Elizabeth the Bible and Common Prayer were firſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into the Welſh Tongue, and at that time the People are ſaid to have adhered to the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick and Conſtitution of the Church with a ſcrupulous exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; how far the Doctrines and Worſhip of Chriſtianity may have deviated from their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal purity, or how far the Welſh may have been affected by the refined Tenets of their Engliſh Neighbours, I ſhall not preſume
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:0616900400:150"/>
to determine, at preſent I think there is every where much to be feared, from the Growth of Enthuſiaſm, the ſubtleties of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, and the Neceſſity, as well as Danger of Innovation.</p>
            <p>Many Popiſh cuſtoms are ſtill retained in Wales, particularly Offerings made to the Dead,—theſe Offerings muſt of courſe vary according to the Rank of the Perſons deceaſed, as well as the Affection that is borne to their Memories; I was at a
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:0616900400:151"/>
Pauper's Funeral where the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations amounted to half a Crown, and I met with a Clergyman afterwards who had once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ninety Guineas.</p>
            <p>Great complaints are made in many parts of this Country of the exorbitant Demands of Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords, and that the Rent of Ground is now advanced much higher than it will bear;—ſuch Complaints muſt of courſe be expected from the Sufferers, but I believe, they are here in
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:0616900400:152"/>
ſome inſtances made with reaſon; the landlords on the contrary may urge perhaps, that they act with ſtrict Juſtice, and that they have a Right at leaſt to try the experiment; but it ſhould be remembered that the Extreme of Right is Wrong, and there is a Tribute of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity due from the Superior, that He ſhould be always on a Certainty that he does not exact too much.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:0616900400:153"/>National Characters ſhould always be read with Exceptions; but if I muſt give my opinion of the Inhabitants of North Wales, I ſhall ſay, that the common people in general are civil and grateful, the Farmers rather ſlow and ſuſpicious, a Few of the inferior 'Squires re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſomewhat of the ſottiſh and the brutal, but among the higher Ranks, I have found, in the ſame proportion as in
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:0616900400:154"/>
England, lettered Society, hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Reception, and refined Addreſs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
