<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An appendix to the Representation: (printed in the year 1769,) of the injustice and dangerous tendency of tolerating slavery, or of admitting the least claim of private property in the persons of men in England. By Granville Sharp.</title>
            <author>Sharp, Granville, 1735-1813.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>28 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-06">2011 June</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004796386</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T22329</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW106046800</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K030995.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3306046800</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECSS</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">1135001200</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An appendix to the Representation: (printed in the year 1769,) of the injustice and dangerous tendency of tolerating slavery, or of admitting the least claim of private property in the persons of men in England. By Granville Sharp.</title>
                  <author>Sharp, Granville, 1735-1813.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Benjamin White, and Robert Horsefield [sic],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1772.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Sabin, 79809</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT22329.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1135001200:1"/>
            <p>AN APPENDIX TO THE REPRESENTATION, (Printed in the Year 1769,) OF THE Injuſtice and Dangerous Tendency of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerating Slavery, or of Admitting the leaſt Claim of Private Property in the PERSONS of MEN in ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>BY GRANVILLE SHARP.</p>
            <p>LONDON: PRINTED FOR BENJAMIN WHITE, (NO. 63.) IN FLEET-STREET, AND ROBERT HORSEFIELD, (NO. 22.) IN LUDGATE-STREET.</p>
            <p>MDCCLXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:1135001200:2"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Page 3. l. 12. for <hi>Principals</hi> read Principles.</item>
               <item>Page 12. l. 5. for <hi>them</hi> read him.</item>
               <item>Page 14. l. 22. for <hi>part</hi> read parts.</item>
               <item>Page 15. l. 14. for <hi>is untrue</hi> read is an untrue.</item>
               <item>Page 19. l. 8. for <hi>wordly</hi> read worldly.</item>
               <item>Page 24. l. 17. for <hi>ineffectually</hi> read ineffectual.</item>
               <item>Page 24. l. 18. for <hi>the</hi> read their.</item>
               <item>Page 26. l. 13. dele <hi>not.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:1135001200:3"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX TO THE REPRESENTATION, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>SINCE the Publication of my Book on <q>the Injuſtice and dangerous Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of Tolerating Slavery in England,</q> ſeveral unforeſeen circumſtances ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me to conſider that ſubject more ſtrictly, in order to obviate the inſinuations of ſome intereſted Perſons, who ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to inculcate and maintain, even in this Iſland, the ungenerous Weſt Indian Notions concerning property in Slaves.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe dangerous princip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſeveral violent Outrages have lately been commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1135001200:4"/>for the recovery of ſuch pretended property; and ſeveral Negroes have been knocked down and kidnapped by Ruffians, hired for that purpoſe, and have been hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on Ship Board in order to be tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Weſt Indies, in open Contempt of the Engliſh Laws, and of the Habeas Corpus Act in particular, which denounces heavy Penalties againſt thoſe who attempt to tranſport <hi>any Perſon whatever</hi> from this Kingdom againſt their Will: for I have ſhewn in my former Treatiſe in Pages 20 to 28 that Negroes, and all other Aliens are the <hi>King's Subjects,</hi> when reſiant in this Kingdom; and that they are entitled to the Protection of the Engliſh Laws in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and of the Habeas Corpus Act in particular. The ſame Arguments are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inforced in Pages 152 to 159.</p>
            <p>In Pages 136 to 146 of the ſame Book will be found a full Anſwer to ſuch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as had then been offered, concerning <hi>any right which the Maſter may have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to the perpetual ſervice of a Man;</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:1135001200:5"/>and in Pages 163 and 164 it is (I hope) demonſtrated that the Service of <hi>a Slave</hi> cannot juſtly be compared to the Service of <hi>an Apprentice;</hi> and that <hi>a Contract</hi> cannot be <hi>implied</hi> in ſuch a Caſe, as ſome learned Men have inſinuated.</p>
            <p>In the fourth and laſt Part of the ſaid Tract the Doctrines of <hi>Villenage</hi> are ſhewn to be <hi>obſolete,</hi> ſo that the leaſt Claim of <hi>perpetual Service,</hi> cannot be juſtified thereby.</p>
            <p>Theſe References to my former Work are inſerted here, partly to avoid a recapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation of theſe neceſſary points, and partly, that thoſe, who have any concern at preſent in ſuch matters, may thereby be enabled to conſider and examine theſe ſeveral Heads without the trouble of reading the whole Book; which is not ſo compendious as the Author could wiſh, it having been wrote at ſeveral different Periods, as occaſion offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and new Arguments were oppoſed, during the time that an Action (which was ſhamefully prolonged) depended againſt the Author and one of his Brothers, for having
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1135001200:6"/>accidentally (not officiouſly) aſſiſted a poor Negro Servant who was kidnapped and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined in the Poultry Compter without a Warrant, and there ſold to a Weſt-India Planter to be tranſported to Jamaica.</p>
            <p>It has already been proved, in the places before referred to, that <hi>no right whatever</hi> can be acquired to <hi>the perpetual Service of a Man</hi> without a <hi>Contract,</hi> and that ſuch a <hi>Contract</hi> cannot be <hi>implied,</hi> unleſs the free Conſent of both Parties is <hi>implied</hi> likewiſe, and clearly proved. Nevertheleſs as ſome ſordid and tenacious Contenders for this kind of imaginary Property are ſtill ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate as to riſque all the Penalties of a <hi>Premunire,</hi> beſides heavy Fines, by ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing to ſeize and carry away by force their quondam Slaves, I am willing for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to admit their <hi>Plea of Private Property</hi> merely that I may examine the Weight of it, and balance it with the Negroes <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty in his own Perſon,</hi> which, in a Land of Juſtice, doth equally demand ſome ſhare of our Conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:1135001200:7"/>The Authors and Abettors of the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and Inhuman Outrages of which I complain, cannot poſſibly ground their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence on any other Point whatſoever, than this ſingle Plea <hi>of private Property,</hi> and the neceſſary obligation of the Courts of Juſtice to <hi>ſecure to every Man his own.</hi> Now if a Negro Man, or any other human Being whatever, is conſidered as <hi>property</hi> in this Country, he falls under the Head of <hi>Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels</hi> and muſt neceſſarily (ſo far I mean as the Maſter's right ought to be conſidered) be ranked under that denomination.</p>
            <p>Now A CHATTEL is <hi>"res eſtimabilis;"</hi> a thing to be valued; a thing merely of a <hi>pecuniary</hi> conſideration; and the Slaveholder, accordingly, rates his ſuppoſed Property in <hi>a Man</hi> at <hi>a baſe price,</hi> not more, upon an average, than the value of <hi>a good Horſe,</hi> viz. 30 <hi>l.</hi> 40 <hi>l.</hi> or 50 <hi>l. to the diſgrace of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man nature:</hi> whereas, on the other hand, the Negro (though conſidered as <hi>a Chattel</hi> with reſpect to the Maſter's claim, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, alſo, <hi>a Man</hi>) has certainly a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1135001200:8"/>ſuperior right and title to <hi>his own Perſon;</hi> a claim <hi>of natural Property</hi> in himſelf, which is <hi>ineſtimable;</hi> far above all <hi>pecuniary</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; for, with reſpect to <hi>his ſide of the queſtion,</hi> THE HUMAN BODY IS ABOVE ALL PRICE, <q>Corpus humanum non recipit aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mationem.</q>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Principia Legis &amp; Aequitati', p. 14.</note> Surely <hi>his Liberty</hi> to him is <hi>ineſtimable!</hi>—at leaſt, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Law preſumes that it is ſo. <q>LIBERTAS EST RES INEST<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IMABILIS..</q> 
               <hi>Jenk. Cent.</hi> 52. Now let the idea of the CHATTEL, even at the higheſt price it will bear, be weighed and compared with the ſubject of the laſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned maxim, and <hi>let Juſtice hold the ſcale!</hi>—Shall we doubt whether the <hi>Eſtimable</hi> claim or <hi>the Ineſtimable</hi> claim is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred?</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Law regards <hi>the Perſon</hi> above his <hi>Poſſeſſions;</hi>
               </q>—<q>
                  <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Liberty moſt;</hi>
               </q>—<q>
                  <hi>Freehold</hi> and <hi>Inheritance above Chattels,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Ibid: p. 56.</note>—ſo that <hi>Chattels,</hi> we find, are but of a very inferior conſideration, being <hi>ranked only in the third degree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1135001200:9"/>
               <q>
                  <hi>Law favoureth, Life, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Dower,</hi>
               </q> and cannot, therefore, give the preference to the Maſter's mere <hi>mercenary</hi> claim of <hi>property,</hi> without a manifeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to itſelf,— <q>
                  <hi>And the Law abhors Falſhood, Variance, Contrariety,</hi> &amp;c.</q>—<q>
                  <hi>Lex Angliae non patitur</hi> ABSURDUM. 9. <hi>Cook.</hi> 22.</q>—<q>
                  <hi>Lex rejicit</hi> PUGNANTIA, incongrua. <hi>Jenk. Cent.</hi> 140, 133, 176.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, indeed, that the Law, in this caſe, may ſeem to ſuffer (or permit) a wrong by the Maſter's loſing his ſuppoſed right and property; but if we conſider, that the admitting <hi>ſuch a Property</hi> would be a want of <hi>Mercy</hi> in the Law, nay, even an act <hi>of Cruelty</hi> (which the Law abhors) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe perſons who have <hi>a ſuperior,</hi> becauſe <hi>a natural intereſt</hi> in the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this queſtion, it muſt appear to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, that the Law <hi>doth no wrong,</hi> when it rejects the <hi>leſſer</hi> claim of <hi>eſtimable</hi> property, in favour of that <hi>natural intereſt</hi> which is <hi>ineſtimable:</hi> And therefore, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the imaginary proprietor may think
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1135001200:10"/>himſelf aggrieved, yet the law is vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated herein, when we conſider that every claim <hi>of Property</hi> is abſolutely <hi>unjuſt in itſelf,</hi> and muſt neceſſarily be ſet aſide through <hi>the mercy</hi> of the Law, if it interferes, or is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with that <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>equitable</hi> claim to <hi>perſonal ſecurity,</hi> which the law of this kingdom hath <hi>always favoured;</hi> for <hi>"the Law of England is a Law of Mercy."</hi> 
               <q>LEX ANGLIAE EST LEX MISERICORDIAE, 2 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 315.</q> ſo that each Slaveholder muſt ſtill be obliged to allow, <q>
                  <hi>that the Law</hi> (even in this unavoidable deciſion againſt himſelf) <hi>doth injury to no man:</hi>
               </q>—<q>
                  <hi>Lex nemini operatur iniquum.</hi>
               </q>—<q>
                  <hi>nemini facit injuriam.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Let the Slaveholder remember, alſo, that his being thus deprived of his imaginary Property, cannot be conſidered otherwiſe (let him make the moſt of it) than merely, as <hi>a private loſs;</hi> whereas, if ſuch an <hi>unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural right</hi> be admitted without due conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the ſuperior <hi>Perſonal Right</hi> of the Negro, a worſe Vaſſalage, than the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1135001200:11"/>Villenage, <note n="*" place="bottom">The Antient Villenage was long ſince extinguiſhed through the virtue and continual oppoſition of the King's Courts in favour of the <hi>Common Law,</hi> which I have elſewhere ſhewn: ſo that ſuch another <hi>unjuſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi> cannot poſſibly be admitted, without an apparent violation of the <hi>Common Law.</hi>
               </note> would in time be introduced into this free Chriſtian Country, by which <hi>the Publick</hi> would <hi>be materially injured,</hi> as well <hi>in Honour,</hi> as <hi>in Morals,</hi> and <hi>National Safety:</hi> therefore, <q>the Law will rather endure <hi>a particular miſchief</hi> (as the loſs of private <hi>property) than a general incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience.</hi>
               </q> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Lex citius tollerare vult</hi> PRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VATUM DAMNUM <hi>quam</hi> PUBLICUM MALUM. Co. <hi>Lit.</hi> 152.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus ſtands the Common Law, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the point in queſtion; and it is not (I apprehend) in the leaſt altered by Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Law; ſo that unleſs the Advocates for Slavery can prove that it is altered, we may ſafely conclude with the following maxim, that <q>
                  <hi>whatever was at Common Law, ana is not taken away by Statute, remaineth ſtill,</hi> Co. Lit. 115.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:1135001200:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>I flatter myſelf, that no Gentleman of the Law will attempt to contradict or ſet aſide the eſtabliſhed Maxims which are here quoted, becauſe ſuch a behaviour would neceſſarily draw upon them that juſt cenſure and contempt, which the learned Author <note n="*" place="bottom">Chriſtopher Seyniarmayne, or St. German, who died in 1539.</note> of the <hi>Doctor and Student</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in his VIIIth <note n="†" place="bottom">See the Engliſh Tranſlation printed in 1746. page 27.</note> Chapter againſt all Lawyers, <hi>without exception, to dignity,</hi> that preſume to contradict approved maxims.— <q>The Fourth Ground of the Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (ſays he) ſtandeth in divers princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that be called <hi>in the Law, Maxims,</hi> the which have been always taken for Law (SEMPER HABITA ET TENTA SUNT PRO LEGE) in this Realm, <hi>ſo that it is not lawful for any that is learned to deny them;</hi> for every one of thoſe <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims</hi> is ſufficient authority to himſelf.</q>— Thus far the Tranſlator, but we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the words of the excellent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1135001200:13"/>himſelf <note n="*" place="bottom">See the Latin Edition in 12mo. printed in 1604. page 27.</note>, that Men, who deny theſe Maxims <hi>are no longer worthy to be talked with;</hi>—for he adds, <q>
                  <hi>in tanto quod cum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantibus ea</hi> (viz. Maxima) <hi>non eſt ulterius arguendum</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">
                     <q>Quartum fundamentum Legis Angliae ſtat in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſis principiis quae a peritis Legis Angliae MAXIMA vocantur, quae SEMPER HABITA ET TENTA SUNT PRO LEGE in hoc Regno Angliae, quibus NON EST LICITUM ALICUI LEGIS PERITO CONTRADICERE, quia <hi>unumquodque maximorum illorum</hi> eſt ſibi ipſi fides, in tanto quod CUM NEGANTIBUS EA NON EST UL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERIUS ARGUENDUM.</q>
                  </note>.</q>
            </p>
            <p>A more modern, but not leſs reſpectable Author, has furniſhed us with a Maxim nearly to the ſame effect, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>Thoſe that forego (or ſet aſide) the Law of the Land, deſervedly incur from thence a perpetual ſtain of Infamy.</q>—<q>
                  <hi>Legem terrae amittentes perpetuam infamiae notam inde merito incurrunt.</hi> Sir Ed. Cook. IIId. Inſt. 221.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Plea of private property in the Perſons of Men</hi> muſt neceſſarily fall to the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1135001200:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ground, when it is meaſured by the Maxims of the Common Law.</p>
            <p>I have not, deſignedly, done any injuſtice to this Plea; and, tho' I may, perhaps, have treated my ſubject injudiciouſly, and not according to Method, yet I defy the moſt intereſted advocate for Slavery to give more real weight or value to ſuch kind of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty than what I have already ſtated, if, at the ſame time, the Learned Judge Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone's arguments concerning the three Origins of Slavery be duly conſidered.</p>
            <p>I have quoted theſe Arguments at length in my former Tract (from page 141 to 145) but ſhall, nevertheleſs, repeat them here and pledge them as unanſwerable by the moſt able Caſuiſt, or even by the Learned Author himſelf were he to undertake it. But this I ſpeak only comparatively, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to his great <hi>abilities,</hi> not his <hi>will:</hi> for though I have been obliged to guard againſt ſome doubtful expreſſions in other part of his Works (See my former Tract pages 136 to 141) yet I have too good an opinion of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1135001200:15"/>that worthy Gentleman to conceive that he will ever entertain any real inclination for ſo ungenerous a taſk.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The three origins of the right of Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, (ſays he) aſſigned by Juſtinian, are all of them built upon falſe foundations. As firſt, Slavery is held to ariſe <hi>"jure gentium,"</hi> from a ſtate of captivity in war; whence Slaves are called <hi>mancipia, quaſi manu capti.</hi> The conqueror, ſay the Civilians, had a right to the life of his captive; and, having ſpared that, has a right to deal with him as he pleaſes. But it is untrue poſition, when taken generally, that, by the law of nature or nations, a man may kill his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: he has only a right to kill him, in particular caſes; in caſes of abſolute neceſſity, for ſelf-defence; and it is plain this abſolute neceſſity did not ſubſiſt, ſince the victor did not actually kill him, but made him priſoner. War is itſelf juſtifiable only on principles
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1135001200:16"/>of ſelf-preſervation; and therefore it gives no other right over priſoners, but merely to diſable them from doing harm to us, by confining their perſons: much leſs can it give a right to kill, torture, abuſe, plunder, or even to enſlave an enemy, when the war is over. Since there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the right of <hi>making</hi> Slaves by capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, depends on a ſuppoſed right of ſlaughter, that foundation failing, the conſequence drawn from it muſt fail like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. But ſecondly, it is ſaid, that Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very may begin <hi>"jure civili;"</hi> when one man ſells himſelf to another. This, if only meant of contracts to ſerve or work for another, is very juſt: but when ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to ſtrict Slavery, in the ſenſe of the laws of old Rome, or modern Barbary, is alſo impoſſible. Every ſale implies a price, a <hi>quid pro quo,</hi> an equivalent given to the ſeller in lieu of what he transfers to the buyer: but what equivalent can be given for life and liberty, both of which (in abſolute Slavery) are held to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1135001200:17"/>be in the maſter's diſpoſal?—His pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty alſo, the very price he ſeems to receive, devolves <hi>ipſo facto</hi> to his maſter, the inſtant he becomes his Slave. In this caſe therefore the buyer gives nothing, and the ſeller receives nothing: of what validity then can a ſale be, which deſtroys the very principles upon which all ſales are founded?—Laſtly, we are told, that beſides theſe two ways by which Slaves <hi>"fiunt,"</hi> or are acquired, they may alſo be hereditary: <hi>ſervi naj<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunter;"</hi> the children of acquired Slaves are, <hi>jure naturae,</hi> by a negative kind of birth-right, Slaves alſo. But, this being built on the two former rights, muſt fall together with them. If nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther captivity, nor the ſale of one's ſelf, can by THE LAW OF NATURE AND REASON reduce the parent to Slavery, much leſs can they reduce the offspring. <hi>Upon theſe principles</hi> THE LAW OF ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND <hi>abhors, and will not endure the exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Slavery, within this nation:</hi>
               </q> ſo that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1135001200:18"/>when an attempt was made to introduce it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <q>by ſtatute 1 Edward VI. c. 3. which ordained, that all idle vagabonds ſhould be made Slaves, and fed upon bread, water, or ſmall drink, and refuſe meat; ſhould wear a ring of iron round their necks, arms, or legs; and ſhould be compelled by beating, chaining, or otherwiſe, to perform the work aſſigned them, were it never ſo vile; <hi>the ſpirit of the nation could not brook this condition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> even in the moſt abandoned rogues; and therefore this ſtatute was repealed in two years afterwards.</q> Coms. 1. Vol. p. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3.</p>
            <p>Thus it is clear that there can be no claim of right to <hi>the perpetual Service of a man</hi> which is not ORIGINALLY FOUNDED EITHER IN RAPINE THEFT OR NOTORI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUS INJUSTICE. <q>For it muſt be obvious to every perſon, who is not blinded by the deſire of gain,</q> ſays the author of a Short Account of the Slave Trade, &amp;c. which I cauſed to be reprinted in 1768, p. 64) <q>that the Right, by which theſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1135001200:19"/>men hold the Negroes in Bondage, is no other than what is derived from thoſe who ſtole them, who, having no other Title, but that which Robbers have over their Prey could not convey any better to the purchaſer; and that therefore to continue to hold them in Bondage, for wordly Advantage, by no other right than that which thoſe guilty men give them, is conſenting to, and partaking of their Guilt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore when a Notorious Outrage and Breach of the Peace is committed under the pretence of any ſuch <hi>groundleſs claim of ſervice,</hi> the Magiſtrate who neglects to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> the perſon oppreſs'd, and <hi>to puniſh</hi> the Offenders, is certainly a partaker of their Guilt; and no upright and conſcientious Judge (who does not ſet up his <hi>own will above the laws of the Land</hi>) can poſſibly entertain any <hi>doubt in his mind</hi> about the puniſhment of ſuch Offenders: for when the Laws of the Land, and eſpecially the Habeas Corpus Act, are expreſsly and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1135001200:20"/>clearly <hi>on one Side of the Queſtion</hi> (without the leaſt exception whatever concerning any difference or diſtinction of Perſons,) and when the <hi>only plea</hi> on the <hi>other ſide of the Queſtion</hi> is abſolutely without Foundation either in Natural Equity or the eſtabliſhed Law and Cuſtoms of this Country, what room can there be for <hi>doubt?</hi> and how would a Judge be able to juſtify an Arreſt of Judgment in ſuch a caſe?</p>
            <p>Every Judge is (or ought to be) ſworn, that <hi>he will miniſter Juſtice indifferently</hi> (or without reſpect of Perſons) <hi>to all Men.</hi>— <q>Se juſtitiam miniſtraturum indifferenter omnibus hominibus.</q> (Forteſcue de Laudibus Leg. Angliae, Chap. 51.) And therefore if the Laws and Eſtabliſhed Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms of the land with reſpect to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Queſtion make <hi>no diſtinction of Perſons</hi> (whether Bond or Free, White or Black) neither can a Judge, without riſquing <hi>the guilt of Perjury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have proved in Page 159 of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Tract, <q>that the Laws of England
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1135001200:21"/>(in the late Reign) were eſteemed obnox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious to any involuntary Bondage without a juſt cauſe, and to all <hi>private jurisdictions whatſoever;</hi> ſo that <hi>an extenſion of</hi> THE INFLUENCE,<note n="*" place="bottom">See the Act of 20 Geo. II. intituled an Act for taking away and aboliſhing the heretable juriſdictions in that part of Great Britain called Scotland, &amp;c.</note> BENEFIT AND PROTEC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION</q>
               <hi>of theſe laws</hi> was conſidered as a relief to our Fellow Subjects in Scotland from all <hi>private</hi> oppreſſion. I mean the late pernicious <hi>Vaſſalage</hi> of Scotland; the extinction of which has happily produced the preſent flouriſhing State of Arts, Trade, and Manufactories amongſt our Brethren in that part of the Iſland.</p>
            <p>But as the claim of <hi>private property in the perſons of men</hi> is the very root and foundation of the worſt kind of <hi>Vaſſalage,</hi> I muſt obſerve, that, if any Judge ſhould hereafter venture to ſuſpend the execution of the Engliſh Laws in conſideration of <hi>any ſuch kind of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions whatever,</hi> he might be ſaid to ſtab the conſtitutional freedom of two Great and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1135001200:22"/>ancient Kingdoms at one blow. For how ſhould our fellow ſubjects at the other end of the Iſland be able to truſt in the parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Promiſe of the <q>
                  <hi>Influence, Benefit and Protection of the King's Laws</hi>
               </q> to be <hi>extended</hi> as far as Scotland, if the ſaid Laws were really liable to be rendered <hi>ineffectual,</hi> even in England, by a mere <hi>groundleſs doubt</hi> of one ſingle Judge.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Doubt</hi> is certainly a very inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient excuſe for an <hi>arreſt of Judgment,</hi> in any caſe whatever, unleſs <hi>"ſtrong and probable Grounds"</hi> are alledged to juſtify it; but a <hi>groundleſs doubt</hi> upon the preſent queſtion would be more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly criminal; becauſe it would, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably, tend to the introduction of the <hi>diabolical</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">See a Note in my former Tract, page 153, where this hard Epithet is proved.</note> Tyranny and Injuſtice of our Weſt Indian Colonies, whereby <hi>human Nature is vilifyed and degraded to the Rank and level of brute Beaſts;</hi> for not only the groſſeſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of our <hi>fellow man</hi> but even <hi>murder</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Ibid. page 66 and 67.</note>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:1135001200:23"/>is there tolerated, and <hi>Marriage</hi> exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <note n="*" place="bottom">Ibid. page 152.</note> as I have ſhewn in the notes to my former work. <note n="†" place="bottom">Ibid. page 39 to 73. The laſt of theſe pages, (73) is now earneſtly recommended by the Author to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious peruſal of all perſons who have any influence in Government, if they ſincerely wiſh proſperity to England.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Whatever tends to the ſame point (viz. the <hi>degradation of human nature</hi> and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction of that conſummate wickedneſs which muſt of courſe prevail <hi>wherever Slavery is tolerated</hi>) does certainly promote the Work and Service of the <hi>Grand Enemy of Mankind,</hi> and conſequently ought to be eſtemed highly offenſive to Almighty God.</p>
            <p>Some Perſons may, perhaps, alledge in vindication of the <hi>ſuppoſed doubt</hi> above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, that the Legiſlature has, at diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent times, given encouragement to the <hi>African Slave Trade,</hi> (however deteſtable, and <hi>pernicious to mankind</hi> it may be eſteemed) and that the ſame ought to be accounted
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1135001200:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>an acknowledgment, that <hi>Property in Slaves</hi> is, in ſome degree, <hi>lawful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such Arguments, and Inſinuations I have frequently heard, but let the Advocates for Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very make the moſt of them they can, yet ſhall they not be able to avail themſelves of any ſuch ſtrained, conſequential Doctrines: for ſuppoſe that the Legiſlature ſhould, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warily, happen to <hi>do wrong</hi> in any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular point whatſoever, and that any one of their Subjects in a judicial character ſhould, inſtead of giving them warning of <hi>the evil,</hi> be ready to go before them in it, and ſhould even ſhew himſelf prone to carry the <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief</hi> to a much higher pitch, than the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlature</hi> ever conceived or intended, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to render ineffectually one of their moſt ſolemn acts, relating, in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, to the ſame point, which we will ſuppoſe to have remained <hi>unrepealed</hi> and <hi>in full force,</hi> and which might therefore have been uſed as a juſt and honeſt expedient to ſave <hi>the honour</hi> of the <hi>Legiſlature</hi> and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the inadvertent <hi>evil.</hi> Such a neglect
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1135001200:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>and contempt of a <hi>poſitive and eſtabliſhed ſtatute,</hi> added to a diſregard of <hi>natural as well as national Juſtice,</hi> ought to be eſteemed as a ſufficient reaſon for condemning ſuch a man as <hi>a moſt undutiful ſubject, and dangerous Politician.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, to carry the Argument ſtill further, let us ſuppoſe (what I truſt will never come to paſs) that even the <hi>Legiſlature itſelf</hi> ſhould become ſo miſerably degenerate as to repeal, or annul, the Habeas Corpus Act, and adopt, inſtead of it, the moſt horrid and diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal of the Weſt Indian Laws; yet, even in this caſe, the natural <hi>unlawfulneſs</hi> and wickedneſs of ſuch principles as thoſe laws contain, would <hi>ſtill remain;</hi> for <q>No Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lature on Earth, which is the ſupreme power in every Civil Society, can alter the Nature of things, or make that to be lawful, which is contrary to the Law of God, the ſupreme Legiſlator and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of the World. Miſchief may be framed, and eſtabliſhed by a Law, but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1135001200:26"/>if it be, it is miſchief ſtill, as much ſo as it was before it was eſtabliſhed, tho' its being ſo may make Men inſenſible of their Guilt, or bold and fearleſs in the Perpetration of it; for too many, among Chriſtians, are, contrary to <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, more influenced by the Fear of Man, than by the Fear of God.—It is really a ſerious Subject, and I own it raiſes a ſerious concern in my Mind, that ſuch Barbarity ſhould be ſuffered in Chriſtian Nations. It is enough to make a Man's Heart ach, unleſs he has not loſt all Love and Regard to his Kind, to think that ſo many Thouſands of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Race ſhould be ſacrificed every year to that greedy voracious God <hi>Mammon</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Short Account of the Slave Trade, p. 52.</note>.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Number of Negro Slaves bought <hi>in one Year only</hi> (viz. 1768) on the Coaſt of Africa, from Cape Blanco to Rio Longo, amounted to 104, 100 Perſons, according to a particular ſtate of that Trade inſerted in the Gazetteer of the 8th of July, 1769.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1135001200:27"/>Theſe miſerable creatures, it is ſaid, <q>
                  <hi>were bought by Barter for European and Indian Goods, chiefly at</hi> 15 <hi>l. Sterling each.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now it is dreadful to conſider <hi>what multitudes of men</hi> muſt have been <hi>killed</hi> merely in the attempt to take ſo many wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Captives for ſale; and again <hi>what multitudes,</hi> out of ſo large a number, would <hi>die,</hi> as uſual, in their paſſage to the Weſt Indies and America either of Grief and deſpair, or by being inhumanly ſtifled in the Holds of Ships; beſides the large proportion (nearly one half) that would <hi>die</hi> of the ſeaſoning, (as it is called) after their arrival in the plantations; and laſtly that all the remainder of <hi>this vaſt multitude of</hi> 104, 100 <hi>miſerable human beings</hi> will probably be <hi>worn out</hi> by hard ſervice and oppreſſion in the ſpace of about 16 years, or leſs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the average rate of ſome calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that have been publiſhed. Theſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, I ſay, muſt needs inſpire us with indignation and horror even though the evil, at preſent, is at a conſiderable diſtance from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1135001200:28"/>us. But if the advocates, for <hi>the unnatural and unlawful claims,</hi> againſt which I contend, ſhould receive ſuch encouragement as to <hi>confirm their pretenſions;</hi> the ſame muſt inevitably introduce by degrees a Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Weſt India Slavery, with all its <hi>direful conſequences,</hi> into this Kingdom: which, added to the manifold corruptions and deprav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ties into which this Kingdom has already unhappily fallen, will certainly cauſe our meaſure of Iniquity to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow, and, in all probability, draw down upon us ſome dreadful and ſpeedy <hi>national</hi> calamity<note n="*" place="bottom">The Iriſh at the firſt Council of Armagh, in the Reign of K. Henry the II. were perſuaded (and they had, but too much cauſe for it) that the miſeries, with which their Iſland was then afflicted, were the <hi>effect of God's Wrath</hi> for their having tolerated Slavery amongſt them. See Rapin, 2 Vol. p. 521.</note>, beſides that ſevere judgment, which is already but too apparent amongſt us, I mean that deplorable <hi>Hardneſs of Heart,</hi> and abandoned <hi>Spirit of Injuſtice,</hi> which has rendered the publication of this remonſtrance neceſſary.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Old Jewry,</hi> 
                  <date>16th <hi>Jan.</hi> 1772.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>GRANVILLE SHARP.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
