<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Marcellus: a monody. Humbly inscrib'd to Her Royal Highness the Princess of Wales. By Mr Delap, M.A.</title>
            <author>Delap, J. (John), 1725-1812.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>8 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008 September</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004805659</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T38961</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW110483615</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K039429.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3310483615</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECLL</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">0163500100</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Marcellus: a monody. Humbly inscrib'd to Her Royal Highness the Princess of Wales. By Mr Delap, M.A.</title>
                  <author>Delap, J. (John), 1725-1812.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11,[1]p. ; 4⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Dodsley, and sold by M. Cooper,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1751.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a half-title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT38961.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:0163500100:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>MARCELLUS: A MONODY.</p>
            <p>Humbly inſcrib'd to Her Royal Highneſs THE PRINCESS of <hi>WALES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>DELAP,</hi> M. A. Fellow of <hi>Magdalen</hi> College, CAMBRIDGE.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Multis ille bonis flebilis occidit</l>
               <l>Nulli flebilior quam tibi.</l>
               <bibl>HOR.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for R. DODSLEY in <hi>Pall-mall;</hi> And ſold by M. COOPER in <hi>Pater-noſter-Row.</hi> 1751.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:0163500100:2"/>
            <head>MARCELLUS: A MONODY.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>YE virgin-train, that whilom wak'd your lyres,</l>
               <l>Faſt by the chryſtal ſprings of <hi>Helicon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To heav'nly ſtrains of joy thoſe dulcet Notes</l>
               <l>Ill ſuit a Nation's univerſal moan,</l>
               <l>When ev'ry hope with their loſt Prince is gone.</l>
               <l>The thrilling voice of joy no longer floats</l>
               <l>O'er pale <hi>Britannia's</hi> ſadly-ſilent ſhore;</l>
               <l>MARCELLUS is no more!</l>
               <l>But oh, the doleful change! the plaintive muſe,</l>
               <l>In cypreſs crown'd, muſt pour her piteous loan</l>
               <l>Of ſigh, and tear, and heart-empiercing groan!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:0163500100:3"/>
               <l>Come then, <hi>Melpomene,</hi> begin the Lay,</l>
               <l>With rueful Tears your ſorrowing Dirges ſteep,</l>
               <l>Such tears as erſt your ſiſter-muſe did weep</l>
               <l>For her dear twin<hi>-Palici:</hi> every ſtream</l>
               <l>Shall ſtop to hear your theme,</l>
               <l>Then ſadly murmur to the plaintive ſhore</l>
               <l>MARCELLUS is no more!</l>
               <l>And feeble Echo from her aery cave</l>
               <l>Shall back return the note, and ev'ry vale,</l>
               <l>With all its flow'rs ſhall droop to hear the tale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How can he lie unwept who knew to raiſe</l>
               <l>Eſteem and love in every loyal heart.</l>
               <l>He was the pride of ev'ry Shepherd's praiſe,</l>
               <l>Grac'd with each decent and each princely part.</l>
               <l>Nor did the muſe ungrateful pour her lays;</l>
               <l>He oft wou'd liſten to the poet's art:</l>
               <l>And oft alone, beneath the muſe's grot,</l>
               <l>Hid from a nation's eye, he ſat and thought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:0163500100:4"/>
               <l>Full many an hour, his Offspring pratling round,</l>
               <l>In gentle dalliance has he fondly ſmil'd;</l>
               <l>Full many an hour, ſequeſter'd from annoys,</l>
               <l>In tender amorous talk, has he beguil'd,</l>
               <l>With the dear Partner of his deareſt joys.</l>
               <l>Mean while the foe of Life, with treacherous art,</l>
               <l>In ſly deſtruction prey'd upon his heart;</l>
               <l>And yet no fatal ſymptom did appear;</l>
               <l>The blood ſtill mantled on his roſy cheek.</l>
               <l>As <hi>Phaebus</hi> oft the clouds with gold doth ſtreak,</l>
               <l>While brooding ſtorms engender in the air.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where was your knowledge then, you ſapient Tribe,</l>
               <l>That boaſt commandment o'er the pulſe of life?</l>
               <l>Was not a Princeſs' tears ſufficient bribe,</l>
               <l>Cou'd not a King's, a Nation's pray'rs prevail</l>
               <l>To make your niceſt ſkill explore his ail?</l>
               <l>Some few more Years the breath of Life ſupply,</l>
               <l>And keep him from the Sky—</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:0163500100:5"/>
Ah me, what boots your ſkill?—Not all the pray'rs</l>
               <l>That pale <hi>Britannia,</hi> and her King might pour;</l>
               <l>Not all <hi>Auguſta</hi>'s ſadly-flowing Tears,</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Aeſculapius'</hi> Sons with all their care,</l>
               <l>Might ward the black inevitable hour.</l>
               <l>Or could their Prince's vital Band repair,</l>
               <l>Which in their mood the fatal Siſters tore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alaſs, he droop'd in life's matureſt age,</l>
               <l>While <hi>Albion</hi>'s ſceptre hung before his view;</l>
               <l>And thrice the wiſe <hi>Machaon</hi> did preſage</l>
               <l>That <hi>Febris</hi> her inflaming rage withdrew;</l>
               <l>Yet then renewing her malignant ſtrife,</l>
               <l>The deadly Fiend unhous'd his tender Life.</l>
               <l>Then ſtream'd the tear from ev'ry <hi>Britiſh</hi> eye.</l>
               <l>But chief th' unhappy ſire, in diſmal plight,</l>
               <l>Deteſts the odious light,</l>
               <l>And with loud wailings tears the arched ſky.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:0163500100:6"/>
And calls on death to bring a kind reprieve,</l>
               <l>And lay his cruel ſorrows in the grave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ah! my Muſe, how may thy voice record,</l>
               <l>Tho' well I ween thou ſhar'ſt her piteous ſtate,</l>
               <l>The tender unimaginable woe,</l>
               <l>Of his dear Conſort for her raviſh'd Lord,</l>
               <l>Torn by the hand of unrelenting Fate!</l>
               <l>Then hide the tears thou canſt not give to flow.</l>
               <l>Enough, that when reviving life did chaſe</l>
               <l>Death's diſmal image from her pallid face;</l>
               <l>With manly ſhew ſhe maſk'd her ſorrows dread;</l>
               <l>And greatly ſtrove to chear with kind relief</l>
               <l>Her tender Offspring's ſympathetic grief,</l>
               <l>Who at their Mother's wretched plight grew ſad.</l>
               <l>What heart ſo ſtony but did melt in tears?</l>
               <l>See pale <hi>Britannia</hi> wears,</l>
               <l>Thro' all her Sons, one diſmal face of woe.</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Britiſh</hi> eyes alone do overflow;</l>
               <l>See even the <hi>Orcades</hi> and frozen Realms</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:0163500100:7"/>
By Ocean's wat'ry barrier ſunder'd far,</l>
               <l>Pay their full tribute of a tender tear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mean while the awful tongue of death doth pierce</l>
               <l>Night's drowzy ear, with tollings, deep and ſlow;</l>
               <l>And now the ſolemn pealing Organs blow.</l>
               <l>The winking Lamps a duſky luſtre ſhed</l>
               <l>Along the Manſions of the Dead,</l>
               <l>Where mould'ring Kings in ſilent duſt repoſe.</l>
               <l>And now with often interrupted ſighs,</l>
               <l>The Lawn-rob'd Prelate his laſt duty pays,</l>
               <l>And duſt to duſt conveys:</l>
               <l>And now entomb'd his ſacred body lies,</l>
               <l>Free from the cares, that this vain life encloſe.</l>
               <l>Up to yon regions of eternal day,</l>
               <l>The free, unbodied ſpirit wings its way;</l>
               <l>There in the boſom of its god doth bide</l>
               <l>In pure, immaculate, unſhaken bliſs;</l>
               <l>Nor recks the loſs of earthly Kingdom's pride,</l>
               <l>Enthron'd for aye in heavenly paradiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:0163500100:8"/>
               <l>And thou, ſad Conſort of a Prince too good</l>
               <l>Longer to viſit this forſaken clime;</l>
               <l>Ah! ceaſe to weary the relentleſs ſky,</l>
               <l>With bitter penance and with bootleſs tears.</l>
               <l>Nor deem with vainly-pious pray'rs</l>
               <l>To draw him from his bliſsful dear abode;</l>
               <l>Where now he never more may fear to die,</l>
               <l>Nor grieve, ſave when your plaints wou'd him recall,</l>
               <l>Not lent for aye to your fond hopes, I ween!</l>
               <l>And oh! forgive the muſe, whoſe daring lays</l>
               <l>Wou'd grateful pour her artleſs loyal teen;</l>
               <l>Reckleſs that true to draw a Prince's praiſe,</l>
               <l>Aſks the nice touches of a maſter-hand,</l>
               <l>Since ſhe may ſee in your fair Offspring plann'd</l>
               <l>The graceful dowries of their Father's mind;</l>
               <l>See Mercy, Truth, Religion, Liberty,</l>
               <l>Beneath the ſhine of your enliv'ning eye,</l>
               <l>And ev'ry virtue that may bleſs mankind.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
