<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tears of the muses; in a conference between prince Germanicus, and a male-content party</title>
            <title>Tears of the muses</title>
            <author>Hill, Aaron, 1685-1750.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>39 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008 September</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004902903</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T49906</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW111927118</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K046076.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3311927118</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECLL</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">0122601600</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tears of the muses; in a conference between prince Germanicus, and a male-content party</title>
                  <title>Tears of the muses</title>
                  <author>Hill, Aaron, 1685-1750.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40p. ; 4⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for T. Ward,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1737.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. By Aaron Hill.</note>
                  <note>Titlepage in red and black.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Foxon, H231</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT49906.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:0122601600:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Tears of the Muſes; IN A CONFERENCE, BETWEEN Prince <hi>GERMANICUS,</hi> AND A Male-content Party.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for T. WARD, near <hi>Pater-noſter Row.</hi> M.DCC.XXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:0122601600:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honorable, and Publick-Spirited, The <hi>Preſident, Officers,</hi> and <hi>Committee,</hi> OF THE SOCIETY FOR <hi>Encouragement</hi> of LEARNING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords, and Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>LEST it ſhou'd be conſider'd as a Diſregard of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, when a Poem of a <hi>Satirical</hi> Species, is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs'd to the Patronage moſt diſtinguiſh'd for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Humanity, pleaſe to receive it, as a poetical <hi>Janus</hi>; of whoſe Oppoſite two Faces, the faireſt and beſt drawn you will find to be <hi>Panegyric.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT, on That Side, you were <hi>attach'd.</hi>—And, ſuch devoted Admirers of the <hi>Life</hi> wou'd with Difficulty have been brought to allow a <hi>Reſemblance</hi> in the <hi>Picture.</hi> Whereas, on the Side of the <hi>Satire,</hi> you cou'd not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:0122601600:3"/>
be Parties concerned: and were, therefore, beſt qualify'd, to judge it, impartially.</p>
            <p>YET, ſince it is not by any Merit of mine, that you are ſo ſafe on the Satirical Quarter, It was fit I ſhou'd do <hi>ſomething,</hi> that might have room to expect your Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment. I have, therefore, declin'd any <hi>Encomium</hi> on your generous Society; or on Any of its particular Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: tho', to Every Reader, <hi>not ſuch,</hi> It wou'd have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd the <hi>Delight</hi> of the Poem.</p>
            <p>BUT, You are ſuch Enemies to every Kind of <hi>Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that I apprehended the very Appearance, of an Attempt at evading your <hi>Judgment,</hi> by engaging your <hi>Generoſity</hi> in my Favour.</p>
            <p>IN this Situation, there are preſerv'd to you all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Rights of the <hi>Critic.</hi> Yet, I am under no Pain from the Uſe you may make of that Freedom: For, what candid Writer wou'd wiſh to eſcape a Reproach, where, being ſure of its <hi>Juſtice,</hi> he can be made but the Wiſer, from Effect of its <hi>Severity?</hi> And, as to the more deſirable <hi>Reverſe</hi> of the Proſpect, no Man is in Danger of miſſing your <hi>Approbation,</hi> unleſs he has, no where, <hi>deſerved</hi> it.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Muſes</hi> have uſed you too kindly, not to expect your <hi>Concern,</hi> for the Fate you will find 'em reduc'd to: And, to hear of <hi>your</hi> Grief, and good Wiſhes in their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, may, from the Knowledge they have of your <hi>Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,</hi>
               <pb n="v" facs="tcp:0122601600:4"/>
deſerve to be thought little leſs, than a <hi>Balance,</hi> for the Neglect they are under, from Thouſands.</p>
            <p>BUT, to ſpeak a plain Truth, without <hi>Metaphor,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Advantage the Poetical World wou'd have deriv'd from imaginary <hi>Muſes,</hi> might be, <hi>really,</hi> an Effect, of ſome ſuch confederate Influence as yours, in good Earneſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erted.</p>
            <p>HOW many great and deſirable Changes in literate Taſte, may we not reaſonably expect, from the aſſociated Preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of Numbers, united, as <hi>you</hi> are, upon the moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Principle in Nature, an unprofitable and voluntary Purſuit of the Benefit of Others, from Effect of your own Coſt, and Labour?</p>
            <p>TO inſtance, in One, the moſt obvious and eaſy of many: How ſoon wou'd our preſent low Reliſh for <hi>dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Buffoonery</hi> give Way, to your <hi>nobler Example?</hi>—perſevering (indeed, with ſome neceſſary Obſtinacy) to applaud, and ſupport, good <hi>Tragedy</hi> and <hi>Comedy:</hi> till what is now but mere <hi>Reaſon,</hi> might have the Honour to be conſider'd as <hi>Faſhion</hi>—by Concurrence of your munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Endeavours, but for one or two ſhort Winters?</p>
            <p>AND, yet, what a National Deliverance were This!—With what Effuſion of <hi>unmercenary</hi> Gratitude would it immortalize thoſe generous Conquerors, who, protecting the nobleſt of our Youth from bad Principles, had, by
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:0122601600:5"/>
expelling Mean-ſpiritedneſs, Corruption, and Folly, from our <hi>Theatres,</hi> intercepted them in their Paſſage upward, into Situations whence their Effects, extended wider, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in Proportion more dreadful.</p>
            <p>WHATEVER Miſconceptions have ariſen, with View to your more immediate and particular good Purpoſe, from its Relation to the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of a conſiderable Body, in Trade, whoſe Intereſt may appear to be concern'd, not in the <hi>Intention,</hi> but <hi>Effect,</hi> of your Eſtabliſhment, There will never, I am perſuaded, lie any Objection at all againſt this opener and eaſier Road, to the Redemption of one Branch of Polite Learning, that ſtands in too viſible Need of your Patronage.</p>
            <p>AND, now, ſince All the Motive I had to this diſtant Addreſs was the Pleaſure of profeſſing, in public, my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for ſo <hi>public</hi> a <hi>Spirit</hi>; you will forgive me, that I with-hold from your Knowledge a Diſcovery of ſo little Importance, as the <hi>Name,</hi> of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lords, and Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>Your devoted Humble Servant, <hi>The Author.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:0122601600:6"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>NOT aſſuming ſuch an Air of Authority, as to give Rules, much leſs <hi>Examples,</hi> of Writing, the Author in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Verſes intended no more, than an humble Attempt, from mere private Curioſity, upon an Idea of <hi>Satire,</hi> which appear'd to be <hi>New:</hi> or not <hi>practis'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is indeed, ſomething ſo like <hi>Cruelty</hi> in the <hi>Face</hi> of that Species of Poetry, that it can only be reconcil'd to <hi>Humanity,</hi> by the general Benevolence of its <hi>Purpoſe:</hi> attacking Particulars, for the Public Advantage.</p>
            <p>But, methinks, It gives up this <hi>End,</hi> (which is Reformation) when, miſtaking the <hi>Means,</hi> It attempts the good Work with a Hand either too <hi>rough,</hi> or too <hi>gentle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt Caſe, It <hi>corrodes,</hi> where It profeſſes to <hi>cure:</hi> In the ſecond, It is only ſportive and wanton, with what It ſhou'd <hi>correct,</hi> and diſcountenance.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Medium</hi> perhaps might be found, in an Art like that of the <hi>Painters:</hi> who, by oppoſing their <hi>Shades</hi> againſt <hi>LIGHTS,</hi> call out Darkneſs into open Diſtinction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="viii" facs="tcp:0122601600:7"/>So, Enormities, which <hi>Satiriſts</hi> wou'd cenſure, are but dimly and imperfectly mark'd, till the <hi>Defect</hi> admits Diſgrace, from the Neighbourhood of <hi>Perfection.</hi>—Then Contempt ſtings more ſcarply, in <hi>One,</hi> by the compar'd Admiration of the <hi>Other:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that the Cenſur'd are driven, at the ſame Time, from their la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t little Refuge of Vanity, and can no longer recriminate upon the Cenſurer his <hi>Ill-nature,</hi> and Malevolence of Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>I am afraid, there is another Particular, that calls aloud for the Regard of the <hi>Satiriſt:</hi> and That is, a Reflexion, how far Decency may make it a <hi>Duty,</hi> to abandon his perſonal Self, and inſinuate Opinions, with <hi>Modeſty.</hi> I mean from the Mouth of ſome <hi>figurative Speaker,</hi> whom He ought to <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> of more Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; and whoſe Sentiments the Reader will <hi>be ſure</hi> to receive with leſs Scruple.</p>
            <p>There is a Meaning, in the very <hi>Name,</hi> of a <hi>Poet,</hi> that ſhou'd ſeem to preſcribe us this Duty: And the Uſe and Neceſſity of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> can never be more manifeſt, than where the Subject is ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>vidious, as <hi>Satire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who is there, to ſay Truth, ſo unguilty of the Follies of Life, that he dares, in his own proper Perſon, ſtand out and <hi>juſtify</hi> the Right he aſſumes, of reproaching the Conduct of Others?</p>
            <p>Reproof is too bitter a Potion, to be welcome from our Senſe of its <hi>Uſe.</hi> And the adminiſtring Hand ſhou'd be <hi>dear,</hi> not <hi>diſguſtful,</hi> if it would incline us to taſte it, with Pleaſure.</p>
            <p>I thought it but neceſſary, to prefix this ſhort Note, to an Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay toward a <hi>New Kind of Satire.</hi> I will not pretend to aſſert my own Syſtem: becauſe it is the moſt probable Thing in the World, that I ſhou'd conceive a <hi>miſtaken Idea.</hi> Yet, ſince by frequent At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts and Miſcarriages, there are ſtarted, at leaſt, ſome good <hi>Hints,</hi> He, whoſe falſe Steps have contributed either to the Caution, or Direction, of Others, may be ſaid to have <hi>err'd, with Good Fortune.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:0122601600:8"/>
            <head>THE Tears of the Muſes; A POEM.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>GERMANICUS,</hi> for Love, and Empire, born,</l>
               <l>At once to <hi>govern</hi> Kingdoms, and <hi>adorn</hi>;</l>
               <l>Too good for Greatneſs, but that Kings can <hi>bleſs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Too firm for Fear, but of his <hi>Friend</hi>'s Diſtreſs:</l>
               <l>Fore-temp'ring Pow'r by Reaſon's generous Plan,</l>
               <l>To taſk the <hi>Monarch,</hi> meditates the <hi>Man.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>IN a Town Grove, whence Dryads <hi>Noiſe</hi> exclude,</l>
               <l>And huſh loud Streets, to Sylvan Solitude,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:0122601600:9"/>Veil'd by a verdant Skreen's incircling Shade,</l>
               <l>Whoſe angly Sides eight arching Lights pervade,</l>
               <l>Friend to Mankind, their penſive Fav'rite ſtood;</l>
               <l>Revolving previous Plans of purpos'd Good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SOFT, to his Sight, a <hi>Female Suppliant</hi> preſs'd,</l>
               <l>In all the ſpeaking Marks of Mis'ry dreſs'd:</l>
               <l>Down-look'd, relax'd of Mien, oft bending, low;</l>
               <l>Now ſtopping ſhort, now re-advancing, ſlow:</l>
               <l>Pardon, ſhe cry'd, th' intruding Sighs of Grief;</l>
               <l>Hope is the friendleſs Wretche's <hi>laſt</hi> Relief.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>GERMANICUS,</hi> who when Diſtreſs draws nigh,</l>
               <l>Catches quick Sorrow, from the Suff'rer's Eye,</l>
               <l>With gentle Waft invites her back'ning Fears,</l>
               <l>And ſmiles the Warmth of Pity on her Tears.</l>
               <l>Her, while advancing, heedful he ſurvey'd,</l>
               <l>Chance ſtretch'd his Eye to the remoter Shade:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:0122601600:10"/>Where, dimly obvious from the bord'ring Wood,</l>
               <l>Dark'ning the Arches, Eight new Phantoms ſtood;</l>
               <l>All, like the Firſt, thin Forms of ſhivering Woe,</l>
               <l>Wept All—in dumb, ſad, ſolemn, circly Show!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THINK, cry'd th' Approacher, proſtrate at his Feet,</l>
               <l>How ſharp is Inſult! and Relief how ſweet!</l>
               <l>Pity a wretched Siſterhood of Tears:</l>
               <l>Nine friendleſs Mourners, whom no Comfort chears.</l>
               <l>All Arts were Ours, that poliſh'd Life cou'd gain:</l>
               <l>But Arts, and poliſh'd Life, were Ours in vain.</l>
               <l>See! what Reward wiſh'd Knowledge cou'd impart!</l>
               <l>Where Fool is Faſhion, Ignorance is <hi>Art.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Urg'd by Deriſion, and eſcaping Hate,</l>
               <l>We, ſad, ſlow, Exiles, ſeek ſome gentler Fate.</l>
               <l>To the bleak <hi>North's</hi> new-riſing Coaſts we go;</l>
               <l>Leſs <hi>cold</hi> than Theſe, amidſt eternal <hi>Snow.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Glory's gay Beams, to whoſe felt Warmth we run,</l>
               <l>More than ſupply the Abſence of their Sun.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:0122601600:11"/>There, mourning Merit cannot miſs Relief;</l>
               <l>Where watchful <hi>Pow'r</hi> ſupplants <hi>prevented</hi> Grief.</l>
               <l>Fam'd for Munificence, Thy princely Hand</l>
               <l>Singly <hi>abſolves</hi> an unbeſtowing Land.</l>
               <l>Ah! Save the Friendleſs—Help the Wrong'd away:</l>
               <l>Too <hi>poor</hi> to go, yet too <hi>un-lov'd</hi> to ſtay!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pay</hi> but wiſh'd <hi>Paſſage</hi> from this cruel Shore:</l>
               <l>And never, never, will we truſt it more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SCARCE had th' imploring Accents voic'd her Pray'r,</l>
               <l>When the known Sounds and recollected Air</l>
               <l>Through the falſe Semblance, natively convey'd,</l>
               <l>To the charm'd Prince, a ſpeaking <hi>Muſe,</hi> betray'd.</l>
               <l>Round, while, uncrediting the ſtoried Woe,</l>
               <l>His curious Eyes diſcov'ring Glances, throw,</l>
               <l>Th' examin'd Umbrage, as he turn'd, reveal'd</l>
               <l>Each <hi>Muſe,</hi> that every diſtant Arch conceal'd.</l>
               <l>Waiting impatient, for the finiſh'd Tale,</l>
               <l>Quit your vain Hope, he cry'd, by <hi>Want's</hi> thin Veil</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:0122601600:12"/>
                  <hi>Unhid,</hi> to 'ſcape the Rev'rence of my Zeal,</l>
               <l>Who all your Power, through all your Changes, feel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>JOYFUL, He ſnatch'd th' Implorer from the Ground,</l>
               <l>Then, turning graceful, bow'd progreſſive, round;</l>
               <l>Preſs'd their joint Acceſs undiſguis'd and gay;</l>
               <l>And ſhone, receptive of each effluent Ray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SEATED, and circled by the beamy Train,</l>
               <l>Their Shapes, reſuming, and Themſelves again,</l>
               <l>Tell me, ſaid He—Ye Soul-inſpiring <hi>Nine!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ye living Fires, that give the Great, to <hi>ſhine!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who, quick'ning Regal Courage into Flame,</l>
               <l>Guide it, by Juſtice, to immortal Fame!</l>
               <l>Why wou'd ye <hi>leave</hi> a Land diſtinguiſh'd, long,</l>
               <l>For Love of Valour, and for Hate of Wrong?</l>
               <l>Where Freedom unreſtrain'd her Empire holds,</l>
               <l>And Legal Monarchy new Bloom unfolds?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:0122601600:13"/>
               <l>HE paus'd—and CLIO anſwering, thus began,</l>
               <l>Periſh pale <hi>Malice!</hi>—It oblit'rates <hi>Man.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where Envy <hi>blaſts,</hi> the Muſe inſpires in vain:</l>
               <l>No human Culture, there, extends its Reign.</l>
               <l>Loſt in Malignity by civil Hate,</l>
               <l>Virtues that claſh with Virtues curſe a State.</l>
               <l>Stifled in Faction, Arts unfriended ſink:</l>
               <l>Or, pigmy'd into partial Flatt'ry ſhrink.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hiſt'ry</hi> muſt bluſh, the Wiles of <hi>Spleen</hi> to pen,</l>
               <l>And grace the bloodleſs Broils of angry Men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SMOTHER'D in <hi>Self,</hi> there breathes no public Soul,</l>
               <l>Where ſep'rate Strugglings gen'ral Strength controul:</l>
               <l>There, Policy's old gen'rous Straitneſs <hi>bends</hi>;</l>
               <l>And ſhifting <hi>Medium</hi> crawls, to ſidelong Ends.</l>
               <l>There, Fraud <hi>triumphant</hi> tempts the Juſt to fall:</l>
               <l>And every one Man's Gain is Loſs, to All.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:0122601600:14"/>There, Love internal, checking Sighs that roam,</l>
               <l>Begins, and ends, all Charity,—at Home.</l>
               <l>Each Pray'r appropriates one Man's modeſt Aim:</l>
               <l>And humbly truſts to <hi>God</hi> the Common Claim.</l>
               <l>Cruſh'd by Contempt of Praiſe, <hi>Exertion</hi> dies:</l>
               <l>And Public Spirit, laugh'd at, ſhuns to riſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THITHER when Hope miſleads th' Hiſtoric Muſe,</l>
               <l>Swift let her ſeek ſome Scene of nobler Views.</l>
               <l>Where guileleſs Pow'r no Praiſe to <hi>Graft</hi> aſcribes,</l>
               <l>Where Courage ſcorns <hi>Deceit,</hi> and Duty—<hi>Bribes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where nervous Meaning dares, <hi>directly,</hi> ſpeak:</l>
               <l>And crooked Windings teach no Truth to <hi>ſneak.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'TIS <hi>found</hi>—for, ſee!—The icy <hi>Pole</hi> diſſolves!</l>
               <l>Honour's new Warmth with ſunny Force evolves!</l>
               <l>There, glows <hi>Event!</hi> There, more than <hi>Roman</hi> Arms</l>
               <l>Claſh their <hi>prophetic</hi> Thunder's fear'd Alarms!</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:0122601600:15"/>There, the puls'd Public beats, in ev'ry Vein:</l>
               <l>Strong, to one Purpoſe, lifts with equal Strain.</l>
               <l>No <hi>vile</hi> Pretenſion, there, at <hi>Titles</hi> aims:</l>
               <l>No Pride-ſwoln Lumber <hi>lazy Lordſhip</hi> ſhames.</l>
               <l>There, ſhines the <hi>Sword,</hi> in Honour's guarded Track,</l>
               <l>No Knighthood bluſhes, on a <hi>Miſer</hi>'s Back.</l>
               <l>No bought Emblaz'nings Eminence efface,</l>
               <l>No dirty Dignity ſublimes Diſgrace.</l>
               <l>There, <hi>Heroes</hi> multiply: and labouring Fame</l>
               <l>Grows buſy,—to record each ſparkling Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SHE ceas'd.—The Prince his Patriot Eyes withdrew,</l>
               <l>Weigh'd the long Charge, and wiſh'd it, Half, untrue.</l>
               <l>Sigh'd at the Waſte domeſtic Diſcord made:</l>
               <l>And mourn'd unfriended Arts, by Spleen betray'd.</l>
               <l>Then view'd the Siſters, re-prepar'd to hear:</l>
               <l>While ERATO, ſoft ſighing, charm'd his Ear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:0122601600:16"/>
               <l>LUR'D, ſaid the <hi>am'rous</hi> Muſe, from Realms above,</l>
               <l>Pleas'd I deſcended on this Land of <hi>Love</hi>;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Look'd</hi> and <hi>approv'd:</hi> and form'd aerial Schemes,</l>
               <l>Of heart-felt Tyes, and Hope's eluſive Dreams;</l>
               <l>Vainly propos'd—Each Sex by Each to mend;</l>
               <l>And ſmooth the rugged Paths of Life, with <hi>Friend.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Snatch'd at <hi>One</hi> ſweet Example, <hi>New</hi> to <hi>Fame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Urg'd its dear Pow'r, th' <hi>Unhappier</hi> to reclaim:</l>
               <l>Miſguided Millions hail'd th' acknowledg'd Charms;</l>
               <l>And lov'd Perfection, when it bleſs'd <hi>Thy</hi> Arms.</l>
               <l>But, ah! too loſt a Length <hi>Themſelves</hi> were gone!</l>
               <l>They worſhip'd, and confeſs'd:—but ſtill <hi>ſinn'd</hi> on.</l>
               <l>Yet I, vain Hoper! Still new Helps apply:</l>
               <l>And, ever failing, wou'd for ever <hi>try.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſlighted Beauty wou'd new Powers impart;</l>
               <l>And ſtretch the aided Empire of the Heart.</l>
               <l>Teach Man, that Woman's Strength in Softneſs lies:</l>
               <l>Teach Woman, why the Modeſt charm the Wiſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:0122601600:17"/>Uſeleſs to Either, I from Both, remove.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Money</hi>'s th' inſpiring <hi>Muſe</hi> of modiſh Love!</l>
               <l>O'er Truth and Paſſion, Avarice prevails:</l>
               <l>All Vows are venal, and all Sighs are <hi>Sales.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Int'reſt and Vanity, and Self, diſarm</l>
               <l>Mutual Eſteem, till neither Sex can charm.</l>
               <l>Then, blanc unnat'ral Whims pervert Deſire:</l>
               <l>Attraction failing, they exchange <hi>Attire.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then, Man's <hi>lac'd Lightneſs</hi> apes the Lady's Air:</l>
               <l>And bluff big Boldneſs <hi>maſculates</hi> the Fair.</l>
               <l>With changing Sexes, Love's loſt Motives change,</l>
               <l>From Wiſh to Wiſh the ſhort-liv'd Paſſions range.</l>
               <l>Recorded Conſtancy becomes <hi>Romance:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, among Millions, Two may love—by Chance!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>WHY ſhould I, then, ſupporting preſent Scorn,</l>
               <l>Stretch my too patient Hope, to Times unborn?</l>
               <l>When, to the <hi>North,</hi> where Nature ſhines unſtain'd,</l>
               <l>Confiding Sexes love, with Faith unfeign'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:0122601600:18"/>Their native Beauties, in no Clime excell'd,</l>
               <l>To riſing Force by conſcious Worth impell'd;</l>
               <l>While through the ſparkling Eye taught Spirit breaks,</l>
               <l>And the felt Luſtre of their Fame partakes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THE Lover Prince unwillingly believ'd</l>
               <l>Faults, which his nobler Nature ſcarce conceiv'd.</l>
               <l>Touch'd for the Honour of the Human Heart,</l>
               <l>His own glow'd painful, with ideal Smart.</l>
               <l>When loftier Accents from URANIA broke,</l>
               <l>And ſnatch'd his liſt'ning Soul, while <hi>Science</hi> ſpoke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>FROM Heav'n's unſounded Depth, ſhe cry'd, I ſtole</l>
               <l>Angelic Fire, and form'd a NEWTON's <hi>Soul.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Taught him the ſecret Walks of God to tread;</l>
               <l>And 'twixt the ſtarry Worlds his Spirit led:</l>
               <l>All <hi>Aether</hi> op'ning to a Mortal's Eyes,</l>
               <l>Till Earth ſent Colonies, and held the Skies!</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:0122601600:19"/>What King, for This, magnificently juſt,</l>
               <l>Bleſs'd him in Life, or dignified his Duſt?</l>
               <l>What voted Honours <hi>mark</hi> th' Aſpirer's Race?</l>
               <l>What <hi>thinking Statues</hi> emulate his Face?</l>
               <l>He, who immortaliz'd his Country's Name,</l>
               <l>Beyond Ten Thouſand <hi>Conqu'rors</hi> bounded Fame,</l>
               <l>He, who, to lift Mankind, new Heav'ns diſplay'd,</l>
               <l>And every Human Breather nobler made,</l>
               <l>Did He to public Fame All Nature raiſe?</l>
               <l>And is He poorly left to private Praiſe!</l>
               <l>In ſuch a Land, ah! what can Arts expect?</l>
               <l>What Claim has hopeleſs Science, but Neglect?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O! Fate of wintry Worth, by Climate croſs'd!</l>
               <l>Budding untimely, to be nip'd in Froſt!</l>
               <l>NEWTON has multiplied the <hi>Suns!</hi>—yet pours</l>
               <l>In vain, the Light of all their Orbs, on Ours.</l>
               <l>When will th' incurious Courts, for which, He found</l>
               <l>New Worlds, find Will to trace an Old one round?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:0122601600:20"/>What promis'd Penſion ſhips th' unſhaken Soul,</l>
               <l>To dare Diſcov'ry, and ungloom the Pole?</l>
               <l>What coaſting Keel, indenting <hi>Southern</hi> Strands,</l>
               <l>Starts the long Shores of Cloud-benighted Lands?</l>
               <l>No annual Bounty, perſevering, kind,</l>
               <l>Draws the dark Veil, that covers half Mankind.</l>
               <l>What regal Influ'nce, eaſing Learning's Birth,</l>
               <l>Now, adds new Stars to Heav'n? or Arts, to Earth?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who</hi> ſows Munificence, to root up Sloth,</l>
               <l>And call forth Harveſts, of eternal Growth?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>HAIL, to the Land, where War makes <hi>Science</hi> Room!</l>
               <l>Where Realms from Deſarts riſe! and Ruins bloom!</l>
               <l>Where Conqueſt, ſpreading to embrace Diſtreſs,</l>
               <l>Lets looſe Ambition, not to waſte, but bleſs!</l>
               <l>There, Pow'r inverts Deſtruction, into <hi>Birth</hi>;</l>
               <l>And the <hi>prolific</hi> Sword empeoples Earth!</l>
               <l>There, Deſolation, fruitful in Decay,</l>
               <l>Fades, into Opulence, and ſtrengthens Sway.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:0122601600:21"/>There, Ports (un-native) indrawn Seas confine:</l>
               <l>And climbing Streams o'er channel'd Mountains ſhine.</l>
               <l>There, public Splendor <hi>ſwallows</hi> private Pride,</l>
               <l>And Claims which All Men ſhare in, All Men, <hi>guide.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There, Art rewarded, ſtrains excited Skill;</l>
               <l>Till dazling Wonders wid'ning Empire fill.</l>
               <l>The fierce free <hi>Tartar</hi> ſees the <hi>Tartar taught</hi>;</l>
               <l>Grins, at advancing <hi>Rule,</hi> and pants for <hi>Thought.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then, in long Link, new Nations forward draw:</l>
               <l>And the drain'd Wilds of Nature crowd to <hi>Law.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hail, promis'd Land!—All, now, that ſeems ſevere,</l>
               <l>Is—that, removing hence, We leave YOU here.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>URANIA ſtopp'd, and bow'd.—The Prince, whoſe Heart</l>
               <l>Inly confeſs'd the Pow'r of cheriſh'd Art,</l>
               <l>Nobly approving Praiſe, ſo juſtly warm;</l>
               <l>Smil'd, conſcious of his inborn Right to charm.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:0122601600:22"/>
               <l>NEXT, roſe TERPSICHORE,—<hi>melodious</hi> Muſe!</l>
               <l>Soft, her firſt Accents, like deſcending Dews:</l>
               <l>Sweet, and ſlow-ſwelling, till in livelier Sound,</l>
               <l>Gay, to the raviſh'd Ear, quick Tranſports bound.</l>
               <l>Tim'd to the tuneful Voice, each trembling Tree</l>
               <l>Strain'd its tugg'd Roots, and labour'd to be free.</l>
               <l>Warm'd through the wak'ning <hi>Stone,</hi> the ſculptur'd Ear</l>
               <l>Of every ſtarting Statue ſeem'd to <hi>hear.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Air catch'd, and length'ning back the mazy Notes,</l>
               <l>Curls, while the undulating Muſic floats.</l>
               <l>Earth, liſt'ning, to <hi>inhale</hi> harmonious Pain,</l>
               <l>Sigh'd it, in ſoft Vibration, back again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>PARDON a mourning Muſe, that leaves, with Tears,</l>
               <l>The Land, that lov'd GERMANICUS endears.</l>
               <l>But, ah! what Toils, what Anguiſh, ſhalt thou bear!</l>
               <l>What endleſs Labour muſt o'erload thy Care!</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:0122601600:23"/>Ere thy loſt Views a Taſte like Thine, inſpire,</l>
               <l>And ſparkling Kingdoms catch Thy manly Fire!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>NEAR <hi>Opera</hi>'s fribling <hi>Fugues,</hi> what Muſe can ſtay?</l>
               <l>Where wordleſs Warblings winnow <hi>Thought,</hi> away!</l>
               <l>Muſic, when <hi>Purpoſe</hi> points her not the Road,</l>
               <l>Charms, to betray, and ſoftens, to <hi>corrode.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Empty of Senſe, the Soul-ſeducing Art</l>
               <l>Thrills a ſlow Poiſon to the ſick'ning Heart.</l>
               <l>Soft ſinks <hi>Idea,</hi> diſſolute in Eaſe,</l>
               <l>And all Life's feeble Leſſon is, to <hi>pleaſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Spirit, and Taſte, and generous Toil, take Flight:</l>
               <l>And lazy Love, and indolent Delight,</l>
               <l>And low luxurious Wearineſs of Pain,</l>
               <l>Lull the loſt Mind,—and all its Powers are vain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>HENCE, to the Realms of <hi>Fame,</hi> ye Muſes, fly.</l>
               <l>There, to the Drum's big Beat, the Heart leaps high.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:0122601600:24"/>There, ſighing Flutes but temp'ring Martial Heat,</l>
               <l>Teach diſtant Pity and Revenge to <hi>meet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The manly Pipe, there, ſcorns th' expanded <hi>Shakes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That wind wav'd Nothings, till Attention <hi>akes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There <hi>now,</hi> concurring Keys and Chords increaſe</l>
               <l>The Heart's ſoft ſocial Tyes, and cheriſh <hi>Peace.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then,</hi> Trumpets, anſw'ring Trumpets, ſhrill, and far,</l>
               <l>Swell to the ſounding Wind th' inſpiring <hi>War.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There, the rows'd Soul, in Exerciſe, grows ſtrong:</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>pools</hi> to puddly Foulneſs, ſtopp'd, too long.</l>
               <l>Strength'ning, and ſtrengthned by, the Poet's Fire,</l>
               <l>There, Muſic's meaning Voice <hi>exalts</hi> Deſire.</l>
               <l>There, Harmony not drowns, but quickens, Thought;</l>
               <l>And Fools, unfeeling Words, by Notes are <hi>caught.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SOFT ſigh'd the Prince, for ſuff'ring Muſic, pain'd,</l>
               <l>And POLYHYMNIA, riſing warm, complain'd.</l>
               <l>Deign to be told, Impartial, Gen'rous, Wiſe!</l>
               <l>Why fruitleſs <hi>Eloquence</hi> indignant flies.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:0122601600:25"/>Gall'd at loſt Time, in Caſes vainly clear'd,</l>
               <l>At Truths, <hi>untouching,</hi> and at Sounds, <hi>unheard</hi>;</l>
               <l>Bluſhing, while Oratory's lab'ring Strains</l>
               <l>On <hi>Prae-deciſion,</hi> waſte derided Pains;</l>
               <l>And flouriſh'd Periods, to no Purpoſe <hi>fine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like Suns in Deſarts, without <hi>Notice,</hi> ſhine,</l>
               <l>Hating <hi>grave</hi> Inſult, I diſdain to ſtay,</l>
               <l>Where Talk but trifles, and where Tropes but play.</l>
               <l>If ſerious Rhet'ric ſweats, where ſneering <hi>Mutes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Haſt'ning the hurried <hi>Queſtion,</hi> crop Diſputes;</l>
               <l>If <hi>Law</hi> ſells Argument, yet <hi>Forms</hi> muſt reign,</l>
               <l>And, Cuſtom pleading, Equity is vain;</l>
               <l>If the dark <hi>Pulpit</hi>'s ſhort myſterious Art</l>
               <l>Lifts <hi>Faith</hi> to Heav'n; and damns the <hi>Moral Heart</hi>;</l>
               <l>Bear me, diſhonour'd God! to ſome plain State,</l>
               <l>Where Truth, in ſpite of <hi>Aye</hi> and <hi>No,</hi> is Weight.</l>
               <l>Where Pleas of Right a reas'ning Bench perſuade,</l>
               <l>And Juſtice ſcorns in <hi>Precedent</hi> to trade.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:0122601600:26"/>Where no bold Blaſphemy wou'd Faith enſlave:</l>
               <l>But, humble, honeſt, doubting, <hi>Works</hi> can <hi>ſave.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>EUTERPE, watchful of her Siſter's Cloſe,</l>
               <l>Snatch'd her ſunk Cadence, and impatient roſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> ſhe cry'd, is Mine; Mine, the gay Skill,</l>
               <l>To paint the Fancy, and adorn the Will.</l>
               <l>But, where dry <hi>Avarice</hi> has Taſte betray'd,</l>
               <l>Pleaſure is <hi>Robbery,</hi> in <hi>Maſquerade,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Contending Sexes puſh One common Aim:</l>
               <l>And Youth, and Wit, and Beauty, meet, to <hi>game!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At Cards to conquer, or at Dice to ſweep,</l>
               <l>Is all the humble Joy, the <hi>Poliſh'd</hi> reap!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>OR, if, aſpiring to robuſter Praiſe,</l>
               <l>Some livelier Genius, Warmth more <hi>active</hi> ſways,</l>
               <l>Then, frock'd in groomy Sleekneſs, tight, and ſmart,</l>
               <l>The pert, capp'd, <hi>Racer</hi> dares the <hi>Jockey</hi>'s Art.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:0122601600:27"/>At Stake and Plate, his Skill profoundly ſhewn,</l>
               <l>He from his <hi>Horſe</hi>'s Worth, preſumes his own.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>OR, nobly ſtung by <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Coachman</hi>'s Claim,</l>
               <l>Climbing th' advent'rous <hi>Box,</hi> diſputes his Fame!</l>
               <l>Scatt'ring malignant Duſt, cracks Voice and Thong,</l>
               <l>Glows, for a Livery's <hi>Right,</hi> and burns along!</l>
               <l>Proudly diſplay'd, looks back, and ſhouts, to find</l>
               <l>Poor conſcious <hi>John,</hi> leſs glorious, hang behind:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>NOT <hi>ſo,</hi> th' <hi>Olympian</hi> Rivals charm'd, of Old,</l>
               <l>When fiery Youths in whirling Chariots roll'd!</l>
               <l>Then, the watch'd Signal bad the Rank disjoin;</l>
               <l>And ruſhing Wheels diſſolv'd the breaking Line:</l>
               <l>Strain'd to th' expanded Whip's impulſive Sound,</l>
               <l>Light leap'd th' exulting Axles o'er the Ground:</l>
               <l>'Twixt crowding Nations, partial, panting, gay,</l>
               <l>The prais'd plum'd Heroe <hi>ſkim'd</hi> the leſſ'ning Way.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:0122601600:28"/>The ſmoaking Steeds obey'd the watchful Rein,</l>
               <l>And winding warlike, ſwept the ſhouting Plain.</l>
               <l>Now, graceful <hi>rais'd,</hi> now <hi>pendent</hi> in Carier,</l>
               <l>High, and far-glitt'ring, ſhone the Charioteer;</l>
               <l>Firm in his Seat, ſuperior in his Mien,</l>
               <l>Flew o'er the Courſe, and flam'd along the Green:</l>
               <l>Martial in Geſture, Eminent in Grace,</l>
               <l>His Birth and Grandeur light'ning from his Face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>OR, if to ſweeter Conteſt match'd he mov'd,</l>
               <l>And, in ſome <hi>Ball,</hi> led the kind Hand he lov'd,</l>
               <l>The modeſt Fair, ſlow through the mazy Dance,</l>
               <l>Swam to the love-ſick Soul, in ſoft Advance.</l>
               <l>No light coarſe <hi>Friſking</hi> kick'd off Woman's Air:</l>
               <l>No ſtrong, ſtretch'd, Limb out-trod Attraction, there.</l>
               <l>Decent their Pleaſures, and diſcreetly weigh'd;</l>
               <l>Active the Youth, and delicate the Maid.</l>
               <l>Honour, by Elegance, its Right maintain'd:</l>
               <l>And, Thought correcting Rapture, Prudence reign'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:0122601600:29"/>
               <l>MOURNFUL MELPOMENE, with <hi>Tragic</hi> Frown,</l>
               <l>Spoke next: and thus deplor'd a taſteleſs Town.</l>
               <l>Why ſtrove the <hi>Scenic</hi> Muſe to ſhine, in vain,</l>
               <l>Where Wit is Levity, and Art is Gain?</l>
               <l>Where Law's blind Hope wou'd curb Corruption's Rage,</l>
               <l>Yet, left undue <hi>Contempt</hi> to taint the Stage?</l>
               <l>Hence, Theatres, neglected into Shame,</l>
               <l>Catching at Concourſe, Purity diſclaim.</l>
               <l>By Pow'r deſerted, make their humbler Court</l>
               <l>To Rake, and Rancour, or to Fool and Sport.</l>
               <l>Piqu'd to Reprizal, unconfed'rate Wit,</l>
               <l>Noting the <hi>popular,</hi> evades the <hi>fit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then, the Play plots on State-craft, laughs at Truth:</l>
               <l>Miſguides Allegiance, or unſinews Youth.</l>
               <l>Thither crowds Faction, to be taught Complaint:</l>
               <l>Where Pow'r, the <hi>Martyr,</hi> might have reign'd, the <hi>Saint.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There, Wiſdom bleeds, by Pleaſure's feath'ry Dart:</l>
               <l>And Love's looſe Hand unſtrings the ſlacken'd Heart.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:0122601600:30"/>There, Diſcontent firſt trys her tim'rous Force;</l>
               <l>Hints, and finds <hi>Help,</hi> and <hi>dares</hi> her dang'rous Courſe.</l>
               <l>There, Froth, Farce, Flatt'ry, Chance, Sedition, rule:</l>
               <l>And Virtue ſcarce finds Place, in Virtue's <hi>School!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>FAREWELL, forſaken Stage.—When <hi>Courts</hi> refuſe</l>
               <l>To <hi>urge</hi> Wit's wand'ring Rein, ſhe <hi>ſhames</hi> a <hi>Muſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hail! from AFAR—Thou, fate-foretelling Light!</l>
               <l>Beaming <hi>prognoſtic,</hi> through the Eye of Night!</l>
               <l>Kindling a hundred Realms, th' enliv'ning Flame</l>
               <l>Wings the wak'd Energy of courted Fame.</l>
               <l>There, Empire flaſhing into Glory's Blaze,</l>
               <l>Conſcious Intention bluſhes not at Praiſe.</l>
               <l>There, ſpurring Virtue, Wit has leave to <hi>mean:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And Pow'r, exciting Paſſion, prompts the <hi>Scene.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SO <hi>muſt it be,</hi> ere Tragic Fire is felt!</l>
               <l>But, where grave Thoughts are Marks, for Fools to pelt;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:0122601600:31"/>Where tir'd, illit'rate, viewleſs, yawning Pride</l>
               <l>Muſt hear, unliſt'ning, and, un-taught, decide,</l>
               <l>There, let loſt <hi>Sentiment</hi> miſpoint no Beam;</l>
               <l>To hope, were Blindneſs: and to wiſh, a Dream!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>UP leap'd THALIA, glowing red with Rage,</l>
               <l>Fir'd and indignant at a farceful Age.</l>
               <l>Shall <hi>Comedy</hi>'s inſulted Muſe, ſhe cry'd,</l>
               <l>Hold <hi>Hoops,</hi> to <hi>Tumblers!</hi>—</l>
               <l>She paus'd,—unable to proceed;—ſigh'd ſtrong:</l>
               <l>Repell'd the big Diſdain—and trac'd her Wrong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SHALL COMEDY, for ſworded <hi>Harlequin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Split <hi>Lathes?</hi> and arm him, for the mimic Scene!</l>
               <l>While <hi>He,</hi> proud Impotence! with modiſh Strut,</l>
               <l>Cocks bluff, diffuſive of his <hi>wooden Cut!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Muſt ſhe <hi>ſwing Gypſies</hi> o'er the winnow'd Pit,</l>
               <l>Mounting <hi>Poſteriors,</hi> in Defect of <hi>Wit!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:0122601600:32"/>Or clap ſome <hi>human Whirlwind</hi>'s bluſt'ring Rage,</l>
               <l>That, o'er twelve Heads deſcending, ſhakes the Stage!</l>
               <l>Stare, while th' unmanly Reptile's wriggling Twiſt</l>
               <l>Threads the ſtav'd Ladder, and deſcends, <hi>unhiſs'd?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or, for the Rope-Aſpirer's jirkful Tread,</l>
               <l>Shall ſhe poize right their emblematic <hi>Lead?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>NO.—Let implor'd Expulſion wing me thence!</l>
               <l>Far let me fly, to ſome fair Seat of Senſe:</l>
               <l>Where Life's ſtol'n Humour glows with mirthful Grace,</l>
               <l>And Comic Picture copies Nature's Face.</l>
               <l>Where imag'd Paſſion, dear to the Polite,</l>
               <l>Leaves low Buffoon'ry to the Rabble's Right.</l>
               <l>Tir'd, yet untaſk'd, let me no longer wait,</l>
               <l>Laughing unheeded,—at the laughing <hi>Great:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>While, with the Roar of Boys, to Tricks they run,</l>
               <l>Which Mobs ſhou'd ſhout at, and the Wiſe ſhou'd ſhun.</l>
               <l>Gravely, good Souls! reſerving ſolid Scorn,</l>
               <l>For Thoughts, to feel whoſe <hi>Force,</hi> Themſelves were <hi>born.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:0122601600:33"/>
               <l>WARM'D in Wit's Cauſe, lamenting Genius loſt,</l>
               <l>Nor taſting Ecſtaſy, at Judgment's Coſt,</l>
               <l>Liſt'ning GERMANICUS, with penſive Grace,</l>
               <l>Revolv'd wiſh'd Soft'nings, for a pitied Race:</l>
               <l>When, like a Trumpet pouring Muſic's <hi>Flood,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Speaking CALLIOPE thrill'd through his Blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THERE was a Prince! ah! bid me add, ere long,</l>
               <l>There is:—impulſive of the <hi>Epic</hi> Song.</l>
               <l>Flame of imperial Prominence, He ſhin'd:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Terror,</hi> at once, and <hi>Charm,</hi> of Humankind!</l>
               <l>All the ſoft Praiſe of ſocial Life his Due:</l>
               <l>All the rais'd Pow'rs, of Arms, and Arts, he knew.</l>
               <l>Fearleſs impell'd his Father's Fortune on:</l>
               <l>And, in Youth's Dawn, a dazzling Victor, ſhone!</l>
               <l>In Force reſiſtleſs, yet undaring Wrong:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Honeſt,</hi> in Vengeance! and in Pity, <hi>ſtrong!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:0122601600:34"/>Without, dwelt War, in all her thund'ring Din:</l>
               <l>While Peace, in all her Stillneſs, wept, within.</l>
               <l>Form'd for a Lover, for a Thinker taught;</l>
               <l>Bloodleſs <hi>reflective</hi> Eminence, He ſought:</l>
               <l>Born to be <hi>greateſt,</hi> choſe but to be <hi>beſt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But Heav'n, that knew his Uſe, forbad his Reſt.</l>
               <l>Then, from the Calms of conqu'ring <hi>Thought,</hi> he roſe,</l>
               <l>Glow'd in tempeſtuous <hi>War,</hi> and ſcorn'd Repoſe.</l>
               <l>Uncrown'd, <hi>gave</hi> Crowns, at Will, their <hi>Thorns</hi> untry'd;</l>
               <l>And, <hi>more</hi> than reigning, <hi>without</hi> reigning died.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SUCH, though the Land I <hi>leave</hi> cou'd ſhew me, ſtill,</l>
               <l>Calm Seaſons call not for a Pilot's Skill.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Peace</hi> is the Bleſſing, Commerce loves to chuſe:</l>
               <l>But <hi>War,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> taſk the <hi>Epic Muſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Farewel, ſure Subject of my future Song!</l>
               <l>When, riſing flameful at a <hi>People</hi>'s Wrong,</l>
               <l>In Times yet diſtant, Thy rememb'ring Hand</l>
               <l>Lets looſe <hi>Correction</hi> at ſome foreign Land.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:0122601600:35"/>Then, loud as Thy Applauſe, reclaim us, All:</l>
               <l>And every Muſe of Nine ſhall wait thy Call.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SPEAKING ſhe roſe: and, with her, riſing ſlow,</l>
               <l>Her Eight ſad Siſters, ſighing, turn'd to go.</l>
               <l>Lively upſtarting from his ſhadow'd Seat,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Stay,</hi> cry'd the Prince, alarm'd,—ſuſpend Retreat.</l>
               <l>Juſt though your Anger, yet Revenge forbear:</l>
               <l>Leſt, taught by Muſes, Man forgets to <hi>ſpare.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Too ſoon, degen'rate Nature warps awry,</l>
               <l>The Bad to copy, and the Good to fly.</l>
               <l>Have you beheld Wit's Stream <hi>diſcolour'd</hi> glide,</l>
               <l>And pour'd loſt Azure on th' unconſcious Tide?</l>
               <l>Think the Blame <hi>yours,</hi> who Heav'n's beſt Tincture bring,</l>
               <l>To ſtain the Current, yet neglect the <hi>Spring!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wou'd you, at once, <hi>coerulean</hi> Depth renew?</l>
               <l>And, gayly bright'ning, fluſh th' Improvement, <hi>through?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>High, at the <hi>Source,</hi> th' infuſive <hi>Tinge</hi> beſtow:</l>
               <l>And ev'ry downward Drop ſhall tinctur'd flow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:0122601600:36"/>
               <l>BUT, while, a <hi>Vagrant,</hi> Inſpiration ſtrays,</l>
               <l>And, here and there, unlicens'd Pow'r diſplays,</l>
               <l>Though ſep'rate individual <hi>Strollers</hi> ſhare</l>
               <l>Some uncollective Scatt'rings, of your Care;</l>
               <l>This Way, and That, though ſome faint Hint of Light</l>
               <l>Gleams, like a Meteor, and ſhrinks back in Night,</l>
               <l>Or, mingling Beams, to form ſome deathleſs Blaze,</l>
               <l>Once in an Age, You, POPES, or THOMSONS, raiſe:</l>
               <l>All the loſt Labour ſerves but to expreſs</l>
               <l>How wide our Wants! how thinly we poſſeſs!</l>
               <l>Till the <hi>Day breaks,</hi> expect no gen'ral Glow:</l>
               <l>For, the Sky darken'd, keeps all dark, below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>HERE, for Wit's <hi>Fountain,</hi> dream not of a <hi>Court.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Falſe and injurious, ſlight th' unweigh'd Report.</l>
               <l>Meant, for a Clime, where <hi>Thrones</hi> appropriate Pow'r,</l>
               <l>And One Man's Paſſions All Mens Rights devour.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:0122601600:37"/>But, in free States, where Liberty may <hi>chuſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Taſte knows no <hi>Monarch,</hi> and obeys no <hi>Muſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Senates</hi> their Muſes, <hi>Property</hi> their Aim:</l>
               <l>Their Boaſt but <hi>Safety</hi>;—and their Plaything, <hi>Fame.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>NO</hi>—wou'd your willing Culture waſte no Toil?</l>
               <l>Wou'd your Bays thrive, in a reluctant Soil?</l>
               <l>Ductile of Form, and changing Shapes at Will,</l>
               <l>Aſſume <hi>new Sex,</hi> new Names, new Views, <hi>new Skill.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Safe, in ſage <hi>Politics,</hi> conceal your <hi>Wit:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then, by my Bounty, <hi>qualify'd</hi> to <hi>ſit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nine <hi>Corniſh</hi> Boroughs might aſſign you Place,</l>
               <l>Where, mix'd unthought-of, You may ſhun Diſgrace.</l>
               <l>There, breathing unſuſpected Influence, <hi>lurk,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Till patient Progreſs crowns your arduous Work.</l>
               <l>Thence, ſhall deſcending Radiance <hi>Taſte</hi> convey:</l>
               <l>And willing Kingdoms make the <hi>Muſes</hi> Way.</l>
               <l>Till, Time ſlow fav'ring, You may quit Diſguiſe,</l>
               <l>And wear Wit, <hi>plain,</hi> among th' unlaughing Wiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:0122601600:38"/>
               <l>PAUSING, He ſmil'd Humanity, ſo kind,</l>
               <l>That ev'ry Muſe was touch'd, and chang'd her Mind:</l>
               <l>All bow'd Conſent, to His grave Purpoſe wrought;</l>
               <l>And, thus, URANIA voic'd her Siſter's Thought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>BORN to a People's <hi>Hearts,</hi> their DARLING, ſhine!</l>
               <l>Let ev'ry Wiſh, and Hope, and Joy, be Thine!</l>
               <l>Mov'd by the magic Mercy of Thy View,</l>
               <l>We feel good Counſel, and embrace it too.</l>
               <l>One ſole <hi>Condition</hi> grant, and we obey:</l>
               <l>No dang'rous <hi>Notice</hi> muſt detect our Stay!</l>
               <l>Hid in <hi>Thy Grove,</hi> each menial Muſe ſhall claim</l>
               <l>Domeſtic Shelter from Reproach and Shame:</l>
               <l>Till, by thy Scheme, their yet unrival'd <hi>Friend!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Their Infl'ence widens, and their Suff'rings end.</l>
               <l>Then, ſhewn the World, and <hi>privileg'd</hi> to pleaſe,</l>
               <l>And, gath'ring Face and Faſhion, by Degrees,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:0122601600:39"/>Seen at <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> Belles may Jokes forbear:</l>
               <l>Nor, ſhocking modeſt <hi>Strangers,</hi> turn and <hi>ſtare!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THUS, in his Shade, from public Pain exempt,</l>
               <l>Sleeping, the Viſionary Poet <hi>dreamt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then wak'd; and found his ſparkling PRINCE was there:</l>
               <l>But ev'ry empty <hi>Muſe</hi> was loſt in Air.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>Shortly will be publiſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An ESSAY on the <hi>Merits</hi> of ASSASSINATION: With a VIEW to The Dictator's True Character; AND His Deſigns on the <hi>Roman</hi> Republick.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
