<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Annette and Lubin: a comic opera, in one act. As it is performed at the Theatre-Royal in Covent Garden</title>
            <author>Dibdin, Charles, 1745-1814.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>22 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008 September</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004832613</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T54523</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW110152553</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K048829.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3310152553</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECLL</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">0072601000</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Annette and Lubin: a comic opera, in one act. As it is performed at the Theatre-Royal in Covent Garden</title>
                  <author>Dibdin, Charles, 1745-1814.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for G. Kearsly,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1778.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The advertisement signed: C. Dibdin.</note>
                  <note>Based on 'Annette et Lubin' by M.J.B. Favart and C.H. Fusée de Voisenon.</note>
                  <note>With a half-title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT54523.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:0072601000:1"/>
ANNETTE and LUBIN: A COMIC OPERA, IN ONE ACT.</p>
            <p>[Price SIX-PENCE.]</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:0072601000:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ANNETTE and LUBIN: A COMIC OPERA, IN ONE ACT.</p>
            <p>As it is performed at the THEATRE-ROYAL IN COVENT GARDEN.</p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for G. KEARSLY, No. 46, Fleet-Street. M.DCC.LXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:0072601000:3"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE following little Piece is an imitation of the French comic operas of one act, which are generally characterized, either by their natural ſimplicity, or ſome ſingle ſtriking incident, and little or nothing more is deſigned.—It is now firſt attempted to introduce this ſpecies of entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the Engliſh theatre, as containing excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſituations for light airs.—On the French ſtage, notwithſtanding all their merit, they tire in the length of time taken for repreſentation; and, were they ſpun out to the common length of our after-pieces, it is conceived they would be found ſtill more inſufficient.</p>
            <p>The ſubject matter therefore being wholly preſerved, and the dialogue both varied and compreſſed, they are, with every deference, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to public judgment.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. DIBDIN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:0072601000:4"/>
            <head>CHARACTERS.</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>MEN.</head>
                  <label>The Lord of the Manor,</label>
                  <item>Mr. FEARON,</item>
                  <label>His Bailiff,</label>
                  <item>Mr. WILSON,</item>
                  <label>Lubin,</label>
                  <item>Mrs. FARRELL<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>WOMAN.</head>
                  <label>Annette,</label>
                  <item>Miſs BROWN.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:0072601000:5"/>ANNETTE and LUBIN: A COMIC OPERA.</head>
         <div n="1" type="scene">
            <head>SCENE I.</head>
            <stage>A view on the borders of the Seine—near the front of the ſtage is a little cabin made with leaves, not quite finiſhed—Lubin comes on with a load of branches on his back.</stage>
            <stage>AIR.</stage>
            <l>'TIS late in the day,</l>
            <l>Work away! work away!</l>
            <l>At the cottage where Annette's to dwell.</l>
            <l>I ſing as the branches I fell;</l>
            <l>'Tis not fine, 'tis not gay,</l>
            <l>But 'tis done for her ſake,</l>
            <l>And the pains which I take</l>
            <l>Love, and her, will repay</l>
            <l>Mighty well.</l>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:0072601000:6"/>
            <l>For a carpet, to ſerve where ſhe'll tread,</l>
            <l>This matting of ozier I ſpread;</l>
            <l>Come, Lubin, my lad, work away!</l>
            <l>Love, and Annette, thy toil will repay.</l>
            <p>If the houſen of your great folks in town are larger, and a got more chambers than ours, I can tell 'em thoſe within lead ſadder lives—Here Annette and I are happier than a king and queen—one branch the more, if we are cold, keeps out the wind and the rain—If we are warm, one branch the leſs lets in the air to fan us—and, when the ſun ſcorches up the leaves, away trudge I, as I did this morning, to the wood, and bring home a new houſe upon my back—Annette will be ſtruck all of a heap when ſhe comes home, to ſee how gay we look <stage>(ſinging behind)</stage> Ah, there ſhe is! I'll work away without ſeeming to mind her.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="scene">
            <head>SCENE II.</head>
            <stage>LUBIN, ANNETTE.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <stage>(behind)</stage>
               <l>The village, all, may rave and ſcold,</l>
               <l>To taunt and rail, and jeer, they're free;</l>
               <l>The young, with ſneers, with threats the old,</l>
               <l>Still Lubin is the lad for me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:0072601000:7"/>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <l>Here comes Annette!</l>
               <l>Let us nothing forget!</l>
               <l>Well ſaid! my boy, Lubin, well ſaid!</l>
               <l>Thy toil to compleat,</l>
               <l>On this hillock her ſeat,</l>
               <l>Theſe panſies and violets ſpread.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <stage>(behind)</stage>
               <l>The Bailly does our conduct blame;</l>
               <l>Couſins to love!—that muſt not be;</l>
               <l>But did the parſon cry out ſhame,</l>
               <l>Lubin is the lad for me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <l>I hear her, I hear her,</l>
               <l>Come nearer, and nearer;</l>
               <l>Let's ſee, have I got ev'ry thing?</l>
               <l>When ſhe ſpeaks, one may gueſs,</l>
               <l>How her accents can bleſs,</l>
               <l>If one's charmed, thus, in hearing her ſing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <stage>(behind)</stage>
               <l>They ſay this joy will end in ſmart,</l>
               <l>That all the men are falſe—but he</l>
               <l>Is true, if I may truſt my heart,</l>
               <l>And Lubin is the lad for me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <l>My Annette I hear!</l>
               <l>That Annette ſo dear,</l>
               <l>Who, ſo much I regret, when away,</l>
               <l>That the ſky ſeems to lour;</l>
               <l>And evr'y hour,</l>
               <l>To me, is as long as a day.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:0072601000:8"/>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <stage>(coming on)</stage>
               <l>But, wherefore, in a moment's pain?</l>
               <l>He's here, and I from doubt am free;</l>
               <l>That ſmile, which welcomes me again,</l>
               <l>Says Lubin is the lad for me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <l>But, wherefore, in a moment's, &amp;c.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Here I am—I am quite out of breath!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>You have been a good while gone!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſure I run as faſt as ever I could.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, you have made yourſelf all in a heat—what did you run ſo faſt for?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, that was only as I come back again—when I leave you I go ſlow enough—Oh! dear, how fine we are!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Not very fine, Annette; but it will be main pretty when thou art within it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Ah! Lubin, how glad I was to come back to thee!—En't we much happier than the people in town?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Happier!—a thouſand times; on the fineſt days in all the year they ſhut themſelves up in a parcel of quarries; Is it not true that our cabin is prettier than their fine priſons which they call palaces?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>For my part, I wonder they don't come, in the fine weather, and live, two and two, in a little hut, as we do—Have you ſeen, Lubin, their carpets they are ſo fond of?—Lord, they en't a quarter ſo pretty as a bed of daiſies!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:0072601000:9"/>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>And, Annette, haſt thee obſerved how they try to make their walls look like the country, by ſticking a parcel of pictures about them?—They ſay, too, it coſts them a mint of money; if that's the caſe, I am ſure they are great fools, for our pictures here are ten times handſomer; and we have them for nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Dear me! t'other day, when I carried ſome milk to my lord's. I heard a band of muſick too—Lord, Lubin, what a terrible noiſe! I could not help ſaying, if they wanted muſick, why did not they come and hear our nightingales?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Well ſaid, Annette!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Ah! but, dear Lubin, I met that naſty Bailly again; and he ſays he'll come and ſcold thee for loving me ſo much.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Oh! he will, will he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>—I'll give him as good as he brings—'tis a plaguy ſtrange thing they can't let us alone—I'cod, in our village, the folks no ſooner ſee two people happy, but they try to make them as miſerable as they can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed he frightens me out of my wits—I can't tell thee what a heap of ſtuff he ſays—that we are couſins; and that we love one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other—I am ſure I thought all we did was out of good-will; but he ſhewed me, as plain as could be, that it was all love, and that love is a terrible thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:0072601000:10"/>
            <stage>AIR.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>Young, and void of art or guile,</l>
               <l>From ill intentions free;</l>
               <l>If love I've cheriſh'd all this while,</l>
               <l>It came in 'ſpight of me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When you've to me, and I've to you,</l>
               <l>Try'd who cou'd kindeſt prove;</l>
               <l>If that was love—what then to do,</l>
               <l>To fly from this ſame love?</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>II.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>When abſent from you I have mourn'd,</l>
               <l>And thought each hour a ſcore;</l>
               <l>When, on a ſudden, you return'd,</l>
               <l>I've thrill'd with joy all o'er;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They ſay 'twas love—I thought 'twas you</l>
               <l>Had made my heart thus move;</l>
               <l>Alas! what can a poor girl do</l>
               <l>To fly from this ſame love?</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>III.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>To every thing that you can ask,</l>
               <l>What ſhould I ſay but yes?</l>
               <l>It is becauſe I like the task,</l>
               <l>I freely grant each kiſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:0072601000:11"/>
               <l>You're all to me—I'm all to you—</l>
               <l>This truth our deaths would prove</l>
               <l>Were we to part—What then to do,</l>
               <l>To fly from this ſame love?</l>
            </lg>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Never mind them, Annette,—we'll be happy in ſpight of them—I'll go and ſee that the ſheep don't ſtray from the valley—and then you ſhall hear what I'll ſay to Mr. Bailly.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="scene">
            <head>SCENE III.</head>
            <stage>ANNETTE and the BAILLY.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <stage>(Sitting in the cabin.)</stage>
               <p>I don't care if they won't let me love Lubin, I'll never love any body, eſpecially after being to him as I am.—Poor ſoul, what pains he takes for me, and then we have neither kin nor kind!—and as I often ſays, who ſhould love us if we don't love one another?</p>
               <stage>(Here the Bailiff, who had ſtole behind the cabin to liſten, puts the branches aſide and thruſts in his head and hands.)</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>E'nt you aſhamed of yourſelf?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Lord! you frightened me out of my wits.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>Are theſe the leſſons of your late mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?—The poor woman!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:0072601000:12"/>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Why what's the matter with you?—You are always in a paſſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>Did ſhe inſtruct you to liſten to the men?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Oh Lord! I never does any ſuch thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>And Lubin, you baggage, Lubin!</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>AIR.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <l>They tell me you liſten to all that he ſays;</l>
               <l>That each hour of the day you are full of his praiſe;</l>
               <l>That you always together your flocks lead to graze;</l>
               <l>Is this true, damſel?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <l>Yes, Miſter Bailly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <l>They tell me, alſo, you are ſo void of grace,</l>
               <l>As to brag that dear form, and that ſweet pretty face,</l>
               <l>That young dog ſhall be welcome to kiſs and embrace;</l>
               <l>Is this true, damſel?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <l>Yes, Miſter Bailly.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:0072601000:13"/>
            <stage>II.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <l>The neighbours all ſay, though I credit them not,</l>
               <l>They have heard you declare, that content with your lot,</l>
               <l>Any King you'd refuſe for that lout and a cot;</l>
               <l>Is this true, damſel?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <l>Yes, Miſter Bailly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <l>But one thing I vow, frights me out of my life,</l>
               <l>'Tis allowed on all hands, that is barring the ſtrife,</l>
               <l>That you both live together juſt like man and wife;</l>
               <l>Is this true, damſel?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <l>Yes, Miſter Bailly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>How!—How's this, you have granted him then—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Every thing, I can aſſure you—I ſhould be ſorry indeed if Lubin and I had any thing to refuſe one another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>What confidence!—And pray tell me, the firſt time this misfortune happened to you, did it not thunder and lighten? Did not the ſun hide itſelf?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:0072601000:14"/>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Oh no, 'twas the fineſt day I ever ſaw in all my life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>But do you know what a crime you have been guilty of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>I don't know what a crime is—But for what has happened, I can ſafely ſwear, 'twas all done out of love and kindneſs; and not out of malice the leaſt bit in the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>You are couſins, I tell you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Well, ſuppoſe we are?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>Suppoſe you are! Why in that conſiſts the crime.—My Lord is hunting hard by, he muſt be made acquainted with this affair.—Lord! Lord! What will this world come to?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>AIR.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>Lord! Lord! if to paſs are permitted theſe ways,</l>
               <l>We ſhan't quietly ſleep in our beds;</l>
               <l>It calls out for vengeance, and one of theſe days,</l>
               <l>The thunder will fall on our heads.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſhall I ſuch enormities tamely behold,</l>
               <l>Who fight under Juſtice's banner?</l>
               <l>Who as Bailiff, and Steward, am placeman two-fold,</l>
               <l>To his honour, the Lord of the Manor.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:0072601000:15"/>
            <stage>II.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>If your mother, you baggage, was not dead and gone,</l>
               <l>Between you and that wicked young thief,</l>
               <l>We ſhould ſhortly ſee written upon her tomb ſtone,</l>
               <l>That her daughter had killed her with grief.</l>
               <l>And ſhall I, &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="scene">
            <head>SCENE IV.</head>
            <stage>ANNETTE and LUBIN.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Dear me, I am all in a twitter—What wickedneſs have poor Lubin and I been guilty of? For after all we have done no harm to any body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>What's the matter, Annette?—You are crying.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Oh Lubin, the Bailly has been here, and he ſays that we have been guilty of a crime—Do you knowwhat a crime is, Lubin?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>A crime!—Yes, a crime is a very wicked thing—'Tis a crime to take away a life, but I never heard 'twas a crime to give it.—The Bailly is an old fool, and does not know what he ſays.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſure he is a wicked man to come here and make me all in a tremble.—I could cry my eyes out!—The poor child will hate its mother, the Bailly told me ſo—and we have been guilty of a ſin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>What ſin, my dear Annette?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:0072601000:16"/>
            <stage>AIR.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis true that oft, in the ſame mead,</l>
               <l>We both have led our flocks to feed,</l>
               <l>Where by each other's ſide we've ſat;</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <l>Alas! there was no harm in that!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis true, for thee, this cot I roſe,</l>
               <l>Where thou takeſt pleaſure to repoſe;</l>
               <l>For which I found the greeneſt plat;</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <l>Alas! there was no harm in that!</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>II.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis true, when tired thou fain would reſt,</l>
               <l>And thy dear lips to mine I've preſs'd,</l>
               <l>Thy breath, ſo ſweet! I've wondered at;</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <l>Alas! there was no harm in that!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <l>Ah! but 'tis true, when thou haſt ſlept,</l>
               <l>Cloſer and cloſer have I crept;</l>
               <l>And while my heart went pit-a-pat—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <l>Alas! there was no harm in that.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Ay, ay, we may think, but 'twill be no eaſy matter to find any harm we have done;—hang it, Annette, let them talk till their hearts ach, and let us love one another in ſpight of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>The Bailly ſaid my Lord was a coming this way, and he'd acquaint him with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Wounds, Annette, I deſires no better!—My Lord is kindneſs itſelf, that every body
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:0072601000:17"/>
knows, and we ſhould be the firſt unfortunate folks that went away from him with heavy hearts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Dear Lubin! I ſhan't be able to look at him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Never fear.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Here comes the Bailly—I'll hide myſelf.</p>
               <stage>[ſhe goes into the hut.</stage>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="scene">
            <head>SCENE V.</head>
            <stage>LUBIN, and the BAILLY.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, ho, you are come, Mr. Bailly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>O you vile wretch! how dare you look me, or any other honeſt man, in the face, after abuſing the loſt Annette?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Vile wretch, in your teeth, Mr. Bailly.—Annette is not loſt, ſhe is in our cabin—'tis you, with your meddling, has vexed her, and put a heap of ſtuff in her head.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>What, you pretend you have not robb'd her of what ought to be deareſt to her in the world?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Me!—of what?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>Of what!—her innocence, and her honour!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>I tell you I love her more than my life; and if I have done her any wrong, here I ſtand to make it good—Marry us! who hinders you?—I'cod we deſires no better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis impoſſible! and you muſt be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated for ever.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:0072601000:18"/>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>You are a wicked man to propoſe ſuch a thing, Mr. Bailly; who's to take care of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nette and her innocent child?—me be ſeparated from her—you ſhall kill me firſt, I can tell you that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>The law will oblige you to it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>The law ſhall do no ſuch thing.</p>
               <stage>(putting on his hat.)</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>Oh the little impudent raſcal, how he rails againſt the law!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Oh the great wicked men, to want me to leave Annette! Come here, Annette.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>AIR,</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>A plague take all ſuch grumbling elves,</l>
               <l>If they will rail, ſo be it;</l>
               <l>Becauſe we're happier than themſelves,</l>
               <l>They can't endure to ſee it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For me I never ſhall repine,</l>
               <l>Let whate'er fate o'ertake us;</l>
               <l>For love and Annette ſhall be mine,</l>
               <l>Tho' all the world forſake us.</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>II.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>Then, dear Annette, regard them not,</l>
               <l>The hours we'll paſs on gayly,</l>
               <l>And laugh at every ſnare and plot,</l>
               <l>Of that old doating Bailly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:0072601000:19"/>
               <l>No never, Annette, thou'lt repine,</l>
               <l>Let whate'er fate o'ertake us;</l>
               <l>For love and Lubin ſhall be thine,</l>
               <l>Though all the world forſake us.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="scene">
            <head>SCENE Laſt.</head>
            <stage>All the CHARACTERS.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>Here comes my Lord; we ſhall hear what you'll ſay to him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhan't be afraid to tell him the truth, any more than you. Come here, Annette, don't be aſham'd; here is his Honour's Lordſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bail.</speaker>
               <p>Your Lordſhip is acquainted with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, and here and pleaſe you are the criminals.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>My Lord, if it ſhall pleaſe you, I'll tell you the long and the ſhort on't. The Bail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here ſays, that we muſt be married to have children, and that we can't be married, becauſe we are couſins; and ſo, that being, we are guilty of a great ſin; and that all the world will cry out ſhame of us; and that if any harm happens in the country, we ſhall be the cauſe of it.—In ſhort, and pleaſe your Lordſhip's honour, the Bailly gives us to the Devil; and ſo, as a body may ſay, we recommend ourſelves to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The <hi>Lord.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <stage>(Conſtraining a laugh)</stage>
               <p>My children, the Bailiff is right—But comfort yourſelves, and tell me ingenuouſly the whole truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>There! did not I tell you his Lordſhip
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:0072601000:20"/>
would be kind to us? Speak to his honour, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nette.</p>
               <stage>AIR, ANNETTE.</stage>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Lord, and pleaſe you, him and I,</l>
                  <l>Morn, noon, and night, in every weather,</l>
                  <l>From little children, not this high,</l>
                  <l>In the ſame cottage liv'd together.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our parents left me to his care,</l>
                  <l>Saying, let no one put upon her:</l>
                  <l>No, that I won't, ſays he, I ſwear!</l>
                  <l>And he ne'er lies, and like your honour.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>II.</stage>
               <lg>
                  <l>As I was ſaying, we grew up</l>
                  <l>For all the world, ſiſter and brother;</l>
                  <l>One never had nor bit nor ſup,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs it was partook by t'other;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, I am ſure, inſtead of me,</l>
                  <l>Were it a Dutcheſs, he had won her;</l>
                  <l>He is ſo good! and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, d'ye ſee,</l>
                  <l>A tender heart, and like your honour.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>III.</stage>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, woe is ours, now comes the worſt;</l>
                  <l>To-day our ſorrows are beginning;</l>
                  <l>What I thought love—oh, I ſhall burſt!</l>
                  <l>That naſty Bailly ſays was ſinning:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:0072601000:21"/>
                  <l>With Lubin, who, of all the bliſs</l>
                  <l>I ever taſted, is the donor,</l>
                  <l>I took delight to toy and kiſs;—</l>
                  <l>'Till I'm with child, and like your honour.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>And ſo, my Lord, you ſee what has happened; and if I have done any harm, I ſhall die with ſhame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lub.</speaker>
               <p>Pray don't let Annette die, my Lord—I ſhould die too, and that would be a pity.—If you could but have ſeen how we lived together before this Old Bailly came and frighten'd us ſo, Nothing was ever ſo gay—All that vexes us is, he ſays my child won't know its father nor mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that it will reproach us with its birth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>'Twill reproach me in my grave then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The <hi>Lord.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>They really intereſt me—Don't afflict yourſelves, you are not criminal, you are only unfortunate: if you were rich, you might obtain a permiſſion to love and be united: 'tis not juſt that, becauſe you are poor, you ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied ſo equitable a deſire.—I'll take this matter upon myſelf, and the week ſhall not paſs before I procure a diſpenſation from the church, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward your innocence and affection as it deſerves.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>AIR.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bailly.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>His Lordſhip really is too good!</l>
                  <l>What will the people ſay!</l>
                  <l>Marry two folks one fleſh and blood!—</l>
                  <l>Henceforth young maids will ſtray.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:0072601000:22"/>
                  <l>The wolf will creep</l>
                  <l>Among the ſheep,</l>
                  <l>Corn will on fire be ſet,</l>
                  <l>What can come leſs,</l>
                  <l>From the wickedneſs</l>
                  <l>Of Lubin and Annette!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Annette.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Peace, miſter Bailey—for my Lord</l>
                  <l>Has now untied my tongue;</l>
                  <l>And I may bold put in my word—</l>
                  <l>I own we've been ſo wrong.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our former ſhame</l>
                  <l>Each fair ſhould blame,</l>
                  <l>And yet, without regret,</l>
                  <l>Might imitate</l>
                  <l>The future ſtate</l>
                  <l>Of Lubin and Annette<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lubin.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wounds let un talk, and talk again!</l>
                  <l>He'll never get his ends;</l>
                  <l>His ſpite will give me little pain</l>
                  <l>If here we find but friends.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Forgive's the word!</l>
                  <l>You ſee my lord</l>
                  <l>Has the example ſet;</l>
                  <l>Do'e then, pray,</l>
                  <l>Clap hands, and ſay,</l>
                  <l>Smile Lubin and Annette!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
