<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Magdalens: an elegy: By the author of The nunnery.</title>
            <author>Jerningham, Mr. (Edward), 1737?-1812.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>10 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04">2009 April</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004846554</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T74530</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW111222619</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K062802.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3311222619</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECLL</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">0273201600</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Magdalens: an elegy: By the author of The nunnery.</title>
                  <author>Jerningham, Mr. (Edward), 1737?-1812.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12p. ; 4⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. and J. Dodsley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1763.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The author of The nunnery = Edward Jerningham.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT74530.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:0273201600:1"/>
            <p>THE MAGDALENS: AN ELEGY. By the AUTHOR of the NUNNERY.</p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for R. and J. DODSLEY, at Tully's-Head, Pall-Mall. M DCC LXIII. [Price Six-pence.]</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:0273201600:2"/>
            <p>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE MARY LEPEL, <hi>Baroneſs Dowager</hi> HERVEY <hi>of</hi> ICKWORTH. THIS ELEGY IS, WITH THE GREATEST RESPECT, INSCRIBED,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>BY HER LADYSHIP's OBLIGED AND HUMBLE SERVANT, THE AUTHOR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:0273201600:3"/>
            <head>THE MAGDALENS.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>LO! kneeling at yon Rail with penſive Air,</l>
               <l>A num'rous Train of ſuppliant Nymphs I ſpy:</l>
               <l>Their youthful Cheek is pal'd with early Care,</l>
               <l>And Sorrow dwells in their dejected Eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hark, They attune a ſolemn plaintive Lay,</l>
               <l>Where Grief with Harmony delights to meet:</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Philomela</hi> from her lonely Spray</l>
               <l>Trills her clear Note, more querulouſly ſweet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:0273201600:4"/>
               <l>Are Theſe the Fair who wont with conſcious Grace</l>
               <l>Proud <hi>Ranelagh's</hi> reſplendent Round to tread?</l>
               <l>Shine in the ſtudied Luxury of Dreſs?</l>
               <l>And vie in Beauty with the high-born Maid?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſmiling Scenes of Pleaſure they ſorſake,</l>
               <l>Obey no more Amuſement's idle Call,</l>
               <l>Nor mingling with the Sons of Mirth partake</l>
               <l>The Treat voluptuous, or the feſtive Ball.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For ſober Weeds they change their bright Attire,</l>
               <l>Of the Pearl Bracelet ſtrip the graceful Arm,</l>
               <l>Veil the white Breaſt, that lately heav'd Deſire,</l>
               <l>And thrill'd with tender exquiſite Alarm:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Unbraid the cunning Treſſes of the Hair,</l>
               <l>And each well-fancied Ornament remove,</l>
               <l>The glowing Gem, the glitt'ring Solitaire—</l>
               <l>The coſtly ſpoils of proſtituted Love!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:0273201600:5"/>
               <l>Yet Beauty lingers on their mournful Brow,</l>
               <l>Unwilling to forſake the Tear-dew'd Cheek,</l>
               <l>Which ſcarcely bluſhing with a languid Glow</l>
               <l>Partakes a Softneſs delicately meek.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No more compare then to the ſtately Flow'r,</l>
               <l>Whoſe painted Foliage wantons in the Gale:</l>
               <l>They look the Lily drooping from the Show'r,</l>
               <l>Or the pale Vi'let ſick'ning in the Vale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let not the Prude with acrimonious Taunt,</l>
               <l>Upbraid the humble Tenants of this Dome,</l>
               <l>That Pleaſure's roſy Bow'r they us'd to haunt,</l>
               <l>And in the Walks of looſe-rob'd Dalliance roam.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If fond of Empire, and of Conqueſt vain,</l>
               <l>They frequent Vot'ries to their Altars drew,</l>
               <l>Yet blaz'd thoſe Altars to the Fair ones' Bane,</l>
               <l>The Idol They, and They the Victim too!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:0273201600:6"/>
               <l>Some in this ſacred Manſion may reſide,</l>
               <l>Who loſt their Parents in their Infant Years,</l>
               <l>And hapleſs Orphans! trod without a Guide</l>
               <l>The Maze of Life perplext with guileful Snares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some, that encircled by the Great and Rich,</l>
               <l>Were won by Wiles, and deep-deſigning Art,</l>
               <l>By ſplendid Bribes, and ſoſt perſuaſive Speech,</l>
               <l>Of Pow'r to cheat the young unguarded Heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some, on whom Beauty breath'd her choiceſt Bloom,</l>
               <l>Whilſt adverſe Stars all other Gifts remov'd,</l>
               <l>Who fled from Mis'ry and a Dungeon's Gloom,</l>
               <l>To Scenes their inborn Virtue diſapprov'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What tho' Their Youth imbib'd an early Stain:</l>
               <l>Now gilded by the Rays of new-born Fame,</l>
               <l>A ſecond Innocence they here obtain,</l>
               <l>And Nun-clad Penance heals their wounded Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:0273201600:7"/>
               <l>So the young Myrtles nipt by treach'rous Cold,</l>
               <l>(While ſtill the Summer yields his golden Store,)</l>
               <l>In ſhelt'ring Walls their tender Leaves unfold,</l>
               <l>And breathe a ſweeter Fragrance than before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tho' white-wing'd Peace protect this calm Abode,</l>
               <l>Tho' each tumultuous Paſſion be ſuppreſs'd,</l>
               <l>Still Recollection wears a Sting to goad,</l>
               <l>Still arrowy Remorſe afflicts their Breaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The tort'ring Hour of Mem'ry this may prove,</l>
               <l>Who wrapt in penſive Secrecy forlorn,</l>
               <l>Sits muſing on the Pledges of her Love,</l>
               <l>Expos'd to chilly Want, and grinning Scorn:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Left by their Father in the Time of Need,</l>
               <l>Juſt in th' unfolding Bloſſom of their Age!</l>
               <l>"Was this, Seducer, this the promis'd Meed?"</l>
               <l>She cries: Then ſinks beneath Affliction's Rage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:0273201600:8"/>
               <l>Another mourns her Fall with Grief ſincere,</l>
               <l>Whom tranquil Reaſon tells ſhe's ſhun'd, diſdain'd,</l>
               <l>Repuls'd as vile by thoſe who held her dear,</l>
               <l>Who call'd her once Companion, Siſter, Friend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That recollects the Day, when loſt to Shame</l>
               <l>She fondly ſacrific'd her veſtal Charms:</l>
               <l>Reſign'd the Virgin's for an Harlot's Name,</l>
               <l>And left a Parent's for a Spoiler's Arms.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Imagination pencils to her Mind</l>
               <l>The Father's Rage, the Mother's ſofter Woe:</l>
               <l>Unhappy Pair! to that Diſtreſs conſign'd</l>
               <l>A Child can give, a Parent only know.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The dreadful Picture fixes Sorrow's Dart,</l>
               <l>Fond filial Paſſions in her Breaſt revive:</l>
               <l>She feels keen Anguiſh preying at her Heart,</l>
               <l>To Nature's Pangs too ſenſibly alive.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:0273201600:9"/>
               <l>If this, or ſimilar tormenting Thought,</l>
               <l>Cling to their Soul, when penſively alone,</l>
               <l>For Youth's Offence, for Love's alluring Fault,</l>
               <l>Say, do they not ſufficiently atone?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O mock not then their penitential Woes,</l>
               <l>Thou, who may'ſt deign to mark this humble Theme,</l>
               <l>Nor ſeek with foul Deriſion to expoſe</l>
               <l>And give to Infamy their tainted Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor deem me one of Melancholy's Train,</l>
               <l>If anxious for the Sorrow-wedded Fair,</l>
               <l>(Tho' little ſkilful of poetic Strain</l>
               <l>Whoſe pleaſing Muſic takes the tuneful Ear)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ſteal impatient from the idle Throng,</l>
               <l>The roving, gay, Companions of my Age,</l>
               <l>To temper with their Praiſe my artleſs Song,</l>
               <l>And ſoft-ey'd Pity in their Cauſe engage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:0273201600:10"/>
               <l>'Tis Virtue's Taſk to ſoothe Affliction's Smart,</l>
               <l>To join in Sadneſs with the Fair diſtreſt:</l>
               <l>Wake to another's Pain the tender Heart,</l>
               <l>And move to Sympathy the feeling Breaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
