<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lues venerea, rationally handled, in its original cause: with its cure. By J. A. surgeon.</title>
            <author>Atkins, John, 1685-1757.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>50 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-01">2012 January</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004855235</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T87986</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW108896460</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K071504.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3308896460</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECMS</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">0968300300</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lues venerea, rationally handled, in its original cause: with its cure. By J. A. surgeon.</title>
                  <author>Atkins, John, 1685-1757.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4],47,[1]p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and sold by T. Bickerton; Cha. Pickman, and J. Cluer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1730?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J. A. = John Atkins.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT87986.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:0968300300:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Lues Venerea,</hi> Rationally handled, in its Original CAUSE: WITH ITS CURE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nemo unquam legendo, fit Artifex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>J. A.</hi> Surgeon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Bickerton</hi> in <hi>Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſter-Row; Cha. Pickman</hi> in <hi>Upper-Shadwell,</hi> and <hi>J. Cluer,</hi> Printer, in <hi>Bow</hi> Church-Yard. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:0968300300:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>BY what can be collected from Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, the <hi>Lues</hi> has, in all <hi>Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pean</hi> Countries, been found an obſtinate Diſtemper. The ill Succeſs of former Practice, one would be apt to attribute to wrong <hi>Hypotheſis's,</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes</hi> conſequent thereto, did not many Particulars at this Day juſtifie their <hi>Complaints,</hi> and ſhew us the ſame <hi>Difficulties</hi> remain about the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Cure</hi> of this Diſtemper, as ever. No <hi>Noſtrum</hi> as yet, how infallible ſoever in the Opinion of its Poſſeſſor, will anſwer to all <hi>Symptoms,</hi> or to all <hi>Patients</hi> under the ſame <hi>Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> I have had Tryal of ſeveral com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated as ſuch, but finding nothing extraordinary in them, I conclude the Art of <hi>Curing</hi> here, as in other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes,
<pb facs="tcp:0968300300:3"/>lies as much in the <hi>Managemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as in the <hi>Medicines</hi> themſelves, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they be adminiſtred in Seaſon, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> adapted to Conſtitutions; ſo that to ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mercury</hi> is the Foundation of <hi>Cure</hi> will be of little import to a Reader o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Subject, unleſs at the ſame tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Skill</hi> of uſing it could be convey'd and this will never be attained in any great Perfection without Practice However, an attention to Rules is no altogether unworthy a Regard, <hi>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which Reaſon</hi> I have ventur'd on thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Eſſay,</hi> wherein I have, as it fell in my way, made a ſummary of the beſt Opinions in the <hi>Therapeutick Part,</hi> ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with no Reſtraint to my own Senti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments, which thro' the whole, I have endeavoured to make appear Rational if it ſhall be thought ſo by the proper Judges, it may poſſibly hereafter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an Improvement.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:0968300300:4"/>
            <head>Lues Venerea.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOSE who fetch the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of this Diſtemper no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther back than the Siege of <hi>Naples</hi> by the <hi>French,</hi> 1494, thence calling it the <hi>French,</hi> and ſometimes the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Diſeaſe, muſt only mean that it received its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Name there, that it became more common, or that luckily about that Time ſome Remedy was found better adapted to its Cure than any before known: For no doubt it reaches in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity the Firſt Ages; it being irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal either to ſuppoſe a World drowned for their Sins, Strangers to the Vice that contracts it, or that their Wickedneſs any more than ours deſerved Exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. No; Providence, we may ſafely
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:0968300300:5"/>believe, ſtamped an immediate Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on this, as on all other Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Sin, <hi>ab Origine,</hi> that the Pains and Sufferings ſucceeding a vicious Courſe of Life, might, if nothing elſe would, reſtrain us to Vertue, and be both a natural and moral Good to us. We find <hi>Moſes</hi> deſcribing a Leproſy, <hi>Levit.</hi> 13 and 14, that correſponds with the Symptoms, and ſeems to have been a Species of this Diſtemper; ſo does the Difficulty of the Cure, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. where it is ſaid, <hi>The botch and ſcab of Egypt of which thou canſt not be healed:</hi> And thoſe many Laws found here relating to a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſy, would ſuffer a greater Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than ſeems intended, as well from the Obſtinacy as infrequency of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, if applied only to what we now ſtrictly underſtand by that Term: The ſame may be ſaid of many Ancient Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Authors, who with the like or grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Plainneſs have deſcribed the Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms, tho' not under the modern Titles.</p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this Subject I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſet forth the Nature and Manner of Inſection in all thoſe Symptoms com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly underſtood by a Clap, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrhea, Chancre, Phymoſis, &amp;c.</hi> and then exhibit a Method of Cure; mentioning
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:0968300300:6"/>the Symptoms occaſionally under either Head, as they ſerve to enlighten each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And <hi>First</hi> of the <hi>Gonorrhaea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Gonorrhaea</hi> is benign or malign: The firſt ſort is an Emiſſion of Humour from the <hi>Glandulae proſtatae,</hi> a Weakneſs only, and commonly proceeding from great Strains, and where the natural Strength has been too far exerted in any ſort, whether by Labour or Venereal Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; it has its Symptoms as well as Proceſs of Cure very different from the malignant, which at preſent I ſhall make the only Subject of my Enquiry, and that under two Heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By ſhewing how either Sex be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes infected. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Cure for that Infection.</p>
            <p>And 1st. Of the Woman: Her I look on muſt be primarily and originally Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that is <hi>ſine amplexu infecto,</hi> to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the being of this Diſtemper in the World: For let a Man correſpond with what Variety he pleaſes (provided they are ſound) he receives no Malignancy, which could it be ſo with her, I cannot ſee why we ever ſhould thus unhappily have had its Knowledge; but Experience too fatally contradicting this, is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, that Coition with Numbers has
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:0968300300:7"/>firſt of all, and probably does ſtill, at ſome times effect the ſame, as at other times Communication with an infected Perſon; and this I ſhall endeavour to make out in a few Words.</p>
            <p>Such who ſay the promiſcuous Mixture of different Sperms excites a Ferment, which in a little Time throws off ſuch an Exſpumation as we call a Running, do agree that Numbers (tho' ſound) car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Infection, we only differ in the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they accompliſh it, which I rather ſuppoſe to be thus: When the Venereal Appetite is jaded with the too intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Efforts of ſeveral Men, it will be next to impoſſible for thoſe Parts to ſuffer the continued Frictions made there (as common Women do) without excori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating and fretting the Membranes of the Vagina; and ſuch Excoriations, how ſmall ſoever in the beginning, meeting with an ill Habit of Body, together with the natural Incaleſcence and Moiſture of the Parts, will ſoon degenerate to an Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer; which Ulcer will be the Diſtemper: And perhaps herein lies the Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a <hi>Fluor Albus</hi> and <hi>Gonorrhaea,</hi> (when thus contracted) that the one is a Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from too frequent Irritations made there, and the other beſides that extrinſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:0968300300:8"/>Accident, has an ill Habit of Body joined, that induces Intemperies.</p>
            <p>What I think gives Credit to this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is the Cuſtoms of the Jewiſh, Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan, and many other Countries, who allow a Plurality of Wives, and an unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Number of Concubines, reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Sex at the ſame time to one: For this, tho' an inferiour Motive of the Law, argues the World to have previouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experienced ſuch a Liberty in them more deſtructive of Health and a ſound Conſtitution than in us. Among other Creatures there is an Inſtinct anſwering ſuch a Purpoſe of the Law whereby the Females are <hi>provoked only at certain Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to Propagation,</hi> and <hi>abſtain after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception;</hi> Nature <hi>intimating by it a Leſſon of Chaſtity to the Fair; that it ſhould be their</hi> peculiar <hi>as well as most</hi> ornamental <hi>Vertue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt it, I can form to my ſelf only two Objections: Firſt, That it may be alleged the Activity of ſome Men this Way, might prejudice a weak Woman the ſame as a Number: And Secondly, it may be asked how an Ulcer, <hi>in Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gina,</hi> can acquire Malignity enough to communicate Infection on Coition, when the greateſt Degree of Virulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:0968300300:9"/>in another Ulcer produces no ſuch Effect?</p>
            <p>But, to theſe it may be anſwered, That the Strength and Activity of any two in Health will ſeldom be found ſo diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate as to become hurtful, when it is; the Diſorder enſuing can be no more than a <hi>Fluor Albus,</hi> or a Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without Malignity. And as to the other; why an Ulcer here ſhould ſooner impart its Miſchief than any other? Is, that the Parts concerned are in all Reſpects more commodious for giving and receiving any Injury, and that the Heat raiſed and excited by Luſt gives a Force and Activity to the Salts gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated under the Corruption; whereas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Ulcer, tho' never ſo virulent, cannot emit Effluvia's in ſuch Force or Numbers, nor to Parts ſo ſuſceptible of their Reception; but if they had thoſe Advantages, it is likely their Effects would be equal, many ill Conſequences following from an Ulcer with Virulency in any Part incautiouſly dry'd up.</p>
            <p>That Luſt alſo is a very neceſſary Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct for communicating Infection, and giving Force to thoſe virulent Miaſms that are as it were darted by it from her, we judge by that particular Power and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:0968300300:10"/>Influence, Imagination is found to have in the Commotion of theſe Parts: In this Caſe it is ſo much, that many infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Women avoid hurting their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands principally on the Moderation and Coolneſs of their Enjoyments, whereas a Stranger inciting more intenſe and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous Deſires as ſeldom eſcapes. The ſame may be ſaid where two or three, with weaker or ſtronger Inclinations, lie with one and the ſame infected Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that one perhaps ſhall be catch'd, and the others come off unhurt, chiefly as the Fancy on either ſide is brisk and lively, inclin'd or diſinclin'd.</p>
            <p>Venereal Contact ſeems of ſuch Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for communicating Infection, that with me it is a very unlikely thing for Venereal Matter ever to do it without, thoſe who have aſſerted the contrary of this have done it in ſuch improbable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which whoever can aſſent to, will be very unreaſonable if they deny their Acquieſcence in what I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced of Numbers. For Inſtance:</p>
            <p>The <hi>Practical Scheme</hi> (Page 4.) ſays, It is not always neceſſary a Woman be clapp'd to give it a Man, but that he may take off all the virulent Matter left in the Paſſage by a preceding Gallant,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:0968300300:11"/>and ſhe remain perfectly well; or that ſhe may give it him by only taking the corrupted Matter from her Body in her Hand and wetting his Privities.</p>
            <p>And others relate its higheſt Degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, or a Pox, to be Contagious by wearing the Clothes, Lying, or Cohabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with an infected Perſon; eſpecially if we ſuppoſe it of that Stage of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper wherein the Body becomes over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with Cutaneous Eruptions and Blotches.</p>
            <p>There are but Two Ways in this latter Caſe (for the former I have no Notion of) whereby Contagion can be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to paſs, and that is by their throwing off a greater Quantity of noxious and virulent Effluvia, able to contaminate where they reach, or elſe, (like what is related in the Philoſophical Tranſactions concerning Contagion in the Itch) <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimalculae,</hi> are bred in thoſe Globules, diſperſed about the Skin, which making their Way through, ſhift from Place to Place, and ſo carry Infection, they liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (ſays the Relation) two or three Days when from the Body.</p>
            <p>But how well theſe <hi>Aſſignata</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve other contagious Diſtempers, they will here be found but light in the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:0968300300:12"/>Fact baffles Philoſophy, and if all thoſe who have ſuffered this Way are like what have fallen to my Share, there is not one who could ſtand by any other Pretence than Coition: Whence we ought to account the Diſtemper a Mark of Divine Diſpleaſure, and a preſent bodily Correction for our Sin, that the Senſe of our own Intereſt, might work on us, and bring us back to Temperance and Vertue.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How a Man becomes infected.</head>
               <p>WOmen we have adjudged ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to become infected by the Admiſſion of Numbers, tho' ſound and healthful; but a Man cannot by the ſame Means, becauſe among other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons there is this invincible one, That Nature is not able to ſupport the Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thoſe Acts to ſuch a Multiplicity, or in ſuch Meaſure as with her who is paſſive; but could that be, I believe alſo he might ſo contract it: Inſatiable and impotent Efforts, or too painful Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments through the Straitneſs of the <hi>Vagina,</hi> frequently diſcovers ſomething like this, in what we call <hi>ſimple Gonor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhaea's</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:0968300300:13"/>and <hi>Chriſtallins,</hi> which perhaps Time and an ill Habit would change, and make to become virulent, did not Pain or the Debility of Nature prevent a further Uſe of the Cauſe that firſt produced them, and hinder our Actions from keeping Pace with the Viciouſneſs of our Wills and Inclinations. For this Reaſon therefore Venereal Symptoms thus contracted, never ſettle or terminate in a Pox; and I am apt to think all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity that does ſo to him, or is contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>Muſt always be from an infected Perſon, and always by Coition:</hi> For a clearer Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of which, and <hi>the Manner of Communication,</hi> I ſhall <hi>Cite</hi> Two or Three <hi>Celebrated Opinions about it,</hi> and then <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe my own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Keil</hi> ſays, <hi>It's Conveyance is by the Elaſticity of the Air, thruſting the Morbifick Matter into the Excretory Ducts of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlatae, which are empty on Coition; and that a ſimple</hi> Gonorrhaea <hi>is nothing, but a Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Spongious Borders of thoſe Veſſels terminating in the Urethra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some think, <hi>a Gonorrhaea to be the Effect of a Fermentation made between the Infectious Liquor, and that of the</hi> Proſtatae, <hi>and ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Corroſion an Efflux thrown off like Yeſt from Beer.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:0968300300:14"/>
               <p>Laſtly, Dr. <hi>Cockburn</hi> ſuppoſes <hi>a Gonor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhaea to be the encrcaſe of that Liquor that is diſcharged by the Excretory Glands of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethra, and done by the Venereal Stimulus, in the ſame manner as</hi> Cantharides <hi>apply'd would do; the Quantity of Matter diſcharg'd being in proportion to the Stimulating Force they are affected with: And this</hi> Stimulus (he ſays) <hi>encreaſing its Acrimony, does in Proceſs of time, make Ulcers in the</hi> Urethra. This he farther oppoſes to Dr. <hi>Keil</hi>'s Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, by ſaying, the <hi>Urethra</hi> will admit very little, and that there is no <hi>Muſcle, Membrane,</hi> or <hi>Machine</hi> alleged to help it for ward.</p>
               <p>But theſe Opinions, beſides their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to one another, are deficient in carrying their Aim ſingly to a <hi>Gonorrhaea,</hi> without any Attempt at the Cauſe of a <hi>Chancre, Chordee,</hi> or <hi>Phymoſis,</hi> which Men often become infected with, without a <hi>Gonorrhaea:</hi> I ſhall therefore begin my Enquiry here, being aſſured that they at leaſt want another and different Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, which perhaps when found, will facilitate alſo our Search in a <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norrhaea;</hi> and if I am right in my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, They ariſe from the Strength, Activity, and Solidity of the Salts hid with the Corruption, which being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:0968300300:15"/>about the <hi>Vagina,</hi> are volatiliz'd and made fitter for Communication by the Heat of Luſt, and received by the enlarged Pores of the <hi>Penis,</hi> where, by their Pointedneſs, they ſhortly effect an Eroſion.</p>
               <p>The manner of this Imbibing or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the Man's ſide, is not abſurdly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for by the general Relaxation that attends all ſenſual Pleaſures, of which Coition is perhaps the greateſt: Now, as it moſt exquiſitely affects us, the Parts are relaxed and made more eaſily ſuſceptible of any Venom to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and that again from her becomes enabled to inſinuate and eſcape through the Pores by the Pungency of their Salts, and Power they are darted with; and if the Degree of Relaxation in any Part be in Proportion to the Pleaſure, (as in the agreeable Objects of any other Senſe, it is, where tho' ſome Degree of it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults to the whole Man, yet ſomething remains peculiar to the Senſe of which it is an Object) then the Inſtruments of Generation, by being moſt relaxed, will be alſo moſt fitted on that Account for the Reception of morbifick Matter.</p>
               <p>Hence the Genital Parts ſhould always ſuffer firſt, and amorous Men ſooneſt.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:0968300300:16"/>
               <p>And if virulent Matter, thus externally lodged, can act like Cantharides, and produce a <hi>Chancre, Chordee,</hi> or <hi>Phymoſis,</hi> then I believe we may alſo, without any repugnancy to Reaſon, think this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Application of it in Coition ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to produce a <hi>Gonorrhaea:</hi> The Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty againſt it being only how this Taint can be tranſmitted hence to the <hi>Proſtatae,</hi> which will not be ſo hard to Imagine, if we conſider what has been already ſaid of the Power impelling, and the Aptitude to receive. We find all Parts of the Body Porous, and by many Experiments re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptive of any proper Matter incumbent on them, conveying and mixing a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Humours of the Body, as in Bathing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all Tranſlations of Tumours, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Revulſion or Derivation, this Sympathy and Communication of Parts is evident, and particularly in the preſent Caſe, where, on an improper handling, the Virulency will revert into the Blood, and produce all the Symptoms of a <hi>Pox,</hi> and indeed all outward Applications to any Malady deeper than the Skin (without this) would be impertinent: Why then ſhould it be thought ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary for infectious Matter arm'd with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:0968300300:17"/>other Properties than bare Fluidity, to affect theſe Glandules at ſo ſmall a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance? Since it muſt be acknowledged the ſeveral Parts of a Member have a much eaſier Communication with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves than with the whole, as we often ſee in the quick and ready Tranſlation of a <hi>Gonorrhaea</hi> to the Groin and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, <hi>&amp; Vice Verſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The only remaining Objection to this Tranſmiſſion by the Pores is, that the greateſt Corroſions at the <hi>Glans</hi> and <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putium</hi> are rarely attended with a <hi>Gonor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhaea,</hi> whereas were ſuch Corroſions thus effected, as it would be an Argument of a ſtronger Infection, and the Corroſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that Venereal Matter to be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it ſhould as ſeldom miſs. This ſeems to be from the Contraction, Pains and Swelling that attend thoſe Ulcers, whereby the Paſſages to the <hi>Proſtatae</hi> are ſtraitned and obſtructed; but a ſlighter Degree, creating no ſuch Impediments, eaſily paſſes, and is ſuſſicient to propel that Humour from the Glands which in a leſs Proportion is their Nature and Office. From hence we may learn a <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norrhaea</hi> to be the mildeſt Species of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:0968300300:18"/>
               <p>If any one ſhould yet object and think the <hi>Mucous Glands</hi> of the <hi>Urethra</hi> more eaſily reached than the <hi>Proſtatae,</hi> and ſo to be the <hi>Seat</hi> of a <hi>Gonorrhaea:</hi> I ſhall no further inſiſt, but only remark to the Favourers of ſuch an Opinion, That a Running is not produced by an Ulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or Corroſion of the <hi>Oſtiolae</hi> of the Glands terminating there, for ſuch would be an irreparable Loſs, and is the very Cauſe of ſome <hi>Gleets,</hi> being incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; but it is rather from the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Veſſels of thoſe Glands being rendred weak and flaccid, that were before vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grous and elaſtick, parting eaſily (for that reaſon) with their Contents.</p>
               <p>From the whole of this Explication we may ſee a Reaſon for that Cuſtom in many Foreign Countries of waſhing the Privities well after <hi>Coition,</hi> (to wit) that they find it preventive of <hi>Infection,</hi> and perhaps <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was not <hi>inſtituted</hi> by that renowned Law-giver <hi>Moſes,</hi> or the Impoſtor <hi>Mahomet,</hi> nor practiſed by Ancienter Nations, without a View to the Cleanlineſs of this Part, and Preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of foul and loathſome Diſtempers.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who account for a <hi>Gonorrhaea</hi> thus, do not ſay a <hi>Diſuria</hi> is from an <hi>Exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation in the Urethra,</hi> but that the Sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:0968300300:19"/>of the Infection thinning and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying off the <hi>Mucus</hi> from the Membrane that lines it, is made more ſenſible of the <hi>pungent Salts</hi> of <hi>Urine</hi> paſſing through; which the would confirm by the Nature of <hi>Patients Complaints,</hi> who don't ſpeak of the <hi>Heat of Water</hi> as a <hi>Pain confin'd to one particular Spot of the Paſſage,</hi> but diffuſed, and ſeems an equal <hi>Vellication of the whole Membrane.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I come now to the ſecond and moſt uſeful Part,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Cure of this Diſtemper:</hi> And Firſt its <hi>Deſcription.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AVirulent Gonorrhaea</hi> or <hi>CLAP,</hi> is <hi>the Emiſſion of infectious Matter from the corroded Glandulae Proſtatae,</hi> or <hi>thoſe of the Urethra,</hi> accompanied with a DISURIA; or in other Words, <hi>the involuntary Flowing of Matter through the Urethra,</hi> with <hi>Pain, Inflammation</hi> and <hi>Heat of Urine;</hi> Theſe are its <hi>Patho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnomick Signs,</hi> and the Degree they are in, with Reſpect to Conſiſtence and Colour in the <hi>Running</hi> (as <hi>Yellow, Green,</hi> or the like) or <hi>Pain in Water,</hi> are what we may take the Meaſure of Virulency from, and will be found more or leſs in different
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:0968300300:20"/>Subjects, according to the Malignity of the infected Perſon, and Conſtitution of the Receiver.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Diſuria</hi> is a Neceſſary Conſequence of the <hi>Running,</hi> it being a Pain from the <hi>Acriminious Salts</hi> of Urine waſting thro' the Parts which that has excoriated.</p>
               <p>The Cure I ſhall lay down under theſe two Intentions:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> To conquer and carry off the Malignancy, and</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> To heal and ſtrengthen the Debilitated Parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> only is able to anſwer our firſt Intention, and effectually to ſubdue the Poiſon of this Diſtemper: The Reaſon why it has a Power beyond other Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines for this purpoſe, is its <hi>Gravity,</hi> and becauſe its conſtituent Parts are extreme ſmall, ſmooth and ſphaerical: The latter Qualification fits them for an admittance into the ſmalleſt Paſſages (even thoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt indiſcernible ones of the Glands) and its weight breaks all Coagulations, and fits the Morbifick Matter for natural Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretions. And whatever ſlights ſome may put on this common Road of proceeding; yet, till better convinced in the Vertues of the ſeveral applauded <hi>Specificks</hi> that have appeared abroad in the World, I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:0968300300:21"/>take leave to defend it, as a <hi>Safe Practice:</hi> For altho' a tedious, or an ill Cure, may now and then happen, it is not juſtly ſo much a Charge on the Medicine, as the Method; when we leave off too ſoon, or continue it with Purges too long, a Practice equally Miſchievous. But more of this by and by.</p>
               <p>I am ſurprized, that every body, by their Practice, ſhould allow <hi>Mercury</hi> to be the only Foundation and Retreat for Cure, in the laſt and ſtubborneſt Stage of this Diſtemper, a <hi>Pox,</hi> and yet deny its Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in a milder Seaſon. It muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, there are too often ſeen many ill Effects from this Mineral; and on a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reflection, I cannot but think, moſt of thoſe deplorable Objects found in Hoſpitals, or elſewhere, whoſe ruined Conſtitutions are attributed to the <hi>Lues,</hi> to be with more Truth and Juſtice, aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to <hi>Mercury;</hi> but then this is not the <hi>Uſe,</hi> but <hi>Abuſe</hi> of it; an unskilful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement often precipitating Patients, (and that in a ſhort time) into ſuch miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Circumſtances, as the Diſtemper, left to it ſelf, could not in Years (if ever) have produc'd: From this Prepoſſeſſion many take a handle to recommend their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:0968300300:22"/>infallible <hi>Noſtrums,</hi> which when good for any thing ſtill have this for their Baſis.</p>
               <p>The Ingenuity of making <hi>Mercury Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifical,</hi> will lie in the Meaſure and Manner of Adminiſtration; that it ſuit ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Infection, and ſuch Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; a Point wherein one Man will excel another, according to their different Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, and Opportunities of Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: All other ways are ſupported by nothing but a <hi>Braſs Front.</hi> The many ſucceſsleſs Attempts of thoſe who publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly invite Men to <hi>Safe and Speedy Cures,</hi> have pretty well expoſed their Credit; and People ſee it to be nothing but a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition in Cunning, who ſhall betray with moſt ſucceſs, without the leaſt Candour, or regard to the Promiſes they make: nor is it a ſmall Diſparagement to <hi>Arcana</hi>'s here, that they are generally lodg'd with the Illiterate. I ſhall further ſtrengthen this Argument for <hi>Mercury,</hi> in Oppoſition to other Specificks, by a ſhort Excurſion on the <hi>Practical Scheme;</hi> becauſe it has made the loudeſt Noiſe of late, and has been Famous, if not for attracting Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet for attracting the Pence, <hi>Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus vult decipi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Compounded Medicine, as is the <hi>Practical Scheme</hi>'s, tho' it ſhould ſeldom
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:0968300300:23"/>miſs the Ends it is giv'n for, and ſo be ſaid to act Electively, yet by being Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, is properly and ſignificatively ranked under the Name of an <hi>Arcanum;</hi> which the Elder Brethren have choſen with Judgment, the Term of <hi>Specifick</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſually apply'd to ſingle Natural Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſuch as he has mention'd (<hi>p.</hi> 12.) And tho' they may be diverſly mix'd for conveying and uſing them with advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, yet the Term is retained ſingly to that Body which is ſaid to be <hi>Specifical:</hi> As for inſtance, in the <hi>Cortex;</hi> whatever Form or Vehicle we give it in, there is nothing but it ſelf has any Claim to the Title: Therefore making the Vertue of his Compoſition to be the <hi>Joynt Force and Reſult of all,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 15.) is not only a Miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of it, but a Confeſſion, that this <hi>Specificality</hi> lieth in none of them ſingly; or if it does, 'tis as yet a hidden thing to him. For he goes on, and tells ye (<hi>p.</hi> 12.13, 16. <hi>&amp; Certificat. p.</hi> 22.) <hi>Their United Force, like a Loadſtone, draws the Contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to it, and exactly hits the different Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of any Age, and that from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of the Diſtemper, to their being in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable State.</hi> And for further Proofs of theſe Abſurdities, he ſays (<hi>p.</hi> 14.) <hi>Perſons after having taken the Specifick, will void
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:0968300300:24"/>large quantities of naſty corrupted ſtinking Water, of ſuch an unſufferable Stench, they will not be able to bear the ſmell; and give but any Dog (that will take it) a Quart of this Urine, and he will in a little time break out with Pocky Sores; recoverable again with ſo ſmall a Doſe of the Specifick as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to the bigneſs of a Pea, whsch will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge it in ſuch ſtinking corrupted Urine, as the Perſon's was who made it.</hi> A plain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion it was the Effect of the Medicine, yet ſerves him for a Conviction of the great Power of this Remedy: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, granting the Relations true, it muſt be allow'd (as was the <hi>Gamboge</hi> the poor <hi>Weavers</hi> took) to be of <hi>Stupendious Efficacy</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 14.)</p>
               <p>I ſhall not wrong this Gentleman, I believe, in ſuppoſing his <hi>Scheme</hi> to be (like other ſhorter <hi>Schemes</hi> that are daily thruſt into our Hands) for drawing in of Cuſtomers; he differs only in having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd their Conciſe way of Writing, and recommending in many Words what they have done Compendiouſly. <hi>The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Vertues of their Incomparable Nover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>failing Anti-venereal PILL.</hi> Through a great part of his Book he inſinuates to his Readers ſuch aſtoniſhing Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from the <hi>Specifick,</hi> as come but little
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:0968300300:25"/>ſhort of Infallibility: <hi>It is a Cure</hi> (ſays he) (<hi>p.</hi> 21.) <hi>for Nineteen in Twenty.</hi> A very ſmall Exception, yet ſerves a double End, being both <hi>Good News to the Afflicted (Title of a Quack Bill)</hi> and a Salvo for Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages: For ſhould the Reverſe of this be, and the Uncur'd 19 in 20, they might every one ſingly lament themſelves and he with them as the unhappy excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Perſon, and their Certificates muſt be wanting, becauſe like his Cures, it would not be allowable to publiſh their Names and Abodes. And indeed, he that gives out a Bill of Promiſes on this Head, is much more ſafe from Detection and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach than any other; becauſe, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the thing is taking a publick Shame, and may be one Reaſon the Infallibility of a Cure is oftner and more confidently aſſerted here than in any other Caſe. The Certificates publiſh'd on theſe Occaſions, (to confirm the Unbelieving) are few e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to be a concerted Cheat; and if real, is only a cunning in common with the Fraternity.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The Pictures which eſcape they wiſely keep,</l>
                  <l>But HIDE all thoſe that periſh in the Deep.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:0968300300:26"/>
               <p>Mrs. <hi>Avery</hi>'s Caſe (poor Gentlewoman) (<hi>p.</hi> 22. <hi>the Certificate</hi>) may be granted ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bad, and the Cure as Extraordinary; yet to ſhew the World ſomething of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel, and that others Parts of it do not want for Wonders, I refer to the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Story, tranſcrib'd from the Patient's own Lips; abbreviated and drawn into a Certificate, will run thus:</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>I T. H. <hi>of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> having been for many Months afflicted with a Swelling in my Belly, Gripings, great Pains in my Limbs, and in a weak and languiſhing Condition, for which I had been a long while under the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of ſeveral eminent Phyſicians, but to ſuch purpoſe, that I was reduced even to Death's Door: At laſt, in a Deſpondency of Mind, I betook my ſelf to little Dr.</hi> Le F ... <hi>at the upper end of</hi> Three C...Alley: <hi>On examining my Caſe, and what had been done for it, he ſhook his Head and ſaid,</hi> His Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren had very much miſtook the Illneſs, or elſe they would not have bottom'd their Hopes on Medicine Internal or External; That the Planets were more concern'd in this Affair, and had <q>
                           <hi>"United their ſelecteſt Influences againſt me"</hi>
                        </q>: He bid me be cheery and confident in him, and only
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:0968300300:27"/>lend him my Servant next Morning at Three o' Clock, with ſome of my Urine, to <hi>Epping Foreſt. Knowing his Wiſdom, I ſhew'd all the Tokens of a glad Compliance my weak State would permit, and begg'd him, as a Chriſtian, to uſe his utmoſt Skill for my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery. He promis'd he would; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly took my Man with him as appointed. At his Return he told me My Buſineſs was done: That I ſhould have only one ſevere Fit of Gripes more, but be perfectly recover'd in a Week. After the Doctor had taken his Leave, my Curioſity led me to enquire of</hi> John, <hi>what had been done at the Foreſt, and he told me, all he knew was, that he had ſeen the Doctor bore ſeveral Holes in an old Oak, put my Water in them, and then fill'd them up with Trunnels again, muttering withal ſome Words inwardly which he could not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. My Heart ak'd for the Succeſs of this Myſtical way of Application a whole day; but praiſed be God his Words had Truth to a Tittle: I had next day, or next but one, the expected Fit; and before the expiration of a Week (as he had foretold) walked about to Admiration.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>What may compleat the Author's Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and recommend the Cure to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, is his taking but Twelve Guineas for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:0968300300:28"/>it: The Preſents that were afterwards added (tho' very ſhort of a Requital) were, as I hope to be ſ— forced on him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>To the Truth of all which Premiſſes, I freely, and without Fee, do certifie, this 20th, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>J. T.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>But to return from this Digreſſion, I begin the Cure with a ſtrict Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in Living, particularly an Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from ſpirituous Liquor and ſalt Food, and preſcribe directly a <hi>mercurial Bolus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Mer. Dul. gr.</hi> xij. <hi>Conſ. Roſ. q. ſ. f. bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus hora ſomni ſumend.</hi> purging it off next Morning with an Infuſion of <hi>Senna.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the firſt or ſecond time, I increaſe the <hi>Mercury</hi> in the <hi>Bolus,</hi> and give ſtronger <hi>Catharticks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Pil. ex duobus</hi> ℈j. <hi>rez Jelap. Balſ. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruv. ana gr.</hi> ij. <hi>Calomel. gr.</hi> vj. <hi>fiat Pil. Not.</hi> v. <hi>mane vorandus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vel, ℞ <hi>Pil. Cochiae</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ſ. <hi>Calomel. gr.</hi> x. <hi>Ol. Junip. gr.</hi> iij. <hi>f. Pil. deaurand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vel, ℞ <hi>Elect. Lenitiv.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. <hi>Mer. dul. gr.</hi> x. <hi>rez Scammon. Jalap. an. gr.</hi> iv. <hi>Ol. Carui g.</hi> ij. <hi>M.</hi> Conſtantly adminiſtring, at the end of their Operation, a <hi>Paregorick</hi> Draught.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PURGES</hi> are given after <hi>Mercurials</hi> (I believe) not ſo much from a Suppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:0968300300:29"/>that their Vertues immediately reach the Part affected, and ſubdue the Poiſon directly, as from a diſtant View of alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Habit of Body, and carrying off thoſe vicious Humours that would elſe probably take their Courſe that way, and heighten the Fury: This Opinion is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Practice; where nothing is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner than from two Men infected by the ſame Woman, to ſee the one cur'd in a few Days, when the other perhaps re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires Months; which can be from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſooner than their different Habits.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Purges</hi> are deſign'd likewiſe to prevent any ill Effect from too great a quantity of <hi>Mercury</hi> remaining at once in the Body.</p>
               <p>This may ſuffice for their Defence in general. There remains another mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Conſideration in the Uſe of them, and that reſpects the frequency of their Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition. And rightly to underſtand a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in this, we are to conſider, that as the Malignancy of a <hi>Gonorrhea,</hi> Nature her ſelf, in good Conſtitutions, would run off in a due Quantity of time; and that our Adminiſtrations are but her Aſſiſtants thereto: The Faults may be equal, in leaving them off too ſoon, or continuing them too long; by the former the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is not conquer'd, and by the latter
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:0968300300:30"/>the Conſtitution is enervated, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's Efforts weakned inſtead of being aſſiſted: In conſequence of this I repeat the <hi>Mercurial Bolus,</hi> and purge no oftner than Reaſon tells me their Strength will admit, without a <hi>Hypercatharſis,</hi> Fainting or Loathings (which is with ſome every other Day, with others twice a Week, or leſs;) and in the Intermiſſions give largely of the following <hi>Apozems</hi> or <hi>Emulſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Sem.</hi> 4. <hi>frig.</hi> ℥j. <hi>aq. Ment. ſ.</hi> 
                  <abbr>lb</abbr>ij. <hi>Sal Tartar</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>ſiat Emulſio Sacchar. candid. ad gratiam edulcorand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Amygdal. dul. No.</hi> xij <hi>Sem. Papav</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iſ. <hi>Contundantur &amp; ſenſim affunde aq. Plantag. vel decoct. Hord.</hi> 
                  <abbr>lb</abbr> ij. <hi>Syr. Althae</hi> ℥j. <hi>f. Emulſio</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Decoct. Pectoral.</hi> 
                  <abbr>lb</abbr>ij. <hi>Spir. Nitri dul. g.</hi> xxx. <hi>f. Apozema.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Sal Prunel. Sacchar. candid. p. ae M. f. Pulvis ſumat ad quantitatem Scrupuli in Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reviſia tepid. ter in die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As theſe, or other Forms of <hi>Diureticks,</hi> are ſuppos'd to eaſe the Heat of Water by increaſing the Quantity, and ſo diluting the Salts; ſo, to this end ſuch an Inje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction may be ſerviceable alſo as is ſoft, and can leave ſomething of a Muci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laginous Subſtance to lubricate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the <hi>Urethra.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:0968300300:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solvatur G. Tragacanth. vel Arab. vel Ich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiocol. in ſero. Lactis, Colatura tepide injic.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>While we are continuing the uſe of theſe, it will be proper to weigh with our ſelves, what are the Signs of our firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention being anſwer'd, and ſufficiently authorize us to leave them off: For there is no doubt a Period, which the Skilful diſcern, wherein a Change for Healing Balſamick Medicines is neceſſary and required, and which as we come ſhort off, or exceed, may be either way pernicious: For, Firſt, If (while the Signs of Malignancy abide) too ſudden a Check be given to the Running, either by the unſeaſonable uſe of Aſtringents, or too quick and ſtrong purging in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, which turns to the ſame; then it will either revert and taint the whole Maſs of Blood, or produce by a nearer Tranſlation acute Pain, Tumour, and Inflammation of the Groin or Teſticles; which may prove of as unhappy Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; particularly in the laſt the Pains are agonizing, and attended with <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Syncope</hi> and <hi>Nauſea,</hi> and the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane wanting Fat, never without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Corruption and Gangrene.</p>
               <p>Again: If, on the other ſide, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Seaſon is miſs'd of doing it, and there
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:0968300300:32"/>is too cautious and long an adherence to <hi>Mercurials,</hi> or irritating Medicines, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Catharticks or Diureticks, the Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning goes on without end, and at laſt brings an irrecoverable Laxity on the Parts, converting a <hi>Venereal</hi> to a troubleſom <hi>Seminal Gleet.</hi> To avoid theſe Extremes, I take the proper In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications for ſuch an Alteration to be Abſence of Pain and Soreneſs about the Groin and Teſticles, When the Diſtention of the Yard is gone off, When the Heat of Urine is conſiderably abated, and when the Running is of thick and equal Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, chang'd in Colour and leſſen'd in Quantity; for as the contrary of theſe are what conſtitutes its Virulency, ſo their Remiſſion muſt be Signs of Amendment, and a proper <hi>Stadium</hi> for changing the Method. It is not to be expected a Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhould ever ſo intirely change as not to leave a Stain, which ſome do ſillily imagine; no, it will be ſufficient that there are conſiderable Alterations in the Reſpects abovemention'd; the better thoſe appear, indeed, the ſafer ſhall we be in ſtopping it; and let the remaining Matter revert where it will (ſeparate from Signs of Malignancy) it can be of no more hurt, than the drying of an Iſſue, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſimple or common Ulcer.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:0968300300:33"/>
               <p>The ſecond Intention is, to dry up the Running, and heal and ſtrengthen the debilitated Parts. The former part of this Intention I have compaſs'd ſometimes (in <hi>Athletick</hi> Conſtitutions) by a ſingle quick Purge; which ſhows, that a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thartick,</hi> without any other Property than its ſtimulating Power increas'd, will turn Aſtringent, and dry up the Liquor of the Glands: But as Circumſtances will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent this from being the conſtant Effect of it, and that (like Mr. <hi>Avery</hi>'s Caſe) it will be far from happening every Day, I ſhall ſelect ſome of thoſe Preparations I've moſt ſucceſsfully experienced, and range them in their Order of Healing and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tringency, to ſort with the better or worſe appearance of the Indications above; and doubt not but a due Obſervance to the Seaſon of their Adminiſtration, together with a thick glutinous Diet (which under this Intention ſhould always be directed) will make them anſwer as effectually with others.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Sal Prunel.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iij. <hi>Pulv. Rhabarb.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. <hi>Troch. de Agaric. Alhandal. an.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij <hi>Antim. Diaphoret. CC ppt. Mer. dul. bene levigat, rez Jalap. an.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Elect. Lenitiv.</hi> ℥ij. <hi>Balſ. Capivi q. ſ. ſumat ad magnitud. Caſtaneae omni Mane &amp; Veſpere.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:0968300300:34"/>
               <p>℞ <hi>Pul. Rhabarb.</hi> ℥ij. <hi>Sal Prunel.</hi> ℥j. <hi>Nucis Moſchat.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Balſ. Capiv. Peru. ana</hi> ℥jſſ. <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat omni mane ad duas vel tres Dejectiones promovendas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Ichthyocoll. Albiſſ.</hi> ℥j. <hi>decoq. in aq. Font.</hi> ℥xij. <hi>Colaturae adde aq. Roſar.</hi> ℥j. <hi>M. ſumat. Coch.</hi> ij. <hi>(in lacte vaccino diſſolut.) quater in die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Cortic. Peruv.</hi> ℥j. <hi>decoq. in aq. Font. q.ſ. ad</hi> ℥viij. <hi>Colatur. hujus</hi> ℥ij. <hi>PP</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>i. <hi>aq. Cinam</hi> ℥j. <hi>M. f. hauſt.</hi> 8va <hi>quaque hora ſumend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Terebinth. Venet.</hi> ℥ſ. <hi>Vitill. ovi ſyr. Balſ.</hi> ℥j. <hi>M. è Cyatho vin. alb. ſumend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Bol. Arm.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Balſ. Capiv.</hi> ℥iij. <hi>capiat un. ſemis quotidie, ſemel vel bis alvos promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Bol. Arm. ſang. Dracon. Terr. ſigillat. Pul. Rhabarb. tort. an. p ae Tereb. Venet. q. ſ. f. Pil. mediocres ſumat quinque bis in die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Pil. Cretaceae B. eodem modo ſumend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Decoct. Guaiac. ſaepe ſumat hauſt. in qua inſtillat g.</hi> xx. <hi>Tinct. Guaiac. vel Tinct. ex Balſ. Peruv. Gilead, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Sacch. Saturn. Vitriol. R. an.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ſ. <hi>diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut. in aq. Ferrariae</hi> 
                  <abbr>lb</abbr> iſſ. <hi>&amp; filtretur pro inje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Aq. Plantag.</hi> ℥vj. <hi>Tinct. Myrrae</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>vel Tinct. Veneris</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ſſ. <hi>tepide injicitur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To theſe we may add the uſe of the <hi>Cold-Bath;</hi> it gives a Contraction and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:0968300300:35"/>Tenſity to the Fibres in general, and therefore muſt cloſe the Orifices of theſe Ducts in particular.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§ III.</head>
               <p>THE other Symptoms of <hi>Virulency</hi> which Denominate a Perſon Clapp'd, and that as well without as with a <hi>Gonorrhaea,</hi> are the <hi>Chordee, Phymoſis; Paraphymoſis, Chancre</hi> and <hi>Bubo.</hi> Theſe I chuſe to ſpeak of ſeparately in their Cures, becauſe they require (beſides an Internal uſe of <hi>Mercurials</hi>) Local Applications.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Chordee</hi> is a painful Contraction of the <hi>Fraenum</hi> in Erection, cauſed from an Inflammation of that Membrane, which on that accounr being thicker, is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſhorter, and muſt excite a Pain when the Erection of the <hi>Penis</hi> ſtretches it.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Cockburn</hi> diſtinguiſhes another Chor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Pain, ariſing from a Sore or Ulcer in the <hi>Urethra,</hi> as often as it comes to be compreſs'd by an Erection of the <hi>Penis,</hi> and infers from it, how far within the <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethra</hi> the Seat of a <hi>Gonorrhaea</hi> is: But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this I object,</p>
               <p>That if an inflated <hi>Penis</hi> can ſo pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully compreſs this Ulcer on all ſides, why
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:0968300300:36"/>ſhould not a greater Compreſſion with the Hand do it without Erection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> If a <hi>Gonorrhaea</hi> be an Ulcer in the <hi>Urethra,</hi> and the Chording Pain a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on that Ulcer, then they muſt be inſeparable Companions, and no <hi>Gonorrhaea</hi> could be without it.</p>
               <p>And, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I have known the <hi>Chordee</hi> often continue after a Running has been ſtopp'd, which by this Allegation could not be true; ſuppoſing (as we reaſonably may) that where there is no Running there is no Ulcer: The proper local Remedies to it are <hi>Fotus's</hi> of Milk wherein Lilly, Elder, or Marſhmallow-Root has been boiled, and a little <hi>Sacchar. Saturn.</hi> added, or in their ſtead the <hi>Cataplaſma Reſolvens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Phymoſis,</hi> is when the <hi>Praeputium</hi> is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to bring backward: A <hi>Paraphymoſis,</hi> when it choaks at the Neck of the <hi>Penis,</hi> and will not without pain or trouble be brought forward over the <hi>Glans:</hi> In ſome theſe are Natural Difficulties; but here, the effect of Tumour and Inflammation, as thoſe are again of <hi>Shankers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shankers</hi> are Venereal Ulcers on the <hi>Glans Praeputium,</hi> or <hi>Fraenum:</hi> They are, with the <hi>Phymoſis</hi> (as was obſerved in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) occaſioned when the Venereal Taint is lodged here, and does by its ſharp Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, both coagulate thoſe Liquors that lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricate
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:0968300300:37"/>the Glands, and corrode the Fibres conſtituting them: The latter are <hi>Shankers,</hi> the former <hi>Phymoſis;</hi> for a <hi>Phymoſis</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the effecting a Tumour on the <hi>Glans</hi> and <hi>Praeputium</hi> at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>To a <hi>Phymoſis</hi> the Injections ſhould be mild.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Aq. Plantag.</hi> ℥ij. <hi>Troch. alb. Rhaſ.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Mer. Potab. gr.</hi> vi. to be thrown between the <hi>Glans</hi> and the Fore-skin with a Syringe, and retained there a little to waſh and cleanſe it; a Fomentation ſhould be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe uſed, and a Cataplaſm of the Seeds with a little <hi>Ol. Libior.</hi> in it; or this ſollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Mica Panis m.</hi> j. <hi>Farin. Hord. pul. flor. Cham. ana m.</hi> ſſ. <hi>coquantur in lacte ad conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent. Cataplaſm. finita Decoct. adde ol. Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buc.</hi> ℥j.</p>
               <p>To a <hi>Shanker</hi> this Lotion. ℞ <hi>Aq. Plant. Roſar. an.</hi> ℥j. <hi>Troch. alb. Rhaſ.</hi> ℥ij. <hi>in hac in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillat g.</hi> xv. <hi>ſequent. liquor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Mer. ſublimat.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. <hi>diſſolut. in ſp. vin.</hi> ℥ſſ. <hi>&amp; filtretur.</hi> Or,</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Aq. Calcis</hi> ℥j. <hi>Mor. ſublimat</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>ſolut. &amp; filtretur pro uſu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Un. Baſilic.</hi> ℥j. <hi>Praecipit. rub.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>m. pro Unguento.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Cockburn</hi>'s <hi>Arcanum.</hi> ℞ <hi>Hydrargyr. Tereb. Venet. an. P. Ae. F. Unguent.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:0968300300:38"/>
               <p>A Malign, or Venereal <hi>Bubo</hi> is dangerous to repel, and ſhould, from the beginning, be aſſiſted to Suppuration by Emplaſticks, Cataplaſms, Cupping, and the like: An Intention that will be found difficultly to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in moſt, and when compaſſed, without great care, will turn fiſtulous.</p>
               <p>I have run over this Section with little more than placing ſome proper Preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons under the ſeveral Heads of <hi>Chancre, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſis, &amp;c.</hi> avoiding any nicer Diſquiſition in the choice of them, or Seaſon of their uſe, not becauſe they are intirely void of Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but becauſe I am ſatisfy'd neither they, or any other <hi>Arcana</hi> will alone anſwer the purpoſe: They are all ſhort of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiums beſtow'd on them; and if not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to the Ends propoſed, are yet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xatious and tedious. And ſince they are ſo, and have a greater tendency to a <hi>Pox</hi> than a <hi>Gonorrhaea,</hi> its expedient, and I think a very good Practice, preſently to reſort to <hi>Turbith</hi> for a Revulſion, or elſe by ſome other equivalent <hi>Merourials</hi> to procure a Spitting; there is nothing theſe Symptoms better or ſooner ſubmit to; for as the Mouth grows ſore, there follows a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigation, the Matter is diverted, the <hi>Shankers</hi> heal, and the Parts ſuddenly regain their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Form and Tenſion.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:0968300300:39"/>
               <p>Eight or ten Days continuance in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Salivation will ordinarily ſuffice to vanquiſh them; but if the Diſtemper proves more deeply rooted, requiring one of ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Confinement and Regimen, take the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Rules.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECTION IV.</head>
               <p>THE Symptons of the <hi>Pox</hi> are cuticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Eruptions, Blotches, Ulcers in the Throat and Palate, Nocturnal Pains of the Head, Shoulders and Shins, <hi>Caries,</hi> Night-Sweats, <hi>Alopecia's,</hi> falling off of the Nails, <hi>Gummas,</hi> Nodes, <hi>Talpas,</hi> Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption and <hi>Maraſmus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How a Clap comes to end in ſuch contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macious and intractable Symptoms, may be partly attributed to the Malignancy of the Original Infection, partly to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition, or ill Habit, whereby the Blood becomes more eaſily receptive of that Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom, but moſt often to an irregular Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of Cure, and uſe of <hi>Specificks:</hi> It exceeds my Deſign, as well as Capacity, to unriddle further the Nature of this Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom, in its ſeveral Appearances under that general Denomination of a <hi>Pox;</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only intended here the ſhort <hi>Hiſtory of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:0968300300:40"/>a Salivation,</hi> by which the moſt of them are effectually to be removed.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Salivation</hi> is dangerouſly undertaken with Aged People, with ſuch as are lean, or dejected thro' Trouble or Misfortunes, or much emaciated; but eſpecially with thoſe whoſe Lungs are any way diſtemper'd, that are Hectical, Phthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical and Conſumptive, becauſe, as this Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit is acquired by the Glandulous Secretions being increas'd, <hi>Mercury</hi> pejorates the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and the more ſo, if ſuch Indiſpoſition has proceeded from a former ill uſe of it. Dr. <hi>Moulin</hi> aſſures us from Experiments, that <hi>Mercury</hi> is very prejudicial to the Lungs, becauſe they want that ſtrong brisk Motion the Muſcles have in other Parts, and by their lax and ſpongy Texture are extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unfit for clearing themſelves of ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome a Gueſt: This <hi>(ſays he)</hi> we daily ſee from Perſons often flux'd; who are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards obſerv'd to die of Conſumptions, that will not give way to any Courſe of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine: To which likewiſe agrees many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſperſed Places in Mr. <hi>Martin</hi>'s Collection of <hi>BAWDY Letters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> ordinarily Operates by a Flux thro' the Salival Glands, and by the parvity of its compounding Parts has a peculiar Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude thereto: The Benefits from it ſeem as much from the uninterrupted
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:0968300300:41"/>Continuance of its Operation, as any Spec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fick Vertue in the <hi>Mercury;</hi> for the Blood has leiſure by ſuch a length of time as a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livation</hi> takes up, to ſeparate its noxious and incongruous Parts, which are daily waſhed and ſpewed out by the thin Liquors conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually taken, and conſequently the Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, after ſuch a Defaecation, becomes more Homogeneous.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Salivation</hi> is raiſed by <hi>Mercurials</hi> and that either Externally or Internally uſed; Two or three Purges always precede as preparative, and after that if we intend it by Unction, make up the following Ointment, and draw on a pair of Gloves and Stockings after the uſe of it, to keep the Linen and Bedcloaths clean.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Argent. Vivum</hi> ℥iv. <hi>Axuug. Porcin.</hi> ℥xij. <hi>M.</hi> An Ounce of this is to be uſed at a time for three days ſucceſſively, beginning the firſt Illination on the Wriſts and Ancles on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, leaving the Patient to chafe it in with his Hands warm'd before the Fire; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond higher about the Joynts of the Knees and Elbows; and the third yet further up, but cautiouſly, becauſe the nearer you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint to the <hi>Abdomen,</hi> the more likely the Body will be of being Laxative, and elude its proper Operation: If theſe Three In-un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions anſwer not the purpoſe, we muſt ſtill
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:0968300300:42"/>repeat it, and help forward with a Bolus of <hi>Turbith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This way by Unction I preſer, eſpecially in weak Bodies, the other more certainly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auſing <hi>Nauſea,</hi> Vomiting, Looſneſs, Faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the like Accidents that interrupt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Regular Courſe of Proceeding, and give great uneaſineſs to a Patient: But ſince Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion has alſo its Faults, and is Offenſive by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts Smell and naſtying the Cloths; ſince ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny alſo differ from me in this Preference, and give it to <hi>Mercurials,</hi> internally admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred; and laſtly, ſince the Rules to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent thoſe Symptoms mentioned, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more Attention in the Internal than External uſe of <hi>Mercury:</hi> I ſhall chuſe to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Courſe in that Method, and for eaſier Apprehenſion, divide the Flux into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Beginning, a State, and a Declenſion.</p>
               <p>In the Beginning, or Firſt Attempts to raiſe a Flux, the only thing to be fear'd and guarded againſt, is a <hi>Diarrhaea,</hi> which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts the Operation of the <hi>Mercury</hi> from the Salival Glands: This we muſt take notice is prevented, or abates and goes off, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion as we can procure a Soreneſs in the Mouth and Jaws, and increaſe the Drib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; and therefore a very great Streſs lies in the Manner and Method, as well as in the Adminiſtrations themſelves, and in a good ordering the Patient as to Diet and Confinement.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:0968300300:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> We have ſaid two or three Purge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are to precede: And the Reaſon of this is that beſides preparing the Body for ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Mercurials,</hi> they leave an Aſtringency that makes a Patient leſs apt to it after wherefore thoſe of them that leave more than others of that Property behind beſt ſuit the Purpoſe; as the
<q>
                     <hi>Potio Communis Purgativa Sydenham.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> In adminiſtring <hi>Mercurials,</hi> the <hi>Bolus</hi> ſhould contain but a ſmall Doſe at firſt.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Mer. Dul. gr.</hi> x. <hi>Laud. L. gr.</hi> ij. <hi>Conſ. Roſ. q. ſ. fiat Bolus quaque nocte ſumend.</hi> And be increaſed two or three Grains every Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition; becauſe large Doſes of it in the beginning exert too much force in the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae viae,</hi> and by the effect of their own Irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, are paſs'd off with their Contents; whereas a ſmall one, without giving ſuch diſturbance, leiſurely intrudes it ſelf, and in the Circulation arrives at and wounds the Salival Glands; and when once it has obtain'd that Path, the ſubſequent Doſes more eaſily follow, and ſuppreſs all Fears of a Diverſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Diet has its Uſe towards this End, and ſhould be dry and aſtringent; Rice, toaſted Cheeſe, Yolks of Eggs in mull'd Whitewine, a Harts-horn-Drink, and Roaſt-meats, in general, are proper
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:0968300300:44"/>Food; minding to continue the moſt nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing of them (the Meats) as long as we can to ſupport the Strength thro'; for in the Progreſs the Throat will be too ſore to bear ſwallowing any thing but Liquids.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Another means conducive to it, will be guarding againſt Cold, which would by conſtipating the Pores make the Body looſe <hi>Cutis Denſitas alvi Laxitas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe few Rules premis'd, we may go on with the <hi>Mercurial Bolus's</hi> for three or four Nights ſucceſſively; and if the Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in that time is found to have advanc'd but ſlowly, or the Body is laxative, alter it for one of <hi>Turb. Min. à gr.</hi> v <hi>ad</hi> viij, giving an Anodyne Draught at the end of its Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>Two or three <hi>Turbith Bolus's</hi> following the other, and increaſing their Doſe a Grain every Repetition (<hi>a</hi> v <hi>ad</hi> viij) may be expected to raiſe the Flux; but Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions differ, and will be always an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception to any ſtated number: I've known two Bolus's of <hi>Calomel</hi> raiſe a Salivation, and I have ſeen <abbr>lb</abbr>iſ. of Mercury by Unction in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual. And here it may not be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unfit to mention the oppoſite Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences that at ſome times proceed from the uſe of ſuch a Quantity under different Symptoms: I have known nocturnal Pains of the Head and Shoulders that have been
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:0968300300:45"/>removed by uſing ſuch a quantity in Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, tho' a Spitting never ſucceeded; and yet the ſame perſiſting when the Caſe ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> been Eruptions and ſtinking putrid Ulcers has not only failed, as to the Salivation, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> render'd the Caſe deplorable, by increaſing their Number and Quantity of Matter, and conſuming the Patient in colliquativ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sweats: But in this, Reaſon and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence muſt be our Guide; we muſt be abl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to know when the Mercury operates kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and whether the Patient's Conſtitution and Courage will ſupport him thro' the Courſe; becauſe now, if the Succeſs i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doubted, we may ſafely divert with Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharticks, which in the increaſe will be dangerous and impracticable; for my own part, I have ſeldom miſs'd, more or leſs, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Looſeneſs in the raiſing a Salivation, and have perſiſted in the uſe of <hi>Turbith,</hi> when a Patient has had ſixteen or eighteen Stools in a Night; but this has been in robuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong Bodies, and with this Caution, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> giving a Reſpit for a Day or two, a <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lf horn</hi> Drink, and an <hi>Anodyne</hi> Draught.</p>
               <p>If in the beginning of a Flux there ſhould be a more than ordinary Pain in the Jaws and Mouth, and the <hi>Saliva</hi> running o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bloody, we are not to be ſtartled at it, they are the common Attendants of Mercury and reach no further than the Parts imm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:0968300300:46"/>affected; a Day's Intermiſſion from Mercurials will palliate, and in a great meaſure correct ſuch Uneaſineſſes; and to prevent their return and Aggravation, we may perfect the remainder of our Work by Unction, which does not affect with ſo much Pain as Mercury received by the Mouth does.</p>
               <p>The Spittle at firſt is thick and clammy; but as it increaſes in Quantity, grows thin and ſerous.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The STATE.</head>
               <p>By the State of a Salivation, I mean all that time from a Patient's ſpitting about a Quart in 24 Hours, till its height and return to that Quantity again, which may include a Fortnight or more; and during this, the exacteſt Regulation is required to promote the Flux, and avoid the danger of a Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The beginning has leſs regard in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimen, becauſe the <hi>Fauces</hi> as yet ſuffer ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and nouriſhing Diet to paſs and ſuſtain Nature; but in this their Soreneſs will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of nothing but ſoft Liquors, as thin Broths and Gruels, which as they afford very little Nouriſhment, and that the Flux is ſtill greater, a Faintneſs and Debility of neceſſity follows, that will conſtrain us to ſtricter Rules. The Patient muſt be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether confin'd to the Bed; he muſt be kept between the Blankets; the Bed well
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:0968300300:47"/>lin'd; the Room cloſe and warm, and a Julap <hi>pro Languoribus;</hi> the Head and Jaws ſhould be covered alſo with Flannel, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels the Effects of Cold, and is <hi>Anodyne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The Mouth ſhould be frequently waſh'd with the Liquids they drink, to cleanſe and ſcour the Glands from Filth, that they may the more freely ſpue out their Contents; for this purpoſe therefore, and alſo for quenching the continual Thirſt they will be under from a large Spitting, plenty of them muſt be in readineſs; and they ſhould be uſed warm, becauſe Cold (in this general Ulceration of the Mouth) would create great Pain, check the Flux, and hazard the falling out of the Teeth. If there ſhould be a neceſſity to check its A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctivity, <hi>Flos Sulphuris</hi> is the Medicine.</p>
               <p>I account the Salivation well raiſed, if I can make it amount to about two Quarts in a Natural Day, and continue it ſo for eight or ten; but let the higheſt Quantity be what it will, whenever it leſſens regn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, it ſignifies the Mercury to have ſpent its utmoſt Force and Power, and puts us on Conſiderations for our Third and laſt Branch, <hi>The Recovery, or State of Declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:0968300300:48"/>
               <head>The DECLENSION.</head>
               <p>A Flux that has advanced kindly to its Height, will as gradually decline, and in the cloſe of it calls for Phyſick and Diet Drink, to expel the Remains and Recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Mercury: They are not giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en till the Swelling and Soreneſs of the Jaws and Mouth are well abated, and the Draining little; ſome there will be while the Mouth continues ſore, becauſe, while the Fibres are excoriated, there will be a proportionable Vellication that will expreſs the Juices within their Contact; and this might continue an inconvenient length. if the Humours were not diverted, and the Ulcerations dried in the end, by <hi>Enema's, Catharticks</hi> and <hi>Gargles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Pil. Coch. Extr. Rud. ana gr.</hi> xv. <hi>rez Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lap. gr.</hi> iv, <hi>Ol. Carui gutt.</hi> ij. <hi>f. Pil. no.</hi> v. <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aurand. ad ſex vices repetand. alternis diebus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Fol. Sennae Alex.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Zinzib. Sal Tartar. ana</hi> ℈j. <hi>Infunde tepide per noctem Colatur.</hi> ℥iij. <hi>adde Ol. Aniſi gutt.</hi> j. <hi>Syr. Roſar. Solutiv.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>vj. <hi>M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Manna opt.</hi> ℥j. <hi>diſſolv. in</hi> 
                  <abbr>lb</abbr>j. <hi>Aq. Stre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thamenſ. &amp; ſuperbib.</hi> 
                  <abbr>lb</abbr>iij. <hi>Aquae ejuſdem ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis diebus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:0968300300:49"/>
               <p>℞ <hi>Aq. Roſar. Plantag. ana</hi> ℥iij. <hi>Mell roſar.</hi> ℥j. <hi>Ol. Vit. gutt.</hi> vi. <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Gargariſm. ad os eluen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Fol. Plantag. Myrtill. in Aq. I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct. Colatur.</hi> ℥viij. <hi>adde Syr. è Moris</hi> ℥j. <hi>M. F. Gargariſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Diet Drinks are appointed in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with theſe, and may be continued ſix Weeks or two Months. They, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſubdue and carry off the Remnants of the Mercury, heal the Excoriations of the Mouth, and the Drinks, in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, correct the Acidities of the Blood, and procure a gentle <hi>Diaphoreſis,</hi> which very much avails in finiſhing a removal of all Pains.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Baccar. Junip.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Rad. Liquirit. Sem. Faenic. ana</hi> ℥j. <hi>infunde in Cereviſia tenuis conq.</hi> j. <hi>Colaturae, adde Sp. Cochlear.</hi> ℥ij. <hi>pro uſu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Lign. Saſſaphraſ.</hi> ℥iij. <hi>Sarſae, Guaiac. ana</hi> ℥ij. <hi>Rad. Liquir. Sem. Coriand. Aniſi, ana</hi> ℥j. <hi>CC Raz.</hi> ℥iſ. <hi>bulliant in</hi> 
                  <abbr>lb</abbr>xvj. <hi>Aq. ad</hi> Cxij. <hi>Colaturae bibat ſaepe in die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Thaeae ex Saſſaphraſ. bibat bis vel ter in die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Cereviſia è Lignis Doctoris Fuller.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Decoct. Dtaeteticum Sydenham pro P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> communc.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:0968300300:50"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suffumigation</hi> is ſometimes ſubſtituted in room of the preceding Courſe; and is ſaid to remove Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns, an dry up running Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, or a <hi>Caries,</hi> better, and with more Diſpatch.</p>
               <p>In the Management of it, the Patient is ſtripped naked, and placed on a Stool with a Hole thro', under which the Fume is put: He is covered all over with Blankets, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Head, for fear of Suffocation) which are drawn pretty cloſe about the Neck to keep the Fume in. When Sweat begins to come, he muſt be put to Bed, and there well covered for an Hour or two and this repeated ſix, ſeven, or more Days, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Urgency of the Symptoms: The Fume is made always of <hi>Cinnabar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Cinnabar. factitia</hi> ℥iiſ. <hi>Thuris, Styracis, ana</hi> ℥j. <hi>M. F. Pulvis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Cinnabar.</hi> ℥ij. <hi>Styrac. Calamit. Nucis Moſchat. ana</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. <hi>Benzoin</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iij. <hi>cum Terebinth. E Trochiſci.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
