<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay on redemption by Jesus Christ. ... By J. Murray,</title>
            <author>Murray, James, 1732-1782.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>51 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-06">2011 June</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004856821</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T90013</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW119862253</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K073091.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3319862253</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECRP</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">0297001300</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay on redemption by Jesus Christ. ... By J. Murray,</title>
                  <author>Murray, James, 1732-1782.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2],50p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T. Slack,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Newcastle :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1768.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Horizontal chain lines.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT90013.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:0297001300:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY ON REDEMPTION BY <hi>JESUS CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shewing from Scripture, the CHARACTER of our RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEEMER, the NATURE of his REDEMPTION, and the BENEFITS ariſing from it to MEN.</p>
            <p>By J. MURRAY, Of NEWCASTLE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>NEWCASTLE:</hi> Printed by T. SLACK; and ſold by the Bookſellers in Town and Country. 1768.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:0297001300:2"/>
            <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>A Great part of the <hi>miſtakes</hi> about Religion have ariſen from men's paſſing <hi>too ſuddenly</hi> from one object to another. Mankind naturally are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to proceed rapidly in their progreſs after truth: and ſeldom come to the true knowledge of it, by reaſon of not conſidering <hi>one thing before another.</hi> The words of <hi>Job</hi> may be fitly applied to mankind in general;—<q>For vain man would be wiſe, though man is born like a wild aſſes colt, <bibl>
                     <hi>Job</hi> xi. 12.</bibl>
               </q> Notwithſtanding we are <hi>dull</hi> in our capacities in learning the knowledge of <hi>truth,</hi> yet we are <hi>ever</hi> ready to make too <hi>much</hi> haſte, and to ſtretch ourſelves beyond our meaſure.—Paſſing too quickly from <hi>one</hi> thing to <hi>another,</hi> we leave the former before we inveſtigate <hi>its</hi> properties.
<q>In ſeeking to become wiſe, we become fools,</q> by ſtopping ſhort in our enquiries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we underſtand <hi>any</hi> ſubject. Wiſdom is not attained by the ordinary methods of ſeeking after her.—We ſhould "ſearch for her as for hid treaſure." We ought not to leave <hi>any</hi> truth before we have examined <hi>it</hi> on <hi>all ſides,</hi> and enquired into its various properties, on purpoſe to underſtand the <hi>whole complex</hi> or <hi>particular notions</hi> included in <hi>its</hi> general character:—How far <hi>it</hi> may be poſſible to know the ſeveral ſimple properties which are underſtood in <hi>general terms,</hi> or <hi>univerſal propoſitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IT is neceſſary if we would underſtand things as they are in their ſeveral conſtitutions, <hi>phyſical, moral,</hi> and <hi>oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomical,</hi> to examine the conſtitutions in which they are conſidered as <hi>parts</hi> of a <hi>whole.</hi> By this means we ſhall be led to conſider the various relations which conſtitution<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ideas have to one another:—Which may be of <hi>ſingular ſervice</hi> to us in the chuſing terms to expreſs either general or particular things. By this means we ſhall proceed <hi>gradually</hi> from <hi>one</hi> property of <hi>any</hi> ſubject to another, and be able to diſtinguiſh between <hi>primary</hi> and <hi>ſecondary truths,</hi> and their qualities:—And know what we are already in the poſſeſſion of; and what we ought to enquire after, on purpoſe to <hi>conſummate our knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="ii" facs="tcp:0297001300:3"/>IT is a great part of our preſent infelicity that we think we have knowledge when we have <hi>ſome perceptions;</hi>— whereas perceptions are but the materials of knowledge, or the ſteps by which we advance to underſtanding. It is neceſſary that we judge our perceptions, and compare them with <hi>thoſe objects</hi> which we think we perceive, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe what we call knowledge will be no more than a <hi>chaos</hi> of <hi>ill arranged perceptions, huddled together without any order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ONE <hi>chief</hi> thing to be obſerved in all our purſuits after truth is <hi>Analyſis.</hi> The Almighty has ſeen meet to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Truth</hi> to men <hi>as it were in bundles,</hi> and when they are well directed in their enquiries after <hi>it,</hi> they proceed by <hi>Analyſis</hi> to find out the ſeveral ſimples contained in <hi>every concert.</hi> But I muſt obſerve <hi>here,</hi> that we know <hi>nothing</hi> of abſolute ſimplicity: Things to us are only ſimple by being compared with other things that are more complex; but we cannot ſay that we know <hi>any</hi> thing abſtractly in a perfect ſenſe. Our notions of ſimplicity are <hi>entirely</hi> form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from our notions of compoſition;—and we call things ſimple that are <hi>fartheſt</hi> from ſome known compound. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very object meets us at <hi>firſt</hi> in a compounded or conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional ſtate;—and our knowledge of conſtitutional truth conſiſts in our being acquainted with the <hi>Analyſis</hi> of its conſtitution. The ſeveral individual truths arranged in <hi>ſuch</hi> a conſtitution; when conſidered diſtinct from the reſt, are called <hi>ſimple.</hi>—This I take to be <hi>all</hi> that is implied in our ideas of ſimplicity. Our notions of ſimplicity are therefore <hi>only</hi> relative.</p>
            <p>I ſhall obſerve before I proceed, that all our knowledge of the Divine Nature and Operations is founded upon a conſtitution of his government; and we attain to <hi>that</hi> knowledge by being <hi>gradually</hi> let into the <hi>Analyſis</hi> of that conſtitution. By unfolding the <hi>various</hi> parts and <hi>relations, principles</hi> and <hi>ends</hi> of that conſtitution, the Deity makes <hi>his ways</hi> known to men;—and the whole ſyſtem of phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and moral truth, as it relates to <hi>this</hi> conſtitution, comes to be known by comparing thoſe parts and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The underſtanding of parts and their relations, in
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:0297001300:4"/>natural philoſophy, may be called phyſical knowledge; the underſtanding of relations and ends, in morals may be called <hi>moral knowledge.</hi> The term relation is truly no more than the condition of ſome object with regard to another in ſome ſyſtem, either as to connection, or oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. Relations are all the parts we poſſibly can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of, in a moral ſyſtem, and in <hi>any</hi> moral conſtitution bear the ſame reſpect to one another, that parts, <hi>properly ſo called,</hi> do in <hi>phyſics,</hi> or <hi>natural philoſophy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>GOOD and evil, are to one another as <hi>heavy</hi> and <hi>light,</hi> namely, oppoſites;—they are equally parts of the ſyſtem they belong to. The term <hi>part</hi> is relative, and has a reſpect to a whole, as the term <hi>good</hi> is relative, and has a relation to <hi>evil.</hi> They are only ſo ſyſtematically, as far as we know; what they are in themſelves, we cannot cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſay. Moral evil ſuppoſeth <hi>ſome law</hi> and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of government;—<q>For where there is no law, there is no tranſgreſſion.</q> It can therefore be evil <hi>only</hi> ſyſtematically, and cannot be conceived of, <hi>out of a ſyſtem.</hi> The true knowledge of the conſtitution and ſyſtem we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to, with all the various relations and diſpenſations thereof, are taught us in <hi>revelation;</hi>—the right knowledge of the ſcriptures is the true <hi>Analyſis</hi> of the divine govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and adminiſtration.
<q>Which are profitable for all things to make the man of God perfect, and to furniſh him thoroughly for every good word and work, <bibl>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> iii. 17.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>THE plan of the divine government hath <hi>never</hi> varied, though the external adminiſtration thereof hath been va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, at different times, ſince the beginning of the world. It argues the infinite capacity of the great author, that he hath ſupported an uniform plan of government, amidſt the <hi>various</hi> diſpenſations thereof, among ſo many different nations and people.</p>
            <p>THE firſt account we have of the conduct of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty towards man is, that he made him after <hi>his own image,</hi> and placed <hi>him</hi> under a <hi>law;</hi>—which <hi>law</hi> he qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified <hi>him</hi> to obey, by endowing <hi>him</hi> with powers ſuitable to the <hi>taſk</hi> he enjoined <hi>him.</hi> The reſt of the creatures
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:0297001300:5"/>were made ſubject to man, as the <hi>Repreſentative</hi> of his <hi>Maker</hi> in this lower world. <hi>Adam,</hi> the firſt of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors, was intruſted with the adminiſtration of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this world, and was the <hi>vicegerent</hi> of <hi>his Maker</hi> over all the creatures; yet he himſelf was put under a <hi>law,</hi> and made <hi>accountable</hi> to the great Legiſlator of the univerſe. He was God's chief miniſter under this firſt conſtitution.</p>
            <p>GOD, who is poſſeſſed of infinite preſcience, could not but know what would be the iſſue of <hi>Adam</hi>'s adminiſtration, had therefore provided againſt <hi>all future contingencies;</hi> yet ſaw meet to ſuffer a ſpecimen to be handed down through all ages, what the moſt perfect beings were liable to when left entirely to the exerciſe of their own liberty. By permitting <hi>Adam</hi> to betray <hi>his truſt,</hi> and ſuffering him to tranſgreſs that law he was placed under, <hi>He</hi> has evidently ſhewn that the moſt perfect human liberty, yea angelic freedom, cannot ſecure creatures in happineſs, without the divine care and agency to uphold them. All human powers are created, and need as much the concurrence of the power of God to ſupport them in their exerciſes, as it was neceſſary for their firſt exiſtence: For it is true in a moral as well as a natural ſenſe;
<q>That in him we live, and move, and have our being, <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts</hi> xvii. 28.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>ADAM being the ſubject of his Maker, and his prime miniſter with reſpect to the creatures, by breaking that <hi>poſitive law</hi> concerning the <hi>fruit</hi> of the forbidden <hi>tree,</hi> loſt his dominion over the creatures, and became liable himſelf to ſuffer puniſhment, becauſe the law of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution threatened death in caſe of diſobedience. It is manifeſt from ſcripture, that the firſt man being in a <hi>public</hi> character tranſmitted <hi>his guilt</hi> to <hi>his poſterity;</hi> for the Apoſtle plainly declares,
<q>That the judgment was by one to condemnation,</q> and
<q>that death reigned by one man's offence:</q> That
<q>by the offence of one, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment came upon all men to condemnation:</q> That
<q>by one man's diſobedience, many were made ſinners, <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> v. 16, 17, 18, 19.</bibl>
               </q> It is plain from the Apoſtle's o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the firſt tranſgreſſion, that it brought both <hi>death</hi> and <hi>condemnation</hi> along with it. How this was conſiſtent
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:0297001300:6"/>with <hi>that</hi> conſtitution man <hi>at firſt</hi> was placed in; and how it was juſt in the Almighty to impute the ſin of <hi>Adam</hi> to his poſterity, may <hi>next</hi> fall under our conſideration.</p>
            <p>HERE we muſt confine our views of <hi>juſtice,</hi> to what was expreſſed in the law of the firſt conſtitution of man. According to that law, it was juſt for God to puniſh man with death and condemnation, becauſe his offence was <hi>treaſon</hi> againſt the divine government, by affecting <hi>inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency.</hi> The offence was aggravated by man attempting to be <hi>like to God,</hi> or rather <hi>independent</hi> upon Him. It was not <hi>merely</hi> a <hi>ſimple</hi> breach of <hi>truſt,</hi> but an attempt to uſurp the throne of the Almighty; it was <hi>more</hi> than diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the law that the Almighty gave to <hi>Adam;</hi>— eating of that fruit <hi>at any rate</hi> might have deſerved con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, but to eat thereof to be as God, was ſeeking to become Deities. As man had now taken part with beings who had already renounced the <hi>Divine ſupremacy</hi> as far as they could, it was but fit he ſhould ſhare in <hi>their</hi> puniſhment as far as the offence was <hi>ſimilar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHENEVER <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould have children, they could not but ſtand in a relation to him as <hi>a parent under for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture</hi> of happineſs, till ſuch time as it ſhould appear whether they would approve of their father's miſconduct or not:—For the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>all laws</hi> ſaith, that the ſons of <hi>traitors</hi> ſhall not have the inheritance their fathers have forfeited, till once the government hath <hi>ſome proof</hi> of their fidelity. The imputation of the guilt of fathers to their children is implied in the <hi>ſpirit of all laws,</hi> and interwoven with <hi>all forms</hi> of wiſe government. But in caſe ſons ſhall diſapprove of their fathers conduct, and approve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves worthy of the notice of the <hi>Sovereign,</hi> it is <hi>but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable</hi> that they be taken under his protection, and have the forfeiture removed which their parent brought upon their inheritance.—But this is far from being the caſe with the ſeed of <hi>Adam.</hi> They became partakers of the <hi>ſame</hi> rebellious temper of mind that was in him, and diſcover it as ſoon as they are able to do any thing.</p>
            <p>NOT to carry this point too far, it was and is <hi>juſt</hi> in our Great Sovereign to impute the guilt of <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin to
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:0297001300:7"/>all his poſterity, till <hi>they</hi> diſapprove of his deed, and teſtify their diſlike of it, by conformity to that law which he tranſgreſſed. But ſhall none of <hi>his race</hi> diſapprove of <hi>his conduct,</hi> but walk in <hi>his very footſteps,</hi> what does the ſpirit of all good laws ſay, but that, the children ſhall ſuffer even for the ſin of their fathers, and their own alſo? I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily agree with what the Prophet ſays:
<q>If a father beget a ſon that ſeeth all his father's ſins which he hath done, and conſidereth and doth not ſuch like. If he walk in the ſtatutes of life without committing iniquity: he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not die. He ſhall not bear the iniquity of his father, <bibl>
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> xviii. 14. and xxxiii. 15.</bibl>
               </q> But where do we find among all the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> ſuch wiſe and conſiderate children? Do not they
<q>all go aſtray as ſoon as they are born, and are eſtranged from the very womb?</q> The ſcripture account of all men as deſcendants of <hi>Adam</hi> is;
<q>There is none righteous, no not one; there is none that underſtandeth, there is none that ſeeketh after God. They are all gone out of the way, they are altogether become unprofitable, there is none that doth good, no not one, <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> iii. 10, 11, 12.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>ADAM and all his poſterity were now <hi>juſtly</hi> accounted <hi>guilty</hi> by the law of their conſtitution they were firſt placed in, both on account of the promiſe they deſpiſed, and the authority of God they ſet at nought. It would border upon profanity to ſay, that the Almighty placed man under a <hi>faulty</hi> conſtitution; for it ſeems to have been as well calculated for free agents, that are <hi>dependent,</hi> as any thing could be to anſwer an end. The moſt mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial objection that ſeem to have <hi>any</hi> weight in <hi>it,</hi> is at the ſame time <hi>full of impiety,</hi> namely, that God ought to have prevented what he knew would ſo much tend to the <hi>hurt</hi> of his rational creatures.—But not to mention the <hi>abſurdity</hi> of ſaying what the Almighty <hi>ought</hi> to have done, we ſhould rather conceive that God did things for the <hi>beſt;</hi>—and more eſpecially, as it was through an abuſe of the <hi>beſt</hi> of <hi>privileges,</hi> that man ruined <hi>himſelf.</hi> Liberty is what all wiſe men account a valuable privilege, and it is neceſſary to make rational creatures <hi>accountable;</hi> and had man at firſt not been formed a free agent, as far as a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:0297001300:8"/>can be <hi>dependently free,</hi> he could neither had <hi>merit,</hi> nor <hi>demerit.</hi> It is ſufficient to ſay, that God made man upright, and neither impelled him to the one ſide or the other; and as he had power to do good or evil, he is <hi>juſtly</hi> accountable for the abuſe of <hi>his liberty. The only ſource of moral obligation is the divine will;</hi> and ſeeing God decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that it was his pleaſure that man ſhould abſtain from <hi>the fruit of the forbidden tree,</hi> it was an act of the <hi>higheſt</hi> rebellion againſt God, to gainſay his public declaration. Man was therefore condemned for a <hi>breach</hi> of moral obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, attended with the <hi>higheſt</hi> aggravations.</p>
            <p>IT would be needleſs to ſay what man loſt through his diſobedience;—the favour of his Maker, which is life, and every other bleſſing that tends to happineſs he forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>by ſinning againſt God.</hi> It would be abſurd to ſay, that man could <hi>really</hi> enjoy <hi>life,</hi> when he had loſt the <hi>favour</hi> of his Maker, in which <hi>it</hi> conſiſted;—what is therefore meant by death in the <hi>full</hi> extent of the word, under this conſtitution, is <hi>miſery</hi> and <hi>pain,</hi> as well as the <hi>diſſolution</hi> of the body <hi>through mortality.</hi> The fabric of this firſt conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution was <hi>totally</hi> ruined, as far as it reſpected human happineſs; and the weight of its fall would have ſunk the whole human race down to <hi>endleſs</hi> miſery, had not the Almighty, who knew all future events <hi>before-hand,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a remedy ſuitable to the breach made in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. This law, which man was made under, ſtood in <hi>full force</hi> againſt <hi>him,</hi> and as it was the firſt public re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of God's will, to which <hi>he</hi> had annexed a threaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where <hi>his veracity</hi> was concerned; for the ſake of his public credit, as the juſt governor of the univerſe, he deals with all men according to this <hi>firſt</hi> revelation of his will. This <hi>Law, Covenant, Revelation,</hi> or what you pleaſe to call it, comes always <hi>firſt</hi> under conſideration when the Almighty deals with men.</p>
            <p>As this is really the caſe, that the Almighty begins with every man of <hi>Adam</hi>'s poſterity, where their father ended, and is obliged <hi>in honour</hi> to do ſo, it appears <hi>plainly,</hi> that
<q>by the deeds of the law no fleſh living can be juſtified.</q> The Almighty cannot, <hi>in character,</hi> depart from the firſt publication of his will, and men cannot
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:0297001300:9"/>walk up to <hi>it ſince Adam fell,</hi> but fall miſerably ſhort in <hi>Principles, Meaſure, Motives,</hi> and <hi>Ends:</hi>—The conſequence is, they muſt either be miſerable, or <hi>ſome other ſcheme</hi> muſt be revealed, ſuited to the character of God, and the miſerable condition of mankind. The condition of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind is very wretched through ſin:—They are in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of the <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>equity</hi> of God, as a <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> expreſſed in <hi>that law</hi> given to man at firſt, conſigned over to <hi>death</hi> and <hi>condemnation;</hi>—they are held faſt by the fetters of prejudice and corrupt affections, and have neither <hi>will</hi> nor <hi>inclination</hi> to do the will of God. Hence they are <hi>doubly</hi> in bondage;—bound over to condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the ſanction of the law of God;—and bound by their own corrupt affections as <hi>ſlaves</hi> to the <hi>God of this world.</hi> Whatever different <hi>Theories</hi> men may have of this matter, every man, <hi>in fact,</hi> feels the truth of this double bondage;—which they plainly diſcover by fears at death, and enmity to truth while they live.</p>
            <p>SUCH is the ſtate and condition of man, that without a <hi>Redeemer</hi> he can have <hi>no</hi> hope of happineſs, nor <hi>any</hi> real pleaſure in this life.—<hi>Redemption</hi> by <hi>the blood of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is neceſſary to <hi>give hope</hi> of happineſs to men: And <hi>this</hi> ſhall now be conſidered.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:0297001300:10"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY ON REDEMPTION.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Shewing the</hi> Nature <hi>of</hi> Redemption <hi>according to</hi> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; <hi>wherein</hi> it <hi>conſiſteth, and what</hi> Qualifications <hi>were requiſite in the</hi> Redeemer <hi>to accompliſh</hi> it.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 1ſt.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EDEMPTION, in Scripture, ſignifies the buying back ſomething that is <hi>loſt, alienated,</hi> or <hi>mortgaged;</hi> or, it ſignfies deliverance from <hi>danger, violence,</hi> or <hi>oppreſſion.</hi> It is applied to perſons or things; to either the <hi>lives</hi> or <hi>eſtates</hi> of men. It always has relation to ſome <hi>law of equity,</hi> and <hi>moral juſtice.</hi> That redemption which our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> wrought for his people, was alſo according to the <hi>law</hi> and <hi>juſtice</hi> of the firſt conſtitution which man was placed in. It was obſerved in the introduction, that the will of God is the <hi>ſource of moral obligation;</hi> it was his revealed will, that man ſhould have kept that poſitive law he gave him, in a ſtate of innocence, or in caſe he ſhould tranſgreſs the precept that was given to him, he ſhould fall under the <hi>weight</hi> of <hi>the threatening,</hi> and <hi>forfeit</hi> the <hi>favour</hi> of <hi>his Maker,</hi> in which his true life and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs conſiſted; for in the <hi>favour</hi> of the Almighty is life;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:0297001300:11"/>yea, it is in ſcripture ſaid to be <hi>better than life,</hi> in as much as moral ſatisfaction is <hi>better</hi> than <hi>mere</hi> creature exiſtence. The threatening implied what is death in a moral ſenſe: The <hi>want</hi> of friendſhip with God, and in conſequence thereof, <hi>pain</hi> and <hi>bitter</hi> remorſe of ſoul, at the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the divine diſpleaſure, and the thoughts of <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture evil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>THE Almighty placed our firſt parents under a <hi>very caſy</hi> and equitable law;—he laid no heavier burthen upon them than <hi>a ſingle prohibition,</hi> to put them in mind of their dependence upon their Maker. He gave them all things <hi>richly</hi> to enjoy, and did not <hi>ſparingly</hi> diſtribute his bounty unto them; only, as was juſt, he put them in mind of their dependence, by withholding from them the fruit of <hi>a ſingle tree.</hi> While man kept the <hi>ſupremacy</hi> and <hi>moral character</hi> of God in his eye, there was no danger of his breaking his law; but he forgot that he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, and brake the law of his Maker, by affecting to be <hi>his equal.</hi> By affecting independence upon God who made him, he became like <hi>the beaſts that periſh.</hi> The threatening purſued him faſt:
<q>For the Lord drove out the man.</q> The preſence of JEHOVAH, in which a perfect creature cannot but have the <hi>moſt exquiſite</hi> pleaſure, became dreadful to minds <hi>ſo conſcious</hi> of their guilt:
<q>
                        <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and his wife hid themſelves from the Lord God, among the trees of the garden.</q> But <hi>boundleſs mercy,</hi> which never had <hi>any</hi> motive but the Sovereign Pleaſure from whence it flowed, in <hi>due time</hi> revealed a Saviour, and made known a reaſon of hope to man, who had nothing in himſelf but every reaſon of deſpair. A Saviour is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and Redemption through his blood:—<q>The ſeed of the woman ſhall bruiſe the ſerpent's head.</q> But will God <hi>truly</hi> paſs over the <hi>ſpirit</hi> and <hi>intention</hi> of his law to man, and make <hi>void</hi> his Own word and declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that poſitive affirmation of His holineſs:
<q>In the day that thou eateſt, thou ſhalt die.</q> Shall God's moral character, as a righteous Legiſlator, ſuffer for the ſake of man, <hi>that is a worm,</hi> and the ſon of man, <hi>that is a worm?</hi> This would expoſe the character of the God of truth, and give reaſon for rebellious mortals to <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume</hi> upon his mercy and goodneſs. Shall ever favour be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:0297001300:12"/>beſtowed upon guilty man, it muſt be in conſiſtency with that <hi>firſt revelation</hi> which God made to the world. If ſinners be ſaved and redeemed from ſin and puniſhment, it muſt be <hi>according to law.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>THE law which JEAOVAH gave to his rational crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, man, was <hi>eaſy, reaſonable</hi> and <hi>light;</hi> and could be <hi>no way</hi> hard or difficult to <hi>ſuch</hi> perfect creatures as our firſt parents were;—and as this firſt moral precept was an abſtract of all righteouſneſs, and implied all the duties which dependence upon the Almighty binds men to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve; ſo <hi>no deed</hi> or <hi>action,</hi> contrary to this law, done by any in the nature of man, could be lawful and right.— And ſuppoſing this law either broken or <hi>ſtrictly</hi> obſerved, it was ſtill the condition of life and happineſs to the poſterity of <hi>Adam.</hi> In keeping of it, it is plain that <hi>life</hi> was the <hi>reward,</hi> and in caſe <hi>it</hi> ſhould be broken, <hi>death</hi> ſhould be <hi>the wages;</hi>—<q>The wages of ſin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life, <bibl>
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> vi. 23.</bibl>
                     </q> Upon ſuppoſition that man ſhould <hi>tranſgreſs,</hi> and be <hi>expoſed</hi> to the curſe of the law; if any ſhould be ſo wiſe, mighty, and merciful, as to redeem him from his miſery, this law was ſtill to come under the <hi>firſt conſideration,</hi> and the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to be obtained muſt be conſiſtent with <hi>this abſtract</hi> of the <hi>will</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As God's moral character was concerned in this rule of righteouſneſs, and called in queſtion by man's diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; —ſo there was <hi>no other way</hi> known to us, how his character and our ſalvation might be made conſiſtent; but by beginning where our firſt parents <hi>failed.</hi> To have overlooked the firſt tranſgreſſion of his law altogether, would have repreſented man's duty not ſo neceſſary as God ſaid it was, when <hi>He</hi> annexed the threatening of <hi>death</hi> to <hi>diſobedience;</hi>—<q>In the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely die.</q> For ſuppoſe we ought not to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, "to limit the holy one of Iſrael," in the exerciſe of his attributes, nor ſay what he might or could do;— yet we may ſay, according to what he has revealed to us in <hi>his word,</hi> he could not have granted life to man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out firſt having reſpect to his own holy character, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:0297001300:13"/>in <hi>his law;</hi>—as,
<q>the Judge of all the earth, he muſt do right.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>WHENEVER God intended to expreſs his mercy and compaſſion towards miſerable mortals, it was neceſſary that his wiſdom ſhould deviſe a method, whereby mercy and compaſſion might appear conſiſtent with the truth of the divine threatening, and the purity of the holy law. We find from ſcripture, that benevolence and wiſdom are both conſpicuous in the plan of man's happineſs; Wiſdom, in contriving a ſcheme where there is the <hi>Greateſt</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will to men, and yet the divine law taken firſt into conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; Benevolence, in taking into conſideration the caſe of <hi>enemies, wretched,</hi> and <hi>miſerable,</hi> and conferring favours upon them, they never could have deſerved. This is clearly pointed out in the xl. <hi>Pſal.</hi> ver. 6.
<q>When ſacrifice and offerings were not required,</q> JEHOVAH, the Meſſiah, ſays;
<q>a body haſt thou prepared me, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to do thy will, O my God,—thy law I have within my heart.</q> Chriſt was made under the very <hi>ſame law</hi> which the firſt man tranſgreſſed. He was made ſubject to all <hi>its</hi> precepts, to obtain a title to eternal life to all his ſeed, according to the covenant of promiſe, and ſubjected to <hi>its</hi> curſe to redeem them from temporal, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, and eternal death.—From temporal death, as to its ſting;—from ſpiritual death, as to its power;—and from eternal death, as to its nature, degrees, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences.</p>
                  <p>THE <hi>chief end</hi> of man was to <hi>glorify God,</hi> by doing <hi>his will,</hi> and CHRIST had a <hi>ſpecial</hi> reſpect to this end;— "I delight to do thy will." The Redemption obtained by JESUS CHRIST, and applied to believers, is neither <hi>more</hi> nor <hi>leſs,</hi> than a perfect fulfilling of the chief end of man;—which was <hi>at firſt,</hi> and ſtill is, <hi>to glorify God,</hi> and <hi>to enjoy him for ever.</hi> CHRIST, as our Redeemer, was made <hi>under the law of God</hi> in all <hi>its various forms.</hi>
                     <q>In the fullneſs of time, God ſent forth his ſon, made of a woman, made under the law, to redeem them that were under the law, that we might receive the adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſons, <bibl>
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> iv. 4.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:0297001300:14"/>HE was made under the law in that form in which <hi>it</hi> was revealed to our firſt parents, both as to <hi>its command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>curſe.</hi>—As a rule of righteouſneſs, it was the delight of his life;—and he called <hi>it,</hi> with all the other forms of <hi>it, His Father's buſineſs.</hi> He was made under the law of God in its ceremonial form, as connected with the doctrine of <hi>all</hi> the prophets;—<q>for he came not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the law and the prophets, but to fulfil them, <bibl>
                           <hi>Matth.</hi> v. 17.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>IT would lead me from my ſubject to give inſtances of each of them.—But in a word, That Redemption which our Redeemer perfected, was according to all the known forms of the divine law: But more than <hi>all,</hi> it was perfectly conformable to the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> The <hi>ſpirit</hi> of our Saviour's obedience was quite anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the <hi>intention</hi> and <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>law of God:</hi> The <hi>principles</hi> and <hi>motives</hi> from whence he <hi>acted, ſerved,</hi> and <hi>obeyed,</hi> were <hi>holy, juſt,</hi> and <hi>pure;</hi>—love to God and man were his <hi>devoted principles.</hi> His motives were to glorify Him that ſent him; to deliver his people from wrath, and make them happy;—His end to give ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of God's moral character to the world, as ſhould appear quite conſiſtent with itſelf, and the firſt revelation of God to man. In the Meſſiah thoſe draughts of moral character, <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>truth, righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> met together, and in the <hi>moſt</hi> regular, moral oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy, ſhewed the juſtice of the divine proceedings, and vindicated the <hi>ways of God to man.</hi> Whatever was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>firſt law,</hi> and <hi>revelation</hi> of the <hi>will of God,</hi> was by our Saviour's Redemption perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fulfilled.</p>
                  <p>THE beſt of men, <hi>even</hi> when they obſerve the <hi>letter</hi> of the law of God, are much defective as to the <hi>ſprings</hi> of action, and fall much ſhort of the ſpirit and deſign of God's holy commandment.—But CHRIST had the whole law in its <hi>largeſt extent</hi> and <hi>compaſs</hi> in <hi>his heart,</hi> and could ſay with the ſtricteſt propriety:
<q>I have reſpect to all thy commandments.</q> This Redemption which JESUS CHRIST perfected was according to law, becauſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:0297001300:15"/>he was <hi>appointed</hi> to the office of Redeemer by the oath of God. As the High Prieſt over the houſe of God, he was conſecrated and appointed to fulfil the law, for thoſe whom he repreſented as a High Prieſt:—<q>The Lord hath ſworn and will not repent, thou art a prieſt for ever, <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> cx. 4.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>THE <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the ſon of the Higheſt, was made a Prieſt by an <hi>Oath,</hi>—which is generally accounted the <hi>moſt</hi> ſolemn and <hi>ſureſt</hi> ratification of <hi>any deed, law,</hi> or <hi>office.</hi> The Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſays,
<q>that the word of the oath maketh the ſon a prieſt, <bibl>
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> vii. 28.</bibl>
                     </q> i. e. Mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him one in the divine appointment of JEHOVAH, which is the ſame with <hi>any</hi> law that <hi>ever</hi> was revealed.</p>
                  <p>OUR Saviour in his death, and offering of himſelf an atonement for our ſins, had a <hi>ſpecial</hi> view to the law and appointment of God:
<q>I have power to lay down my life, and power to take it up again, this commandment have I received of my father, <bibl>
                           <hi>John</hi> x. 18.</bibl>
                     </q> The High Prieſt who was a type of JESUS CHRIST, upon the day of expiation, was obliged to obſerve <hi>ſtrictly</hi> the law of atonement;—for upon it depended both his own life, and the ceremonial remiſſion of the ſins of the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The leaſt deviation from the law was death to the prieſt, and non acceptance to the people:—The whole congregation therefore ſtood without in <hi>great fear</hi> and <hi>terror,</hi> in the outer court, till the expiation was finiſhed, and the prieſt came out from the <hi>holy of holies.</hi> What ſupported their hope in the midſt of their fears was, the <hi>ſound</hi> of the <hi>bells</hi> that were upon the <hi>hem</hi> of his garments, which were heard in the outer court.
<q>And it ſhall be upon Aaron and his ſons to miniſter: And his ſound ſhall be heard when he goeth into the holy place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and when he cometh out, that he die not, <bibl>
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> xxviii. 33.</bibl>
                     </q>—And it is an evidence to us that <hi>our High Prieſt</hi> hath obſerved the law of the atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, appointed him,—when <hi>now</hi> that he is gone to heaven, the <hi>holy place not made with hands,</hi> we hear the <hi>ſound</hi> of his acceptance in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth "repentance and remiſſion of ſins through his blood." It is a ſign that JESUS CHRIST, our High Prieſt, is alive, and his ſacrifice is accepted of as an atonement for his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:0297001300:16"/>church and people, when <hi>life</hi> and <hi>immortality</hi> are publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through his death, in the goſpel, to <hi>the chief of ſinners.</hi>
                     <q>I am alive, <hi>ſays he,</hi> for evermore, and have the keys of hell and death, <bibl>
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> i. 18.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 2d.</head>
                  <p>THIS Redemption was <hi>vicarious,</hi> or one redeeming others, by being ſubſtitute in their place; one paying a price of Redemption as a repreſentative of others, who were guilty. JESTS CHRIST is in this reſpect,
<q>the ſurety of the better covenant.</q> When <hi>he</hi> aſſumed the office of Redeemer he obliged himſelf to <hi>do</hi> and <hi>perform</hi> what his people <hi>ought</hi> to have done, and to ſuffer what they ought to have ſuffered.—All the <hi>ſin-offerings</hi> under the law were <hi>types</hi> and <hi>figures</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> and had their <hi>full</hi> accompliſhment in that offering which he made of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the fullneſs of time. It was impoſſible that the whole human race, or <hi>any</hi> individual amongſt <hi>them,</hi> could make a ſufficient atonement for their guilt;—man's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption would have ceaſed <hi>for ever,</hi> for all that any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal could have done to obtain it:
<q>But the Lord laid on him the iniquities of us all;</q> and in his mercy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for himſelf a <hi>true</hi> ſin-offering.</p>
                  <p>THERE was a tranſmutation of guilt from the <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple</hi> to the <hi>ſurety;</hi>—which in ſcripture is called, <hi>bearing our ſins.</hi> Our Redeemer is ſaid
<q>to bear our ſins on his own body on the tree, <bibl>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> ii. 24.</bibl>
                     </q>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">
                        <p>The words <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, might read thus, <hi>Who himſelf liſted up our ſins in his own body upon the Tree,</hi> viz. the <hi>croſs;</hi>— which he could not have done unleſs they had been imputed to him, or transferred upon him. The Apoſtle ſeems to refer to <hi>Iſa.</hi> liii. 4. where the prophet ſays,
<q>He was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniquities, the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, and with his ſtripes we are healed.</q> The original words are very ſtrong, and much more expreſſive than our tranſlation: <hi>Ve-bu me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholal mip-ſhanem, meducah me-avonotenu, muſar ſhelemenu Gnalav, U-backa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burato ni-rpah.</hi> They may be thus rendered: <hi>He was pierced through for our iniquities, he was bruiſed to duſt for our ſins: The transferring of our puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was upon him, and by his ſtripes we are made whole.</hi> Theſe words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the ſufferings of Chriſt in the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> manner, and point out the reaſon and the effects of them clearly and emphatically.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="16" facs="tcp:0297001300:17"/>The reaſons of our acceptance with God, and the cauſe of our ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, are plainly pointed out in them. If we compare the words in this paſſage with the 10th verſe of this chap. and with theſe words God ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ke from the excellent Glory:
<q>This is my beloved ſon, in whom I am well pleaſed,</q> it will be found, that God is <hi>only</hi> perfectly pleaſed with his own ſon, and with finners for what he hath done and ſuffered.</p>
                        <p>As our guilt is pardoned <hi>only</hi> on account of what Chriſt hath ſuffered, ſo the wounds and moral bruiſes of our ſouls by ſin, are healed by his ſtripes.</p>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:0297001300:16"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:0297001300:17"/>THAT this was the caſe we have no reaſon to doubt, if we believe divine revelation; for the ſcripture is both <hi>full</hi> and <hi>plain</hi> on this ſubject.
<q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> liii. 6.</bibl> All we, like loſt ſheep, have gone aſtray; we have turned every one to his own way, and the Lord hath laid on him the iniquities of us all. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> ii. 24. who himſelf bare our ſins on his own body on the tree. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> v. 21. For he hath made him ſin for us, who knew no ſin, that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> iii 18. For Chriſt alſo hath once ſuffered for ſins, the juſt for the unjuſt, that he might bring us to God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put to death in the fleſh, but quickened by the ſpirit.</q> If words have any meaning at all, thoſe texts muſt point out one ſuffering for another;—and ſince God has ſo aſſured us in his word of this truth, it would be preſumption in us to ſay, it was inconſiſtent with <hi>his character</hi> to demand ſatisfaction, when he has told us the contrary by his own <hi>expreſs teſtimony.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>DR SIKES, and ſome others, would willingly explain away the meaning of theſe paſſages, without giving them a <hi>better,</hi> yea, without giving them any meaning at all, and ſay, they cannot mean a <hi>vicarious</hi> Redemption; for this would be contrary to the character of God:—But how came thoſe <hi>Critics</hi> to be <hi>better</hi> informed what was ſuitable to the divine character than the Deity himſelf? It is evident from both the Old and New Teſtaments, that the Almighty did not want thoſe paſſages to have <hi>any</hi> other meaning, than <hi>a common</hi> reader may find at <hi>firſt inſtance,</hi> becauſe he has often repeated them after the ſame manner, and does not ſeem to have thought that underſtanding them ſo would injure his character. In ſcripture, where the Almighty ſpeaks in a myſtical and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:0297001300:18"/>figurative manner, it is plain he does not want to have his words underſtood <hi>literally,</hi> and always explains <hi>his meaning</hi> by other plain paſſages of ſcripture:—But with regard to <hi>thoſe</hi> already cited, we do not find <hi>any</hi> other paſſages, when taken in their <hi>connection</hi> and <hi>ſcope,</hi> that lead us to any other meaning.</p>
                  <p>ONE would be ready to apprehend that ſuch literary cenſors are more zealous for their own pride, than for the character of the Deity, and rather ſuppoſe what they themſelves would do, if they were in his place, than what they are ſure is his mind and will. What their wiſdom thinks beſt, they conclude is fitteſt for the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of their maker;—and have the <hi>aſſurance</hi> to ſay what <hi>he ought</hi> to do, even when he has ſaid the quite contrary:—Nor will they allow the Deity to be the propereſt judge of his own character. They have a <hi>ſtandard quite</hi> above both God and the Scriptures, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their <hi>own natural notions:</hi>—What is not ſuitable to <hi>theſe,</hi> they will not allow to be conſiſtent with either the divine character or common ſenſe.—Nothing is more contrary, and inconſiſtent with <hi>their notions,</hi> than <hi>vicarious</hi> Redemption, when it implies puniſhment. It is indeed ſurpriſing, that theſe wiſe men who know the character of the Deity ſo well by their natural notions, ſhould give ſuch viſible demonſtrations of their ignorance;—when in every branch of their conduct in very momentous matters, they are not <hi>very</hi> ſtudious to imitate <hi>that</hi> character they pretend to know, more than other people. They tell us that the Almighty is all goodneſs, which no ſober man will deny more than they, but will perhaps ſay, that he is as much all juſtice, equity and holineſs.—But not to ſay <hi>any thing</hi> of the abſurdity of pretending to ſay what the Deity is,—which no man can tell further than he himſelf hath revealed, it might be expected if they believed the Almighty was <hi>ſo very good,</hi> that they would imitate his character. If indulging the paſſions, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying the appetites, be imitations of God in goodneſs, thoſe devotees of goodneſs have made <hi>conſiderable</hi> attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.—They can receive bondſmen for debts, throw debtors into jail, domineer over their inferiors and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents like other men;—and if their lives and conduct
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:0297001300:19"/>be a real imitation of their <hi>Deity,</hi> they are in ſome jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy notwithſtanding of that goodneſs they have learned by their natural notions. They in real life expreſs as much vengeance towards thoſe who injure or offend them, as the <hi>reſt</hi> of their fellow men that differ from them in ſentiment; and when <hi>fairly</hi> provoked, forget what they profeſs to believe concerning their Maker:—And though they conceive the Deity to be ſo good as to demand no ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, yet they want to be ſatisfied themſelves. Such conduct is a <hi>burleſque</hi> of their pretended belief, and makes <hi>them</hi> truly ridiculous. If the Deity, they profeſs to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, be as unmerciful as they themſelves are, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of that goodneſs they boaſt of, they are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being miſerable enough. But after all, it ſeems not more inconſiſtent with God to accept of a <hi>vicarious</hi> Atonement, or Redemption, and CHRIST to give it, than it was inconſiſtent with him to make the world: For if we conſider the character of God, revealed to us in his word, and not what our <hi>natural notions</hi> ſuggeſt, we will find it drawn in ſuch a manner, that this world, as it now appears, is not anſwerable to that character, <hi>i. e.</hi> it is nothing in compariſon with what God could have made it.—And we may as well complain of God for not making us angels, as complain of his conduct for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring an atonement for our ſins;—for God was good before Time, as well as after it commenced, and according to <hi>ſome people's natural notions</hi> of goodneſs, ſhould have made man ſo that he could not have fallen;—or in other words, made him a Deity; for this is the language of pride, "ye ſhall be as Gods."</p>
                  <p>THERE was <hi>certainly</hi> neceſſity for a <hi>vicarious</hi> Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, otherwiſe God would not have required <hi>any;</hi>—but in his diſpenſations towards the <hi>Jews, vicarious atonements</hi> were among the firſt inſtitutions that were made <hi>a part</hi> of their religious <hi>oeconomy.</hi> The Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us, that all theſe <hi>vicarious</hi> atonements were ſhadows of <hi>Chriſt to come,</hi> yea that the whole <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and <hi>Temple</hi> ſervice were figures of JESUS CHRIST, the true Meſſiah.— And we are expreſsly told, that
<q>he came in the end of time to put away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:0297001300:20"/>x. 1, 11. That he was manifeſted to take away ſin, and in him was no ſin, <bibl>1 <hi>John</hi> iii. 5.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>IT ſeems to have been the common opinion of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, where <hi>any</hi> notions of God ever entered, that there was neceſſity for <hi>vicarious Atonements;</hi>—for all nations who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſtory we have mentioned <hi>in hiſtory,</hi> had ſome ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals of this ſort, in their religious worſhip.—But <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe</hi> tells us, that it is not inconſiſtent with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty's goodneſs to demand a <hi>vicarious</hi> Redemption;— for what is the meaning of requiring ſatisfaction for the breach of human laws, if this notion of ſatisfaction be not taken from <hi>ſome notices</hi> we have received from the Deity? If it be good for civil government, which all men, for the moſt part, agree is from God, <hi>thus</hi> to demand <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> in the lower <hi>ſyſtem</hi> of his adminiſtration, it cannot well be ſuppoſed inconſiſtent with his goodneſs to demand ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in the more exalted part of his government.</p>
                  <p>THAT this Redemption was <hi>vicarious</hi> will appear from the <hi>very goodneſs of God</hi> made uſe of againſt its neceſſity.— For how was it conſiſtent with the Divine Goodneſs to make CHRIST ſuffer ſuch grievous ſorrows, if he was in no ſenſe guilty?—For it is agreed on all hands, that he had no ſin of his own. It is abundantly evident from ſcripture, that there never were <hi>any ſorrow</hi> like unto his.
<q>Is it nothing unto you all ye that paſs by? Behold, and ſee, if there be any ſorrow like unto my ſorrow, which is done unto me, wherewith the Lord hath afflicted me in the day of his fierce anger, <bibl>
                           <hi>Lam.</hi> i. 12.</bibl>
                     </q> Could there be any thing more tyrannical and arbitrary, than to make an innocent perſon undergo ſuch grievous ſufferings,—when JEHOVAH from the excellent glory had declared he was well pleaſed with him? In puniſhing an offender there is <hi>nothing unjuſt,</hi> or contrary to the nature of moral goodneſs;—but to puniſh an innocent perſon, <hi>ſo well approved</hi> of by God, is not ſo <hi>eaſily</hi> accounted for. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation <hi>only</hi> can ſatisfy us as to this:
<q>He bare our ſins in his own body on the tree, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> ii. 28. The Lord laid on him the iniquities of us all, <bibl>
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> liii. 8.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>IF JESUS CHRIST came to ſet us an example of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:0297001300:21"/>and reſignation to the will of God under all our afflictions and ſufferings,—and this was all that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by his death:—Why did God himſelf afflict him ſo grievouſly in his ſoul, with ſuch <hi>horrible terrors,</hi> which made the very blood ſweat from his body, when there were no viſible trouble upon him? This does not well agree with the character of the Almighty:—<q>Who doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the children of men without a a cauſe.</q> There was certainly <hi>ſomething more</hi> than ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample here; otherwiſe, it was all in vain, for never man was or will be able to copy after it.—What had <hi>almoſt</hi> broke the heart of our Redeemer, would <hi>altogether</hi> break the hearts of the ſons of men. JESUS CHRIST himſelf ſeems to have had <hi>quite</hi> different views in his ſufferings,— for he ſays to thoſe who came to apprehend him,
<q>If ye ſeek me, let theſe go their way, <bibl>
                           <hi>John</hi> xviii. 8.</bibl>
                     </q> He ſeems plainly to have conſidered himſelf as a <hi>vicarious Redeemer,</hi> one ſubſtitute in the room and place of others. But if CHRIST came only to inſtruct us as a Prophet, and to ſet us an example by his ſufferings, he has ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us the <hi>moſt fearful example</hi> that ever was ſet before <hi>mortals:</hi>—An example of bearing the puniſhment of ſin, and the wrath of God, due on account of our iniquity. Ah fearful example! Tremendous pattern! Who among the ſons of men can follow the footſteps of ſuch a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our? What <hi>ſo ſeverely</hi> ſcorched the green tree, would effectually burn up all the dry ones;—and unleſs men were qualified in the ſame degree that CHRIST was, his <hi>very</hi> example would be a ſufficient hell to them. Ye fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of CHRIST upon this plan! Could you follow him to the garden of <hi>Gethſemene,</hi> with all that anguiſh of ſoul which he ſuffered there? Could you undergo ſuch a bloody ſweat as JESUS did, and live?</p>
                  <p>NONE but a divine perſon could endure ſuch grief and ſorrow, as were inflicted upon JESUS CHRIST;—and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs CHRIST could endow his people with the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of perfection, power, and holineſs that was in him, it would be impoſſible to copy his pattern.</p>
                  <p>THAT our Redeemer did bear the wrath of God, the ſcriptures affirm expreſsly;
<q>Thy wrath lieth hard upon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:0297001300:22"/>me, and thou haſt afflicted me with all thy waves:— Thy fierce wrath goeth over me; thy terrors have cut me off, <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> lxxxviii. 7, 16.</bibl>
                     </q> It is becauſe the chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement of our peace was upon him, that he ſuffered ſuch grievous ſorrows, and becauſe he came in the room of the guilty, that he ſuffered unto death;—and not m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rely to ſet us an example. <q>He gave himſelf a ranſom to redeem us from all iniquity, and to purify unto himſelf a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar people zealous of good works.</q>—From all which it appears evident that our LORD's Redemption was <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 3d.</head>
                  <p>THIS Redemption was a procuring of that inheritance which man loſt. Man's portion and inheritance, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he could have lived happy, and enjoyed life, was the favour and fellowſhip of his Maker:—This enjoyment he forfeited by breaking the divine law, and tranſgreſſing the holy commandment.—Man was driven from his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and became a vagabond upon the earth, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing his allegiance to the Almighty. He had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing after he had ſinned that he could call his own, but what he would have been better without; namely, the divine diſpleaſure, threatened in the ſanction of the law of works:—And beſides, he was miſerable by what he had loſt. All enjoyments whatſoever, unleſs connected with the divine favour, tend only to make the curſe ſit faſter upon guilty minds. It is only in the favour of God there is life; all other vital acts are only the ſhadow of life:—For without the favour of God a man is dead while he liveth. When God created man at firſt, he made him lord of this lower world, and heir of everlaſting felicity in the next, upon condition, that he ſhould obey that law which he gave him, as the teſt of his dependence upon him; and his acknowledgment of his Maker's ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty. His faithful ſervice for a ſeaſon, would have entitled him to a crown of immortal life;—but he ſold himſelf to Satan, for the pleaſures of ſenſe, and loſt his liberty by gratifying his taſte.
<q>By ſeeking to become
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:0297001300:23"/>wiſe, he became a fool,</q> and marred his happineſs, by ſtretching its limits beyond the divine prohibition. By giving himſelf up to be the ſervant of ſin and Satan, God, in righteous judgment, condemned him to be their ſlaves; and inſtead of that bleſſed inheritance of immortal life, he had reaſon, as the ſon of God, to expect, if he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in his ſervice, he was made a ſlave to the devil, and a ſubject of death. Through pride and ſeduction he loſt an inheritance which would have for ever enriched both him and his poſterity.</p>
                  <p>Now, man is miſerable for wanting what only can make him happy, and is not able to pay a ranſom for what he hath loſt. But God, who is abundant in love, and infinite in mercy, ſent his ſon in human nature,—who hath given his life's blood to redeem the loſt inheritance. The ſtrong One, JEHOVAH's partner, the Man, his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, or of his Right Hand, was ſent to redeem that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited inheritance, that his "little ones might not periſh, but have everlaſting life." This holy life and obedience, which we call active, to diſtinguiſh it from his paſſion and ſufferings, is the meritorious reaſon of men's being received again into the favour of God. It was through diſobedience that man loſt the favour of his Maker, and it is by obedience, that any of fallen <hi>Adam</hi>'s poſterity are reſtored to it again:—For,
<q>as by one man's diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence many were made ſinners, ſo by the obedience of one ſhall many be made righteous, <bibl>
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> v. 19.</bibl>
                     </q> But before our Redeemer could procure the favour of God, as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance to eternal life, it was neceſſary that he ſhould be related to thoſe for whom he was to obtain it.
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <p>That queſtion, whether JESUS CHRIST procured the love of God, is a very needleſs one. Had thoſe who moved it attended to the plain meaning of words, they would never have propoſed it.</p>
                        <p>Love and Benevolence, in as far as we know any thing of them, are the ſame, namely, Sovereign Good Pleaſure. Favour and Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance alſo ſignify the ſame thing, and may be expreſſed by the word Friendſhip. Though JESUS CHRIST did not procure the Divine good will, yet he obtained our acceptance with God. The Apoſtle tells us,
<q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Eph.</hi> ii. 18</bibl> That through him we have acceſs by one ſpirit to the Father;</q>—which the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſays, is obtained by the blood of CHRIST.
<q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Heb.</hi> x. 19.</bibl> Having therefore, brethren, boldneſs, to enter into the holieſt, by the bood of Jeſus.</q>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="23" facs="tcp:0297001300:24"/>The Almighty, according to his moral character, expreſſed in the firſt public revelation of his will, is a declared enemy to ſin; and as the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme and righteous Governor of the world, an enemy to ſinners on account of it. But this implies no more than the oppoſition of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely perfect moral character, to the guilty and vile character of ſinners.</p>
                        <p>There is no ſuch paſſion in the Divine nature as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>red;—it is only the oppoſition of his nature to what is oppoſite to and unlike itſelf.</p>
                        <p>God beſtows his love or good-will ſovereignly, without any reaſon out of himſelf: He loves becauſe he pleaſeth.—But his favour and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip are beſtowed upon the guilty for moral conſiderations. He g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ve his ſon freely, and ſovereignly, without any reaſon but his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;—but he beſtows his favours upon ſinners for his ſon's ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ke,
<q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Iſa.</hi> liii. 11.</bibl> By his knowledge ſhall my righteous ſervant make many righteous, for he ſhall carry their iniquities impoſed upon him.</q> Where the connection between our Saviour's bearing the ſins of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and their juſtification is manifeſt. The Divine good-will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is the ſource of all grace and favour to guilty men;—but the blood of JESUS CHRIST is the channel through which theſe favours are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to them The firſt channel through which the favour of God was conveyed to the world was ſtopt by the offence of our firſt parents: Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, friendſhip, and acceptance with God, could no more run in that channel.—But JESUS CHRIST, by giving his life's blood for that offence, hath opened "a new and living way," whereby grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour "might reign through his righteouſneſs" to the moſt worthleſs and chief of ſinners, conſiſtently with JEHOVAH's moral character, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the firſt revelation of his will</p>
                        <p>The Divine love or good-will conſiders all the choſen of God as one in CHRIST, but his grace and favour reſpect them as many members of the one body. The Almighty had but one good-will to all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as the body of CHRIST, which he expreſſed in
<q>chuſing them in him before the world began.</q> But his favours are many, according to the number and wants of his members. It is agreed, almoſt on all hands, that man loſt the favour of God, by tranſgreſſing his law.—It is alſo manifeſt from ſcripture that man's life lies in the favour of his Maker. If this is really the caſe, that the firſt man loſt life and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by forfeiting the favour of the Almighty, it is as manifeſt that the ſecond man obtained it to his people, by procuring his favour. Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life which lies in the favour of God, is now beſtowed through the channel of a ranſom, or purchaſe, which our Redeemer paid to remove the forfeiture of happineſs, by ſhedding his blood.</p>
                        <p>The Apoſtle tells us,
<q>that the gift of God is eternal life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord;</q> for though our Redeemer paid the ranſom price of his blood for the chriſtian's inheritance, it is ſtill the gift of God to us, as much as it had never been procured by price;—becauſe we can give nothing for its ranſom.—Beſides, it was JEHOVAH himſelf that provided, and was pleaſed to admit a Goal. According to the firſt revelation of the will of God, Redemption was neceſſary to clear the character of the Lawgiver from all imputation of unrighteouſneſs,—and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:0297001300:25"/>ſo he ſhewed, in all his after-dealings with men, a reſpect to that firſt revelation.</p>
                        <p>But to fulfil the pupoſe of his good-will, he provided a Goal or Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Saviour, who ſhould fulfil the whole of the firſt law, as to both the <hi>letter</hi> and <hi>ſpirit</hi> of it; and thereby open free acceſs to ſinners to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and friendſhip of God. With reſpect to that firſt law, the death of CHRIST was in reality a ranſom price: For he came into the world to fulfil it Eternal life is the purchaſe of CHRIST as far as it reſpects that l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>w which threatened everlaſting puniſhment, but it is the gift of God, as far as God provided a Redeemer, and was pleaſed to admit of a furety. None of theſe things, according to the ſpirit of the firſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, he was obliged to do Eternal life, the Apoſtle tells us,
<q>was given to us in Chriſt Jeſus before the world began:</q>—But it was given to him to work out by his obedience unto death,—ſo by his death he wrought out eternal life. Believers therefore obtain eternal life by a <hi>work which Chriſt finiſhed upon the croſs.</hi> Fallen men are like a ſon baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from his father's houſe, for breaking the laws of the family, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling againſt his father. The father according to the laws of his houſe, cannot receive his ſon into favour without ſome atonement and ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the rebellion againſt his ſupremacy, for if he ſhould, it would ſhew that his laws were of no weight.—Yet notwithſtanding his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will to his prodigal ſon inclines him to find out a friend, or prevail with the elder brother, to pay the prodigal ſon's ranſom;—that he may again receive him into favour, and the reſt of his dependents may ſee how righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and juſt he is,—and his ſon may feel how gracious and good both his father and elder brother are.</p>
                        <p>The love and benevolence of the father is the reaſon of him prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the elder brother to pay the ranſom,—but it is the ranſom which the elder brother pays that is the reaſon of the prodigal's being again received into favour. The younger brother is juſtified and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted from the guilt on account of the elder brother becoming his <hi>Goal</hi> or <hi>Red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>emer</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Dr <hi>Gill,</hi> and ſome others, by not attending to the plain diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Benevolence</hi> and <hi>Favour,</hi> have endeavoured to ſupport an eternal juſtification of the elect;—and becauſe God out of his good pleaſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to juſtify them, have concluded that they are really juſtified. But they ought to have conſidered, that the divine love is not the reaſon in law whereby ſinners are acquitted from the guilt of an <hi>evil action,</hi> but <hi>ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> deed</hi> conformable to the moral juſtice and equity expreſſed in the firſt publication of the will of God.—For upon the ſame principles that eternal juſtification is built upon,—eternal guilt and condemnation may alſo be ſupported.—Alſo the eternal exiſtence of men, and the revelation of a law to them;—<hi>for where there is no law, there is no tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</hi> The ſons of God were like <hi>Abſolom</hi> in the land of the <hi>Philiſtines, out of ſavour,</hi> but the King's good-will or love was not abated towards them. It was God's benevolence that made him ſend his ſon to pay the price of man's Redemption, that he might, conſiſtently with that public character, which he firſt aſſumed, as a <hi>lawgiver</hi> to men, receive ſinners into favour. CHRIST's doing and ſuffering were all that law and juſtice
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:0297001300:26"/>could demand, and were fully as powerful and prevalent to reſtore the guilty to favour, as man's diſobedience was to caſt him out of it.</p>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:0297001300:23"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:0297001300:24"/>IT was by his holy active obedience, that he procured that favour which man loſt by his ſin and tranſgreſſion.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:0297001300:25"/>The whole human race had forfeited their right to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and fellowſhip with God,—ſo there was a forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:0297001300:26"/>upon their inheritance, which was neceſſary to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, before they could again enter upon the poſſeſſion. This forfeiture our LORD JESUS CHRIST paid by his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto death, and hath reſtored his people into the forfeited favour of God, and makes them partakers of thoſe divine pleaſures that are in his preſence. It was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in the ſervice of God, that would have ſecured the inheritance of eternal life to man;—and it was by our firſt parents, their coming ſhort, before the time of probation was ended, that they and their ſeed loſt that inheritance:—<q>For curſed is he that continueth not in all things written in the book of the law to do them.</q> Had there been no ſanction annexed to the law, then any perſon who had been able to have taken up the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k where <hi>Adam</hi> left it, might have ſet all to right again.— But juſtice had a claim for ſatisfaction, by virtue of the curſe annexed to the law; <q>in the day thou eateſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, thou ſhalt die.</q> Our Redeemer was therefore o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to fulfil that law which man left unfiniſhed, that he might procure acceſs into the divine favour,—and alſo to bear the curſe,—that the juſtice and truth of JEHOVAH's character might appear, in re-inſtating man into the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his Maker. But as man was alſo himſelf a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, as well as an inſolvent debtor to juſtice, there was ſtill ſomething more neceſſary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 4th.</head>
                  <p>THIS Redemption which CHRIST accompliſhed for his people, was a Redemption of perſons. There was a neceſſity of looſing the bonds of the priſoners, and of opening the priſon doors, as well as procuring a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in the enjoyment of the favour of God. The divine favour is what the ſervants of ſin cannot enjoy;— becauſe they are Satan's captives, and led by him at his pleaſure. This Redemption of the perſons of believers was two-fold, according to the nature of their bondage. They were bound over by a juſt ſentence of the law to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:0297001300:27"/>death, and were arreſted at the inſtance of juſtice, and could not get clear ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l the uttermoſt farthing was paid. In this ſenſe they are held like perſons under attainder,— as guilty of treaſon, againſt the Sovereign of heaven and earth. Nothing but the <hi>price of blood</hi> could releaſe them; ſo the Prophet informs us,
<q>That by the blood of the covenant, Chriſt brings forth the priſoners out of the pit wherein there is no water.</q> He paid the price of their Redemption by his precious blood, and died to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue them out of the priſon of ſpiritual and eternal death. He paid their ranſom by his blood, and hath delivered them from going down to the pit.—By virtue of this ranſom, their perſons became his property, and he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts them free agreeable to both law and juſtice.—Hence they are juſtified and acquitted from the curſe by which they were held,—which like a heavy chain held them faſt in the priſon of ſpiritual death,—ſo that they were unable to move in <hi>any</hi> holy acts of duty towards God.
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                        <p>The curſe of the law hinders men in the practice of moral duty, becauſe it leaves them no hopes,—without which no man living will pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue virtuous actions. It is the hope of the glory of God that makes men rejoice in tribulations, ſuffer patiently unto the end;—but no man can have any reaſon of hope who is under the curſe.</p>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>BUT not only are men, as they are the deſcendants of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> priſoners of juſtice, but they are alſo captives to ſin and Satan, made to grind in his priſon-houſe, by ſerving divers luſts and pleaſures. Chriſt redeems them from Satan's dominion by his power, as he delivers them from juſtice by the price of his blood:—So hereby the captives are delivered,
<q>and the prey of the terrible taken away.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>THIS deliverance the Redeemer performs by the goſpel which is the "rod of his ſtrength ſent out of mount Zion." whereby he pulls down Satan's kingdom, and relieves his people. Satan, that cruel enemy of man's happineſs, is not willing to part with his captives, and notwithſtanding of their ranſom being paid, endeavours to hold them faſt in the fetters of ſin and prejudice.—But,
<q>their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer is mighty, the LORD OF HOSTS is his name, <bibl>
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> l. 34:</bibl>
                     </q>—He ſends his powerful word,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:0297001300:28"/>
                     <hi>come forth,</hi> and all the powers of hell cannot hold them longer.</p>
                  <p>THE goſpel, as the rod of CHRI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>T's power, bruiſeth Satan under his people's feet, and perſuades and enables them to flee from the wrath to come. This part of the Redemption which our Redeemer performs, conſiſts in changing the purpoſes of his people's minds by the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior evidence of the goſpel of peace: It is by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,
<q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> viii. 2.</bibl> called, a fulfilling of the law in them.</q>—This is a Redemption of the perſons of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers with a ſtrong hand, and belongs to JESUS CHRIST under the character of a Conqueror,—<q>travelling in the greatneſs of his ſtrength.</q> The goſpel, which is a
<q>ſtumbling block to the Jews, and fooliſhneſs to the Greeks, is the power of God, and the wiſdom of God, in calling his people out of darkneſs into his marvelous light.</q> The word of truth, however ſimple in itſelf, is by the evidence which the ſpirit that ſpeaks in it, gives it,
<q>mighty through God to pull down ſtrong holds, and every imagination, that exalteth itſelf againſt the kingdom of Chriſt.</q> Its evidence ariſeth from its ſimplicity, and is not like
<q>the enticing words of man's wiſdom,</q> which pleaſe thoſe who belong to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of this world. It flatters no man while in a ſtate of ſin, or while living in the practice of it, but plainly tells him his doom, while he remains in that condition:— But at the ſame time,
<q>proclaims liberty to the captives, and the opening of the priſon doors to thoſe who are bound.</q> It exhibits very great and precious promiſes, to all who believe in JESUS CHRIST, and affords the ſureſt reaſon of hope to the miſerable and wretched. It ſpeaks nothing but woes to hypocrites, and ſuch as go about to eſtabliſh a righteouſneſs of their own; for it
<q>calls not the righteous but ſinners to repentance.</q> This goſpel looks with no favourable aſpect upon ſuch as are ſeeking requiſities to prepare them to come to CHRIST, but looks benignly upon the poor, the miſerable, the blind, and the naked. It ſays not one word of peace or pardon to the wiſe man, or the diſputer of this world, while it ſcatters its influence among thoſe who are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted worſt by the ſons of pride.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:0297001300:29"/>THIS word of JESUS CHRIST, which ſaves men from the power of ſin, and the captivity of the Devil, has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed an influence upon its enemies;—but it is to torment them, as it doth their father the Devil,—<q>who believes and trembles.</q> The ſame word that begets faith in the ſouls of thoſe who are called, and gives hope and great joy to the wretched and miſerable among men, begets pain and remorſe in the conſciences of the proud, and torment in the minds of Devils. Though this faith, which the goſpel produces and brings forth, has received the opprobrious name of the faith of Devils; yet it is the word of CHRIST's patience and power, which begets in the ſouls of his choſen people a belief of the ſame truth which makes thoſe evil ſpirits tremble. The faith of ſaints and devils is no way different; the difference lies in their hopes. The one hath no hope from the truth they believe, but pain and ſorrow; whereas the others from the ſame truth, have a noble reaſon of hope, which revives and ſupports their minds.</p>
                  <p>WHENEVER any man believes the truth of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as firmly as the Devils do, it preſents to him a ground of hope, that overbalanceth all his reaſons of deſpair. Among thoſe inhabitant of the regions of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, notwithſtanding of their believing the truth, their reaſons of deſpair outweigh their reaſons of hope,—be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the goſpel is not ſent to them.—But to men under every guilty circumſtance, it ſays,
<q>to you is the word of this ſalvation ſent.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>JESUS CHRIST delivers his people when they are in captivity, by opening their eyes, and pointing out to them the way of eſcape. He opens men's blinded underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings by the light of his goſpel, and brings them
<q>out of darkneſs into his marvelous light:</q>—The ſcripture calls this a
<q>turning them from darkneſs unto light, and from the power of Satan unto God.</q> When Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan got man into his priſon, he did with him as the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines</hi> did with <hi>Sampſon,</hi>—put out his eyes, and it is through ignorance that he holds them in his power.— For whenever the light is made to ſhine into their hearts,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:0297001300:30"/>they break his priſon, and eſcape. Hence the goſpel ſaves men, by making them
<q>know the things which belong to their peace.</q> In this reſpect, knowledge is the principle of faith, and faith the exerciſe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:—For,
<q>only thoſe who know JEHOVAH's name will put their truſt in him.</q> The goſpel becomes a principle of underſtanding,—which by its own evidence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets aſſent to its truth in the ſoul, which in ſcripture hath received the name of <hi>Faith.</hi> This faith is termed
<q>the ſubſtance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not ſeen.</q>—Or, as that paſſage may more properly be read;—<q>The firm foundation of things hoped for, and the <hi>argument</hi> or <hi>proof</hi> of things not ſeen.</q> The teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony of God, made known to men, is the firm foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of faith, and faith is the argument or proof to us of the truth and reality of what is teſtified. The goſpel gives being to faith, and faith realizes the object to us, or gives it a real exiſtence in our ſouls. It is by the power of CHRIST's word that the ſouls of his people eſcape out of the ſnares of the Devil, and forſake his ſervice.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 5th.</head>
                  <p>THIS Redemption is meritorious. It is not <hi>merely</hi> an alluſive and figurative one.—When CHRIST is called a Redeemer, it is not becauſe <hi>Moſes, Joſhua, David,</hi> and others, were ſo called, but becauſe he is really a Saviour and Redeemer,—who paid the price of our Redemption. The price he paid was truely worthy of all that ever his people can receive on account thereof. It is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient reaſon, and argument in law and equity, why God ſhould juſtify the ungodly. The merit of this Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aroſe from the nature and dignity of the perſon who paid the price of it. Our Saviour was truly God, as well as very man,
<note n="‡" place="bottom">
                        <p>The modern enemies of our SAVIOUR begin to ſneer at ſuch phraſe as the above, and like <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> are ready to ſay, <hi>how can theſe-things be?</hi> And what they are not able to refute with any ſhew of reaſon or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:0297001300:31"/>argument, they endeavour to turn into <hi>ridicule.</hi> Yet one may eaſily perceive that they ſmile <hi>but aukwardly,</hi> for the force of ſcripture evidence being ſo <hi>very</hi> clear againſt <hi>them,</hi> makes them, <hi>on occaſions,</hi> betray <hi>ſome</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of <hi>concern,</hi> mixed with their <hi>irrefragable ſmile.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It would require a good degree of critical knowledge to enable any man to explain away the meaning of ſo many plain paſſages of holy ſcripture, which at firſt view ſeem to point out this truth, that the <hi>Meſſiah is God,</hi> as well as <hi>Man.</hi>—For at the ſame time that he aſſumes the title of our <hi>Goal</hi> and <hi>Kinſman Saviour,</hi> he takes to himſelf the higheſt name that ever is aſſumed by the <hi>Creator</hi> of the <hi>Univerſe.</hi> Iſa. xliv. 6. <hi>Ka omar Jehovah Melech Iſrael, ve-goalo. Jehovah ſabaoth Ani Riſhon, va ani acharon, U. mib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal Gnadi in Elokim.</hi> Thus ſaith JEHOVAH <hi>King of Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Redeemer,</hi> the Lord (JEHOVAH) of Hoſts, <hi>I am the firſt and the laſt, and beſides me there is no God.</hi> Comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>red with Rev. i. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. <hi>I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end, ſaith the Lord, who is, who was, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s to come, the Almighty.</hi> Iſa xliv. 24. <hi>Ka Omar Jehovah Goaleka, ve-jitzerka mib-baten, anki Jehovah Gnoſhe Kol; note ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ajim Lebadi, rokagn haaretz me-jitti.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord, thy kinſman Redeemer, I formed thee from the womb; I am he who made all things; I alone ſtretched forth the heavens, and by myſelf ſpread abroad the earth. Iſa. xli. 14. <hi>Al-tiri Tolaath Jakol, mete Iſrael, ani Aſart-tick Neum Jehovah ve-goalck, Kedoſh Iſrael.</hi> Fear not worm Jacob. and ye men of Iſrael; I Jehovah your kinſman Redeemer, the holy one of Iſrael, will help you. Compared with Acts iii. 14. <hi>And ye denied the holy one and the juſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I am inclined to think, that wherever JEHOVAH is in ſcripture repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as a <hi>Goal</hi> or <hi>kinſman Redoemer,</hi> that the Meſſiah is meant. <hi>Jacob</hi> gives this name of <hi>Goal</hi> to an angel, which could be no other but the angel of the covenant: Gen xlviii. 16. <hi>Hamalach ha-goaloti. Michal roagn.</hi> The angel, my kinſman Redeemer, from all evil;—which our verſion reads, "hath redeemed me from all evil." <hi>Job</hi> xix. 25. gives the like character to the Meſſiah: <hi>Jad-gnati Goali hai ve-acharon al-gnaphar jakum.</hi>
                           <q>I know that my kinſman Redeemer is living, and that at laſt he ſhall ſtand upon the duſt of the earth.</q>
                        </p>
                        <p>It would be but kind in thoſe, who will not allow the Meſſiah to be the true God, to give us ſome good reaſon why he aſſumes ſuch names, and affirms that he hath performed ſuch works, as none but the <hi>Supreme</hi> can juſtly claim, or is able to perform The old <hi>Jewiſh</hi> principles rule ſtill in the hearts of the children of diſobedience; for they cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the conſiſtence of Jeſus's claim to ſuch a high character, when he was pleaſed to appear in ſuch a low one.—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hat is to ſay, unleſs they are able to underſtand as <hi>much</hi> as their Maker, they will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>him.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:0297001300:30"/>
                     </note> and the relation his work had to his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:0297001300:31"/>holy perſon, gave it a value, worthy of all that ſinners can ever ſtand in need of. It is for this reaſon that our Redeemer is ſo highly exalted as Mediator,— becauſe being the true God he humbled himſelf unto the death. The Actions of our Saviour's human nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived an infinite value and dignity from their being the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:0297001300:32"/>works of him who is "the true God, and eternal life." No finite creature can ever receive <hi>more</hi> or <hi>greater</hi> favours than our Redeemer merited by his death.—For this reaſon there is an eternity ordained for the enjoyment of them;—that what can never be exhauſted may be ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed. The ſong of the redeemed in heaven, is filled with the worth and excellence of JESUS CHRIST, and his Redemption;
<q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 19.</bibl> Worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain to receive glory, honour, dominion, and power.—For thou waſt ſlain, and haſt redeemed us to God by thy blood.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The Qualifications neceſſary to fit the Redeemer to perform Man's Redemption</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 1ſt.</head>
                  <p>IT was neceſſary that our Redeemer ſhould be a party in that covenant, according to which ſinners were to be ſaved. No perſon who was not able, and worthy to treat with JEHOVAH, and to engage his heart to approach unto him, could be qualified to redeem loſt ſinners.— And ſuppoſe he had been qualified, yet if he had not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually done it, he would have wanted a true legal qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for his work. Such as do act for others in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters where law is concerned, do not merely act according to their ability, and perſonal endowments, but according to the law that relates to the tranſaction. Perſonal endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were eſſentially neceſſary, but mutual and actual engagements were morally neceſſary alſo. As our LORD JESUS CHRIST intended to redeem his people, it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for him as their covenant-head, to be mutually en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged for them, in a contract mutually with his Father, and their God;—that ſo the will of the parties engaged might be one joint counſel:—So the Prophet tells us, that
<q>the council of peace was between them both, <bibl>
                           <hi>Zech.</hi> vi. 13.</bibl>
                     </q> Had not CHRIST been a party in the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of peace, all that he did could not have been anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:0297001300:33"/>to the breach of the covenant of works. The firſt covenant was broken by <hi>Adam,</hi> as a party in it, and his poſterity were ruined in conſequence thereof;—ſo the children of our Redeemer are ſaved from the ruin of the firſt covenant by his being a party in the ſecond: I have, ſaith God,
<q>made a covenant with my choſen, <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> lxxxix. 3.</bibl>
                     </q> By our Redeemer being a party in the covenant of grace, he was qualified to plead the benefits of his redemption for his people when the conditions in that covenant were fulfilled, and could plead the original contract, as a party that was worthy to covenant with God.—Thus, by having really covenanted for guilty ſinners, he was qualified to aſcertain the number of his ſeed,—through his knowledge of the contract in which he was a party:—And could plead the word of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that covenant made with him,
<q>when he ſhall make his ſoul an offering for ſin, he ſhall ſee his ſeed, and prolong his days, and the pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand.</q> With regard to all this as a party in the covenant of peace, he could ſay, Lord, do as thou haſt ſaid.</p>
                  <p>OUR Redeemer's being a party in the new covenant qualified him to know both the number of his ſpiritual ſeed, and the great and good things that are laid up for them in the covenant of grace and promiſe. In conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence thereof he could very properly pardon ſin, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give the iniquity of the guilty, becauſe he knew what he had contracted for in their behalf, and what he was able to do in fulfilling his contract. Had not our Saviour been a party in that covenant his ſuretyſhip could have no way been anſwerable to the neceſſity of guilty man,— who needed one ſubſtituted in his place as a covenant-party. It was entirely owing to the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s being a party in the firſt covenant, that his poſterity were found guilty for the breach of it, and it is becauſe JESUS CHRIST is a party in the ſecond covenant, that his righteouſneſs in fulfilling it, as their ſurety, is the reaſon of their accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God. Our Saviour's righteouſneſs could not have been a covenant one, unleſs he had been a party in it. So it was an eſſential qualification to JESUS CHRIST our Saviour to be a party in the covenant of grace.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:0297001300:34"/>
                  <head>SECT. 2d.</head>
                  <p>IT was an eſſential qualification in our Redeemer to be related to both God and man. Man's Redemption could not have been effected by any not truly God, and really man:—For Deity could not ſuffer, and a mere man could not have given ſuch a ranſom as was anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the ſpirit of the law, and the demands of juſtice.— And moreover, as man had offended God, and incurred his juſt diſpleaſure by diſobedience, it was neceſſary the Reconciler ſhould be able to pleaſe God, and reſtore man into his favour.
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <p>When we ſpeak of CHRIST reconciling us to GOD, I know that ſome alledge that no more is meant than taking away of the enmity of our minds againſt him.—But the ſcripture ſeems to ſignify ſomething more, that CHRIST had to peform a work whereby it might appear conſiſtent with GOD's holy character, to expreſs himſelf well pleaſed towards them who have offended him—And though nothing which CHRIST did made any change in the Divine mind, yet it makes a great alteration in his conduct towards man.</p>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>THE moſt perfect man that ever exiſted, even the human nature of JESUS CHRIST, unleſs it had been u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to the Deity, could not have effected man's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption:—For the moſt perfect finite ſervice could merit no more than a finite reward, and the death of a finite perſon could not in the nature of the thing be a price of Redemption from an infinite curſe,—juſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt ſin, wherever it ſhould be found, or in whatever form.</p>
                  <p>THERE were two things which made it impoſſible for a mere man to redeem a guilty world.—The nature of juſtice required that there ſhould be adequate ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made for the offence committed, that the character of the Moſt High might be juſtified in juſtifying the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly. Though we may conceive many things, which we think the Almighty might do, or have done, ſo far as they reſpect our intereſt; yet we are not certain that he could have done otherwiſe:—On the contrary, we are rather ſure, that he could not morally have acted other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe or than he would have done it. It is not our part
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:0297001300:35"/>to ſay what our Maker could have done as to his power, or any other attribute of his nature;—but whether ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſyſtem of his government revealed to us, could he have acted otherwiſe agreeable thereto? Was the firſt ſyſtem which man was placed in perfect: And did God ſpeak in earneſt when he ſaid,
<q>in the day thou eateſt, thou ſhalt die?</q> Will it not appear more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to that ſyſtem, that a perfect ſatisfaction be given to his juſtice expreſſed in his law, by one who was able to give it, than that the Divine character be any way ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured in its truth and veracity?</p>
                  <p>IT was therefore neceſſary that our Redeemer ſhould be God and Man, or EMMANUEL,—that he might be able to ſupport the moral character of the Deity, by giving a righteous and perfect obedience conformable to that law,—which was an exact image of his character;— and might be able to give ſatisfaction to what truly may be called juſtice, to make a complete Redemption con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the truth and holineſs of God. Thus quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied he could give all the ſatisfaction the pureſt juſtice could exact, in the ſame nature that had given the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.—Nor does this repreſent religion in any unfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable point of light, or ſet forth the Almighty as cruel and capricious:—When out of his mercy he found a choſen one,—who at the ſame time that he repaired that awful breach, could ſuffer no loſs to himſelf.</p>
                  <p>HAD what JESUS CHRIST did for ſinners ruined him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or had death been able to detain him priſoner;— or had the making of men eternally happy, made him miſerable, then might the enemies of the atonement called the ſcheme of man's redemption a cruel ſcheme,—and the Deity ſevere.—But when the ſufferings of JESUS CHRIST were ſalutary to men, and in the event exalted the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Moſt High in the eſteem of men and angels, and brought honour to our Redeemer alſo, there does not appear any thing in the whole ſcheme but what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with perfect goodneſs. Yea, it exalts the goodneſs, and extolls the love of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:0297001300:36"/>
                  <head>SECT. 3d.</head>
                  <p>IT was neceſſary that the human nature which CHRIST aſſumed ſhould be perfectly innocent. Had our Saviour's human nature had either original or actual ſin, it could not have been a proper ſin-offering;—for in this caſe he would have needed an atonement for his own iniquity.— But that nature which he aſſumed, though it was equally related to the believing ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> yet it was not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of any of that pollution which is common to the nature of man. This human nature of JESUS CHRIST was ſanctified by the Holy Ghoſt, and brought forth in an extraordinary manner of a virgin;—and though of the ſame kind with that of others, was yet free of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural pollution which ſtains the beſt ſervices of ſuch where it prevails.—But JESUS CHRIST
<q>was holy, harmleſs, undefiled, and ſeparated from ſinners;</q> without ſin, nor was guile found in him. His ſacrifice was ſinleſs and perfect, as well as divinely pure and holy,—on account of its relation to him who is the true GOD. Though as a ſurety he was accounted guilty, as bearing our ſins,—yet was he ever ſeparated from ſinners, in reſpect of every moral impurity.</p>
                  <p>THE pure law could not find the ſmalleſt defect in his ſin-offering, nor could the ſevereſt juſtice ſpy the leaſt imperfection in that nature which was given him for a ſacrifice.</p>
                  <p>THERE was a paſſive innocence in the human nature of JESUS CHRIST,—whereby he was morally inoffenſive. He had no diſpoſition to give or to take offence, as is common among men.—He had no ſelfiſh pride in him, nor any inordinate paſſions ariſing from the connection between his ſoul and body. Paſſions and appetites, not ſubordinate to pure reaſon and the will of God, are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to corrupt and imperfect creatures: In CHRIST there were none ſuch. He had no ambition to make him envy or grieve at the good of others, but he conſtantly rejoiced to ſee men happy, and to make them ſo. All the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:0297001300:37"/>affections of his human ſoul were paſſively pure and holy, and could not be moved to think or do evil.</p>
                  <p>BUT this was not all; the purity of his nature did not merely diſpoſe him to do no evil, or injury to any, but it inclined him to ſeek men's happineſs on all occaſions. "He went continually about doing good," from a holy propenſity of mind towards what was worthy and virtuous. Our Redeemer had no occaſion to be excited to do good by any motives from without,—for he had the law of God in his heart. He had a perfect knowledge of moral rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and a perfect love of all truth;
<q>Thou loveſt righteouſneſs, and hateſt iniquity, therefore God, thy God, hath anointed thee with the oil of joy above thy fellows, <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> xiv. 7.</bibl>
                     </q> It was as natural for him to love truth, as it is for other men under the influence of corruption to err and go aſtray from it. It was the love of righteouſneſs which conſtantly inclined him to do his Father's wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,—and made him purſue the great end for which be came into the world,—which was
<q>to ſeek and ſave that which was loſt.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 4th.</head>
                  <p>IT was neceſſary that he ſhould be appointed and have inſtructions for his office of Redeemer. Without a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial appointment and proper inſtructions, the execution of any office would be intruſion. Natural endowments may fit a perſon for the execution of an office, but does not morally qualify him in law, without appointment thereto. Our Redeemer did not run unſent,—but
<q>was called of God as was <hi>Aaron.</hi>
                     </q> Hence we have frequently in the goſpel his declaration, "that the Father ſent him." He demonſtrated his divine miſſion by works, that were truly miraculous and wonderful:—To theſe he appeals as a proof of his being ſent of God,—<q>If I do not the works of my Father, believe me not, <hi>John</hi> x. 37. The Father which ſent me, he doth the work, <hi>John</hi> xiv. 10.</q> CHRIST was called to his office by God in the moſt ſolemn man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;—<q>The Lord hath ſworn, and will not repent.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:0297001300:38"/>Thou art a prieſt for ever, <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> cx. 4.</bibl>
                     </q> When CHRIST ſpeaks of himſelf as the Good Shepherd, he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth himſelf to ſuch as came <hi>unſent,</hi>—whom he calls <hi>thieves</hi> and <hi>robbers.</hi> It was becauſe our Saviour was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to this office of ſurety, that he had ſecurity for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to ſupport him in his work. His miſſion and appointment were conſtantly before his eyes, and upon this he founds his arguments in his prayer to the Father.
<q>I have finiſhed the work thou gaveſt me to do,— therefore glorify thou me with that glory which I had with thee before the world was, <bibl>
                           <hi>John</hi> xvii. 5.</bibl>
                     </q>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <p>Dr <hi>Watts,</hi> Mr <hi>Allen,</hi> and ſome others, from this text, would attempt to prove the pre-exiſtence of CHRIST's human ſoul. But it does not ſeem that our Saviour's prayer refers to any glory he had in poſſeſſion before the world, but to what he had in promiſe. As one of the <hi>Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him.</hi> or <hi>Swearers,</hi> or <hi>Covenanters,</hi> he had a promiſe made to him in that covenant of peace, of aid and ſupport in his ſuffering, and of a glorious reſurrection from the dead He had this glory promiſed him before the world began. This was a glory he had with the Father, to receive a right by promiſe of a glorious reſurrection:—So his prayer here muſt refer to a promiſe he had in his eye,—for the promiſe is the rule of the prayer of faith.</p>
                        <p>The royal prophet perſonating JESUS CHRIST, foretold what our Saviour here prays for, <hi>Pſal.</hi> xvi. 10
<q>Thou wilt not leave my life, or ſoul, in the grave; nor ſuffer thy holy One to ſee corruption.</q>— Which may be explained by <hi>Luke</hi> i. 35
<q>The holy Thing which ſhall be born of thee, ſhall be called the Son of God:</q>—For the word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> xvi. 10. is <hi>Cheſed,</hi> not <hi>Kodeſh,</hi>—the word which in the Old Teſtament is uſed to ſignity the <hi>Holy One of Iſrael.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Our Redeemer had the glory to be a partner in the great tranſaction where man's redemption was ſettled,—and received a promiſe, that his human nature ſhould not ſink under ſuffering, nor be left to ſee corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,—And he here ſays, that the mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ual glory of him and his Father was concerned in that work he was now about to engage in. He puts up a prayer of faith for the accompliſhment of that promiſe, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned both his Father's glory and his own.
<q>Glorify me with thine own ſelf;</q> intimating that the glory of both was concerned, <hi>i e.</hi> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil thy promiſe to me, and make thy faithfulneſs appear conſpicuous. When the council of peace was between us both, it was my glory to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a promiſe of help and aſſiſtance, and thine to make it — Therefore glorify me with thine own ſelf. Here our SAVIOUR aſks what he bare witneſs to, when he bare record, as one of the <hi>Elohim,</hi> concerning the tranſaction of grace. There ſeems no occaſion of aſſuming any new hypotheſis upon this ſubject, when the truth may be accounted for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any.</p>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>HE could plead the law of his appointment, and the oath that was made to him, as the High Prieſt over the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:0297001300:39"/>houſe of God. Without an appointment to his office and work, there would have been no certainty that ever his work ſhould have been accepted:—But as he was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly appointed by the oath of JEHOVAH, the law of the appointment ſecured to him acceptance whenever he ſhould finiſh his work.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Effects of</hi> CHRIST<hi>'s Redemption, when it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to the Souls of Believers.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 1ſt.</head>
                  <p>IT produceth an eſteem of CHRIST, and all things that are his. When JESUS CHRIST makes himſelf known to his people as a Redeemer, and diſplays the glory of his Redemption unto them, the amiableneſs of his perſon, and the greatneſs of the ſalvation he hath procured by his blood, quite ſubdues their hearts, and gains their eſteem. Such as ſaw no comelineſs in him, why he ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired,—while under the power of ignorance, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of error, become by the manifeſtation of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies altogether charmed with his beauty. It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible but thoſe who know this bleſſed object ſhould eſteem him;—becauſe his excellencies are morally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging, and have the power to transform the mind into a ſameneſs of moral likeneſs with himſelf. The Apoſtle, who underſtood this ſubject better than moſt of men, affirms it as a matter of certainty,—That
<q>by beholding the glory of God, through Jeſus, we are transformed into the ſame image, from glory to glory.</q> There are none who know the Redeemer but do love him, and ſuch as do not render him their ſupreme regard, do teſtify that they know him not.</p>
                  <p>THERE is ſomething in the world which men call Knowledge, which is only a <hi>ſpecious</hi> reſemblance of it, yet is oftentimes miſtaken for true underſtanding. Thro' means of the goſpel revelation men may come to <hi>ſome</hi>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:0297001300:40"/>ſpecious underſtanding of the character of JESUS CHRIST, ſo as to enable them to ſpeak <hi>as if</hi> they knew him:— But then their knowledge is no more than the wiſdom of words. This kind of knowledge may be called a paſſing view of CHRIST's character, which may lead men to ſome ſpeculation, but can never be reduced to practice. This ſort of ſpurious knowledge is like that which we learn of the characters of men at court in the common news,— which may enable us to form conjectures concerning the leading draughts of <hi>certain</hi> reputations, but being remote from the perſons, and the theatre on which they act, we are uncertain of the juſtneſs of the various deſcriptions of character which may be given them.—But true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of JESUS CHRIST by the goſpel, is like that which we attain by friendly information,—where the informer acts the part of a friendly inſtructor;—and knowing himſelf the things which he teacheth and deſcribeth, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly repreſents them with ſuch evidence, that our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge becomes certain and real.</p>
                  <p>THE truths of the goſpel, to All who have not felt their power, are only like the common news to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reader,—which may learn him to ſpeak, but does not afford any certain knowledge, nor make him any wiſer: —Yet, a ſtranger would perhaps not know the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between ſuch perſons, and men of more wiſdom, if he only heard them ſpeak. It is action <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hich teſtifies the truth of true knowledge;—he who pretends to know, but is not truly inſtructed, expoſeth his own ignorance when brought to trial. Chriſtians who are really inſtructed in the knowledge of the goſpel, and underſtand the character of JESUS CHRIST, are enabled according to their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to act his character as a pattern of holineſs;— their lives and that of CHRIST are as like one another, in the leading parts of character, as the image of babes and perfect men are like one another. It is a ſaying common enough with regard to ſome perſons, that it is not for want of knowledge in religion that they do not live as becomes the goſpel. This is not true in fact, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the word Knowledge in a ſtrict ſenſe.—Whenever any perſon knows JESUS CHRIST rightly, it transforms him into his likeneſs, and diſpoſeth him to walk as he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:0297001300:41"/>alſo walked. The knowledge of things in which men are not much intereſted, may be attained without producing any viſible alteration in their conduct,—nor would men judge fairly of their underſtanding, if they ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them ignorant of what they did not practiſe,— when neither <hi>pleaſure</hi> nor <hi>happineſs</hi> are connected with ſuch practice.—The knowledge of things indifferent, may be obtained without any viſible evidence in action;— for being indifferent, the practice upon knowing them is not abſolutely neceſſary. But to walk as CHRIST alſo walked, and to imitate him, as the bleſſed pattern of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and perfection, is abſolutely neceſſary to happineſs in this life, or that which is to come.</p>
                  <p>WHEN the excellencies of CHRIST are made known to the ſouls of men, the connection between an imitation of them, and everlaſting happineſs, is alſo made known;— and the very power of that knowledge inclines the minds of chriſtians to obſerve the imitation,
<q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> ix. 10.</bibl> They that know thy name, will put their truſt in thee.</q>
                     <q>He that loveth not, knoweth not God, <bibl>1 <hi>John</hi> iv. 8.</bibl>
                     </q> The Apoſtle points out the connection between true knowledge of CHRIST, and the work and labour of love.
<q>
                        <bibl>1 <hi>John</hi> ii. 4.</bibl> He that ſaith, I know him, and keepeth not his commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him. ver. 9. He that ſaith he is in the light, and hateth his brother, is in darkneſs even until now. He that loveth his brother, abideth in the light, and there is no occaſion of ſtumbling in him. But he that hateth his brother is in darkneſs, and walketh in darkneſs, and knoweth not whither he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, becauſe that darkneſs hath blinded his eyes.</q> Thoſe who know God, hear and obey what the Apoſtles of CHRIST hath ſaid;—but whoever form their religious practice upon any other plan, teſtify that they know not God,—even ſuppoſe they ſhould make a great ſhew of Godlineſs in will-worſhip.—Let the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this point: <q>
                        <bibl>1 <hi>John</hi> iv. 6.</bibl> We are of God: He that knoweth God, heareth us; he that is not of God, heareth not us.—Hereby we know the Spirit of truth, and the ſpirit of error. Beloved, let us love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For love is of God; and every one that loveth,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:0297001300:42"/>is born of God, and knoweth God.</q> The reaſon why men do not eſteem JESUS CHRIST, and all things that are his, is becauſe they know him not. <hi>Luke</hi> gives this for the reaſon in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, why the <hi>Jews</hi> condemned and crucified JESUS CHRIST, becauſe they knew him not,
<q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Acts</hi> xiii. 27.</bibl> For they that dwell at Jeruſalem, becauſe they knew him not, nor yet the voices of the prophets, which are read every Sabbath day, they have fulfilled them in condemning him.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>WHEREVER JESUS CHRIST makes a true and real diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his own Character and Redemption to the ſouls of men by his goſpel,—ſo as the diſcovery becomes the materials of knowledge, or rather knowledge itſelf, it as neceſſarily begets eſteem of JESUS, as any active principle produceth its <hi>proper</hi> effects. It becomes a part of a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever's moral conſtitution, and operates in the ſoul as a principle of action:—And this knowledge expreſſeth it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the way of eſteeming CHRIST, and all that is his. Such as do not eſteem our Redeemer, it is becauſe they do not know him:—They have not the full conviction of his excellence, fitneſs, and ſufficiency.</p>
                  <p>I KNOW it has been often ſaid, that men may have the knowledge and full conviction of the truth, and yet not be truely reformed thereby.—This I cannot ſo eaſily underſtand:—For our Saviour tells us, that ſuch as know the truth, are ſet at liberty.—<q>Ye ſhall know the truth, and the truth ſhall make you free, <bibl>
                           <hi>John</hi> viii. 32.</bibl>
                     </q> Wherever the ſcripture ſpeaks of wicked men knowing God, it muſt be underſtood comparatively with others who are more ignorant of the things which they are ſaid to know. A ſervant may know his maſter's will, and not do it, <hi>i. e.</hi> the things which he knoweth may be what his maſter requireth, but ſtill he does not know as he ought to know,—and it is called knowledge, in contraſt to other men's total ignorance. As long as men are not reformed in their hearts and lives, they cannot properly be ſaid to be convinced of truth,—nor accounted ſuch who know JESUS CHRIST;—and it is their ignorance which keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them in bondage to Satan.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:0297001300:43"/>THEY have ſuch wiſdom which paſſeth for true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the world, and which may make a very ſpecious appearance, and deceive men;—but it never proves its efficacy by that labour of love, and eſteem of JESUS CHRIST, which true knowledge produceth in them who have it. What <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays of wiſdom, may be ſtrictly ſaid of knowledge,—<q>It giveth life to them who have it.</q> What has made men fall into a miſtake, in thinking that themſelves or others have been poſſeſſed of true knowledge, when they have been really ignorant of truth, is their not conſidering the difference between tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient views, and ſolid underſtanding. There are many tranſient and paſſing views, which perſons may have of objects, which cannot juſtly be called true knowledge.— In objects of ſenfe they may be called glances,—in objects of moral truth, they may be called hints,—in matters of fact, or teſtimony, they may be called notices. Men may have ſome glances of a figure whoſe properties they do not underſtand, and ſuppoſe they had a paſſing view of it, yet they do not underſtand the form nor uſe of it without inſtruction:—A moral truth may be repreſented to our mind by ſome hints, but is either removed before we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, or the mind parts with it before it knows it:— Matters of fact may be brought to our hearing upon a credible enough teſtimony, which may give notice of very ſurpriſing or profitable things;—but the notices may either be ſhort and imperfect, or not often enough repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to leave an impreſſion of the truth of the facts, and the authority of the author upon our minds,—and in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect is not true knowledge. This is ſomething like a tale that is told,—which though it may afford for the time ſome entertainment, is not competent to be reduced into practice.</p>
                  <p>THOSE three kinds of paſſing views may be illuſtrated by theſe ſimilitudes.—The firſt is like one who views his face in a glaſs, but forgets what manner of man he was:—The ſecond is like one who receives the dictates of a maſter upon a ſubject, the rudiments of which he hath never learned,—ſo has no knowledge of, but as far as any thing he hath heard ſaid is agreeable with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:0297001300:44"/>he has already learned:—The latter is like one who receives the news from another who paſſeth by, but is not able to form a judgment of what is reported,—becauſe he has not time to be acquainted with the author who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the facts. That knowledge which ſuperficial en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirers have in matters of religion, is like the two laſt forts of knowledge. Things marvelous may tranſiently be pointed out to them,—and alarming facts may be told them, which may ſurprize them,—or create a ſudden tranſport of wonder or fear, according to the nature of the things intimated.—But what ſo ſuddenly ſtruck them, may as quickly be removed, ſo that it never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a principle of action in their hearts, nor leaves any juſt or laſting impreſſion upon their minds.—This nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affords a ſufficient information to the judgment, nor produceth a full conviction in the conſcience, of the truth of what is reported. It is only a tranſient paſſing view of truth, but not the knowledge thereof. The knowledge of JESUS CHRIST conſiſts in the underſtanding of the character of him that ſpeaketh;—when he makes the report the matter of knowledge in the ſoul, he maketh it ſhew his own veracity, and a believer is inſtructed as well in the character of the perſon who reveals the truth, as in the report he makes.</p>
                  <p>THE goſpel has this excellency above all other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports:—That it is calculated to make known the charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and veracity of him who publiſheth it, and ſheweth with the ſureſt evidence, who he is that is the author of it. We have no proof but what the goſpel itſelf contains, that God is the author of it,—nor have we any certain evidence to ſatisfy us that we are not impoſed upon, but what is expreſſed in the very teſtimony we believe. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever believes the goſpel, is firmly perſuaded at once, that it is God that ſpeaks, and his word they believe. The firſt true knowledge of God comes by the goſpel,—and it is calculated to produce it. It is much better contrived to make us underſtand, what God is, and what are his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, than all his works put together, for it gives light. "The entrance of thy word giveth light." Divine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation is too often conſidered as a <hi>ſort</hi> of paſſive organ, ſomething like the ſun, moon, and ſtars, which are ſaid
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:0297001300:45"/>to declare the Glory of God;—and there are ſeveral people in the world will with difficulty admit that we can know it to be from God, till we learn it <hi>extra ſeipſum,</hi> without itſelf.—But the difficulty here is inſurmount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and ends in <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> For when men depart from ſcripture itſelf, to ſeek for the knowledge of its author,— where do they land? In eternal doubts, and ſcepticiſm.
<q>By faith we underſtand, that the worlds were made by the word of God.</q>—By the knowledge of the ſacred records we learn the character of their author, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the certain proof that God made the world:—But when we begin to ſeek the Divine Character among his works at firſt hand, on purpoſe to ſettle the character of ſcripture, we are obliged firſt to prove, that the univerſe is his handy work.—This is ſtill more difficult to prove without help from the ſcripture, than to find the charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the author of revelation without ſuch aid. The goſpel ſeems to be ſuited to ſome capacity in us, whereby it produceth in our minds an aſſent to its truth by making known its author.</p>
                  <p>THIS knowledge is not like opinion, which is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon probability, nor like conjecture, which is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only on ſome probable marks of truth;—but is founded upon certain underſtanding of facts, concerning which there can be no reaſonable doubt; and on the teſtimony of one who neither will nor can deceive us.</p>
                  <p>WHEN this knowledge is obtained, it is not like opinion, which may vary with probability, but it becomes a principle of action in the mind,—and in its nature varies no more than the record on which it is founded. It may have degrees, according to the meaſure of divine manifeſtation;—but as to its nature, it is founded upon principles that are invariable. It may increaſe or decline upon occaſions, but can never totally fail, more than its firſt principles can be deſtroyed. It is compared
<q>to the ſhining light, which ſhineth more and more unto the perfect day.</q> This knowledge begets a laſting eſteem of CHRIST, on account of his many excellencies that are the ſum of that heavenly wiſdom.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:0297001300:46"/>FROM the divine records the chriſtian is informed, that the Redeemer is a divine perſon,—<q>Fairer than the ſons of men, and more excellent than all mountains of prey.</q>—That he excells in wiſdom, power, goodneſs and truth;—but reſts in his love, and rejoiceth in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Thoſe who know JESUS CHRIST, conſider him not only as mighty to ſave, but as the moſt excellent object of contemplation and delight,—having in him every beauty which can give pleaſure to the mind. It was from a certain knowledge of <hi>this</hi> that <hi>David</hi> expreſſed himſelf ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe pathetic lines,
<q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> xxvii. 4.</bibl> One thing have I deſired of the Lord, and that will I ſeek after; that all the days of my life I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord, to behold his beauty, and enquire in his temple.</q> The chriſtian's eſteem of JESUS is founded upon what is amiable in his character;—what is not more ſtriking than it is ſweet. In this, love and eſteem are ſomething diſtinct. Love, which is the deſire of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any object that is agreeable, conſidered at ſome diſtance, is more engaged with what is ſtriking, than what is amiable;—but when the object is obtained, and all the ſtriking parts of character appear mixed with ſweetneſs and amiableneſs,—then love reſts in the object, and becomes laſting eſteem.</p>
                  <p>WHEN a miſerable ſinner, under the apprehenſions of guilt and the Divine diſpleaſure, receives the intimation of the Redeemer's character, as one who hath paid his ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, and hath delivered him from going down to the pit, he is ready to be enamoured with his love and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion,—and admires him rather as one who hath done him a real ſervice, than one who is intrinſickly worthy of his higheſt regard;—but when he comes to conſider his character more ſtrictly, after his ſurprize at his mercy is ſomewhat abated, he comes to ſee that his chief happineſs lies in being joined in fellowſhip with one, who in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects is ſo engaging, that his ſoul will never need any thing more to ſatisfy its deſires, through an endleſs tract of duration. When CHRIST and his redemption is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in the ſoul, the mind reſts in the eſteem of him,— who is worthy of its moſt exalted regards.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:0297001300:47"/>BUT this knowledge makes chriſtians alſo eſteem all that is CHRIST's.—Every appointment of his, and every ordinance which bears the ſtamp of his authority, are dear to them who know him.—His character as a Lawgiver, who rules in mount Zion, is the object of their eſteem,— and therefore all his laws appear righteous. It is not how agreeable ſome ordinances are to fleſh and blood, or how they may ſuit the ends of worldly policy and temporal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, that engageth a chriſtian to obſerve them,—but whether they have the ſeal of CHRIST's appointment add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them. The knowledge of CHRIST, our Redeemer, teacheth all his children to conſider obedience to him in obſerving his ordinances, not as means which merely lead to glory,—but a very part of glory <hi>itſelf;</hi>—for it is their glory to keep his commandments, in every ſtage of exiſtence whatſoever. The children of heavenly wiſdom wiſely conſider, that there is no difference between the militant ſtate of CHRIST's church, and that of the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, with reſpect to men's obligation to obey him,— nor will they ever have any deſire to be freed from his ſervice.—And therefore they conſider theſe ordinances, which are appointed to them in this life to obſerve, as the only heavenly exerciſe they are capable of for the preſent.</p>
                  <p>THOSE who know JESUS CHRIST, their Redeemer, are not taken with the ſplendour of rituals, nor engaged with the pompous means of devotion;—but are more concerned about the ſpirit and truth of religion, than the elegance of external modes of worſhip. When they come to the houſe of God,
<q>they are more ready to hear than to give the ſacrifice of fools.</q> The vocal praiſe of chriſtian worſhip gives them more pleaſure,—becauſe they can mutually join in that devotion, than all the ſymphany of inſtrumental muſic. The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> ſound of Organs, Symbols, and Harps, give no delight to a chriſtian's ear, becauſe CHRIST has not commanded that mode of praiſe in the New Teſtament ſanctuary. Such as know CHRIST crucified, chuſe to direct their devotion by ſome expreſs laws of his authoriſing, and will not venture to perform his ſervice according to their own will and pleaſure.—
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:0297001300:48"/>They eſteem all his precepts and promiſes,—they ſay of his commandments, that in all things they are right. Every promiſe is the object of a believer's truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,—and what their Lord ſays, they are able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive as faithful ſayings:—Becauſe they know the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity of the author, they chearfully truſt his promiſe. Though many circumſtances in providence may intervene, ſeemingly unfavourable to the accompliſhment of God's promiſe, yet the knowledge they have of the Divine cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, ſupports their confidence under every unfavourable circumſtance.—Being ſatisfied concerning God's love towards them, by his giving his ſon, they conclude, that with him he will freely give them all things.</p>
                  <p>MOREOVER, they who have been favoured with the diſcovery of CHRIST's character as their Redeemer, will love all the children of their heavenly father;—for as they eſteem him that begat, they will alſo love them that are begotten. This eſteem is of the ſame kind towards all thoſe who receive the truth in the love thereof, and who bear the image of their heavenly father.—And tho' the children of God may differ in their moral ſtature, or have different views of ſome things:—Though they may have different gifts, and various imperfections, in this preſent ſtate;—yet they eſteem one another on account of their common relation to the one Father in JESUS CHRIST. Difference in outward circumſtance, or variance in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, will not alter their opinion of one another,—while they agree in the original principles of knowledge;— namely, the knowledge of CHRIST crucified. Whenever men begin to diſeſteem one another, and inſtead of loving one another, do moſt heartily hate each other, there is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fear ſomething worſe than difference in opinion.— Nothing but total ignorance of JESUS CHRIST will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch a diſmal effect. Men's opinions are what they cannot help, more than they can add a cubit to their ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,—and if we think them wrong, we ought to pity them, but not hate them. Chriſtian love begets compaſſion for a brother when he errs, and will not ſuffer the mind to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move its regards for what is only his misfortune.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:0297001300:49"/>
                  <head>SECT. 2d.</head>
                  <p>IT produceth peace and tranquillity of mind. When chriſtians have attained to the true knowledge of CHRIST, and the Redemption he hath obtained for them, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive full ſatisfaction concerning their peace with God through him,—and are perſuaded they ſhall not be brought into condemnation; or in the language of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi>
                     <q>They ſhall not die but live, and diſcover the works of the Lord.</q> This occaſions an inward cafe and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of ſoul,—becauſe God, who is the chief good, and whoſe anger is moſt to be dreaded, is now reconciled through the blood of JESUS to the guilty.</p>
                  <p>WHEN this great privilege is obtained, the children of heavenly wiſdom find no occaſion to be troubled with what paſſes in the world;—for this reaſon, be they poor or rich, weak or ſtrong, as to the things pertaining to this life, they are content, becauſe their treaſure is in heaven. Satisfaction concerning peace with our Maker, not only makes us eaſy ourſelves, but makes us behave eaſily towards others with whom we may be concerned. It does not appear that perſons who behave with ſeverity towards their fellow man, have any pleaſure in contemplating the Divine character;—for all ſeverity proceeds from a ſour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind, which the love of God ſubdues wherever it prevails. When men, called chriſtians, through a cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of diſpoſition, endeavour to hurt one another, for conſcience ſake, it argues they have but bad conſciences: For if their conſciences were purified, they would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to follow peace with all men. All true peace of mind ariſes from ſatisfaction with thoſe things that are the object of moral contemplation. There are two things eſpecially which fall under this denomination,—the relations we ſtand in to God,—and the happineſs or miſery that ariſe to us from thoſe relations. When theſe appear favourable to us, they make us happy, when we contemplate them; if unfavourable, they make us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy.</p>
                  <p>WHEN upon enquiry it is found, that the character
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:0297001300:50"/>of God appears oppoſite to what we find to be our own preſent leading character, it muſt produce a very great uneaſineſs in the mind, and make us unhappy. If we find that God ſtands in the relation of a juſt and righteous judge to us, and we in the relation of guilty ſinners, it will cauſe no little pain and uneaſineſs, if we be not quite paſt feeling.—But if it is found, that he is related to us as a gracious and reconciled God, thro' JESUS CHRIST, beſtowing pardon freely upon the guilty, it will produce peace and ſatisfaction in the ſoul. Our happineſs and miſery entirely depend upon what relation we ſtand in to God, and he to us. To conſider him as a juſt Judge, without perceiving his character as reconciled through his beloved Son, ſets before us a very awful proſpect;— for in that character he condemns the guilty.—But when he is conſidered as the LORD GOD, merciful and gracious, in JESUS CHRIST, he is repreſented, as juſt, and yet the juſtifier of the ungodly. When this great point of peace with God is obtained, and the intimation of it made to the conſcience, contentment with every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumſtance of life will be the neceſſary conſequence; this will diſpoſe men to live peaceably, as far as in them lies with every one. It argues a bad conſcience, and corrupt heart, to have a conſtant diſpoſition to quarrel with others about things that are no ways momentous. When we conſider the connection of what has been ſaid, we ſhall not be able to give any other reaſon for men fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out with their fellow chriſtians and brethren, but that they know not JESUS CHRIST, and are at variance with their Maker;—for were they in good terms with the Almighty, they would find no great difficulty to live peaceably with all men.—And we may eaſily learn from obſervation, that a good man is not at ſo much difficulty to live peaceably with his enemies, as bad men and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites are to live in peace with their moſt intimate friends. Whoever is fully perſuaded of what JESUS hath done for them, will not grudge to ſeek peace with their very foes; —they know they cannot follow a better example, than that of CHRIST. The various murmurings which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail among nominal profeſſors of religion, only teſtify how little they are acquainted with that Saviour who died to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:0297001300:51"/>make peace for men, and ſhed his precious blood to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain for them forgiveneſs of ſin.</p>
                  <p>THERE are many more effects which the manifeſtation of CHRIST, and Redemption through him, produce in the ſouls of thoſe who believe the record concerning him,— which I am obliged to leave out of this Eſſay, leſt I ſhould ſwell it to an undue ſize.—I ſhall therefore finiſh it with obſerving, that our whole converſation will be directed according to our knowledge and belief of this ſubject. Wherever it prevails as an article of religion in truth, it will diſpoſe the believers to walk as CHRIST alſo walked. It is one of thoſe doctrines of grace that purify the heart, and animates the whole conduct of chriſtians.—Infidelity in this particular will not long lie concealed,—for as a man thinketh, ſo is he,—and he will ſhew the abundance of his heart by the manner of his acting.—But all who believe in CHRIST will be careful to maintain good works.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
