<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epitome of the natural history of the insects of India, and the islands in the Indian seas: ... By E. Donovan, ...</title>
            <author>Donovan, E. (Edward), 1768-1837.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>133 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-06">2011 June</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004865821</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T102038</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW108502226</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K082106.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3308502226</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECMS</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">0591200400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epitome of the natural history of the insects of India, and the islands in the Indian seas: ... By E. Donovan, ...</title>
                  <author>Donovan, E. (Edward), 1768-1837.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76]p.,plates ; 4⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author, by T. Bensley; and sold by Messrs. Rivingtons; White Faulder; and H. D. Symonds,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1800.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT102038.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPITOME OF THE NATURAL HISTORY OF THE INSECTS OF INDIA, AND THE ISLANDS IN THE INDIAN SEAS:</p>
            <p>COMPRISING UPWARDS OF TWO HUNDRED AND FIFTY <hi>FIGURES AND DESCRIPTIONS</hi> OF THE MOST SINGULAR AND BEAUTIFUL SPECIES, SELECTED CHIEFLY FROM THOSE RECENTLY DISCOVERED, AND WHICH HAVE NOT APPEARED IN THE WORKS OF ANY PRECEDING AUTHOR.</p>
            <p>THE FIGURES ARE ACCURATELY DRAWN, ENGRAVED, AND COLOURED, FROM SPECIMENS OF THE INSECTS;</p>
            <p>THE DESCRIPTIONS ARE ARRANGED ACCORDING TO THE SYSTEM OF LINNAEUS; WITH REFERENCES TO THE WRITINGS OF FABRICIUS, AND OTHER SYSTEMATIC AUTHORS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By E. DONOVAN,</hi> AUTHOR OF THE NATURAL HISTORY OF THE INSECTS OF CHINA, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>LONDON: <hi>PRINTED FOR THE AUTHOR,</hi> BY T. BENSLEY, BOLT COURT, FLEET STREET; AND SOLD BY MESSRS. RIVINGTONS, ST. PAUL'S CHURCH YARD; WHITE, FLEET STREET FAULDER, BOND STREET; AND H. D. SYMONDS, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p>
            <p>1800.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>ABOUT four years since, the Author published an Epitome of the Insects of China, precisely in the same form, and nearly on the same plan, as those of India, which are now submitted to the public. Of the encouragement he experienced on that occasion it might be highly improper to speak with confidence at this moment, lest the sincerity of his motives should be misconceived. Whether he is entitled to expect the like degree of countenance as before, must rest alone with the candid reader to decide. For his own part he will be content to say, that the favourable reception which the Epitome of the Insects of China met with, was an irresistible inducement with the Author to undertake a similar illustration of the Insects of India; and that whatever may have been ultimately his success, he has not been less soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous to render it, in every respect, as interesting and complete as the former work.</p>
            <p>Various arguments might be adduced in behalf of the present publication, to one of which we cannot refrain adverting. It becomes our peculiar province at this time to awaken the public curiosity to a subject of no mean importance: we are about to consider with atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the entomological productions of a country for which we ought to cherish the liveliest and deepest interest, as being connected intimately with the prosperity, the dignity, and honour of the British empire;—in a word, of British India, that invaluable portion of terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torial domains so long retained in our possession, and finally confirmed to us by the brilliant career of glory that has so recently crowned the exertions of British valour in the eastern world. Not that the Author can be disposed to attach any greater degree of consequence to the subject of Indian Entomology in particular, than it may really merit, from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of events of such vast political magnitude as those alluded to: he is only inclined to entertain the opinion, that a work professedly treating upon the Natural History of a country, in which, as a nation, we have such an immediate interest, will not be thought des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titute of some legitimate claim to public protection. Further still; he must believe that a work which, from the extent of its design and style of embellishments, is calculated to display the Entomology of India to advantage, will not prove unacceptable; and as no attempt has been hitherto made to elucidate this beautiful tribe of creatures in a similar manner, that the present work may become hereafter of some utility at least, to many individuals who reside in India, as well as to the naturalist in this country.</p>
            <p>That the Epitome of Indian Insects is not entirely confined to those found in such parts of India as are in the British possession should be clearly stated, since it embraces, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the most choice selection possible of those which inhabit every other part of that vast continent, and also the islands situated in the Indian seas. The far greater number of insects included in this selection, are described and figured from specimens in the cabinet of the Author, that were originally collected by the late Duchess of Portland, Mr. Tunstal, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor Holford, many years resident in India, Mr. Ellis, Mr. Keate, Mr. Yeats, and Mr. Bailey.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:0591200400:3"/>
The author has to acknowledge, likewise, the advantages derived occasionally from inspecting the noble collections of Mr. Francillon, Mr. Drury, and some others spoken of in the course of this work, among which he ought to mention that of A. M'Leay, Esq. especially as being one from which he has received very material assistance. And lastly, the Author cannot permit the opportunity to escape him which the present instance affords, to repeat his thanks to that munificent patron of the sciences, the Right Hon. Sir J. Banks, Bart. K.B. for the unreserved access to his classic cabinet and library, with which he has been at all times indulged, in order to complete his General Illustration of Entomology, of which the Epitome of Indian Insects constitutes the second Volume.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:4"/>
            <div type="order">
               <head>COLEOPTERA.</head>
               <div type="plate">
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Scarabaeus Atlas.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:5"/>
                  <head>SCARABAEUS ATLAS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Antennae clavated; club divided into plates. Palpi four. Jaws horny, ſomewhat toothleſs. Shanks of the anterior legs generally dentated.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Thorax three horned, the fore one very ſhort; on the head a ſingle aſcending horn.</p>
                  <p>SCARABAEUS ATLAS: thorace tricorni: anteriore breviſſimo; capitis cornu adſcendente. <hi>Linn. Syst. Nat.—Mus. Lud. Ulr.</hi> 6.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>We are in poſſeſſion of a fine ſpecimen of this gigantic inſect, the only one perhaps of the kind at preſent in this country. It was purchaſed by the late Mr Tunſtal from the cabinet of a Dutch governor in the Eaſt Indies, with various other uncommon inſects that appear in the courſe of the preſent work. There is every reaſon to believe that it inhabits the iſland of Amboyna; or at leaſt that our ſpecimen was met with in that ſpot.</p>
                     <p>Scarabaeus Atlas is one of the Linnaean ſpecies, being deſcribed by that great naturaliſt from an inſect in the muſeum of the Queen of Sweden. The ſame is likewiſe figured and deſcribed by other continental writers, among whom we may mention Merian, Swammerdam, and Voet. Edwards likewiſe, in his Hiſtory of Birds, Pl. 105, gives a figure of this and another large kind of Scarabaeus <note n="*" place="bottom">Scarabaeus Bilobus. Edwards erroneouſly imagined this to be the female, and S. Atlas the male of the ſame ſpecies.</note>, both of which he tells us had been brought from Borneo, in the Eaſt Indies, a circumſtance that ought to be obſerved, ſince other writers ſpeak of this inſect as a native of South America.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>SCARABAEUS SPINIFEX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Without ſcutel, thorax roundiſh, unarmed: a recurved ſpine on the back of the head.</p>
                  <p>SCARABAEUS SPINIFEX: exſcutellatus, thorace rotundato inermi, occipite ſpina recurva. <hi>Fab. Spec. Inſ.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>Sp.</hi> 131.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Inhabits the coaſt of Coromandel according to Fabricius, who refers to the collection of Sir J. Banks Bart. for this inſect. The ſame ſpecies has alſo been received by us from Bengal.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:6"/>
                  <head>SCARABAEUS MILIARIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Without ſcutel; head and thorax unarmed: ſhield of the head ſix-toothed: thorax and wing caſes dark, with elevated black ſpots.</p>
                  <p>SCARABAEUS MILIARIS: exſcutellatus muticus, clypeo ſex dentato, thorace elytriſque nigris, maculis elevatis atris. <hi>Fab. Spec. Ins.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>Sp.</hi> 141.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This and the following ſpecies ſeem at firſt ſight to reſemble each other, but are nevertheleſs diſtinct: the two kinds are repreſented in the ſame plate, both of the natural ſize and magnified, in order that the exact difference between them may be the more easily diſcriminated.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>SCARABAEUS KOENIGII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Without ſcutel, unarmed, black; ſhield of the head bidentated: thorax ſcabrous: wing-caſes dotted with cinereous.</p>
                  <p>SCARABAEUS KOENIGII: exſcutellatus muticus, niger, clypeo bidentato, thorace ſcabro, elytris punctis cinereis. <hi>Oliv. Hist. Ins.</hi> 163.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>CETONIA HISTRIO.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Teſtaceous: two lines on the thorax: ſuture and three ſpots on the outer margin black.</p>
                  <p>CETONIA HISTRIO: teſtacea, thoracis lineis duabus elytrorum ſutura maculiſque tribus nigris.</p>
                  <p>CETONIA HISTRIO. <hi>Fab. Syst. Ent.—Oliv. Hist. Ins. pl.</hi> 10. <hi>fig.</hi> 94.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>CETONIA CAERULEA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Blue; thorax lobed, immaculate: wing-caſes dotted with white.</p>
                  <p>CETONIA CAERULEA: caerulea, thorace lobato immaculata elytris albo punctatis. <hi>Oliv. Hist. Ins.</hi> CET. <hi>p.</hi> 47. <hi>pl.</hi> 5. <hi>fig.</hi> 31.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Figured by Olivier from a ſpecimen in the cabinet of the unfortunate Louis the Sixteenth, King of France. Our ſpecimens are from Bengal.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:7"/>
                     <figure>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Scarabaeus ſpinifer.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Miliaris Koenigii.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cetonia Histrio.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cetonia caerulea.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:8"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Buprestis sternicornis.</p>
                        <p>Buprestis chrysis.</p>
                        <p>Aenea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4 maculata. </p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:9"/>
                  <head>BUPRESTIS STERNICORNIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Antennae ſetaceous, as long as the thorax. Head half retracted, or drawn back within the thorax.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Entirely ſhining green, with grey impreſſed ſpots. Wing caſes ſerrated and terminated in three teeth. A conic projecting horn on the breaſt.</p>
                  <p>BUPRESTIS STERNICORNIS: elytratis ſerrate tridentatis: punctis cinereis impreſſis, ſterno porrecto conico. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 660. 5. <hi>Muſ. Lud. Ulr.</hi> 88. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 194. <hi>Sp.</hi> 35.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Among the Inſects of China, we have already deſcribed a very beautiful ſpecies of the Bupreſtis genus, which the natives of that country collect in conſiderable numbers, and employ in the various orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their dreſſes, arms, &amp;c. The Bupreſtis Sternicornis, and Chryſis, are collected in India for ſimilar purpoſes, but being ſcarce, are eſteemed more valuable than the other kind, which they receive at a low price from China.</p>
                     <p>Both ſpecies are brought from Madras and Bombay, but generally in a mutilated ſtate; for the Indians perforate them at both ends and ſtring them like beads, when they collect them.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>BUPRESTIS CHRYSIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Thorax green, wing caſes cheſnut colour, and terminated in three teeth. A conic projecting horn on the breaſt.</p>
                  <p>BUPRESTIS CHRYSIS: elytris ſerrato tridentatis caſtaneis, ſterno conico porrecto. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 194. <hi>Sp.</hi> 36.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:10"/>
                  <head>BUPRESTIS AENEA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Shining, bronze, wing-caſes terminated in three teeth.</p>
                  <p>BUPRESTIS AENEA: elytris tridentatis corpore aeneo immaculato. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 193. <hi>Sp.</hi> 31.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>From the coaſt of Coromandel.—Cabinet of the Right Hon. Sir J. Banks, Bart.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>BUPRESTIS 4-MACULATA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Green, two golden ſpots on the thorax, and two on each wing caſe.</p>
                  <p>BUPRESTIS 4-MACULATA: elytris integris viridis thorace poſtice elytriſque maculis duabus aureis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 209. 96.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Deſcribed by Fabricius from the collection of the late Dr. Fothergill, as an Indian ſpecies. It is a minute creature, but admirably beautiful.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:11"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Carabus 6 maculatus.</p>
                        <p>Carabus 2 maculatus</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:12"/>
                  <head>CARABUS 6-MACULATUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Antennae filiform. Palpi ſix, exterior joint obtuſe, and truncated. Thorax heart-ſhaped, truncated at the tip behind, and margined. Wing-caſes margined.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Apterous, black: on the thorax two white downy ſpots; ſhells with four.</p>
                  <p>CARABUS 6-MACULATUS: apterus ater, thorace maculis duabus, elytris quatuor tomentoſo albis.</p>
                  <p>CARABUS SEX-GUTTATUS. <hi>Gmel. Syst. Nat.</hi> 1965. 63.—<hi>Thunb. nov. Ins. Sp.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 70. <hi>f.</hi> 84.— <hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>One of the largeſt ſpecies of the Carabus genus known. Our ſpecimen is from the cabinet of the late Ducheſs of Portland.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:13"/>
                  <head>CARABUS BIMACULATUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Black, with a common interrupted yellow ſtripe: antennae and legs teſtaceous.</p>
                  <p>CARABUS BIMACULATUS: niger, faſcia communi flava interrupta, antennis pedibuſque teſtaceis. <hi>Gmel. Syst. Nat.</hi> 1971. <hi>Sp.</hi> 107.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This neat little inſect we have ſeen from ſeveral parts of the Eaſt Indies.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:14"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Pauſus denticornis.</p>
                        <p>Pauſus thoracicus.</p>
                        <p>Fichtelii pilicornis</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:15"/>
                  <head>PAUSUS DENTICORNIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Antennae conſiſting of two joints, the exterior one clavated and furniſhed with a hook, or ſpinous proceſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Brown: wing-caſes ſuſcous on the back, with a brown poſterior ſpot on each: club of the antennae foliaceous, with a ſingle tooth.</p>
                  <p>PAUSUS DENTICORNIS: brunneus elytris dorſo fuſcis: macula poſtice brunnea, antennarum clava foliacea unidentata.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>The firſt account of the Pauſus genus appears in a ſmall tract written by Linnaeus, and publiſhed at Upſal, in the year 1775, under the title of <hi>Bigas Insectorum,</hi> &amp;c. This paper contains likewiſe a deſcription of the Diopſis genus, which, together with the Pauſus, are unqueſtionably two of the moſt ſingular genera of the many tribes of inſects hitherto diſcovered. Both may poſſibly derive ſome additional celebrity alſo from the recollection that the diſſertation in which they are inſerted concluded the Entomological labours of that diſtinguiſhed naturaliſt: it was the laſt he ever publiſhed in the department of zoology.</p>
                     <p>In the diſſertation alluded to, the Pauſus genus is exemplified by the ſpecies <hi>Microcephalus,</hi> Diopſis by <hi>Ichneumonea,</hi> a plate with figures of both which, drawn by J. Afzelius, and engraved by Berquiſt, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the deſcriptions. It is to this plate, and the original deſcriptions of Linnaeus, that Fuefly is indebted ſolely for the account he gives of both theſe genera in his <hi>Archiv. der Insectengeschichte,</hi> printed at Zurich in 1783. The figures are preciſely copies of thoſe engraved by Berquiſt, as are likewiſe thoſe contained in the French tranſlation of that work which afterwards appeared in Paris. Indeed, as Profeſſor Afzelius has ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, from the repeated errors that appear in thoſe works in tranſlating the Linnaean obſervations, defining the character of the Pauſus genus, &amp;c. it is very likely that neither Fuefly, nor his tranſlators, Herbſt, Gmelin, and ſome other writers who have treated on it, ever ſaw an inſect of the Pauſus genus; the ſame might be truly ſaid of the Diopſis genus alſo.</p>
                     <p>Thunberg during his travels through the country of the Hottentots in 1772, found two coleopterous inſects which he conceived with much propriety ought to be referred to a new genus, neither of thoſe eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed previous to his departure from Europe by Linnaeus being calculated to admit them. But on his return to Sweden, he found that Linnaeus in his abſence had deſcribed that of Pauſus, or as he called it Pauſſus, to which they might be referred. An account of theſe was afterwards inſerted in the Tranſactions of the Royal Academy of Stockholm for 1781: this paper is accompanied with a figure of only one of the inſects mentioned, <hi>lineata,</hi> a ſpecies very aptly named from the diſtinct longitudinal ſtreak on each of the wing-caſes, and which is clearly of the ſame natural family as the Linnaean Pauſus Microcephalus; the other inſect deſcribed by Thunberg he calls ruber.—Fabricius conſigns theſe, with the Linnaean inſect, to his genus <hi>Cerocoma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The lateſt hiſtory of the Pauſus genus is from the pen of Profeſſor Afzelius, a learned, copious, and elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate paper, inſerted in the fourth volume of the Tranſactions of the Linnaean Society. He deſcribes Pauſus Microcephalus, and alſo another kind which he found in Africa, and names Sphaeroides. We may juſtly regret, on the peruſal of this excellent paper, that only two ſpecies of the Pauſus were known to this writer.— Neither of thoſe inſects are allied to the four following ſpecies, which appear to be entirely undeſcribed. For this important acceſſion of new ſpecies to a genus heretofore ſo little known, and, in conſequence ſo imperfectly underſtood, we are indebted to the active and praiſe-worthy zeal of Mr. Fichtel, in compliment to whom one of them is named Fichtelii. They were all found in the vicinity of Bengal.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:16"/>Pauſus denticornis is clearly of the ſame natural family as the reſt, having the ſame kind of biarticulated antennae: the club is even much larger in proportion than in the others, and the lateral pointed proceſs more conſpicuous; yet according to the character laid down by Afzelius, this ſhould not be admitted into the Pauſus genus, the number of joints in each of the <hi>tarsi,</hi> or feet, amounting only to three; and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in the three others they are five in number, notwithſtanding that without very cloſe inſpection they appear to conſiſt only of four. From this circumſtance, we are of opinion, that the Linnaean character while it paſſes clear of the prolixity of that eſtabliſhed by Afzelius, is perfectly ſufficient, "Antennae clavatis, biarticulatis, clava ſolida uncinata." Or with the omiſſion of "clava ſolida" it might be ſtill more applicable.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAUSUS THORACICUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Teſtaceous: diſk of the ſhells fuſcous: thorax bipartite: club of the antennae oblong, excavated behind, cavity oval, denticulated at the margin.</p>
                  <p>PAUSUS THORACICUS: teſtaceis, coleoptris diſco fuſcis, thorace bipartite clava oblonga poſtice excavata: cavitate ovali marginibus denticulatis.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>The thorax in this inſect is ſo deeply divided acroſs the middle that it appears, at the firſt ſight, as if it were really two. Hence it is named <hi>thoracicus,</hi> but it muſt be obſerved, at the ſame time, that the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing differs very little in this reſpect, the thorax being alſo very deeply divided. P. thoracicus, and Fichtelii, are pretty nearly alike in other reſpects, and may be of the ſame ſpecies, differing only in the ſex; the moſt ſtriking difference prevails in the ſtructure of the antennae, the excavation in one of which is of an oval, or rather ſhuttle ſhape, and in the other pyriform.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAUSUS FICHTELII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Teſtaceous: wing-caſes brown, teſtaceous at the anterior and poſterior ends: thorax ſomewhat bipartite: club of the antennae oblong, excavated behind, cavity pyriform.</p>
                  <p>PAUSUS FICHTELII: teſtaceus elytris fuſcis antice poſticeque teſtaceis thorace ſub-bipartito, clava oblonga poſtice excavata: cavitate pyriformi.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAUSUS PILICORNIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Teſtaceous: wing-caſes pitchy: thorax bipartite, club oblong, attenuated, incurvated at the tip, and beſet with a few long hairs.</p>
                  <p>PAUSUS PILICORNIS: teſtaceus elytris piceis, thorace bipartito clava oblonga apice attenuata incurva pilis longis ſparſis.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>In the formation of the club compoſing the ſecond or exterior joint of the antennae, this ſpecies differs altogether from the others: the club is entire or not excavated, and is ſlightly beſet with hairs. Of this ſort Mr. Fichtel met with only a ſolitary ſpecimen, as was likewiſe the caſe with our <hi>Pausus Fichtelii.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Curculio Regalis.</p>
                        <p>Curculio Palmarum.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:18"/>
                  <head>CURCULIO REGALIS. <hi>ROYAL CURCULIO.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Antennae club-ſhaped and inſerted in a horny proboſcis or ſnout.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Roſtrum ſhort. Blue changeable to green, velvety or like ſilk, with bands of reddiſh gold.</p>
                  <p>CURCULIO REGALIS: breviroſtris corpore viridi ſericeo: faſciis aureis repandis. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 616. 75. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 449. 234.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>If our ideas of the term regalis will permit its application to any inſect, we agree with Linnaeus in the appropriate, though pompous title beſtowed on this ſpecies of Curculio. It is an aggregate of beauty and ſplendour: of the lovelieſt coerulean, changing alternately to the deeper glow of the violet, to green, or the tranſitory ſparkling of intermingled ſilver. Every ſpace of blue is conſtantly contraſted with another of crimſon, and which as the violet changes to blue or green, alters its aſpect to a ſtill more vivid expanſe of gold. Each of thoſe colours, the blue and red, are diſtinct; for an irregular ſpace of black limits every ſpot and marking, and relieves the whole. As the effect of ſuch a combination of colours in this compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively ſmall ſpecies is inconceivably ſplendid, and almoſt inimitable, one figure in the plate is intended to ſhow the natural ſize, and to admit of more perfect delineation, another ſomewhat magnified is added alſo.</p>
                     <p>This inſect, which is believed to be <hi>unique</hi> in Great Britain, was brought from France in the collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of MONS. DE CALONNE, and is in the poſſeſſion of the author. Linnaeus met with it in one of the cabinets on the continent, and deſcribes it as a South American inſect. In the <hi>Entomologia Syſtematica</hi> the error is corrected, and it ſtands as an Indian ſpecies.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:19"/>The Curculio regalis has been figured only in the unfiniſhed productions of a French author on Exotic Coleoptera, Olivier, and the extreme ſcarcity of that part of his work which has been publiſhed, would induce us to add this inſect to our Indian ſpecies, were we uninfluenced by any other motive.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>CURCULIO PALMARUM. <hi>PALM TREE CURCULIO.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Roſtrum long. Entirely black. Thorax broad and flattiſh. Wing caſes ſhort and ſtriated.</p>
                  <p>CURCULIO PALMARUM: longiroſtris ater thorace ſupra plano, elytris abbreviatis ſtriatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 395. <hi>ſp.</hi> 2. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 506. 1.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>A very abundant ſpecies in India, where it is found chiefly on the palm trees.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:20"/>
               <head>HEMIPTERA.</head>
               <div type="plate">
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Fulgora pyrorhnchus.</p>
                        <p>festiva hyalinata.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:21"/>
                  <head>FULGORA PYRORHYNCHUS. <hi>RED-TIPPED FIRE FLY.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Forehead elongated. Antennae below the eyes, and conſiſt of two articulations. The beak or roſtrum bent inwards under the body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Trunk aſcending, apex red. Wing caſes brown, pale acroſs the middle. Wings black, green at the baſe.</p>
                  <p>FULGORA PYRORHYNCHUS: fronte roſtrata adſcendente apice rubra, elytris fuſcis faſcia palidiore: alis nigris baſi viridibus.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Amongſt the more valuable acquiſitions, deſigned to enrich this illuſtration, few can afford higher gratification to the ſcientific reader than this Fulgora. In ſize it is inferior only to F. Lanternaria, it is an undoubted nondeſcript, and may be conſidered as a ſtriking example of the entomological riches of a country hitherto ſcarcely known, the <hi>interior</hi> of <hi>Indostan.</hi> It was originally brought from India by the late Governor Holford, and is now in the poſſeſſion of the author. He has ſought in vain for this ſpecies in other cabinets of exotic inſects, and ventures to deem his ſpecimen <hi>unique.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the courſe of our remarks on the Fulgora ſo abundant in China, F. Candelaria, our attention was naturally directed to the aſtoniſhing property ſome inſects of this genus are known to poſſeſs, that of emanating light; and it was to this inſect we alluded in particular, when ſpeaking of one from interior India, that enabled us to extend our obſervations on that property. The trunk is large, of a dark purple, thickly ſprinkled with ſpots of white phoſphoric powder, and the apex, which is ſcarlet, and ſomewhat pellucid, ſtill retains a reddiſh glow, that almoſt convinces us the creature when living could diffuſe light both from the apex and the ſpots. In admitting this conjecture, without wandering into the marvellous, its nocturnal appearance muſt be infinitely more ſingular than either of the known ſpecies of Fulgorae, Lampyrides, or any other luminous inſect yet diſcovered; for, when on the wing, the illuminated apex would reſemble a globule of fire, or heated iron, and the numberleſs phoſphoric ſpots on the tube, form a train of glittering ſtars to accompany it <note n="*" place="bottom">As it may be thought improbable that any inſect can exhibit ſuch an extraordinary appearance, the words of Olivier on ſome ſpecies of Lampyrides may not be unſatisfactory. The inſects are certainly very diſtinct, but reports of travellers coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance an opinion that the phoſphoric emanations are analogous in the ſpecies of both genera. 'The phenomena produced by a natural phoſphorus is ſtill more wonderful in ſome foreign ſpecies, in which the males ſhine, and being provided with wings will produce in their rapid flight a thouſand ſmall ſtars.'—<hi>Olivier, Hiſtoire des Inſectes.</hi>
                        </note>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:22"/>The only figure of a Fulgora in any reſpect reſembling this ſpecies, is given in the works of Stohl under the title of <hi>De Groote Goene Coromandeliſche Lantaarndrager</hi> 
                        <note n="*" place="bottom">Pl. 26, fig. 143. Green Lantern-carrier fly of Coromandel.—At the concluſion of the deſcription Stohl ſays, "<hi>In de Neder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landſche Kabinetten,</hi> &amp;c. &amp;c." 'This inſect was not known in the cabinets of the low countries till within three years,' anno 1780, 'during which time a few were brought from Tranquebar on the Coromandel coaſt, to the cabinet of natural curioſities of his Highneſs the Stadtholder of the United Provinces, of which I have been obligingly permitted to take the figure of a female by Monſ. Voſmar, to whom I owe my public acknowledgments for it.'—99. <hi>tab.</hi> 26.</note>; but among other evident ſpecific diſtinctions we need only notice the ſtructure of the trunk, which is altogether different, being much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curved and tapering gradually from the baſe to an acute point at the apex: its colour is alſo an olive black.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>FULGORA HYALINATA. <hi>CLEAR-WINGED FIRE FLY.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Trunk conic, uneven. Wing caſes tranſparent, ſtreaked acroſs with black.</p>
                  <p>FULGORA HYALINATA: fronte conica inaequalis elytris hyalinis: ſtriga atra. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>ſp.</hi> 16.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Fabricius refers to the collection of Sir Joſeph Banks, Bart. for this and the following ſpecies. The annexed figures are copied from the ſpecimens that author has deſcribed.—F. Hyalinata is from Bengal.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>FULGORA FESTIVA. <hi>HANDSOME FIRE FLY.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Trunk conic. Wing caſes brown: anterior margin green with five black ſpots, ſemi-circled with orange. Wings red at the baſe.</p>
                  <p>FULGORA FESTIVA: fronte conica, elytris fuſcis: margine exteriore vireſcente; punctis nigris fulviſque, alis baſi rubris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>ſp.</hi> 17.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This ſpecies is from Coromandel.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Fulgora lineata.</p>
                        <p>Fulgora pallida.</p>
                        <p>Cicada indica.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:24"/>
                  <head>FULGORA LINEATA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Trunk linear, aſcending: wing-caſes pale, with two brown lines.</p>
                  <p>FULGORA LINEATA: fronte roſtrata lineari adſcendente, elytris pallidis: lineis duabus fuſcis.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>A pretty little undeſcribed ſpecies found in Bengal, where it is not very uncommon.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>FULGORA PALLIDA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Trunk linear, aſcending: thorax pale green, with red lineations; wing-caſes hyaline.</p>
                  <p>FULGORA PALLIDA: fronte roſtrata lineari adſcendente thorace pallide viridi rubro lineato elytris hyalinis.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>From the ſame place as the preceding inſect.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:25"/>
                  <head>CICADA INDICA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Black; on the thorax a yellow ſtripe; towards the extremity of the abdomen an orange band: wing-caſes browniſh olive with red veins.</p>
                  <p>CICADA INDICA: nigra thorace faſcia flava abdomine poſtice faſcia aurantia, elytris fuſco-olivaceis venis rubris.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This is unqueſtionably one of the moſt ſtriking and magnificent ſpecies of Cicada we are acquainted with. A ſingle ſpecimen of this kind was diſcovered in Bengal by Mr. Fichtel about four years ago. It is now depoſited in the Imperial cabinet at Vienna.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Mantis Gigas.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:27"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Mantis Viridis.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Mantis Siccifolia.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:29"/>
                  <head>MANTIS GIGAS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Head ſhaking, or unſteady, armed with jaws, and furniſhed with filiform palpi. Antennae ſetaceous. Wings four, membranaceous, convoluted, inferior ones folded. Anterior legs compreſſed, ſerrated with teeth beneath, and armed with a ſingle claw. Four poſterior ones ſmooth, and formed for walking. Thorax linear, elongated, and narrow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Thorax roundiſh, and ſcabrous; wing-caſes very ſhort; legs ſpinous.</p>
                  <p>MANTIS GIGAS: thorace teretiuſculo ſcabro, elytris breviſſimis, pedibus ſpinoſis. <hi>Linn. Gmel.</hi> 2048. <hi>Sp.</hi> 1.—<hi>Fab. Spec. Ins.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 345. <hi>n.</hi> 1.—<hi>Phasma Gigas. Fab. Ent. Syst.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>The largeſt of this very extraordinary genus known. Our ſpecimen is from the iſland of Amboyna. Rare.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>MANTIS VIRIDIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Green, thorax round, glabrous: wing-caſes very ſhort: wings pale teſtaceous with a green coſtal rib: legs ſimple.</p>
                  <p>MANTIS VIRIDIS: thorace tereti glabro, elytris breviſſimis, alis pallido-teſtaceis coſta viridi pedibus ſimplicibus.</p>
                  <p>PHASMA EDULE, fem. <hi>Lichtenstein in Linn. Trans. vol.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 13?</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Perhaps more ſcarce than the preceding inſect. This we alſo received from Amboyna.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>MANTIS SICCIFOLIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Thorax denticulated: thighs oval and membranaceous.</p>
                  <p>MANTIS SICCIFOLIA: thorace denticulato, femoribus ovatis membranaceis. <hi>Linn. Mus. Lud. Ulr.</hi> 111.— <hi>Fabr. Spec. Ins.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 347. <hi>n.</hi> 14.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:30"/>
                     <p>An erroneous opinion has prevailed pretty generally among naturaliſts reſpecting the colour of this inſect, which when living they conceived to be ſimilar to that of a dried, or withered leaf. This, it may be obſerved, is commonly the appearance of the inſect after death: ſuch was no doubt the colour of the ſpecimens delineated by Roeſel; nor can we for a moment heſitate in believing that the inſects deſcribed by the accurate Linnaeus and Dr. Shaw exhibited the like appearance. The ſpecimen of the winged inſect in our cabinet has been preſerved however with more than uſual care. Immediately after the death of the creature, as we have reaſon to ſuſpect, the abdomen had been opened, and ſo nicely excavated that no portion of the entrails, or oily fluids, which would have inevitably deſtroyed the true colour, was allowed to remain. The natural colour is therefore preſerved, which is not of a pale brown as is commonly imagined, but of a delicate, lovely green; a colour dependant, it appears, upon a thin internal coating im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately beneath the outer ſkin, the latter of which is perfectly tranſparent and deſtitute of any colour.</p>
                     <p>The pupa of this curious ſpecies is repreſented, together with the perfect inſect, on the <hi>Vinca Roſea.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is alſo a much ſmaller pupa depicted in the upper part of the plate, that was diſcovered in one of the iſlands in the Indian ſeas, and did belong to the celebrated Mr. Bailey, the astronomer who sailed in one of the expeditions with Captain Cook. This is of an analogous kind to that of that Mantis ſiccifolia, though evidently diſtinct. The perfect inſect, and in conſequence the ſpecies, is unknown to us. Our only motive for inſerting it is to ſhew the peculiar ſingularity of the abdomen, in the middle of which there are two remarkable ſubquadrangular ſpots, of a filmy texture, that are tranſparent, and may be ſeen through very diſtinctly.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:31"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Gryllus Monstrosus.</p>
                        <p>Gryllus reticulatus.</p>
                        <p>Gryllus punctatus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:32"/>
                  <head>GRYLLUS RETICULATUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Head inflected, furniſhed with jaws: palpi filiform. Antennae ſetaceous, or filiform: wings four, deflected, and convolute; lower ones folded: poſterior legs formed for leaping, claws double on all the feet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Thorax boat-ſhaped, poſterior part produced and acute: wing-caſes reticulated.</p>
                  <p>GRYLLUS RETICULATUS: thorace cymbiformi poſterius producto acuto, elytris reticulatis. <hi>Fab. Spec. Ins.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 362. <hi>n.</hi> 7.—<hi>Gmel. T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 2073. <hi>Sp.</hi> 4.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>An inhabitant of Bengal. There is a ſpecimen of this very rare inſect in the cabinet of Sir Joſeph Banks, Bart.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>GRYLLUS PUNCTATUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Thorax warted: wing-caſes black dotted with yellow: wings black.</p>
                  <p>GRYLLUS PUNCTATUS: thorace verrucoſo, elytris atris flavis punctatis, alis atris. <hi>Fab. Spec. Ins.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 364. <hi>n.</hi> 14.—<hi>Gmel. T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 2074. <hi>Sp.</hi> 143.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:33"/>
                  <head>GRYLLUS MONSTROSUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings, and wing-caſes terminating in a tail-like convolution.</p>
                  <p>GRYLLUS MONSTROSUS: elytris aliſque caudato-convolutis. <hi>Fab. Spec. Inſ.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 353. <hi>n.</hi> 2.—<hi>Gmel. T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 2059. <hi>Sp.</hi> 73.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This very ſingular creature is found in the vicinity of Bengal, where, according to the information of Mr. Fichtel, it is by no means common. It lives under ground like the Gryllus Campeſtris, and ſome other well known analogous European inſects of this tribe.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:34"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Locusta Amboinensis.</p>
                        <p>Locusta citrifolia</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:35"/>
                  <head>LOCUSTA AMBOINENSIS. <hi>AMBOYNA LEAF-LOCUST.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Antennae ſetaceous: feelers unequal: tail of the female armed with an enſiform weapon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Green: thorax quadrangular with the angles dentated: ſcutel large, brown-green; wing-caſes leaf-formed and very broad.</p>
                  <p>LOCUSTA AMBOINENSIS: viridiſſima, thorace tetragona angulis dentatis, ſcutello magno fuſco-viridi, elytris foliaceis latiſſimis.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>The only ſpecimen we have ever ſeen of this elegant ſpecies is that delineated in the annexed plate with Locuſta citrifolia. This inſect was received from Amboyna ſome years ago by Governor Holford, then reſident in India, and is at this time in the collection of the Author.</p>
                     <p>Both the elytra, or wing-caſes, and the poſterior part of the thorax, are of a fine delicate green: the anterior part of the thorax yellowiſh brown; with the head, and body ſtill paler. The wing-caſes, as uſual in this tribe, bear no very diſtant reſemblance to the leaves of certain plants, not only in colour but alſo in the outline, and ſtill more ſo in the conformation of the nerves which ariſe and branch off towards the extremities, exactly in the ſame manner as the nerves ariſe, and ramify, from the mid-rib in the leaves of the far greater number of plants. One peculiarity in the ſtructure of the elytra in our new ſpecies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves remark: the ſcutel, or rather that portion of the wing-caſe on the left ſide that folds over the back when the creature is at reſt, is of a much ſtronger texture than any other part of the inſect except the thorax, and ſerves as an external covering or defence to the correſponding lobe of the other wing-caſe, which is of a more delicate nature, conſiſting only of a thin and pellucid membrane, the ſurface of which is hyaline or glaſſy. The wings are remarkably tender, of a whitiſh colour, and ſemitranſparent.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:36"/>
                  <head>LOCUSTA CITRIFOLIA. <hi>CITRON-LEAF LOCUST.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Thorax quadrangular: crenated at the angles.</p>
                  <p>LOCUSTA CITRIFOLIA: thorace tetragona: angulis crenatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 33. <hi>Sp.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>GRYLLUS CITRIFOLIUS. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 695. 16.—<hi>Mus. Lud. Ulr.</hi> 125.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Received with the preceding inſect from Amboyna.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:37"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Cimex nigripes.</p>
                        <p>papilloſus. cruciatus.</p>
                        <p>mactans. uniguttatus.</p>
                        <p>viridis. ſerratus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:38"/>
                  <head>CIMEX NIGRIPES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Snout inflected. Antennae filiform, longer than the thorax. Wings four, folded acroſs each other, the anterior part of the upper pair coriaceous. Back flat, thorax margined: legs formed for running.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Above ſanguineous with two black ſpots on the ſcutel, and a ſingle one on each of the wing-caſes.</p>
                  <p>CIMEX NIGRIPES: ſupra ſanguineus ſcutello maculis duabus elytris unica nigris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 106. <hi>Sp.</hi> 101.</p>
                  <p>Cimex Melanopus. <hi>Gmel. p.</hi> 2149.—Cimex Incarnatus. <hi>Drury. Inſ.</hi> 2. <hi>t.</hi> 36. <hi>f.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This beautiful ſpecies bears a diſtant ſimilitude to Cimex Aurantius, deſcribed by us among the inſects of China; it is found in the environs of Batavia, as we are informed, but is by no means common there.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>CIMEX PAPILLOSUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Ovate, brown, antennae black, ſternum gibbous and compreſſed.</p>
                  <p>CIMEX PAPILLOSUS: ovatus fuſcus, antennis nigris, ſterno gibbo compreſſo. <hi>Fab. Spec. Inſ. p.</hi> 356. <hi>Sp.</hi> 112.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Profeſſor Thunberg deſcribes this Cimex under the name of Chinenſis. Our figures repreſent both the larva and the perfect inſect. That our ſpecimens are from the Eaſt Indies need not admit of doubt: the ſame kind is mentioned as a native of Sierra Leona by ſome entomologiſts, perhaps without ſufficient authority.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>CIMEX CRUCIATUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Pale yellow with black ſpots; ſcutel black with a pale croſs.</p>
                  <p>CIMEX CRUCIATUS: nigro pallidoque varius ſcutello nigro: cruce alba. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 119. <hi>Sp.</hi> 153.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Deſcribed only by Fabricius, who acquaints us that it was found in the Eaſt Indies by Dr. Koenig. We poſſeſs a ſpecimen of this ſpecies from Bengal.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:39"/>
                  <head>CIMEX MACTANS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Oblong, above rufous, two black dots on the thorax, and on the ſcutel two.</p>
                  <p>CIMEX MACTANS: oblongus ſupra rufus, thorace, ſcutelloque punctis duobus nigris. <hi>Fab. Spec. Ins.</hi> 2. 366. <hi>Sp.</hi> 168.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>CIMEX UNIGUTTATUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Thorax with acute ſpines, ferruginous; ſcutel marked with a large white dot.</p>
                  <p>CIMEX UNIGUTTATUS: thorace acute ſpinoſo ferrugineis, ſcutello puncto magno albo notata. <hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>A curious ſpecies. This is a native of Madras.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>CIMEX VIRIDIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Thorax ſpinous, green: wing-caſes browniſh grey, ſcutel at the apex yellowiſh: ſpines on the thorax cylindrical, and truncated.</p>
                  <p>CIMEX VIRIDIS: thorace ſpinoſo viridis; elytris fuſco-cinereis, ſcutello apice flaveſcente; thoracis ſpinis cylindricis truncatis. <hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This rare inſect is from Ceylon.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>CIMEX SERRATUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Thorax with acute ſpines, teſtaceous: wing-caſes greeniſh: abdomen ſerrated.</p>
                  <p>CIMEX SERRATUS: thorace acute ſpinoſo teſtaceus: elytris vireſcens, abdomine ſerrato. <hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>LEPIDOPTERA.</head>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:40"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Priamus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:41"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Antenor.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Antiphus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:42"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO ANTENOR.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Palpi two, reflected. Tongue ſpiral, exſerted. Antennae terminating in a club.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed, both above and beneath black with white ſpots; a marginal ſeries of red lunated ſpots on the poſterior pair.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO ANTENOR: alis candatis concoloribus atris albo maculatis: poſticis lunulis marginalibus rubris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>Sp.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Papilio Antenor is an inſect of very intereſting figure, and may be numbered with much propriety among the rareſt of the Papilio tribe found in India. It is delineated both in the works of Drury, and Jablonſky.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO ANTIPHUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed, above and beneath black, with ſeven lunar red ſpots on the poſterior pair.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO ANTIPHUS: alis caudatis concoloribus nigris: poſticis lunulis ſeptem rubris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>Sp.</hi> 28.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PRIAMUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings denticulated, ſilky: anterior pair green above with a black diſk: ſix black ſpots on the poſterior ones.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO PRIAMUS: alis denticulatis holoſericeis: anticis ſupra viridibus; macula atra, poſticis maculis ſex nigris. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 744. 1.—<hi>Mus. Lud. Ulr.</hi> 182.—<hi>Amoen. Acad.</hi> 5. <hi>tab.</hi> 3.—<hi>Clerk. Icon. tab.</hi> 17.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:43"/>
                     <p>With the exception of Papilio Ulyſſes, which perhaps in point of ſplendour may excel, Papilio Priamus is beyond compariſon the moſt lovely creature of this tribe of inſects hitherto diſcovered, either in India or any other country. It is a native of Amboyna, where we underſtand it is extremely rare, and bears a conſiderable price among the Dutch amateurs in that iſland. We obtained a pair of them in fine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſome years ago from the cabinet of the late Mr. Tunſtall, who had purchaſed them in Holland, from a collection made by one of the Dutch governors in Amboyna. This rarity is figured in a reſting poſition on the bloſſoms of the MIMOSA GRANDIFLORA.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO DIEPHOBUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed, brown; beneath ſpotted at the baſe with red; ſeven ſubannular red ſpots on the poſterior pair.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO DIEPHOBUS: alis caudatis nigris ſubtus baſi rubro maculatis, poſticis maculis ſeptem rubris ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annularibus. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 746. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO LACEDEMON.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, black, with a marginal ſeries of whitiſh lunar ſpots: poſterior ones beneath brown with black lunar ſpots.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO LACEDEMON: alis dentatis nigris: lunulis marginalibus albidis: poſticis ſubtus brunneis: lunulis nigris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 36. <hi>Sp.</hi> 107.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:44"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Panthous.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:45"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Heliacon.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Idaeus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:46"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO PANTHOUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Dentated, anterior wings black, with white marks. Poſterior chiefly white, with black ſpots.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO PANTHOUS: alis dentatis concoloribus nigris: anticis albo maculatis, poſticis maculis albis nigro foetis. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 748. 17. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 18. <hi>ſp.</hi> 56.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This noble ſpecies is figured in a reſting poſition on a flower of the <hi>Double variegated Japan Roſe,</hi> a ſcarce variety of the Camellia Japonica. It is one of the many magnificent natural productions of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna, and is extremely rare.</p>
                     <p>The ſuppoſed female of this inſect is also conſidered as the female of Papilio Priamus; it is a gigantic creature, being ſtill larger than the butterfly repreſented, but it is leſs beautiful, and the general colour an obſcure reddiſh brown.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO HELIACON.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Dentated. Anterior wings uniform black: poſterior pair yellow in the diſk, with ſpots of black.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO HELIACON: alis dentatis concoloribus nigris: poſticis diſco flavo nigro punctato. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>ſp.</hi> 60.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>An inſect from the Eaſt Indies, in the cabinet of Sir Joſeph Banks, Bart.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:47"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO IDAEUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, black. A ſhort yellow daſh acroſs the anterior margin of the firſt pair. Second pair ſpotted with red: a palmated mark of three red ſpots in the middle.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO IDAEUS: alis dentatis nigris: anticis faſcia abbreviata flava, poſticis macula palmata trifida punc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſque ſanguineis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 16. <hi>ſp.</hi> 48.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Brought from Madras.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO ASTYANAX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, black. A forked broad whitiſh band acroſs the anterior pair. Poſterior pair spotted with red.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO ASTYANAX: alis dentatis concoloribus nigris: anticis faſcia ſeſquialtera ſtriata alba, poſticis rubro maculatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 13. 37.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This ſpecies is deſcribed only by Fabricius in his <hi>Entomologia Syſtematica,</hi> and muſt not be confounded with the P. Aſtyanax in the <hi>Species Inſectorum</hi> of the ſame author, that being a very diſtinct inſect, and a native of America.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO POLYMNESTOR.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, black. Poſterior part of the lower pair bluiſh, with rows of black ſpots.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO POLYMNESTOR: alis dentatis ſubconcoloribus nigris: poſticis apice coeruleſcentibus nigro maculatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 18. <hi>ſp.</hi> 55.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This remarkably fine ſpecies is found in ſeveral parts of Aſia; it is rare, but has been figured by <hi>Cramer</hi> and <hi>Jablonſky.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:48"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Astyanax.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Polymnestor</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:49"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Empedocles.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Deiphobus.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Lacedemon.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:50"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Ulyſses.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:51"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Evalthe.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:52"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO EMPEDOCLES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed, brown: on the firſt pair an abbreviated band, and ſpots of green.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO EMPEDOCLES: alis caudatis fuſcis: anticis faſcia abbreviata maculari viridi, poſticis ſubtus maculis duabus anguli ani. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 70. <hi>Sp.</hi> 217.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO ULYSSES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed, black: diſk radiate, blue: ſeven ocellated ſpots on the under ſide.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO ULYSSES: alis caudatis nigris: diſco coeruleo radiante, poſticis ſubtus ocellis ſeptem. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 748. 21.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Our ſpecimens are from one of the Dutch ſpice iſlands in the Eaſt Indies.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO EVALTHE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, black: two yellow bands on the anterior ones; and one of yellow, with red ſpots on the poſterior pair. Underſide red, with a band of yellow ſpots.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO EVALTHE: alis integerrimis nigris: anticis faſciis duabus, poſticis unica flavis maculiſque rubris, ſubtus rubris: faſcia maculari flava. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>Sp.</hi> 136.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>A ſcarce and beautiful ſpecies: repreſented on a ſprig of the VITEX NEGUNDO, FINE-LEAVED CHASTE TREE.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:53"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO LETHE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, tailed, and fulvous: anterior pair black, yellowiſh at the baſe, with two ſtripes and fulvous ſpots.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO LETHE: alis dentato caudatis fulvis: anticis apice nigris: faſcia apiceque flavis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 80. <hi>Sp.</hi> 250.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO COCLES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings ſlightly tailed, whitiſh, with ſtreaks of brown: in the middle a whitiſh green ſtripe; on the lower ones beneath a row of ocellated dots.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO COCLES: alis ſubcaudatis albo flaveſcentique ſtrigoſis: faſcia media alba, poſticis ſubtus ſtriga punctorum ocellatorum. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 65. <hi>Sp.</hi> 204.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This delicate inſect is a native of Siam.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO TIRIDATES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, with two tails: above black with blue ſpots, and a marginal row of pale yellow dots.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO TIRIDATES: alis dentato bicaudatis: ſupra nigris coeruleo maculatis margineque albo punctato. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 62. <hi>Sp.</hi> 195.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Inhabits Amboyna.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:54"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Lethe.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Cocles.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Tiridates.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:55"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Idea.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:56"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Hippia.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Affinis.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Pyhilomela.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:57"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO IDEA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings ſemi-tranſparent, white, veined and ſpotted with black.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO IDEA: alis denudato-albis: venis maculiſque nigris. <hi>Fab. Spec. Inſ.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 38. <hi>n.</hi> 160.—<hi>Gmel. p.</hi> 2258. <hi>Sp.</hi> 73.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>There is a peculiar delicacy in the appearance of this large and rare Papilio that ſtrongly recommends itſelf to our attention, and, notwithſtanding that the figure of it has a place already in ſeveral works on entomology, impels us to include it in the preſent ſelection of Indian Inſects. Clerk, Cramer, and Drury, have each given a delineation of it, the latter of whom names it Papilio Lynceus; but it is almoſt ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous to add, that it is beyond diſpute the Papilio Idea of Linnaeus. Our ſpecimens are from Amboyna, and are repreſented on the common <hi>Indian Yellow Jaſmine.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO HIPPIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings greeniſh white, veins and border black.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO HIPPIA: alis repandis vireſcenti albis: venis limboque nigris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 59. <hi>Sp.</hi> 185.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO AFFINIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, black, with white ſpots: border of the poſterior one beneath black, ſpotted with yellow and white.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO AFFINIS: alis dentatis nigris albo maculatis: poſticis ſubtus limbo nigro flavo alboque maculato. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 58. <hi>Sp.</hi> 181.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:58"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO PHILOMELA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings black, ſpotted with white; poſterior pair radiated with yellow at the baſe.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO PHILOMELA: alis repandis nigris albo maculatis: poſticis baſi flavo radiatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 57. <hi>Sp.</hi> 179.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>From a ſpecimen in the cabinet of the Right Hon. Sir Joſeph Banks, Bart.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO LEUCIPPE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire: anterior pair orange, with a black margin: poſterior ones yellow.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO LEUCIPPE: alis integerrimis: anticis rubris; margine nigro, poſticis flavis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 198. <hi>Sp.</hi> 617.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>A very rare and elegant ſpecies from the iſland of Amboyna. The under ſide is of a lovely yellow, with ſhades of orange, ſprinkled with a paliſh brown.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO DANAE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings rounded, white: a reddiſh (or ſaffron coloured) ſpot at the tip of the anterior pair, with a black band, and margin; beneath a moniliform abbreviated ſtreak.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO DANAE: alis rotundatis albis: anticis apice croceis; margine faſciaque nigris, ſubtus ſtriga mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niliformi abbreviata. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 203. <hi>Sp.</hi> 635.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Fabricius, in addition to the ſpecific character of this beautiful Butterfly, has given a copious and very minute deſcription of it, as one that had not been figured by any author. Our ſpecimen is from the Myſore country.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Leucippe.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Danae.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Maerula.</p>
                        <p>Judith. Libythea.</p>
                        <p>Eucharis. Genutia.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:61"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO MAERULA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, angulated, yellow: a black spot on the anterior pair above, and a ferruginous one beneath.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO MAERULA: alis integris angulatis flavis: anticis ſupra macula atra, reliquis ferruginea. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 212. <hi>Sp.</hi> 664.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO JUDITH.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above and beneath alike: anterior wings white, with black veins and margin: posterior pair fulvous, with a black margin.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO JUDITH: alis integerrimis ſubconcoloribus: anticis albis; venis margineque nigris, poſticis fulvis margine nigris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 202. <hi>Sp.</hi> 632.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO LIBYTHEA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings rounded, entire, and white: a coſtal brown ſpot at the baſe of the anterior ones, apex brown.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO LIBYTHEA: alis rotundatis integerrimis albis: anticis coſta baſeos apiceque fuſcis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 190. <hi>Sp.</hi> 591.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO EUCHARIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings rounded, entire, and white: firſt pair fulvous at the tip, with a black margin: ſecond pair immaculate.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO EUCHARIS: alis rotundatis integerrimis albis: anticis apice fulvis; margine nigro, poſticis immaculatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 195. <hi>Sp.</hi> 605.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:62"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO GENUTIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings falcated, entire, white; anterior pair fulvous at the apex: lower ones marbled with green beneath.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO GENUTIA: alis falcatis integerrimis albis: anticis apice fulvis, poſticis viridi marmoratis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 193. <hi>Sp.</hi> 601.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO AMARYLLIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above and beneath alike dull white, with a black lunated ſpot in the middle of the anterior ones.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO AMARYLLIS: alis rotundatis integerrimis concoloribus obſcure albidis: anticis lunula media nigra.. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 189. <hi>Sp.</hi> 586.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO CASTALIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, white; above immaculate: beneath yellowiſh at the baſe.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO CASTALIA: alis integerrimis rotundatis albis ſupra immaculatis, ſubtus baſi flaveſcentibus. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 188. <hi>Sp.</hi> 580.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO SCYLLA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, rounded, yellow: anterior pair above white, bordered with black: all clouded beneath.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO SCYLLA: alis integerrimis rotundatis flavis: anticis ſupra albis; limbo nigro, ſubtus omnibus nebuloſis. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.—Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 201. <hi>Sp.</hi> 630.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>The three laſt ſpecies are repreſented on <hi>Dolichos Lignosus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Amaryllis.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Caſtalia.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Scylla.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Cacta.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Octavius.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Pyrrhus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:65"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO CACTA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings angulated, indented: anterior pair black, purple at the baſe, with a ſulvous ſpot.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO CACTA: alis angulato dentatis: anticis nigris baſi purpureis: macula fulva. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 116. <hi>Sp.</hi> 356.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO OCTAVIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed, and black, with an abbreviated green band: beneath grey, with a brown ſtreak.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO OCTAVIUS: alis caudatis nigris: faſcia abbreviata viridi, ſubtus griſeis: ſtriga fuſca. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 73. <hi>Sp.</hi> 228.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PYRRHUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed, brown, with a common white band.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO PYRRHUS: alis caudatis fuſcis, faſcia communi alba anticarum dimidiata. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 749.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO MENETHO.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings indented, brown, with a marginal ſeries of yellow ſpots: two ocellated marks on the under ſide of the poſterior pair.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO MENETHO: alis dentatis fuſcis: margine flavo maculato, poſticis ſubtus ocellis duobus. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 83. <hi>Sp.</hi> 260.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:66"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO ARCESILAUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above ferruginous, and without ſpots: beneath brown, with three dark ſtreaks, and a row of white dots.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO ARCESILAUS: alis integerrimis ſupra ferrugineis immaculatis, ſubtus fuſcis: ſtrigis duabus obſcurioribus <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 153. <hi>Sp.</hi> 470.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Fabricius deſcribes this ſpecies from a ſpecimen in the cabinet of the Right Hon. Sir J. Banks, Bart. It is a native of Siam.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO BLANDINA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings indented, black, ſpotted with white: a blue ſtreak at the baſe of the anterior pair; and another at the margin of the poſterior ones.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO BLANDINA: alis dentatis atris albo maculatis: anticis ſtria baſeos poſticis ſtriga marginali coeruleis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 129. <hi>Sp.</hi> 397.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO LIBERIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings indented, fulvous, with a black curved mark at the tip of the anterior pair: a black dot on the poſterior ones above, and three ocellated ſpots beneath.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO LIBERIA: alis dentatis ſulvis: anticis arcu apicis, poſticis ſupra puncto atro, ſubtus tribus ocellaribus. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 135. <hi>Sp.</hi> 418.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PHEGEA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings indented, brown; with either a white or ferruginous band on the anterior pair: diſk of the poſterior ones ferruginous or white; beneath paler with black waves.</p>
                  <p>POPILIO PHEGEA: alis dentatis fuſcis: anticis faſcia poſticis diſco ferrugineo aut albo, ſubtus pallidioribus nigro undatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 132. <hi>Sp.</hi> 407.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Menetho.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Arcesilaus.</p>
                        <p>Blandina.</p>
                        <p>Liberia.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio. Phegea.</p>
                        <p>Fatima. Thyelia.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Nero</p>
                        <p>Papilio Gnidia.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Hiarba.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:70"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO FATIMA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings ſlightly, tailed black, with a common yellow; poſterior ones with the band abbreviated and red ſpots.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO FATIMA: alis ſubcaudatis atris: faſcia communi flava, poſticarum abbreviata maculiſque rubris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 81. <hi>Sp.</hi> 252.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO THYELIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, fulvous with black ſpots: on the baſe of the poſterior pair beneath a white band, and two ſcarlet dots at the baſe.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO THYELIA: alis dentatis fulvis nigro maculatis: poſticis ſubtus faſcia alba punctiſque duobus baſeos coccineis <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 142. <hi>Sp.</hi> 437.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO NERO.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, ſanguineous, margin browniſh: poſterior wings beneath orange.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO NERO: alis integerrimis ſanguineis: margine fuſcente, poſticis ſubtus aurantiis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 153. <hi>Sp.</hi> 471.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>The Fabrician deſcription of this fine Papilio is taken from a ſpecimen in the Britiſh Muſeum.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO GNIDIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, teſtaceous: anterior pair brown at the apex, with a white band; poſterior ones with a fulvous ſtreak, and black lunated ſpots.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO GNIDIA: alis dentatis teſtaceis anticis apice fuſcis, faſcia alba, poſticis ſtriga fulva: lunulis nigris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 137. <hi>Sp.</hi> 422.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:71"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO HIARBA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, black, with a common white band, abbreviated on the anterior pair.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO HIARBA: alis dentatis nigris: faſcia communi alba anticarum abbreviata. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 128. <hi>Sp.</hi> 391.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO ISIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated; anterior pair black with the diſk ſanguineous: beneath entirely lineated with green.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO ISIS: alis dentatis: anticis atris; macula diſci ſanguinea, omnibus ſubtus viridi lineatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 124. <hi>Sp.</hi> 377.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PHORCYS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, ſlightly tailed, and brown: beneath obſcurely ſtreaked, with two cinereous ſpots on the poſterior pair.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO PHORCYS: alis dentato ſubcaudatis fuſcis: ſubtus obſcurius ſtrigoſis: poſticis punctis duobus cinereis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 80. <hi>Sp.</hi> 248.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO ERIBOTES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings ſlightly tailed, fulvous, blueiſh at the baſe: beneath grey.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO ERIBOTES: alis ſubcaudatis fulvis baſi caeruleſcentibus, ſubtus griſeis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 73. <hi>Sp.</hi> 229.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Isis.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Phorcys.</p>
                        <p>Eribotes Isidore.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Cydippe.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Dirce.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Euronimene.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:74"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO ISIDORE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings hooked, tailed, and fulvous: two pale dots in the middle of the anterior ones; tip black.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO ISIDORE: alis falcato caudatis fulvis: anticis punctis duobus mediis pallidis apiceque nigris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 78. <hi>Sp.</hi> 244.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO CYDIPPE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, black with a common rufous diſk: beneath teſtaceous at the baſe, and varied with black and blue.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO CYDIPPE: alis dentatis nigris albo maculatis: area communi rufa, ſubtus baſi teſtaceis nigro coeruleoque variis. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 776. 136.—<hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 112. <hi>Sp.</hi> 345.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO DIRCE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings angulated, brown, with a yellowiſh band on the anterior ones: beneath undulated with blackiſh brown ſtripes.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO DIRCE: alis angulatis fuſcis: faſcia anticarum flaveſcente, ſubtus nigro undulatis. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 778. 771.—<hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 123. <hi>Sp.</hi> 376.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO EURINOME.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings indented, black, ſpotted with white: poſterior pair white at the baſe.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO EURINOME: alis dentatis nigris albo maculatis: poſticis baſi albis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 57. <hi>Sp.</hi> 178</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:75"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO HIPPONA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings indented, tailed, varied with yellow and black: on the poſterior ones four white dots.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO HIPPONA: alis dentato caudatis flavo nigroque variis: poſticis punctis quatuor albis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syst. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 180. <hi>Sp.</hi> 559.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO CYANE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings indented, black, a white band on the anterior wings; diſk of the poſterior ones white, dotted with black.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO CYANE: alis dentatis nigris: anticis faſcia, poſticis diſco nigro punctato albis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syst. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 115. <hi>Sp.</hi> 352.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO COENOBITA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings indented, black: anterior ones with a white ſtreak and ſpots; poſterior pair with a white band above, beneath white with four bands, and marginal ſpots of brown.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO COENOBITA: alis dentatis nigris: anticis ſtria maculiſque, poſticis ſupra faſcia alba, ſubtus albis: faſciis quatuor maculiſque marginalibus fuſcis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syst. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 247. <hi>Sp.</hi> 769.—<hi>UN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO COCALIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, brown: anterior ones ſpotted with black and yellow; beneath entirely greyiſh, with a row of white dots.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO COCALIA: alis dentatis fuſcis: anticis nigro flavoque maculatis, ſubtus omnibus griſeis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtriga punctorum alborum. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syst. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 250. <hi>Sp.</hi> 777.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Hippona.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Cyane.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Coenobita.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Cocalia.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Sophia.</p>
                        <p>Baldus.</p>
                        <p>— Auge.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:78"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO SOPHIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, variegated with yellow, fulvous, and black: margin brown, dotted with black, and white lunated ſpots on the poſterior ones.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO SOPHIA: alis dentatis flavo fulvo nigroque variis: margine fuſco nigro punctato lunuliſque poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticarum albis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 248. <hi>Sp.</hi> 771.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO AUGE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, brown: anterior ones faſciated with greeniſh: poſterior pair fulvous ſpotted with black, with a black ſpot at the baſe beneath.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO AUGE: alis dentatis faſciis: anticis faſciis viridibus, poſticis fulva nigro maculata, ſubtus baſeos atro. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 248. <hi>Sp.</hi> 773.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO BALDUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, brown: an ocellated ſpot with a double pupil on the anterior wings; on the poſterior pair four upon the upperſide, and ſix beneath.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO BALDUS: alis integerrimis fuſcis: anticis utrinque ocello; pupilla gemina, poſticis ſupra ocellis quatuor, ſubtus ſex. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 223. <hi>Sp.</hi> 699.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PERIANDER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed, above and beneath white ſtriped with yellow: tips brown with white ſtreaks.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO PERIANDER: alis caudatis concoloribus albis flavo faſciatis fuſcis albo ſtrigoſis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 67. <hi>Sp.</hi> 208.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>A rare ſpecies; from the Myſore country.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:79"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO ALLICA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings dentated, above and beneath obſcure fulvous, with numerous black dots, and ſmaller ones of white.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO ALLICA: alis dentatis ſubconcoloribus obſcure fulvis: punctis nigris numeroſis albo foetis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 244. <hi>Sp.</hi> 761.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Inhabits Siam.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO OBRINUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above brown, with a green ſtripe on the anterior pair, and a ferruginous ſpot on the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ones: beneath greeniſh with a white band.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO OBRINUS: alis integerrimis ſupra fuſcis: faſcia coerulea maculaque ferruginea, ſubtus viridibus: faſcia albicante. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 766. 113.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO LIRIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings ſomewhat dentated, cinereous, waved with brown: on the anterior wings a white ſtripe, and four white ocellated ſpots on the poſterior pair.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO LIRIA: alis ſubdentatis cinereis fuſco undatis: anticis faſcia alba, poſticis punctis quatuor ocel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laribus albis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 239. <hi>Sp.</hi> 747.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO CRANTOR.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, brown; on the poſterior pair above an ocellated ſpot with a double pupil: beneath five, the firſt and fourth bipupillated.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO CRANTOR: alis integerrimis fuſcis: posticis ſupra ocello unico bipupillato ſubtus quinque primo quartoque bipupillato. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 158. <hi>Sp.</hi> 489.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Periander.</p>
                        <p>Allica. Obrinus.</p>
                        <p>Crantor. Liria.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Pann.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Pindarus.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Vulcanus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:82"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO PANN.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed, brown; a yellow ſpot on the anterior pair, and another with a black mark in the middle, near the margin of the poſterior pair: beneath, cinereous, with two black eyes in the anal angle.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PANN: alis caudatis fuſcis; anticis macula fulva poſticis atra ſubmarginali, ſubtus cinereis: ocellis duobus anguli ani. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt.</hi> 2. <hi>T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 276. <hi>ſp.</hi> 67.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PINDARUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Three ſhort tails, blue ſurrounded with black. Beneath brown, with ſpots of red and ſilver.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PINDARUS: alis ſubtricaudatis coeruleis: limbo atro, ſubtus fuſcis argenteo fulvoque maculatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 262. 15.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Fabricius deſcribes this beautiful inſect as a native of India, and for its figure refers only to the original drawings of William Jones, Eſq. We have aſcertained the ſpecies from thoſe drawings, collated with the manuſcript in the hand-writing of Fabricius, and on this authority give it a place in our ſelection of Indian Inſects.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO VULCANUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Two tails. Above dark brown with fulvous ſpots. Beneath yellow, variegated with fulvous ſtreaks and ſilvery interlineations.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA VULCANUS: alis bicaudatis ſupra fuſcis fulvo maculatis, ſubtus ſtrigis fulvis flavis argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teiſque variegatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 264. <hi>ſp.</hi> 22.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>The figures of Papilio Vulcanus repreſent the male inſect, the female is rather larger, the colours on the under ſide more obſcure, and the ſilver ſtripes broader.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO CHITON.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Three tails. Blue, ſurrounded with dark brown. Beneath yellowiſh white ſtreaked with black.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA CHITON: alis tricaudatis coeruleis: limbo fuſco, ſubtus flaveſcenti albis nigro faſciatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 262. 16.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>The P. Phaleros of Linnaeus agrees with this inſect except the ſpot in the upper wing.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:83"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO HERODOTUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Tailed. Above, wings blue. Beneath green, with a row of black and white points on the poſterior pair.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA HERODOTUS: alis caudatis coeruleis ſubtus viridibus: poſticis ſtriga punctorum nigro alborum. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 286. <hi>ſp.</hi> 100.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PYTHAGORAS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Three tails. Above black, disk and poſterior margin yellow. Beneath white, varied with ſtreaks of black brown; a broad white ſpace acroſs the middle.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PYTHAGORAS: alis tricaudatis atris: limbo flavo, ſubtus nigris albo variis faſciaque media alba. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 259. <hi>ſp.</hi> 6.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO FLORUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, red, margin black. The baſe of the under wings ſpotted with black.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA FLORUS: alis integerrimis fulvis: margine nigro ſubtus baſi nigro punctatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 310. <hi>ſp.</hi> 176.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO LISIAS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Three tails. Above, anterior wings dark brown with an orange ſpot. Beneath, poſterior wing white with black and brown marks.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA LISIAS: alis tricaudatis: anticis fuscis; macula fulva, poſticis ſubtus albis nigro maculatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1 <hi>p.</hi> 261. <hi>ſp.</hi> 12.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:84" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Chiton.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Herodotus.</p>
                        <p>Pythagoras. Florus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:85" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Lisias.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Sophocles.</p>
                        <p>Jarbas. Thales.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:86"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO SOPHOCLES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Two tails. Above black, the whole diſk blue. Beneath white, with yellowiſh undulated marks: a red ſpot at the apex of the poſterior pair.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA SOPHOCLES: alis bicaudatis nigris: diſco communi coeruleo, ſubtus albis: ſtrigis undatis flaveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centibus, poſticis puncto apicis fulvo. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 267. 31.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO JARBAS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Tailed. Above, fulvous, ſurrounded with dark brown. Beneath cinereous, ſtreaked with white: two black ſpots on the poſterior pair.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA JARBAS: alis caudatis fulvis: limbo fuſco, ſubtus cinereis: ſtriga alba, poſticis punctis duobus atris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 276. <hi>ſp.</hi> 65.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Brought from Siam. Cabinet of the Right Hon. Sir Joſeph Banks, Bart.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO THALES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Two tails. Black. Under ſide marked with blue lunar ſpots; and a double abbreviated band of gold next the poſterior margin of the lower wings.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA THALES: alis bicaudatis atris ſubtus lunulis coeruleis: poſticis faſcia abbreviata ſubmarginali aurea. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt.</hi> 3. 268. 35.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO MELIBOEUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Two tails. Above, diſk bluiſh, ſurrounded with brown. Beneath yellowiſh, anterior wings ſtreaked acroſs with brown, poſterior with black. In the anal angle a blue circle encloſing two black ſpots.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA MELIBOEUS: alis bicaudatis coeruleſcentibus: limbo fuſco, ſubtus flaveſcentibus: anticis fuſco poſticis nigro ſtrigoſis, angulo ani atro: annulis coeruleis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt.</hi> 3. 271. <hi>ſp.</hi> 44.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:87"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO TYRTAEUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Two tails. Above brown. An undulated white ſtreak, and black margin, with two intermediate red ſpots on the under ſide of the poſterior wings.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA TYRTAEUS: alis bicaudatis fuſcis: poſticis ſubtus ſtriga undata alba lunuliſque marginalibus nigris, intermediis rufis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt.</hi> 3. 271. <hi>ſp.</hi> 46.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO XENOPHON.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Two tails. Above brown, diſk yellow. Beneath cinereous, a white and brown ſtreak acroſs the middle.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA XENOPHON: alis bicaudatis fuſcis: diſco flavo, ſubtus cinereo ſtriga media alba fuſcae innata. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt.</hi> 3. 272. <hi>ſp.</hi> 47.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO ACHAEUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Two very ſhort tails. Above brown, with yellow ſpots. Beneath yellow ſpotted with gold.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA ACHAEUS: alis ſub-bicaudatis fuſcis: maculis flavis, ſubtus flavis duro maculatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt.</hi> 3. 273. <hi>ſp.</hi> 53.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PHORBAS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed. Above brown, diſk white. Beneath white, with cinereous ſtreaks: two black ſpots in the anal angle of the lower wing.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PHORBAS: alis caudatis fuſcis: diſco albo, ſubtus albis cinereo ſtrigoſis: punctis duobus anguli ani atris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt.</hi> 3. 277. <hi>ſp.</hi> 68.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Meliboeus.</p>
                        <p>Tyrtaeus. Xenophon.</p>
                        <p>Achaeus. Phorbas.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Aeolus.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Strephon.</p>
                        <p>Philippus. Pericles.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:90"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO STREPHON.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed, brown, blueiſh in the diſk, beneath cinereous, with a white band: a double ruſous eye at the anal angle.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA STREPHON: alis caudatis fuſcis disco caeruleſcentibus ſubtus cinereis: faſcia alba anguloque ani ocello gemino rufo. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 281. <hi>Sp.</hi> 80.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO AEOLUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed, blue, with a black ſpot on the anterior pair: beneath dark, with a white band, and ſtreaked with black.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA AEOLUS: alis caudatis cyaneis; anticis macula nigra, omnibus ſubtus faſcia alba nigro ſtriata. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 284. <hi>Sp.</hi> 90.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PERICLES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings with two tails, black; beneath brown waved with white: a double ſilvery ſpot at the anal angle.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PERICLES: alis bicaudatis nigris ſubtus fuſcis albo undatis: angulo ani macula duplici argentea. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 273. <hi>Sp.</hi> 54.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:91"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO PHILIPPUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tailed, brown, beneath white with two fulvous ſtreaks; and two ſomewhat ocellated dots at the anal angle.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PHILIPPUS: alis caudatis fuſcis ſubtus albis: ſtrigis duabus fulvis punctiſque duobus anguli ani atris ſubocellaribus. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 283. <hi>Sp.</hi> 87.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO THUCYDIDES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, dark brown; with a fulvous ſpot in the diſk: beneath cinereous waved with rufous.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA THUCYDIDES: alis integerrimis nigris: macula diſci fulva, ſubtus cinereis rufo undatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 323. <hi>Sp.</hi> 225.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PETRONIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, blue ſtreaked with black: beneath cinereous brown dotted with black.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PETRONIUS: alis integerrimis caeruleis nigro ſtrigoſis, ſubtus fuſco cinereis nigro punctatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 324. <hi>Sp.</hi> 227.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:92" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Thucidides.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Petronius.</p>
                        <p>Regulus. Lucanus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:93"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO REGULUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, black, with two yellow bands: the poſterior one on the upper wings interrupted.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA REGULUS: alis integerrimis nigris: faſciis duabus flavis; poſtica anticarum interrupta. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 318. <hi>Sp.</hi> 205.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO LUCANUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, black, diſk yellow: poſterior pair beneath red with ſquare brown ſpots.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA LUCANUS: alis integerrimis nigris: diſco flavo, poſticis ſubtus rubris: maculis quadratis fuſcis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 322. <hi>Sp.</hi> 221.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO SALUSTIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, fulvous varied with black: anterior ones beneath ſpotted with black; poſterior pair cinereous with black ſpots.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA SALUSTIUS: alis integerrimis fulvis nigro variis: anticis ſubtus nigro punctatis, poſticis cinereis fuſco maculatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 310. <hi>Sp.</hi> 175.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:94"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO TARQUINIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, black: an oblong ſinuated yellow ſpot at the baſe of the firſt pair: lower ones yellow, ſpotted with black at the anal angle.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA TARQUINIUS: alis integerrimis nigris: anticis macula oblonga baſeos ſinuata, poſticis angulo ani flavo nigro maculato. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 319. <hi>Sp.</hi> 207.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO AEMULIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, cinereous, ſpotted with brown and white: poſterior wings pale above; the lower ſurface entirely dotted with brown.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA AEMULIUS: alis integerrimis cinereis fuſco alboque maculatis: poſticis ſupra pallidis, ſubtus omnibus fuſco punctatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 322. <hi>Sp.</hi> 219.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO NUMITOR.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, fuſcous: diſk of the poſterior pair above yellow; beneath entirely yellow and without ſpots.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA NUMITOR: alis integerrimis fuſcis: poſticis ſupra diſco flavo, ſubtus totis flavis immaculatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 324. <hi>Sp.</hi> 228.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Tarquinius.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Aemulius.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Numitor.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Plinius.</p>
                        <p>Plato. Hippocrates.</p>
                        <p>Theocritus. Parrhasius.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:97"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO PLINIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings furnished with a tail, white, variegated with brown: a double golden ſpot in the anal angle of the poſterior wings.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PLINIUS: alis caudatis albo fuſcoque variis, poſticis ſubtus puncto gemino aureo anguli ani. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 284. <hi>Sp.</hi> 92.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PLATO.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings furniſhed with a tail. Above blue, with a deep brown border. Beneath grey, with white undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated ſtreaks; a black eye, having two white central ſpots near the poſterior margin of the ſecond pair.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PLATO: alis caudatis coeruleis: limbo fuſco ſubtus cinereis albo undatis: poſticis ocello atro: pupilla gemina. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 288. <hi>Sp.</hi> 103.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO HIPPOCRATES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings furniſhed with a tail. Above brown, firſt pair tipped with white. Beneath white, with black ſpots.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA HIPPOCRATES: alis caudatis fuſcis apice albis ſubtus albis nigro punctatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 288. <hi>Sp.</hi> 105.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO THEOCRITUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings furniſhed with a tail; above greeniſh, anterior margin and apex dark; beneath brown ſpotted with yellow.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA THEOCRITUS: alis caudatis vireſcentibus: coſta obſcuriore, ſubtus nigris flavo punctatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 289. <hi>Sp.</hi> 106.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:98"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO PARRHASIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings furniſhed with a tail. Above either blue or brown, with a row of white circles along the poſterior margin of the ſecond pair. Beneath aſh-coloured, ſtreaked with white: gold ſpots near the tail.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PARRHASIUS: alis caudatis coeruleis (fuſcis) ſubtus cinereis albo ſtrigoſis: poſticis punctis marginalibus aureis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 289. <hi>Sp.</hi> 108.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>The two ſexes of Papilio Parrhaſius are very diſſimilar. The female is largeſt, the diſk of the wings blue, the male is brown with the ſlighteſt tinge of that colour.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO BIBULUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above brown; beneath white, with a tranſverſe ſtreak of brown and ſilver circles.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA BIBULUS: alis integerrimis fuſcis ſubtus albis: poſticis faſcia argentea fuſco punctata. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 307. <hi>Sp.</hi> 163.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO HYLAX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above brown, without ſpots; beneath aſh-colour, ſpotted with black.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA HYLAX: alis integerrimis ſupra fuſcis immaculatis ſubtus cinereis nigro punctatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 304. <hi>Sp.</hi> 152.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO COENUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, white, anterior and exterior margins of the firſt pair brown, and encloſing two white ſpots.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA COENUS: alis integerrimis albis: anticis margine exteriore fuſco albo maculato. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>Sp.</hi> 308. <hi>Sp.</hi> 169.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:99" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Bibulus.</p>
                        <p>Hylax. Coenus.</p>
                        <p>Livius. Romulus.</p>
                        <p>Ptolemaeus. Ovidius.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:100"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO LIVIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above black, with a large blue ſpot in the diſk of each; beneath greyiſh, with ſeveral tranſverſe red bars edged with ſilver acroſs the poſterior pair.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA LIVIUS: alis integerrimis atris: macula diſci coerulea poſticis ſubtus cinereis: faſciis rufis argenteo marginatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 315. <hi>Sp.</hi> 194.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO ROMULUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above uniformly browniſh-black: beneath green, with a rufous ſpot near the exterior margin of the poſterior wings.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA ROMULUS: alis integerrimis fuſcis ſubtus viridibus: poſticis macula rufa. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 316. <hi>Sp.</hi> 195.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:101"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO PTOLEMAEUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above ferruginous ſtreaked with brown; beneath blue, pale at the baſe.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PTOLEMAEUS: alis integerrimis ferrugineis fuſco ſtrigoſis ſubtus coeruleis baſi pallidioribus. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 319. <hi>Sp.</hi> 209.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO OVIDIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, ſpotted with gold: above fulvous, beneath yellowiſh.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA OVIDIUS: alis integerrimis auro punctatis ſupra fulvis, ſubtus flaveſcentibus. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 320. <hi>Sp.</hi> 212.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Papilio Bibulus, Hylax, Coenus, Livius, Romulus, Ptolemaeus, and Ovidius, are repreſented on the <hi>Adiantum ſucculentum.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:102" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Curius.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Propertius.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Tibullus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:103"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO CURIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Very long tails. General colour black: a tranſparent and a white ſtripe acroſs the anterior wings, the latter extending acroſs the poſterior ones.</p>
                  <p>PAPILIO CURIUS: alis caudatis concoloribus atris: anticis faſciis duabus hyalinis, poſticis unica alba. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 28. <hi>ſp.</hi> 81.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This extraordinary creature ſeems to partake of characters common to the <hi>Equites,</hi> as well as the <hi>Plebeii.</hi> Fabricius, who deſcribes it, refers it to the EQ. ACH. in the Entomologia Syſtematica, but we are perſuaded its characters are more deciſively thoſe of the Plebeii. The ſpecimen is from Siam.—Cabinet of the Right Hon. Sir Joſeph Banks, Bart.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PROPERTIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings divaricated, black, ſpotted with yellow. Beneath, poſterior pair barred alternately with rufous and yellow.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PROPERTIUS: alis divaricatis nigris flavo maculatis: poſticis ſubtus faſciis rufis flaviſque alternis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 325. <hi>ſp.</hi> 234.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO TIBULLUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire. Anterior pair black, ſpotted with yellow. Poſterior pair yellow ſurrounded with black.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA TIBULLUS: alis integerrimis: anticis nigris flavo maculatis, poſticis flavis: limbo nigro. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. p. 1. 326. <hi>ſp.</hi> 235.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO AUGIAS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings divaricated, fulvous, a row of black ſpots along the exterior margin, and an oblique black mark in the middle of the anterior pair.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA AUGIAS: alis divaricatis fulvis: faſcia obliqua margineque poſtico nigris. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 794.—257. <hi>Amoen. Acad.</hi> 4. 410. 80. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 327. <hi>ſp.</hi> 239.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:104"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO ORIGINES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings divaricated. Uniform brown; baſe of the anterior wings more teſtaceous: an oblique row of whitiſh ſpots nearly acroſs the middle.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA ORIGINES: alis divaricatis concoloribus fuſcis: ſtriga punctorum alborum, anticis baſi teſtaceis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 328. <hi>ſp.</hi> 245.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO PLUTARGUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above dark brown, powdered with gold: a yellow ſpot at the tip of the anterior wings: the exterior margin teſtaceous.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA PLUTARGUS: alis integerrimis fuſcis auro irroratis: anticis ſupra macula apicis, ſubtus margine exteriori teſtaceis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 329. <hi>ſp.</hi> 251.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO EPICTETUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above blackiſh, diſk yellow: a brown ſpot along the centre of the anterior wing, having a lunar yellow mark in the middle. Beneath yellow, without ſpots.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA EPICTETUS: alis integerrimis nigris: diſco flavo, anticis macula fuſca: lunula flava, poſticis ſubtus flavis immaculatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 330. <hi>ſp.</hi> 252.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO CHEMNIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Somewhat tailed; brown, with tranſparent ſpots, poſterior margin yellow.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA CHEMNIS: alis ſubcaudatis fuſcis hyalino maculatis margineque poſtico flavo. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 331. <hi>ſp.</hi> 257.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:105" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Augias.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Origines.</p>
                        <p>Plutargus. Epictetus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:106" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Chemnis.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Thrax.</p>
                        <p>Mithridates. Thrasibulus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:107"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO THRAX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings brown, with a few tranſparent ſpots, poſterior pair ſomewhat lengthened in the anal angle. Antennae hooked at the extremity.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA THRAX: alis ecaudatis fuſcis: maculis aliquot feneſtratis, antennis uncinatis. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 794. 260. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 337. <hi>Sp.</hi> 282.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Cramer has figured three varieties of Papilio Thrax as diſtinct ſpecies, under the names of Salus, Sebaldus, and Ramaſis; it may be proper therefore to obſerve that our ſpecimen correſponds with that in the Linnaean cabinet.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO MITHRIDATES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings rotund, diſk black, ſpotted with purple; a deep purple band with a central ſtreak of pale lunar marks.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA MITHRIDATES: alis rotundatis atris: macula faſciaque poſtica purpureis; lunulis pallidioribus. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 336. <hi>Sp.</hi> 278.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO TRASIBULUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire; above black, with numerous blue lunar marks; beneath paler: ſpace of the anal angle fleſh-colour, with brown ſpots.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA THRASIBULUS: alis integerrimis atris: lunulis coeruleis, poſticis ſubtus angulo ani cinereo fuſco punctato. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 346. <hi>Sp.</hi> 315.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO JOVIANUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings black, diſk of the poſterior pair blue, radiated with ſeveral oblong white ſpots near the baſe.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA JOVIANUS: alis concoloribus atris: poſticis coeruleo alboque radiatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 348. <hi>Sp.</hi> 324.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:108"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO SALVIANUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire; above brown ſpotted with green; beneath, poſterior pair white, with a marginal ſtreak of brown ſpots.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA SALVIANUS: alis integerrimis fuſcis viridi maculatis: poſticis ſubtus albis; ſtriga marginali punctorum fuſcorum. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 348. <hi>Sp.</hi> 325.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO GALENUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, uniformly brown with yellow ſpots; beneath nearly as above.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA GALENUS: alis integerrimis concoloribus fuſcis flavo maculatis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 350. <hi>Sp.</hi> 332.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO CATULLUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, uniformly black, with a marginal ſtreak of white points: a few ſimilar white points in the centre of the anterior pair alſo.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA CATULLUS: alis rotundatis integerrimis atris: anticis albo punctatis, poſticis ſtriga punctorum alborum. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 348. <hi>Sp.</hi> 323.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO SPIO.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, reverſed, blackiſh with many white ſpots.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA SPIO: alis integerrimis reverſis nigricantibus undique albo maculatis. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 796. 271. <hi>Muſ. Lud. Ulr.</hi> 330. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 354. <hi>Sp.</hi> 348.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Papilio Jovianus, Salvianus, Galenus, Catullus, and Spio, are figured on the <hi>Clerodendrum Infortunatum,</hi> A plant recently introduced from the Eaſt Indies.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:109" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Jovianus.</p>
                        <p>Salvianus. Galenus.</p>
                        <p>Catullus. Spio.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:110" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Ennius.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Polybius.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Zelucus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:111"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO ENNIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings brown, anterior pair with tranſparent ſpots: poſterior pair black above with a yellow diſk, beneath brown with a white diſk.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA ENNIUS: alis fuſcis: anticis hyalino maculatis, poſticis ſupra atris: diſco flavo, ſubtus fuſcis: diſco albo. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 337. <hi>Sp.</hi> 283.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO POLYBIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings without tails, and black: on the firſt pair a fulvous ſpot; ſecond pair yellow at the anal angle.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA POLYBIUS: alis ecaudatis atris: anticis macula fulva, poſticis angulo ani flavo. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 337. <hi>Sp.</hi> 281.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO ZELEUCUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above and beneath black: margin of the lower ones white; head and tail ſanguineous.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA ZELEUCUS: alis integris concoloribus atris: poſticis margine albo, capite caudaque ſanguineis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 346. <hi>Sp.</hi> 317.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>The three preceding Butterflies are repreſented on a ſprig of the LAGERSTROEMIA INDICA, or INDIAN LAGERSTROEMIA.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:112"/>
                  <head>PAPILIO ORCUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings rotundated, brown: anterior ones ſpotted with yellow: poſterior pair beneath blueiſh.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA ORCUS: alis rotundatis fuſcis: anticis flavo maculatis, poſticis ſubtus caeruleſcentibus. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 341. <hi>Sp.</hi> 296.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO BUSIRIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings oblong, entire, brown: two large ſpots, and dots of yellow on the anterior pair; diſk of the poſterior ones yellow.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA BUSIRIS: alis oblongis integerrimis atris: anticis maculis punctiſque duobus flavis, poſticis diſco flavo. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 345. <hi>Sp.</hi> 310.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PAPILIO CELSUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings entire, above and beneath dark brown, with a yellow band on the anterior ones.</p>
                  <p>HESPERIA CELSUS: alis integerrimis concoloribus atris: anticis faſcia flava. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 347. <hi>Sp.</hi> 316.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:113" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Papilio Orcus.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Busiris.</p>
                        <p>Papilio Celsus.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:114" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Phalaena Mineus.</p>
                        <p>Phalaena Scalaris.</p>
                        <p>Phalaena Sanguinolenta.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:115"/>
                  <head>PHALAENA MINEUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Antennae gradually tapering from the baſe: tongue ſpiral: wings in general deflected when at reſt. Fly by night.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Cyaneous: wings orange, with blue ſpots.</p>
                  <p>BOMBYX MINEUS: cyanea alis concoloribus aurantiis maculis cyaneis.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Cramer has given the figure of a ſmall ſpecimen of this fine Phalaena under the trivial name of Mineus. This is evidently of the male; the antennae of which are not however very correctly expreſſed. Both ſexes of this rare inſect are repreſented in the annexed plate, the drawings of which were taken from ſpecimens met with in Bengal by Mr. Fichtel of Vienna. The originals are at this time in the cabinet of the Emperor of Germany.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PHALAENA SCALARIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Snowy white, with numerous abbreviated black ſtreaks, and a longitudinal fulvous ſtria.</p>
                  <p>COSSUS SCALARIS: niveus ſtrigis numeroſis abbreviatis nigris ſtriaque longitudinali fulva. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>Sp.</hi> 5.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>HEPIALUS SCALARIS. <hi>Mant. Inſ.</hi> 2. 135. 7.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Deſcribed by Fabricius, from a ſpecimen in the cabinet of Mr. Monſon, as a native of China. The ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimen repreſented in the annexed plate was brought from Bengal, and is as well as the preceding at this time in the cabinet of the Emperor of Germany.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PHALAENA SANGUINOLENTA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings incumbent ſnowy, coſtal edge of the anterior pair ſanguineous: poſterior pair ſpotted with black.</p>
                  <p>BOMBYX SANGUINOLENTA: alis incumbentibus niveis: anticis coſta ſanguinea, poſticis maculis atris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 473. <hi>Sp.</hi> 206.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This inſect is rare: our ſpecimen was received from Bombay.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:116"/>
                  <head>PHALAENA FIGURA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Anterior wings whitiſh, with brown and black ſpots; in the middle a black character reſembling figure 7: poſterior wings cinereous.</p>
                  <p>BOMBYX FIGURA: alis anticis albidis fuſco nigroque maculatis: medio figura 7 nigro notatis, poſticis cinereis.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>A nondeſcript ſpecies in our poſſeſſion; from Madras.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PHALAENA STRIGATA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Anterior wings brown, with a longitudinal green daub: poſterior pair yellowiſh, with a lunar ſpot, and border of black.</p>
                  <p>NOCTUA STRIGATA: laevis alis anticis fuſcis; litura longitudinali viridi, poſticis luteis: lunula lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boque nigris.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This moth agrees entirely with the <hi>Noctua Dioſcoreae</hi> of Fabricius, <hi>Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 16. <hi>n.</hi> 26. except in having a large green ſtreak on the upper wings. It appears, indeed, to have been hitherto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded with that ſpecies, either as a ſexual difference, or variety; but we are perſuaded it is neither. Both ſexes of N. Dioſcoreae in particular, have occurred to our obſervation, without this ſtreak.—Found in Bengal.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>PHALAENA HIEROGLYPHICA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings broad, dentated, black: on the firſt pair an abbreviated band, and ſomewhat ocellated ſpot: two notches in the margin of the poſterior ones.</p>
                  <p>NOCTUA HIEROGLYPHICA: alis patulis dentatis atris: anticis faſcia abbreviata alba maculaque ſubocellari; poſticis biemarginatis, <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>Sp.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Common in the East Indies.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:117" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Phalaena figura.</p>
                        <p>Phalaena ſtrigata.</p>
                        <p>Phalaena hieroglyphica.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:118" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>NEUROPTERA.</head>
               <div type="plate">
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Myrmeleon Pardalis.</p>
                        <p>Myrmeleon punctatum.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:119"/>
                  <head>MYRMELEON PARDALIS. <hi>PANTHER MYRMELEON.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Mouth armed with jaws, two teeth and four long palpi. Tail of the male furniſhed with forceps or two ſtraight filaments. Antennae club-ſhaped, length of the thorax. Wings deflected.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings whitiſh ſprinkled with black. Thighs yellow.</p>
                  <p>MYRMELEON PARDALIS: alis albis: punctis nigris ſparſis, femoribus flavis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 92. <hi>ſp.</hi> 2.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Few ſpecies of the Myrmeleon genus have been diſcovered. Linnaeus deſcribes only five, and thoſe are chiefly natives of Europe. Fabricius adds ſeven more, beſides three others in the genera <hi>Aſcalaphus,</hi> in the <hi>Entomologia Syſtematica,</hi> and particularly two from India, in the cabinet of Sir JOSEPH BANKS, Bart. <hi>M. Pardalis</hi> and <hi>M. Punctatum;</hi> theſe are the only Indian Myrmeleons hitherto aſcertained; to the Ento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mologiſt they are equally intereſting as new and unfigured ſpecies, but <hi>M. Pardalis</hi> is much ſuperior in beauty to the other. The characteriſtic diſtinction of M. Punctatum is the alternate black and white ſpecks, or interrupted daſhes in the reticulations of the wings. M. Pardalis is reticulated alſo with deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate browniſh nerves, and its general colour a fine yellow, elegantly barred with tranſverſe ſtreaks of brown.—From the coast of Coromandel.</p>
                     <p>The Natural Hiſtory of the Myrmeleon-larva is curious, and has been traced in ſome of the European kinds by <hi>Reaum. Roeſel,</hi> and others, particularly in the <hi>M. Formica-Leo</hi> of Geoffroy; this creature, among other peculiarities, is furniſhed in the front with a large pair of forceps, with which it takes its prey. It forms circular cavities in the ſand, and concealing itſelf in the center with only the forceps above the ſurface catches the weaker or unwary inſects that come within the verge of its cell.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:120"/>
                  <head>MYRMELEON PUNCTATUM. <hi>PUNCTATED MYRMELEON.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Wings tranſparent, nerves alternately punctured with black and white.</p>
                  <p>MYRMELEON PUNCTATUM: alis hyalinus: nervis punctis albis nigriſque alternis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 94. <hi>ſp.</hi> 7.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>An Eaſt Indian ſpecies, in the cabinet of Sir Joſeph Banks, Bart.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:121" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>HYMENOPTERA.</head>
               <div type="plate">
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Chryſis fasciata.</p>
                        <p>Chryſis oculata.</p>
                        <p>Chryſis splendida.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:122"/>
                  <head>CHRYSIS FASCIATA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Mouth horny, projecting. Jaws much longer than the lip, linear, membranaceous, and emarginate at the tip. No tongue. Palpi four, advanced unequal, filiform. Antennae ſhort and filiform, conſiſting of twelve joints, the firſt of which is longeſt. Body ſhining like gold, and gloſſy. Abdomen arched beneath, with a ſcale on each ſide. Tail moſt commonly dentated. Sting ſomewhat exſerted. Wings flat.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Thorax green, with a blue band: anterior part of the abdomen blue faſciated with violet, golden in the middle, poſterior end red, with four teeth.</p>
                  <p>CHRYSIS FASCIATA: thorace viridi faſcia cyanea abdomine antice cyaneo-violaceoque faſciato; medio aureo, poſtice rubro quadridentato.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This charming inſect is from Tranquebar, where we have every reaſon to believe it to be uncommonly rare. The ſpecies does not appear to be deſcribed by any author, the only ſpecimen we are acquainted with, is in the cabinet of the Right Hon. Sir J. Banks, Bart.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>CHRYSIS SPLENDIDA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Shining blue, with four teeth at the tail.</p>
                  <p>CHRYSIS SPLENDIDA: coerulea nitida, ano quadridentato. <hi>Fab. Spec. Inſ. p.</hi> 454. <hi>Sp.</hi> 1.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:123"/>
                     <p>Very ſcarce. This is a native of Tranquebar, where it was diſcovered by Dr. Koenig. Fabricius deſcribes this inſect from a ſpecimen in the cabinet of Sir Joſeph Banks, Bart.—A variety of the ſame ſpecies is found in New Holland.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>CHRYSIS OCULATA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Shining green: an ocellated golden ſpot on each ſide of the abdomen: tail blue, armed with ſix teeth.</p>
                  <p>CHRYSIS OCULATA: viridis nitens, abdomine utrinque macula ocellari aurea, ano ſexdentato coeruleo. <hi>Fab. Ent. Inſ. p.</hi> 455. <hi>Sp.</hi> 4.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Chryſis oculata is diſtinguiſhed for the peculiar brilliancy of its colours. This, as well as the foregoing ſpecies, was found by Dr. Koenig at Tranquebar. Fabricius deſcribes this inſect from a ſpecimen in the collection of Sir Joſeph Banks, Bart.; from whence our figure is alſo taken. We have ſince received the ſame kind from Bengal through the medium of Mr. Fichtel of Vienna.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="plate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:124" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Vespa cincta.</p>
                        <p>petiolata. arcuata.</p>
                        <p>Macensis. tepida.</p>
                        <p>Apis violacea.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:125"/>
                  <head>VESPA CINCTA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Mouth horny: jaws compreſſed: palpi four, unequal, filiform. Antennae filiform: firſt joint longeſt and cylindrical. Eyes lunar. Body gloſſy. Sting concealed. Upper wings folded in both ſexes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Black, thorax obſcurely ſpotted; body black, with a ferruginous band.</p>
                  <p>VESPA CINCTA: nigra thorace obſcure maculato, abdomine atro: faſcia ferruginea. <hi>Fabr. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 253. <hi>ſp.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>SPHEX TROPICA. <hi>Sulz. Hiſt. Inſ. tab.</hi> 27. <hi>fig.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>From Tranquebar.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>VESPA PETIOLATA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Ferruginous and yellow varied; abdominal petiole incurved and ferruginous, with a black band.</p>
                  <p>VESPA PETIOLATA: ferrugineo flavoque varia abdominis petiolo incurvo ferrugineo: faſcia atra. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 278. 87.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This, with the foregoing ſpecies, is remarkably common in many parts of the Eaſt Indies. Fabricius ſpeaks of it as a native of Malabar.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>VESPA ARCUATA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Black, variegated with yellow; petiole of the abdomen incurved, with four yellow ſpots.</p>
                  <p>VESPA ARCUATA: nigra flavo variegata abdominis petiolo incurvo: maculis quatuor flavis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 276. <hi>Sp.</hi> 83.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Deſcribed by Fabricius as a native of New Holland; we have received it Madras.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:126"/>
                  <head>VESPA MACAENSIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Yellow: thorax black with yellow lines: abdomen marked with undulated black ſtreaks.</p>
                  <p>VESPA MACAENSIS: flava thorace lineis abdomine faſciis undulatis nigris. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syſt. T.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 259. <hi>Sp.</hi> 22.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>Rare. The ſpecimen from which our figure is copied is in the cabinet of the Right Hon. Sir J. Banks, Bart. From Macao.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>VESPA TEPIDA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Black; anterior lobe of the thorax, two dots, and tip of the abdomen ferruginous.</p>
                  <p>VESPA TEPIDA: nigra thorace lobo antico punctiſque duobus abdomineque apice ferrugineis. <hi>Fab. Ent. Syst. T.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 262. <hi>Sp.</hi> 31.—<hi>UNFIGURED.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <head>APIS VIOLACEA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Mouth horny; jaw and lip membranaceous at the apex; tongue inflected: palpi four, unequal, and filiform; antennae filiform and ſhort: wings flat; ſting of the females and nenters acute, and concealed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Hirſute, black, wings violaceous.</p>
                  <p>APIS VIOLACEA: hirſuta atra alis violaceis. <hi>Linn. Syſt. Nat.</hi> 2. 959. 38?</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>This inſect is deſcribed by writers as a native of the South of Europe. We have the ſame ſpecies from the Eaſt Indies.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:127" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>DIPTERA.</head>
               <div type="plate">
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Diopsis Ichneumonea.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="species">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:128"/>
                  <head>DIOPSIS ICHNEUMONEA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>GENERIC CHARACTER.</label>
Horns on the head two, filiform, without joints, much longer than the head, with the eyes at the tips.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>SPECIFIC CHARACTER.</label>
Black; head, anterior part of the abdomen, and legs ferruginous: two ſpines on the poſterior extremity of the thorax.</p>
                  <p>DIOPSIS ICHNEUMONEA: nigra capite abdomine antice pedibuſque ferrugineis, thorace poſtice biſpinoſo.</p>
                  <div type="description">
                     <p>The appearance of this curious inſect is peculiarly ſtriking. Nothing can be more ſingular than the diſpoſition of the eyes, which are ſituated at the extremity of two long immoveable pedicles ariſing from the head, moſt exactly in that part which in other inſects bears the antennae. In this particular the Diopſis differs not only from other inſects of the kindred genera, but alſo from all the other kinds we are acquainted with. Some few of the <hi>Cancri,</hi> &amp;c. have indeed the eyes placed at the extremity of elongated pedicles, as is for example inſtanced in the <hi>Cancer angulatus,</hi> yet theſe are obvious diſſimilar in conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for they are moveable at the baſe, and may be directed towards any object at the will of the animal with the utmoſt facility; but to accompliſh this, the motion of the pedicle in the Diopſis muſt be neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarily accompanied by that of the head, or even of the whole body. The eyes of the latter are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo conveniently ſtationed at the globular extremity of the pedicles, as to embrace a far more comprehenſive range of ſight than is uſual with the generality of inſects.</p>
                     <p>To the inexperienced entomologiſt, the Diopſis would rather ſeem to be furniſhed with remarkable horns, and be deſtitute of eyes, although the latter are ſo very conſpicuous when they are pointed out; it is on the contrary the true horns or antennae that are ſo minute as to be moſt likely to eſcape attention, for each of theſe conſiſts only of a ſingle ſetaceous hair, or briſtle ſeated on a very ſmall tubercle juſt beneath the eye.</p>
                     <p>It has been previouſly intimated, in the deſcription of the Pauſus denticornis, that the firſt account of the <hi>Diopsis</hi> was inſerted in a ſmall tract publiſhed by Linnaeus at Upſal, in 1775. From this we learn, that both the Diopſis and the Pauſus were found by Andreas Dahl among a parcel of inſects in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Dr. Fothergill, of London, by whom they were ſent to Linnaeus. Theſe conſiſted chiefly of inſects
<pb facs="tcp:0591200400:129"/>
collected in North America and Guinea, but the habitat either of the Pauſus, or the Diopſis in particular, it is very certain was by no means exactly known. Fueſly notwithſtanding deſcribes the latter upon this ambiguous authority, only as a native of Cayenne, and after him Gmelim notes the ſame inſect from South America, and Guinea perhaps with as little reaſon. Latreille tells us it is from the coaſt of Angola, on the information of Perrin, a zealous naturaliſt of Bordeaux. Our own ſpecimens (and they are moſt aſſuredly the Diopſis Ichneumonea of Linnaeus) were brought from Bengal, where it was diſcovered by Mr. Fichtel, who has thus eſtabliſhed the habitat of this ſingular creature beyond diſpute.</p>
                     <p>Linnaeus, to whom only this individual ſpecies of Diopſis was known, as uſual with him under ſuch circumſtances, does not aſſign to it any ſpecific character. We are acquainted with another ſpecies of this genus, a native of Africa, in the collection of T. Marſham, Eſq. which will render our deviation from his example excuſable, although the latter is at preſent undeſcribed.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:130"/>
            <head>INDEX ACCORDING TO THE SYSTEMATICA NATURAE OF LINNAEUS.</head>
            <div type="order">
               <head>COLEOPTERA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>SCARABAEUS. Pl. 1, 2.</head>
                  <item>Atlas</item>
                  <item>ſpinfex</item>
                  <item>Miliaris</item>
                  <item>Koenigii</item>
                  <item>Cetonia hiſtrio</item>
                  <item>— Caerulea</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>BUPRESTIS. Pl. 3.</head>
                  <item>ſternicornis</item>
                  <item>Chryſis</item>
                  <item>Aenea</item>
                  <item>4-maculatus</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>CARABUS. Pl. 4.</head>
                  <item>6-maculatus</item>
                  <item>2-maculatus</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>PAUSUS. Pl. 5.</head>
                  <item>denticornis</item>
                  <item>thoracicus</item>
                  <item>Fichtelii</item>
                  <item>pilicornis</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>CURCULIO. Pl. 6.</head>
                  <item>Regalis</item>
                  <item>Palmarum</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>HEMIPTERA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>FULGORA. Pl. 7, 8.</head>
                  <item>Pyrorhynchus</item>
                  <item>Hyalinata</item>
                  <item>feſtiva</item>
                  <item>lineata</item>
                  <item>pallida</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>CICADA.</head>
                  <item>Indica</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>MANTIS. Pl. 9, 10, 11.</head>
                  <item>gigas</item>
                  <item>viridis</item>
                  <item>ſiccifolia</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>GRYLLUS. Pl. 12.</head>
                  <item>reticulatus</item>
                  <item>punctatus</item>
                  <item>Monſtroſus</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>CIMEX. Pl. 13.</head>
                  <item>nigripes</item>
                  <item>papilloſus</item>
                  <item>cruciatus</item>
                  <item>mactans</item>
                  <item>uniguttatus</item>
                  <item>viridis</item>
                  <item>ſerratus</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>LEPIDOPTERA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>PAPILIO. Pl. 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 31, 39, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 48, 49.</head>
                  <item>Antenor</item>
                  <item>Antiphus</item>
                  <item>Priamus</item>
                  <item>Panthous</item>
                  <item>Heliacon</item>
                  <item>Idaeus</item>
                  <item>Astyanax</item>
                  <item>Polymnestor</item>
                  <item>Diephobus</item>
                  <item>Lacedemon</item>
                  <item>Empedocles</item>
                  <item>Ulyſſes</item>
                  <item>Evalthe</item>
                  <item>Lethe</item>
                  <item>Cocles</item>
                  <item>Tiridates</item>
                  <item>Idea</item>
                  <item>Hippia</item>
                  <item>Affinis</item>
                  <item>Philomela</item>
                  <item>Leucippe</item>
                  <item>Danae</item>
                  <item>Maerula</item>
                  <item>Judith</item>
                  <item>Libythea</item>
                  <item>Eucharis</item>
                  <item>Genutia</item>
                  <item>Amaryllis</item>
                  <item>Caſtalia</item>
                  <item>Scylla</item>
                  <item>Cacta</item>
                  <item>Octavius</item>
                  <item>Pyrrhus</item>
                  <item>Menetho</item>
                  <item>Arceſilaus</item>
                  <item>Blandina</item>
                  <item>Liberia</item>
                  <item>Phegea</item>
                  <item>Fatima</item>
                  <item>Thyelia</item>
                  <item>Nero</item>
                  <item>Gnidia</item>
                  <item>Hiarba</item>
                  <item>Iſis</item>
                  <item>Phorcys</item>
                  <item>Eribotes</item>
                  <item>Iſidore</item>
                  <item>Cydippe</item>
                  <item>Dirce</item>
                  <item>Euronime</item>
                  <item>Hippona</item>
                  <item>Cyane</item>
                  <item>Coenobita</item>
                  <item>Cocalia</item>
                  <item>Sophia</item>
                  <item>Auge</item>
                  <item>Baldus</item>
                  <item>Periander</item>
                  <item>Allica</item>
                  <item>Obrinus</item>
                  <item>Liria</item>
                  <item>Crantor</item>
                  <item>Pann</item>
                  <item>Pindarus</item>
                  <item>Vulcanus</item>
                  <item>Chiton</item>
                  <item>Herodotus</item>
                  <item>Pythagoras</item>
                  <item>Florus</item>
                  <item>Liſias</item>
                  <item>Sophocles</item>
                  <item>Jarbas</item>
                  <item>Thales</item>
                  <item>Meliboeus</item>
                  <item>Tyrtaeus</item>
                  <item>Xenophon</item>
                  <item>Achaeus</item>
                  <item>Phorbas</item>
                  <item>Strephon</item>
                  <item>Aeolus</item>
                  <item>Pericles</item>
                  <item>Philippus</item>
                  <item>Thucydides</item>
                  <item>Petronius</item>
                  <item>Regulus</item>
                  <item>Lucanus</item>
                  <item>Saluſtius</item>
                  <item>Tarquinus</item>
                  <item>Aemulius</item>
                  <item>Numitor</item>
                  <item>Plinius</item>
                  <item>Plato</item>
                  <item>Hippocrates</item>
                  <item>Theocritus</item>
                  <item>Parrhaſius</item>
                  <item>Bibulus</item>
                  <item>Hylax</item>
                  <item>Coenus</item>
                  <item>Livius</item>
                  <item>Romulus</item>
                  <item>Ptolemaeus</item>
                  <item>Ovidius</item>
                  <item>Curius</item>
                  <item>Propertius</item>
                  <item>Tibullus</item>
                  <item>Augias</item>
                  <item>Origines</item>
                  <item>Plutargus</item>
                  <item>Epictetus</item>
                  <item>Chemnis</item>
                  <item>Thrax</item>
                  <item>Mithridates</item>
                  <item>Thraſibulus</item>
                  <item>Jovianus</item>
                  <item>Salvianus</item>
                  <item>Galenus</item>
                  <item>Catullus</item>
                  <item>Spio</item>
                  <item>Ennius</item>
                  <item>Polybius</item>
                  <item>Zeleucus</item>
                  <item>Orcus</item>
                  <item>Buſiris</item>
                  <item>Celſus</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>PHALAENA. Pl. 50, 51.</head>
                  <item>Mineus</item>
                  <item>ſcalaris</item>
                  <item>ſanguinolenta</item>
                  <item>figura</item>
                  <item>ſtrigata</item>
                  <item>hieroglyphica</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>NEUROPTERA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>MYRMELION. Pl. 52.</head>
                  <item>Pardalis</item>
                  <item>punctatum</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>HYMENOPTERA</head>
               <list>
                  <head>CHRYSIS. Pl. 53.</head>
                  <item>faſciata</item>
                  <item>ſplendida</item>
                  <item>aculata</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>VESPA. Pl. 54.</head>
                  <item>Cincta</item>
                  <item>petiolata</item>
                  <item>arcuata</item>
                  <item>Macaenſis</item>
                  <item>tepida</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>APIS.</head>
                  <item>violacea</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>DIPTERA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>DIOPSIS.</head>
                  <item>Ichneumonea</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:131"/>
            <head>INDEX ACCORDING TO THE ENTOMOLOGIA SYSTEMATICA OF FABRICIUS.</head>
            <div type="class">
               <head>CLASS 1. ELEUTERATA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>2.</hi> Scarabaeus.</head>
                  <item>Atlas</item>
                  <item>ſpinifex</item>
                  <item>Miliaris</item>
                  <item>Koenigii</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>76.</hi> Cetonia.</head>
                  <item>Hiſtrio</item>
                  <item>Caerulea</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>19.</hi> Carabus.</head>
                  <item>2-maculatus</item>
                  <item>6-maculatus.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>78.</hi> Bupreſtis.</head>
                  <item>ſternicornis</item>
                  <item>Chryſis</item>
                  <item>Aenea</item>
                  <item>4-maculatis</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>61.</hi> Cerocoma. (Pauſus <hi>Linn.</hi>)</head>
                  <item>denticornis</item>
                  <item>thoracicus</item>
                  <item>Fichtelii</item>
                  <item>pilicornis</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>102.</hi> Curculio.</head>
                  <item>Regalis</item>
                  <item>Palmarum</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="class">
               <head>CLASS 2. ULONATA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>120.</hi> Mantis.</head>
                  <item>gigas</item>
                  <item>viridis</item>
                  <item>ſiccifolia</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>125.</hi> Gryllus.</head>
                  <item>recticulatus</item>
                  <item>punctatus</item>
                  <item>monſtroſus</item>
               </list>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>ORDER 9. GLOSSATA.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>186.</hi> Papilio.</head>
                     <item>*Equites Trojani.
<list>
                           <item>Antenor</item>
                           <item>Antiphus</item>
                           <item>Priamus</item>
                           <item>Panthous</item>
                           <item>Heliacon</item>
                           <item>Idaeus</item>
                           <item>Aſtyanax</item>
                           <item>Polymneſtor</item>
                           <item>Deiphobus</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>**<hi>Equites Achivi.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Ulyſſes</item>
                           <item>Curius</item>
                           <item>Lacedemon</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>***<hi>Feſtiva.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Evalthe</item>
                           <item>Eurinome</item>
                           <item>Philomela</item>
                           <item>Hippia</item>
                           <item>affinis</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>****<hi>Nymphales.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Pyrrhus</item>
                           <item>Tiridates</item>
                           <item>Cocles</item>
                           <item>Periander</item>
                           <item>Empedocles</item>
                           <item>Octavius</item>
                           <item>Iſis</item>
                           <item>Eribotes</item>
                           <item>Iſidore</item>
                           <item>Phorcys</item>
                           <item>Lethe</item>
                           <item>Fatima</item>
                           <item>Menetho</item>
                           <item>Cydippe</item>
                           <item>Cyane</item>
                           <item>Cacta</item>
                           <item>Dirce</item>
                           <item>Hiarba</item>
                           <item>Blandina</item>
                           <item>Phegea</item>
                           <item>Gnidia</item>
                           <item>Thyelia</item>
                           <item>Liberia</item>
                           <item>Arceſilaus</item>
                           <item>Hippona</item>
                           <item>Nero</item>
                           <item>Obrinus</item>
                           <item>Crantor</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>******Parnassii.
<list>
                           <item>Idea</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>*******Danai.
<list>
                           <item>Amaryllis</item>
                           <item>Caſtalia</item>
                           <item>Scylla</item>
                           <item>Leucippe</item>
                           <item>Danae</item>
                           <item>Maerula</item>
                           <item>Judith</item>
                           <item>Libythea</item>
                           <item>Eucharis</item>
                           <item>Genutia</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>********Satyri.
<list>
                           <item>Baldus</item>
                           <item>Liria</item>
                           <item>Allica</item>
                           <item>Coenobita</item>
                           <item>Auge</item>
                           <item>Sophia</item>
                           <item>Cocalia</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>187.</hi> Heſperia.</head>
                     <item>*Rurales.
<list>
                           <item>Pythagoras</item>
                           <item>Liſias</item>
                           <item>Pindarus</item>
                           <item>Chiton</item>
                           <item>Vulcanus</item>
                           <item>Sophocles</item>
                           <item>Thales</item>
                           <item>Meliboeus</item>
                           <item>Tyrtaeus</item>
                           <item>Xenophon</item>
                           <item>Pericles</item>
                           <item>Jarbas</item>
                           <item>Pann</item>
                           <item>Phorbas</item>
                           <item>Strephon</item>
                           <item>Philippus</item>
                           <item>Aeolus</item>
                           <item>Plinius</item>
                           <item>Herodotus</item>
                           <item>Plato</item>
                           <item>Hippocrates</item>
                           <item>Theocritus</item>
                           <item>Parrhaſius</item>
                           <item>Florus</item>
                           <item>Livius</item>
                           <item>Romulus</item>
                           <item>Regulus</item>
                           <item>Ptolemaeus</item>
                           <item>Coenus</item>
                           <item>Hylax</item>
                           <item>Lucius</item>
                           <item>Tarquinus</item>
                           <item>Ovidius</item>
                           <item>Suetonius</item>
                           <item>Aemulius</item>
                           <item>Saluſtius</item>
                           <item>Lucanus</item>
                           <item>Thucydides</item>
                           <item>Petronius</item>
                           <item>Numitor</item>
                           <item>Bibulus</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>**Urbicolae.
<list>
                           <item>Propertius</item>
                           <item>Tibullus</item>
                           <item>Augias</item>
                           <item>Origines</item>
                           <item>Plutargus</item>
                           <item>Epictetus</item>
                           <item>Chemnis</item>
                           <item>Mithridates</item>
                           <item>Polybius</item>
                           <item>Thrax</item>
                           <item>Ennius</item>
                           <item>Buſiris</item>
                           <item>Thraſibulus</item>
                           <item>Celſus</item>
                           <item>Zeleucus</item>
                           <item>Catullus</item>
                           <item>Jovianus</item>
                           <item>Salvianus</item>
                           <item>Galenus</item>
                           <item>Spio</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>191.</hi> Bombyx.</head>
                     <item>ſanguinolenta</item>
                     <item>figura</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>192.</hi> Coſſus.</head>
                     <item>Mineus</item>
                     <item>ſcalaris</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>194.</hi> Noctua.</head>
                     <item>ſtrigata</item>
                     <item>hieroglyphica</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>ORDER SYNISTATA.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>133.</hi> Myrmellon.</head>
                     <item>pardalis</item>
                     <item>punctatum</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>ORDER PIEZATA.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>147.</hi> Chryſis.</head>
                     <item>faſciata</item>
                     <item>ſplendida</item>
                     <item>oculata</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>151.</hi> Veſpa.</head>
                     <item>cincta</item>
                     <item>petiolata</item>
                     <item>arcuata</item>
                     <item>Macenſis</item>
                     <item>tepida</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>158.</hi> Apis.</head>
                     <item>violacea</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>ORDER RYNGOTA.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>201.</hi> Fulgora.</head>
                     <item>Pyrorhynchus</item>
                     <item>Hyalinata</item>
                     <item>feſtiva</item>
                     <item>lineata</item>
                     <item>pallida</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>204.</hi> Cicada.</head>
                     <item>Indica</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>213.</hi> Cimex.</head>
                     <item>nigripes</item>
                     <item>Papilloſus</item>
                     <item>cruciatus</item>
                     <item>mactans</item>
                     <item>uniguttatus</item>
                     <item>viridis</item>
                     <item>ſerratus</item>
                  </list>
                  <note place="bottom">T. Benaley, Printer, Bolt-court, Fleet-street.</note>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:132"/>
            <head>INDEX ACCORDING TO THE SYSTEMA NATURAE OF LINNAEUS.</head>
            <div type="order">
               <head>COLEOPTERA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>SCARABAEUS. Pl. 1, 2.</head>
                  <item>Atlas</item>
                  <item>ſpinfex</item>
                  <item>Miliaris</item>
                  <item>Koenigii</item>
                  <item>Cetonia hiſtrio</item>
                  <item>— caerulea</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>BUPRESTIS. Pl. 3.</head>
                  <item>ſternicornis</item>
                  <item>Chryſis</item>
                  <item>Aenea</item>
                  <item>4-maculata</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>CARASUS. Pl. 4.</head>
                  <item>6-maculatus</item>
                  <item>2-maculatus</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>PAUSUS. Pl. 5.</head>
                  <item>denticornis</item>
                  <item>thoracicus</item>
                  <item>Fichtelii</item>
                  <item>pilicornis</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>CURCULIO. Pl. 6.</head>
                  <item>Regalis</item>
                  <item>Palmarum</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>HEMIPTERA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>FULGORA. Pl. 7, 8.</head>
                  <item>Pyrorhynchus</item>
                  <item>hyalinata</item>
                  <item>feſtiva</item>
                  <item>lineata</item>
                  <item>pallida</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>CICADA.</head>
                  <item>Indica</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>MANTIS. Pl. 9, 10, 11.</head>
                  <item>gigas</item>
                  <item>viridis</item>
                  <item>ſiccifolia</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>GRYLLUS. Pl. 12.</head>
                  <item>reticulatus</item>
                  <item>punctatus</item>
                  <item>monſtroſus</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>LOCUSTA. Pl. 13.</head>
                  <item>Amboinenſis</item>
                  <item>citrifolia</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>CIMEX. Pl. 14.</head>
                  <item>nigripes</item>
                  <item>papilloſus</item>
                  <item>cruciatus</item>
                  <item>mactans</item>
                  <item>uniguttatus</item>
                  <item>viridis</item>
                  <item>ſerratus</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>LEPIDOPTERA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>PAPILIO. Pl. 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 31, 39, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 48, 49. 50, 51, 52.</head>
                  <item>Antenor</item>
                  <item>Antiphus</item>
                  <item>Priamus</item>
                  <item>Panthous</item>
                  <item>Heliacon</item>
                  <item>Idaeus</item>
                  <item>Astyanax</item>
                  <item>Polymnestor</item>
                  <item>Diephobus</item>
                  <item>Lacedemon</item>
                  <item>Empedocles</item>
                  <item>Ulyſſes</item>
                  <item>Evalthe</item>
                  <item>Lethe</item>
                  <item>Cocles</item>
                  <item>Tiridates</item>
                  <item>Idea</item>
                  <item>Hippia</item>
                  <item>Affinis</item>
                  <item>Philomela</item>
                  <item>Leucippe</item>
                  <item>Danae</item>
                  <item>Maerula</item>
                  <item>Judith</item>
                  <item>Libythea</item>
                  <item>Eucharis</item>
                  <item>Genutia</item>
                  <item>Amaryllis</item>
                  <item>Caſtalia</item>
                  <item>Scylla</item>
                  <item>Cacta</item>
                  <item>Octavius</item>
                  <item>Pyrrhus</item>
                  <item>Menetho</item>
                  <item>Arceſilaus</item>
                  <item>Blandina</item>
                  <item>Liberia</item>
                  <item>Phegea</item>
                  <item>Fatima</item>
                  <item>Thyelia</item>
                  <item>Nero</item>
                  <item>Gnidia</item>
                  <item>Hiarba</item>
                  <item>Iſis</item>
                  <item>Phorcys</item>
                  <item>Eribotes</item>
                  <item>Iſidore</item>
                  <item>Cydippe</item>
                  <item>Dirce</item>
                  <item>Eurinome</item>
                  <item>Hippona</item>
                  <item>Cyane<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </item>
                  <item>Coenobita</item>
                  <item>Cocalia</item>
                  <item>Sophia</item>
                  <item>Auge</item>
                  <item>Baldus</item>
                  <item>Periander</item>
                  <item>Allica</item>
                  <item>Obrinus</item>
                  <item>Liria</item>
                  <item>Crantor</item>
                  <item>Pann</item>
                  <item>Pindarus</item>
                  <item>Vulcanus</item>
                  <item>Chiton</item>
                  <item>Herodotus</item>
                  <item>Pythagoras</item>
                  <item>Florus</item>
                  <item>Liſias</item>
                  <item>Sophocles</item>
                  <item>Jarbas</item>
                  <item>Thales</item>
                  <item>Meliboeus</item>
                  <item>Tyrtaeus</item>
                  <item>Xenophon</item>
                  <item>Achaeus</item>
                  <item>Phorbas</item>
                  <item>Strephon</item>
                  <item>Aeolus</item>
                  <item>Pericles</item>
                  <item>Philippus</item>
                  <item>Thucydides</item>
                  <item>Petronius</item>
                  <item>Regulus</item>
                  <item>Lucanus</item>
                  <item>Tarquinus</item>
                  <item>Aemulius</item>
                  <item>Numitor</item>
                  <item>Plinius</item>
                  <item>Plato</item>
                  <item>Hippocrates</item>
                  <item>Theocritus</item>
                  <item>Parrhaſius</item>
                  <item>Bibulus</item>
                  <item>Hylax</item>
                  <item>Coenus</item>
                  <item>Livius</item>
                  <item>Romulus</item>
                  <item>Ptolemaeus</item>
                  <item>Ovidius</item>
                  <item>Curius</item>
                  <item>Propertius</item>
                  <item>Tibullus</item>
                  <item>Augias</item>
                  <item>Origines</item>
                  <item>Plutargus</item>
                  <item>Epictetus</item>
                  <item>Chemnis</item>
                  <item>Thrax</item>
                  <item>Mithridates</item>
                  <item>Thraſibulus</item>
                  <item>Jovianus</item>
                  <item>Salvianus</item>
                  <item>Galenus</item>
                  <item>Catullus</item>
                  <item>Spio</item>
                  <item>Ennius</item>
                  <item>Polybius</item>
                  <item>Zeleucus</item>
                  <item>Orcus</item>
                  <item>Buſiris</item>
                  <item>Celſus</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>PHALAENA. Pl. 53, 54.</head>
                  <item>Mineus</item>
                  <item>ſcalaris</item>
                  <item>ſanguinolenta</item>
                  <item>figura</item>
                  <item>ſtrigata</item>
                  <item>hieroglyphica</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>NEUROPTERA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>MYRMELEON. Pl. 55.</head>
                  <item>Pardalis</item>
                  <item>punctatum</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>HYMENOPTERA</head>
               <list>
                  <head>CHRYSIS. Pl. 56.</head>
                  <item>faſciata</item>
                  <item>ſplendida</item>
                  <item>oculata</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>VESPA. Pl. 57.</head>
                  <item>cincta</item>
                  <item>petiolata</item>
                  <item>arcuata</item>
                  <item>Macaenſis</item>
                  <item>tepida</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>APIS.</head>
                  <item>violacea</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>DIPTERA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>DIOPSIS. Pl. 58.</head>
                  <item>Ichneumonea</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:0591200400:133"/>
            <head>INDEX ACCORDING TO THE ENTOMOLOGIA SYSTEMATICA OF FABRICIUS.</head>
            <div type="class">
               <head>CLASS 1. ELEUTERATA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>2.</hi> Scaraboeus.</head>
                  <item>Atlas</item>
                  <item>ſpinifex</item>
                  <item>Miliaris</item>
                  <item>Koenigii</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>76.</hi> Cetonia.</head>
                  <item>Hiſtrio</item>
                  <item>Caerulea</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>19.</hi> Carabus.</head>
                  <item>2-maculatus</item>
                  <item>6-maculatus.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>78.</hi> Bupreſtis.</head>
                  <item>ſternicornis</item>
                  <item>Chryſis</item>
                  <item>Aenea</item>
                  <item>4-maculata</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>61.</hi> Cerocoma. (Pauſus <hi>Linn. &amp; Fabr.</hi> Sys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tema Eleute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorum.)</head>
                  <item>denticornis</item>
                  <item>thoracicus</item>
                  <item>Fichtelii</item>
                  <item>pilicornis</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>102.</hi> Curculio.</head>
                  <item>Regalis</item>
                  <item>Palmarum</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="class">
               <head>CLASS 2. ULONATA.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>120.</hi> Mantis. (Phasma Ent. Syst. Supp.)</head>
                  <item>gigas</item>
                  <item>viridis</item>
                  <item>ſiccifolia</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>124.</hi> Locusta.</head>
                  <item>Amboinenſis</item>
                  <item>citrirolia</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Genus <hi>125.</hi> Gryllus.</head>
                  <item>reticulatus</item>
                  <item>punctatus</item>
                  <item>monſtroſus</item>
               </list>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>ORDER 9. GLOSSATA.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>186.</hi> Papilio.</head>
                     <item>*<hi>Equites Trojani.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Antenor</item>
                           <item>Antiphus</item>
                           <item>Priamus</item>
                           <item>Panthous</item>
                           <item>Heliacon</item>
                           <item>Idaeus</item>
                           <item>Aſtyanax</item>
                           <item>Polymneſtor</item>
                           <item>Deiphobus</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>**<hi>Equites Achivi.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Ulyſſes</item>
                           <item>Curius</item>
                           <item>Lacedemon</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>***<hi>Feſtiva.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Evalthe</item>
                           <item>Eurinome</item>
                           <item>Philomela</item>
                           <item>Hippia</item>
                           <item>affinis</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>****<hi>Nymphales.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Pyrrhus</item>
                           <item>Tiridates</item>
                           <item>Cocles</item>
                           <item>Periander</item>
                           <item>Empedocles</item>
                           <item>Octavius</item>
                           <item>Iſis</item>
                           <item>Eribotes</item>
                           <item>Iſidore</item>
                           <item>Phorcys</item>
                           <item>Lethe</item>
                           <item>Fatima</item>
                           <item>Menetho</item>
                           <item>Cydippe</item>
                           <item>Cyane</item>
                           <item>Cacta</item>
                           <item>Dirce</item>
                           <item>Hiarba</item>
                           <item>Blandina</item>
                           <item>Phegea</item>
                           <item>Gnidia</item>
                           <item>Thyelia</item>
                           <item>Liberia</item>
                           <item>Arceſilaus</item>
                           <item>Hippona</item>
                           <item>Nero</item>
                           <item>Obrinus</item>
                           <item>Crantor</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>******<hi>Parnassii.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Idea</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>*******<hi>Danai.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Amaryllis</item>
                           <item>Caſtalia</item>
                           <item>Scylla</item>
                           <item>Leucippe</item>
                           <item>Danae</item>
                           <item>Maerula</item>
                           <item>Judith</item>
                           <item>Libythea</item>
                           <item>Eucharis</item>
                           <item>Genutia</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>********<hi>Satyri.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Baldus</item>
                           <item>Liria</item>
                           <item>Allica</item>
                           <item>Coenobita</item>
                           <item>Auge</item>
                           <item>Sophia</item>
                           <item>Cocalia</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>187.</hi> Heſperia.</head>
                     <item>*<hi>Rurales.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Pann</item>
                           <item>Pindarus</item>
                           <item>Vulcanus</item>
                           <item>Chiton</item>
                           <item>Herodotus</item>
                           <item>Pythagoras</item>
                           <item>Florus</item>
                           <item>Liſias</item>
                           <item>Sophocles</item>
                           <item>Jarbas</item>
                           <item>Thales</item>
                           <item>Meliboeus</item>
                           <item>Tyrtaeus</item>
                           <item>Xenophon</item>
                           <item>Achaeus</item>
                           <item>Phorbas</item>
                           <item>Strephon</item>
                           <item>Aeolus</item>
                           <item>Pericles</item>
                           <item>Philippus</item>
                           <item>Thucydides</item>
                           <item>Petronius</item>
                           <item>Regulus</item>
                           <item>Lucanus</item>
                           <item>Tarquinus</item>
                           <item>Aemulius</item>
                           <item>Numitor</item>
                           <item>Plinius</item>
                           <item>Plato</item>
                           <item>Hippocrates</item>
                           <item>Theocritus</item>
                           <item>Parrhaſius</item>
                           <item>Bibulus</item>
                           <item>Hylax</item>
                           <item>Coenus</item>
                           <item>Livius</item>
                           <item>Romulus</item>
                           <item>Ptolemaeus</item>
                           <item>Ovidius</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>**Urbicolae.
<list>
                           <item>Propertius</item>
                           <item>Tibullus</item>
                           <item>Augias</item>
                           <item>Origines</item>
                           <item>Plutargus</item>
                           <item>Epictetus</item>
                           <item>Chemnis</item>
                           <item>Thrax</item>
                           <item>Mithridates</item>
                           <item>Thraſibulus</item>
                           <item>Jovianus</item>
                           <item>Salvianus</item>
                           <item>Galenus</item>
                           <item>Catullus</item>
                           <item>Spio</item>
                           <item>Ennius</item>
                           <item>Polybius</item>
                           <item>Zeleucus</item>
                           <item>Orcus</item>
                           <item>Buſiris</item>
                           <item>Celſus</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                           <head>Genus <hi>191.</hi> Bombyx.</head>
                           <item>ſanguinolenta</item>
                           <item>figura</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                           <head>Genus <hi>192.</hi> Coſſus.</head>
                           <item>Mineus</item>
                           <item>ſcalaris</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                           <head>Genus <hi>194.</hi> Noctua.</head>
                           <item>ſtrigata</item>
                           <item>hieroglyphica</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>ORDER SYNISTATA.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>133.</hi> Myrmeleon.</head>
                     <item>pardalis</item>
                     <item>punctatum</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>ORDER PIEZATA.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>147.</hi> Chryſis.</head>
                     <item>faſciata</item>
                     <item>ſplendida</item>
                     <item>oculata</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>151.</hi> Veſpa.</head>
                     <item>cincta</item>
                     <item>petiolata</item>
                     <item>arcuata</item>
                     <item>Macenſis</item>
                     <item>tepida</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>158.</hi> Apis.</head>
                     <item>violacea</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>ORDER RYNGOTA.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>201.</hi> Fulgora.</head>
                     <item>Pyrorhynchus</item>
                     <item>Hyalinata</item>
                     <item>feſtiva</item>
                     <item>lineata</item>
                     <item>pallida</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>204.</hi> Cicada.</head>
                     <item>Indica</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Genus <hi>213.</hi> Cimex.</head>
                     <item>nigripes</item>
                     <item>Papilloſus</item>
                     <item>cruciatus</item>
                     <item>mactans</item>
                     <item>uniguttatus</item>
                     <item>viridis</item>
                     <item>ſerratus</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>ORDER ANTLIATA.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Diopsis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ichneumonea</item>
                  </list>
                  <note place="bottom">T. Benaley, Printer, Bolt-court, Fleet-street.</note>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
