<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Critical reflections upon the emmenology of Dr. Freind. By Dr. Le Tellier, ... Translated from the French</title>
            <title>Réflexions critiques sur l'emménologie. English</title>
            <author>Le Tellier, médecin de Peronne.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>82 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-11">2012 November</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004811117</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T149712</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW108587846</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K115214.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3308587846</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECMS</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">0650600600</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Critical reflections upon the emmenology of Dr. Freind. By Dr. Le Tellier, ... Translated from the French</title>
                  <title>Réflexions critiques sur l'emménologie. English</title>
                  <author>Le Tellier, médecin de Peronne.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>viii,73,[3]p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and sold by J. Watson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1731.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a half-title and a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the National Library of Medicine.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT149712.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:0650600600:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CRITICAL REFLECTIONS UPON THE EMMENOLOGY OF Dr. <hi>FREIND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY Dr. LE TELLIER, a <hi>French</hi> Phyſician.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated from the</hi> FRENCH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rinted and Sold by J. WATSON, over-againſt <hi>Hungerford-Market</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> and by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> 1731.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Price One Shilling and Six-pence.]</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="v" facs="tcp:0650600600:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE beſt Preface, in my Mind, that can be made to this Book is, a Quotation out of itſelf, p. 59. where the Author, as in a Sort of Corollary, drawn from his own Reflections, ſays:</p>
            <p>
               <q>"From the Reflections that have been hitherto made, it may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd, that 'tis by no Means, an indifferent Matter in Practice, to
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:0650600600:3"/>adopt indifferently, the Syſtem of the Rupture of the Veſſels, or that of the Intruſion of the Blood into the lymphatick Canals: It is of the higheſt Conſequence, to chuſe either the one or the other, to liſt on one Side or the other, and to appear more than ordinarily engaged or concern'd therein. If the Diſpute here was only about ſome inſipid, barren Point of Speculation, amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing perhaps to the Curious, but altogether uſeleſs, and without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence on Practice, thoſe who regard Things only as they are uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, might perhaps ſlumber over
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:0650600600:4"/>it: But as our Buſineſs is here about a capital Point, which affects and concerns Practice to the higheſt Degree; ſince in the two Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſes the Manner of Cure is quite different; this ought to awake the Attention of all Practitioners, inſpire them with an extraordinary Reliſh for the preſent Subject, and rouze them totally out of their Indifference."</q>
            </p>
            <p>And this ſhould, indeed, rouze out of their Indifference, not only all Gentlemen of the Faculty, but even, methinks, ſhould tempt all Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who are (as all Gentlemen
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:0650600600:5"/>ſhould be) Men of Learning, to ſtudy this Point, on purpoſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern themſelves in this Controverſy, as it regards the Well-being of the Fair Sex, the lovely Fountain whence, under Heaven, we all have our Being; Women! to promote whoſe Health and Happineſs, the Man that is not ambitious, is a Monſter! the Object of all Mankind's juſt Deteſtation!</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:0650600600:6"/>
            <head>CRITICAL REFLECTIONS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>OMEN are ſubject to ſuch regular Evacuations, that 'tis very hard to account for, and aſſign the Cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Some have been of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that Nature, by this Flux, propos'd to purge the Blood of the Sex from the Impurities it contracts, thereby to render them more fruitful. Others, by obſerving the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Blood which Women in Health <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe in their Courſes, have been perſuaded, that 'tis ſo far from being an Excrement, or Maſs of Filth, that, on the contrary, it is a moſt pure Blood, and of Conſequence, very fit and proper to nouriſh the <hi>Foetus.</hi> So much for the Final Cauſe, or End, for which theſe Flowings ſeem ordain'd.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:0650600600:7"/>
            <p>As for the Efficient Cauſe, the moving, or mechanick Principle, which, in the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Body produces theſe Effects, Men do not agree much better about this, than about the Final Cauſe, and are not much leſs divided in their Opinions, as to the Manner in which this Evacuation is made, than they are concerning the End, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and Deſign, which Nature may have in procuring it.</p>
            <p>Some Authors, much devoted to Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culture, and accuſtomed to trample under Foot ſuch immediate Cauſes as they have juſt at Hand, Objects that are too plain, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar, palpable, and natural for them to look upon but with Contempt, as Things common, ordinary, trivial; theſe Men erect the Moon for the efficient Cauſe, and make her abſolute Miſtreſs of the Courſes in Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. Others, ſomewhat more indulgent, and better diſpoſed towards ſublunary Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, have taken Care to make Cavities in the Womb, where they lodge in Ambuſcade a certain Ferment, or Leaven, which they have order'd to ſally regularly thence every Month, to attack the Blood in its Paſſage, put the Humours all in Combuſtion, diſturb the Harmony of the Motions, the Exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Functions, and, in fine, to play the little Devil, that, full of Malice, bent upon Mutiny, and breathing nought but wild Sedition, is never at Reſt, nor lays down his Arms, till he has rais'd in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:0650600600:8"/>Blood a tumultuous Agitation, a diſorderly Efferveſcence, a more than ordinary Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, and laid under Fire and Gore all the Region of the <hi>Matrix,</hi> which he makes a Field of Battle, that is, for ſome Days, to be quite overflown with Blood, and as the Object of his Rage, to appear alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether diſmal, and in Diſorder. They who judge in the moſt ſimple, and moſt natural Way, and, of courſe, the neareſt to Truth, are thoſe who, after the famous <hi>Galen,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge for Cauſe and Mover of this Flowing, the <hi>Plethora,</hi> or Abundance of Blood, among whom, we muſt confeſs, that Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Phyſician, has moſt diſtinguiſh'd himſelf, in a Treatiſe he has publiſh'd upon this Subject; which, tho' it be not exempt from Miſtakes (as we ſhall obſerve in the Sequel of this) is, however, in the main, a valuable Piece, both for the ſingular Clearneſs that ſhines every where throughout the Performance (which makes its principal Merit) and for the great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of very excellent Reaſonings, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Obſervations, that we ſee there diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play'd in the faireſt Light. If one will but vouchſafe to ſtoop a little, to ſeek for Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the ſublunary Empire, and not to be over-ſmitten with the Charms of the Moon, and dazzled with her mighty Power; in fine, if we'll be impartial Judges, we ſhall eaſily ſide with <hi>Galen,</hi> and without Heſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, give to the Syſtem of the <hi>Plethora</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:0650600600:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:0650600600:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:0650600600:11"/>(which has ſince been ſo illuſtrated by Dr. <hi>Freind</hi>) the Juſtice due to it, and the Preference it deſerves.</p>
            <p>Women, in their Courſes, do but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their Superfluity; and, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of this, it is enough to obſerve, that after they have had theſe Flowings long enough, for Inſtance, the Space of Five Years, they are no ways diſorder'd thereby, but, on the contrary, they continue always alike, hold the very ſame State, enjoy the ſame Vigour, and, if you weigh 'em, you'll find 'em no lighter; and yet, in this Time, they have loſt a Hundred Pound of pureſt Blood; as Loſs! that ſhould not only weaken them, but conſume almoſt their whole Subſtance, and reduce them to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, were it any thing elſe but Superflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Now, if Women have this Redundan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Blood, this is what we call the <hi>Plethora,</hi> and the Matter we are ſeeking. There is therefore this <hi>Plethora,</hi> or Redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy of Blood in Women; that is prov'd: But how, and by what Means is this <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thora</hi> contracted in the Perſons of the Sex? This is what we now muſt unfold in two or three Words; <hi>Women tranſpire leſs than Men;</hi> which is prov'd by four Reflections: 1ſt. Their Bodies are more weak and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; the Parts thereof leſs robuſt; the Texture of the Fibres more fine and ſoft, and leſs proper for oſcillatory Motions; and, in fine, leſs vigorous; witneſs their gentle
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:0650600600:12"/>and languiſhing Pulſe; which ſhews us plain, that the peaceable Blood, moving eaſy in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts Courſe, and ſlowly rowling through the drowſy Veſſels, runs not rapidly to the Glands, neither towards the Skin, nor elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; ſo that the Secretion of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours cannot very much be promoted: Add to this, that the Juices, ſeparated in the Strainers, are not in Haſte to iſſue; becauſe the ſecreting Pipes have not a ſyſtaltick Virtue ſtrong enough to ſqueeze 'em thro', <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd drive 'em forth with Precipitation. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dly.</hi> The Veſſels in Women are of a ſtraiter Orifice. Now, as the Secretion of Humours is more or leſs abundant, according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the Strainers are bigger or ſmaller, and the Blood more or leſs animated, it follows of Courſe, that, the Motion of the Blood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing leſs ſtrong at the ſame time that the Pipes or Organs of Secretion are more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>treight in the Woman, the Secretion of the Humours muſt be perform'd more ſlowly. <hi>3dly.</hi> Women are of a moiſt Temperament, as plainly appears by the Suppleneſs and Softneſs of their Skin; now, if the Fibres are ſo ſoak'd in Humidity, 'tis becauſe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave not Vigour enough to rid themſelves of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; for that Body muſt be dry which expels with Force the Juices that come into it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd diſcharges a great Part of its Moiſture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Tranſpiration, which is the more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant in Proportion as the Oſcillation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Veſſels is the more vigorous. <hi>4thly.</hi> The
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:0650600600:13"/>Fair Sex is not ſo active, has not ſo much Exerciſe; they lead an idle, indolent, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentary Life, which does not much excite Tranſpiration: 'Tis true, we ſee ſome Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men robuſt, and ingag'd in hard Labour Theſe, becauſe they are as ſtrong as Men and have a manly Complection and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, are call'd Virago's; and ſuch are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the uſual Courſes of Women We have alſo ſeen Women-Singers an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dancers exempted from theſe. But here may be objected what Dr. <hi>Andry</hi> advance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in his excellent Theſis upon Exerciſe, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Womens frequent Tattle may ſupply the Want of other Bodily Labour; and, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, hence it comes, that Women, chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering much more than Men, have leſs Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for other Excerciſe. We muſt ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that Tranſpiration is aſſiſted by the Motion of the Voice in Converſation; yet theſe Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are not ſo conſiderable, as not to leave ſufficient Matter for Womens Courſes. Thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is the <hi>Plethora</hi> bred in the Sex; whenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nature is obliged to prepare a Diſcharge for the ſuperfluous Blood, whoſe Sally, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeveral Reaſons, is thro' the Womb; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this is the Part where the Blood more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully iſſues, becauſe of the great Number of Blood-Veſſels, which, being wound and interwoven together, ſpread all over and through the Subſtance, in a Thouſand Warps and Turnings, after a ſerpentine Manner; and that which the more conveys
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:0650600600:14"/>the Blood this Way, is the Trunk of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſcending <hi>Aorta,</hi> which is remarkably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rger in Women than in Men, to the End <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat, the Blood flowing more abundantly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ownwards, the <hi>Foetus</hi> may thereby be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etter nouriſhed, and the eaſier thruſt out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the Muſcles in Time of Child-Birth. Now, as much Propenſion as the Blood has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deſcend towards the <hi>Matrix,</hi> ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as it the greater Difficulty to return from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ence; for thither it tends, through the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rteries, which jirk it pretty faſt along, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d the more readily, as the Blood of itſelf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y its own Weight, concurs to the Motion: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut it returns through the Veins, which have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot the like Force to ſhove it, beſides the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſiſting Clog of its own Weight, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey have to conquer; ſo that 'tis always <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Diſpoſition to recoil, ſuſpended as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Veſſels which labour to make it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe; and which, to increaſe the Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, have not ſo much as a Place of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rve, to ſuſtain it in its March; and don't <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pply it with Suckers to facilitate its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inful Journey. For this alſo is a Point to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> obſerv'd, that the Veins of the Womb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave no Valves; ſo that the Blood has a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eal of Difficulty to gather in this <hi>Viſcus;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d, of Conſequence, has the like Difficulty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> paſs through the Conduits that there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rminate. Here it is that I am obliged to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffer in Opinion with Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Manner of explaining this Paſſage; he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:0650600600:15"/>pretends, that, to make way for the Blood to eſcape, the Arteries muſt break in their Extremities, that is, towards theſe Parts where they take the Name of <hi>Capillaries;</hi> he undertakes to prove this Rupture by Principles deduced from the Mathematicks whence he draws Concluſions for his Purpoſe and, in the Manner he goes about it, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeems to reaſon very ſecurely, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vance nothing but what ſeems infallible an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> undoubted; and his Argument has all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Air of a Demonſtration, victorious and un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>exceptionable. A Geometrician, who was t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prove, that all the Angles of a Triangle ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> equal to two Right ones, and that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Tangent touches the Circle but in on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Point, would not go more boldly about i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nor with more Confidence. At the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Time, the Doctor's Demonſtration is fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from Geometrical; and the Geometrica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Certainty will, perhaps, be rather found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my Side. He advances two Propoſition eſtabliſh'd by Mathematicians: <hi>1ſt.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Force of a Body increaſes, as it acquir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> either more Bulk, or more Swiftneſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> both together, <hi>2dly.</hi> If the Force of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Body is ſuperior to that of the Obſtac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which it encounters, this Obſtacle will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſurmounted. Whence he concludes, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Force of the Blood augments in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Plethora,</hi> becauſe there is together, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> once, both more Bulk and more Velocity more Bulk, becauſe the <hi>Plethora</hi> conſiſts
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:0650600600:16"/>abundance of Blood; more Velocity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auſe, ſays he, as there is abundance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lood, provided it be not ſlow and viſcous, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t emits the greater Quantity of Spirits, which flow to the Heart and the Arteries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he more briskly to animate them, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edouble their Contractions. Now, the Veſſels are to be conſider'd as Obſtacles that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inder the. Blood from extravaſing; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch they continue to be, whilſt they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uperior or equal in Force to the Blood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey contain within them; but, when they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome to be over-power'd, and the Strength <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Blood is increas'd to that Degree, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to conquer their Reſiſtance, they ſtraight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ield, are readily broken, and open a free <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſſage through the Breaches of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unicks. Now, the Veſſels the eaſieſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tteſt to yield, are thoſe of the Womb; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich, being the moſt attack'd, are leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble to make Reſiſtance; and to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>end perfectly well how they give way, one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeds only to take Notice, that the <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hora,</hi> at the ſame Time it augments the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orce of the Blood, weakens the Reſiſtance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Veſſels; for, ſays Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>equence of the big Volume of Blood that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eighs upon the Veins and Arteries, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly on their Sides, but perpendicular, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecauſe of the winding Diſpoſition of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſels, which, by their Turnings and Counter-turnings, in their Folds and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olds, expoſe their Angles and Corners to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:0650600600:17"/>the direct and perpendicular Impulſe of the Fluid: By Means, I ſay, of this big Volume of Blood, the Veſſels are ſtretch'd and dilated, and thereby the Fibres that compoſe theſe Veſſels leave an Opening be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt 'em; ſo that their Texture being leſs cloſe and firm, and more preſs'd upon, they are more diſpos'd to ſeparate, and yield to the Attack of the Blood, if it juſt ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, that when they are at their weakeſt, the Blood has more Force than ordinary, as it truly has; ſince the <hi>Plethora</hi> gives it more Strength, as we have prov'd, both by Reaſon of the Blood's greater Bulk and greater Velocity: The Blood therefore will take the Advantage of the Veſſels diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous Situation, which, being violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtretch'd, widen'd, and preſs'd, loſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great deal of their Reſiſtance, and can offer but a weak Bar againſt the impetuous Force and Impulſe of the Blood. Wherefore, the Barrier being ſurmounted, becauſe the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of the Veſſels being widen'd, and but weakly helping each other, nor able to make any great Struggle againſt thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Diſunion, there is but little to hinder the Fluid from breaking its Priſon, from tearing their Canals, and extravaſing; the more eaſily, as theſe winding Canals, that make a Thouſand Circumvolutions, are more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the Strokes of the Blood, being be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſides deſtitute of the Muſcles and the Fat to uphold, maintain and defend 'em againſt the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:0650600600:18"/>Rupture: They muſt therefore yield to the Impulſe of the Blood, and be broken to give it way to eſcape.</p>
            <p>This is the Explication of Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> and one can't help agreeing with him in this Part of it, that the <hi>Plethora</hi> contributes much to the Monthly Courſes; at the ſame Time we muſt alſo own, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all theſe Advantages which we have juſt now attributed to the Blood, yet it ought to be contain'd in a juſt Meaſure, and reſtrain'd to certain Bounds. We muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs with <hi>Etmuller</hi> and <hi>Riverius,</hi> that an exceſſive <hi>Plethora</hi> is more likely to ſuppreſs, than to excite the Courſes; nay, we may further aſſert, that this is the moſt uſual, and almoſt the general Cauſe of theſe Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions that afflict the Sex. The two fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Phyſicians, we have juſt now quoted, account for theſe Suppreſſions by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Redundance of Blood, which they make the Cauſe thereof, much in the ſame Manner as we impute the Stoppage of Urine to the too great Quantity of Liquor gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Bladder; which Anology is judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious enough; 'tis true, it is not exact, it runs not upon all Four; becauſe (according to the Remark of Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> who refutes it) the Bladder is much better furniſh'd than the Blood-Veſſels are, being fortified with a Tunick firm and fleſhy, too ſtrong to be torn and broken by the Affluence of Urine, which coming there to lodge but in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:0650600600:19"/>a ſlow, indolent Manner, without any Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuoſity, is not able to make any great Havock there; all that it does in this Caſe, is ſo to ſtretch the Fibres of the Bladder, that they cannot come to themſelves again, and have not Freedom enough to contract in order to expel the Urine. That which alſo contributes a great deal to the Stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page is, that the <hi>Sphincter</hi> of the Bladder, to wit, the Muſcle that ſtops the Paſſage thereof, has, in this Caſe, all the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and remains Maſter of the Field of Battle, becauſe its Antagoniſt, namely, the Muſcular Tunick, which ſerves to drive out the Urine, being ſtretch'd, dilated, conſtrain'd and hinder'd, has not Strength enough to counterbalance the <hi>Sphincter,</hi> much leſs to over-power it. In this reſpect, I ſhall believe the Parallel betwixt the two Stoppages to be imperfect; but 'tis juſt at leaſt in this, that it compares a Blood, which iſſues not from the Veſſels, becauſe, oppreſſing them by its Weight, it leaves them not Play enough to expel it; I ſay, as it compares this Blood to the Urine that remains in the Bladder, becauſe being there too abundant, it ſo dilates the Bladder, that it cannot contract to drive it out. On both Sides we ſee a ſuper-abundant Fluid; a Solid groaning under the Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Super-abundance; and on both Sides is obſerv'd a Canal or Reſervior, choak'd with its Liquor, which it is forc'd
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:0650600600:20"/>to retain, becauſe it is depriv'd of the Means to diſcharge it; inaſmuch as this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iquor, by its exceſſive Quantity, triumphs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver the Spring of the moving Fibres, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich, by being more ſtretch'd, loſe all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir Power and Play. Therefore our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o Authors Compariſon is, in this Senſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery juſt; and the Reaſons we ſhall alledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Sequel will help to ſet off the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ntage of it, and render its Validity the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore ſenſible.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> pretends, that the <hi>Plethora</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n never, of itſelf, cauſe ſuch a Suppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, and does never cauſe it, unleſs when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>in'd with a Viſcoſity and Slowneſs of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ood; for, ſays he, the Particles of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ood being incorporated, and cloſe link'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gether, form ſuch a groſs Body as can by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> means be inſinuated into the Capillaries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here, of Courſe, it forms an Obſtruction: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow, theſe Veſſels being ſtopt, thro' which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Blood us'd to paſs, it remains ſhut up in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e bigger Veſſels, which are too ſtrong to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve it Vent through the Rupture of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unicks.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time, according to this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>or's Reaſons, one might demonſtrate, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſe Veſſels, big and ſtrong as they are, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght to crack at laſt, and be broken. For, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the big Veſſels are more robuſt than the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>all, they are alſo attack'd by a greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>antity of Blood. In the natural State, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey are counter-balanced, and in an <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>librium</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:0650600600:21"/>with the Fluid; but, in the preſent Caſe, the Fluid muſt get the better, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it augments in Strength, by reaſon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> its Bulk being ſwoln and re-inforced from the Reflux of the Juices that ſpring out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Capillaries; whilſt the Veſſels extremel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſurcharged, loſe their Power, and canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hinder the Interſtices of the extended an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuffering Fibres from being forc'd by the Af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fluence of the Blood that ſeeks an Out-le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and, by its exorbitant Maſs, has Powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> enough to make itſelf one thro' the Dyke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whoſe Reſiſtance is diminiſhed in proportio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as the Strength of the Blood is encreaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> This is what might be maintain'd on o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Author's Syſtem, and by his own Proof Among Phyſicians, there are ſome who ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plain the monthly Courſes by the Ruptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Veſſels; others again take a diffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rent Road; but it ſeems as if People we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> only dreaming over this Point, and ſhew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an Indifference that does not appear to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> well grounded: Yet, as we have here eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bliſh'd the Sentiment of Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is the moſt in vogue, it may not be ami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſay ſomething of another Opinion, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tho' leſs common, does not fail, neverth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> leſs, ſtrongly to engage us in its Favou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The Blood of Women being, for the Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons we have declar'd, liable to gather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Veſſels, it ſhould, of Courſe, happe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the Blood tending particularly to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lower Parts, and the Veins having no Valve
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:0650600600:22"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Arteries may bring more Blood than can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e return'd by the Veins. Wherefore, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eins, being fill'd to the Top at a certain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me, cannot receive the Blood that is ſtili <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought afreſh to them from the Arteries: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Blood being once ſhut out from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eins, is ſtill leſs liable to return from hence it came, whither then will it go? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat will become of it? Thither, no doubt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here it finds leaſt Reſiſtance, and that is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Side of the Lymphaticks; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g only made to admit the <hi>Lympha,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nvey it to the <hi>Matrix,</hi> in order to moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en and lubricate this <hi>Viſcus,</hi> are oblig'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yield to the Torrent, to an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Extenſion of their Texture, and ſuffer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>olence in their Diameter, in order to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ive this ſuperfluous Blood, puſh'd out from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Arteries, and rejected by the Veins. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow, as the Lymphaticks muſt terminate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome Iſſue, the Canals, or excretory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ucts, deſtin'd to the Diſcharge of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ympha,</hi> ſerve here to give an Out-let to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Blood, and diſcharge it.</p>
            <p>This mechanical Account, is it not more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſy, more ſimple, more plain and ſatisfactory? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d does it not more Honour to Nature, than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Syſtem of the Rupture of the Veſſels? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is a conſtant Maxim with Philoſophers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at Nature does every thing by Ways the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt ſimple, and leaſt expenſive. Now, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k, on which of theſe two Sides it coſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e moſt? In the firſt Place, does it not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:0650600600:23"/>impair the Veſſels much more, by making them ſo often to ſuffer a Solution of their Continuity? Is not this Hurt done to the Subſtance in its ſolid Parts too dear a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe? and the frequent tearing of the vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Tunicks, which muſt every Month be broken, is not this paying too great a Price for the Exit of this Portion of ſuperfluou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> troubleſome Blood? But by the other Way how will it coſt ſo dear? Only a little En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of the Bounds of the lymphatic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Arteries, a little Straining of their Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which is far from making ſuch Havoc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as this Rupture does, yet, at once, does al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Buſineſs. But let us carry this Point <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> little further. Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> pretends to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate how the <hi>Plethora</hi> procures th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Flux. He has Recourſe to the Force <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Blood, which over-powers the For<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Veſſels; and, to eſtabliſh in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Blood this Superiority, he ſays, that the Blood encreaſes in its Maſs and Velocity while the Reſiſtance of the Veſſels dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes; becauſe their Fibres being ſtretch and widen'd, are thereby depriv'd of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtrict Union and Connection, in which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts their Force. The Author admits i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Blood a conſiderable Velocity, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, at the ſame Time, that the Veſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are ſtretch'd and reſtrain'd as if the Swift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Blood did not proceed, from its being ſo briskly jerk'd, beaten and puſh forward, by the powerful Oſcillation of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:0650600600:24"/>Veſſels, which being ſtretch'd and reſtrain'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re not able to puſh the Fluid with ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igour; whence it neceſſarily follows, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Fluid muſt loſe of its Velocity, inſtead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f gaining more, as the Author pretends. Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> would have avoided this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>exity, had he taken Care to obſerve the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oving Force of the Blood, and had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain'd himſelf a little more particularly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n it. Rejecting, as he does, the Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of Fermentation, it is to be preſum'd he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bſcribes to the Oſcillation of the Solids, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in Truth he ſeems to hint in ſeveral Parts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f his Book. Now, this Syſtem makes the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gitation, or progreſſive Motion of the Flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, to depend upon the ſyſtaltick Virtue of he Solid, whoſe Spring being more or leſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nimated, makes the Blood and all the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours move with more or leſs Precipitation. This is a Principle which we think cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e denied by Dr. <hi>Freind;</hi> and yet this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iple makes againſt himſelf, becauſe thence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> follows, that in Proportion as the Veſſels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe of their Eaſe and Liberty, the Blood, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar from taking the Advantage of their Weakneſs, to attack and break them, as it does in the Senſe of this Author, does it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf abate of its Impulſe, and conſequently of its Force, and ſo ſhares in the Feebleneſs of the Veſſels, inſtead of triumphing over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. This carries us yet farther.</p>
            <p>This Swiftneſs of the Fluid being a pure Effect of the ſtrong Vibration of the Solid,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:0650600600:25"/>which at once both contains and chaſes it, is not a Portion of the Force of the Blood, but of the Force of the Veſſels, which, without doubt, are ſtrong enough to defend themſelves againſt the Irruption and Inſult of a Humour that has no other Arms than what they vouchſafe to lend it, and which would remain dormant, lazy, languiſhing, if the Veſſels were not ſo kind as to put it in Motion. Here now, pray what has the Blood to boaſt of, poor and beggarly in it ſelf! What has it, which it hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd? And if it has receiv'd all it hath, wherewith can it prevail? How can it have the Infolence to employ its Strength againſt thoſe that gave it, and turn its Arms to the Diſadvantage of thoſe that arm'd it? Hence we may plainly ſee, that the Blood having no Aſſiſtance but what it borrows, cannot thence take any Advantage againſt the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels; ſo that there only remains its own Maſs whence it can draw any Succour. But here viſibly falls our Author's Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for the Force of the Stroke, or of the Percuſſion, being infinitely greater than any Preſſure, as he himſelf ſays after <hi>Borelli, Vis actûs omni preſſione infinitò major eſt;</hi> and the Percuſſion being the Effect of the Velocity, which 'tis confeſs'd does not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the Blood's own Force, it conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently follows, that the Blood, to break the Veſſels, wants juſt that which is the moſt proper and conducive to this Effect; ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:0650600600:26"/>that the Force of the Percuſſion failing, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lood has no more Force, than from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſſure of its own Maſs; and this, 'tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow'd, is not ſo powerful by far as the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſſion. Whence, after all, one may judge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at <hi>Borelli</hi>'s Propoſition is falſe in one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enſe, and in the preſent Caſe may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed; for the Blood ſwiftly mov'd attacks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Veſſels, and yet it is prov'd, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orce of the Attack is leſs than that of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſure; becauſe the Preſſure comes from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Maſs, and the Maſs is properly that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich belongs to the Fluid: It is its own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oper Force, and it can do more with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Addition of one Degree of Maſs, than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith that of twenty extraordinary Degrees <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Swiftneſs; the Reaſon whereof is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. 'Tis, for that by its additional De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ree of Maſs, it weakens the Veſſel, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idening its Fibres, and rendering them leſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le to withſtand their Diſ-union, which it ever can do by its Swiftneſs, ſuppoſe it aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ented to what Degree you pleaſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re, the Force of the Preſſure, unaccompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y'd with that of the Percuſſion, is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Choice they have, who, after Dr. <hi>Friend,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>plain the Monthly Courſes by the Rupture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Veſſels; for, this being pre-ſuppos'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Blood can never be in too great a Maſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d the Exceſs of the <hi>Plethora</hi> can never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o any thing but Good: The Blood will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave the more Force, as it is the more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>undant and leſs hurried; for as ſoon as it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:0650600600:27"/>fails of its Swiftneſs, that will be a Sig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that the Veſſels have not Spring enough to puſh it vigorouſly; and, in this Caſe, the more Bulk it requires, the more it reſtrain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, the more it widens their Fibres, and puts them out of Condition to ſuſtain it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Weight, to ply to its Volume, and reſiſt it Power; can any thing be more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to him than this Situation? In this Syſtem let us examine how we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the Monthly Suppreſſions, and wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way we muſt proceed to remedy the ſame We are going to obſerve, that it is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different in Practice to make Choice eithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Rupture of the Veſſels, or of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>truſion of the Blood in to the Lymphaticks as one pleaſes; for theſe two Syſtems by no means agree; they offer for the Cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> quite different Views and contrary Indicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: It is then very important, heedfully to diſtinguiſh them; to chuſe one of them and to take great Care which of the two we chuſe, and to which of the two we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here. This is not to be done with Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as but too often happens, but very carefully, with the utmoſt Exactneſs, and after having maturely thought upon it When the Blood gathers, ſays the<note place="margin">Cap. 10.</note> Author the Pulſe then grows more ſtrong, mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lively, more quick, till the <hi>Plethora</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rais'd to the higheſt Degree; for there are certain Limits of Plenitude, beyond which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:0650600600:28"/>the Quantity of Blood cannot augment, without affecting and altering its Quality; <hi>Eſt enim certus quidam plenitudinis gradus, ultra quem, illaeſâ qualitate ſanguinis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugeri nequeat quantitas;</hi> for the <hi>Plethora</hi> cannot be long a gathering, without lackening the Pace of the Blood; <hi>Plethora enim diú nequit increſcere, quin comitem ſibi adſciſcat ſanguinis lentorem:</hi> Since, continues he, towards the Approach of the Flux, the Veſſels are ſtretch'd and dilated to the Degree that I have mentioned; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Quantity, and conſequently the Force of the Blood is increas'd almoſt a Tenth. If the Courſes fail twice ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Maſs of the Blood will be a Fifth Part augmented, unleſs the Flux be equall'd by ſome other Evacuations. Therefore, the Preſſures which the circulating Fluid makes upon the Sides of the Veſſels muſt augment in Proportion; which ſaid Preſſure the Veſſels cannot ſuſtain, without being ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put to it, labouring already under the the Load of the Blood that eſcap'd in the firſt Month; <hi>Adeoque eadem rations in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſcit ea, quâ latera vaſorum a fluido cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culante urgentur, Preſſio; quam a vaſis citra virium noxam ſuſtineri poſſe nemo credet, qui quam graviter ea ſub primae periodi incurſum laborent meminerit:</hi> The Slowneſs of the Blood may be ſuppoſed from its great Abundance, which ſwells ſo much, that the Veſſels, to what Degree ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:0650600600:29"/>they yield and ſtretch themſelves can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, without breaking, give it a Space ſufficiently vaſt; ſo that the Maſs of the Fluid is reſtrain'd and impriſon'd in a Veſſel, whoſe Capacity it far ſurpaſſes: <hi>Lentor al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ipſâ copiâ oriri poteſt, quae it a ſupra modum intra vaſa turgeſcit, ut ea, utcumque di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenta, ſatis amplum ſanguini circuland<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpatium praebere nequeant, niſi penitù<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſſiliant fibrae, ita tit cum uberior ſit, quam pro vaſorum capacitate fluidi moles, majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem patiatur retinentiam ſanguis redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dans:</hi> Who would think that theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which ſeem to tend to explain the Flux, ſhould end, nevertheleſs, in proving the Suppreſſion? That to ſhew how the <hi>Menſes</hi> are ſtopt, one ſhould make uſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the Conditions requiſite to make then flow? Theſe Conditions are on one Side the great Stretching of the Fibres in the Veſſels, which hinders them from reſiſting their Diviſion, and puts them in the neareſt Diſpoſition to be diſ-united; and on the other Side, the exorbitant Volume of the Blood as compact, as maſſive, as cloſe in its Texture, as the vaſcular Fibres are looſened, and which bears hard upon the Sides of the Veſſels that contain it; is it not viſible, that all the Advantage is here on the Side of the Blood? The Solid is dilated; the Fluid is cloſe knit; behold! here is the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion and the Preſſure that is demanded: As for the Swiftneſs or Percuſſion; we have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:0650600600:30"/>poved, there is no Occaſion for it: The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>luid then has here all the Force it can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave; ſince it has an enormous Reinforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent of Maſs, in which, as we have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rv'd, conſiſts all its Power; and the Solid as weak as it can be; ſince 'tis own'd by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Author himſelf, that it cannot, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it Pain, <hi>Citra virium noxam,</hi> ſuſtain the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> eight of the Fluid; and that the Veſſels, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wever dilated, cannot, without burſting, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e a free Space to the Blood: <hi>Niſi peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> diſſiliant fibrae:</hi> Then what can hinder is Burſting? Why don't we immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſee the Fibres crack, they who loſe as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch of their Reſiſtance, as the Blood ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ires of Strength? All morbifick Suppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n, ſays<note n="*" place="margin">Cap. 10.</note> Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> depends either on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Fault of the Veſſels, or on the Fault of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Blood; the Fault of the Veſſels conſiſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their Reſtraint; that of the Blood, in its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wneſs; 'tis agreed, that the Veſſels are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> here in a State of Conſtriction, but, on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e contrary, that they are in great Diſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n: So here is no Fault of theirs, neither the Blood to blame, if it be ſlow, for its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wneſs only proceeds from its great Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, in which all its Strength conſiſts; ſo at this Slowneſs, far from impeding, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er provokes the Flux; for, if the Blood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s leſs ſlow, the Veſſels would be leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain'd, more left, as it were, to themſelves, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d enjoying the Advantage of their Eaſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:0650600600:31"/>and Liberty, as the Blood would have that of its Velocity; they would, by Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, be leſs diſpos'd to be broken. So, the exceſſive <hi>Plethora,</hi> and the extreme Slowneſs, far from cauſing Suppreſſions, cannot, on the Syſtem of the Rapture o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Veſſels, but rather procure, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in the Sex this particular Evacuation Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> calls it a Vice in the Veſſels, to be in a Condition to hinder themſelves from being broken; this is indeed a Vice in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Syſtem, and in reſpect of his Opinion, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> abſolutely, and in the main, it is none. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the contrary, it is a Frailty, a Diſhonour a Defect in them, ſo to break: For the Veſſels to be of a Structure ſufficiently foli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſufficiently furniſh'd and fortify'd, ſeate ſufficiently to Advantage, ſtrong enough t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reſiſt the Diſ-union of their Fibres, to with ſtand their breaking, and ſtoutly to mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain themſelves found and whole, this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Defect, 'tis a Perfection. On the conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> calls Slowneſs a Vice in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Blood, which however is none, on his Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem, and according to his Hypotheſis, the in the main, and in Fact, it is one; for the Slowneſs of the Blood, tho' it be abſolut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in itſelf an ill Quality, is a good one the preſent Caſe, it being that which give Power to the Blood, and makes it ſtrong It follows from thence, that the Blood ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>never be too ſlow, nor too abundant, procure the Courſes; then how are the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:0650600600:32"/>ſtopt? how account we for their Suppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n? <hi>Etmuller, Riverius,</hi> Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf, agree, that an exceſſive <hi>Plethora</hi> may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auſe this Suppreſſion; but how is this to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e explain'd in the Doctrine of our Author? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it not evident, that the more enormous <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Quantity of the Blood is, the Diſtenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of the Veſſels is made the more conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le, and the readier they are to break? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Hypotheſis of the Blood's Intruſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>to to the Lymphaticks, nothing is more eaſy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> explain than this Suppreſſion; the Blood-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſels being ſtuffed, diſtended, dilated, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l groaning under the oppreſſive Weight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f their Fluid, have not Play and Liberty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nough to expel it into the Lymphaticks, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to chaſe it thro' the Pipes that diſcharge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Excrement, ſo as the Fluid cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oved, chaſed, drove on, becauſe the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious Maſs reſtrains the Solid, ſtops and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns its ſyſtaltick Virtue; ſo that it remains <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>agnant in the ſanguine Capillaries, for want <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f a Force ſtrong enough to puſh it into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lymphaticks, and, not being able to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake its Way through the excretory Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>els, it remains engag'd in the Veſſels, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith its Bulk it oppreſſes, and makes the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ex feel the over-whelming Weight that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttends the Suppreſſion of their Courſes.</p>
            <p>Every morbifick Suppreſſion, ſays our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Author, which depends upon the Fault <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Veſſels, or of the Blood, offers two
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:0650600600:33"/>Indications; the one to open the Canals that are obſtructed and ſtopp'd; the other to correct and reduce the Blood: The Fault of the Canals, continues he, is either to grow hard and ſtiff by a natural Dryneſs, or to be contracted by a ſudden Coldneſs, in ſuch wiſe, that they oppoſe the Impulſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Blood, and reſiſt their being broken. To remove this Impediment, according to the Opinion of this Illuſtrious Phyſician, we muſt relaxe the Fibres; but there is an Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation in this <hi>Relaxe,</hi> which 'tis wort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> while to clear up; we uſually underſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by Laxity or Relaxation, a State oppoſite to Tenſion, a State where the Fibres are ſupple and not ſtretch'd, where they a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> freely, and without Reſtraint; becauſe being ſufficiently moiſten'd, they are flexibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and pliant; whereas Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> ſeems t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> underſtand by Laxity, the State of the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres widen'd, pull'd, and ſtretch'd into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtrong Diſtention: So, according to thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Idea, the more the Canals are ſwell'd wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Abundance of the Liquid, the more th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fibres will be widened one from another and the more they will be relaxed; whenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it follows, that, to effect the Relaxation taken in this Senſe, and on the preſent Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis to make the <hi>Menſes</hi> flow, the ſure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Means is to draw into the Pipes as muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as one can, wherewith to ſwell, obſtruc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtuff and clog them. 'Tis viſible, that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this ſtrangely dilating the Veſſels, ſo w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:0650600600:34"/>their Fibres, that they ſcarce touch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne another; and this procures the Laxity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> demands. The Laxity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat I firſt mention'd, taken in the natural <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ordinary Meaning of the Word, is quite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifferent from this; and, on the Syſtem of Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> as much contrary to the Month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Courſes, as the other is favourable to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem; the one is procured by the Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs and Flexibility, the other by the Force, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Torture, the Pulling and Stretching of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Fibres: Wherefore, if it be proper, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rder to make the Courſes flow, that the Fibres ſhould be pull'd, ſtretch'd, widen'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd forc'd, nothing can be more adverſe and oppoſite to this Flowing, than this State is, where the Fibres are ſupple, flexible, pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant, at their Eaſe, their own Maſters, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrain'd, no way ſuffering, no way mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted. This pre-ſuppos'd, we are going to ſee which of theſe two Relaxations Dr. <hi>Friend</hi> propoſes to us as the Subject of our Conſideration; and we ſhall obſerve, upon this Occaſion, that he does not too well, here, agree with himſelf; for, as theſe two Relaxations are incompatible, to admit the one, is excluding the other; tho' Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> ſeems as if he would chime in with both. For this End, ſaith he, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to conquer the Reſiſtance of the Veſſels, and to procure the Relaxation of the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres, we muſt apply exterior Remedies moderately warm, ſuch as Fumigations,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:0650600600:35"/>Baths, and Fomentations, prepar'd with emollient and penetrating Herbs: <hi>Ad hunc finem tepidé adhibentur externa Remedia, qualia ſunt Suffitus, Balnea, Fomenta, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herbis emollientibus, &amp; penetrantibus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flata.</hi> This is proper to procure that Sort of Relaxation which conſiſts in the Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Flexibility of the Fibres, but not the other, which conſiſts in the ſtretching, widening, and conſtraining them, to render them leſs able to reſiſt the Impulſe of the Fluid: <hi>Contractu autem vaſorum inhibito, vaſorum later a laxiùs explicantur, &amp; fluido impingenti debilius reſiſtunt.</hi> If one has a Mind to break the Veſſels, methinks 'tis going the wrong Way about it, to make them ſupple, pliant, tractable, yielding; for the more flexible and yielding they are, the leſs they are diſpos'd to be broken; the more ſupple, ſure the lefs frangible; a dry Cord will ſooner break than a moiſt one; and if Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> will be pleaſed to take a little Notice of this, he will obſerve, that a dry and hard Veſſel is more frail and eaſy to be broke than a pliant, ſoften'd, moiſten'd one; what View then can this able Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an have? and what Indication leads him to relaxe the Veſſels, by Emollients, ſuch as Baths, Fumigations, Fomentations? I here appeal to the Judgment of this excellent Author himſelf, ſo well vers'd as he is in Mechanicks, perhaps I am dazzled with a falſe Light myſelf; yet, till I am enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:0650600600:36"/>I ſhall always imagine, that the Blood in its Motion will ſooner break Veſſels hard and dry, which make Head againſt it, are directly expos'd to the full Strength of its Impulſe, to the Force of its Colliſions, more within the Reach of its Sallies, more the Mark of its Impetuoſity, and of its fierceſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd briskeſt Attacks, than Veſſels ſoftened, which, by their yielding Suppleneſs, dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erouſly avoid all the Thruſts the Blood can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake againſt them; as we ſee the pliant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeds elude the Attack of the moſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ageous Tempeſts, whilſt Oaks that ſtand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll butt againſt them, and ſtiffly ſuſtain the Aſſault, lye rooted up, and proſtrate upon the Ground, the illuſtrious Victims, and the magnificent Trophies of the furious Tempeſt's Power. The Cold-too that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iffens the Fibres ſeems alſo to render them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he more frail, and liable to break. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing ſo, who does not ſee that Deſiccatives <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere are much more proper than Emollients? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho does not here ſee, that inſtead of soften<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g the Veſſels that are too dry and hard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſlackening the Fibres that are too ſtiff, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e muſt maintain them in their Dryneſs and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iffneſs, and far from diminiſhing any thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe, we muſt augment them as much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we can; becauſe we ſhall infallibly ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r the Veſſels and Fibres more frail, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oportion as we ſhall render them more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y and ſtiff; the more Violence we do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em, the more Streſs and Torture we put
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:0650600600:37"/>them to. Emollients, in this Caſe, ſeem quite contrary to our Purpoſe, becauſe they ſeem more proper to make the Conduits play, by ſetting them at their Eaſe, than to make them yield to ſuch a Rupture as our illuſtrious Author deſires. <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> he obſerves, in a Suppreſſion of the Courſes, adviſes to begin with a Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Fomentations; <hi>ſuppreſſis menſibus fomenta purgationi eſſe praemittenda mone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hippocrates:</hi> But if the Purgation operate in the ſame Manner as they ſay the Fluxe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do, by the Rupture of the Veſſels, the Uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Fomentations, far from being ſerviceabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> here, would be hurtful; but as it is confeſs'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the Purge don't work in this Manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but by quite different Ways; to ſay tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Fomentation is uſeful here, is at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame time to ſay, that it is not prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for the Fluxes, which differ ſo much fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Purgation: We foment before Purgation to make the excretory Ducts more yielding and more diſpoſed to emit their Juices, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they may the better hearken to the Inſtig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Purgative, and be the more e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caciously perſuaded to do what we wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> have them: This is our Drift in Foment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and this does not drive at breaking tearing and disjoining the Fibres, but tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſooth, temper, refreſh and ſupple the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to give the Juices we deſign to diſcharge, free, eaſy, natural Paſſage thro' the Iſſue the Pipes deſtin'd for that Purpoſe. So th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:0650600600:38"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o foment in the Suppreſſion of the Terms, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the ſame as in Purgation, is to go againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Indication that preſcribes the Rupture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Veſſels; 'tis to have oppoſite Views, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd take oppoſite Courſes to the Syſtem in Queſtion. Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> obſerves, that the Veſſels are more eaſy to open in Summer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han Winter; yet they are more ſtiff, more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>retch'd, and, of Conſequence more frail, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Winter; ſo that their Opening ſeems to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>epend leſs upon the Rupture that the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er favours moſt, than upon the Diſoppila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on of the Capillaries, which the Summer's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat promotes moſt, by means of which the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lood flows more freely, its Velocity is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>forced, its Impetuoſity is augmented, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Rapidity it contracts in this charming <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſon, prepares it the better to paſs thro' <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Lymphaticks, and to eſcape thro' the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xcretories. Here behold the Flux re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſh'd; let us now come to the Way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oving the ſecond Cauſe of Suppreſſion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>knowledged by Dr. <hi>Friend,</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ends upon the Fault of the Blood, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich he makes an inſenſible Tranſition. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut, ſays he, if the Veſſels continue too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng hard, the <hi>Plethora,</hi> which augments very Day, corrupts, and at laſt perverts the Blood, whence we have before drawn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nother Cauſe of Suppreſſions, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore frequent: <hi>Quod ſi diutiùs perſtiterit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſorum durities, Plethora indies accreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns ſanguini tandem vitium inducit; unde
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:0650600600:39"/>altera, eaque multò frequentior ſuppreſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum menſium cauſa in prioribus deducta eſt.</hi> Here we ſee, beyond Doubt, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive <hi>Plethora,</hi> which we have ſhewn was ſo proper to break the Veſſels, acknowledg'd however as the principal Cauſe of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. This ſeems to me very hard to clear up. Pray don't forget this laſt cited Paſſage, for we ſhall want you to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it in the Sequel.</p>
            <p>We would re-ſettle the Courſes; 'tis a thick, abundant, viſcous Blood that ſtop them; we muſt change its Quality. Now the Source of this Quality is its Exceſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Quantity; it is this we muſt fall foul of the Point is to correct the Slowneſs: Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Slowneſs, 'tis own'd, produces the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive <hi>Plethora;</hi> our Affair is then with this <hi>Plethora;</hi> 'tis this we muſt firſt attac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Upon this Principle, we immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Bleeding to be of Uſe. <hi>Bellini,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we are told by Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> proves, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bleeding increaſes the Motion of the Blood here we ſhould diſtinguiſh: Bleeding raiſe the Fever, and cures it; quickens th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Blood, and makes it run ſlower: Thoſe wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have a right and juſt Notion of the anima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mechaniſm perceive the Reaſon of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeeming Contrarieties; the Veſſels bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtuff'd exceſſively, have not Freedom enou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to exert their Oſcillations, to kindle the feveriſh Motions, and to conquer the gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Bulk of ſtagnant Humours, by hot Strok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:0650600600:40"/>of Syſtole and redoubled Vibration, we let Blood, the Reſiſtance is diminiſhed, the Solids are let looſe, the Fluids are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engaged, the Blood is ſet a running; this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the Caſe of an Apoplexy, to which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is wholeſome that a Fever ſhould ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed; the Solids, after having been ſo long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppreſs'd, are, at laſt, at their Eaſe, ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t large, and in full Power, and make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he agglomerated Fluids that had conſpir'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainſt them feel the Force of their Blows, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Effect of their Reſentment, and the Experience of their Revenge. The Blood, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fter firſt Bleeding, tho' ſtill abundant enough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o vex, irritate, and ſtretch 'em, yet is no more able to over-power and conquer 'em. Mean while, the Bleeding, having ſet the Blood in Motion, will in a little time abate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts Sallies, and reſtrain its Frolicks. The Reſiſtance of the Fluids, that maintains the Solids in their unbridled Oſcillations, in proportion as it diminiſhes, will calm and reduce them to their natural Vibrations; the Fury of the Veſſels will abate in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion as the Maſs of the Blood diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, becauſe, by how much the Bulk of the Blood is leſſened, by ſo much leſs Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will the Veſſels feel; the leſs, of courſe, will they be excited to furious Motions, and the more diſpoſed to recover their uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Courſe, their ordinary Oſcillations, their natural Motions: Then, as the Blood con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts its Slowneſs from its exceſſive Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:0650600600:41"/>the Bleeding diminiſhing this, ſhews us how much it contributes to correct the Slowneſs of the Blood. This being pre-ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, one would think the Doctor ſhould favour this Remedy, and one would not imagine, how, in conſequence of his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, he could advance, that in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a Diſeaſe, the Blood being too ſlow, it ſhould not be proper to let Blood, unleſs there be Reaſon to hope, that thereby the Viſcidity of the Blood may be corrected; and even tho' there ſhould be an Appearance of this, yet ought not Bleeding to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, if any other Method can be thought of, to reſtore the Blood to its Velocity, without leſſening its Volume. But what is ſtrangely ſurprizing is, to ſee ſuch a Man as Dr. <hi>Friend,</hi> in whom ſound Judgment takes Place ſo much of Prejudice, giving into vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Notions and Fancies without Foundation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He has Regard to the Weakneſs of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who ſuffer in theſe Stoppages, which does not proceed from Inanition, but Over-Repletion; not from a Scarcity, but from a Stock of Forces ſtow'd in too narrow Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, which only want to be ſet at large, as they are by Bleeding; a Weakneſs how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, from which a Pretence is drawn, to ſave that Blood, which wants to be dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, in order to exert its hidden Force, that is quite ſtifled by its own Redundancy; a Weakneſs whence a Counter-Indication is drawn againſt Bleeding, to cure it, to make
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:0650600600:42"/>its unactive, diſſembling Force exert and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare itſelf. Women, they uſually ſay, are ſo weak in theſe Suppreſſions, that they cannot bear Bleeding, which cauſes ſuch a prompt and brisk Revolution in the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours: Is not this Language altogether vulgar? 'Tis what the common Sort of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple uſually ſay thro' Prepoſſeſſion, rather than Reflection. Dr. <hi>Friend</hi> alſo ſays, <hi>Neque <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oc ſané praetermitti debet, quod in iis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us ſupperſſi ſunt menſes, it a ferè vires im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ninutae ſint, ut ſanguinis miſſionem, à quâ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deo expedita inducitur humorum mutatio, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ninùs ſuſtinere queant.</hi> At this rate, Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoricks ſhould not be let Blood; for the <hi>Plethora</hi> takes away their Strength; and we ſee that the more Blood they have, the weaker they are. But this Notion was too unworthy of Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> for him to fix for any time upon it; ſo 'tis not long before he goes off from it; Bleeding happens to fall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto Diſgrace; but a few Lines lower, it again recovers its Credit, and in the very ſame Caſe where it underwent the Diſgrace. Sometimes, however, ſays our Author, the Blood gives certain Symptoms of its State and Conſtitution, which, carefully conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, oblige to open a Vein, and to open it too with Succeſs. One of theſe Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms may be a Pulſe full and weak, which is ſometimes obſerved in the Beginning of a Diſtemper; nothing but Good can come of Bleeding upon this Occaſion; for thence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:0650600600:43"/>reſults a greater Velocity, and, of Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, in the Opinion of Dr. <hi>Friend,</hi> the greater Force of the Blood. <hi>Nonnunquam tamen ſanguis ea de ſe praebet indicia, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſiquis diligentùs ſtuduerit, venam haud inauſpicatò poterit ſecare: talis indicii ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplum ſit pulſus plenus &amp; imbecillis, qui morbo nondum inveterato aliquando obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; itaque ad hunc modum conſtituto pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus venae ſectio, ſi adhibita ſit, ſanguis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum intendet.</hi> Since a full and weak Pulſe allows, and even obliges to bleed, the Weakneſs of People afflicted with theſe Suppreſſions, is not therefore a good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to forbear Bleeding; for, with a full and weak Pulſe, as our Author obſerves, and which, in his Opinion, preſcribes Phlebotomy, Women cannot but be weak: It is not the Weakneſs then that forbids Bleeding. The Reaſon Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> adds to authorize the Precaution he adviſes, in order to diminiſh the Blood, is not very ſure; he ſays, that when the Arteries are ſo full, that the Tunicks are ſtretch'd, and take up a greater Space, 'tis a Sign that the Humours are not yet thickened; for, if their Maſs was conſiderably thick and ſizy in its Texture, it would take up leſs Room, becauſe its Particles would be leſs cloſe, and the Arteries thereby leſs ſtretch'd. This is however, what a Body cannot truſt to, becauſe the Maſs of Humours, cloſe thicken'd and condens'd, may happen to be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:0650600600:44"/>in ſuch Abundance, as to ſtretch the Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icks to a conſiderable Dilatation, without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bating the Velocity of the Humours, whoſe Redundance is no way incompatible with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir extreme Condenſation. So that, from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Arteries taking up no great Space, there; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s no concluding, that the Fluid they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain is very maſſive; for it may be maſſive, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ompact, and cloſe in its Texture, at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame time that it is ample, large, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ended in its Volume. A little Attention <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere will ſhew there is no Repugnance in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his. A little further, the Author ſays, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he vaſcular Tunicks, unbent by the Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, leſs reſiſting the Blood that ſtrikes upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, the Force of the Stroke is thereby weakened: <hi>Tunicis ſanguini affluenti mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ùs renitentibus deficit ictûs magnitudo.</hi> At this rate, 'tis ill done to bleed, ſince it weakens the Force of the Blow, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r. <hi>Freind</hi> makes the principal Promoter of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Fluxes. The Buſineſs therefore is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſlacken the Tunicks, nor to render them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>upple and pliant, but, on the contrary, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tretch them all we can, and to render them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tiff, dry, and hard; for Dr. <hi>Friend</hi> agrees, that in this State they make the moſt Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. Now, according to his Account in his 4th Mathematical Propoſition,<note n="*" place="bottom">Cap. 5.</note> the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion loſt (that is communicated) is propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to the Reſiſtance; <hi>motus deperditus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt ut reſiſtentia;</hi> but the Force of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:0650600600:45"/>Strokes is alſo meaſured by the Motion loſt: <hi>In percutientibus corporibus ictuum magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo motui deperdito proportionalis eſt.</hi> Then, as there is moſt Reſiſtance made by the Fibres ſtretch'd, ſtiff, dry, and hard, the Blood that ſtrikes upon 'em loſes ſtill the more of its Motion, ſince the Motion loſt is anſwerable to the Reſiſtance made: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Force of the Stroke is the greater in theſe Fibres; ſince the Force of the Strokes are ſuitable to the Quantity of the Motion loſt. Therefore, in fine, theſe Sor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Fibres muſt ſooner crack, than Fibre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that are ſupple, ſlack, and flexible. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Blood is ſuppoſed abundant, obſerve her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then the Force! the Fibres are ſuppos'd t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be widened and diſtended, behold Weakneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> here! Wherefore, all the Power and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage is here on the Side of the Blood Now, if the Force of a Body ſurmount the Force of the Obſtacle it has to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, this Obſtacle muſt give way, according to the ſecond Propoſition: <hi>Si momentu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> corporis ſit majus quam contraria impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti vis, id impedimentum removebitur</hi> the Veſſels, in this Caſe, muſt be broken and cannot hinder the Blood from extravaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Upon theſe Principles, ſettled by Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> himſelf, methinks, I may, with out the Imputation of too much Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, on, defy him to explain the Suppreſſion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Fluxes by an exceſſive <hi>Plethora,</hi> and by the Dryneſs and Hardneſs of the Veſſels
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:0650600600:46"/>which make too great a Reſiſtance; for all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his wonderfully contributes to the Flux, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s I think has been heretofore ſufficiently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emonſtrated. Our Author is inclin'd to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Opinion, that Bleeding ſhould be us'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather after than before the Purgatives and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmenagogues, which are the Remedies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore eſpecially deſign'd to promote the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ular Courſes. The Reaſon he gives for it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that the Purgatives and Emmenagogues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eak, refine, and attenuate the groſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acted Humours; whence the Blood being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore clear, is more diſpos'd to be divided, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>parated, diſlodg'd, and to acquire Force, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fter Bleeding: But this Advice ſeems con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ary to what he gives before, where he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dviſes not to let Blood, if there be any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther Means to increaſe its Velocity, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t leſſening its Quantity; becauſe in Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g we diminiſh the <hi>Plethora,</hi> which <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ora</hi> contributes in a particular manner to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Force of the Flood, and which, if we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave it entire, cannot but augment its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower. Now, ſince the Remedies which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r. <hi>Freind</hi> would preſcribe previous to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leeding, would break the compact Texture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Blood, rectify that, and, of Courſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive it Velocity, why not ſtop there? Why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eddle with the <hi>Plethora,</hi> which is ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ended, and held ſo ſacred (as we may ſay) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the preſent Syſtem, that we can't be without it? Why not rather ſpare it, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e have procured the Velocity of the Blood
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:0650600600:47"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:0650600600:48"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:0650600600:49"/>another Way, by other Means than Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? Hence we ſee, that Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eſtabliſh'd nothing certain here upon the Matter of Bleeding in Caſes of Suppreſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So we don't know what to ſtick to, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what to build upon in his Syſtem. He doe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not explain himſelf preciſely enough; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> does not ſufficiently dive into, and unfol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Matter: He ſometimes loſes Sight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Principles to which all ſhould tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and by that means he is led into Perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and falls into Contradictions but to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> frequently; of all which I ſhall take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Notice; for I do not here pretend to tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> thro' all the Windings and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viations that appear in his Book.</p>
            <p>Before we paſs on to an Article ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, as to inquire of the Place where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is fit to bleed, whether it be in the Arm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Foot; I deſire it may be call'd t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mind, that the Swiftneſs of the Blood is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> principal Foundation of our Author's Syſtem and yet we have prov'd it to be a ruino<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Foundation; ſince the Blood cannot app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to the Diſadvantage and Prejudice of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Veſſels, a Strength it receives from them and a Velocity for which it is obliged t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them: So that the Doctrine of our Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is, in that Point alone, ſapp'd from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Foundation. This is what I deſire ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be well remember'd, once for all; for have no Inclination to be troubleſome, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> repeating it ſo often over; <hi>Lindanus
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:0650600600:50"/>Etmuller</hi> counſels, at the Approach of the Courſes, to bleed in the Arm; whereas in the actual Courſe, already begun, he ſends you to bleed in the Foot; which he never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rders to be done, but in a Courſe either actually flowing, or ſuddenly ſtopp'd: And <hi>Etmuller</hi> accounts for this Doctrine in the following Manner.</p>
            <p>Upon the Approach of the <hi>Menſes,</hi> the Blood being abundant and ſwell'd, Nature <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xerts all her Efforts to precipitate it to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower Parts; but the Conduits being ſmall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>annot, on a ſudden, yield and open ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on; on the contrary, being ſtretch'd and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſtrain'd, they refuſe a Paſſage to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lood; becauſe they are not at Freedom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o contract themſelves, and make way for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Blood. In this Circumſtance, if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leed at the Foot, you draw the Blood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ownwards, you charge the <hi>Matrix</hi> more, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou add Clog upon Clog, and raiſe the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emper to the higheſt Degree. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rary, bleed in the Arm, you divert the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lood from the Parts that are oppreſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; you facilitate its Courſe, you clear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Ways through which it is to paſs; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou give the Conduits the Suppleneſs they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant to iſſue forth the Blood they convey; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the Bleeding at the Foot will never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rovoke the Terms, unleſs they be actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly flowing, or by a ſudden Cold, or ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng Fright, have their Courſe interrupted. This way of Reaſoning Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> can no
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:0650600600:51"/>wiſe reliſh; it has ſomething in it that is ſtrange and ſhocking to him. Here it is ſuppos'd, ſays he, that the Blood is ſo ſwell'd and rarified, that it might eaſily flow thro'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Veſſels, if, when 'tis carried downwards, the Plenitude it contracts did not form an Obſtacle to its Diſcharge; that the Veſſels, the more they are gorg'd with Blood, are leſs in a Condition to yield to the Torrent. He rejects this; finds it contrary to Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Philoſophy, and even inconſiſtent with common Senſe. But is this Reproach well grounded? and have not we a Right to make it recoil upon its Author? <hi>Etmuller</hi> is here accus'd not to have common Senſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> This Accuſation, if it be found unjuſt, will it not rebound upon Dr. <hi>Freind?</hi> Shall we have more Reſpect for him than he has for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one of the greateſt Maſters in Phyſick? The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Phyſician is ſo pre-poſſeſs'd with his own Opinion, and ſo glew'dd, as it were to his own Syſtem, that he conſiders n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other's; and takes no Pains to enter into the Sentiments of the <hi>German</hi> Phyſician. There is a Syſtem which is ſatisfy'd to make the Veſſels yield or burſt to give way to the <hi>Menſes;</hi> according to this Idea, it is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and reaſonable, that the more the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels are ſwell'd and diſtended by the Blood the more fit they are to yield and to be broken: But have we not obſerv'd, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> himſelf falls into the ſame Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity, which he reprimands in <hi>Etmuller</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:0650600600:52"/>have we not obſerv'd a Caſe where the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tention of the Veſſels being pre-ſuppos'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the Abundance of the Blood that dilates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, he ſtill owns a Suppreſſion? We need <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut call to Mind what has been lately ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the Slowneſs of the Blood. Bye and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye we ſhall ſee another parallel Caſe; ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat it is important not to let flip, without Notice, what he advances here. At the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame Time this Syſtem, which we have juſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow ſeen, is not the only one; there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her which does not make the Veſſels yield, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut, on the contrary, makes them act to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rovoke the Terms. Now, the Fluxes, on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Hypotheſis, not depending on the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels that yield, but which make the Blood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ield to them; not on their conquer'd Forces, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut on their ſuperior Action, on their victor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious Power, on their ſovereign Empire, on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir triumphant Oſcillation: 'Tis not, on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Syſtem, a thing contrary to common Senſe, that the Veſſels ſhould be ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs fit to procure the Courſes, the more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey are dilated and ſwell'd to Exceſs; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then, tho' much more eaſy to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, they are leſs qualified to ad act and free themſelves; which is what is requir'd in this other Syſtem. Our Author will have it, that, if the Bleeding in the Foot provokes the Terms that flow, or that are ſtopp'd in Flowing, it would alſo recal them, when ſuppreſs'd, from their Flux, tho' of a long Standing. This Conſequence is not juſt;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:0650600600:53"/>but why, ſays he, in the firſt Caſe, does this Bleeding augment the Force of the Blood, in hurrying it downwards, and does not augment it in the ſecond Caſe, acting ſtill in the ſame Manner? The Queſtion is not here about the Force of the Blood: <hi>Etmuller</hi> is not obliged to ſpeak in Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to the Principles of Dr. <hi>Freind;</hi> and Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> is but ill warranted to meaſure every thing by his own Ideas, and ſuit eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing to his own Hypotheſis, To do this, he firſt muſt prove, that the only way to be taken is that which he has taken; and that his is the only Syſtem that can ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally be follow'd: He ought firſt to have made it impregnable, and not have left ſuch a Hold to be laid on't as he has done; ſince this Syſtem, according to what appears in our Remarks, is by ſo many Ways ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully ſhaken.</p>
            <p>The Bleeding in the Foot excites the Terms that flow, and that are interrupted in flowing; becauſe then the ſole Buſineſs is to aſſiſt the Blood's Determination towards the Uterine Region; the Blood flows; this is a Sign that it is clear'd, refin'd, well-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition'd; and that the Veſſels are not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baraſs'd; now, the Paſſages, the Iſſues, the Conduits being free, and clear'd, the new Blood which the Bleeding in the Foot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines that way, will eaſily paſs, and without Pain, proceed to its Exit. The Blood that juſt now flow'd, ceaſes, and flows
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:0650600600:54"/>no more. In this Caſe, it is only repell'd; only its Determination happens to be alter'd by ſome unlucky Accident; and you muſt recal the Blood to its Determination down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Here you have nothing to conquer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut the Repercuſſion wrought, either, for Example, by a ſtopping Cold, or by a ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng Fright; and this the Bleeding in the Foot does; it determines the Blood towards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Matrix,</hi> and reſtores it to its former Tendency: But a Suppreſſion of a long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tanding, being caus'd by the Congeſtion and Stoppage of the Blood in the Uterine Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>illaries, our Buſineſs is not here about its Tendency towards the Veſſels, but about its Diſcharge and Enlargement from the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels themſelves: The Matter is not now to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttract the Blood downwards, but to clear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>way that which is already there, and which is there but in too great a Quantity; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ince it is this very Quantity itſelf that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers it there ſo very clogging and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome. Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> agrees, that the Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng in the Arm practis'd in ſuch a Caſe, withdrawing a Portion of the Blood towards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſuperior Parts, the Conduits of the Womb are thereby in Truth reliev'd; but, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ays he, the Diminution of the <hi>Plethora</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bating the Impetuoſity of the Blood, the Veſſels are not ſo diſpos'd to break, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Veſſels are leſs extended. This is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther irregular Reaſon, which ſuppoſes we can't take from the Abundance of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:0650600600:55"/>without abating aught of its Velocity; which is directly contrary to what the Author owns himſelf, a little before, in theſe Words: <hi>Igitur triduò anté, conſultum perioditempus, ſecatur vena, ut tum praecipué novus ſanguini accreſcat impetus, cum aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti ſummam attigerit Plethora.</hi> What Streſs can we lay, after this, upon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions of Dr. <hi>Freind?</hi> What can we reckon upon? To what Principle ſhall we adhere? The Sentiment of <hi>Etmuller</hi> is confirm'd by a famous Obſervation of <hi>Riverius</hi> upon a Woman whoſe Terms always ſtopp'd as often as ſhe was blooded in the Foot, and very largely flow'd when ſhe was blooded in the Arm: This Phaenomenon agrees but little with the ordinary Ideas of Phyſicians The Doctors of <hi>Montpellier</hi> have explain'd it by a Mechaniſm very well contriv'd, but incompatible with the Syſtem of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; whom one may defy, with all hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Efforts and vaſt Capacity, to account for this Fact, related in the Second Hiſtory o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Firſt Century of <hi>Riverius</hi>'s Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. This Woman, ſay the Doctors, being Plethorick, and attack'd with a Suppreſſion, caus'd by the prodigious Maſs of the Blood, which dilated the Veſſels of the <hi>Matrix</hi> to ſuch a Degree, that they could not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently uſe their contracting Power; when, by bleeding in the Foot, the Blood was deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd towards thoſe Parts which were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready over-charg'd therewith, the Clog
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:0650600600:56"/>was augmented; and Occaſion given to an obſtinate Suppreſſion; but when, by bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng in the Arm, the Blood was invited to the ſuperior Parts, the Veſſels of the <hi>Uterus</hi> were diſengag'd: Now, their Plenitude and Diſtention being diminiſhed, they could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ract and play with more Eaſe, and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure the natural and periodical Evacuation, which is made thro' Iſſues of the <hi>Matrix.</hi> Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> intrenches himſelf in this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erfuge, which is in a Diſtinction he makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etwixt a <hi>Plethora,</hi> which he calls ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, and that which is join'd with a <hi>Lentor;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd he ſays, 'tis only in this that the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aution of <hi>Lindanus,</hi> noted in <hi>Etmuller,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>akes Place. He adds, that the Woman, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f whom <hi>Riverius</hi> ſpeaks, was troubled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith this Sort of <hi>Plethora;</hi> and upon this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ottom he approves the Indication which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Montpellier</hi> Doctors have taken, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ubſcribes to their Practice. The Author <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen grows a little more mild towards <hi>Lindanus,</hi> and declares, that what is rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed by <hi>Etmuller</hi> takes Place in one Caſe; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is therefore in the wrong, to cry out ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard againſt it, and pronounce, without Ground, that there is not common Senſe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Reaſoning of that Author. Here he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould make Reparation to his Honour: He agrees, that, in Suppreſſions, one bleeds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irſt in the Arm, and then in the Foot; he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſigns for a Reaſon of this, that the bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng in the Arm augments the Velocity of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:0650600600:57"/>the Blood, and bleeding in the Foot aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the <hi>Plethora,</hi> in regard to the ute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine Veſſels. But is this what he ſaid at firſt? Might not one prove by his own Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that the Conſent he gives to this Practice is not very rational? Let us call to Mind what Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> hath ſaid; does not common Senſe require, that the more the Veſſels are ſwell'd, the more they are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to yield, crack and break? <hi>Ne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis quidem ſenſus ferret, vaſa quò magis ſanguine diſtenta ſint, eo minùs eſſe ad ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum facilia.</hi> Now, in the Plethorick Woman we are talking of, when ſhe is blooded in the Foot, this augments the Swelling of the uterine Conduits, which are thereby more diſpoſed to break, and give way; yet the Doctors of <hi>Montpellier</hi> cauſed the Woman to be blooded in the Arm and, by this Bleeding, one will ſay with Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> it is true, that the uterine Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages are clear'd of their Stoppage and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; but as the Impetuoſity of the Blood languiſhes by the Diminution of the <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thora,</hi> the Veſſels are render'd leſſ liable to break, becauſe they are then leſs extended <hi>Sectâ Brachii venâ, cum nonnihil ſurſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> revellitur, liberantur quidem ab oppreſſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> viae uterinae, ſed impetu ob Plethoram im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minutam languente, haud ita facile diſſili unt vaſa, quia minùs ſunt diſtenta.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Slowneſs and the Viſcidity of the Blood is according to our Author, a Reaſon not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:0650600600:58"/>bleed; and Bleeding does no good in Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſſions, ſave when the Particles of the Blood are enough diſengaged, and not very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enacious; becauſe then they eaſily ſhift <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Place, and are perſwaded to what he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alls <hi>Dimotion.</hi> Now, he agrees, that the Blood of the Woman we talk of was viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous, ſlow, and tenacious; how then, on his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rinciples, can he allow her to be blooded? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne has only to compare what he has ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anced with the Explications he now gives, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Occaſion of this Woman, to ſee that all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on't agree, and that the Syſtem which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffered to us, as inconteſtable, and as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſt Principle avow'd by every body, is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell ſupported. I ſhould have a great many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore Remarks to make upon it, but I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e myſelf to this preciſe Reflection, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay furniſh many more: If the Flowing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Menſes</hi> could be wrought by the Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re of the Veſſels, it would be more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>larly done when the Veſſels were the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>angible; now, the Veſſels are moſt frail, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen they are the moſt extended; but they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re the moſt extended, when they; are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt gorg'd with Blood; and they are more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>org'd with Blood, by bleeding in the Foot, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an by bleeding in the Arm; therefore, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeding in the Foot ſtuffs them more with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lood, ſtretches them more, and makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em more frangible. Then, as bleeding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Foot renders the Uterine Veſſels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore frail, and more ready to be broken,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:0650600600:59"/>it ſhould, in the Woman we are ſpeaking of, provoke the monthly Flux. If this Flux is wrought by the Breaking of the vaſcular Tunicks, the Blood is exceſſively abundant, it has all that it can want to prevail; the Veſſels on their Part are dilated and ſtretch'd to the laſt Degree; ſo here is all that's want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to conquer them; the, what hinder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them from being broken? and ſince the bleeding of the Foot, in ſtretching them diſpoſes them more than ever to burſt, is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not evident, that it favours, and ought eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neceſſarily to produce the Flux, if thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt be explain'd by the Rupture of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels? I omit ſeveral Irregularities, to finiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Diſcuſſion with two Words of Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon ſome Hiſtories of Fact, relate by our Author, concerning Suppreſſion. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt Hiſtory is of a Girl Eighteen Years old yet without her Terms, who complain'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a great Pain in her Loins, Knees, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; ſhe had Difficulty in breathing, Squea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhneſs, and Gripes; her Heart, upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> leaſt Exerciſe, panted; her Complexion wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lively and florid; her Pulſe weak an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſlow; ſhe was very much afflicted with the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Symptoms for about Six Months: Dr. <hi>Frein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> did not find here any Indication for Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he only propos'd to break and refin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by Attenuants, the viſcous Texture of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Blood.</p>
            <p>But is it not a wiſe Precaution, when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Veſſels are too much ſtretch'd, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:0650600600:60"/>Blood too thick, ſizy and ſtiff, to unbend the Veſſels; and to diminiſh the Volume of the Blood, in order to facilitate the Action of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nciſive Remedies, that they may lay more Hold upon the maſſive Humours? Is it not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſquing a great deal to undertake to rarify <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Blood which we don't diminiſh in the Veſſels, whoſe Sides we cannot further <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tretch, and all whoſe Space the Blood, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts Thickneſs, now takes up? Where then will be Space for it in its Rarefaction? But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his is the Means, one will ſay, to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Uterine Capillaries crack; but this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo the Means to burſt other Veſſels too: This Practice makes us juſtly fear the Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of other important Veſſels, and of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence terrible Hemorrhages. Beſides, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s enough, if we conſult the Motions of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, to perſwade us, that a Maſs of Juices, thick, groſs, glewy and compact, reſiſts too much the Action of Attenuants, and the Virtue of Inciſives, for them to be able to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay hold of, penetrate, and thruſt themſelves thereinto: They can do no more in this Caſe, but ſhove, ſtruggle, and rummage in this Maſs, inſtead of inſinuating nicely into the Pores, wriggling ſubtilly, and without Noiſe, into the Interior of the Subſtance, ſo to ſeparate with as much Efficacy, as little Diſturbance, the Particles thereof. Bleeding, which is preparative to the Uſe of <hi>Opium,</hi> and which the moſt ſecures us in it, as has been clearly proved in the judicious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:0650600600:61"/>that have been made thereupon, ſhould, for the ſame Reaſons, be a Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative for Emmenagogues, and ſecure their Succeſs.</p>
            <p>Bleeding then might have been apply'd in curing the ſick Perſon in Queſtion; every thing ſeem'd to indicate this, and, above all, the Difficulty of breathing, the Palpitation of the Heart, and the ruddy Colour of the Face; but the Obſtruction which appear'd in the Region of the <hi>Matrix,</hi> whither the Blood had flow'd with too much Precipitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and where it had contracted a powerful and well-knit Body, requir'd the Bleeding to be not in the Foot, but in the Arm; therefore it ſeems, that had the Patient been bled in the Arm, one might have thereby freed the lower Parts, that were gorg'd, and, as it were, ſuffocated; and, by un-corking them, one might have engag'd them to yield readily to the deſired Evacuation. Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> however, declares, that he did not think fit to employ this Remedy, by reaſon of the Weakneſs of the Girl, and becauſe he apprehended, by this means, he might diminiſh, inſtead of augmenting the Blood: But theſe are Conjectures too weak and light to divert from the Uſe of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy indicated, in other reſpects, by ſuch preſſing Motives; the Weakneſs, above all, is not in itſelf, as we have already ſhewn, a good Reaſon to omit Bleeding. Our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, in his third Obſervation, gives us the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:0650600600:62"/>Hiſtory of a Waſher-woman, of a ſanguine Complexion, about Twenty Four Years old, who, in waſhing with her Terms upon her, was ſeiz'd with a Fit of Coldneſs; ſhe was alſo waſhing her Legs with cold Water; wherefore, the Flux having been here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell'd by the Cold, her Terms diſappeared <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or a Year, without any great apparent Conſequence. Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> accounts, by her great Fatigue and Labours, for the little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rejudice this ſeem'd to do her Health: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut, about the End of the Year, ſhe felt a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery conſiderable Change; ſuch as, a great Heavineſs and Weakneſs, the Action of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tomach infeebled, the Function diſorder'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pain in almoſt all her Limbs, a Cough, a Difficulty of Breathing, a Paleneſs, a Swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of her Legs, where ſo hard a Tumor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red, that it was impoſſible, by any Plaſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Cataplaſm, to ſoften it, or to bring it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Suppuration; and her Pulſe became fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, and languiſhing. The Patient would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave prevented all theſe Accidents, if, at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Time of her Flux's Repercuſſion, ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad got herſelf blooded in the Foot, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Remark of <hi>Lindanus,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Reflections of <hi>Etmuller.</hi> Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> who, in all Likelihood, did not ſee the Waſher-woman, but in the Time of the inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erate Suppreſſion, took from the Tumor an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndication to make her be bled in the Arm; which he owns did no great good; but bleeding in the Foot, tho' a long time after
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:0650600600:63"/>the Interruption of the Flux, wou'd perhap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have had better Succeſs, in regard to the Source of the Suppreſſion which ſeems to require this Bleeding, and which we the more readily believe, as the Blood ſhews no Appearance of gathering, ſlakening and Congeſtion, in the Uterine Conduits; and if it don't flow that way, this ſeems to be net ſo much through any Clog or Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that might be there contracted, as for want of its being determined towards thoſe Parts. And what juſtifies this Thought o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mine is, the Remark it ſelf of Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> who explains how the Suppreſſion might have been ſo long a Time inoffenſive, by the great Exerciſe of the Waſher-woman which did not allow much Time for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Blood to ſojourn, ſtagnate, corrupt, and ſtick in the Uterine Region, ſo toſt an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> jumbled as it was, and by Conſequence re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd more tranſpirable by the Woman Agitation. There ſeems then nothing her wanting to the Blood, but a proper Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination towards the <hi>Matrix,</hi> which is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd and promoted by bleeding in the Foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and that ought here to have been done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Notions I offer; which, after all, are but Conjectures I venture to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſubmit, with all my Heart, to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Judgment of Phyſicians, among who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> ſhines in ſo diſtinguiſh'd a Ran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> This able Phyſician, who judg'd it not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>venient at firſt to uſe this Bleeding, did u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:0650600600:64"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t towards the End of the Diſtemper, after Purgatives and Emmenagogues, to give the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iniſhing Stroke to the Cure, and ſo compleat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Work. Four or Five Days after this Bleeding, her Terms appear'd, the Patient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecovered her roſy Colour, and all the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idents vaniſhed. Now we have nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eft to do, but to apply to the Emmena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ogues the Inconvenience that Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nds in bleeding, in Relation to the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſſions: This will pin up the Basket, and hew that his Principles claſh, and that his Syſtem, tho' diſplay'd with all the Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs, and prov'd with all the Reaſons that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is ſuſceptible of, don't appear well ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orted. When, ſays he, after <hi>Bellini,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Cap. 11.</note> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eady Removal of the Blood follows after bleeding, or when the Blood is ſo rarified, that its Particles are diſ-unitedy and eaſily divided one from another, this Liquor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a Velocity that fortifies its Power, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecauſe the animal Spirits, enlarg'd and free, flow to the Heart in a chearful Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and the Blood, broken and ſubtiliz'd, makes leſs Reſiſtance againſt the Action of the Veſſels: But, if no Removal follows, the Quantity of the Blood being abated, the Velocity is ſo likewiſe; and ſo the Blood loſes of its Force. It were to be wiſh'd, inſinuates Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> that <hi>Bellini</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>had eſtabliſh'd a conſtant Token, a certain Sign of this Conſtitution of the Blood, that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:0650600600:65"/>ſuffers a Removal by bleeding, and of that other which does not ſuffer any thereby; becauſe, for want of knowing this State and Diſpoſition of the Blood, the Phyſician cannot be ſure in what manner Bleeding will change it, and modify its Motion for the better or the worſe. By reaſon of this Uncertainty and doubtful Succeſs of Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we muſt abſtain therefrom, unleſs the Violence of Accidents inforce it: For if, in letting Blood, we render it more ſlow and compact, not only fewer animal Spirits will ariſe from it, and ſo the Stroke of the Beating of the Heart will be the more weak, but the Obſtruction that afflicts the Capillaries, and holds 'em Captives, will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new Force. Therefore, in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Suppreſſion, Bleeding does not ſeem to be indicated, unleſs one plainly ſees the Means to break infallibly the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact Texture of the Blood, and to redouble its Force by renewing its Velocity; let us examine, according to his Model, the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Emmenagogues, that makes a Part of the Alteratives, and then conſider, after<note n="*" place="bottom">Cap. 14.</note> Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> if the Action is more certain, and the Succeſs more allured. How ſays he, can the ſame Force ſurmount ſuch different Reſiſtances? How can a Remedy act in ſo uniform a manner, when the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects upon which it operates are ſo unlike? There is nothing more ridiculous than to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:0650600600:66"/>expect from a Medicament a conſtant Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a faithful Energy, an infallible and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent Virtue, ſince it is not ſtrange or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>epugnant for one and the ſame Remedy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o produce contrary Effects. Suppoſe, for Example, the Diſpoſition of the Blood be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch, that the greater Part thereof is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>remely vitiated, and the <hi>Lentor</hi> too obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate to be conquer'd by the Force of Atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uants; in this Caſe, if we apply a Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utive or Subtiliſant, it has no Effect but upon the thinner Part of the Blood, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t melts and refines, till it makes it paſs in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bundance thro' the Strainers, that is, thro' <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Glands and the Filtres of Secretion; ſo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he moſt ſubtle, or fineſt Parts of the Blood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing diſcharged by the Force of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icine, the Remainder of the Maſs will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hereby be but the more compact, thick, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd cloſe. Do but obſerve, how the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>horeticks, thoſe powerful Attenuants, do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>metimes even augment the <hi>Lentor,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Groſsneſs of the Humours, as we ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Experience. <hi>Quomodo enim eadem vis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iverſa longé momenta queat pervincere? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uomodo ſimilis ſemper eſſe poſſet agentis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ergia, cùm it a diſſimilis prorſus ſit corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is in quod agitat Natura? Conſtantem hanc medicamentis ſperare efficaciam, ita ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iculum eſt, ut nihil mirum ſit, ſi etiam ab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dem medicamento educi poſſit effectus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arius: Concipiamus enim earn eſſe ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is craſin, ut pars ejus longè maxima in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigniter
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:0650600600:67"/>lenteſcat, cohaeret aequè in eâ momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum validius ſit quam quae ab attenuantium biribus reſolvi queat. In hoc caſu, ſi adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veatur medicamentum reſolvens, eam qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſanguinis partem, quae minus lenteſcit, ita fundit &amp; attenuat, ut per glandulas ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretorias uberiùs extrudatur: ita medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti vi, eliminatis particulis tenuioribus, craſſior erit reliqui ſanguinis compages: ad hunc modum, uti &amp; docet experientia, len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem aliquando augent Diaphoretica.</hi> Yet muſt we not exclude Reſolutives, becauſe of their doubtful Succeſs, and uncertain Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue: Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> makes often uſe of them, without Heſitation, at the ſame time that he ſhould either abſtain from them, or not uſe them, but with ſuch Precautions as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf preſcribes in bleeding: We muſt before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand be aſſured of the State of the Blood know, in that Point, what we have to go upon, have Tokens that denote the Degre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Lentor</hi> or Viſcidity requiſite to be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed off by the Emmenagogues. As we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> admoniſhed, that we muſt have ſome o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe Signs that mark to us the Degree o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Thickneſs capable of being corrected by the bleeding, for want of which the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefs are no more practicable than the laſt they are both alike uncertain: Then, upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what Account is the one preferr'd to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other? This ſhould have been clear'd up Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> ſhould have inſtructed us in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and in this, as well as many other thing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:0650600600:68"/>but for the Death of the illuſtrious Author, we had Reaſon to hope from him further Lights. He flatters himſelf, that this fine Phaenomenon about the Courſes can no way be explain'd, but by his Principles; yet I have ventured upon other Principles, and the Syſtem of the red Part of the Blood being engag'd in the Canals of its white Part, the prevailing Opinion of Dr. <hi>Helve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius;</hi> and which he has ſo much illuſtrated on the Subject of the Small Pox, of which he has ſo learnedly and uſefully treated: A Syſtem! which gives Light into the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Hemorrhages and Inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and which ſo perfectly agrees with the animal OEconomy, and natural Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm. This Syſtem, I ſay, yields in nothing to that which Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> has given us, not only as the beſt, but as the only one. From the Principles I have already laid down, every one may make his Remarks upon the other Parts of the Author's Book, which I have not touch'd; and 'tis likely, that with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow much the more Attention and Care one ſhall apply to this, the more the Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Reaſoning will appear, and the Uncertainty of his Hypotheſis. From the Reflections that have been hitherto made, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t may be gather'd, that 'tis, by no means, an indifferent Matter in Practice, to adopt indifferently, the Syſtem of the Rupture of the Veſſels, or that of the Intruſion of the Blood into the lymphatick Canals: It is of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:0650600600:69"/>the higheſt Conſequence, to chufe either the one or the other, to liſt on one Side or the other, and to appear more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily engaged or concern'd therein. If the Diſpute here was only about ſome inſipid, barren Point of Speculation amuſing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to the Curious, but altogether uſeleſs, and without Influence on Practice, thoſe who regard things only as they are uſeful, might perhaps ſlumber over it: But as our Buſineſs here is about a capital Point, which affects and concerns Practice to the higheſt Degree; ſince in the two Hypotheſes the Manner of Cure is quite different; this ought to awake the Attention of all Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, inſpire them with an extraordinary Reliſh for the preſent Subject, and rouze them totally out of their Indifference. Some will perhaps attack the fundamental Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of theſe Reflections, which is, that the Blood owes its Velocity to the Impulſe, and ſyſtaltick Virtue of the Solids; they will tell me, that the Veſſels may be enormouſly diſtended and ſtretch'd to Exceſs, and ſtill the Fluid which they contain may move on with Impetuoſity, by virtue of the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caments that act upon it, that break its Texture, bruiſe its Maſs, correct its Viſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, quicken its <hi>Lentor,</hi> and ſeparate its Parts; whence may reſult an Increaſe of its Force, a Renewal of its Velocity, and all this independent of the Oſcillation of the Veſſels, which ſtill remain ſtretch'd, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:0650600600:70"/>and, as it were, captive. This has been proved by a Number of Experiments: A Mixture has been made of the Blood newly drawn from the Artery of a Dog, with ſeveral Druggs, which Mixture has given Occaſion to various Phaenomena. The Blood mixt with the Spirit of Salt Armoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c, was of a beautiful Red, and fine Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tence, mixt with a Decoction of Savin, or Horehound, it appeared of a deeper Red, and of a finer Subſtance; with <hi>Sydenham</hi>'s Liquid Laudanum, it was of a brighter Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our, than with the Decoction of Savin, tho' not of a much finer Subſtance; with the Diſtilled Water of Rue, or Wormwood, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ontinued very fluid from the Firſt till the Thirteenth of <hi>February.</hi> A Mixture was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo made of the Serum of Human Blood with the Tincture of Aloes drawn with Mint Water, with a Decoction of Savin, a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oction of Gentian, Spirit of Tartar, of Saffron, of Turpentine, of Guaiacum, and of Hartſhorn; the Oil of Turpentine, of Guaiacum, of Lavender, and of Cloves: By means of theſe Druggs ſucceſſively ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, the Serum held fluid many Days, but nothing render'd it near ſo fluid and ſo fine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the Decoction of the Jeſuit's Bark. We have been alſo aſſured of the Working of Medicines upon the Blood, by Injections and Intromiſſions into the Body of a living Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal: We need but conſult thereupon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4. Chap. of the <hi>Emmenology</hi> of Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:0650600600:71"/>which proves by unqueſtionable Experiments, that the Blood is altered, changed, modifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, attenuated, broken, refin'd, ſet in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and render'd fluid, by the Power of Emmenagogues: Therefore the Fluid hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another Mover than the Oſcillation of the Solid, may be moved rapidly, impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and precipitately, even when this Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillation is languiſhing, feeble, and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: Therefore the Blood may have the Advantage of Maſs, Velocity, Preſſure and Percuſſion: Therefore, the Veſſels being enormouſly dilated, weakened, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, may be forc'd by the Action of the Blood, an Action which it has independent of the Veſſels, and from which they can draw no Advantage; a Stroke conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which it can give them, without being accuſed of Ingratitude, and without incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the odious Reproach of turning it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Power againſt thoſe who gave it. This Stroke the Veſſels will be unable to reſiſt and be forc'd to yield to it, broken, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd, and overwhelm'd, not by the Power which they (the Veſſels) lend to the Blood ſince they have none to lend, but by that which the Blood has borrowed elſewhere This is what may be objected againſt me and certainly I have given the Objection al its Weight, and wiſh heartily it might ſcreen Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> from any Attack. I agree, that Medicines act upon the Humours, and inſpire them with divers Qualities; but it is proper
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:0650600600:72"/>to obſerve firſt, that this is not always im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, nor without the Participation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Solids. The firſt Operation of Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies inwardly taken is upon the Stomach, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd thence ſpreads thro' the whole <hi>Genus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ervoſum,</hi> whereof this <hi>Viſcus</hi> is a Part; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd conſequently it is not ſtrange, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tomach ſhould tranſmit the Modifications <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the Impreſſions which it receives. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uickeſt Operation of Medicines, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riskeſt Revolutions they cauſe, are due to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſudden Emotion which the Solids ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uire, when they are affected by the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ines, Smoke raiſes the Vapours, and cures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem; the Sprinkling of cold Water, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are Taſte of good Wine, recovers from a Swoon, recals the ſtraying Soul, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ores the loſt Faculties. Remedies often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imes make no Change in the Blood, but by means of the Solids, which they firſt change, and whoſe Tone they alter, ſo that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecome more elaſtick, or more moderate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccording to the Action of the Remedies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat work and drive on the Fluids with more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r leſs Heat; whence enſues in the Blood more or leſs Refinement and Celerity. Dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Experience proves the great Share the Solids have both in the Diſeaſe and in the Cure; they are the Lords of the Animal OEconomy, the Principle of every Good, and of every Evil there.</p>
            <p>But now, after thoſe general undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined Ideas, which it is good to advance,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:0650600600:73"/>let us deſcend to ſomething more particular, which more nearly regards the Difficulty we have been forming. Upon this I have two Reflections to make; the firſt, that the Virtue of Medicines has nothing at all to do with a State of Health. In the Caſe of an ordinary and natural Flowing, the Blood then makes its own Way through the Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks of the Veſſels, yet is not put in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor puſh'd, nor made fluent, refin'd and fluid, by the Power of the Medicines; therefore, if it has Celerity, it owes this to the Oſcillation of the Solids, which, with redoubled Strokes of Syſtole, impart to it its preſent Motion, and accelerate its Flowing: For, I believe, it will be granted, without Difficulty, that the Blood which is not broken, agitated, and attenuated, by Remedies, can be no otherwiſe ſo, but by the Means of the Veſſels; ſo that, if it is in Action, it muſt owe this Action ſolely to the Spring and Vibration of the Solids; what other Cauſe, on the preſent Hypotheſis, can move the Blood? what other Mover, what other Principle can give any other ways Agitation to this Fluid? Does it move itſelf? Has it in its own Stock wherewitha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to put itſelf in Play? Does it draw its Power from its own Choice? I appeal to Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> himſelf, who undermines the Foundation of the Blood's inteſtine Power, and who, from the Beginning of his Work, gives a mortal Blow to the Fermentation
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:0650600600:74"/>already ſo much diſcredited, and the finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Stroke to the Diſgrace of this unhappy Hypotheſis, by the deſolating Refuſal of his Protection to it, leaving it helpleſs in black Deſpair, and reducing it to a Condition ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly abandon'd. The abſurd Hypotheſis, ſays he, of the Fermentations and Leavens is ſcarce any more in Vogue; 'tis even a long Time ſince the ſoundeſt Part of the Learned have baniſh'd it out of their Writings: <hi>Sed exolevit ferè hodie abſurda illa de fermentis Doctrina, &amp; a ſaniſſimis ſaltem ſcriptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, jamdiù exploſa eſt.</hi> See then this Idol of the new Phyſick, and of the modern Philoſophy, neglected, abandon'd, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd! What a Spectacle! a Doctrine which attracted ſuch a Crowd of Partiſans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecomes deſerted and forlorn; the predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Hypotheſis, the ſovereign Doctrine, the reigning Opinion, is falling into Widow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, into Contempt and Slavery; is made a Tributary, languiſhing in Obſcurity, and ſighing all alone, finding none to comfort her in her Miſery, and to raiſe her from the Ground, where ſhe miſerably grovels: Even thoſe that liſted under her Standard are aſham'd to defend her Cauſe, quit her Side, and leave her in the Lurch. The Ways by which it was pretended to explain all the <hi>Animal OEconomy,</hi> Ways beaten and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beaten with ſo much Pomp and Solemnity, are now no more frequented; the Niches of the Ferments are deſtroy'd, and the Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:0650600600:75"/>even the Inſtruments of Fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are taken from her, poor Thing! ſhe has not allow'd her a Space ample enough to make her Puſhes and her Sallies in; pent in Canals too ſtreight, in Places too cloſe for her; where ſhe undergoes the Cruelty of being oppreſs'd and ſtifled, deſtitute, in theſe inextricable Difficulties, of all Relief, and unable to defend herſelf; all her Charms are fled from her; and her armed Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries have laid violent Hands on all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to her, depriving her of all that ſhe can deſire, or that can give her any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage O ye that have run thro' all the different Hypotheſes! conſider if there is one of 'em all ſo cruelly treated, and that languiſhes in a Situation ſo very deplorable as hers. What! ſays one, the Doctrine of the Ferments is no more in Uſe! and the <hi>Literati</hi> have hiſs'd it off the Stage; ſad Caſe! Is this the Fermentation that a while ago made ſuch a Figure! Can you know her again by this Picture, you that uſed ſo to idolize her! you that ſtill are ſo fond of her, is it poſſible, Sirs, that this can be the Object of your Delight and tendereſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes! This Offal, this May-game, this Bitch with a Bottle at her Tail, can this be your Favourite Miſtreſs! Can you own this your Idol in ſo diſguis'd a Metamorphoſis Fermentation is then in Diſgrace with Dr. <hi>Freind;</hi> and according to him, with al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the beſt Authors too. Then he can't admi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:0650600600:76"/>in the Blood a Virtue proper to make it cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate; it is therefore allow'd to believe, that the Motion, the Swiftneſs of the Blood, in the natural State of Health, is the Effect of the Action of the Veſſels that preſs, puſh, and hurry it; and the Acknowledgment of Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> who rejects this Fermentation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eads to this Thought, conducts to this Conſequence. This juſt comes to what we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave been demonſtrating, that the Blood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>annot make an ill Uſe of the Celerity which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t has from the Veſſels, thereby to break <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe; whence it follows, either that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erms can never naturally flow, without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Aid of Medicines; or that the Velocity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Blood is not neceſſary to the Flux, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut is even contrary to it. If the Fluid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aturally holds its Celerity from the Solid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich haſtens its Way; and if, by Virtue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f this Celerity, the Fluid cannot break the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olid, as hath been prov'd; then, of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſity, Nature alone cannot puſh the Terms, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nleſs it be the Abundance, and not the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>city of the Blood that makes 'em flow. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> makes the principal Mover <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Flux to conſiſt in the Swiftneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Blood; and the principal Hinderance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ordinary Cauſe of the Suppreſſion, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſiſt in its Slowneſs. So that it does not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em poſſible, on the Principles of this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>or, to explain how the Flowing of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erms is procur'd by Nature alone. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>econd Reflection I have to make is, That
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:0650600600:77"/>the Fluids attenuated, bruiſed, and broken; by the Force of Emmenagogues, do not ſo ſtrongly oppoſe the Action of the Solids; the Blood render'd ſupple, flowing, and docile, by theſe Medicaments, ſuffers itſelf to be led, ſubdued, and jerk'd along by the Veſſels, which, finding no more, as before, an invincible Obſtacle in the groſs and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact Maſs that the Remedies have reduc'd and ſubtiliz'd, recover their Eaſe, reſume their Vigour, and ſet themſelves at Liberty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Whence we ſee, that the Emmenagogues at the ſame Time that they ſet the Bloo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at large, ſet alſo the Veſſels at their Eaſe too. Now, being at their Eaſe, 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent, that they are not ſo liable to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> broken; yet the Blood, upon which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Remedies act, might be ſo abundant, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it could not ſwell and rarify, without for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cing the Canals to burſt: In this Caſe, if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Medicines melt and rarify it, it ſeems tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they will infallibly occaſion the breaking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the vaſcular Tunicks, which, as they can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not ſtretch any further, muſt needs crac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> But we have obſerv'd, that the Blood, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riv'd to ſuch a Pitch of Abundance, to ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Degree of Groſſneſs, is not fit to be wroug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon by Attenuants, becauſe theſe can la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no Hold of it: We have obſerv'd, in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Circumſtance, the Uſefulneſs, and even th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Neceſſity of Bleeding, to ſet the Attenuan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> at Work; therefore, in an exceſſive <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thora,</hi> in an extream Viſcidity, Emmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gogues,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:0650600600:78"/>being equally as impotent as the Veſſels, are as little able to do any thing as theſe are. That which hinders theſe from ſtrongly contracting, hinders alſo thoſe from faſtening upon the thicken'd Humours; whence it ſeems to follow, that the Blood cannot apply even the Velocity which it receives from the Emmenagogues to break the Veſſels; becauſe the Remedies cannot animate it ſo much as it ſhou'd be, but with the Aſſiſtance of the elaſtick Veſſels. They do not indeed import Fluidity; but this is not progreſſive Motion, the Motion of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, which is not to be obtain'd but by the ſyſtaltick Virtue of the Veſſels. The Blood attenuated by Emmenagogues, may well become Fluid; but it cannot acquire Velocity, ſave only by being puſh'd, beaten, and jerk'd along. According to Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> the Stroke of the Blood is that which makes its greateſt Strength: Now, the Stroke, that is to ſay, the Briskneſs of the Shock, the Violence of the Percuſſion, does not preciſely come from the Fluidity; but, becauſe the Fluid is ſtrongly ſtruck upon by the Solid, which Blows it again retaliates, and, in its Turn, re-buffets the Solid; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if the Veſſels were flat and unactive, in Torture, and in Captivity, and the Fluids left to the ſole Action of the Attenuants, theſe Fluids would not receive Force enough wherewith to ſtrike upon the Solids; they would acquire but an indolent Fluidity,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:0650600600:79"/>only a Diſ-union of their Parts, a Diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Maſs, incapable of any great Effects; they could not contract that Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoſity neceſſary to give Strength to their Blow, Briskneſs to their Shock, Power and Force to their Percuſſion. Our Author him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf deduces the Velocity of the Blood from the vehement Pulſation of the Heart, and of the Arteries; a Pulſation produc'd, as he ſays, by the Affluence of the animal Spirits: Whereas, theſe animal Spirits them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves can be nothing but the Work and Effect of the Spring of thoſe Parts that agitate and puſh them to the Degree of Fineneſs which they have. Therefore the Velocity of the Blood is the Effect of the Expulſion of the Veſſels; wherefore, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make Uſe thereof to break them: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if Emmenagogues excite the Flux of the <hi>Menſes,</hi> this cannot be by the Velocity which they impart to the Blood; but rather by the Swelling, the Rarefaction, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly Turgeſcence which they produce therein; by the Means of which the vaſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Tunicks give way, not to the Force of the Percuſſion, but to the Exceſs of their own Dilation. Another Difficulty might be ſtarted againſt me; the Veſſels, in the Effort they make to drive on with Swift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Percipitation the Blood ſubjected to their Power, may they not break them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? Are they not even more liable to be broken, being active than unactive; by
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:0650600600:80"/>Exerciſe, than Indolence; by Fatigue, than Repoſe? Are not they who labour hardeſt, moſt expos'd to the Misfortune of burſting Veins and Arteries? Have not we ſeen Veſſels broken by the Shocks of a violent Cough, and the cruelleſt Hemorrhages produc'd by the Heat of a burning Summer? It is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtrange, that the uterine Veſſels, tho' vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous enough to animate the Blood, ſhou'd yield to the Blow of which themſelves are the Cauſe; and their Vigour, far from forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and defending them againſt their Burſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, only renders them more proper, more fit and diſpos'd for it. I own the Veſſels may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roken by their own Pains and Fatigue; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t muſt be alſo confeſs'd, that it is by Accident when this Misfortune happens, and that theſe are Caſes for which none undertakes to give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nvariable Rules, and Geometrical Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trations, ſuch as Dr. <hi>Freind</hi> has attempted to give us; there is too much Uncertainty in the Rupture of the Veſſels; and 'tis too fortuitous a Caſe, to draw and deduce thence an Effect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſure, ſo conſtant, ſo natural, ſo regular, as the Phaenomenon of the Monthly Courſes. Beſides, the Rupture of the Veſſels is not a thing ſo common as one imagines; bleeding at the Noſe, ſpitting of Blood, Accidents very frequent and vulgarly attributed to Ruptures, don't ſo much denote broken Veſſels, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch as meet diſcharging Canals, that terminate in the Sanguines; and do not ſo much declare the Extravaſation of the Blood,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:0650600600:81"/>as its Paſſage into the Emunctories. Why, indeed, ſo few Ruptures in the ſlendereſt, tendereſt Fibres within the Body, which are remote from Places of Diſcharge, whilſt we diſcover ſo many and ſo often juſt by the Iſſues, near the Excretories, and in the Blood-Veſſels, moſt within the Reach of the Outlets, moſt known and beſt remark'd? This Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation juſtly intimates that which is attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Rupture of the Canals, is uſually but the Effect of the Intruſion of the Blood into the Lymphaticks. Theſe ſeem to me the ſtrongeſt Objections that can be made againſt me; and the proper Anſwers to be made to them: Dr. <hi>Freind</hi>'s Syſtem, therefore, cannot be defended, and ſtill lies under the ſame Difficulties.</p>
            <p>Yet, after all, can't flatter myſelf, that I have, with any Solidity, taken up ſo learned a Man as Dr. <hi>Freind:</hi> What I have hitherto advanced I look upon it rather as a Web of Objections to be anſwer'd, than as a Criticiſm to be redoubted: If I have not attack'd my Author with Advantage, I ſhall at leaſt have the Glory of having ſtudied him with Application. It is always good to betake ourſelves to the beſt Authors, 'tis pleaſant to contemplate their Beauties; and even when we attack them unſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, yet don't we apply thereto, without reaping an Advantage. But, ſhould my Objections be made with ſome Foundation, I would not take it amiſs to be compared
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:0650600600:82"/>to a rebellious Child, who battles its own Nurſe, becauſe, by her ſucculent and well-condition'd Milk, ſhe has ſupplied him with the Strength to do it. Foſter'd by the Reading of Dr. <hi>Freind,</hi> imbu'd with his Leſſons, improv'd by his Knowledge, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten'd by his Light, I have made uſe thereof againſt himſelf. I own, I ſhould have had no Succeſs in engaging him, if I had not improv'd by ſtudying him; if I had not gather'd my Knowledge from reading and meditating him; and if, before I made War upon him, I had not learnt my Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline under him. If we gain a Victory over good Authors, 'tis becauſe themſelves ſupply us with the Means to gain it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
