<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Sheridan's argument in the case of Daly against Magee, on a motion to discharge the defendant on common bail</title>
            <author>Sheridan, Richard, d. 1793.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>25 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008 September</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004815612</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T171024</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW124304509</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K119722.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3324304509</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECLW</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">1296001000</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Sheridan's argument in the case of Daly against Magee, on a motion to discharge the defendant on common bail</title>
                  <author>Sheridan, Richard, d. 1793.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>London printed, and Dublin re-printed for J. Moore,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Dublin] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1790]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a half-title.</note>
                  <note>The case was heard in 1790.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part of 'A collection of tracts on the doctrine of fiats', Dublin, 1791.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT171024.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:1296001000:1"/>
            <p>MR. SHERIDAN's ARGUMENT IN THE CASE OF DALY AGAINST MAGEE.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1296001000:2"/>
            <p>MR. SHERIDAN's ARGUMENT IN THE CASE OF <hi>DALY AGAINST MAGEE,</hi> ON A MOTION TO DISCHARGE THE DEFENDANT ON COMMON BAIL.</p>
            <p>LONDON PRINTED, AND DUBLIN RE-PRINTED FOR J. MOORE, No. 45, COLLEGE-GREEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:1296001000:3"/>
            <p>☞ <hi>It may be neceſſary juſt to mention, for the Information of thoſe not of the Profeſſion of the Law, That</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A JUDGE's FIAT is a Warrant or Authority to the Officer of the Court, to iſſue a Writ marked in ſuch Sum as the Fiat directs, on which Writ the Defendant is arreſted, and muſt either find Bail to the Amount of ſuch Sum or remain in Priſon.</p>
            <p>SPECIAL BAIL is Bail by Sureties to the amount of a certain Sum.</p>
            <p>COMMON BAIL is only an Appearance to the Action, by Attorney, without any Security.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:1296001000:4"/>
            <head>IN THE KING's BENCH. <hi>Michaelmas Term, 30th Geo.</hi> 3.</head>
            <head>DALY againſt MAGEE.</head>
            <p>MR. JOHN MAGEE being in confinement under a Writ, marked for the ſum of 4000<hi>l.</hi> at the ſuit of the Plaintiff <hi>for defamation,</hi> by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of A FIAT for that purpoſe, granted by the Lord Chief Juſtice, cauſed a notice of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing purport to be ſerved on the Plaintiff's Attorney.</p>
            <p>SIR,</p>
            <p>COUNSEL on behalf of the Defendant will move the Court the firſt opportunity, to ſet aſide the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1296001000:5"/>
order made in this cauſe, on the 27th day of June laſt, whereby it was ordered, that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant ſhould give SPECIAL BAIL in this cauſe, to the amount of the ſum marked at the foot of the Writ of <hi>Capias ad reſpondendum,</hi> which iſſued in this cauſe; and that the Defendant's COMMON APPEARANCE may be taken, and ſtand without holding him to SPECIAL BAIL. But if the Court ſhould not be pleaſed to grant ſuch motion, Counſel will then move the Court to vary the ſaid order, and that the ſum for which the ſaid writ was marked, and the Defendant thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to find Bail to ſuch amount, may be RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DUCED from 4000<hi>l.</hi> to 500<hi>l.</hi> and the notice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes in ſuch caſe with a tender of Bail to the amount of <hi>the laſt mentioned ſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>N.B. Similar Notices were ſerved in the caſe of Brennan againſt Magee, Tracy againſt Magee, and Higgins againſt Magee, who had ſeverally obtained Fiats on the ground of DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FAMATION.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1296001000:6"/>
            <head>MR. SHERIDAN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am in this caſe Counſel for Mr. <hi>John Magee,</hi> the alledged Proprietor of a News Paper, called, The <hi>Dublin Evening Poſt;</hi> and I could wiſh that the notice on his behalf, and on which I move, had not a double aſpect; I could wiſh that it had been confined to his claim of <hi>right,</hi> and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to an application for <hi>favor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When we move, that a <hi>common appearance</hi> may be taken, without holding him to <hi>Special Bail,</hi> a great queſtion of conſtitutional and public im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance is involved in the ſubject; but when we apply to <hi>reduce</hi> the ſum, the application appears like an appeal to the <hi>diſcretion</hi> of the Court. My duty to my client, obliges me to ſubmit my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations in each point of view, though I ſhould rather argue it in the abſtract, for another reaſon, I might thereby avoid the ſtrange ſtuff and mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial which the Plaintiff has introduced as <hi>merits</hi> into his affidavit, and I might thereby avoid (to uſe a dramatic quotation in a caſe partly theatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1296001000:7"/>
that ſtile of ſpeech <q rend="inline margQuotes">"which though it may make the unſkilful laugh, cannot but make the judicious grieve; the cenſure of one of whom, out-weighs, in my mind, a whole theatre of others."</q>
            </p>
            <p>My Lords, I am in this caſe, with due defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to contend, that the learned Judge was not warranted by <hi>law</hi> in iſſuing his Fiat for <hi>any ſum;</hi> for that in this caſe <hi>common bail,</hi> which is no more than <hi>an appearance</hi> for the party, and properly ſpeaking no bail at all, is all that the <hi>law</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; but if your Lordſhips ſhall be of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the learned Judge was authoriſed by law in iſſuing ſuch Fiat, holding the Defendant to 4000<hi>l.</hi> bail, then I am to ſubmit to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, that you are bound in conſcience to reduce the ſum, becauſe you are bound, and it is the true ſpirit of the law, to hold him to no greater bail, than in your conſcience you ſhall think the <hi>Plaintiff can recover:</hi> and here my Lords it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to call your attention to the affidavit of the Plaintiff; it is <hi>his caſe,</hi> and therefore I preſume, put in the ſtrongeſt and beſt manner that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of that caſe would allow; it is the ground upon which a Judge's Fiat for 4000<hi>l.</hi> iſſued; and there never was an affidavit containing the griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the party complaining, more <hi>weak,</hi> and more <hi>defective:</hi> THERE IS NOT THROUGHOUT
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1296001000:8"/>
THIS AFFIDAVIT A SINGLE PER QUOD. The al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legded Libel is libellous only by <hi>forced</hi> conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by <hi>violent</hi> interpretation of an apparently <hi>unmeaning</hi> poem: the damages in amount are ſo far from approaching to <hi>any</hi> degree of certainty, that it is rather obvious, that <hi>none</hi> were <hi>actually</hi> ſuſtained: it <hi>hints</hi> at damages which <hi>may be,</hi> not which <hi>are</hi> ſuffered; and ſuch damages are <hi>ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary:</hi> they are <hi>poetic;</hi> they are in the <hi>fancy;</hi> the <hi>conception</hi> of the party <hi>intereſted;</hi> of him who ſeeks redreſs in <hi>damages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Richard Daly</hi> ſtiles himſelf, in this, his affidavit, Manager of the Theatre Royal in the City of Dublin. He ſtates that the Defendant, Mr. <hi>John Magee,</hi> is (as he believes) Printer and Publiſher of a certain News Paper, called The <hi>Dublin Evening Poſt,</hi> in which Paper he, <hi>John Magee,</hi> cauſed to be publiſhed a defamatory Poem of the <hi>tenor</hi> in the Affidavit.</p>
            <p>I ſhould be ſorry to feel myſelf under any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to recite this Poem to the Court; it is in truth a very ſtrange compoſition, but may have its merit with thoſe who underſtand it; but as it is the cauſe of a Fiat, for 4000<hi>l.</hi> and as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, or rather is itſelf, the offence for which my client is in dureſs, until he ſhall procure bail to that amount; I have ſelected and ſhall faithfully
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1296001000:9"/>
ſtate ſuch paſſages or parts of this poem, as by <hi>poſſibility</hi> may be deemed libellous.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <l>"<hi>The Gamblers retired and Roſcius alone.</hi>"—</l>
               </q>I am free to admit that Mr. <hi>Daly,</hi> being Manager of the Theatre, <hi>may be</hi> the Roſcius intended by the Poet, but this conceſſion is ſomewhat unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, as Mr. <hi>Daly</hi> in his Affidavit, ſwears that <hi>he</hi> is the perſon ſo deſcribed, or in other words <hi>that he is</hi> ROSCIUS.—How far this may be a Libel on Roſcius deceaſed, on Roſcius the companion of Cicero, the name at leaſt will ſcarcely be deemed a Libel on Roſcius the companion of Higgins.</p>
            <p>Roſcius laments:<q>
                  <l>"<hi>That humble Actreſſes will no longer obedient bend:</hi>"</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>That,<q>
                  <l>"<hi>Franciſco now delights the admiring throng.</hi>"</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He then proceeds to kill himſelf,<q>
                  <l>"<hi>The tragic tin bent harmleſs on his breaſt.</hi>"</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Then Cupid arrives, to whom Roſcius ſays,<q>
                  <l>"<hi>Does ſome lady court me to her arms,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>And buy with brilliant gold my manly charms.</hi>"</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:1296001000:10"/>
Cupid replies,<q>
                  <l>"<hi>There live, he ſaid, ſome men of fame well known,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>For punctual dealing, and to candour prone:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>—the Wights have money;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>Honeſty againſt cunning has no force,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>—we'll fleece the villains.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Here a Judge is to conceive, and a jury here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after are to conceive, that the Lottery-Office Keepers are underſtood, who ſometime ago were ſo ſucceſsfully, and ſo <hi>ſurpriſingly</hi> hit. I am en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to give to this ſilly poem all the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed effect that conjecture can admit:<q>
                  <l>"<hi>I know the wily plot</hi> RICARDO <hi>cry'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>The</hi> DOCTOR <hi>in thoſe ſchemes is fully try'd:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>The</hi> DOCTOR <hi>ſails to the Cambrian ſhore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>Then ſtraight to the enchanted fane,—</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>—the prieſts the cabaliſtic numbers cry,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>The Doctor ties them round a pigeon's neck,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>—who flies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>And on Franciſco's portal plumes his wings.</hi>"</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the <hi>criminal</hi> extracts from the alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Libel, a poem full of nonſenſe, ribaldry, and bombaſt, not to be matched in a Mock Tragedy, truly farcical, were it not that the ſum of 4000<hi>l.</hi> has changed the performance to a Tragi-Comedy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:1296001000:11"/>
For the publication of this poem the defendant has been arreſted under a writ iſſued by authority of a Fiat, and marked for 4000<hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lords, there have been of late, and I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it, many bold, impudent, plain, and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſible Libels; why are the weakeſt ſelected to diſgrace the records of the Court, and to bring contempt upon the Juſtice of the country.—And now, my Lords, let me call your attention to what ought to be the <hi>material</hi> part of an affidavit, to warrant a Fiat in any caſe; to that part which relates to <hi>the damage ſuſtained.</hi> In this caſe the <hi>ſingle inſtance</hi> in which the Plaintiff <hi>endeavours</hi> to ſhew any ſpecial damage, HE FAILS IN THE AT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEMPT, and the fair inference, from his own words, is, that he has ſuffered <hi>little, if any.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After ſwearing that he had expended conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſums, in the embelliſhment of the Theatre Royal, and that he has hitherto ſupported a good repute and credit; he proceeds, and ſtates in his affidavit <q rend="inline margQuotes">"that by the falſe and ſcandalous publications concerning him, he has already experienced their injurious tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>as</hi> a very eminent performer, whom he had retained in Great Britain to act at his Theatre in this City, did, from the falſe and ſcandalous publications againſt him, expreſs <hi>a doubt</hi> of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1296001000:12"/>
his credit and punctuality, and that therefore <hi>a large</hi> and <hi>conſiderable</hi> ſum muſt be paid in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance; and <hi>if it had not been</hi> for the interfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſome friends, <hi>he would have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived</hi> of the advantage of ſuch performer."</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now, what is the inference here?—he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced nothing, and the actreſs came and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled her engagement:—take it, that he did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance—<hi>how much</hi>—and where is the magnitude of the injury, in advancing to a performer a ſum, <hi>on account,</hi> if the manager ever intended to pay? and this is the <hi>only</hi> ſtatement of an injury <hi>actually</hi> ſuſtained.</p>
            <p>The uſe of indefinite words in an affidavit, may be ſometimes very convenient, but when injury is to be redreſſed in damages, and the party held to bail, the ſecurity ſhould be proportioned to the probable redreſs; and the law requires ſome meaſure, whereby ſuch ſecurity may be <hi>limited</hi> and not <hi>extended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Plaintiff in this caſe feeling, perhaps, that a Fiat for 4000<hi>l.</hi> on the ground he has ſtated, and which I have followed, would be as ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as it is outrageous, adds, that he has chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, among whom are ſour growing-up daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1296001000:13"/>
who, in their <hi>future</hi> proſpects in life, <hi>may</hi> receive conſiderable injury; and he then ſwears, that he has <hi>good reaſon</hi> to be <hi>convinced</hi> he <hi>has</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered damages to the amount of FOUR THOU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SAND POUNDS and upwards—how?—by an <hi>advance</hi> to a performer, and the injuries his family or himſelf <hi>may hereafter</hi> ſuffer. See, my Lords, the danger that might ariſe from any man carving the meaſure of his own redreſs, in eſtimating the value of the injury he has ſuſtained; that which is but <hi>ideal</hi> will become <hi>real,</hi> and he will tell you he has <hi>good reaſon</hi> to be <hi>convinced:</hi> and I beſeech your Lordſhips attention to this, becauſe it illuſtrates the doctrine of the law (which I ſhall ſubmit to you) with reſpect to <hi>bail</hi> in actions of <hi>defamation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Plaintiff concludes his affidavit in ſtating, that John Magee (the Defendant) gives out that he is a man of <hi>very conſiderable property,</hi> as well in money as in ſeveral News Papers. Why this is introduced I cannot diſcover, it is introduced <hi>as true,</hi> and if true, it is a reaſon for a common appearance, becauſe the Plaintiff himſelf alledges a ſufficient reſponſibility in the Defendant whom he ſues.</p>
            <p>The Defendant, John Magee, has made an affidavit in aid of the preſent application, in which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1296001000:14"/>
he ſwears, that a writ iſſued in or as of laſt Trinity Term, to the Sheriffs of the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> marked for the ſum of 4000<hi>l.</hi> under authority of a Fiat granted by the Lord Chief Juſtice, and founded on an affidavit of Richard Daly the Plaintiff; that upon ſuch writ he was arreſted in <hi>June</hi> laſt; that in conſequence of a number of vexatious ſuits and proſecutions againſt him, and in conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the proceedings in this cauſe, and from the reiterated abuſe he has received in the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Journal, he is extremely injured in his credit, inſomuch, that though he has uſed every effort in his power, <hi>he cannot now procure bail in this cauſe for the amount of the ſum marked at the foot of ſaid writ,</hi> or to any larger amount than 500<hi>l.</hi> and ſaith, he verily believes, that the Plaintiff hath not ſuffered damage in this cauſe to any amount whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Your Lordſhips have now before you the facts or merits of the caſe, but I truſt your Lordſhips will decide on a great queſtion of public and of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutional importance, without any reference to the particular circumſtances of the preſent caſe; I reject them as unneceſſary, ſave only to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of the application, the <hi>reducement</hi> of the bail, which will alſo become unneceſſary, if your Lordſhips ſhall be of opinion, that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1296001000:15"/>
is not bound by law to give <hi>any ſecurity whatever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then, my Lords, I with confidence aſſert, that <hi>a common appearance</hi> is all the law requires in actions of <hi>defamation,</hi> and to compel <hi>any ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> to <hi>any amount</hi> is an <hi>extortion</hi> on the ſubject, and <hi>illegal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is pleaſing to obſerve in what great eſteem the law holds <hi>perſonal freedom,</hi> juſtly conſidering the general liberty of the ſubject, as dependant on that of the individual; and ſo tender has the law been of this liberty, that no man could be deprived of his perſonal freedom, unleſs for ſome <hi>criminal, fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant</hi> offence, injurious to the government under which he lived, or for ſome <hi>tortius</hi> act, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with <hi>force,</hi> and conſequently <hi>in breach of the peace,</hi> which his allegiance and duty required him to keep and preſerve. It is thus well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in <hi>Crompton</hi>'s admirable introduction to a late very excellent compilation.</p>
            <p>I grant that the legal requiſition of bail, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called Special Bail, is, and has been, for many years leſs confined; but then, it has been extended from <hi>neceſſity,</hi> and upon <hi>principle;</hi> as in DEBT,—what is the rule of law—if the debt <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:1296001000:16"/>
amounts to a ſum <hi>certain,</hi> then the debtor may be held to <hi>ſpecial bail;</hi> but where the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is not <hi>abſolute</hi> but <hi>uncertain,</hi> and ſounds in damages—NOT SO:—And the principle, is;—the Plaintiff ſhall not be the <hi>judge</hi> of the injury he cannot <hi>aſcertain,</hi> becauſe it would make the Defendant the victim of the Plaintiff's <hi>conception.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Judge indeed may in ſeveral caſes grant a Fiat, to hold a party to ſpecial bail, but in every caſe, it can only be where the demand is <hi>certain</hi> as IN DEBT, or where the injury is <hi>ſo outrageous,</hi> that damages muſt <hi>neceſſarily</hi> have been ſuffered; there the Judge has ſome <hi>meaſure,</hi> ſome <hi>guide;</hi> but even there he is bound to be <hi>moderate;</hi> for in the language of the Bill of Rights <q rend="inline margQuotes">"exceſſive bail ought not to be required."</q>
            </p>
            <p>And here, my Lords, I think I take the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine in its utmoſt latitude: In caſes of DEFAMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION or SLANDER (ſave only <hi>two</hi> exceptions which I ſhall mention,) a Judge is not warranted to grant a Fiat, for the Defendant ſhall be held only to <hi>common bail.</hi> As to SPECIAL BAIL, caſes of defamation are excepted in every authority, from the oldeſt down to <hi>Crompton's</hi> late Digeſt on the ſubject.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:1296001000:17"/>
The firſt mention of Special Bail in ſlander was in the reign of <hi>Charles</hi> II. and that only in the caſe of <hi>ſlandering the title of lands;</hi> previous to that time, ſpecial bail was required in no caſe of <hi>perſonal</hi> ſlander: Afterwards ſpecial bail was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> and no further; ſo that the two exceptions evidently ſupport the doctrine.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Crompton</hi> 29, title BAIL, "in treſpaſs, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault, battery, conſpiracy, falſe impriſonment, there ſhall be <hi>common bail</hi> only, <hi>unleſs on a motion or order made by the Court or a Judge:</hi> your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips will obſerve, that this ſaving of motion, or order, applies only to <hi>ſuch</hi> actions, in which, in the firſt inſtance, common bail is all the law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; and you will obſerve what follows: <q rend="inline margQuotes">"IN SLANDER common bail <hi>only,</hi> unleſs in ſlander of <hi>title,</hi> and <hi>then</hi> common or ſpecial in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of the Court."</q> This is laid down as the law in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> 1654: and the authority adds, as the practice <hi>after</hi> that period, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"<hi>or unleſs ſpoken of a perſon of quality.</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>This complimentary conceſſion was introduced, perhaps, conſidering peers as the hereditary legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the realm, the king's hereditary counſellors, and forming the Court of ultimate appeal and final juriſdiction; the welfare of the empire depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1296001000:18"/>
in a degree, on <hi>their</hi> good name and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. So in <hi>Ray.</hi> 74—Earl of <hi>Stampford</hi> againſt <hi>Goodall,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"in <hi>ſcandalum magnatum,</hi> the Plaintiff may have ſpecial bail on motion and order."</q>
            </p>
            <p>Lord Chief Baron <hi>Comyn</hi> in his Digeſt Vol. I. Fol. 507, enumerates the caſes where ſpecial bail, may be required; where the debt or damage in an action of debt, detinue, treſpaſs, action upon the caſe (<hi>except in ſlander</hi>) amounts to 20<hi>l.</hi> SPECI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AL BAIL, ſo where the damages are <hi>uncertain,</hi> the Judges in their diſcretion may grant ſpecial bail, as in battery, <hi>if it appears to be outrageous,</hi> in conſpiracy, falſe impriſonment—<hi>in ſlander of title,</hi> or, <hi>ſcandalum magnatum.</hi> There in <hi>ſlander</hi> ſpecial bail is <hi>confined</hi> to the two inſtances; in the caſes where ſpecial bail is allowed of <hi>right,</hi> it is founded on the <hi>certainty</hi> of the injury, where it ariſes from <hi>diſcretion,</hi> it is meaſured by the <hi>enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> of the offence.</p>
            <p>In 1 <hi>Blackſtone</hi> 192, <hi>Smith</hi> againſt <hi>Frazer.</hi>—In treſpaſs and aſſault, the Plaintiff made affidavit before <hi>Forſter</hi> Juſtice, to hold the Defendant to bail; <hi>on the flagrant circumſtances of which</hi> he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected 200<hi>l.</hi> bail to be given.</p>
            <p>My Lords, there is not any diſtinction taken with reſpect to <hi>bail,</hi> between ſlander written and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1296001000:19"/>
uttered; between defamation by <hi>libel</hi> or <hi>parole.</hi>—there is no variance, as to the doctrine to be found in the books, and the <hi>principle</hi> cannot be affected by the <hi>nature</hi> or <hi>claſs</hi> of the DEFAMATION.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Siderfin,</hi> 183, <hi>Chetwin</hi> againſt <hi>Skinner:</hi> it is there laid down, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"in action ſur le caſe pur parole <hi>ou outrement,</hi> NUL SPE BAIL."</q>
            </p>
            <p>I call upon gentlemen to ſhew any diſtinction taken in any authority, between ſlander <hi>written</hi> and SLANDER <hi>ſpoken, with reſpect to the doctrine of bail,</hi> I know there are diſtinctions between <hi>libel</hi> and ſlander <hi>ſpoken;</hi> I know one has juſtly a greater degree of criminality annexed to it, than the other: but with regard to <hi>bail,</hi> I ſay, DEFA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MATION is the general head, including every ſpecies of ſlander, written, painted, engraved, ſpoken, <hi>ou outrement,</hi> or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>My Lords, ſo tenacious is the law of perſonal liberty, and ſo tender have Judges been with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to it, that even in caſes where the law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogniſed, and allowed ſpecial bail, where even the ground of the application ſeemed fair and reaſonable, Courts have refuſed to hold the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſpecial bail, becauſe the caſe <hi>might not</hi> ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately warrant it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:1296001000:20"/>
In 2 <hi>Strange,</hi> 1157, <hi>Heathcot</hi> againſt <hi>Goſlin.</hi>—The affidavit to hold to bail was, that the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant borrowed 2000<hi>l.</hi> of the Plaintiff on bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ree, <hi>which money is now due and owing</hi> to this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent, by virtue of the ſaid bond, <hi>as thereby may appear</hi>—Objected, that this was no oath of the debt; for ſuppoſe every penny is paid, and a ſeparate receipt taken, yet upon the face of the bond the whole will appear due, <hi>et per curiam;</hi> it is not ſufficient; the Plaintiff would have made a <hi>ſupplemental</hi> affidavit, but the court refuſed to receive it; for the act of parliament requires a full oath, previous to the iſſuing the proceſs, that Defendants may not be <hi>haraſed;</hi> and therefore in this caſe the Defendant was diſcharged upon <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> bail.</p>
            <p>In the preſent caſe, Mr. <hi>Daly</hi> has made a <hi>ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent</hi> affidavit; but ſuch affidavit could be no ground for the arreſt, for it was not <hi>in eſſe,</hi> when the Fiat was granted.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Strange,</hi> 975, <hi>Gammage</hi> againſt <hi>Watkin</hi>—The original debt was <hi>under</hi> the ſum entitled to ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al bail; but the coſts ſwelled it <hi>over;</hi> and the Plaintiff had judgment, on which he brought debt, and held the Defendant to bail; and now upon motion the court ordered <hi>common bail</hi> to be accepted; for as the original demand did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1296001000:21"/>
bail, the addition of coſts will not alter the caſe.</p>
            <p>And yet, my Lords, here, the coſts and the original demand were liquidated, and in law became <hi>one debt;</hi> but the Court in its deciſion, guided by attention and attachment to perſonal li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, made the diſtinction in its favour; and the like attention and attachment appear to govern in every caſe.</p>
            <p>4 <hi>Burrow,</hi> 655, <hi>Pomp.</hi> verſ. <hi>Ludrigſon.</hi>—A rule for diſcharging the Defendant upon <hi>common</hi> bail was made abſolute; the affidavit to hold him to <hi>ſpecial</hi> bail, <hi>not</hi> being <hi>poſſitive;</hi> which, it is the eſtabliſhed rule of the court, <q rend="inline">"that it <hi>muſt</hi> be."</q> This was the caſe of a merchant in <hi>London,</hi> whoſe correſpondent in <hi>Sweden</hi> had ſent him over the accounts from <hi>Sweden, where the debt aroſe:</hi> and conſequently the Plaintiff, the merchant in <hi>London,</hi> could only ſwear to his <hi>belief,</hi> with a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi> to the accounts ſent to him from <hi>Sweden;</hi> the fact itſelf not being within his own perſonal knowledge: ſo that the affidavit could not have been more poſitive than it was, unleſs the correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondent in <hi>Sweden</hi> could have come over to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> to ſwear it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:1296001000:22"/>
2 <hi>Strange,</hi> 1209, <hi>Rios</hi> verſ. <hi>Relifante.</hi>—The affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit to hold to <hi>ſpecial</hi> bail was made by a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in <hi>London,</hi> ſwearing that the Defendant owed the Plaintiff 270<hi>l.</hi> as appears by an affidavit made by the Plaintiff in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> which he, the Deponent, <hi>believes</hi> to be true, <hi>et per curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am;</hi> there can only be <hi>common</hi> bail; the oath abroad is no ground, and there is nothing but <hi>belief,</hi> which is not ſufficient.</p>
            <p>Your Lordſhips will obſerve, that theſe are <hi>commercial</hi> caſes, and from the nature of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and the ſituation of parties connected with it, ſimilar caſes may every day occur; yet we find no attempt at an argument founded on <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> or <hi>public benefit</hi> to extend the power of the Court.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Strange,</hi> 1226, <hi>Claphamſon</hi> verſ. <hi>Bowman.</hi> The Plaintiff's BOOK-KEEPER, ſwore, that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant was indebted to the Plaintiff in 3400<hi>l.</hi> for money had and received by the Defendant, to the uſe of the Plaintiff, <hi>as this Deponent verily believes;</hi> and the Court held it not ſufficient to hold the Defendant to <hi>ſpecial</hi> bail.</p>
            <p>This was the caſe of a <hi>book-keeper,</hi> ſwearing as fully as he conſcientiouſly could; no merchant keeps his own books, becauſe he cannot be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1296001000:23"/>
to prove any debt due to himſelf; his clerk who muſt be his witneſs, who ſhould be privy to the dealing, and who keeps the account, can ſcarcely extend his oath, were he ever ſo correct beyond the beſt of his belief; yet, in ſuch caſe, if the charge be not POSITIVE <hi>common</hi> bail only is allowed.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Strange,</hi> 1219, <hi>Walrond</hi> verſ. <hi>Franſham,</hi> an executrix in order to hold the Defendant to bail, made an affidavit, that he was indebted to her teſtator (ſo much) <hi>as appears by the books of the teſtator;</hi> and it was held inſufficient and <hi>common</hi> bail ordered.</p>
            <p>Here could have been no <hi>poſitive</hi> affidavit; the creditor was dead; the Plaintiff was an exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutrix, and ſued in ſuch right; the office is highly favoured in law; the aſſets (of which credits may make a principal part) are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for the beſt purpoſes; and among the firſt, the payment of the teſtator's debts: yet in this caſe, the caſe, I ſay, of an <hi>executrix,</hi> ſuing in the right of another, in whom no private or perſonal intereſt could be preſumed, and laying before the Court the beſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in her power—<hi>common</hi> bail only.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:1296001000:24"/>
Compare, my Lords, ſuch caſes with the preſent, and can you doubt; compare ſuch af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidavits with that of Mr. Daly, whoſe <hi>preſent</hi> loſſes are the conjecture, ſurmiſe, apprehenſion and belief of <hi>future</hi> injuries.</p>
            <p>The caſes I have quoted are caſes within the deſcription, and reach of <hi>ſpecial</hi> bail; the caſe of Daly is that of <hi>defamation,</hi> entitled only, as I apprehend, to <hi>common</hi> bail; certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to no more, where no <hi>actual</hi> damage is ſworn to have been ſuffered, certainly, not to the extent, which confines him <hi>before</hi> trial to an amount, which might be conſidered as exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive in damages <hi>after</hi> verdict.</p>
            <p>But, my Lords, laying aſide the parties, and the particular circumſtances of the caſe, what is the great and important queſtion?—if the exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and extending conſcience of a ſuitor, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to himſelf, in fancied injuries and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ills, can impoſe on the credulity of a Judge; if the Judge may, at his <hi>diſcretion,</hi> hold a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in priſon <hi>previous to trial,</hi> on terms with which he cannot comply; the <hi>diſcretion</hi> of the Judge may become the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of the Man; where then will be the difference between FIAT and LETTER DE CACHET: if ſuch be the practice, <hi>we are not ſafe;</hi> we have obtained
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1296001000:25"/>
nothing by the glorious Revolution; we have no ſecurity in the great Charter, in the Bill of Rights, in the Habeas Corpus: the atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of liberty may decorate the monument of a former conſtitution, or be like ſtandards taken from an enemy, hung up, old, torn and uſeleſs, ſave only to ſhew a degraded poſterity, the virtue and valour of their anceſtors.—No, my Lords, I truſt, that a great and able Judge, will this day add a brighter glory to his name, his rank, and office, than any in the power of Majeſty to confer, by nobly ſaying, what the beſt have ſaid, and what none but the beſt will ſay, <hi>I have been wrong:</hi>—a generous and a grateful people will applaud, bleſs, record the expreſſion, and honour even the error that cauſed it.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
