<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The patriot enterprize: or an address to Britain. A poem. Inscribed to the Right Hon. William Pitt, ... by Mr. Jones, author of The Earl of Essex. To which is added, The Prussian campaign, a poem. Celebrating the atchievements [sic] of Frederick the Great, in the years 1756-57. By William Dobson, L.L.B.</title>
            <author>Jones, Henry, 1721-1770.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>25 600dpi bitonal TIFF page images and SGML/XML encoded text</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009 October</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">004817460</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T178537</idno>
            <idno type="DOCNO">CW114807644</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K121574.000</idno>
            <idno type="GALEDOCNO">CW3314807644</idno>
            <idno type="CONTENTSET">ECLL</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGESETID">0874900200</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The patriot enterprize: or an address to Britain. A poem. Inscribed to the Right Hon. William Pitt, ... by Mr. Jones, author of The Earl of Essex. To which is added, The Prussian campaign, a poem. Celebrating the atchievements [sic] of Frederick the Great, in the years 1756-57. By William Dobson, L.L.B.</title>
                  <author>Jones, Henry, 1721-1770.</author>
                  <author>Dobson, William, b. 1714 or 15.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27,[1]p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>London, printed, and Dublin: re-printed for William Whitestone,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Dublin] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1758.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the Bodleian Library (Oxford).</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT178537.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=ecco-$1&amp;index=ecco&amp;pageId=ecco-$1-$20"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:0874900200:1"/>
            <p>THE PATRIOT ENTERPRIZE: OR An Addreſs to BRITAIN. A POEM.</p>
            <p>Inſcribed to the Right Hon. WILLIAM PITT, <hi>&amp;c. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Mr. JONES, Author of the Earl of ESSEX.</p>
            <p>To which is added, the <hi>PRUSSIAN</hi> CAMPAIGN, A POEM.</p>
            <p>Celebrating The ATCHIEVEMENTS of <hi>FREDERICK</hi> the GREAT, in the Years 1756—57.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM DOBSON,</hi> L.L.B.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and <hi>DUBLIN:</hi> Re-printed for WILLIAM WHITESTONE, oppoſite <hi>Dick</hi>'s-Coffee-Houſe in <hi>Skinner-Row.</hi> 1758.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0874900200:2"/>
                  <head>THE PATRIOT ENTERPRIZE.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>ONE Briton yet aſſerts that aweful name,</l>
                     <l>One Patriot yet ſupports the glorious theme!</l>
                     <l>Amidſt Corruption's flood ſtill ſpotleſs ſeen,</l>
                     <l>A heart ſtill faithful, and a hand ſtill clean.</l>
                     <l>Aſſiſt him, Seraphs, ſtoop from heav'n ye few</l>
                     <l>That once were Patriots, once were firm and true</l>
                     <l>To Britain's cauſe, ye kindred Spirits glow,</l>
                     <l>Deſcend, and ſhield him in this ſtorm below;</l>
                     <l>Your ſhelt'ring wings around his virtue ſpread,</l>
                     <l>Inſpire his heart, and crown with wreaths his head;</l>
                     <l>With gleams of Heav'n's pure light his ſoul array,</l>
                     <l>And all the glories of the Juſt diſplay</l>
                     <l>Full in his ſight; parental Heroes ſmile;</l>
                     <l>His virtue aid—O ſnatch from fate this Iſle;</l>
                     <l>Point out the paths you trod, the arms you bore,</l>
                     <l>Bid Truth return, and ancient worth reſtore;</l>
                     <l>Let Britain lift once more her laurel'd head</l>
                     <l>Above the waves, and ſtrike the world with dread.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou, PITT, this verſe with patient ſoul attend,</l>
                     <l>Her buckler, ſword, her guardian, and her friend;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſtedfaſt heart no virtuous toil can tire,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe tongue is touch'd with Heav'n's reſiſtleſs fire,</l>
                     <l>In Heav'ns own injur'd cauſe ſupreme to ſhine</l>
                     <l>With dazzling force, with ſplendors all divine.</l>
                     <l>Thou Man belov'd! thy country's boaſt and choice,</l>
                     <l>To whom afflicted millions lift their voice,</l>
                     <l>Thou laſt remaining champion of the ſtate,</l>
                     <l>On thee Integrity and Wiſdom wait,</l>
                     <l>Still lift thy dreaded arm, ſtill, ſtill purſue</l>
                     <l>The monſtrous Python, and his pois'nous crew;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:0874900200:3"/>
Repeat each righteous blow, repeat each wound,</l>
                     <l>And bring the bloated Hydra to the ground:</l>
                     <l>Lo earth, and ſea, and heav'n ſhall then rejoice,</l>
                     <l>In one triumphant Paean lift their voice.</l>
                     <l>The marks of gratitude, ye Britons, pay,</l>
                     <l>And ſtrew with thankful wreaths the Patriot's way;</l>
                     <l>Let breathing braſs, let feeling ſtone confeſs,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt arches bend, and ſtory'd piles expreſs</l>
                     <l>To ages yet unborn the glorious Man,</l>
                     <l>His falling country's prop, whoſe godlike plan</l>
                     <l>On curs'd Corruption trod, on Faction fell,</l>
                     <l>Who drives th' infernal monſters back to hell,</l>
                     <l>Spurning their gilded bait—who ſtrikes down Fraud,</l>
                     <l>At home our boſom peſt, our bane abroad,</l>
                     <l>That ſap'd the vitals of our ſinking pow'r,</l>
                     <l>When hungry Vengeance urg'd the rip'ning hour:</l>
                     <l>Then ſtood forth PITT, unaided and alone,</l>
                     <l>The People's friend, yet faithful to the Throne;</l>
                     <l>Trampling on Britiſh bribes with Roman ſcorn,</l>
                     <l>Another TULLY for his country born,</l>
                     <l>To counterwork each villain's dark deſigns,</l>
                     <l>For Britain too may dread her CATILINES:</l>
                     <l>He comes exulting in a heart ſincere,</l>
                     <l>A tongue that ſtrikes Corruption's ſoul with fear;</l>
                     <l>An arm ſtill ready to redreſs the cauſe</l>
                     <l>Of Majeſty oppreſs'd, or injur'd Laws;</l>
                     <l>Like CECIL bold in Virtue's ſacred might,</l>
                     <l>Like HAMPDEN glorious, when reſtrain'd by right,</l>
                     <l>Like FAULKLAND ſervid for his country's good,</l>
                     <l>No pride provokes, no faction fires his blood;</l>
                     <l>For Britain's laſting weal his wiſhes glow,</l>
                     <l>His Patriot heart ſee pant, his blood ſee flow:</l>
                     <l>Embrace him, Britain, to thy boſom preſs</l>
                     <l>One Patriot Son, long, long that Son poſſeſs.</l>
                     <l>O quickly come, thou Genius that ſuſtains</l>
                     <l>Of Britain's ancient worth the ſmall remains,</l>
                     <l>O quickly come, and kindle up thoſe fires</l>
                     <l>With Freedom's breath that warm'd our godlike ſires;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:0874900200:4"/>
The bleſs'd occaſion ſnatch, perhaps the laſt,</l>
                     <l>And round your liberties a rampart caſt,</l>
                     <l>That ſhall, like Nature's laws, remain entire,</l>
                     <l>Till Virtue darkens and the ſtars expire;</l>
                     <l>Th' immortal taſk begin; ſee Virtue riſe,</l>
                     <l>And lift her glorious flag to Britain's eyes;</l>
                     <l>Leaning on PITT her dreaded ſword ſhe draws,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt angels trumpet wide th' eternal cauſe:</l>
                     <l>See panting millions to her ſtandard crowd;</l>
                     <l>See Truth aſſert, ſee Faith proclaim aloud</l>
                     <l>The grand beheſt—from heav'n the ſound is ſpread</l>
                     <l>(Whilſt cruſh'd Integrity uprears her head.)</l>
                     <l>Britons, be honeſt to yourſelves, be juſt,</l>
                     <l>In this unblemiſhed man repoſe your truſt;</l>
                     <l>PITT the firm phalanx forms with manly pride,</l>
                     <l>Integrity his ſhield, and Truth his guide;</l>
                     <l>See, ſee each venal peſt before him fly,</l>
                     <l>Shrink from his voice, and ſhudder at his eye;</l>
                     <l>Such heav'n-fraught powers appal the guilty ſoul,</l>
                     <l>Where vengeance lightens, and where thunders roll;</l>
                     <l>Dreadful he marches on, and void of fear,</l>
                     <l>With Fortitude his front, with Worth his rear;</l>
                     <l>With every virtue ſee his ſoul ſupply'd,</l>
                     <l>With Loyalty, with Honour near his ſide;</l>
                     <l>Auxiliars worthy of a cauſe deſign'd</l>
                     <l>To reſcue Nature's right in human kind:</l>
                     <l>From venal leproſy to purge the land,</l>
                     <l>And all the taints of ſoul Corruption's hand;</l>
                     <l>To puſh the barrier back that Freedom braves,</l>
                     <l>To mark the bounds of ſubjects, not of ſlaves,</l>
                     <l>To call up Britiſh honeſty once more,</l>
                     <l>And ev'ry virtue to its reign reſtore.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ye Britons join with heart, with voice unite,</l>
                     <l>'Tis Wiſdom calls you forth, and native Right;</l>
                     <l>Let future deeds your preſent crimes efface,</l>
                     <l>Your fleets and armies that bring back diſgrace,</l>
                     <l>Council's o'erthrown by Caution's ghaſtly dreams,</l>
                     <l>Orders rejected, unattempted ſchemes;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:0874900200:5"/>
O biot—for ever blot the hateful page,</l>
                     <l>Quick cancel, Time, the ignominious age</l>
                     <l>From out thy records —See, a train appears!</l>
                     <l>Of Britiſh worthies, and of glorious years!</l>
                     <l>See Time (by Virtue led) o'er Albion ſmile,</l>
                     <l>Returning Juſtice bleſs once more the iſle;</l>
                     <l>Exulting Commerce iſſuing from the main,</l>
                     <l>And Britain's thunder ſhake the poles again:</l>
                     <l>See Truth aſcend her adamantine throne,</l>
                     <l>Deſpotic Truth, eternal, and alone;</l>
                     <l>Parent of Wiſdom, whoſe unbounded ſway</l>
                     <l>The Virtues bend to and the Worlds obey;</l>
                     <l>Great queen of harmony, whence order ſprings,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe moral ſcepter rules the hearts of kings,</l>
                     <l>Before thy throne with Concord's emblems grac'd,</l>
                     <l>See all the Virtues in their order plac'd:</l>
                     <l>Hail, ſacred Truth, O ſtretch thy ancient reign</l>
                     <l>O'er Britain's kindred iſle, call back again</l>
                     <l>Her golden age of plenty, pow'r and wealth,</l>
                     <l>Her honour, temperance, fortitude and health,</l>
                     <l>Her juſtice, courage, conqueſt and renown,</l>
                     <l>Let tyrants ſtart, and tremble at her frown,</l>
                     <l>New brace her arm, her trident's ſtrength reſtore,</l>
                     <l>Hark! hark! her thunder ſhakes yon hoſtile ſhore;</l>
                     <l>Around the globe her dreaded flag diſplay,</l>
                     <l>Let ocean's utmoſt bounds her flag obey;</l>
                     <l>Her crimſon croſs invincible let fly</l>
                     <l>Above the waves, triumphant in the ſky.</l>
                     <l>'Tis done; ſee direful Fraud, ſee Diſcord bound,</l>
                     <l>See hell-born Faction gaſping on the ground,</l>
                     <l>See bloated Luxury with famiſh'd jaws,</l>
                     <l>See curs'd Corruption with her gilded claws,</l>
                     <l>See pois'nous Perfidy with patriot air,</l>
                     <l>See venal Villainy, ſee mad Deſpair,</l>
                     <l>A ghaſtly groupe! in fell confuſion lie</l>
                     <l>Beneath thy aweful frown, O Truth, and die.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The caverns yawn, the rocky bars give way,</l>
                     <l>See Genius burſt her bands, and ſpring to day,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:0874900200:6"/>
Spurning the cave, accurs'd Corruption's cell,</l>
                     <l>Where Envy broods, where venal vapours dwell,</l>
                     <l>Thy bane, O Truth; ſee, ſee, ſhe joyful ſoars,</l>
                     <l>She drinks th' etherial ray, ſhe high explores</l>
                     <l>Her native heav'n, by Virtue's hand ſet free</l>
                     <l>She gains new ſtrength, her piercing eye ſhall ſee</l>
                     <l>With tenfold force where Wiſdom's ſecrets lie</l>
                     <l>Beneath th' abyſs, above the ſtarry ſky;</l>
                     <l>Through Nature's works her mimic hand ſhall play</l>
                     <l>Where Freedom prompts, where Virtue points the way:</l>
                     <l>Ambition there to blameleſs heights ſhall riſe,</l>
                     <l>There guiltleſs Glory gain th' immortal prize;</l>
                     <l>See Sculpture rear her life-creating hand,</l>
                     <l>See thinking ſtone on ſtory'd baſis ſtand;</l>
                     <l>There claſſic piles attract the wond'ring ken,</l>
                     <l>Here Genius dips the pencil and the pen;</l>
                     <l>In kindred lights with friendly ray ſhall ſhine</l>
                     <l>A MASON's muſe, a HAYMAN's groupe divine,</l>
                     <l>Unrival'd lov'd; ſee HOGARTH's fancy reign</l>
                     <l>In BUTLER's rich, unborrow'd matchleſs vein;</l>
                     <l>Through bliſsful ſcenes the raptur'd mind ſhall rove,</l>
                     <l>New POPES ſhall ſing, new LAMBERTS paint the grove:</l>
                     <l>Did PHIDIAS there indent the magic ſteel?</l>
                     <l>Did ROUBILIAC inſtruct the rocks to feel?</l>
                     <l>A HUDSON's teint, by beauty's beam refin'd,</l>
                     <l>Shall through th' expanſive features call the mind;</l>
                     <l>Nature and Art their utmoſt pow'r ſhall ſhew,</l>
                     <l>And SHAKESPEARS yet unborn, and GARRICKS glow.</l>
                     <l>The Arts exult at Virtue's great command</l>
                     <l>With Taſte, with Liberty in either hand;</l>
                     <l>Triumphant Britain ſmiles, near, near each ſide</l>
                     <l>See native Honeſty, ſee native Pride,</l>
                     <l>With Grecian worth, with Roman bent to vye,</l>
                     <l>Fame at her heart, and Glory in her eye,</l>
                     <l>With ancient Rome in her MAECENAS' days,</l>
                     <l>When Judgment gave, when Genius wore the bays,</l>
                     <l>With both ſhall Britain now maintain the ſtrife,</l>
                     <l>To lift up nature and to poliſh life.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:0874900200:7"/>
Be hence thy high concern, be hence thy care,</l>
                     <l>From Gallia's haughty brow provok'd to tear</l>
                     <l>The rival wreaths; a twofold empire gain,</l>
                     <l>Science at land, and conqueſt on the main.</l>
                     <l>By both MINERVAS crown'd, O Britain, ſhine,</l>
                     <l>Let learning ſtill, let conqueſt ſtill be thine;</l>
                     <l>Let courage, taſte, and truth thy ſons adorn,</l>
                     <l>Let BACONS yet, let MARLBOROUGHS yet unborn,</l>
                     <l>For arts and arms above mankind rever'd,</l>
                     <l>By Europe honour'd, and by Europe fear'd,</l>
                     <l>Expand the circles of thy vaſt renown;</l>
                     <l>Let PITT, let Virtue wear the immortal crown.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0874900200:8"/>
                  <p>THE <hi>PRUSSIAN</hi> CAMPAIGN, A POEM: CELEBRATING The ATCHIEVEMENTS OF <hi>FREDERICK</hi> the GREAT, In the Years 1756—57.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>WILLIAM DOBSON,</hi> LLB.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and DUBLIN Re-printed for WILLIAM WHITESTONE, in <hi>Skinner-Row.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0874900200:9"/>
                  <p>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE, Lord Viſcount CHARLEMONT, PATRON Of Literature, Sciences, and Arts, This Poem is Inſcribed: An unworthy Teſtimony Of truly affectionate and indeliable Gratitude From his Sincereſt Friend WILLIAM DOBSON.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:0874900200:10"/>
                  <head>THE <hi>PRUSSIAN</hi> CAMPAIGN, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A PRINCE, unrival'd in puiſſant deeds,</l>
                     <l>Of nobleſt proweſs and unconquer'd ſoul,</l>
                     <l>I ſing; and with ambition lyre this verſe</l>
                     <l>Attune the mighty FRED'RICK's honour'd name.</l>
                     <l>Bleſs'd, while my CHARL'MONT his propitious ear</l>
                     <l>Inclines, attentive to the glorious theme:</l>
                     <l>How amply bleſs'd, if, by the Bard invok'd</l>
                     <l>So oft, deſcending Health her genial balm</l>
                     <l>Would round thee pour benign, rekindling fair</l>
                     <l>Thy roſeate bloom, thou amiable Youth,</l>
                     <l>Crown'd with each virtue, with each grace adorn'd!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O that a ray of the celeſtial flame,</l>
                     <l>That erſt illum'd the animated Bard,</l>
                     <l>(Who ſung of <hi>Eden,</hi> and o'er <hi>Eden</hi>'s bow'rs</l>
                     <l>High-ſoaring, trac'd th' embattel'd Seraphim</l>
                     <l>In fiery conflict on th' ethereal plains,)</l>
                     <l>Beam'd on this breaſt: that I might ſwift purſue</l>
                     <l>Thro' every vaſt deſign, thro' every high</l>
                     <l>Emprize, the great, th' inimitable Chief.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Muſe, in various raptures ſweetly loſt,</l>
                     <l>This ſhining path, and that, by turns ſurveys,</l>
                     <l>Bewilder'd; unreſolv'd, th' advent'rous taſk</l>
                     <l>Where to begin; which ſplendor firſt, which laſt,</l>
                     <l>To celebrate in ſong: his matchleſs might,</l>
                     <l>His martial diſcipline exact, or kind</l>
                     <l>Indulgence to the Brave; his active ſoul</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:0874900200:11"/>
Rapt with fierce fury, thro' the glorious field,</l>
                     <l>Or ſteddieſt counſels, and deliberate care.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But hark! the trumpet's clangor rends the ſky,</l>
                     <l>And the loud clarions ſound the voice of war.</l>
                     <l>Forth iſſue <hi>Pruſſia</hi>'s troops, in various bands;</l>
                     <l>While theſe to <hi>Leipſic</hi>'s walls their rapid march</l>
                     <l>Direct, thoſe to proud <hi>Dreſden</hi>'s royal tow'rs.</l>
                     <l>When lo, th' impetuous monarch in juſt ire</l>
                     <l>Aroſe, and with unerring clue purſued</l>
                     <l>The wily labyrinths of th' ambitious foe,</l>
                     <l>By keen perception trac'd: and all their dark</l>
                     <l>Device, and machinations dire, diſclos'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Near thrice three circling years his generous Soul</l>
                     <l>Had cultivated peace, whoſe ſtudious arts</l>
                     <l>Of peace, and martial deeds alike expert.</l>
                     <l>When rous'd at length his wrath, with various clouds</l>
                     <l>From various climes beſet, the perilous ſtorm</l>
                     <l>Soon as he ſaw concentring from afar,</l>
                     <l>Furious he flew; and borne on ſwifteſt wing,</l>
                     <l>Pierc'd the perfidious <hi>Saxon</hi>'s inmoſt realms.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>At FREDERICK'S dread advance, the tim'rous <hi>Pole</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Inſtant the court, the capital deſerts,</l>
                     <l>Leaves his afflicted conſort, bath'd in tears,</l>
                     <l>Diſconſolate; and ſpeeds with eager courſe</l>
                     <l>His martial pow'rs to <hi>Pirna</hi>'s cloſe retreats:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pirna,</hi> whoſe ſtrong-fenc'd camp acceſs defy'd,</l>
                     <l>Proud of high battlements and ramparts vaſt,</l>
                     <l>Fort above fort, impenetrably firm.</l>
                     <l>As when the tow'ring Eagle ſoars the ſkie,</l>
                     <l>Sublime, in numerous flocks th'aerial train</l>
                     <l>Speed their ſwift flight to many a winding cell</l>
                     <l>Deep in the caverns of ſome craggy rock,</l>
                     <l>Cleft by Time's rigid hand; there pant immur'd,</l>
                     <l>With ſhuddring wings.—Mean time the vigilant Chief</l>
                     <l>Three ſeveral hoſts their ſeveral charge aſſign'd;</l>
                     <l>There to ſecure <hi>Sileſia</hi>'s plains, and here</l>
                     <l>His native realms defend, ſhould <hi>Ruſſia</hi> pour</l>
                     <l>Th' unnumber'd legions from her fertile loins.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:0874900200:12"/>
Himſelf the <hi>Saxon</hi> troops, as couch'd they lay</l>
                     <l>Wrapt in the boſom of their ſhelt'ring camp,</l>
                     <l>Nor daring to the field, with pow'rful force</l>
                     <l>Inveſts, on every hand environ'd round.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet ſtill the generous Prince his ire repreſs'd:</l>
                     <l>And while th' avenging ſword his arm diſplay'd,</l>
                     <l>That ſtretch'd the gentle olive forth, fair pledge</l>
                     <l>Of amicable peace. The <hi>Pole</hi> that pledge</l>
                     <l>Diſdain'd, thro' <hi>Auſtrian</hi>'s vaunted aid, ſecure.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Forthwith, from every circle, ſtem decrees,</l>
                     <l>Loud-echoing mandates, comminations dire,</l>
                     <l>Fraught with each pompous circumſtance of wrath,</l>
                     <l>Pour through the Empire, levelling their rage</l>
                     <l>At mighty <hi>Brandenburgh.</hi> In furious tides</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ruſſia</hi> rolls down her thund'ring menaces:</l>
                     <l>Whom thy vain inſolence, ſuperb <hi>Verſailles,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy haughty taunts ſucceed. He unappall'd</l>
                     <l>With ample breaſt receives th' united ſtorm:</l>
                     <l>Firm, as the ſtately promontory's height</l>
                     <l>Erect, by ſurges laſh'd on every ſide,</l>
                     <l>Foaming redundant on the big-ſwoln main:</l>
                     <l>His elevated brow o'er the mad waves</l>
                     <l>Rears it's dread honors, and diſdains their roar.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now while the <hi>Saxons</hi> with their hapleſs Prince</l>
                     <l>Clung to the trenches, and the fort embrac'd,</l>
                     <l>In deep deſpair involv'd' no ſuccour nigh,</l>
                     <l>Exhauſted, ſpiritleſs, by <hi>Pruſſian</hi> troops</l>
                     <l>Encompaſs'd ſore: at length th' auxiliar hoſt</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Auſtria</hi>'s land in numerous ſquadrons move,</l>
                     <l>Led by their mightieſt Chieftain<note n="*" place="bottom">Count Brown.</note>. Swift they march.</l>
                     <l>As ſwift great FREDERICK (whoſe quick-darting eye</l>
                     <l>No hoſtile motion ſcap'd) his troops to join</l>
                     <l>Haſtes, where experienc'd KEITH his ſtandard rear'd</l>
                     <l>All in a moment tow'ring in the van,</l>
                     <l>Of choice battalions form'd, to <hi>Tournitz</hi>'s walls</l>
                     <l>He drives his rapid way. Thither anon</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:0874900200:13"/>
March his whole hoſt, in two main columns rang'd,</l>
                     <l>Obſequious to his high beheſts. Nor ſtaid</l>
                     <l>Th' impatient Heroe, till <hi>Welmina</hi>'s plains</l>
                     <l>He reach'd: thence to his view at once appear'd</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Auſtria</hi>'s vaſt pow'rs, from wing to wing diſplay'd.</l>
                     <l>E'er yet the parting Sun his weſtern goal</l>
                     <l>Attain'd, light's ſcant remains the vigorous Chief</l>
                     <l>Seiz'd, and explor'd the plains, whence to aſſail</l>
                     <l>The foe at earlieſt dawn. The night's long ſtage</l>
                     <l>His troops the rigour of th' inclement ſky</l>
                     <l>With hearts unchill'd endure. He in the front,</l>
                     <l>Pre-eminent in danger and in toil,</l>
                     <l>Unmindful of repoſe, his liſt'ning bands</l>
                     <l>Inceſſant animates: with livelieſt cheer,</l>
                     <l>And with endearing accents fires their ſouls.</l>
                     <l>"My glorious partners in the bold emprize</l>
                     <l>On many a well-fought field: in me your friend,</l>
                     <l>In me your fire behold. The morning ſun,</l>
                     <l>(Or my preſages err) ſhall ſee the plains</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Auſtrian</hi> corſes ſtrown. Myſelf ſhall ſhare</l>
                     <l>Each perilous attempt, each brave exploit</l>
                     <l>Witneſs, and amply recompence. Purſue</l>
                     <l>Yon path, where glory, where your country's love</l>
                     <l>Invites, and <hi>Pruaſſia</hi>'s ſtill unſullied fame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thus while he ſpake, th'invigorated troops</l>
                     <l>Glow with freſh fire, and feel the gen'rous flame</l>
                     <l>Glance thro' their thrilling veins: the loit'ring Sun</l>
                     <l>They chide, impatient, panting for the field.</l>
                     <l>Scarce bluſh'd the morn with ſtreaks of orient day;</l>
                     <l>FREDERICK up-ſprung: with his attendant Chiefs</l>
                     <l>Led forth the valiant troops: their various bands</l>
                     <l>In ſtrong battalions regularly ranged;</l>
                     <l>Line after line, and file ſucceeding file;</l>
                     <l>Here the right wing diſplay'd, and there the left,</l>
                     <l>Each on a tow'ring hill. In order due</l>
                     <l>Onward they march: when in broad front appear</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Auſtria</hi>'s equeſtrian bands, array'd for war.</l>
                     <l>"Advance (ſaid mighty <hi>Brandenburgh</hi>) advance;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:0874900200:14"/>
Ruſh to the plains, and Horſe to Horſe oppoſe.</l>
                     <l>Swift they deſcend, and with impetuous force</l>
                     <l>Burſt on the foe: when from the hoſtile rear</l>
                     <l>Sudden the latent enginry diſgorge,</l>
                     <l>Hurl'd from their brazen throats, the flaming balls</l>
                     <l>Innumerable: at the dire din alarm'd</l>
                     <l>And ſtorms of thund'ring metal, back they bend</l>
                     <l>Their not imprudent ſteps: then form'd afreſh,</l>
                     <l>To the briſk charge return. Now nor the roar</l>
                     <l>Of bellowing cannon, nor inceſſant fire,</l>
                     <l>Nor wide-extended dyke, nor obvious mound</l>
                     <l>Retard: with furious onſet the fierce ſteeds</l>
                     <l>And their diſmounted warriors down they trod,</l>
                     <l>In groans expiring, welt'ring in their gore,</l>
                     <l>In heaps on mangled heaps o'erthrown: nor ceas'd,</l>
                     <l>Till undiſtinguiſh'd ſunk th' imperial Horſe,</l>
                     <l>All ſunk, in univerſal ruin whelm'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Forthwith, down-ruſhing from the mountain's brow,</l>
                     <l>FREDERICK's fierce Infantry, with furious ſpeed</l>
                     <l>Thro' iron tempeſts and thro' floods of fire,</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Low' ſchatz</hi>'s walls intrepid flew, aſſail'd</l>
                     <l>With unreſiſted force, th' aſtonied foe</l>
                     <l>Repell'd, and from their boaſted fortreſs drove,</l>
                     <l>With rout on rout confounded. The fell ſtroke</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vienna</hi>'s General mourns, his ſcattered hoſt</l>
                     <l>Driving precipate to <hi>Budin</hi>'s plains.</l>
                     <l>FREDERICK, triumphant on the foughten field</l>
                     <l>Stands, and ſurveys the ſoil, with thouſands ſlain,</l>
                     <l>And thouſands wide o'erſpred whoſe nobler doom</l>
                     <l>The captive warriors envy and admire.</l>
                     <l>Amid the ill-ſtar'd train, gall'd at his fate,</l>
                     <l>Undaunted <hi>Lobkowitz'</hi> ſuperior tow'rs</l>
                     <l>With clouded aſpect and indignant mien.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hail, mighty <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> hail! With eagle wing,</l>
                     <l>Hov'ring around thee, Victory attend</l>
                     <l>They every march! — Beneath the hallow'd ſhade</l>
                     <l>Reſt thee awhile: thy noble toil ſuſpend:</l>
                     <l>Deign o'er thy brows to bind this laurel wreath,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:0874900200:15"/>
Th'ambitious Muſe with pleaſing labour wove.</l>
                     <l>How did thine heart exult, when thou ſurveyd'ſt</l>
                     <l>Thy daring legions, by thy conduct fir'd,</l>
                     <l>And all thy emulous Chiefs: above thoſe Chiefs</l>
                     <l>High-blazing, as the peerleſs Star, that leads</l>
                     <l>Th'ethereal hoſt o'er the wide azure pour'd,</l>
                     <l>Reſplendent train! Next thee, great BEVERN ſhone</l>
                     <l>Sublime, and darted terror on the foe,</l>
                     <l>Reflecting his illuſtrious Monarch's rays.</l>
                     <l>Nor, valiant MULLER, ſhall thy proweſs paſs</l>
                     <l>Unſung; who with reſiſtleſs might diſpers'd</l>
                     <l>Th'embattel'd ranks, like clouds of ſleeting ſand</l>
                     <l>Driv'n by th'impetuous whirlwind's rapid wing.</l>
                     <l>With theſe, the tribute of th'applauding bard</l>
                     <l>Unnumber'd heroes claim, whoſe various deeds</l>
                     <l>Were long to trace. The gen'rous FREDERICK's love</l>
                     <l>Shall crown their merits, and their glorious names</l>
                     <l>Live in the records of immortal fame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thence to the <hi>Saxon</hi> bands, in <hi>Pirna</hi>'s fort</l>
                     <l>Immur'd, he wings his way, bent to ſubdue</l>
                     <l>That treach'rous foe. Nor long, e'er from the camp</l>
                     <l>Th'impriſon'd ſquadrons ſtart, o'er <hi>Egra</hi>'s ſtreams</l>
                     <l>From the bridg'd path, while ſable Night reſum'd</l>
                     <l>Her reign alternate, and th'incumbent miſts</l>
                     <l>Spred o'er heaven's face impenetrable gloom,</l>
                     <l>Deep'ning the wonted ſhades. How vain th'attempt!</l>
                     <l>Their wiles how fruſtrate! The vaſt ſummit's height,</l>
                     <l>Fronting thy turrets, <hi>Koningstein,</hi> with march</l>
                     <l>Laborious as they climb, th'upriſing ſun</l>
                     <l>Shew'd them to PRUSSIA's view; whoſe ſtrong defiles</l>
                     <l>Enclos'd them round. What gleam of hope remains?</l>
                     <l>Where ſhall they fly? how force th'obſtructed way?</l>
                     <l>Aghaſt, and thunder-ſtruck, th'obdurate King</l>
                     <l>His high-ſwoln pride ſubmits, in ſuppliant terms</l>
                     <l>Sues for that peace he inſolently ſcorn'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thus quell'd proud <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and th'ambitious <hi>Pole</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Flung from his tow'ring hopes, the wint'ry ſtorms,</l>
                     <l>On bluſtring <hi>Boreas</hi> and bleak <hi>Eurus'</hi> wings</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:0874900200:16"/>
Ruſhing impetuous, with malignant blaſts</l>
                     <l>Warn to retire from forth the tented field.</l>
                     <l>His troops th' indulgent Chief, albeit inur'd</l>
                     <l>To each ſevere extreme, his well-lov'd troops</l>
                     <l>Withdraws, and to his <hi>Saxon</hi> camp retires.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Soon as the balmy Zephyrs' earlieſt gales</l>
                     <l>Led on the genial ſpring, great FREDERICK's breaſt</l>
                     <l>Fraught with deep counſels in ſtill ſilence form'd,</l>
                     <l>Sudden unfolds. His ev'ry valiant band</l>
                     <l>Inſtant he ſummons: at his great command</l>
                     <l>Their tacit march they ſpeed; and ſwift attain</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bohemia</hi>'s realm, three formidable hoſts.</l>
                     <l>This the fam'd BEVERN, that brave SCHWERIN led;</l>
                     <l>The third their Monarch's fav'rite conduct boaſts.</l>
                     <l>War ſoon reſumes his flaming torch. — Again</l>
                     <l>Imperial <hi>Auſtria</hi>'s congregated pow'rs.</l>
                     <l>Appear, in numerous ſquadrons firmly rang'd,</l>
                     <l>A mighty hoſt: and KONINGSEGG commands.</l>
                     <l>Deep was their rear entrench'd; by village walls</l>
                     <l>Their right was ſhelter'd, by impervious woods</l>
                     <l>Encompaſs'd the left wing. Yet not the leſs</l>
                     <l>BEVERN impetuous drove his rapid bands,</l>
                     <l>By every valiant Chieftain well ſuſtained;</l>
                     <l>Storm'd the ſtrong cover, thro' th' intrenchments ruſh'd,</l>
                     <l>And pierc'd their denſe array. In ſudden rout</l>
                     <l>All their vaſt cavalry involv'd the Foe</l>
                     <l>Aſtoniſh'd views: while gallant LESWITZ ſprings</l>
                     <l>Fierce and undaunted 'mid the hoſtile fire,</l>
                     <l>Swift flies thro' many a perilous defile,</l>
                     <l>And with dread chaſe purſues the timorous hoſt,</l>
                     <l>(Havoc and ruin marching in their rear)</l>
                     <l>From hill to hill in wild confuſion driv'n.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To join thee, BEVERN, bends his eager courſe</l>
                     <l>Intrepid SCHWERIN, to thy ſoul endear'd</l>
                     <l>By kindred Virtue's ever ſacred tie.</l>
                     <l>Him to enſnare, within cover'd dale</l>
                     <l>Lurks the ſecreted foe, a numerous band!</l>
                     <l>Soon their inſidious wiles the wary chief</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:0874900200:17"/>
Eſpied; encounter'd, and diſcomfited.</l>
                     <l>Thence his impetuous progreſs onward rolls</l>
                     <l>Wide o'er the land, unbounded, uncontroll'd,</l>
                     <l>With torrent force. Before his fiery ſword</l>
                     <l>On every hand they ſcour, nor dare confront</l>
                     <l>His mighty rage: inactive, down they throw</l>
                     <l>Their unavailing arms. The regions round</l>
                     <l>Bend to the victor, and confeſs his ſway.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now mighty FRED'RICK with obſervant ken</l>
                     <l>Saw, where the foe their various ſquadrons drew</l>
                     <l>From the tow'rd fortreſs, and each banner'd hoſt;</l>
                     <l>Rang'd in proud pomp beneath their mightieſt Chief,</l>
                     <l>Who from the terror of dread PRUSSIA's arm</l>
                     <l>So late retreated, with ſad overthrow</l>
                     <l>Gall'd on <hi>Welmina</hi>'s memorable plains:</l>
                     <l>Yet dares again, by conſcious valour fir'd.</l>
                     <l>Again his thundring arm dread PRUSSIA rears.</l>
                     <l>Impatient of delay, with inſtant march</l>
                     <l>O'er <hi>Moldaw</hi>'s ſtreams he paſs'd: when lo! in camp.</l>
                     <l>High-fenc'd, by nature's favour and by art</l>
                     <l>Strong-cover'd, deep-entrench'd, proudly deem'd</l>
                     <l>Impregnable, th' imperial Army lay,</l>
                     <l>Much glorying in their ſtrength, in numbers far</l>
                     <l>Superior. Still undaunted his bold march</l>
                     <l>FRED'RICK purſues: He nor their 'vantag'd ground,</l>
                     <l>Nor high-fenc'd camp, nor trenches deep regards,</l>
                     <l>Nor numbers far ſuperior. On he leads</l>
                     <l>To the fierce combat his courageous bands.</l>
                     <l>They, by their Monarch's voice, (that fav'rite voice,)</l>
                     <l>Enliven'd, joyous ſpring, with ſweet preſage</l>
                     <l>Of victory; their ſtandards wide unfurl'd</l>
                     <l>In awful pomp, with rich emblazonry</l>
                     <l>Of vivid colours, ſtreaming to the wind:</l>
                     <l>And o'er the horrent plain of glitt'ring ſteel</l>
                     <l>A wavy Harveſt formidably gleam'd,</l>
                     <l>Innumerable faulchions, the ſun's blaze</l>
                     <l>(Oft as his radiant beams from fleecy cloud</l>
                     <l>Emerg'd) reflecting fierce with burniſh'd ſheen;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:0874900200:18"/>
E'er long to be imbru'd in <hi>Auſtrian</hi> gore.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>E'er long to be imbru'd in <hi>Auſtrian</hi> gore.</l>
                     <l>Nigh to the foe advanc'd, each Warrior brave,</l>
                     <l>Commanders, and Commanded, with like zeal</l>
                     <l>Inflam'd, and emulation high, contend,</l>
                     <l>Who firſt ſhall the untrodden path explore,</l>
                     <l>Who tempt the mariſh, who the threat'ning mound</l>
                     <l>Clime hazardous, plunge thro' the hoſtile fire</l>
                     <l>Foremoſt, and burſt their ſerried files. Now 'gan</l>
                     <l>The onſet dire, enkindled at th' alarm</l>
                     <l>Of drums loud-thundring, and the trumpet's clang</l>
                     <l>Sonorous. Fierce the conflict rag'd 'twixt hoſt</l>
                     <l>And hoſt: The field throughout, was ſeen no glimpſe</l>
                     <l>Of daſtard fear: each nobly ſignaliz'd</l>
                     <l>Their valorous ardor. Front to front they met,</l>
                     <l>Warrior with warrior clos'd, and ſteed with ſteed</l>
                     <l>In ſtern encounter. The hoarſe cannon's voice</l>
                     <l>Echoes with bellowing roar: redundant ſmoke</l>
                     <l>Pours o'er the envelop'd ſky, with horrid flaſh</l>
                     <l>Pierc'd frequent, and quick glance of ſulph'rous flames.</l>
                     <l>Swift thro' the ranks undaunted FRED'RICK ſprung,</l>
                     <l>High brandiſhing his faulchion, <hi>Auſtria</hi>'s dread,</l>
                     <l>From wing to diſtant wing unwearied flew,</l>
                     <l>Now in the Van, now Rear: on ev'ry part,</l>
                     <l>Thro' each viciſſitude, each varying ſcene,</l>
                     <l>With ſplendid conduct, animating ſounds,</l>
                     <l>And brave example, his obſequious bands</l>
                     <l>Inſpir'd, directed, inſtigated, cheer'd,</l>
                     <l>And all his various pow'rs by turns diſplay'd:</l>
                     <l>Fervid, yet vigilant; with temper'd fire</l>
                     <l>Guiding the rapid war's alternate reins.</l>
                     <l>On every part his victor arm prevails.</l>
                     <l>At length o'erpow'r'd, diſcomfited, recede</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Auſtria</hi>'s faint troops, abandoning the field</l>
                     <l>Drench'd in their ſlaughter'd friends' commingled blood.</l>
                     <l>How ſhall the Muſe the wondrous havoc paint,</l>
                     <l>The various images of horror trace</l>
                     <l>O'er the wide champain? Now fierce-iſſuing balls</l>
                     <l>Swept mighty numbers: now th'impetuous ſword</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:0874900200:19"/>
Clove with keen edge the tortur'd foe in twain.</l>
                     <l>Thro' many a valiant breaſt with adverſe ſtroke</l>
                     <l>Pierc'd the ſharp wound, and fix'd a glorious ſcar.</l>
                     <l>Here from the quiv'ring trunk the ſever'd head</l>
                     <l>Swift flies: here the lop'd limb their lord deſert,</l>
                     <l>His agonizing groans, and fruitleſs plaint</l>
                     <l>In the rude clamour drown'd. With giant ſtrides</l>
                     <l>Death travers'd the dread plain, with all his pomp</l>
                     <l>Of terrors, and each ghaſtly form, enclos'd.</l>
                     <l>What multitudes, great FRED'RICK, by thy arm,</l>
                     <l>Thy juſt avenging arm, what crouds on crouds</l>
                     <l>Deſcended to the baleful realms of night,</l>
                     <l>E'erwhile with <hi>Auſtrian</hi>'s throng'd! of adverſe ſtars</l>
                     <l>There jointly they complain, their mutual woe</l>
                     <l>Sooth with condolence bland, and enterchange</l>
                     <l>Sad gratulation: ſoon with gloomy joy</l>
                     <l>Hailing their mightieſt Chieftain, new arriv'd,</l>
                     <l>Thy great Antagoniſt; who gor'd with wounds</l>
                     <l>On the ſame fatal plain (heart-piercing wounds,</l>
                     <l>That barr'd each glorious proſpect of renown)</l>
                     <l>At length groan'd forth indignant his high ſoul,</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Prague</hi>'s vain ſhelt'ring walls—Th' illuſtrious Shade</l>
                     <l>Stalks on, nor deigns return th' unwelcome <hi>Hail.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Paſs we theſe dolorous regions, chearful Light</l>
                     <l>Reviſiting; with wonder to ſurvey</l>
                     <l>The living monuments of PRUSSIA's fame:</l>
                     <l>The thouſands foil'd, who yet this vital air</l>
                     <l>Breathe, and in thraldom grace the Conqueror's train,</l>
                     <l>Lo what unnumber'd Trophies, what rich Spoils</l>
                     <l>Torn from the graſping foe, the ſolemn pomp</l>
                     <l>Attend: their raviſh'd Enſigns, wav'd ſublime,</l>
                     <l>With ſplended painture ſloating thro' the air,</l>
                     <l>Diſplay puiſſant FREDERICK's ample fame.</l>
                     <l>See how th' imperial Cannon, many a row,</l>
                     <l>Move in ſlow pageantry; the brazen throats</l>
                     <l>Silenc'd, till FREDERICK bid them the dire roar</l>
                     <l>Renew, and on their late Poſſeſſors proud</l>
                     <l>Pour the retorted rage.—Yet 'mid this Scene,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:0874900200:20"/>
In all thy height of luſtre, matchleſs Prince,</l>
                     <l>To check thy triumph with th' ingenious tear</l>
                     <l>Due to the mighty ſlain, on the dread plains</l>
                     <l>Where graſp'd whole ſquadrons of th' expiring Foe,</l>
                     <l>Fell valiant SCHWERIN, by each virtuous breaſt</l>
                     <l>Lov'd and lamented: gloriouſly he fell,</l>
                     <l>With many a Chieftain of exalted name</l>
                     <l>Accompanied; who prodigal of life,</l>
                     <l>Pour'd in their Country's cauſe their generous blood.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Auſtria</hi>'s deep conſternation and diſmay,</l>
                     <l>(Of every aid, of her whole camp bereft)</l>
                     <l>What tongue can utter? Or what pow'r deſcribe</l>
                     <l>FREDERICK's vaſt victory?—But other Scenes</l>
                     <l>Ariſe, of different hue. O hadſt thou ne'er</l>
                     <l>Deſerted <hi>Prague</hi>'s 'ſieg'd wall, to charge the foe</l>
                     <l>High-poſted on th' aerial mountain's brow,</l>
                     <l>With legions heap'd on legions, firm array'd</l>
                     <l>Beneath th' imperial DAUN! Forgive the Muſe,</l>
                     <l>Great Chief, who with thy ſundry glories charm'd,</l>
                     <l>Yet void of adulation, while ſhe ſtrives</l>
                     <l>With fainteſt pencil to delineate</l>
                     <l>Shadowy thy godlike virtues, paints thee <hi>man;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The wiſeſt of whoſe race, diſcreeteſt, beſt,</l>
                     <l>'Mid all his ſhining faculties betrays</l>
                     <l>Some tincture of th' impure alloy, deriv'd</l>
                     <l>From his frail Anceſtor.—Sagacious DAUN</l>
                     <l>With ſkill th' important ſituation choſe;</l>
                     <l>And look'd diſdainful down. Tho' fierce defiles,</l>
                     <l>Tho' thund'ring batteries intercept the way,</l>
                     <l>Undaunted FREDERICK with his furious hoſt,</l>
                     <l>Thro' thund'ring batteries and thro' fierce defiles,</l>
                     <l>Up the ſteep cliff his arduous road maintain'd.</l>
                     <l>Thrice he aſſay'd the <hi>Auſtrian</hi>'s pow'rful wing</l>
                     <l>To burſt; repell'd them thrice; yet thrice return'd.</l>
                     <l>Then calm receding with ſerene retreat</l>
                     <l>Soft he deſcends to the ſubjacent vale,</l>
                     <l>(Where <hi>Elbe</hi> her liquid courſe obliquely rolls</l>
                     <l>Meand'ring) unretarded, unpurſu'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:0874900200:21"/>
                     <l>Soon <hi>Ruſſia</hi>'s legions (from her populous clime</l>
                     <l>With tardy ſteps advanc'd) their ling'ring march</l>
                     <l>Accelerate, and FREDERICK'S realms invade.</l>
                     <l>Thus tho' inſulted, the conſiderate Chief</l>
                     <l>With terms of mild compoſure deigns invite</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Moſcow</hi>'s imperial Queen his plan t' embrace,</l>
                     <l>Surceaſing hoſtile rage; and war's dire flames</l>
                     <l>Extinguiſhing, o'er harraſs'd <hi>Europe</hi> pour</l>
                     <l>The ſalutary boon of proſp'rous Peace.</l>
                     <l>His generous terms diſdain'd, his pow'r defy'd,</l>
                     <l>His territories ſpoil'd, war he declares</l>
                     <l>Immediate; truſting in his righteous Cauſe,</l>
                     <l>And Heav'n's protecting Arm. LEWHALD led on</l>
                     <l>The ſqudrons, and encounter'd more than twice</l>
                     <l>His force, entrench'd on tow'ring hill ſecure.</l>
                     <l>Nathleſs he vigorous charg'd; their foremoſt lines</l>
                     <l>Burſt, and on every hand deſtruction dealt</l>
                     <l>Wide-waſting. Yet, leſt the ſuperior Foe</l>
                     <l>Cruſh his brave hoſt, by the unfriendly ſite</l>
                     <l>Disfavour'd, by enormous multitudes</l>
                     <l>Oppreſs'd, to <hi>Velau</hi>'s camp the Chief mature</l>
                     <l>Retreated, unrepulſed. The <hi>Moſcovites</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Diſmay'd, nor ſtudious of purſuit, lament</l>
                     <l>Their thouſands ſlaughter'd and, their<note n="*" place="bottom">General Lapuchin.</note> General thrall'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now in their ſeveral camps each Hoſt enwrapt</l>
                     <l>Retire; and War's tremendous thunder reſts</l>
                     <l>Suſpended: when at once, their ſudden flight</l>
                     <l>Aſſaying, <hi>Ruſſia</hi>'s troops with rapid ſpeed</l>
                     <l>Scud as precipitant, as ſlow they advanc'd</l>
                     <l>E'erwhile.—But lo! the fierce confed'rate Pow'rs</l>
                     <l>Vaunting united terrors, onward move</l>
                     <l>Under their gallant Leaders, great SOUBISE</l>
                     <l>And HILDBURGHAUSEN. Their proud threats t'oppoſe</l>
                     <l>FREDERICK delay'd not: his aſſembled troops</l>
                     <l>He rang'd in juſt array, and thus addreſs'd:</l>
                     <l>"My Friends, my Warriors brave!—The Foe's advanc'd;</l>
                     <l>PRUSSIA ſhall meet them. Haſte we to the field.</l>
                     <l>With you your FREDERICK conquers or expires.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:0874900200:22"/>
Think how we've fought! what glorious laurels won!</l>
                     <l>Think on the equitable plea, that drew</l>
                     <l>Theſe valiant ſwords, and vindicate the cauſe:</l>
                     <l>God be our Guardian, Confidence and Shield.</l>
                     <l>He ended; on he led his valiant files</l>
                     <l>Dauntleſs, and bid them ſtorm the the adverſe wing:</l>
                     <l>But on the edge of onſet (his quick eye</l>
                     <l>Determining) inſtant as lightning's glance,</l>
                     <l>Invert they their poſition, leſt the foe</l>
                     <l>Surround them unnaware. Now <hi>Pruſſia</hi>'s Horſe</l>
                     <l>Spring furious on the <hi>Gaul,</hi> in front direct</l>
                     <l>Oppos'd, of vaſt immeaſurable depth;</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Gaul</hi> as furious, the briſk charge receive</l>
                     <l>With equal brav'ry. Long in dubious ſcale</l>
                     <l>Hung the fierce conflict: till the <hi>Gallic</hi> bands</l>
                     <l>Swerv'd; to the neighbouring ſummit's reſuge flew,</l>
                     <l>And recent form'd. FREDERICK their rallied force</l>
                     <l>Soon diſarray'd, and with purſuit ſevere</l>
                     <l>Drove, as the Lion drives his trembling chace.</l>
                     <l>Then from each hoſt the Cannon's bellowing voice</l>
                     <l>Inceſſant roar'd. <hi>Pruſſia</hi>'s bold infantry</l>
                     <l>Ruſh forth, and battery after battery gain,</l>
                     <l>With ſtorms impetuous and unwearied fire</l>
                     <l>Rage their artillery, on either wing</l>
                     <l>The foe ſore galling: till, conſtrain'd, they ſpeed</l>
                     <l>Their ignominious flight, with ſoul defeat</l>
                     <l>Confounded, and in ruin dire involv'd.</l>
                     <l>And, but the Sun now prone deſcended ſwift</l>
                     <l>To th' Ocean waves; and all-involving night</l>
                     <l>Threw her deep-ſhaded mantle o'er the plains,</l>
                     <l>Fav'ring their trepid flight; of that vaſt hoſt,</l>
                     <l>Who ſpread at morning dawn their vaunted files</l>
                     <l>So proud, how few had from the deathful field</l>
                     <l>Return'd, to tell the melancholy tale.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou Miracle of Chiefs! and will our Sons</l>
                     <l>Believe, by ſtoried Chronicles inform'd</l>
                     <l>How <hi>Brandenburgh</hi>'s illuſtrious Prince, with force</l>
                     <l>Immenſely diſproportionate, ſubdu'd</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:0874900200:23"/>
Thouſands on thouſands of confederate Hoſts!</l>
                     <l>What numerous ſquadrons of the ſlaughter'd foe</l>
                     <l>Fell in their prime of Youth: Of <hi>Pruſſian</hi> blood</l>
                     <l>How ſlight th' effuſion: what redundant tides</l>
                     <l>Of captiv'd troops the Victor's camp o'erflow'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The generous FREDERICK his triumphant joy</l>
                     <l>Attempers ſweet with piety humane</l>
                     <l>For guiltleſs Widows and for Orphan babes,</l>
                     <l>Thus multiplied by his victorious arm.</l>
                     <l>Nobly compaſſionate to the fallen foe,</l>
                     <l>With blandeſt treatment he beguiles their pain,</l>
                     <l>Pours the ſoft balm in their freſh-bleeding wounds;</l>
                     <l>And bids Captivity her dejected head</l>
                     <l>Rear, and unbend her brow with grateful ſmile.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now ſhall the humbled <hi>Gaul</hi> his vaunts ſuſpend;</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Moſcow</hi> tremble at the <hi>Pruſſian</hi> name.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Auſtria</hi> has felt, by oft repeated ſcourge,</l>
                     <l>What martial diſcipline effects; what the wiſe Chief's</l>
                     <l>Aſſiduous Care: how fires each manly breaſt</l>
                     <l>To bold emprizes FREDERICK'S generous Soul,</l>
                     <l>His fond Affection and paternal Love,</l>
                     <l>In boundleſs ſtreams impartially diffus'd.</l>
                     <l>And thou, ambitious POLE, thy lawleſs pride</l>
                     <l>Repreſs; nor with vain arrogance aſpire,</l>
                     <l>Graſping at alien realms: with wiſer aim</l>
                     <l>Guard well thy own, and to fair Truth adhere.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hark how the Sons of <hi>Albion</hi>'s glorious Iſle</l>
                     <l>Tune in harmonic choir the Conqueror's praiſe!</l>
                     <l>Thee, FREDERICK, all her gliſt'ning cliffs reſound,</l>
                     <l>Thee her gay vallies, thee her moſſy caves;</l>
                     <l>And grove to grove repeats the pleaſing ſong</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Britannia,</hi> reſting on her ported ſpear,</l>
                     <l>Majeſtic ſmiles; and with the pleaſing ſong</l>
                     <l>Enraptur'd, venerates the Prince, ſo bright</l>
                     <l>Reſembling her lov'd Lord; to valorous GEORGE</l>
                     <l>In magnanimity, as in blood, allied.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Still other wars, ſtill other triumphs riſe.</l>
                     <l>The muſe, unequal to the arduous taſk,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:0874900200:24"/>
Breathleſs purſuing her unwearied Chief</l>
                     <l>From plain to tented plain, at length retires.</l>
                     <l>O could ſhe from the turmoils of the field,</l>
                     <l>The clang of trumpets and the cannon's roar,</l>
                     <l>Convey thee, FREDERICK, to thy dear Retreat,<note n="*" place="bottom">POTSDAM.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wrapt in the arms of Peace! In ſweet repoſe</l>
                     <l>There would the royal Bard thro' echoing ſhades</l>
                     <l>With other notes than theſe, with loftier ſtrains</l>
                     <l>To his reſounding lyre, hymn the great POW'R,</l>
                     <l>Whom ever he adores with filial love,</l>
                     <l>And reverential awe: Whoſe out-ſtretch'd arm</l>
                     <l>Bows down th' obdurate fierceneſs of the proud,</l>
                     <l>Th' un-ambitious rears; who with a breath</l>
                     <l>Wields all the thunder of the various war,</l>
                     <l>OMNIPOTENT; and with his ſovereign nod</l>
                     <l>The ſate of mightieſt Monarchies decides.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:0874900200:25"/>
            <head>BOOKS juſt Publiſhed by W. WHITESTONE, Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller, in <hi>Skinner-Row.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Life of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, with the Lives of the APOSTLES and ENANGE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LISTS. By the Reverend THOMAS STACKHOUSE, A. M. late Vicar of <hi>Beenham</hi> in <hi>Berkſhire,</hi> and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Hiſtory of the Bible, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Price bound and Letter'd, <hi>5s. 5d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Supplement to the Works of <hi>Alexander Pope,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Containing ſuch <hi>Poems, Letters,</hi> &amp;c. as are omitted by the Reverend Doctor <hi>Warburton;</hi> with the Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of, The Three Hours after Marriage, and a <hi>Key</hi> to the <hi>Letters:</hi> To which is added (not in the <hi>London</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition) A <hi>Key</hi> to the <hi>Three Hours</hi> after <hi>Marriage;</hi> and and a Letter giving an account of the Origin of the Quarrel between <hi>Cibber, Pope</hi> and <hi>Gay.</hi> Price bound <hi>2s.</hi> 8<hi>d.</hi> half. Cover'd in blue Paper 2<hi>s</hi> 2<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Sermon Preached before the <hi>Society</hi> Correſponding with the Incorporated <hi>Society</hi> in <hi>Dublin,</hi> for promot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant Working Schools,</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> By <hi>Thomas Seckor,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> now Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> Price 3<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Juſtice of the Supreme Being. A Poem; which obtained Mr. <hi>Seaton</hi>'s Premium, at the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> neatly printed in Quarto. Price 6<hi>d.</hi> half.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pope</hi>'s Eſſay on Man. Price 6<hi>d.</hi> half.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
