<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2007-08-30</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Jonathan Blaney</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>proofed text and revised markup</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K032473.000">
<STC T="C">T027111</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3318280288</BIBNO>
<VID SET="ECRP">0210502000</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A SERMON Preach'd at Queen-Street Chapel, AND St. Paul's, Covent-Garden; On FRIDAY the 17th of <HI>February,</HI> 1758. Being the Day appointed for a General fast.</P>
<P>By the Rev. THOMAS FRANCKLIN, M. A.</P>
<P>Publish'd at the Desire of those who heard it.</P>
<P>LONDON: Printed for R. FRANCKLIN, in <HI>Russel-street, Covent-Garden.</HI> 1758.</P>
<P>Price SIX-PENCE.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>JONAH, c. 3. v. 7, 8.</BIBL>
<Q><P>Let neither Man nor Beast, Herd nor Flock taste any Thing, let them not feed nor drink Water.</P></Q>
<Q><P>But let Man and Beast be covered with Sack∣cloth, and cry mightily unto God; yea, let them turn every one from his evil Way.</P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>THE perpetual superintendency of Divine Pro∣vidence in the government of the Universe, and Direction of natural▪ Causes, towards the Encouragement of good, and the Punishment of evil Doers, are Truths which none but the Impious and Prophane have ever dared to call in Question. The Powers and Qualities of all created Beings are render'd subservient to the Design and Purpose of him who made them, and become the Instrument of his Favour or Displeasure towards the Sons of Men.</P>
<P>IN the common and ordinary Course of Things, we do not indeed so visibly discern this great and universal Spring which actuates every Motion: In the Conduct and Fate of Individuals therefore, the Interposition of the Almighty doth too frequently escape our Notice
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
and Observation; but when his Hand is stretch'd out over the Nations of the Earth, when Millions feel his Wrath, and Kingdoms bow down before him; when his signal Judgments affright, and his Terrors dismay us; when the Angel of Destruction is commission'd by him to punish offending Multitudes, and call Sin∣ners to Repentance; when Sword, Pestilence and Famine, Snow and Hail, Storm and Tempest fulfill his Word, then doth Mankind awaken from it's Le∣thargy of Sin and Ignorance, and discover the imme∣diate Agency and Interposition of the Divine Being; then is the Sentence of an angry God legible to every Eye, written as it were in Characters of Fire, and pointing out the Finger of the Almighty.</P>
<P>IF we turn over the instructive Pages of Holy Writ, we shall find this perpetual governing Providence ex∣plain'd by incontestible Evidence, and illustrated by the most signal Examples.</P>
<P>AND amongst them all, there is not perhaps one, wherein the Power, the Justice, and the Goodness of God are more immediately visible than in that which is recorded in the third Chapter of the Book of the Prophet <HI>Jonah.</HI></P>
<P>THE <HI>City of</HI> Nineveh, says the Prophet, <HI>was an ex∣ceeding great City,</HI> probably as eminently superior to Others in the Wickedness, as in the Number of it's In∣habitants; a profligate and abandon'd Race of Men, who went on from Folly to Folly, and from Sin to Sin, till they had exhausted the Patience and Long-suffering of an offended God, and fill'd up the Measure of their Iniquity; till at length, the Lord sent unto them his faithful Prophet, the Messenger of sad and heavy Ti∣dings,
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
to denounce unto them their immediate De∣struction; and <HI>Jonah</HI> cried and said, <HI>yet forty Days, and</HI> Nineveh <HI>shall be overthrown.</HI></P>
<P>A Sentence so dreadful, and so unexpected, was received, we may imagine, with an equal Degree of Terror and Astonishment; they beheld themselves in a Moment on the Brink of Ruin, the Stroke was certain, the Fate was unavoidable.</P>
<P>THE Truth of what was foretold, would admit of no Doubt or Disputation; the Authority of the Person who deliver'd the Prophecy, the Preciseness of the Time affix'd for it's Accomplishment, the Conscious∣ness of their own Guilt, all conspired to persuade them that their Destruction was nigh at Hand; their Fears were alarm'd, their Souls awaken'd, their Hearts melted by the approaching Danger; what therefore could be done on so solemn, so melancholy an Occa∣sion? Omnipotence was not to be resisted, nor Omnis∣cience to be deceived; they could only humble them∣selves before the Lord, implore Pardon and Forgive∣ness, and throw themselves on his Mercy. <HI>Who can tell,</HI> said they, <HI>if God will turn and repent, and turn away from his fierce Anger, that we perish not? So the People of</HI> Nineveh <HI>believed God, and proclaimed a Fast, and put on Sackcloth, from the greatest of them even to the least.</HI></P>
<P>THE Sovereign of this distressed Nation, is described to us by the Prophet as exactly resembling our own; so∣licitous for the Welfare, feeling for the Calamities, anxious for the Reformation of his afflicted People; he recommends to them in the most pressing Manner the strict and religious Observance of the Fast, and enforces it by his own Royal Example.</P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="5"/>
<HI>HE</HI> arose from his Throne, and laid his Robe from him, and covered him with Sackcloth, and sat in Ashes, and he caused it to be proclaimed and published through <HI>Nineveh,</HI> by the Decree of the King and his Nobles, saying,</P>
<P><HI>LET</HI> neither Man nor Beast, Herd nor Flock taste any Thing; let them not feed, nor drink Water.</P>
<P><HI>BUT</HI> let Man and Beast be covered with Sackcloth, and cry mightily unto God, yea, let them turn every one from his evil Way.</P>
<P>NO sooner was this solemn Decree pronounced, but it was universally complied with; they fasted, prayed, and repented; they lamented their Sins, wept for their Iniquities, and turned unto the Lord their God.</P>
<P>AND now let us carefully observe the Consequence of their Conduct and Behaviour; the Effect was pros∣perous, far beyond all which their most sanguine hopes could promise them.</P>
<P><HI>GOD,</HI> whose Mercy is over all his Works, and who hateth nothing that he has made, <HI>took Compassion on them; he beheld their sorrow and Contrition, and would not that it should pass unobserved or unrewarded;</HI> he saw their Works, <HI>says the Prophet,</HI> that they turned from their evil Way, and God repented of the Evil that he had said that he would do unto them, and he did it not.</P>
<P>SUCH an Instance of gracious Condescension, and unspeakable Mercy, cannot but affect our Minds with the strongest Sense of Gratitude, and afford Matter of Comfort and Consolation to a sinful and afflicted People.</P>
<P><PB N="7" REF="6"/>
IT is indeed an Example, which if duly attended to by us on this solemn Occasion, may be an useful Monitor, and serve in this Hour of Peril, to direct our Ways, and to guide our Footsteps aright.</P>
<P>LET us then seriously consider and reflect on the Ex∣ample before us, and as we but too nearly resemble the People of <HI>Nineveh</HI> in the Multitude of our Sins, let us endeavour to imitate them in our Repentance also; and to this End let us lay before ourselves the Means which they pursued, and the Methods which they made use of to bring on this salutary Effect.</P>
<P>AND first then, it appears by the History of the <HI>Ninevites,</HI> as recorded in holy Writ, that the Duty of Fasting was always highly acceptable unto God, and that therefore it will most probably always continue to be so.</P>
<P>FASTING is a Duty indeed which though it had not the Sanction of the Almighty to recommend, or his Authority to enforce it, would by the common Rules of Prudence and Discretion lay Claim to our frequent Practice and Observation of it: Even when she is not employ'd in the solemn Offices of Religion, to assist Repentance and raise Devotion, she may still be consi∣dered as the Hand▪maid of Temperance, the Compa∣nion of Health, and the Counsellor of Virtue.</P>
<P>THE most poignant of human Pleasures will cloy without some Pause, and satiate without some inter∣mission; Abstinence therefore is necessary to enhance the Value of every Blessing, and give a Relish to every Enjoyment.</P>
<P>BUT if this Virtue is useful in the common Course of our Affairs, it becometh an Act still more solemn and
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
important when it is made use of to avert the Judgments of God, and turn aside his Indignation from us.</P>
<P>WE have seen the great and glorious Effect which it produced in the Case of <HI>Nineveh;</HI> to the same End, and for the same Purposes was it appointed on this Day; and may the God of Patience and long-suffering assist us with the same Portion of his divine Favour, and reward us also in like Manner for our Observance of it.</P>
<P><HI>LET us then, my Brethren,</HI> not taste any Thing, nei∣ther feed, nor drink Water; <HI>but let us, with the Peo∣ple of</HI> Nineveh, cover ourselves with Sackcloth, and turn every one from his evil Way.</P>
<P>THE Pulpit is not, ought not, certainly to be the Seat of Politics, or the Field for national and public Affairs; but here Occasion warrants, and Necessity de∣mands it of us.</P>
<P>WE are call'd upon this Day by the Voice of public Authority to cry aloud, and forbidden to spare; to echo the Voice of our Rulers and lament the Crimes and Calamities of our Country; to say, that from a brave, a virtuous, and a successful, we are now grown a sinful, weak, and unhappy People. <HI>We are become,</HI> as the Psalmist says, <HI>an open Shame to our Enemies; the very Scorn and Derision of all those that are round about us.</HI> Is it not, my Brethren, a melancholy Consideration, to see a Land of Plenty like this, reduced to a State of Penury and Famine; a Land of Honour and Virtue, changed into a Land of Folly and Corruption; a Land of Freemen, into a Land of Slaves; a Land of Chris∣tians, into a Land of Pagans, Deists, and Freethinkers?</P>
<P>THERE was a Time when private Virtue supported public Welfare and Prosperity; when the Peace and
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
Safety of Society was ensured by the Prudence and Pie∣ty of every Individual: There were once such things as Patriotism, Sincerity, and Integrity amongst us. Our Ancestors sacrificed every thing to the Love of our Country, whilst we sacrifice the Love of our Country to every thing else. Fashion, in short, hath deluded, Luxury hath enervated, Pleasure hath enchanted us.</P>
<P>THE slow and secret Poison of Corruption hath insi∣nuated itself into every Vein; inffused a Listlesness and languor over the whole Frame; undermined and prey'd upon the Constitution. We remain supine and inac∣tive; and even whilst Misery is pouring in upon us, seem utterly insensible of it. We lull our Senses to Oblivion in the Arms of Indolence, and at the same Time fondly imagine ourselves reposing on the Bosom of Security.</P>
<P>THIS, my Brethren, is not Declamation, but Fact; it is not the malignant Suggestion of Calumny and Sa∣tire, but the serious melancholy Reflection of Experi∣ence and Truth.</P>
<P>IF the <HI>Ninevites</HI> had not been great and miserable Sin∣ners, the solemn Denunciation of the Prophet <HI>Jonas</HI> would not have fallen upon them; and if we also had not offended the Lord of Heaven and Earth, he would not have sent down his heavy Judgments upon us. To bring this Matter home then to our own Breasts and the present solemn Occasion; the Angel of Destruction is gone forth, the Sword of War is unsheathed, and the Arrows of the Almighty are sharpened against us. A great and powerful Enemy threatens us from abroad; our own Sins and Wickedness oppress and weigh us down at Home.</P>
<P><PB N="10" REF="9"/>
LET me then ask you a few serious and important Questions; is this a Time to spread the Table of Lux∣ury, or to wanton in the Gardens of Pleasure? Is it a Time to revel in the Feast of Sensuality, whilst thou∣sands are starving around us? or to sound the Instru∣ments of Joy and Festivity amidst the Groans of War, and the Shrieks of public Calamity? Shall the Mourner for his Country, and such we ought all to be, put on his gorgeous apparel, and appear at the Funeral of his fellow-Citizens in the Wedding Garment? Is there yet amongst us a Head so void of Understanding, as not to perceive our wretched Situation? Is there a Heart so callous and insensible as not to feel for and sympathize with our bleeding Country? Shall we then pollute our last Moments with Sin, and expire in the Arms of Riot and Debauchery?</P>
<P>REMEMBER the People of <HI>Nineveh;</HI> they were grie∣vous Sinners like ourselves, but they fasted, repented, and were forgiven: As we have been guilty of their Sins, we have reason to fear the Judgment denounced against them; but if we imitate their Example in our Reformation, we may still hope for their Pardon, and look for their Reward.</P>
<P>LET us then consider this Day's Solemnity, as the Foundation on which we are to build the Structure of our future happiness; as the Time appointed to sow the Seeds of our Repentance, which with due Care and Culture may take Root, and shoot forth hereafter into a rich and plenteous Harvest: Let us consider this Day's Abstinence as only an Emblem or Type of that total, that far more necessary Abstinence from Sin and Wick∣edness which we all purpose henceforth religiously to observe. <HI>Let us keep the Fast, not with the Leaven of</HI>
<PB N="11" REF="10"/>
<HI>Malice and Sin, but with the unleavened Bread of Since∣rity and Truth.</HI></P>
<P>LET me address you then as Fellow-Creatures, Fellow-Citizens, and Fellow-Subjects: By the decay of public Virtue one Link of the great Chain of Per∣fection is lost, which hath loosen'd the whole; let us strive to restore and reunite it. It may be said in∣deed, and perhaps with some truth, that we still keep up the Appearance of Religion and Virtue; that the Places of public Worship are still not only open, but frequently, (and the Congregation now before me is a Confirmation of it) resorted to, and even crouded; but let us not therefore, because we can deceive others, de∣ceive ourselves also: It is not merely the assembling ourselves together in the House of the Lord, Fasting, or <HI>appearing unto Men to fast,</HI> which will recommend us to his divine Favour; unless we observe his Laws, and obey his Commandments. For if the Moment we return to our own Homes, we return also to all the Vices and all the Follies that we left behind us, what is our short Attendance on the Almighty but a solemn Mock∣ery of his Power, and an impious Distrust of his Omni∣science?</P>
<P>WE have all been accessary to the Guilt of our Coun∣try; should we not then contribute to her Repentance and Reformation also? National Iniquity must bring on national Ruin, and in that Ruin must we all be involved, if we are not careful to prevent it. If then we would save, let us help ourselves; let us remember that the <HI>worst of Foes,</HI> when they are Foes, <HI>are those of our own Houshold.</HI> The Traitor within must conspire with the Enemy without, before we can be entirely lost. <HI>England,</HI> whenever she falls, must fall by her own Hand; and to the Guilt of Murther must add the Crime of Suicide also.</P>
<P><PB N="12" REF="11"/>
THE late extraordinary and unparallel'd Success of our noble Friend and Ally, is a recent and a striking Instance to convince us how much the Virtue, the Con∣duct, the Example of one Man may influence the Ac∣tions and rule the Fate of thousands: His Arms were crown'd with Conquest, and we, it is to be hoped, shall in some Measure reap the Fruits of it. But should it not chastise our Joy, and lessen our Exultation to reflect that this Nation should thus borrow that Fame, which she used to bestow; and stand indebted to foreign Courage for what she had a Right to expect from domestic Vir∣tue. Is <HI>Britain</HI> at last so poor in Valour as to depend upon another's Arms for her Safety; another's Bravery for her Defence; another's Victory for her Triumphs?</P>
<P>LET us for Shame, my Fellow-countrymen, at length see, and think, and act for ourselves. If we have that Reverence for our Country, and that Regard for our Sovereign which we all profess, let Religion be our Patriotism; if we are ambiti∣ous to be thought good Subjects, let us endeavour to be good Christians; let us shew our Loyalty by our Lives, and our Obedience by our Virtue. Let every Man be persuaded, that the Welfare, the Safety, and the Preservation of these Kingdoms depends on his own Conduct and Behaviour: We cannot all of us take the Field and bear the Sword in the Service of our King, but we may all gird on us the Sword of Truth, and defend him with the Buckler of Righteousness; Virtue would add fresh Strength to every Arm, and Sharpness to every Sword; Innocence would give us Courage, Integrity would make us brave; and if the Enemy could once find us uncorrupted, they would soon prove us to be unconquerable. As by our Fol∣lies and our Crimes we have brought on Danger and
<PB N="13" REF="12"/>
Difficulty, so may we remove them by Goodness and Reformation; and insure Success and Victory abroad, by Penitence and Piety at Home.</P>
<P>BUT farther; every Man has some Friends who love and esteem him; some who are guided by his Exam∣ple, and led by his Direction; every one has some Power, and some Influence over others; let that Pow∣er be exerted, let that Influence be diffused, that so the generous Flame may catch from Breast to Breast, spread itself through every Limb, and animate the whole reformed, pardoned, happy Nation.</P>
<P><HI>BUT lastly, let us remember what that Fast is which the Lord hath chosen, not only</HI> to loose the Bonds of Wickedness, but to loose the heavy Burthens, and let the oppressed go free; to deal our Bread to the hungry, and relieve the afflicted Soul.</P>
<P>A LITTLE, a very little will suffice to satisfy Na∣ture; if it were not so, how few in these cruel Days would be able to survive! What therefore we may spare from our own Superfluities, let us bestow on the Necessity of others; what we save by fasting, let us give in Charity; thus shall we, at the same Time, preserve ourselves innocent, and make our Fellow-creatures happy, <HI>cease to do Evil, and learn to do Good.</HI></P>
<P>WE all feel the Necessity of the Times, and all com∣plain of it. If even the Rich lament it, in the Bo∣som of Affluence, how must the Poor and Destitute, who shiver in the cold Regions of Adversity and Af∣fliction; alas! what is our Want to their Penury, our Difficulty to their Despair! The Storm, which we only dread at a Distance, is even now pouring on their Heads, shall we not then afford them a little Relief, a little Shelter from it?</P>
<P><PB N="14" REF="13"/>
To conclude then, let us all heartily and speedily set about a general Reformation; from this Day of solemn Humiliation let us count our Righteousness; from this auspicious Aera let us date our Virtue; let it be re∣corded in the Annals of our Nation, that this Year open'd the Eyes of an offending People, and reconciled them to their God; saved them from his just Judg∣ment, recommended them to his Pardon, and restored them to his divine Favour and Protection; that he took them once more under the Shadow of his Wings, saved his repenting Nation, <HI>fed them, and set them up for ever; preserved them from Trouble, and com∣passed them about with Songs of Deliverance: that the Lord gave Strength unto his People, and gave his People the Blessing of Peace.</HI></P>
<P>PERMIT me to hope then, my Brethren, that you will heartily and sincerely join with me in this neces∣sary and humble Supplication;</P>
<P><HI>ALmighty and ever-living God, thou great and in∣exhaustible Fountain of Good and Happiness! in whose Hand are all the Corners of the Earth; on whose Aid we must depend for our Support, on whose Bounty we must rely for Succour, and to whose Mercy we must sue for Pardon; accept the Prayers of thy penitent Peo∣ple; behold, O! Lord, we acknowledge our Faults; our Transgressions are multiplied before thee, and our Sins testify against us; but thy Hand, O! Lord, is not shortened that it cannot save, neither thine Ear heavy that it can∣not hear; hear then, O! Lord, and save; let this Day's Humiliation be accepted as an Earnest of our future Repentance, and this Day's Acknowledgment of our Sins plead with thee for Pardon of our past Iniquities: Turn away thy Wrath, and be not angry with us for ever.
<PB N="15" REF="14"/>
Return, we beseech thee, O! God of Hosts, look down from Heaven and behold, what only thou canst behold, the Heart of the repentant Sinner: Spare us, thou God of Mercy; assist us, thou God of Power; prosper us, thou God of Victory; suffer not our Follies to sink, or our Iniquities to overwhelm us; go forth, we beseech thee, in this Hour of Peril, with our Fleets and Armies; strengthen the Hands of our gracious Sovereign; preside over his Councils, and direct his Ways; sheath, O! Lord, the Sword of Battle that is drawn forth against us; take off from this afflicted Nation the bloody Garment of War, and put upon us the Robe of Peace; that by the Provi∣dence of thy Goodness, every Evil dispersed, and every Enemy subdued, we, thy repentant Servants, being hurt by no Persecutions, may serve and please thee in Newness of Life, praising and giving Thanks unto thee in thy holy Church, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

