<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2007-02-28</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Emma Leeson Huber</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Corrected 2 illegibles of 4. Converted 2 illegibles To GAP DESC="illegible RESP="oxf".</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K047007.000">
<STC T="C">T051747</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3312769126</BIBNO>
<VID SET="ECLL">0131403000</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE TRIUMPH of ISIS, A POEM. OCCASIONED BY ISIS, an ELEGY.</P>
<Q><L>Quid mihi nescio quam, proprio cum Tybride, Romani</L>
<L>Semper in ore geris? referunt si vera Parentes,</L>
<L>Hanc Urbem insano Nullus qui Marte petivit</L>
<L>Laetatus violâsse redît. Nec numina sedem</L>
<L>Destituunt.—</L></Q>
<BIBL>CLAUDIAN.</BIBL>
<P>LONDON, Printed for W. OWEN, at <HI>Homer</HI>'s <HI>Head</HI> near <HI>Temple-Bar.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE TRIUMPH OF ISIS.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>ON closing flow'rs when genial gales diffuse</L>
<L>The fragrant tribute of refreshing dews;</L>
<L>When chaunts the milk-maid at her balmy pail,</L>
<L>And weary reapers whistle o'er the vale;</L>
<L>Charm'd by the murmurs of the quiv'ring shade,</L>
<L>O'er ISIS' willow-fringed banks I stray'd;</L>
<L>And calmly musing, thro' the twilight way,</L>
<L>In pensive mood I fram'd the Doric lay.</L>
<L>When lo! from opening clouds a golden gleam</L>
<L>Pour'd sudden splendours o'er the shadowy stream;</L>
<L>And from the wave arose its guardian queen,</L>
<L>Known by her sweeping stole of glossy green:</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="3"/>
While in the coral crown that bound her brow,</L>
<L>Was wove the Delphic laurel's verdant bough.</L>
<L>As the smooth surface of the dimply flood</L>
<L>The silver-slipper'd virgin lightly trod,</L>
<L>From her loose hair the dropping dew she press'd,</L>
<L>And thus mine ear in accents mild address'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>"No more, my son, the rural reed employ,</L>
<L>Nor trill the trifling strain of empty joy;</L>
<L>No more thy love-resounding sonnets suit</L>
<L>To notes of past'ral pipe, or oaten flute.</L>
<L>For hark▪ high thron'd on you majestic walls,</L>
<L>To the dear Muse afflicted Freedom calls▪</L>
<L>When Freedom calls, and OXFORD bids thee sing,</L>
<L>Why stays thy hand to strike the sounding string?</L>
<L>While thus, in Freedom's and in Phoebus' spite,</L>
<L>The venal sons of slavish CAM unite▪</L>
<L>To shake you tow'rs when malice rears her crest,</L>
<L>Shall all my sons in silence idly rest?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Still sing, O CAM, thy fav'rite Freedom's cause,</L>
<L>Still boast of Freedom—while you break its laws;</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="4"/>
To pow'r your songs of <HI>gratulation</HI> pay,</L>
<L>To courts address soft flatt'ry's soothing lay.</L>
<L>What tho' your gentle M—N's plaintive verse</L>
<L>Has hung with sweetest wreaths MUSAEUS' herse;</L>
<L>What tho' your vaunted bard's ingenuous woe,</L>
<L>Soft as my stream in tuneful numbers flow;</L>
<L>Yet strove his Muse, by fame or envy led,</L>
<L>To tear the laurels from a Sister's head?—</L>
<L>Misguided youth! with rude unclassic rage,</L>
<L>To blast the beauties of thy whiter page;</L>
<L>A rage that sullies ev'n thy guiltless lays,</L>
<L>And blasts the vernal bloom of half thy Bays.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Let GR—boast the patrons of her name,</L>
<L>Each pompous fool of fortune and of fame;</L>
<L>Still of preferment let her shine the queen,</L>
<L>Prolific parent of each bowing Dean!</L>
<L>Be her's each Pr—te of the pamper'd cheek,</L>
<L>Each courtly Chaplain sanctify'd and sleek:</L>
<L>Still let the Drones of her exhaustless hive</L>
<L>On fat pluralities supinely thrive.</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="5"/>
Still let her senates titled slaves revere,</L>
<L>Nor dare to know the patriot from the peer;</L>
<L>For tinsel'd courts their laurel'd mount despise</L>
<L>In stars and strings superlatively wise:</L>
<L>No longer charm'd by virtue's golden lyre,</L>
<L>Who sung of old amid th' Aonian choir,</L>
<L>Where CAM, slow-winding thro' the breezy reeds,</L>
<L>With kindly wave his groves of laurel feeds.</L>
<L>'Tis ours, my son, to deal the sacred bay,</L>
<L>Where honour calls, and justice points the way;</L>
<L>To wear the well-earn'd wreath which merit brings▪</L>
<L>And snatch a gift beyond the reach of kings!</L>
<L>Scorning and scorn'd by courts, yon Muses bow'r</L>
<L>Still nor enjoys, nor asks the smile of pow'r.</L>
<L>Tho' wakeful vengeance watch my chrystal spring,</L>
<L>Tho' persecution wave her iron wing,</L>
<L>And o'er yon spiry temples as she flies,</L>
<L>"These destin'd feats be mine" exulting cries;</L>
<L>On ISIS▪ still each gift of fortune waits,</L>
<L>Still peace and plenty crown my beauteous gates.</L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="6"/>
See Science walks with freshest chaplets crown'd,</L>
<L>With songs of joy my festal groves resound;</L>
<L>My Muse divine still keeps her wonted state,</L>
<L>The front erect, and high majestic gait.</L>
<L>Green: as of old, each oliv'd portal smiles,</L>
<L>And still the Graces build my Parian piles:</L>
<L>My Gothic spires in ancient grandeur rise,</L>
<L>And dare with wonted pride to rush into the ski<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Ah should'st thou fall (forbid it heav'nly pow'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Dash'd into dust with all thy hundred tow'rs;</L>
<L>Who but would mourn to British virtue dear,</L>
<L>What patriot could refuse the manly tear:</L>
<L>What British <NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot"><HI>Vid. Vell. Paterc. Lib.</HI> ii. <HI>&amp; Plutarch. in Vit. Marii:</HI></NOTE> MARIUS would refuse to weep</L>
<L>O'er mighty CARTHAGE fall'n, a prostrate heap!</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>E'en late when RADCLIFFE'S delegated train</L>
<L>Auspicious shone in ISIS' happy plain;</L>
<L>When you proud ‖<NOTE PLACE="foot">‡ The Radcliffe Library.</NOTE> dome, fair Learning's amplest shrine,</L>
<L>Beneath its Attick roofs receiv'd the Nine; </L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="7"/>
Mute was the voice of joy and loud applause,</L>
<L>To RADCLIFFE due, and ISIS' honour'd cause?</L>
<L>What free-born crouds adorn'd the festive day,</L>
<L>Nor blush'd to wear my tributary bay?</L>
<L>How each brave breast with honest ardours heav'd,</L>
<L>When SHELDON'S fane the patriot band receiv'd;</L>
<L>While, as we loudly hail'd the chosen few,</L>
<L>Rome's awful senate rush'd upon our view!</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>O may the day in latest annals shine,</L>
<L>That made a BEAUFORT and an HARLEY mine!</L>
<L>That bade them leave the loftier scene awhile,</L>
<L>The pomp of guiltless state, the patriot toil,</L>
<L>For bleeding Albion's aid the sage design,</L>
<L>To hold short dalliance with the tuneful Nine.</L>
<L>While music left her golden sphere on high,</L>
<L>And bore each strain of triumph from the sky;</L>
<L>Swell'd the loud song, and to my chiefs around,</L>
<L>Pour'd the full Paeans of mellifluous sound;</L>
<L>My Naiads blythe the floating accents caught,</L>
<L>And list'ning danc'd beneath their pearly grot:</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="8" MS="y"/>
In gentle eddies play'd my wanton wave,</L>
<L>And all my reeds their softest whispers gave;</L>
<L>Each lay with brighter green adorn'd my bow'rs,</L>
<L>And breath'd a fresher fragrance on my flow'rs.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But lo! at once the swelling concerts cease,</L>
<L>And crouded theatres are hush'd in peace.</L>
<L>See on yon sage how all attentive stand,</L>
<L>To catch his darting eye, and waving hand.</L>
<L>Hark! he begins with all a TULLY's art</L>
<L>To pour the dictates of a CATO's heart.</L>
<L>Skill'd to pronounce what noblest thoughts inspire,</L>
<L>He blends the Speaker's with the Patriot's fire;</L>
<L>Bold to conceive, nor timorous to conceal,</L>
<L>What Britons dare to think, he dares to tell:</L>
<L>'Tis his alike the ear and eye to charm,</L>
<L>To win with action, and with sense to warm:</L>
<L>Untaught in flow'ry diction to dispense</L>
<L>The lulling sounds of sweet impertinence;</L>
<L>In frowns or smiles he gains an equal prize,</L>
<L>Nor meanly fears to fall, nor creeps to rise:</L>
<L><PB N="10" REF="9"/>
Bids happier days to ALBION be restor'd,</L>
<L>Bids ancient justice rear her radiant sword:</L>
<L>From me, as from my country wins applause,</L>
<L>And makes an OXFORD's a BRITANNIA's cause.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>While arms like these my stedfast sages wield,</L>
<L>While mine is Truth's impenetrable shield;</L>
<L>Say, shall the PUNY CHAMPION fondly dare,</L>
<L>To wage with force like this <HI>scholastic</HI> war?</L>
<L>Still vainly scribble on with pert pretence,</L>
<L>With all the rage of pedant impotence?</L>
<L>Say, shall I foster this domestic pest,</L>
<L>This parricide that wounds a mother's breast?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus in some stately ship, that long has bore</L>
<L>Britain's victorious cross from shore to shore:</L>
<L>By chance beneath her close sequester'd cells▪</L>
<L>Some low-born worm, a lurking mischief dwells;</L>
<L>Eats his blind way, and saps with secret toil</L>
<L>The deep foundation of the watry pile.</L>
<L>In vain the forrest lent its stateliest pride,</L>
<L>Rear'd her tall mast, and fram'd her knotty side.</L>
<L><PB N="11" REF="10"/>
In vain the thunder's martial rage she stood,</L>
<L>With each fierce conflict of the stormy flood;</L>
<L>More sure the reptile's little arts devour,</L>
<L>Than waves, or wars, or Eurus' wintry pow'r.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Ye venerable bow'rs, ye seats sublime,</L>
<L>Clad in the mossy vest of fleeting time;</L>
<L>Ye stately Piles of old munificence,</L>
<L>At once the pride of Learning, and defence,</L>
<L>Where ancient Piety, a matron hoar,</L>
<L>Still seems to keep the hospitable door;</L>
<L>Ye cloisters pale that lengthening to the sight,</L>
<L>Still step by step to musings mild invite;</L>
<L>Ye high arch'd walls, where oft the bard has caught</L>
<L>The glowing sentiment, the lofty thought:</L>
<L>Ye temples dim, where pious duty pays</L>
<L>Her holy hymns of ever-echoing praise;</L>
<L>Lo! your lov'd ISIS, from the bord'ring vale,</L>
<L>With all a mother's fondness bids you hail!</L>
<L>Hail, OXFORD, hail! of all that's good and great,</L>
<L>Of all that's fair, the guardian and the seat;</L>
<L><PB N="12" REF="11"/>
Nurse of each brave pursuit, each generous aim,</L>
<L>By truth exalted to the throne of fame!</L>
<L>Like Greece in science and in liberty,</L>
<L>As Athens learn'd, as Lacedaemon free!</L>
<L>Ev'n now confest to my adoring eyes,</L>
<L>In awful ranks thy sacred sons arise:</L>
<L>With ev'ry various flow'r thy temples wreath'd,</L>
<L>That in thy gardens green its fragrance breath'd.</L>
<L>Tuning to knightly tale his British reeds,</L>
<L>Thy crowding Bards immortal CHAUCER leads:</L>
<L>His hoary head o'erlooks the gazing choir,</L>
<L>And beams on all around caelestial fire.</L>
<L>With graceful step see ADDISON advance,</L>
<L>The sweetest child of Attic elegance</L>
<L>To all but his belov'd embrace deny'd,</L>
<L>See LOCKE leads Reason, his majestic bride:</L>
<L>See sacred HAMMOND, as he treads the field,</L>
<L>With goldlike arm uprears his heav'nly shield.</L>
<L>All who beneath the shades of gentle peace,</L>
<L>Best plan'd the labours of domestic ease;</L>
<L><PB N="13" REF="12"/>
Who taught with truth, or with persuasion mov'd;</L>
<L>Who sooth'd with Numbers, or with sense improv'd;</L>
<L>Who told the pow'rs of reason, or refin'd</L>
<L>All, all that strengthen'd or adorn'd the mind;</L>
<L>Each priest of health who mix'd the balmy bowl,</L>
<L>To rear frail man, and stay the fleeting soul;</L>
<L>All crowd around, and echoing to the sky,</L>
<L>Hail, OXFORD, hail! with filial transport cry.</L>
<L>And see yon solemn band! with virtuous aim,</L>
<L>'Twas theirs in thought the glorious deed to frame:</L>
<L>With pious plans each musing feature glows,</L>
<L>And well-weigh'd counsels mark their meaning brows.</L>
<L>"<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">Vid. the ELEGY. Pag. 4.</NOTE> Lo these the leaders of thy patriot line,"</L>
<L>HAMDEN and HOOKER, HYDE and SIDNEY shine.</L>
<L>These from thy source the fires of Freedom caught:</L>
<L>How well thy sons by their example taught;</L>
<L>While in each breast th' hereditary flame</L>
<L>Still blazes unextinguish'd and the same!</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="13"/>
Nor all the toils of thoughtful peace engage,</L>
<L>'Tis thine to form the hero as the sage.</L>
<L>I see the sable-suited prince advance</L>
<L>With lillies crown'd, the spoils of bleeding France,</L>
<L>EDWARD—the Muses in yon hallow'd shade</L>
<L>Bound on his tender thigh the martial blade:</L>
<L>Bade him the steel for British freedom draw,</L>
<L>And OXFORD taught the deeds that CRESSY saw.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And see, great father of the laureat band,</L>
<L>The <NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot"><HI>Alfred. Regis Romani. V. Virg. Aen.</HI> 6.</NOTE> BRITISH KING before me seems to stand;</L>
<L>He by my plenty-crowned scenes beguil'd,</L>
<L>And genial influence of my seasons mild,</L>
<L>Hither of yore (forlorn, forgotten maid)</L>
<L>The Muse in prattling infancy convey'd;</L>
<L>From Gothic rage the helpless virgin bore,</L>
<L>And fix'd her cradle on my friendly shore:</L>
<L>Soon grew the maid beneath his fost'ring hand,</L>
<L>Soon pour'd her blessings o'er th' enlighten'd land.</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="14"/>
Tho' rude the dome, and humble the retreat,</L>
<L>Where first his pious care ordain'd her seat,</L>
<L>Lo! now on high she dwells in Attic bow'rs,</L>
<L>And proudly lifts to heav'n her hundred tow'rs.</L>
<L>He first fair Learning's and Britannia's cause</L>
<L>Adorn'd with manners, and advanc'd with laws;</L>
<L>He bade relent the Briton's savage heart,</L>
<L>And form'd his soul to social scenes of art;</L>
<L>Wisest and best of Kings!—with ravish'd gaze</L>
<L>Elate the long procession he surveys:</L>
<L>Joyful he smiles to find, that not in vain</L>
<L>He plan'd the rudiments of Learning's reign:</L>
<L>Himself he marks in each ingenuous breast,</L>
<L>With all the founder in the race exprest:</L>
<L>With rapture views, fair Freedom still survive</L>
<L>In yon bright domes (ill-fated fugitive.)</L>
<L>(Such scene, as when the Goddess pour'd the beam</L>
<L>Unsullied, on his ancient diadem) <NOTE PLACE="foot"><L>†<HI>———Ad capitolia ducit</HI></L>
<L><HI>Aurea nunc, olim Sylvestribus horrida dumis.</HI></L>
<P>VIRG. Aen.</P></NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="15"/>
Well pleas'd that in his own Pierian seat</L>
<L>She plumes her wings, and rests her weary feet;</L>
<L>That here at last she takes her fav'rite stand,</L>
<L>"Here deigns to linger e'er she leave the land."</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

