<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE><DATE>2003-10-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><NAME>John Latta</NAME><RESP>MURP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure; changed Q to P (image 10). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, oe's, and UNCLEARs. Corrected $s. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked CLOSERs, BYLINEs, SIGNEDs, OPENERs, SALUTEs, and TRAILERs. Checked for startqs and endqs, abq's, Ae's, q;s, and Qs. Sample: 0 minutes. Proofing: 0 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 35 minutes. DONE.</ITEM></CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N08170">
<STC T="E">10435</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99030385</BIBNO>
<VID>0F7FD26BC3E279F0</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="010435_0000_0F7FC2352A984C00"/>
<PB REF="010435_0001_0F7FC237392D0238" MS="y"/>
<P>THE
CLAIM
OF THE
INHABITANTS
OF THE
TOWN OF <HI>NEWARK,</HI>
IN VIRTUE OF
The INDIAN PURCHASE made by the first
Settlers of NEWARK, in 1667.</P>
<P>STATED AND CONSIDERED.</P>
<P>WOODBRID<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" REASON="blotted" DISP="•"/>E, in <HI>New-Iersey:</HI>
Printed by SAMUEL F. PARKER.
M.DCC.LXVI.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="treatise">
<PB REF="010435_0002_0F7FC2382ABA81D0"/>
<HEAD>The Claim of the Inhabitants of the
Town of NEWARK, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P>KING CHARLES the Second, being by Discovery
and the actual Possession of the Dutch by his
Licence, intitled to the Lands now called NEW-YORK
and NEW-JERSEY did, by his Letters
Patent dated the 12th Day of <HI>March, 1663-4,</HI> grant
and convey to his Brother JAMES Duke of <HI>York,</HI> all the
Lands within the Colonies of <HI>New-York</HI> and <HI>New-Iersey,</HI>
with the Powers of Government.</P>
<P>JAMES Duke of <HI>York,</HI> on the 2d Day of <HI>April,</HI> 1664,
commissioned <HI>Richard Nicholls</HI> to be Governor of his
said Territories in <HI>America.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Richard Nicholls,</HI> on the 20th Day of <HI>August,</HI> 1664,
arrived in <HI>America,</HI> and on the 27th of the same Month,
had the Possession of said Colonies of <HI>New-York</HI> and
<HI>New-Iersey,</HI> delivered him by the Dutch.</P>
<P>It is said, that Governor <HI>Nicholls,</HI> soon after his Arrival
in his said Government, issued a Proclamation, containing
the Conditions for new Plantations in the Territories of
his Royal Highness the Duke of <HI>York,</HI> among which
are these following, viz.</P>
<P><Q>The Purchases are to be made from the Indian Sa∣chems,
and to be recorded before the Governor.</Q></P>
<P><Q>The Purchasers are not to pay for their Liberty of
purchasing, to the Governor.</Q></P>
<P><Q>The Purchasers are to set out a Town, and inhabit
together.</Q></P>
<P><Q>No Purchaser shall at any Time, contract for himself
with any Sachem, without Consent of his Associates, or
Special Warrant from the Governor.</Q></P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="010435_0003_0F7FC239163418E8"/>
<Q>All Lands thus purchased, shall remain to the Pur∣chasers
and their Heirs, as free Lands, to dispose of as
they please.</Q></P>
<P><Q>The Lands which I intend shall be first planted, are
those upon the West side of <HI>Hudson</HI>'s River, at or ad∣joining
to <HI>Esopus;</HI> but if any Number of Men, sufficient
for two, three, or more Towns, shall desire to plant upon
any other Lands, they shall have all due Encouragement
proportionable to their Quality and Undertaking.</Q></P>
<P><HI>Note.</HI> No Proclamation has ever appeared; and all that
has appeared, are Papers without any Date, said to be
Copies.</P>
<P>JAMES Duke of <HI>York,</HI> by his Letters Patent, dated
the 24th Day of <HI>Iune,</HI> 1664, (about two Months before
Governor <HI>Nicholls</HI> arrived in <HI>America</HI>) granted and con∣veyed
the now Province of <HI>New-Iersey,</HI> to <HI>Iohn</HI> Lord
<HI>Berkeley,</HI> and Sir <HI>George Carteres,</HI> in Fee.</P>
<P>The said Lord <HI>Berkeley</HI> and Sir <HI>George Carteret,</HI> on the
10th Day of <HI>February,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Recorded Lib. 3. p. 27.</NOTE> 1664-5, appointed
<HI>Philip Carteret</HI> to be Governor of <HI>New-Iersey,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Recorded Lib. 3. p. 28.</NOTE>
and on the same Day, by a separate
Instrument under their Hands and Seals, gave
Power to the said <HI>Philip Carteret,</HI> with Ad∣vice
of the major Part of his Council, to grant Lands
to all such Persons as should by their Concessions be in∣titled
thereto; but expressly therein declare, that they
grant no Power but according to the Concessions.</P>
<P>The said Lord <HI>Berkeley</HI> and Sir <HI>George Carteret,</HI> on the
same 10th Day of <HI>February,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Recorded Lib. 3. from Pages 66 to 74.</NOTE> 1664-5, did, by
another Instrument, under their Hands and
Seals, grant their Concessions, establishing
thereby the Constitution of the said Pro∣vince,
to be strictly observed by all inhabiting them;
which Concessions direct and order, that the Form of
Government should be by a Governor, Council and an
Assembly; and fix the Powers of each and of all the
<PB N="5" REF="010435_0004_0F7FC239BA507398"/>
Officers of Government; and declare, that a Title to
Lands was to be obtained by the Settlers, by having a
Survey made by the Surveyor General or his Deputy,
duly recorded with the Register, and a Grant or Patent,
under the Seal of the Province, signed by the Governor
and the major Part of the Council, to the Person for
whom said Survey was made; and that by no other
Method a Title to Lands could be obtained by the In∣habitants
of <HI>New-Iersey.</HI></P>
<P>In or before the Month of <HI>August,</HI> 1665, Governor
<HI>Carteret</HI> arrived in <HI>New-Iersey,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Lib. 1. p. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" REASON="blotted" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> and execu∣ted
the Powers of Government agreeable to
his Commission and said Concessions.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Lib. 3. p. 1.</NOTE></P>
<P>In the Year 1665,<NOTE PLACE="marg">This appears from Governor Carteret's Let∣ter and Memo∣randum Book.</NOTE> Mr. <HI>Treat</HI> and others,
from <HI>Connecticut,</HI> after treating with Go∣vernor
<HI>Carteret</HI> about settling in <HI>New-Iersey,</HI>
after examining the Concessions, (which
they saw and considered) and after having
some religious and other Privileges (not contained in the
Concessions) granted them, came into <HI>New-Iersey</HI> with
an Intent of settling on the River <HI>Delaware,</HI> near <HI>Bur∣lington;</HI>
but on viewing the Country, they did not like it.</P>
<P>On their Return from <HI>Delaware,</HI> they called on
Governor <HI>Carteret</HI> at <HI>Elizabeth-Town;</HI> who persuaded
them to settle on the Lands now called NEWARK, and
wrote a Letter to the Indian Sachem to sell the same to
Captain <HI>Treat,</HI> promising the Indian Sachem to satisfy
him for the same.</P>
<P>In Consequence whereof the said <HI>Treat</HI>
and Company purchased of the Indians all
the Lands within the Town of <HI>Newark;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Samuel Edsell and Joseph Harrison's Af∣fidavit, and Indian Deed to Newark, in 1667.</NOTE>
and afterwards in 1667, took a Bill of Sale
from the Indians for those Lands, paid the
Consideration Sum to the Indians, and
began in that Year to settle the Town of NEWARK.</P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="010435_0005_0F7FC23A769DEF00"/>
The said first Settlers of NEWARK,<NOTE PLACE="marg">This appears from a List of the several Pa∣tents taken from the pub∣lick Records of New-Jersey.</NOTE> soon
after their said Indian Purchase, and before
the Year 1700, applied for and obtained
One Hundred and ten Patents from the
Proprietor's Governors and Council of
<HI>New-Iersey,</HI> for 12439 Acres of Land,
lying within the Bounds of said Indian Purchase; 8134
Acres thereof, at the annual Rent of one Half-Penny per
Acre, agreeable to the said Concessions of the Lords
Proprietors, amounting in the whole to <HI>16l. 18s. 11d.</HI>
a Year; and the remaining 4305 Acres, at the yearly
Rent of six Pence per hundred Acres, according to an
Agreement entered into between the Town of <HI>Newark,</HI>
and the General Proprietors of <HI>New-Iersey,</HI> herein after
mentioned.</P>
<P>In 1676, <HI>New-Iersey</HI> was divided into <HI>East</HI> and <HI>West-Iersey;</HI>
and <HI>East-Iersey</HI> was assigned for the Part and
Share of Sir <HI>George Carteret;</HI> and by sundry mesne Con∣veyances
from him, the Eastern Division, whereof <HI>New∣ark</HI>
is a Part, was in and about 1681, vested in those
called the twenty-four General Proprietors of <HI>East New-Iersey;</HI>
whose Heirs and Assigns, and the Patentees of
Lord <HI>Berkeley</HI> and Sir <HI>George Carteret,</HI> claim the same
to this Day.</P>
<P>The first Settlers of <HI>Newark</HI> not having in and before
the Year 1692, obtained Patents for more than about
8000 Acres of Land, within their said Indian Purchase,
at one Half-Penny per Acre Quit-rent, but having paid
the Consideration Sum to the Indians for the whole Tract
(containing upwards of 40000 Acres) and yet being
unwilling to take Patents for all the remaining Lands
within their Bounds on the Terms of granting Patents at
one Half-Penny per Acre fixed by said Concessions, did
by their Committee, <HI>Iohn Curtice,</HI> and others, chosen for
that Purpose, on the 28th Day of <HI>February,</HI> 1692, meet
and propose to the General Proprietors of <HI>East New-Iersey,</HI>
<PB N="7" REF="010435_0006_0F7FC23B41D38780"/>
an amicable and friendly Accommodation relating
to the Lands held by the Inhabitants of <HI>Newark</HI> under
the Proprietors, and those which they possessed by Pur∣chase
from the Indians; and after a long Conference had
thereon, it was proposed, that the Inhabitants of <HI>Newark</HI>
(such of them as yet had not) should take out Patents for
the Lands they possessed,<NOTE PLACE="marg">As appears on Record, in Lib. A. B. p. 118.</NOTE> and pay their
Arrears of Quit-Rents; and that all the old
Settlers should have one hundred Acres of
Land, each at six Pence per Annum Quit-Rent:
Which Proposals were agreed to be referred by
said Committee, to said Town of <HI>Newark,</HI> for their
Approbation.</P>
<P>Which Proposals were afterwards mutually agreed to,
and carried into Execution by both Parties,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Lib. A. B. 12<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" REASON="blotted" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE>
by the general Proprietors ratifying the same,
and by the first Settlers of <HI>Newark,</HI> signifying their
Consent thereto, and obtaining in Virtue of said Agree∣ment,
upwards of Forty Patents from the General Pro∣prietors
for 4305 Acres of Land, at the annual Quit-rent
of Six Pence per Hundred Acres; which several Patents
are recorded in Lib. E. and F.</P>
<P>Besides said several Patents granted in Virtue of said
Agreement, about five Hundred Acres of Land, have
also, since the granting of Letters Patent in <HI>New-Iersey</HI>
ceased, been surveyed and returned to the Heirs of the
first Settlers of <HI>Newark,</HI> on said Agreement, who hold
the same to this Day. And it is conceived, that there are
not more than two of the old Settlers of <HI>Newark,</HI> but
what have, either by themselves, their Heirs or Assigns,
taken out Patents, or had Surveys granted them, for said
Hundred Acres agreed upon, for the consideration Sum
paid the Indians for the Lands they held by Purchase
within the Town of <HI>Newark.</HI></P>
<P>It is alledged by some of the present Inhabitants of
<HI>Newark,</HI> that Governor <HI>Carteret</HI> granted a Licence to
<PB N="8" REF="010435_0007_0F7FC23BEAC7A900"/>
the first Purchasers of <HI>Newark,</HI> to make their Purchase
of the Indians; which is founded on the Affidavits of
<HI>Ioseph Harrison,</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> deceased, taken in 1742, and of
<HI>Ionathan Pierson,</HI> taken in 1764. Mr. <HI>Harrison</HI> swears,
that he about forty Years, then last past, heard a Writing
read by one <HI>Iohn Cooper,</HI> which he understood to be a
Licence from Governor <HI>Carteret,</HI> as Governor, <HI>Iohn
Ogden</HI> and others, of <HI>Elizabeth-Town,</HI> to purchase of
the Indians, the Lands now called <HI>Newark;</HI> does not re∣member
that there were any particular Boundaries men∣tioned
in said Licence, but believes it was for the Lands
purchased by the People of <HI>Newark</HI> as aforesaid. <HI>Ionathan
Pierson</HI> swears, that when he was a Boy, his Father
<HI>Theophilus Pierson,</HI> came Home from attending a Proxy
Meeting of the Proprietors, held at <HI>Elizabeth-Town</HI> or
<HI>Perth-Amboy,</HI> and said, that he had lost the <HI>Newark</HI>
Licence, and believed it was taken out of his Pocket;
but does not remember ever to have heard his Father
declare the Contents thereof.</P>
<P>In the Year 1666, and afterwards, several Licences
were granted by Governor <HI>Carteret,</HI> to make Purchases
of the Indians, and recorded in the publick Records at
<HI>Perth-Amboy,</HI> all containing a Condition that the Persons
to whom the Licences were granted should truly perform
all such Acts and Things as are contained in the Lords
Proprietors Concessions; one of which dated the Twenty-fourth
Day of <HI>Iune,</HI> 1666, is recorded in Lib. 1. Page 9.
and is in the Words following, <HI>to wit.</HI></P>
<P><Q>Whereas Mr. <HI>Isaac Ienna,</HI> alias <HI>La Pierre,</HI> hath
requested my Leave, for the purchasing a certain Tract
of Land from the Indians, on the East Side of <HI>Delaware</HI>
River, within this Government, with an Intent to
inhabit and plant the same: These are therefore to
permit and suffer the said <HI>Isaac,</HI> to purchase the said
Tract of Land from the Indians, upon Condition, that
he truly perform all such Acts and Things as are con∣tained
<PB N="9" REF="010435_0008_0F7FC23CAA673980"/>
in the Lords Proprietors <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="6 letters" REASON="faint" DISP="••••••"/>sions, and to be
conformable and obedient to the Laws of this Province.
Given under my Hand, and the Seal of the Province,
the 24th Day of <HI>Iune,</HI> 1666.</Q></P>
<P>One other Licence in like Manner, granted to <HI>Eli<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="4 letters" REASON="blotted" DISP="••••"/>
Wardel,</HI> and his Associates, dated <HI>November</HI> the 4th,
1666, recorded in Lib. 3. fol. 10.</P>
<P>One other in like Manner, granted to <HI>Peter Abriske,</HI>
dated <HI>November</HI> 15th, 1666, recorded in Lib. 1. fol. 6.
and several other like Licences to five different Persons,
from the Year 1668, to 1671, recorded in said Lib. 1.
from p. 21 to 33.</P>
<P>After the Surrender of the Government of <HI>New-Iersey,</HI>
by the General Proprietors to the Crown of <HI>England,</HI> in
the Year 1702, Letters Patent ceased to be granted for
Land in <HI>East New-Iersey,</HI> and the Constitution instead
thereof was establish'd, that the General Proprietors, or
their Assigns, should have Warrants of Survey granted
them by the Council of Proprietors, for such Shares of
Land as they were entitled to, the Surveyor General
making a Survey and Return thereof, which being
entered on Record, gave a Title to hold in Severalty.</P>
<P>Agreeable to said last Constitution, several Thousand
Acres of Land were purchased, surveyed, and taken up
on the Proprietors Title, within the Bounds of Newark-Purchase,
by the Inhabitants of <HI>Newark,</HI> and others;
which are now possessed by the People of <HI>Newark,</HI> under
the Proprietors Title only; as the <HI>Indian</HI> Purchase Right
had long before been given up to the General Proprietors
of <HI>New-Iersey,</HI> by the first Settlers of <HI>Newark,</HI> as
aforesaid. And it is conceived, that there is not the
Quantity of 500 Acres of Land, within the Bounds of
Newark Township, at this Day, but what are now in
the actual Possession of the Inhabitants of <HI>Newark,</HI> under
the Title derived from the General Proprietors.</P>
<P><PB N="10" REF="010435_0009_0F7FC23D8229A278"/>
That since the said Agreement made between the first
Settlers of <HI>Newark,</HI> and the General Proprietors of <HI>East
New-Iersey,</HI> in 1694, there has been no Division made
of the unappropriated Lands within the Bounds of said
<HI>Indian</HI> Purchase, among the Heirs and Assigns of the
first Settlers of <HI>Newark,</HI> according to their antient
respective Claims; but all the Inhabitants were at Liberty
to purchase a Proprietor's Title, and take up such Parts
of the unappropriated Lands in the Township of <HI>Newark,</HI>
as they from Time to Time saw fit: Some took up
several hundred Acres, some a less Quantity, and others
none; wherewith, and with said Agreement, made
between the General Proprietors and the first Purchasers
of <HI>Newark,</HI> there has been a general Acquiescence, till
very lately a few of the Descendants (the third Generation)
of the first Settlers of <HI>Newark,</HI> have set up a Claim
under the Newark Indian Purchase.</P>
<P>Quere. Have the present Inhabitants of <HI>Newark,</HI> any
Right either in Law or Equity, to claim Title to the
Lands purchased by their Ancestors, of the Indians, in
1667, in Virtue of said Indian Purchase?</P>
<P>To which I answer,</P>
<P>First, That altho' Governor <HI>Nicholis</HI>'s Proclamation
should be admitted genuine, (which is disputed; as the
Title to Lands within either New-York or New-Jersey
hath never from the first Settlement thereof, been acquired
by Indian Purchases, agreeable to said Proclamation, but
by Letters Patent under the publick Seal of the Colony,
or Grants from the Crown of <HI>England</HI>) and should it
also be admitted, that the Proclamation did issue soon after
Governor <HI>Nicholls</HI>'s Arrival in <HI>New-York;</HI> yet the Descen∣dants
of the first Purchasers of <HI>Newark,</HI> can't have the
least Pretence of claiming Title under said Proclamation,
for the following Reasons.</P>
<P>1. Because the Duke of <HI>York</HI> had, near two Months
before Governor <HI>Nicholls</HI>'s said Arrival, sold <HI>New-Iersey</HI>
<PB N="11" REF="010435_0010_0F7FC23F7A8DE610"/>
to Lord <HI>Berkeley</HI> and Sir <HI>George Carteret;</HI> therefore
neither the Duke nor his Governor, could have any
Right to declare and fix the Terms of gaining a Title to
Lands in <HI>New-Iersey.</HI></P>
<P>2. Because the Newark Indian Purchase was made
after Lord <HI>Berkeley</HI> and Sir <HI>George Carteret</HI> had made
and published in <HI>New-Iersey,</HI> certain Concessions as and
for the Constitution of the Province.</P>
<P>3. Because <HI>Philip Carteret,</HI> the Governor appointed
by Lord <HI>Berkeley</HI> and Sir <HI>George Carteret,</HI> arrived in
<HI>New-Iersey,</HI> in 1665, and executed the Powers of
Government there, one Year before the Newark Purchase
was made.</P>
<P>4. Because the first Purchasers of <HI>Newark</HI> were, before
they made their Purchase, acquainted with said Con∣cessions,
and purchased under the Terms and Conditions
thereof.</P>
<P>Wherefore it is clear, that the Proclamation of Governor
<HI>Nicholis,</HI> if genuine, can't avail the Newark Purchasers,
or their Heirs.</P>
<P>Secondly, With Respect to the formal Licence, said
to be granted by Governor <HI>Carteret,</HI> to the first Settlers
of <HI>Newark,</HI> to purchase of the Indians, I am induced to
believe he never granted any, and that for the following
Reasons.</P>
<P>1. Because Governor <HI>Carteret</HI> in his Letter to the
<HI>Indian</HI> Sachem, sent by Mr. <HI>Treat,</HI> when he went to
make the Purchase, writes, that he had sent Mr. <HI>Treat</HI>
to finish the Purchase of the Lands he had before treated
with him about; and that he the Governor, would
satisfy the <HI>Indians</HI> for the same Lands; which he could
not with Propriety have done, had Mr. <HI>Treat</HI> received a
formal Licence for said Purchase.</P>
<P>2. Because said <HI>Indian</HI> Purchase Deed, does not recite
a Licence being given, but that the Purchase was made
by the Advice and Consent of Governor <HI>Carteret.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="12" REF="010435_0011_0F7FC23FF7E543E0"/>
3. Because there is no Licence to make said Purchase
of the Indians, entered on the publick Records of <HI>New-Iersey;</HI>
which was the Practice before, and ever since
said Purchase.</P>
<P>4. Because there is great Reason to believe, that the
Paper which Mr. <HI>Harrison</HI> and Mr. <HI>Pierson</HI> mention,
must have been the Letter wrote to said Indian Sachem,
as it might with some Propriety be called a Licence.</P>
<P>5. Because it is highly improbable, that Governor
<HI>Carteret</HI> did grant any formal Licence or other Writing,
or make any Agreement with the Newark Purchasers;
contrary to the Concessions of the Lords Proprietors,
which he by his Commission and Instructions was bound
to obey and observe: Had he even acted otherwise with
respect to Newark Purchase, the same would have been
void and of none Effect; as thereby he would have
exceeded his Commission, and the Powers granted him
by the Lords Proprietors his Constituents.</P>
<P>If a written Licence was granted by Governor <HI>Car∣teret,</HI>
to make Newark Indian Purchase, the same must be
presumed to have been in the same, or like Form, with all
the other Licences on Record, granted before, and for
some Years after the Newark Indian Purchase was made,
<HI>viz.</HI> with Condition of complying with the Concessions;
as thereby Governor <HI>Carteret</HI> would not only be perfor∣ming
the Duty of his Office, and act consistent with his
Treatment of others in the like Cases, but also would be
acting in Conformity to the Treaty between him and
Newark Purchasers, before the Indian Purchase was
made.</P>
<P>From whence I think it evident, that the first Settlers
of <HI>Newark</HI> had no legal Title to the Lands within the
Bounds of the Town, in Virtue of their Indian Purchase:
but all that they acquired thereby was the Equity of a
Preference to all others, of having the same Lands ap∣propriated,
surveyed, and patented to them, in a reason∣able
<PB N="13" REF="010435_0012_0F7FC2406E44F880"/>
Time after the Purchase, agreeable to the Constitu∣tion
of the Province; which Equity they had, and en∣joyed
uninterrupted, until the said Agreement in 1694,
made between the first Settlers of <HI>Newark,</HI> and the General
Proprietors of <HI>New-Iersey,</HI> was carried into Execution:
And since said amicable Agreement for the Lands held by
Indian Purchase, expressly fixes and limits the Quantity
of One Hundred Acres for each old Settler of <HI>Newark</HI>
to have, of the unappropriated Land, within their Indian
Purchase; and all the said first Settlers, except two, did
actually take out Patents and had Surveys for the same, in
Pursuance of said Agreement; I am clearly of Opinion,
that all future Pretence of claiming any Title, either in
Law or Equity, to any Part of the Lands within the
Bounds of <HI>Newark,</HI> in Virtue of said Indian Purchase,
must be idle, and without the least Foundation to support
it, unless it be an Equity, which I conceive still due to
the Heirs of the two old Settlers, who have not had
patented or surveyed to them, the One Hundred Acres
agreed upon for each old Settler to have.</P>
<P>Those who now set up said Indian Purchase Claim, in
Opposition to the Proprietors Title, they have to the
Lands they possess, wou'd do well to consider these fol∣lowing
Matters.</P>
<P>1. That the first Settlers of <HI>Newark,</HI> taking out soon
after their first Settlement, a great Number of Patents,
agreeable to the Constitution of <HI>New-Iersey,</HI> is an Evi∣dence
of their Submission to hold their Lands under
the General Proprietors.</P>
<P>2. That the Agreement in 1694, carried into Execu∣tion,
is a further Evidence of said Submission, and also
of the first Settlers receiving ample Satisfaction for what
they paid the Indians for the Lands by them purchased.</P>
<P>3. That several of the Inhabitants of <HI>Newark,</HI> pur∣chasing
Proprietary Rights, (after said Agreement, made
in 1694, was carried into Execution) and laying the
<PB N="14" REF="010435_0013_0F7FC241396BA948"/>
same on the then unappropriated Lands, within the
Bounds of Newark Purchase, without any Regard to the
Share they held within said Purchase; is a further Evi∣dence,
that the Inhabitants of <HI>Newark</HI> did not pretend
any Title under their Indian Purchase, but under the
General Proprietors altogether.</P>
<P>4. That the Pretence now set up by some of the In∣habitants
of <HI>Newark,</HI> of claiming under the Newark In∣dian
Purchase, is a Violation of the Constitution of <HI>New-Iersey,</HI>
wherewith the first Purchasers were acquainted
before they made their Purchase, and contrary to the many
solemn Acts and Agreements of their Ancestors, which
always have been countenanced in Courts of Law and
Equity.</P>
<P>5. That if the Proprietors Title to the Lands in <HI>New∣ark</HI>
should be held valid and good, the general Peace of
the Town would be preserved, and the many antient
Possessions secured to the Possessors; but should the In∣dian
Purchase Claim be the legal Title to hold the Lands
within the Bounds of <HI>Newark</HI> by, the many Thousands
of Acres surveyed and taken up after the Year 1694,
will remain without Title to the Possessors, and be subject
to a new Division among the Heirs and Assigns of the
said first Purchasers.</P>
<P>Which several Matters being duly considered by the
Inhabitants of NEWARK, I am inclined to believe, that
all those who have a due Regard to the general Peace and
real Interest of the Town, and would yield the proper
Respect due to the Memory of the Transactions of their
deceased Forefathers, will join me, that the Proprietors
Title by Patent and Surveys, is the only just and equitable
Title to claim under within the Town of NEWARK.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>
