<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>09-28-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Benjamin Griffin</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Added DIV3's ("entry") running alongside existing MILESTONES structure. Shifted advertisements into BACK. Corrected $s. Sample: 15 minutes. Proofing: 35 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 90 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N14122">
<STC T="E">17872</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99000436</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="half title">
<PB REF="017872_0000_0FA37BE8C0593BC0"/>
<PB REF="017872_0001_0FA37BE981290328" MS="y"/>
<P>A CATALOGUE OF THE ANNAPOLIS CIRCULATING LIBRARY.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="017872_0002_0FA37BEA405E21A8"/>
<P>A CATALOGUE OF THE ANNAPOLIS CIRCULATING LIBRARY, Consisting of near FIFTEEN HUNDRED VOLUMES, IN Agriculture, Arithmetic, Astronomy, Biography, Chymistry, Commerce, Gardening, Geography, Geometry, History, Husbandry, Law, Military Affairs, Mathematics, Navigation, Painting, Physic, Rhetoric, Surgery, Surveying, Voyages, Travels, Plays, Novels, Magazines, &amp;c.</P>
<P>Which are lent to read, BY STEPHEN CLARK, Bookseller, Stationer and Bookbinder, IN CHURCH-STREET, ANNAPOLIS, Where may be had, All new Books, Stationary Wares of all Sorts, School-Books, Jewellery, Plated <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and a great many other Articles <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Goods too tedi∣ous to mention.</P>
<P>Books bought, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>▪</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="rules">
<PB REF="017872_0003_0FA37BEAFB805C60"/>
<PB REF="017872_0004_0FA37BEC399E0000"/>
<HEAD>CONDITIONS, To be observed and consented to by every subscri∣ber to CLARK'S CIRCULATING LIBRARY.</HEAD>
<P N="1">I. Every yearly subscriber to pay one guinea; half yearly subscribers to pay three dollars; quarterly subscribers to pay twelve shillings and six-pence; monthly subscribers to pay one dollar; single book to a nonsubscriber, (a deposit being made) twelves, six-pence, octavo one shilling.</P>
<P N="2">II. In town one book at a time to be allowed, to be changed once a day, and no more; to sub∣scribers in the country two books.</P>
<P N="3">III. No book to be kept longer than one week in town, and two in the country.</P>
<P N="4">IV. Subscribers to pay one eighth of a dollar for their catalogue.</P>
<P N="5">V. All books lost or abused, leaves folded down, torn or wrote upon, to be replaced in the libra∣ry, or if the book lost or abused belongs to a set, the set to be taken and paid for.</P>
<P N="6">VI. That so long as subscribers (through any cause whatsoever) do keep a book or books in their hands, belonging to the library, beyond the time they agreed and paid for, they shall be deemed subscribers, whether they read or not, and pay accordingly.</P>
<P N="7">VII. Subscribers, to prevent being disap∣pointed in the books they want, are to send a list of six or eight different num∣bers taken from the catalogue, as thus,
<LIST>
<ITEM>50</ITEM>
<ITEM>100</ITEM>
<ITEM>200</ITEM>
<ITEM>500</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="library catalogue">
<PB REF="017872_0005_0FA37BECCC2062A8"/>
<HEAD>A CATALOGUE, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>HISTORY, &amp;c. FOLIO, QUARTO AND OCTAVO.</HEAD>
<P>BURNET's (bishop) history of his own time, 2 vols.
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="1"/> Vol. 1. Contains affairs from the restoration of king Charles II to the settlement of king Wil∣liam and queen Mary, at the revolution.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="2"/> Vol. 2. From the revolution to the conclusion of the treaty of peace at Utrecht, in the reign of queen Anne, to which is added the author's life, by the editor.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P>Universal history from the earliest account of time to the present, compiled from original au∣thors, and illustrated with maps, cuts, notes, chronological and other tables, 7 vols.
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="3"/> Vol. 1. Contains history of the world to the birth of Abraham; history of Egypt to Alexan∣der the Great; history of Egypt, of the Moa∣bites, Syrians, Phoenicians and Holy Land; his∣tory of the Jews to the Babylonish captivity; history of the Assyrians, Babylonians and Phry∣gians.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="4"/> Vol. 2. History of the Medes, Persians, Scythi∣ans, Lydians, Attica, Sparta, Athenians, Lace∣doemonians,
<PB N="8" REF="017872_0006_0FA37BED418052B8"/>
Thebans, Achaia, Athens and Ionia.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="5"/> Vol. 3. Sicily, Syracuse, Rhodes, Macedonians, Seleucidae in Syria, the Ptolemies, the Arme∣nians, kingdoms of Pontus, Cappadocia, Perga∣mus, Thrace, Epirus, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="6"/> Vol. 4. History of the Jews from their return from the Babylonish captivity to the destruction of Jerusalem by Titus Vespasian, with an ac∣count of their dispersion and condition to the present time; of the Parthians, Persians, Ro∣man history to the end of the sedition of the Gracchi.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="7"/> Vol. 5. Roman history from the end of the sedi∣tion of the Gracchi to the death of Domitian, the last of the 12 Caesars.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="8"/> Vol. 6. Roman history from the death of Do∣mitian to the taking of Constantinople by the Latins; history of the Carthaginians to the commencement of the second Punic war.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="9"/> Vol. 7. History of the Carthaginians from the second Punic war to the destruction of Car∣thage by Aemilianus, Numidians, Mauritanians, Ethiopians, Arabs, Spaniards, Gauls, ancient Germans, Britons, Hunns, Goths, Franks, Lombards, &amp;c. with a copious index to the foregoing 7 volumes.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><MILESTONE N="10"/> Ralegh's (Sir Walter) history of the world in five books, to which is prefixed the life of the author, 2 vols. in 1.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="11"/> An Inquiry into the prices of wheat, malt, and other provisions as sold in England, from the year 1000 to the year 1765, 1 vol.</P>
<DIV3 N="quarto" TYPE="size">
<PB N="9" REF="017872_0007_0FA37BEDFB78A3D0"/>
<HEAD>QUARTO.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="12"/> Description of East-Florida, with a journal kept, by John Bartram of Philadelphia, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="13"/> General history of the science and practice of music, by John Hawkins, 5 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="14"/> History of the discovery and conquest of the Canary Islands, by George Glase, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="15"/> Poetical works of the late William Dunkin, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="16"/> Rise, progress and present state, of the northern governments, viz. the United Provinces, Den∣mark, Sweden, Russia and Poland, by J. Wil∣liams, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="17"/> Collection of the most remarkable trials, in which the most remarkable of the state trials is included, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="18"/> Travels through the middle settlements of North America in the years 1759 and 1760, by An∣drew Burnaby, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="19"/> Voyage round the world in his Britannic ma∣jesty's sloop Resolution, commanded by captain James Cook, during the years 1772,—3,—4,— 5, by George Foster, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="20"/> Observations made during a voyage round the world, on physical geography, natural history, and ethic philosophy, by John Reinold Foster, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="21"/> Minor Atlas, by H. Moll, 1 vol.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="octavo" TYPE="size">
<HEAD>OCTAVO.</HEAD>
<P>Annual <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, or a view of the history, politics <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,
<PB N="10" REF="017872_0008_0FA37BEEC284BEB0"/>
clusive, in which is included the most complet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> history extant of the war between Great-Bri∣tain and the United States of America, also a collection of interesting and authentic papers, tending to elucidate the history, 26 vols.
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="22"/> Vol. 1. 1758.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="23"/> 2. 1759.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="24"/> 3. 1760.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="25"/> 4. 1761.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="26"/> 5. 1762.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="27"/> 6. 1763.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="28"/> 7. 1764.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="29"/> 8. 1765.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="30"/> 9. 1766.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="31"/> 10. 1767.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="32"/> 11. 1768.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="33"/> 12. 1769.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="34"/> 13. 1770.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="35"/> 14. 1771.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="36"/> 15. 1772.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="37"/> 16. 1773.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="38"/> 17. 1774.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="39"/> 18. 1775.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="40"/> 19. 1776.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="41"/> 20. 1777.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="42"/> 21. 1778.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="43"/> 22. 1779.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="44"/> 23. 1780.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="45"/> 24. 1781.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="46"/> 25. 1782.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="47"/> 26. Index to the whole.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><MILESTONE N="48"/> Monthly review, or literary journals, from<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
<P><PB N="11" REF="017872_0009_0FA37BEF80ABF770"/><MILESTONE N="49"/> Gentlemens and ladies magazines for the years 1778 to 1783 inclusive, in 6 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="50"/> Hibernian magazine for the years 1778 to 1783 inclusive, in 6 vols.</P>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>HISTORIES, VOYAGES, TRAVELS, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="51"/> Guthries history of the world from the creation to the present time, 13 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="52"/> Hook's Roman history, from the building of Rome to the ruin of the commonwealth, 8 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="53"/> Ferguson's history of the progress and termina∣tion of the Roman republic, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="54"/> Raynal's philosophical and political history of the settlements and trade of the Europeans in the East and West-Indies, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="55"/> Campbell's political survey of Great-Britain, being a series of reflections on the situation and land, inhabitants, revenues, colonies and com∣merce, of that island, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="56"/> History of modern Europe, with an account of the decline and fall of the Roman empire, and a view of the progress of society from the fifth to the eighteenth century, in a series of letters from a nobleman to his son, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="57"/> Hume's history of England from the invasion of Julius Caesar to the revolution in 1688, 8 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="58"/> History of Ireland, from the earliest accounts, up, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="59"/> History of Louisiana, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="60"/> History of the island of Minorca, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="12" REF="017872_0010_0FA37BF041B14DC8"/><MILESTONE N="62"/> History (military) of Europe from the com∣mencement of the war with Spain in 1739, to the treaty of Aix la Chapelle in 1748, 1 vol. Millot's elements of general history, ancient and modern, 5 vols.
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="63"/> Vol. 1 contains history of the Egyptians, Medes and Persians, Grecians and Romans.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="64"/> Vol. 2. History of the Romans from the year 552 to 620.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="65"/> Vol. 3. Modern history, first Epocha to the sixth Epocha.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="66"/> Vol. 4. From the sixth Epocha to the thir∣teenth Epocha.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="67"/> Vol. 5. From the thirteenth Epocha to the be∣ginning of the reign of Louis XIVth.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><MILESTONE N="68"/> Robertson's history of America, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="69"/> — history of Scotland, during the reigns of queen Mary, and of king James VIth, till his accession to the crown of Eng∣land, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="70"/> Steuart's history of Scotland, from the esta∣blishment of the reformation to the death of queen Mary, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="71"/> Cook's voyages in the years 1772, 1773, 1774 and 1775, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="72"/> — Last voyages in the years 1776, 1777, 1778, 1779 and 1780, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="73"/> — Voyage in 1772, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="74"/> Coxe's travels into Poland, Russia, Sweden and Denmark, interspersed with historical rela∣tions, and political inquiries, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="75"/> Forrest's voyage to New-Guinea and the Mo-</P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="017872_0011_0FA37BF101A77640"/><MILESTONE N="76"/> Gulliver's travels, by Swift, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="77"/> Dillon's travels through Spain, with a view to illustrate the natural history and physical geo∣graphy of that kingdom, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="78"/> Irwin's voyage up the Red Sea, on the coasts of Arabia and Egypt, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="79"/> Swinburn's travels in the two Sicilies, in the years 1777, 1778, 1779 and 1780, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="80"/> Pennant's tour in Scotland, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="81"/> — Journey from Chester to London, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="82"/> Account of the voyages undertaken by the or∣der of his Britannic majesty for making disco∣veries in the southern hemisphere, and succes∣sively performed by commodore Byron, captain Wallis, captain Carteret, and captain Cook, in the Dolphin, the Swallow, and the Endea∣vour, by John Hawkesworth, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="83"/> Tour through Wales, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="84"/> Tour through Sicily and Malta, in a series of letters to William Beckford, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> from P. Brydone, F. R. S. 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="85"/> Lothian's history of the United Provinces of the Netherlands, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="86"/> Letters on Iceland, containing observations on the civil, literary, ecclesiastical and natural his∣tory, antiquities, volcanos, basaltes, hot springs, customs, dress, manners of the inhabitants, &amp;c. made during a voyage, undertaken in the year 1772, by Joseph Banks, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="87"/> History of the origin and progress of the late war, from the commencement to the exchange of the ratification of peace▪ between Great-Bri∣tain,
<PB N="14" REF="017872_0012_0FA37BF1C187BD28"/>
France and Spain, on the 10th of Fe¦bruary, 1763, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="88"/> History of the war in America, between Great-Britain and the colonies, from its com∣mencement to the end of the year 1778, in which its origin, progress and operations, are faithfully related, together with anecdotes and characters of the different commanders, and accounts of such personages in congress as have distinguished themselves during the contest, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="89"/> History of the late revolution in Sweden, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="90"/> Observations on Italy and its inhabitants, by Thomas Nugent, L. L. D. 2 vols.</P>
<P>Geographical dictionary, containing an histo∣rical and critical account of the lives and writings of the most eminent persons of every nation, 12 vols.
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="91"/> Vol. 1. Containing, life of Adam, Aelfred, Alexander, Anderson, Arnulph, Atkins, At∣terbury, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="92"/> Vol. 2. Bacon, Barlowe, Beveridge, Blake, Bossuet, Boyle, Briggs, Burton, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="93"/> Vol. 3. Caesar, Cartes, Cavendish, Chambers, Cicero, Cleopatra, Coke, Columbus, Cowley, Cromwell, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="94"/> Vol. 4. Dacier, Davenport, Davereux, Dio∣genes, Drake, Dryden, Dudley, Eachard, Epicharmus, Erasmus, Euclid, Eugene, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="95"/> Vol. 5. Faber, Fleetwood, Forbes, Fowler, Fuller, Gardiner, Gat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ker, Gay, Gilpin, Godwin, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB N="15" REF="017872_0013_0FA37BF28104D570"/><MILESTONE N="96"/> Vol. 6. Grabe, Graunt, Gregory, Grey, Grotius, Hall, Handel, Hoffman, Hooper, Humphrey, Hyde, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="97"/> Vol. 7. James, Johnson, Julian, Junius, Ju∣venal, Latimer, L'Estrange, Lilly, Lister, Li∣vius, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="98"/> Vol. 8. Lokman, Lucian, Luther, Mahomet, Masson, Middleton, Moliere, More, Nelson, Newton, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="99"/> Vol. 9. Octavia, Oldenburgh, Origen, Owen, Pamelius, Parsons, Patrick, Paul, Penn, Peter the Great, Philips, Pococke, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="100"/> Vol. 10. Quintilianu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Rawlegh, Rochester, Rubins, Sallustius, Seneca, Shakespear, Syd∣ney, Socrates, Spencer, Stanley, Steele, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="101"/> Vol. 11. Sto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Swift, Tas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o, Thomson, Til∣lotson, Vandyke, Virgil, Walton, Whiston, Wood, Wren, Xenophon, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="102"/> Vol. 12. Alexander, Barrington, Catharine, Churchill, Cromwell, Doddridge, Hervey, King, Quin, Sloane, Thomas, Walpole, &amp;c.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><MILESTONE N="103"/> Biographical history of England, from <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Great to the revolution, by J. Granger 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="104"/> Campbell's lives of the British admirals, 5 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="105"/> History of the famous preacher, Friar Gerand de Campazas, 2 vols.</P>
<P>Johnson's lives of the English poets, and a criticism on their works, 3 vols.
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="106"/> Vol. 1. Contains, li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Cowley, Waller, Mil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ton, Butler, Dryden, Denham, Sprat, Ros<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>common,
<PB N="16" REF="017872_0014_0FA37BF34172DD68"/>
Yalden, Otway, Duke, Dorset, Halifax, Stepney, Walsh, Garth, King, J. Philips, Smith, Pomfret, Hughes.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="107"/> Vol. 2. Addison, Blackmore, Sheffield, Gran∣ville, Rowe, Tickell, Congreve, Fenton, Prior, Pope, Swift.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="108"/> Vol. 3. Gay, Broom, Pitt, Parnell, A. Phi∣lips, Watts, Savage, Somerville, Thomson, Hammond, Collins, Young, Dyer, Mallet, Shenstone, A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de, Lyttelton, West, Gray.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><MILESTONE N="109"/> Life of Edward, earl of Clarendon, lord high chancellor of England, and chancellor of the universities of Oxford. 1. An account of the chancellor's life, from his birth to the restoration in 1660. 2. A continuation of the same, and of his history of the grand re∣bellion, from the restoration to his banishment in 1667, 3 vo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="110"/> Life of Benvenuto Cellini, a Florentine artist, containing a variety of curious and interesting particulars, relative to painting, sculpture and architecture, by Thomas Nugent, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="111"/> History of the life of Reginald Pole, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="112"/> Life of Richard Nash▪ <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> late master of the ceremonies at Bath, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="113"/> Life of Henry Prine, of Wales, eldest son of king James Ist, by Thomas Birch, D. D. 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="114"/> Essay upon the life, writings and character, of Dr. Jonathan Swift, by Deane Swift, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="115"/> Life of Pope Clement IVth, (Ganganelli), 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="17" REF="017872_0015_0FA37BF4017BAB50"/><MILESTONE N="116"/> Memoirs of Peter Henry Bruce, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> a mili∣tary officer in the services of Russia, Prussia and Great-Britain, containing, account of his travels in Germany, Russia, Tartary, Turkey, the West-Indies, &amp;c.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="117"/> Universal Biography, ancient and modern, containing a circumstantial and curious detail of the lives, actions, opinions, writings and characters, of the most celebrated persons of both sexes, of all ranks, in all countries, and in all ages, alphabetically disposed, by Tho∣mas Flloyd, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="118"/> Watson's history of the reign of Philip the IId, king of Spain, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="119"/> — history of the reign of Philip the IIId, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="120"/> Robertson's history of the emperor Charles the Vth, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="121"/> Memoirs of the bashaw count Bonneval, from his birth to his death, interspersed through∣out with an entertaining diversity of secret in∣trigues, amorous adventures, military and political atchievements, being, in effect, the secret history of Europe for the current centu∣ry, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="122"/> History of the chevalier Bayard, by Joseph Sterling, 1 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>DIVINITY, AGRICULTURE, &amp;c. OCTAVO.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="123"/> Dutton (Anne) letters on spiritual subjects, to which are prefixed, memoirs of the dealings of God with her in her last sickness, 2 vols.</P>
<P><PB N="18" REF="017872_0016_0FA37BF4C157A4A8"/><MILESTONE N="124"/> Essay on faith, and its connexions with good works, by John Rotheram, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="125"/> Farquhar's sermons on several subjects, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="126"/> Forsayeth's life of Jesus Christ, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="127"/> Jortin's sermons on different subjects, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="128"/> Rowe (Elizabeth) letters from the dead to the living, to which are added, letters moral and entertaining, in prose and verse, with the author's life, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="129"/> Sherlock's sermons, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="130"/> Seed's posthumous works, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="131"/> Works of Flavius Josephus, the Jewish histo∣rian, with the life of Josephus, by William Whiston, 5 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="132"/> An essay on the proper lessons appointed by the liturgy of the church of England to be read on Sundays and chief festivals throughout the year, 4 vols. by W. Wogan.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="133"/> Mason's spiritual treasury for the children of God, consisting of a meditation for each day in the year, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="134"/> Universal salvation, the Grand Thing aimed at in the scheme of God—as opened in the New Testament writings, and intrusted with Jesus Christ to bring into effect, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="135"/> Hume's dialogues of natural religion, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="136"/> Kaime's essay on the principles of morality and natural religion, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="137"/> Priestley's examination of Dr. Reid's inquiry in∣to the human mind, on the principles of common sense—Dr. Beattie's essay on the nature and im∣mutability of truth—and Dr. Oswald's appeal to common sense in behalf of religion, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="19" REF="017872_0017_0FA37BF580979C80"/><MILESTONE N="138"/> Principal truths of natural religion, defend∣ed and illustrated, in nine dissertations, by H. S. Reimarus, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="139"/> Conformity between modern and ancient ce∣remonies, wherein is proved, by incontestible authorities, that the ceremonies of the church of Rome are entirely derived from the Hea∣thens, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="140"/> Treatise concerning eternal and immutable morality, by Ralph Cudworth, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="141"/> Universal prayer book, or Christian assistant, containing, meditations and prayers for every day in the week—A discourse on the nature and end of the Lord's Supper, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="142"/> Common prayer book illustrated and explain∣ed, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="143"/> Whole duty of man, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="144"/> Dodd's thoughts in prison, in five parts, viz. the imprisonment, retrospect, public punish∣ment, the trial, futurity, to which is added his last prayer, written the night before his death, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="145"/> Anderson on the means of exciting a spirit of national industry, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="346"/> Dossie's memoirs of agriculture, and other oeconomical arts, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="147"/> Ellis's practice of farming and husbandry, in all sorts of soils, according to the latest im∣provements, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="148"/> Farmer's guide in hoeing and stocking farms, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="149"/> Tull's horse-hoeing husbandry, or an essay on the principles of tillage and vegetation, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="20" REF="017872_0018_0FA37BF6404E6268"/><MILESTONE N="150"/> Young's course of experimental agriculture, containing an exact register of all the business transacted during five years—on near three hundred acres of various soils, 4 vols.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>TRADE, PHYSIC, MEDICINE, CHIRURGERY, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="151"/> Sheffield on the commerce of the American states, containing, tables of the imports and exports of Great-Britain, to and from all parts, from 1700 to 1782, also, the exports of America, &amp;c. with remarks on those tables, on British navigation, &amp;c. 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="152"/> Physical and chemical essay, translated from the original Latin of Sir Torbern Bergman, by Edmund Cullin, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="153"/> Cullin (William) first lines in the practice of physic, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="154"/> Buchan's domestic medicine, being an at∣tempt to render the medical art more useful, by shewing people what is in their own power, both with respect to the prevention and cure of diseases, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="155"/> Lewis's experimental history of the materia medica, or of the natural and artificial sub∣stances made use of in medicine, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="156"/> Mead's medical works, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="157"/> Medical and philosophical commentaries, by a society of physicians in Edinburgh, 9 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="158"/> Pott's chirurgical works, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="159"/> Watson's chemical essays, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="160"/> Tissot on health, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="161"/> New Edinburgh dispensatory, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="21" REF="017872_0019_0FA37BF701883640"/><MILESTONE N="162"/> Haller on morbid bodies, 1 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>LETTERS, MISCELLANIES, POEMS, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="163"/> Boulter's letters to several ministers of state in England, and some others, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="164"/> Blair's lectures on rhetoric and belles lettres 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="165"/> Chesterfield's (lord) miscellaneous works, to which are prefixed, memoirs of his life, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="166"/> Montaigne's essays, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="167"/> Cicero's Cato major, or discourse on old age, by Benjamin Franklin, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="168"/> Campbell on civil government, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="169"/> Chesterfield's letters to his son, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="170"/> Cunningham's poems, chiefly pastoral, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="171"/> Cook's elements of dramatic criticism, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="172"/> Dalrymple's tactics, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="173"/> Baker's companion to the play-house, con∣taining, historical and critical memoirs, and original anecdotes, of British and Irish dramatic writers, from the commencement of our theatrical exhibitions, amongst whom are some of the most celebrated actors, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="174"/> Hanway on the importance of the rising gene∣ration of the labouring part of our fellow-sub∣jects, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="175"/> Letters by Arthur Capel, earl of Essex, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="176"/> Lawson's lectures concerning oratory, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="177"/> Hughes's letters, and several other eminent per∣sons, deceased, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="178"/> Raspe's account▪ of some German volcanos, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="22" REF="017872_0020_0FA37BF7C6A92F58"/><MILESTONE N="179"/> Parnell's poems, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="180"/> Remarks on the life and writings of Dr. Jonathan Swift, by the earl of Orrery, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="181"/> Observations on lord Orrery's remarks on the life and writings of Dr. Jonathan Swift, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="182"/> Swift's works, 20 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="183"/> Kaime's sketches of the history of man, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="184"/> Wood's essay on the original genius and writings of Homer, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="185"/> Lyttelton's works, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="186"/> Orations of Demosthenes, by Thomas Leland, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="187"/> Creech's Lucretius, 2 vols.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>LAW.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="188"/> Blackstone's commentaries on the laws of England, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="189"/> Dalrymple's feudal property, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="190"/> Gilbert's law of evidence, 1 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>ASTRONOMY, NAVIGATION, GEOGRAPHY, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="191"/> Ferguson's astronomy, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="192"/> — gentlemen and ladies astronomy, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="193"/> Moore's practical navigation, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="194"/> Atkinson's epitome of the art of navigation, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="195"/> Euclid's elements of geometry, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="196"/> West's elements of mathematics, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="197"/> Gregory's practical geometry, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="23" REF="017872_0021_0FA37BF881590FF0"/><MILESTONE N="198"/> Salmon's geographical grammar, improved and brought down to the year 1786, 1 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>TRAVELS, TRIALS, COOKERY, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="199"/> Burney's tour through Germany, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="200"/> — tour through France and Italy, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="201"/> Trial of Augustus Keppel, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="202"/> Dalrymple's practice of modern cookery, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="203"/> Bellegarde's models of conversation for per∣sons of polite education, 1 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>DICTIONARIES. OCTAVO.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="204"/> Bailey's dictionary, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="205"/> Barclay's ditto. 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="206"/> Fenning's ditto. 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="207"/> Johnson's ditto. 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="208"/> Entick's pocket ditto. 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="209"/> Ainsworth's Latin ditto. English ditto. 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="210"/> Boyer's French and English ditto. 1 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>HISTORY, VOYAGES, TRAVELS, &amp;c. DUO DECIMO.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="211"/><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> history, by Voltaire, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="212"/> Chalon's history of France, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="213"/> Goldsmith's Grecian history from the earliest state to the death of Alexander the great, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="214"/> Goldsmith's Roman history, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="215"/> Historical account of North-America, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="216"/> Rollin's ancient history, 10 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="217"/> — method of teaching and studying the belles lettres, 4 vols.</P>
<P><PB N="24" REF="017872_0022_0FA37BF93B78CEC8"/><MILESTONE N="218"/> Rapin's history of England by question and answer, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="219"/> Brydone's tour through Sicily and Malta, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="220"/> Johnson's journey to the western islands of Scotland, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="221"/> Richard's tour from London to Petersbo∣rough, and from thence to Moscow, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="222"/> Sterne's sentimental journey through France and Italy, 4 vols. complete in 1.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="223"/> Tour through the island of Great-Britain, di∣vided into circuits or journies, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="224"/> Tour through Ireland, wherein the present state of that kingdom is considered, and the most noted cities, towns, seats, buildings, loughs, &amp;c. described, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="225"/> Thicknesse's journey through France and Spain, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="226"/> Smollett's travels through France and Italy, containing observations on characters, cus∣toms, religion, government, police, com∣merce, arts and antiquities, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="227"/> Twis's travels through Portugal and Spain in 1772 and 1773, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="228"/> Travels in Europe, Asia and Africa, describ∣ing characters, customs, manners, laws, and productions of nature and art, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="229"/> Andrews's remarks on English and French ladies, in a series of letters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="230"/> Remarks on the characters and manners of the French, in a series of letters, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="231"/> Voyages and adventures of captain Robert Boyle in several parts of the world.</P>
<P><PB N="25" REF="017872_0023_0FA37BFA7A588DD0"/><MILESTONE N="232"/> Barrow's naval history of Great-Britain, with the lives of the most illustrious admirals and commanders, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="233"/> Bolingbrooke on the study and use of history.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>MISCELLANEOUS PERIODICAL POEMS, &amp;c. DUO DECIMO.</HEAD>
<P>Addison's miscellaneous works in verse and prose, 3 vols.
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="234"/> Vol. 1. Contains campaign, and other poems.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="235"/> Vol 2. Rosamond, an opera, Cato, a tragedy, Drummer, a comedy, count Tariff and Whig Examiner.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="236"/> Vol. 3. Usefulness of ancient medals, &amp;c.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><MILESTONE N="237"/> Addison's freeholder, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="238"/> Art of painting, of Charles Alphonse du Fres∣noy, translated into the English verse by Mr. Mason, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="239"/> Turner's introduction of the arts and sci∣ences, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="240"/> Art of knowing mankind, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="241"/> Brookes's art of angling, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="242"/> Art of speaking, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="243"/> Ovid's art of love, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="244"/> Brown's works, serious and comical, in prose and verse, with his remarks, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="245"/> Collier on ridicule, or what it is that makes a man ridiculous, and the means to avoid it, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="246"/> Goldsmith's citizen of the world, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="247"/> Collection and selection of English prologues and epilogues, commencing with Shakespear, and concluding with Garrick, 4 vols.</P>
<P><PB N="26" REF="017872_0024_0FA37BFB06C4B638"/><MILESTONE N="248"/> Country gentleman's companion, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="249"/> Description of three hundred animals, with a particular account of the whale fishery, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="250"/> Dodington's diary from March 1748—9 to 1761, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="251"/> Davies's dramatic miscellanies, consisting of critical observations on several plays of Shake∣spear.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="252"/> Secret history of the university of Oxford in several essays, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="253"/> Home's experiments on bleaching, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="254"/> Johnson's miscellaneous and fugitive pieces, 2 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="255"/> — gazetteer, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="256"/> Universal gazetteer, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="257"/> King's original works in verse and prose, 8 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="258"/> Linguet's memoirs of the Bastile, containing a full exposition of the mysterious policy and despotic oppression of the French government, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="259"/> Morality of Shakespear's drama illustrated, by Mrs. Griffith, 2 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="260"/> Liberal opinions, or history of Benignus, by Mr. Pratt, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="261"/> Origin and progress of despotism in the ori∣ental and other empires of Africa, Europe and America, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="262"/> Knox's essays, moral and literary, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="263"/> Pope's works, 8 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="264"/> Additions to the works of Alexander Pope, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="265"/> Shenstone's works in verse and prose, 2 vols.</P>
<P><PB N="27" REF="017872_0025_0FA37BFB812D21D8"/><MILESTONE N="266"/> The mirror, a periodical paper published at Edinburgh in the years 1779 and 1780, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="267"/> World, by Adam Fitz-Adam, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="268"/> Spectator, 8 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="269"/> Tatler, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="270"/> Guardian, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="271"/> Rambler, by Johnson, 6 vols. bound in 3.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="272"/> Idler, by Johnson, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="273"/> Valuable secrets concerning arts and trades, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="274"/> Constitution of the several independent states of America, the declaration of independence, the articles of confederation between the said states, &amp;c. 1 vol.</P>
<P>Beauties of history, or pictures of virtue and vice drawn from real life, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="275"/> Vol. 1. Contains examples of conjugal af∣fection, ambition, chastity, clemency, courage, cruelty, public faith, gaming, &amp;c.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="276"/> Vol. 2. On indolence, ingratitude, love, luxu∣ry, pride, revenge, contempt of wealth, &amp;c.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="277"/> Beauties of the English drama, digested al∣phabetically, according to the date of their performances, consisting of the most cele∣brated passages, soliloquies, similies, descrip∣tions, and other poetical beauties, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="278"/> Beauties of Shakespear, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="279"/> — of Pope, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="280"/> — of Milton, Thomson and Young, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="281"/> — of Johnson, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="282"/> — of Fielding, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="28" REF="017872_0026_0FA37BFC400007D0"/><MILESTONE N="283"/> Clark's peerage of the nobility of England, Scotland and Ireland, containing their titles, date of their creations, description of their arms, crests, seats, and town residence, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="284"/> Enfield's speaker, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="285"/> Beattie's essay on the nature and immutability of truth in opposition to sophistry and scep∣ticism, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="286"/> Bettesworth's new and correct tables of in∣terest, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="287"/> Decker on trade, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="288"/> Philosophical dictionary, or the opinions of modern philosophers on metaphysical, moral and political subjects, 4 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="289"/> Essay on history, in three epistles to Edward Gibbon, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> with notes, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="290"/> Journey to the world under ground, by Ni∣cholas Klimius, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="291"/> Leland on eloquence, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="292"/> Scott's lessons in elocution, or a selection of pieces in prose and verse, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="293"/> Paris in miniature, taken from the French picture at full length.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="294"/> Millar's description of ranks in society, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="295"/> Sterne's works complete, with the life of the author, 5 vols.</P>
<P>Savage's works, 2 vols.
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="296"/> Vol. 1. Contains Dr. Johnson's life of the author, Love in a Veil, a comedy, Sir Tho∣mas Overbury, a tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="297"/> Vol. 2. The wanderer, a poem, the bastard, and poems on several occasions.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><PB N="29" REF="017872_0027_0FA37BFD03E446E0"/><MILESTONE N="298"/> Essay on the treatment and conversion of Af∣rican slaves in the British sugar colonies, by James Ramsay, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="299"/> Treatise on the effects and various preparati∣ons of lead, by Goulard.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="300"/> Sentimental lucubrations, by Peter Pennyless, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="301"/> Voltaire's Giphantia, or a view of what has passed, what is passing, and what will pass, in the world, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="302"/> Mariners compass rectified, by Andrew Wake∣ly, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="303"/> Tooke's pantheon, representing the fabulous history of the heathen gods, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="304"/> Dictionary of love, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="305"/> Priestley's miscellaneous observations relating to education, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="306"/> Ash's sentiments on education, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="307"/> Locke's thoughts concerning education, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="308"/> Loose hints upon education, chiefly concerning the culture of the heart, by Henry Home, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="309"/> Introduction to the knowledge of nature, to which is added an essay on female education, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="310"/> Theatre of education by the countess de Genlis, 4 vols.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>MEMOIRS, LIVES, LETTERS, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="311"/> Memoirs of cardinal de Retz, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="312"/> Memoirs of Guy Joli, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="313"/> Memoirs of Maximilian de Bethune, duke of Sully, prime minister to Henry the great, 6 vols.</P>
<P><PB N="30" REF="017872_0028_0FA37BFDC2CBD200"/><MILESTONE N="314"/> Memoirs and adventures of the marquis de Bretagne and duc D'Harcourt, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="315"/> History of Maurice count Saxe, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="316"/> Private life of Lewis XV, in which are con∣tained the principal events, remarkable oc∣currences, and anecdotes of his reign, by J. O. Justamond, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="317"/> History of the life of William Pitt, earl of Chatham, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="318"/> History of Hyder Ali Khan, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="319"/> Historical memoirs of Voltaire, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="320"/> History of the marquis de Cressey, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="321"/> Life of Petrarch, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="322"/> Life of Colley Cibber, comedian, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="323"/> Life and opinions of Tristram Shandy, Gen∣tleman, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="324"/> Life of madam de Maintenon, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="325"/> Life of the marchioness de Pompadour, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="326"/> Life of the Swedish countess de G * * *, written in German by the late ingenious C. F. Gellert, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="327"/> Lives and characters of the Greek and Ro∣man classics, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="328"/> Life of colonel James Gardiner, who was slain in the battle of Preston Pans, Septem∣ber 21, 1745, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="329"/> Lives of the English and Irish admirals, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="330"/> Letters on the English nation, by M. de Voltaire, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="331"/> Letters of the late Ignatius Sancho, an Afri∣can, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="332"/> Letters from several parts of Europe and the east, 2 vols.</P>
<P><PB N="31" REF="017872_0029_0FA37BFE806FF040"/><MILESTONE N="333"/> Letters from Scotland, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="334"/> Letters from Edinburgh, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="335"/> Letters and essays on the most important and interesting subjects, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="336"/> Letters from lord Rivers to Sir Charles Car∣digan, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="337"/> Letters by lady Mary Wortley Montague, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="338"/> Letters from a Persian in England to his friend in Ispahan, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="339"/> Letters on the improvement of the mind, by Mrs. Chaphone, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="340"/> — of Junius, 1 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>TRANSLATIONS from the CLASSICS.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="341"/> Plutarch's lives, by Dacier, 8 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="342"/> Gordon's translation of the works of Tacitus, 5 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="343"/> Pitt's translation of the works of Virgil, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="344"/> Macpherson's translation of the Iliad of Ho∣mer, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="345"/> Pope's translation of the Iliad and Oddisy of Homer, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="346"/> Coleman's translation of the comedies of Terence, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="347"/> Franklin's translation of the tragedies of So∣phocles, 2 vols.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>GARDENING, POEMS, PLAYS, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="348"/> Every man his own gardener, by Thomas Mawe, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="349"/> Weston's gardener's and planter's calendar, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="32" REF="017872_0030_0FA37BFF41FB1C50"/><MILESTONE N="350"/> Churchill's poems, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="351"/> Dodsley's collection of poems, 6 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="352"/> Dryden's poems and fables, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="353"/> Parnell's poems, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="354"/> Freneau's poems, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="355"/> Prior's poems, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="356"/> Philips's, (John) poems attempted in the style of Milton, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="357"/> Denham's poems, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="358"/> Langhorne's poetical works, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="359"/> Ancient Scottish poems, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="360"/> Collection of poems, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="361"/> Penitent of Egypt, a poem.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="362"/> The kite, an heroic comical poem, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="363"/> The task, a poem, by William Cowper, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="364"/> Paradise lost, a poem, by John Milton, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="365"/> Infancy, a poem, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="366"/> M▪ Fingal, a modern epic poem, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="367"/> Essay on epic poetry, by William Hayley, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="368"/> Thomson's seasons, 1 vol.</P>
<P>Thomson's works, 4 vols.
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="369"/> Vol. 1. Contains the seasons.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="370"/> Vol. 2. Liberty, the castle of indolence, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="371"/> Vol. 3. Sophonisba, Agamemnon and Alfred.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="372"/> Vol. 4. Edward and Eleonora, Tancred and Segismunda, and Coriolanus.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><MILESTONE N="373"/> Butler's hudibras, 1 vol.</P>
<P>Gay's works, 4 vols.<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="374"/> Vol. 1. Contains poems, &amp;c. and What d'ye call it, a tragi—comi—pastoral farce.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="375"/> Vol. 2. Epistles, tales, eclogues, &amp;c. Dione, a pastoral tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB N="33" REF="017872_0031_0FA37C000139CFF0"/><MILESTONE N="376"/> Vol. 3. The Captives, Beggars opera, Polly, an opera, Achilles, the Distressed Wife, Re∣hearsal of Goatham.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="377"/> Vol. 4. Fables.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><MILESTONE N="378"/> Leonidas, a poem, 1 vol.</P>
<P>British theatre, 14 vols.
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="379"/> Vol. 1. Contains the Mourning Bride, Siege of Damascus, Theodosius, or the Force of Love, and Cato.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="380"/> Vol. 2. All for Love, or the World well lost, Oroonoko, Fair Penitent, Oedipus.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="381"/> Vol. 3. Mahomet, Phoedra and Hippolitus, Tamerlane, Isabella, or the Fatal Marriage.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="382"/> Vol. 4. Mustapha, Jane Shore, the Revenge, Orphan.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="383"/> Vol. 5. Barbarossa, lady Jane Gray, Mari∣amne, Zara.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="384"/> Vol. 6. Tancred and Sigismunda, Venice Preserv'd, Distress'd Mother, the Brothers.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="385"/> Vol. 7. George Barnwell, Royal Convert, Spanish Friar and Douglass.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="386"/> Vol. 8. Beaux Stratagem, Every Man in his Humour, the Old Bachelor, Suspicious Hus∣band.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="387"/> Vol. 9. Conscious Lovers, Rule a Wife, Re∣cruiting Officer, Careless Husband.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="388"/> Vol. 10. Beggars opera, Busy Body, Twin Rivals, Love for Love.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="389"/> Vol. 11. She Wou'd and She Wou'd not, Man of Mode, Gentle Shepherd, and Funeral.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="390"/> Vol. 12. Provok'd Husband, or a Journey to London, Double Dealer, Constant Couple, or a Trip to the Jubilee, the Miser.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB N="34" REF="017872_0032_0FA37C00C1FA0AE0"/><MILESTONE N="391"/> Vol. 13. Love Makes a Man, or the Fop's Fortune, Rehearsal, Bold Stroke for a Wife, the Alchymist.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="392"/> Vol. 14. Wonder, a Woman Keeps a Secret, Plain Dealer, Way of the World, Provok'd Wife.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P>British and Irish theatres, 8 vols.
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="393"/> Vol 1. Contains Cato, Sethona, the Favour∣ite, Douglass, Henry IV.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="394"/> Vol. 2. The Revenge, Braganza, Othello, Boadicia, Orphan of China, and Distress'd Mother.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="395"/> Vol. 3. Provok'd Husband, Summers Tale, the Choleric Man, She Stoops to Conquer, Good Natur'd Man, Provok'd Wife.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="396"/> Vol. 4. The Jealous Wife, Measure for Measure, Love in a Wood, Belle's Stratagem.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="397"/> Vol. 5. The Tempest, Brothers, Fashiona∣ble Lover, Gentle Shepherd, and Pamela.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="398"/> Vol. 6. West-Indian, Albumaza, School for Rakes, Modest Couple, and Wife's Relief.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="399"/> Vol. 7. Love in a Village, Cymon, Maid of the Vale, and the Golden Pippin.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="400"/> Vol. 8. Maid of the Mill, Midas, Lionel and Clarissa, and the Village Opera.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><MILESTONE N="401"/> Hayley's plays. 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="402"/> The Hive, a collection of the most celebrated songs, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="403"/> Humming bird, containing above 14 hundred of the most celebrated English, Scotch, and Irish songs, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="404"/> Friskey songster, 1 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<PB N="35" REF="017872_0033_0FA37C018125BF38"/>
<HEAD>DIVINITY, PHYSIC, &amp;c. DUODECIMO.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="405"/> Clayton's vindication of the Old and New Testament, in answer to the objections of the late lord Bolingbroke, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="406"/> Hervey's dialogues and letters upon the most interesting subjects, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="407"/> Hervey's meditations and contemplations, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="408"/> Purves's attempt to investigate and defend the scripture doctrine, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="409"/> Law's serious call to a devout and holy life.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="410"/> — upon christian perfection, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="411"/> Doddridge's rise and progress of religion in the soul, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="412"/> Sherlock's discourse concerning death, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="413"/> Dodd's reflections on death, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="414"/> Essay towards a proposal for catholic commu∣nion, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="415"/> Doctrine of grace, or the office and operati∣ons of the Holy Spirit, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="416"/> Devout christian's companion, being a com∣plete manual of devotions, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="417"/> Nelson's practice of devotion, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="418"/> Death of Abel, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="419"/> Collection of the texts of scripture, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="420"/> Watts's hymns, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="421"/> — psalms, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="422"/> Bunyan's Holy War, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="423"/> — pilgrim's progress, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="424"/> Virtue and morality, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="425"/> Oeconomy of human life, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="36" REF="017872_0034_0FA37C0242D7DFF0"/><MILESTONE N="426"/> Mrs. Rowe's devout exercises of the heart, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="427"/> Monro's anatomy, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="428"/> Innes's description of the muscles, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="429"/> Modern practice of physic in London hospi∣tals, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="430"/> Culpepper's English physician, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="431"/> Berdmore on the disorders of the teeth and gums, 1 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>NOVELS, ROMANCES, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="432"/> Artless lovers in a series of letters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="433"/> Adventures of Mark, the rambler, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="434"/> Arabian Nights entertainments, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="435"/> Adventures of Peregrine Pickle, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="436"/> — of Roderick Random, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="437"/> — of a rupee, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="438"/> — of a guinea, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="439"/> — of Robinson Crusoe, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="440"/> — of Joseph Andrews, 2 in 1.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="441"/> Adventurer, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="442"/> Adventures of Gil Blas, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="443"/> — of Telemachus, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="444"/> — and armours of the marquis de Noailles and madam Tencin, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="445"/> Amelia, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="446"/> Affected indifference, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="447"/> Arminius, or Germania freed, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="448"/> Abelard and Heloise, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="449"/> Adelaide and Theodore, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="450"/> Belle Grove, or the fatal seduction, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="451"/> Bachelor of Salamanca, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="452"/> Belisarius, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="37" REF="017872_0035_0FA37B3642A830E8"/><MILESTONE N="453"/> Count de Poland, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="454"/> Citizen of the world, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="455"/> Child of nature improved by chance, a phi∣losophical novel, by Mr. Helvetius, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="456"/> Clio, or a discourse on taste, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="457"/> Count de Aubigny, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="458"/> Combe Wood, a novel in a series of letters.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="459"/> Colonel Ormsby, or the genuine history of an Irish nobleman, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="460"/> Convent, or the history of Julia, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="461"/> Constantia and her daughter Julia, an Italian history, with a discourse on romances, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="462"/> Cecilia, or memoirs of an heiress, 5 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="463"/> Clarissa, or the history of a young lady, 8 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="464"/> Count de —'s confessions, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="465"/> Conquest of the heart, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="466"/> Disinterested marriage, or the history of Mr. Frankland, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="467"/> Dean of Coleraine, a moral history founded on the memoirs of an illustrious family in Ireland, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="468"/> Dangerous connexions, or letters collected in a society, and published for the instruction of other societies, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="469"/> D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>linda, or the Double Marriage, being the genuine history of a very recent and interest∣ing adventure, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="470"/> Distressed Lovers, or the history of Edward and Eliza, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="471"/> Expedition of Humphrey Clinker, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="472"/> English Baron, a Gothic story, by Clara Reeve, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="38" REF="017872_0036_0FA37B37029BC538"/><MILESTONE N="473"/> Excursion, by Mrs. Brooke, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="474"/> Example, or the history of Lucy Cleveland, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="475"/> Evelina, or a young lady's entrance into the world, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="476"/> Emma, or the unfortunate attachment, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="477"/> Edwy and Edilda, a Gothic tale, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="478"/> Eloisa, or a series of original letters, by J. J. Rousseau, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="479"/> Emilius, or a treatise of education, by J. J. Rousseau, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="480"/> Emma Corbett, or the Miseries of Civil War, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="481"/> Family Picture, or Domestic Dialogues on amiable and interesting subjects, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="482"/> Fashionable follies, containing the history of a Parisian family, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="483"/> Fair Philosopher, or the history of the ho∣nourable Miss Eloisa Howard, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="484"/> Fatal Obedience, or the history of Mr. Free∣land, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="485"/> Fatal Legacy, or the memoirs of the count of Comminge, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="486"/> Friendship and matrimony, or the history of Emilia and Henry, of lord and lady P—, and of Frederick and Fanny, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="487"/> Fashionable Life, or the history of Miss Louisa Fermor, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="488"/> Female Monitor, in a series of letters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="489"/> Female Friendship, or the Innocent Sufferer, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="490"/> Fine Gentleman, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="491"/> Fine Lady, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="39" REF="017872_0037_0FA37B37C2AD64F0"/><MILESTONE N="492"/> Fashionable Friend, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="493"/> Fool of Quality, or the history of Henry, earl of Moreland, by Mr. Brooke, 5 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="494"/> Greenwood Farm, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="495"/> George Bateman, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="496"/> Gulliver's travels, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="497"/> History of Christiana, princess of Swabia▪ and Eloisa de Livarot, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="498"/> — of lord Stanton, 5 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="499"/> — of John Juniper, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> alias Juniper Jack, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="500"/> — and adventures of the renowned Don Quixote, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="501"/> — of Miss Jenny Salisbury, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="502"/> — of Sir George Ellison, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="503"/> — and adventures of an Atom, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="504"/> — of Tom Rigby, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="505"/> — of lady Julia Mandeville, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="506"/> — of Charles Wentworth, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> in a series of letters, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="507"/> — of Sir Charles Beaufort, containing the genuine memoirs of a family of distinc∣tion in the south of England, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="508"/> — of Miss Carolina Manners, in a se∣ries of letters to a friend, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="509"/> — of Arsaces, prince of Betiis, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="510"/> — of female favourites, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="511"/> — of lady Bettesworth and captain Hast∣ings, in a series of letters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="512"/> — of Fanny Meadows, in a series of letters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="513"/> — of Henry Dumont, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> and Miss Charlotte Evelyn, by Mrs. Clarke, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="40" REF="017872_0038_0FA37B388185CD10"/><MILESTONE N="514"/> History of his royal highness the duke of Cum∣berland, and lady Grosvenor, with an ac∣count of their trial for crim. con. 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="515"/> — of the marquis de Roselle, in a series of letters, by madam Elie de Beaumont, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="516"/> — of Sir Charles Grandison, in a series of letters, by Samuel Richardson, 7 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="517"/> — of Will Ramble, a libertine, com∣piled from genuine materials, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="518"/> — of Julia Benson, in a series of letters, founded on well known facts, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="519"/> He is found at last, or memoirs of the Be∣verley family, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="520"/> Henrietta, countess Osenvor, a sentimental no∣vel, in a series of letters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="521"/> Incognita, or Emily Villars, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="522"/> Independent, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="523"/> Interesting sketch of genteel life, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="524"/> Incas, or the destruction of the empire of Peru.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="525"/> Julia de Roubigne, a sentimental novel, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="526"/> Juliet Grenville, or the history of the human heart, by Mrs. Brooke, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="527"/> Letters from Juliet, lady Catesby, to her friend lady Henrietta Campley, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="528"/> — from Elizabeth Sophia de Valiere to her friend Louisa Hortensia de Canteleu, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="529"/> — written by a Peruvian princess, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="530"/> — genuine, between Henry and Frances, 4 vols.</P>
<P><PB N="41" REF="017872_0039_0FA37B3981E104A0"/><MILESTONE N="531"/> Letter writer, or lady's polite secretary, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="532"/> Literary amusements, or evening entertainer, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="533"/> Lesson for lovers, or the history of colonel Melville and lady Charlotte Richley, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="534"/> Lucinda, or the self devoted daughter, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="535"/> Laura and Augustus, an authentic story, in a series of letters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="536"/> Memoirs of Signior Gaudentio de Lucca, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="537"/> Marriage act, in which the ruin of female honour, the contempt of the clergy, are consi∣dered, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="538"/> Memoirs of the Manstein family, pathetic, sentimental, humourous and satirical, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="539"/> Moral tales, by M. Marmontel, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="540"/> Masqued weddings, in a series of letters, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="541"/> Memoirs of the right honourable lord vis∣count Cherington, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="542"/> Myrtle, or effects of love, in a series of let∣ters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="543"/> Man of the world, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="544"/> — of feeling, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="545"/> Mount Henneth, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="546"/> Mother-in-law, or the innocent sufferer, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="547"/> Married Libertine, or the history of Miss Melville, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="548"/> Memoirs of Miss Sternheim, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="549"/> Margaretta, countess of Rainsford, a senti∣mental novel, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="42" REF="017872_0040_0FA37B3AB0AFFD40"/><MILESTONE N="550"/> Memoirs of the Marchioness de Louvoi, in a series of letters, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="551"/> Memoirs of a clergyman, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="552"/> — of Mrs. Williams, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="553"/> — of Miss Sidney Bidulph, 5 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="554"/> — of lady Woodford, written by her∣self, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="555"/> Miss Melmoth, or the New Clarissa, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="556"/> Modern anecdotes, or the ancient family of the Kinkvervankotsdarsprakengotchderns, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="557"/> Narrative of the honourable John Byron, commodore, in a late expedition round the world, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="558"/> Original love-letters between a lady of quali∣ty and a person of inferior station, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="559"/> Peruvian tales, related in 1000 hours by one of the select virgins of Cusco to the ynca of Peru, to dissuade him from a resolution he had taken to destroy himself by poison, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="560"/> Persian and Turkish tales, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="561"/> Pilgrim, or a picture of life, in a series of let∣ters, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="562"/> Princess of Cleves, an historical novel, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="563"/> Perplexed lovers, or the history of Sir Ed∣ward Balchen, bart. 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="564"/> Pictures of the heart, sentimentally delineated in the danger of the passions, an allegorical tale, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="565"/> Peggy and Patty, or the sisters of Ashdale, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="566"/> Princess of Babylon, by Voltaire, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="567"/> Parsonage-house, in a series of letters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><PB N="43" REF="017872_0041_0FA37B3AD1CE9BE8"/><MILESTONE N="568"/> Rival mother, or the history of the countess de Salens and her two daughters, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="569"/> Rational lovers, or the history of Sir Charles Leusum and Mrs. Frances Fermor, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="570"/> Reginald du Bray, an historical tale, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="571"/> Recess, or a tale of other times, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="572"/> Storm, or the history of Nancy and Lucy, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="573"/> Siberian anecdotes, containing real histories and living characters, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="574"/> Suspicious lovers, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="575"/> Sylph, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="576"/> Sorrows of Werter, a German story, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="577"/> Sutton—Abbey, in a series of letters founded on facts, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="578"/> St. Ruthin's Abby, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="579"/> Trial, or the history of Charles Horton, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="580"/> Triumvirate, or the authentic memoirs of A. B. and C. 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="581"/> Trifler, or a ramble among the wilds of fan∣cy, the works of nature and the manners of men, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="582"/> True merit, true happiness, exemplified in the entertaining and instructive memoirs of Mr. P—, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="583"/> Two mentors, a modern story, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="584"/> The tutor, or the history of George Wilson and lady Fanny Melfont, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="585"/> Tutor of truth, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="586"/> Vicissitudes of human life, a narrative found∣ed on facts, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="587"/> Woman of honour, 3 vols.</P>
<P><PB N="44" REF="017872_0042_0FA37B3B81A084E8"/><MILESTONE N="588"/> Way to lose him, or the history of Miss Wyndham, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="589"/> Way to win him, or the history of lady Sed∣ley, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="590"/> Wilmot, or the pupil of folly, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="591"/> Young widow, or the history of Mrs. Sed∣wich, in a series of letters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="592"/> Woodbury, or the memoirs of William Marchmont and Miss Walbrook, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="593"/> Wonderful conversion to Christianity of Solo∣mon Duit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="594"/> Young Misses magazine, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="595"/> Adventures of Ferdinand, count Fathom, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="596"/> An apology for the life of George Anne Bel∣lamy, late of Covent-Garden theatre, written by herself, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="597"/> Adventures of Sir Launcelot Greaves, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="598"/> Anecdotes of the reign of Lewis the XVIth, present king of France, also containing Mr. Necker's account of his administration, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="599"/> Belmont Grove, or the discovery, a novel, in a series of letters, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="600"/> Childrens friend, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="601"/> Devil upon Two Sticks, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="602"/> Emma, or the child of sorrow, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="603"/> Gulliver revived, containing singular travels, campaigns, voyages and adventures, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="604"/> Female spectator, by Mrs. Eliza Haywood, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="605"/> History of Miss Betsey Thoughtless, 4 vols.</P>
<P><PB N="45" REF="017872_0043_0FA37B3C42974CB0"/><MILESTONE N="606"/> History of Tom Jones, a foundling, by Hen∣ry Fielding, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="607"/> History of the knights of Malta, 5 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="608"/> History of Charles XIIth, king of Sweden, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="609"/> Pamela, or virtue rewarded, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="610"/> Sentimental deceiver, or the history of Miss Hammond, in a series of letters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="611"/> Tales of the castle, or stories of instruction and delight, by the countess de Genlis, 5 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="612"/> Tale of a tub, written for the universal im∣provement of mankind, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="613"/> Vicar of Wakefield, a tale, supposed to be written by himself, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="614"/> Virtuous prince, or travels and adventures of Usong, an oriental history, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="615"/> Anson's voyage round the world, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="616"/> Adams's defence of the constitutions of go∣vernment of the United States of America, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="617"/> Confessions of J. J. Rousseau, with the reve∣ries of the solitary walker, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="618"/> Fordyce's sermons to young women, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="619"/> Beattie's poems, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="620"/> Beattie's evidences of the Christian religion, 1 vol.</P>
<P>Collection of the most eminent farces and entertainments performed on the British stage, 4 vol.
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="621"/> Vol. 1. Contains, the Guardian, the Ap∣prentice, the Anatomist, Florizel and Perdita, High Life Below Stairs, the Mock Doctor,
<PB N="46" REF="017872_0044_0FA37B3D028B6DA0"/>
Taste, the Upholsterer, Lethe, the Knights, the Deuce is in Him, the Sultan, the Chap∣let, Miss in her Teens.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="622"/> Vol. 2. The Mayor of Garrat, the Reprisal, the Devil to Pay, the Lying Valet, the Vir∣gin Unmask'd, the Liar, the Cunning Man, the Old Maid, Thomas and Sally, Chronon∣hotonthologos, Neck or Nothing, the Lot∣tery, the Musical Lady, Midas.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="623"/> Vol. 3. The Citizen, the Toy-Shop, the Golden Pippin, the Englishman in Paris, the Englishman returned from Paris, the In∣triguing Chambermaid, Polly Honeycombe, Captain O'Blunder, the Author, the Miller of Mansfield, the Padlock, Catharine and Petruchio, the Register-Office, Cymon.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="624"/> Vol. 4. The Twins, the Deserter, the Com∣missary, Edgar and Emmeline, the Rival Candidates, Three Weeks after Marriage, Bon Ton, Comus, the Orators, All the World's a Stage, the Contrivances, Flora, the Spirit of Contradiction, the Patron, Bucks have at ye All.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><MILESTONE N="625"/> Moore's fables for the ladies, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="626"/> Chesterfield's advice to his son, with lord Burghley's ten precepts, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="627"/> Aesop's fables, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="628"/> Adventures of Alphonso, after the destruction of Lisbon, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="629"/> Unfortunate mother's advice to her absent daughters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="630"/> Gregory's legacy to his daughters, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="631"/> Oxford sausage, or select poetical farces. 1 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<PB N="47" REF="017872_0045_0FA37B3DC3233CE8"/>
<HEAD>ARITHMETIC, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="632"/> Dowling's arithmetic, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="633"/> Fenning's do. 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="634"/> Dilworth's schoolmaster's assistant, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="635"/> Fisher's young man's best companion, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="636"/> Universal pocket companion, 1 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>POEMS, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="637"/> Bell's edition of the British poets, 109 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="638"/> Akenside, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="639"/> Addison, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="640"/> Armstrong, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="641"/> Butler, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="642"/> Broome, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="643"/> Churchill, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="644"/> Cowley, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="645"/> Chaucer, 14 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="646"/> Congreve, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="647"/> Cunningham, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="648"/> Collins, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="649"/> Donne, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="650"/> Dryden, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="651"/> Dillon, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="652"/> Dyer, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="653"/> Denham, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="654"/> Fenton, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="655"/> Gay, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="656"/> Granville, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="657"/> Garth, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="658"/> Gray, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="659"/> Hughes, 2 vols.</P>
<P><PB N="48" REF="017872_0046_0FA37B3E82867048"/><MILESTONE N="660"/> King, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="661"/> Lyttelton, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="662"/> Moore, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="663"/> Mallet, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="664"/> Milton, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="665"/> Pope, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="666"/> Parnell, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="667"/> Prior, 3 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="668"/> Pomfret, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="669"/> Philips, A. 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="670"/> Philips, John, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="671"/> Pitt, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="672"/> Rowe, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="673"/> Spenser, 8 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="674"/> Swift, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="675"/> Somervelle, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="676"/> Sheffield, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="677"/> Savage, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="678"/> Shenstone, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="679"/> Tickell, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="680"/> Thomson, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="681"/> Waller, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="682"/> West, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="683"/> Watts, 7 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="684"/> Young, 4 vols.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>FRENCH BOOKS, in DUODECIMO.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="685"/> Recuel par Scot, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="686"/> Revolution de l'Amerique, par l'Abbe Ray∣nal, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="687"/> Adventures de Telemaque, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="688"/> Les Liaisons dangereuses, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="689"/> Roland l'Amoureux, 2 vols.</P>
<P><PB N="49" REF="017872_0047_0FA37B3F40F22448"/><MILESTONE N="690"/> Les Vielles du Chateau, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="691"/><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Enfans Morale, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="692"/><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> l'Education, 4 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="693"/><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> De Societe, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="694"/><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>nch scholar's guide, 2 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="subject">
<HEAD>VOYAGES, TRAVELS, MISCELLANIES, &amp;c. OCTAVO.</HEAD>
<P><MILESTONE N="695"/> Travels in North-America, in the years 1780, 1781 and 1782, by the marquis de Chastellux, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="696"/> Moore's view of society and manners in France, Switzerland, Germany and Italy, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="697"/> Carver's three years travels in the interior parts of North-America, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="698"/> Constitution of England, by J. L. de Lolme, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="699"/> Kaime's elements of criticism, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="700"/> Locke's essay on human understanding, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="701"/> Hume's essays and treatises on several subjects, 2 vols.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="702"/> Life of the late lord Chesterfield, or the man of the world, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="703"/> Gibson's surveying, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="704"/> Mr. Burke's speech on Mr. Fox's East-India bill, 1 vol.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="705"/> Considerations on the present situation of Great-Britain and the United States of Ame∣rica, with a view to their future commercial connexion, by Richard Champion, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 1 vol.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="advert">
<P><PB REF="017872_0048_0FA37B406F8515B8" MS="y"/>THE proprietor of the above <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> cata∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>gue of books is always furnished <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> as∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ortment of Stationary, School-Boo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>-Books, Primers, Legers and Journals, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, Invoice, Receipt, and Waste Books, Quill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>-knives, Ink-Powder, Sealing-Wax and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪ Slates and Black Lead Pencils, Ink-Chests and Instruments, Writing, Drawing, and Wrapping Paper, Playing and Message Cards, Shaving-Boxes, Brushes, Cloth-Burshes, and Tooth ditto. Pocket-Books, Ladies Etwee Cases and Purses, Gentlemens Gloves, Combs, Black Hair Pins▪ &amp;c. with a Great Assortment of the Best Plated Wares, Jewellery, &amp;c. Variety of Elegant En∣graved Prints, Various Sizes and Prices of Bibles, Prayer Books and Manuals, Tortois<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-Shell, Lea∣ther, and Paper Snuff-Boxes, Gentlemens Pla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d and Steel Spurs, Shoe-Buckles, &amp;c. &amp;c.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<HEAD>ERRATA.</HEAD>
<P>Page <HI>11.</HI> No. <HI>49.</HI> Read, Gentleman's and London magazine, &amp;c.</P>
<P>Page <HI>16.</HI> No. <HI>113.</HI> Read, Life of H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ry, prince of Wales, &amp;c.</P>
<P>Page <HI>19.</HI> For <HI>346</HI> read <HI>146.</HI></P>
<P>—. No. <HI>148.</HI> Read, Farmer's guide in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and stocking farms.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

