<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2008-05-19</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Alexis Jakobson</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>*Proofed title page(s).
*Reviewed structure.
*Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). 
*Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. 
*Checked for N=""s. 
*Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. 
*Checked placement and completeness of PBs. 
*Checked for foreign, damage and missing-page GAPs, #, --. 
*Checked for LBs, startqs / endqs, q;s, {que}s, ABBRs and Qs. 
*Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials.
*Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. 
*Corrected <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>s etc. 
*Converted <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="[vendor name]".
*Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N01972">
<STC T="E">2343</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99032371</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="002343_0000_0FDBCCA72BCDE5D0"/>
<PB REF="002343_0001_0FDBCC90F1B31178" MS="y"/>
<PB N="1" REF="002343_0002_0FDBCC9349427BC0"/>
<P>A TREATY OF Peace and Friendship Made and Concluded between His Excellency Sir WILLIAM KEITH, Bart. Governor of the Province of <HI>PENNSYLVANIA,</HI> For and on Behalf of the said Province, AND THE Chiefs of the Indians of the Five Nations, At <HI>ALBANY,</HI> in the Month of <HI>September,</HI> 1722.</P>
<P><HI>PHILADELPHIA:</HI> Printed by <HI>Andrew Bradford,</HI> at the BIBLE in the Second Street; MDCCXXII.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="2" REF="002343_0003_0FDBCC9582BEC628"/>
<OPENER><DATELINE><DATE>Septem. 27, 1722.</DATE></DATELINE></OPENER>
<P><HI>THE Honourable Sir</HI> William Keith, <HI>Bart. Governor of the Province of</HI> Pennsylvania, &amp;c. <HI>having, upon the Report that an</HI> Indian <HI>of the</HI> Five Nations <HI>had lost his Life by Means of some Traders of this Province, sent two Members of Council, in</HI> March <HI>last, to</HI> Conestogoe, <HI>to enquire into the Fact. Those Members, in Pursuance of the Governor's Orders, dis∣patched an</HI> Indian <HI>called</HI> Satcheechoe, <HI>one of the</HI> Cayoogoes, <HI>to the Chief of the</HI> Sinnekaes, <HI>to acquaint him with the Care the Governor had already taken in that Affair, and would further take, to-punish the Offenders. In Answer, the said Chief, by the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Messenger, desired to see our Governor in their country.</HI></P>
<P><HI>The Governor hereupon sent back the same</HI> Indian <HI>with some Presents, to inform the Chiefs of the</HI> Sinnekaes, <HI>and others of the Five Nations,</HI> That Col. <HI>Spotswood,</HI> Governor of <HI>Virginia,</HI> designing with Col. <HI>Burnet,</HI> Go∣vernor of <HI>New-York,</HI> to meet their Chiefs this Summer at <HI>Albany,</HI> He would take that Opportunity to see them in the same Company.</P>
<P><HI>The Time approaching that the Governors had appointed to meet the</HI> Indians, <HI>the Assembly of this Province, by whose Advice the Governor had engaged to the</HI> Indians <HI>to visit them, were called together to provide for the Charge. The Subject of the intended Treaty, The Value of the Presents to be made, and Members of Council to accompany the Governor,</HI> viz. Richard Hill, Isaac Norris <HI>and</HI> Andrew Hamilton, <HI>Esqrs. were agreed on by the Governor, Council and Assembly, and Sums of Money to defray the Charge were voted.</HI></P>
<P><HI>The Governor set out from</HI> Philadelphia <HI>the 8th Day of</HI> August, <HI>taking Col.</HI> John French, <HI>another Member of Council, with him, whom by his Letter he had called, on Behalf of the Counties on</HI> Delaware, <HI>to assist at the intended Treaty. The other Members followed a few Days after. On the 17th Day the Three Governors, with their respective Companies, set Sail in several Sloops from</HI> New-York <HI>up</HI> Hudson'<HI>s River. On the 20th they arrived at</HI> Albany.</P>
<P><HI>The Governor of</HI> New-York <HI>spoke first to the</HI> Indians; <HI>the Governor of</HI> Virginia <HI>treated next with them: But the Chief of the</HI> Sinnekaes, <HI>with whom the Business of</HI> Pennsylvania <HI>principally lay, having delayed his Coming, Sir</HI> William Keith <HI>our Governor deferred his Treaty the longer.</HI></P>
<P><HI>On the 7th of</HI> September <HI>our Governor spoke to them, and the same Day the Two</HI> Sinneka <HI>Chiefs arrived. Immediately after their Arrival they waited on our Governor at his Chamber, and laid on Otter Skin at his Feet.</HI> Connisooa <HI>shew'd the Golden Medal sent him last Summer by our Governor from</HI> Conestogoe, <HI>being hung at his Neck.</HI> Cajenquarahto <HI>also produced the Mourning Ring the Governor had sent last Spring by</HI> Satcheechoe, <HI>with the other Presents.</HI></P>
<P><HI>The Governor's Speech was in the following Words, Interpreted by</HI> James le Tort, <HI>and an</HI> Indian <HI>from</HI> Sasquehannah <HI>call'd</HI> Capt. Smith, <HI>whom the Governor took with him, together with</HI> Satcheechoe, <HI>the Messenger, who had been twice sent to the</HI> Five Nations.</P>
<Q><PB N="3" REF="002343_0004_0FDBCC97C1257CD0"/>
<TEXT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="speech">
<HEAD><HI>The Honourable Sir</HI> William Keith, <HI>Baronet, Governor of the Province of</HI> Pennsylvania, <HI>and Counties of</HI> Newcastle, Kent <HI>and</HI> Sussex <HI>upon</HI> Delaware, <HI>His Speech to the Five Nations of</HI> Indians <HI>at</HI> Albany, <HI>the 7th Day of</HI> Sep∣tember, 1722.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>BRETHREN,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I Have travel'd a great Way to see you, and to hold some Dis∣course with you. The People of <HI>Pennsylvania</HI> have always been Friends to the <HI>Five Nations:</HI> They have punctually kept all their former Treaties with you. They expect, that you do not forget them, and therefore I am come to brighten the Chain between us. You sent me Word, that you desired to see me, and I have ob∣tained Leave of my Brother, the Governor of <HI>New-York,</HI> to renew at this Place our former Treaties with you; and I am glad he is present with us, to hear and observe all that is spoken.</P>
<P>Some of your ancient Men can yet remember the first Settlement of the Province of <HI>Pennsylvania</HI> by <HI>William Penn:</HI> He was a good Man, and had a great Affection for all the <HI>Indians:</HI> He entred into Leagues of Friendship with them, and treated them as his Brethren; and he gave it in Charge to his Governors, whom he left in his Place, and to all his People, that they should continue to do the same.</P>
<P>Divers Great Men from the <HI>Five Nations</HI> have, on several Occasions, visited us at <HI>Philadelphia</HI> and <HI>Conestogoe.</HI> We were always glad to see them, and treated them kindly like Brethren. They made firm Leagues of Friendship with us, and frequently renew'd and strengthned them. We became as one People, and hope always to continue so; and as often as the <HI>Five Nations</HI> renew'd their Leagues with our great and good Friends the Governors of <HI>New-York,</HI> it still united them more nearly to us, as being Subjects of one and the same Great KING.</P>
<P>Last Summer the wise and good Man <HI>Gesaont,</HI> with some others of your People, came, in the Name of all the <HI>Five Nations,</HI> to visit us at <HI>Conestogoe</HI>▪ We received them with Joy, and opened our Hearts to each other. He rejoyced to see us and our <HI>Indians</HI> live in so much Love together. We then brightned the Chain, that it might be clear, strong and lasting as the Sun and Stars. But when we heard that <HI>Gesaont</HI> died in <HI>Virginia,</HI> we were very sorry; yet I hope the <HI>Five Nations</HI> received my Words of Love and Friendship to their <HI>Sachims,</HI> and to all their People, with the Golden Medal and the Presents then delivered.</P>
<P>It was then stipulated and agreed between us, That we should all be as one People; That the <HI>Five Nations</HI> should not do an Injury to any
<PB N="4" REF="002343_0005_0FDBCC9AAF44EFD8"/>
of us more than to themselves; and that we should not do an Injury to any of the <HI>Five Nations</HI> more than to our own People: Or, if any Person did such Injury, they should be punished for it in the same Manner as if done to an <HI>Englishman.</HI></P>
<P>Since that Time a very unhappy Accident has fallen out, which gave us great Grief: Last Winter we heard, that one of the <HI>Five Na∣tions</HI> had lost his Life by Means of some of our People.</P>
<P>The very next Day after the News came to me at <HI>Philadelphia,</HI> I sent two of my Council to <HI>Conestogoe,</HI> to enquire into the Matter and bring me the Truth. They sound that the Quarrel arose about <HI>Rum,</HI> between a Brother of the <HI>Five Nations,</HI> who hunted near <HI>Potomack,</HI> and two of our Traders.</P>
<P>The <HI>Indian</HI> was angry, and went hastily and took his Gun to kill the <HI>Englishmen</HI>; they, in Defence of themselves, seized the <HI>Indian,</HI> and in struggling gave him some Blows, and left him. We heard, that our <HI>Indian</HI> Friend and Brother died the next Day.</P>
<P>The Men who did this were brought to <HI>Philadelphia</HI> and put in Prison; and they will be tried according to our Laws, in the same Manner as if they had kill'd an <HI>Englishman.</HI> And to prevent such Mischief for the Future, we have made a severe Law against selling <HI>Rum</HI> to the <HI>Indians.</HI></P>
<P>Though this Misfortune gave us great Grief, yet we are perswaded that the Chief <HI>Sachims</HI> of the <HI>Five Nations</HI> are so wise as to know, that such Accidents may happen without any ill Design amongst the nearest Brethren. And by this they will see, how strictly we keep our Leagues and Treaties, in punishing those who shall dare to offend and injure them, or any of their People.</P>
<P>I made haste to send a Message to the <HI>Five Nations</HI> by <HI>Satcheecho</HI> to express our Sorrow, and I received their kind Answer by the Return of the same Messenger. You received our Message like true Brethren, desiring us, to wipe away our Tears, and invited me to come and see you. Immediately I sent <HI>Satcheecho</HI> back with this Answer, <HI>That I would meet you at</HI> Albany, <HI>with my good Friends the Governors of</HI> New∣York <HI>and</HI> Virginia; and I sent some Tokens to your <HI>Sachims,</HI> which I hope they received, with a Mourning Gold Ring off my own Finger to <HI>Sakaunkauta.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Satcheecho</HI> returned speedily, and said, <HI>You would be glad to see me at</HI> Albany; He also told me, You desired <HI>John Cartlidge</HI> might be released out of Prison, and the Injury done to your Kinsman might be forgot. But <HI>Satcheecho</HI> brought no Belt, nor any other Token to confirm his Words; and therefore I have brought him along with me, that you may know and tell me if he spoke Truth.</P>
<P><HI>Brethren,</HI></P>
<P>You see I am come here with Four of my Council to visit you. I have left my Family and People, and have travel'd a great Way to take you by the Hand, to join Hearts, and to rejoyce in seeing each other's Faces: For all Clouds and Darkness must be done away, that the Flame of Love and Af<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ction may burn clear in our Breasts.</P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="002343_0006_0FDBCC9E748DD3B0"/>
I have brought these Goods with me to bind my Words, <HI>viz. Five Pieces</HI> of <HI>Strouds</HI> for Cloathing, <HI>Five Casks of Powder</HI> and <HI>Five Hundred Weight of Lead</HI> to encourage your Hunting, that you may grow rich and strong. And I desire you may receive them as a Pledge of our firm Resolutions to live in Perpetual Peace, and under the strongest Ties of Friendship with the <HI>Five Nations</HI>; that you will ever remember us as your Brethren, and not suffer your young Men, when they travel, to hurt any of our Inhabitants, no more than they would their own, or to kill their Cattle and Stock: And that this Visit, and the Cove∣nant-Chain which is hereby brightned, may be recorded in everlasting Remembrance, to be sent down to your and our Children, and to our Children's Children, to last as long as the Mountains and Rivers, and the Sun and Moon shall endure.</P>
<P>I also give you these two Pieces of <HI>Blankets,</HI> to wipe away and to dry up the Blood that has been spilt, and to cover it so as that it may never be seen or heard of any more.</P>
<P>I live at a great Distance from the Brethren, and perhaps may never see so many of your grave ancient Men together again; I will there∣fore, like a true Brother, leave with you my best Advice, for the Happiness and Welfare of all your People: And as oft as you look upon those two Belts remember,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Two Belts said down</NOTE> that <HI>This One signifies the Strength which a wise Nation acquires and secures to its People by peaceable Councils; and encreasing the Number of its Friends:</HI> And this other Belt represents to you <HI>A bold, firm, true Heart, that abhors Falshhood, but is ever faithful to its Friends, and punctually observes whatsoever it promises.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<Q><TEXT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="speech">
<HEAD><HI>The Answer made by the</HI> Indians <HI>of the Five Nations,</HI> viz. <HI>The</HI> Maquase, Oneydes, Onnondages, Cayouges <HI>and</HI> Sinnekaes, <HI>to the Propositions made by the Honourable Sir</HI> William Keith, <HI>Bart. Governor of</HI> Pennsylvania, &amp;c. <HI>in</HI> Albany, <HI>the 10th Day of</HI> September, Anno 1722.</HEAD>
<P>PRESENT</P>
<P>The Honourable Sir <HI>WILLIAM KEITH,</HI> Baronet, Governor of <HI>Pennsylvania,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Esqrs. Members of the Council of <HI>Pennsylvania.</HI></HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Richard Hill,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Isaac Norris,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Col. <HI>John French,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Andrew Hamilton,</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<PB N="6" REF="002343_0007_0FDBCCA310E16170"/>
<HEAD>Esqrs. Commissioners of the <HI>Indian</HI> Affairs.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Col. <HI>Peter Schuyler,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Peter Van Brugh,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>John. Cuyler,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Hend Hanse,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Evert Banker,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Philip Livingston,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Joh. Bleecher,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>John Collins,</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><HI>Interpreted by</HI> Lawrence Claese <HI>into</HI> Dutch, <HI>and rendred into</HI> English <HI>by</HI> Robert Livingston; Tanachaha <HI>being Speaker.</HI></P>
<Q><P>Brother <HI>ONAS</HI>;</P>
<P>[<HI>which signisies a</HI> Pen <HI>in the Language of the</HI> Five Nations, <HI>by which Name they call the Go∣vernors of</HI> Pennsylvania, <HI>since it was first setled by</HI> William Penn.]</P>
<P>I. YOU told us in your Proposition some Days ago, That you was come a great Way to see us of the <HI>Five Nations</HI>; We thank you for your Good Will to us, and are very glad to see you here in good Health: And we hope a good Understanding and Agreement will be made and concluded between us.</P>
<P>You told us also, That you are come to renew the Covenant-Chain that has been made between us so long ago, even at the first Setling the Province of <HI>Pennsylvania,</HI> and to brighten the Chain, and to re∣move and do away any Spot of Rust that may be grown upon it since our last Meeting and Conference at <HI>Conestogoe.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Brother Onas,</HI></P>
<P>II. You have told us, That at that Time you brighten'd the Covenant Chain between us, that it might be clear and lasting as the Sun and Stars in Heaven: For which we thank you. And we being now all present, do, in the most solemn and publick Manner, renew the Covenant and brighten the Chain made between us. that the Lustre thereof may never be obscured by any Clouds or Dark∣ness; but may shine as clear and last as long as the Sun in the Firmament.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Onas,</HI></P>
<P>III. You have likewise told us, How <HI>William Penn,</HI> who was a good Man, did, at his first Settlement of the Province of <HI>Pennsyl∣vania,</HI> make Leagues of Friendship with the <HI>Indians,</HI> and treated them like Brethren; and that, like the same good Man, he left it in Charge to all his Governors who should succeed him, and to all the People of <HI>Pennsylvania,</HI> that they should always keep the Covenant and Treaties he had made with the <HI>Five Nations,</HI> and treat them with Love and Kindness. We acknowledge that his Governors and People have always kept the same honestly and truly to this Day: So we on our Part always have kept, and for ever shall keep, firm Peace and Friendship, with a good Heart, to all the People of <HI>Penn∣sylvania.</HI> We thankfully receive and approve of all the Articles in your Proposition to us, and acknowledge them to be good and full of Love: We receive and approve of the same with our whole
<PB N="7" REF="002343_0008_0FDBCC8EE20DD988"/>
Hearts, because we are not only made one People by the Covenant▪ Chain, but we also are People united in One Head, One Body and One Heart, by the strongest Ties of Love and Friendship.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Onas,</HI></P>
<P>IV. You desire there may be a perpetual Peace and Friendship between you and the <HI>Five Nations,</HI> and between your Children and our Children, and that the same may be kept as long as the Moun∣tains and Rivers endure. All which we like well, and on our Part desire, that the Covenant and Union made with a clean and true Heart, between you and us, may last as long as the Sun and Moon shall continue to give Light. And we will deliver this in Charge to our Children, that it may be kept in Remembrance with their Children, and Children's Children to the latest Ages. And we desire, That the Peace and Tranquility that is now established be∣tween us, may be as clear as the Sun shining in its Lustre, without any Cloud or Darkness, and that the same may continue for ever.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Onas,</HI></P>
<P>V. We have well consider'd all that you have spoken, and like it well, because it is only the Renewing of former Leagues and Treaties, made between the Government of <HI>Pennsylvania</HI> and Us of the <HI>Five Nations</HI>; which we always believed we were obliged to keep. And as to the Accident of one of our Friends being kill'd by some of your People, which has happen'd by Misfortune and against your Will, we say, That as we are all in Peace, we think it hard the Persons who kill'd our Friend and Brother should suffer: And we do, in the Name of all the <HI>Five Nations,</HI> forgive the Offence, and desire you will likewise forgive it; and that the Men who did it may be released from Prison, and set at Liberty to go whither they please. And we shall esteem that as a Mark of Regard and Friend∣ship for the <HI>Five Nations,</HI> and as a farther Confirmation of this Treaty.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Onas,</HI></P>
<P>VI. We say farther, We are glad to hear the former Treaties we have made with <HI>William Penn</HI> repeated to us again, and renewed by you; and we esteem and love you, as if you were <HI>William Penn</HI> Himself. We are glad you have wip'd away and cover'd the Blood of our dead Friend and Brother; and we desire the same may be forgot, so as it may never be more mentioned or remembred.</P>
<P>It is needless for us to answer every Particular of your Proposition, because we acknowledge the Whole to be good and acceptable to us; especially your good Advice, which we will always remember: And in Testimony thereof, and as a full Confirmation of our Agree∣ment, Consent and Approbation of all that you have proposed, and we have here said and promised, we lay down a few Beaver, Bear and dress'd Deer Skins: <HI>And so concluded.</HI></P></Q>
<P>Then the Governor express'd his Satisfaction with their Answer; and gave them Thanks for their Good Will and Love to Him, and the People of <HI>Pennsylvania.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Indians</HI> then desired to know of the Governor, <HI>If the Men who were in Prison for Killing their Friend and Brother were discharged?</HI> To which the Governor answered, That "they were let out upon Bail."
<PB N="8" REF="002343_0009_0FDBCCAC5312A8F0"/>
They then desired, That <HI>the Men might be discharged:</HI> To which the Governor answered, That as soon as he returned to <HI>Philadelphia,</HI> he would give such Orders in that Affair, as should fully Answer the Request of the <HI>Five Nations,</HI> in Order to confirm the Friendship that is so happily renewed and established by this Treaty.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>A true Copy, Examined by</HI> PHILIP LIVINGSTON, <HI>Secr. for the</HI> Indian-<HI>Affairs.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P>The Chiefs of the <HI>Indians</HI> express'd a great Affection for the Governor and the People of <HI>Pennsylvania.</HI> And it appeared that <HI>Satcheechoe</HI> had faithfully discharged his Trust in both the Messages sent by him.</P>
<P>When our Interpreters were coming away the Chiefs informed them, That they had something further to say to the Governor; upon which they were detained. The next Day, the 14th of <HI>September,</HI> the Governor received at his Chamber the Ten Chiefs of the Five Nations, being Two from each; together with Two others, said to be of the <HI>Tuscororoes</HI>: And by the Interpretation of <HI>Lawrence Claese,</HI> Publick Interpreter for the <HI>Indians,</HI> in the Presence of <HI>Philip Livingston,</HI> Secretary for <HI>Indian</HI> Affairs at <HI>Albany,</HI> both whom our Governor desired to be present, they spoke as follows:</P>
<Q><P>Brother Onas,</P>
<P><HI>WE here now freely surrender to you all those Lands about</HI> Conestogoe, <HI>which the</HI> Five Nations <HI>have claimed: And it is our Desire that the same may be setled with <HI>Christians;</HI> in Token whereof we give this String of Wampum.</HI></P>
<P>Brother Onas, <HI>According to the best of our Understanding, we have renew'd at this Time with you all former Treaties between your People and us; we there∣fore expect, that if any of our People come to trade at</HI> Philadelphia, <HI>you will order that they be received like Brethren, and have the Goods as cheap as possible. So we wish you all Prosperity and a good Journey Home.</HI></P>
<P>Now we are going to depart from one another, we your Brethren, the <HI>Sachims of the</HI> Five Nations, <HI>desire that you would give us some Provisions, to help us on our Journey.</HI> On which they gave 2 small Bundles of Beaver and dress'd Skins.</P></Q>
<Q><TEXT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="speech">
<HEAD><HI>Sir</HI> William Keith'<HI>s Answer.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Brethren,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>YOU know very well, that the Lands about <HI>Conestogoe,</HI> upon the River <HI>Sasquehannah,</HI> belong to your old Friend and kind Brother <HI>William Penn</HI>; nevertheless I do here, in his Name, kindly accept of the Offer and Surrender which you have now made to me, because it will put an End to all other Claims and Disputes, if any should be made hereafter.</P>
<P><HI>Brethren,</HI> I understand, as you do, that we here at this Time renew'd all former Treaties between the <HI>Five Nations</HI> and <HI>Pennsylvania</HI>; and con∣sidering how well you are provided with Goods at <HI>Albany,</HI> I think <HI>Phila∣delphia</HI> will be far out of your Way to trade; but as often as any of your People come to us in Love and Friendship, they shall be treated like Brethren.</P>
<P>I am not able to provide for you here as if I were at Home; but I will order some Bread to be got for your particular Use: And I heartily wish you well Home to your own Families.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

