<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2008-05-22</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Alexis Jakobson</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>*Proofed title page(s).
*Reviewed structure.
*Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). 
*Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. 
*Checked for N=""s. 
*Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. 
*Checked placement and completeness of PBs. 
*Checked for foreign, damage and missing-page GAPs, #, --. 
*Checked for LBs, startqs / endqs, q;s, {que}s, ABBRs and Qs. 
*Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials.
*Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. 
*Corrected <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>s etc. 
*Converted <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="[vendor name]".
*Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N03229">
<STC T="E">3916</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99019854</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="003916_0000_10034B9566838AF8"/>
<PB N="1" REF="003916_0001_100354F6A9F155D0"/>
<P>AT A CONFERENCE Held at <HI>Deerfield</HI> in the County of <HI>Hampshire,</HI> the Twenty seventh Day of <HI>August,</HI> Anno Regni Regis GEORGIJ Secundi, Magnae, Britan∣niae, Franciae et Hiberniae, &amp;c. Nono, <HI>Anno{que} Domini,</HI> 1735. By &amp; between His Excellency <HI>JONATHAN BELCHER,</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> Captain General and Governour in Chief in and over His Majesty's Province of the <HI>Massachusetts-Bay</HI> in <HI>New England.</HI></P>
<P>AND</P>
<P><HI>Ountaussoogoe</HI> and others, Chiefs of the <HI>Cagnawaga</HI> Tribe of Indians, &amp;c. who were accompanied by a Number of the <HI>St. Francoi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> Indians, who at their own desire were included in the Treaty with the <HI>Cagnawagas,</HI> the whole being Twenty seven.</P>
<P><HI>Cuncaupot</HI> Captain, with his Lieutenaut and several others of the Chiefs of the <HI>Houssatonuoc</HI> Indians &amp;c, being upwards of Forty in the whole.</P>
<P><HI>Marsequunt, Naunautooghija<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> and <HI>Weenpauk,</HI> Three Chiefs of the <HI>Scautacook</HI> Tribe and others, including Seventeen of the <HI>Moheegs,</HI> making Eighty in the whole.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="conference account">
<PB N="2" REF="003916_0002_100354F983EE1A80"/>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">H</SEG>IS Excellency being seated at a large Table under a spacious Tent for that Purpose prepared, attended by a Quorum of His Majesty's Council, and a Committee of the honourable House of Representatives, thereto appointed by the General Court; with a great Number of Gentlemen and others Spectators.</P>
<P>The Union Flagg flying at the Head of the Tent.</P>
<P>His Excellency first received the <HI>Cagnawaga</HI> Tribe of Indians, with the <HI>St. Francois,</HI> who were placed on Seats at a suitable Distance over against His Excellency; they having first made their Compliments to the Gover∣nour by shaking Hands &amp;c.</P>
<P><HI>Joseph Kellogg,</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> being a Sworn Interpreter, Governour— <HI>to the Interpreter</HI> — Inform the Chiefs I shall speak.</P>
<SP>
<P><HI>My good Friends and Brethren,</HI></P>
<P>I Am glad to see you: I give Thanks to the Great GOD who has safely conducted you through a long and tedious Journey; It is a great plea∣sure to me that we have the Opportunity of refreshing our Faces with the sight of each other. <STAGE>—Holding out one String of <HI>Wampum,</HI>—proceeds, and says,—</STAGE></P>
<P><HI>My good Friends and Brethren,</HI> THIS is to wipe away all Tears from your Eyes. <STAGE>—Then holding out a second—</STAGE> THIS is to open your Throats that you may speak with all Freedom <STAGE>—Then a third—</STAGE> THIS is to wipe away all Blood, and to comfort you under all your past Difficulties.</P>
</SP>
<P>And then His Excellency delivered them the three Strings in one.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Auountauresaunkee</HI> Indian Speaker.</SPEAKER>
<P>WE that are deputed from our Tribes are come at Your Excellency's Call —at your desire — and are glad we are got safe here, after a long and tedious Travel over Hills and high Mountains, and join with the Gover∣nour in our Thanks to GOD that we see the Faces of each other in Health and Peace. As Your Excellency has done to Us, we do the same in answer to You <STAGE>— holding a String of <HI>Wampum</HI>— proceeds and says, —</STAGE> Our desire is that all Tears may be wiped from Your Excellency's Eyes. <STAGE>— Then hold∣ing out a second String —</STAGE> That your Throat may be open, that all freedom of Speech may be had, we desire the Path may be clear and open, and no difficulty in the way. <STAGE>— Then holding out a third String—</STAGE> We desire the Place where the Governour stands may be clean from all filth of Blood:</P>
<STAGE>And then he delivered the three Strings to the Governour.</STAGE>
<P>The Governour sent for Three of Us, but usually more of us come than are sent for, we are Eight instead of Three. We have brought our Wives who we always want with us. <STAGE>(Then delivers a Belt of <HI>Wampum,</HI> being in Answer to One the Governour sent them by the Messenger that called them)</STAGE></P>
<P><PB N="3" REF="003916_0003_100354FB1A3DFCB0"/>
We incline to be short left we should be troublesome to the Governour. We are here the Representatives of the Three Families of the <HI>Cagnawaga</HI> Tribe, <HI>Ountaussoogoe</HI> and Three others, one of the Families having sent two Delegates.</P>
<P>We desire nothing may be taken amiss by Your Excellency; if a wrong Word should happen to fall from us, we desire it may be taken up and recti∣fyed; it is what has been usual, and we desire it may be so now.</P>
<P>The Way is now clear, and the Door open for Freedom of Speech; but we have nothing to say at present. We were sent for, and it is not custo∣mary for those that are drawn by the Hand to speak first, and therefore wait to hear what Your Excellency has to say, and desire You would please to appoint the time, when we shall be ready to attend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> It is not at all disagreable to me that more of you are come than were sent for; You are all doubly welcome, and I am glad to see you all; and if more had come than are here they should have been very wel∣come too; I am glad to see your Wives and Children also.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ountaussoogoe.</SPEAKER>
<P> Brother, Governour, and <HI>Broad Way,</HI> we have now shaken Hands, finished Salutation, and we take it the Method thereof is now ended: according to the Custom of Our Forefathers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I take it so too. I shall signify to you by Capt. <HI>Kellogg</HI> when I shall be ready to speak further to you on Business, which I intend to Mor∣row in the forenoon.</P>
</SP>
<P>His Excellency drank a Health to King GEORGE to them.</P>
<P>They all drink with proper Salutations.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ountaussoogoe.</SPEAKER>
<P> We are here at Your Excellency's Call, and when You say we are dismiss'd we are ready to go: We return Thanks that we have been well provided for since we have been here; we have wanted nothing, and thank the Governour. When we came from Home we told Our People we purposed to return in forty Days, we have been in this Place near thirty, and now wait Your Excellency's Pleasure for our Return.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> It is in some measure owing to your Selves that so much time is already spent; Your Answer to me not coming seasonably, I waited for it a long while, more than Six Months. It is the Great GOD that governs the Winds and Weather, and by his Providence the Vessel sent by the Go∣vernment from <HI>Boston</HI> with Stores has been delayed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ountaussoogoe.</SPEAKER>
<P> When we received Your Excellency's Message Our Young Men were out at War, and we inclined to see the Event; for if great Loss had hapned, we should have been obliged to revenge it Our Selves; and we are now come at Your Excellency's desire. Although I am an Old Man, I 
<PB N="4" REF="003916_0004_100354FCC544A5E8"/>
am not wanting of Business, sometimes being called to one Place, sometimes to another, on publick Affairs or otherways; and here we are now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> We can't avoid Disappointments; I will endeavour you shall be early dispatch'd; there are other Tribes here expecting to be treated with as well as you, but I consider your distance, and shall give you the first dispatch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ountaussoogoe.</SPEAKER>
<P> We take it all Matters are over as has been customary by Our Fathers at first meeting on such Occasions, and are now ready to take leave.</P>
</SP>
<P>Then the Indians made their Compliment and withdrew.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="day">
<HEAD>Thursday <HI>August</HI> 28. 1735. The Conference Continued.</HEAD>
<P>PRESENT</P>
<P>His Excellency <HI>Jonathan Belcher,</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR></P>
<P>Captain General and Governour in Chief, &amp;c.</P>
<P><HI>Cuncaupot</HI> Captain, and Chief of the <HI>Houssatonuoc</HI> Tribe of Indians, attended with Twenty three Men and Twenty Indian <HI>Women</HI> and <HI>Children.</HI></P>
<P>THE Indians made the usual Compliment by Shaking Hands, &amp;c.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I thank GOD who has brought you here in Safety and Health after a long and tedious Journey. I look upon you as my Children, and hope you are good Subjects of King GEORGE. I shall always take the same Care of you as of the English, and take you under my Protection at all times; if you meet with any Difficulty at any time, I expect to have Notice of it; and if you have any thing to lay before me now I am ready to hear it. <STAGE>— <HI>After some Pause by the Indians</HI> —</STAGE> If you are not prepared now to speak, I will give you a further Opportunity till the afternoon, or to morrow Morning. And I will now go on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="5" REF="003916_0005_10034B9C52FC7D28"/>
<SPEAKER>Indians.</SPEAKER>
<P> We are come here to pay Our Respects to the Governour, and hear what the Governour has to say to Us, but we have nothing to say at this time.</P>
<P><HI>Governour.</HI> I rejoyce very much at your Disposition to receive the Gospel by One of Our Ministers, I hope you are all well satisfied with Mr. <HI>Sargent,</HI> and with Mr. <HI>Woodbridge,</HI> (who are your Minister and your School-Master,) and that you will diligently and constantly attend on Mr. <HI>Sargent</HI> and Mr. <HI>Wood∣bridge</HI> with your Children, to receive Instruction from them. Religion is a serious thing, and it ought to be always born on your Minds. If you have any thing to say or propose further to me herein, I shall rejoyce in it, and be ready to do it for the good of your Souls.</P>
<P>I hope you have been well entertained since you have been here, and that every thing has been agreable to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Indians.</SPEAKER>
<P> Yes Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I have nothing further to say to you at present, I will meet you when you are ready, this Afternoon, or to morrow Morning.</P>
<P>I drink to you all with an Heart full of respect: I drink the great King GEORGE's Health to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt. <HI>Cuncaupot.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P> We drink a Health to King GEORGE, and the Governour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Indians.</SPEAKER>
<P> We are very glad the Governour takes so much Care of us, it takes all sorrow from our Hearts, and we hope (as GOD shall enable us) to perform what Your Excellency has recommended to us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I have nothing further to say to you at present, but when∣ever you would speak to me I shall be ready to hear you.</P>
</SP>
<P>The Indians withdrew.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="day">
<PB N="6" REF="003916_0006_10035500401BE0B8"/>
<HEAD>Thursday <HI>August</HI> 28. 1735. The Conference Continued.</HEAD>
<P>PRESENT</P>
<P>His Excellency <HI>Jonathan Belcher,</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR></P>
<P>Captain General and Governour in Chief, &amp;c.</P>
<P><HI>Marsequunt, Naunautooghijau, Weenpauk,</HI> Chiefs of the <HI>Scautacooks,</HI> with Sixty three Men and Women at∣tending, and also Seventeen of the <HI>Mobeeg</HI> Tribe with them.</P>
<P>The Chiefs above with the others, paid the usual Compliment to the Captain General, by shaking Hands &amp;c.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GOvernour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I am very glad to see such a Number of King GEORGE's good Subjects in Health and Peace here together; I look upon you all as my Children, and shall take the same Care of you as I do of the English at all times: If you meet with any Difficulty at any time from the People, you must repair to me, where you shall meet with all manner of Justice. The Government has set up a Trading House under Capt. <HI>Kellogg</HI>'s Care, that you may be continually Supplied in the best manner, and not cheated in your Trade; they have also sent a Minister to the Trading House at <HI>Fort Dummer</HI> and another to <HI>Houssatonnoc,</HI> that you as well as the Indians there may be instructed in the true Knowledge of JESUS CHRIST.</P>
<P>The Government as well as particular Gentlemen are very willing to be at great Charge in spreading the Gospel among you, that you may live the better here, and be happy for ever hereafter. 'Tis the highest Respect and Friendship the Government can shew you to instruct you in the true Religion; and I hope you'l express your thankfulness for it to GOD, by leading better Lives than ever yet you have done, and that you your Selves as well as your Wives will make it your business to attend on the Ministers, and observe their Instructions, especially on GOD's holy Day, and that you will command your Children also, that they may be taught to Read and to Write, and that they may be instructed in the true Religion of JESUS CHRIST.</P>
<P>I hope you have been well entertained here, and that every thing has been agreable to you since you have been here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="7" REF="003916_0007_10034BA3D3CF6558"/>
<SPEAKER>Indians.</SPEAKER>
<P> In the Morning we eat, are well entertained at Noon, and at Night lye down to Sleep; we Sleep well and are in good Health.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> If you have any thing to propose or offer to me now or to Morrow, or at any other time; when you are ready I am ready to receive it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Indians.</SPEAKER>
<P> Our Father, We have heard Your Excellency Say,—We take ex∣traordinary kindly Your Care of us, not only for our temporal Good, but for the good of the Life to come (which is of the greatest Concern) that so it may be well with us with that GOD who takes care for all Men, and with whom all are alike.</P>
</SP>
<P>And then laid down a Belt of <HI>Wampam,</HI> which they said was according to their Custom of shaking Hands.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I have nothing further to say to you at this time; I am ready to hear whatever you may have to say to me when you please.</P>
</SP>
<P>His Excellency drinks King GEORGE's Health to the Indians.</P>
<P>The Indians return the Compliment; drink King GEORGE's Health and the Governour's, and expressed their thankfulness for the Opportunity of so doing; and then took leave, and withdrew.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="day">
<HEAD>Thursday <HI>August</HI> 28. 1735. The Conference Continued.</HEAD>
<P>PRESENT.</P>
<P>His Excellency <HI>Jonathan Belcher,</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR></P>
<P>Captain General and Governour in Chief, &amp;c.</P>
<P><HI>Ountaussoogoe,</HI> and the others of the <HI>Cagnawaga</HI> Tribe.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> <HI>My good Friends and Brethren,</HI></P>
<P>THere has been a long Friendship between King GEORGE's Subjects, and the <HI>Five Nations</HI> from whence you originally came, and there was a special Covenant made between this Government and You (the <HI>Cagnawaga</HI> Indians) at <HI>Albany,</HI> eleven Years ago, which you on Your part as well as we on Ours, have faithfully observed hitherto; and we now readily acknowledge that you have 
<PB N="8" REF="003916_0008_10035506370192D0"/>
testified your Faithfulness in divers Instances of your Friendship; and I now come by the desire of the People of this Government to renew that Covenant, and to brighten the Chain, that a good Understanding of Peace and Friend∣ship may be Cultivated and Continued for ever, that so the Children unborn may in times to come rejoyce in Our meeting together this day.</P>
</SP>
<P>His Excellency delivers them a large Belt of <HI>Wampum.</HI></P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Auountauresaunkee</HI> Indian.</SPEAKER>
<P> It is not to be questioned but when the Gover∣mour has done saying, He will inform us He has done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> There are some of your People who resort to <HI>Fort Dummer,</HI> where Captain <HI>Kellogg</HI> Commands: The Government have placed A FATHER there, who will be ready to learn them and their Children to Read and Write, and to inform them of the Principles of Our Religion; If any of you are willing to be instructed therein, I look upon you to be a free People, You are my Brethren, and you need not be afraid of any body, nor of re∣ceiving Knowledge: It will cost you nothing to have your Children in∣structed by the FATHER that lives at that Fort. It is from the same respect and love that I have for my self, that I would have you and your Children Instructed. And this Matter I leave to your Consideration at your return Home.</P>
<STAGE>Then His Excellency delivered another Belt of <HI>Wampum.</HI></STAGE>
<P>There is a Present from the Government to be given you, which you shall have to Morrow.</P>
<P>I have done speaking for the present.</P>
</SP>
<P><HI>Auountauresaunkee,</HI> Indian Speaker — Stands up, — And distinctly repeats every thing His Excellency has said, and he in the Name of the rest, re∣turns their hearty Thanks for the Governour's Care over them and Kindness for them; gratefully acknowledging the Respect shewn them by the Gover∣nour, — <HI>and proceeds</HI> — It is exceeding kind of the Governour (and we re∣joyce to see it) that the BROAD WAY is kept Open between Us, that there is safe passing, and no hindrance or stop therein. Matters of such Consequence as these are of great Moment, and deserve the Attention of a better Head than mine (which is weak) to speak to, especially what the Governour mentions as to the Covenant made about eleven Years ago at <HI>Albany.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ountaussoogoe,</HI> Indian Chief, — Rises up, — And repeats again Article by Ar∣ticle what His Excellency had said: Then lays down a large Belt of <HI>Wam∣pum</HI> doubled; and in answer to the Governour, (with one End of the Belt) says, —</P>
<SP>
<PB N="9" REF="003916_0009_10034BAD22AC86A0"/>
<P><HI>Brother,</HI> the <HI>Broad Way.</HI> I am poor in the Case: Don't expect a full Answer from us here; but I take up <HI>Your Word</HI> and shall carry it home to them that have sent us here; they are now upon their Knee waiting for Our return, they are the Three Families of the <HI>Cagnawaga</HI> Tribe, and they with us will take these Affairs, which are of such great Weight under Con∣sideration, in order to give the Governour an Answer. And we give thanks to the Great GOD that has given Your Excellency and Our Brethren of the BROAD WAY, an Heart to continue of the same Mind as when the Co∣venant was entred into: We also rejoyce that GOD has continued Us of the same Mind, and that there is no seeking of any kind, but Good.</P>
<STAGE>With the other End of the Belt. He returns thanks for the Favours received.</STAGE>
<P>And now we have gone through the Work, what have we further to do? We desire to know His Excellency's Pleasure when we may be re∣turning Home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I have had News from <HI>Boston</HI> to day; there is a Ship lately arrived from <HI>England,</HI> and brings the Account that the Peace is still subsist∣ing between King GEORGE and the <HI>French</HI> King; but if there should happen a War between King GEORGE and the <HI>French</HI> King, yet I shall have a good Opinion of your Fidelity. If it should be War, there is no question but your Justice and Faith, as well as your Interest will hold you to Peace with us; You will be always honestly dealt with by Capt. <HI>Kellogg</HI> at the Truck House, where you may have such things as you need, at a cheaper rate than any others can or will let you have them.</P>
<P>It is with a great deal of Pleasure I have undertaken the fatigue of this Journey to meet you here, and save you the trouble of going to <HI>Boston.</HI> The Way to <HI>Boston</HI> is open and clear, and I shall always be glad to see you there, whenever you please to come. On Monday I hope you will be ready to be going home, when you shall have Provision for your Journey: But you must dine with me to Morrow — when you shall have the Present, and take leave after dinner.</P>
</SP>
<P>The Governour drinks lasting Health and Prosperity to their Tribe.</P>
<P><HI>Ountaussoogoe</HI> drinks King GEORGE's Health and the Governour's, &amp;c.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="day">
<PB N="10" REF="003916_0010_10034BC916682520"/>
<HEAD>Friday <HI>August</HI> 29. 1735. The Conference Continued.</HEAD>
<P>PRESENT</P>
<P>His Excellency <HI>Jonathan Belcher,</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR></P>
<P>Captain General and Governour in Chief, &amp;c.</P>
<P><HI>Cuncaupot</HI> Captain, and the others of the <HI>Houssatonnoc</HI> Tribe &amp;c.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P>CAptain <HI>Cuncaupot,</HI> I am now ready to hear what you have to say. I understand you desire what you have got to say should be drawn up in Writing, and that Mr. <HI>Williams</HI> will read it, which shall be rendred to you again by your Interpreter, in short Sentences.</P>
</SP>
<P>And it was accordingly done, and thereupon the Indians manifested an universal Approbation thereof; which is in the words following, <HI>viz.</HI></P>
<Q><TEXT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="approbation">
<OPENER><DATELINE><HI>Deerfield</HI> <DATE><HI>August 29th.</HI> 1735.</DATE></DATELINE>
<HI>May it please Your Excellency,</HI></OPENER>
<P>WE thank Your Excellency as Our Father, that we have received Your Kindness and Love, and we would express Our Duty and Subjection to Our Rightful Sovereign King GEORGE, whom we pray GOD long to preserve.</P>
<P>We are desirous to receive the Gospel of Our LORD JESUS CHRIST; and hope that Our Hearts are in what we say, and that we don't speak only out of our Lips: And we are thankful that Mr. <HI>Williams</HI> and other Ministers are come to us, and especially that Mr. <HI>Sargent,</HI> and Mr. <HI>Wood∣bridge,</HI> have been sent to us, and pray to the Great GOD to keep them, and cause they may have Health, and live long with us.</P>
<P>And <HI>Sir, Our Father,</HI> We did not come to you of our Selves, and tell you that we wanted any thing, and yet you have taken Care of Us as your Children, and given us Learning &amp;c. No Child says to his Father, I would have so and so; but a Father when he sees his Children in want, is ready to help them: And so we think Your Excellency as our Father is willing to do to us upon every account; and we pray that when we are wanting any thing we may be directed to tell Col. <HI>Stoddard</HI> of it, that he may send to Your Excellency, that what we want may be done for us.</P>
<P><PB N="11" REF="003916_0011_10034BB5DFBB0C00"/>
<HI>Sir, Our Father,</HI> As we have been taught the Gospel, so we hope to have it to Our Heart for ever.</P>
<P><HI>Sir, Our Father,</HI> Our Children are afraid of strict Laws, and of being brought into trouble, and put in Prison for Debt &amp;c. and we pray that Care may be taken by your Excellency as Our Father, and by the General Assembly, that we be not hurt by the severity of the Laws, seeing we don't understand how to manage in such Affairs, so as that there may not be any danger at any time that Our Children be taken away from us for Debt &amp;c.</P>
<P>We don't pretend to desire any thing, but that if any of Our People should commit Murder or any other crying Wickedness, they should be lia∣ble to the Law.</P>
<P><HI>Sir, Our Father,</HI> We are concerned for our own Children, as we think you, as a Father are for Us, and therefore we pray that it may be given us in Writing (or establish'd by a Law) that Our Children after us be not wronged or injured.</P>
<P>We thank your Excellency, You sent for Us here to see Your Face, and so many honourable Gentlemen, and that there has been such Care taken of us on all Our Journey, and since we came to this Place. We find that by what we have experienced of Your Excellency's Care for us, that we need not <HI>Crave</HI> of You, but leave Our selves to your Care for the time to come.</P>
<CLOSER>And are <SIGNED>Your Excellency's dutiful Servants,
<LIST>
<ITEM>Cuncaupot <FIGURE REND="inline">
</FIGURE> Captain</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vmpecheny <FIGURE REND="inline">
</FIGURE> Lieutenant</ITEM>
<ITEM>Wauntauga <FIGURE REND="inline">
</FIGURE> Meet</ITEM>
<ITEM>Naunaune <FIGURE REND="inline">
</FIGURE> Canutt</ITEM>
</LIST>
in the Name of the rest.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P>And then Capt. <HI>Cancanpot</HI> laid down a percel of <HI>Deer Skins</HI> as a Present.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I take very kindly what you have said, and you shall have a particular Answer to it to Morrow.</P>
</SP>
<P><PB N="12" REF="003916_0012_1003550C73362738"/>
The Governour drinks the great King GEORGE's Health to the Indians, and says, That under GOD, the King is the common Father of them and us, and wishes they may always prosper in Soul and Body.</P>
<P>Captain <HI>Cuncaupot</HI> returns the Salute, and drinks the King's Health.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I shall see you to Morrow, when there will be a Present for you from the Government, and after dinner I shall take leave of you.</P>
</SP>
<P>One of the Indians complained he had left a Gun at Mr. <HI>Stebbins</HI>'s at <HI>Northampton,</HI> and can't get it again.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I will inquire into that matter, and shall give direction to Col. <HI>Stoddard</HI> that Justice be done therein.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Indian.</SPEAKER>
<P> There were also Eight <HI>Deer Skins</HI> at Mr. <HI>Miller</HI>'s, which I can't have any account of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> When you meet with any Injustice you may repair to Col. <HI>Stoddard,</HI> as you have desired, who will see you have Justice done you.</P>
</SP>
<P>His Excellency then gave them a Caution against drinking too hard, by which they would prevent their being imposed on or defrauded by any body.</P>
<P>After which the Indians withdrew.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="day">
<HEAD>Friday <HI>August</HI> 28. 1735. The Conference Continued.</HEAD>
<P>PRESENT.</P>
<P>His Excellency <HI>Jonathan Belcher,</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR></P>
<P>Captain General and Governour in Chief, &amp;c.</P>
<P>Ountaussoogoe Chief, and others of the <HI>Cagnawagas.</HI></P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I hope you are all well this Morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ountaussoogoe.</SPEAKER>
<P> No Sir, One was taken Sick this Morning, and a Child has been Sick ever since we came.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="13" REF="003916_0013_1003550E2AFA74E8"/>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I am sorry for it; the Doctor shall tend on them — I expect none here now, but those of the <HI>Cagnawaga</HI> Tube. —</P>
<STAGE>[Some others being under the Tent.]</STAGE>
<P>The Present of the Government which lays before you, is designed only for your Tribe, and you must take care that it be justly distributed among your Selves: The Government has made other Provision for the others.</P>
<STAGE>Then the Present was delivered.</STAGE>
<P>I hope you will carefully lay up all I have said to you, and though we are at such a distance in Our Persons, yet I hope Our Hearts will be always near one another: And you shall be provided with what may be necessary for your Journey, as well Provisions as Skins for Shoes &amp;c.</P>
<P>To Morrow will be the last day of the Week, and the next Day will be GOD's Day, so you had best tarry till Monday morning; but I don't say this to put you out of your Way. You shall do as you please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Auountaurcsaunkee Indian Speaker.</SPEAKER>
<P> We return thanks for the Care Your Exceilency has taken of us, and for the Present of the Government.</P>
<P>Your Excellency has minded us of Our Duty, and we shall keep it in mind and observe it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I drink King GEORGE's Health, and wish you Health and Happiness.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ountaussoogoe.</SPEAKER>
<P> I Salute the Governour and all the Gentlemen here. I have been so handsomely treated since I have been with you, that I have almost fancied my self to be in Heaven, and I shall not be able to forbear Weeping when I leave the Governour.</P>
</SP>
<P>The Present was delivered, and the Indians dined with His Excellency &amp;c. under the Tent.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="day">
<PB N="14" REF="003916_0014_10035515D64A2958"/>
<HEAD>Saturday <HI>August</HI> 30. 1735. The Conference Continued.</HEAD>
<P>PRESENT</P>
<P>His Excellency <HI>Jonathan Belcher,</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR></P>
<P>Captain General and Governour in Chief, &amp;c.</P>
<P><HI>Cuncaupot</HI> Captain, and others of the <HI>Houssatonnoc</HI> Tribe.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Am glad to see you this Morning: I hope you are all in good Health. I shall now make you a particular Answer to what you said to me yesterday.</P>
<P><HI>My good Friends of</HI> Houssatonnoc,</P>
<P>I take very well the Expressions of your Duty and Loyalty to Our com∣mon Father the great King GEORGE, and I shall do my self the Honour of giving Him the Account of it; and you may be assured He will always look on you as his Children and good Subjects, and I shall think it my Duty as his Governour and Representative to let you feel upon all Occasions, the Advantage and Happiness of being under so good and gracious a Sovereign.</P>
<P>There are good Laws provided by this Government to save you and your Children from being hurt, or from their being taken away from you for Debt, and if you should meet with any difficulty on this or any other Ac∣count (as you have desired) you may with the greatest Freedom apply your selves to Col. <HI>Stoddard</HI> of <HI>Northampton,</HI> whom I have directed to take a particular Care of you, and you may depend on his favour and friendship, and that he will do every thing in his power that you may have Justice done you from time to time.</P>
<P><HI>My Friends and Children,</HI></P>
<P>Although I am much pleased with the Duty you express to my Royal Master King GEORGE; yet it rejoyces my Heart above all things that you are desirous to know and understand the Gospel of Our LORD JESUS CHRIST, who is GOD as well as Man, and the only SAVIOUR of all 
<PB N="15" REF="003916_0015_10034BBB5D7050E0"/>
Men; by the Knowledge of His Glorious Gospel, and by living in Obedi∣ence to it, you will become good Subjects to the KING of Kings, and be led in the Way to be happy here, and eternally so in a better World.</P>
<P>I am thankful to GOD, and well pleased with you that you so kindly receive and entertain the Ministers of JESUS CHRIST, who have been sent among you, and more particularly Mr. <HI>Sargent,</HI> and also your School∣Master Mr. <HI>Woodbridge.</HI> These Gentlemen are sent to you by an honoura∣ble Company of Gentlemen in <HI>Old England,</HI> who alone are at the Charge of their Preaching to you and Instructing you; and as I am One of their Agents here, I think it is a Respect and Honour due to them to let you know this, that you may in due time express your thankfulness for their pious Care and Compassion to your Souls.</P>
<P>And I must also take Notice to you how the GOD of the Spirits of all Flesh, seems to be encouraging and supporting your worthy Minister in the difficult Undertaking he is engaged in for your best Happiness, and I expect you will carefully attend upon his Instructions, and always pay him great respect and honour.</P>
<P>To morrow will be the Lord's Day, and the time intended for the Ordi∣nation of Mr. <HI>Sargent</HI> to the special Work of a Minister of JESUS CHRIST among you; and that you and your Children may thereafter as you may become worthy, enjoy the priviledge and happiness of the holy Sacra∣ments of Baptism and the Lord's Supper; and I pray GOD so to succeed the Endeavours used with you as to recover you from a state of Darkness, to the clear Light of his blessed Gospel.</P>
<P>I have been sometimes informed that you live remote from one another, and that you are not accommodated with Land sufficient to support your Families: This Matter I shall lay before the great Council of this Govern∣ment, and recommend to them the giving you Lands to Settle you more conveniently and compact, and what may be enough for your living com∣fortably upon; and at the same time I shall recommend your whole People to the special Care and Favour of this Government.</P>
<P>All I have said to you from Our first meeting here shall be printed, and then be sent to you, that you may as often as you please refresh your Memories with it.</P>
<P>I expect you to be very careful to morrow in observing the LORD's DAY, It is GOD's Day, and always to be kept holy, and you must attend the publick Worship both parts of the Day: You shall have a Place by Your Selves, that you may the better see Mr. <HI>Sargent</HI>'s Ordination.</P>
<P>I have nothing more to say at present.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="16" REF="003916_0016_10035519363DF898"/>
<SPEAKER>Captain <HI>Cuncaup<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Father,,</HI> We can't but thank you for the Love and Care you have taken of us as to Our Knowledge of the Gospel.</P>
<P><HI>Sir, Father,</HI> We can't but return Our humble thanks for the Kindness shewn us, while we have been here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I now deliver you the Government's Present.</P>
<P>After the LORD's DAY is over you shall be going homewards whenever you please, and you shall be provided with Necessaries for your Journey; and while you stay here you shall be kindly entertained.</P>
<P>I intend to go away next Monday; and if you would say any thing to me in the mean time by Mr. <HI>Williams,</HI> he will tell me; and I would have you dine with me to Day.</P>
<P>I drink King GEORGE's Health to you, and wish you Health and Prosperity.</P>
</SP>
<P>The Indians drink the King's Health, and return the Salutation.</P>
<P><HI>Ompawmet</HI> One of the Chiefs of this Tribe being Sick, sent his Son to inform His Excellency he could not wait on him Personally, but had sent him to thank the Governour for his Favours to their Tribe.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="day">
<HEAD>Saturday <HI>August</HI> 30. 1735. The Conference Continued.</HEAD>
<P>PRESENT.</P>
<P>His Excellency <HI>Jonathan Belcher,</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR></P>
<P>Captain General and Governour in Chief, &amp;c.</P>
<P><HI>Marsequunt,</HI> and the Two other Chiefs, and the rest of the <HI>Scautacooks,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Naunautookeau</HI> Indian Speaker.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>OUr Father and the Governour.</HI> We have considered what Your Excellency said to us the day before yesterday, and we take great Pleasure in it.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Lays down three</HI> Beaver Skins <HI>in token thereof.</HI></STAGE>
<P><PB N="17" REF="003916_0017_10034BC45B1DE118"/>
Furthermore, <HI>Father—the Governour</HI> — In all you have said we adhere.</P>
<STAGE><HI>And in token thereof lays down three</HI> Beaver Skins.—</STAGE>
<P><HI>Our Father,</HI> We thank Your Excellency, that ever since we have had Know∣ledge of THE WAY it has been kept very Streight without any Crook; and we thank Your Excellency you have kept it so very plain and clear.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Lays down three</HI> Beaves Skins <HI>in token thereof.</HI></STAGE>
<P>We pray Your Excellency, that as it has formerly been agreed that Your Excellency has been <HI>Our Father,</HI> and We Your Children, so Our hearty desire is that that <HI>Agreement</HI> may be continued.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Lays down three</HI> Bever Skins <HI>in token thereof.</HI></STAGE>
<P>We have done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I hope you are all in good Health.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Indians.</SPEAKER>
<P> We are all well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Governour.</SPEAKER>
<P> I hope you are entertained to your own Satisfaction. I take particular Notice of what you have said now. I depend you will always continue faithful Subjects to King GEORGE, and then you will have the Favour and Protection of this Government; You shall always be treated like the rest of the Children of this Country. I am glad you are come near to the Fort to live, and I shall endeavour you shall have Land to live on.</P>
<P>You must carefully and diligently attend on the Instructions of Mr. <HI>Hins∣dale</HI> your Minister. And in token and confirmation of all I have said to you, I deliver you this Belt.</P>
<STAGE>The Governour delivers them a Belt of <HI>Wampure.</HI></STAGE>
<P>To morrow is the LORD's DAY, I expect you keep your selves sober, and attend on the publick Worship of GOD at the Meeting House.</P>
<P>I shall be glad to hear from you by Capt. <HI>Kellogg,</HI> whenever you have any thing to say to the Governour. And whenever you have a mind to it, I shall be glad to see any of you at <HI>Boston.</HI></P>
<P>And in token of the Friendship of this Government, there is the Present They have sent you.</P>
<P>I drink King GEORGE's Health to you, and wish you all Prosperity.</P>
</SP>
<P>The Indians manifested great Satisfaction in what the Governour said, and returned the Salutation.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Weenepauk.</SPEAKER>
<P> We return Your Excellency thanks for all Favours, and we thank GOD Almighty that he has given us Opportunity to see Your Excel∣lency, and so many Gentlemen with you.</P>
<P>Though we are ignorant and not capable of seeing for want of Under∣standing, yet we praise GOD that he has fixed a Day—this Day; and the time of Day—<HI>about Noon</HI> — When the Sun shines so bright upon us.</P>
</SP>
<P><PB N="18" REF="003916_0018_1003551AC10C99B8"/>
Here follows the Order of the Proceedure in the Ordination of Mr. <HI>Sar∣gent,</HI> within mentioned. <HI>viz.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="account">
<OPENER><DATELINE><HI>Deerfield,</HI> <DATE><HI>September</HI> 1<HI>st.</HI> 1735.</DATE></DATELINE></OPENER>
<P>YEsterday being the LORD's DAY, the Reverend Mr. <HI>John Sargent,</HI> the Gentleman that has been sometime preaching to the <HI>Houssatonnoc</HI> Indians, was solemnly set apart, and Ordained to the Work of the Ministry in presence of His Excellency Our GOVERNOUR, the honourable His Majesty's Council, and a Number of the Gentlemen of the honourable House of Representatives, who accompanied His Excellency at the Confe∣rence with the Indians; and also a very numerous Assembly being present, both of English and Indians.</P>
<P>The <HI>Houssatonnoc</HI> Indians being seated by themselves in one of the Galle∣ries of the Meeting House, many of the Indians of the <HI>Cagnawaga</HI> and <HI>Scautacock</HI> Tribes with the <HI>Mobeegs</HI> being also present; the whole Affair was carried on with great decency and solemnity.</P>
<P>The Ministers that managed the Ordination were the Reverend Mr. <HI>Williams</HI> of <HI>Hatfield,</HI> Mr. <HI>Appleton</HI> of <HI>Cambridge,</HI> Mr. <HI>Williams</HI> of <HI>Long∣Meadow</HI> (<HI>Springfield</HI>) Mr. <HI>Hinsdale,</HI> and Mr. <HI>Ashley</HI>; the said Gentlemen having the day before the Ordination made Inquiry of Mr. <HI>Sargent,</HI> and re∣ceived satisfaction as to his Orthodoxy.</P>
<P>The Reverend Mr. <HI>Ashley</HI> began with Prayer, the Reverend Mr. <HI>Appleton</HI> preached a suitable Sermon to the Occasion from 2 <HI>Tim.</HI> 2.21. The Reverend Mr. <HI>Williams</HI> of <HI>Hatfield</HI> as Moderator opened the Affair, and in a parti∣cular manner addressed himself to His Excellency the GOVERNOUR, as Head of the Commissioners of the honourable Company for Propagating the Gospel among the Indians in <HI>New England,</HI> and Parts adjacent; and asked Him whether it was his desire that Mr. <HI>Sargent</HI> should be set apart to the Work of the Ministry (among the Indians at <HI>Houssatonnoc</HI>) by Ordination; and His Excellency said, it was.</P>
<P>The Moderator then proceeded to Mr. <HI>Sargent</HI>'s Consent herein &amp;c. And then Hands were laid upon Mr. <HI>Sargent</HI> by all the Ministers before named. The Reverend Mr. <HI>Williams</HI> of <HI>Hatfield</HI> made the first Prayer after Impositi∣on of Hands, and then gave the Charge; the Reverend Mr. <HI>Appleton</HI> made the other Prayer; and the Reverend Mr. <HI>Williams</HI> of <HI>Long Meadow</HI> gave the Right Hand of Fellowship to Mr. <HI>Sargent.</HI></P>
<P>After which Mr. <HI>Williams</HI> turned himself to the <HI>Houssatonnoc</HI> Indian Tribe, who were Seated in the Gallery by themselves; and asked them if they 
<PB N="19" REF="003916_0019_1003551F12C3FC50"/>
were desirous of having Mr. <HI>Sargent</HI> for their Minister; that if they were, they would shew some Sign or Manifestation thereof: Whereupon they all rose up by one Consent, and with grave as well as chearful Countenan∣ces signified their full, and hearty Acceptance of him.</P>
<P>The Sermon in the Afternoon was from <HI>Isaiah</HI> 2.4. by the Reverend Mr. <HI>Williams</HI> of <HI>Long Meadow.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<OPENER><DATELINE>Prov. of the Mass. Bay.</DATELINE></OPENER>
<P>THE aforegoing Conference was taken as it passed by and between His Excellency JONATHAN BELCHER, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> Captain General &amp;c. and the respective <HI>Indians</HI> within mentioned.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>By His Excellency's Command. John Wainwright, <HI>Cler.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

