<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2008-06-17</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Check for blanks. Checked for signatures. Checked for #s. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Corrected 4 $-groups. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N17311">
<STC T="E">22361</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99027657</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="022361_0000_0FB8483EA2F81A48"/>
<PB REF="022361_0001_0FB848402333E6E0" MS="y"/>
<P>A PLAN FOR A SCHOOL On an Establishment similar to that at ACKWORTH, in <HI>Yorkshire, Great-Britain,</HI> varied to suit the Circumstances of the Youth within the Limits of the YEARLY-MEETING For <HI>Pennsylvania</HI> and <HI>New-Jersey:</HI> introduced with the Sense of Friends in <HI>New-England,</HI> on the Subject of Education; AND An Account of some Schools in <HI>Great-Britain:</HI> TO WHICH IS ADDED, OBSERVATIONS AND REMARKS, Intended for the Consideration of Friends.</P>
<P><HI>PHILADELPHIA:</HI> PRINTED BY <HI>JOSEPH CRUKSHANK.</HI> M DCC XC.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="plan">
<PB REF="022361_0002_0FB848436A93AC68"/>
<HEAD>A PLAN FOR A SCHOOL.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>SECTION I.</HEAD>
<P>THAT there has been a considerable degree of attention given to the subject of education, and a number of useful schools established, nearly agree∣able to the recommendation of the Yearly Meeting, under religious-minded tutors; also a growing con∣cern in the minds of many friends, to provide for the due instruction of the rising youth, has been ob∣served with satisfaction.</P>
<P>Yet when the state of the young people within the extensive limits of this Yearly Meeting, is taken into consideration, with the care manifested by Friends in Great-Britain, in the establishment of schools for the
<PB N="4" REF="022361_0003_0FB848461B73C948" MS="y"/>
benefit of their young people not in affluent circum∣stances, as well as others, and attending to the weigh∣ty reasons which have been urged on various occasions in favor of a more guarded course of instruction than is customary, it has been apprehended, that a use might arise from having an abstract of what relates to those schools in Great-Britain, mentioned in a publication made by Dr. John Fothergill deceased, on the institu∣tion at Ackworth, brought more generally into the view of society at large, with the sense of Friends in Great-Britain and America, on the subject of board∣ing schools, and the necessity for a greater care in the education of their young people: for which purpose I have collected such materials as would enable me to answer the expectation of Friends, who may be desirous of information on this interesting subject. And as the Meeting for Sufferings, in New-England, has given the sense of their Yearly Meeting on this head, so early as the year 1690, with some judicious observations, calculated to recommend a greater at∣tention to the education of their youth, I shall, therefore, introduce the subject with a quotation from their epistle dated the 11th of the 11th month, 1782, signed Moses Brown,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Note,</HI> This Epistle contains an account of the recommenda∣tion of then Yearly Meeting to form an establishment or establish∣ments nearly similar to that at ACKWORTH, anno 178O.</NOTE> as follows, viz.</P>
<P>Their Yearly Meeting recommend
<Q>to Friends every where, as far as they are able or capable,
<PB N="5" REF="022361_0004_0FB84847A0722ED0"/>
to provide school-masters and mistresses who are faithful Friends, to teach and instruct their chil∣dren, and not to send them to such schools where they are taught the corrupt ways, manners, fashions, and language of the world, &amp;c.</Q> To which the Meeting for Sufferings add, <Q>The <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of attention to which advice has occasioned the well-concerned amongst us, for the happiness of the rising generation, and prosperity of truth, to mourn for the hurt thereby sustained in our so∣ciety—Our principles lead to a separation from the world, its customs, habits, language, and manners; how, then, can we hope for faithful successors in our posterity, or that they will come up in principles and practice agreeable thereto, if we continue so far to neglect the <HI>early</HI> care of our offspring, as to send them to schools, where principles and practices so repugnant are taught.— It is essential to the continuance of every society upon the foundation of its rise and establishment, that its first principles be often recurred to. The principles of light and truth, which first separated our antients from the world, early led George Fox into a sight of the necessity of a separation from the world in the education of succeeding ge∣nerations.</Q></P>
<P>Which advice, if attended to in some instances, has never been so fully regarded as its importance requires; owing to various circumstances which can∣not
<PB N="6" REF="022361_0005_0FB84849B7174580"/>
but be obvious to the well-informed, and which likewise appears to have been the case in Great-Britain, from what has been observed by Doctor Fo∣thergill, respecting the schools amongst them; and as an account of these schools may prove satisfactory to many, and shew the necessity for a greater care in the education of our youth, I have been large in my quotations respecting them, more especially as the inconveniences which have attended most of them, led to the foundation of that noble institution at Ackworth, and appear to be the same which we have experienced in America, with other circum∣stances which are mentioned.</P>
<P>In the account of these schools we are informed
<Q>of one at Gildersome in Yorkshire, which was set on foot by the activity of Friends, who have the immediate care of it, and from whom it has re∣ceived a generous support; yet as it is only pro∣vided for by the liberality of friends within the limits of the neighbourhood, or of the Monthly Meeting of Brighouse, by whose generosity it was set on foot, it was thought the plan was <HI>too con∣fined</HI> to admit of that usefulness, which that at Ackworth promised: especially as the <HI>price of education</HI> was necessarily greater, as was found on experience; altho' by the activity of Friends, who had the care of it, Gildersome school has proved beneficial to many children, and occasi∣oned many to be brought from a great dis∣tance.</Q></P>
<P><PB N="7" REF="022361_0006_0FB8484AA2A34F40"/>
<Q>Besides this, there is another house for the edu∣cation of Friends' children, which has been founded in London, and supported almost solely by Friends of the Quarterly Meeting of London, that is, Friends' school-house and workhouse at Clerken∣well; the following circumstances are mentioned respecting it: many well-disposed persons, on con∣sidering the state of the poor in LONDON, appre∣hended that many of the aged, as well as the chil∣dren of divers, might be better supported and more suitably educated, were they collected toge∣ther in one place, where every thing necessary for their well-being might be provided, more to their comfort than at their own habitations. Accord∣ingly about the year 1700, this business was un∣dertaken and liberally proceeded in, and was so prudently conducted, that it drew many persons of note of other persuasions, to visit it; which was the means of deriving credit to the society, and of exciting a degree of the like attention to such useful undertakings.</Q></P>
<P><Q>A committee of eighteen Friends, chosen from the several Monthly Meetings, meet for the most part once a month to transact the business of the house; besides weekly visitors who inspect at <HI>un∣certain seasons</HI> the conduct of the family.</Q></P>
<P><Q>Under such management it cannot be wonder∣ed at, that the establishment should become con∣siderable.
<PB N="8" REF="022361_0007_0FB8484C21F88498"/>
The fund is about £. 20,000; arising from the generosity and bequests of individuals among Friends in that metropolis, a very few in∣stances excepted; in which sum is included a le∣gacy left by our deceased friend, Devereaux Bow∣ley of London, of THREE THOUSAND POUNDS.</Q></P>
<P>But it appears from a local circumstance that the benefits derived from this institution have not been in every respect equal to the hopes of Friends;
<Q>too few of the youth educated, the number considered, having turned out useful or reputable members of society.</Q></P>
<P>Two causes are assigned for this disappointment; one is,
<Q>the scholars were permitted too frequently to be in the streets, also had liberty at times to visit their friends and relations, not always the most exemplary in their conduct; by which means they contracted ill manners and worse prac∣tices, and returned to the house in every respect worse than when they left it." Another cause as∣signed is, "that a considerable number of antient poor are maintained under the same roof▪ some of whom have been brought to this situation by their misconduct, and consequently, not the most likely persons to set the children a commendable example.</Q>
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">At this house the poor of the society of London are em∣ployed and provided for.</NOTE></P>
<P><PB N="9" REF="022361_0008_0FB8484D9E80C6E0"/>One other school is mentioned which shows the pernicious influence of bad example, which is wor∣thy of notice;
<Q>A school-house was built, an able and well-qualified master procured, and three thou∣sand pounds generously subscribed by Friends, for a day-school: but such was the ill effects of the children <HI>mixing with others,</HI> so much were they hurt by bad examples and bad company, that those who had engaged in the generous design, found it necessary to abandon it, merely, as it ap∣peared, from this circumstance.</Q></P>
<P><Q>The school at Clerkenwell has lately had divers bequests made to it for the purpose of increasing apprentice-fees, and further encouragement to such children of both sexes as may deserve it after a certain age, and some regulations have been made to prevent the youth mixing with others; with a view to preserve them from the influence of bad example.</Q></P>
<P>How far Friends' care in this respect may be at∣tended with the desired benefits in that large metro∣polis, we are yet to learn in the conduct of the youth who may be brought up at that school: that consi∣derable endeavours were not used previous to the publication of these remarks, cannot be urged as an objection to a more select and guarded education, as will appear by the following short account of
<PB N="10" REF="022361_0009_0FB8484F2F20A2E0"/>
Friends' labor to preserve them in <HI>so exposed a situa∣tion.</HI> "There is not," proceeds the said Friend,
<Q>an institution existing, upon which more labor and disinterested endeavours, that every thing might be managed with order, oeconomy, reputa∣tion, and general benefit, have been employed, than in this house (Clerkenwell:) such is the ne∣cessity of preserving youth from the influence of bad example, if we hope to preserve them in in∣nocence and simplicity.</Q></P>
<P>The importance of a right education is such, that it is no occasion of surprise when we consider the failure of those institutions already mentioned, of answering all the salutary purposes expected from them, with the concern of friends, as mentioned in the following extract from the Minutes of the Year∣ly Meeting of Great-Britain in 1777, that they should be induced to turn their attention to this sub∣ject on an enlarged plan, so as to obviate the incon∣veniences which they had so discouragingly experi∣enced. The extract is as follows, viz.</P>
<P><Q>It is the renewed concern of this Meeting to recommend a care for the offspring of such pa∣rents, whose earnings or incomes are so small as to render them incapable of giving their children a suitable and guarded education, and that especi∣ally from home, by which they may be prevent∣ed from mixing with others who are not of our
<PB N="11" REF="022361_0010_0FB848519B0B2050"/>
religious persuasion, which so often leads into hurt∣ful habits, from which they are not afterwards easily reclaimed: and as some of our members may in∣cautiously permit their offspring to suffer this great loss, rather than apply for assistance from their Monthly Meetings; it is recommended to Friends in every Monthly Meeting, to seek out such of their members as may be thus straitened, and ad∣minister to their help, and it is desired that such will receive the salutary aid with a willing mind, and thankfulness to the great Author of all good. And it being the judgment of this meeting that encouragement for boarding schools, suitable for the education of children whose parents are not in affluence, will be advantageous, the considera∣tion of a plan for that purpose is referred to the Meeting for Sufferings, to be laid before this Meeting next year; to which Friends in the coun∣try are also desired to join their attention and as∣sistance.</Q></P>
<P>These circumstances gave occasion to the pur∣chase of a large and commodious building which had been erected at a place called ACKWORTH, in Yorkshire, for a Foundling HOSPITAL, but through mismanagement had been left unsupport∣ed.</P>
<P><Q>This building with the premises was offered for sale for £. 7000, a purchaser having appeared
<PB N="12" REF="022361_0011_0FB84852E3E11EA0"/>
who offered £. 6800 for it: in consequence of which the matter was laid before the Meeting for Sufferings. This Meeting, upon deliberation, were desirous to refer the subject to the considera∣tion of the ensuing Yearly Meeting; but this was necessarily prevented by the unexpected ap∣pearance of the other purchaser: this induced a number of Friends to step forward with an offer to bear the Meeting for Sufferings harmless, should the Yearly Meeting decline the purchase: this be∣ing accepted, a contract for the buildings, &amp;c. was made, and the matter reserved for the deter∣mination of the Yearly Meeting in 1778, when it was agreed to, and became a society concern.</Q></P>
<P>I shall be more particular in what relates to this school, as it furnishes us with an instance of great liberality in Friends of Great-Britain, and the regu∣lations intended to be (and which afterwards were) introduced into that school are proper for imitation, and may be considered as part of the Plan of education now proposed for the young people in these parts: for which reasons I hope it will nei∣ther prove unacceptable nor useless. I shall there∣fore proceed.</P>
<P>Previous to the Yearly Meeting coming to a de∣termination,
<Q>a committee of one Friend out of every county, together with the Meeting for Suf∣ferings, with any others who chose to attend, was
<PB N="13" REF="022361_0012_0FB8485527E47E70"/>
early appointed to take this weighty subject into consideration, after various meetings of their com∣mittee, a report was agreed to, recommending, besides the purchase of the buildings, &amp;c. a sub∣scription to be set on foot during the sitting of the Meeting, by donations, by annuities on two lives, at 5 per cent. each,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The person who chooses to make his subscription in this way, names any two persons, and fixes a sum, on which he agrees to pay 5 per cent. per annum during the continuance of their two lives, be they longer or shorter.</NOTE> and by bills of admis∣sion at eight guineas each:<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">It is apprehended, the person who subscribes in this way is entitled, for every eight guineas he subscribes, to a ticket, which will give admittance to any person into the school for one year to whom he pleases to present it, provided they are approved of by the committee nominated for that purpose.</NOTE> after deliberate con∣sideration, the report was received by the Yearly Meeting, and the proposed subscription was be∣gun, and strongly recommended to the coun∣ties.</Q></P>
<P>Upon which proceedings our friend John Fother∣gill observes;
<Q>The great unanimity that prevailed in the several sittings of the committee, apparently proceeding from a just sense of the want of some such institution; the cordial, tho' not hasty, con∣currence of the Yearly Meeting with the report of the committee; and the generous exertions of many Friends in consequence of this concurrence, afforded such an indication of the propriety of the
<PB N="14" REF="022361_0013_0FB848572370A5A8"/>
concern, that FOUR THOUSAND POUNDS was sub∣scribed in three or four days, and dispelled all the doubts he had entertained about it.</Q></P>
<P>ACKWORTH is situate in Yorkshire, about 180 miles from London; the building appears by a front view given of it, in the account from which these extracts were made, nearly to resemble the state-house in Philadelphia, and equally extensive, besides having two wings, which, with the centre buildings, form a hollow square: the whole being in good repair, large, commodious, and judiciously con∣trived; every convenience in the arrangement of the apartments seems to have been attended to, and no kind of office or out-house omitted, which might be necessary for the accommodation of a large family; hence it appears to have been a circumstance peculi∣arly favorable to Friends' views, that this building with the appurtenances was to be had at this time.</P>
<P>By a ground-plot it appears, that there was about 85 acres of land belonging to the premises, and pur∣chased with them, containing a garden and other in∣closures: since then there has been added about 40 acres more, which they were enabled to purchase by legacies left for that particular purpose.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">In future it is intended that all donations or bequests of £. 50. or upwards, be placed out so as to form a fund, and the principal not to be applied towards the current expenses of the institution.</NOTE></P>
<LIST>
<PB N="15" REF="022361_0014_0FB84859C232E590"/>
<HEAD>The centre building contains the following rooms, viz.</HEAD>
<LABEL>The boys' dining-room</LABEL>
<ITEM>70 by 23 feet.</ITEM>
<LABEL>The girls' ditto</LABEL>
<ITEM>70 by 23 ditto.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Court ditto</LABEL>
<ITEM>40 by 26 ditto.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Passage</LABEL>
<ITEM> </ITEM>
<LABEL>Apothecary's shop and Clerk's office</LABEL>
<ITEM>30 by 20 ditto.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Store-room</LABEL>
<ITEM> </ITEM>
<LABEL>Masters' apartments</LABEL>
<ITEM> </ITEM>
<LABEL>Housekeeper's room</LABEL>
<ITEM>20 by 20 ditto.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Servants' Hall</LABEL>
<ITEM> </ITEM>
<LABEL>Pastry room</LABEL>
<ITEM> </ITEM>
<LABEL>Kitchen and back-kitchen</LABEL>
<ITEM>40 by 20 ditto.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Laundry</LABEL>
<ITEM> </ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The two wings contain</HEAD>
<ITEM>Four rooms chiefly made use of by the boys for carding, spinning, and other business.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three rooms for mantua-makers and school-mis∣tresses.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Five rooms, where the girls are employed in knit∣ting, spinning, sewing, reading, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM>With two apartments particularly intended for the use of the tailors and shoemakers.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><PB N="16" REF="022361_0015_0FB8485FD8F55BC8"/>
And there are on the premises,</P>
<P>A slaughter-house, cow-house, barn, bake-house, five pig cotes, two stables, and two other cow-houses, two necessaries, two coal-yards, and two farm-yards and stack-yards.</P>
<P>The management of this institution was originally committed to the Meeting for Sufferings, but is since under the direction of a large committee united with them, composed of representatives from the Quarter∣ly Meetings, of the agents of the institution for the several counties and places, the treasurer of the same, with the members of the London and county com∣mittees, who meet annually at Ackworth on the last fourth day of the seventh month in every year, for the purpose of making regulations, &amp;c.</P>
<P>The fund and provision made by Friends have been sufficient to enable them to pay for the estate, edu∣cate, victual, clothe, and accommodate upwards of 300 children, girls and boys, annually, for a num∣ber of years, besides making a proper compensation to the necessary masters, mistresses, and other persons employed, at what they consider a small expense to the children's parents or friends; and by reports made of the proceedings in this very laudable and beneficent work, there appear grounds to hope that it will prove an useful establishment, and not unwor∣thy the labor and patronage of Friends.</P>
<P><PB N="17" REF="022361_0016_0FB84863F77C6C08"/>
<Q>As this school was more particularly designed for the children of Friends not in affluent circumstan∣ces, it is intended to direct their education accord∣ingly, and to have them not only <HI>maintained and clothed,</HI> but instructed in reading, writing, and ac∣compts, as fully as the time allowed them will permit; some useful employment may be provided for the boys, according to their age, strength, ta∣lents, or as their condition may require. The girls will also be instructed in knitting, spinning, use∣ful needle-work, and in such domestic occupations as are suitable to their sex and stations.</Q></P>
<P>Our Friend before mentioned observes,
<Q>that as many Friends were not able to make the necessary provision for their offspring in such a way as would preserve them from the ill effects of mixing with corrupt company; and being apprized of this as well as many other circumstances," it is supposed "he was led to consider the subject of edu∣cation," in its fullest extent, "with a warm de∣sire to promote it;</Q>
in consequence of which he has left some profitable instructions, which those who are entrusted with the care of youth, would do well to attend to, and for their benefit I have subjoined some of the most necessary to be known, viz.</P>
<P>He says, that
<Q>it is the wish of those concerned, as he believes, by gentleness, kind and affectionate
<PB N="18" REF="022361_0017_0FB848650C5DAA28"/>
treatment, holding out encouragement and appro∣bation to the deserving, exerting the influence of the fear of shame,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Whether this may operate to the children's advantage, will altogether depend upon the qualification of the teacher.</NOTE> and by prompting them to acts of kindness and beneficence one towards another, to bring forward into the society and its service, a number of youth who may have been made ac∣quainted under such tuition, in degree, with the discipline of wisdom.</Q></P>
<P><Q>Many children amongst us (proceeds the said Friend) sustain a grievous loss by not being early and properly made acquainted with the principles we profess. For want of this instruction, they become too easy a prey to the customs of the world and its habitudes; and that which would be as a kind of hedge about them, and preserve from many temptations, is laid waste, and all the allurements of vice and folly suffered to seduce their affections to their ruin. For when they cease to be distinguished from others by their garb and deportment, they too often cease to be distinguish∣ed from the world by their morals, and the recti∣tude of their conduct.</Q></P>
<P><Q>It is therefore intended to make the children of both sexes acquainted with the history of the rise and progress of Friends, their sufferings, and
<PB N="19" REF="022361_0018_0FB848666ADA3700"/>
the indulgences granted them by the legislature, as well as the general doctrines of religion and morality," and to train them up in the knowledge of the sacred writings; on which there is this re∣mark: "Too few are the parents who can honestly say, that they train up their children in a godly conversation; in plainness of speech, behaviour, and apparel; and the frequent reading of the Holy Scriptures. Here (at Ackworth) care will be taken both of their principles and conduct: be∣sides, it is hoped that suitable opportunities will be embraced of cherishing in their tender minds, obedience to the inward principle of light and truth.</Q></P>
<P><Q>And as it is of great importance to habituate children from their infancy to silence and attenti∣on, not only as a preparative to their advance∣ment in a religious life, but as the ground-work of a well cultivated understanding, it will be par∣ticularly regarded.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">To watch over the human heart is a circumstance of greater importance than mankind in general seem to understand.</NOTE> We are almost the only pro∣fessors of Christianity, who acknowledge the use of this absolutely necessary introduction to Chri∣stian knowledge and Christian practice. To have the active minds of children early put under this kind of restraint, to be accustomed to turn their attention from external objects, and habituated to
<PB N="20" REF="022361_0019_0FB84867F3FE8430"/>
a degree of abstracted quiet, is a matter of great consequence, and may be of lasting benefit to them. To this they are inured in our assemblies, and to sit in silence with decency and composure. Tho' it cannot be supposed their young and active minds are always engaged as they ought to be, yet to be accustomed thus to stillness, and brought to curb and restrain the sallies of their youthful dis∣positions, is no small point gained towards fixing a habit of patient recollection, and a regard to de∣corum, which seldom forsakes those who have been accustomed to it, and have been properly in∣structed in this entrance to the school of wisdom, during the residue of their days.</Q></P>
<P><Q>If it was needful it might not be difficult to shew, from abundant authority and reason itself, the vast aid afforded to the improvement of the human mind, by early habits of silent attention. The most antient schools of philosophy taught and practised it; and the Scriptures are so full of pre∣cepts on this head, as ought to remove every ob∣jection to this necessary duty.</Q>
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">It has been thought that a use would arise from a care in the masters and mistresses, to have their schools adjourned with greater decorum than is generally the practice; and that a short pause previous thereto would afford them an opportunity, when necessary, to extend suitable reproof or encouragement, as well as to dismiss their scholars more in the quiet.</NOTE></P>
<P><PB N="21" REF="022361_0020_0FB8486A267F7FD0"/>To which he subjoins, as a further motive for en∣gaging in the undertaking,
<Q>And as there are many children, who, by the remoteness of their parents' situation from meetings, are destitute of such op∣portunities, it is another call to the society, to pre∣vent as much as possible the loss arising from such a circumstance. To this consideration it will not be improper to add another which is connected with it, and that is, the want of opportunities of sending their children to Friends' schools; by which means, if they have any learning at all af∣forded them, it is under the tuition of such as are mostly strangers to our principles, and the practices derived from them, plainness of speech, simplicity of manners, and that beginning of wis∣dom which is inspired by the fear of the Lord. On the contrary, they are liable to associate with such children as are unacquainted with all these things, taught to deride those who practise them, and live at large to appetite and custom: and how often does it happen that the children of Friends in such situations, bred up with unprincipled, li∣centious youth, form connexions with them, to their own great hurt, the distress of their parents, and the loss of many valuable members to society.</Q></P>
<P><Q>It is proposed, when the school is opened, a meeting for worship shall be held in the house <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Which is accordingly done.</NOTE>
<PB N="22" REF="022361_0021_0FB8486BBA7F4BC8"/>
every first-day morning and afternoon: likewise a meeting on the fourth day of the week, these times being judged most convenient.</Q></P>
<P>As an instance of the care which was intended to be taken with the youth in that school, the follow∣ing quotation may not be unacceptable, viz.</P>
<P><Q>Perhaps (says our Friend) there is nothing in the course of public education in the world, that so unfits men for that humble attention to the di∣vine monitor within, renders them such perfect strangers to the spirit of Christianity and all its happy effects, as the cultivation of a bold, unfeel∣ing disposition, under a notion of promoting man∣liness and courage: it too often sets aside that great defence and ornament of youth, a modest, ingenuous temper, accustoms them to throw off all the restraints of duty and affection, and at length to bid defiance to intreaty, admonition, and reproof. At Ackworth, endeavours will be used to form in the children a temper widely different, equally remote from a culpable fear and servility, and an audacity that knows no respect for order or authority.</Q></P>
<P>With respect to the dress of the children at that school, it is remarked,
<Q>The children at Ack∣worth are to wear the same kind of garments;
<PB N="23" REF="022361_0022_0FB8486DE3DF2E88"/>
regard being had to the dress of the different sexes;" he says, "for various reasons the propo∣sal is a good one. The children there ought to value themselves on no other superiority than that of behaving themselves better than others, both in respect to learning and conduct. They are all to consider themselves, and be considered, as the chil∣dren of one family, under the care of that body, which deeply interests itself in the welfare of them all. The riches, the poverty, the good or bad conduct of their connexions, must have no other regard paid to them, than such as may proceed from the necessity of guarding them from the in∣fluence of any circumstances prevailing to their future disadvantage.</Q></P>
<P>To conclude what relates to the subject of the children's education, I shall add the following ju∣dicious observation;
<Q>Tho' the children's improve∣ment in learning, their health, and other suita∣ble accommodations, are matters of great mo∣ment in such an institution as this, yet there is one of a superior nature, to promote a tender, teachable disposition, inuring them to bear that yoke in their youth, which will moderate their desires, and make way for the softening influence of divine good-will in their hearts, fitting them for the faithful discharge of every duty in life, yielding content in affliction, moderation in prospe∣rity, becoming at once the safeguard and ornament
<PB N="24" REF="022361_0023_0FB8486F6E8F9DE0"/>
of every stage in life, from youth to ripe old age.</Q></P>
<P><Q>This should be the constant, uniform endeavour of those who may be engaged in the immediate care and service of the family, in whatever station they may be placed: for the encouragement, of those who may be thus engaged, he adds, "it is hoped they will bear some little difficulties, should they occur, as endeavours will be used to pre∣vent them, so that the good of the youth com∣mitted to their care shall be built as little as pos∣sible on the sufferings of any individual.</Q></P>
<P>As these observations will convey some idea of the education which is desired for our young people, and the nature of the institution which is now proposed, I hope it will be needless to apologize for their length, and it may be sufficient to add, that school has been conducted nearly agreeable to these princi∣ples, much to the satisfaction of Friends, as far as we learn, and there is a pleasing prospect of its con∣tinuing extensively useful to society, and beneficial to the youth who may be educated therein.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="section">
<PB N="25" REF="022361_0024_0FB84872767B1138"/>
<HEAD>SECTION II.</HEAD>
<P>TO ripen this concern, and to prepare it for the consideration of Friends in a collective capaci∣ty, it was supposed that a PLAN more particularly accommodated to our circumstances would be useful. With this view the following outlines of one are sug∣gested. If it should not meet with general approba∣tion in all its parts, it is to be hoped that it will not prove a discouragement to the undertaking; as it cannot be doubted, that a solid committee of the Yearly Meeting would be enabled to improve upon any hints that might be offered for consideration by an individual, and that such parts as may appear ex∣ceptionable, would be either explained or expunged, and such others added, as would bring it into a state to meet with general acceptance.</P>
<P>The PLAN is as follows:</P>
<P N="1">I. It has been thought advisable that a standing committee be appointed by the Yearly Meeting, vested with all the necessary powers <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The epistle on this subject from the Meeting for Sufferings, in New-England, particularizes what is meant by these powers, and may be referred to, should information be wanting.</NOTE> to transact the business relating to this concern in its fullest extent; their proceedings and conduct to be subject to the direction and revision of the said Meeting, as it may think proper.</P>
<P N="2"><PB N="26" REF="022361_0025_0FB848742EC7CCB0"/>II. That a tract of good land of 1000 acres be purchased in a healthy situation, not too remote from the seat of the Yearly Meeting, where suitable build∣ings be provided or erected, according to the views of Friends, so as to accommodate the scholars and all others concerned on the premises, and the land occupied in such way as will best contribute to afford supplies to the scholars, and promote the institu∣tion.</P>
<P N="3">III. That it be recommended to Friends in the subordinate Meetings to encourage a free, voluntary, and liberal contribution for this purpose, which should be continued from time to time until a permanent and adequate provision be obtained.</P>
<P>Note, I have proposed a much larger tract of land for the use of the institution amongst us than they have at Ackworth, for these reasons: land of equal quality is to be had at a much lower price here, where it would suit for such a purpose, than in Great-Bri∣tain; and the product of land properly occupied would afford a better return for money than could be had in any other way, for the supply of the fami∣ly with necessary food, fuel, timber, &amp;c. and after having overcome the difficulty of a first purchase, would become a permanent and improving estate; and a foundation might be laid for a settlement where artificers and husbandmen would be collected to in∣struct many youth in various branches of business,
<PB N="27" REF="022361_0026_0FB848756020F1F0"/>
free from the corrupt examples which a mixture of different people might occasion, as well as other ad∣vantages that would probably attend it, which need not be mentioned.</P>
<P N="4">IV. That regular minutes be kept of all pro∣ceedings and expenditures, with the sums subscribed, or the estates granted, and which may be receiv∣ed, or remain in reversion; with all other matters relative to, and for the support of, this establish∣ment; so as to afford a clear view of the state of the institution and fund belonging to it; in order that proper endeavours may be used, and suitable advice extended from year to year, for the encouragement and support of the undertaking.</P>
<P N="5">V. Besides useful learning, the boys and girls are to be instructed in such manual business and do∣mestic employments of every kind, as may be con∣sistent with Friends' prospects of usefulness and im∣provement, or redound to the benefit and reputa∣tion of the institution.</P>
<P N="6">VI. In providing of buildings regard is to be had to such as may be necessary for tradesmen and others, whose assistance may be required, either for labor or the instruction and accommodation of the youth, <HI>ac∣cording to the extent of the fund,</HI> as well as for the accommodation of those who may have occasion to resort to, or be resident at, the place; and it is to
<PB N="28" REF="022361_0027_0FB84876E1F0BC68"/>
be observed, that none be permitted to be resident there, but such as are of sober, exemplary conduct, and pious conversation; that the youth may be in∣structed in such way that there may be a rational prospect of their being preserved in innocence.</P>
<P N="7">VII. That a steward and clerk, with a man and wo∣man Friend to act as superintendants, be appointed; the two latter continually or occasionally to inspect into the state of the schools, the places of accommo∣dation and maintenance of the youth, and report to the committee of the Yearly Meeting, the state of things from time to time, extend the advice of the said committee with their rules and orders to all concerned, and see to the due execution of the same.</P>
<P>Besides these general heads of a plan, some other rules will be necessary for the government of the schools, and accommodation of the families; the discipline to be observed by the youth, and order to be established where they are boarded; as well as for the improvement to be made on the premises, and management of the farms, with a view to pro∣vide for the support of the family, tend to the im∣provement of the young people, and add a reputation to the school; likewise to preserve order and esta∣blish a necessary system of oeconomy, so as to afford a proper supply without profusion or waste: all which should be attended to by the general committee of
<PB N="29" REF="022361_0028_0FB84878BB1BE1B8"/>
the Yearly Meeting, as there may be occasion, with such other matters as may be needful.</P>
<P>Those very pertinent remarks made by our valued friend John Fothergill deceased, with a view to pro∣mote the moral and religious improvement of the youth, will no doubt claim the attention of those entrusted with the management of this institution, as objects of superior consequence; or any hints for that purpose which may be suggested by Friends of experience.</P>
<P>To enter into every minute circumstance which will be proper for their attention, cannot be necessa∣ry on this occasion: yet, as a few leading rules for the government of those concerned, may be of fu∣ture use, and afford to others a more satisfactory view of the design, as well as prove an encourage∣ment to some to unite in their endeavours to pro∣mote it, or induce them to entrust the care of their tender offspring at such a place, the following are subjoined by way of information, viz.</P>
<P N="1">I. The houses for the accommodation of the youth are proposed to be of a moderate size, and at proper distances from each other, with necessary apart∣ments, &amp;c. so as to afford comfortable accommodati∣ons to the children, who ought not to be crowded in too great numbers together, that they may have
<PB N="30" REF="022361_0029_0FB8487AC3AA9170"/>
the benefit of a private residence and a public educa∣tion at the same time.</P>
<P N="2">II. That each family consist of not more than the man and woman Friend who are to board the scho∣lars, with their children, and the necessary domestics, and <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The number is left for future consideration.</NOTE> <HI>pupils,</HI> whereby they may with more ease extend the necessary care and attention to the conduct of the youth; apply suitable advice, admonition, or reproof, or occasionally, by kind and gentle treat∣ment, encourage those who may require it; besides, the health of the young people would be more like∣ly to be preserved, when not too numerous in one family; their accommodations made more agreeable, as well as more suitable to their age, so that in case of indisposition they might be better attended, and their wants more suitably relieved: nor would it be less conducive to their general improvement; as the girls might, by rotation, as they became able, be as∣sisting in domestic employments, so as to qualify them in turn to fill up those stations in society which may fall to their allotment, with propriety: the boys likewise may find a share, and not unprofitably, in those duties, added to the care of the gardens, &amp;c. whereby they would find employment for their leisure hours, be taught to fill up a painful vacancy by some profitable labor, derive instruction from the obser∣vation of the works of Providence, be benefited by
<PB N="31" REF="022361_0030_0FB8487C9B5BB150" MS="y"/>
moderate exercise, and probably enjoy
<Q>a healthy mind with a healthy body:</Q>
and might have afford∣ed to many young people who have been brought up in cities or large towns, advantages which cannot be obtained in such places.</P>
<P N="3">III. It is supposed that the school-houses for the boys should be situate at a convenient distance from those for the girls, to prevent any improper familiari∣ties: likewise that they be boarded in different hou∣ses; yet not so far separated but that an innocent and cheerful intercourse may be allowed and en∣couraged under suitable inspection at proper sea∣sons:</P>
<P N="4">IV. And that each one employed be generally confined to their respective duties. The youth had better not be boarded with their tutors; as it might draw their attention from their schooling, and occasion a greater burden than ought to be the share of any individual, besides other inconveniences which might attend it; it is therefore proposed, that the persons who board the youth should confine them∣selves to the care of their wards, and see that they give proper attendance at school, and also watch over their general conduct and attention to religi∣ous duties.</P>
<P N="5">V. Care should likewise be taken to prevent rambling in the scholars, as well as unprofitable
<PB N="32" REF="022361_0031_0FB8487DF47B5168"/>
collections of neighbouring people at leisure seasons, in such a manner as might disturb the order and quiet of the family.</P>
<P>Having taken into consideration such circumstan∣ces as opened in my view, as most likely to promote the accommodation of the youth, and tend to their preservation in innocence, what relates to their in∣struction is so well known and so judiciously encou∣raged by Friends, that at this time it only remains for me to add, with respect to the intention of this institution, that it is designed to provide for any who may need the benefit of such a school; the wealthy and those who are not in affluent circumstan∣ces are intended to be alike the objects of Friends' care, with this distinction only, that those who can afford it, may be accommodated, schooled, and sup∣ported on such reasonable terms as shall be assessed by the committee of the Yearly Meeting; but those not in affluence shall receive the same advantages ei∣ther free of cost, or at such moderate charge as may be suited to their circumstances.</P>
<P>A plan so large and calculated to be so extensively useful, may startle some who have been accustomed to view things on a more contracted scale, appear to be difficult in the execution, and be supposed to ex∣ceed the abilities of the society: with respect to these points, the prospects of some may differ until the ex∣periment be made; it may be remembered that there
<PB N="33" REF="022361_0032_0FB8487F76E99630"/>
is nothing new in the design, nor in the execution;<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The extraordinary instance of the school at Glaucha, near Hall in Saxony, is worthy of notice on this occasion. Au∣gustus Herman Franck, a German minister at that place, un∣dertook, from motives of humanity, to school and provide support for poor children, whose ignorance had excited his compassion; for which purpose he fixed up a charity-box in his place of residence, with an inscription on it intimating his design: upon which some person was moved, in about a quarter of a year afterwards, to put into his box to the value of 18<HI>s</HI>6 sterling at one time; which so encouraged this pious person, that he resolv∣ed to lay the foundation of a charity-school, without any other provision than what he might be furnished with from time to time from the benevolence of well-disposed persons, and without hav∣ing any united with him in this concern, but such as were em∣employed in the service of the school; which experienced such a series of providential support, that he was enabled to carry on his generous design thro' many difficulties and great distress without obstruction, until he had laid the foundation of considerable build∣ings, which he at length accomplished; and in the course of a few years, it is related, that this school, which was begun with so slender a capital as 18<HI>s</HI>6 sterling, had upwards of 200 poor scho∣lars clothed, fed, and accommodated with good dwelling-places, besides receiving the necessary school-learning, &amp;c. free of cost: and this charity was continued, as he remarks,
<Q>without any settled provision, and without any regard to human support, but reliance on Providence, and he did not scruple to make daily additions to the number of their children; and thus the first foundation of the school was laid: and he observes, that he was led to engage in this design without having premeditat∣ed such a project, but thinks it was by a secret guidance of the Lord, that he was carried to the performance of such things as tended to an end he had not as yet conceived; and that the experience for such a work grew up with the work itself.</Q>
The many instances of unexpected relief which he met with in the prosecution of this laudable undertaking, as related in the account published respecting this school, were accompanied with such cir∣cumstances as will scarcely be received as credible in an age of scepticism and unbelief: otherwise the recital of a few of those passages might afford encouragement to those who are engaged in similar designs, and be a stronger confirmation of the sacred pages in what relates to a providential support, than some who are hedged <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with large possessions are willing to believe.</NOTE> which might be made appear from numerous
<PB N="34" REF="022361_0033_0FB84881B7BEDBD8"/>
examples; great benefits can never be obtained but with suitable exertions, nor the calls of duty answer∣ed, in favor of this or any other interesting subject, if obstacles are suffered to be magnified thro' the medium of ill-founded apprehensions, so as to dis∣courage us from devoting a portion of our time and substance to a purpose so deserving of the approbati∣on of a religious mind.</P>
<P>Friends might be called upon by various motives to favor such an undertaking, as the sufferings of their ancestors, and the sacrifices they had to make of a large portion of their property by spoiling, &amp;c. in obedience to Christ, whereby we have been favor∣ed to experience an exemption from many grievous burdens yet imposed on the professors of other reli∣gious denominations, thro' their attachment to ex∣pensive forms and ceremonies introduced amongst them in times of greater ignorance; not to mention the various instances of extravagance and dissipation which too many freely indulge themselves in, with the very expensive education which they give their chil∣dren: and yet we have been shown in this institution at Glaucha near Hall, as well as in other instances, what might be done with proper exertions and a re∣liance on divine Providence; which encourages a hope we shall be enabled to establish, provide for, and support, in a reputable, useful manner, the in∣stitution now proposed, which seeems to be, at this time of outward care, both our interest and duty.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="section">
<PB N="35" REF="022361_0034_0FB848849A6C4070"/>
<HEAD>SECTION III.</HEAD>
<P>AS there are some whose engagements will not permit them to enter minutely into an inquiry of this nature, so as to form an adequate idea of the undertaking without some assistance; for the advan∣tage of these, and that they may be encouraged to unite in promoting such a plan, the following exami∣nation into the propriety thereof is added, especially as it may afford some useful information, and point out the necessity of attention to this very weighty subject.</P>
<P>When we consider that the youth amongst us need the same care that they do in Great-Britain, and that the same measures are necessary to be pursued to pro∣mote their welfare here as there, and as we have the benefit of their experience to assist us in the prosecution of our endeavours, it is an encourage∣ment to the undertaking.</P>
<P>And notwithstanding there may be an apparent languor in some minds with respect to this moment∣ous concern, yet when the case of our young people is brought into view, and found to claim our sym∣pathy, as well as call for some relief, no doubt that it will be considered as a powerful motive to engage in so beneficent a design.</P>
<P><PB N="36" REF="022361_0035_0FB84888963EA038"/>And when we consider how many there are who are favored with abundant opportunities of instructi∣on beyond what others have, and how small a part of the redundancy of that property which many are possessed of, if brought together into one sum, would afford a fund which, under the management of a ju∣dicious and well qualified committee of the Yearly Meeting, would lay the foundation of a school which might have all the advantages of that at Ackworth, with such others as the peculiar circumstances of the youth in this highly favored country might make ne∣cessary, we cannot but suppose that Friends might be brought to unite with, and support, a plan for so valuable a purpose. And it should be remembered, as was observed on the like occasion by John Fother∣gill,
<Q>that it is not intended to burden any, for large contributions are not to be expected where there is but little to be spared,</Q>
nor would it add a reputation to those who have abundance, should they withhold the necessary assistance.</P>
<P>Many advantages are expected to result from this undertaking, that are not so apparent on a superfici∣al view as they would be found on a closer inquiry, both with respect to what relates to the temporal con∣cerns of the young people, as well as their future well-being: besides as all things here below are in a state of mutability, we know not but that, whilst we are providing for others, some of our particular de∣scendants may be benefited by such an institution, and
<PB N="37" REF="022361_0036_0FB8488C05D00980"/>
that we may be laying the foundation of a retreat for them, in a healthy part of the country, un∣der the care of sober, well qualified friends, where they may be instructed and supported, free from the corrupt examples, which cities and too many schools afford, whilst they are in a state of incapacity to form a proper judgment or take suitable care for them∣selves.</P>
<P>These, with other important considerations which might be mentioned, show that it is both seasonable and proper for this concern to rest with weight upon Friends' minds; and it is hoped that what has been said will be sufficient to prepare them for the investi∣gation of this subject free from those biasses, which habits, with local or partial attachments, might cre∣ate; neither regarding the objects of this benevo∣lence, as they may be rich or poor, remote from us in their residence, or near; otherwise than as it may tend to their individual advantage and the benefit of society in general: and after having the situation of many of our young people brought into their view, with other circumstances, it is expected they would be enabled to form a clear judgment how far they might extend their prospects, so as not to exceed the abilities of society, nor yet forget the extensive be∣nefits which such an institution would afford.</P>
<P>For which purpose the following state of the youth who are descendants of Friends, and for whose be∣nefit
<PB N="38" REF="022361_0037_0FB8488D84CCAB10"/>
this institution is more particularly intended, with the observations and remarks which are subjoin∣ed, are offered to their perusal, with a belief that when they are convinced of the following particulars, they will cheerfully concur with, and unite their endea∣vours to promote it, viz.</P>
<P N="1">1st, That there is occasion for such an institution as is now proposed:</P>
<P N="2">2nd, And that there has been a concern resting on some minds for a considerable time past, to promote something of this kind.</P>
<P N="3">3d, That there is ability in the society for such an undertaking.</P>
<P N="4">4th, And lastly, that it will be attended with ad∣vantages that cannot be obtained in any other way.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="report">
<HEAD>A STATE OF THE YOUTH, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P N="1">I. On an examination into the situation of the young people within the compass of this Yearly Meeting, it must be acknowledged that many would be found, who, at an early period of their days, have been deprived of one or both their parents; perhaps left under the care of strangers, or entrusted
<PB N="39" REF="022361_0038_0FB84893A7387F30"/>
to guardians not in all respects qualified to sympa∣thize with them in their afflictive situations, nor dis∣posed to extend that kind attention to their cases, which might in some degree compensate for the loss of parental care and affection: and perhaps some of this number might not be suitably provided for, as well as others who have parents, who, thro' various circumstances, have been deprived of the means of providing a decent support for their tender offspring, and much less of ability to school and educate them properly. These with many other circumstances open a field continually for the exercise of Christian sympathy and benevolence.</P>
<P>Besides, there are many in affluent situations who are earnestly desirous that their children might have the benefit of a select and guarded education, at such an institution, under well qualified tutors, remote from the corrupt examples which are too prevalent in cities and common schools; these would freely contribute of their substance, and they ought to be encouraged in the commendable disposition, agree∣able to the pious recommendation of Friends already expressed, and to the soundest maxims of prudence and wisdom.</P>
<P>There are likewise other cases that would occur, where the disposition of children of the same family, as well as other causes which might make it necessa∣ry or useful to separate them for awhile one from
<PB N="40" REF="022361_0039_0FB84750493888E0"/>
another; sometimes to dissolve unprofitable acquain∣tances or unpromising connexions, which otherwise might terminate to their disadvantage, if not eventu∣ally to their ruin. That a large number of young people of both sexes would come under these descrip∣tions, in one or more instances, must be allowed; as also others, who, from inclination, would prefer the opportunity which such an institution would af∣ford, of being instructed under a well regulated sys∣tem with sober Friends.</P>
<P>And yet it is with satisfaction to be acknowledged, that many of our young people are so peculiarly fa∣vored as to have every accommodation necessary to render their situations easy and agreeable; and some who have the additional advantage of well informed friends and relations, whose pious conversation and exemplary conduct are the sources of continual in∣struction and improvement; independent of the ad∣vantages which schooling may afford: but as this is not the case generally, and there are others so situat∣ed as to need the care of Friends, it therefore be∣hoves us, as members of one religious community, to afford that relief which their several cases may re∣quire, which cannot be so effectually done in any other way. These circumstances, without bringing into view others which might be mentioned, which arise from weakness in parents and sorrowful declen∣sion in too many children, which cannot but be ob∣vious, show the propriety of an attention to this
<PB N="41" REF="022361_0040_0FB84751AC1F8840"/>
weighty subject, and that such an institution as is now proposed, is wanting.</P>
<P N="2">II. That there has been a growing concern within the limits of this Yearly Meeting may be inferred from what has appeared for some years back, when a num∣ber of persons of our profession have been engaged to promote something of this kind;<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">When this was wrote it was intended to give some account of the school at Nottingham, in Chester county, with some other matters, in an appendix; but the length of this essay has occasi∣oned their being laid aside for the present.</NOTE> and some still continue to be so disposed, notwithstanding they have been unprovided with a regular plan, so fully matur∣ed as to obtain the concurrence of the Yearly Meet∣ing, to direct their proceedings by. Yet, under these disadvantages, considerable bequests have been made, and some donations added; as well as offers to a more considerable amount,
<Q>apparently proceeding (as our friend John Fothergill observed with re∣spect to Ackworth school) from a just sense of the want of some such establishment,</Q>
on an en∣larged and liberal plan, subject to the directions of a committee of that Meeting.</P>
<P>And it is likewise hoped, that this concern will have more place, and be found to have increasing weight, on Friends' minds, when the nature of it is more clearly understood, and that so beneficent an undertaking will be remembered by many, not only
<PB N="42" REF="022361_0041_0FB8475464230D88"/>
when they are making a final arrangement of their temporal affairs, but likewise at other seasons, when they find that there is a probability that their chari∣table intentions will be fulfilled, and any donations or bequests appropriated agreeable to their benevo∣lent designs and Christian duty, under the direction of such a committee.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">It has been thought proper to recommend this concern to the attention of our women Friends, as it has been apprehended that they might not consider themselves as equally bound with the men to promote it; but as it is intended for the benefit of both sexes, and they are favored with a portion of providential bounty, with suitable qualifications to be useful, it is hoped they will at∣tend to it, and, when called upon, afford that assistance, which, in the wisdom of truth, may be pointed out.</NOTE></P>
<P N="3">III. With respect to the third proposition, that there is an ability in society for such an undertaking, it may be observed:</P>
<P>To effect any thing that will be extensively useful in this way, that will attract the attention of society at large, or add a reputation to it, it is necessary we should have a plan of considerable magnitude in view; which cannot be attended with any inconveni∣ences, if it is concluded afterwards to conduct it and carry it into execution on a smaller scale, as it is much easier to retrench a large one than it might be to enlarge a small one; and as it is not the intention of those who have this subject most at heart, to ex∣ceed the abilities of society, there can no disad∣vantage arise from their having an extensive plan in
<PB N="43" REF="022361_0042_0FB84755E1696010"/>
view, but rather otherwise, as we are sometimes en∣couraged to engage in smaller difficulties by having large ones made familiar: and it may be remem∣bered, that the plan of a small institution, ex∣pressed in all its parts in writing, will have the ap∣pearance of something greater than it is intended to be; so that I hope none will be harmed with suspici∣ons that any thing burdensome is intended, or what is inconsistent with the essential interest and good of the rising generation.</P>
<P>If too small a plan was proposed, it might tend to limit the views of some well-informed Friends, who may be favored with discernment to perceive what the abilities of the society could perform, and the benevolence of wealthy individuals disposed to ac∣complish, when united with others less able; and might by this means prevent its becoming so exten∣sively useful as it otherwise would; as well as discou∣rage those who may come after us, with more expe∣rience, and perhaps with more ability, from im∣proving upon our labors to advantage: for which reasons I have thought it best not to be too contract∣ed in my prospects, lest we might lose the benefits arising from a proper education, for want of suitable exertions.</P>
<P>When we are considered but as instruments in the Divine Hand, and that he can dispose the hearts of men, beyond what human reason might suggest, to fa∣vor
<PB N="44" REF="022361_0043_0FB84757F850BB98"/>
such an undertaking, and with so much liberality as rather to excite our admiration than disappoint our wishes, it has raised some degree of confidence that this undertaking will not be left unaccomplish∣ed, nor fail to answer the valuable purposes expected from it; and I have been strengthened in this per∣suasion, when I have remembered the manner in which the schools under the direction of Friends in this city originated, and how their funds have in∣creased.</P>
<P>These schools were first set on foot by a single Monthly Meeting, and were liberally provided for when our numbers were comparatively few to what they are at this time, nor were they near so wealthy, besides having difficulties to contend with, in the early periods of this settlement, which we are stran∣gers to at this day.</P>
<P>Afterwards they were principally endowed and provided for by a few persons who had the sub∣ject weightily on their minds, who left property suf∣ficient to form a fund, which has been adequate to the support of schools for the poor of the Monthly Meeting, besides many others, the offspring of per∣sons belonging to other religious societies. The overseers of these schools have been able to allow sa∣laries, and grant encouragement, in divers ways, to well-qualified tutors; and at this time their fund is quite sufficient to answer all the necessary purposes
<PB N="45" REF="022361_0044_0FB84759F9347090"/>
of keeping them up, and fully equal to what is necessary to begin an establishment, such as is now proposed for the whole society to undertake.</P>
<P>And this can only be considered as a private fund, accumulated within the limits of one Monthly Meet∣ing,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Since divided into three.</NOTE> and the result of a benevolent disposition in only a few individuals, principally effected above half a century ago: so that the present generation has had no share in forming it; but have derived considerable benefits from this fund: hence there seems to be an obligation on the present generation of Friends to make the like provision for those who are to succeed them, <NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">Many young people, who are in a way to have increasing fa∣milies, are apt to be inattentive to concerns of this nature, and to the important consequences which result from a right education; I have wished that they might remember, that unless suitable schools are begun to be established before they want them, their offspring cannot be benefited by them when they do; and it has been my desire that they may not neglect an early attention to the right education of their offspring, nor be indifferent with respect to the making provision for suitable schools, according to their circum∣stances, lest they should experience the necessity for them when too late to be remedied, and have to lament their inattention, in consequence of the depravity or ill conduct of their children; which has been the sorrowful experience of many.</NOTE> as well as for the present: indeed such is the nature of institutions of this kind, that they not only serve those who may be living at the time of their establishment, but likewise have a more re∣mote effect; and by an attention to such useful un∣dertakings, we may confer a benefit upon many ge∣nerations, who are to succeed us, which is a very
<PB N="46" REF="022361_0045_0FB8475BCC785648"/>
encouraging circumstance to those who may be en∣gaged to promote them.</P>
<P>There is another instance in a school under the care of Friends of this city, for the instruction of the blacks: where unexpected provision has been made, by unforeseen ways, of a sufficient fund to support it, in the course of a few years, and those who had the first burden, were exonerated sooner than was look∣ed for. At present they have an annual income of about £. 200, arising from ground-rents, &amp;c. so con∣solidated that there is a pleasing prospect that it will afford a permanent establishment to this generous un∣dertaking; which, it is said, originated with the wo∣men of our religious society in this city.</P>
<P>If such institutions as these have been begun and supported within the limits, and by the benevolence of Friends mostly within, this city, what may we not hope from the united endeavours of the whole society? to infer an inability in them to make a con∣siderable establishment, and provide for the school∣ing, accommodation, and support of a number of those who need it, and have a religious claim upon them for assistance, would be contrary to the prospect of such Friends as have considered the subject in a solid, weighty manner; and if the number of fami∣lies which constitute this Yearly Meeting, was known, it could be made appear: but as this is uncertain, any calculations founded on our numbers must be
<PB N="47" REF="022361_0046_0FB8475CE000FA58"/>
vague; some have supposed, that if the expense was liquidated, it would not take more than a bushel of wheat for each family to effect something reputable and extensively useful in this way.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Of this I do not consider myself as a competent judge, nei∣ther have I built altogether on our numbers▪ as it is hoped a spi∣rit of liberality will be excited in those who are abundantly able.</NOTE></P>
<P>And as we may reasonably conclude that a consi∣derable sum would be generously given for this pur∣pose by wealthy individuals, we might hope that a fund would be gradually formed so as to relieve the apprehensions of its being attended with any consi∣derable expense; and that donations and bequests would be made, unsolicited, at times, to enable Friends to erect many of the most expensive and ne∣cessary buildings: so that when we compare the bene∣fits which may be expected from such an institution with the expense likely to attend it; and consider the foundation there is to believe that many wealthy indi∣viduals, as well as others, will be disposed to favor so useful a design; and reflect upon what has been done by a part of the society; <NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">Within the limits of Philadelphia Monthly Meetings.</NOTE> we need not hesitate to conclude that there is sufficient ABILITY for such an undertaking.</P>
<P N="4">IV. And that it would be attended with many ad∣vantages not to be had in any other way, may be de∣duced from the following considerations, viz.</P>
<P><PB N="48" REF="022361_0047_0FB8475E69CF8D60"/>Amongst other circumstances which might be men∣tioned, the excellent regulations introduced into the school at ACKWORTH, and the manner in which that institution has been conducted, with the experience which has been since had of the beneficial effects of those regulations on the manners and deportment of the youth brought up at that place, affords a pleas∣ing prospect that a system of oeconomy and manage∣ment is practicable at a large institution, which may be productive of many advantages not to be obtained at smaller schools, particularly so as to reduce the cost of board and schooling, which are circumstances wor∣thy of regard in the establishment of schools.</P>
<P>Nor is it unlikely, as was observed respecting Ack∣worth school,
<Q>that one on a large plan would fix the attention, and excite the bounty, of Friends, whilst those upon a smaller scale would be over∣looked, and soon disappear,</Q>
as was found to be the case in Great-Britain; besides, it might be expected that this institution would draw forth from a state of less activity, men and women, who may have been raised up and suitably qualified for every station which so large an undertaking would require, however arduous, who might be willing to engage in any line of duty to which they might be called, from an enlarged prospect of usefulness, and a desire that their labors may be blessed to the be∣nefit of the young and rising generation; as has been the case at that valuable institution at Ackworth: nor
<PB N="49" REF="022361_0048_0FB8475FE4A2BD08"/>
is there any doubt in my mind, but such are now amongst us, unnoticed and in a state of greater ob∣scurity.</P>
<P>Another evident advantage which must arise from such an establishment is, that a number of young people of both sexes would be forming from time to time, under the excellent regulations which are ex∣pected to be introduced at such an institution, who Would be likely to come forward with all the advan∣tages which could be obtained from a well regulated course of instruction, to engage as masters and mi∣stresses at those schools which are recommended to be established throughout the society by the Yearly Meeting, and thereby advance what that Meeting have had in view,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">As expressed in the extracts from their minutes lately spread thro' the society under the direction of our Meeting for Suffer∣ings.</NOTE> by removing a principal discou∣ragement to the establishment of such schools, that is, <HI>the want of suitable persons for teachers.</HI></P>
<P>There are other circumstances which might ren∣der such an institution useful above any other which could be established on a more contracted scale, viz. it might be laying the foundation for greater im∣provement in the system of instruction to be pursued for the benefit of the youth at such a place; likewise in the manner of bringing them up, that there
<PB N="50" REF="022361_0049_0FB8476225C8BEA8"/>
might be a greater conformity to what has been invariably recommended by Friends from the first rise of the society, as the only probable means, of deriving to our offspring those substantial be∣nefits which have been uniformly experienced to flow from an attention to their advice, in additi∣on to those useful qualifications which would arise from so judicious a course of school-learning, and it is likely that the example afforded at this school would be followed by others; hence, its influence on the manners and conduct of the youth might extend to remote seminaries: whereby Friends would be in∣strumental in promoting the happiness and improve∣ment of many young people, who might otherwise remain in a less cultivated and less happy state; nor could such an institution, properly conducted, fail of adding a reputation to the <HI>society,</HI> and perhaps have a tendency to diffuse the principles of LIGHT and TRUTH which we profess; by awakening a spirit of inquiry after them, amongst other people.</P>
<P>Another advantage which would result from this undertaking, and seems worthy of notice is, that by engaging in this laudable design, it might excite a greater disposition to attend to the religious instructi∣on of the young people, in some who have been too inattentive to this important concern; who might be brought, by giving up to it, to become more zea∣lously engaged to encourage other schools, agreeable to what has been recommended by Friends: for it 
<PB N="51" REF="022361_0050_0FB84763DAD61E00"/>has been considered as an approved maxim,
<Q>the more any person gives towards <HI>charitable</HI> institu∣tions,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Although this institution is not intended for the use of those young people <HI>only</HI> who are not in affluent circumstances, never∣theless it may, according to the nicest construction of the inten∣tion, be considered as a charitable design; for there is no way in which we can so effectually relieve difficulties, as by suitable endeavours to prevent them: nor can a better system of oeconomy be adopted by a society in extending alms, than by providing for the proper education and instruction of the young people who may have occasion for such assistance. How great have been the difficulties which some have been involved in for want of this care? what irretrievable evils do many unguardedly plunge into for want of early instruction? and what misfortunes have ensued, so as to produce a series of fatal consequences which have excited a painful recollection? merely thro' the neglect of an early care for that purpose, and perhaps I might not improperly add, for want of more liberality and necessary attention to such useful schools.</NOTE> the more willing he becomes to give to∣wards the encouragement of <HI>others,</HI></Q>
especially when it is for the like benevolent purposes; we might therefore conclude that it would have a tendency to promote a greater degree of liberality with a better disposition to support lesser schools on the system, and for the valuable purposes recommended by the Year∣ly Meeting.</P>
<P>All these circumstances ought to afford us grounds to believe, that such an institution will be attended with advantages which cannot be had in any other way.</P>
<P>Being confirmed in this opinion, and that such a school, somewhere in the country, in a healthy situ∣ation, free from the objections which have been
<PB N="52" REF="022361_0051_0FB84766C347F358"/>
mentioned, and on a large establishment, will have many advantages which cannot be obtained either in town or country. I have, therefore, engaged in this essay, with an expectation that Friends will be favored to judge of the propriety of the concern, and that in due season it will claim their solid atten∣tion, obtain suitable encouragement, and be the means, under Divine Providence, of many of our young people, who may be left in an unprovided condition, as well as others, being suitably taken care of, instructed, and prepared to enter upon the du∣ties of life, with every advantage which a well di∣rected education can afford: which is the desire of their friend and well-wisher in the truth,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>OWEN BIDDLE.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE>Philadelphia,
<DATE>6th Month. 19th, 1790.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="notice">
<HEAD>ADVERTISEMENT.</HEAD>
<P>The more effectually to ripen the fore-mentioned concern▪ to mature the PLAN so as have it brought forward for the consideration of some future Yearly Meeting; and to afford an opportunity to any Friends of manifesting their benevo∣lent intentions, who may be disposed to encourage it; as well as to afford an opportunity to those who may have any useful hints to offer for the improvement of what has been proposed; or to satisfy others who may have different prospects; it is designed that a few Friends, who have had this subject weightily on their minds for some time past, have occasional meetings: when letters on these subjects, di∣rected and forwarded to <HI>John Field, James Cresson, Arthur Howell,</HI> or <HI>Samuel Clark,</HI> will be laid before the said Friends and duly noticed, and any information communicated in answer which may be necessary to the occasion.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

