<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2008-05-15</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Check for blanks. Checked for signatures. Checked for #s. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Corrected 5 $-groups. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N32543">
<STC T="E">42813</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99024151</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="042813_0000_101C95FDA427B8D8"/>
<PB REF="042813_0001_101C95C09C5C1DD8"/>
<P>AN ESSAY ON PUBLIC SPEAKING, SHEWING THE GREAT USEFULNESS OF CHRISTIAN-ORATORY, AND THAT READING IS NOT PREACHING. Collected from various Authors.</P>
<Q><P><HI>And he closed the Book—and he began to say unto them—and all wondered at the gracious Words that proceeded out of his Mouth</HI></P>
<BIBL>LUKE <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> 20 21 22.</BIBL></Q>
<P><HI>PROVIDENCE:</HI> PRINTED AND SOLD BY JOHN CARTER, AT SHAKE∣SPEAR'S HEAD, NEAR THE COURT-HOUSE. M,DCC,LXXV.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="042813_0002_101C95C41D68C730"/>
<HEAD>AN ESSAY ON PUBLIC SPEAKING.</HEAD>
<P>IT is only the <HI>elegant speaker,</HI> who can at <HI>once</HI> regale the <HI>eye</HI> with the view of its most amiable object, the human form in all its glory; the <HI>ear,</HI> with the original of all music; the <HI>understanding,</HI> with its proper and natural <HI>food,</HI> the knowledge of im∣portant truth; and the <HI>imagination,</HI> with all that is beau∣tiful in nature and art—For the orator's <HI>field</HI> is the <HI>uni∣verse,</HI> and his subjects are all that is known of <HI>God</HI> and his works; of superior natures, good and evil, and their works; and of inferior natures, and their's.—In a consum∣mate speaker, whatever there is of corporal dignity or beauty, the majesty of the human <HI>face divine,</HI> the grace of <HI>action,</HI> the piercing <HI>glance,</HI> or gentle languish, or fiery <HI>flash</HI> of the eye; whatever of lively passion, or striking <HI>emotion</HI> of mind; whatever of fine imagination, of wise reflection, of irresistible <HI>reasoning</HI>; whatever excellent of human nature; all that the hand of the <HI>Creator</HI> has impressed of his own <HI>image,</HI> upon the noblest creatures we are acquainted with; all this appears in the <HI>consummate speaker</HI> to the highest <HI>advantage.</HI> And whoever is proof against such a display of all that is noble in human na∣ture, must have neither <HI>eye,</HI> nor <HI>ear,</HI> nor <HI>passion,</HI> nor <HI>imagination,</HI> nor <HI>taste,</HI> nor <HI>understanding.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="042813_0003_101C95C7490C6BE8"/>
THOUGH it may be alledged, that a great deal of <HI>ges∣ture</HI> or <HI>action</HI> at the bar, or in the pulpit, especially in the latter, is not wanted, nor is quite in character; yet most certain it is, that there is no part of a man that has not its proper <HI>attitude.</HI> The <HI>eyes</HI> are not to be rolled along the cieling, as if the speaker were taking care how the flies behave themselves. Nor are they to be con∣t<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>antly cast down upon the ground, as if he were before his judge, receiving sentence of <HI>death.</HI> Nor are they to be fixed upon <HI>one point,</HI> as if he saw a <HI>ghost.</HI>—The <HI>arms</HI> of a preacher are not to be needlessly thrown out, as if he were drowning in the pulpit; or brandished after the manner of the ancient boxers, when they fought with their own shadows, to prepare themselves for the olimpic contests. Nor on the contrary are his <HI>hands</HI> to be <HI>pocketed up,</HI> nor his <HI>arms</HI> to hang by his sides, as if they were both <HI>withered.</HI> The <HI>head</HI> is not to stand fixed, as if the preacher had a crick in his neck; nor is it to nod at every third word, as if he were acting Jupiter.</P>
<P>A JUDICIOUS speaker is master of such a <HI>variety</HI> of decent and natural <HI>motions,</HI> and has such a command of attitude, that he will not be long enough in any <HI>one pos∣ture</HI> to offend the eye of the spectator. The matter he has to pronounce, will easily suggest to him the propriety of changing his <HI>look,</HI> his <HI>posture,</HI> his <HI>motion</HI> and tone of voice, which if they were to continue too long, would become disagreeable to the beholders. But yet, he is not to be every moment changing posture like a harle∣quin, nor throwing his hands about, as if he were shew∣ing legerdemain tricks. And above all things, the public speaker is never to forget the great rule, ARS EST CELARE ARTEM. It would be infinitely more pleasing, to see him deliver himself with as little motion as an Egyptian <HI>mummy,</HI> than distorting himself into all the violations of 
<PB N="5" REF="042813_0004_101C95C8CE506208"/>
<HI>decorum,</HI> which affectation produces; for art, seen through, is <HI>execrable.</HI> Modesty ought ever to be conspicuous in the behaviour of all, who exhibit themselves before the <HI>public.</HI> Whatever of gesture or exertion of voice such persons use, they ought apparently to be <HI>drawn</HI> into them, by the <HI>importance,</HI> spirit or humour of the matter. For if the speaker uses any arts of delivery which appear plainly to be studied, and unnatural, the effect will be, that his aukward and vain attempt to work upon the passions of his hearers by means, of which he is not <HI>master,</HI> will render him odious and contemptible to them.—With what <HI>stiff</HI> and <HI>pedantic solemnity</HI> do some public speakers utter thoughts so trifling, as to be hardly worth uttering at all? And what unnatural and unsuitable tones of voice and gestures do others apply, in deliver∣ing what, by their manner of delivering, one would be apt to question, not only whether it is their own compo∣sition, but whether they understand it?—Nor is it to be expected, that <HI>decorum</HI> of <HI>manner</HI> in preaching can ever be carried to any great perfection, while <HI>reading</HI> is thought to be <HI>preaching</HI>
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><LG>
<L>For, what's a sermon, good or bad,</L>
<L><HI>If a man reads it,</HI> like <HI>a lad</HI>?</L>
<L>To hear some people, when they preach,</L>
<L>How they run o'er all parts of speech,</L>
<L>And neither <HI>raise</HI> a word nor <HI>sink,</HI></L>
<L>Our learned clergy, one would think,</L>
<L>Had taken school-boys from the red,</L>
<L>To make <HI>ambassadors for God.</HI></L>
<L>In point of sermons, if consist</L>
<L>Our English clergy make the best;</L>
<L>Yet this appears, we must consist,</L>
<L>Not from the <HI>pulpit,</HI> but the <HI>press.</HI></L>
<L>They manage with disjointed skill</L>
<L>The <HI>matter</HI> well, the <HI>manner</HI> ill;</L>
<L>And, what seems paradox at first,</L>
<L>They <HI>make the best,</HI> and <HI>preach the worst.</HI></L>
</LG></NOTE>—If the Greek and Roman 
<PB N="6" REF="042813_0005_101C95CBE8C9C1D8"/>
orators had <HI>read</HI> their sermons, the effect would have been pretty much the same, as that which the <HI>reading</HI> of sermons produces among us. The hearers might have, many of them, <HI>dropped asleep.</HI> In some foreign countries, preachers are so much aware of the great disadvantage of <HI>reading,</HI> that such as have weak memories have a prompter behind in the pulpit, out of sight.—However, it must be owned, that if preachers would take suitable pains in committing to <HI>memory</HI> the substance of their discourses, so as not to be <HI>slaves</HI> to written <HI>notes,</HI> and endeavour to gain a tolerable readiness at extemporary <HI>amplification,</HI> their discourses might have effect, though the <HI>eye</HI> should now and then be cast upon the notes, if not in a clumsy manner, and with <HI>hesitation.</HI>—To hear a judicious and <HI>elegant</HI> discourse from the pulpit, which in <HI>print</HI> would make a noble figure, murdered by him who had learning and taste enough to <HI>compose</HI> it, but having neglected the important part of his education, knows not how to deliver it otherwise than with a dull tone, between <HI>singing</HI> and <HI>saying,</HI> or with a <HI>nod of his head,</HI> to enforce, as with a hammer, every <HI>emphatical</HI> word, or with the same unanimated <HI>monotony</HI>
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Having but one tone.</NOTE>, in which he was used to repeat <HI>quae genus</HI> at school; what can be imagin∣ed more lamentable! Yet, what is more common? Were the educators of youth intended for the ministry, of the opinion of the prince of orators, viz. that <HI>delivery</HI> is the <HI>first, second</HI> and <HI>third</HI> part of <HI>oratory,</HI> they would <HI>spare</HI> some time from the <HI>many less necessary</HI> parts of school learning, to apply it to <HI>one</HI> so very essential; without which, the weight of the most <HI>sacred subject,</HI> the greatest depth of critical disquisition, the most unexceptionable reasoning, the most accurate <HI>arrangement</HI> of <HI>matter,</HI> and the most striking <HI>energy</HI> of <HI>style,</HI> are all lost upon an au∣dience,
<PB N="7" REF="042813_0006_101C95CF1AD30508"/>
who sit <HI>unaffected,</HI> and depart <HI>unimproved.</HI> From hence it is, that while places of divine and public wor∣ship are almost <HI>empty,</HI> theatres are <HI>crowded.</HI> Yet in the former the most <HI>interesting subjects</HI> are treated of, and in the latter <HI>all is fiction.</HI> But it will not be otherwise, so long as the speakers, in places of divine worship, take no more pains to enforce their public instructions, and the most <HI>important truths,</HI> than if they delivered <HI>fictions</HI>; while the speakers in theatres bestow <HI>so much pains,</HI> to make their <HI>fictions seem to be true.</HI>—It may be said that this observation has been made before. The more is the <HI>pity.</HI> And it ought to be often made again and again, until the fault be mended.—Did preachers labour to acquire a <HI>masterly delivery,</HI> places of <HI>public instruction</HI> would be as crowded as places of public diversion. <HI>Rakes</HI> and <HI>infidels,</HI> merely to shew their <HI>taste,</HI> would frequent them. Could <HI>all</HI> frequent them, and <HI>none</HI> profit? It is common to hear complaints from our clergy, of the <HI>inattention</HI> of their hearers, even to dozing, and some∣times profound sleep. But where does this complaint fall at last? Even upon the preachers themselves, who address their hearers with so much coolness and infiffer∣ence, as leaves them nothing to do but <HI>to go to sleep.</HI> Let the preacher be but suitably animated, and exert him∣self, and he may desy his hearers to sleep, or withdraw their attention for a moment.</P>
<P>THE clergy are likewise full of their complaints, of the little effect their labours produce.—Infidelity and vice, they say, prevail more than ever. But what is the plain English of this complaint? Why are churches so poorly filled? Why is it that those who attend, per∣haps do it only for fashion's sake, and are not much better than their neighbours? Why, truly, the clergy
<PB N="8" REF="042813_0007_101C95D09D92B1A8"/>
find people loath to go to places of public instruction, to be disgusted, or lulled to sleep. And when they have them there, they cannot persuade them to quit their vices and follies, by lolling thirty or forty, or per∣haps but twenty minutes, upon a <HI>velvet cushion</HI>; and only <HI>reading</HI> to them a learned discourse.—They cannot <HI>warm</HI> them to the love of virtue, by a <HI>cold, ill∣read pulpit harangue.</HI> They cannot win their <HI>affections,</HI> while they neglect all the natural means for working upon the <HI>human passions.</HI> They cannot kindle in them that burning zeal, which is necessary for the most important of all interests, by talking or rather reading only, with the coolness of a sett of <HI>stoic philosophers,</HI> con∣cerning <HI>the terrors of the Lord,</HI> of <HI>the worm that dies not,</HI> of future glory, honour and immortality, of everlasting kingdoms, and heavenly thrones.—It is common for preachers to plead their modesty, and fear of being ac∣cused of affectation, in excuse of the <HI>dulness</HI> and the <HI>coldness</HI> of their manner of addressing their hearers. But are those any hinderance to the elocution of the <HI>actors,</HI> or even the actresses, who by study and practice get the better of fear, and attain an <HI>elegant</HI> and correct utterance, and are indeed almost the only speakers we have without appearance of <HI>affectation</HI>? But do our preachers in general bestow any thought, or use any means of any kind, for improving themselves in speak∣ing? The younger part of the players rehearse and prac∣tise over and over many times, and are long under the tuition of the principal actors, before they appear in public. But there are perhaps no other public speak∣ers among us, who take such pains; though they be∣stow great pains in improving themselves in learning; and yet of the two <HI>learning</HI> is less necessary to a preacher, than skill in <HI>persuading.</HI> Let the reader only con∣sider,
<PB N="9" REF="042813_0008_101C95D5C9A8BB88"/>
that a mechanic is under a master <HI>seven years</HI> at least, before he sets up for himself. But the preacher goes into the pulpit <HI>at once,</HI> without ever having had <HI>one lesson</HI> of instruction in that part of his art which is the chief and most necessary, and without which all his other accomplishments are worth nothing, toward gain∣ing the great end of preaching.—It may be alledged, and it often has been alledged, by the clergy, that they cannot be expected to be great orators for fifty or an hundred pounds a year. The answer is ready, are there not many players who do not get more than the lower clergy? and yet they study <HI>hard,</HI> and take great pains, for no greater gain or encouragement, and do actually acquire such skill in speaking and performing, that for my part, if I desired to have a composition of mine <HI>well spoken,</HI> I would put it into the hands even of a second∣rate stage-player, rather than of almost any preacher I ever heard.—What could be imagined more <HI>elegant,</HI> if entertainment alone were sought? What more <HI>useful,</HI> if the <HI>everlasting good of mankind</HI> were the object, than the sacred office of <HI>preaching properly performed?</HI> Were the most <HI>interesting</HI> of subjects treated with proper <HI>perspi∣cuity,</HI> and adequate <HI>judgment,</HI> and <HI>well-composed discourses</HI> delivered to the listening crowds, with that <HI>dignity</HI> which becomes a teacher of <HI>divine truth,</HI> and with that <HI>energy</HI> and <HI>pathos,</HI> which would shew that the preacher spoke from his <HI>own heart,</HI> and really meant to speak to the <HI>hearts</HI> of his hearers, should we not soon see the good effects of such preaching? For mankind are not wood or stone. They may be <HI>drawn.</HI> They may be <HI>allured.</HI> They may be <HI>roused</HI> and <HI>startled.</HI> The voice of an able and well-accomplished preacher, thundering out the <HI>di∣vine threatnings</HI> against <HI>vice,</HI> would be in the ear of the of∣fender as if he heard the sound of the <HI>last trumpet,</HI> sum∣moning
<PB N="10" REF="042813_0009_101C95DB90EAF690"/>
the dead to judgement. And <HI>the gentle call of mercy,</HI> encouraging the terrified and almost despairing <HI>penitent</HI> to look up to his offended heavenly <HI>father,</HI> would be as <HI>the song of angels.</HI>—A whole multitude might as it were be lifted to the <HI>skies,</HI> and the world of <HI>spirits</HI> be opened to the eyes of their minds.—The <HI>terrors</HI> of that punishment which awaits <HI>vice</HI>; the <HI>glories</HI> of that state to which virtue and true piety, through <HI>divine grace,</HI> will raise the pious, might be, by a powerful preacher, rendered present to their understandings, with such conviction, as would make indelible impressions upon the hearts of the hearers, and work a substantial re∣formation in their lives. The convincing and irrefragable <HI>proof,</HI> that real and important effects might he produced by preachers, by a proper use of <HI>oratory,</HI> to the good purposes of instructing and amending mankind, is, that <HI>oratory,</HI> in all times, has been known actually to pro∣duce great alterations in mens ways of thinking and act∣ing. And there is no denying plain facts. No one can imagine that <HI>oratory</HI> could have been so laboriously cultivated by <HI>statesmen,</HI> in all free and flourishing govern∣ments, had they not found it useful to the state. But if any one should alledge that there is nothing in the power of <HI>preachers</HI> by means of <HI>oratory,</HI> I would ask, does it not then follow, that the whole office of preaching may as well be laid aside? For if <HI>good speaking</HI> will have no effect, surely <HI>bad</HI> will have none. A <HI>Perecles,</HI> or a <HI>Demosthenes,</HI> could <HI>shake</HI> all Greece, when they warned their coun∣trymen against an <HI>invasion,</HI> or alarmed them about the danger of their liberties, whilst our preachers can hardly keep their hearers <HI>awake,</HI> when they stand forth in the <HI>name of God,</HI> to warn them against the consequences of <HI>vice,</HI> so ruinous to individuals, so ruinous to nations; the cause not only of the subversion of states and kingdoms, when luxury and corruption spread their fatal contagion, 
<PB N="11" REF="042813_0010_101C95DD18229E90"/>
and leave a people the unthinking prey of <HI>tyranny</HI> and <HI>oppression,</HI> but of utter and irretrievable destruction, from the presence of the Lord, and the glory of his power, when the trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised, and he shall sit upon the throne of judgment, from whose face heaven and earth shall flee away.</P>
<P>IT may perhaps be objected, that <HI>sacred truth</HI> needs no <HI>ornament</HI> to set it off, nor <HI>art</HI> to enforce it: That the <HI>apostles were artless and illiterate men,</HI> and yet they gain∣ed the great end of their mission, the conviction of mul∣titudes, and the establishment of Christianity: And that therefore there is no necessity of such attention to deli∣very, in order to qualify the preacher for his sacred of∣fice, or to render his labours successful.—To all this an answer it ready.—The apostles were not <HI>all</HI> artless and illiterate men. St. <HI>Paul,</HI> the greatest and most ge∣neral propagator of Christianity, is an eminent exception. He could be no mean orator who confounded the Jews at Damascus; made a <HI>Prince,</HI> before whom he stood to be judged, confess that he had almost persuaded him to become a convert to a religion every where spoken against; threw another into a fit of trembling, as he sat upon his judgment seat; made such a defence before the learned court of <HI>Areopagus,</HI> as gained him for a convert, who was a member of the court itself; struck a whole people with such admiration, that they took him for <HI>the God of eloquence</HI>; and gained him a place in <HI>Longinus</HI>'s list of <HI>famous orators.</HI> Would <HI>the cold mono∣tony</HI> of our English <HI>sermon-readers</HI> have produced such effects as these? Surely it would not.</P>
<P>BUT farther it may be added, the apostles might very well spare human accomplishments, having what was worth 
<PB N="12" REF="042813_0011_101C95DEC8D53718"/>
them all, the divine gift of working <HI>miracles,</HI> which if our preachers had, we should not have much to say about their qualifying themselves in <HI>elocution.</HI> But, as it is, pub∣lic instruction is the preacher's <HI>weapon,</HI> with which he is to combat <HI>infidelity</HI> and <HI>vice.</HI> But what avails a weapon without <HI>skill</HI> to weild it? Therefore the preacher ought, above all other public speakers, to labour to enrich and adorn, in the <HI>most</HI> masterly manner, his addresses to man∣kind, his views, if as they ought to be, being the most important.</P>
<P>WHAT grand point has the <HI>player</HI> to gain? Why, to draw an audience to the <HI>theatre.</HI> The pleader at the bar, if he lays before the judges and jury the true state of the case, so as they may be most likely to see where the right of it lies, has done his duty. The speaker in either house of Parliament has only to consider that the good of his country may in a great measure depend upon his tongue. But the infinitely important subject of preaching is <HI>the reformation of mankind,</HI> upon which de∣pends their happiness in this world, and throughout the whole of their being. Of how great importance is it then, that the art of preaching be carried to such perfec∣tion, that all may be drawn to places of public instruc∣tion, and that those who attend them may receive bene∣fit! And if almost the whole of preaching, to any good effect, depends upon delivery, how necessary is the stu∣dy of delivery! That a good and lively delivery is in∣comparably the most important part of public instruction, is plainly manifest from this, <HI>that very indifferent matter, well delivered,</HI> will make a considerable <HI>impression.</HI> But <HI>bad utterance</HI> will defeat the whole <HI>effect</HI> of <HI>the noblest</HI> composition that ever was produced. While exorbi∣tant appetite and unruly passion <HI>within,</HI> while evil ex∣ample,
<PB N="13" REF="042813_0012_101C95E877E3C8F8"/>
with alluring sollicitation, without, invite and ensnare the frail and thoughtless into guilt; shall <HI>virtue and religion,</HI> preached from the pulpit, hold forth <HI>no charms</HI> to engage votaries? <HI>Pleasure</HI> decks herself out with <HI>rich attire,</HI> and must <HI>Religion</HI> present herself with every disadvantage, and must she appear quite unadorn∣ed? What chance can she then have, in competition with an enemy so much <HI>better furnished</HI> with every necessary <HI>invitation</HI> and <HI>allurement?</HI></P>
<P>LET it be considered that our preachers do not address <HI>innocents in Paradise,</HI> but thoughtless and <HI>habituated sin∣ners.</HI> Mere <HI>cold reading</HI> will have but little effect upon such. For weak is the hold which <HI>reason</HI> has on most men. <HI>Few</HI> of mankind have <HI>able heads. All</HI> have <HI>hearts</HI>; and all <HI>hearts</HI> may be <HI>touched,</HI> if the speaker is but <HI>master</HI> of his art. The business of the preacher is not so much to <HI>inform</HI> the <HI>understanding,</HI> as to <HI>warm</HI> the <HI>heart.</HI> For there are few who do not <HI>know</HI> their duty; to allure them to the <HI>doing it,</HI> is the difficulty. Nor is this to be effected by <HI>cold reasoning.</HI> Accordingly the <HI>scripture ora∣tors</HI> are none of them <HI>cold.</HI> They spake <HI>in demonstration of the spirit, and with power,</HI> as having <HI>authority,</HI> and not as the cold Scribes. Their addresses are such as hardly any man can utter without <HI>warmth.</HI> It is true, the preach∣er is carefully to avoid <HI>ostentation</HI>; he is not to preach <HI>himself,</HI> but Christ. But, at the same time, he is to stir up every gift that is in him; to <HI>cry aloud,</HI> and not to spare; to lift up his voice like a trumpet; to reprove, correct and instruct; to be instant in season and out of season; to become, innocently, all things to all men, and consequently <HI>to become and orator,</HI> if his hearers are not to be affected by simple and unadorned truth, how∣ever <HI>weighty.</HI> What can people think about <HI>the sincerity,</HI> 
<PB N="14" REF="042813_0013_101C95EA02E91E00"/>
or rather about <HI>the insincerity</HI> of the preacher, who is <HI>cold,</HI> languid, and wholly unanimated in his public instructions; but is as warm as other men, in the defence of an incon∣siderable part of his <HI>estate</HI>? Would he speak as calmly, as unconcernedly for his <HI>life,</HI> as he does in the cause of <HI>virtue</HI> and <HI>religion?</HI>—If it should be said by preachers, "the people will be as much offended with us, if we <HI>over-act</HI> our part, as they are now indifferent about at∣tending our ministry; so that it will avail nothing to study and practise <HI>a more lively delivery:</HI>" To this it may be answered, that a manner of preaching may be used, which shall have ten times more <HI>life</HI> and <HI>vivacity</HI> in it than the <HI>present,</HI> and yet, if it be not incorrect, or un∣natural, be very safe from all danger of exceeding due bounds, as to <HI>vivacity</HI> and <HI>force.</HI> And in fact we do ob∣serve, that no preacher is <HI>admired,</HI> I do not mean by the mob, but by people of education, whose <HI>delivery is dull and unanimated.</HI>—The great Doctor <HI>Delany,</HI> among other hints proper for a young preacher, said, that "when∣ever he went up into a pulpit, he desired to look upon it as the last time he should ever preach, or the last time that the people should ever hear him." If all preachers, however dignified, went always up into their respective pulpits thus impressed; they would then preach, as <HI>Ap∣pelles</HI> once said he painted, <HI>for eternity.</HI> They would then act the part of <HI>true gospel Christian orators,</HI> and not only calmly and coolly inform the <HI>understanding,</HI> but by <HI>persuasive and pathetic address</HI> endeavour to <HI>move the affections, and warm the heart.</HI> To act otherwise, be∣speaks a sad ignorance of human nature, and such an inexcusable indolence and indifference in the preacher, as must constrain his hearers to suspect that the preacher, let him be who he will, <HI>only deals in the false commerce of 
<PB N="15" REF="042813_0014_101C95EBC1CBD2D8"/>
unfelt truth.</HI> The late pious and learned Doctor <HI>Isaac Watts,</HI> speaking of <HI>words without spirit,</HI> and of preaching by written notes, said, <Q>that paper, with the most <HI>pathetic</HI> lines written upon it, has no <HI>fear</HI> nor <HI>hope,</HI> no <HI>zeal</HI> or <HI>compassion</HI>; it is conscious of no <HI>design,</HI> nor has any <HI>sollicitude</HI> for the <HI>success</HI>: And a mere <HI>reader,</HI> who <HI>coldly tells</HI> the people what his <HI>paper says,</HI> seems to be as void of all these necessary qualifications, as his paper is.</Q></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

