<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bethlehems beauty, Londons charity, and the cities glory. A panegyrical poem on that magnificent structure, lately erected in Moorfields, vulgarly called New Bedlam. Humbly addrest to the honourable master, governours, and other noble benefactors of that splendid and most useful hospital.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.2[106]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99886914</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99886914</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181433</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. B01565)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181433)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A1:1[107])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bethlehems beauty, Londons charity, and the cities glory. A panegyrical poem on that magnificent structure, lately erected in Moorfields, vulgarly called New Bedlam. Humbly addrest to the honourable master, governours, and other noble benefactors of that splendid and most useful hospital.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Sear [i.e. Sare] in Sweethins Ally near the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed September 16. 1676. Roger L'Strange."</note>
                  <note>Spelling of printer's name from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>Verse: "Story no more shall antient fabricks boast,".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:181433:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
            <head>BETHLEHEMS BEAUTY, LONDONS CHARITY, AND THE CITIES GLORY.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Panegyrical Poem on that Magnificent Structure, lately Erected in <hi>Moorfields,</hi> vulgarly called <hi>New-Bedlam.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Humbly Addreſt to the Honourable Maſter, Governours, and other Noble <hi>Benefactors</hi> of that Splendid and moſt uſeful <hi>Hoſpital.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Licenſed</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>September 16. 1676.</date>
                           </dateline> 
                           <signed>Roger L'Strange.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <l>STory no more ſhall <hi>Antient Fabricks</hi> boaſt,</l>
            <l>The mould'ring <hi>Pyramids</hi> on <hi>Egypts</hi> coaſt;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Sol</hi>'s vaſt <hi>Coloſsus,</hi> or thoſe mighty Things</l>
            <l>Which with <hi>Mortality</hi> upbraided <hi>Kings:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>All theſe could but vain Oſtentation yield,</l>
            <l>Whilſt we for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> do <hi>Build.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>When <hi>LONDON</hi> did in <hi>Funeral Aſhes</hi> lie</l>
            <l>But Ten years ſince, The <hi>Grief</hi> of every Eye,</l>
            <l>VVhere <hi>Deſolation</hi> Triumph'd in each <hi>Street,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Trampling our Stately'ſt Structures under Feet.</l>
            <l>VVho durſt <hi>Predict,</hi> or hope ſo ſoon to ſee</l>
            <l>Her thus <hi>Rebuilt,</hi> with greater <hi>Majeſtie?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Houſes! whoſe height and ſtrength ſeem to <hi>Conſpire,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To o'retop <hi>Thunder,</hi> and defiance <hi>Fire;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>Sun</hi> beholds not a more Brave <hi>Exchange,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Nor ſpacious Streets that in like order Range;</l>
            <l>VVhoſe lofty Fronts harmoniouſly Advance,</l>
            <l>As if (like <hi>Thebs</hi>) their Building were a Dance:</l>
            <l>Her <hi>Publick Halls</hi> as <hi>Pallaces</hi> appear,</l>
            <l>And out-vie Princes <hi>Courts</hi> ſomtimes for <hi>Chear:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Her <hi>Sacred Temples</hi> in a Decent State,</l>
            <l>Teach us with <hi>Awe</hi> and <hi>Reverence</hi> to wait</l>
            <l>There on our <hi>Glorious Maker,</hi> at once free</l>
            <l>From profane Filth, and gawdy Pageantree;</l>
            <l>Nor doubt I, Aged <hi>Pauls!</hi> Thy Reverend Pile</l>
            <l>To ſee <hi>Reſtor'd,</hi> The Glory of our Iſle,</l>
            <l>And for Rare <hi>Works,</hi> as well as <hi>Faith,</hi> become</l>
            <l>Superior far to <hi>Peters</hi> Fane at <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But to ſpeak theſe Glories, needs an abler Muſe,</l>
            <l>Ours only dares a <hi>Suburb Wonder</hi> chuſe:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>BEDLAM!</hi> That ſhall a laſting <hi>Witneſs</hi> be</l>
            <l>Of this great Cities generous <hi>Piety:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Magnificent Foundation! ſuch as ſhows</l>
            <l>The greatneſs of their Souls by whom it Roſe;</l>
            <l>So <hi>Brave,</hi> ſo <hi>Neat,</hi> ſo <hi>Sweet</hi> it does appear,</l>
            <l>Makes one <hi>Half-Madd</hi> to be a <hi>Lodger</hi> there;</l>
            <l>And thoſe poor Souls, whoſe <hi>Crazed Brains</hi> advance</l>
            <l>Their <hi>Roving Fancies</hi> to'th Extravagance</l>
            <l>Of being <hi>Princes,</hi> needs muſt think it True,</l>
            <l>VVhen they ſhall ſuch a Towering <hi>Pallace</hi> View.</l>
            <l>Since, <hi>Strangers</hi> that Survey the <hi>Galleries,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Find the <hi>Vaſt Length</hi> wearies their Travelling eyes;</l>
            <l>And ſome cry-out, "If ſuch a Place befits</l>
            <l>
               <hi>"Madmen, Henceforth who'le Study to be Wits?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>A hundred Rooms in curious order ſtand</l>
            <l>Each with its Bed and Furniture at hand.</l>
            <l>Th' Approaching Air, in every gentle Breeze,</l>
            <l>Is <hi>Fan'd</hi> and <hi>Winnow'd</hi> through the neighbouring <hi>Trees,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And comes ſo <hi>Pure,</hi> the <hi>Spirits</hi> to Refine,</l>
            <l>As if th' wiſe Governours had a Deſigne</l>
            <l>That ſhould alone, without <hi>Phyſick</hi> Reſtore</l>
            <l>Thoſe whom <hi>Groſs Vapours</hi> diſcompos'd before;</l>
            <l>But this <hi>Conceit</hi> is ſtifled by their <hi>Care,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The beſt of <hi>Arts Aſsiſtance</hi> to prepare,</l>
            <l>VVhat e're <hi>Galenick</hi> or <hi>Hermetick</hi> Skill</l>
            <l>Offers in Natures Aid, is ready ſtill.</l>
            <l>Convenient <hi>Diet's</hi> liberally beſtow'd,</l>
            <l>And all meet <hi>Helps</hi> from time to time Allow'd:</l>
            <l>Though many here their <hi>Reaſon</hi> do Regain,</l>
            <l>Yet none has ever <hi>Reaſon</hi> to <hi>Complain.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Here that miſcheivous Hagg, black <hi>Melancholly,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Mother</hi> of Diſcontent, and <hi>Nurſe</hi> of Folly</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Circe</hi>'s Transforming Magick ſtrangely Apes,</l>
            <l>And changes <hi>Men</hi> into a Thouſand ſhapes,</l>
            <l>Some <hi>Raving Wild,</hi> and ſome like <hi>Statues</hi> fixt,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Democritus</hi> with <hi>Heraclitus</hi> mixt.</l>
            <l>One Fancies ſtill his <hi>Cruel Miſtreſs</hi> by,</l>
            <l>To'ther upbraids her Friends <hi>Inconſtancy,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>He, <hi>Weaves</hi> Straw-Bracelets, which he calls her <hi>Hair,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And She, o'th' <hi>Wall</hi> writes Letters to her <hi>Dear,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Th' only <hi>True Lovers,</hi> now adays are here.</l>
            <l>One ſtill makes <hi>Almanacks,</hi> and thoſe as True,</l>
            <l>I dare engage, as moſt that <hi>Print</hi> them, do.</l>
            <l>Another Rails at <hi>Rome,</hi> with as much <hi>Senſe</hi>
            </l>
            <l>As ſome <hi>abroad</hi> for <hi>Conventicle Pence.</hi>
            </l>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus do fond <hi>Love,</hi> wild <hi>Zeal,</hi> fierce jealouſie,</l>
               <l>Immod'rate <hi>Studies,</hi> pinching <hi>Poverty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All Clubb to People this ſad <hi>Colony.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <l>VVhat <hi>Objects</hi> then more claim our <hi>Charity,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Than theſe that know not their own <hi>Miſery;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And where ſuch poor Diſtracted Souls are fed,</l>
            <l>How fitly is it call'd, <hi>The Houſe of Bread.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Thrice <hi>Noble Patriots,</hi> you have made it ſo,</l>
            <l>Immortal <hi>Thanks</hi> we to your <hi>Bounty</hi> owe,</l>
            <l>VVhoſe <hi>Liberal Hands</hi> and <hi>Contributions</hi> raiſe</l>
            <l>This <hi>Mighty Work,</hi> which the next Age muſt <hi>praiſe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Ours only can <hi>Admire;</hi> may Heaven bleſs</l>
            <l>Your <hi>Brave Deſigns</hi> with ſuitable <hi>Succeſs.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>May every <hi>Wretch</hi> comes here his <hi>Senſe</hi> obtain,</l>
            <l>To pay your <hi>Coſts</hi> with <hi>Grateful Pray'rs</hi> again,</l>
            <l>That when full Ripe with <hi>Honour,</hi> and with <hi>Years,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Your happy Diſſolution day appears.</l>
            <l>Perfuming Earth with your Exemplar <hi>Fames,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Th' <hi>Eternal Book</hi> may <hi>Regiſter</hi> your Names,</l>
            <l>Free <hi>Citizens</hi> o'th' <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To <hi>Raign</hi> with <hi>Him</hi> was Born in <hi>Bethlehem.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Sear</hi> in <hi>Sweethins Ally</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
