<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of Elizabeth Fenton widow, the relict and administratrix, of Richard Fenton gent. deceased respondent to the petition of William Crabb and Tho. Goldsmith appealants, humbly offered to the Lords spiritual and temporal in Parliament assembled.</title>
            <author>Fenton, Elizabeth, fl. 1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C911B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173517</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53298983</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53298983</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179760</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. B02578)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2802:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of Elizabeth Fenton widow, the relict and administratrix, of Richard Fenton gent. deceased respondent to the petition of William Crabb and Tho. Goldsmith appealants, humbly offered to the Lords spiritual and temporal in Parliament assembled.</title>
                  <author>Fenton, Elizabeth, fl. 1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Bristol :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Chicago Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fenton, Richard, fl. 1655 --  Estate --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Decedents' estates --  Cases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:179760:1"/>
            <head>The Caſe of <hi>Elizabeth Fenton</hi> Widow, the Relict and Adminiſtratrix, of <hi>Richard Fenton</hi> Gent. deceaſed Reſpondent to the Petition of <hi>William Crabb</hi> and <hi>Tho. Goldſmith</hi> Appeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, Humbly offered to the Conſideration, of the Right Honourable the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament Aſſembled.</head>
            <p>THE ſaid <hi>Richard Fenton</hi> being Owner of the ⅜ parts of the Ship <hi>Rainbow</hi> of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> whereof <hi>William Crabb</hi> and <hi>Thomas Goldſmith,</hi> (now Appealants from a Decree of the High Court of <hi>Chancery</hi>)And <hi>Richard Crabb, Alexander Gray,</hi> and <hi>Henry Haines,</hi> had each of them one 8th. part. They together in the year 1655. let the Ship to Freight, on a Voyage to <hi>Virginia;</hi> which ſhe performed, and returned ſafe to <hi>Briſtol,</hi> where the Appealants and <hi>Richard Crabb</hi> received her Freight, and other Profits ariſing by the ſaid Voyage, ⅜ parts whereof Apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to the aforeſaid <hi>Richard Fenton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſaid Part-Owners gave no Account of the aforeſaid Frieght and Profits to the ſaid <hi>Fenton,</hi> but inſtead thereof ſet forth the ſaid Ship a ſecond Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to <hi>Virginia:</hi> Whereto ſhe was Freighted, and ſet Sail, made her <hi>Voyage,</hi> and returned ſafe; but before ſuch her return the ſaid <hi>Richard Fenton</hi> dyed inteſtate. After whoſe deceaſe Letters of Adminiſtration of his Goods and Chattels were granted to <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his Wife, whereby ſhe became juſtly intituled to all his Perſonal Eſtate. And particularly to ⅜ parts of the Freight of the Ship <hi>Rainbow,</hi> for the aforeſaid two Voyages. All which the ſaid Part-Owners Received.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elizabeth Fenton</hi> demanded her Husbands and Inteſtates proportion of the ſaid Ship, for the aforeſaid Two Voyages from the Appealants, and other the Part-Owners; who refuſed to Accompt for the ſame, pretending that one <hi>Stafford</hi> was imployed by all the Owners, to Let the ſaid Ship and receive the Freight thereof, which he had done, and therefore was onely Accountable for the ſame. And thereupon prevailed with the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Fenton</hi> to referre the aforeſaid matters in controverſie to Arbitration. And Arbitrators for that purpoſe were appointed, before whom (when the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was abſent, and could not Attend) the Books of Account of the aforeſaid <hi>Stafford</hi> were produced, relating to the aforeſaid Ship, and two ſeveral Freights. And they thereupon (by ſurprize upon the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Fenton</hi> made their Award, whereby they directed and ordered only 14 l. to be paid her for her proportion, of the Profits and Freight of the aforeſaid two Voyages, (when there was 1000 l. due.) And the Appealants having Lett out the Ship a third Voyage, at 24 l. 7 s. 6 d. <hi>per Month.</hi> in which Voyage ſhe continued about 16 <hi>Months.</hi> Attached the ſaid <hi>Fentons</hi> proportion thereof to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell her to ſubmit to the ſaid Award.</p>
            <p>Thereupon ſhe preferred her Bill in the High and Honourable Court of <hi>Chancery,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hillary 1660.</note> to have an Accompt of the ſaid three Voyages, and to ſet aſide the undue Award made as aforeſaid, which cauſe came to be heard 12 <hi>July</hi> 17 <hi>Car. nunc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon the aforeſaid Award was ſet aſide, and Account directed to be taken by a Maſter, who (being aſſiſted by Merchants) after Examination of Witneſſes, and hearing Council, reported, 747 l. 16 s. 6 d. due to the Reſpondent, <hi>Elizabeth Fenton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Appealants prevailed for a Reference, upon which the Report aforeſaid was confirmed, and afterwards decreed, and the decree Signed, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled.</p>
            <p>Whereupon the Appealants and <hi>Richard Crabb</hi> aforeſaid, brought their Bill of review, aſſigning the ſame Errors they now do in their Appeal to this moſt Honourable Houſe, upon which they obtained an Order that paying 247 l. 16 s. 6 d. And ſecuring 500 l. more (remainder of the 747 l. 16 s. 6 d. decreed) all proceeding upon the ſaid Decree ſhould be ſtayed.</p>
            <p>To which Bill of review the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> put in her Anſwer, and Witneſſes being thereupon examined, and publication paſt, the Cauſe alſo came to be heard on the 22 <hi>April</hi> 22 <hi>Car. nunc.</hi> Upon which hearing the Court propoſed, That the ſaid <hi>Fenton</hi> ſhould go back to the firſt Referrees to review the account. Or that ſhe ſhould pay back the 247 l. 16 s. 6 d. aforeſaid (which was impoſſible for her to do) And then the Court would name new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrees.</p>
            <p>The ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Fenton</hi> being neceſſitated to make Choice of One of theſe two propoſals, choſe to go back to the former Referrees, who made their ſecond Award without hearing the Reſpondent, which was afterwards ſet aſide alſo; and a ſecond referrence made to a Maſter to take an Account of the aforeſaid three Voyages, which referrence being transferred to Sir <hi>John Coell</hi> be proceeded therein, and 10 <hi>April.</hi> 1675. made his Report, That the Reſpondent declaring her unwillingneſs that <hi>Stafford</hi> ſhould be imployed, and that the Appealants had promiſed ſhe ſhould have a juſt Account of the aforeſaid three Voyages, and that no wrong ſhould be done her, but that ſhe ſhould receive her proportion of the Profits of the ſaid Ship, And that the Appealants undertook the management thereof; after which he proceeded upon the ſaid Accounts, ſtated the ſame, and Reported above 500 l. due to the Reſpondent <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Appealants procured a new Referrence, <note place="margin">July 23, 1675.</note> with Order, that the aforeſaid <hi>Stafford</hi> ſhould be Examined, which was done accordingly: upon which, the ſaid Maſter made another Report, and made ſome further Abatement by the Reſpondents conſent in order to an Accommodation.</p>
            <p>To which Report, though in their Favour, the Appealants took Exceptions.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Exceptions coming to be Argued, <note place="margin">Feb. 26.27 Reg. nunc.</note> the Lord Chancellor approved, and Confirmed what the Maſter had done in Rejecting <hi>Staffords</hi> Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and upon ſome of the Exceptions, referred it back to the ſame Maſter, who having the Aſſiſtance of many Eminent Merchants in <hi>London,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Made his Third Report; <note place="margin">May 25, 1677.</note> To which the Appealants excepting, many Hearings were thereupon had, and a Re-referrence made, with Direction for the ſaid Maſter to State the Particulars of the Account, with the Values of the Cargo; which being done, he made his Fourth Report, and thereby certified 555 <hi>l.</hi> 8 <hi>s.</hi> 5 <hi>d.</hi> ½ due to the Reſpondent. To which Report, the Appealants alſo Excepted.</p>
            <p>The Exceptions being Argued, <note place="margin">Feb 20, 1678.</note> were Over-ruled; and the Report confirmed by Decree of the Court, ſince Signed and Inrolled.</p>
            <p>From which Decree, after Twenty Years proceeding in Chancery, and above 1000 <hi>l.</hi> Charges ſpent by the Reſpondent, by the Appealants Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Proſecution (to Her, and her five Childrens Ruine) the Appealants for further Vexation, have Appealed from the Decree pronounced upon the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Bill of Review, above Ten years ſince; Alledging,</p>
            <p>That the Award aforeſaid is ſet aſide by Surprize, <note place="margin">Firſt.</note> without conſent of Parties or proof of any undue Means uſed in obtaining thereof.</p>
            <p>That the Appealants, <note place="margin">Secondly.</note> 
               <hi>Gray</hi> and <hi>Haynes</hi> two of the Part-Owners in the ſaid Ship <hi>Rainbow,</hi> were no Parties to the Decree; Nevertheleſs the Sum Reported due to the Reſpondent, is Decreed to be paid by them; Therefore, and foraſmuch as <hi>Staffords</hi> Evidence was ſuppreſt, and the Decree made only againſt the Appealants, who were but two of the five Part-Owners, with the ſaid <hi>Richard Fenton</hi> in the ſaid Ship: And Foraſmuch as they Received never one peny of Money for the Freight of her, for the firſt two Voyages, but only for the Third, for which they were ready to Account.</p>
            <p>Therefore pray a Reverſal of the aforeſaid Decree.</p>
            <p>But the Reſpondent humbly Hopes for, and Prays the Juſtice of this moſt Honourable Houſe and then doubts not but to be Diſcharged from this Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Court, and receive all Coſts for the Charge and Vexation ſhe is put unto.</p>
            <p>And, For Reaſons for Diſmiſſing the Appealants Appeal, this Reſpondent Humbly Offers.</p>
            <p>That all the proceedings in the High Court of Chancery, have been and are Juſt and agreeable to Equity; and ſuch as againſt which the Appealants ought not to expect Relief.</p>
            <p>Becauſe by Sir <hi>John Coells</hi> Report, <note place="margin">Firſt.</note> It Appears, the Appealants did themſelves undertake and agree to Account for, and make Good what ſhould be due to the Reſpondent for the Freight aforeſaid, and ſo no need to make other Parties which otherwiſe would have been done.</p>
            <p>It Appeared, <note place="margin">Secondly.</note> the Awards before-mentioned were obtained on Falſe Allegations, and by Surprize; And (as ſo procured) were juſtly ſet aſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Staffords</hi> Evidence was ſet aſide for very good Reaſon, <note place="margin">Thirdly.</note> it appearing he had ſworn an Account to be Peruſed and Allowed by the Reſpondents Husband, whenas by Subſtantial Evidence it was made Appear, that he was Dead long before the Account was Writ; beſides other Falſities,</p>
            <p>Upon the whole Matter, the Reſpondent Humbly layes her ſelf, and five Fatherleſs Children, with this her Sad and Deplorable Condition, at your Lordſhips Feet; And ſubmits it to your Grave Judgment and Serious Conſideration.</p>
            <p>Whether, After two ſeveral Decrees of the High Court of <hi>Chancery,</hi> and Twenty Years Litigation, meerly upon Matters of Account <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> where Maſters have ſince the Decree been Attended above 100 times upon thoſe Accounts, and no Exceptions all that time taken to the Decree, nor any Appeal to this Honourable Houſe from the ſame, till after four ſeveral Reports made, and thoſe duly Confirmed; (after Exceptions put in thereto by the Appealants, were Argued) Whether, after all theſe Solemn proceedings, The Appealants, now finding that they are to pay this Reſpondent Money, (though not half ſo much as the Charges ſhe hath been put unto for Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the ſame) They ſhall be admitted to Appeal to this moſt Honourable Houſe to be Relieved, againſt a Decree to which themſelves have ſubmitted by all their Subſequent proceedings before the Maſter in that Court; Whereas if there had been any Juſt Cauſe of Complaint againſt the ſaid Decree, they might have Appealed from the ſame before their proceeding to Account, which (it is Humbly Conceived) is no leſs than a Submiſſion to the ſame, and owning it to be Juſt.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
