<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An elegy or, final farewel to Sir John Fenvvick, Baronet, who, for high-treason, &amp;c. was beheaded on Tower-Hill, Thursday the 28. of this instant January, 1697. / Written by a late converted Jacobite, and recommended to all male-content and disaffected persons of these kingdoms.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.2[207]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99886970</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99886970</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181530</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. B03255)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181530)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A1:1[209])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An elegy or, final farewel to Sir John Fenvvick, Baronet, who, for high-treason, &amp;c. was beheaded on Tower-Hill, Thursday the 28. of this instant January, 1697. / Written by a late converted Jacobite, and recommended to all male-content and disaffected persons of these kingdoms.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by J. Bradford, in New-street, without Bishopsgate near Hand-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "Behold, you Grandees, of this earthly globe,".</note>
                  <note>Within mourning borders.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:181530:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <p>MEMENTO MORI</p>
               </figure>AN ELEGY <hi>Or, final farewel to</hi> Sir JOHN FENWICK, Baronet, Who, for High-Treaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was Beheaded on <hi>Tower-Hill, Thurſday</hi> the 28. of this 
Inſtant <hi>January,</hi> 1697.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by a late Converted</hi> Jacobite, <hi>and Recommended to all Male-content and Diſaffected</hi> Perſons <hi>of theſe Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>BEhold, you <hi>Grandees,</hi> of this <hi>Earthly Globe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How ſickle <hi>Fortune</hi> HEROES dos diſrobe,</l>
               <l>Diſrobe, degrade, and utterly caſt down;</l>
               <l>No <hi>States</hi> are free, no not a very <hi>Crown.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have not late Years <hi>Exceſſive</hi> Changes wrought?</l>
               <l>Yea, have not KINGS <hi>Experience</hi> dearly bought?</l>
               <l>Thoſe <hi>Kings,</hi> I mean, who, by <hi>Deſpotick Power,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have ſought both <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Charters</hi> to devour</l>
               <l>The late King <hi>James</hi> (by ſome firnam'd the <hi>Juſt</hi>)</l>
               <l>Is not his <hi>Grandeur</hi> levell'd with the <hi>Duſt?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whilſt his <hi>Machines, Incendaries</hi> of Hell,</l>
               <l>Profuſely even their own <hi>Bloods</hi> do ſpill:</l>
               <l>CROVVNS, tho' uncertain, and a <hi>Mortal</hi> GEM,</l>
               <l>Are firmly fix'd upon a <hi>Sacred</hi> STEM,</l>
               <l>Not to be <hi>mov'd,</hi> but by a <hi>Power Sublime,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Scepter</hi> ſurely is a <hi>Staff Divine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achitophels</hi> a while may <hi>Favour</hi> Gain,</l>
               <l>Yet at the laſt their <hi>Labours</hi> are but vain</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Plots, Intriegues,</hi> their <hi>Treaſons</hi> diſanull'd</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Reaſon</hi> Captives, and their <hi>Senſes</hi> lull'd</l>
               <l>In <hi>Frantick Dreams,</hi> which ſo exaſperate</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Miſtaken Courage,</hi> that before too late,</l>
               <l>They ſeldom ſee the <hi>Error</hi> of their <hi>Way,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Miſplac'd Zeal</hi> dos in a Trice decay</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But, Oh ſtupendious! <hi>Folly</hi> dos ſo Reign</l>
               <l>That ſad Examples cannot Men refrain,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Towering Pride:</hi> AMBITION <hi>Satan</hi>'s Bait</l>
               <l>Draws <hi>Thoughtleſs Men</hi> into a diſmal ſtate:</l>
               <l>The <hi>ſoaring Mortal</hi> that to SOL would <hi>flye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>Wings</hi> dropt off, and from the <hi>lofty Skie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He fell a <hi>Victim</hi> to the <hi>Raging Sea;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So <hi>Haughty</hi> FENVVICK <hi>threw</hi> himſelf <hi>away.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ungrateful Sir! How couldſt thou ſtrive to tare</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Mothers Bowels, Queen</hi> EUROPA <hi>fair</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her <hi>choiceſt Food</hi> did ſhe not to thee give,</l>
               <l>And didſt not thou ith' midſt of <hi>Goſhen</hi> live</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Stores</hi> increas'd, thy <hi>Bleſſings</hi> did abound</l>
               <l>And nought but <hi>Pleaſures</hi> did thy TENT ſurround</l>
               <l>Thy VINE thus planted in a <hi>Fruitful Place,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With Joy thou might have run thy <hi>Human Race,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, <hi>full of Days</hi> laid down thy <hi>Life</hi> in PEACE,</l>
               <l>But woe! alas, inſtead of <hi>grateful</hi> PRAISE,</l>
               <l>Againſt thy DONOR thou didſt <hi>Treaſon</hi> raiſe,</l>
               <l>Deſpiſe <hi>His</hi> POVVERS: His <hi>Wiſe</hi> DECREES reject</l>
               <l>KINGS, next JEHOVAH claim <hi>profound Reſpect,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And now thy CEDAR's levell'd to the <hi>Ground</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Own Device</hi> thy ſelf did quite confound;</l>
               <l>For <hi>Pleaſures, Sorrow; Chains</hi> for <hi>Liberty;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For <hi>Fragrant Odours, Noyſom Scents</hi> annoy;</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>pleaſant Wines,</hi> thy moſt <hi>Delicious Fare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Quails, a loathſomneſs do bear,</l>
               <l>Thy LIFE a Pain, each DAY a heavy <hi>Yoke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Till at the length the <hi>Ax's</hi> fatal Stroke</l>
               <l>Thy Head lopps off; they juſtly looſe their <hi>own,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who dare their <hi>King,</hi> their Countries <hi>Head</hi> diſown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>FENVVICK to <hi>Folly</hi> thou a <hi>Martyr</hi> dies;</l>
               <l>Thy feeble MARTLETS muſt not think to riſe</l>
               <l>And ſoar in <hi>Grandeur</hi> with the EAGLE <hi>High,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe <hi>Fleeting Pinions</hi> mount unto the SKIE:</l>
               <l>Ambitious <hi>Phaetons</hi> may pretend to <hi>Steer</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sol's</hi> Mighty CHARIOT in a <hi>full Career,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But in a Moment they will ſurely find</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Feet</hi> too weak for their <hi>Ambitious</hi> MIND:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Martlet</hi>'s FEET, are for her <hi>Whiffling</hi> BRAIN</l>
               <l>Too <hi>ſhort</hi> and <hi>ſlender,</hi> therefore ſhe in vain</l>
               <l>Her Projects frames, when ſeated on the Ground;</l>
               <l>For Treaſon Here no Riſing Steps are found.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <head>EPITAPH.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>IF a</hi> Traytor <hi>may ſuch Favour have,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As to be lodg'd within the Grave.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon his Tomb, Inſcribe this Verſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which plainly dos his</hi> Fame <hi>expreſs:</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here <hi>Fenwick</hi> lies, whoſe reſtleſs <hi>Brain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No Bounds of <hi>Reaſon</hi> could contain;</l>
               <l>Who Courted Death, perſu'd his <hi>Fate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſought to ruin Church and State:</l>
               <l>Deſtroy'd his Cauſe, Orethrew his Friend,</l>
               <l>And brought himſelf to a fatal End.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>J. Bradford,</hi> in <hi>New-ſtreet,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Biſhopſgate,</hi> near <hi>Hand-Alley,</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
