<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The London prodigal, or The unfortunate spendthrift.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.4[131]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99884992</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99884992</idno>
            <idno type="VID">182800</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. B04152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 182800)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A4:2[132])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The London prodigal, or The unfortunate spendthrift.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.W. for R.C. over against the Globe in Little Brittain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "Oft have I wonder'd at the various state ..."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prodigals (Law) --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Saving and investment --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:182800:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <head>THE LONDON PRODIGAL, Or the Unfortunate Spendthrift.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>OFt have I wonder'd at the various ſtate,</l>
               <l>The ſtrange <hi>Moeanders</hi> and the turns of Fate,</l>
               <l>All humane actions topſie turvy hurl'd;</l>
               <l>Let's find ſome <hi>Bedlem</hi> for the frantick World.</l>
               <l>Some curſe their ſtars, and think the Gods unjuſt;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ye Heavens! and will ye thus reward our truſt?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Virtue's great, but our requital ſmall;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let's Act for ſomething, or not Act at all!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet I have ſeen ſome Philoſophick Souls,</l>
               <l>Whom ſo ſupine a piety controuls;</l>
               <l>That 'midſt their Poverty will preach Content,</l>
               <l>As Quaking Brethren do, <hi>Repent, repent.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Young Gallant who huffs it up and down,</l>
               <l>The Spendthrift, ſon of ſome penurious Clown;</l>
               <l>Thinking his Father hath good ſtore of pelf,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ah Bleſsed Jeſus take him to thy ſelf!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis time, grown old in grace, from hence to flee;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heaven's fit for him, and his Eſtate for me:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grant this requeſt, and I this vow will make,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſpend it bravely for my Fathers ſake.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Miſer dead, he ſtands no more in aw;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who dares affront? God damme, Sir, I'll draw.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then combs and ſets his flaxen Wig with art,</l>
               <l>To make ſome <hi>Whetſtones</hi> Lady break her heart;</l>
               <l>Feaſts nobly, ſets ſome Crowns upon the ſcore,</l>
               <l>Then to the Play-houſe, Tavern, or a Whore:</l>
               <l>Ere evening comes perhaps gets ſoundly drunk,</l>
               <l>And ſpends an hour in paſtime with a Punk;</l>
               <l>A dainty Girl as ere did catch a fall,</l>
               <l>She clings as cloſe as Ivy to the wall.</l>
               <l>But now reſolv'd to purchaſe great applauſe,</l>
               <l>And ſhow his valour in a womans cauſe,</l>
               <l>He builds a ſconce, the Bawd, the Whore he kicks,</l>
               <l>Then runs; <hi>Pox take you, Sir, are theſe your tricks?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Proud of his late ſucceſs, he doth defie</l>
               <l>All future dangers, and as ſtout as <hi>Guy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Breaks through the Watch, and then more valiant grows;</l>
               <l>The windows feel his fury as he goes;</l>
               <l>Claſh goes the Glaſs; the people wake, and fear</l>
               <l>Some Regiment of Cut-throat Papiſts near.</l>
               <l>Thus their fantaſtick thoughts themſelves beguile,</l>
               <l>When 'tis ſome drunken <hi>Hector</hi> all the while.</l>
               <l>But now i'th' midſt of his triumphant Reign,</l>
               <l>His greateſt Pleaſure proves his greateſt Pain;</l>
               <l>He finds his Stock diminiſh, and beſide</l>
               <l>Percieves himſelf compleatly Frenchify'd.</l>
               <l>Such pocky luck does to the Brave befall;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ah rotten Whores! Hells curſe light on you all!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now doth himſelf with purging med'cines drench,</l>
               <l>And thinks his <hi>Doctor</hi> dearer than his <hi>Wench.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Purge, the Syringe, and the Flux endur'd;</l>
               <l>His pocket drein'd, himſelf three quarters cur'd;</l>
               <l>Ventures abroad ſometimes, but yet by ſtealth;</l>
               <l>His <hi>Purſe</hi> b'ing now grown poorer than his <hi>health:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He finds his wants no longer can be hid,</l>
               <l>Nor can he huff, nor ſwagger as he did.</l>
               <l>His <hi>Taylor</hi> duns, his credits almoſt loſt,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Tavern</hi>-ſcores do haunt him like a <hi>Ghoſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He ſees his fault, and knows not what to think,</l>
               <l>At laſt reſolves to ſpunge on Gameſters drink;</l>
               <l>To pimp, to ſhark for all that ere he gets;</l>
               <l>Or fright ſome Cully from their Coyn and Wits.</l>
               <l>This further Curſe theſe Prodigals attends,</l>
               <l>Their Lives are oft leſs wretched than their Ends;</l>
               <l>Their thoughts, their actions ſacrific'd to vice,</l>
               <l>To ſwearing, drinking, huffing, whores and dice.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They headlong to their certain ruine run;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Gallows ſeems to call them, and they come.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>WITH ALLOWANCE.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.W.</hi> for <hi>R.C.</hi> over againſt the Globe in <hi>Little Brittain,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
