<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lamentation of a bad market, or, The drownding of three children on the Thames. With this fantastick tragy [sic] comedy, tis like that one or other pleas'd will be; because the method carrie, mirth there[i]n, or else the subject were not worth a pin: howe're you'l say it is no laughing matter, to see poor children drowned in the water. Tune of, The ladies fall. With allowance.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674-1679?</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L284A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide EBB65H[149]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99887190</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99887190</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181898</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. B04135)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181898)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A2:3[149])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lamentation of a bad market, or, The drownding of three children on the Thames. With this fantastick tragy [sic] comedy, tis like that one or other pleas'd will be; because the method carrie, mirth there[i]n, or else the subject were not worth a pin: howe're you'l say it is no laughing matter, to see poor children drowned in the water. Tune of, The ladies fall. With allowance.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for F[rancis]. Coles, T[homas]. Vere, J[ohn]. Wright, and J[ohn]. Clarke.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[between 1674-1679]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "Some Christian people all give ear ..."</note>
                  <note>Date, place of publication and publisher's names from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University, Houghton Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:181898:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
            <head>The lamentation of a bad Market,</head>
            <head type="sub">OR, The Drownding of three Children on the <hi>Thames.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>
                  <hi>With this fantaſtick Tragy Comedy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tis like that one or other pleas'd will be;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Becauſe the Method carrie, Mirth there<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or elſe the Subject were not worth a pin:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Howe're you'l ſay it is no laughing matter,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſee poor Children Drowned in the Water.</hi>
               </l>
            </argument>
            <opener>Tune of, The Ladies Fall.</opener>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>With Allowance.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>SOme</hi> Chriſtian people all give ear,</l>
               <l>unto the grief of us,</l>
               <l>Caus'd by the death of three children dear,</l>
               <l>the which it happned thus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And eke there befell an accident;</l>
               <l>by fault of a Carpenters Son,</l>
               <l>Who to ſaw chips, his ſharp Axe lent,</l>
               <l>woe worth the time may <hi>Lon.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>May <hi>London</hi> ſay woe worth the Carpenter,</l>
               <l>and all ſuch <hi>Block-head</hi> fools,</l>
               <l>Would he were hang'd like Serpent here,</l>
               <l>for jeſting with edg'd Tools.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For into the chips there fell a Spark,</l>
               <l>which <hi>put out</hi> in ſuch flames.</l>
               <l>That it was known into <hi>Southwark,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>which lies beyond the <hi>Thames.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For <hi>loe</hi> the Bridge was wondrous <hi>high,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>with water underneath;</l>
               <l>O're which as many <hi>Fiſhes</hi> flye,</l>
               <l>as <hi>Birds</hi> therein do breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And yet the fire conſum'd the bridge,</l>
               <l>not far from place of landing,</l>
               <l>And though the building was full big,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>it fell down</hi> not with <hi>ſtanding.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And eke into the water fell,</l>
               <l>ſo many Pewter Diſhes,</l>
               <l>That a man might take up very well,</l>
               <l>both <hi>boil'd</hi> and <hi>roaſted</hi> Fiſhes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And thus the Bridge of <hi>London</hi> Town,</l>
               <l>for building that was ſumptuous,</l>
               <l>Was <hi>all</hi> by fire <hi>half</hi> burnt down,</l>
               <l>for being too contumptious.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus you have <hi>all, but half</hi> my Song,</l>
               <l>pray liſt to what comes after,</l>
               <l>For now I have <hi>cool'd</hi> you with the <hi>fire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>i'le <hi>warm</hi> you with the <hi>water.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ile tell you what the Rivers name is,</l>
               <l>where theſe children did ſlide-a:</l>
               <l>It was fair <hi>Londons</hi> ſilver <hi>Thames,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>that keeps both tune and <hi>Tide-a.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All on the tenth of <hi>J<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nuary,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>to the wonder of much people,</l>
               <l>Twas frozen o're that <hi>well</hi> 'twould bear,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>almoſt</hi> a Country Steeple.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Three children ſliding thereabouts,</l>
               <l>upon a place <hi>too thin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That ſo at laſt it did fall <hi>out,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>that they did all fall <hi>in.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A gallant that was ſtanding near,</l>
               <l>a willing wager makes,</l>
               <l>But when he ſaw it would not bear,</l>
               <l>he would have drawn his ſtakes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He ſaid 'twould bear a man to ſlide,</l>
               <l>and laid a hundred pound:</l>
               <l>The other ſaid 'twould break, ſo it did,</l>
               <l>for three children there were drown'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of which ones head from his <hi>Should—</hi>
               </l>
               <l>ers ſtricken, whoſe name was <hi>John,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who then cry'd out as loud as he could,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O Lon, O Lon, a London.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh, Tut, Tut, Turn</hi> from thy ſinful race,</l>
               <l>thus did his ſpeech decay,</l>
               <l>I wonder that in ſuch a caſe,</l>
               <l>he had no more to ſay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And thus being drown'd, <hi>alack, alack,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>the water run down their throats,</l>
               <l>And ſtopt their breaths 3 hours by the clock,</l>
               <l>before they could get any Boats.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye Parents all that <hi>chidren</hi> have,</l>
               <l>and ye that have none yet,</l>
               <l>Preſerve your children from the grave,</l>
               <l>and teach them at home to ſit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For had theſe at a Sermon been,</l>
               <l>or elſe upon dry ground,</l>
               <l>Why then I would have never been ſeen,</l>
               <l>if that they had been <hi>drown'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Even as a Huntſman tyes his dogs,</l>
               <l>for fear they ſhould go fro him,</l>
               <l>So tye your children with ſtrict clogs,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>unty um</hi> and you'l <hi>undo um.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let Maids and Nurſes lye in wait,</l>
               <l>and watch them to a tittle,</l>
               <l>Becauſe your grief will be full great,</l>
               <l>to have them dye ſo <hi>little.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Story you have heard is call'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Children in the Wood.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Although the Subjects both are <hi>bad,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>yet this may be as <hi>good.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now for to conclude at laſt,</l>
               <l>I wiſh all others may,</l>
               <l>Be careful of their children dear,</l>
               <l>for fear they go aſtray.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for F. Coles, T. Vere, J. Wright, and J. Clarke.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
