<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Loyalty unfeigned, or, The true Protestants admonition. Being a pleasant new song. Two dangerous rocks on either hand appear, we now 'twixt Scilla and Caribdis steer, our pilot's care (you'l say) had need be great it had so, for on each hand stands a fate. On either hand to saile we suffer wrack, either to starboard or the larboard tack, therefore in wisdom he has thought it best to saile foreright, for there the danger's least. To the tune of, Busie fame, Young Pheon, or, The fathers exhortation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04262</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide EBB65H[13]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.8[322]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99887220</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99887220</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183464</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. B04262)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183464)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A2:4[13]; A5:2[255])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Loyalty unfeigned, or, The true Protestants admonition. Being a pleasant new song. Two dangerous rocks on either hand appear, we now 'twixt Scilla and Caribdis steer, our pilot's care (you'l say) had need be great it had so, for on each hand stands a fate. On either hand to saile we suffer wrack, either to starboard or the larboard tack, therefore in wisdom he has thought it best to saile foreright, for there the danger's least. To the tune of, Busie fame, Young Pheon, or, The fathers exhortation.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for P. Brooksby in VVest Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Verse: "Hold fast thy sword and scepter Charles ..."</note>
                  <note>Item at A5:2[255] imperfect: trimmed, affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University, Houghton Library and the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:183464:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <head>
               <hi>Loyalty unfeigned, Or,</hi> The true Proteſtants Admonition. <hi>Being a Pleaſant News SONG.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Two dangerous Rocks on either hand appear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We now 'twixt <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Caribdis</hi> ſteer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our Pilot's Care (you'l ſay) had need be great</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It had ſo, for on each hand ſtands a Fate.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>On either hand to Saile we ſuffer wrack,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Either to Starboard or the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arboard Tack,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Therefore in Wiſdom he has thought it beſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To Saile foretight, for there the danger's leaſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </argument>
            <opener>
               <hi>To the Tune of, <hi>Buſie Fame, Young Pheon,</hi> or, <hi>The Fathers Exhortation.</hi>
               </hi>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>HOld faſt thy Sword &amp; Scepter <hi>Charles</hi>
               </l>
               <l>ſad Times may elſe come on</l>
               <l>The murmurs that do dayly riſe</l>
               <l>ſmell Rank of Forty One.</l>
               <l>When Subjects g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve their Kings advice</l>
               <l>what their Errence ſhould be</l>
            </lg>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <lg>
               <l>But mark the Papiſts wills a while</l>
               <l>and you will find them great</l>
               <l>How willing they are to a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a new,</l>
               <l>from forty one to eight;</l>
               <l>The world againſt them doth complain,</l>
               <l>their cruelties abhor</l>
            </lg>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>They Plotted our late troubles here,</l>
               <l>though others puſhed them on,</l>
               <l>Fanaticks they were in the Keer,</l>
               <l>but Papiſts in the Van:</l>
               <l>Whilſt thoſe who firſt embroyl'd the Stats</l>
               <l>did laugh at our ſad woes,</l>
               <l>When they beheld our ſtrong debate</l>
               <l>turn'd to unfriendly blows.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Till three great Nations ſweat in blood,</l>
               <l>and many thouſands ſlain,</l>
               <l>The boſome of the Earth beſtrew'd,</l>
               <l>like dewey drops of Rain;</l>
               <l>Then was the time that <hi>Rome</hi> laugh'd loud,</l>
               <l>ſtand ſported with our rage,</l>
               <l>Till thruſting in amongſt the Croud,</l>
               <l>that did fierce Battel wage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Againſt the Lords anointed King,</l>
               <l>perſwading 'twas the way</l>
               <l>The Royal Power to nought to bring,</l>
               <l>by killing him bore ſway,</l>
               <l>This Ieſuitick Doctrine ſoon,</l>
               <l>(Oh fatal for to tell)</l>
               <l>Trampl'd upon the ſacred Crown,</l>
               <l>by it the Mitre fell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus Church &amp; State bled whilſt <hi>Rom's</hi> whore</l>
               <l>the Scarlet Beaſt did ride,</l>
               <l>The many headed factions bore</l>
               <l>her in her greateſt Pride;</l>
               <l>And patiently ſuſtain'd the Yoak</l>
               <l>from which they deem d them free,</l>
               <l>For then Religion was a Cloak</l>
            </lg>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor can it be more grievous ſure</l>
               <l>then when the proud Command</l>
               <l>Of Vſurpation we indure,</l>
               <l>curb'd by our Equals hands:</l>
               <l>Princes are noble, and what they</l>
               <l>impoſe we can diſguſt,</l>
               <l>In their commands we God obey,</l>
               <l>for they diſpence Heav'ns truſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then let us all beware in time,</l>
               <l>that <hi>Rome</hi> don't us deceive,</l>
               <l>And evermore abhor the crime</l>
               <l>of ſuch as ſeek <hi>Geneve:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let the blood-thirſty Papiſts all,</l>
               <l>and ſlaughter ſeeking Crew,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Scismaticks</hi> before the fall,</l>
               <l>great Monarch juſt and true.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then will the Nation reſt in peace,</l>
               <l>both Church and State will be</l>
               <l>Founded on perfect happineſs</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Charles</hi>'s Monarchy</l>
               <l>Will then its former Luſire gain,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>France</hi> then will ſtand in awe,</l>
               <l>Who now does triumph o're the ſlain,</l>
               <l>and gives the Nations Law.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Remember Kings are gods on Earth,</l>
               <l>for Heaven 'tis they bear ſway,</l>
               <l>And are moſt ſacred from their Birth,</l>
               <l>which binds us to obey:</l>
               <l>Then let ſuch periſh who deny</l>
               <l>obedience to the Laws,</l>
               <l>That do repine at Majeſty,</l>
            </lg>
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
