<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Protestants petition against popery, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04877</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 11893701</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3852</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide Lutt.III[132]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.2[151]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6189</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99890805</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99890805</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181477</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. B04877)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181477)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C6:1[134]; A1:1[152])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Protestants petition against popery, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B. Tooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse. First line of text: "From sawing the crown 'twixt phanaticks and fryars;".</note>
                  <note>An anti-Catholic satire.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  England --  Controversial literature --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:181477:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <head>THE Proteſtants Petition againſt Popery, &amp;c.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>FRom ſawing the Crown 'twixt Phanaticks and Fryars;</l>
               <l>From <hi>Whitehall</hi> Scaffolds, and <hi>Smithfield</hi> Fires;</l>
               <l>From the Jeſuits Morals, outdone by the Tryers,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From every Religion which Treaſon allows;</l>
               <l>From the <hi>Geneva</hi> Stiffneſs, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Bows;</l>
               <l>From affronting of God, or adoring of Shows,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From ſlicing the <hi>Pope</hi> into <hi>Presbyter John,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>More ſawcy in Conſort than he is alone;</l>
               <l>From a Legion of Devils to extirpate one,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From fermenting the Rout with <hi>Chemaerical</hi> Fears;</l>
               <l>From buying with Blood, and enjoying with Tears,</l>
               <l>A Liberty copied by that of <hi>Argiers,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From being twice chous'd with the ſame ſort of <hi>Cant;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From defending the King by <hi>Scotch Covenant;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From Reforming the Church till we leave nothing on't,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From a bifronted Conſcience, like the Sign of an Ale-houſe,</l>
               <l>That faces the Church, and outfaces the Gallows,</l>
               <l>With one ſide ſtark raw, and the other ſide callous,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From a Supreme Vicar to ſhackle the King;</l>
               <l>From a long round Senate, which means the ſame thing;</l>
               <l>From a Monk without, and a Devil within,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From advancing God's Church by ſuch Sins as wou'd fright ye,</l>
               <l>From liſting of Rebels to aid the Almighty;</l>
               <l>From taking of Ratsbane for <hi>Elixir Vitae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From the Popiſh Rage, and the Popular Fret,</l>
               <l>Which with Brotherly Malice their Sov'reign beſet;</l>
               <l>From reſcinding Bull, and reforming Bullet,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From the Lords in the Tower, and the Lords that are out;</l>
               <l>From aſſulting the King by Dagger or Vote;</l>
               <l>From our Ruine Point blank, or Nine Mile about,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From the Dark-Lanthorn Plot, and the Green-Ribbon Club;</l>
               <l>From brewing Sedition in a Sanctified Tub;</l>
               <l>From reforming a Prince by the Model of <hi>Job,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From the National Wealth by a <hi>Junto</hi> poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>By cajolling of one half, and plundering the reſt;</l>
               <l>From the Commonwealths Arms-with his Holines's Creſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The SECOND PART.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FRom meaſuring Devotion with Beads, or with Sand,</l>
                  <l>In a Language or Phraſe that we don't underſtand;</l>
                  <l>From a Preacher with Reliques or Spoons in his Hand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From ſtripping Religion to avoid the Exceſſes</l>
                  <l>Of a cumberſom Ruff, and a Collar of SS;</l>
                  <l>From His Holineſs, and Their Holineſſes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From Plot upon Plot, which no Herald admits,</l>
                  <l>Nor any Man elſe that is well in his Wits;</l>
                  <l>From Conſcience that comes like an Ague, by Fits,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From the Pope in One Stick, or the Pope in a Faggot;</l>
                  <l>From the Catholick Worm, and Schiſmatical Maggot;</l>
                  <l>From ſuch as ſwear round to keep what they ha'got,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From Penance reformed to a Stool of Repentance;</l>
                  <l>From a new Inquiſition to aid the <hi>Tridentines,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And the Savager Courts where the Godly give Sentence,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From ſetting Chriſt's Vicar to teaze his Vicegerent;</l>
                  <l>From the Saints in whom the ſame Sin is inherent,</l>
                  <l>The beſt Friends he has, though they ſeldom appear in't,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From <hi>St. Omers</hi> Conſult, and a <hi>Leyden</hi> Cabal,</l>
                  <l>Inveterate Foes both to <hi>Pauls</hi> and <hi>Whitehal;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From a Plot <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> like a Tennis-ball,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From the <hi>Roman</hi> Diſeaſe, and <hi>Geneva</hi> Phyſician;</l>
                  <l>From admitting Prophaneneſs to purge Superſtition;</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Raviliack</hi>'s or <hi>Bradſhaw</hi>'s Commiſſion,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From taking the Covenant, or baulking the Teſt;</l>
                  <l>From both the Renouncers when th'are but in jeſt;</l>
                  <l>From the Pope's hatching Eggs in a Presbyter's Neſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From the Godly Diſguiſes of Cropping and Shaving,</l>
                  <l>The different Ear-marks of Fooling and Knaving,</l>
                  <l>Though both can do both for the ſake of Soul-ſaving,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From a Jeſuit transformed to a Sanctified Elder,</l>
                  <l>And curſing <hi>Romes</hi> Church to her dear <hi>Hans-en-Kelder;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From hugging her Brats, and yet hope w' ave expell'd her,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From the <hi>Maſs</hi> and the Directory bound in one Volumn;</l>
                  <l>From the <hi>Trent</hi> Conventicle, and the <hi>Dort</hi> What d'e call'um;</l>
                  <l>From the Votaries of Saints, and thoſe that <hi>Peter</hi>'um and <hi>Paul</hi>'um,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From transforming a Cowl to an <hi>a-la-mode</hi> Jump;</l>
                  <l>From the Jeſuit's Bucket in the Miniſter's Pump;</l>
                  <l>From a Repreſentative Monſter, that's all over <hi>Rump.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Tooke,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
