<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pyramus and Thisbe: or, Love's master-piece. Behold the downfall of two lovers dear, and to their memorys, let fall a tear, a sad mistake their ruine did procure, when as they thought their friendship should endure; oh cruel fate! That cut them off in prime, and for enjoyment, would afford no time. To the tune of, Digby's farewel.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670-1677?</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide EBB65H[65]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99887273</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99887273</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181982</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. B04893)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181982)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A2:4[65])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pyramus and Thisbe: or, Love's master-piece. Behold the downfall of two lovers dear, and to their memorys, let fall a tear, a sad mistake their ruine did procure, when as they thought their friendship should endure; oh cruel fate! That cut them off in prime, and for enjoyment, would afford no time. To the tune of, Digby's farewel.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W[illiam]. Thackeray, T[homas]. Passenger, and W[illiam]. Whitwood.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[between 1670-1677]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "When all hearts did yeild unto Cupid as King ..."</note>
                  <note>Date of publication and publishers' names from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University, Houghton Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:181982:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
            <head>
               <hi>Pyramus</hi> and <hi>Thisbe:</hi> Or, Love's Maſter-piece.</head>
            <argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Behold the downfall of two Lovers D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ar,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And to their Memorys, let fall a Tear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A ſad miſtake their Ruine did procure,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When as they thought their FriendſhiP ſhould endure;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh Cruel Fate! That Cut them off in Pr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>me,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And for Enjoyment, would afford no time.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </argument>
            <opener>To the Tune of, <hi>Digby's Farewel.</hi>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen all hearts did yeild unto <hi>Cupid</hi> as King,</l>
               <l>And dying for Miſtreſſes was no ſtrang thing,</l>
               <l>When Maids without coyneſs did candidly deal,</l>
               <l>And men lov'd with conſtancy, faith, and true Zeal:</l>
               <l>There liv,d a fair pare of true Lovers in <hi>Greece</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who have ſtill bin accounted as Lov's maſter-piece.</l>
               <l>The Youth was call'd <hi>Pyramus, Thisbe</hi> the Maid:</l>
               <l>Their Love was immortal, and never decay'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But alaſs! their affections were croſt by ſad Fate:</l>
               <l>To wit, by the fewd and immortal debate.</l>
               <l>That had bin fomented for many years ſpace,</l>
               <l>Between both their Families, &amp; their whole Race.</l>
               <l>Which made the fair Cuple, tho ſcorcht w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loves fire,</l>
               <l>Still ſmother their Flames &amp; conceal their deſire:</l>
               <l>They ſigh'd ſtill in private, and wept all alone;</l>
               <l>And dar'd not diſcover a Tear or a Groan.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They ſigh'd all the Night, &amp; they gaz'd all the Day:</l>
               <l>Thus weeping and gazing, and ſighing away</l>
               <l>Their languſhing Lives, which they ſpent all in Tears,</l>
               <l>In ſighs, &amp; in groans, &amp; in amorous fears.</l>
               <l>And when the whole world was composd in a ſleep,</l>
               <l>Their grief kept them waking to ſigh &amp; to weep.</l>
               <l>Thus wandring all night, to the ſtars they complain,</l>
               <l>Of hardſhip, of fate, of their torments, and pain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when they no longer thoſe pains cou'd endure</l>
               <l>Their Love did begin for to ſeek out ſome Cure.</l>
               <l>And ſo they appointed one Night for to meet</l>
               <l>In ſome neighbouring Vally, and there for to greet:</l>
               <l>And thence fly away to ſome far diſtant Cave,</l>
               <l>To love at their leaſure: contented to have</l>
               <l>The joyes of each other; and there let loves flame</l>
               <l>Burn quietly out without danger of blame.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:181982:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſo when that <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> had run out his Race,</l>
               <l>Fair <hi>Thisbe</hi> came firſt into the meeting place.</l>
               <l>Impatient ſhe ſtood and expected her Dear;</l>
               <l>She thought that each moment he ſtaid, was a year.</l>
               <l>Then under a Mulbery-tree down ſhe lies,</l>
               <l>But ſcarce was lay down when ſhe preſently ſpies</l>
               <l>A grim and fierce Lyon beſmea'd all vvith Blood,</l>
               <l>Came wandring down from ſhe neighbou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing wood</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Away run the Nimph to a Cave in a Fright.</l>
               <l>She fly's, &amp; her Mantle is loſt in the flight:</l>
               <l>Which the bloody Lyon takes up in his Pawes</l>
               <l>He tears it, &amp; then with the Raggs wipes his jaws.</l>
               <l>Soon after p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oor <hi>Pyramus</hi> came for to find.</l>
               <l>His long vviſht for <hi>Thisbe:</hi> but fate prov'd unkind.</l>
               <l>For vvhen divine joys he did hope for to have</l>
               <l>He found but a vvinding ſheet, death, &amp; cold Grave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For vvhen that he ſaw his loves Mantle all tore.</l>
               <l>Bedew'd all vvith blood, &amp; beſmear'd all with Goar:</l>
               <l>And then ſaw the Lyon trot over the plain,</l>
               <l>He falſly concluded his <hi>Thisby</hi> vvas ſlain.</l>
               <l>O vvho can expreſs the vaſt torment and ſmart,</l>
               <l>The pangs and the anguiſh &amp; grief of his heart?</l>
               <l>He made the Woods ring vvith his pitiful moanes</l>
               <l>The Rocks &amp; the Mountains dis Eccho his Groans.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alaſs: (ſaid <hi>Pyramus</hi>) could ſhe then find</l>
               <l>No help from the Gods! are they ſo unkind?</l>
               <l>Or elſe have they ſtole her avvay from our ſight,</l>
               <l>And ſo Rob d the Earth to make Heaven more bright?</l>
               <l>O tell me kind Sta<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s! come and tell me but vvhere</l>
               <l>My <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sbe</hi> is gon, and Ile follow my dear.</l>
               <l>Two death-vvounds already I bear in my breaſt.</l>
               <l>Once vvounded by Love &amp; by grief novv oppreſſ.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ile vveep out my life, &amp; Ile ſigh out my Soul:</l>
               <l>Ile groan for my Love till my Carcaſs grows cold.</l>
               <l>Her Mantle Ile take for my ſad Winding-ſheet,</l>
               <l>In that mournful poſture my <hi>Thisbe</hi> Ile meet.</l>
               <l>But a languiſhing death comes vvith too much delay:</l>
               <l>Great grief is impatient of ſo long a ſtay.</l>
               <l>Ile make greater haſt to my Love: at vvhich vvord</l>
               <l>The Youth ſtab'd himſelf to the hea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t with his Sword.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By this time fair <hi>Thisbe</hi> was came from he Cave</l>
               <l>So pale that ſher ris like a Ghoſt from its Grave,</l>
               <l>For when ſhe her <hi>Pyramu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> dying did ſee,</l>
               <l>She look'd much more like to a Carcaſs than he.</l>
               <l>You'd have thought that the Nymph woud before him have dy d</l>
               <l>She fel on his body <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen mournfully c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y'd</l>
               <l>O <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy my dear <hi>Pyramus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy ſo unkind;</l>
               <l>Why <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un you avvay and leave <hi>Thisbe</hi> behind?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At <hi>Thisbie<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſvveet Name they Youth lifts up his eyes:</l>
               <l>He looks, &amp; he ſighs, &amp; then ſhuts them &amp; dyes:</l>
               <l>He gaz'd till he dy'd then content vvith the ſight.</l>
               <l>Away to <hi>Eliziu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> his Soul took its flight.</l>
               <l>And <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> did after it preſently flye:</l>
               <l>She ſtruggled, &amp; ſtrove, and made haſt for to dye.</l>
               <l>And ſuch haſt ſhe made in <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>retaking her dear</l>
               <l>She ne <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſtay'd <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o complain nor ſca<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce drop a Tear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her tender, and gentle heart ſoon burſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith grief!</l>
               <l>And Death ſtole away her fa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Soul like a Thief.</l>
               <l>Then <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er cold body ſhe lay by her Love.</l>
               <l>Both pitty'd by all the kind Gods of the G<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ove.</l>
               <l>The amorous <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les and Nigh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ingalls <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ung</l>
               <l>Their Obſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>qu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es: &amp; n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>s their Knell rung.</l>
               <l>And each loving beaſt of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he wood left his Cave,</l>
               <l>And came ſo: to make the dead Lovers a Grave,</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London Printed for <hi>W. Thack<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ray, T. Paſſinger,</hi> and <hi>W. Whitwood.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
