<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pattern of love; or, The faithful lovers well met. Here's love for love you may behold, and true love better is than gold: for if my song you well do mind, patterns of true love here you'l find. To the tune of, The cannons rore. This may be printed, R.P.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685-1688?</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P872</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide EBB65H[51]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.8[250]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99887256</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99887256</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183404</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. B04952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183404)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A2:4[51]; A5:2[195])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pattern of love; or, The faithful lovers well met. Here's love for love you may behold, and true love better is than gold: for if my song you well do mind, patterns of true love here you'l find. To the tune of, The cannons rore. This may be printed, R.P.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Blare at the Looking-Glass on London-bridge.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[between 1685-1688]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date and place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Verse: "Come and help me to complain ..."</note>
                  <note>Item at A5:2[195] imperfect: trimmed, affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University, Houghton Library and the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb n="250" facs="tcp:183404:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
            <head>A Pattern of LOVE; OR, The Faithful Lovers well met.</head>
            <argument>
               <l>Here's Love for Love you may behold,</l>
               <l>And true love better is than Gold:</l>
               <l>For if my Song you well do mind,</l>
               <l>Patterns of true love here you'l find</l>
            </argument>
            <opener>To the Tune of, <hi>The Cannons Rore.</hi>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>This may be Printed,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>R. P.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>COme and help me to complain,</l>
               <l>Er'e my heart doth break with pain,</l>
               <l>My love unkind doth me diſdain,</l>
               <l>which doth increaſe my paſſion,</l>
               <l>His perſon it is ſo compleat,</l>
               <l>All Females do delight to ſee't</l>
               <l>And ſtand amaz'd when him they meet,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>the flower of all the Nation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He is ſo rare in every part,</l>
               <l>So full of vertue and deſert,</l>
               <l>That he did quickly win my heart,</l>
               <l>and made ſuch alteration:</l>
               <l>That all my comforts ſoon were gon</l>
               <l>And him alone I doted on;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea night and day I think upon</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>the flower of all the Nation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus languiſhing in Bed all night,</l>
               <l>And thinking on my hearts delight,</l>
               <l>As if he had been in my ſight</l>
               <l>ſuch was Loves operation;</l>
               <l>I wrung my hands and tore my hair,</l>
               <l>And almoſt fell into diſpair,</l>
               <l>Becauſe my deareſt was not there,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>the flower of all the Nation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I often ſtretched forth my arms,</l>
               <l>And with a kind of ſeeming Charms,</l>
               <l>I ſtrove to keep him from all harms,</l>
               <l>by <hi>Cupids</hi> ſtrong perſwaſion;</l>
               <l>Then in a moment I did cry,</l>
               <l>O come my Love, or elſe I dye,</l>
               <l>Wanting thy precious company,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>I love beſt in the Nation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>For while ſhe made this grievous moan,</l>
               <l>For her beloved deareſt one,</l>
               <l>He was hard by, to her unknown,</l>
               <l>and near her kept his ſtation;</l>
               <l>At laſt he bluſhing to her came,</l>
               <l>Which ſet the Damſel on a flame,</l>
               <l>'Cauſe ſhe againſt him did Exclaim,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>ſhe lov'd beſt in the Nation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Don't complain, my deareſt dear,</l>
               <l>For I thy hearts delight, am here,</l>
               <l>And come to baniſh all thy fear,</l>
               <l>then do no more torment thee;</l>
               <l>For I will work both night and day,</l>
               <l>To keep my true love fine and gay,</l>
               <l>Then all the world will ſurely ſay,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>I ſtrive for to content thee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nothing ſhall be too dear for thee,</l>
               <l>If it for Gold may purchas'd be,</l>
               <l>For ſince thou haſt made choice of me,</l>
               <l>thou need'ſt not to repent thee;</l>
               <l>Thy Beauty I moſt highly praiſe,</l>
               <l>I will be kind to thee always,</l>
               <l>And thou ſhalt ſee brave Golden days,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>let this my love, content thee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And whereſoever I do go,</l>
               <l>The world ſhall all thy Vertues know,</l>
               <l>And i'le ſet forth thy praiſes ſo,</l>
               <l>that nothing ſhall torment thee;</l>
               <l>I'le write Encomiums on thy Name,</l>
               <l>And ſpread them on the Wings of fame,</l>
               <l>Then do no more thy true love blame;</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>that ſtrives for to content thee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I'le truly keep my Nuptial Vows,</l>
               <l>As Law and Reaſon both allows,</l>
               <l>And be ſo careful of my Spouſe,</l>
               <l>that nothing ſhall torment thee;</l>
               <l>I'le feaſt mine eyes with thy dear ſight;</l>
               <l>And in thy company delight,</l>
               <l>Yea, never leave thee day nor night,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>my Dear let this content thee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnto the Church ſtraightway we'l go,</l>
               <l>And to the world will plainly ſhow,</l>
               <l>The faithful love to thee I owe,</l>
               <l>then do not thou torment thee;</l>
               <l>According to thy just Deſert,</l>
               <l>I'le change with thee my love-ſick heart,</l>
               <l>Till cruel death our loves ſhall part,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>my Dear let this content thee.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
