<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The royoters [sic] ruine, in a dialogue betwixt a spend-thrift and a whore. Or, a relation of a two-penny bargain. Of a spend-thrift proffering two pence to a whore having spent all but that on her before. The tune is, He that hath most money is the best man.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670-1682?</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05002</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide EBB65H[72]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99887280</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99887280</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181989</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. B05002)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181989)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A2:4[72])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The royoters [sic] ruine, in a dialogue betwixt a spend-thrift and a whore. Or, a relation of a two-penny bargain. Of a spend-thrift proffering two pence to a whore having spent all but that on her before. The tune is, He that hath most money is the best man.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T[homas]. Passenger at the three Bibles on the middle of London Bridge.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[between 1670-1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "A lusty young shaver, a [...] gallant ..."</note>
                  <note>Date, place of publication and publisher's name from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University, Houghton Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:181989:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <head>The Royoters Ruine, In a Dialogue betwixt a Spend-thrift and a Whore. Or, a Rlation of a two-penny Bargain.</head>
            <argument>
               <l>Of a Spend-thrift proffering two pence to a Whore</l>
               <l>Having ſpent all but that on her before.</l>
            </argument>
            <opener>The Tune is, <hi>He that hath moſt Money is the beſt Man.</hi>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> Luſty young Shaver, a vapouring Gallant,</l>
               <l>That vainly had ſpent, and conſum'd his eſtate,</l>
               <l>In Taverns and Ale-houſes waſting his talent</l>
               <l>Reſolving, repentance did then come too late,</l>
               <l>Examining then of his Pocket, he found it</l>
               <l>Was very much empty, and he was grown poor,</l>
               <l>Quoth he now my Moners gone all to one two-pence</l>
               <l>I'l make a clear end and ſpend that on a Whore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as along in the ſtréets he was walking</l>
               <l>He chanced with one of his Mobs for to méet,</l>
               <l>All in her ſilks and her bravery adorned</l>
               <l>With a Complement he there his Mobſie did gréet,</l>
               <l>Swéet heart if you will go with me to an Ale-houſe,</l>
               <l>And grant me thy pleaſure now <hi>I</hi> am grown poor.</l>
               <l>I have but one two-pence left, on thée I'l ſpend it,</l>
               <l>Quoth ſhe then go look out your two-penny Whore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My deareſt thou knoweth my former condition</l>
               <l>And how <hi>I</hi> have ſpent my eſtate upon thée</l>
               <l>And now for to ſlight me it breeds my contrition,</l>
               <l>And makes me with ſorrow tormented to be.</l>
               <l>For <hi>I</hi> have but two-pence left, and I will ſpend it,</l>
               <l>On thee, <hi>I</hi> proteſt my love <hi>I</hi> have no more,</l>
               <l>Quoth ſhe you may ſerve for a Pimp to another</l>
               <l>For <hi>I</hi> will be none of your two-penny Whore.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen formerly <hi>I</hi> in my ſilks was adorned</l>
               <l>And obout my neck wore, a fine flanders lac'd Band</l>
               <l>Vpon my head was nole's then a Beaver,</l>
               <l>What was there then <hi>I</hi> had not at command</l>
               <l>Remember that we two, at that time together,</l>
               <l>Took ſweet recreation, before I was poor,</l>
               <l>Quoth ſhe Sir at that time <hi>I</hi> was your companion,</l>
               <l>And what muſt <hi>I</hi> now be your two-penny Whore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My former acquaintance with neareſt relations</l>
               <l>Becauſe <hi>I</hi> before their adviſe would not take</l>
               <l>Do very much ſlight me, men of reputation</l>
               <l>My company ſhuns, and do me quite forſake,</l>
               <l>And bids me go ſeek for my baudy companions</l>
               <l>Where <hi>I</hi> have conſum'd my eſtate all before,</l>
               <l>Qd. ſhe <hi>I</hi> would have all your friends for to know it</l>
               <l>That <hi>I</hi> will be none of your two-penny Whore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou know'ſt that in company we two together</l>
               <l>Have cauſed five pounds to be ſpent at a Clap</l>
               <l>All out of my Pocket O how canſt thou ſlight me,</l>
               <l>And then could ſo c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ely hugge me in thy Lap.</l>
               <l>It was for my money and not for my perſon,</l>
               <l>That you did my company ſo much adore</l>
               <l>However I pray thée beſtow me this two pence,</l>
               <l>Quoth ſhe I will not be your two penny whore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How often with Oaths, and with great proteſtation</l>
               <l>Ingaged you have to be faithful to me,</l>
               <l>In weal or in wee <hi>I</hi> ſhould nere be forſaken,</l>
               <l>And now all my Coyn's gone, <hi>I</hi> ſlighted muſt be</l>
               <l>But yet here<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a two pence left pray thée now take it</l>
               <l>And let us do once as we have done before.</l>
               <l>Quoth ſhe <hi>I</hi> nere did for two pence and therefore</l>
               <l>Be packing and hunt out your two penny whore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wen then my dear Love if you, <hi>I</hi> not be perſwaded</l>
               <l>To take this my money becauſe it is ſmall,</l>
               <l>Let us do a little, a very, very little</l>
               <l>For former acquaintance and that ſhall be all.</l>
               <l>Quoth ſhe, <hi>I</hi> do ſcorn for to break my old cuſtome,</l>
               <l>Another man I have to wait on therefore</l>
               <l>I muſt bid a farewel both to you and your two pence</l>
               <l>For I ſcorn to be counted a two penny whore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quoth ſhe Sir before we depart I will tell you,</l>
               <l>I dare undertake, toproſcribe you a way</l>
               <l>How you may be doing, then let's to an Alehouſe</l>
               <l>But take notice before, Halfe a Crown is my pay</l>
               <l>Then give your two pence in earneſt at preſent</l>
               <l>You ſhall have your requeſt ſir, although you be poor</l>
               <l>But this I muſt tell you before you begin it,</l>
               <l>Ile ſet ſeven Groats Sir upon your old ſcore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And thus you may ſée the condition of wantons</l>
               <l>And in what a wanton condition they are,</l>
               <l>Before they will leave of their luſtful occaſions</l>
               <l>If they cannot get money they truſt out their ware,</l>
               <l>They'l kéep a man company while his Coyn laſteth</l>
               <l>And never forſake him untill he be poor.</l>
               <l>And then much ado he ſhall have with his wanton,</l>
               <l>For one ſingle Iobbe to ſet on the ſcore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You Gallants and others I wiſh you be careful,</l>
               <l>That have an Eſtate, leſt you vainly <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> waſte</l>
               <l>And fly evil company, of them be fearful,</l>
               <l>Leſt into Poverty you ſhould be caſt,</l>
               <l>And afterwards you be forc't with ſubmisſion</l>
               <l>To creep unto thoſe where you ſpent all your ſtore</l>
               <l>The beſt way <hi>I</hi> know of, for you to prevent i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Is to keep your goods out of the hands of a Whore.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for T. Paſſenger at the three Bibles on the middle of London Bridge.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
