<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true lovers knot untied: being the right path whereby to advise princely virgins how to behave themselves, by the example of the renowned princess, the Lady Arabella, and the second son of the Lord Seymore, late Earl of Hartfort. To the tune of, Frog's galliard, &amp;c. Licensed and entered according to order.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695-1700?</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2749</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide EBB65H[118]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99887324</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99887324</idno>
            <idno type="VID">182035</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. B06254)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 182035)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A2:4[118])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true lovers knot untied: being the right path whereby to advise princely virgins how to behave themselves, by the example of the renowned princess, the Lady Arabella, and the second son of the Lord Seymore, late Earl of Hartfort. To the tune of, Frog's galliard, &amp;c. Licensed and entered according to order.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by and for W[illiam]. O[nley]. and A[lexander]. M[ilbourn]. and are to be sold by the booksellers of Pye-corner and London-bridge.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[between 1695-1700]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "As I to Ireland did pass ..."</note>
                  <note>Date of publication and publishers' names from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University, Houghton Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:182035:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <head>THE <hi>True Lovers Knot Vntied:</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Being the right PATH whereby to adviſe Princely Virgins how to Behave themſelves, by the Example of the Renowned Princeſs, the Lady <hi>ARABELLA,</hi> and the Second SON of the Lord <hi>Seymor,</hi> late Earl of <hi>Hartfort.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <opener>To the Tune of, <hi>Frog</hi>'s Ga<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liard, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </opener>
            <argument>
               <p>Licenſed and Entered according to Order.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>AS I to <hi>Ireland</hi> did paſs,</l>
               <l>I ſaw a Ship at Anchor lay,</l>
               <l>Another Ship likewiſe there was,</l>
               <l>which from fair <hi>England</hi> took her way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Ship that ſa<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l'd from fair <hi>England,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>unknown unto our Gracious King,</l>
               <l>The Lord Chief Iuſtice did command,</l>
               <l>that they to <hi>London</hi> ſhould her bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I drew more near and ſaw more plain,</l>
               <l>Lady <hi>Arabella,</hi> in Diſtreſs,</l>
               <l>She wrung her hands and wept amain,</l>
               <l>bewailing of her Heavineſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When near fair <hi>London</hi> Tower ſhe came,</l>
               <l>whereas her Landing-<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lace ſhould be,</l>
               <l>The King and Queen with all their Train,</l>
               <l>did meet this Lady gallantly:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How now, <hi>Arabella,</hi> ſaid our King,</l>
               <l>unto this Lady ſtraight did ſay,</l>
               <l>Who hath firſt ty'd ye to this thing,</l>
               <l>that you from <hi>England</hi> took your way?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>None but myſelf, my Gracious Liege,</l>
               <l>theſe ten long years i've been in love</l>
               <l>With the Lord <hi>Seymor</hi>'s ſecond Son,</l>
               <l>the Earl of <hi>Hartford</hi> ſo we prove:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though he be not the mightieſt Man,</l>
               <l>of Goods and Livings in the Land,</l>
               <l>Yet I have Lands us to maintain,</l>
               <l>ſo much your Grace doth underſtand:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Lands and Livings are well known</l>
               <l>unto your Books of Majeſty,</l>
               <l>Amounts to twelveſcore pound a week,</l>
               <l>beſides what I do give, quoth ſhe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In gallant <hi>Darby-ſhire</hi> likewiſe,</l>
               <l>I nineſcore Beadſmen maintain there,</l>
               <l>With Hats and Gowns, and Houſe-rent free,</l>
               <l>and every Man five Marks a Y<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I never raiſed Rent, ſaid ſhe,</l>
               <l>nor yet oppreſt the Tennant poor,</l>
               <l>I never took no Bribes for <unclear>Fines</unclear>,</l>
               <l>for why, I had enough before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whom of your Nobles will do ſo,</l>
               <l>for to maintain the Commonalty?</l>
               <l>Such Multitudes would never grow,</l>
               <l>nor be ſuch ſtore of Pove<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I would I had a Milk-maid been,</l>
               <l>or born of ſome more low Degree,</l>
               <l>Then I might have loved where I like,</l>
               <l>and no Man could have hindred me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or would I were ſome Yeoman's Child,</l>
               <l>for to receive my Portion now,</l>
               <l>According unto my Degree,</l>
               <l>as other Virgins as I know.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The higheſt Branch that ſoars aloft,</l>
               <l>needs muſt beſhade the Mirtle-tree,</l>
               <l>Needs muſt the ſhaddow of them both,</l>
               <l>ſhaddow the third in his Degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when the Tree is cut and gone,</l>
               <l>and from the Ground is bore away,</l>
               <l>The loweſt Tree that there doth ſtand,</l>
               <l>in time may grow as high as they.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Once when I thought to have been Queen,</l>
               <l>but yet t<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at ſtill I do deny,</l>
               <l>I knew your Grace had right to th' Crown,</l>
               <l>before <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You of the eldeſt Siſter came,</l>
               <l>I of the ſecond in Degree,</l>
               <l>The Earl of <hi>Hartford</hi> of the third,</l>
               <l>a Man of Royal Blood was he.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſo Good-night, my Soveraign Leige,</l>
               <l>ſince in the Tower I muſt lye,</l>
               <l>I hope your Grace will condeſend,</l>
               <l>that I may have my Liberty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lady <hi>Arabella,</hi> ſaid our King,</l>
               <l>I to your Freedom would conſent,</l>
               <l>If you would turn and go to Church,</l>
               <l>there to receive the Sacrament.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſo Good-night, <hi>Arabella</hi> fair,</l>
               <l>our King reply'd to her again,</l>
               <l>I will take Counſel of my Nobility,</l>
               <l>that you your Freedom may obtain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Once more to Priſon muſt I go,</l>
               <l>Lady <hi>Arabella</hi> then did ſay,</l>
               <l>To leave my Love breeds all my Woe,</l>
               <l>the which will be lives decay,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Love is a Knot none can unknit,</l>
               <l>Fancy a liking of the Heart,</l>
               <l>Him whom I love I cannot forget,</l>
               <l>though from his preſence I muſt part.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The meaneſt People enjoy their Mates,</l>
               <l>but I was born unhappily,</l>
               <l>For being croſt by cruel Fates,</l>
               <l>I want both Love and Liberty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But Death I hope will end the Strife,</l>
               <l>Farewel, farewel, my Love, quoth ſhe,</l>
               <l>Once I had thought to have been thy Wife,</l>
               <l>but now am forc'd to part with thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At this ſad Meeting ſhe had cauſe,</l>
               <l>in heart and mind to grieve full fare,</l>
               <l>After that time <hi>Arabella</hi> fair,</l>
               <l>did never ſee Lord <hi>Seymor</hi> more.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>London:</hi> Printed by and for <hi>W. O.</hi> and <hi>A. M.</hi> and are to be ſold by the Bookſellers of <hi>Pye-corner</hi> and <hi>London-bridge.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
