<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of Capt. Kempthorn's engagement, in the Mary-Rose, with several Algier men of war.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2899B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R185675</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52612467</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52612467</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179691</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. B06274)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179691)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2796:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of Capt. Kempthorn's engagement, in the Mary-Rose, with several Algier men of war.</title>
                  <author>Hollar, Wenceslaus, 1607-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Text in four columns.</note>
                  <note>Engraving signed: W. Hollar delineanit et sculpsit.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Naval battles --  Mediterranean Sea --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:179691:1"/>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>A. The Mary Rose</item>
                  <item>B. The Hambererough Frigatt a Merchant</item>
                  <item>C. The Roe Keleh</item>
                  <item>D. a Scotch Merchant bound for Cadiz</item>
                  <item>E. a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> which came with us from Tangier bound for Sal<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>F. The Half Moon an Algier Man of Ware the charging <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> had <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Gunns and 400 men</item>
                  <item>G. Orange tree being the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all 30 Gunns <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Men</item>
                  <item>H. Seven Starrs 30 Gunns 300 Men</item>
                  <item>I. Whi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 30 Gunns 240 Men</item>
                  <item>K. The Har<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 28 Gunns 260 Men</item>
                  <item>L. Golden <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Turks Admirall he had <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Gunns 300 Men</item>
                  <item>M. The <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ell <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Pri<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>N. The P<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>O. French Merchant</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>A</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>B</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>C</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>D</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>E</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>F</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>G</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>H</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>I</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>K</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>L</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>M</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>N</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>O</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of sailing ship</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <byline>W. Holler delineauit et ſculpſit</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <head>A True Relation of Capt <hi>Kempthorn's</hi> Engagement, in the <hi>Mary-Roſe</hi>; with ſeven <hi>Algier</hi> Man of War.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ANue</hi> 1669, in the beginning of <hi>December,</hi> His Excellency the Lord Ambaſſador <hi>Hanry Howard,</hi> having obtain'd from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror ot <hi>Barbary, Taſſaleta,</hi> a Letter of Security, to his content, had reſolv'd to proſecute his Journey to the Court; to which end, he order'd his Baggage, and moſt of his Retinue, to be Embarqu'd in the <hi>Mary Roſe,</hi> which had Tranſported him from <hi>England</hi>; and purpos'd himſelf, with ſome few of his Gentlemen and Servants, to the number of fifteen or ſixteen, to go by Land, and the Ship by Sea to <hi>Salee</hi>; reſolving, as ſoon as we were under Sail, to begin his Journey alſo.</p>
            <p>Thus accordingly we ſet Sail on Wedneſday the eighth of the ſaid Month, at two a clock in the morning, with the Wind at North-Eaſt, along the Shore of <hi>Barbary</hi>; and having paſt <hi>Arzila</hi> that Evening, aſter Midnight, we overtook a great Flyboat of 300 Tuns; and finding her to be an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Veſſel, fraighted with Deal, Maſts, Salt, and Tobacco, coming from <hi>New-England,</hi> or thoſe Parts, and taken by the <hi>Algier</hi> Men of War off of the <hi>Cape St. Vincent,</hi> being bound for <hi>Cadiz,</hi> we took, and made Prize of her; and having found 22 <hi>Turks</hi> aboard her, and three <hi>chriſtians,</hi> one a <hi>Ruſsian,</hi> and two <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> we tranſported them aboard us, and ſent other Men aboard her; and having examin'd the Principal of them, found them to belong to a Squadron of <hi>Algier</hi> Men of War, who were Cruiſing in thoſe Seas: But the Prize being heavy loaders, and a bad Sailer (inſomuch that we were forc'd to tow her) did much prolong our Voyage, as that we could not arrive till Saturday at Noon before <hi>Salee</hi>: Yet that flowneſs did us a Courteſie for that time, though a Diſcourtefie afterwards; for having for the moſt part of the Forenoon taken notice of a Barque keeping betwixt us and the Shore, and thinking her to be otherwiſe than ſhe prov'd afterwards, Captain <hi>Kempthorn</hi> ſent his Ketch to ſpeak with her In the mean time we arriv'd before <hi>Salee</hi>; and having handſomly trimm'd our Ship with Pendants and other Ornaments, and caſt Anchor, we Saluted the Town with 11 Guns, and receiv'd for Anſwer, ſilence . However, we made ready for Landing; and firſt the Steward onely, in a Pinace with another Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, rowed towards the Shore; and while that was doing, we ſaw at a diſtance, that our Ketch had overtaken the Barque, and after a l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttle time of Conference let her go with diſcharging ot a Gun; which Barque made with full Sails towards us, to our great admiration; till coming nearer, we pereceiv'd that ſhe bore the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Colors, and diſcharg'd two Guns; Then we concluded, that it was ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Meſſage from his Excellency; therefore the Captain commanded to diſcharge a Gun, and to make a Waft for thoſe who were roving to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Shore, who ſeeing that, turn'd back again, and came aboard. And the Veſſel, being a Brigantine belonging to <hi>Tangier,</hi> having aboard her a Gentleman of Quality, and a Captain, with 40 Soldie<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and 6 Braſs Guns, did alſo approach, and deliver'd his Meſſage, which was, That we ſhould not Land, but rather get aboard, if we could, ill thoſe who were aſhore before, with the Goods alſo, matters at <hi>Tangier</hi> ſince our departure being much alter'd; and had we not been retarded by the fore-mention'd Prize, this Meſſage would have come too late</p>
            <p>However, we ſtay'd there till Munday, and ſeeing there could nothing be effected, in getting thoſe People aboard (becauſe they were deram'd) and a Storm being at hand forcing us from the Shore, we took the Sea; and having faſtned the ſaid Brigantine at our Stern, we Cruiſel that night and the day following, in a Storm, far in the Sea, all the Men <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Brigantine being aboard her, and ſuffer'd much. This evening we ſa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> two <hi>Turks</hi> Men of War afar off; and at night was a very great Storm, ſo that we were forc'd to take all the Men of the Brigantine aboard us, and ſuffer her to be caſt away. Next day, the 15. the Weather continued: Toward evening we ſaw again a <hi>Turks</hi> Man of War, chacing a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Veſſl but having pereciv'd us making towards him, he fled: By and by we ſaw Land, it being <hi>La Rotta</hi> on the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Coaſt; which we could not reach, the Storm blowing out of the <hi>Levant,</hi> but were forc'd to keep at Sea further off, and there to be toſs'd all that night and the day after. The 7 came to us a <hi>French Canary</hi> Man, bound for <hi>Cadiz</hi>; by and by, a <hi>Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> from the ſame place; We ſaw alſo two <hi>Turks</hi> Men of War; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe two Ships came to us for Protection. Next morning at break of day we diſcover'd ſeven <hi>Turks</hi> Mer of War; and becauſe their Courſe was towards us, therefore all poſſible Preparation was made aboard us for the Fight, and all that might be hurtful, or hinder us, remov'd, and thrown overboard, and our aforeſaid Prize forſaken, the Men taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board into the <hi>Mary Roſe,</hi> and the Ship let drive before the Wind. The ſame day before noon the <hi>Turks</hi> paſs'd by us; but neither Party attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any thing; yet our Preparation went on to the utmoſt of our power.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, one of the <hi>Turks</hi> Ships, being a ſlow Sailer, and full of Men (being the <hi>Half-Moon</hi>) lagg'd about an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mile behind the reſt; ſo that they were forc'd to ſtay for her, and to ſend out two Boars Man'd to tow her. Our Captain ſeeing that, who was near betwixt them both, ſent alſo a Boat with Men to intercept theirs, which caus'd a ſmall Skirmiſh among them; but when we ſaw that the <hi>Turks</hi> put out another Boat ſtrongly provided, our Captain commanded to make a Waft for our Man to come back again: After that, we ſaw them to ſtand cloſe together, no doubt, to conſult what was to be done; and we ſtill preparing; ſtill about three a clock they began to charge, whereupon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Service, and much harm done on both ſides; but the night being at hand, they retired a little way, and there ſtay'd till day, obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Motion; and becauſe they ſhould not think that we would run away in the dark, Captain <hi>Kempthorn</hi> commanded Lights to be ſet out, that they might ſee where we were; and ſo having taken ſome reſt the ſame night, early in the morning we were alarm'd again; and having perform'd Solemn Prayers, immediately every one repair'd to his Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for they were coming: And all things being well order'd, especially that every other Gun ſhould be fir'd at every Ship, to preſerve the reſt for the ſecond; by which means, every one of the <hi>Turks</hi> Men of War re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd a ſufficient oppoſition. We had alſo, beſides our ordinary Ships Crew, about 70 Land-Soldiers of <hi>Tangier,</hi> and about 4.0 of his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies Retinue; in all about 250 Men.</p>
            <p>Thus began the Fight with a great courage; and they coming in a Line from the Somh-Eaſt Quarter, the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> was the foremoſt; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving come within Piſtol-ſhot, gave us his Small-ſhot, and his Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and receiv'd as much from us, and then having paſs'd, bore off a little toward the Starboard, North-Eaſt; the ſame order kept all the reſt, the <hi>Golden-Lion,</hi> or Admiral being, in the Rere, with intention to board us: After we had receiv'd theſe five Broad-ſides, even as he was coming up, with more Sails ſpread than the reſt, he receiv'd a Shot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Wind and Water, and another which tore his Main-Sail from end to end, and being thus diſabled, ſtood off: His Companions ſeeing that, tack'd about, and compaſſing him round, went away fore the Wind with all ſpeed, which put an end to the Fight, God be thanked. The ſeventh Ship all that while was purſuing our Prize, by which means we had one Enemy the leſs. Thus we follow'd our Courſe, having loſt thac day in the time of the Fight our <hi>French</hi> Ship Companion, and the following night, the <hi>Scotchman</hi> and the Pink; which Pink having aboard a number of <hi>Jews, Armenians,</hi> and the like Companions, having during the Fight re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted againſt the Maſter of the Veſſel, endeavour'd to comply with the <hi>Turks,</hi> and having given ſome Signal, bore towatds them: they miſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be a Fire-ſhip, began to avoid; but our Captains providence hinder'd that Deſign. There were kill'd aboard us 11 Perſons, 17 wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Ship; much dammag'd. The next day in the evening we ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd in the Bay of <hi>Cadiz,</hi> being <hi>December</hi> 30. <hi>S. V.</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
