<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2008-03-30</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Alexis Jakobson</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>*Proofed title page(s).
*Reviewed structure.
*Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). 
*Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. 
*Checked for N=""s. 
*Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. 
*Checked placement and completeness of PBs. 
*Checked for foreign, damage and missing-page GAPs, #, --. 
*Checked for LBs, startqs / endqs, q;s, {que}s, ABBRs and Qs. 
*Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials.
*Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. 
*Corrected $$s and $word$s etc. 
*Converted $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="[vendor name]".
*Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K007863.000">
<STC T="C">N012801</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3310018354</BIBNO>
<VID SET="ECLL">0149202500</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="014920250000010"/>
<P>THE ROYAL VISION: IN AN ODE TO PEACE. BY HENRY JONES, Author of the EARL OF ESSEX, KEW GARDEN, &amp;c.</P>
<P>DUBLIN: Printed for WILLIAM WATSON, Bookseller, at the Poets Heads in Capel-street.</P>
<P>M DCC LXIII.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<PB REF="014920250000020" MS="y"/>
<PB N="1" REF="014920250000030"/>
<HEAD>THE ROYAL VISION.</HEAD>
<L>THE mighty God of armies bows his ear</L>
<L>To wailing mankind's moan,</L>
<L>The Lord of Hosts from heav'n looks down,</L>
<L>No more with awful eye severe;</L>
<L>He hears the bleeding nations groan,</L>
<L>He sees the vanquish'd fall, the victor frown;</L>
<L>He turns aside his face</L>
<L>By pity touch'd and godlike grace:</L>
<L>He calls BRITANNIA's guardian angel loud,</L>
<L>Go, quell the sanguine, and assuage the proud:</L>
<L>Thy glorious lot on yonder orb below</L>
<L>That globe shall rule, my laurel there shall grow;</L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="014920250000040"/>Arrest the rapid bolt, beat down the mortal steel,</L>
<L>For man laid waste my tender mercies feel.</L>
<L>He said, and pointed to the bless'd around</L>
<L>The gasping soldier, and the gushing wound,</L>
<L>With human nature fainting on the ground.</L>
<L>The bless'd themselves seem'd sad that space,</L>
<L>And begg'd that mankind might have peace.</L>
<L>Go forth, my strength, thy mighty wings outspread,</L>
<L>Yon crimson guilty banners tread,</L>
<L>Beneath the foot of peace, he said;</L>
<L>And sheath, oh! sheath the murd'rous sword;</L>
<L>This olive from thy radiant wing</L>
<L>(That near my mercy-seat still grows)</L>
<L>In GEORGE's breast make joyful spring,</L>
<L>And with it wast my world creating word:</L>
<L>Let famine, pestilence and slaughter cease,</L>
<L>'Tis my command, give weeping EUROPE peace,</L>
<L>And let her angry kings no more be foes.</L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="014920250000050"/>With loud hosannas heav'ns eternal concave rung,</L>
<L>And halleluiahs to the God of peace were sung.</L>
<L>Th' obedient angel cleaves th' ethereal skies,</L>
<L>To GEORGE's downy pillow straight he flies,</L>
<L>When balmy slumbers closed his happy eyes,</L>
<L>And on the organs of his fancy wrought,</L>
<L>The inmost fibres of his feeling heart;</L>
<L>With mystic sketch divine, angelic trace,</L>
<L>Before his melting mental eye he spread</L>
<L>The sick, the wounded, dying, and the dead:</L>
<L>The burning city sack'd, the raging battle fought,</L>
<L>In hideous groupes by form creating art;</L>
<L>With all the barb'rous mischiefs that deface</L>
<L>The works of God, since CAIN his brother slew,</L>
<L>He placed before his visionary view:</L>
<L>The infant sprawling on the soldier's spear,</L>
<L>Or clinging to the murther'd mother's breast,</L>
<L>Whose face retains a tenderness in death,</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="014920250000060"/>What heart of flesh a sight like this can bear?</L>
<L>See, for her babe she looks, ev'n now distress'd!</L>
<L>Her swelling sorrows seem to give her breath,</L>
<L>How agonizing fear her features fix</L>
<L>Lest with her flowing blood her milk should mix!</L>
<L>The venerable sire, see, by the hoary hairs,</L>
<L>Athwart the pavement dragg'd, that floats in blood,</L>
<L>The dagger through the matrons bosom thrust,</L>
<L>Who, 'twixt the murd'rer and her husband, stood;</L>
<L>The screaming daughter mad her tresses tears,</L>
<L>When ravish'd at her gasping mother's feet,</L>
<L>Whilst fury, blood, and lust</L>
<L>Polute each guilty street:</L>
<L>As if some fiend had snatch'd the love of kind,</L>
<L>And hell itself was lodg'd within the human mind:</L>
<L>There mines, and caves of death, their entrails burst</L>
<L>At one infernal blast, one horrid blow accurst:</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="014920250000070"/>See limbs and heads of men, and bodies fly</L>
<L>Like whirling feathers, scatter'd thro' the frighted sky!</L>
<L>There wrapt in smoke, in sulphur, stench, and fire,</L>
<L>Whole armies in th' astonish'd air expire!</L>
<L>But those, alas! are scenes of single woe,</L>
<L>Behold vast empires fall, at one destructive blow—</L>
<L>The king lamented inly as he slept,</L>
<L>With tender throbs, for murder'd mankind wept;</L>
<L>When straight before his eye the angel plac'd</L>
<L>Those human fiends that lay all nature waste:</L>
<L>Ambition in the guilty front was there,</L>
<L>Who tortures heav'n and earth, and sea and air;</L>
<L>And tyranny with smiling frown,</L>
<L>Whose iron rod seems deck'd in down;</L>
<L>Discord in human gore deep dy'd,</L>
<L>With fire and water at her side;</L>
<L>Her hostile visage with itself at war,</L>
<L>Inverted eyes that glare, and horrid brows that jar:</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="014920250000080"/>And bigotry in meek disguise,</L>
<L>With dagger'd hand, and upcast eyes;</L>
<L>And envy, daughter of despair,</L>
<L>With palid lip, and ghastly air,</L>
<L>Who copies from tormented fiends her face,</L>
<L>The pest of hell, and bane of human race:</L>
<L>And pride, that parent of th' infernal crew,</L>
<L>With haughty eye askance, and sanguine hue:</L>
<L>All these were martial'd in their dread array,</L>
<L>And horrid attributes before his eye,</L>
<L>The monarch startled, as in sleep he lay;</L>
<L>And from his inmost soul upheav'd a sigh.</L>
<L>The angel now with pow'r serene,</L>
<L>All gracious chang'd the horrid scene;</L>
<L>A milder vision gently drew,</L>
<L>The kings of EUROPE in his view,</L>
<L>With lifted hands and bended knees</L>
<L>Imploring peace, he pitying sees;</L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="014920250000090"/>The christian virtues all around</L>
<L>Were kneeling near him on the ground:</L>
<L>Religion mounted mild, up to her sacred place,</L>
<L>Sublime she rose, awful, with heav'nly grace,</L>
<L>(That white-rob'd queen of sweet command,)</L>
<L>Still near his best-lov'd throne, and heart would stand:</L>
<L>The cross erect in one seraphic hand,</L>
<L>She held before the royal eye,</L>
<L>His love immense, that would for mankind die:</L>
<L>A precious crown, by purest virtue won,</L>
<L>Richer than rubies, brighter than the sun;</L>
<L>Where twice ten thousand various gems unite</L>
<L>Their trembling rays, in one celestial light</L>
<L>Her other hand divine holds up to view:</L>
<L>The horrid vices dazzled at the glorious sight</L>
<L>Sunk down at once to hell's eternal night;</L>
<L>Whilst ravag'd realms, and sea, and air, look new.</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="014920250000100"/>Bid mankind smile whom heav'n ordains</L>
<L>To bind EUROPA's bleeding veins,</L>
<L>Religion said; bid discord cease,</L>
<L>And open wide the gates of peace:</L>
<L>Call back that precious dove, my son proceed,</L>
<L>Compleat the god like work, behold thy glorious meed!</L>
<L>With seraphs thron'd thy diadem shall shine,</L>
<L>This crown to all eternity is thine:</L>
<L>Let christian kings in christian leagues agree,</L>
<L>And give the human heart to God and me.—</L>
<L>The king bid EUROPE's prostrate monarchs rise,</L>
<L>Whilst tears of pity from his flowing eyes,</L>
<L>Ran trickling down his crimson cheek,</L>
<L>Religion made him mild and meek,</L>
<L>And half his soul consented;</L>
<L>He bad the weeping world rejoyce,</L>
<L>With intellectual voice,</L>
<L>And ev'ry manly faculty relented:</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="014920250000110"/>CAESAR himself might now give o'er;</L>
<L>Conquest has her fill;</L>
<L>A christian monarch should do more,</L>
<L>Forbear the christian blood to spill:</L>
<L>Let glory hide her guilty rays,</L>
<L>Be mercy now my highest praise,</L>
<L>Let me my foes forgive;</L>
<L>Arise, ye vanquish'd monarchs, rise — and live.—</L>
<L>The social angel, when by pity press'd,</L>
<L>That moment lodg'd the heav'nly olive in his breast,</L>
<L>And fill'd his heart with clemency and grace,</L>
<L>The king awoke, he will'd; and all was peace.—</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>HENRY JONES.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

