<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2008-04-27</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Alexis Jakobson</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>*Proofed title page(s).
*Reviewed structure.
*Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). 
*Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. 
*Checked for N=""s. 
*Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. 
*Checked placement and completeness of PBs. 
*Checked for foreign, damage and missing-page GAPs, #, --. 
*Checked for LBs, startqs / endqs, q;s, {que}s, ABBRs and Qs. 
*Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials.
*Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. 
*Corrected $$s and $word$s etc. 
*Converted $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="[vendor name]".
*Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K038561.000">
<STC T="C">T037612</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3306676499</BIBNO>
<VID SET="ECFA">1193000400</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE LAW OF LOMBARDY; A TRAGEDY: AS IT IS PERFORMED AT THE THEATRE-ROYAL IN DRURY-LANE.</P>
<P>WRITTEN BY ROBERT JEPHSON, ESQ. AUTHOR OF BRAGANZA.</P>
<P>LONDON. PRINTED FOR T. EVANS, NEAR YORK-BUILDINGS, STRAND. MDCCLXXIX. [Price One Shilling and Sixpence.]</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE KING.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>YOUR Majesty's having graciously permitted me to prefix your royal name to this tragedy, has impress'd me with so deep a sense of the honor, that I despair of find∣ing terms sufficient to express my acknowledgments.</P>
<P>Tho' the public, which is seldom disposed to receive favourably, performances destitute of merit, has been pleased to give this a very indulgent reception, I must still regret its imperfections, when I consider that it may for a moment become the object of your Majesty's atten∣tion. Having omitted nothing in my power to render it not entirely unworthy of such an exalted patronage, I can't forbear to flatter myself, that it may raise in the breast of your Majesty those emotions which well imagined di∣stress never fails to excite in the noblest natures: but at the same time I more anxiously wish, that no other un∣easiness but from such fictitious sorrow may ever ap∣proach you; and that the greatest and most amiable so∣vereign in Europe, may be also for ever distinguished as the most prosperous and happy.</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>I am, SIR,</SALUTE>
<SIGNED>Your Majesty's most dutiful subject, and most obliged humble servant, ROBERT JEPHSON.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>DRAMATIS PERSONAE.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><LABEL>PALADORE,</LABEL> Mr. SMITH.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>KING,</LABEL> Mr. BENSLEY.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>RINALDO,</LABEL> Mr. PACKER.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>ASCANIO,</LABEL> Mr. HURST.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>LUCIO,</LABEL> Mr. FARREN.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>SENATOR,</LABEL> Mr. CHAMBERS.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>SHEPHERD,</LABEL> Mr. WRIGHT.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>FORESTERS,</LABEL>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Mr. WRIGHTEN.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. FAWCET.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>SQUIRE TO PALADORE,</LABEL> Mr. PHILEMORE.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>AND</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM><LABEL>BIRENO,</LABEL> Mr. HENDERSON.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>PRINCESS,</LABEL> Miss YOUNGE.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>ALINDA,</LABEL> Mrs. ROBINSON.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>THE LAW OF LOMBARDY. A TRAGEDY.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT I.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD><HI>SCENE I.</HI> A Chamber in the Palace.</HEAD>
<STAGE>BIRENO, ALINDA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Wonder not you should suspect me slow</L>
<L>In this strange office: had you but enjoin'd me,</L>
<L>Shut out the sun ten times his annual rounds,</L>
<L>Feed all my life on pulse, or with coarse weeds</L>
<L>Obscure the little grace which Nature's hand</L>
<L>Has lent my outside, then, without a wherefore,</L>
<L>(From the meek humbleness of love I bear you)</L>
<L>My obedience wou'd have follow'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet impatience,</L>
<L>Smooth that contracted brow—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>But to commend</L>
<L>To any other woman, those fond vows</L>
<L>I hop'd to own unpartner'd, is it less</L>
<L>Than to expect my tongue suborn'd, should plead</L>
<L>Against the dearest interest of my life,</L>
<L>And make me earnest for my own undoing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I again call down the saints to witness,</L>
<L>That for convenience only, not from love,</L>
<L>I seek to wed the princess? My ambition</L>
<L>Aims at the crown, her dower; were that bright gem</L>
<L>Heir'd by a pigmy, the meer mock of sight,</L>
<L>By ideot drawling, and a shrew's perverseness,</L>
<L>No less shou'd I desire it. If I prosper,</L>
<L>My heart, as ever, shall be thine; and hers,</L>
<L>The dull legitimate languor of the husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>But when to royal state Sophia joins</L>
<L>Such rare endowments, as make doubtful strife</L>
<L>'Twixt Nature's gifts, and Fortune's; can I hope</L>
<L>More than some grateful note from memory,</L>
<L>How much Alinda lov'd you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me, fair one,</L>
<L>Beauty's degrees are in the lover's fancy,</L>
<L>Not in a scal'd perfection. Varying nature</L>
<L>Has lineaments for every appetite:</L>
<L>Not her arch'd brows, nor stature Juno-like,</L>
<L>Her crisped tresses spun from finest gold,</L>
<L>Nor the intelligent lustre of her eye,</L>
<L>To me have half such charms as thy soft mien,</L>
<L>The pure carnation of thy dimpling cheek,</L>
<L>And unassuming sweet simplicity.—</L>
<L>But hast thou urg'd my suit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spite of ourselves,</L>
<L>The tongue interprets from the abundant heart.</L>
<L>Bireno's image filling all my thoughts,</L>
<L>Cou'd I be silent on a theme so lov'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how does she receive the gentle tale?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="3" REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sometimes she chides, and sometimes smiling tells me,</L>
<L>But that she knows me wise, such lavish praise</L>
<L>Might hint a heart touch'd deeply, and ill suits</L>
<L>The sober preference of an humble maid,</L>
<L>Who cannot hope to call you hers in honour.</L>
<L>Then with discreetest lessons will she school me,</L>
<L>To guard my breast 'gainst love; forgetting still</L>
<L>How much she wants the counsel she bestows.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does she then love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>She never told me so;</L>
<L>But signs far more significant than speech</L>
<L>Reveal it hourly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me know my rival,</L>
<L>Tho' my foreboding heart already whispers</L>
<L>It must be Paladore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, rightly guess'd!</L>
<L>Her love for him makes her unjust to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Curses o'ertake him! Near his brighter fires</L>
<L>My star shines dimly; I was wonder'd at</L>
<L>Till this new meteor shot across men's eyes,</L>
<L>And drew all gaze to follow. At our tournaments</L>
<L>He foils me like a novice; in grave council</L>
<L>I prate unmark'd, while hoary heads bow down</L>
<L>In reverence to his weighty utterance;</L>
<L>And thus the upstart heresy of opinion</L>
<L>Runs on this smooth impostor—By what signs</L>
<L>Take you this note of her affection towards him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>By such we women deem infallible.</L>
<L>If unexpectedly she hears him nam'd,</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="7"/>Sweet discomposure seizes all her frame;</L>
<L>Suffasion, softer than Aurora's blush,</L>
<L>Spreads o'er her beauteous cheek. If she expect</L>
<L>His presence at the court, studious to please,</L>
<L>Beyond her wonted elegance of dress,</L>
<L>With nicer care she counsels at her glass,</L>
<L>To make the daintiest workmanship of nature</L>
<L>By ornament more winning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indications</L>
<L>That speak, and shrewdly; yet their vanity</L>
<L>To catch the flattery of the fool they scorn,</L>
<L>Will bait such hooks as these. Have you no proof</L>
<L>More unequivocal?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wou'd you more?</L>
<L>We reason from ourselves, looking within,</L>
<L>We find in our own breasts the according springs</L>
<L>Of motions similar; when first I lov'd,</L>
<L>So did I wish to please, so doubt my power.</L>
<L>Yet more than this; her eye still follows him,</L>
<L>And when the unwelcome hour of parting comes,</L>
<L>The chearful flame that lighted up her countenance</L>
<L>Expires; sighs heave, and a soft silent tear</L>
<L>Steals down her cheek.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, I'm satisfied</L>
<L>She loves him, and the frost of my reception</L>
<L>Conspires in proof. Now then, my best Alinda!</L>
<L>You must assist me; on this single push</L>
<L>Hang all my fortunes—If my rival wed her,</L>
<L>Farewel my hopes, my country—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! your country!</L>
<L>A voluntary exile for the loss</L>
<L>Of one you swear you love not—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="5" REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>My possessions,</L>
<L>The means of pleasure to my thriftless youth,</L>
<L>Moulder in confiscation; thus my dukedom,</L>
<L>My royal ancestry, and rank in the state,</L>
<L>So scantily supported will but mock me.</L>
<L>A marriage with the princess wou'd heal all.</L>
<L>But if I fail, I will not stay to see</L>
<L>Upstarts made rich by my inheritance;</L>
<L>Nor the proud finger of the slave I scorn</L>
<L>Point at the princely beggar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, good heaven!</L>
<L>Devise, command—Can my best industry</L>
<L>Prevent this ruin? Tell me but the means,</L>
<L>And bid me fly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more of jealousy,</L>
<L>But with appliance dext'rous call her thoughts</L>
<L>To me, and my deservings; speak with slight</L>
<L>(Yet not as by suggestion) of my rival.</L>
<L>I've known more way made in a woman's grace</L>
<L>By such confederate arts, than could be won</L>
<L>By a long siege of amorous enginry,</L>
<L>Soft flatteries, sighs, protestings infinite,</L>
<L>And all the fervor of impatient love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>But should this fail!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll spread a finer snare,</L>
<L>Subtle as fabled Vulcan forg'd in Lemnos,</L>
<L>To enmesh them: thy soft hand, my dear Alinda!</L>
<L>Must help to hold the toils—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>But see, she comes;</L>
<L>The king too and her lover—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="6" REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll retire,</L>
<L>And seek thee presently: rivet thine ear</L>
<L>Meantime to what they utter: thy report</L>
<L>Shall somewhat shape my course. High-flighted fool!</L>
<L>Check thy bold soaring, else my hot revenge</L>
<L>Shall melt thy waxed plumes, and hurl thee down</L>
<L>To a devouring sea that roars beneath thee.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alinda <HI>retires.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>KING, PRINCESS, PALADORE, ATTENDANTS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall no more, Sophia, to the chase;</L>
<L>This morning's danger makes my blood run cold.</L>
<L>Had not thy well-sped lance, brave Paladore,</L>
<L>Pierc'd the huge boar that gor'd her foaming horse,</L>
<L>These eyes, now rais'd in thanks to heaven and thee,</L>
<L>Had wept her lifeless.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ever prais'd be Fortune,</L>
<L>That plac'd me near her! Since a common feat</L>
<L>That daily dies our weapons, thus ennobled</L>
<L>By blest conjunct on with her precious safety,</L>
<L>I would not change for the best garland won</L>
<L>By Caesar's conquering sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are not nice</L>
<L>In dangers imminent to chuse the means</L>
<L>Of our deliverance; yet, believe me, Sir,</L>
<L>More than for life preserv'd, I thank the chance</L>
<L>That made you my preserver. Th' unwelcome hand</L>
<L>Rendering us service, like sharp frost in sunshine,</L>
<L>Chills the fresh blossom of our gratitude,</L>
<L>Which else uncheck'd would put forth all its sweetness.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="7" REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have much serious matter for your ear;
<STAGE><HI>To</HI> Paladore.</STAGE></L>
<L>Our helms must be lac'd close, our swords new edg'd</L>
<L>'Gainst fiercer foes than these rude foresters,</L>
<L>That make us sport with peril.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my life!</L>
<L>My cruel heart beats high to give it welcome;</L>
<L>For Virtue's test is action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus my paper:</L>
<L>(Brief its contents, but fearful) Burgundy,</L>
<L>Stung by refusal of my daughter's love,</L>
<L>Stirs up commotion 'gainst our kingdom's peace;</L>
<L>And soon the golden grain of Lombardy</L>
<L>Shall be trod down beneath the furious heel</L>
<L>Of peasants cas'd in iron.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven avert it!</L>
<L>For sure 'twere better I had ne'er been born,</L>
<L>Than live the fatal cause why war's rude blast</L>
<L>Disturb'd the quiet of my father's age,</L>
<L>Which soft repose shou'd foster. The griev'd people</L>
<L>Will chide your gentleness, that did not bend</L>
<L>My heart to this obedience; and your virtue,</L>
<L>Seen thro' th' unwelcome colour of the event,</L>
<L>For reverence find upbraiding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Sophia!</L>
<L>I would not violate the meanest right</L>
<L>Of my least subject, for the fear or promise</L>
<L>Of any issue. Is my child, my daughter,</L>
<L>(Sweet, duteous, amiable, burn free and royal)</L>
<L>Less charter'd from oppression than a stranger?</L>
<L>A self-invited wooer here he sojourn'd,</L>
<L>To thrive as your approving gave him licence:</L>
<L>I fed him not with promise, you with hope,</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="11"/>Nor shall audacious menace ere extort</L>
<L>What courtesy denied him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>To his teeth</L>
<L>Hurl your defiance, King! 'tis proud to threaten,</L>
<L>But baseness to be aw'd by it. From my breast</L>
<L>I'd tear these hallow'd symbols, give this steel</L>
<L>To be a baby's play-thing, cou'd my heart,</L>
<L>Distrustful of the event, forbode one fear,</L>
<L>To cast black presage on a cause so noble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou gem of Britain! Dear in my esteem</L>
<L>As wert thou native here, be Pavias' shield</L>
<L>Her pride, her pillar; yes, our hardy files,</L>
<L>Led on by thee, shall drive the boaster back,</L>
<L>To mourn at home his baffled preparations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, wou'd the fortune of this glorious strife</L>
<L>Hung on my arm alone!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our daughter's hand</L>
<L>Is destin'd for a prince who draws his blood</L>
<L>From the same source as mine, our kingdom's heir,</L>
<L>(Did not this sweet prevention stand between)</L>
<L>To bless Bireno with two matchless gifts,</L>
<L>Her beauty and a royal diadem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bireno, Sir!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Even he, I know his worth—</L>
<L>But is there poison in my kinsman's name?</L>
<L>It pales the healthful vermeil of your cheek,</L>
<L>Dims your bright eye, and viels your wonted smiles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! I cannot speak—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="9" REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then, hereafter</L>
<L>Will better suit this subject. Sir, farewel!</L>
<L>We shall expect your aid to counsel with us,</L>
<L>What present mounds our wisdom, best may raise</L>
<L>'Gainst this loud torrent that at distance roars,</L>
<L>Ere it rush down to spread its ruin round us.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>PRINCESS, PALADORE.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, stay, and hear me now! Alas! he's gone</L>
<L>Who smiles on me, and kills me; bids my heart</L>
<L>Be traitor to itself, yet with soft words</L>
<L>Fetters my tongue, which free, wou'd boldly answer!</L>
<L>Such kindness but destroys me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>My soul's idol!</L>
<L>I was indeed presumptuous to believe</L>
<L>These humble arms were destin'd to enfold</L>
<L>So vast a treasure, yet aspiring love</L>
<L>Hopes things impossible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bireno! He!</L>
<L>I'd rather waste my life in singleness;</L>
<L>Like the pale votarist, pour faint orisons</L>
<L>At the cold shrines of senseless marble saints,</L>
<L>And wear the eternal pavement with my knees,</L>
<L>Than at the sacred altar load my soul</L>
<L>With holy perjuries, to love the man,</L>
<L>At whose approach my heart alarm'd shrinks back,</L>
<L>While thought confirms instinctive Nature's hate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, like a haughty conqueror he comes;</L>
<L>Pleasure and pride on his exulting brow</L>
<L>At distance speak his triumph.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="10" REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arm me, Disdain,</L>
<L>To meet the bold intruder!—Gentle Paladore!</L>
<L>'Tis thus thy rival woo's me. Courtship's season</L>
<L>Is the short date of woman's sovereignty.</L>
<L>For liberty, we have but in exchange</L>
<L>The little tribute of a lover's sighs,</L>
<L>His humble seeming, and soft courtesy;</L>
<L>Yet these, he thinks too rich a sacrifice,</L>
<L>And owns no advocate but pride in love.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE IV. <HI>To them</HI> BIRENO.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confirm'd, fair princess! By the King's command</L>
<L>You see me here a joyful visitant.</L>
<L>'Tis not unknown why warlike Burgundy,</L>
<L>Spreading his hostile banners to the wind,</L>
<L>Makes sword and fire his dreadful harbingers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cause I have heard—But on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>[Aside.]</STAGE>
<L>Down, swelling heart!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your yet unplighted hand gives to this war</L>
<L>Its edge and colour; to remove that prize</L>
<L>Beyond the invader's reach, my sovereign's wisdom</L>
<L>Deems the best means to blunt his hostile sword;</L>
<L>Therefore on me he deigns—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I understand;</L>
<L>But have no present ear for such a theme.</L>
<L>My father's goodness left my choice unforc'd</L>
<L>Of one unwelcome suitor; the same justice</L>
<L>Secures me from compulsion in a second.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>And must I bear this answer to the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="11" REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Myself will be my own interpreter,</L>
<L>And save your trouble. Once more, Sir, I thank you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>To</HI> Paladore <HI>and exit.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE V. BIRENO, PALADORE.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well! go thy ways, woman's epitome!</L>
<L>Beauteous aenigma! Who wou'd solve you rightly,</L>
<L>Must thus interpret: make your outward semblance</L>
<L>An index pointing to its contrary.</L>
<L>When your smooth polish'd vizors beam in smiles,</L>
<L>Displeasure's at your hearts; the moody brow</L>
<L>Tells inward sun-shine; tears are joy, not sorrow;</L>
<L>You sooth where you approve not, and look gall,</L>
<L>When sweet content honies your appetites.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>These common railings 'gainst that gentle sex,</L>
<L>Denote his humour more who utters them,</L>
<L>Than their defect, or any deep conception.</L>
<L>But you have chosen a season for hard thoughts</L>
<L>Rebukes your censure; still the chamber's air</L>
<L>Winnows her balmy breathing; from our eyes</L>
<L>Scarce glides her beauteous form, when your dark spleen</L>
<L>As venom'd things suck poison from sweet flowers,</L>
<L>Finds matter for distemper's nourishment,</L>
<L>And food for calumny in excellence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her form indeed is fair.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay, and her mind</L>
<L>(If more can be) more fair, more amiable.</L>
<L>Thy never-render'd snow-cold Apenine,</L>
<L>Is not so free from taint, as from offence</L>
<L>Her spotless bosom; yet has she a tear,</L>
<L><PB N="12" REF="15"/>Healing as balm for others frailties,</L>
<L>That makes remission heavenly; sweet persuasion</L>
<L>Hangs on her words with power oracular,</L>
<L>To shame the cynic's chiding—Spirit of truth!</L>
<L>She is thy visible divinity,</L>
<L>And 'tis thy reverence to pay homage to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis to my wish
<STAGE>[Aside.]</STAGE>
—I grant her well endow'd,</L>
<L>And in fair seeming most pre-eminent;</L>
<L>But for these other virtues you have nam'd,</L>
<L>They are of different climes, and earlier ages;</L>
<L>Our Pavias ladies, cast in earthly moulds,</L>
<L>They make the most of Nature's liberal gifts,</L>
<L>Put pleasure out to usury, and love</L>
<L>As ease, convenience, or the moment sways them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>You're pleasant, lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, soberly thy friend.</L>
<L>Shall I be plain?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>What call you your past measure,</L>
<L>Was it a courtier's strain!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>You love the princess?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>And heaven may be belov'd—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay, and hop'd too;</L>
<L>For heaven has many mansions, and receives,</L>
<L>Too large for limitation, all deservers;</L>
<L>But in a lady's heart, there's but one place,</L>
<L>Though many may contend for't: therefore, friend,</L>
<L>Waste not your precious sighs, which might enkindle</L>
<L>Bright sparks of equal love in some soft breast</L>
<L>Destined to mate your fondness, in hopeless wooing.</L>
<L><PB N="13" REF="16"/>Search not the cause; believe me, on my truth,</L>
<L>'Tis past all reckoning hopeless.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing's hopeless,</L>
<L>Though deeds, untried, oft seem impossible;</L>
<L>And craven Sloth molting his sleekless plumes</L>
<L>With drowsy wonder views the advent'rous wing</L>
<L>That soars the shining azure o'er his head.</L>
<L>What will not yield to daring? Victory</L>
<L>Sits on the helm whose crest is Confidence;</L>
<L>And boldness wins success in love's soft strife,</L>
<L>As in the dangerous din of rattling war.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>How cou'd I make me sport were I light minded,</L>
<L>Were I malignant; mischief, from this mood,</L>
<L>That runs so contrary to all sober sense—</L>
<L>But here I rest in kindness—Be advis'd,</L>
<L>Push not a desperate purpose; by my life!</L>
<L>The princess loves you not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll bear no more—</L>
<L>Matchless audacity! Let me take thee in</L>
<L>From crown to toe, walk round thee, and survey thee</L>
<L>Like a prodigious thing; for such thou should'st be,</L>
<L>To put my course of love in circumscription,</L>
<L>And school me, like a boy, with unsought precept.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lovers are sick with fevers of the brain,</L>
<L>Diseas'd by airy hope, high flighted fancy,</L>
<L>Imaginations bred from self-conceit.</L>
<L>An arch deluder, which presents the Juno</L>
<L>Their frenzy grasps at, with a zone unbound;</L>
<L>While, like Ixion's mistress, the coy queen</L>
<L>Slumbers on golden beds in high Olympus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hear me, proud duke▪ had I no other spur</L>
<L>But thy forbidding; were there no incitement</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="17"/>From her transcendent beauty; did no beam</L>
<L>Shoot from her eye to light eternal love</L>
<L>At passion's altar; were she swart, and froward,</L>
<L>(Oh, blasphemy to think it) in despight,</L>
<L>I would assume an unfelt extasy,</L>
<L>Invoke her name, till echo should grow faint</L>
<L>With the perpetual burden, and devise</L>
<L>All means of contradiction, to proclaim</L>
<L>Scorn of thy council, and defiance to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then hear, to dash thy pride, since thus you urge me.</L>
<L>My experience of her lightness, well she knows</L>
<L>Would freeze me as her husband, and her hand</L>
<L>(Which, but to save appearances, I ask)</L>
<L>I wou'd reject, if offer'd; so her craft</L>
<L>Sooths you with feign'd endearments. As a mistress,</L>
<L>I find her worth my holding; but a wife,</L>
<L>Fit for a prince, must come with better gifts</L>
<L>Than amorous blood, and beauty—Nay, but mark me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust not too far the reverence of this place—</L>
<L>Away—thou yet art safe—my sword once drawn—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I so lost in your esteem, you hold me</L>
<L>(Your friend profess'd) in malice capable,</L>
<L>Or falsehood thus to wound you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both, by Heaven!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>And will maintain this thinking?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALODORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>With my life.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a deep venture—Mine upon my truth—</L>
<L>When full-orb'd Phoebe wheel her fleecy car</L>
<L>To silver yon blue concave, midst the pines</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="18"/>That wave their green tops o'er the battlement</L>
<L>Of her night-chamber, in the garden meet me</L>
<L>Alone: when we encounter in that place,</L>
<L>You there shall listen to conditions meet</L>
<L>For both our honours. So till then, farewel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE,</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>alone.</STAGE>
<L>I'll meet thee, be assur'd I will.</L>
<L>Gird on thy keenest edge: if thou hast aught</L>
<L>Unsettled in this world, dispatch it quickly;</L>
<L>We stand upon the utmost verge of Fate,</L>
<L>And one, or both of us, must plunge for ever.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE VI.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>alone.</STAGE>
<L>The wise should watch the event on fortune's wheel,</L>
<L>That for a moment circles at the top,</L>
<L>And seiz'd not, vanishes—I must about it,</L>
<L>My all's at stake—Ye ministers of vengeance!</L>
<L>That hide your gory locks in mist-hung caves,</L>
<L>And roll your deadly eyeballs o'er the edge</L>
<L>Of your insatiate daggers, shaking ever</L>
<L>Dews of oblivious sleep from your stung brows,</L>
<L>Receive me of your band! ne'er to know peace</L>
<L>Till this keen writhing vulture quit my heart,</L>
<L>And with blunt beak, and flagging wings outstretch'd,</L>
<L>Drowze o'er the mangled victims of my rage.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>END OF THE FIRST ACT.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB N="16" REF="19"/>
<HEAD>ACT II.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE I. <HI>a Chamber.</HI></HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS,</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>alone.</STAGE>
<L>OH, blessed, most blessed are the insensible!</L>
<L>In the mild zone of calm indifference:</L>
<L>No hatred chills them, and no passion burns;</L>
<L>To feed, and sleep, and do observance due</L>
<L>To the stale ritual of quaint ceremony,</L>
<L>Fills up the humble measure of their hope;</L>
<L>Smooth and unruffled glides their temperate stream,</L>
<L>And one day rounds their whole life's history.</L>
<L>Oh, had my heart been such! but Nature poiz'd</L>
<L>In distribution, when she gives the touch</L>
<L>Alive to exstacy, in like extreme</L>
<L>Subjects the sense to anguish: the same soul,</L>
<L>That in the hope of wedding Paladore,</L>
<L>Enjoy'd its sum of bliss, with equal pain</L>
<L>Averts me from his rival: thus entranc'd</L>
<L>'Twixt love and fear, I feel the pangs of both,</L>
<L>And the sharp conflict rends me. Ha! my father!</L>
<L>Now comes the trial.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE II. KING, PRINCESS.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! in tears, Sophia?</L>
<L>Come, 'tis not well—I fear, I guess the cause.</L>
<L>This morn I did but hint a purpose to you,</L>
<L>Of import, dear to your own happiness,</L>
<L>And your chang'd brow reproving my intent</L>
<L>Cut short my free discourse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="17" REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, good my Lord!</L>
<L>I am not practis'd to conceal my thoughts</L>
<L>(And least from you) by casting o'er my looks</L>
<L>The unalter'd vizor of tranquility,</L>
<L>When perturbation, like a sleepless guest,</L>
<L>Forbids my bosom's quiet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have lov'd thee</L>
<L>With fondness so unbated, that 'twere needless,</L>
<L>For confirmation, to attest by words,</L>
<L>What all my thoughts, my life's whole carriage towards thee,</L>
<L>Have set beyond the question.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, to me,</L>
<L>Your love has been like those perpetual springs,</L>
<L>"That ever flow," and waste not my least wish</L>
<L>Scarce had its birth, ere its accomplishment</L>
<L>In your preventive kindness.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since 'tis so,</L>
<L>If chance the current of my present will</L>
<L>To yours run contrary, you must not deem</L>
<L>That meerly to enforce authority,</L>
<L>Or wake controlement, which might sleep to death.</L>
<L>In its difuse, I now expect the course</L>
<L>Of your desires should lose themselves in mine,</L>
<L>Or flow by my direction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>As my father,</L>
<L>The giver of my life, I reverence you;</L>
<L>Next, as your subject, my obedience stands</L>
<L>Bound by the general tie; but since your power</L>
<L>Has still been temper'd so with lenity,</L>
<L>That even the stranger's cause, with patient hearing,</L>
<L>Is weigh'd ere you determine; I, your daughter,</L>
<L><PB N="18" REF="21"/>May hope, at least, an equal privilege,</L>
<L>With favour in my audience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>I were else</L>
<L>Unnatural, withholding from my child,</L>
<L>What aliens claim by justice. Give me hearing—</L>
<L>The Duke Bireno loves you, has my promise,</L>
<L>That like a well-grac'd advocate, my tongue</L>
<L>Shou'd win your gentle favour to his suit,</L>
<L>Urging such commendations of his love,</L>
<L>As modesty, though conscious of desert,</L>
<L>May wish you hear, yet cannot speak itself.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah, Sir! forbear, he knows my heart already,</L>
<L>Already has he heard, from my own lips</L>
<L>I cannot love him; poorly he engages</L>
<L>Your honour'd combination, in a league</L>
<L>That (whatsoe'er its issue) must conspire</L>
<L>To wound your daughter's peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>By heaven, you wrong him.</L>
<L>To wound your peace! He seeks your happiness,</L>
<L>And so am I his second.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>But these means</L>
<L>Are adverse to the end; for if I wed him,</L>
<L>(This is no raving of rash extacy)</L>
<L>On death, that only can dissolve my chain,</L>
<L>Will hang my future hope: as eagerly</L>
<L>As the poor weary sea-beat mariner</L>
<L>Pants for the shore, so shall my outstretch'd arms</L>
<L>Embrace the welcome terror. My refusal</L>
<L>To you, the gentlest, kindest, best of fathers,</L>
<L>Must seem repugnance harsh, and o'er my duty,</L>
<L>Before untainted, casts the sickly hue</L>
<L>Of pale suspicion; thus begins his love,</L>
<L>Fearful to me in each alternative.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="19" REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, this is infant rhet'ric, to protest</L>
<L>The impulse of a strong antipathy,</L>
<L>Which never causeless sways the human breast,</L>
<L>Yet give no reason why.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! to feel it,</L>
<L>O'er-masters every reason. Need we search</L>
<L>To ground aversion on weigh'd argument,</L>
<L>When instinct cuts the tedious process short,</L>
<L>And makes the heart our umpire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hear me calmly—</L>
<L>My days are almost number'd: this white head</L>
<L>Bears not in vain its reverend monitors;</L>
<L>Time puts a tongue in every hoary hair,</L>
<L>To warn the wise man of mortality:</L>
<L>When I am gone, behold thy single state</L>
<L>Unhusbanded, unfather'd, stands expos'd,</L>
<L>Ev'n as the tender solitary shrub,</L>
<L>On the bleak mountain's summit—Every blast</L>
<L>May bend or break thy sweetness: this strong fence,</L>
<L>This union, would enroot its shelter round,</L>
<L>And, like a forest, shield thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me hope</L>
<L>A stronger sence in a whole people's love:</L>
<L>Their grateful memory of my father's virtue,</L>
<L>And loyalty hereditarly mine,</L>
<L>Descending, like the sceptre, to your issue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Think'st thou, my aspiring kinsman, whose ambition,</L>
<L>Impatient, waits till my declining beam</L>
<L>Give place to his meridian, who, already</L>
<L>Wins from my side a moiety of my court,</L>
<L>By his succession's hope, will tamely view</L>
<L>That sceptre wielded by a woman's hand,</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="23"/>Nor wrest it from thy grasp? No, my fair kingdom!</L>
<L>I see the meeting torrents of contention</L>
<L>Deluge thy peaceful vales, while her weak sex,</L>
<L>Unable to direct, or stem the tide,</L>
<L>Will be borne down, and swept to ruin with it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>These evils, but in possibility,</L>
<L>May never come: but, Oh, 'tis certain sorrow</L>
<L>To promise love, obedience, duty, honor,</L>
<L>When the heart's record vouches 'gainst the tongue:</L>
<L>It changes order's course; the holy tie</L>
<L>Of weil-proportion'd marriage still supposes</L>
<L>These bonds have gone before; nor is there power</L>
<L>Creative in the simple ceremony,</L>
<L>The seed unsown, to give that harvest growth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here break we off—To sue, and sue in vain,</L>
<L>But ill becomes a father: may my augury</L>
<L>Be more in fear than wisdom. Hold; to-morrow</L>
<L>The council meets to scan this threaten'd war:</L>
<L>The people call it thine: then be thou present</L>
<L>To thank and animate their zeal to serve us.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE III.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS,</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>alone.</STAGE>
<L>I shall attend your order. This cold parting</L>
<L>Speaks his displeasure; and my heart accustom'd</L>
<L>To the kind sunshine of approving smiles,</L>
<L>Droops at the chilling change. Ye gentle breasts,</L>
<L>Strangers as yet to love, be warn'd by me.</L>
<L>Soft as the printless step of midnight sleep,</L>
<L>The subtle tyrant steals into the soul:</L>
<L>Once seated there, securely he controuls</L>
<L>The idle strife of unimpassion'd ties,</L>
<L>And laughs to scorn their sober impotence.</L>
<L>As feeble vassals list their arms in vain,</L>
<L>In the unequal conflict soon o'erthrown,</L>
<L>They prove their weakness, and his power supreme.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="21" REF="24"/>
<HEAD>SCENE IV. <HI>A Garden.</HI></HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>alone. Night.</STAGE>
<L>He must pass this way: thro' the postern gate</L>
<L>That leads here only, with distemper'd pace</L>
<L>I saw him hasten. Since the evening banquet</L>
<L>His wild demeanour "<HI>has put on more change</HI>"</L>
<L>Than yonder fickle planet in her orb.</L>
<L>Just now he seiz'd his sword, look'd at, and poiz'd it,</L>
<L>Then girt it round him, while his bloodshot eye,</L>
<L>And heaving bosom, spoke the big conception</L>
<L>Of some dire purpose. There is mischief towards—</L>
<L>I may perhaps prevent it—these tall shrubs</L>
<L>Will hide me from his view.—Soft, soft, 'tis he.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Rinaldo <HI>retires.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE V. PALADORE <HI>alone.</HI></HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why do I shake thus? If, indeed, she's false,</L>
<L>I shou'd rejoice to have the spell unbound</L>
<L>That chains me to delusion. He swears deeply:</L>
<L>But bad men's oaths are breath, and their base lies</L>
<L>With holiest adjurations stronger vouch'd</L>
<L>Than native truth, which center'd in itself,</L>
<L>Rests in its simpleness; then this bold carriage</L>
<L>Urging the proof by test infallible,</L>
<L>The witness of my sight. Why these combin'd,</L>
<L>(Spite of my steady seeming) viper-tooth'd</L>
<L>Gnaw at my constancy, and inward spread</L>
<L>Suggestions, which unmaster'd, soon would change</L>
<L>The ruddy heart to blackness. But, Oh, shame!</L>
<L>These doubts are Slander's leigers.—Sweetest innocence!</L>
<L>That now, perhaps, lapt in Elysian sleep</L>
<L>Seest heaven in vision, let not these base sounds</L>
<L>Creep on thy slumber, lest they startle rest,</L>
<L>And change thy trance to horror.—Lo, he comes:</L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="25"/>Yon light that glimmers 'twixt the quivering leaves</L>
<L>(Like a small star) directs his footsteps hither.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE VI.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To him</HI> BIRENO, <HI>with a Lanthorn.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon, Sir; I fear I've made you wait—</L>
<L>But here, beneath the window of his mistress,</L>
<L>A lover favour'd, and assur'd like you,</L>
<L>Must have a thousand pleasant fantasies</L>
<L>To entertain his musing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, my fancy</L>
<L>Has various meditations; no one thought</L>
<L>Mix'd with disloyalty of her whose honour</L>
<L>Your boldness wou'd attaint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you hold firm,</L>
<L>I am a boaster?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my present creed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twere kind, perhaps, to leave you in that error.</L>
<L>The wretch who dreams of bliss, while his sleep lasts,</L>
<L>Is happy as in waking certainty;</L>
<L>But if he's rous'd, and rous'd to misery,</L>
<L>He sure must curse the hand that shook his curtain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have no time for maxims, and your mirth</L>
<L>Is most unseasonable. Thus far to endure</L>
<L>Perhaps is too much tameness.—To the purpose—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all convenient speed. You're not to learn,</L>
<L>We have a law peculiar to this realm,</L>
<L><PB N="23" REF="26"/>That subjects to a mortal penalty,</L>
<L>All women nobly born (be their estate</L>
<L>Single or husbanded) who to the shame</L>
<L>Of chastity, o'er-leap its thorny bounds,</L>
<L>To wanton in the flowery path of pleasure.</L>
<L>Nor is the proper issue of the king</L>
<L>By royalty exempted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I have heard.</L>
<L>But wherefore urge you this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not without reason.</L>
<L>I draw my sword in peace. Now place your lips</L>
<L>Here on this sacred cross. By this deep oath,</L>
<L>Most binding to our order, you must swear,</L>
<L>Whate'er you see, or whatsoe'er your wrath</L>
<L>From what you see, that never shall your tongue</L>
<L>Reveal it to the danger of the princess.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>A most superfluous bond!—But on; I swear.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold yet a little. Now, Sir, once again</L>
<L>Let this be touch'd.—Your enmity to me,</L>
<L>If by the process it should be provok'd,</L>
<L>Must in your breast be smother'd, not break out</L>
<L>In tilting at my life, nor your gage thrown</L>
<L>For any after quarrel. The cause weigh'd,</L>
<L>I might expect your love: but 'tis the stuff,</L>
<L>And proper quality of hoodwink'd rage,</L>
<L>To wrest offence from kindness.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should your proof</L>
<L>Keep pace with your assurance, scorn, not rage,</L>
<L>Will here be paramount, and my sword sleep,</L>
<L>From my indifference to a worthless toy,</L>
<L>Valued but in my untried ignorance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="24" REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>So you determine wisely. I must bind you</L>
<L>To one condition more. If I make palpable</L>
<L>Her preference in my favour, you must turn</L>
<L>Your back on Lombardy, and never more</L>
<L>Seek her encounter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>By a soldier's faith!</L>
<L>Should it be so, I wou'd not breathe your air</L>
<L>A moment longer, for the sov'reignty</L>
<L>Of all the soil wash'd by your wand'ring Po.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Summon your patience now, for sure you'll need it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have tried it to the last: dally no more,</L>
<L>I shiver in expectance. Come, your proofs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well you will have them. Know you first this writing?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Gives a paper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the character of fair Sophia.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I think so, and as such receiv'd it from her;</L>
<L>Convey'd with such sweet action to my hand,</L>
<L>As wak'd the nimble spirit of my blood,</L>
<L>Whispering how kind were the contents within.</L>
<L>This light will aid the moon, tho' now she shines</L>
<L>In her full splendor. At your leisure read it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE,</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>reading.</STAGE>
<L>Kind words indeed; I fear, I fear too common.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>It works as I could wish. How his cheek whitens!</L>
<L>His fiery eye darts thro' each tender word</L>
<L>As it would burn the paper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE,</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>reading.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Ever constant—</HI></L>
<L><PB N="25" REF="28"/>Let me look once again. Is my fight false?</L>
<L>Oh, wou'd it were! Fain wou'd I cast the blame,</L>
<L>To save her crime, on my imperfect sense.</L>
<L>But did she give you this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look to the address.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, darkness on my eyes! I've seen too much.</L>
<L>There's not a letter, but like necromancy</L>
<L>Withers my corporal functions. Shame confound her!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you before were tardy of belief,</L>
<L>You now are rash. Behold these little shadows.</L>
<L>These you have seen before.
<STAGE>Producing two pictures.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's this, what's this!</L>
<L>My picture, as I live, I gave the false one,</L>
<L>And her's she promis'd me! Oh, woman's faith!</L>
<L>I was your champion once, deceitful sex!</L>
<L>Thought your fair minds—But hold, I may be rash—</L>
<L>This letter, and these pictures, might be your's</L>
<L>By the king's power, compelling her reluctant</L>
<L>To write and send them; therefore let me see</L>
<L>All you have promis'd.—You expect her summons</L>
<L>At yon Miranda—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, the time draws near;</L>
<L>She ever is most punctual. This small light</L>
<L>Our wonted signal: stand without its ray;</L>
<L>For shou'd she spy more than myself beneath,</L>
<L>Fearing discovery, she'll retire again</L>
<L>Into her chamber—When her beauteous form</L>
<L>Breaks like the moon, as fair, tho' not so cold,</L>
<L>From yonder window.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! by hell it opens!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="26" REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand you apart a moment. While I climb,</L>
<L>Yon orb, now braz'd to this accustom'd scene,</L>
<L>Will shew you who invites me. I'll detain her,</L>
<L>To give you ample leisure for such note</L>
<L>As counterfeits abide not.
<STAGE>Bireno <HI>retires</HI>▪</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="7" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE VII.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>alone.</STAGE>
<L>Death! 'tis she!</L>
<L>There's not a silken braid that binds her hair,</L>
<L>One little shred of all that known attire</L>
<L>That wantons in the wind, but to my heart</L>
<L>Has sent such sweet disturbance, that it beat</L>
<L>Instinctive of her coming, ere my sight</L>
<L>Enjoy'd the beauteous wonder.—Soft! What now!</L>
<L>See she lets down the cordage of her shame,</L>
<L>To hoist him to her arms, I'll look no more—</L>
<L>Distraction! Devil! How she welcomes him!</L>
<L>That's well! that's well!—Again: grow to her lips—</L>
<L>Poison and aspics rot them! Now she woo's him,</L>
<L>Points to her chamber, and invites him inward.</L>
<L>May adder's hiss around their guilty couch!</L>
<L>And ghosts of injur'd lovers rise to scare them!—</L>
<L>Ay, get you gone—Oh, for a griffin's wing,</L>
<L>To bear me thro' the casement! Deeds like this</L>
<L>Shou'd startle every spirit of the grove,</L>
<L>And wake Enchantment from her spell-hung grot,</L>
<L>To shake the conscious roof about their heads,</L>
<L>And bare them to the scoff of modest eyes</L>
<L>Twin'd in the wanton fold. Oh, wretch accurs'd!</L>
<L>See there the blasted promise of thy joys,</L>
<L>Thy best hopes bankrupt.—Do I linger still?</L>
<L>Here find a grave, and let thy mangled corse,</L>
<L>When her lascivious eye peers o'er the lawn,</L>
<L>Satiate the harlot's gaze.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Going to fall on his sword,</HI> Rinaldo <HI>rushes out and prevents him.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB N="27" REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO.</SPEAKER>
<L>What frenzy's this!</L>
<L>Arm'd 'gainst your life! In pity turn the point</L>
<L>On your old faithful servant, whose heart heaves</L>
<L>Almost to bursting to behold you thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast seen it then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have seen your wild despair;</L>
<L>And bless'd be the kind monitor within</L>
<L>That led me here to save you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather curs'd</L>
<L>Be thy officious fondness, since it dooms me</L>
<L>To lingering misery. Give me back my sword—</L>
<L>Is't come to this! Oh, I cou'd tear my hair!</L>
<L>Rip us this credulous breast! Blind dotard! Fool!</L>
<L>Did Wit, or Malice, ere devise a legend</L>
<L>To parellel this vile reality?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disgrace not the best gift of manly nature,</L>
<L>Your reason, in this wild extravagance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>And think'st thou I am mad without a cause!</L>
<L>I'll tell thee—'Sdeath! It choaks me—Lead me hence—</L>
<L>I will walk boldly on the billowy deep,</L>
<L>Or blindfold tread the sharp and perilous ridge</L>
<L>Of icy Caucasus, nor fear my footing;</L>
<L>Play with a fasting lion's fangs unharm'd,</L>
<L>And stroke his rage to tameness.—But hereafter,</L>
<L>When men wou'd try impossibilities,</L>
<L>Let them seek faith in woman.—Furies seize them!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>END OF THE SECOND ACT.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB N="28" REF="31"/>
<HEAD>ACT III.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE I. <HI>A Hall.</HI></HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>alone.</STAGE>
<L>HER death must be the means. If these be crimes,</L>
<L>Thou bright Ambition, whose rare alchimy,</L>
<L>Like Midas' palm, turns all it grasps to gold,</L>
<L>Give them thy glorious splendor! What a coil</L>
<L>Does puny Conscience make in little minds,</L>
<L>Ere they o'erleap obstruction! Fear, not virtue,</L>
<L>Keeps mankind honest. Each inordinate wish</L>
<L>Is guilt unacted, and the canon points</L>
<L>More 'gainst the coward heart, that wou'd and dare not,</L>
<L>Than the bold deed, that braves the penalty.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE II.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO, ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome, Ascanio! Thanks for this kind speed</L>
<L>To meet my summons. I have business for thee,</L>
<L>Worthy thy subtle genius; thou shalt aid me</L>
<L>To spread a banquet forth, where two sharp guests,</L>
<L>Ambition and Revenge, shall both be feasted,</L>
<L>Even to satiety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not pall</L>
<L>Performance by protesting. Is there aught</L>
<L>In which a pliant tongue, and ready hand,</L>
<L>(No despicable engines) may do service?</L>
<L>To their best cunning use them; your poor bondman</L>
<L>Will think himself much honour'd in obedience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have profess'd myself thy friend, Ascanio!</L>
<L><PB N="29" REF="32"/>And when the golden autumn of my hopes,</L>
<L>(Whose rich maturity I now wou'd hasten)</L>
<L>Is ripe for bearing, thou shall taste the fruit</L>
<L>That bends my swelling branches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have liv'd</L>
<L>The creature of your bounty; and my life</L>
<L>I would cast from me, like a useless load,</L>
<L>When to your gracious ends unprofitable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>My means have hitherto been poor and scanty,</L>
<L>My power confin'd; but I shall be, Ascanio,</L>
<L>Like a great river, whose large urns dispense</L>
<L>Abundance to the subject rills around him,</L>
<L>Till they o'erpeer their banks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, my good lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll trust thee as I know thee—for a villain.—
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE></L>
<L>Place thyself near me when the council meets,</L>
<L>(I shall make matter for them they foresee not)</L>
<L>Whate'er I urge, or whomsoe'er I charge,</L>
<L>Be ready thou with the grave mockery</L>
<L>Of uplift eyes, thy hand thus on thy breast,</L>
<L>And heaven-attesting oaths to second me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prime in the catalogue of mortal sins,</L>
<L>I hold unthankfulness, and a friend's need,</L>
<L>Makes fiction virtue when its end is kindness.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>To give more ready credence to the imposture,</L>
<L>Put on reluctant seeming; earnestly</L>
<L>Entreat, they urge you not; sadden thy brow,</L>
<L>And cry, "Alas! compell me not to speak—</L>
<L>"I know not what I saw." Mumble some cant,</L>
<L>"Of frailty, and compassion, sins of youth,</L>
<L><PB N="30" REF="33"/>"The danger of the law, if it were urg'd</L>
<L>"'Gainst all transgressions;" thus shall thy declining</L>
<L>Be eked out to a stubborn certainty</L>
<L>In each suspended hearer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, my Lord;</L>
<L>Disparage not the good gifts were born with me,</L>
<L>To think I can want schooling for this office.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you pardon me.—Oh, Nature! Nature!
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE></L>
<L>There is a pride even in stark villainy,</L>
<L>Which flattery's heat must soften, ere the metal</L>
<L>Bend to our purposes.—Come this way with me,</L>
<L>The hall will soon be throng'd; what more remains</L>
<L>I will impart within.—No ceremony.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>LUCIO, <HI>an</HI> OFFICER.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFFICER.</SPEAKER>
<L>See where they pass; what bodes that conference?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Danger, my life on't. That smooth knave Ascanio</L>
<L>Is the Duke's crucible, his breast receives</L>
<L>The mass of his crude projects, and his brain</L>
<L>A subtle fire refines the drossy ore,</L>
<L>To bear the ready stamp for present mischief.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFFICER.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke of late grows past his custom courteous,</L>
<L>Joins hands with us, and calls us by our names,</L>
<L>Gives praise, and largess to the soldiery,</L>
<L>Whom he was wont to style, State caterpillars,</L>
<L>Burthens of peace, and but endur'd in war,</L>
<L>As necessary evils.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>It denotes</L>
<L><PB N="31" REF="34"/>(Or I lack charity) trouble to the state.</L>
<L>I know him proud, subtle, and pitiless;</L>
<L>Nor will his nature change these elements,</L>
<L>However for a season he put on</L>
<L>A smoother guise, and fashion suitable</L>
<L>To the end he aims at.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFFICER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Best conceal these thoughts,</L>
<L>For one day he may rule us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay, that <HI>may,</HI></L>
<L>If I mistake not, he will snatch from chance,</L>
<L>And make a certainty. But see the king.</L>
<L>The providence of heaven be ever round him!</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE>KING, <HI>Counsellors, Knights, Attendants.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Health to your Majesty!</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks, gentle friends!</L>
<L>But why this faintness in your salutations?</L>
<L>Why wear your brows that ominous livery?</L>
<L>I trust our gallant spirits will not palter,</L>
<L>Because a rash invader threatens us.</L>
<L>When I was young as you, to hear of war</L>
<L>Made my blood dance: but these good days are past,</L>
<L>This sapless trunk shrinks from its mailed bark;</L>
<L>Yet age has still its use, count me your steward,</L>
<L>Holding the honours of the state in trust</L>
<L>For all deservers;—She shall better thank you;</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE V.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To the above,</HI> PRINCESS, <HI>Attendants.</HI></STAGE>
<L>More retribution dwells in beauty's smile,</L>
<L>Than in whole volumes of an old man's praise.</L>
<L><PB N="32" REF="35"/>Approach, my child! Come, grace thy father's side:</L>
<L>These are thy champions; give your women tasks,</L>
<L>Bid all the looms of Pavia ply their labors,</L>
<L>A scarf for every warrior, they'll deserve them.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>They will not want my thanks, nor such poor tokens</L>
<L>How much I prize their worth; their high-touch'd virtue</L>
<L>Finds in itself the source and end of action;</L>
<L>Secures its right to praise, but scorns to take it.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE VI.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To the above,</HI> BIRENO, ASCANIO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome, my cousin! Doubt not of my zeal;</L>
<L>Tho' ill has the success kept pace with it,</L>
<L>To speed your amorous suit, still let us hope,</L>
<L>Time, and your fair pretensions, will have weight</L>
<L>To win her to our wishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it pass;</L>
<L>I must take comfort: women's appetites</L>
<L>Will be their own purveyors. Are we met?</L>
<L>The hall, methinks, seems full.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's Paladore?</L>
<L>He had our summons, yet I see him not:</L>
<L>His skill in war, and wisdom to advise,</L>
<L>Have been most tutelary to our realm,</L>
<L>And well deserve the waiting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take your place;</L>
<L>He cannot now be present; when we are seated,</L>
<L>I will declare the reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>[Aside.]</STAGE>
<L>Ha! not present!</L>
<L><PB N="33" REF="36"/>What fatal bar prevents him? Oh, my heart!</L>
<L>Is Paladore the fountain of thy life,</L>
<L>That thy stream scarce can flow, when sever'd from him?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>They take their places; the</HI> Princess <HI>on the</HI> King's <HI>right hand, a little beneath him.</HI> Bireno <HI>and</HI> Ascanio <HI>in the front of the stage, some seated, others standing round.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>The danger of our frontiers, you, sage lords,</L>
<L>Calls this assembly; but, as wise physicians,</L>
<L>The heart being touch'd, neglect the extremities,</L>
<L>Giving their first care to the seat of life:</L>
<L>So now, the wounded vitals of our honour,</L>
<L>Demand our prior tendence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speak, good cousin!</L>
<L>Do dark conspiracy, and home-bred treason,</L>
<L>(Unnatural leaguers with a foreign foe)</L>
<L>Bid the sharp sword of vengeance turn its edge</L>
<L>'Gainst our own children?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes; though nature bleeds,</L>
<L>Justice will take her course; I see before me</L>
<L>The prime of the kingdom; and from some among you,</L>
<L>Since they, in whose authority abides</L>
<L>The executive of power, best can tell.</L>
<L>I now wou'd hear, why do our registers</L>
<L>Contain that rigorous ordinance, which respects</L>
<L>The chastity of women?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST SENATOR.</SPEAKER>
<L>To that question,</L>
<L>The law's preamble answers. 'Tis rehears'd,</L>
<L>That the wild licence of our countrywomen,</L>
<L>O'erleapt all modest bounds. Sweet pudency</L>
<L>(That ruby of the sex) had been cast by</L>
<L>For casual wantonness, till our name abroad</L>
<L>Became a by-word, and confusion, strange,</L>
<L><PB N="34" REF="37"/>Disturb'd domestic peace. A spurious issue,</L>
<L>The slips of chance and wildness, were engrafted</L>
<L>In rich inheritances, while the sire</L>
<L>Caress'd the child, not his, and left to fortune,</L>
<L>The true heirs of his fondness: these abuses</L>
<L>Required an iron curb; so pass'd the law,</L>
<L>Making transgression death, with no remittance</L>
<L>To high rank, or degree in the offender,</L>
<L>But in its bloody gripe comprizing all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>And is this so allow'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST SENATOR.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis so allow'd:</L>
<L>Nor is there a decretal, in our rolls,</L>
<L>Of less ambiguous import, or more known.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is beyond devining: I have mark'd</L>
<STAGE><HI>To the</HI> Princess, <HI>half aside.</HI></STAGE>
<L>His changing feature: some strong passion shakes him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He plays emotion well, most masterly,</L>
<L>Even to the life of feigning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I on?</L>
<L>Or must I, like a novice to your forms,</L>
<L>First prove my right of audience?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not anger'd;</L>
<L>We questioned not your right—All counsellors</L>
<L>Speak what they list with freedom. You, our cousin,</L>
<L>Have with your right, pre-audience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray, proceed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="35" REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO</SPEAKER>
<STAGE><HI>to the</HI> SENATOR.</STAGE>
<L>Most learned lord, now please you to recite</L>
<L>The dangerous predicament of those</L>
<L>Who do awake this statute?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST SENATOR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Willingly.</L>
<L>'Tis there provided, that, the accus'd being cited</L>
<L>In the king's presence, he, who brings the charge,</L>
<L>Shou'd state each circumstance: that done, the herald</L>
<L>Thrice in six hours, first, in the market place,</L>
<L>Next, in the hippodrome, last, in the porch</L>
<L>Of the great temple, must invite all knights</L>
<L>(Whether impell'd by pity, love, or justice)</L>
<L>To appear her champions in the marshal'd lists:</L>
<L>There, if the accuser falls, she is held free,</L>
<L>And her fair fame restor'd; but, if he conquers,</L>
<L>The event confirms her guilt, and the sharp axe</L>
<L>Severs the wanton's life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then in this peril</L>
<L>Stand I at present—Bid your trumpets sound;</L>
<L>And call forth every bold adventurer.</L>
<L>To try what desperate valour may achieve</L>
<L>'Gainst truth, and my keen sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>But whither wou'd'st thou?</L>
<L>Suspense and horror fit on every brow;</L>
<L>Like the red comet, thy denouncing eye,</L>
<L>Forebodes disaster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, relentless justice!</L>
<L>If these be drops of weakness, let them fall:</L>
<L>'Tis the last tribute of a human sorrow,</L>
<L>And now I am wholly thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="36" REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pr'ythee, go on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twere vain to waste your patience in persuasion;</L>
<L>I would not wantonly play with the fangs</L>
<L>Of such a lion law, whose terrible roar</L>
<L>Must be appeas'd with blood—So rests my truth.</L>
<L>A lover's fondness, last night, prompted me,</L>
<L>Attended by this gentleman.
<STAGE><HI>Pointing to</HI> Ascanio.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Curs'd chance!</L>
<L>Oh, would the darkness of the delving mole</L>
<L>Had been my portion; then I had not seen—</L>
<L>What have I said? Nay, do not call on me;</L>
<L>Was it for this I was commanded hither?</L>
<L>I'll close my lips for ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST SENATOR.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have ways</L>
<L>To force a necessary truth—My Lord,</L>
<L>Please you, proceed—The rack shall make him answer.</L>
<L>Have eye upon him—He was your companion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was, he was, when love or destiny</L>
<L>Led me a wanderer, in the palace garden,</L>
<L>To gaze upon the window of the princess.</L>
<L>When, Oh, sad object for a lover's eyes!</L>
<L>The casement open'd, and the full-orb'd moon,</L>
<L>Bright as the radiance of meridian day,</L>
<L>Shew'd me a lusty rival in her arms,</L>
<L>Embracing, and embrac'd—
<STAGE>All rise from the table.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shame! Death! Confusion!</L>
<L>My daughter! Oh, my daughter!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Host of heaven!</L>
<L>Does no deep thunder roll, no lightning flash?</L>
<L><PB N="37" REF="40"/>Can the tremendous courriers of your wrath,</L>
<L>Sleep o'er this perjury?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gage is thrown;</L>
<L>And here I stand to answer with my life,</L>
<L>If I have charg'd her falsely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>[Kneeling.]</STAGE>
<L>On my knees,</L>
<L>If ever pity touch'd your noble breast,</L>
<L>I beg you speak no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>[<HI>To</HI> Ascanio.]</STAGE>
<L>Thou vile confederate</L>
<L>Of his bloody-thirsty malice! Have I liv'd</L>
<L>To hear a wretch suborn'd, his sycophant,</L>
<L>Mock me with intercession?
<STAGE>[<HI>To</HI> Bireno.]</STAGE>
I behold thee,</L>
<L>And scorn so struggles with astonishment,</L>
<L>That my full heart, and intercepted tongue</L>
<L>Almost refuse their active offices,</L>
<L>Till passion's choak'd in silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Powers of mercy!</L>
<L>Am I reserv'd for this? My only child,</L>
<L>The pride, the joy, the treasure of my soul,</L>
<L>My age's cordial, and my life's best prop,</L>
<L>In the sweet spring, and blossom of her youth,</L>
<L>Thus blasted in my sight!—
<STAGE>[<HI>To</HI> Bireno.]</STAGE>
But, Oh, dark fiend!</L>
<L>Whom hell lets loose to spread destruction round thee,</L>
<L>Why does thy vengeance fasten upon me?</L>
<L>Have I deserv'd this from thee? Well thou know'st,</L>
<L>I strove to make her thine; I would have given thee</L>
<L>My crown, and daughter. Thou requit'st my love,</L>
<L>By daggers steep'd in poison to my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank thy kindness, and forgive thy rage;</L>
<L>The father shall have licence—Honor, witness!</L>
<L>Nor malice, nor ambition loos'd my tongue,</L>
<L><PB N="38" REF="41"/>To this heart-rending office. Reverend Lords!</L>
<L>Let your unclouded wisdom judge between us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can I be patient? Most abandon'd ruffian!</L>
<L>Thou scoffer at all ties! with the same breath</L>
<L>That violates a virgin's sanctity,</L>
<L>(Holy and pure beyond thy gross conceiving)</L>
<L>Thus conscious of thy lie, dar'st thou invoke</L>
<L>Honour to witness for thee? Wherefore call</L>
<L>On these to judge between us? See, barbarian!</L>
<L>Amaz'd, and struck with horror, they have heard thee;</L>
<L>Too well, thou know'st, they must pronounce me guilty;</L>
<L>Thy oath must be their law: but there is one,</L>
<L>An unseen judge, an all discerning eye:</L>
<L>Now if thou dar'st look up, poor shivering wretch!</L>
<L>He views the dark recesses of thy soul:</L>
<L>Tremble at him thy judge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I were a slave,</L>
<L>Fit for abuses, cou'd I tamely bear</L>
<L>To see the rich reversion of my blood</L>
<L>Seiz'd by a base, and spurious progeny,</L>
<L>An alien Briton, in his sport of lust,</L>
<L>Stamping a brood of illegitimate kings,</L>
<L>To bend our necks to bastard tyranny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>An alien Briton!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bid <HI>her</HI> answer thee,</L>
<L>Call for her paramour, her Paladore.</L>
<L>Say, why is he not present?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why indeed!</L>
<L>Hast thou not practis'd on his precious life?</L>
<L>And to consummate this day's guilt and horror,</L>
<L>Crown'd perjury with murder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="39" REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Paladore!</L>
<L>Search, find him out; put pinions to your speed,</L>
<L>And bear him to our presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spare your labour—</L>
<L>Fear will outstrip their haste—The dastard's gone;</L>
<L>He had my challenge for this injury,</L>
<L>And answer'd it by flight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confusion! fled!</L>
<L>Am I then doubly wretched? Must she die?</L>
<L>And die dishonour'd too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>[Kneeling.]</STAGE>
<L>All-seeing Heaven!</L>
<L>If e'er thy interposing Providence</L>
<L>Dash'd the audacious councils of the wicked;</L>
<L>If innocence, ensnar'd, may raise its eye,</L>
<L>In humble hope, to thy eternal throne,</L>
<L>Look down, and succour me! I kneel before thee,</L>
<L>Distrest, forlorn, abandon'd to despair,</L>
<L>By all deserted, and my life beset;</L>
<L>The man, my soul adores, traduc'd, and wrong'd:</L>
<L>Yet, Oh, there is a pang surpassing all!</L>
<L>While the envenom'd rancour of this fiend</L>
<L>Casts its contagion on my spotless fame,</L>
<L>And, unrebuk'd, persists to blast my virtue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hear, she avows her love—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, glory in it—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, have a care, rash girl! nor turn my grief</L>
<L>To curses on thy head—Dar'st thou confirm</L>
<L>Thy doubtful infamy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="40" REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>A love so pure,</L>
<L>What bosom might not feel, what tongue not own?</L>
<L>It was a fault to hide the secret from you:</L>
<L>But are such fighs as vestal breasts might heave,</L>
<L>Such spotless vows as angels might record,</L>
<L>Pollution worthy death? These are my crimes;</L>
<L>And if I labour with with a guilt more black,</L>
<L>May the full malice of that villain reach me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can I think? His absence—Yet thy truth,</L>
<L>Thy nature's modesty plead strongly for thee—</L>
<L>Away with doubt—Oh, thou obdurate heart!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>We trifle time—The lists must be-prepar'd,</L>
<L>The heralds sound defiance—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold a moment—</L>
<L>I'll tell thee how to arm thee for the combat:</L>
<L>Steep thy keen sword in poison, that no balm</L>
<L>May heal the wounds it gives, but each be mortal;</L>
<L>Let a staunch blood-hound, with devouring fangs,</L>
<L>And eye-balls fiery red, couch o'er thy helm;</L>
<L>The deadly sable of thy mail besmear'd</L>
<L>With scaffolds, wheels, and engines, virgin's heads</L>
<L>Fresh bleeding from the axe's severing stroke:</L>
<L>Scorn thou the mean device of vulgar knights,</L>
<L>Who fight for what they reverence, truth and honour;</L>
<L>But be profess'd their champion whom thou serv'st,</L>
<L>And write in bloody letters, hell and falshood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>This passion, lady! ill becomes your state:</L>
<L>Shame is wash'd out by sorrow, not by anger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="41" REF="44"/>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence, from my sight, detested parricide!</L>
<L>Assassin! butcher! lest these feeble hands,</L>
<L>Brac'd by my wrongs to more than mortal strength,</L>
<L>Fix on thy throat, and bare thy treacherous heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Old man, I go—Compassion for thy grief,</L>
<L>Forbids me to retort these outrages.</L>
<L>Let frenzy take its course—When next we meet,</L>
<L>Summon thy fortitude; and learn, mean time,</L>
<L>Crowns cannot save the wearer from affliction,</L>
<L>But kings, like meaner men, were born to suffer.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Bireno, Ascanio, Senators.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="7" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE VII.</HEAD>
<STAGE>KING, PRINCESS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Morality from thee! He braves high heaven,</L>
<L>And well may scorn my anger. Oh, my child!</L>
<L>This little hour, while I can call thee mine,</L>
<L>Close let me strain thee to my bursting heart:</L>
<L>Alas! thy aged father can no more</L>
<L>Than thus to fold thee; pour these scalding tears,</L>
<L>And drench thy tender bosom with his sorrows.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my best hopes of happiness hereafter!</L>
<L>To see that reverend frame thus torn with anguish;</L>
<L>To hear those heart-fetch'd groans, is greater misery,</L>
<L>Than all the horrors of the doom that waits me:</L>
<L>I could put on a Roman constancy,</L>
<L>And go to death like sleep, did no soft sorrow</L>
<L>Hang on the mourning of surviving friends,</L>
<L>And wake a keener pang for their affliction.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="8" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="42" REF="45"/>
<HEAD>SCENE VIII. <HI>To them,</HI> LUCIO.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgive the obedience of reluctant duty!</L>
<L>I have the council's order to commit</L>
<L>The Princess to a guard's close custody.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art my subject, Lucio! and my soldier;</L>
<L>Do thy unhappy master one last service;</L>
<L>Draw forth thy sword, and strike it through my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>No; let our grief be sacred: if we weep,</L>
<L>Let them not see, and triumph in our tears.</L>
<L>Martyrs have died in voluntary flames,</L>
<L>And heroes rush'd on death inevitable,</L>
<L>By faith inspir'd, or glory. Thou, Sophia!</L>
<L>Sustain'd alone by peace and innocence,</L>
<L>Meet fate as firmly, and transcend their daring.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>END OF THE THIRD ACT.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB N="43" REF="46"/>
<HEAD>ACT IV.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE I. <HI>a Forest.</HI></HEAD>
<STAGE>PALADORE, RINALDO <HI>following.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>AM I the slave of sense, that know her fickle,</L>
<L>Ungrateful, perjur'd, yet still doat thus fondly?</L>
<L>Faith, prudence, honor, govern'd appetites,</L>
<L>(Whose everlasting bonds make passion wise)</L>
<L>In her were only seeming, or like ornament</L>
<L>Thrown by, or worn at pleasure; then this sorrow</L>
<L>Hangs on her outside only, that's unchang'd,</L>
<L>For falshood did not dim her radiant eyes,</L>
<L>Her cheek was damask'd with as pure a rose,</L>
<L>Her breath as odorous, when she most deceiv'd,</L>
<L>As when her virture, like her specious form,</L>
<L>Seem'd spotless, and unparagon'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord!</L>
<L>Court not this solitude, speak out your grief;</L>
<L>Mine is no flinty breast; this dangerous spleen,</L>
<L>That makes your bane its nurture, then shews worst,</L>
<L>When nothing spent in loudness, and complaint,</L>
<L>Like a deep stream it rolls its noiseless way,</L>
<L>Mining the banks in silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wou'd the pain</L>
<L>Vanish with the exposure of the cause,</L>
<L>I shou'd make blunt the patience of your ear</L>
<L>By endless iteration. But why tell thee?</L>
<L><PB N="44" REF="47"/>Thinkst thou there is a charm in soothing words</L>
<L>To pluck the sting from anguish? Good Rinaldo,</L>
<L>Thou hadst a son and lost him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, I had so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>See there, his very name provokes thy tears.</L>
<L>Say, can wise counsel stop them? Shall I tell thee,</L>
<L>The lot of mortals is mortality?</L>
<L>That fate will take its course, 'twas Heaven's high will;</L>
<L>And man is born to sorrow. This is wise;</L>
<L>The sum of consolation. Strains like these</L>
<L>Flow smoothly from the tongues of moralists,</L>
<L>Patient as sleep in others sufferings,</L>
<L>But vex'd as wasps and hornets in their own.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO.</SPEAKER>
<L>From these imperfect starts I cannot answer,</L>
<L>They speak but passion. If my guess deceive not,</L>
<L>A woman sure has wrong'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>A true woman;</L>
<L>I thought her angel once, most basely wrong'd me.</L>
<L>Yet if revenge kept measure with her shame,</L>
<L>I cou'd wash out in her polluted blood</L>
<L>This stain to modesty. Yes, fair falsehood!</L>
<L>Shou'd I appeal thee of the incontinence</L>
<L>My blasted eyes have witness'd, the stern law</L>
<L>Wou'd give me ample vengeance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your great spirit</L>
<L>(Whoe'er she be that thus has injur'd you)</L>
<L>Wou'd scorn your reparation from that law,</L>
<L>The shame even of justice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fear not; still she twines</L>
<L>Here round my heartstrings. No, let late remorse,</L>
<L><PB N="45" REF="48"/>For sure it will o'ertake, punish her sin.</L>
<L>But hie thee back to Pavia presently,</L>
<L>Dismiss my attendants, (useless pageantry</L>
<L>To my now alter'd state!) send hither to me</L>
<L>My arms and horses; these may hasten death</L>
<L>Fitting a soldier; then return and seek me.</L>
<L>A little longer will I hold in life,</L>
<L>Till in requital of her father's kindness,</L>
<L>I render some brave service. 'Midst these oaks,</L>
<L>Till you return, I'll keep my lonely haunt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO.</SPEAKER>
<L>There stands an humble hamlet in yon glade,</L>
<L>Own'd by some simple peasants, who supply</L>
<L>The western suburbs with such homely fare</L>
<L>As their few fields afford; thither bestow you,</L>
<L>And take some nourishment. I will return</L>
<L>With my best diligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go, get thee gone.</L>
<L>Sorrow's my food; I'll drink my falling tears.</L>
<L>Ye savage denizons of this wild wood,</L>
<L>Gaunt wolves, and tusky boars! No more my hounds</L>
<L>Shall dash the spangled dew-drops from your brakes!</L>
<L>No more with echoing cries, or mellow horn,</L>
<L>I'll rouse your dreadful slumber! Sleep securely—</L>
<L>With disposition deadly as your own,</L>
<L>I go to mingle with you.
<STAGE>Exeunt severally.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE II. TWO FORESTERS.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>This place will suit our purpose, 'twere lost time</L>
<L>To lead her further; so we but dispatch her,</L>
<L>No matter for the spot. The deed once done,</L>
<L>The Duke will not be nice, but pay us nobly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="46" REF="49"/>
<SPEAKER>SECOND FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Half of our hire's to come. How shall we do it</L>
<L>Stab her, or strangle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make this cord her necklace:</L>
<L>Blood may beget suspicion. When she's dead,</L>
<L>We'll drag her body to yon hazel copse,</L>
<L>And leave the maws of wolves to bury it.</L>
<L>There's scarce a bush in this green labyrinth</L>
<L>But is familiar to me. Many a traveller,</L>
<L>When I was master of us stout a gang</L>
<L>As ere defied the law, here has paid down</L>
<L>His life in conflict for the gold I wanted,</L>
<L>And never more was heard of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SECOND FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sound your horn.</L>
<L>I told her, we'd a little on before</L>
<L>To give our horses forage, and directed</L>
<L>Her way to follow; shou'd she miss the path,</L>
<L>Her ear will be her guide —See, Carlo! see,</L>
<L>The pretty innocent caught by her eye</L>
<L>Stops for a while to pluck the velvet bells</L>
<L>That blow beneath her feet, then forward bounds,</L>
<L>Light as the roe, till some fresh floweret</L>
<L>Lures her again.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay, like the lamb that plays,</L>
<L>And crops his pasture, in the butcher's eye,</L>
<L>Even while the knife's a whetting. Hush! She's here.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE III. <HI>To them</HI> ALINDA.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beneath a rugged thorn I found this flower</L>
<L>Blushing unmark'd its odorous life away;</L>
<L>I'll wear it in my breast, and all who see,</L>
<L>Will praise its beauty, modest worth's sweet emblem,</L>
<L>That first must be conspicuous ere 'tis priz'd.</L>
<L><PB N="47" REF="50"/>Oh, are you there? I'm ready, my good guides!</L>
<L>Where is our equipage? The way's but short,</L>
<L>We shall be there ere moonshine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pretty lady!</L>
<L>You have a longer journey than you wot of,</L>
<L>And a dark dreary road to travel thro.'</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then the Duke deceiv'd me, for he said</L>
<L>The way was pleasant, and the distance nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SECOND FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have helped many forward the same way,</L>
<L>And all were much averse to travel it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>They had no lover to obey like me,</L>
<L>For I am light, and were it ten times further,</L>
<L>To please my Lord I'd go it blithesomely.</L>
<L>Come, come, to horse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you prepar'd to die?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercy defend me! How! Prepar'd to die!</L>
<L>'Tis a strange question.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>But most seasonable;</L>
<L>As fit as if your couch were spread at midnight</L>
<L>To ask if you were weary. With our will</L>
<L>We do it not, for we were gently bred,</L>
<L>And hous'd with gallants once: but this rough trade</L>
<L>Necessity enforces. Come, prepare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What do you search for? And why turn you pale?</L>
<L>You make me shake, to see your stedfast eye.</L>
<L>Does this become the servants of the Duke,</L>
<L>To frighten whom they shou'd protect from fear?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="48" REF="51"/>
<SPEAKER>SECOND FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are, indeed, the servants of the Duke,</L>
<L>For we receive his hire; then for your fears,</L>
<L>We mean to rid you of them by your death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can this be sport? Alas! What have I done,</L>
<L>That such detested thoughts shou'd rise in you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are troublesome. Our business is to kill you.</L>
<L>If you have a ready prayer, and brief, kneel there,</L>
<L>And say it presently. We run great hazard</L>
<L>To let you live so long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll kneel to you,</L>
<L>Make you my saint, if you'll have mercy on me.</L>
<L>I never injur'd you, nay, cou'd not injure,</L>
<L>For till this hour that I was made your charge,</L>
<L>I never saw you. Do not turn away.</L>
<L>Think how you'll answer this to him whose love</L>
<L>Trusted me to your care. He will require</L>
<L>A strict account.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SECOND FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pr'ythee let go my arm.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I not know why you do wish to kill me?</L>
<L>If for these sparkling bawbles, take them freely;</L>
<L>Rob me of all, but do not murder me.</L>
<L>I am not fit to die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>We need not thank you</L>
<L>For what you can't withhold. Fall to your prayers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>But are you not the servants of the Duke?</L>
<L>Think how you swore to tend me faithfully,</L>
<L>How he enjoin'd you, as you priz'd his favor.</L>
<L><PB N="49" REF="52"/>Ev'n in your looks he'll read this cruelty,</L>
<L>And find how you have abus'd him. Think on that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twere pity she shou'd die in ignorance.</L>
<L>Caught in the falcon's pounce, the dove as well</L>
<L>Might gurgle to the kite to stoop, and save her,</L>
<L>As you cry to Bireno. Know, 'tis he</L>
<L>Who laid this snare, and pays us for your blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke Bireno?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SECOND FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, the Duke Bireno.</L>
<L>You have been privy to some passages</L>
<L>Require concealment. Being wise, he thinks</L>
<L>They are safest when you are dumb, so gives us gold</L>
<L>To stop your blabbing. If you doubt our word,</L>
<L>Peruse that paper. Are you satisfied?
<STAGE>Shews a paper.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, if 'tis satisfaction to be torn</L>
<L>With worse than death ere death, I'm satisfied.</L>
<L>But yet you will not kill me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's no end.</L>
<L>She'll prate us from our purpose. Bind her arms.</L>
<L>All strife is vain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, Sir! yet hold a moment;</L>
<L>You murder more than one. An innocent pledge</L>
<L>Of my disastrous love leaps at my side,</L>
<L>And joins his speechless prayer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SECOND FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>And not his wife!</L>
<L>Why then your head's a forfeit to the law,</L>
<L>And we but take before, what sport or malice</L>
<L>Might make you render at the bloody block,</L>
<L>With process more afflicting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="50" REF="53"/>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Barbarous villains!</L>
<L>Is there no help? Oh, spare me!—With my cries</L>
<L>I'll wake the dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SCCOND FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispatch her with your dagger.</L>
<L>Be quick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST FORESTER.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis done.
<STAGE>Stabs her.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE IV. <HI>To them</HI> PALADORE.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure 'twas the scream of woe—</L>
<L>A woman struggling! Villains, loose your hold!</L>
<L>Dogs! hell-hounds!
<STAGE>He drives them out and returns.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA,</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>fainting.</STAGE>
<L>Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Guilt has the wings of wind,</L>
<L>My sight can scarce o'ertake them. On the ground!</L>
<L>I came too late to save her. Hearts of stone</L>
<L>Might feel compunction sure, to mar a form</L>
<L>So soft and fair as this. Thou beauteous marble,</L>
<L>Forgive my tardy succour! Here's a mould</L>
<L>So delicate, 'twere worth a miracle</L>
<L>To give it second life. I've seen this face.—</L>
<L>Ha! As I live, 'tis she; the beauteous girl</L>
<L>That waited on the Princess. Soft! the blood</L>
<L>Steals to her cheek again, the azure lids</L>
<L>Begin to open.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lock up, sweet maid!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="51" REF="54"/>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bless me! Where am I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Safe from violence,</L>
<L>Nor in a stranger's arms.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your voice is gentle.</L>
<L>But will you save me from these barbarous men,</L>
<L>Shou'd they again return? I tremble still,</L>
<L>Still feel their ruffian gripe, nor can believe</L>
<L>I yet am safe, tho' I no more behold them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are fled far: but, ah! thy side is pierc'd;</L>
<L>Nor does this houseless solitude afford</L>
<L>The chance of timely succour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven is just,</L>
<L>(For now I know you) since it bids me die,</L>
<L>Weeping for pardon at your injur'd knees;</L>
<L>For I have basely wrong'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wrong'd me! How?</L>
<L>All who have ever serv'd, or lov'd that false one,</L>
<L>As they bring back her irksome memory,</L>
<L>I shou'd avoid in wisdom. So confin'd,</L>
<L>It is not in thy sphere to wake a thought,</L>
<L>More than compassion for thy helpless sex,</L>
<L>And aid my order binds to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have but patience,</L>
<L>Nor waste the few short moments fate allows me</L>
<L>To doubt my truth; the seal of death is on it.</L>
<L>You left the court on much supposed proof</L>
<L>Of her incontinence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Supposed proof!</L>
<L><PB N="52" REF="55"/>By Heaven! I saw her in the fulsome twine</L>
<L>Of riotous dalliance with one she swore,</L>
<L>That very noon, (a budding perjury)</L>
<L>Excited but her loathing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>At her window</L>
<L>I know you think you saw her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Think I saw her!</L>
<L>Is there for visible objects better sense</L>
<L>Than sight to hold by?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, most injur'd lady!</L>
<L>My sullied lips wou'd but profane thy virtue</L>
<L>To say I know it spotless.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not mock me</L>
<L>With hopes impossible. I see her still—</L>
<L>Her snowy veil and sparkling coronet,</L>
<L>Peculiar in their form—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>By me were worn,</L>
<L>While she and harmless thoughts slept sound together:</L>
<L>Bireno's was the fraud; my boundless love</L>
<L>Made me his instrument.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, hold my brain!—</L>
<L>But one thing more—How came he by that letter?</L>
<L>Her picture, mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>These too I found, and gave him,</L>
<L>By her for you intended. 'Midst her notes</L>
<L>I found his title writ, and trac'd the address</L>
<L>Stroke after stroke agreeing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="53" REF="56"/>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wretch! fond wretch!</L>
<L>Have I for this with viperous calumny</L>
<L>Traduc'd her virgin fame? With desperate hand</L>
<L>Rais'd this sharp sword against my tortur'd breast?</L>
<L>But I will turn an usurer in revenge,</L>
<L>And take such bloody interest for my wrongs—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let Heaven be my avenger—How I lov'd him!</L>
<L>Oh, savage! merciless! To snare my life,</L>
<L>From mere suspicion my unwary tongue</L>
<L>Might publish his contrivance—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! thy life!</L>
<L>Inhuman dog! Were these his ruffians then,</L>
<L>I found thee struggling with?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought they led me,</L>
<L>By his especial care, far from the city,</L>
<L>Where he ordain'd I shou'd remain secure</L>
<L>To hide this swelling witness of my shame</L>
<L>My fatal passion bears him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven defend me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>There lies the bloody contract. Oh, forgive me!</L>
<L>I have struggled hard to make this last confession:</L>
<L>The icy grasp of death chills my shrunk heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wou'd I cou'd save thee!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say but you forgive me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I wou'd be forgiven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="54" REF="57"/>
<SPEAKER>ALINDA.</SPEAKER>
<L>And will you plead</L>
<L>My pardon with my ever gracious mistress,</L>
<L>When she shall know?—'Tis dark—Let this attone.
<STAGE>Dies.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace to thy hapless shade! Thou hast wash'd out</L>
<L>Thy offences in thy blood.—Unnatural slave!</L>
<L>Hell shou'd invent new torments for thy crimes,</L>
<L>And howling fiends avoid thee. I have heard,</L>
<L>Have read, bold fables of enormity,</L>
<L>Devis'd to make men wonder, and confirm</L>
<L>The abhorrence of our nature, but this hardness</L>
<L>Transcends all fiction. Mover of the world!</L>
<L>Send not thy sulphurous lightning forth to strike,</L>
<L>Nor cleave the ground to gape and swallow him;</L>
<L>But, Oh! reserve him for the sharper pangs</L>
<L>My vengeance meditates. Poor blasted flower!</L>
<L>Which way shall I bestow thee? It were cruel</L>
<L>To leave thee thus to insult.—Hold, yon peasant</L>
<L>May help to bear her hence. Shepherd, approach.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE V.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To</HI> PALADORE <HI>a</HI> SHEPHERD.</STAGE>
<P>Hast thou a habitation near this place?</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SHEPHERD.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fair Sir, I have. There eastward turn your eyes;</L>
<L>The curling smoke above yon tufted trees</L>
<L>Mounts from my cottage fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then call for aid,</L>
<L>And bear this body thither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SHEPHERD.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercy guard us!</L>
<L>This is a piteous sight. What cou'd provoke</L>
<L><PB N="55" REF="58"/>A youth of such a sweet and comely outside,</L>
<L>To act so sad a deed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wrong me, shepherd;</L>
<L>She fell by ruffians. Pr'ythee call thy hinds,</L>
<L>And for thy soul's sake do this courtesy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SHEPHERD.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir, detain me not. I haste to the city,</L>
<L>Where all our villagers flock to behold</L>
<L>A most strange sight, and sad as it is strange;</L>
<L>With their best speed, my old limbs will be late;</L>
<L>The sun goes down apace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whate'er the sight,</L>
<L>Respite thy curiosity for gold.</L>
<L>Take this, and give a covering to that corse.
<STAGE>Gives a purse.</STAGE></L>
<L>I must away; you shall hear further from me.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE VI.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To the</HI> SHEPHERD, <HI>at an opposite Entrance,</HI> RINALDO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SHEPHERD.</SPEAKER>
<L>He had a hard heart, lady, struck thee down.</L>
<L>I wou'd not for the herds that graze these hills</L>
<L>Beyond my eyes, not, no, nor for the wealth</L>
<L>Of all who throng the city, I or mine</L>
<L>Shou'd answer for a sin like this at doom's-day.</L>
<L>Oh, if thy father lives, what bitter tears</L>
<L>Will this misdeed wring from his watery eyes!</L>
<L>Thou shalt not want what I can do for thee.</L>
<L>I'll make thy bed with leaves, and strew thee o'er</L>
<L>With herbs and flowers, wild thyme and lavender,</L>
<L>White lilies, and the prime of all our fields:</L>
<L>And for thy soul's peace, till thy knell is toll'd,</L>
<L>I'll number many an ave.—Come, for help.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="56" REF="59"/>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, cursed chance! Vain is my search to find him;</L>
<L>Yet all his life to come, from one lost moment</L>
<L>May take its mournful colour. Doom'd to die;</L>
<L>And he alike accus'd, leave her to perish!</L>
<L>Most horrible!—Kind shepherd! answer quickly;</L>
<L>Saw'st thou a youth clad in a shining robe,</L>
<L>Of noble port, wandering these tangled woods?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SHEPHERD.</SPEAKER>
<L>Even such a one as you describe, but now,</L>
<L>(Him of your question doubtless) went from hence,</L>
<L>And left with me in charge—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter what.</L>
<L>Know you the path he took, which way his course?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SHEPHERD.</SPEAKER>
<L>I follow'd him a little with my eye,</L>
<L>And saw him wind round yonder shrubby hill,</L>
<L>Then pass the row of olives.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leads it not</L>
<L>Strait to the city?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SHEPHERD.</SPEAKER>
<L>As the falcon flies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>RINALDO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, Fortune! Guide his steps once more to Pavia,</L>
<L>Else, never ending misery awaits him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt severally.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>END OF THE FOURTH ACT.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB N="57" REF="60"/>
<HEAD>ACT V.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE I. <HI>a Hall.</HI></HEAD>
<STAGE>LUCIO, <HI>an</HI> OFFICER.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFFICER.</SPEAKER>
<L>THINK on the danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who sees only that,</L>
<L>Will ne'er surmount it. More than life I owe her.</L>
<L>Adversity's hard hand had crush'd my hopes,</L>
<L>Doom'd my sweet wife, and infant family,</L>
<L>To shameful beggary: my affliction reach'd her:</L>
<L>Can I forget her all-dispensing bounty,</L>
<L>That rais'd my soul from comfortless despair,</L>
<L>That bad my cheerful house again receive me,</L>
<L>Bless'd us with plenty?—If I fall, and save her,</L>
<L>'Tis well; I ask no nobler epitaph.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFFICER.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's virtue in your motive, and your purpose;</L>
<L>But how effect her rescue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you join us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFFICER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or why these questions?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare trust your honour,</L>
<L>The bond of soldiers. Know then, I command</L>
<L>(And sought it with this hope) her prison guard:</L>
<L>I have sounded them, they hate the cruel service.</L>
<L>A little, ere the fatal hour's approach,</L>
<L><PB N="58" REF="61"/>We mean to pass their unresisting force,</L>
<L>Throw wide the iron gates, and bear her safe</L>
<L>Beyond the danger of this bloody edict.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFFICER.</SPEAKER>
<L>It looks success, may fortune second it!</L>
<L>The throngs assembled to behold the sight,</L>
<L>Will count for idle gazers, and conceal</L>
<L>Your bold design, till 'tis too late to twhart it.</L>
<L>How brooks she her sad plight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>With fortitude</L>
<L>So sweet, so even-temper'd, that her death</L>
<L>Seems but a phantom, dress'd by Fancy's trick,</L>
<L>To frighten children. All her soul's employ'd</L>
<L>In minist'ring, with softest piety,</L>
<L>To her distracted father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFFICER.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's a spectacle,</L>
<L>Indeed, heart-rending. Cast on the cold ground,</L>
<L>He strews his head with ashes, by the roots</L>
<L>Tears out his silver hair, beats his poor breast;</L>
<L>While the significant dumbness of his gesture,</L>
<L>Beggars all power of words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou blind mischance,</L>
<L>Stand neuter! we shall cheer him presently.</L>
<L>I'll to my station. Keep thy sword conceal'd,</L>
<L>Nor sheathe it drawn, but in the villain's breast,</L>
<L>That dare oppose us. Be but firm, and fear not.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt severally.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE II.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO,</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>alone.</STAGE>
<L>By their description, it was Paladore;</L>
<L>The place, the glittering robe, his courage too,</L>
<L><PB N="59" REF="62"/>In so assailing them. If their keen daggers</L>
<L>Left her enough of breath to tell the tale,</L>
<L>She has, no doubt, told all, and wing'd him back,</L>
<L>To wreak his vengeance on me; this way only,</L>
<L>Can I be safe; firm as he is, and fearless,</L>
<L>My ambush cuts him off; and, by his death,</L>
<L>The full tide of my prosperous fortune flows,</L>
<L>Never to ebb.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE III.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To</HI> BIRENO, ASCANIO.</STAGE>
<L>Well, the great period comes;</L>
<L>No champion meets my challenge?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, not one.</L>
<L>Fear puts the livery of conscience on:</L>
<L>They cannot think one of your nobleness,</L>
<L>Wou'd charge a lady falsely to the death;</L>
<L>And few are the examples of success</L>
<L>Against conviction: "true, 'tis pitiful,</L>
<L>"That one so fair, so young, of royal birth,</L>
<L>"For the meer frailty of impulsive nature,</L>
<L>"Should meet so sad a doom; the law's to blame,</L>
<L>"That bloodily enrolls a venial trespass,</L>
<L>"With those o'ergrown and huge enormities,</L>
<L>"That shake society;" but they can no more,</L>
<L>Than drop a tear or two, and let her die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>True; she must die; and the heart-wounded king,</L>
<L>Whose age already totters o'er the grave,</L>
<L>Like a crush'd serpent, but a little longer</L>
<L>Will drag his painful being. Yet one fear</L>
<L>Sits, like a boding raven o'er my breast,</L>
<L>And flaps its heavy wing to damp my joy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>What fear can reach you now? From Paladore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="60" REF="63"/>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perdition seize him! yes. But, my good ruffians,</L>
<L>Ere this, I trust, have sent to his account,</L>
<L>That ill-star'd Briton. Doubly arm'd they wait him—</L>
<L>Close by a brambled cavern he must pass,</L>
<L>Returning hither. Yet, should he escape—</L>
<L>It cannot be—Heart, re-assume thy seat.</L>
<L>But, come, the time draws on—Bear to the lists,</L>
<L>My martial ensigns; I must seem prepar'd</L>
<L>To oppose a danger that will never meet me.</L>
<STAGE>As be is going, a servant delivers a paper. Reads.</STAGE>
<L>The hand of Bernardine, my trusty spy.</L>
<L>Confusion! rescue her! Come back, Ascanio!</L>
<L>Fly to St. Mark's, collect the cohort there;</L>
<L>Go, place them instantly around the prison;</L>
<L>Bid them disarm the guard that holds that place,</L>
<L>And, on their lives, drive back the populace.</L>
<L>I'll to Honorias—These stout veterans</L>
<L>Will sweep the rabble like vile chaff before them.</L>
<L>Away—A moment may be fatal to us.
<STAGE>Exeunt severally.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE IV. <HI>a Prison.</HI></HEAD>
<STAGE>PRINCESS, WOMEN <HI>attending.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, dry these tears—The aweful eve of death</L>
<L>Is but profan'd by shews of common sorrow.</L>
<L>I have a triple armour round my heart,</L>
<L>'Gainst all the shapes of terror; yet it owns</L>
<L>The soft contagion of affection's drops,</L>
<L>And melts at kindness. Come, this must not be —</L>
<L>You, Laura! must be near me at the block,</L>
<L>And help to disarray me.—What, more tears?</L>
<L>Stop them, for shame; I must have strangers else,</L>
<L>For this last office. When the axe has fallen,</L>
<L>They have no further power—Save from disgrace,</L>
<L>My poor remains, and on your loves, I charge you,</L>
<L><PB N="61" REF="64"/>When I am dead, see, that they touch me not.</L>
<L>I have not been unmindful of your service.</L>
<L>It is not much—There were too many poor,</L>
<L>Too many comfortless, to leave me rich:</L>
<L>But you will find a father in the king,</L>
<L>And, for my sake, he will be bounteous to you.</L>
<L>Retire, and weep, I dare not look upon you.</L>
<STAGE>Takes a picture from her breast.</STAGE>
<L>Thou dear dumb image of a form belov'd!</L>
<L>Soul of my soul, and precious even in death,</L>
<L>A while be sensible! Receive this sigh,</L>
<L>And take my last farewel. When thou shalt know</L>
<L>My truth, and sufferings, let not the sad tale</L>
<L>Blast the fair promise of thy noble youth,</L>
<L>But, with a sweet, a sacred melancholy,</L>
<L>Embalm the soft remembrance of my love.</L>
<L>My father! Oh, angelic host support me,</L>
<L>To bear this parting, and death's pang is past!</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE V.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS, KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am indeed subdued—To see thee thus!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>They would not let me die—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>These few short hours,</L>
<L>Alas, how have they chang'd thee! Murderous sorrow!</L>
<L>Thy furrows sink more deep than age or time.</L>
<L>Your cheek is ashy pale, your eyes quite sunk.</L>
<L>Will you not look upon me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, no, no;</L>
<L>I came to give thee comfort, to sustain thee;</L>
<L>But, looking on thee, I shall weep again,</L>
<L>And add my load of misery to thine.</L>
<L>Yet teach me to be patient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="62" REF="65"/>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>View me well;</L>
<L>Nor think these tears fall for my own distress;</L>
<L>The throbbings of my heart are for my father.</L>
<L>'Tis apprehension makes death terrible;</L>
<L>Cowards, from weakness, tremble; guilt, from conscience;</L>
<L>But the firm bosom innocence invests;</L>
<L>Knows it a fix'd inevitable end,</L>
<L>Meets the pale guest, nor startles at the encounter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wert my all, a mote that vex'd thy eye,</L>
<L>A thorn that raz'd thy finger, snatch'd my thoughts</L>
<L>From every care but thee. And thus to lose thee!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, were our being circumscrib'd by earth,</L>
<L>This end indeed might shake my constancy:</L>
<L>But, faith apart: think what bright evidence</L>
<L>Shines here within of immortality.</L>
<L>Who has not felt the heavenly overflow</L>
<L>Of thought congenial to the eternal mind?</L>
<L>Why are there tears of virtuous sympathy?</L>
<L>Whence that coelestial fluid of the eye,</L>
<L>That sheds such full, such satisfied delight?</L>
<L>But that the God of all benevolence,</L>
<L>Thus gives a glimpse of blessedness to come,</L>
<L>In joys refin'd from sense, and far transcending?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>What has old age to lose? Is the poor remnant</L>
<L>Of life worn thread-bare, precious for itself?</L>
<L>Can we be fond of pain, and feebleness?</L>
<L>No; but our second spring, our soul's renew'd</L>
<L>In our dear children, there we cling to life:</L>
<L>Mortality! thy last, thy heaviest curse.</L>
<L>Bids us remain the mournful monument,</L>
<L>The living tomb of all our comforts buried,</L>
<L>Telling no more in our sepulchral sorrow,</L>
<L>Than that they were, and are not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="63" REF="66"/>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must live</L>
<L>(For sure the hour will come) to see this cloud</L>
<L>Pass from my memory; and the shame he merits,</L>
<L>Fall on my base accuser.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>[Kneeling.]</STAGE>
<L>Hear me, Heaven?</L>
<L>On the devoted murderer of my child,</L>
<L>With tenfold visitation pour my sorrow!</L>
<L>Let fear, mistrust, and horror ever haunt him!</L>
<L>Slumber forsake his couch, and joy his table!</L>
<L>If he must reign, Oh, line his crown with thorns!</L>
<L>Turn reverence to contempt, the friend he trusts,</L>
<L>Meet him for smiles with daggers: war abroad,</L>
<L>Treason at home, pursue, and harrass him!</L>
<L>And may the steam, that mounts from innocent blood,</L>
<L>Make heavier the dire thunderbolt,</L>
<L>Lanc'd from thy red right arm, at last to crush him!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spirit of peace! on his distemper'd rage,</L>
<L>Oh, shed thy healing balm!
<STAGE>A noise without.</STAGE></L>
<L>What mean these shouts?</L>
<L>This wild tumultuous noise?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>To them an</HI> ATTENDANT.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTENDANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our prayers are heard:</L>
<L>The guard gives way, the massy bars are forc'd;</L>
<L>And, like delivering angels, the rous'd people,</L>
<L>Burst in to lead you from this den of horror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, joy unhop'd! Millions of blessings crown them!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTENDANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Led by the gallant Lucio, they advance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="64" REF="67"/>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>The tiger then may seek his prey in vain;</L>
<L>My brave, my generous people! Hark! they come.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>More noise.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah, Sir! retire—Your heart must thank their purpose;</L>
<L>Yet sure 'twere most unmeet for royalty.</L>
<L>Whose sway, and throne, are hallow'd in obedience,</L>
<L>To countenance this outrage. Pray, retire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I will go; but, Oh, be swift, my child!</L>
<L>Nor dally with this blessed chance to save thee.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE VI.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To her,</HI> LUCIO, <HI>his sword drawn.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>[Advancing.]</STAGE>
<L>Your purpose, quickly?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>[Kneeling.]</STAGE>
<L>Your deliverance, lady!</L>
<L>I owe a debt of boundless gratitude,</L>
<L>And thus in part wou'd pay it. Madam, fly!</L>
<L>The people all are yours, a chosen band,</L>
<L>Faithful, and brave, wait to conduct you hence:</L>
<L>This smiling moment seiz'd, may place you safe,</L>
<L>Beyond the dreadful fate that threatens you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not beyond the reach of soul disgrace,</L>
<L>The noble mind's worst fate—I know thee, Lucio!</L>
<L>And thank thy kind intention. Cou'd my flight</L>
<L>Restore my name to its original whiteness,</L>
<L>Make palpable his lie who slanders me,</L>
<L>I'd think thee thus commission'd from above,</L>
<L>And welcome life with transport.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do I wake!</L>
<L>When your good angel thus by me invites you,</L>
<L><PB N="65" REF="68"/>Is this a time to doubt? Can you devote</L>
<L>That rosy youth, that all commanding beauty,</L>
<L>To voluntary death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were it a pain,</L>
<L>Worse than the fear of cowards can conceive,</L>
<L>I wou'd abide it. Have I not endur'd</L>
<L>A greater horror, heard myself proclaim'd,</L>
<L>The thing I scorn to utter? Shall I live,</L>
<L>To bear about a disputable fame,</L>
<L>Scattering the eternal seeds of strife and war,</L>
<L>Over my country, for the privilege</L>
<L>To draw a little transitory breath,</L>
<L>And be consign'd to infamy, or honour,</L>
<L>But as the sword of conquest arbitrates?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are suggestions of your generous anger,</L>
<L>And not your reason—Oh, most honour'd lady!</L>
<L>Again behold me prostrate at your feet:</L>
<L>Thus, thus, by me the people supplicate.
<STAGE>Kneels.</STAGE></L>
<L>We have but one short moment left to save you;</L>
<L>Seize it, and live, live to be still rever'd</L>
<L>Your country's pride, her boast, her ornament.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not to be chang'd. But, Oh, my father!</L>
<L>The good old king, he wants a friend like thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>[Without.]</STAGE>
<L>Force down the bridge. Kill all who dare oppose.</L>
<L>They fly; stand fast —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He cuts my purpose short.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="7" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="67" REF="69"/>
<HEAD>SCENE VII.</HEAD>
<STAGE>ASCANIO, <HI>with Soldiers to them.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LUCIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, death to all our hopes! 'tis now too late.</L>
<L>I cast thee from my hand, vile instrument!</L>
<L>Since she disdains thy service.
<STAGE>Throws down his sword.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seize that traitor—</L>
<L>Quick, bear him hence—Madam, I grieve to speak it,</L>
<L>The herald, to the temple porch, has issued</L>
<L>For final proclamation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spare your sorrow—</L>
<L>A shameful world, disgrac'd by souls like thine,</L>
<L>Turns grief to joy, when noble natures leave it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Princess <HI>guarded.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="8" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE VIII.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To</HI> ASCANIO, BIRENO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, let me clasp thee! This was worthy service.</L>
<L>But for thy zeal, the high-rais'd edifice</L>
<L>So near complete, had tumbled to the earth,</L>
<L>And crush'd me in its fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haste to the lists;</L>
<L>A moment more consummates our design,</L>
<L>And Fate itself may strive in vain to shake us.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="9" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="67" REF="70"/>
<HEAD>SCENE IX.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>The Lists in the middle of the stage. A scaffold, guard, and executioner at the bottom. Many spectators, officers, and sena∣tors, preceding the Princess, supported by women.</HI> Bireno <HI>with</HI> Ascanio, <HI>who bears his shield and sword. Heralds, with trumpets, on the sides.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFFICER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make room. Fall back. Let the procession pass.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis known why I stand here; yet once again,</L>
<L>And for the last time, herald, sound my challenge.</L>
<L>Proceed, none answer.
<STAGE>Bireno'<HI>s Trumpet sounds.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wou'd have it so.</L>
<L>You generous people, who behold with horror</L>
<L>These gloomy preparations, do not deem me</L>
<L>Cold, and unthankful, for my offer'd safety,</L>
<L>Tho' I prefer'd this dire alternative.</L>
<L>Before the tongue of slander struck my fame,</L>
<L>The rude hand of affliction never touch'd me;</L>
<L>Life had a thousand bonds to tie me to it,</L>
<L>Young spirits, royal birth, fortune, and greatness:</L>
<L>But honour was the prop, round which, like stalks</L>
<L>Tender and weak, these accessaries twin'd.</L>
<L>When Calumny's sharp edge cut down that trunk,</L>
<L>Then these poor tendrils lost their hue, and wither'd.</L>
<L>With that great ruin fell my happiness.</L>
<L>I now stand on eternity's dark verge,</L>
<L>Nor dare I to the God, and Judge of Truth,</L>
<L>Bring lips with falsehood fullied. Of the offence</L>
<L>Cast on me by vile malice, I am free,</L>
<L>Even to abhorrence; this to Heaven is known,</L>
<L>My own heart, and my accuser: therefore boldly,</L>
<L>And for your sakes, will I arraign the law,</L>
<L>Which thus has pass'd upon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="68" REF="71"/>
<SPEAKER>FIRST SENATOR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious lady!</L>
<L>If in this censure we too stand accus'd,</L>
<L>Think we pronounc'd, but did not make the law.</L>
<L>And let my bleeding heart bear witness for me,</L>
<L>I wou'd lay down the dearest thing I own,</L>
<L>To save you from the forfeit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, my Lord!</L>
<L>All forms of justice have been well observ'd;</L>
<L>My blame lights on the law, not on your office,</L>
<L>Which you with truth and mercy minister.</L>
<L>But let these mute spectators mark my counsel:</L>
<L>Fall at the king's feet, clasp the senate's knees,</L>
<L>And pray them, they wipe out clear from their rolls,</L>
<L>This more than cruel edict; else, be sure</L>
<L>From every roof there hangs a dangerous sword,</L>
<L>(Hangs by a thread) which each dark hand may drop</L>
<L>To pierce and sever nature's dearest ties.</L>
<L>She who profanes her honor's sanctity,</L>
<L>Upbraided by her heart, by her own sex</L>
<L>Shun'd or neglected, nay, held cheap, and vile,</L>
<L>Even to the loathing of the lover's sense,</L>
<L>Who wrought her easy nature to transgress;</L>
<L>These are sharp penalties: but added death</L>
<L>Turns the clear stream of justice into blood,</L>
<L>And makes such law more curs'd than anarchy.</L>
<L>Forget not my example; let me perish:</L>
<L>But if you pluck your safety from my ruin,</L>
<L>I shall not die in vain. Farewel—Lead on—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Princess <HI>goes toward the Scaffold, a Trumpet sounds.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FIRST SENATOR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, on your lives.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>What means that trumpet's voice?</L>
<L>It sounds a shrill alarm.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="10" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="69" REF="72"/>
<HEAD>SCENE X. <HI>To them a</HI> SQUIRE.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SQUIRE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arrest your sentence.</L>
<L>I come in the name of one, who hears with horror</L>
<L>This barbarous process, to proclaim the accuser</L>
<L>Of that most innocent and royal lady,</L>
<L>A slanderer and villain; who accepts</L>
<L>Her just defence, and by the law of arms</L>
<L>Throws down this gage, and claims the combat for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take it, Ascanio. Bid your knight appear,</L>
<L>(If such his order) for to none beneath</L>
<L>Am I thus bound to answer. Speak his titles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SQUIRE.</SPEAKER>
<L>He wills not I reveal him; but suffice it,</L>
<L>He has a name in arms that will not shame</L>
<L>The noble cause he fights for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bid him enter.</L>
<L>My shield and sword. Say, I am deck'd to meet him.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Squire.</STAGE>
<L>Some rash adventurer, prodigal of life,</L>
<L>Brib'd by her father's gold to grace her fall,</L>
<L>And add an easy trophy to my banners.—</L>
<L>Confusion! Paladore!</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="11" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE XI. <HI>To them</HI> PALADORE.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis he, 'tis he!—</L>
<L>Then, life, thou art welcome.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A loud Murmur among the People.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marshal, do your office!</L>
<L><PB N="70" REF="73"/>Furies and hell!—Keep order in the lists!—</L>
<L>Silence that uproar—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, behold me, villain!</L>
<L>I have thee in the toils; thou can'st not scape me.—</L>
<L>But Oh! most wrong'd, and heavenly excellence!</L>
<STAGE><HI>To the</HI> Princess.</STAGE>
<L>How shall I plead for pardon?—Can the abuse</L>
<L>Of his deep craft, and devilish artifice,</L>
<L>Fooling my nature's plainness, blanch my cheek</L>
<L>From the deep shame that my too easy faith</L>
<L>Combin'd with hell against thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise, my soldier!</L>
<L>Though yet I know not by what subtle practice</L>
<L>Thy nobleness was wrought on, nor the means</L>
<L>That since reveal'd his fraud, praise be to Heaven!</L>
<L>Thy presence plucks my honour from the grave;</L>
<L>Thou liv'st, thou know'st my truth, thou wilt avenge me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Avenge thee!—Yes—Did his right-hand grasp thunder,</L>
<L>Did yelling furies combat on his side,</L>
<L>(Pal'd in with circling fires) I wou'd assail him,</L>
<L>Nor cast a look to Fortune for the event.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Presumptuous Briton! Think not that bold mien,</L>
<L>A wanton's favour, or thy threats, have power</L>
<L>To shrink the finews of a soldier's arm.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>A soldier's arm! Thou double murderer!</L>
<L>Assassin in thy intention, and in act.</L>
<L>But ere my falchion cleave thy treacherous breast</L>
<L>I will divulge thee.—Bring that russian forth.—</L>
<STAGE><HI>One of</HI> Alinda<HI>'s murderers is brought out.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Two hell-hounds, such as this, he set upon me;</L>
<L>One fell beneath my sword; that wretch I spar'd,</L>
<L>Kneeling for mercy: let your justice doom him.</L>
<L>Look you amaz'd! Peruse that paper, Lords,</L>
<L><PB N="71" REF="74"/>His compact for the blood of a fair minion,</L>
<L>He taught to sin, and made her wages death.—</L>
<L>Ha! Does it shake thee? See Alinda's form,</L>
<L>Thy panting image mangled in her side,</L>
<L>Stalks from her sanguine bed, and ghastly smiles,</L>
<L>To aid the prowess of this dauntless soldier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>[Aside.]</STAGE>
<L>Destruction! All's reveal'd!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ASCANIO</SPEAKER>
<STAGE><HI>to</HI> BIRENO.</STAGE>
<L>What, turn'd to stone!</L>
<L>Droop not, for shame.—Be quick, retort the charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>All false as hell! And thou—Defend thyself;</L>
<L>Nor blast me thus with thy detested presence.—</L>
<L>This to thy heart.
<STAGE><HI>Fight.</HI> Bireno <HI>falls.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, impotence of guilt!</L>
<L>An infant's lath had fell'd him. Villain, die!</L>
<L>And know thy shame, and the deep wound that wriths thee,</L>
<L>Are but a feeble earnest of the pangs</L>
<L>Reserv'd beneath for giant crimes like thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haste to the King, proclaim this bless'd event!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BIRENO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perfidious chance! Caught in my own device!—</L>
<L>Accursed!—Ha! they drag me, tear me!—Oh!—
<STAGE>Dies.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRINCESS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a thousand things to ask, to hear:</L>
<L>But, Oh! the joy to see thee thus again,</L>
<L>To owe my life, my honour, to thy love—</L>
<L>These tears, these rapturous tears, let them speak for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PALADORE.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cou'd endure the malice of my fate:</L>
<L>But this full tide of such excessive bliss,</L>
<L>Sure 'tis illusion all! It quite transports me.</L>
<L><PB N="72" REF="75"/>When I have borne thee from this scene of horror,</L>
<L>Perhaps I may grow calm, and talk with reason.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="12" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE XII. <HI>and last.</HI></HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them,</HI> KING, LUCIO, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is she? Let me strain her to my heart.—</L>
<L>They cannot part us now, my joy! my comfort!—</L>
<L>Thou generous youth! How can my o'erflowing soul</L>
<L>Find words to thank thee?—Words! Poor recompense!</L>
<L>Here I invest thee with the forfeit lands,</L>
<L>The wealth and honours of that prostrate traitor.</L>
<L>This too is little—then receive her hand,</L>
<L>Due to thy love, thy courage, and thy virtue,</L>
<L>And joys unutterable crown your union.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>END OF THE FIFTH ACT.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="76"/>
<HEAD>PROLOGUE to the LAW of LOMBARDY,</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Written by the AUTHOR.</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Spoken by Mr. FARREN.</BYLINE>
<SP>
<L>HARD is the task, in modern days to choose,</L>
<L>Congenial subjects for the tragic muse:</L>
<L>The historian's page, the fertile epic store,</L>
<L>Were known, and ransack'd centuries before:</L>
<L>Like luscious gardens, unenclos'd they lay,</L>
<L>To ev'ry saunt'ring bard an easy prey.</L>
<L>They enter'd, and, as taste impell'd, they fed</L>
<L>On Homer some, and some on Hollingshead.</L>
<L>From loftiest numbers, or from humblest prose,</L>
<L>As each conspir'd, the artless structures rose.</L>
<L>Thus one great labour of their work was o'er,</L>
<L>They found a fable, and they fought no more.</L>
<L>Careless were they of action, place, or time,</L>
<L>Whose only toil was dialogue and rhyme.</L>
<L>"Rules which the rigid Stagyrite devis'd,</L>
<L>"Our fathers knew not, or, if known, despis'd.</L>
<L>Whilst side by side, were mingled in the scene,</L>
<L>A laughing rustic, and a weeping queen.</L>
<L>Space was obedient to the boundless piece,</L>
<L>That op'd in Mexico, and clos'd in Greece.</L>
<L>Then thick with plots the crowded tale was sown,</L>
<L>'Till the divided bosom felt for none;</L>
<L>"They fear'd no censures of a frowning pit,</L>
<L>"That judg'd as loosely as the authors writ."</L>
<L>But we, who posted in time's tardy rear,</L>
<L>Before a learn'd tribunal now appear;</L>
<L>With anxious art a fable must design,</L>
<L>Where probability, and interest join:</L>
<L>Where time, and place, and action, all agree</L>
<L>To violate no sacred unity.</L>
<L>And thus each candid critic must confess</L>
<L>The labour greater, and indulgence less;</L>
<L>When such the task, the wonder is to meet,</L>
<L>Not many pieces bad, but one complete.</L>
<L>Nor let presumptious poets fondly claim</L>
<L>From rules exemption, by great Shakespeare's name;</L>
<L>Though comets move with wild excentric force,</L>
<L>Yet humbler planets keep their stated course.</L>
<L>But now, a bard, who touch'd your hearts before,</L>
<L>Again salutes you from a neighbouring shore.</L>
<L>Fir'd by the applause you gave his early lays,</L>
<L>He stands again a candidate for praise;</L>
<L>Nor from your former favour dares foresee</L>
<L>To worthless strains a partial destiny.</L>
<L>But if his virgin palm was fairly won,</L>
<L>And this next course with equal vigour's run,</L>
<L>Now join to bind his fresher laurels on.</L>
<L>He fears no jaundic'd rival's envious <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reath,</L>
<L>The hands which twin'd, shall still preserve the wreath.</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="77"/>
<HEAD>EPILOGUE to the LAW of LOMBARDY.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Written by the AUTHOR.</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Spoken by Miss YOUNGE.</BYLINE>
<SP>
<L>OF all the Gothic laws I ever heard,</L>
<L>This Lombard Law was sure the most absurd:</L>
<L>What! could the monsters mean to make us die,</L>
<L>But for a little harmless gallantry?</L>
<L>Were such a barbarous custom now in fashion,</L>
<L>Good Lord! it would unpeople half the nation.</L>
<L>Scaffolds on scaffolds now the streets would fill,</L>
<L>As sign-posts did, before the paving-bill.</L>
<L>Were British law-makers such rigorous churls,</L>
<L>They'd hardly leave a head to wear false curls.</L>
<L>Besides, what champion now would risque his life,</L>
<L>To gain what most men shudder at—a wife.</L>
<L>Instead of arm'd knights, at trumpet's summons,</L>
<L>Commend me to our proctors, and the Commons.</L>
<L>There, though we lose our husbands, and our fame,</L>
<L>We get our portion, and a maiden name.</L>
<L>And if her fortune, and her charms remain,</L>
<L>Then Miss may wed—and be divorc'd again.</L>
<L>Yet, though these frolics have of late been common,</L>
<L>Lay not the blame entirely on weak woman.</L>
<L>The careless mate his rival recommends,</L>
<L>We find him 'midst his own obliging friends.</L>
<L>Some swain, who swears he lives but in our eyes,</L>
<L>And plies us with such cunning flatteries,</L>
<L>That spouse neglecting us, and lover wooing,</L>
<L>One strives, and t'other leads us, to our ruin.</L>
<L>So, if weak ladies, chance to go astray,</L>
<L>Their lords, methinks, are more in fault than they:</L>
<L>The goal of marriage reach'd, the men lie down,</L>
<L>Like weary racers when the prize is won;</L>
<L>Mere catching us alone their care engages;</L>
<L>The nets they spread, but never mind the cages.</L>
<L>The married gamester more delight can find,</L>
<L>In "Seven's the main," than all dear womankind.</L>
<L>Acteon wedded, to our voice prefers</L>
<L>The sweeter music of his yelping ours;</L>
<L>While the dull sot, who his six bottles boasts,</L>
<L>Thinks women good for nothing—but for toasts.</L>
<L>Thus slighted for the glass, the hound, the die,</L>
<L>Our pride steps in, and to revenge we fly;</L>
<L>One obvious method only can preserve us,</L>
<L>Strive, by your own attentions, to deserve us;</L>
<L>And now, as formerly, be sure you'll prove,</L>
<L>Contempt will meet contempt, as love meets love.</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's advertisement">
<PB REF="78"/>
<HEAD>Books printed for T. Evans in the Strand.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 BRAGANZA, a Tragedy, by Robert Jephson, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 1s. 6d.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 The Countess of Salisbury, a Tragedy, by Hall Hartson, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 1s. 6d.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3 The Heroine of the Cave, a Tragedy, by the Author of the Earl of Essex, 1s. 6d.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4 Cleonice, a Tragedy, by John Hoole, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 1s. 6d.</ITEM>
<ITEM>5 The Man is the Master, a Comedy, by Sir William Davenant, 1s. 6d.</ITEM>
<ITEM>6 Zenobia, a Tragedy, by Arthur Murphy, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 1s. 6d.</ITEM>
<ITEM>7 The Songs in the Duenna, by R. B. Sheridan, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 1s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>8 The Brothers, a Comedy, by R. Cumberland, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 1s. 6d.</ITEM>
<ITEM>9 The Fashionable Lover, a Comedy, by R. Cumberland, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 1s. 6d.</ITEM>
<ITEM>10 The Duellist, a Comedy, by Dr. Kenrick, 1s. 6d.</ITEM>
<ITEM>11 Southerne's Plays, with an Account of his Life and Writings, 3 vol. <HI>price bound</HI> 10s. 6d.</ITEM>
<ITEM>12 Shakespeare's Plays, with the Notes of various Commentators, and S. Johnson and George Steevens, Esqrs; 10 vol. <HI>new edit. price bound</HI> 3l. 10s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>13 Beaumont and Fletcher's Plays, with Notes of various Com∣mentators, and a preface by George Colman, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> adorned with fifty-five elegant Engravings, <HI>price bound</HI> 3l. 10s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>14 Massinger's Plays, with Notes, by Mr. Mason, and Critical Reflections on old English Dramatic Writers, by George Col∣man, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> 4 vol. <HI>new edit. price bound</HI> 1l. 4s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>15 A Collection of old Plays, illustrative of Shakespeare, with a Preface, 2 vol. <HI>price bound</HI> 8s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>16 Plays and Poems written by his Grace George Villiers, Duke of Buckingham, 2 vol. <HI>price bound</HI> 8s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>17 Plays and Poems written by Richard Savage, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> son of the Earl Rivers, with an Account of his Life and Writings, by Dr. Samuel Johnson, 2 vol. <HI>price bound</HI> 8s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>18 Plays and Poems written by T. Smollet, M. D. with an Ac∣count of his Life and Writings, <HI>price bound</HI> 4s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>19 Poems written by William Shakespeare, <HI>price bound</HI> 4s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>20 Old Ballads, Historical and Narrative, (<HI>none of which are in∣cluded in Dr. Percy's Collection</HI>) with Notes, 2 vol. with an elegant Engraving, <HI>price bound</HI> 8s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>21 The complete Works of M. De Montesquieu, containing his Spirit of Laws, and other Pieces, now first collected, with his Eulogium, by M. D'Alembert, 4 vol. large 8vo. with an elegant Engraving, <HI>price bound</HI> 1l. 4s.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB REF="79"/>22 The Universal History of M. Bossuet, Bishop of Meaux, Pre∣ceptor to the Dauphin, <HI>a new edit. complete, in one volume, large</HI> 8<HI>vo. price bound</HI> 6s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>23 Letters from Yorick to Eliza, <HI>price sewed</HI> 2s. <HI>These Letters complete Mr. Sterne's Works.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>24 Select Works of Mr. Abraham Cowley, <HI>a Supplement to Bishop Hurd's Edition, price sewed</HI> 3s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>25 The Universal Mentor, or entertaining Instructor; consisting of Essays on the most important Subjects in Life, selected from the best Writers, by Sir John Fielding, <HI>price bound</HI> 3s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>26 The Grand Tour; or a Journey through the Netherlands, Germany, Italy and France: <HI>containing a Description of the principal Cities and Towns, the public Edifices, Seats and Pa∣laces, their Libraries, Cabinets, Paintings and Statues, Coins, Commerce, &amp;c. and an exact List of the Post Routs and Prices,</HI> by M. Nugent, 4 vol. <HI>new edit. price bound</HI> 14s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>27 Desiderata Curiosa, a Collection of curious Tracts, chiefly on English History, Lives, Memoirs, Wills, Letters, Epitaphs, &amp;c. from Original MSS. by Francis Peck, 2 vol. Royal Quarto, with Plates, <HI>price in boards,</HI> 1l. 11s. 6d.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><HI>In a few Days will be published,</HI></P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>THE WORKS OF THE ENGLISH POETS, With Portraits elegantly engraven, and Prefaces Biographical and Critical, by Dr. Johnson, 57 vol. <HI>price, sewed,</HI> 7l.</ITEM>
<ITEM>In 2 vol. small Octavo, adorned with a most exquisite En∣graving by Sherwin, from a Design of Mortimer, <HI>price, sewed,</HI> 7s. THE POETICAL WORKS OF MATTHEW PRIOR, New, first collected with Explanatory Notes and Memoirs of the Author.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Proposals for printing by Subscription, an elegant Edition, in one Volume, Folio, NOTITIA MONASTICA. By WILLIAM TANNER, Lord Bishop of St. Asaph.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

