<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2008-05-13</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Alexis Jakobson</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>*Proofed title page(s).
*Reviewed structure.
*Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). 
*Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. 
*Checked for N=""s. 
*Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. 
*Checked placement and completeness of PBs. 
*Checked for foreign, damage and missing-page GAPs, #, --. 
*Checked for LBs, startqs / endqs, q;s, {que}s, ABBRs and Qs. 
*Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials.
*Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. 
*Corrected $$s and $word$s etc. 
*Converted $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="[vendor name]".
*Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K126403.000">
<STC T="C">T196353</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3315800305</BIBNO>
<VID SET="ECLL">1028601000</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="song">
<PB REF="1"/>
<HEAD>In the Dead of the Night.</HEAD>
<P>Sung by Mrs. Jordan in the Wedding Day.</P>
<P>(Sold by <HI>J. EVANS,</HI> No. <HI>41,</HI> Long-lane.)</P>
<LG>
<L>IN the dead of the night, when with labor oppress'd</L>
<L>All mortals enjoy the sweet blessing of rest,</L>
<L>A boy knock'd at my door, I awoke with the noise,</L>
<L>Who is it, I said, who is it that my rest thus destroys</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>He answered so softly, so gently, so mild,</L>
<L>I am a poor little unfortunate child;</L>
<L>Its a cold rainy night, I am wet to the skin,</L>
<L>And I have lost my way, so pray let me in.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>In compassion I rose, and striking a light,</L>
<L>I open'd the door, when a boy stood in sight</L>
<L>He had wings on his shoulders, the rain from them drip'd,</L>
<L>And with bow and with arrows the boy was equip'd</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I stir'd up my fire, set him down by my side,</L>
<L>And with a warm napkin the wet from him dry'd</L>
<L>I chal'd him all o'er, to keep out the cold air,</L>
<L>And I wrung with my hands the wet from his hair.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>No sooner from wet and from cold he found ease,</L>
<L>Then he took up the bow and said, Ma'am, if you please,</L>
<L>would fain, with your leave, by experiment know,</L>
<L>the rain has not damag'd the strings of my bow.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Then straight from his quiver an arrow he drew.</L>
<L>Which he aim'd at my heart, and twang went the yew.</L>
<L>My bow is undamag'd, said he, and my dart,</L>
<L>And you will find trouble in bearing the smart.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

