<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A catalogue of the damages for which the English demand reparation from the United-Netherlands as also a list of the damages, actions, and pretenses for which those of the United-Netherlands demand reparation and satisfaction from the English, together with the answer of the English, subjoyn'd to the several and respective points of their demands.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A31291</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing C1371</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R10634</IDNO>



<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 11680688</IDNO>


<AVAILABILITY><P>This text has been selected for inclusion in the EEBO-TCP: Navigations collection, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities. To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication ( http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31291)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48101)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 485:6)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A catalogue of the damages for which the English demand reparation from the United-Netherlands as also a list of the damages, actions, and pretenses for which those of the United-Netherlands demand reparation and satisfaction from the English, together with the answer of the English, subjoyn'd to the several and respective points of their demands.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[8], 75 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Henry Brome,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1664.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Concerns the English and Dutch East India Companies.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2016-01-29.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM TYPE="corporate name">East India Company.</TERM><TERM TYPE="corporate name">Nederlandsche Oost-Indische Compagnie.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2012-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2012-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2012-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Colm MacCrossan</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2012-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Colm MacCrossan</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A31291">
<STC T="W">C1371</STC>
<STC T="C">R10634</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">11680688</BIBNO>
<VID>48101</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="license">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>Let this CATALOGUE and LIST of <HI>DAMA∣GES</HI> be Printed.</P>
<CLOSER><DATE><HI>Novemb.</HI> 1. 1664</DATE>
<SIGNED>Roger L'Estrange.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A CATALOGUE OF THE DAMAGES FOR WHICH THE ENGLISH Demand REPARATION from the United-Netherlands. AS ALSO A <HI>LIST</HI> of the <HI>DAMAGES, ACTIONS,</HI> and <HI>PRETENSES</HI> for which Those of the <HI>ƲNITED-NETHER∣LANDS</HI> demand <HI>Reparation</HI> and <HI>Satisfaction</HI> from the <HI>ENGLISH.</HI> TOGETHER WITH The <HI>Answer</HI> of the <HI>ENGLISH,</HI> subjoyn'd to the Several and Respective Points of Their <HI>Demands.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed for <HI>Henry Brome,</HI> at the <HI>Gun</HI> in <HI>Ivy-lane,</HI> 1664.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="preface">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE PREFACE.</HEAD>
<P>THE <HI>Practices</HI> of our <HI>Neighbours</HI> the <HI>States General</HI> of the <HI>Ʋnited Provinces</HI> towards his Majesty of <HI>Great Britain,</HI> and his <HI>Subjects,</HI> have been so <HI>notorious,</HI> both at <HI>home</HI> and <HI>a∣broad,</HI> in <HI>Private</HI> and in <HI>Publique,</HI> in their <HI>Prints, Writings,</HI> and <HI>otherwise,</HI> that the whole world is sufficiently enform'd how great a part they have made it of their business to traduce the <HI>Honour</HI> and <HI>Justice</HI> of his <HI>Most Sa∣cred Majesty,</HI> and to multiply <HI>Injuries</HI> upon his <HI>People.</HI> Which <HI>proceeding</HI> of theirs we cannot but look upon as somwhat <HI>irregular,</HI> considering their deep <HI>obligations</HI> to <HI>This Crown;</HI> together with their long <HI>Experience</HI> of the <HI>English Nation,</HI> which they have found upon several <HI>trials,</HI> and <HI>occasions,</HI> to be either <HI>the most necessary Friend,</HI> or <HI>the most dangerous Enemy</HI> to their <HI>Interest,</HI> and <HI>Government,</HI> up∣on the face of the <HI>Earth.</HI> But whether they have done <HI>well,</HI> or <HI>ill,</HI> we are not to <HI>deter∣mine,</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>having only obtain'd leave, nakedly to publish the <HI>Fact</HI> of the <HI>Case,</HI> submitting the <HI>merits</HI> of it to all <HI>Indifferent Judges.</HI></P>
<P>For the Better understanding of the whole Affair, we are to advertise the <HI>Reader,</HI> that his <HI>Majesty</HI> out of a <HI>Pious</HI> and <HI>Generous disposition</HI> to preserve a <HI>fair Intelligence</HI> with the <HI>States</HI> above-mention'd, (and notwith∣standing divers motives, and provocations to the contrary) hath been graciously pleased, since his happy <HI>Restauration,</HI> to renew an <HI>Al∣liance</HI> with them, and leave the <HI>Adjustment</HI> of, and <HI>Satisfaction</HI> for the <HI>Damages</HI> done to the <HI>English</HI> by those of the said <HI>Provinces,</HI> to a <HI>long,</HI> and <HI>deliberate</HI> way of <HI>decision;</HI> his <HI>Majesty</HI> obliterating many <HI>past misdemeanors,</HI> in order to a better Correspondence for the <HI>future;</HI> and promising to himself undoubtedly a <HI>Return</HI> answerable to so great a <HI>Goodness.</HI> Instead whereof, they have only rendred further <HI>dis-Obligations,</HI> and <HI>Reproaches;</HI> supplying a palpable <HI>defect</HI> of <HI>Right,</HI> and <HI>Reason,</HI> with a proportional <HI>measure</HI> of <HI>Confidence,</HI> and <HI>Cla∣mour.</HI> Witness the <HI>dishonourable Constructi∣ons</HI> they have made of his <HI>Majesties long-for∣bearance;</HI> together with the <HI>Peremptory Judg∣ment</HI> they have past upon the <HI>English De∣mands;</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>and all This, without so much as a thought either of a <HI>Pertinent Reply,</HI> or a <HI>Reaso∣nable Satisfaction.</HI> Which we do the less won∣der at; <HI>First,</HI> in regard that the <HI>Truth,</HI> and <HI>Equity</HI> of our <HI>Pretences</HI> are effectually <HI>Ʋnan∣swerable;</HI> having suffered so strict an <HI>Exami∣nation,</HI> (even by the <HI>Parliament</HI> it self) and after <HI>That</HI> having been made out upon so <HI>clear</HI> and <HI>undeniable Proofs,</HI> that it was impos∣sible to add any thing, either to the <HI>Solemni∣ty</HI> of the <HI>Debate,</HI> or to the <HI>Light</HI> of the <HI>Evi∣dence.</HI> And in the <HI>next</HI> place, as to the point of <HI>Satisfaction;</HI> (not to aggravate mat∣ters) we shall content our selves to say, That measuring things <HI>to come</HI> by things <HI>past,</HI> we did not find much reason to <HI>expect</HI> it; and so we shall leave them to the fate of their own Errors. But in the mean time, for the <HI>dis∣abusing</HI> of the <HI>World,</HI> and for the <HI>manifesta∣tion</HI> of <HI>our own Integrity,</HI> we shall present the <HI>Reader</HI> in this following publication, <HI>first,</HI> with A CATALOGUE <HI>of the</HI> DA∣MAGES <HI>for which the</HI> ENGLISH <HI>de∣mand</HI> REPARATION, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> And af∣ter <HI>That,</HI> with our <HI>Neighbours Recrimination</HI> upon <HI>Ʋs,</HI> under the <HI>Form</HI> and <HI>Title</HI> of A LIST <HI>of the</HI> DAMAGES, ACTIONS,
<PB REF="4"/><HI>and</HI> PRETENCES <HI>whereof the</HI> EAST-INDIA-COMPANY <HI>of the</HI> LOW-COUNTRIES <HI>do promise Themselves to have</HI> REPARATION <HI>and</HI> SATIS∣FACTION: With the <HI>Answer</HI> of the <HI>English,</HI> subjoyn'd to the several and respe∣ctive Points of their <HI>Demands,</HI> remitting it upon the <HI>whole,</HI> to <HI>God, Angels,</HI> and <HI>Men,</HI> to <HI>Judge betwixt</HI> Us.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>A CATALOGUE OF THE DAMAGES For which the <HI>English</HI> demand <HI>Repa∣ration.</HI> And, </HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>First;</HI> Of the <HI>Damages</HI> which the <HI>English East-India-Company</HI> has sustein'd by the <HI>East-Indian-Company</HI> of the <HI>Ʋnited Pro∣vinces.</HI></HEAD>
<P>COncerning the <HI>Ship</HI> call'd the <HI>May-flower,</HI> <MILESTONE N="1"/> whereof one <HI>William Curtis</HI> was the <HI>Commander:</HI> Who (being <HI>Agent</HI> also for the <HI>English-Company</HI>) having obtein'd liberty from the Queen of <HI>Acheene</HI> to traffique there, was about the <HI>Month</HI> of <HI>Aug:</HI> 1658, <HI>old style,</HI> debarr'd of all Commerce, by one <HI>Baltha∣zar,</HI> who at that time commanded 3 <HI>Ships</HI> belong∣ing to the <HI>East-Indian-Company</HI> of the <HI>Netherlands;</HI> and seiz'd <HI>Three Thousand Eight Hundred Seventy and Eight pounds</HI> of <HI>Pepper</HI> which the said Ship had be∣gun to lade with, forcing the said <HI>Curtis</HI> to depart
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>Empty; and nothing of this was known at <HI>London</HI> upon the <HI>Tenth</HI> of <HI>January following,</HI> 165 8/9.</P>
<P>Touching the <HI>Ship</HI> the <HI>Dragon,</HI> <MILESTONE N="2"/> (one <HI>Nicholas Bu∣diford, Commander</HI>) which came before <HI>Bantam</HI> a∣bout the <HI>Month</HI> of <HI>October,</HI> 1658, <HI>old style:</HI> which was forbidden, and hinder'd to <HI>Traffique</HI> there, by certain <HI>Netherland Ships</HI> then upon the Place, and by the <HI>General</HI> of <HI>Batavia,</HI> by whom the said Ship was constrain'd to depart without her lading, and also necessitated to stay in the <HI>Indies</HI> till her <HI>Provi∣sion</HI> was spent, and forced at last to return in the <HI>Winter,</HI> and so she was lost. Of This likewise, no∣thing was known at <HI>London</HI> upon the <HI>Tenth</HI> of <HI>Janu∣ary following,</HI> 165 8/9.</P>
<P>Touching the <HI>Ship</HI> the <HI>Advice;</HI> <MILESTONE N="3"/> <HI>(Robert Mayne, Commander)</HI> which being arrived at <HI>Bantam</HI> about the <HI>Month</HI> of <HI>October</HI> 1658, <HI>Old Style,</HI> was in like manner as the <HI>Dragon</HI> forbidden all Commerce there, and forc'd to depart. And neither was this known at <HI>London</HI> upon the <HI>Tenth</HI> of <HI>January follow∣ing,</HI> 165 8/9.</P>
<P>Concerning the <HI>Ship Marigold;</HI> <MILESTONE N="4"/> <HI>(John Connis, Commander)</HI> which arriving at <HI>Bantam</HI> about the <HI>Month</HI> of <HI>February</HI> 1658, <HI>Old Style;</HI> one <HI>Keyser,</HI> who commanded at that time 5 <HI>Ships</HI> before the Place, shot at the said Ship, and hinder'd her either to Enter, or Traffique there, so that she was necessi∣tated to go her way.</P>
<P>Touching the <HI>Factory</HI> of <HI>Jambee</HI> in the <HI>Isle</HI> of <HI>Summatra,</HI> <MILESTONE N="5"/> upon the 9<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>August</HI> 1659, <HI>Old Style:</HI>
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>When <HI>Peter de Goyer, Principal</HI> of the <HI>Dutch Com∣pany</HI> at <HI>Jambee,</HI> and <HI>Jonathan Clas</HI> his <HI>Second,</HI> with about 40 <HI>Dutch</HI>-Men, and 150 <HI>Slaves,</HI> all arm'd, and in form of an <HI>Enemy,</HI> enter'd by force into the <HI>Magazin</HI> of the <HI>English,</HI> in which outrage the Eng∣lish were very much damnified.</P>
<P>The <HI>Ship</HI> called the <HI>Merchants Delight,</HI> <MILESTONE N="6"/> <HI>(Thomas Bell, Commander)</HI> arriving at <HI>Bantam</HI> in 1659. <HI>Old Style,</HI> was hindred from either Entring or Trading there, by certain Ships of the <HI>Dutch Company,</HI> who were there at that time; and so she was enforced to depart thence.</P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="7"/> the <HI>Merchant of Constantinople, (Robert Brown, Commander)</HI> in the <HI>Month</HI> of <HI>Sept:</HI> 1659. <HI>Old Style,</HI> sailing betwixt <HI>Vingola</HI> and <HI>Goa,</HI> upon the Coast of <HI>India,</HI> was attacqued by 7 <HI>Ships</HI> in the Service of the <HI>Dutch-East-India-Company,</HI> whereof <HI>Peter</HI> of <HI>Beeter</HI> was <HI>Vice-Admiral,</HI> who took by force out of the said Ships, <HI>One Thousand Nine Hundred Seventy and Eight Granades, Fifty Nine Iron Guns,</HI> and <HI>Three Brass Morter-pieces.</HI></P>
<P>For Monyes disburs'd about 166 1/2. <MILESTONE N="8"/> to make a Provision of <HI>Ships, Victuals,</HI> and all other <HI>Necessaries</HI> for the <HI>possessing, planting,</HI> and <HI>fortifying</HI> of the <HI>Isle</HI> of <HI>Pouleron.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
<HEAD>Damages <HI>susteined by the</HI> Dutch-West-Indian Company.</HEAD>
<P>THe <HI>House</HI> and <HI>English Factory</HI> of <HI>Cape-Corse,</HI> <MILESTONE N="1"/> was upon the first of <HI>May</HI> 1659. <HI>Old Style,</HI> burnt, and ruin'd, together with all the <HI>Merchandize</HI> and <HI>Moveables</HI> therein, by the <HI>Dutch,</HI> who were then in the <HI>Castle</HI> of <HI>Cape-Corse,</HI> and in the Service of the <HI>Dutch-West-Indian-Company.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>House</HI> and <HI>Factory</HI> of <HI>Cape-Corse,</HI> <MILESTONE N="2"/> after that the same was re-built, and well furnished with several sorts of Merchandizes, for the Trade of that place, was burnt again upon the 22<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>May,</HI> 1661. <HI>Old Style,</HI> with all the Merchandizes, and Moveables in the same, by some whom those of the <HI>Nether∣land-East-Indie Company</HI> had <HI>hyr'd</HI> for that purpose.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Damages <HI>susteined by the</HI> English Turkey-Company.</HEAD>
<P>THe <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="1"/> <HI>Reformation,</HI> belonging to the Com∣pany of <HI>London,</HI> laden at <HI>Scanderon</HI> in <HI>No∣vember</HI> 1659. as she was quietly sailing in the <HI>Me∣diterranean,</HI> was there seized, upon the 15<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>May</HI> 1660. by a certain Ship which came from <HI>Holland,</HI> call'd the <HI>Holy Mary,</HI> whereof <HI>Lawrence Andreas</HI> was <HI>Commander.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="2"/> <HI>Free-Trade,</HI> design'd from <HI>London</HI> to <HI>Scanderon,</HI> by some Merchants belonging to the said
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>Company, in the year 1659. was seiz'd upon the 15<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>May,</HI> 1660, by the said <HI>Holy Mary.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>Damages</HI> susteined by other <HI>English.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THe <HI>Ship,</HI> the <HI>Experience</HI> of <HI>London,</HI> <MILESTONE N="1"/> <HI>(John Kingsman, Commander)</HI> was seiz'd upon the Coast of <HI>Portugal,</HI> by one <HI>Quaerts,</HI> and others of <HI>Zealand,</HI> in the year 1660.</P>
<P>Concerning a <HI>French Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="2"/> call'd <HI>the Golden Sun, (Nicolas de Breton du Pre, Commander) Edward Adams</HI> Merchant of <HI>London,</HI> as well for himself as for other <HI>English</HI> Merchants, demands to have satisfaction for the Merchandizes belonging to them, which were taken in the said Ship, in the year 1660. upon the Coast of <HI>Portugal</HI> by <HI>four Zealand Men of War,</HI> commanded by <HI>Philip Ros, Tousain le Sage, Albert Johnson,</HI> and the <HI>Masters Mate</HI> of the Ship of <HI>Matthias Quaerts.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="3"/> <HI>Falcon, (Hendrick Hughes, Comman∣der)</HI> was seiz'd upon the Coast of <HI>Portugal,</HI> upon the 31<SUP>th</SUP> day of <HI>May,</HI> 1660, by one <HI>Claus Rous,</HI> and another of <HI>Zealand.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> Saint <HI>John Baptist,</HI> <MILESTONE N="4"/> <HI>(Emanuel Hart, Com∣mander,</HI> who had taken aboard some <HI>Negros</HI> upon the Coast of <HI>Guinne,</HI> and <HI>barter'd</HI> them for <HI>Sugars</HI> and <HI>other Commodities</HI> at <HI>Baghia</HI> in <HI>Brazil</HI>) was seiz'd in his Return in <HI>June,</HI> 1661, by a <HI>Zealand Man of War,</HI> call'd <HI>the Golden Port of Middleburgh,</HI>
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>whereof <HI>Cornelius Thrumcap</HI> was <HI>Commander.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="5"/> the <HI>Merchants Delight,</HI> belonging to one <HI>John Young,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants, (John Bonner, Commander)</HI> having set sail from <HI>Dover</HI> in the County of <HI>Kent,</HI> was seized upon near to <HI>Cape Corso</HI> in <HI>Guiney,</HI> about <HI>August,</HI> 1661, by a Ship call'd the <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> belonging to the <HI>Nether∣land West-Indie Company.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="6"/> <HI>Paragon,</HI> belonging to <HI>Bernard Sparke, John Cooke,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants,</HI> (whereof one <HI>John Bariford</HI> was <HI>Master</HI>) laden at <HI>Topsam.</HI> near to <HI>Exeter</HI> in <HI>Devon,</HI> and bound for <HI>Guiney,</HI> was seiz'd about the 15<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>October,</HI> 1661, by <HI>two Ships</HI> belonging to the <HI>Netherland West-Indie-Company;</HI> the one, call'd the <HI>Amsterdammer</HI> of <HI>Am∣sterdam,</HI> (whereof <HI>Aaron Couzens</HI> was <HI>Master</HI>) and the <HI>other,</HI> call'd the <HI>Arms of Amsterdam,</HI> (whereof <HI>Nicholas Yole</HI> was <HI>Commander.</HI>)</P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="7"/> the <HI>Daniel,</HI> (belonging to <HI>John Knight, Thomas Knight, Henry Oakes,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants,</HI> and commanded by the said <HI>Henry Oakes</HI>) set sail from <HI>London</HI> about <HI>May,</HI> 1661, to go for the Coast of <HI>Guiney,</HI> and was seiz'd in a hostile manner by a Ship of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> belonging to the <HI>Netherland West-Indie Company,</HI> call'd the <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> whereof one <HI>Aaron Couzens</HI> was <HI>Commander.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="8"/> the <HI>Brotherhood</HI> of <HI>London,</HI> (belonging to <HI>Peter Caulier, Bartholomew Caulier, Abraham Cau∣lier,</HI> and <HI>John Beverley,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Mer∣chants</HI>) was seized upon the Coast of <HI>Guiney,</HI> in
<PB N="7" REF="7"/><HI>February,</HI> 1655, <HI>Old Style,</HI> by one <HI>Cox, Commander</HI> of the <HI>Fregat,</HI> call'd <HI>Gat;</HI> and one <HI>Yapoone, Com∣mander</HI> of a Ship call'd the <HI>Kater,</HI> both of them com∣missioned by the <HI>Netherland West-Indie Company.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> call'd the <HI>Rappa Hanoeck,</HI> <MILESTONE N="9"/> (belonging to one <HI>John Jeffryes,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Mer∣chants</HI>) laden at <HI>London,</HI> and design'd for the Coast of <HI>Guiney,</HI> was seiz'd near to <HI>Cape Lopes,</HI> about the 11<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>September,</HI> 1656, by two <HI>Netherland Ships;</HI> the <HI>one</HI> call'd the <HI>Mary</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> and the <HI>other</HI> the <HI>Ʋnicorn</HI> of <HI>Middleburgh,</HI> commanded by one <HI>John Serael</HI> of <HI>Munekedam.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship, Sarah,</HI> belonging to one <HI>Ann Leuellin,</HI> <MILESTONE N="10"/> <HI>Administratrix</HI> of one <HI>Robert Leuellin,</HI> (Merchant) <HI>Humphry Beane,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants,</HI> (whereof <HI>Arthur Perkins</HI> was <HI>Commander</HI>) was sei∣zed upon the Coast of <HI>Guiney,</HI> in <HI>August</HI> 1656, near to <HI>Cape Lopes</HI> by <HI>two Ships</HI> of those Countries; the one call'd the <HI>Mary</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> and the <HI>other,</HI> the <HI>Ʋnicorn</HI> of <HI>Middleburgh,</HI> commanded by the afore∣said <HI>Serael</HI> of <HI>Munekedam.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="11"/> <HI>Fortune</HI> (belonging to one <HI>Constant Silvester,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants</HI>) was seiz'd about <HI>August,</HI> 1656; near to <HI>Cape Lopes,</HI> upon the Coast of <HI>Guiney,</HI> by the said <HI>Mary</HI> of <HI>Amster∣dam,</HI> and the <HI>Ʋnicorn</HI> of <HI>Middleburgh,</HI> whereof the said <HI>John Serael</HI> of <HI>Munekedam</HI> was <HI>Commander.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship, Blackboy</HI> of <HI>Dover;</HI> <MILESTONE N="12"/> (belonging to one <HI>Arnold Breames,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants,</HI> whereof <HI>Ralph Wood</HI> was <HI>Commander</HI>) laden at <HI>Do∣ver</HI>
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>in <HI>January</HI> 1660, was seiz'd about the <HI>Thirteenth</HI> of <HI>April</HI> 1661, near to <HI>Comenda,</HI> upon the Coast of <HI>Guiney,</HI> by a Ship of those Countries, call'd <HI>The Grafenna;</HI> which came from the <HI>Castle</HI> of <HI>Mina,</HI> and carried thither the said <HI>English</HI> Ship.</P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="13"/> <HI>Speedwell</HI> (belonging to M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>John Taylor,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants</HI> of <HI>London,</HI> where∣of <HI>Robert Cooke</HI> was <HI>Master</HI>) pursuing her Voyage from <HI>Gottenburgh</HI> for <HI>London,</HI> was seiz'd in <HI>May</HI> 1657, by a <HI>Man of War</HI> of <HI>Ostend,</HI> Commanded by <HI>Peter Tysen,</HI> who carried the said <HI>Ship</HI> to <HI>Amsterdam;</HI> and there sold her, together with her entire lading, to one <HI>William Hunton, Merchant</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam:</HI> without any <HI>legal proceeding</HI> or <HI>sentence</HI> against her.</P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="14"/> <HI>Lubeck</HI> (whereof <HI>Ditmar Pieterson</HI> was <HI>Master</HI>) being laden in <HI>May,</HI> by <HI>Thomas Nisbet,</HI> and <HI>Richard Metcalfe</HI> of the City of <HI>York,</HI> with 1858 <HI>Tun</HI> of <HI>Rye,</HI> at <HI>Strale-Sond</HI> in <HI>Pomerland,</HI> to be trans∣ported for <HI>Hull</HI> in <HI>England,</HI> was seiz'd upon by five <HI>Netherland men of War,</HI> viz. <HI>One</HI> commanded by <HI>Edward Anchuysen, another</HI> by <HI>Laurence Deden∣camp</HI> of <HI>Groningen,</HI> a <HI>Third</HI> by one Captain <HI>Sunck, another</HI> call'd the <HI>black Eagle,</HI> and the <HI>Fifth</HI> the <HI>golden Lyon,</HI> which carried the said Ship to <HI>Copenha∣gen,</HI> and there disposed of her lading.</P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="15"/> <HI>Anne</HI> and <HI>Margaret,</HI> (belonging to <HI>Ri∣chard Wescombe, Nicholas Warren,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>Merchants</HI> of <HI>London</HI>) having taken in her Lading at <HI>Tunis,</HI> with some Merchandise, in the year 1658, for the service of the said Proprietors, was seized in her Voyage to <HI>Legorn,</HI> by a Ship of those Coun∣tries
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>call'd the <HI>Geldre,</HI> whereof <HI>John Jacobson Zens</HI> was <HI>Master.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="16"/> <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> John (Cornelius Van Ringen, Master)</HI> belonging to one <HI>Vincent de la Barre,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants,</HI> being bought by their order at <HI>Middleburgh,</HI> in <HI>April</HI> 1658, and there laden, on design to go for <HI>Calbarine</HI> to trade for <HI>Negroes,</HI> was taken near to the Port of <HI>Calbarine</HI> by a Ship be∣longing to the <HI>Netherland-West-Indie Company,</HI> and confiscated at <HI>Calbarine</HI> aforesaid; notwithstanding that the said <HI>Company</HI> had given permission to the said <HI>Vessel</HI> to the end aforesaid.</P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> the <HI>Assada Merchant,</HI> <MILESTONE N="17"/> being employed by Mr. <HI>Nicholas Buckeridge</HI> to go to <HI>Bantam</HI> to take in such Goods as the said <HI>Buckeridge</HI> had prepared there, in <HI>July</HI> 1657, was hindered by a Ship of the <HI>Netherland-East-Indie Company,</HI> which was sent ex∣presly from <HI>Batavia:</HI> And this was not known at <HI>London</HI> the 10/20 of <HI>January</HI> 165 8/9, as will be made to appear.</P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="18"/> <HI>Anne Piercy</HI> (belonging to <HI>Daniel Fair∣fax, John Dethick,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Mer∣chants</HI>) as she pursued her Voyage from <HI>England</HI> in <HI>March</HI> 1656, to go to <HI>Pantelorea,</HI> between <HI>Legorn,</HI> and <HI>Smyrna,</HI> and being design'd for <HI>Smyrna,</HI> was assaulted by a Ship of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> call'd the <HI>Anto∣nio,</HI> whereof one <HI>Ree Morice</HI> (a <HI>Hollander</HI>) was <HI>Com∣mander;</HI> who burnt, and sunk her with all her La∣ding.</P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> the <HI>Aethiopian,</HI> belonging to <HI>John Allen,</HI> <MILESTONE N="19"/>
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>and <HI>Matthew Babb, English Merchants,</HI> (whereof <HI>Pe∣ter Blake</HI> was <HI>Commander</HI>) being sent to <HI>Bobuee</HI> up∣on the Coast of <HI>Guiney,</HI> with design to trade for <HI>Negroes,</HI> was seiz'd in a hostile manner, in the <HI>month</HI> of <HI>January</HI> 1661, by a Ship belonging to the <HI>West-Indie Company</HI> of the <HI>Ʋnited Netherlands,</HI> call'd the <HI>Post-horse,</HI> which carried her to the <HI>Castle</HI> of <HI>Mina.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="20"/> the <HI>Lyon Providence</HI> of <HI>London,</HI> (be∣longing to <HI>Sir William Thompson,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants,</HI> who laded the said Ship at <HI>Lon∣don,</HI> for <HI>Guiney</HI>) was seiz'd on in <HI>August</HI> 1656, near to <HI>Cape Lopez</HI> in <HI>Guiney,</HI> by two Ships belonging to the <HI>Netherland-West-Indie Company;</HI> the <HI>one</HI> call'd the <HI>Mary</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam;</HI> and the <HI>other,</HI> the <HI>Ʋnicorn</HI> of <HI>Middleburgh,</HI> whereof <HI>John Serael</HI> of <HI>Munekedam</HI> was <HI>Commander.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="21"/> call'd the <HI>Brazil-Fregat</HI> of <HI>London,</HI> (be∣longing to <HI>John Bushell, Edward Bushell,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants</HI>) was seiz'd between <HI>Angola</HI> and <HI>Fernambuck,</HI> in the year 1657, by a Ship of <HI>Flushing,</HI> call'd The <HI>Sluce,</HI> whereof one <HI>Quaerts</HI> was <HI>Commander.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="22"/> <HI>Charles,</HI> (whereof <HI>Captain Sprag</HI> was <HI>Commander</HI>) was seized in the <HI>Road</HI> of <HI>St. Martins</HI> in <HI>France,</HI> in <HI>July</HI> 1660, by <HI>Three men of War</HI> in the service of the <HI>States General,</HI> and commanded by Captain <HI>Enno Dondestarre.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="23"/> <HI>Content of London</HI> (whereof <HI>William Jordan</HI> was <HI>Commander</HI>) as she set sail from the <HI>Downes,</HI> in <HI>October</HI> 1661, on design to trade upon
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>the Coast of <HI>Guiney,</HI> was seized there by a Ship be∣longing to the <HI>Netherland-West-Indie Company,</HI> call'd the <HI>Holy Barbara,</HI> which carried the said <HI>English Ship</HI> to a certain <HI>Island</HI> call'd the <HI>Isle</HI> of <HI>Gene.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship, True love,</HI> <MILESTONE N="24"/> belonging to Sir <HI>Draper,</HI> and other <HI>English Merchants (Edmund Ni∣cholas Commander)</HI> for certain Goods taken out of her belonging to <HI>English,</HI> and for the freight of such Merchandizes as were taken out belonging to <HI>Portu∣ghueses,</HI> near to <HI>St. Michell,</HI> (one of the <HI>Western Islands</HI>) by <HI>Abraham Dominicus, Commander</HI> of the Ship, <HI>The Dauphine</HI> of <HI>Flushing,</HI> in 1659. As like∣wise for Merchandizes taken out of the same in her Voyage between <HI>Lisbon</HI> and <HI>New-England,</HI> in the year 1660, by the Ships, the <HI>St. John Baptist,</HI> whereof <HI>John Lopez</HI> was <HI>Commander,</HI> the <HI>Catharine,</HI> Captain <HI>Oncruise, Commander,</HI> and the <HI>golden Burgh,</HI> Captain <HI>Thrumcap, Commander.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship, Charles,</HI> belonging to M<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>James Burkin,</HI> <MILESTONE N="25"/> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants,</HI> (whereof one <HI>John Blackler</HI> was <HI>Commander</HI>) being laden for their Particular, upon the Coast of <HI>Guiney,</HI> was seiz'd upon the said Coast, in <HI>August</HI> 1661, by a Ship belong∣ing to the <HI>Netherland West-Indie Company,</HI> call'd the <HI>Amsterdammer</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> (one <HI>Aaron Couzens, Commander</HI>) and carried by him to <HI>Castle Mina.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="26"/> <HI>Packet Fregat</HI>) whereof <HI>Edward Harri∣son</HI> was <HI>Master,</HI> (belonging to one <HI>James Drawater,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants</HI>) being laden at <HI>Genoa,</HI> and <HI>Final,</HI> and design'd for <HI>London,</HI> was seiz'd in her Voyage at the <HI>Streights Mouth,</HI> by a
<PB N="12" REF="10"/><HI>Netherland Ship,</HI> call'd the <HI>Golden Duyk,</HI> command∣ed by Captain <HI>Albert Cock,</HI> about the 13<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>May,</HI> 1654, <HI>Old Style,</HI> and carried to <HI>Cadiz</HI> in <HI>Spain,</HI> where the said <HI>English</HI> Ship, with part of her lading was re∣stored: And <HI>Satisfaction</HI> is now demanded for the rest, and for the <HI>Cordage</HI> of the said Ship.</P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="27"/> the <HI>Constant Mary,</HI> belonging to <HI>Fran∣cis Bellars, Thomas Fowke, Richard Glover,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants,</HI> (whereof one <HI>Daniel Lester</HI> was <HI>Master</HI>) being laden at <HI>London,</HI> and de∣sign'd for <HI>Guiney,</HI> was seized upon the 8<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>May,</HI> 1654, <HI>Old Style,</HI> about 20 <HI>Leagues</HI> from the <HI>Cape Saint Vincent,</HI> by a <HI>Netherland man of War,</HI> call'd the <HI>Holy Cicilie,</HI> whereof one <HI>Hanse Alburge</HI> was <HI>Commander,</HI> being, as he confessed, in the Service of the <HI>States</HI> of the <HI>Ʋnited Netherlands.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="28"/> <HI>Nostra Seigniora di Remedia,</HI> having taken Merchandizes abord in the Port of <HI>Macassar,</HI> upon the <HI>Island</HI> of <HI>Celebes,</HI> in the <HI>Great Indies,</HI> in the year 1660, <HI>Old Style,</HI> was seized the 29<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>May,</HI> of the same year, by <HI>two Ships of War</HI> in the Service of the <HI>Netherland East-Indie Company,</HI> which carried the said Ship to <HI>Batavia.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="29"/> the <HI>Leopard,</HI> (belonging to <HI>Nicholas Bau∣chart</HI> of <HI>London,</HI> and <HI>Company</HI> of <HI>English Merchants</HI>) was seized near to <HI>Capo Blanco,</HI> in <HI>October</HI> 1656, by the <HI>Challoup</HI> of a <HI>Holland man of War,</HI> (both be∣longing to the <HI>Netherland West-Indie Company</HI>) and carried to the <HI>Castle</HI> of <HI>Arangeny,</HI> at <HI>Capo Blanco.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> <MILESTONE N="30"/> the <HI>Golden Sun</HI> of <HI>Lubeck,</HI> having a∣bord
<PB N="13" REF="10"/>her 110 <HI>Last</HI> of <HI>Rye,</HI> and being <HI>freighted</HI> at <HI>Revel,</HI> (upon the <HI>Baltick Sea</HI>) by one <HI>Thomas Beau∣try, Merchant</HI> of <HI>London,</HI> and for his accompt, in the year 1659, was seiz'd by some <HI>Netherland men of War,</HI> belonging to the <HI>States General,</HI> and com∣manded by <HI>Admiral Opdam,</HI> who sent the said Ship to the <HI>Admiralty</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> call'd the <HI>Dove</HI> of <HI>London,</HI> <MILESTONE N="31"/> belong∣ing to one <HI>Jacob Granger, John Warner,</HI> and <HI>Compa∣ny</HI> of <HI>English Merchants, (John Johnson, Master)</HI> was seiz'd near to <HI>Shetland,</HI> on the <HI>North-side</HI> of <HI>Scot∣land,</HI> by a <HI>Netherland man of War,</HI> and sent to <HI>En∣chuysen.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Ship,</HI> call'd the <HI>Rebecca</HI> of <HI>Ipswich,</HI> <MILESTONE N="32"/> <HI>(George Buckenham, Master)</HI> was seiz'd by a <HI>man of War</HI> of <HI>Ostend,</HI> (commanded by one <HI>Derwelly</HI>) and carried into <HI>Zealand,</HI> and there they unladed a part of her Goods, before any Tryal in the <HI>Admiralty;</HI> and not∣withstanding all the Addresses and Applications which were made to the <HI>Admiralty</HI> of <HI>Zealand,</HI> the said Ship of War was suffer'd to return to Sea and escape.</P>
<P>Seized by <HI>Admiral Opdam,</HI> <MILESTONE N="33"/> and other Vessels un∣der his Command, upon the Coast of <HI>Portugal,</HI> in the year <GAP DESC="blank" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP=" _____ "/> abord the Fleet, or <HI>Portuguese Ships,</HI> a quantity of <HI>Sugars,</HI> and other Merchandizes belonging to the <HI>English,</HI> and carried away to <HI>Am∣sterdam, and other parts of the Ʋnited Provinces.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
<HEAD>A <HI>LIST</HI> of the <HI>Damages, Actions,</HI> and <HI>Pre∣tenses,</HI> whereof the <HI>East-India-Company</HI> of the <HI>Low-Countries</HI> do promise themselves to have <HI>Reparation,</HI> and <HI>Satisfaction</HI> from the <HI>English.</HI></HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>The <HI>Damages</HI> which the <HI>Company</HI> hath <HI>really</HI> suffer'd, or that have been <HI>caused</HI> to them, by the <HI>English.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THE <HI>Counsellors</HI> deputed in the <HI>Colledge</HI> of the <HI>Admiralty</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Dutch</HI> Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 1.</NOTE> do represent, that Captain <HI>Abraham Vanderhulst,</HI> having in the year 1657 taken a <HI>Portuguez</HI> Ship la∣den with <HI>Sugars,</HI> was forc'd by storm to Har∣bor at <HI>Portsmouth,</HI> and though the <HI>English</HI> could not pretend any right, nor cognizance, in justice to the Prize, and much less ought they to seize her <HI>de facto,</HI> without any form or colour of <HI>Process;</HI> Nevertheless the <HI>English Commissioners</HI> of <HI>Prize-goods</HI> taken by their men of War, passing over all considerations of good Neighbour∣hood and Hospitality, took away the said Prize from the said Captain, and delivered her to the <HI>Portugal Embassadour</HI> then at <HI>London,</HI> who disposed of her: and the <HI>deputed Coun∣sellors</HI> do pretend that they ought to be re-imbursed of the va∣lue of the said <HI>Prize, cum omni causâ &amp; accessione.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
<HEAD><HI>The</HI> East-India-Company <HI>of</HI> England, <HI>having seen the List of</HI> Damages, Actions, <HI>and</HI> Pre∣tenses, <HI>exhibited against them by the</HI> Ne∣therlands East-India-Company, <HI>do find it to be,</HI> A deliberate Mass of FRIVOLOUS, INSOLENT, <HI>and</HI> UNJUST Demands, built upon Conclusions made without the leave of any Premises of TRUTH, REASON, <HI>or</HI> LAW OF NATIONS; <HI>as we hope all im∣partial, and rational men will judge, not on∣ly from the</HI> Articles themselves, <HI>but when they shall see this subsequent</HI> Answer.</HEAD>
<P>TO the <HI>first Article,</HI> we answer,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">English <HI>Answer.</HI> 1.</NOTE> That no Com∣plaint is entred in the <HI>Admiralty Court;</HI> if there had, the question would have born a hard dispute in <HI>Law;</HI> Whether a Ship being taken as <HI>Prize,</HI> shall be brought into the Harbor of a Prince in <HI>Amity,</HI> with both the <HI>Taker,</HI> and the <HI>Taken,</HI> or to which of them the said Ship shall be delivered?</P>
<P>He that did reside at <HI>Jambee</HI> for the Company of these Countries, having bought there in the Month of <HI>May,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 2.</NOTE> 1660. a quantity of 700 <HI>Picols,</HI> or 85000 <HI>l.</HI> of <HI>Pepper,</HI> at four <HI>Royals and a half</HI> the <HI>Picol,</HI> the <HI>English</HI> did take it <HI>violently,</HI> and seized on it by <HI>force.</HI></P>
<P>To the <HI>second</HI> we say,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer.</HI> 2.</NOTE> That we know not of any such <HI>Violence</HI> offered to the <HI>Hollanders,</HI> as the taking of any <HI>pepper</HI> from them: They name not the <HI>per∣sons</HI> by whom it was that the pretended force was
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>done; nor have we received any <HI>pepper</HI> from <HI>Jambee,</HI> or any other part of <HI>India,</HI> but what our <HI>Factors</HI> have paid for, and placed the money to our Accompt: Nor have we ever had any the least hint of the matter of fact complained of in this <HI>Article;</HI> But we have very good proofs of such things attempted against <HI>Ʋs</HI> in <HI>That Port,</HI> and elsewhere, by the <HI>Hollanders;</HI> and had not the greater Justice of the Magistrates of the place relieved us, we had had much more rea∣son to complain of our Losses in that kind then we can have to hope that if they had been done, the <HI>Hollanders Company</HI> would have made us <HI>repa∣rations</HI> for it.</P>
<P>An <HI>English-man,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 3.</NOTE> called Mr. <HI>Paul,</HI> dwelling at <HI>Ganara</HI> (a place not a League distant from <HI>Bilipatman,</HI> on the <HI>North-side</HI>) took by force, and carried away, a very great quantity of <HI>Rice,</HI> amounting to many <HI>hundred Lasts,</HI> which the <HI>Company</HI> of these Countries or their <HI>Agents</HI> had contracted for, and bought; (and this, notwithstanding all the protestations of Mr. <HI>Kestlerus,</HI> (who did then reside there for the said <HI>Company</HI>) against such violence) which, was the cause that the Ship freighted by the <HI>Company,</HI> and design'd to go fetch the said quantity of <HI>Rice,</HI> were not only retarded; but also that the <HI>Gathering</HI> in the mean time being past, not any of the said Ships could accomplish their Voyage; which caused a very considera∣ble damage, and prejudice to the said <HI>Company.</HI></P>
<P>To the <HI>Third Article,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer.</HI> 3.</NOTE> we say, <HI>we know no such man as Mr. Paul,</HI> nor ever heard any thing of <HI>Rice,</HI> bought for our Accompts at <HI>Canara,</HI> nor any wrong or injuries done them by our people there, and there being no time mention'd when it was done, the <HI>Ar∣ticle</HI> answers it self.</P>
<PB N="17" REF="12"/>
<P>It is only by the Treaty,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 4.</NOTE> made betwixt the King of <HI>Great Britain,</HI> and <HI>This Estate,</HI> the 4/14 <HI>Sept.</HI> 1662. and not <HI>before,</HI> That it was agreed and Convened (amongst other things) that <HI>Pouleron</HI> should be restored to the said King, or else to such as should by his Majesty be fully Authorized in <HI>Writing</HI> under the <HI>Great Seal</HI> of <HI>England:</HI> And to that purpose the necessary Or∣ders should be put into his Majesties hands presently after the <HI>Ratification</HI> of the said <HI>Treaty,</HI> his Majesty having also demand∣ed the said Orders from their <HI>Lordships,</HI> by his Letters of the 18 of <HI>December</HI> of the same year, which were then accordingly expedited: And nevertheless, those of the <HI>East-India Company</HI> of <HI>England</HI> made no difficulty to send their Ships and Men into the <HI>Indies</HI> about <HI>two moueths</HI> before, to take possession thereof; who also accordingly did address themselves to the <HI>General,</HI> and <HI>Council</HI> of <HI>Batavia;</HI> and summon'd them to give them the necessary orders for the rendring to them the said Island. And though the said <HI>General</HI> and <HI>Council</HI> had no Authority to do it, because that difference had not as yet been ended in <HI>Europe;</HI> they were nevertheless so bold to go thither without any order or command from <HI>Batavia:</HI> so that the said <HI>General,</HI> and <HI>Coun∣cil</HI> foreseeing the disorders that might thereupon ensue, even to the shedding of Blood; particularly since they could not know with what intent the <HI>English</HI> went that way, were necessitated for fear of ill consequence, as also for the conservation of the Forts, Places, and Goods of the <HI>Company,</HI> to send thither with all speed a recruit of Ships and Men, by which the <HI>English</HI> were kept back, and hindred from undertaking any thing by violence, whereof they would have made use, but for that stop.</P>
<P>Therefore the <HI>Company</HI> doth demand <HI>re-imbursement</HI> of the Charges laid out and imployed to that purpose, comprehending therein the freight of the Ships, as also the Souldiers pay, and Mariners wages; and of the Victuals, and withall, a reparati∣on for the Affront made to the whole Nation, and to the pre∣judice of their Reputation.</P>
<P>Secondly, They demand the Charges laid out by the <HI>Compa∣ny,</HI> and the <HI>Damages</HI> by them suffered, whereof they pretend re-imbursement from the <HI>English,</HI> as also of the Damages ha∣ving been caused by them.</P>
<PB N="18" REF="13"/>
<P>To the <HI>fourth</HI> we say,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer.</HI> 4.</NOTE> That for the first Affirmation on which they ground their whole discourse, they cannot but know to the contrary in <HI>Fact;</HI> for they lay down that the Restitution of the <HI>Island Pouleron</HI> was not agreed on, but by the Treaty made between the <HI>King</HI> and the <HI>States</HI> the 4th / 14 of <HI>September</HI> 1662; Whereas they could not but remember, that by the 9<SUP>th</SUP> <HI>Article</HI> of the <HI>Treaty</HI> in 1662, they were ob∣lig'd to do it, <HI>in haec verba:</HI></P>
<P><HI>Those of the</HI> Netherlands <HI>do faithfully promise, that if so be they are in possession of the</HI> Islands, <HI>and</HI> Forts <HI>of</HI> Pouleron, <HI>or if they have been taken directly or indirectly by Them, or by their</HI> Mi∣nisters, <HI>or by any others in their Name, to aban∣don, give over, and forsake them; and to re∣store them unto those of the</HI> English Company, <HI>in the same state and condition they enjoyed them during the time of the</HI> Treaty.</P>
<P>And when notwithstanding this <HI>Covenant</HI> they had deteined it, unto the year 1654; It was then agreed <HI>de Novo,</HI> by the <HI>Commissioners</HI> of <HI>Both Sides,</HI> and ratified by the <HI>States, in haec verba:</HI></P>
<P><HI>Et praeterea Statuimus, ac Ordinamus, ut praedicta</HI> Societas Belgica <HI>cedat ac restituat</HI> Societati An∣glicae <HI>praedictae,</HI> Insulam Pouleron <HI>eo in statu &amp; conditione, in qua nunc est; ita tamen ut licitum sit dictae</HI> Societati Belgicae <HI>tollere &amp; amo∣vere ex insulâ praedictâ</HI> apparatum Bellicum, Merces, Suppellectilem, <HI>&amp;</HI> omnia mobilia, <HI>si quae fortassis in dicta insula habeant.</HI></P>
<P>So that then the word of <HI>Restitution</HI> us'd in both those <HI>Articles,</HI> evinceth our original right to it; and convinceth them of their Injustice in disposses∣sing
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>us, and deteining it so long from us: And neither of those Articles obliges us to any Formalities of the <HI>King's Commission,</HI> or more then a bare <HI>Demand</HI> of it, when we had a mind to receive it. And our Ships that were sent to possess it being departed, as they confess, before the conclusion of the <HI>Treaty</HI> in 1662; and <HI>That Treaty</HI> containing nothing that derogates from the two former Treaties, they cannot but with monstrous confidence accuse us of proceeding irre∣gularly; especially, when it shall be considered that our Ships carried not onely the <HI>King's Commission</HI> under the <HI>Great Seal</HI> to possess and plant it, but even <HI>Orders</HI> also from <HI>their States</HI> and <HI>Company;</HI> Dated the 18<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>October,</HI> 1660. The receipt of which, the <HI>General</HI> and <HI>Councell</HI> of <HI>Batavia</HI> acknowledged by their Letter of the 8<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>November</HI> 1661, and though in the same Letter, they say, that since the Date of those Orders, they had by their last Ship out of <HI>Holland</HI> received Intelligence that <HI>new debates</HI> were arisen between the <HI>two Companies,</HI> and there∣fore we could not with Reason demand surrender of the said <HI>Island,</HI> until they had farther Intelligence from their <HI>Masters</HI> in <HI>Holland;</HI> yet our Commanders had both the <HI>Order</HI> of <HI>their Masters,</HI> and a <HI>just title</HI> to the liberty of sailing into those Seas to Trade, without the <HI>Hollanders</HI> leave or disturbance. Nor was there any colour of <HI>Jealousie</HI> given to the <HI>Dutch</HI> of any hostile design, when the <HI>English Com∣manders</HI> declared their Resolution to follow their Masters Orders, and went onely with two Merchants Ships provided for Trade, and planting the Island (if it had been amicably delivered as it ought to have been) and therefore we think it had been ridi∣culous and imprudent for the Commanders of our
<PB N="20" REF="14"/>Ships to have desisted from the prosecution of their Voyage, and demanding the Island upon the place, as it is in them now to demand of us satisfaction, for the expence of those forces which they say they sent to affront his Majestie, and keep us from our right; while under the Fictitious Pretense of a Jealousie, they designed (according to their usual practise) to give us a forcible and real interuption in our just course and liberty of Trade: for which, we hope in time to receive <HI>satisfaction,</HI> and <HI>security</HI> against the like in future.</P>
<P>After that the <HI>East-India Company</HI> of these Countries had in the year 1655.<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 5. Vide <HI>page</HI> 22. <HI>for the Answer.</HI></NOTE> really paid in <HI>England,</HI> under good and suffici∣ent Acquittance, the Moneys contained in the <HI>Arbitrary sen∣tence</HI> pronounced in the year 1654. by the Commissioners na∣med on both sides, amounting unto the sum of 88615 <HI>l. Sterling,</HI> by which they thought to have fully stopped all pretenses, and therefore might safely order their Ships to take (in their return) the usual <HI>Channel,</HI> and to those that they dispatch'd from hence, to land in <HI>England,</HI> as if they should be thereunto forc'd by storms or contrary winds, there to expect fair weather and a favourable wind: Nevertheless, the <HI>English</HI> did not omit to raise new actions and pretenses against this Company, as soon as they heard in the <HI>Month</HI> of <HI>Sept.</HI> 1657, that there was ar∣rived in the said <HI>Channel</HI> a Ship of the said <HI>Company,</HI> call'd <HI>Henrietta Louisia;</HI> and they obtained presently, by direction of their <HI>Admiralty,</HI> a <HI>Warrant</HI> or <HI>Commission</HI> to make a <HI>Seizure</HI> of the said <HI>Ship,</HI> and of its <HI>Cargo,</HI> to the prejudice and contempt of the <HI>Treaty</HI> so lately made with them; and That, under a <HI>frivolous pretense</HI> of the <HI>English-East-India-Company,</HI> for the sum of 100000 <HI>l. Sterling:</HI> and of the <HI>Commissioners</HI> Established up∣on the disaster of <HI>Will. Courteen</HI> after his <HI>Bankrupt</HI> of the like sum of 100000 <HI>l.</HI> But the said Ship having very happily es∣caped their hands, the <HI>Admiralty</HI> did anew grant (in the <HI>Month</HI> of <HI>November</HI> following) a <HI>second</HI> leave for <HI>seizure,</HI> which was effectually executed upon the <HI>Ship</HI> call'd <HI>Sterling,</HI> which
<PB N="21" REF="14"/>being departed from hence to go to the <HI>East-Indies</HI> was forc'd by storm, to Harbor at <HI>Portsmouth,</HI> so that the <HI>Company</HI> of this Country seeing the irregular and unjust proceedings of the <HI>English,</HI> to prevent such like inconveniences for the future; hath been obliged to order their Ships (instead of passing the <HI>Chan∣nel</HI>) in their return, to go about by <HI>Scotland,</HI> and to take their way <HI>Northward,</HI> as they did formerly, which does not only cause that the Merchandizes arrive, and are sold later every year then before, to the great damage and prejudice of the <HI>Company,</HI> which is thereby obliged to pay <HI>greater Wages;</HI> and their men are expos'd to greater and longer dangers, and suffer greater damages and inconveniencies, but they are also oblig'd, as well for the safety and preservation of their Fleet when it is coming home, as for the refreshing of the men, who coming from that Country hot, do suffer by the cold in making so long turns by the <HI>North,</HI> to fit every year a great number of <HI>Men</HI> of <HI>War,</HI> and <HI>Pinnaces</HI> to send before to meet them by the <HI>North.</HI> The <HI>Charges</HI> disbursed, and that must yet be disbursed to that purpose, and the <HI>Damages</HI> amounting to a most con∣siderable sum, as it shall appear by the Accompt that shall be thereof given.</P>
<P>From the time that the Company of these Countries did un∣derstand that the grant of seizing the said Ship,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 6. Vide <HI>page</HI> 22. <HI>for the Answer.</HI></NOTE> call'd <HI>Henrietta Louisia</HI> was given, because that about That time they did ex∣pect the <HI>two Ships</HI> call'd <HI>Arnhem</HI> and the <HI>Castle of Honigen,</HI> which were to return by the <HI>Channel,</HI> they found themselves obliged by a warrantable apprehension, and necessary care to cause some <HI>Men of War</HI> and <HI>Pinnaces</HI> to be made ready, and to depart with speed, to meet and convoy the others; So that the <HI>re-imbursement</HI> of those charges may justly be demanded from the <HI>English.</HI></P>
<P>Furthermore,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 7.</NOTE> Whereas the <HI>Company</HI> abovesaid apprehended some like seizures in all the Ports of <HI>England,</HI> they have been obliged expresly to forbid the Ships they dispatch from hence to enter there or cast Anchor in the <HI>Road:</HI> which is the cause that many of their Ships finding themselves often surprized by storms, have been forc'd to come back and enter into the Ports of these Countries, to stay for a more favourable wind, to the
<PB N="22" REF="15"/>great prejudice of their Voyage, and exposing themselves to great danger; the damages thereby suffered, and by those de∣lays, amounting to a sum also very considerable.</P>
<P>To the <HI>fifth, sixth,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer.</HI> 5, 6, 7.</NOTE> and <HI>seventh Articles,</HI> we think it sufficient for <HI>Answer,</HI> that if their being conscious to Themselves of the injuries done by <HI>Them</HI> to the Subjects of <HI>This Kingdom,</HI> and yet not honest enough to be willing to make legal satisfaction, does fright them from passing with their Ships through the <HI>Channel,</HI> lest they might fall within the <HI>Virge</HI> of the <HI>Law,</HI> they may Themselves blame their own unreasonable fears; but yet to shew the world how unreasonably they would ground a pretense of satis∣faction from <HI>Ʋs,</HI> for their <HI>own unjust Jealousies;</HI> We desire it may be noted, that all that they complain of, was <HI>an attempt of a Legal Proceeding against the two Ships,</HI> the <HI>Henrietta Louisia,</HI> and <HI>L' Estourneau,</HI> one of which was never Touched with an Arrest, and the other released as soon as it was requested.</P>
<P>During the War that those of <HI>Bantam</HI> have begun against the said <HI>Company,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 8.</NOTE> against all equity and reason; with so much perfidiousness, that even the <HI>English</HI> have been obliged to avouch, and testifie as much by their Letters: the said <HI>Com∣pany</HI> had no other means to oppose themselves to it, and to do them hurt, then by keeping their <HI>Harbour</HI> and <HI>City surrounded,</HI> and <HI>besieged</HI> with a <HI>Fleet</HI> of <HI>Men of War,</HI> and to hinder their <HI>Trade;</HI> and that there should not go in or out the <HI>Merchan∣dizes</HI> and <HI>Provisions</HI> they might have need of, thereby to di∣sturb them; so that they might be constrain'd to submit to reason, or else to weaken them so much, that causing their Forces to draw neer, and assaulting them vigorously on the <HI>Land-side</HI> they might be utterly vanquished thereby, and wholly subjected: The <HI>Experience</HI> and <HI>Event</HI> having also made it known, that they have been so much humbled thereby, that they have been forc'd to come to desire peace, (as with joyned
<PB N="23" REF="15"/>hands) But the <HI>English,</HI> who (by virtue of the <HI>Treaty</HI> made with them by this <HI>State</HI>) were obliged to be helpers to the <HI>Company</HI> of these Countries in this Encounter, so much the more, that it was They that were set upon; and that only by an aversion, and irrreconcileable hatred whereof the <HI>Moors</HI> are prepossessed against all <HI>Christians;</HI> in lieu of helping them, have lost no opportunity to oppose themselves to our designs, and have endeavoured with their <HI>Ships</HI> to procure the <HI>Harbour</HI> free, and to make them lose the Benefit of a <HI>siege</HI> which had cost them so much trouble and charges; and in Consequence, to cause the said <HI>Company</HI> to be consumed by those means, because That hath been the cause, that not only the said <HI>War</HI> and <HI>Siege</HI> have endured far longer then they should otherwise have done (which hath caused great prejudice to the said <HI>Company,</HI> and hath much vexed it) but also that they have been obliged to hinder the <HI>English</HI> to obtain their end, to have the said <HI>Road surrounded</HI> and <HI>besieged</HI> by a greater number of Ships, and those bigger then otherwise they should have needed to em∣ploy: so that besides the other delays, hinderances, and pre∣judice, caused to the said <HI>Company</HI> for that cause, in other oc∣casions they have been obliged to be at a very great charge, and have been very much incommodated with other Ex∣pences.</P>
<P>To the <HI>eighth;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer.</HI> 8.</NOTE> We say it ought not to come in consideration at all; because no time is assigned of the fact, nor any person or Ships named; nor have we knowledge of any thing but our sufferings, du∣ring the time that some of their Ships lay before <HI>Bantam,</HI> unless they will call it a crime that we en∣deavoured amicably to obtain from them the just liberty of Trade which the <HI>Law</HI> of <HI>Nations</HI> allows, and they denyed us: And <HI>we can guess at no other ground of that War, unless it were to force the King of</HI> Bantam <HI>to a</HI> Contract <HI>to</HI> exclude <HI>us.</HI></P>
<PB N="24" REF="16"/>
<P>The <HI>English</HI> know that the abovesaid <HI>Company</HI> have ever treated with the <HI>Queen</HI> of <HI>Acheen,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 9.</NOTE> as well for the <HI>Tynn</HI> which is bought at <HI>Perager,</HI> as principally for the <HI>Pepper</HI> which grows in the <HI>Western Coast</HI> of the <HI>Island</HI> of <HI>Sumatra;</HI> by which <HI>Treaty,</HI> the said <HI>Pepper</HI> is to be all delivered at a certain Rate, whereof there is an agreement made with the said <HI>Company,</HI> to the ex∣clusion of any other <HI>Nations,</HI> as the <HI>Company</HI> is likewise obliged on their side to go fetch all the <HI>Pepper</HI> at the said rate. The <HI>English</HI> have heretofore made such <HI>Contracts,</HI> as well <HI>joyntly</HI> with the said <HI>Company,</HI> as by <HI>themselves</HI> with several of the <HI>Indians:</HI> for it doth appear by the <HI>Agreement</HI> made in the year 1619 be∣twixt the <HI>two East-India Companies</HI> of <HI>England,</HI> and that of the <HI>Low-Countries,</HI> for the <HI>re-establishing</HI> of the Affairs of <HI>Ban∣tam,</HI> by the <HI>Approbation</HI> and <HI>Authority</HI> of the King of <HI>Great Bri∣tain,</HI> and of the <HI>States,</HI> That there had been then such a <HI>Con∣tract</HI> made with the King of <HI>Acheen,</HI> by the which it was also agreed, how, and in what manner both the <HI>Companies</HI> could joyntly make such a <HI>Contract</HI> with the King of <HI>Bantam,</HI> for the <HI>Pepper</HI> which groweth in his Country; and the same to the ex∣press and formal exclusion of all other Nations, as well <HI>Indians,</HI> as <HI>Europeans,</HI> who would trade therewith. The which was ac∣cordingly perform'd, and practised; And although for That rea∣son the <HI>English</HI> were obliged not to trouble the <HI>Company</HI> of the <HI>Low-Countries,</HI> in performance of the <HI>Agreements</HI> made (which do as yet remain in force) they have however always endea∣voured to frustrate the said <HI>Company</HI> of the Benefit of the said <HI>Contract,</HI> by indirect ways, and evil means, in corrupting the Inhabitants of that Country, in obliging them to sell them the <HI>Tynn,</HI> and the <HI>Pepper,</HI> by the greater Price, or Rate, which they caused to be offered them from time to time, without taking any notice of the <HI>protests</HI> made by the said <HI>Company,</HI> or their <HI>Agents,</HI> against such proceedings: so far that the said <HI>Company,</HI> not able to forbear any longer, was forced, for the observation and execution of the said <HI>Contracts,</HI> to take up <HI>Arms</HI> to bring those men to their <HI>Duties</HI> by meer <HI>strength,</HI> they having been taken off, by the ill practices and cunning ways of the <HI>English.</HI> The peace was not so soon renewed with the said <HI>Queen</HI> (as also the <HI>old Contracts</HI>) but the <HI>English</HI> came in with their Ships with a design to disappoint also the abovesaid <HI>Company</HI> of that <HI>Pepper,</HI>
<PB N="25" REF="16"/>if they could have done it; so that the <HI>English</HI> have been the movers, and given occasion not only for the said <HI>War</HI> which the said <HI>Company</HI> was forc'd to make against the Kingdom of <HI>A∣cheen,</HI> with so excessive charges, but also by the sleights they have made of their <HI>protests,</HI> they have obliged the <HI>Company</HI> to keep there continually a number of Ships to hinder the <HI>Inhabi∣tants</HI> to sell their <HI>Tynn</HI> and <HI>Pepper</HI> to the <HI>English,</HI> by hidden and indirect ways, and frustrate thereby the <HI>Company</HI> of the <HI>Low-Countries,</HI> which hath caused a very considerable preju∣dice and damage to the said <HI>Company</HI> which doth conceive it self to have a right of demanding reparation thereof from the <HI>English Company.</HI></P>
<P>In the <HI>third</HI> place, the Injuries, Affronts, and Hinderances, as also the troubles, and incumbrances, which the <HI>English Com∣pany</HI> hath procured to <HI>This Company,</HI> whereof <HI>This Company</HI> doth demand reparation, and refaction.</P>
<P>To the <HI>ninth Article;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer.</HI> 9.</NOTE> We know that they have made <HI>Contracts</HI> with the <HI>Queen</HI> of <HI>Acheen</HI> both for <HI>Tynn</HI> and <HI>Pepper;</HI> and it may be <HI>exclusive</HI> to <HI>us;</HI> but if so, they have violated the express terms of that <HI>Treaty</HI> 1619, which they misreport for the 27<SUP>th</SUP> <HI>Ar∣ticle,</HI> in express terms provides, as follows.</P>
<P><HI>That neither of the</HI> two Companies <HI>shall</HI> prevent, <HI>or</HI> exclude <HI>the other, for time to come, whether it be by means of</HI> Fortifications, <HI>or</HI> Contracts, <HI>that one would make hereafter in any part of the</HI> Indies: <HI>But</HI> all the Trade shall be free and common to one, and the other, in every place <HI>thereof.</HI></P>
<P>We do not deny, but where there is no obligati∣on to the contrary, it may be lawful for them or us
<PB N="26" REF="17"/>to contract with any Prince or people, for the whole of any commodity of their growth or manu∣facture; but if the <HI>Hollanders</HI> say truth in their own <HI>allegations,</HI> that <HI>they have always had such a</HI> Contract <HI>with the</HI> Queen <HI>of</HI> Acheen; they confess that they have injured us in it, contrary to the 27<SUP>th</SUP> <HI>Article</HI> of the <HI>Treaty</HI> 1619 aforesaid. But supposing them now absolved from that <HI>Article,</HI> and that con∣trary to that good neighbourhood which they ought to shew us, they have made such use of that liberty as to contract with the <HI>Queen</HI> of <HI>Acheen,</HI> and others, by the influence of their <HI>arms</HI> to exclude us from the Trade of their Countries; yet we being no par∣ties, nor consenting to that <HI>Contract,</HI> cannot be un∣derstood to be under any obligation, not to endea∣vour to share in the Trade, if either party be wil∣ling to admit us; and if they do it to the violation of their <HI>Contract,</HI> the <HI>Contractant</HI> only is the person upon whom both by <HI>Law</HI> and <HI>Reason</HI> the party inju∣red must have recourse for satisfaction, and not upon us: And That especially since those <HI>Contracts</HI> have been for the most part extorted from the <HI>Natives</HI> by pure force of <HI>Arms,</HI> even while we have had our <HI>Factories</HI> amongst them; and so have been <HI>fellow-sufferers</HI> with the <HI>Natives</HI> in the injuries they have done by the War. And therefore <HI>We think it will be judged very frivolous in the</HI> Hollanders <HI>to require from</HI> us <HI>satisfaction for the expence</HI> of Their conti∣nued Forces, <HI>by which they maintain the advantages of their first extorted</HI> Contract <HI>from the</HI> Natives <HI>to</HI> our prejudice.</P>
<PB N="27" REF="17"/>
<P>The <HI>English</HI> have of late begun to introduce and practise in the <HI>Indies</HI> to protect and defend the <HI>Ships</HI> and <HI>Barques</HI> belong∣ing to some <HI>Nations</HI> with whom <HI>This Company</HI> is in <HI>Wars</HI> gi∣ving them a <HI>Warrant,</HI> or <HI>Poss-port,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 10.</NOTE> whereby they do maintain that those people ought to be free of any trouble, or molesta∣tion. And whereas that hath caused already many disorders, and distastes which apparently will breed open hostilities, the a∣bovesaid <HI>Company</HI> doth beseech the King of <HI>Great Britain</HI> to give such necessary orders that such things may cease, for want of which they do protest that they cannot be blamed of the incon∣veniences which may thereby happen.</P>
<P>To the <HI>tenth Article;</HI> we say; It is true,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer.</HI> 10.</NOTE> that we have and do practise to give <HI>Pass-ports</HI> to the <HI>Ships</HI> of those <HI>Natives</HI> that are in friendly <HI>commerce</HI> with us: by which; all the Commanders of Ships in our service, are required not to hinder or disturb them; but rather to lend them assistance: and the <HI>Holland∣ers</HI> do the like; and we know not why it may not be as free for <HI>us as them:</HI> And if we have given such <HI>Pass-ports</HI> to <HI>Our friends</HI> whom the <HI>Hollanders</HI> may please to call <HI>Their Enemies,</HI> and therefore attaque them, We know not of any disorders that have fol∣lowed upon it; but it seems by the <HI>confidence</HI> of the <HI>request</HI> of this <HI>Article</HI> to his <HI>Majesty,</HI> and the <HI>Impu∣dence</HI> of the <HI>threat</HI> of an <HI>open War,</HI> and <HI>Protest</HI> a∣gainst Him, in case of his <HI>non-complyance,</HI> that the <HI>Netherlands Company</HI> doth most <HI>insolently</HI> pretend in their <HI>own names,</HI> to be <HI>sole Sovereigns</HI> of those Seas, and would have his Majesty own them for such, but that being a matter of <HI>State,</HI> this Company leaves it to his <HI>Majesties Royal Resentment.</HI></P>
<PB N="28" REF="18"/>
<P>And whereas it is daily more and more seen that the <HI>English</HI> have no other intent but to trouble and molest <HI>This Company</HI> in the <HI>Indies,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 11.</NOTE> and to offer any kind of injuries, and affronts to their men; and That only to pick a quarrel, that they may have pre∣tense to make some <HI>protests;</HI> since they have not stuck openly to <HI>declare,</HI> that they get a greater benefit from those <HI>protests,</HI> then by their <HI>Trade;</HI> seeking only thereby to alter the peace and quietness between both Nations. The which doth clearly appear by the <HI>Impertinent pretenses</HI> which they have thought good to produce here, and to make use thereof, the which doth much concern the <HI>Authorities</HI> of <HI>both Estates</HI> to hinder as soon as possible, and to oppose vigorously: And the <HI>Companies</HI> of <HI>these Countries</HI> do demand that it may be provided thereto, and remedied as soon as can be: Above all, that they may be instructed how to govern and carry themselves in the <HI>Indies,</HI> in regard of that Nation; because that having surrounded or be∣sieged any <HI>Enemies</HI> place, the <HI>English</HI> shall endeavour to get in, or land with their Ships, and so <HI>vice versa,</HI> because that hath caused many distastes and disorders some years since past.</P>
<P>To the <HI>eleventh Article,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer.</HI> 11.</NOTE> we can but say that the <HI>whole affirmation</HI> of it is <HI>scandalous,</HI> and <HI>false,</HI> and will never be believed unless they can perswade the world to judge that our <HI>peaceable endeavours</HI> to follow any part of the <HI>right</HI> of our <HI>Trade</HI> in the <HI>Indies,</HI> is a <HI>declared intention</HI> to <HI>trouble</HI> and <HI>disquiet</HI> the <HI>Netherlands Company,</HI> and to <HI>injure</HI> and <HI>affront Their people:</HI> Nor can it possibly be credited, that we should attempt <HI>to injure or affront them upon design to quarrel there, that we might have a pretense for</HI> Protests, <HI>and boast that we had gotten more by That then by our Trade;</HI> For <HI>first;</HI> We have not for many years last past been in a condition in <HI>those Seas</HI> to contest our <HI>right</HI> with them; and there∣fore
<PB N="29" REF="18"/>could not be so inconsiderate, as to provoke those whose <HI>avarice</HI> and <HI>might,</HI> would, could and hath destroyed our interests. <HI>Secondly,</HI> It were as <HI>ridiculous</HI> for any man to <HI>believe,</HI> as it is <HI>scanda∣lous</HI> in them to <HI>affirm,</HI> that we should get by <HI>Pro∣tests</HI> against <HI>Them,</HI> when hitherto it is notorious to the whole world, that we never obtained from them after the clearest conviction of them, <HI>Resti∣tution</HI> of one <HI>tenth part</HI> of those <HI>losses</HI> which have been brought upon us, by <HI>Their Robbery,</HI> and <HI>Inju∣stice:</HI> But we can with very great truth affirm, that when their people have taken our Ships and Goods, and could not deny but the Act was unjust, that they replied; <HI>It was better for their</HI> Masters <HI>to pay for it at home, when we could get it, then for them not to improve all ways and means to discourage us in the Trade.</HI> And whereas in the <HI>Close</HI> of this <HI>Article,</HI> the <HI>Netherlands Company</HI> presume to prejudge the differences now depending, and to instruct both <HI>Our</HI> and <HI>Their Sovereignty,</HI> in what they assume to judge to be their <HI>duty.</HI> We shall onely say, that when his <HI>Majesty</HI> shall in his <HI>Royal Wisdom</HI> think fit to establish any <HI>regulation</HI> between us, we shall du∣tifully and cheerfully conform to it.</P>
<P>Amongst others, an <HI>English Ship,</HI> called the <HI>Surat Mer∣chant,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 12.</NOTE> being in <HI>May</HI> 1662, on the <HI>Road</HI> of <HI>Gameron,</HI> did force a <HI>Moorish Ship</HI> of <HI>Matulipatuan,</HI> which did carry <HI>two Flags</HI> of <HI>This Estate,</HI> to strike down, and to take them off, in the view of all the World, which was no small affront to the whole Nation.</P>
<PB N="30" REF="19"/>
<P>To the <HI>twelfth Article,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer.</HI> 12.</NOTE> we say; We know nothing of it; but were it so, <HI>That Company</HI> could not have had the <HI>Impudence</HI> to have made it an <HI>Objection,</HI> that an <HI>English Ship</HI> riding with the <HI>English Flag</HI> would not suffer the <HI>States Colours</HI> upon a <HI>Moors Ship</HI> to be <HI>born up</HI> in her <HI>presence,</HI> unless they concluded themselves, both <HI>Sovereigns</HI> of the <HI>Indian,</HI> and <HI>Per∣sian Seas,</HI> and <HI>Masters</HI> of the <HI>English Nation</HI> at <HI>Home.</HI> But perchance they fancy, that this their frivolous and unknown complaint, might serve to ballance that <HI>unsufferable affront</HI> that was offer'd in <HI>February</HI> 16 62/63, to the <HI>English Flag</HI> of Saint <HI>George</HI> at <HI>Swallow Marine,</HI> in <HI>presence</HI> of the <HI>English Nation;</HI> when <HI>Captain Bence,</HI> Commander of the <HI>Holland Ship, (Gouldstloome)</HI> Riding <HI>Admiral</HI> there, first made faste the said <HI>English Flag</HI> to the <HI>Star-bord list</HI> of the <HI>main-top-sail yard,</HI> where it hung <HI>half an hour;</HI> and was thence remov'd to the head of the <HI>main Mast;</HI> and thence down to the <HI>Top,</HI> and there remained all day, <HI>under</HI> the <HI>Dutch Flag.</HI> And the same day, the <HI>Dutch</HI> landed, and marched with their <HI>Flags flying round</HI> the <HI>English yard,</HI> in <HI>derision</HI> of the <HI>English Flag</HI> there <HI>on shore;</HI> and that they did the like with higher <HI>Insolence</HI> about the <HI>English House</HI> in the City of <HI>Surat</HI> it self.</P>
<P>Whilst the Forces of <HI>This Company</HI> did besiege lately the Ci∣ty of <HI>Cochin,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 13.</NOTE> the <HI>English</HI> which were in the Port of the said Ci∣ty so far forgot themselves, as to serve the Artillery of the said City against the <HI>Besiegers,</HI> and this directly against the <HI>Treaty</HI> made here with them in the <HI>Hague,</HI> the 6th of <HI>February,</HI> 1659. which saith expresly, that <HI>both the</HI> Companies <HI>shall live quietly, and in good Intelligence together, and shall reciprocally
<PB N="31" REF="19"/>shew one another proofes of friendship, as well in the</HI> East-Indies, <HI>as</HI> elsewhere: for which, the said <HI>Company</HI> of the <HI>Low-Countries</HI> doth demand reparation, and satisfaction.</P>
<P>To the <HI>thirteenth Article,</HI> we say;<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer.</HI> 13.</NOTE> We know not that any of our men served as <HI>Gunners</HI> in the Town of <HI>Cochin</HI> against the <HI>Hollanders;</HI> or if they did, it is like it was done in defence of <HI>This Companies Inter∣est There,</HI> which the <HI>Hollanders</HI> had equally designed for <HI>destruction</HI> with that of those whom they call their <HI>Enemies;</HI> and when our <HI>differences</HI> come to the <HI>test,</HI> it will then appear, <HI>which</HI> of the <HI>two Companies</HI> hath <HI>observed,</HI> or <HI>violated</HI> the <HI>Articles</HI> of <HI>Amity</HI> made <HI>in Anno</HI> 1659.</P>
<P>Whilst in the <HI>Month</HI> of <HI>April,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 14.</NOTE> 1662. some <HI>Sea-men</HI> of this Country were about diverting themselves neer the <HI>Road</HI> of <HI>Suali,</HI> in a Village call'd <HI>Selein Dammetyens,</HI> they were not only ill-used with Cudgels by some <HI>English</HI> which hapned to come in, but also three of them were so much wounded, that one, call'd <HI>Paul Francis Schoone, fellow</HI> or <HI>Adjutant helper</HI> to the <HI>Gunner</HI> in the <HI>Ship</HI> called <HI>Buyenskereke,</HI> dyed of his wounds <HI>two days</HI> after, without any punishment inflicted on the <HI>Offen∣ders</HI> by the <HI>English President</HI> of <HI>Surat,</HI> called <HI>Matthew An∣drews,</HI> although he was summoned and motion'd to do it: Therefore <HI>This Company</HI> cannot chuse but demand reparation of the affront and wrong done to the whole Nation, and is ob∣lig'd to maintain that there is an obligation to punish the guilty exemplarily.</P>
<P>To the <HI>fourteenth,</HI> we say;<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer.</HI> 14.</NOTE> We conceive that nei∣ther <HI>This</HI> nor the <HI>tenth, eleventh, twelfth,</HI> and <HI>thir∣teenth Articles,</HI> (being matters of <HI>State,</HI> and not of
<PB N="32" REF="20"/><HI>Trade</HI>) do fall within the <HI>Cognizance</HI> of the <HI>fifteenth Article</HI> of the <HI>Last Treaty,</HI> and therefore ought not to be here admitted: But yet we <HI>Answer,</HI> that we know nothing of <HI>Paul Franc Schoone,</HI> his being <HI>bastonaded</HI> by the <HI>English</HI> to <HI>death;</HI> onely we find by good and sufficient <HI>Attestation,</HI> dated at <HI>Sualy</HI> in <HI>March</HI> and <HI>April</HI> 16 62/63; that about that time <HI>three Dutch-men</HI> assaulted <HI>two English-men</HI> in the open field, and one of the <HI>Dutch</HI> with his drawn knife struck at the <HI>face</HI> of one <HI>Wilks,</HI> who receiv'd the <HI>stab</HI> on his <HI>hand;</HI> and when the <HI>Dutch-man</HI> was making a <HI>second stab</HI> at the <HI>other English-man,</HI> one <HI>Brewer,</HI> (whom he wounded in the <HI>Arm</HI>) <HI>Brewer,</HI> in his own defence, stroke the <HI>Dutch-man</HI> with his <HI>staff</HI> over the <HI>face,</HI> and felled him to the ground; and if the <HI>Dutch-man dyed</HI> of the <HI>blow,</HI> the <HI>English-man</HI> cannot be accused of a <HI>murther;</HI> when what he did, was <HI>se defendendo.</HI> But on the <HI>other side,</HI> we found that in <HI>April</HI> 1661, <HI>Joseph Goodson,</HI> an <HI>English-man,</HI> and <HI>other English-men,</HI> were barbarously <HI>assaulted</HI> at <HI>Sualy,</HI> by the <HI>Chy∣rurgeon</HI> of the <HI>Dutch Ship, Henrietta Louisia,</HI> and one <HI>John Abramson,</HI> with drawn swords, and run into the belly the said <HI>Chyrurgeon,</HI> and in few hours after dyed of his wounds. And another <HI>English-man,</HI> one <HI>John Jones,</HI> endeavouring to rescue the said <HI>Jos: Goodson,</HI> was then likewise slain by the <HI>two Dutch</HI> parties.</P>
<PB N="33" REF="20"/>
<P>That upon the 16. of <HI>March,</HI> 1662, about 30.<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 14.</NOTE> <HI>Hollanders</HI> entered into the <HI>English Bazar,</HI> with <HI>Lances, Swords, Clubs,</HI> &amp;c. and <HI>Colours flying,</HI> and enquired for <HI>English men,</HI> swearing by their <HI>Sacra∣ment,</HI> and threatning the Death of all the <HI>English</HI> they could meet; but finding none, they brake in∣to a mans house adjacent, where they found an old man, a <HI>Servant</HI> of the <HI>English Company,</HI> to whom they gave <HI>four Mortal wounds,</HI> and left him: And now <HI>let the whole world judge, whether the</HI> English, <HI>or the</HI> Dutch <HI>bee</HI> the affronters, <HI>and</HI> Murtherers.</P>
<P>That on the 14 of <HI>April,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>15.</HI></NOTE> 1658. the <HI>great Barque</HI> of the <HI>Holland-West-India-Company</HI> coming from <HI>Curaso,</HI> was at∣tacqued in the open Seas, and brought to <HI>Jamaica</HI> by an <HI>Englishman of War,</HI> named <HI>Sabado.</HI> That the said <HI>Barque</HI> was not only arrested at <HI>Jamaica</HI> until the 23 of the <HI>same month;</HI> but also during that time, there was taken from her the sum of 900 <HI>Livres;</HI> and therefore the said <HI>Company</HI> do demand sa∣tisfaction for what they have suffered by the said Encounter, and by the retardment of the said <HI>Barque,</HI> and restitution of the said 900 <HI>Livres.</HI></P>
<P>To the 15. <HI>Article,</HI> it is <HI>Answered;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 15.</NOTE> That we have heard that about the time alleadged, there was one <HI>Sabado,</HI> who had Commission to be a <HI>pri∣vate Man of War</HI> from <HI>Lieutenant General Branio,</HI> but knew nothing of any such <HI>Prize</HI> taken by him, or that was brought into <HI>Jamaica.</HI></P>
<P>The said <HI>Company</HI> do say, that upon the 29 of <HI>November,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>16.</HI></NOTE>1659. one of their <HI>Ships,</HI> named the <HI>St. John,</HI> coming from <HI>Guyne</HI> laden with a considerable number of <HI>Slaves,</HI> was put on shore near the said <HI>Island</HI> of <HI>Curaso;</HI> and that those of <HI>Cu∣raso</HI> sending one of the <HI>Barques</HI> of the said <HI>Company,</HI> (to save the said <HI>Slaves</HI>) named the <HI>Ostridge;</HI> while the men were la∣bouring to transport them from the Ship to the <HI>Barque,</HI> there
<PB N="34" REF="21"/>came upon them an <HI>English Fregat,</HI> called the <HI>Castle Fregat,</HI> of which <HI>John Peterson du Caldican</HI> was <HI>Captain;</HI> who did not onely hinder them from their designe, but fell upon them by force, and made himself Master of them, and took away 84 <HI>blaves</HI> as a lawful <HI>Prize,</HI> and carried them to <HI>Jamaica.</HI></P>
<P>To the 16.<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 16.</NOTE> <HI>Article,</HI> it is <HI>Answered;</HI> That about the time in the <HI>said Article</HI> mentioned, there was a <HI>Dutch man,</HI> named <HI>Peterson,</HI> who brought in a <HI>boat</HI> with 6 or 7 <HI>Negroes</HI> to <HI>Jamaica,</HI> having dis∣posed of more, as he said; and alleadging great scarcity of provisions, did sell the <HI>Negroes</HI> to the <HI>Inhabitants</HI> of <HI>Jamaica;</HI> and being examined how he came by them, did aver that he took them at <HI>Sea</HI> as a <HI>Wrack;</HI> and the <HI>Carpenter</HI> and <HI>others</HI> of the Ship so <HI>wracked,</HI> did justify the same: All which <HI>depositions</HI> were sent to the <HI>Governour</HI> of <HI>Curasso</HI> by <HI>Col. Doyly.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Directors</HI> of the said <HI>West-India-Company</HI> do complain,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>17.</HI></NOTE> that upon the 12 of <HI>March,</HI> 1660. the <HI>Agents</HI> that they had at <HI>Cabo Verde,</HI> were hindered by <HI>five English Ships</HI> from Tra∣ding there, as they had customarily done; which frustrated them of very great advantages and profits, and yet notwith∣standing, they remain charged with the Entertainment of their Officers and People, both Military and others, as also other Forts, Lodges, Ships, and what depends on them.</P>
<P>To the 17.<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 17.</NOTE> <HI>Article,</HI> it is <HI>Answered;</HI> That <HI>this Article</HI> is so <HI>general,</HI> that no <HI>particular Answer</HI> can be made unto it; it making no particular mention of any violence done, nor to whom, except in that <HI>general word</HI> of the <HI>Complaynants Agents</HI> at <HI>Capo de Verde:</HI> And all that can be said, is, that some <HI>Ships</HI> in which the <HI>Royal Company</HI> had an <HI>Interest,</HI> did about that time pass to the <HI>River Gambia;</HI> but
<PB N="35" REF="21"/>we never heard of any the least violence or injury they did offer to any persons or Ships in their pas∣sage thither: And when that <HI>complaint</HI> shall be so cloathed with <HI>circumstance,</HI> that we can have any <HI>particular</HI> to six upon, an <HI>Answer</HI> shall be made thereunto.</P>
<P>In pursuit of this pretence,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>18.</HI></NOTE> the said <HI>Company</HI> complain a∣gain, that the same <HI>English</HI> after they had thus abused them, went to the River of <HI>Gambia,</HI> where they dispossest the <HI>Mini∣sters</HI> of the <HI>Company</HI> with violence and force, and took all, so as that people were constrained to abandon all the Forts, Lodges, Houses, and all that the <HI>Company</HI> possest. And for as much as since that time the <HI>Company</HI> hath not been able to Trade, they alledge that the <HI>Damage</HI> they have suffered by reason hereof ought to be sufficiently repaired.</P>
<P>To the 18. <HI>Article,</HI> it is <HI>Answered;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 18.</NOTE> That it is much of the like nature; for it runs all in <HI>general words,</HI> without naming any <HI>Fort</HI> or <HI>Lodg,</HI> to which the <HI>Dutch Nation</HI> have any <HI>claim,</HI> as we believe will most evidently appear, when the <HI>Dutch</HI> shall de∣scend to a particular naming of any <HI>Fort</HI> or <HI>Lodge;</HI> which we have cause to think they avoid, lest the grossness of the allegation should be too notorious.</P>
<P>The same <HI>Company</HI> do further represent, that in <HI>Aug.</HI> 1660.<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>19.</HI></NOTE> one of their <HI>Ships,</HI> called the <HI>Peacock,</HI> being at Sea near the <HI>Island</HI> of <HI>Aruba,</HI> was set upon with force by an <HI>Englishman of War</HI> and his <HI>Complices,</HI> who brake open the Coffers and Chests, and took away what they thought fit, and did very much hurt and outrage, as <HI>declared Enemies</HI> to the <HI>Company</HI> of that Ship; and therefore they do declare, that they may lawfully demand restitution for the violences done to them.</P>
<P>To the 19. <HI>Article,</HI> we <HI>Answer;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 19.</NOTE> That the <HI>Man of War,</HI> which the complaynants say took their Ship,
<PB N="36" REF="22"/>is not named, therefore we cannot <HI>Answer;</HI> but we know that about the time mentioned in <HI>this Article,</HI> there was a <HI>Dutch Ship</HI> taken about <HI>Aruba,</HI> by <HI>Capt. Mynges,</HI> which as it appears to the <HI>Admi∣ralty,</HI> was in the <HI>service</HI> and <HI>pay</HI> of the <HI>Spaniard,</HI> then in hostility with the <HI>English,</HI> and had shot at <HI>Captain Mynges,</HI> and furnished the <HI>Spaniard</HI> with <HI>Ammunition,</HI> and had <HI>Spaniards aboard;</HI> and there∣fore legally condemned by the said <HI>Court</HI> of <HI>Ad∣miralty.</HI></P>
<P>About the end of the year 1660.<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>20.</HI></NOTE> (to wit, the 25 of <HI>Decem∣ber</HI>) one of their Ships named the <HI>St. Peter</HI> being at <HI>Anchor</HI> in the <HI>South-Bay,</HI> near the <HI>Isle</HI> of <HI>Cuba</HI> in the <HI>West-Indies,</HI> was not onely pillaged (to the loss of her <HI>Merchandizes,</HI> her <HI>Car∣gazon,</HI> and all the <HI>Ʋtensils</HI> of the <HI>Ship</HI>) by an <HI>Englishman of War,</HI> called the <HI>Pearl, N. Freeborn, Captain;</HI> and <HI>that</HI> in the presence and sight of another <HI>English Ship,</HI> of which <HI>Richard Reesby</HI> was <HI>Commander,</HI> with a Commission of his Majesties of <HI>England:</HI> but also the people of the said Ship were treated in a horrible, and indeed barbarous manner: for among o∣ther cruelties which they exercised, they put a Cord about the Neck of the <HI>Masters Mate,</HI> and hung him up in that condi∣tion till the blood came out at his Nose and Ears, so that the Cord was then cut, thinking he had been dead; after which they put burning Matches to his Fingers, until they had consumed the flesh to the bones; and in fine, constrained the <HI>Master</HI> and <HI>Factor</HI> of the said Ship, (as well by the sad spe∣ctacle, as by horrible threats) to pass and signe an Act, obli∣ging them to approve of all these insolent and inhumane a∣ctions, and to avow that the Ship was fair <HI>Prize,</HI> with all her Lading.</P>
<P>To the 20.<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 20.</NOTE> <HI>Article,</HI> we <HI>Answer;</HI> That it is true, that one <HI>Freeborn,</HI> a <HI>pyrate</HI> (who had no <HI>Commis∣sion,</HI> but had formerly been in service of the <HI>Spani∣ard,</HI> and is since <HI>taken</HI> by them, and <HI>hang'd</HI> for his <HI>pyracy</HI> at <HI>Cuba</HI>) did plunder such a Ship as is men∣tioned
<PB N="37" REF="22"/>in the said <HI>Article;</HI> but coming to <HI>Jamaica,</HI> the then Governour, <HI>Colonel Doyly</HI> apprehended him, and <HI>five others</HI> of his Company, as <HI>pyrates,</HI> and sent them in <HI>Irons</HI> to <HI>London,</HI> with a <HI>charge</HI> against them, and secured the rest of the <HI>pyrates-company</HI> at <HI>Jamaica,</HI> and gave a <HI>Dutch-Master</HI> 50 li. to go to <HI>England,</HI> and prosecute the said <HI>pyrates,</HI> and promised them passage in the <HI>Diamond Fregat;</HI> but for want of <HI>prosecution,</HI> the <HI>pyrates</HI> after 6 <HI>months imprisonment</HI> in <HI>England,</HI> were discharged, and <HI>Col. Doyly</HI> restored the <HI>Ship,</HI> and all that re∣mained by her; and furnished her with what she wanted to enable her to sail, out of the <HI>Kings stores;</HI> and what small remainder of goods were found belonging to her <HI>Cargo,</HI> the <HI>Colonel</HI> tendred the <HI>Ma∣ster</HI> to be freely restored to him; but he refused to accept of them, and there was never any de∣mand made of them since; and how freely, and clearly they were dealt with by the said <HI>Governor,</HI> will appear by the following <HI>Copy</HI> of a Letter, writ∣ten to the <HI>Supra Cargo</HI> of the said <HI>Dutch Ship,</HI> upon the <HI>first notice</HI> of the <HI>Pyracy</HI> committed.</P>
<DIV3 TYPE="letter">
<OPENER><DATELINE><HI>Jamaica,</HI> <DATE>20th of <HI>January,</HI> 1660.</DATE></DATELINE></OPENER>
<HEAD>To <HI>Henry Hamburk, Merchant</HI> of the Ship of <HI>St. Peeter</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> These.</HEAD>
<P>WHereas certain goods belonging to you, have been <HI>pyratically</HI> taken, and brought into this <HI>Harbor,</HI> and found out by my labor and industry;
<PB N="38" REF="23"/>I do according to the <HI>14. Article</HI> of <HI>Peace</HI> and <HI>Con∣federation</HI> between <HI>England</HI> and the <HI>United Pro∣vinces;</HI> offer you your <HI>Ship, Tackle, Arms, Furni∣ture,</HI> and <HI>Apparel,</HI> as also all such goods as are in being, and found out, that so such Justice may be done, for and on your behalf, as lies in my power.</P>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<HEAD><HI>A</HI> List <HI>of the</HI> Pretensions <HI>which the</HI> Inhabitants <HI>and</HI> Subjects <HI>of the</HI> United Provinces <HI>of the</HI> Low Countries <HI>have put in</HI> Writing, <HI>and produc'd against the</HI> State, <HI>or some</HI> Particular Subjects <HI>of the</HI> King <HI>of</HI> Great Britain, <HI>for the</HI> Injuries <HI>and</HI> Damages <HI>which the</HI> Inha∣bitants <HI>and</HI> Subjects <HI>of the said</HI> Provinces <HI>have suffered, as well by the</HI> Attaque, Prize <HI>and</HI> Pillage <HI>of their</HI> Vessels <HI>and</HI> Goods, <HI>as otherwise, in other manner, since the</HI> year 165 3/4. <HI>in several parts of the world; and since the</HI> year 165 8/9. <HI>in the</HI> East-Indies, <HI>to be repaired according to the</HI> Tenor <HI>of the</HI> 15 Article <HI>of the</HI> Treaty <HI>last concluded.</HI></HEAD>
<P><HI>PHilip Vanhulten,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>21.</HI></NOTE> and his <HI>associates, Merchants</HI> dwelling in <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> do say, that in the year 1657. they had freighted a <HI>Ship</HI> named the <HI>Sancta Maria,</HI> (<HI>John Lynen</HI> Ma∣ster) to go from <HI>Amsterdam</HI> to the <HI>Canaries,</HI> and from <HI>thence</HI> to the <HI>West-Indies,</HI> belonging to the King of <HI>Spain,</HI> and from thence to return to the <HI>Canaries,</HI> and afterwards to <HI>Cadiz</HI> in <HI>Spain,</HI> and finally to return to <HI>Amsterdam.</HI> That the said Ship after she had made her <HI>West-India Voyage,</HI> and returned with
<PB N="39" REF="23"/>her <HI>Lading</HI> to the <HI>Canaries;</HI> where the <HI>Master</HI> of the Ship ha∣ving found the Orders of the said <HI>Vanhulten,</HI> and of the rest of the <HI>Owners,</HI> went from thence with his Ship to <HI>Cadiz,</HI> where the said Master being arrived in <HI>November</HI> 1658. and beginning to apprehend lest the <HI>Minister</HI> of the King of <HI>Spain</HI> at <HI>Cadiz,</HI> might give him some trouble, he steered his course for <HI>Gibraltar,</HI> and there he met the <HI>Ship</HI> call'd the <HI>Pro Patria,</HI> whereof <HI>Jacob Muts</HI> was <HI>Master;</HI> whom he thought good to entrust with the <HI>Hides,</HI> and other <HI>Merchandizes,</HI> to be carri∣ed in his <HI>Vessel</HI> to <HI>Amsterdam.</HI> That while the said Master of the Ship was busie in the Lading of the <HI>Hides</HI> from one Ship to another, there came upon him one of the <HI>Parliaments Ships,</HI> called the <HI>Fairfax,</HI> commanded by <HI>Robert Story,</HI> of the <HI>Squadron</HI> of <HI>General John Stoaks,</HI> which assaulted and took those two <HI>Ships,</HI> and carried them to the Coast of <HI>Barbary:</HI> and being there, the said <HI>Robert Story</HI> unladed all the Goods out of the Ship <HI>Pro Patria,</HI> and carried them away to <HI>Toulon</HI> in <HI>France,</HI> together with the Ship <HI>Sancta Maria,</HI> with all her Lading, (as she came from the <HI>West-Indies</HI>) which consisted of 13897 <HI>Hides,</HI> 1384 <HI>Cargoes</HI> of <HI>Cacao,</HI> 2225 <HI>Rolls</HI> of <HI>Tobacco,</HI> 772 pieces of <HI>Brazil Wood,</HI> 18 <HI>Kintals</HI> of <HI>Ginger.</HI> And the said <HI>Vanhulten</HI> and his Associates having complained thereof to the <HI>Admiralty</HI> of <HI>England,</HI> did obtain a discharge of the said <HI>Merchandizes</HI> upon <HI>caution;</HI> and accordingly on the 11 of <HI>December</HI> 1660. they obtained <HI>sentence,</HI> by which the <HI>caution</HI> was <HI>discharged,</HI> and the <HI>Goods</HI> declared <HI>free,</HI> adjudging resti∣tution thereof to the said <HI>Vanhulten,</HI> or to his <HI>Assignes.</HI> But in stead of restitution in full, the said <HI>Vanhulten</HI> received short of his due, 2095 <HI>Hides,</HI> 27963 pounds of <HI>Cacao,</HI> 4360 <HI>l.</HI> of <HI>Tobacco,</HI> 4722 <HI>l.</HI> of <HI>Brazil Wood,</HI> and 1813 <HI>l.</HI> of <HI>Ginger.</HI></P>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>The <HI>Answer</HI> of the <HI>English,</HI> to the <HI>Pretensions</HI> exhibited by the <HI>Subjects</HI> of the <HI>United Provinces.</HI></HEAD>
<P><HI>THis Complaint</HI> doth Answer it self;<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 21.</NOTE> that upon complaint to the <HI>Admiralty</HI> of <HI>England,</HI> be obtained a <HI>discharge of the said Merchandizes; upon
<PB N="40" REF="24"/>caution,</HI> and on the 11 of <HI>December,</HI> 1660. he ob∣tained <HI>sentence</HI> of <HI>Restitution;</HI> whereby his <HI>caution</HI> was <HI>discharged,</HI> and the <HI>Merchandizes</HI> declared <HI>free;</HI> condemning those that had detained them, to restore them: Now, if all the merchandizes came not to his hand, that were in the Ship, (as he saith they did not) yet is there not to be found in the <HI>Admiralty</HI> any <HI>complaint</HI> thereof, nor any proof made upon any such <HI>complaint</HI> of the <HI>reality</HI> or <HI>truth</HI> thereof; so that here can be no cause of <HI>com∣plaint</HI> of the defect of <HI>Justice;</HI> he himself not <HI>pro∣secuting</HI> any farther to have the <HI>sentence</HI> put in <HI>execution.</HI></P>
<P><HI>William Mumma,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>22.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Huter Peterson,</HI> and <HI>Gilbert Skouten,</HI> (all Merchants of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> and interested in the said Ship, the <HI>Maria</HI>) referring themselves to what hath been alledged by the said <HI>Philip Vanhulten,</HI> and his <HI>Parteners</HI> concerning the said Ship; do say further for a ground of their <HI>complaint,</HI> That the same Ship was stopt at <HI>Toulon</HI> for the space of <HI>three years</HI> and <HI>five moneths;</HI> and that during all that time, the <HI>Owners</HI> could not make any benefit of their <HI>Stock,</HI> nor yet get the Ship discharged. And for as much as by the <HI>sentence</HI> of the <HI>High Court</HI> of <HI>Admiralty</HI> of <HI>England</HI> of the 5th of <HI>Decem∣ber,</HI> 1660. it was declared, that the said Ship being wrong∣fully taken, ought to be restored to the <HI>Owner,</HI> (as in effect it was, after a tedious pursuit) they think that they have very good grounds to demand <HI>satisfaction</HI> for all their <HI>Expences, Damages,</HI> and <HI>Interests,</HI> beside the <HI>restitution</HI> of their <HI>Merchan∣dizes.</HI></P>
<P>And as to the <HI>complaint</HI> of <HI>William Mumma,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 22.</NOTE> <HI>Huter Peterson, Gilbert Skouten, Merchants</HI> of <HI>Am∣sterdam,</HI> interessed in the said Ship, the <HI>Mary:</HI> They complain of an <HI>arrest</HI> laid upon the said Ship at <HI>Tou∣lon,</HI> and that they lay under that <HI>arrest</HI> for the space
<PB N="41" REF="24"/>of 3 <HI>years,</HI> and 5 <HI>months,</HI> and that during that time, the <HI>owners</HI> could not make use of their <HI>Stock,</HI> and that the <HI>restitution</HI> being made after long persuits, they think themselves <HI>well grounded</HI> to demand <HI>satisfaction</HI> for all their <HI>expenses</HI> and <HI>damages.</HI></P>
<P>For the <HI>arrest laid upon the Ship</HI> at <HI>Toulon,</HI> it is neither said <HI>when,</HI> nor by <HI>whom;</HI> so that we know not the meaning of it, or why any satisfaction for any damages sustained by any <HI>arrest</HI> at <HI>Toulon,</HI> should be demanded from <HI>England:</HI> And as for the <HI>da∣mages</HI> and <HI>expenses</HI> sustained by the <HI>suit depend∣ing here:</HI> If there was <HI>just cause</HI> of the <HI>seizure,</HI> then was there <HI>no cause</HI> of the giving them <HI>dama∣ges</HI> or <HI>expenses;</HI> If there was <HI>no cause</HI> of the <HI>seizure,</HI> and the <HI>damage</HI> and <HI>expenses demanded</HI> at the <HI>time</HI> of the <HI>sentence,</HI> and not <HI>given</HI> they might have <HI>appealed,</HI> and have had <HI>remedy,</HI> but now it is too late.</P>
<P>The said <HI>Philip Vanhulten</HI> doth represent farther,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>23.</HI></NOTE> that one of his <HI>Correspondents</HI> in <HI>Gibraltar,</HI> (having bought at a pub∣lique sale 507 <HI>Bales</HI> of <HI>Galles</HI>) laded the same in the Ship called the <HI>Campien, Peter Johnson Veltmuys</HI> Master, and consign∣ed them to the said <HI>Vanhulten</HI> at <HI>Amsterdam.</HI> That the <HI>Ma∣ster</HI> being arriv'd, and about to unlade the said <HI>Galles</HI> accor∣ding to his <HI>Bills</HI> of <HI>Lading,</HI> there came upon him one <HI>Law∣rence Lowe,</HI> as being empowered from Sir <HI>Andrew Richaut,</HI> Go∣vernour of the <HI>Levant Trade</HI> in <HI>England,</HI> who under a far setch'd and frivolous pretence, caused the said quantity of <HI>Galles</HI> to be seized: And for as much as fince, by a sentence of the <HI>Schepen</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam</HI> of the 7 of <HI>February,</HI> 1653. the same <HI>sei∣zure</HI> was declared to be <HI>injurious,</HI> and the Acter thereof con∣demned to restore the same, with the expences, damages and interest; and also that during the time of the said seizure, the price of <HI>Galles</HI> was much faln, they pretend to be <HI>In∣dempnified.</HI></P>
<PB N="42" REF="25"/>
<P>To the 23.<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 23.</NOTE> <HI>Article,</HI> it is <HI>Answered;</HI> That if the <HI>Sebepen</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam</HI> discharged the <HI>arrest,</HI> and <HI>condemned</HI> the <HI>Arrestant</HI> in <HI>cost, damage,</HI> and <HI>in∣terest,</HI> the same Court ought to have taxed it, and the Complaynant to prosecute the <HI>Execution</HI> there, while the person was upon the place; and may not seek satisfaction here: But the <HI>Judges</HI> knew very well, that those goods were part of the <HI>charges</HI> of <HI>two English Ships,</HI> the <HI>Reformation,</HI> and <HI>Free-trade,</HI> that were attaqued by a <HI>Holland Ship,</HI> the <HI>Mary</HI> under the <HI>Hollands Flag,</HI> and taken by a <HI>Spanish Commission,</HI> contrary to a <HI>security</HI> given by <HI>the owners</HI> of the said <HI>Ship of War,</HI> before her departure from <HI>Amsterdam;</HI> that she should not disturb nor preju∣dice any <HI>English Subjects</HI> within one <HI>year</HI> from that time; so as it is likely, those <HI>Judges</HI> thought it kind∣ness enough at that time, to let their <HI>fellow-burger</HI> remain in <HI>possession</HI> of what was <HI>pyratically</HI> taken, and not to punish the <HI>Arrestants</HI> farther, for de∣manding what was their own: And this <HI>complaint</HI> of <HI>Vanhultens,</HI> will finde its decision in the ajust∣ment of the <HI>general demand</HI> of the <HI>English,</HI> for the <HI>restitution</HI> of the whole <HI>lading</HI> of <HI>both Ships,</HI> which his <HI>Majesty</HI>'s <HI>Envoy extraordinary</HI> is, and hath been ever since in persuit of.</P>
<P>The same <HI>Vanhulten,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>24.</HI></NOTE> and his <HI>Associates,</HI> do further repre∣sent, That although in the year 1655. the King of <HI>Spain</HI> be∣ing then in <HI>hostility</HI> with <HI>England</HI> and <HI>France,</HI> issued out a se∣vere <HI>Prohibition</HI> against the entrance of any <HI>Ships,</HI> or <HI>Goods</HI> from either of those Kingdomes, into any of the <HI>Ports</HI> what∣soever of his <HI>Catholick Majesty;</HI> yet his said <HI>Majesty</HI> dispensing for a while to his Subjects the rigour of that <HI>Inhibition,</HI> was pleased to permit a <HI>Commerce</HI> with the <HI>French,</HI> suffering them to enter his Ports both with their <HI>Ships</HI> and <HI>Merchandizes:</HI>
<PB N="43" REF="25"/>And that the said <HI>Vanhulten</HI> and his <HI>Associates,</HI> building upon that <HI>Permission,</HI> caused to be bought at <HI>Rouen,</HI> the same year, 69 <HI>Bales</HI> of <HI>Linnen,</HI> and laded them in the <HI>Ship</HI> call'd the <HI>Hare in the Field, (John Kin, Master)</HI> to carry them from <HI>Havredesrace,</HI> to <HI>Cadiz</HI> in <HI>Spain.</HI> That in <HI>June</HI> 1665. the said Ship pursuing her Voyage, was assaulted, taken, and carried to <HI>London,</HI> by a <HI>Squadron</HI> of <HI>English Ships,</HI> under pretence that she was a <HI>French Vessel.</HI></P>
<P>That the said <HI>Vanhulten</HI> and his <HI>Associates,</HI> reclaiming their Goods, made it evidently appear that they did not belong to <HI>French-men,</HI> but were onely bought in <HI>France</HI> upon their ac∣compt, and so charg'd, and addressed to <HI>Cadiz:</HI> which being prov'd to the <HI>High Court</HI> of <HI>Admiralty</HI> of <HI>England;</HI> the said Court being fully satisfied as to the matter of Fact, did by a sentence of the 23 of <HI>Febr.</HI> 1665. discharge the said Goods, as having been seized against all Right and Reason.</P>
<P>That immediately after the said <HI>sentence</HI> given, the said Merchandizes were again laden, and the said Ship resumed her course to <HI>Cadiz.</HI> But in the mean time, the <HI>Term</HI> of the said <HI>Permission</HI> or <HI>Dispensation</HI> being <HI>expired;</HI> the said Ship co∣ming to <HI>Cadiz,</HI> was there <HI>seized</HI> and <HI>confiscated,</HI> with all her Lading, <HI>July</HI> the 30. 1665.</P>
<P>Now in regard that all these Disorders happened onely in consequence of this vexatious and perverse manner of pro∣ceeding of the <HI>English;</HI> and from that <HI>Delay</HI> which was but an effect thereof, the time of freedome being so far spent du∣ring this Dispute, that it was impossible to finish the Voyage before it was out; They have reason to demand to be <HI>In∣dempnified.</HI></P>
<P>To the <HI>second complaint</HI> of the said <HI>Vanhulten,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 24.</NOTE> in the 24. <HI>Article;</HI> we find by the <HI>Acts</HI> of the <HI>Ad∣miralty Court,</HI> the Ship, <HI>the Hare in the field,</HI> with all her Merchandizes (except those that were con∣demned for lawful prize) were the same year re∣stored, and that the owners of the said Ship could have no expenses, nor damages, she being taken with an <HI>enemies goods</HI> in her, which was just cause
<PB N="44" REF="26"/>enough for the taking and seizing of her, and bring∣ing her in.</P>
<P><HI>Isaac Fawquier,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>25.</HI></NOTE> and his <HI>Associates</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> do say, that it is true, that <HI>one</HI> of their Ships named the <HI>Cavillia,</HI> (<HI>Antho∣ny Balthensen,</HI> Master) did lade the 13 of <HI>January,</HI> 1658. in the <HI>Island</HI> of <HI>Sardinia,</HI> 2756 <HI>Salmes</HI> of <HI>Wheat</HI> to carry to <HI>Va∣lentia,</HI> at the rate of 11 <HI>Ryals freight</HI> for each <HI>Salme;</HI> and that withal he had taken on board his Ship a <HI>Spanish Mar∣quess,</HI> with a quantity of baggage, that he had promised to carry for 600 <HI>Ryals of</HI> 8. That the said Ship being arrived at <HI>Valentia,</HI> and busie in unlading her Wheat, there arrived in in the same road <HI>three English ships,</HI> commanded by <HI>Cap∣tain John Stoakes,</HI> who took the said Ship, with part of the <HI>Wheat</HI> not yet unladen, and with the <HI>Goods</HI> and <HI>Baggage</HI> of the said <HI>Spanish Marquess,</HI> carried them to <HI>Marseilles,</HI> without al∣lowing the Master any thing for his <HI>Freight;</HI> neither did the <HI>English Commander</HI> make him satisfaction for the <HI>retard∣ment</HI> of his <HI>Voyage,</HI> nor for the <HI>Wages</HI> of his <HI>Seamen</HI> for that time.</P>
<P>To the 25.<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 25, 27.</NOTE> and 27. <HI>Articles,</HI> we <HI>Answer;</HI> That the Ships were taken by <HI>Capt. Stoaks,</HI> in the time of an open War between <HI>England</HI> and <HI>Spain;</HI> and that the <HI>complaynants</HI> do not say but their <HI>goods</HI> were <HI>contra banda,</HI> and <HI>good prize;</HI> and therefore it is conceived there could be no pretence to the <HI>Freight,</HI> for the <HI>Ships</HI> were likewise forfeited; and if they had them <HI>freed,</HI> it was of <HI>Grace,</HI> much more if any <HI>freight</HI> was paid them, and therefore they ought to give thanks, and not complain.</P>
<P><HI>John Rombouts Merchant</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>26.</HI></NOTE> saith, that one of his Ships named the <HI>Golden Royal,</HI> of which <HI>Cornelius Isbrant∣son Smit</HI> was Master, belonging to <HI>Flyland,</HI> was taken in <HI>Ja∣nuary,</HI> 1661. near the <HI>Dogger Sand,</HI> by a <HI>Scotch Man of War,</HI> (the <HI>Capt.</HI> called <HI>Wutworth</HI>) and brought to <HI>Leith</HI> in <HI>Scotland</HI>
<PB N="45" REF="26"/>and that the said Ship being <HI>reclaim'd</HI> by the <HI>Proprietors,</HI> who made great and seriours Endeavours with his Majesty the King of <HI>England,</HI> he was pleased to order the delivery of the said Ship in <HI>October</HI> next following: but immediately after the release of the said Ship, she being in disorder, the <HI>Master</HI> repaired and fitted her with <HI>Guns, Victuals, Artillery, Ammu∣nition,</HI> and all other necessaries: And she being ready to sayl into <HI>Holland,</HI> his Majesty was pleased to <HI>revoke</HI> the <HI>Release</HI> he had made; whereupon the Magistrate of <HI>Edinburg</HI> made him∣self again Master of the said Ship by force, and the advantage of the night, and turned out the <HI>Master</HI> and all the <HI>Seamen.</HI></P>
<P>That the <HI>Proprietors</HI> having represented this to his Majesty, did in the end obtain a <HI>second discharge,</HI> in <HI>August</HI> 1662. the <HI>Master</HI> of the Ship hoping after this to enjoy the full effect of his <HI>Order,</HI> was forced to content <HI>Captain Wutworth,</HI> and to fit out the Ship again, after she had been the second time plundered.</P>
<P>To the 26. <HI>Article,</HI> it is <HI>Answered;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 26.</NOTE> That we never heard of any <HI>Scotch Man of War,</HI> called <HI>Wutworth;</HI> but true it is, that his Majesty upon the first complaint, did write a peremptory <HI>Letter</HI> to the <HI>Lords</HI> of his <HI>Privy Council</HI> in <HI>Scotland,</HI> in these words.</P>
<P><HI>Being informed that there are</HI> 2. Vessels <HI>belong∣ing to the</HI> States <HI>of the</HI> United Provinces, <HI>the</HI> one <HI>named the</HI> Vogukay, <HI>and the</HI> other, <HI>the</HI> Goude Real; <HI>and a</HI> Busse <HI>taken some of our Subjects: Our will and pleasure is, that you command them to be forthwith restored unto the hands of</HI> James Davidson, <HI>or to the</HI> Masters <HI>of the same Ships who are now in</HI> Scotland, <HI>to require them: and withal, that express order be given, that none of our Sub∣jects presume, upon whatsoever</HI> Pretext <HI>or</HI> Commis∣sion, <HI>to take or molest any Ship or Boat belonging to the said</HI> States, <HI>under all</HI> highest pains. <HI>This</HI>
<PB N="46" REF="27"/>Letter was dated the 21. of <HI>August,</HI> 1661.</P>
<P>There was <HI>another Letter</HI> written by his Majesty, 5 <HI>July,</HI> 1662. directed to the <HI>Earl</HI> of <HI>Middleton,</HI> then his Majesties <HI>Commissioner,</HI> making mention of his former Letter, and then adding;</P>
<P><HI>But soon after, upon an humble</HI> Petition <HI>presen∣ted to</HI> Us, <HI>and our</HI> Privy Council <HI>of</HI> England, <HI>by some pretending interest in the said Ships: We ap∣pointed our</HI> Council <HI>to examine the Truth of what was alleadged, and to certifie the same to Ʋs; and in the mean time, to cause the said Ships, with all their materials, to be secured till our farther pleasure. And now, they having examined the whole business, and having reported the same to Ʋs, upon conside∣ration of the whole matter: We do require you, that the said</HI> 2. Vessels, <HI>with all their</HI> materials, <HI>be fourth-with restored to</HI> James Davidson, <HI>or to the</HI> Masters <HI>of the said</HI> Ships, <HI>who do attend to receive them: Of which, expecting your performance, We bid you farewel.</HI></P>
<P>That the <HI>Magistrate</HI> of <HI>Edinborough</HI> did any violence; or that the <HI>Master</HI> was constrained to content <HI>Capt. Wutworth</HI> after the Ship had been a second time plundered, was never complained of to his Majesty, and therefore is not like to be <HI>true.</HI> And seeing the King did so readily order <HI>restitu∣tion,</HI> it seems a groundless complaint.</P>
<P><HI>William Mumma,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>27.</HI></NOTE> and his <HI>Associates,</HI> Merchants of <HI>Amster∣dam,</HI> do say, that one of their <HI>ships</HI> named the <HI>Hercules,</HI> (<HI>David Wouters,</HI> Master) departing from St. <HI>Sebastians, anno</HI> 1657. to go to St. <HI>Lucar</HI> and <HI>Cadiz,</HI> was the 14 of <HI>August</HI> in the <HI>same year,</HI> taken and detained by the said Captain <HI>John Stoakes,</HI> who took out all the <HI>Merchandize</HI> laden upon her,
<PB N="47" REF="27"/>without giving him any reasonable satisfaction for his <HI>Freight;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">See for the An∣swer to this, <HI>pag.</HI> 44.</NOTE> onely that the said <HI>Commander</HI> paid him 1500 <HI>Ry∣als of</HI> 8. and no more. The said <HI>Mumma</HI> and his <HI>Associates</HI> do pretend that they ought to be re-imbursed of their <HI>Ex∣pences, Damages</HI> and <HI>Interests.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Albert Lemmerman</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> says, that in <HI>Octob.</HI> 1655.<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>28.</HI></NOTE> one of the ships named the <HI>St. James,</HI> of the burthen of 300 <HI>Tuns,</HI> (<HI>Aaron Martin,</HI> Master) coming from <HI>Porto</HI> in <HI>Portu∣gal,</HI> laden with <HI>Tobacco, Sugars, Shumack,</HI> and <HI>Elephants Teeth,</HI> having sprung a Leak at Sea by <HI>foul weather,</HI> and being there∣by made incapable of prosecuting her Voyage; the said Ma∣ster of the Ship (to avoid a further danger) ran ashore upon the Coast of <HI>Arundel;</HI> and being there busie in unlading the Ship of some of her choicest Goods, an Officer came to him, and commanded him presently to leave his Ship, not permit∣ting him to carry any thing away with him. That the said <HI>Master</HI> and <HI>Mariners</HI> being thus constrained to leave the said Ship and Goods, there fell upon them presently a great num∣ber of the Country people, who by the <HI>order,</HI> or at least with the <HI>consent</HI> of the <HI>Officer,</HI> pillaged the Ship, carried away all the <HI>Merchandizes,</HI> and took away the <HI>Cordage, Rigging,</HI> and all to the very <HI>bolts</HI> and <HI>nails,</HI> leaving the very <HI>hulk</HI> of the Ship worth nothing. And though the said Master made his complaint of this barbarous proceeding, and in persuit of the business spent a great deal of his time and money; and though the <HI>Ministers</HI> of <HI>State</HI> and the <HI>Admiralty</HI> of <HI>England</HI> were fully convinced of the reason of his complaint; yet so it is, that the said <HI>Lemmerman</HI> could never obtain the least sa∣tisfaction, either by way of <HI>Justice</HI> or <HI>otherwise,</HI> but was con∣tinually put off with delays and excuses.</P>
<P>As to the 28. <HI>Article,</HI> it is <HI>Answered;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 28.</NOTE> That it may be very well so; and the parties may escape with so foul an Act, unless a <HI>complaint</HI> had been made against some <HI>particular persons</HI> of them by <HI>name,</HI> that they might have been proceeded a∣gainst, and prosecuted according to the Law of the
<PB N="48" REF="28"/><HI>Admiralty,</HI> which hath certain Rules to proceed by against such Offendors; yet we do find in the <HI>Court</HI> of <HI>Admiralty,</HI> a complaint entered; upon which a <HI>commission</HI> of <HI>Inquiry,</HI> issued forth for discovery of such persons as had done such violence, but can find no return thereof, so that it seemeth no such discovery could be made.</P>
<P><HI>Peter Pouilly,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Preten. Art. <HI>29.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Jerome Boshe,</HI> the <HI>Widow</HI> of <HI>Heertgen Johnson,</HI> the <HI>Heirs</HI> of <HI>Daniel Johnson,</HI> Merchants of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> do all say, that it is very true, that one of their Ships named the St. <HI>Nicholas,</HI> (of which Baron <HI>Claessen Spierdyck</HI> was Master) co∣ming in <HI>January</HI> 1657. from the <HI>Isle</HI> of St. <HI>Vincent,</HI> was taken by an <HI>English Fregat</HI> call'd the <HI>Mackdethem,</HI> and was delivered to <HI>Admiral Blake:</HI> That the same Ship being carried to <HI>Lis∣bon,</HI> was there unladen of all her Merchandize, part whereof was sent to <HI>London,</HI> and the rest sold with the Ship it self at <HI>Lisbon.</HI> The same Ship and goods being reclaimed by the said Merchants in the month of <HI>December</HI> in the same year, 1657. after long and painful pursuits, the said Goods were declared free and exempt from all confiscation, by two successive sentences of the <HI>High Court of Admiralty</HI> of <HI>England,</HI> the <HI>one</HI> of the 17 of <HI>January,</HI> and the <HI>other</HI> on the 20 of <HI>Octo∣ber,</HI> 1659. That there being made in <HI>England,</HI> an exact ac∣compt of the proceeding upon the sale of the said Ship and Goods, it was found to amount to the sum of 11407 l. 3. s. 9d. <HI>sterling:</HI> (making 120 <HI>m. Florens</HI>) And forasmuch as the said Merchants could never enjoy the effects of the said <HI>sentence,</HI> nor obtain any <HI>satisfaction;</HI> They pretend that they may de∣mand the <HI>same summe,</HI> by vertue of the said <HI>sentence;</HI> with the <HI>Expenses, Damages,</HI> and <HI>Interests.</HI></P>
<P>To the <HI>complaint</HI> of <HI>Peter Ravilli,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Ans.</HI> 29.</NOTE> and others, set forth in the 29. <HI>Article,</HI> it may receive the same Answer as is made to the complaint of the said <HI>Vanhulten,</HI> upon the 21 <HI>Article.</HI></P>
<PB N="49" REF="28"/>
<P><HI>Lawrence Kettles,</HI> Merchant of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> saith,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 30.</NOTE> That in <HI>May</HI> 1659. his Ship named the <HI>King David,</HI> (<HI>Oche Alberts</HI> of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inlopen, Master</HI>) laden with <HI>Salt</HI> at St. <HI>Ʋvall,</HI> and bound for <HI>Dronton</HI> in <HI>Norway,</HI> was taken and carried to <HI>Dunkirk,</HI> by Captain <HI>Lonis de Hay</HI></P>
<P>To the 30. <HI>Article,</HI> We answer,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answ.</HI> 30.</NOTE> that the Captain was neither an <HI>English Subject,</HI> nor had any <HI>English Commission,</HI> and therefore the <HI>English</HI> cannot be re∣sponsible for his action.</P>
<P><HI>William Johnson Brunan</HI> saith,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 31.</NOTE> That in the Moneth of <HI>Aprill,</HI> 1659. his Ship named the <HI>Black Raven (James John∣son Vanderschelling, Master)</HI> coming from <HI>Rochel</HI> laden with <HI>Salt</HI> was taken in the <HI>Channel</HI> by an <HI>English man of Warr,</HI> called <HI>John Jaquerson hill.</HI> That the said <HI>ship</HI> being brought to <HI>Dunkirk</HI> the Governour released her by order of His Majesty, but she was afterward seized by Order of the <HI>Admiralty</HI> of <HI>England;</HI> so that the Master was constrain∣ed after the pursuit of one <HI>Moneth,</HI> to redeem his Ship with the summ of 3333 <HI>Livres</HI> 17 <HI>Solz.</HI></P>
<P>As to the 31. <HI>Article,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answ.</HI> 31.</NOTE> It is answered that the <HI>Ma∣ster</HI> of the Ship knew his <HI>Ship,</HI> or some of her <HI>Lading,</HI> to be subject or liable, in some respect, to <HI>Confiscati∣on,</HI> that he voluntarily would so redeem her; and <HI>for such voluntary act, no satisfaction can be required.</HI></P>
<P><HI>John Vanderhell</HI> and his <HI>Associates,</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 32.</NOTE> say that it is very true, that in the year 1659. the Ship named the <HI>Salamander (Albert Jaquerson, Master)</HI> coming from <HI>Mala∣ga</HI> to go to <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> was attaqued, taken and brought to <HI>Toulon</HI> in <HI>France,</HI> by an <HI>English man of Warr.</HI> That the <HI>Master</HI> and the <HI>Interessed</HI> having upon their complaint ob∣tained a Release, which was adjudged afterwards, That before she should be absolutely discharged, the Interessed should furnish the summ of <GAP DESC="blank" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP=" _____ "/> who
<PB N="50" REF="29"/>to get clear of the business, and to deliver themselves from this vexation, were necessitated to pay the said summ for <HI>Redemption</HI> and <HI>Runsome</HI> thereof. That the recovery of the money having been made by that Rule upon the <HI>Goods;</HI> and the <HI>Interessed</HI> having paid it at <HI>Toulon,</HI> could not yet obtain the effect of that <HI>Release,</HI> but were disap∣pointed of the <HI>Money,</HI> as also of the <HI>Ship</HI> and <HI>Goods.</HI></P>
<P>To the 32.<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answ.</HI> 32.</NOTE> <HI>Article,</HI> We say that seeing the <HI>Captain</HI> complained of, hath <HI>no name,</HI> nor the <HI>ransome</HI> preten∣ded to be paid for him, any <HI>summ,</HI> it may as well be a <HI>Barretry</HI> of the <HI>Master</HI> of the <HI>Salamander,</HI> as an <HI>act</HI> of an <HI>Englishman:</HI> but whosoever he was that took him, and whatsoever he had for composition, un∣doubtedly the owner of the <HI>Salamander</HI> knew he could justifie the capture, or they would not have compounded with him in the Ports of the <HI>French</HI> King, their good <HI>Allie,</HI> where they might have had <HI>justice</HI> against a <HI>Pyrate.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Benjamin Lanson,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 33.</NOTE> the son of <HI>Julien Lanson</HI> deceased, re∣presents that in the year 1655, certain <HI>Parliament ships</HI> took away out of the <HI>ship</HI> called the <HI>Medea (Horman Sue∣rinse, Master)</HI> these goods following, 92 <HI>Pipes</HI> of <HI>Oyl,</HI> 283. <HI>Chests</HI> of <HI>Soap;</HI> 8. <HI>Bales</HI> of <HI>Cotten;</HI> 102. <HI>Barrels</HI> of <HI>Sul∣phur;</HI> 14 <HI>Bales</HI> of <HI>Galls.</HI> All which belonged to the said <HI>Julien Lanson;</HI> and that the said goods were placed in manner of <HI>Sequestration</HI> in the hands of <HI>John Sparrow, Ri∣chard Hill, Richard Blackwell, Samuel Wilson, Humphrey Blake,</HI> and <HI>Robert Turpin;</HI> being all <HI>Commissioners</HI> established by the <HI>Admiralty</HI> for <HI>Prize good.</HI></P>
<P>That the 23. of <HI>December</HI> 1657. the very <HI>Admiralty</HI> it self ordered the said <HI>Commissioners</HI> to make <HI>restitution</HI> of the said <HI>goods,</HI> or of the monies raised thereupon, to the said <HI>Julien Lanson;</HI> But that notwithstanding a constant soli∣citation of three <HI>years</HI> continuance for a dispatch, the said <HI>Commissioners</HI> would not yet be perswaded to comply with the said <HI>sentence.</HI></P>
<PB N="51" REF="29"/>
<P>That in the year 1660. the said Commissioners were the <HI>second time</HI> formally condemned to the said <HI>restitution;</HI> there being likewise adjudged to the said <HI>Lanson</HI> upon his accompt then produced, the summ of 3385 <HI>pounds</HI> 2 <HI>shil∣lings</HI> and 10 <HI>pence, sterl.</HI> or 36000 <HI>Florens.</HI></P>
<P>Now in regard that the said <HI>Julien</HI> could never receive the benefit either of the <HI>one</HI> or the <HI>other sentence,</HI> he de∣mands it now with <HI>charges, damages,</HI> and <HI>interest.</HI></P>
<P>To the 33. <HI>Article</HI> we answer,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer</HI> 33.</NOTE> That the <HI>neat pro∣ceed</HI> of the <HI>goods</HI> therein mentioned, amounted to no more then 1841 <HI>pounds,</HI> and that they themselves at last, left the <HI>dispute</HI> undetermined: so that if they did not receive the fruit they expected from the said <HI>Decree,</HI> they may blame themselves for not making a more effectual <HI>prosecution.</HI></P>
<P><HI>William Belin de la Garde,</HI> Merchant of <HI>Amsterdam,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Artic.</HI> 34.</NOTE> saith that in the Moneth of <HI>May,</HI> 1655. some ships of the Parlia∣ment of <HI>England</HI> did carry to <HI>London</HI> a <HI>ship</HI> named <HI>the Hare in the Field (John Kin, Master:)</HI> and though by <HI>sentence</HI> of the High Court of <HI>Admiralty,</HI> it was declared, that <HI>three parts</HI> of the Goods should be discharged; to wit, 7 <HI>Bales</HI> of <HI>Linnen,</HI> 1 <HI>Bale of Yellow Linnen,</HI> 4 <HI>Cask of Mercery ware;</HI> all belonging to the said <HI>De la Garde:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">See for the Answer to this Pre∣tense, <HI>pa. 53.</HI></NOTE> And though in pur∣suance of the said sentence, most of the said Goods were restored to him, yet so it is, that a great part of those Goods were quite spoyled, and the rest so perished and damnified, that they lost much of their just value.</P>
<P>The same person complains again, <MILESTONE N="35"/> that one of his ships called the <HI>Cross of Jerusalem</HI> (<HI>Peter Johnson Master,</HI> Native of <HI>Purmerent</HI>) being set upon and taken by a Vessel of the Parliament of <HI>England,</HI> was in <HI>June</HI> 1655. carried to <HI>Ply∣mouth,</HI> and in <HI>August</HI> following, to <HI>London.</HI> That the said <HI>La Guarde</HI> having represented (by certain persons whom he authorized) the injury and violence that had been
<PB N="52" REF="30"/>done to the said ship; and having demanded the release thereof, the Court of <HI>Admiralty</HI> finding themselves con∣vinced by the force of Reason and Truth, did agree to re∣lease her by a <HI>sentence</HI> of the 18. of <HI>June</HI> 1656. and did Ordain that the said ship should be restored to the said <HI>De la Garde,</HI> together with the <HI>freight</HI> of the goods that were laden on her, according to the <HI>Bills</HI> of <HI>Lading</HI> that were produced. And forasmuch as the said <HI>De la Garde</HI> could not enjoy the effect of the said <HI>sentence,</HI> but onely in part: And that during the time of <HI>three Moneths,</HI> while they said ship lay seized, he could not onely make no pro∣fit, but was likewise obliged to pay the <HI>Seamens</HI> wages, and to entertain them with <HI>Victuals,</HI> undergoing a great expence before he could obtain the <HI>sentence;</HI> for which he demands to be indemnified. The said <HI>De la Garde</HI> be∣ing <HI>interessed</HI> not onely in the <HI>ship</HI> and <HI>freight,</HI> but also in <HI>two Parcels</HI> the <HI>one</HI> of 65, and <HI>the other</HI> of 3 <HI>Bales</HI> of <HI>Linnen</HI> of <HI>Roan,</HI> did in fine obtain that they might be also com∣prehended in the said <HI>Restitution</HI> adjudged him by <HI>two se∣veral sentences,</HI> the <HI>one</HI> of the 25 of <HI>February,</HI> and <HI>the other</HI> of the 4. of <HI>July</HI> 1656. And forasmuch as all the said Merchandizes were not delivered to the said <HI>De la Garde,</HI> nor to his <HI>Assurers,</HI> to whose use he had made over the pro∣fit of the same: And also that by the long seizure, and o∣ther mischances that happened thereupon, their <HI>value</HI> was <HI>diminished</HI> by <HI>one quarter:</HI> Whereas on the contrary, if the said <HI>English</HI> ship had not done them this Injury there had been got at least 30. <HI>per cent.</HI> so that the said <HI>Complainant</HI> doth believe that he may demand to be <HI>Indemnified.</HI></P>
<P>The same <HI>De la Garde</HI> doth complain that one of his ships called the <HI>Golden Fortune (Francis Johnson</HI> of <HI>Amster∣dam,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 36.</NOTE> <HI>Master</HI>) was taken in <HI>July</HI> 1655. and carried to <HI>Poully</HI> by Captain <HI>Green,</HI> being then in Commission and under Oath to the <HI>State</HI> of <HI>England;</HI> and forasmuch as the said <HI>De la Garde</HI> did make it evidently to appear, that when the said ship was taken and reclaimed, the <HI>propriety</HI> was solely in himself: and that the said Captain had extream∣ly abused his <HI>Commission,</HI> by vertue of which he could not
<PB N="53" REF="30"/><HI>Arm</HI> himself but against the <HI>Subjects</HI> of the King of <HI>France.</HI> The said <HI>High Court</HI> of <HI>Admiralty</HI> by their <HI>sentence</HI> of the 28. of <HI>July</HI> 1655. did not onely decree a full release of the said ship, but did also order, That the said <HI>Henry Green</HI> and all others, should restore the said ship with her apper∣tinences, without any reserve; and also to pay to the <HI>Owners</HI> the <HI>freight</HI> which the Master of the said ship was to have had for the <HI>carriage</HI> of the said <HI>Goods</HI> that were found aboard her, and taken by the said <HI>Henry Green.</HI> And though according to the said <HI>sentence,</HI> the said <HI>restitution</HI> ought to have been effective, and the payment made; yet so it is, that the said <HI>freight</HI> was not <HI>paid,</HI> nor the <HI>ship restored</HI> until they had taken away, and pillaged more of what did belong to her.</P>
<P>The same person doth further complain,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 37.</NOTE> That in <HI>Au∣gust</HI> 1655. one of his ships named the <HI>St. James</HI> (<HI>Peter John∣son</HI> of <HI>Amsterdam, Master</HI>) returning from the <HI>Maderas</HI> to∣ward <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> was assaulted, taken, and carried to <HI>Dover,</HI> by an <HI>English</HI> Captain (<HI>Edward Goodwin</HI> by vertue of a Commission from <HI>England.</HI> That the <HI>High Court</HI> of <HI>Admiralty,</HI> being duly informed of the injustice of the <HI>Prize,</HI> did give release to the said ship, and by a <HI>sentence</HI> of the 28. of <HI>November,</HI> 1655. ordered the said <HI>Edward Goodwin</HI> to make speedy and full restitution, which was not done; and the said <HI>De la Garde</HI> did not enjoy the ef∣fect of the said <HI>sentence,</HI> but onely in part; the restitution having been made by little and little, in <HI>four Moneths</HI> time, and therefore he demands his damages.</P>
<P>To the 34, 35, 36, and 37. <HI>Articles,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answ. to</HI> 34, 35, 36. &amp; 37. <HI>Art.</HI></NOTE> The <HI>com∣plaints</HI> therein contained, are to be answered as to the <HI>complaints</HI> of <HI>Van Hulten,</HI> set forth in the 21 <HI>Article; viz.</HI> that there is no <HI>complaint</HI> entered in the <HI>Admi∣ralty</HI> that can be found; whereas not onely <HI>complaint,</HI> ought to have been made, but likewise <HI>proof</HI> of the <HI>Truth</HI> of such <HI>complaint,</HI> which being not done, there
<PB N="54" REF="31"/>can be no cause of <HI>Complaint</HI> now made of the want of <HI>Justice,</HI> himself not prosecuting any farther to have the said <HI>Sentence</HI> put in due <HI>Execution.</HI> Nor can they make any <HI>Demand</HI> here, in regard the ship was taken in the time when there was <HI>Hostility</HI> between <HI>France,</HI> and <HI>Cromwell,</HI> and the said <HI>L'Guard</HI> being a <HI>French-man.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Godfrey Wassemburgh</HI> dwelling at <HI>Amsterdam,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 38.</NOTE> complains that an <HI>English</HI> ship, commanded by Captain <HI>Christopher Mennys,</HI> did in the Year, 1658. near the <HI>Barbadoes</HI> take the ship called the <HI>Charity,</HI> which he carried with her lading to <HI>Jamaica,</HI> where he caused the said Goods by Order of the <HI>Admiralty</HI> of <HI>England</HI> residing in that <HI>Island,</HI> to be dischar∣ged, and amongst the rest, <HI>two Cases of fine Linnen,</HI> belong∣ing to the said <HI>Wassemburgh.</HI> And further, that since <HI>Oliver Cromwell,</HI> who took upon him at that time the Stile of <HI>Pro∣tectour</HI> of <HI>England,</HI> knowing that the said <HI>ship,</HI> the <HI>Charity</HI> was an <HI>English Vessel</HI> set out by <HI>English Merchants,</HI> some li∣ving at <HI>London,</HI> and others in this <HI>Country,</HI> to whom the Trade of <HI>Barbadees</HI> was not forbidden, did declare, that the said <HI>ship</HI> and <HI>goods</HI> in her were free, so that a good part of the said <HI>Merchandizes</HI> was restord to the owners, Never∣theless, the said <HI>Wassemburgh</HI> could never obtain restitution of those <HI>two Cases</HI> of <HI>fine Linnen.</HI></P>
<P>To the 38. <HI>Article;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answ <HI>38.</HI></NOTE> We Answer, That it is true, that <HI>Captain Mennys</HI> did take such a ship which was af∣terwards restored entire, as it was brought in, save only what might be plundered by the <HI>Seamen:</HI> (which no care can prevent) but by the <HI>Act</HI> of <HI>Navigation;</HI> the whole <HI>ship</HI> and <HI>goods</HI> ought to have been <HI>Confiscated,</HI> but the <HI>Intention</HI> of the <HI>Law</HI> was deluded by some <HI>En∣glish Men,</HI> pretending a <HI>Propriety</HI> in the goods, who never since made any demand of the goods menti∣oned in <HI>this Article.</HI></P>
<PB N="55" REF="31"/>
<P><HI>John Van Wickford,</HI> and his <HI>Associates,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 39.</NOTE> do complain, that one of their (<HI>ships</HI> called <HI>Campen</HI> was attacqued, taken, and carried to <HI>Jamaica</HI> by <HI>Three English Fregats,</HI> and that the said <HI>ship</HI> was since released after it was known that it was not laden with any goods of <HI>Contrabanda:</HI> But in the mean while there was taken out of her a Quantity of <HI>goods,</HI> and by reason of this stop, the <HI>ship</HI> could not accomplish her <HI>Voyage,</HI> for which they demand <HI>Satisfaction.</HI></P>
<P>To this 39. <HI>Article,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answ. <HI>39.</HI></NOTE> we Answer as to the <HI>Preceding Complaint.</HI></P>
<P><HI>William Van Meekerel</HI> and his <HI>Associates,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 40.</NOTE> Proprietours of the <HI>ship</HI> called the <HI>Peace,</HI> and of her <HI>Cargazon,</HI> do complain that on the 26 of <HI>Feb.</HI> 1655. the said <HI>ship</HI> having taken in some <HI>Slaves</HI> upon the <HI>Coast</HI> of <HI>Guyne,</HI> and that she had put them off for <HI>Sugars</HI> at the <HI>Barbadoes,</HI> where she had also tra∣ded for <HI>Elephants Teeth,</HI> and other <HI>Merchandize,</HI> was attac∣qued upon the open <HI>Seas,</HI> and carried to the <HI>Barbadoes</HI> by a <HI>Parliament Vessel of England,</HI> of the <HI>Squadron of Admiral Penn.</HI> And although the <HI>Interressed</HI> made their <HI>Complaint,</HI> and re∣presented the <HI>Injuries</HI> and <HI>Wrongs</HI> that had been done them unto <HI>Cromwell;</HI> which Complaints were from time to time seconded by the continual Instances of the <HI>Embassadours</HI> by <HI>Order</HI> from the <HI>States,</HI> yet so it is, that they could never ob∣tain any <HI>satisfaction,</HI> neither for <HI>ship</HI> nor <HI>goods,</HI> for which they now demand it.</P>
<P>To the 40. <HI>Article,</HI> we Answer, That the said ship,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answ. <HI>40.</HI></NOTE> the <HI>Peace,</HI> was taken as trading contrary to the <HI>Act</HI> for <HI>Navigation,</HI> and according to the practise of the <HI>Holland West India Company;</HI> who constantly give <HI>Letters of Mart</HI> to all their ships, to take Vessels that trade to any of their <HI>Plantations.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Abraham,</HI> and <HI>John Clawsen Ritsert, Merchants,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 41.</NOTE> dwelling at <HI>Rotterdam,</HI> do represent, that the ships, <HI>Red Lion,</HI> and <HI>Gol∣den
<PB N="56" REF="32"/>Port,</HI> upon each of which they had <HI>Ensured</HI> 2000 <HI>Flo∣rens</HI> departing from <HI>Bourdeaux</HI> in <HI>May</HI> 1661. and arriving at <HI>New found Land,</HI> the 14. of <HI>June</HI> following, were there ta∣ken by an <HI>English ship of War,</HI> called the <HI>Jersey; Richard Hacks Captain,</HI> who pillaged her, and took away her best, and most Valuable Goods and sent her afterward to <HI>Ports∣mouth</HI> And though upon the 5. of <HI>October</HI> following, the same <HI>ship</HI> and <HI>Goods</HI> were declared <HI>free;</HI> this yet not∣withstanding, the Restitution was not made but in part, the Goods that were taken away remaining in the hands of those that took them. Now forasmuch as in the Quality of being <HI>Ensured,</HI> they were condemned the 30. of <HI>April</HI> 1661. by two several <HI>sentences</HI> of the Commissioners for <HI>Sea Affairs,</HI> and <HI>Assurance</HI> of <HI>Rotterdam,</HI> to <HI>re-imburse,</HI> and <HI>indemnifie</HI> the <HI>interessed</HI> in proportion to what they <HI>signed,</HI> for the loss that they have suffered upon the said Merchandizes: And that the said loss hath been since valued by <HI>Arbitratours,</HI> upon the <HI>ship,</HI> the <HI>Red Lion,</HI> at 44. and the <HI>ship,</HI> the <HI>Golden Port,</HI> at 38. <HI>per Cent.</HI> They demand Satisfaction.</P>
<P>To the 41. <HI>Article,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answ. <HI>41.</HI></NOTE> We say that the ship was taken trading contrary to the <HI>Act</HI> of <HI>Navigation,</HI> and there∣fore <HI>Legally Confiscate;</HI> and if any thing was restored; it was of <HI>Grace,</HI> and though the <HI>Interessed</HI> might have recourse upon their <HI>Assurers,</HI> who were obliged to Indemnifie the <HI>Assured</HI> against all kind of <HI>Losses,</HI> yet the <HI>Insurers</HI> had no <HI>colour</HI> of <HI>pretence</HI> against the <HI>En∣glish.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Paul Timmers,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 42.</NOTE> and his <HI>Associates</HI> dwelling at <HI>Rotterdam,</HI> do say, that one of their ships, named the <HI>Stroy Yoncker (Jum Alberts Master)</HI> coming for <HI>Bourdeaux</HI> laden with <HI>Wines,</HI> and <HI>Aquavitae,</HI> was in the <HI>month</HI> of <HI>July,</HI> 1661. <HI>attacqued,</HI> and <HI>taken</HI> near the <HI>Maaz,</HI> and carried to <HI>Dover</HI> by an <HI>English Captain,</HI> named <HI>John Penny;</HI> and though it were easie to make it appear Evidently that the said <HI>ship</HI> and <HI>goods</HI> were taken from the <HI>Owners,</HI> without <HI>Justice</HI> and <HI>Reason;</HI> so that
<PB N="57" REF="32"/>they ought to have promised <HI>Restitution</HI> without delay, es∣pecially such earnest and pressing Instances being made for the same: And that the <HI>Injustice</HI> of this <HI>Action</HI> was suffici∣ently represented to the <HI>High Court</HI> of <HI>Admiralty,</HI> who ought to have taken <HI>Cognizance</HI> of it; Nevertheless, the said <HI>Interessed,</HI> after they had taken much pains, and been at much expence, were obliged to <HI>Compound</HI> with the said <HI>Captain Penny,</HI> upon very unjust Conditions, and to give him 200 l. <HI>sterling,</HI> though the <HI>Wine</HI> were in part <HI>spoiled,</HI> and that the rest had lost the <HI>half</HI> of its value, after so long a time.</P>
<P>To the 42. <HI>Article,</HI> We say,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answ. <HI>42.</HI></NOTE> That if the <HI>Complaynant</HI> had not the <HI>patience</HI> to attend the <HI>due proceedings</HI> of the <HI>Admiralty,</HI> for a <HI>decision</HI> of his <HI>pretended right,</HI> but <HI>Anti∣cipated</HI> it by a <HI>voluntary composition,</HI> with the <HI>Captain;</HI> It must necessarily be concluded that he was <HI>conscious</HI> of his <HI>guilt,</HI> and therefore durst not stand the <HI>Tryal.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Simon Tunemans,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Artic.</HI> 43.</NOTE> and his <HI>Associates,</HI> dwelling at <HI>Rotter∣dam,</HI> do <HI>Complain,</HI> that having in <HI>July,</HI> 1662. sent one of their ships named the <HI>Swan,</HI> to the <HI>fishing</HI> of <HI>Whales</HI> in <HI>Green-Land,</HI> was hindred from the <HI>beginning</HI> of his <HI>fishing,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">See <HI>58.</HI> for this Answ.</NOTE> and so evilly entreated by an <HI>English Man of War</HI> that took all his <HI>Shallopps, Cordage,</HI> and <HI>Nets, Oares,</HI> and <HI>Sails,</HI> and all his ne∣cessary Instruments; that finding himself no longer able to continue his <HI>fishing,</HI> he was constrained to retire, and return to <HI>Rotterdam,</HI> for which he demands <HI>Indempnity.</HI></P>
<P>The same doth further represent,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 44.</NOTE> that another of his ships named the <HI>Collier,</HI> (<HI>Gerard Cornelisen</HI> Master) com∣ing from <HI>Bourdeaux,</HI> was taken by an <HI>English Man of War,</HI> and carried to <HI>Portsmouth;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">See <HI>59.</HI> for this Answ.</NOTE> and he alledgeth, that the <HI>da∣mage</HI> he received in that <HI>Encounter</HI> ought to be made good to him, <HI>cum omni causâ &amp; accessione.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Henry Van Leith,</HI> and his <HI>Associates,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 45.</NOTE> dwelling at <HI>Dort.</HI> doe
<PB N="58" REF="33"/>represent that in the year, 1661. one of their ships, called the <HI>Prince William, (John Werbeck</HI> Master) being at <HI>Anchor</HI> at the entrance of the <HI>Harbour</HI> at <HI>Plymouth,</HI> under the <HI>Canon</HI> of the <HI>Castle,</HI> was attacqued by the <HI>Burgesses,</HI> and <HI>Inhabi∣tants</HI> of that place, who took from him his <HI>Sails, Cables, Cor∣dage,</HI> and other necessaries. That the said <HI>Burgesses</HI> not daring to bring the said ship into any Harbour, because they knew there was none could approve of the <HI>Pyracy;</HI> extorted from the Master of the ship, by way of <HI>Ransom</HI> the summ of 26l. 10. <HI>shil. sterling.</HI></P>
<P>To the 43,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer to</HI> 43, 44, 45.</NOTE> 44, 45. <HI>Articles,</HI> we can give no An∣swer, untill the <HI>Persons</HI> complained of, be <HI>Named,</HI> and the <HI>Circumstances</HI> more <HI>Explained.</HI></P>
<P>The said <HI>Henry Van Leith,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Arti</HI> 46.</NOTE> and his <HI>Associates</HI> say yet fur∣ther, that on the 2. of <HI>June</HI> following, the same ship being Arriv'd before the same Harbour of <HI>Plymouth</HI> was again At∣taqued by a Captain, named <HI>Stephen Evers,</HI> apparently at the Instigation of the said <HI>Burgers;</HI> who took him and car∣ried him into <HI>Ireland,</HI> and though they made the most Active Instances, and all possible endeavours for it, yet so it is, that they could not obtain the Restitution of the <HI>ship</HI> or <HI>Merchandizes,</HI> nor the <HI>value</HI> of the <HI>one,</HI> or of the <HI>other.</HI></P>
<P>To the 46. <HI>Article,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answ. <HI>46.</HI></NOTE> <HI>That Stephen Evers</HI> was no <HI>En∣glish Man,</HI> nor had any <HI>English Commission,</HI> and there∣fore we cannot Answer for <HI>Him.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Proprietours</HI> of the ship named the <HI>steeple of Dort,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Arti.</HI> 47.</NOTE> as also <HI>Jacob Vandergraff, Isaac Biesheuvel,</HI> and their <HI>Associates,</HI> as <HI>Freightours,</HI> and <HI>Proprietours</HI> of the goods, do say, that the said ship being sunk at <HI>Harwich,</HI> the <HI>Burgers</HI> of the <HI>Town,</HI> and the <HI>Souldiers</HI> of the <HI>Garrison</HI> of the Castle, instead of succouring and comforting the <HI>Master</HI> of the said ship in his misfortune, as they were obliged, did cut his <HI>Sails</HI> and <HI>Cordage,</HI> and put him quite out of condition to set sail; and
<PB N="59" REF="33"/>after this, they pillag'd his <HI>ship,</HI> and took away the goods that were laden upon her; so that the <HI>Interessed</HI> could not recover any thing, neither in <HI>part,</HI> nor in <HI>whole,</HI> notwith∣standing all the endeavours they used; so that it cannot be denyed but that they ought to be <HI>Indemnified,</HI> with <HI>Costs,</HI> and <HI>Interests.</HI></P>
<P>To the 47. <HI>Article,</HI> That no <HI>time</HI> is <HI>mentioned,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answ. <HI>47.</HI></NOTE> nor <HI>persons named</HI> that are complained of; nor is it <HI>alleadg∣ed,</HI> that any <HI>Appeal</HI> was made for <HI>Justice.</HI></P>
<P><HI>John Pychen, Theodore Van herweere,</HI> and their <HI>Associates,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Arti.</HI> 48.</NOTE> all <HI>Merchants,</HI> dwelling at <HI>Dort,</HI> do say, that one of their ships called the <HI>Prince,</HI> whereof <HI>(Laurence Davids Captain)</HI> who was taken near the <HI>Caribes,</HI> by <HI>five English ships,</HI> and brought to the <HI>Barbadoes,</HI> under pretence that the said <HI>Lau∣rence Davids</HI> might discover the design the <HI>English</HI> had to surprize the <HI>Island</HI> of <HI>Jamaica.</HI> And forasmuch as by rea∣son thereof, the said ship could not finish her Voyage, they thereby lost the profit which they did infallibly believe to make, as well upon the <HI>Cargason,</HI> as upon the <HI>Return;</HI> and on the <HI>contrary,</HI> by that hinderance, they suffered great <HI>Losses,</HI> and pretend to be <HI>Indemnified.</HI></P>
<P>To the 48. <HI>Article,</HI> It is Answered,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answ. <HI>48.</HI></NOTE> That the <HI>Com∣plainant</HI> doth not affirm that ever he made any de∣mand of <HI>Satisfaction;</HI> nor have we any <HI>Evidence</HI> that he <HI>received</HI> any <HI>Injury,</HI> and therefore we think the <HI>Ar∣ticle</HI> to be <HI>frivolous,</HI> and out of time.</P>
<P><HI>Albert Arentsen, Merchant,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Arti.</HI> 49.</NOTE> dwelling at the <HI>Brill</HI> complains that about the <HI>middle</HI> of <HI>Sep</HI> 1659, a bark of his serving for the <HI>fishing</HI> of <HI>Herrings</HI> did meet between the <HI>Maaz,</HI> and the <HI>Sea,</HI> an <HI>English ship,</HI> commanded by one <HI>Captain Hamil∣ton,</HI> who in a <HI>frolick,</HI> without any offence in any manner offered him, <HI>Boarded</HI> him, <HI>took</HI> him, and carried him to <HI>Yar∣mouth.</HI></P>
<PB N="60" REF="34"/>
<P>To the 49.51,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answer <HI>49.</HI></NOTE> 52, 53, 54, 56, 61, 62, 63, 64, 68, 70, 71, 72. We Affirm the several Actions therein mentioned, were not done by <HI>English Com∣missions;</HI> and if they were done by any <HI>Foraign Com∣missions, Portugal, Swedes,</HI> or any <HI>Other;</HI> we are no more responsible for them, then the <HI>Hollanders</HI> would be for those <HI>Hundred Ships</HI> and their <HI>Charges</HI> that were taken by <HI>Hollands Ships,</HI> and <HI>Persons,</HI> from the <HI>English,</HI> by <HI>Spanish Commissions,</HI> in the time of the <HI>late Warr</HI> be∣tween <HI>the King of Spain,</HI> and <HI>Cromwell.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Leonard Licoghton,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 50.</NOTE> and <HI>John Ham, Merchants,</HI> dwelling at <HI>Enchuysen,</HI> do complain that in <HI>August.</HI> 1660. an <HI>English Captain,</HI> (called <HI>George Wotworth</HI>) did seize at <HI>Haymouth</HI> near <HI>Berwick,</HI> and carried away, <HI>two</HI> ships for <HI>Herring fishing</HI> be∣longing to them. The <HI>One,</HI> the <HI>Prince of Aurange</HI> (<HI>Femme Claessen</HI> Master) and the <HI>Other,</HI> the <HI>Three Golden Herrings,</HI> Commanded by the <HI>Master-Mate, Peter Johnson,</HI> which were unladen, and their <HI>Cargason</HI> sent to <HI>London,</HI> where it was sold; It is true, that after great instance and long so∣licitation, the Commander of <HI>Haymouth,</HI> did release the said ships, and referred them to <HI>Captain Bronsert,</HI> of <HI>Mune∣kedam,</HI> but they never got the rest, nor satisfaction for the <HI>Herrings, Netts, Cordage, Anchors, Victualls,</HI> and other ne∣cessaries of the ships which were utterly lost; as also a 9<SUP>th</SUP> <HI>part</HI> of the said ships, which was condemned by the <HI>High-Court of Admiralty</HI> of the <HI>North-Holland,</HI> as an <HI>acknowledge∣ment,</HI> and that without prejudice to the <HI>Charge</HI> which the said <HI>Captains</HI> have been at to bring home the ships into their Country.</P>
<P>To the 50. <HI>Article,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answ. <HI>50.</HI></NOTE> We never <HI>heard</HI> of the <HI>Two Ships</HI> therein named, and <HI>less</HI> of the <HI>Men,</HI> called <HI>Com∣missioners</HI> of <HI>Haymouth,</HI> who are said to have released them. <HI>Haymouth</HI> being a very small <HI>Village,</HI> consist∣ing of a <HI>Dozen</HI> or <HI>Sixteen Fisher-Mens Hovells.</HI></P>
<PB N="61" REF="34"/>
<P><HI>Leonard Licoghton,</HI> and <HI>John Ham,</HI> do represent further,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Arti.</HI> 51.</NOTE> that in the Year 1659. one of their ships, namely the <HI>Forest,</HI> (<HI>Herman Janssen</HI> of <HI>Enchuysen, Master</HI>) was attacqued, ta∣ken,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">See for the Answer to these Pre∣tenses, <HI>pa. 60.</HI></NOTE> carried away, and sold, at <HI>Yarmouth,</HI> by an <HI>English Man of War</HI> and that the ship was likewise sold with her <HI>Herrings, Salt, Caske,</HI> and other necessary <HI>Instruments</HI> for <HI>fishing,</HI> to one <HI>George England Alderman</HI> of <HI>Yarmouth,</HI> in∣teressed in the said <HI>Man of War.</HI></P>
<P>The same person saith further,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Arti.</HI> 52.</NOTE> that in the year 1660. the same <HI>Man of War, (Wotworth)</HI> took one of his <HI>Barques</HI> at the <HI>Herring-fishing,</HI> named the <HI>Faith, (Cornelius Barentson Kelocker Master)</HI> and carried it to <HI>Montross</HI> in <HI>Scotland.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Peter Peterson, (Masters Mate)</HI> dwelling at <HI>Enchuysen,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Arti.</HI> 53.</NOTE> complains that in the Year 1659 he was taken with his ship named the <HI>Green Tree, fishing</HI> for <HI>Herrings,</HI> laden with seven <HI>Last</HI> and a half of <HI>Herrings,</HI> by an <HI>English ship,</HI> of which the <HI>Captain</HI> was called <HI>Cooler,</HI> who carried him to <HI>Ely.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Roemer Cant, Burgomaster,</HI> and <HI>Cornelius Mossel, Schepen</HI> of <HI>En¦chuysen,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Arti.</HI> 54.</NOTE> do represent, that in <HI>September</HI> 1655. a <HI>Man of Warr</HI> that went from <HI>Dunkirk,</HI> and was <HI>mann'd</HI> from <HI>Thence,</HI> took <HI>Two</HI> of their <HI>ships</HI> upon the Sea, <HI>fishing</HI> for <HI>Herrings,</HI> the <HI>One</HI> named the St. <HI>Peter,</HI> of which (<HI>Reyn Engëlse</HI> of <HI>Egmont</HI> was Master.) And the <HI>Other</HI> named the <HI>Turtle,</HI> (of which <HI>Cor∣nelius Janssen</HI> was Master;) which <HI>Two</HI> ships were carried to <HI>Dunkirk;</HI> That they have made very many pressing In∣stances for release of the said <HI>Two ships,</HI> but could obtaine nothing, onely it was permitted them to make an <HI>Agree∣ment;</HI> so that the said <HI>Interessed</HI> to obtain their <HI>release,</HI> were constrained to pay the <HI>summ</HI> of 5277. <HI>Livres,</HI> 3. <HI>Solz,</HI> of which they demand <HI>Restitution,</HI> with <HI>Indempnity,</HI> for the rest of their <HI>ships.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Cornelus Olphersen,</HI> dwelling at <HI>Enchuysen,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 55.</NOTE> Complains that in the Year, 1655. a ship of his named the <HI>Arms of
<PB N="62" REF="35"/>Nimmegen,</HI> of which <HI>Richard Trexe</HI> of <HI>Enchuysen</HI> was <HI>Master,</HI> coming from <HI>Roüen</HI> laden with <HI>French Goods,</HI> was taken in the <HI>Channel,</HI> by an <HI>English Captain</HI> (one <HI>Green.</HI>) That the <HI>Goods</HI> were declared <HI>Prize,</HI> but with express condition that the <HI>freight</HI> should be paid to the <HI>Master</HI> of the <HI>ship:</HI> And though in pursuance thereof, he ought to have received the said <HI>freight,</HI> and to be put into the condition he was in before he was taken, as to his <HI>Cordage, Anchors, Sails, Cables,</HI> and other <HI>necessaries</HI> of his <HI>ship,</HI> which the said <HI>Cap∣tain</HI> and his men had taken from him; yet so it is, that after a great deal of <HI>pains</HI> and <HI>solicitation,</HI> and <HI>expence,</HI> he never recovered more then 2000 <HI>Florens.</HI></P>
<P>To the 55. <HI>Article,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answ. <HI>55.</HI></NOTE> We say that the <HI>Complaynant</HI> had his <HI>freight adjudged</HI> him; and if it were not <HI>fully paid</HI> him, why did he <HI>accept</HI> of less, without <HI>appealing</HI> to the <HI>Court,</HI> who would have seen their own <HI>sen∣tence</HI> fully <HI>executed?</HI></P>
<P><HI>Gerard Seager,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense <HI>Art.</HI> 56.</NOTE> <HI>Burgomaster</HI> of <HI>Enchuysen</HI> and his <HI>Asso∣ciates, Owners</HI> of, and <HI>interessed</HI> in the ship called <HI>the Fortune,</HI> do say, That the said ship departing from the <HI>Texel</HI> on the 16 of <HI>December,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">See this Answ <HI>p. 60.</HI></NOTE> 1659. was about <HI>two days</HI> after met at Sea, and fallen foul upon by <HI>two other ships</HI> near the <HI>Isle of Wight;</HI> so that being very <HI>Leaky</HI> and unfit to pursue her Voyage, she was constrained to put into the <HI>first Harbour;</HI> and for avoiding present danger, took her Course for <HI>Weymouth</HI> in <HI>Portland,</HI> where being arrived in the <HI>Road,</HI> she cast Anchor, with intent to send out one to ask leave of the <HI>Governour</HI> before she entred the <HI>Port.</HI> Whereupon the 20. of <HI>December,</HI> in the <HI>morning,</HI> three <HI>English Vessels</HI> came directly to her; <HI>One</HI> of which was Commanded by Cap∣tain <HI>Peter Morell,</HI> who without having received any of∣fence, took her, pillaged her, and brought her to <HI>Dun∣kirk:</HI> where the <HI>Associates</HI> of the said <HI>Captain</HI> plundred her of all that was left, as <HI>Victuals, Cordage,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<PB N="63" REF="35"/>
<P><HI>Symon Semeynsse,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 57.</NOTE> <HI>Burgomaster</HI> of the said Town of <HI>En∣chuysen,</HI> and his <HI>Assiciates</HI> say that in <HI>September</HI> 1659. a ship of theirs serving in the <HI>Herring fishing,</HI> called the <HI>Aa∣ron, (John Arentsen, Master)</HI> coming from the <HI>Fishery,</HI> la∣den with about 44 <HI>Tun</HI> of <HI>Salt Herrings,</HI> and 10 <HI>Tun</HI> of <HI>Fresh Herrings,</HI> was attacqued and taken at Sea, and car∣ried to <HI>Yarmouth</HI> by an <HI>English man of War,</HI> called <HI>Alexan∣der Simmons.</HI> That the same <HI>Man of War</HI> having taken out of the said ship all the said <HI>Herrings,</HI> both <HI>fresh</HI> and <HI>salt;</HI> as also all the <HI>Sails</HI> and <HI>Cordage;</HI> after he had kept the said <HI>Master</HI> in <HI>Arrest</HI> 7 <HI>Moneths,</HI> so that he was utterly ruined; he constrained him to come to a <HI>Composition,</HI> and to oblige himself by the interposition on of one <HI>John Gardi∣ner</HI> to pay him the summ of 21 7 <HI>Florens,</HI> 2 <HI>Solz.</HI></P>
<P>To the 57. <HI>Article,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answ. <HI>57.</HI></NOTE> The <HI>Complainant</HI> confesseth he <HI>compounded</HI> with the <HI>Captain,</HI> and <HI>voluntarily agreed</HI> by the <HI>interposition</HI> of his <HI>own friend,</HI> and therefore can have no cause for <HI>complaint</HI> of <HI>Injustice</HI> done him.</P>
<P><HI>Heerge Peters Molenear,</HI> and his <HI>Associates,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 58.</NOTE> dwelling at <HI>Enchuysen,</HI> do say, that one of their ships called the <HI>Corn∣mill,</HI> of which <HI>Peter Cornelissen</HI> was <HI>Commander</HI> being arri∣ved in <HI>Greenland,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">See this Answ. <HI>p. 65.</HI></NOTE> was discovered the 6 of <HI>July</HI> 1662. far enough to the <HI>North</HI> from the remotest point of any part of the Coast, and 24 <HI>Leagues</HI> at least from the <HI>Bay Disco,</HI> by an <HI>English Fregat</HI> named the <HI>Mary,</HI> of which <HI>John Clarke</HI> was <HI>Captain.</HI> That the said <HI>Captain</HI> obliged the said Commander to come aboard him, where he kept him <HI>Prisoner</HI> 3 <HI>days</HI> and <HI>nights,</HI> without any reason, and not∣withstanding all the <HI>instances, intreaties,</HI> and <HI>desires,</HI> of the said Commander.</P>
<P>That after this the said <HI>Captain</HI> carried the said <HI>Com∣mander</HI> in his ship toward the <HI>Bay,</HI> where the <HI>English Ad∣miral</HI> lay, and would not dismiss him until he had taken
<PB N="64" REF="36"/>from him by force 4 <HI>Shallops,</HI> 12 <HI>Fishing Lines,</HI> 20 <HI>Nets,</HI> 8. <HI>Harpons,</HI> 4 <HI>Shallop sails,</HI> and all the <HI>Oars,</HI> and other ne∣cessaries for the whole <HI>Whale fishing,</HI> which cast him into such disorder, that in the most proper season of the <HI>Fish∣ing</HI> he was constrained to abandon it, and return home.</P>
<P><HI>Cornelius Peterson,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 59.</NOTE> <HI>Lowen,</HI> and <HI>Peter Adrianson Van Ley,</HI> dwelling at <HI>Purmerent,</HI> do represent that one of their ships, named <HI>the Wooden Fort,</HI> on the 2 of <HI>August</HI> 1662. being <HI>fishing</HI> for <HI>Whales</HI> about 5 or 6 <HI>Leagues</HI> from the <HI>Coast</HI> toward the <HI>Bay</HI> of <HI>Belsont,</HI> and having the day before taken a <HI>Whale 16 Leagues</HI> from <HI>Land,</HI> was attacqued by 2 <HI>English Vessels</HI> of which <HI>one</HI> was a <HI>Fregat</HI> commanded by Captain <HI>John Clark</HI> and the <HI>other</HI> a <HI>Pinnace,</HI> of which <HI>John Piper</HI> was <HI>Captain,</HI> and after they had committed several out∣rages upon him, he was carried by them into the <HI>Bay</HI> of <HI>Belsont</HI> to the <HI>English Admiral, John Mandrey;</HI> and though the said <HI>Admiral</HI> could not pretend any <HI>right</HI> to the <HI>Whale</HI> that had been taken; and confessed he had nothing to pretend to it, if it were taken 14 or 15 <HI>Leagues</HI> from the <HI>Coast;</HI> and notwithstanding all the <HI>Mariners</HI> of the <HI>ship</HI> the <HI>Wooden Fort,</HI> did declare that it was taken at that di∣stance, yet the said <HI>Admiral</HI> did not onely take the said <HI>Whale,</HI> but also the <HI>Finns</HI> of another; 2 <HI>Shallops,</HI> 12 <HI>Lines,</HI> 24 <HI>Oars,</HI> 24 <HI>Nets,</HI> 4 <HI>Harpons,</HI> and many other <HI>Instruments</HI> necessary both for <HI>Fishing</HI> and <HI>Navigation;</HI> so that the said ship finding her self by that means disabled to continue her <HI>fishery,</HI> the <HI>Interessed</HI> have reason to demand <HI>reparation</HI> for their <HI>damages.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Jacob Jeunissen Winding</HI> and his <HI>Associates,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Arti.</HI> 60.</NOTE> do say, That on the 3 of <HI>August</HI> 1662. one of their ships named the <HI>Prince William,</HI> of which <HI>William Jacobson</HI> was <HI>Commander,</HI> being <HI>fishing</HI> for <HI>Whales</HI> in <HI>Greenland,</HI> the said ship was dri∣ven by a small Wind near to <HI>Belsont,</HI> within 5 or 6 <HI>Leagues</HI> of the <HI>Coast;</HI> and there met Captain <HI>John Clark</HI> in Com∣pany with another fair <HI>English ship, well mounted.</HI></P>
<PB N="65" REF="36"/>
<P>That the said <HI>John Clark</HI> did first make a <HI>shot over him,</HI> and then <HI>Another</HI> directly <HI>At</HI> him, and so forced the <HI>Com∣mander</HI> to come aboard him. And while the said <HI>Comman∣der</HI> was <HI>aboard</HI> the said <HI>Fregat,</HI> with some of his <HI>Seamen,</HI> the men of the <HI>Fregat</HI> entred the <HI>ship Prince William,</HI> and took out of her by force, as follows, 2 <HI>Shallops,</HI> 18 <HI>Lines,</HI> 23 <HI>Nets,</HI> 10 <HI>Harpons,</HI> 10 <HI>Foregangers,</HI> 20 <HI>Oars,</HI> 2 <HI>Sails,</HI> 4 <HI>Hatchets,</HI> 1 <HI>slitting Knife,</HI> and other <HI>Instruments;</HI> and moreover, the <HI>Captain</HI> extorted from him for his <HI>two shot</HI> which he had made, 20 <HI>Florens</HI> in <HI>money,</HI> 4 <HI>Cheeses,</HI> 2 <HI>Bar∣rels of Brandy,</HI> and a <HI>bag</HI> of <HI>Grout;</HI> so the said <HI>Commander</HI> being by reason of this <HI>pillage,</HI> put out of all condition to continue his <HI>fishing,</HI> was constrained to return home.</P>
<P><HI>John Claessen, Merchant</HI> and his <HI>Associates,</HI> dwelling in the <HI>Ryp,</HI> do complain, That one of their ships named the <HI>Fisher,</HI> of which <HI>John Arissen Brack</HI> was <HI>Commander,</HI> being in <HI>June</HI> 1662. arrived in <HI>Greenland</HI> to <HI>fish</HI> for <HI>Whales,</HI> had there the ill luck to receive such damage and disorder by the <HI>Ice,</HI> that to <HI>stop</HI> his <HI>Leaks,</HI> and <HI>caulk</HI> his <HI>ship,</HI> he was con∣strained to draw near the <HI>Coast;</HI> and in pursuit thereof, the said <HI>Commander</HI> the 26 of the said <HI>Moneth,</HI> entred with his ship into the said <HI>Harbour,</HI> called <HI>Green-Hauberg,</HI> in <HI>Spits-Bergen,</HI> and caused his ship to be there <HI>Carined,</HI> to <HI>stop</HI> her <HI>Leaks;</HI> where the said ship being thus repaired, and ready to return to the <HI>fishing,</HI> the said <HI>Captain John Clark</HI> came directly upon him, and took from him 4 <HI>Shal∣lops,</HI> 9 <HI>Lines,</HI> 15 <HI>Nets,</HI> 24 <HI>Oars,</HI> some <HI>Sails,</HI> and <HI>Masts,</HI> a great quantity of <HI>Hatchets,</HI> and all sorts of <HI>Knives</HI> and <HI>Ʋ∣tensils</HI> necessary for <HI>fishing;</HI> so that by this means the said <HI>Commander</HI> found himself disabled to continue the <HI>fishing.</HI></P>
<P>To the 58, 59, and 60. <HI>Article,</HI> It is answered;<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answer to</HI> 58, 59, 60.</NOTE></P>
<P>That the Country of <HI>Greenland</HI> was <HI>discovered</HI> by the <HI>English</HI> in the raign of Queen <HI>Elizabeth;</HI> about the beginning of King <HI>James</HI> his raign, the <HI>Kings Stan∣dard</HI>
<PB N="66" REF="37"/>was <HI>set up,</HI> and the <HI>dominion thereof assumed</HI> to be in His Majesty, by the name of King <HI>James</HI> his <HI>New-Land:</HI> in pursuance whereof, his said Majesty did by several <HI>Acts of State,</HI> assert his <HI>right</HI> thereunto; and particularly the 10. of <HI>January</HI> 1613. his plea∣sure was signified unto Sr. <HI>Noel Caroon</HI> Knight, <HI>Am∣bassadour</HI> for the <HI>States</HI> of the <HI>United Provinces,</HI> as followeth; <HI>viz.</HI> That the said Country of <HI>Greenland,</HI> together with the <HI>fishing</HI> of <HI>Whales</HI> upon that <HI>Coast,</HI> and all other <HI>Commodities</HI> arising from <HI>thence,</HI> do pro∣perly belong to his <HI>Majesty, Jure Dominii,</HI> His <HI>Sub∣jects</HI> having been the <HI>first discoverers</HI> thereof, as was made manifest unto the <HI>Lords</HI> of his <HI>Majesties Privy Council;</HI> and <HI>possession</HI> taken in the <HI>name,</HI> and on the <HI>behalf</HI> of his <HI>Majesty,</HI> by erecting his <HI>Highnesses Stan∣dard</HI> on that place, and therefore that without leave first obtained from his <HI>Majesty,</HI> or from those to whom his <HI>Highness</HI> had granted the sole use and pos∣session thereof, it is not <HI>lawful</HI> for any other of his <HI>Majesties Subjects</HI> (much less for <HI>Strangers</HI>) to fish or abide there: And whosoever should presume to at∣tempt any such thing, (as it appeared the <HI>Hollanders</HI> had done) especially being forewarned as they had been the year before) if thereupon any prejudice or loss did happen unto them, either in their persons, or goods, by being forc'd to depart, or having their Commodities taken from them, they cannot justly complain of any wrong, for they came thither upon their own perils.</P>
<P>And in purfuance of their <HI>Right,</HI> his <HI>Then Majesty</HI> and King <HI>Charles the First,</HI> of blessed Memory, and their Subjects, by their Authority, having constantly as∣serted and maintained the <HI>fishing</HI> in <HI>Bell Sound, Green
<PB N="67" REF="37"/>Harbour,</HI> and the <HI>Harbours</HI> and <HI>places</HI> adjacent, against all Nations which have intruded, and in particular, in the year 1618. in the defence and exercise of this Right, therein the <HI>English</HI> sustained great <HI>damages,</HI> to the value of 66436 <HI>pounds</HI> 15 <HI>shillings,</HI> by the <HI>Hollan∣ders</HI> and <HI>Zealanders;</HI> the doing whereof was disown∣ed by the <HI>States,</HI> as a <HI>depredation,</HI> and <HI>satisfaction</HI> trea∣ted upon by <HI>Commissioners;</HI> who not agreeing, it was referred to his <HI>Majesty,</HI> who awarded 22000 <HI>pounds</HI> to the <HI>English Merchants,</HI> but no part thereof was ever paid: And as a farther testimony of their <HI>Right</HI> by <HI>Occupancy,</HI> the <HI>English</HI> are the onely persons that ever did <HI>Winter</HI> there.</P>
<P>That the <HI>Dutch</HI> and <HI>Netherlanders,</HI> to render this Right as ineffectual as they could, have oftentimes of <HI>late years</HI> ridden with their <HI>ships</HI> before the said <HI>Harbours,</HI> to disturb the <HI>fishing</HI> of the <HI>English,</HI> by <HI>sca∣ring</HI> and diverting the <HI>Whales</HI> from <HI>coming in:</HI> To prevent which, the <HI>English</HI> have to their great trouble and damage, been compelled to leave their <HI>fishing</HI> in the <HI>Harbours,</HI> and come forth to warn them away, both by fair means, and by force; which <HI>warning</HI> the <HI>Dutch</HI> have ever used to receive, and to submit to the <HI>English right</HI> by their <HI>departure</HI> accordingly; but no damage was ever heretofore pretended for the same.</P>
<P>Nevertheless, in the Year 1660, and 1661. the <HI>Subjects</HI> of the <HI>United Netherlands</HI> growing more <HI>nu∣merous</HI> and <HI>insolent</HI> upon that <HI>Coast,</HI> complaint thereof being made to his <HI>Royal Highness</HI> the <HI>Duke</HI> of <HI>York, Lord High Admiral</HI> of <HI>England,</HI> his said <HI>Highness</HI> was pleased in the Year 1662. to send Captain <HI>John Clark</HI>
<PB N="68" REF="38"/>with one of his Majesties <HI>Vessels</HI> called the <HI>Little Ma∣ry,</HI> to protect the <HI>fishing;</HI> who in order thereunto, did warn the <HI>Dutch</HI> off from that <HI>Coast,</HI> where the <HI>English</HI> used to <HI>fish,</HI> and have right of <HI>fishing.</HI></P>
<P>As to the <HI>particulars</HI> mentioned; We answer, that Captain <HI>Clark,</HI> and the others named therein, being <HI>Mariners</HI> and <HI>abroad</HI> upon their several <HI>employments,</HI> full answer cannot be given thereunto; but certain it is, that <HI>no claim</HI> hath hitherto been made by any person whatsoever in any of his <HI>Majesties Courts</HI> of <HI>justice,</HI> nor <HI>demand</HI> elsewhere; which gives just oc∣casion to conclude that all those <HI>complaints</HI> are groundless.</P>
<P>All that we can hear of is, That <HI>two ships</HI> of the <HI>Hol∣landers,</HI> riding in one of the <HI>English Harbours,</HI> called <HI>Fair Fore-land, alias,</HI> Sir <HI>Thomas Smiths Bay,</HI> contrary to order before given by the aforesaid Cap. <HI>Clark,</HI> were by him forced to depart: from whom he took only 5 <HI>Shallops,</HI> with some other <HI>fishing instruments,</HI> whereby to disable them from farther disturbance of <HI>fishing</HI> in the <HI>English Harbours,</HI> which could not be much <HI>damage</HI> unto them, the <HI>season</HI> for <HI>fishing</HI> at <HI>Sea</HI> (which was their design) being then past.</P>
<P>For the ship called the <HI>Wooden Fort,</HI> from which it is said there was a <HI>Whale</HI> taken, it is affirmed, that she was riding within <HI>two Leagues</HI> of <HI>Bell point,</HI> in the <HI>mouth</HI> of the Harbour, which is a place proper to do mischief to the <HI>English</HI> in <HI>scaring</HI> and diverting the <HI>Whales,</HI> but not <HI>fit</HI> to <HI>fish</HI> in, and the said <HI>Captain Clark</HI> coming <HI>on board,</HI> and finding a <HI>Whale</HI> newly killed, caused the said <HI>Whale,</HI> as also 2 <HI>Shallops</HI> to
<PB N="69" REF="38"/>be taken from him; being there in contempt of his <HI>Majesties Authority</HI> after warning given, and in <HI>con∣tempt</HI> of his <HI>Highness Commission:</HI> But the said ship had in her <HI>Hold</HI> to the quantity of 5 or 6 <HI>Whales</HI> in <HI>Bubber,</HI> and <HI>Einns,</HI> which he did not meddle withall, conceiving them to have been taken at <HI>Sea.</HI></P>
<P>As to the <HI>fourth ship,</HI> for the reasons aforesaid, no particular accompt can be given thereof; but by all that is alleaged, it appears that Captain <HI>Clark</HI> onely took from her such <HI>Utensils,</HI> as might disable them from <HI>fishing in</HI> or <HI>before</HI> the <HI>Harbour,</HI> to the <HI>disturbance</HI> of the <HI>English;</HI> which His <HI>Majesties Subjects</HI> hold themselves bound to <HI>defend,</HI> so long as his <HI>Majesty</HI> shall please to <HI>assert</HI> his <HI>inte∣rest,</HI> and <HI>right</HI> of <HI>fishing.</HI></P>
<P><HI>William Johnson Kreigt,</HI> dwelling at <HI>Graft,</HI> saith,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 61.</NOTE> That one of his ships <HI>fishing</HI> for <HI>Herrings;</HI> named the <HI>Charity,</HI> (<HI>Martin Geritzen</HI> Masters Mate) returning from <HI>fishing,</HI> la∣den with 21 Last of Herrings;<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">See for the Answer to the <HI>61, 62, 63, &amp; 64.</HI> in <HI>pag. 60.</HI></NOTE> and having withal 120 Livres in <HI>money,</HI> which he had received for a <HI>Last</HI> of <HI>Herrings</HI> that he had sold, was upon the 13. of <HI>September</HI> 1661. attacqued about 8 <HI>Leagues</HI> from the <HI>Texel,</HI> and taken by one Captain <HI>Sadlington,</HI> and carried to <HI>Colche∣ster;</HI> where being arrived, the said Masters Mate saw his ship unladen, and was afterwards constrained to carry her to <HI>Wesnoo,</HI> where he was forced to aban∣don all.</P>
<P><HI>Nicholas-Corssen</HI> of <HI>Adrichen,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 62.</NOTE> Burgomaster of the Town of <HI>Vlaerding,</HI> complains that one of his ships named the <HI>Crescent;</HI> of which <HI>Henry Bastiaens</HI> was Masters Mate, be∣ing
<PB N="70" REF="39"/>laden with 14 Lasts of <HI>Herrings,</HI> was in <HI>August</HI> 1659. taken by Captain <HI>White</HI> of <HI>Newcastle,</HI> whose <HI>Associates</HI> (as the said <HI>Nicholas Corssen</HI> is informed) dwelt at <HI>Leith</HI> in <HI>Scotland.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Aaron de Vosse,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 63.</NOTE> Burgomaster of the same Town, saith that one of his ships <HI>fishing</HI> for <HI>Herring,</HI> named the <HI>Fox,</HI> of which <HI>Joseph Foppen</HI> was Master, being departed with many other Vessels for the said <HI>Fishery,</HI> and being laden with 285 <HI>Barrels</HI> and a <HI>half</HI> of <HI>Herring,</HI> was taken the 11 of <HI>July</HI> 1660. by the above named Captain <HI>Geo. Wot∣worth</HI> of <HI>Leith</HI> in <HI>Scotland;</HI> whither the ship being brought, the said <HI>Aaron de Vosse</HI> took a great deal of pains, and made great solicitation for the <HI>Restitution</HI> of his <HI>ship</HI> and <HI>Goods,</HI> as also for the reparation of <HI>damages</HI> suffered by him, but notwithstanding all his pains and solicitatious, he could not obtain the <HI>restitution</HI> of one <HI>penny.</HI></P>
<P><HI>John Martensen,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 64.</NOTE> <HI>Olden Roggen, Schepen</HI> of the same Town, complains, That a ship of his, of the burden of 54 <HI>Tun</HI> being gone to Sea to <HI>fish,</HI> and being upon the 13 of <HI>April</HI> 1659. about 3 <HI>Leagues</HI> to the <HI>Northwards</HI> of the <HI>Sables,</HI> was attacqued, taken, and carried to <HI>Newcastle,</HI> by a Captain called <HI>John of London.</HI></P>
<P><HI>George Andriesen</HI> formerly Master of the ship called the St. <HI>Peter,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 65.</NOTE> doth complain, That being departed from <HI>Middleburgh</HI> in <HI>Zealand</HI> the 18. of <HI>December</HI> 1661. armed with a <HI>Commission</HI> from the <HI>States</HI> to go to the <HI>West-Indies,</HI> was taken and pillaged 10 <HI>Leagues</HI> from <HI>Cape de Cruze,</HI> in the Island of <HI>Cuba,</HI> by a <HI>Captain</HI> named <HI>James Young,</HI> who had fitted his ship at <HI>London,</HI> and had his retreat in the <HI>Island</HI> of <HI>Jamaica;</HI> which <HI>Prize</HI> was taken the 24. of <HI>May</HI> 1662. and from the ship which was pillaged there was ta∣ken and carried away, (besides what the <HI>Seamen</HI> took) all the <HI>Cargazon</HI> and <HI>Merchandize</HI> that had been entrusted with the Master of the said ship, to trade withal; so that
<PB N="71" REF="39"/>they <HI>find</HI> themselves well warranted to demand satisfaction by the <HI>Authority</HI> of the <HI>Original Factors.</HI></P>
<P>To the 65. <HI>Article;</HI> We say,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answ.</HI> 65.</NOTE> that no such man had any <HI>Commission</HI> from <HI>Jamaica;</HI> but we have heard that such a person had obtained a <HI>Portugal Commission,</HI> and did <HI>Plunder English Ships,</HI> and all Vessels that he took; but durst never go into <HI>Jamaica</HI> for that <HI>Colonel Doyly,</HI> the <HI>Governour</HI> of <HI>That Place,</HI> gave Orders to all <HI>Men of War</HI> to apprehend him, for his <HI>Insolence</HI> to a Vessel called, <HI>The Blessing of London.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Cornelius de Lincourt,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 66.</NOTE> hath presented to their Lordships a <HI>memorial</HI> of <HI>Goods,</HI> that his Father <HI>Jacob de Lincourt</HI> decea∣sed, left in the <HI>Island of</HI> S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Christopher,</HI> on the 5<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>April,</HI> 1655, which have been detained by him that commands for the King of <HI>England</HI> in the same <HI>Island;</HI> under pre∣tense, <HI>that there ought to be a recovery made upon them, for the losses which the</HI> English <HI>pretend to have suffered by the said</HI> Corne∣lius de Lincourt <HI>during the late War with</HI> England; <HI>because he had taken some of their Buildings:</HI> And forasmuch as the <HI>Com∣missioners</HI> established over the said goods, to wit, <HI>Captain Wil∣liam Tresilgem, Captain Samuel Wintrym,</HI> and <HI>Master William Jordan,</HI> have declared that the <HI>Goods</HI> of the deceased are in <HI>their custody;</HI> and of what <HI>Value</HI> they are, according to the accompt of <HI>Sugars,</HI> and <HI>Indico,</HI> which they have Esteem∣ed at 306100<SUP>l</SUP>. of <HI>Sugar,</HI> and 750<SUP>l</SUP>. of <HI>Indico,</HI> he demands <HI>Restitution</HI> with <HI>Indemnity.</HI></P>
<P>To the 66. <HI>Article;</HI> If the <HI>complainant</HI> have <HI>Right,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answ.</HI> 66.</NOTE> he must seek it upon the <HI>Island,</HI> by course of <HI>Justice,</HI> and his <HI>pretence</HI> ought not to be admitted against <HI>our Nation</HI> untill <HI>that</HI> be <HI>denyed</HI> Him.</P>
<P><HI>Leonard Johnson,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 67.</NOTE> formerly Master of the ship called the
<PB N="72" REF="40"/><HI>Martin of Rossum,</HI> of <HI>Middleburgh,</HI> hath represented to the <HI>States</HI> an <HI>Authentick Copy Translated</HI> out of <HI>English,</HI> being in effect, a Declaration of the <HI>Governour</HI> for the KING of <HI>Great Brittain</HI> in <HI>Jamaica,</HI> by which it is testified that the said <HI>Leonard Johnson</HI> Arrived the 16<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>December,</HI> 1661. in that <HI>Harbour,</HI> with his <HI>ship</HI> and <HI>Company,</HI> in a miserable condition, having no more money then 50. <HI>Ryalls of Eight,</HI> to supply their necessities, he therefore obtained leave to fell 30 <HI>Negroes;</HI> but afterwards desiring leave to sell all the rest of the <HI>Negroes</HI> he had, it was refused him, and he had his <HI>Pass-port</HI> to be gone: But notwithstanding, after his say∣ling from thence, the 18<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>February</HI> 1662. he returned thither again, by mischance, <HI>two dayes after,</HI> and was pre∣sently <HI>Borded</HI> by some <HI>Seamen</HI> belonging to his <HI>Majesties Fre∣gat,</HI> called the <HI>Diamond,</HI> commanded by <HI>Captain Richard Whiting,</HI> according to the Instructions of his <HI>Royal Highness</HI> the <HI>Duke</HI> of <HI>York, Lord High Admiral of England:</HI> But the <HI>Governour</HI> having put all under a <HI>Guard,</HI> caused the <HI>ship</HI> to be <HI>visited,</HI> and finding that the said <HI>Leonard Johnson</HI> in the <HI>sale</HI> of his <HI>Negroes,</HI> had not exceeded the <HI>Number</HI> that was allowed him, and because there was no more found in his ship then 260. <HI>pound,</HI> of which 218. <HI>pounds</HI> was carried to the <HI>Governour,</HI> and 50. <HI>Negroes,</HI> who were rated at 478. <HI>pounds sterling,</HI> which <HI>summ</HI> being added to the 218. <HI>pounds,</HI> makes in all the <HI>summ</HI> of 696. <HI>pounds sterling,</HI> which the said <HI>Governour</HI> did remin to his <HI>Royall Highness,</HI> or to his <HI>Order.</HI></P>
<P>To the 67. <HI>Article;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum"><HI>Answ.</HI> 67.</NOTE> The <HI>Admission</HI> of the <HI>complai∣nants Ship</HI> first to <HI>Jamaica,</HI> was a noble excess of <HI>cha∣rity</HI> in the <HI>Governour,</HI> who took upon him to dispence with the <HI>Law,</HI> to <HI>supply</HI> the <HI>complainants</HI> needs; That the taking of the ship <HI>afterwards,</HI> was what the <HI>Captain might,</HI> and <HI>ought</HI> to do by <HI>Law,</HI> and his <HI>Duty;</HI> And if the <HI>complainant</HI> had any thing <HI>restored</HI> him, he owes <HI>thanks</HI> for that, and ought not to <HI>complain,</HI> that a <HI>part</HI> was <HI>detained,</HI> when the <HI>whole</HI> was <HI>Legally consiscable</HI> for
<PB N="73" REF="40"/>his <HI>trading</HI> with <HI>our Plantations, contrary</HI> to the <HI>Act</HI> of <HI>Navigation.</HI></P>
<P>All the <HI>Interessed</HI> in the <HI>ship</HI> named the S<SUP>t</SUP>. <HI>John,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Arti.</HI> 68.</NOTE> of which <HI>Leven Kachlaer</HI> of <HI>Trevere</HI> in <HI>Zealand</HI> was Master, do com∣plain that the said <HI>ship</HI> departing from <HI>Trevere</HI> in the <HI>month</HI> of <HI>January,</HI> 1662. Bound for <HI>France,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">See this Answ. <HI>p. 60.</HI></NOTE> was met near the <HI>Coast</HI> of <HI>England,</HI> by a <HI>Fregat</HI> Commanded by <HI>Captain Jacob Van∣gaber,</HI> who made himself <HI>master of the said ship</HI> on the 29<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>January,</HI> 1662. and carried <HI>her</HI> to <HI>Rye</HI> in <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>It is further represented, that <HI>Bartholomew de Jager,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Arti.</HI> 69.</NOTE> of <HI>Middleburgh,</HI> Master of the ship called the <HI>Fortune,</HI> (a <HI>Vessell</HI> of 150. <HI>Tun,</HI> or thereabouts) departed form <HI>Middleburgh, April</HI> 2<SUP>d</SUP> 1652. with the said <HI>ship</HI> and <HI>lading,</HI> confisting of 450. <HI>Quintalls</HI> (<HI>measure</HI> of <HI>France</HI>) of <HI>salt,</HI> of S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Martin. Twelve</HI> pieces of <HI>Aquavitae</HI> of <HI>Rochel,</HI> which were laden at <HI>Rochel,</HI> by <HI>Christian Denis,</HI> and <HI>Maquet,</HI> and belonging (as it appears by the <HI>Bills of Lading</HI>) to <HI>Regnier Martensse,</HI> and <HI>Ja∣cob Lievens, Merchants</HI> of <HI>Middleburgh,</HI> to go for <HI>Nieuport;</HI> and that being Arriv'd upon the 5<SUP>th</SUP> of the same <HI>moneth,</HI> before the <HI>Harbour</HI> of that <HI>Town,</HI> at break of day he came to an Anchour, and that early in the morning, <HI>Three ships</HI> of the Parliament of <HI>England</HI> came up directly to him, namely <HI>Two</HI> of the <HI>squadron</HI> of <HI>Vice-Admiral Goodson,</HI> who lay before <HI>Ost-end,</HI> and the <HI>third</HI> coming from the <HI>West,</HI> who approaching the said <HI>Vessel,</HI> made several shot at her, so that the <HI>Master,</HI> and his men were fain to leave the <HI>ship</HI> to save their lives; having first nailed his <HI>Sea-brief</HI> to the <HI>main-mast,</HI> to shew that both <HI>ship</HI> and <HI>goods</HI> were <HI>free.</HI> He did also cause to be planted a <HI>white flagg,</HI> joyning with it <HI>One</HI> of the <HI>Prince</HI> of <HI>Orange</HI>'s, to notifie that all was <HI>free;</HI> But this signified lit∣tle, although the said <HI>Lievens</HI> had also given to understand that the <HI>ship</HI> was his; for the <HI>men</HI> of the said <HI>Parliament Vessel</HI> came up notwithstanding with their <HI>Shallops</HI> to the said <HI>ship</HI> the <HI>Fortune,</HI> under <HI>protection</HI> of their <HI>Cannon,</HI> and
<PB N="74" REF="41"/>took away <HI>Anchors, Cordage, Sails, Cable,</HI> &amp;c. and set fire at last both to <HI>ship</HI> and <HI>lading.</HI></P>
<P>To the 69. <HI>Article,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answer <HI>69.</HI></NOTE> we say, That <HI>Vice-Admiral Good∣son</HI> Commanded no <HI>Squadron</HI> of <HI>Ships</HI> in the Year, 1662. and therefore if any thing was done of what is <HI>complained</HI> at that time, it must be done by some other <HI>Nation.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Hierosme Cornelissen</HI> of <HI>Flushing,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Art.</HI> 70.</NOTE> declareth likewise, that he departed from <HI>Flushing,</HI> on the 17<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>May</HI> 1657. under the <HI>Convoy</HI> of <HI>John Thyssen</HI> for <HI>Ostend,</HI> laden with <HI>bay-salt;</HI> and that about two Leagues from the Town of <HI>Ostend,</HI> two <HI>Fregats</HI> came up to him, the one Commanded by <HI>Captain Lambert,</HI> and the other by <HI>Captain Groff,</HI> the latter of which <HI>pillaged</HI> him: But however the said <HI>Captain</HI> promising that he would restore the whole to him,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">See for the Answer to the Pre∣tenses <HI>70, 71, 72.</HI> in <HI>pa. 60.</HI></NOTE> provided he would give him a <HI>Declaration</HI> that he had not been <HI>damnified</HI> by him; which the said <HI>Cornelissen</HI> consented to; but after the giving thereof, he could get no more of him then <HI>nine Livres de gros:</HI> His losse amounting (besides that) to 13 <HI>Livres,</HI> 16 <HI>Solz,</HI> and 9 <HI>Deniers de gros;</HI> and that of his man to four <HI>Livres de gros,</HI> of which he could not obtain <HI>Restitu∣tion.</HI></P>
<P>All the <HI>Interessed</HI> in the 19 <HI>ships</HI> that went from <HI>Flushing</HI> the 6<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>August,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Arti.</HI> 71.</NOTE> 1656. under the <HI>Convoy</HI> of <HI>Captain John Tyson,</HI> do represent that the said <HI>ships</HI> being Arrived near <HI>Blanckenburgh,</HI> did there meet 6 or 7 <HI>English Vessels,</HI> who <HI>at∣tacqued</HI> them, being laden with <HI>Wine, Brandy</HI> and <HI>Salt,</HI> and fired upon them furiously, took and sunk 5 or 6, so that there Arrived at <HI>Ostend</HI> but 13, or 14.</P>
<P><HI>Cornelius Janssen,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Anti.</HI> 72.</NOTE> <HI>Peter Bogart, John Andreessen,</HI> Masters of <HI>ships</HI> dwelling at <HI>Middleburgh,</HI> and <HI>Flushing,</HI> do <HI>Remon∣strate,</HI> That sailing in the Year, 1659. with their <HI>ships</HI> and
<PB N="75" REF="41"/><HI>Merchandizes</HI> which were not <HI>Contrabanda,</HI> towards <HI>Ostend,</HI> were driven back by certain ships in such manner, that they were constrained to return to the place from whence they departed, and where they were <HI>freighted</HI> which did them a great deal of <HI>wrong,</HI> and they have reason to de∣mand to be <HI>Indemnified.</HI></P>
<P>The ship named the <HI>Town and Country Adjacent,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Pretense. <HI>Artic.</HI> 73.</NOTE> belong∣ing to the <HI>West India Company of the Chamber of Groninghen,</HI> was taken by the <HI>English</HI> in the <HI>Channel,</HI> with the <HI>Merchan∣dizes</HI> thereunto belonging, <HI>and Depending.</HI></P>
<P>When we know the <HI>Captain</HI> that <HI>took</HI> her,<NOTE PLACE="marg" TYPE="runSum">Answ. <HI>73.</HI></NOTE> and <HI>time when,</HI> and <HI>where</HI> any <HI>claim</HI> hath formerly been <HI>made, an Answer shall be given.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

