<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Certain propositions relating to the Scots plantation of Caledonia, and the national address for supporting thereof breifly offered to publick view, for removing of mistakes and prejudices.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A31509</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing C1729C</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R221852</IDNO>



<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 31354945</IDNO>


<AVAILABILITY><P>This text has been selected for inclusion in the EEBO-TCP: Navigations collection, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities. To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication ( http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31509)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110293)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1736:11)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Certain propositions relating to the Scots plantation of Caledonia, and the national address for supporting thereof breifly offered to publick view, for removing of mistakes and prejudices.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>1 sheet ([2] p.).   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>Glasgow :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>[s.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>Printed in the Year, 1700.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Caption title.</NOTE><NOTE>Imprint from colophon.</NOTE><NOTE>Imperfect: cropped, stained, creased, and faded, with loss of text; best copy available for photographing.</NOTE><NOTE>Formerly identified as Wing C1732 (number cancelled).</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2016-01-29.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM TYPE="corporate name">Company of Scotland Trading to Africa and the Indies.</TERM><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Darien Scots' Colony, 1698-1700.</TERM><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Panama --  Colonization.</TERM><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Panama --  Discovery and exploration.</TERM><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Scotland --  Commercial policy.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2013-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A31509">
<STC T="W">C1729C</STC>
<STC T="C">R221852</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">31354945</BIBNO>
<VID>110293</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<HEAD><HI>Certain Propositions</HI> Relating to the <HI>Scots</HI> Plantation of <HI>CALEDONIA,</HI> and the National Address for supporting thereof, breifly offered to Publick View, for removing of Mistakes and Prejudices.</HEAD>
<P N="1">I. THAT the <HI>Scotch</HI> Planters have entered upon <HI>Caledonia</HI> by Warrant, and un∣der Security of an Act of Parliament, and Letters patent from his Majesty under the Great Seal, and most strictly within the Terms and Conditions thereof; otherwise there had needed no more to Ruine them, than a De∣claration of their having Forfeited their Act and Charter.</P>
<P N="2">II. That their Right is confirmed by Invitation from, and League with the original free Natives of that Country, who only can have the primary Natural Right to the Soil, and from whom the <HI>Spaniards</HI> have, contrary to all Justice, Faith, and Contract, u∣surp'd what they now prossess in <HI>America,</HI> having obtain'd their Possession by Fraud and Force and Barbarous Cruelty, and by the Popes Donation upon certain Condi∣tions, which they have not in the least observed, as is fully made appear by <HI>Bartholo∣mew de las Casas</HI> Bishop of <HI>Chiapa,</HI> one of there own Missionaries.</P>
<P N="3">III. That the place chosen by the <HI>Scots</HI> was never inhabited by the <HI>Spaniards</HI> or any other <HI>European,</HI> and consequently the <HI>Scots</HI> have the same freedom to take Possession of it, as the <HI>English</HI> to possess any part of the Coast from <HI>New-England</HI> to <HI>Florida,</HI> the <HI>French</HI> in <HI>Canada</HI> and <HI>Messasippy,</HI> the <HI>Portuguez</HI> in <HI>Brasil,</HI> and the <HI>Dutch</HI> in <HI>Suranam,</HI> being all upon the same Continent, which the <HI>Spaniards</HI> from <HI>Columbus's</HI> discovery, do chal∣lenge to themselves. And indeed it is evident, That the Crown and Kingdom of <HI>Scotland</HI> hath not a better Title, nor a more just Right to any <HI>Scots</HI> Territory from the <HI>Mule</HI> of <HI>Galloway</HI> to the <HI>Week</HI> of <HI>Cathnes</HI> then to <HI>Caledonia</HI> in <HI>America.</HI></P>
<P N="4">IV. That not only have the <HI>Scots</HI> the sole unquestionable Right to this Important Place: But likewise, albeit they have been hitherto debarr'd from all Benefit of free Trading in other Plantations, yet they have very frankly offered both to the <HI>English</HI> and <HI>Dutch,</HI> their Protestant Neighbours, a reasonable Share in all the Advantages of <HI>Caledonia,</HI> which for Natural Wealth and Strength, and conveniency of Trading, is without Dispute, the most considerable in the whole World.</P>
<P N="5">V. That if the <HI>Scots</HI> be forced to abandon their Plantation, the <HI>French</HI> will undoubt∣edly seize upon it, not only for the sake of Trade, Gain, and Empire; But likewise in Zeal for rooting out the Northern Heresy, both from <HI>America</HI> and <HI>Europe,</HI> which may be easily foreseen, both by the vast occasion of Power and Wealth, that so impor∣rant a Post will bring to the <HI>French</HI> Greatness, and by the keen Resentment that all the Popish Courts, and particularly the Court of <HI>Rome</HI> have testified against the <HI>Scots</HI> pos∣sessing thereof, and by the no less unpolitick than cruel Persecution that, at this day rages in <HI>France</HI> against the poor Remnant of Protestants, who cannot comply with their Superstition and Idolatry.</P>
<P N="6">VI. That there is such an hopeful appearance of propagating the pure Gospel a∣mongst an Harmless, good Natur'd People in the Neighbourhood of <HI>Caledonia,</HI> who seem well disposed to receive it, as ought to excite Reformed Protestants to contri∣bute thereto with the greatest Vigor; and to strengthen themselves against the Ro∣mish Power; especially when Popery prevails so mightily over all <HI>Europe,</HI> and the Papists compass Sea and Land to gain Proselites; Nor doth the Remotness, Danger and Barbarities of <HI>China, Japan, Tartary,</HI> and all the back parts of the <HI>English</HI> Plantations discourage or faint their Zeal.</P>
<P N="7">VII. That therefore, it is the undoubted Interest and Duty of all Protestants, to sup∣port this Colony in the <HI>Scots</HI> hands, who have the only just Right thereto; and in whose Possession, it must certainly prove more beneficial to all other Protestant King∣dom and States, than any other more wealthy and powerful Kingdom or State would suffer it to be unto the rest, if they did possess it alone. And it must be the unquestion∣able duty of all true hearted <HI>Scots</HI> Men to endeavour by all Just, Legal, and orderly ways, the Preservation of their own Colony.</P>
<P N="8">VIII. That whatever has been the Cause of the late Disaster of <HI>Caledonia,</HI> yet most Evident it is, that the Colony cannot now be preserved to <HI>Scotland,</HI>
<PB REF="2"/> unless the Force and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of the <HI>West-India</HI> Proclamations be taken off, and that ob, very speedily, si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is undeniably manifest, that the Company under t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eir pre∣sent hard Circumsta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>, and now sadly redoubled Misfortunes, are not able to sup∣port the same, and vigio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> the very speedy Assistance of a Parliament, not only must so Great and Honour <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Enterprise fall to the Ground, but the remaining Persons, and the Treasure empl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>d therein must Perish, to the Irreparable Less and Dis∣honour of the Nation▪</P>
<P N="9">IX. That the only <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and effectual Way for Remedy, is (in imitation of the <HI>Dutch-East-India-Compa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ho having been unsuccessful in their two first Voyages, were supported by th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>-General</HI>) in all Humble and Dutiful Manner, to Address the King for the Meeti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the parliament; which having been already done by the Company, and his Majes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y having been pleased to regret their and the Kingdoms loss, and to promise that th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>iament shall meet, when the Good of the Nation does require it; There can <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>othing more Natural, than for the Nation themselves to acquaint his Majesty <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e urgent Necessity of the Parliament's speedy Meeting, upon so weighty and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>sing a Juncture, and of so Universal a Concern to the whole Nation.</P>
<P N="10">X. That the Natural <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>at of Petitioning, in a Legal and Orderly Wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> being revived and asserted by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Claim of Right,</HI> the Happy Purchase of the late <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ricus Revolution: And His Majesty, our Great De<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> under God, having alw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esti∣fied a just Regard to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>oresaid Right of Petiti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en in that Proc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>tion that forbids Illegal Meth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>; However His Majesty <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>me things, h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>een mis-informed, to the Pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ice of this His Ancient King <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Yet it is nev<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be imagined, but that wher<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> understands their true Good from themselves, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill Graciously grant their Je<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and Necessary Desires, and with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>n Countenance, and take <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>e of their Righteous Cause.</P>
<P N="11">XI. That tho it be Di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>yal for any Man, to doubt of the Kings granting <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>¦liament, when sought by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> considerable a part of the Nation: And to doubt o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Parliament's supporting <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>donia,</HI> is unworthy of a <HI>Scots</HI> Man; Yet if the Question<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ask'd, What is to be don<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> case of Refusal? The Answer is pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>in, That first, the N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>¦tion shall have the Satisfa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ion of having done their Duty; and next, they shall have the Melancholly Advant<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e of knowing, that further Attempts for an <HI>American</HI>-Plantation must at present <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ease, so as they need not fruitlesly throw away more Men and Money to be lost in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oubtful Expectations, but must gather up their Shipwrack, and call Home what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ns.</P>
<P N="12">XII. That in a Cas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Universal and Pressing Concern, as Persons of differ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Interests have been in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o enter into the Trading Society, so it ought to frigh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> none from their Duty <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>omoting this Address, because Persons of the same di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>¦ring Interests joyn in it; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nce the Address it self is National, Loyal and Protestan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and one of the best Securities to the present Government; and so also is the Design, in which all doth Center.</P>
<P N="13">XIII. That albeit some ill Minded Persons bestir themselves in blowing about In∣sinuations, Surmises and Jealousies, to raise Dust and blind Peoples Eyes, yet these are so weak and groundless, and are convincingly found to be so very idle Stuff, that they deserve the utmost Contempt, since Persons of all Ranks engaged in the Ad∣dress, do on all Occasions openly disown all Intentions of Disquieting or Prejudging the Government in Church or State, as now by Law established, and declare their only Design to be His Majesty's true Honour, and the Good of the Countrey, which are inseparable, and the Christian Glory of the Church, in the Propagation of the Gospel by the Protestant Presbyterian Ministers of the Church of <HI>Scotland.</HI> Besides, that, there is an absolute Impossibility, if Matters be duly pondered, that it should be otherwise; or that an Address for the Meeting of that Parliament, which effectuated the late Happy Revolution, and for the Support of <HI>Caledonia,</HI> can have any other Tendency.</P>
<P N="14">XIV. That the General Assembly, by their Acts, and the Commission, by their Letter to the Colony, their Mission in Summer last, and their late Recommendation to Presbyteries, have testified so peculiar a Regard to the <HI>Caledonian-Undertaking,</HI> and so just a Sense of the great Interests of Religion therein, That no Minister of the Gos∣pel, who will not blindly truckle to a Party, or is not misled by the Power of Preju∣dice, can hesitat upon the Necessity, much less upon the Expediency of so Dutiful and Loyal an Address, when the Countries Good, and the Service of the Nation, doth so urgently require it.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="colophon">
<P><HI>GLASGOW,</HI> Printed in the Year, 1700.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

