<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The life &amp; death, travels and sufferings of Robert VVidders of Kellet in Lancashire who was one of the Lords worthies together with several testimonies of his neighbors and friends concerning him.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A48409</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing L2019</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R30948</IDNO>



<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 11733820</IDNO>


<AVAILABILITY><P>This text has been selected for inclusion in the EEBO-TCP: Navigations collection, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities. To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication ( http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48409)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48441)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1486:35)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The life &amp; death, travels and sufferings of Robert VVidders of Kellet in Lancashire who was one of the Lords worthies together with several testimonies of his neighbors and friends concerning him.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>16 [i.e. 28] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>[s.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1688.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2016-01-29.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM TYPE="personal name">Widers, Robert.</TERM><TERM TYPE="topical term">Society of Friends --  England.</TERM><TERM TYPE="topical term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2013-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Enrique Valdive</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Enrique Valdive</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A48409">
<STC T="W">L2019</STC>
<STC T="C">R30948</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">11733820</BIBNO>
<VID>48441</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE Life &amp; Death, TRAVELS AND SUFFERINGS OF <HI>Robert VVidders</HI> OF <HI>KELLET</HI> in <HI>LANCASHIRE;</HI> WHO Was one of the Lords Worthies, together with several Testimonies of his Neighbours and Friends concerning him.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI> Printed in the Year, 1688.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<HEAD><HI>A Short Testimony of the Life, Travels, Sufferings, and Death of that Faithful Servant of the Lord,</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>WHo was Born in <HI>Ʋpper-Kellet</HI> in <HI>Lancashire,</HI> of honest sub∣stantial Parentage, who was a Seeker after the Lord, and the knowledge of his way, and wandred from Mountain to Hill, but could find no rest nor satisfaction to my Soul, till it pleased the Lord God, that in the year 1652. Dear <HI>George Fox</HI> came into these parts, who informed my mind, and turned me to the Light of Christ Jesus in my inward parts, which was comfort to me that had long sat in darkness, and so I was convinced of Gods pure eternal Truth.</P>
<P>And in the year 1653. I and <HI>George Fox,</HI> and <HI>James Lancaster</HI> passed into <HI>Cumberland,</HI> where I and <HI>James Lancaster</HI> went to <HI>Emelton</HI> Steeple-house
<NOTE N="(1)" PLACE="marg">Steeple-House.</NOTE> and I spoke to the Priest and People in publique, and charged them in the presence of God, that if any of them could tell what would become of their Souls, if they should be cut off that pre∣sent, let them then speak; but never a one of them durst open their Mouthes.</P>
<P>Then the next First Day,
<NOTE N="(2)" PLACE="marg">Steeple-House.</NOTE> I was moved to go to <HI>Coldbeck</HI> Steeple-house, where I spoke to Priest <HI>Hut∣ton</HI> when he was in his High-place— And the rude people his Hearers did throw me down among the Seats, and drag∣ged, and trailed me forth into the Yard, and threw me down up∣on the Ground, and punshed and beat me till the blood gushed out at my mouth, and I lay for dead some time—But a woman took pity and held up my head, till my breath and life came to me again, as some said that stood by: Ever blessed be the Lord God, who up∣held and strengthened me by his eternal power, that I was not dis∣mayed, nor discouraged.</P>
<P>For on the same day in the afternoon I went seven Miles to <HI>Ackton</HI> Steeple house,
<NOTE N="(3)" PLACE="marg">Steeple-House.</NOTE> where I spoke to Priest <HI>Nicholls</HI> of <HI>Ackton</HI> in his High-place, and said, <HI>Come
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>down thou Deceiver, thou enemy of Christ, the hand of the Lord is against thee</HI>—And one <HI>William Brisco</HI> of <HI>Crofton</HI> then present, a Justice, commanded the Constables to secure me; and after exa∣mined me in the Priests House; and the Priest <HI>Nicholls</HI> flattered and fawned upon me. And I told him, The Spirit of Persecution lodged in him; he said <HI>Nay,</HI> he was no such man.</P>
<P>Then presently after he said to the Justice, I had stoln my Horse, and that he could find in his heart to be my Executioner with his own hands.—Then I told him again, Did not I say unto thee, That the Spirit of Persecution lodged in thee: So the said Justice. <HI>Brisco</HI> made a Warrant to send me to <HI>Carlile</HI> Goal; and after he had given the Warrant to the Constable, he called me before him again, and asked me by what Authority, or Power, I came to Seduce and be∣witch People.—I told him, I came not to Seduce and bewitch Peo∣ple, but I came in that Power which shall make thee, and all the Powers of the Earth bend and bow before it (to wit) the mighty Power of God. And as I spake these words from the word, the Terrour and Dread of God took hold upon him, and sm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te his heart: Then he called for his Warrant again out of the Constables hand, and caused the Constable to put me on to a <HI>Moor,</HI> near Night.—So the Lord delivered me at that time.</P>
<P>But not long after was I moved of the Lord to go to the said <HI>Ack∣ton-Steeple House</HI> again, where the said Justice <HI>Brisco</HI> had Power to send me to the Common-Goal at <HI>Carlile;</HI>
<NOTE N="(1)" PLACE="marg">Prison.</NOTE> where I didly in the Dungeon among Thieves a long time, and never came out Night nor Day till I was released.</P>
<P>Then afterwards I went to <HI>Lamplough Steeple-House</HI> and spoke to the Priest,
<NOTE N="(4)" PLACE="marg">Steeple-House</NOTE> and People; and they were very Rude, and tore the Hair off my Head, and rent my Coat.</P>
<P>And in the Afternoon the same Day, I went to another Steeple House two Miles from thence,
<NOTE N="(5)" PLACE="marg">Steeple-House.</NOTE> and spoke to the Priest: but he went away and would not stay.</P>
<P>Afterward I was with <HI>G.</HI>
<NOTE N="(6)" PLACE="marg">Steeple-House.</NOTE> <HI>F.</HI> in <HI>Scotland,</HI> and went there to a Steeple-House, called, <HI>New Munckland.</HI></P>
<P>Likewise, as I came back, I was at a Steeple House in <HI>Northumberland,</HI>
<NOTE N="(7)" PLACE="marg">Steeple-House.</NOTE> and there spoke to the People: And one <HI>Henry Harbuttle</HI> and his Wife were Con∣vinced that Day.</P>
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>
<P>And in <HI>Bishoprick</HI> I was at several Steeple-Houses. And in <HI>Bishopaukland</HI> I speaking thorow the Town,
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Several Stee∣ple-Houses.</NOTE> the People stoned me with Stones, and bruised my Head very Sore.</P>
<P>And likewise in <HI>York-shire,</HI> where particularly I was at a Steeple-House near <HI>Skipton,</HI> and spoke to Priest <HI>Webster,</HI> and bid him come down thou Inchanter, for he was a false Man, for he had been partly convinced and turned back again, <HI>Simon Magus</HI> like. I also spoke to the people, and to one Justice <HI>Coats,</HI> a moderate man then being present: And I directed them to the Word of God in the heart, which divided between the precious and the vile.</P>
<P>And then I went to a Moor side, where a few Friends were gather∣ed together; and I sat down among them, and it was immediately revealed to me, that the said Justice <HI>Coats</HI> would send for me.—And presently there came many Horse men and Foot, and said I must go before the Justice, who examined me, and said I had broken the Law in disturbing the Minister and People, and he might send me to Gaol at <HI>York</HI> Castle.—I Answered, Send me to <HI>York</HI> Castle if thou durst; for to that of God in thy Conscience am I made manifest. Then said he, I neither dare nor will: So took me by the Hand, and told me, I might take my own time.—And so the Lord preserved and delivered me, for which I praise his Holy Name.</P>
<P>And also, I was at several Steeple Houses in <HI>Lanca∣shire,</HI> as <HI>Warton, Halton, Kellet,</HI> and <HI>Arkholm</HI> Chapel,
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Lancas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ire Steeple-House.</NOTE> where at <HI>Arkholm</HI> the People were like to Fight; and I standing in the Chapel Door held up my Hand and spoke to the Priest to come forth and take up the People, they will needs Fight, they being in the Dogs Nature.</P>
<P>And at the Assize time at <HI>Lancaster,</HI> I went to the Steeple House and spoke to the Priest, whilst he was Preaching before the Judges; and the Priest was all in a Fright, and Smitten, and broke Up, and the People in a hast hurried out.</P>
<P>So the Lord God everlastingly Delivered, Kept, and Preserved me by his Everlasting Power in all my Travels, and Exercises of this kind; Blessed be his Holy Glorious Name for ever.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="account">
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>Here followeth a Breviate of the Heads of the great and sore Sufferings of this Faithful follower of the Lord, <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> both in Body, and Goods, for Tithes, for Sunday Shillings, (so called) and for Meetings by the Act against Conventicles, keeping the Testimony of Jesus, and his Consci∣ence clear in the sight of God.</HEAD>
<P>IN the Year 1654. Priest <HI>Schoolcroft</HI> of <HI>Caton</HI> in the County of <HI>Lancaster,</HI> being concerned in the Tyth of <HI>Ʋpper Kellet,</HI> did run <HI>Robert Widders</HI> to an Outlawry, and by a Writ cast him into Prison at <HI>Lancaster</HI> Castle, where he remained Prisoner about one year and an half, and then was freed by <HI>Supersedeas.</HI> And also the Farmer of the Outlawyrs came and made Distress for a Fine.</P>
<P>And they came again the second time and entred me for an Out∣lawry, but the Priest died; so that came to nothing.</P>
<P>And after that one <HI>William Atkinson</HI> being Farmer of Tythes of the said <HI>Ʋpper Kellet,</HI>
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Sufferings for Tythes.</NOTE> sued me at the Common Law for several years Tythes, and reco∣vered Judgment for ten pounds, and took Goods to the value of 12 <HI>l.</HI></P>
<P>In the year 1678 one <HI>James Greenwood,</HI> now of <HI>Bolton</HI> by the Sands in <HI>Lancashire,</HI> Farmer of the Tythes in <HI>Bolton</HI> Parish (whose manner and Custom is to pay a small Rent in lieu of Tythe Hay) sued <HI>Robert Widders</HI> for Tythe Hay in kind for five years. And brought <HI>Thomas Lucas</HI> his Thresher at <HI>Tytheborn,</HI> to swear at the As∣size at <HI>Lancaster,</HI> that <HI>Robert Widders</HI> had fixty Load of Hay growing in the year, out of which the Tythe-farmer <HI>Greenwood</HI> challenged six load of Hay by the year; tho Tythe hay was not payed in kind but a small Rent as aforesaid. And Judge <HI>Bertie</HI> giving treble dammage, they took Goods worth 6 <HI>l.</HI> 15 <HI>s.</HI></P>
<P>And at the same Assizes in 1678. the said Tythe-farmer <HI>Green∣wood</HI> sued <HI>Robert Widders</HI> for Tythe Corn for five years, he demand∣ing 23 <HI>l.</HI> 17 <HI>s.</HI> 5 <HI>d.</HI> as the said <HI>Thomas Lucas</HI> his Thresher, <HI>Richard Fawcett</HI> of <HI>Ʋpper Kellet,</HI> and <HI>John Greenwood</HI> the Tythe-farmer's Brother swore it, as the single value; and the said Judge <HI>Bertie</HI> gran∣ted treble value, which came to 71 <HI>l.</HI> 12 <HI>s.</HI> 3 <HI>d.</HI> for which the Bay∣liffs, <HI>Thomas Foxcroft</HI> and <HI>George Overend,</HI> both of <HI>Burton</HI> in <HI>Louns∣dall</HI>
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>in <HI>Yorkshire,</HI> with others, came and took Goods from the said <HI>Robert Widders</HI> worth 98 <HI>l.</HI> 1 <HI>s.</HI> as was valued by four credible men of his Neighbours—Locking up the Barn door, and Threshing out Corn at their pleasure, taking the Straw also away, being most part of a year in spoiling.</P>
<P>And again, in the year 1683. the said <HI>James Greenwood,</HI> Tythe-Farmer, sued the said <HI>Robert Widders</HI> at Common Law, for Tythe upon the Statute that gives treble dammage; and brought one <HI>Ri∣chard Tatem</HI> of <HI>Ireby</HI> in <HI>Lancashire,</HI> who swore that the Tythe of <HI>Ro∣bert Widder</HI>'s Corn in the year 1678. was worth 1 <HI>l.</HI> 1 <HI>s.</HI></P>
<P>And he brought one <HI>John Chapm in</HI> of <HI>Capenwray,</HI> whoswore that the Tythe of <HI>Robert Widder</HI>'s Corn in the year 79. was worth 5 <HI>s.</HI> 6 <HI>d.</HI></P>
<P>And again, the said <HI>Richard Tatem</HI> swore that the Tythe of <HI>Ro∣bert Widders</HI> Corn in the year 1680. was worth 1 <HI>l.</HI> 6 <HI>s.</HI></P>
<P>Also the said Tythe-Farmer <HI>Greenwood</HI> brought one <HI>William Mid∣dleton</HI> his Servant, who swore that the Tythe of <HI>Robert Widder</HI>'s Corn in the year 1682. was worth 4 <HI>l.</HI> 19 <HI>s.</HI></P>
<P>And upon these four said Evidences at <HI>Lancaster</HI> Assizes in the said year 1683. Judge <HI>Walcot</HI> gave Judgement for <HI>James Greenwood</HI> treble value, which was 22 <HI>l.</HI> 14 <HI>s.</HI> 6 <HI>d.</HI> the single value being 7 <HI>l.</HI> 11 <HI>s.</HI> 6 <HI>d.</HI></P>
<P>And <HI>Edward Charnock</HI> of <HI>Lancaster,</HI> a Sheriffs Bayliff, and <HI>Josiah Dickinson</HI> of <HI>Nether Kellet,</HI> Son-in-law to the said <HI>James Greenwood,</HI> Tythe-Farrner, came and took Goods from the said <HI>Robert Widders</HI> worth 27 <HI>l.</HI> 15 <HI>s.</HI> as prized by four Neighbours.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="account">
<HEAD>The Sufferings of <HI>Robert Widders</HI> for Sunday Shillings (so called.)</HEAD>
<P>THe 14th day of the 10th Month, 1683. came <HI>Robert Leaper</HI> of <HI>Over Kellet,</HI> Overseer, and demanded 3 <HI>s.</HI> of <HI>Robert Widders</HI> for being three daies absent from their Worship, which <HI>Robert Widders</HI> could not pay for Conscience sake: Then by vertue of a Warrant from <HI>Thomas Coall, Edward Wilson,</HI> and <HI>Roger Moore,</HI> all Justices, took Goods to the value of 3 <HI>s.</HI></P>
<P>Again the said Justice Fined the said <HI>Robert Widders</HI> 3 <HI>s.</HI> upon the said account; and by Warrant from the said Justices, came <HI>John Butterfield,</HI> and <HI>Robert Robinson,</HI> Wardens, upon the 27th of the 6th Month, 1684. and took Goods from the said <HI>Robert Widders</HI> worth 3 <HI>s.</HI></P>
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>
<P>Also <HI>Robert Widders</HI> was Fined the third time upon the said ac∣count 3 <HI>s.</HI> and by Warrant from the said Justices, upon the 10th day of the 9th Month 1684. came <HI>Richard Gibson,</HI> Constable, and <HI>Robert Robinson,</HI> Warden, both of <HI>Over Kellet,</HI> and took Goods worth 4 <HI>s.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="account">
<HEAD>Here followeth the Sufferings of that Dear and Faithful Servant of the Lord <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> for Meetings upon the Conventicle Act, and other waies.</HEAD>
<P><HI>RObert Widders</HI> for being at a Meeting was fined 3 <HI>l.</HI> 6 <HI>s.</HI> 8 <HI>d.</HI> by <HI>William Spencer</HI> and <HI>George Middleton,</HI> both Justices, for which <HI>William Haughton,</HI> Bayliff of <HI>Lancaster,</HI> took one Cow.</P>
<P><HI>Robert Widders</HI> having a peaceable Meeting in his House the 31 day of the 6th Month, 1684. where there came <HI>Richard Gibson</HI> Black∣smith, Constable, and <HI>Robert Robinson,</HI> Warden, both of <HI>Over Kellet,</HI> with a Warrant from Justice <HI>Bindless</HI> of <HI>Borrick,</HI> who put them on. And required Friends to go before the Justice, which they did; and by some Informers took Information, and Fined <HI>Robert Widders</HI> 20 <HI>l.</HI> for his House, himself and his Wife each 5 <HI>s.</HI> for being at the Meeting in his own House, by the Act against Conventicles.</P>
<P>And upon the 26th day of the 7th Month, 1684. came <HI>Richard Gibson</HI> Blacksmith, and <HI>Richard Fawcet</HI> Constables, and <HI>John Helme,</HI> and <HI>Thomas Lucas,</HI> Overseers, and <HI>John Butterfield,</HI> and <HI>Robert Ro∣binson,</HI> Wardens, all of the Township of <HI>Over Kellet,</HI> to <HI>Robert Widder</HI>'s house with a Warrant from the said Justice <HI>Bindless,</HI> bear∣ing date the 26th day of the 7th Month, and demanded the said Fines of <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> which he refusing to pay, they made di∣stress of his Goods worth 22 <HI>l.</HI> 7 <HI>s.</HI> as two of the said Officers did value them.</P>
<P>Again, <HI>Robert Widders</HI> for being at a peaceable Meeting at <HI>William Waithmans</HI> of <HI>Lindeth</HI> the 7th of the 7th Month 84. was Fined 10 <HI>s.</HI> by the said Justice <HI>Bindless</HI> of <HI>Borrick.</HI></P>
<P>Upon the Information of <HI>George Dawson,</HI> Warden, <HI>John Bachouse</HI> and <HI>John Hall,</HI> all of the Township of <HI>Warton,</HI> Officers; and upon the 10th day of the 9th Month, came the said <HI>Richard Gibson,</HI> Con∣stable, and <HI>Robert Robinson,</HI> Warden, both of <HI>Over Kellet,</HI> and took Goods worth 10 <HI>s.</HI> from the said <HI>Robert Widders.</HI></P>
<P>Again, <HI>Robert Widders</HI> for being at a Meeting at <HI>Richard Lancasters</HI> of <HI>Yelland</HI> the 21 day of the 7th Month 84. was fined 10 <HI>s.</HI> by the
<PB N="9" REF="5"/>said Jnstice <HI>Bindless,</HI> upon the Information of <HI>Robert Bachouse</HI> Consta∣and <HI>John Hubersty,</HI> Warden, both of <HI>Yelland,</HI> had Goods taken from him worth 10 <HI>s.</HI> by the said <HI>Richard Gibson, Robert Robinson,</HI> and <HI>Thomas Lucas,</HI> all of <HI>Over Kellet,</HI> the 20th of the 10th Month, 84.</P>
<P>Also <HI>Robbert Widders</HI> for being at a Meeting at <HI>Robert Hubersties</HI> of <HI>Capenwray,</HI> the 19th day of the 8<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h Month, 84. was fined 5 <HI>s.</HI> by <HI>Thomas Goall</HI> Justice, upon the Iuformation of <HI>Richard Gibson,</HI> and <HI>Thomas Lucas</HI> aforesaid, Constables, and <HI>Robert Robinson</HI> Warden—And the 10th day of the 9th Month, came the said Officers, and took Goods from <HI>Robert Widders</HI> worth 9 <HI>s.</HI> 6 <HI>d.</HI></P>
<P>And again, <HI>Robert Widders</HI> for having a peaceable Meeting at his House the 26th. of the 8th. Month, 1684. was fined the second time 20 <HI>l.</HI> for his House by the said <HI>Robert Bindless</HI> Justice, upon the In∣formation of the said <HI>Rich. Gibson</HI> and <HI>George Eskrigge</HI> both of <HI>Over Kellet;</HI> which <HI>George Eskrigge</HI> said it was against his will. And the 20th. day of the 10th. Month came the said <HI>Richard Gibson,</HI> Black∣smith, and <HI>Thomas Lucas,</HI> Constables, and <HI>Robert Robinson,</HI> War∣den, by Warrant from the said Justice <HI>Bindless;</HI> and rifled the House of <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> shot back locks and pulled out staples of Doors, and Arkes (altho they were told what was in them, and that it was not according to the Act) and then took Goods worth 10 <HI>l.</HI> 5 <HI>s.</HI> so let it fall.</P>
<P><HI>Robert Widders</HI> for being at a Meeting at <HI>John Bachouse</HI> of <HI>Yelland,</HI> the 14th. of the 10th. Month, 1684. was fined 10 <HI>s.</HI> by the said Justice <HI>Bindless;</HI> upon the Information of <HI>John Smith,</HI> Constable, and <HI>Thomas Watson,</HI> Warden, both of the said <HI>Yelland,</HI> had Goods taken from him worth▪ 10 <HI>s.</HI> by the said <HI>Richard Gibson, Thomas Lu∣cas,</HI> and <HI>Robert Robinson</HI> all of <HI>Over Kellet</HI> aforesaid, the 20th. day of the 10th. Month, 1684.</P>
<P>Thus the sufferings of <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> that Noble Innocent Suf∣ferer, and Faithful Servant and Witness for the Lord God, may be seen in short.</P>
<P><TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL ROLE="label"> </CELL>
<CELL ROLE="label"> <HI>l.</HI> </CELL>
<CELL ROLE="label"> <HI>s.</HI> </CELL>
<CELL ROLE="label"> <HI>d.</HI> </CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>His Suffering for Tithes</CELL>
<CELL>143</CELL>
<CELL>11</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>His Sufferings for Sunday Shillings</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
<CELL>10</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>His Sufferings for Meetings</CELL>
<CELL>37</CELL>
<CELL>18</CELL>
<CELL>02</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Total</CELL>
<CELL>181</CELL>
<CELL>19</CELL>
<CELL>02</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
<P>And likewise his suffering Imprisonment for the Testimony of the
<PB N="10" REF="6"/>Truth, and keeping his Couscience clear, was once at <HI>Carliste,</HI> and several times at <HI>Laneaster,</HI> which particularly are not here set down.</P>
<P>And of his going to Steeple-houses, and sometimes of his speaking to Priests and People, and warning them to repent, here is twelve particularly set down, besides divers others in the Bishoprick, or else where, not here inserted.</P>
<P>Likewise <HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bert Widders</HI> writ many Letters when he was in <HI>America,</HI> and from divers other parts, where he was in the Service of the Lord, he writ to his Relations and Friends of his Love to them, with good Advice and Counsel, with seasonable Exhortations, To be Faithful, and Noble, and Valiant for God and his Truth, over all Gain-sayers.—For Truth will stand and Remain, when all Hy∣pocrisie and deceit will fail; and come to an end.—Tho all his Writings particularly are not here set down.</P>
<P>But here are several Writings and Testimonies concerning this true and Noble Man for God in his day, <HI>Robert Widders.</HI> And of his Spirit, Gists, and Service in the Church of God, of which Christ Je∣sus is the holy eternal head, from several Friends, as may be seen here following.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD><HI>The T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stimony of</HI> Jane Widders, <HI>concerning her dear Husband,</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>THis Testimony I have to give for my dear and truly loving Hus∣band, That his Love was true and sincere to God, and for the prosperity of his blessed Truth was zealous.—He was a man (ever since it pleased God to joyn him and me together as Man and Wife) that was inclining to seek after the Lord. And in the time of his outward profession was zealous and honest, according to what he then knew, till it pleased the Lord, thorough the Testimony and direction of his faithful Servant and Minister <HI>G. F.</HI> To turn his mind from Darkness to the Light of Christ within, who through be∣lieving, obeying Christ and the Light of Life, and taking up the Cross to self, came to witness true peace with God, and so receiving the Truth in the Love of it, he became a companion of them that suf∣fered for the Truth. He was so faithful to God; and true for the good of his Soul, that he would have been loath to have fled the Cross for any outward advantage. Oh, the integrity of his Spirit and heart, I might speak much of the same: But it is known to God, and I hope
<PB N="11" REF="6"/>to many faithful Brethren and Sisters in the Lord, whom he hath left behind under the exercise of this transitory world. Oh! it is the Cry and breathing of my Soul unto God, that he would preserve me in faithfulness, as he hath done my deat Husband, to the end of my daies, and finishing my Course here.</P>
<P>During the time of his weakness of Body, he was kept by the Lords Power, in a sweet and precious frame of mind, and patient∣ness of Spirit, as one that had Resigned himself up into the Will of God; and many precious Scriptures passed thorow him in that time, as one that might in Truth declare what God had done for his Soul, as that of the Prophet, where he saith, <HI>The Lord will comfort Zion, and repair her decayed places, making her Desart as a Paradice, and her Wilderness as the Garden of the Lord, Mirth and Joy shall be found there, Thanksgiving and the voice of Praise.</HI>—And again that of the Prophet, where he saith, <HI>The work or fruit of Righteousness shall be Peace; and the effect of Righteousness, quietness, and assurance for ever.</HI>—He would often have said, his heart was filled with the Love of God, and that there was nothing betwixt him and the Lord. Thou hast taught me the way of Life, and makest me full of Joy with thy Countenance.—And seeing it is the will of God to take my dear Husband unto himself, to rest with him in eternal Glory, who was a dear and tender Husband unto me. Oh, that I in a holy sub∣mission to his blessed will, may be given up, desiring in all things to be made conformable to his heavenly mind, who alone is worthy to be seared, served, worshipped, and bowed unto, who is God over all blessed for ever. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Jane Widders.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD>Thomas Widders <HI>his Testimony concerning his dear and tender Father</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>THis Testimony I have to bear concerning my dear and Loving Father, who is Deceased, for whom I ever had a Reverent esteem, and that upon a double account, First, as he was a tender natural Father unto me. Secondly, as he was an Example of a holy Life and Conversation, and good Advice and Counsel to me. Also he was sincere and zealous for the propagation of the Name and Truth of God in his Day, which I know by true experience, was the desire of his heart, that all who took upon them the profession of the
<PB N="12" REF="7"/>holy Name of Jesus, might walk answerable to the same, by taking heed to the manifestation of the Spirit, and the appearances of the Grace of God, given them for that end, that they might live up in obedience to the same.—</P>
<P>He had likewise a large share of the sufferings of the People of God in his Day and Age, and did bear his Testimony Faithful for Christ Jesus, whom he witnessed to be come, the High Priest over the Houshold of God. And against the changable Priesthood, as seeing to the end thereof, to the bringing in of the better hope, whereby all them that believe are brought nigh unto God; and for the holding of his Testimony with a constant mind, he was exposed to great Suffe∣rings; but through the assistance of the Almighty God of <HI>Jacob,</HI> and the putting on of the Heavenly Armour, he was enabled to pass tho∣row them all like a valiant man; for which everlastingl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> blessed and praised be the Name of the holy, pure, powerful God, saith my Soul. He was a man that was given up to obey the Lord in what he required of him; neither would he reason with flesh and blood, but had his eye directed by the Lord, to the recompence of the heavenly Reward, which I believe was more to him, than all the fading World. Oh, the remembrance of his Spirit; and the coming up of the same in the endless life, doth often tender my heart. In the time of his weakness of Body, he was very patient, and often blessing and prasing the Name of the Lord for his favours and mercy to him through Christ Jesus. And having been in a weak Fit, he said, Mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e eye beholds <HI>Jerusalem</HI> a quiet-Habitation, into the posses∣sion whereof, it is the belief of my heart, God had gathered him, as one of the number of his Faithful Disciples and Followers, to rest with him in eternal blessedness for ever and evermore, <HI>Amen</HI> and <HI>Amen,</HI> saith my Soul,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thomas Widders.</SIGNED>
<POSTSCRIPT>
<P>My Father was about 68 years old when he deceased at his House in <HI>Over Kellet,</HI> who was Convinced, and owned the Truth above 34 years; who died the 20th of the First Month, 1686.</P>
</POSTSCRIPT></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD><HI>The Testimony of</HI> Margaret Fox <HI>concerning</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>I Have a Real and true Testimony in my heart to bear for my dear Friend and Brother <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> who was a Faithful Servant of
<PB N="13" REF="7"/>the Lord, and a good Souldier under the Banner of Jesus Christ in his Day; he never did shrink nor sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ed aside in no scrive not suf∣ferings, the Lord suffered him to be exercised in. I have known him, and been conversant with him Thirty four years, and we were made partakers of the eternal Truth near together, in the beginning of the infancy of Truth among us, now in out Age, when the Morning Stars Sang together. He was called forth to the service of the Lord early in this glorious Day that hath ever since shined upon us, glory be to the Son of Righteousness for ever. He went forth in the power and demonstration of the Spirit, and turned many unto God early in his Day. He was of a quick understanding, and the Gift of the Spirit of discerning was plentifully bestowed upon him. And tho he was not very much in Declaration, yet I know, and many also can bear Witness and Testimony, that his very presence and counte∣nance, and eye was refreshment and comfort unto them, and that the witness of God in their hearts would have answered his appearance, the power of the Lord was so quick and lively in him. What I write is Sealed in my heart to be true. He was a dear and a faithful Bro∣ther to me, and to my Children, in all our Tryals and Sufferings. It is too much for me to write here, what comfort, strength and as∣sistance he hath been to me and mine, both when we were in Prison and out of Prison; he would not have failed to come to see us night or day over two dangerous Sands, if it had been in the deep of Winter, many a time hath he done so of his own accord; and for the most part I have been sensible of his coming before he came, so near and dear he was unto me. But what shall I say! his Life, and all that ever he had, was given up freely to the Lord and his service: I be∣lieve he never neglected any service of the Lord, if it was made known unto him, either in <HI>England,</HI> or <HI>Scotland,</HI> or <HI>America</HI> be∣yond the Seas. He left his Wife and Family, and took his Life in his hand and went Joyfully to the service of the Lord. And when he went first forth into <HI>Cumberland</HI> and thereawaies, he was beaten, and stoned, and knocked down. O! the Imprisonments, and cold Winters that he passed thorow; so that his body was so starved, that he never quite recovered while he lived. He gave his back freely to the Smiter upon every occasion, and now in the latterend of his daies, the Tythe-mongers fell upon his outward Estate, and swept away many of his Goods; and when he had a little more together, the Tythe-monger and the Informers came again and fetched it away:
<PB N="14" REF="8"/>so that in the latter end of his daies his Sufferings were great, through the Spoilers, who suffered the spoiling of his Goods joyfully for Christs sake.—So that this good Man hath gone thorow many sorts of suf∣ferings, and now he is gone to his Rest, and his Father, for whom he hath suffered, where he certainly receiveth an eternal Reward with a <HI>Well done good and faithful Servant, enter thou into the Joy of the Lord.</HI>—I was with him in his sickness, and he was as patient as a Lamb, tho he could take little food, except such as he could drink, so he passed quietly, and patiently away, and the Lord dealt gently and kindly with him; and he is now in everlasting bliss and felicity with the eternal God, whom he served and suffered for.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>M. F.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD>Sarah Bachouse <HI>her Testimony of</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>THis Testimony did arise in me in tenderness and brokenness of Spirit, concerning our dear Friend <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> who hath laid down his head in peace with the Lord. He was a man sincere for God, and did bear a faithful Testimony for him to the end of his daies.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Sarah Bachouse.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD>Alice Hugginson <HI>her Testimony concerning</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>THis Testimony arises in my heart as a following stream, and issues out to the melting of my Spirit, and the refreshing of my Soul with the tendering love of God in the remembrance of my dear Friend and faithful Brother <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> who in his life time amongst us, was a good Example and pattern of holy life, in and with whom I have often been refreshed, and my heart overcome with the overcomings of the dear love of God to my Soul, so that I can say, dear <HI>Robert,</HI> thou art from us gone, surely for ever to live with the eternal One in Joy and Peace for evermore. Oh, the heart∣breaking tendering love that springs a new and fresh in me, in the re∣membrance of him, often refresheth my Soul, being satisfied that his Memorial in the Truth will never die, nor wear out.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Alice Hugginson.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<PB N="15" REF="8"/>
<HEAD>Anne Camm <HI>her Testimony concerning</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>I Feel a Concern upon my Spirit to write a few lines concerning my Dear deceased Friend and Brother <HI>Robert Widders;</HI> who was a Man that I dearly loved, and honoured in the Truth: for surely he was worthy being Faithful in his day, and Valiant for the Lord and his blessed Truth. I can truly say, he was Dear and Pretious unto me; one whom I had true comfort in, and refreshment by him in our converse together; one of the valiants of <HI>Israel,</HI> I may say he was, that never turned his back, but stood Faithful and Va∣liant for the living Truth upon the Earth, and was a great incou∣rager of all that made profession of the blessed Truth, to be Faith∣ful to the Lord, and true in their Testimony thereunto, as he had time and opportunity. Oh! what shall I say, my Soul lov'd him dearly: he was a true Friend of mine in the time of my Exercise, his true care and many tender visits, of which I have many times been a partaker; the very remembrance hereof makes my heart tender before the Lord, and even pray unto him, that he would raise up many living Testimony bearers for the Propagation of his ever lasting Truth; for which this my entirely beloved Friend and Brother did labour without Weariness, and Travel without Faint∣ing in his day. Oh! wherewithal shall I take up a Lamentation sufficient for the loss, or removal of so near a Friend, or amply demonstrate the tender Affection that ever lived in my heart, since the time I was first acquainted with him; howbeit, in this is my Spi∣rit comforted, and my Soul hath cause to praise the Lord on his be∣half, that is to say, The true sence and consideration of his unfeign∣ed and innocent life, together with his blessed and comfortable de∣parture; a few hours before which I was with him, and we were truly refreshed together by the same heart-tendring power which hath of∣ten consolated our Spirits in the daies that are past.</P>
<P>And further this Testimony lives in my heart, that the Lord hath given him a Mansion in the fulness of Joy, and set a Crown of Re∣joycing upon his head, where all tears are wiped away, and sorrow ended, where he shall sing praises to the everlasting God, who sits upon the Throne, and the Lamb, who is eternally worthy to be glo∣rified for evermore, <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Anne Camm.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Cammsgill,</HI> <DATE>30 of 3 Mo. 1687.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<PB N="16" REF="9"/>
<HEAD>Thomas Camm <HI>his Testimony concerning</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>IT was no doubt the serious Observation of a good man of Old, and therefore recommended unto others, that is to say, to mark the Upright man, especially his latter end, because it is blessedly accompanied with peace; notwithstanding that in his Pilgrimage here, he may meet with many troubles, and deep exercises, yet the Lord his God delivereth out of all; of whose faithfulness, our dear deceased Friend and Brother was a living witness; For tho in his time he met with manifold Troubles and great Sufferings for the Truths sake, that he had received in the love thereof, and did bear a Faithful Testimony unto, being like upright <HI>Joseph</HI> of Old, sorely shot at, yet his bow still abode in strength, his Arms being made strong by the Mighty God of <HI>Jacob,</HI> in whose power his Faith stood firm unto the end, without either <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ainting or wavering, a good Ex∣ample to all that knew him.</P>
<P>And the Memory thereof will live, and be of good savour to Ages to come, <HI>For the Righteous shall be had in everlasting remembrance.</HI> It is not with me to enter into the particulars of his Sufferings, but to leave that to others more capable. Yet having known him this thirty four years, ever since the Lord visited us with his Gospel day, that sprung from on high, and broke forth as a Morning without Clouds, which he with the first in these parts, received with great Joy and gladness of heart; and in this time have I known most of his Sufferings, both by way of Imprisonment, and the great spoil of his Goods, both for his Noble Testimony against the Antichristian Yoke of Tythes, and for Meeting with the Lord's innocent People to worship the eternal God. I shall in a general way say, That his suf∣ferings exceeded most that I know, being several times stript of much that was within the reach of the wicked Spoilers; But as his Sufferings and Troubles exceeded, so also did his Christian Constancy and Va∣lour, well may he be called one of the Valiants of God's <HI>Israel.</HI> O the Nobility, the Zeal, the Courage, and resignedness of his Spi∣rit into the Will of God in his greatest exercises (which fully de∣monstrated his love to the Truth, and his regard to the blessed Testi∣mony thereof) hath often affected my Spirit, for I never saw him in the least dejected or concerned, when his Cattle, Corn, and House∣hold Goods, was, as it were, by Wholesale swept away: But as one
<PB N="17" REF="9"/>that knew well for what he suffered, and enjoyed the sweetness of an eternal Rew<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> in heavenly I reasure, in an hundred sold here, to∣gether with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of a lassing Crown in Eternity.</P>
<P>Could and had <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to be as chearful and well content in the want of those <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> things, as in the abounding thereof, which he through the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ing of Almighty God had had a large share in, yet like upright <HI>Job,</HI> he blessed God that gave, and also permitted them to be taken away. I cannot but with affection remember his frequent expressions, in dircourse of our or other Friends Sufferings, as also mention some of them, that is to say, It is well with all that suffer for Truth's Cause, they are blessed, they enjoy peace. There is nothing that hath come, but there hath been need for it, and a ser∣vice in it; for all our Sufferings worketh together for our good, and Gods glory, and the remainder of the wrath of man will be restrai∣ned, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> And as his Nobility and Courage was exemplary, and of service to many; so also was his care and counsel, so that many have cause to bless the Lord on the behalf thereof.—I may also add to the Nobility of his Spirit, great Gravity, mixed with a Lamb-like inno∣cency, which was as a garment of Praise upon him, and made him right lovely in the eyes of the upright; together with his sound judg∣ment, clear discerning and savour, whereby a perfect distinction was made betwixt things of contrary natures, tho under one name or like∣ness. And as he was tender to cherish every appearance of good, yet sharp and piercing was his Testimony against all wicked∣ness and deceit: so that it was hard for workers of Iniquity or Hypo∣crites to stand before him, being filled with indignation against all false-heartedness, deceit and hypocrisie.—But his very soul was bound up with the upright in heart, and his Joy made full in the Faithful to Truths Testimony. And now the Lord whom beloved above all, and feared above the wrath of Man, and faithfully served in his day, hath given him a Crown of Glory, and a blessed portion in the rest that remains sure for the People of God, where his manifold sufferings are come to an end, his sorrows ceased, and all tears for ever wiped from his eyes, being ascended far above the reach of the wicked one and his Persecutors, where his Spirit lives with Just men made perfect in Christ our Lord, and with them is, and ever will be of blessed Me∣mory, having served out his Generation, and attained to a good old Age, and the honorable Gray Hairs is gathered to Rest in endless G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ory. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thomas Camm.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Cammsgill</HI> <DATE>6 of 4 Mo. 1687.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<PB N="18" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>William Hugginson <HI>his Testimony of the Life, and Death, of that ancient Friend and faithful Brother in the Truth, as it is in Jesus,</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>I having had good experience, and knowledge of him near Forty Years, can do no less, than give a short account of his Godly Life, and holy Conversation he had amongst us; surely he was a Man of a noble Spirit, indued with a large wisdom in Heavenly things.—He had also a deep discerning of the Spirits of men, so knew right well how to speak to their condition, and that in a right Season; his words being in the Lise and Power, he hath left many living wit∣nesses to speak forth the same—And he was a good example in times of Tryals and Sufferings, both in Body and Goods amongst us—for he had a large share of both, as doth appear in his own Testimony of Sufferings before written; only this I can say, being of the same Meeting with him, and very intimate, and open hearted in the things of God, and well knew his care and diligence, both in our quarterly, monthly, and particular Meetings, and more especially in our great suffering time by the Informers: His advice was to me, and that very tenderly, as one said that he became Eyes to the Blind, and Legs to the Lame, and many precious Exhortations proceeded out of his mouth, to the refreshing and comforting of the lowest Member, or hindermost of the Flook, and Heritage of God. He was so tenderly affectioned, that his very Life was given up to serve the Lord in his day, to strengthen and to stir up the pure Spirit of God in the very lowest member, so that I was, and am sensible that he answered the mind and will of God, and did that which was right in his Sight, and laid down his Head in peace with him. And now the remembrance of that great and dear love that he had to our Fa∣mily, often breaks my Heart into tenderenss, and refresheth my Soul, so that I can say my Family misseth him:—But to the Almigh∣ty God, we must all submit, to whom be Glory and praise for ever∣more, <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<P>And now dear <HI>Robert</HI> thou art gone, surely living with the Eter∣nal one, in that heavenly mansion of Rest, and peace for ever∣more, <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>William Hugginson.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<PB N="19" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>Thomas Dockrey <HI>his Testimony concerning</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>AS for our faithful Friend and Servant of the Lord, <HI>Robert Wid∣ders:</HI> He was called early of the day of God, when it pleased him to visit his Seed in the North of <HI>England,</HI> who in the year 1652. sent his faithful Minister, and joyful Ambassadour, <HI>G. F.</HI> with others to declare his Name and his Truth, and his Gospel, and the way of Peace, Life and Salvation by Jesus Christ, which indeed was the greatest joy and satisfaction to many a Soul in these parts, that ever they met with, who had been seeking after the Lord his peace, po∣wer and presence, which now many hath found, and lived in, and hath finished their time and course here, to the laying down of their Heads in peace with God, to whom be praise for ever.</P>
<P><HI>Robert Widders</HI> owned the Truth above 34 years; he was a Man zealous of mind, and fervent in Spirit, and true in Heart to serve the Lord God faithfully all his days, after he was turned to the Lord and to his eternal Truth.—He was steadfast in Faith, and of a sound judgment, and deep discerning, who visited many in Sick∣ness of body, and them that were in trouble of Conscience, and had a true discerning of their spiritual conditions, and could have spoken a word in season sutable to them: And to those that were innocent, and truly desirous after good, he was loving and tender, and of a chearful Countenance.—But to the Hypocrites, and false in Heart, he was sharp, and threshing, having the Spirit of Judgment, so that his Spirit might often have been known by his Countenance.</P>
<P>But he greatly loved Unity amongst Brethren in the Spirit, and power of the Lord God.—And he was one that chosed rather to suffer affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleasure of Sin, and of this world for a season: For as it may be seen before in this little Book, he was a great Sufferer both in Imprisonment and spoiling of Goods: For his Testimony to the Truth, and for keeping his Conscience clear, he was freely given up, and faithful and true in, and thorow them all, well knowing that the Doctrine of Jesus was and is true: Blessed are these that suffer Persecution for Righte∣ousness sake, theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven; and had rather have suffered much, than that the Lord, and his holy Truth should be dishonoured, or his people evil spoken of.</P>
<P>And now he hath finished his course, and kept the Faith, having
<PB N="20" REF="11"/>lived in the Truth, and dyed in the Lord (Aged about sixty eight years) and blessed are such for they Rest from their Labour, and their Works follow them;—And he is gone as to his natural Life, but his Spirit and Life spiritually yet remaineth, and lives; as <HI>He that believeth in me,</HI> said Jesus, <HI>hath everlasting Life:</HI> And this is the will of him that sent me. That every one which seeth the Son, and believeth on him, may have everlasting Life, and I will raise him up at the last day: And he that liveth, and believeth in me shall never die.</P>
<P>And the Saints in the Apostles days, had a Life hid with Christ in God, who were come to the Spirits of just men made perfect, to the general assembly, and Church of the first-born, whose Names are written in Heaven: And to God the judge of all, to whom all must give account, and who is the just rewarder of all, according to their deeds done in the Body, be they good or evil.—And we that yet remain in the Body, God Almighty keep and preserve us faithful and true to him, to his Glory, to the end of our days, and to our eternal Peace and Felicity, <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thomas Dockrey.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD>Thomas Jackson <HI>his Testimony of</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>THis Testimony I have to give, concerning our dear and faith∣ful Friend <HI>Robert Widders.</HI> He was a zealous Man, and sin∣cere, for God in his day, and servent in Spirit always ready, and willing to serve the Lord, wholly resigned thereunto in Spirit and Body, and Estate, and his Travels, Exercises, Tryals and Suffer∣ings doth certifie, ever since he was called into the work of the Lord, and he was called early, and indured the heat of the day.—And after I came into acquaintance and fellowship with him, he was a Strength and Comfort to me, for which I have cause to magnifie the Lord on his behalf; for I was sensible of his labour of Love, and care in the Church of God, that it must be preserved in Unity as one Body, of which Jesus Christ is head, and that it might be presented without spot or wrinkle, or any such thing unto God the Father — He was a good example, and adorned his profession with a good Conversation, (which is the substantial part of Religion) He was one of the Valiants in <HI>Isruel,</HI> whose Bow abode in strength, and
<PB N="21" REF="11"/>carried perfectly to the mark; his Bow was bent against Hypocrifie and Deceit, and Unrighteousness; his Feet was shod with the prepa∣ration of the Gospel of Peace: But prepared, and ready to trample upon that which would have risen in opposition to the Life, and power of Godliness, though never so fair a shew; he was of a good discerning, and found in judgment, his Countenance very amiable, to those that were faithful to God and his Truth. — But terrible to the workers of Iniquity; — his deportment was Grace and Comely; I had a reverent esteem of him in my Heart, being one of the same Meeting with him, he is often fresh in my remembrance, for I have often been refreshed with his presence: And altho his Body be removed from us, yet his memorial lives with us, and is worthy to be recorded to future Ages; that by the Foot steps of the Flock of Christ's Companions, many who make a true enquity after the beloved of their Soul, may come into the fold of Rest, and lay down their Heads in everlasting peace, as he hath done when time here shall be no more.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thomas Jackson.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD>Robert Hubbersty <HI>his Testimony concerning</HI> Robert Widders</HEAD>
<P>THis loving Testimony I have to bear, for our ancient and well beloved Friend and Brother <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> who indeed was a very Fatherly man amongst us, for so I can truly call him, in respect of his Godly care, and unse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gned love he had unto the Lords Chil∣dren and People, for indeed he was one of the Lords Valiants, who ventured his life freely for the Captain of his Salvation, and was never weary nor fainted in his service that he required on him, tho he went many times, as with his life in his Hand to many Steeple∣houses, and spoke the word of the Lord faithfully, both to Priests and People, who often recieved great abuses from them, and castings into Prisons: But blessed be the Lord for ever more, who gave him courage and boldness and made him of an undanted Spirit, that he grew more and more valiant for the Lord, and did bear the Burthen in the heat of the day, and passed thorow great Sufferings, both in Body, Prisons and Goods, for bearing his faithful Testimony to the Truth, and for keeping his Conscience clear in the sight of God. But this good man indured all with great patience, constancy and
<PB N="22" REF="12"/>chearfulness.—Dear <HI>Robert,</HI> the remembrance of thee refresheth my Soul, for thou ever preferred the Lords business before thine own, and was very faithful and valiant for him, and never lost an Inch of Ground: He was a Man of a quick sight spiritually, of good di∣scerning, and sound judgment: I speak my own experience of him, and as I took his Counsel, it always wrought to a good effect.—He was one that truly feared the Lord, his delight was in obeying of him, who taught him to live a Godly life, in this evil World, and hath made his latter end everlastingly blessed.—And now dear <HI>Ro∣bert,</HI> thou hast been an upright man, and hath followed the Lord fully, and hath received the Answer of a good and faithful Servant, and is entered into the joy of the Lord, to reign with him in Glory, out of the reach of all the Persecutors and greedy Informers: But certainly the Lord will plead with them in Judgment, who will reward all according to their deeds, done in the Body and out of the Body, be they good or evil.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Robert Hubbersty.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD>John Hudson <HI>his Testimony of</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>THE Testimony that I have to bear for our dear Friend <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> he was a Man of a Noble and discerning Spirit, and very weighty in judgment, he was tender of the young in the Truth, and if any walked disorderly, he was ready to labour with them for their good, by exhorting them, and would have dealt plainly with all people, and would have said, that was the purest love that dealt plainest, and if any was weak, and had a tenderness in them, he was kind to such, and would have admonished them to mind the Lord, and he would give them strength over the Enemy; yea, he was a Man that was valiant for the Lord, and his Truth, as his life and Sufferings does demonstrate, as by Imprisonments, and spoiling of his Goods for Tithes, and by the Informers: But in them all still was noble and chearful, and exhorting Friends to be faithful, and trust the Lord with all, who was a strength to me in the time of my Sufferings, when the Informers followed us very hotly, both week∣days, and other Meetings: dear <HI>Robert</HI> was very constant, tho weak∣ly of Body, and incouraged Friends to be faithful to the Lord, and diligent to their Meetings, and the Lord in mercy did strengthen us, and made us willing to give up for his Name and Truth-sake, and
<PB N="23" REF="12"/>the Lord hath given us peace therein. And tho dear <HI>Robert</HI> suffered much by the Tythe-mongers and Informers, yet he was still Noble, Patient and chearful, who was so good an Example, as is worthy to be had in Remembrance. And tho he be removed outwardly to endless Rest with the Lord, yet his Memorial of good Savour lives with us.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>John Hudson.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD><HI>The Testimony of</HI> John Beakbayne <HI>concerning</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>THis Testimony I have to bear: He was a man quick spirited, and of a chearful Countenance; and when the Messengers of the Truth came among us, he was one with the first in these parts that re∣ceived them and their Testimony, which he hath faithfully kept and holden, even to the last of his daies. He was sharp in Reproof, gentle in Admonition: his Bow abode in strength; he was as a sharp Sword to Deceit and Hypocrisie, but as Balm and Oyl to help the Tender and afflicted in Spirit about spiritual things. I being newly Convinced of the Truth, he was ready to give good Advice to me, and told me, as concerning the Work of Truth, That there was no∣thing got but through Judgment, which then I knew little of: but since hath found it the way to Life and Mercy.—I have been Prisoner with him several times at <HI>Lancaster,</HI> and his chearful Countenance, and good Example and Advice to Friends, alwaies Ministred strength and comfort. He was as an Elder, and his presence was encouraging. — And tho he be gone as to the outward man, yet his Life and Spi∣rit is in our Remembrance. His Sufferings were great, yet he never did shrink what ever Storm or Tempest came, but followed Christ Jesus his Captain through sufferings patiently, and hath obtained an eternal Reward, where the Spoilers cannot come.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>John Beakbayne.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD>Robert Barrow <HI>his Testimony of</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>O It is freshly in my mind the many comfortable daies and sex∣sons of Love that we have had together in the enjoyment of God's Power and Presence, in our Spiritual exercise from time to time. Within this 34 years since <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Lord our God brought <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o believe in his N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me, and ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,
<PB N="24" REF="13"/>whereby Redemption from the evil of the World is known, and the freeing vertue of the eternal Truth witnessed.—And when I con∣sider his sincerity and-zeal, he was alwaies concerned for the Testi∣mony of Jesus, for the promoting of the glorious Gospel Worship, and for the good of the Brotherhood; in which heavenly exercise the Lord did endue him with wisdom, and gave him a discerning eye, and the Spirit of a sound mind and true judgment, in the Authority and Dominion of which he was made bold and valiant for the Truth of God upon earth; and therein was a terror to Evil-doers where e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er he came of all sorts, as Priests, hypocritical Professors, and profane or Will-worshippers of any kind.—And if any had been overtaken with a fault (as the Apostle said) he would have endeavoured to have restored them with the Spirit of Meekness, good Advice, and sound Judgment; and he would have said our God hath put us upon a Spiritual Travel, and ought not to leave a Hoof in <HI>Egypt;</HI> he was a a strength and encourager to the Faithful.—And as concerning his Travels in godly Zeal for the Truths sake, both in <HI>England, Scotland,</HI> and some parts of <HI>America,</HI> tho his Gift was not much in Declarati∣on, yet he had the word of Wisdom, discerning and sound Judg∣ment: good Advice and Admonition to Friends, and for the esta∣blishing them in the Faith and Truth of God, where ever he came; and herein the Lord prospered his Work, and labour of Love in his service. And he was faithful in his Testimony against Tythes, the Hirling Priests, and Impropriators, and was a great sufferer by them.—And was faithful and zealous, for meeting to Worship God in the Spirit and in the Truth as Christ Jesus set it up above sixteen hundred years since, tho for standing his Testimony herein. He was a Suf∣ferer; but in all these exercises he was valiant and stedfast, and the Lord God did bear up his head, and through the enjoyment of Gods power and presence, he was content in every condition; of a chearful mind and good example.</P>
<P>And when weakness of Body attended him, and the time of his departure drew hear, his love to God, and good will to his Brethren filled his heart with tenderness and heavenly comfort, in the feeling sence of which, I with other Friends being present, was made glad in the Lord on his behalf, for he talked with me very sensibly within unto hours of his departing; at which time I was assured he was Re∣odtemed from the Earth, and quit of all Worldly trouble and care, and in the enjoyment of the seasoning Grace, and sanctifying power
<PB N="25" REF="13"/>of God, he hath ceased from his Labour, and left a good savour be∣hind him, and laid down his Head in peace.—This being the sence, and Testimony of one of his old acquaintance, the blessed Truth and Unity of the peaceable Spirit of Life.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Robert Barrow.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD>James Taylor <HI>his Testimony of</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>THis is a short but true account of the faithfulness, and innocen∣cy of <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> being with him some months to visit Friends, both in prison, and out of prison, in <HI>Cheshire, Darbyshire, Yorkshire, Bishoprick,</HI> often meeting with hardships in the way, it be∣ing in Winter, wicked people would take up Stones, and roul them in Snow, and cast them at us: And in all this time and travel, dear <HI>Robert</HI> was still meek and harmless, yet noble and valiant for the Truth of God.—And I am satisfied that my faithful and well be∣loved Friend is entered into everlasting Rest, Joy and Peace, where I hope e're long to be also.</P>
<P><HI>This is written in much weakness of Body, by me</HI> James Taylor, <HI>who is since Dead.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD>James Lancaster <HI>his Testimony concerning</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>THis Testimony I have concerning our dear Friend, and my fellow Traveller in the Service of God, late deceased, at his own House at <HI>Kellet</HI> in <HI>Lancashire,</HI> yet lives in the Spirit in our remembrance of his works and labour of love, with us in out Ser∣vice all along, as we travelled in the Truth; soon after it appeared amongst us, being well informed in our selves by a Messenger of God, sent of him into our North Country, calling us out of the worlds worships and forms, and likenesses, to the substance, Jesus Christ, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> his Light within Gods Covenant, so came our peace made mani∣fest within, in our Hearts, Souls, Minds and Spirits, and so came to know what did belong to our peace in that day of our Visitation from on high from God, by his Light, Grace and Spirit within, and so were called to go to our neighbouring County, called <HI>Cumber∣land,</HI> that they might come to the same, the Light of Christ Jesus within; in whom and by whom we found that, which we had lost
<PB N="26" REF="14"/>in <HI>Adam</HI> in the fall, thorow disobedience to God, we found Souls, Life and Peace.—This was our message all along in that Coun∣ty: And afterward in <HI>Scotland,</HI> in <HI>Northumberland, Bishoprick, York∣shire,</HI> and in our own County <HI>Lancashire,</HI> and in several Counties in <HI>England,</HI> with <HI>London</HI> City, and were well refreshed, meeting with our Brethren there, who had been in the same work with us, and had our reward from God and Life, and peace in our own Bo∣soms, that which will last and indure, and abode with us in all forms and tempests, great and high Winds, made great Tossings, and put great fears upon many: But blessed everlastingly be the Name of our God, in which we first believed, and went out; none of these things did move us, so that we might finish our course, and testings, as he my dear Brother and fellow Traveller has done and ended his days in peace: And I farther give in my Testimony con∣cerning our dear Brother <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> who was a Man as my self, stricken in years, yet was willingly given up at the requirings of the Lord, as to go into some parts of <HI>America,</HI> where we arrived at <HI>Barbados</HI> in seven weeks time, where we visited our Friends and Brethren in the Truth, and from thence he with other Friends pas∣sed to <HI>Jamaica,</HI> and was very serviceable there, and from thence <HI>Robert Widders</HI> with other Friends passed to <HI>Virginia,</HI> and so to <HI>Mary-land;</HI> after that <HI>Robert</HI> with other Friends passed thorow the Wilderness, to East and West <HI>Jersey, Long-Island, New-York,</HI> and so by several Islands to <HI>Rhode-Is<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>and,</HI> and <HI>New England,</HI> where we had many precious meetings amongst Friends: And after our Ser∣vice was performed in <HI>New-England</HI> with much difficulty, <HI>Robert Widders</HI> with other Friends, returned thorow the Wilderness to <HI>Vir∣ginie,</HI> and <HI>Mary-land</HI> again, and had good Service there in our Jour∣ney, where many were turned from the dumb Idol, Shepherds to serve the living God in the Spirit and in the Truth: And so with much hardship in the Wilderness, having nodwelling places to lay our Heads in, but in the open wilderness, several Nights lodged among the <HI>Indians</HI> and <HI>Savage</HI> Creatures, who did roar and make a noise, when we had kindled a Fire to w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rm us with Sticks—Also we passed thorow some parts of <HI>Pensilbania,</HI> as now so called, where was some <HI>Deans</HI> and <HI>Swedes,</HI> which entortained us quietly, and so to <HI>Maryland</HI> as above-said. — And when we had done our service for God in divers parts of <HI>America,</HI> from <HI>Maryland</HI> (having taken leave of our Brethren) we came for <HI>Old England</HI> our Native Coun∣try,
<PB N="27" REF="14"/>thorow the mercy of God, and was glad to meet with our an∣cient Brethren in the Unity of the Truth, both in <HI>London</HI> and seve∣ral parts of this Nation, who received us in love, and we them, each having our reward from God of well doing; who was, and is the deliverer, keeper and preservet of his people, throughout all Ages, to him be Praise, Honour and Glory for ever, <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>James Lancaster.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD>Richard Lancaster <HI>his Testimony concerning</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>AS for our dear Brother in the Lord, <HI>Robert Widders</HI> deceased, this little Testi∣mony rose in my heart to bear for him. He was a man of a clear understand∣ing, and sound in Judgment in the things that pertains to the way and worship of the Lord. And as I may truly say, he was as one of the Antients of <HI>Israel,</HI> who follow∣ed the Lord fully whilst he had a day on this side the Grave: for his innocent life and blameless Conversation did adorn his profession, and brought honour to the Lord, and now everlasting Joy and Felicity is his Reward. — For indeed he was a wise man, who built upon the sure Foundation that endures for ever, for all the Storms and Winds could not shake this true man, who hath many times been Tryed divers waies, and yet never did shrink. So my desire to the Lord is, that in his Footsteps of Truth I may walk, which is of more worth than bare talk.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Richard Lancaster.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="testimony">
<HEAD>G.F<HI>'s Testimony concerning</HI> Robert Widders.</HEAD>
<P>MAny here are the Testimonies of the Sufferings, and Travels of our Dear Bro∣ther <HI>Robert Widders,</HI> both of his Neighbours and Friends that very well knew him, and his faithfulness to the Lord, and his Godly Conversation which became the Gospel of Christ, which he did profess; who in his Day, was as a Son of Thunder against Sin, Wickedness and Unfaithfulness in People that did not walk according to what they profest. After that he was turned from the Darkness, and to the Light the Life in Christ, and from the power of Satan to God. He was very Valiant for his Name and Truth, and often did Jeopardy his Life for the same, for I knew him all along from his Convincement; and he often Traveled with me, and in great hard∣ships many times: He Travelled with me into <HI>Scotland,</HI> and several times I was had before the Governours, and he abode with me, and did not forsake me. And when I was had before <HI>Oliver</HI>'s Council at <HI>Edenburgh</HI> in <HI>Scotland,</HI> and they Banished me out of <HI>Scotland,</HI> he was with me; and also when I was Banished out of <HI>Johnsons</HI> in <HI>Scot∣land,</HI> and put over the Water with a Company of Souldiers, he was one that was Banished out of the City with me, and many hardships both in <HI>Scotland</HI> and <HI>England,</HI> and other places he went through with me, but the Lord's eternal Arm and Power did support us. And when <HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>th</HI>'s Army was up, he was made to ride among them
<PB N="16" REF="15" MS="y"/>with a Twig in his Hand, and told them, <HI>The Lord with his Rod of Iron would break them to pieces;</HI> and the Lord preserved his Life among them, but they took his Horse from him, and in a few daies after they were all broken to pieces, and scat∣tered.</P>
<P>And about 1670. he Travelled with me into <HI>America, Barbados, Jamaica, Virginia</HI> and <HI>Maryland,</HI> and through the Wilderness to <HI>Long Island,</HI> and from thence to <HI>Rhode Island,</HI> and many other places; and likewise back again from <HI>Rhode Island</HI> through the Wilderness to <HI>Maryland,</HI> lying in the Woods, whether it was Winter or Sum∣mer many times, through great perils and danger of wild Beasts, and Men Eaters, but the Lord carried us by his Arm and Power over all, and out of the fear of all. And many blessed and precious Meetings we had both among Friends and Friendly People, and the <HI>Indian</HI> Emperours, Kings, and Councils of their People. And the Lord by his power preserved us from the Pyrats and Robbers on the Sea, who were very many at that time, and brought him well home to his Wife. And he was both an Elder and Pillar, and one of God's Valiants in his heavenly <HI>Israel,</HI> who died in the Divine, Holy, and Precious Faith, which was his Victory in all his inward and outward Sufferings, who did not account his Life dear for Christ's sake, as knowing that they that Die with him, shall Live with him; and they which Suffer with him, shall Reign with him, and blessed are they that die in the Lord, they Rest from their Labour, and their Works follow them, as certainly this Faithful <HI>Robert Widders</HI> did; and tho the loss of his outward presence to his dear Wife and Family is great, yet they may be glad in the Lord they enjoy him in the Spirit; For Christ said, <HI>He that believeth in me, tho he were dead, yet he shall Live</HI> (mark Live) <HI>and whosoever Liveth and believeth in me, shall never die,</HI> John 11.25, 26. For he that believeth in Christ hath eternal and everlasting Life, a Life in Christ that shall never die, tho they do put off their outward Tabernacle or Earthly House, <HI>Yet they know they have a Build∣ing of God, a House not made with hands, Eternal in the Heavens,</HI> 2 Cor. 5. And of this I do believe our dear Friend and Brother <HI>Robert Widders</HI> had an Assurance; and so I am satisfied that he is well in the Lord: Unto Him for ever be Glory, who is, and hath been, and will be the Support, Succour. Refresher, Strength, and Up∣holder of all his People: Glory over all be unto Him and His Holy Name forever. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>G. F.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>THE END.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="15"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

