<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-03-13</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Check for blanks. Checked for signatures. Checked for #s. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Converted 122 $-groups to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld". Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N00524">
<STC T="E">652</STC>
<STC T="W">M1092</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99018635</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="000652_0000_0FA99F706DC7E4F8"/>
<PB REF="000652_0001_0FA99F712DAB8F10"/>
<P><HI>The Day, &amp; the Work of the Day.</HI></P>
<P>A Brief DISCOURSE, ON What <HI>Fears,</HI> we may have at THIS TIME to quicken us; What <HI>Hopes</HI> there are for us at THIS TIME to comfort us: AND What <HI>Prayers</HI> would be Likely to turn our FEARS into HOPES. WITH Reflections upon <HI>Time</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> now come upon the Church OF GOD, And Collections of certain <HI>Prophesies</HI> relating to the present Circum∣stances of <HI>New-England.</HI> Uttered on a FAST, kept in <HI>Boston, July</HI> 6<HI>th:</HI> 1693.</P>
<P>By COTTON MATHER.</P>
<P><HI>Boston</HI> Printed and Sold by <HI>B. Harris,</HI> 1693.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="discourse">
<PB N="3" REF="000652_0001_0FA99F712DAB8F10"/>
<HEAD>The Day, and the Work of the Day.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Discours'd on a Day of Prayer kept in the Old-Meeting-House, at Bo∣ston, the 6th day of the 5 m. 1693.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>It is written in Job XV. 4.</BIBL>
<Q><HI>Thou Castest off Fear and Restrainest Prayer before God.</HI></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>IN the Dismal and the Cloudy Dayes, which are now come upon us, there are especially two things exceeding Seaso∣nable; namely, <HI>Fear</HI> and P<HI>rayer.</HI></P>
<P N="1">I. The <HI>Frame</HI> of all the most a∣greeable to this <HI>Awful</HI> Day, is FEAR.
<PB N="4" REF="000652_0002_0FA99F71EB778488"/>
As F<HI>ear</HI> is the peculiar <HI>Plague</HI> of the Unhappy Times that are now rol∣ling over us; for we are fallen into those Times whereof it was long since foretold, in <HI>Luc.</HI> 21. 26. <HI>Mens hearts▪ will fail them for</HI> F<HI>ear, and for Looking after those things which are coming on the Earth:</HI> So, <HI>Fear,</HI> 'tis to be the peculiar <HI>Grace</HI> of these Times: <HI>these</HI> are the Times, wherein every one, that would be safe, must follow the pattern of him, concerning whom, we are informed, in Heb. 11. 7. <HI>Be∣ing warned of God, of things not seen as yet, moved with Fear, he prepared an Ark, to the Saving of his House.</HI> There <HI>are,</HI> and one of the Ancients, tho' he <HI>saw not all things,</HI> could yet <HI>see</HI> that there ever <HI>were,</HI> four sorts of people in the world. There are some who, <HI>neither Hope nor Fear:</HI> Such are <HI>Atheistical</HI> Transgressors, to whom neither the Favour of God is Comfortable, nor His Anger For∣midable. There are some who, <HI>Fear but Hope not;</HI> such are <HI>Despair∣ing</HI> Transgressors; to whom the
<PB N="5" REF="000652_0002_0FA99F71EB778488"/>
Dreadful Thundrings of Mount <HI>Si∣nai,</HI> arrive without the Joyful Ti∣dings of Mount <HI>Sion.</HI> There are some who, <HI>Hope but Fear not;</HI> Such are P<HI>resuming</HI> Transgressors, who as the Heathen usually Endued their Gods with Vices like their own, so these may have it spoken by God unto them, <HI>Thou thoughtest I was al∣together such an one▪ as thy self.</HI> But there are some who both <HI>Hope</HI> and F<HI>ear:</HI> because God is <HI>Good,</HI> therefore He is their <HI>Hope,</HI> and because He is <HI>Just,</HI> therefore He is▪ their <HI>Fear;</HI> yea, They <HI>Fear the</HI> L<HI>ord and His Goodness;</HI> and, <HI>They Hope that being a God of Righteousness, He will Hear them. Such</HI> all people should be, and all pious people will be; especi∣ally <HI>Now</HI> at a Time, when every <HI>David</HI> would see more than ordinar<HI>y</HI> cause to say, as in <HI>Psa.</HI> 119. 120. <HI>Lord, my Flesh Trembles for fear of thee, and I am afraid of thy Judg∣ments.</HI></P>
<P N="2">II. And what then should be the <HI>Work</HI> most agreeable to this <HI>Crying</HI>
<PB N="6" REF="000652_0003_0FA99F72AD3BD580"/>
Day, but PRAYER? It is the <HI>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI> verse of that Psalm, which runs over the chief Concernments of Hu∣mane Life, Psal. 10<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 6, 13, 19, 28. <HI>Then they cried unto the Lord in their Trouble, and He delivered them out of their Distresses.</HI> Truly all our Con∣cernments do at all Times call for such <HI>Intercalations;</HI> but especially at these Times, when we may say, with the Dying Martyr, <HI>Pray, Pray, Pray; never more need than Now!</HI> The Great God, is now doing of those things, whereof He says unto us, as in <HI>Amos</HI> 4. 12. <HI>Because I will do this, prepare to meet thy God, O Israel:</HI> But in what posture dare we meet our God, un∣less in <HI>Prayer</HI> upon our Knees? There are several <HI>Ke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> of our Welfare; I do not mention the Jewish Enumeration of them, for there are more than <HI>Fear</HI> of, those <HI>Ke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,</HI> which the God of Heaven still keeps in His own Hands. We have extraordinary oc∣casions for the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urning of those <HI>Ke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,</HI> but it is P<HI>rayer</HI> that must Jog the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Hand, which has the
<PB N="7" REF="000652_0003_0FA99F72AD3BD580"/>
Turning o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> them. Briefly, we are in a Time, of Difficulties, wherein we can have none but <HI>Refuges of Lies,</HI> except we do in Truth come unto, that Experience, in Psal. 34. 6. <HI>This poor man cry'd, and the Lord heard him, and saved him out of all his Troubles.</HI></P>
<P>Well then, To Quicken both our Godly F<HI>ear,</HI> and our Fervent P<HI>rayer,</HI> I have now Read you a <HI>Text,</HI> which cannot be unseasonable.</P>
<P>One of <HI>Jobs</HI> Comforters, is here managing a Disputation against that Afflicted Saint, wherein, methinks, he deals but roughly with him; thereunto Instigated, no doubt, by misunderstanding certain passages in the Discourse of <HI>Job.</HI> It is the <HI>L</HI>ot of many a <HI>good man,</HI> to have many an <HI>Ill Charge</HI> injuriously made upon him. <HI>Defamations,</HI> the fruit of <HI>mis∣constructions,</HI> are among the most usual Trials of the Innocent. Holy <HI>Job</HI> is here charged, first, with S<HI>peaking</HI> unwisely, then, with <HI>Acting</HI> wickedly. As to the <HI>Latter,</HI> in our
<PB N="8" REF="000652_0004_0FA99F736BCA1158"/>
Text, he is Indicted, for Neglecting both the <HI>Inward</HI> and the <HI>Outward</HI> Worship of God. <HI>Fear,</HI> is by a <HI>Sy∣necdoche</HI> put for all the <HI>Inward,</HI> and <HI>Prayer,</HI> by a like <HI>Synecdoche</HI> put for all the <HI>Outward.</HI> The style of our Text, is indeed so Oriental, that we might as lawfully as usefully, il∣lustrate it, with a very various <HI>Para∣phrase.</HI> But we shall confine our selves to the sense most obvious in our own Translation.</P>
<P>The first Article of the Charge is, <HI>Thou Castest off Fear.</HI> By that <HI>Fear</HI> is meant Eminently, <HI>The Fear of God.</HI> When we say, <HI>The Word,</HI> we use to mean, <HI>The Word of God;</HI> as if there were no <HI>Word</HI> but <HI>Gods;</HI> for indeed there is none so considerable as that <HI>Word.</HI> Thus, <HI>The Fear,</HI> here spo∣ken of, may note, <HI>The Fear of God;</HI> inasmuch as there is no <HI>Fear</HI> to be like that, wherewith we are to <HI>Fear</HI> Him who can <HI>Cast both</HI> B<HI>ody and</HI> S<HI>oul into Hell.</HI></P>
<P>But in the mean time, what <HI>ground</HI> for this Charge? I answer, The
<PB N="9" REF="000652_0004_0FA99F736BCA1158"/>
Charge seems grounded on those Expressions, of <HI>Job,</HI> wherein he complains, That <HI>the Righteous are de∣stroyed with the Wicked,</HI> and, That <HI>the Tabernacles of Robbers prosper.</HI> Or, on those, wherein his Challenges made unto the most <HI>High</HI> God, have a sort of peremptoriness, not agree∣ing to that <HI>Lowliness</HI> of mind, with which the <HI>Fear of God</HI> would cause us to speak of all His Managements. Wherefore some of the Ancient and Eastern Versions carry it, as if it were here intimated that <HI>Job</HI> had been speaking to God, without the <HI>Modesty</HI> that became a poor Worm of the Dust!</P>
<P>The Second Article of the Charge is, <HI>Thou Restrainest Prayer before God.</HI> What is here Translated <HI>Prayer,</HI> is promiscuously to be Englished, either M<HI>editation,</HI> or <HI>Supplication;</HI> and indeed, those are such <HI>Twins</HI> that the same Name would well befit both of them; one of them would still be Insignificant without the o∣ther; I may say of them, <HI>They
<PB N="10" REF="000652_0005_0FA99F742B88D238"/>
are Lovely and Pleasant in their Lives, and in their Deaths they are not Di∣vided.</HI></P>
<P>But again, What <HI>ground</HI> for this Charge? I answer, The Writers a∣mong the <HI>Jews</HI> tell us, That the Charge is grounded on those Ex∣pressions of <HI>Job,</HI> that seemed a Denial of <HI>Providence.</HI> To Deny <HI>Providence,</HI> is to Extinguish <HI>Prayer,</HI> for ever. Men will not be the <HI>Diligent seekers of God,</HI> except they Believe that <HI>God is a Rewarder of them who diligently seek him.</HI> Men will soon <HI>Leave off</HI> the <HI>seeking</HI> of God, if they don't Believe that God will <HI>cut off</HI> them that <HI>seek</HI> Him not. Now <HI>Jobs</HI> Assertions, as taken, yea, mistaken, would yield such Consequences, as this, That <HI>Prayer</HI> is to be <HI>Restrained,</HI> that is, Withdrawn, and Lessened, be∣fore God.</P>
<P>But let all issue then in this Lesson</P>
<P><HI>That Prayer may not be Restrain∣ed, fear must not be Rejected.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="11" REF="000652_0005_0FA99F742B88D238"/>
When was it that <HI>Jacob</HI> set him∣self to Wrestle with the <HI>mighty God of Jacob?</HI> It was when, as we read, in Gen. 32. 7. <HI>He was greatly Afraid and Distressed.</HI> When was it that <HI>Jehoshaphat</HI> not only called upon the God of <HI>Judah</HI> himself, but called upon all <HI>Judah</HI> to do so too? We read in 2 Chron. 20. 3. <HI>He Feared, and set himself to seek the Lord, and proclaimed a Fast.</HI> It is written of <HI>Hezekiah,</HI> in Jer. 26. 19. <HI>Did he not Fear the Lord, and</HI> B<HI>esought the Face of the Lord?</HI> It is the <HI>Fear</HI> of God, which is to put men upon seeking the <HI>Face</HI> of God; for which, there are two <HI>Propositions</HI> which now de∣mand a room in your Considerati∣ons.</P>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="proposition">
<HEAD>PROPOSITION I.</HEAD>
<P>PRAYER to God is a Duty to be by no means <HI>Restrained</HI> among the Children of men. As for <HI>Pray∣er,</HI> 'tis indeed such a <HI>Moral</HI> Duty, that they who are sunk into the deepest Abyss of <HI>Immorality,</HI> will
<PB N="12" REF="000652_0006_0FA99F74EB9DC580"/>
scarce utter or mutter an Objection against it.</P>
<P>There is not only the Light of <HI>Scripture,</HI> Enforcing this Duty, but there is the Light of <HI>Nature</HI> too. 'Tis said, in Jer. 10. 25. <HI>Pour out thy Fury on the Heathen, that know thee not, and on the Families that call not on thy Name.</HI> So that the <HI>Heathen</HI> themselves, who <HI>Know</HI> not God a∣right, yet Sin against the Light of what <HI>Knowledge</HI> they have, when they do not <HI>Call on the Name of God.</HI> It is the <HI>Law</HI> of our <HI>Creation,</HI> that we should pray to God as our <HI>Pre∣server,</HI> no less than our <HI>Creator;</HI> and so <HI>Engraven</HI> is this <HI>Law</HI> in the Heart of every Rational <HI>Creature,</HI> that the most <HI>Lawless</HI> Nations of men, count it the most <HI>Rational</HI> Thing imagina∣ble for them, to wait upon their Creator with their <HI>Devotions.</HI></P>
<P>It will only be expected that we now answer two Enquiries.</P>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="inquiry">
<HEAD>The First Enquiry.</HEAD>
<P><HI>What is the Prayer that must have no Restraint?</HI></P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="000652_0006_0FA99F74EB9DC580"/>
I Answer, PRAYER, is <HI>the pre∣senting of our Desire to God in Christ, for His Mercy, in his Time and His Way, and His Measure, to be obtained.</HI> That we may speak yet more di∣stinctly.</P>
<P>First, The <HI>Object</HI> of Prayer, is GOD in CHRIST. It were a detestable <HI>Idolatry</HI> to make a proper <HI>Prayer,</HI> (which is, <HI>The Acknowledg∣ment of a first cause</HI>) unto any be∣sides that <HI>God,</HI> whose Name alone is JEHOVAH, the Infinite and E∣ternal <HI>First Cause</HI> of all Things; a <HI>Daniel</HI> would sooner be torn to pie∣ces with Hungry Lions, and the <HI>Children</HI> of God would sooner broil to Death in the Furnace heated by the <HI>Type</HI> of Antichrist, than commit such an <HI>Idolatry.</HI> It is the Rule in Math. 4. 10. <HI>Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and Him only thou shalt serve;</HI> and the Devil himself could not gainsay that Rule. Who should be the <HI>Object</HI> of Prayer, but the <HI>Hearer</HI> of Prayer? Now the <HI>Hearer</HI> of Prayer, must needs be an <HI>Omni∣present</HI>
<PB N="14" REF="000652_0007_0FA99F76A1EF6890"/>
One, able at once to receive the Supplications of many Thou∣s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s from all Quarters of the Uni∣verse; and He must be an <HI>Omnipo∣tent</HI> One, able to Rescue all, to Sup∣ply all, the miserable. But there is none besides our God, <HI>Who fills Hea∣ven and Earth;</HI> none besides our God, <HI>For whom nothing is too hard;</HI> and hence This our God challenges it as His Title, in Psal. 65. 2. <HI>O Thou Hearer of Prayer!</HI> Why so? Because 'tis <HI>He</HI> alone, to whom we may say, <HI>O Thou Helper of men!</HI> Yea, but This God is not now to be Addres∣sed from sinful men, but in and by and through the Lord Jesus CHRIST. He that is the <HI>Truth,</HI> hath with <HI>it</HI> said unto us, in Joh. 14. 6. <HI>I am the Way; no man comes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nto the Father but by me.</HI> As the Lord of <HI>Egypt</HI> said unto the Sons of <HI>Ja∣cob, Ye shall not see my Face, except ye bring your Brother with you:</HI> So does the King of Heaven say to all the Seed of <HI>Jacob,</HI> I mean, <HI>The Genera∣tion of them that seek Him;</HI> He saith,
<PB N="15" REF="000652_0007_0FA99F76A1EF6890"/>
<HI>I will not Look upon you, unless you bring your Jesus with you.</HI> What are we to do with our <HI>Prayer?</HI> we have an <HI>Angel</HI> in Heaven, the Great Un∣created <HI>Angel of the Covenant,</HI> unto whom we must carry and commit the <HI>Incense</HI> of our Prayer; yea, our Prayer will be no <HI>Incense,</HI> but the rank, filthy, lothsome <HI>Nidor,</HI> of the <HI>Flesh,</HI> which attends all our Sacrifices, will make our <HI>Prayer</HI> become an <HI>A∣bomination</HI> unto Him who dwells in the <HI>Holy of Holies,</HI> except this Blessed <HI>Angel</HI> perfume it, with his Intercessi∣ons. We read in Rev. 8. 4. <HI>The Smoke of the Incense which came with the Prayers of the Saints, ascended up before God, out of the Angels Hand. Prayer</HI> was of old made with an Eye towards the <HI>Temple;</HI> Why, 'tis the Lord Jesus Christ who is the true <HI>Temple</HI> of God; it is in Him that <HI>there dwells the Fulness of the God-Head Bodily.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, For the <HI>Nature</HI> of Pray∣er, 'Tis, <HI>A presenting of our Desire.</HI> In every Prayer, there is the <HI>Desire</HI>
<PB N="16" REF="000652_0008_0FA99F772D1B0AF8"/>
of some Good Thing; yea, but something more than such a <HI>Desire</HI> is also requisite; it must be a <HI>Desire</HI> some how brought forth unto the Lord. P<HI>rayer</HI> is that, whereof 'tis said in Phil. 4. 6. <HI>Let your Requests be made known unto God.</HI> Sometimes the <HI>Desire</HI> becomes a <HI>Prayer</HI> only in our <HI>Minds:</HI> the silent out-goings of the <HI>Soul</HI> and W<HI>ill</HI> to God, are a most speaking Prayer. A P<HI>rayer</HI> may be made with <HI>Unuttered Groans,</HI> yea, with <HI>Unutterables.</HI> Thus 'tis said, in Lam. 3. 41. <HI>Let us Lift up our Heart unto God in the Heavens.</HI> This is indeed the main Ingredient of every P<HI>rayer;</HI> 'tis the most <HI>Omi∣nous</HI> Defect of any Prayer, when the <HI>Heart</HI> shall be found wanting there. But sometimes also the <HI>De∣sire</HI> becomes a <HI>Prayer</HI> in our <HI>Mouths:</HI> the <HI>Arrows</HI> of Prayer are shot into Heaven with the Bowe of the Tongue. A P<HI>rayer</HI> should often be a <HI>Cry,</HI> and this, <HI>Going out from Un∣feigned Lips.</HI> Thus 'tis said in Hos. 14. 2. <HI>Take with you words, and Turn
<PB N="17" REF="000652_0008_0FA99F772D1B0AF8"/>
unto the Lord:</HI> P<HI>rayer</HI> should frequently become Articulate; and indeed a main part of the Homage due to God, from and for the <HI>Organs of Speech</HI> which He has gi∣ven us, is to <HI>Articulate</HI> Prayer un∣to <HI>H</HI>im.</P>
<P>Thirdly, For the <HI>Matter</HI> of Pray∣er, 'Tis <HI>Mercy to be obtained accor∣ding to the pleasure of God.</HI> The Outcry of P<HI>rayer,</HI> is, for <HI>Mercy;</HI> the Language of it, is that in Psal. 51. 1. <HI>Have mercy upon me, O God, according to thy Loving Kindness.</HI> But the <HI>Mercies</HI> of God for which our P<HI>rayer</HI> is to be concerned, are more particularly what the S<HI>crip∣tures</HI> of God have taught us to Implore. We are to P<HI>ray by Book;</HI> but it is the <HI>Bible</HI> that is our <HI>Prayer∣Book.</HI> And the more <HI>special</HI> P<HI>latform of Prayer</HI> which our Lord has given us, in this Book; that I mean, which is commonly called, <HI>The Lords</HI> P<HI>ray∣er;</HI> 'tis that which we are to make the more special Directory of our P<HI>rayers.</HI> We are advised in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> John
<PB N="18" REF="000652_0009_0FA99F77EDBFF5B8"/>
5. 14. <HI>If we ask any thing according to his Will, He Heareth us.</HI> The P<HI>receptive</HI> W<HI>ill</HI> of God, must in all our Prayers be attended unto; about all the <HI>Commandments</HI> of that, our Prayers are to be, <HI>O that my wayes were directed to keep them;</HI> about all the P<HI>romises</HI> and all the <HI>Threatnings</HI> which ratify those Commandments, our P<HI>rayer</HI> is to be, <HI>That we may not miss the one, or meet the other!</HI> But then, the P<HI>rovidential</HI> W<HI>ill</HI> of God, must also be submitted unto, in all our Prayers. We should in our Prayers be content that God bestow His Blessings upon us, W<HI>hen He will,</HI> and, <HI>How He will,</HI> and, <HI>In what pro∣portion He will:</HI> Our Prayers are to be B<HI>eggings,</HI> wherein we must own, <HI>'Tis not for us to know the Times or Seasons, nor may we Limit the Holy One of Israel!</HI></P>
<P>This is PRAYER. <HI>Hac petitur Coelum via!</HI> But then,</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="inquiry">
<HEAD>The Second Enquiry.</HEAD>
<P>W<HI>hat is the</HI> Restraint <HI>of this Pray∣er?</HI></P>
<P><PB N="19" REF="000652_0009_0FA99F77EDBFF5B8"/>
I Answer, <HI>The</HI> Restraint <HI>of Pray∣er, is the Omitting or Abating of such</HI> P<HI>rayer, as we are obliged unto.</HI></P>
<P>Prayer is <HI>Restrained,</HI> when it is altogether <HI>Omitted.</HI> They <HI>Restrained</HI> P<HI>rayer,</HI> to whom it was by the Apo∣stle said, in Jam. 4. 2. <HI>Ye Ask not.</HI> And Prayer is <HI>Restrained</HI> when it is <HI>Abated</HI> of what it either hath been, or should be. When the People of God had so <HI>Restrained</HI> P<HI>rayer,</HI> it was by the Prophet said, in Dan. 9. 13. W<HI>e have not made our</HI> P<HI>rayer before the Lord our God</HI> The <HI>Restraint</HI> of Prayer, is the <HI>Neglect</HI> of such Pray∣er as is required in the Rule of <HI>P</HI>ray∣er. Men do <HI>Restrain</HI> P<HI>rayer,</HI> when their Prayer, for the <HI>Quality</HI> of it, is not according to that Rule, in Jam. 5. 16. <HI>The</HI> P<HI>rayer of a Righteous man, made with an Inwrought vehemency.</HI> Men do <HI>Restrain</HI> P<HI>rayer,</HI> when their Prayer, for the <HI>Duration</HI> of it, is not according to that Rule, in Luc. 18. 1. <HI>That men ought always to</HI> P<HI>ray, and not to Faint.</HI> Men do <HI>Restrain</HI> P<HI>rayer,</HI> when all the <HI>sorts</HI> and <HI>kinds</HI>
<PB N="20" REF="000652_0010_0FA99F78ADC9B5D0"/>
of Prayer, are not performed by them, according to that Rule, in Eph. 6. 18. <HI>Praying always, with all</HI> P<HI>rayer, and Supplication, in the</HI> S<HI>pirit, and watching thereunto, with all perse∣verance, and</HI> S<HI>upplication for all</HI> S<HI>aints.</HI> But why is this called, <HI>A Restraint?</HI> A <HI>Restraint</HI> notes, The keeping in of a Thing, that would fain break out. There are two Things that would cause P<HI>rayer</HI> to break forth; namely, Gods <HI>Command,</HI> and mans <HI>Conscience.</HI> The <HI>Command</HI> of God would fetch it out. It is the Edict of Heaven, in Isa. 55. 6. <HI>Seek the Lord while He may be found, Call ye upon Him, while He is near.</HI> Indeed, it is the <HI>Com∣mand</HI> lying every where, the whole Bible over; <HI>That the Eternal God should be Eternally</HI> P<HI>rayed unto.</HI> You'l see P<HI>rayer</HI> bespoke, in the Sacred <HI>P</HI>ages, dip where you will. But then, the <HI>Conscience</HI> of man would would also push it out. There is mention of some, in Rom. 1. 18. <HI>Who held the Truth in Unrighteousness.</HI> Altho' many a man▪ be so <HI>Unrighte∣ous,</HI>
<PB N="21" REF="000652_0010_0FA99F78ADC9B5D0"/>
as to Live without <HI>Praying</HI> unto God, yet his <HI>Conscience</HI> within him, <HI>holds</HI> this for a <HI>Truth, It should be o∣therwise:</HI> even a Pagan P<HI>late,</HI> a Pagan P<HI>roclus,</HI> have written Treati∣ses, Entituled, <HI>Concerning</HI> P<HI>rayer.</HI> So, when P<HI>rayer</HI> is Neglected, there is a <HI>Violence</HI> done, to hinder both of these Motives, from having of their <HI>Effi∣cacy;</HI> thus Prayer is <HI>Restrained</HI> in the Neglect. But,</P>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="proposition">
<HEAD>PROPOSITION II.</HEAD>
<P>There should be a Gracious and a Devout FEAR in our Soul, to be the <HI>Spur</HI> of our P<HI>rayer</HI> to our God; a <HI>Fear that must not be Reject∣ed.</HI> We have two things here to Think upon.</P>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="question">
<HEAD>The First Question.</HEAD>
<P>W<HI>hat is that</HI> P<HI>rayer-quickning</HI> Fear, <HI>which must not be Rejected?</HI></P>
<P>For Answer, What <HI>Fear,</HI> but the
<PB N="22" REF="000652_0011_0FA99F796C108098"/>
<HI>Fear of God?</HI> even that <HI>Fear,</HI> which is in the Oracles of Wisdom, so ofte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Celebrated as, <HI>The Beginning of Wis∣dom?</HI> We read in Psal. 111. 10. <HI>The Fear of the Lord, is the Beginning of Wisdom, and a good Understanding have all they that do His Command∣ments.</HI> Among the Things <HI>Com∣manded</HI> by our God, there is none more Notable than that of P<HI>rayer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> now 'tis the <HI>Fear of God,</HI> which help men unto the <HI>Understanding,</HI> to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> such a Thing. When it is here said, <HI>Thou hast cast off Fear,</HI> it is by some Translated so, <HI>Thou hast cast off Religion.</HI> The <HI>Fear of God,</HI> is a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> principle of <HI>Religion</HI> in the Heart of man; a principle of Respect unto the <HI>Commands</HI> and P<HI>raises</HI> of the Great God. It is an <HI>Old Testament Name,</HI> for the whole of <HI>Religion;</HI> but this <HI>Fear of God,</HI> includes a <HI>Love</HI> to God, a <HI>Faith</HI> on God, a <HI>Joy</HI> in <HI>G</HI>od, as well as a <HI>Fear</HI> of Him. This is the <HI>Fear,</HI> that must not be <HI>Rejected.</HI> More particularly, This <HI>Fear</HI> im∣ports, <HI>A dread of those Mischiefs that
<PB N="23" REF="000652_0011_0FA99F796C108098"/>
follow upon a Distance from God.</HI> This is a thing of such universal Mixture and Figure in <HI>Religion,</HI> that all Reli∣gion receives a Denomination from it; what said the Psalmist, in Psal. 78. 27, 28. <HI>Lo, They that are far from thee, shall perish; but it is good for me to draw near unto God.</HI> We should have such a <HI>Fear</HI> of Perditi∣on, in being <HI>far from God,</HI> as to Re∣solve that we will <HI>Draw Near,</HI> and <HI>Get Near,</HI> and <HI>Keep Near,</HI> unto Him all our Dayes. This is the true <HI>Fear of God!</HI> Briefly, we should have a <HI>Filial Fear</HI> of those <HI>Rods</HI> wherewith our God chastises them that break His Laws. When the Laws of God were given unto His <HI>Israel,</HI> then <HI>Moses</HI> Hearing the Thun∣ders and the Trumpets, and seeing the Lightnings, and feeling the Earth-quakes, which gave a shadow of the <HI>Fiery Day,</HI> whereas God will Avenge the Violations of those Laws, he cry'd out, <HI>I exceedingly Fear and Quake.</HI> We should accor∣dingly Entertain the Laws of God,
<PB N="24" REF="000652_0012_0FA99F7A2EE20B70"/>
with an <HI>Exceeding Fear</HI> of such <HI>Fi∣ery Plague</HI>s, as we may foresee like∣ly to fall upon those who Trans∣gress the Laws, that are so <HI>Holy,</HI> and <HI>Just</HI> and <HI>Good.</HI> Here is the <HI>Fear</HI> that should Inflame our Pray∣er to our God! But then,</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="question">
<HEAD>The Second Question.</HEAD>
<P><HI>Wherein appears the Influence of this</HI> F<HI>ear, upon the</HI> Non-Restraint of Prayer?</P>
<P>For Answer, First, To <HI>Restrain</HI> P<HI>rayer</HI> is to <HI>Despise the End of</HI> P<HI>ray∣er;</HI> but the F<HI>ear of God.</HI> will not let a man <HI>Despise</HI> a Thing so Tran∣scendently, so Superlatively Glori∣ous.</P>
<P>I am now happily fallen upon the Discussions of that</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="case">
<HEAD>CASE.</HEAD>
<P>W<HI>hat is the END of</HI> PRAYER?</P>
<P>We know, It is not for the <HI>In∣formation</HI> of Almighty God, that we <HI>Spread</HI> our Ails before Him;
<PB N="25" REF="000652_0012_0FA99F7A2EE20B70"/>
nor do we <HI>plead</HI> with Him, to move in Him, any <HI>Affections</HI> or <HI>Compassions</HI> like those which are in our selves. But then,</P>
<P>One End of <HI>Prayer,</HI> is, That we may <HI>Reverently</HI> Realize the <HI>Attributes</HI> of that God, who is greatly to be had in <HI>Reverence</HI> by those that come about Him. 'Tis a <HI>Veneration</HI> of God, as well as a <HI>Petition</HI> to God. Our God whose <HI>Throne</HI> is in the <HI>Highest Heavens,</HI> would be <HI>Enthroned</HI> in the <HI>High Thoughts</HI> of our Souls; now 'tis by Prayer that we are put upon the Forming of such <HI>G</HI>od-A∣doring <HI>Thoughts.</HI> It was said, of a very praying man, in <HI>Heb.</HI> 11. 27. <HI>He saw Him, who is Invisible.</HI> In Prayer 'tis, that we, <HI>Lift up our Eyes,</HI> and so we have a more Distinct S<HI>ight</HI> of the <HI>Unseen</HI> God, in the seri∣ous and suitable Thoughts of Him, so Raised in our minds.</P>
<P>Again, Another End of <HI>Prayer,</HI> is, That we may reduce into Christian <HI>Practice,</HI> the chief <HI>Doctrines</HI> of Chri∣stianity. As now, to instance in
<PB N="26" REF="000652_0013_0FA99F7AEC6A2DA0"/>
one or two; There is the Doctrine of the <HI>Trinity</HI> in the <HI>Unity</HI> of the God-head; the Mystery of God beholding Himself with an Essential P<HI>erception,</HI> producing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ence an Es∣sential <HI>Satisfaction</HI> and so Three Per∣sons in one God, This is a most profound <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI> But in <HI>Prayer,</HI> this Incomp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Mystery, be∣comes practically <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ervable and Applicable. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in Eph. 2. 18. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, we both have Access, by one Spirit unto the Father.</HI> Such a process of Soul-affairs there is in our <HI>Prayers:</HI> First, God the <HI>Father</HI> as a Judge, does by the <HI>Spirit of Bondage</HI> drive us to the <HI>L</HI>ord Jesus Christ, as our <HI>Mediator:</HI> and then, the Lord Jesus Christ, as our <HI>Mediator,</HI> does by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Adoption</HI> carry us <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to God, as our <HI>Father.</HI> So the Trinity becomes as clearly manifest∣ed unto us, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> was on the Banks <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Spectators of our Lords <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. Thus, the whole <HI>Mediation</HI> of the
<PB N="27" REF="000652_0013_0FA99F7AEC6A2DA0"/>
Lord Jesus Christ, with all the me∣thods of Reconciliation between God and us, and many more such Illustriou<HI>s</HI> M<HI>ysteries of Godliness,</HI> are most practically Illustrated in this piece of Godliness, our Prayer unto our God.</P>
<P>Moreover; A Third End of <HI>Prayer</HI> is, That we may Express and Profess our <HI>Dependance</HI> on the God, who made us <HI>Depending Beings.</HI> What said the Psalmist? in Psal. 62. 8. <HI>Trust in him at all Times, ye People.</HI> Well, but how shall <HI>People</HI> show their <HI>Trust</HI> in God? It follows, <HI>Pour out your Heart before him.</HI> Our Out-pou∣red Souls in Prayer, declare, That we must ascribe to God, all that we have, all that we hope, all that we ask; that nothing is owing to any <HI>Blind Chance</HI> at all. When we do by Prayer go to God, <HI>That He would Give us our Daily Bread,</HI> We do thereby say, That our <HI>Bread</HI> is none of our own till He give it us. 'Tis Theevery to take any thing without the Owners Leave: Wherefore 'tis
<PB N="28" REF="000652_0014_0FA99F7BAB9D8ED0"/>
said, <HI>Every Thing is</HI> S<HI>anctified by Prayer;</HI> why, by Prayer for every thing, we do say, <HI>That</HI> God is the Right <HI>Owner</HI> of that Thing; <HI>That</HI> we may not meddle with it, ex∣cept God will allow us to have it; Yea, <HI>That</HI> we cannot come at it at all, except God confer it upon us.</P>
<P>Furthermore; A Fourth End of <HI>Prayer</HI> is, That we may nourish an Humble <HI>Communion</HI> with the God who <HI>Humbles Himself</HI> to take No∣tice of us. 'Tis in Prayer that we come to a marvellous <HI>Familiarity</HI> with the Lord our God, and ar∣rive to that priviledge in Job. 22. 21. <HI>Acquaint now thy self with Him, and be at peace.</HI> The Intercourse be¦tween the Great God, and the Worms of the Dust, in this Exer∣cise, is indeed most Inexpressible! Hence <HI>Prayer</HI> is called, <HI>A Visit un∣to God;</HI> God and man becoming Friends, most <HI>Friendly Visits</HI> are in this way mutually given to one another. And this <HI>Communion</HI> with
<PB N="29" REF="000652_0014_0FA99F7BAB9D8ED0"/>
God, not only Emboldens our Ac∣cess to Him, while we <HI>Live;</HI> of our Neighbour 'tis said, <HI>Withdraw thy Foot from thy Neighbours House, Lest he be weary of thee, and so Hate thee;</HI> with our Maker 'tis not▪ so; No, He tells us, <HI>The oftner you come, the more welcome to me!</HI> So it Em∣boldens our Retreat to God, when we <HI>Dy.</HI> Oh! that my Hearers would sufficiently Lay to Heart, what I am now going to say un∣to them! I say unto you, That it will be a Dreadful Thing for a Soul Departing to appear before a God whom it has altogether been a <HI>Stranger</HI> unto. A Devout Soul going before God, may Rejoyce with a most Heavenly Triumph, saying, <HI>My God, I know thee! This is the God, with whom I have spent many a good Hour, before my coming hither;</HI> much <HI>P</HI>rayer does procure for us, this Felicity! O but for a wicked Soul, at its Expiration to think, <HI>I am about meeting with a God, unto whom I never did <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> any Life▪
<PB N="30" REF="000652_0015_0FA99F7C73AEFCD0"/>
speak one sollicitous word, about my E∣ternal Interests!</HI> 'tis an horrible Ago∣ny that must amaze that wicked Soul.</P>
<P>Once more; A Fifth End of <HI>Prayer</HI> is, That we may preserve such a <HI>good Order of Soul,</HI> at is neces∣sary in order to our Happiness. It is said of some, in 2 Tim. 2. 22. <HI>They call on the Lord, out of a pure Heart.</HI> It is by Prayer, wherein we <HI>Call upon the Lord,</HI> that the <HI>Heart</HI> is made <HI>pure</HI> and kept what it is made. They that are often in the presence of <HI>Princes,</HI> must be <HI>alwayes</HI> Trim, Neat, and in a fit posture. By much Prayer to the Great-King, we main¦tain such a <HI>posture of</HI> S<HI>pirit,</HI> as is in∣tended when we are bidden to <HI>Pray-always.</HI> It is by our <HI>Disorderly Walk∣ing,</HI> that we gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w shy of God; as when <HI>Adam</HI> had sinned, he then gat out of the way; and if we were not so shy of God, we should <HI>Walk</HI> less <HI>Disorderly.</HI> Yea, by Prayer we Lay new and strong Engagements upon our selves unto <HI>Well doing.</HI> We
<PB N="31" REF="000652_0015_0FA99F7C73AEFCD0"/>
speak unto <HI>our selves,</HI> when we so speak unto our God. When we <HI>Pray</HI> and say, <HI>Our Father which art in Heaven,</HI> we do after a sort <HI>Preach</HI> to our selves, and say, <HI>O my Soul, do thou Love and</HI> S<HI>erve, and Rely upon Gods, as thy Heavenly</HI> F<HI>ather!</HI> When we say, <HI>sanctify'd be thy Name,</HI> we say, <HI>O my Soul, Do thou Sanctify that Holy Name!</HI> When we say, <HI>Thy Kingdom come,</HI> we say, <HI>O my</HI> S<HI>oul, Do thou be a Loyal Subject of that King∣dom!</HI> When we say, <HI>Thy Will be done,</HI> we say, <HI>O my</HI> S<HI>oul, Do thou never con∣tradict that Will!</HI> Thus 'tis, that we become gloriously <HI>prepared</HI> for the Favours of God: which is indeed the Thing that He is <HI>waiting</HI> for. <HI>Lord, Thou wilt prepare the Heart of the Humble, cause thine Ear to Hear them.</HI></P>
<P>Finally, A Sixth End of <HI>Prayer,</HI> is, That we may <HI>Support,</HI> yea, <HI>Un∣load</HI> our <HI>Hearts</HI> under our <HI>Griefs.</HI> What is <HI>Prayer,</HI> but the Disburthen∣ing of the Soul? We are Invited, in 1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 5. 7. <HI>Cast all your care upon
<PB N="32" REF="000652_0016_0FA99F7D34A186A8"/>
God:</HI> and it is Explained, in Phil 4. 6. <HI>Be careful for nothing▪ but in eve∣ry thing by Prayer, and Supplication with Thanksgiving, Let your Requests be made known unto God. B</HI>y Prayer it is, that we Transmit our <HI>Care;</HI> and so we Interest our God in eve∣ry thing that were otherwise too hard for us. When was it that the sorrowful <HI>Hannah</HI> became <HI>no more sad?</HI> It was when she had <HI>poured out her Soul unto the Lord.</HI> All unuttered <HI>Care,</HI> is like the Imprisoned <HI>Air;</HI> it makes a grievous Disturbance. When we have carried all our Cares unto God, by Prayer, we may come a∣way with Triumphant Souls from the <HI>Throne of Grace,</HI> and Leave all our Troubles, all our Sorrows, all our Fears behind us there. Our <HI>Prayer</HI> will be our <HI>Hearts ease;</HI> and for this cause 'tis that our kind God, would be the <HI>God of our Prayer.</HI> Well. <HI>The Fear of God</HI> will never permit a man, to have a <HI>Low Esteem</HI> of such Inestimable Benefits. But,</P>
<P>Secondly, If <HI>Prayer</HI> be Restrain∣ed,
<PB N="33" REF="000652_0016_0FA99F7D34A186A8"/>
What good <HI>cause<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> can be assign∣ed for that <HI>Restraint?</HI> In truth, None but such as argues that men have cast off the <HI>Fear of God.</HI> As now,</P>
<P>I am sure, Men don't <HI>Fear God,</HI> if they don't feel that they W<HI>ant God.</HI> But this may be said of all P<HI>rayerless</HI> Ones. As they of old, in Jer. 2. 3. <HI>They said, we are Lords, we will come no more at thee;</HI> so these; They say, W<HI>e can do well enough without the Lord.</HI> They are not sensible of their own Weakness, their own Darkness, and their con∣tinual wretchedness without the con∣tinual Conduct of God.</P>
<P>Again, I am sure, men don't <HI>Fear God,</HI> if they are not willing to <HI>Serve God.</HI> But this also may be said of all P<HI>rayerless</HI> Ones. As it was complained, in Isa. 43. 22. <HI>Thou hast not called upon me, O Ja∣cob, but hast been weary of me, O Israel:</HI> So when men are not eve∣ry Day C<HI>alling</HI> on God, they there∣in proclaim themselves <HI>Weary</HI> of
<PB N="34" REF="000652_0017_0FA99F7DF5691880"/>
Him. And what an unworthy thing is this! The Lord may de∣mand of us, W<HI>herein have I weari∣ed thee?</HI> W<HI>hat is there that should make thee loth to wait upon me?</HI></P>
<P>I add, It is by casting off the <HI>Fear of God,</HI> that men break their P<HI>eace with God.</HI> Now if mens <HI>Peace</HI> with God, were not broken, their P<HI>rayer</HI> to God, would not be remitted. The Psalmist found it so, in Psal. 32. 3. W<HI>hen I kept si∣lence, my Bones waxed old, thro' my Roaring all the Day long.</HI> When our Prayers are <HI>silent,</HI> there is pro∣bably some <HI>Old Roaring</HI> Guilt Ly∣ing upon us. Many complain, <HI>They do not, they cannot</HI> P<HI>ray; a Prayerless Drowsiness has overtaken them, and they know not what's the matter with them.</HI> Why, 'tis well if there be not some unrepented Sin upon you, Grieving the Holy Spirit of God; it is <HI>That</HI> which is a <HI>Quench-Prayer</HI> in your Souls.</P>
<P>Lastly, What <HI>Fear of God</HI> can there be in them, that say, <HI>There
<PB N="35" REF="000652_0017_0FA99F7DF5691880"/>
is no God at all?</HI> But such an <HI>Atheist</HI> is the Wretch, that Lives wholly without P<HI>rayer</HI> to God. Hence, we find those things conjoined, in Psal. 14. 1, 4. <HI>The Fool hath said in his heart, There is no God;</HI> it follows, <HI>They call not upon the Lord.</HI> When a man shall cast such a Contempt upon the God that made him, as to offer no Prayers unto His Maker, 'tis because of a cursed <HI>Atheism</HI> Lurking and Working in the Heart of such a <HI>Fool.</HI> The worst of <HI>Infidels,</HI> are not carried away with so much of <HI>Infi∣delity.</HI> But,</P>
<P>Thirdly, The <HI>Fear of God,</HI> would certainly produce P<HI>rayer to God,</HI> if that Fear were not <HI>Rejected,</HI> but maintained, manifested, Exercised. Those things go together in Psal. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>5. 18, 19. <HI>The Lord is nigh to all them that call upon him, He will fulfil the Desire of them that</HI> F<HI>ear Him.</HI> If men <HI>Fear God,</HI> they cannot but be D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ous to <HI>Call</HI> upon Him. What is very <HI>Godly</HI> Man? He is a P<HI>ray∣ing</HI> man. So we are told, in Psal.
<PB N="36" REF="000652_0018_0FA99F7EB10C4A28"/>
32. 6. <HI>Every one that is Godly shall pray unto thee.</HI> A man does no soo∣ner begin to have the <HI>Fear of God</HI> in his Heart, but it may be said of that man, <HI>Behold, he prays!</HI> As for the Prayerless man, he does neither Obey the P<HI>recept,</HI> nor Credit the P<HI>ower,</HI> nor Adore the <HI>Goodness,</HI> of God; and I may say, <HI>How dwells the Fear of God in such a man.</HI> If men did <HI>Fear</HI> God, they would also <HI>Love</HI> the God whom they Fear. But that would cause them to say after the Psalmist, in Psal. 116. 1, 2. <HI>I Love the Lord, therefore I will call upon Him as long as I Live.</HI> Again, if men did <HI>Fear God,</HI> they would like∣wise <HI>Trust</HI> the God, whom they Fear. But that would cause them a∣gain to say after the Psalmist, in Psal. 116. 10. <HI>I believed, therefore have I spoken;</HI> i. e. <HI>I have prayed.</HI> To have done, The <HI>Spirit</HI> of God is in them that have the <HI>Fear</HI> of God. Now, that <HI>Spirit</HI> is, <HI>The Spirit of Grace, and of Supplication.</HI> Men have the <HI>Grace</HI> to be much in S<HI>upplication</HI>
<PB N="37" REF="000652_0018_0FA99F7EB10C4A28"/>
when that <HI>Spirit</HI> has once Renewed them, and possessed them; they have then a <HI>Spirit for</HI> P<HI>rayer</HI> conti∣nually. Thus you see a fair way made for our Designed</P>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="application">
<HEAD>APPLICATION.</HEAD>
<P>Well then, Let our <HI>Fears</HI> this Day Stimulate and Animate our <HI>Prayers;</HI> and let us therefore Entertain just <HI>Fears,</HI> that we may thereby Enliven our P<HI>rayers.</HI> Our <HI>Fear</HI> is this Day to deal with us, as <HI>Jonahs</HI> Master did by him; 'tis to come and say unto us, <HI>What meanest thou, O Sleap∣er? Arise, and call upon thy God. Fear</HI> is a passion, which the All-wise God, who <HI>Forms the</HI> S<HI>pirit of man within him,</HI> has most wisely put into us. When that <HI>passion</HI> comes to be well placed and well acted, we then be∣come highly <HI>Reasonable;</HI> when San∣ctified, we become Eminently <HI>Religi∣ous.</HI> That <HI>passion</HI> is the Engine which I would Employ this Afternoon, to fetch those P<HI>rayers</HI> wherein we now
<PB N="38" REF="000652_0019_0FA99F7F77E4BB28"/>
are, <HI>To pour out water before the Lord.</HI></P>
<P>I am directed in Jude 23. <HI>Some</HI> S<HI>ave with Fear.</HI> It is very certain, That we cannot be <HI>Saved</HI> without Importunate P<HI>rayer</HI> unto our God. S<HI>aved,</HI> said I? No, we cannot but be Destroy'd, but be Ruin'd, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be Plunged into inex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ricable Confu∣sions. Well, 'tis by the F<HI>ear</HI> of this, that our P<HI>rayer</HI> should be now Invi∣gorated.</P>
<P>We read of an Angel, in Rev. 14. 6, 7. <HI>An Angel Flying in the midst of Heaven, having the Everlasting Gospel, and saying with a Loud Voice, Fear God, and give Glory to Him, for the Hour of His Judgment is come; and worship Him!</HI> I shall endeavour so far to Imitate that Angel this After∣noon; that here I <HI>Stand</HI> in the <HI>midst</HI> of this Great Congregation, which make a little <HI>Heaven</HI> upon Earth; here I have the <HI>Everlasting Gospel</HI> in my Hand; and with a <HI>Loud Voice,</HI> I demand of you, to <HI>Fear God,</HI> because that <HI>Hour of his Judgment</HI> is now come upon the World; and Oh!
<PB N="39" REF="000652_0019_0FA99F7F77E4BB28"/>
<HI>Fear</HI> Him so, as to give Him the <HI>Glory</HI> of the W<HI>orship,</HI> and especially of the P<HI>rayer,</HI> that is due unto Him.</P>
<P>To speak more particularly,</P>
<P N="1">1. Let our P<HI>ersonal Fears,</HI> Restrain us f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the Sin of <HI>Restraining</HI> those P<HI>ersonal</HI> P<HI>rayers,</HI> which God forbid, that any one P<HI>erson</HI> among us all, should Live without. Are there no particular <HI>persons</HI> with us, who <HI>Re∣strain</HI> that Prayer, which the <HI>Fear of God</HI> calleth for? 'Tis to be <HI>Feared,</HI> that there are many such. 'Twere well if most of us were as Innocent as <HI>fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> was, of the Fault here Impu∣ted unto <HI>Job.</HI> Alas, Here is an Indictment laid, <HI>For, that not having the Fear of God before thine Eyes, thou hast Restrained</HI> P<HI>rayer before God:</HI> But how many are there, who can∣not plead, <HI>Not Guilty,</HI> to that Indict∣ment? Do they P<HI>ray?</HI> I wonder, F<HI>or what</HI> it is? For <HI>Spiritual Bless∣ings?</HI> No, they are the profane <HI>Esau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> by whom such things are all Despi∣sed.
<PB N="40" REF="000652_0020_0FA99F80319DF720"/>
For <HI>Temporal Blessings?</HI> No, they feed on such Fruits, without ever giving a L<HI>ook</HI> up to the Tree from whence they fall. Do they <HI>Pray?</HI> I wonder, W<HI>here it is?</HI> In their <HI>Closets?</HI> No, They will S<HI>in</HI> a∣gainst God in Secret, but not in Se∣cret <HI>Seek</HI> the Face of that God. In their <HI>Houses?</HI> No, They I Eat there, Drink there, Smoke there, and Sin there, but not by Calling upon God there make <HI>Bethels</HI> of them. Do they <HI>Pray?</HI> I wonder <HI>When it is?</HI> Not in the <HI>Mornings;</HI> they are then in too much Haste of Business for it. Not in the <HI>Evenings;</HI> they are then too weary, too sleepy, too <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>∣less for it. But Let them now ad∣mit of a few Expostulations with them.</P>
<P>First. As for P<HI>rayer</HI> in your <HI>Re∣tirements,</HI> Let <HI>Fear</HI> drive you to it. If the Angels of God, that are In∣visibly present at this Instant here, might become Audible to the whole Assembly, could they not point out incredibly many, one after another
<PB N="41" REF="000652_0020_0FA99F80319DF720"/>
of us, and say, <HI>'Tis a good part of a week at least since those persons, were upon their Knees Retired for</HI> S<HI>ecret</HI> P<HI>ray∣er before the Lord!</HI> How few S<HI>olo∣mons</HI> are there, in <HI>Retirements,</HI> plying the Throne of Grace, for Divine <HI>Wisdom</HI> and <HI>Knowledge</HI> to be vouch∣safed unto them! How few <HI>Nehe∣miahs</HI> are there, in <HI>Retirements,</HI> Be∣seeching the God of Heaven to Bless all their Undertakings! How few <HI>Jacobs</HI> are there, in <HI>Retirements,</HI> Cry∣ing to God, that neither they, nor their Children, may miscarry! And how few <HI>Nathanaels! Nathanael</HI> knew what it was to be alone under a <HI>Fig tree,</HI> conversing with God; and our Lord said, of him, in Joh. 1. 47. <HI>Behold, An Israelite indeed, in whom is no Gu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e.</HI> But you that have no such a Retired Conversation with God, may then <HI>Fear,</HI> that you are not <HI>Israelites,</HI> that you are but <HI>Hypo∣crites,</HI> before Him. What saith our Lord? P<HI>ray to thy Father which is in</HI> S<HI>ecret.</HI> So then, you that go with∣out <HI>Secret Prayer</HI> from Day to Day,
<PB N="42" REF="000652_0021_0FA99F80EBCCA198"/>
may <HI>Fear,</HI> whether God be your F<HI>ather</HI> or no; but if God be not thy <HI>Father,</HI> man, what a <HI>Black Fa∣ther</HI> hast thou? You are worse than <HI>Balaam</HI> himself, of whom 'tis re∣ported, <HI>That he went alone, to meet the Lord:</HI> and you may then <HI>Fear,</HI> that you shall never have B<HI>alaams</HI> wish, <HI>To Dy the Death of the Righteous.</HI> Yea, on the Day, when you go a∣broad without S<HI>ecret</HI> P<HI>rayer,</HI> you may <HI>Fear</HI> what the Righteous God may Leave you to; to what Sins, what Plagues, the Justice of God may Leave you in that Cloudy Day. Such a Day to poor <HI>Origen,</HI> became the Day of his Lamentable Fall, at which all Ages have been since Amazed. That your <HI>Fear</HI> may be the more sti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r'd, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'l Re∣port unto you, That an Ancient Professor belonging to this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ery Church, in whose House we are now together, after many years of good Repute with good people be∣came a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, for which he was from this Holy Society Excom∣municated.
<PB N="43" REF="000652_0021_0FA99F80EBCCA198"/>
After the Censure, he fell into bitter Horrour and An∣guish of Soul, and at length Dy'd in astonishing Circumstances; but some of his Dying Words were to this purpose; <HI>I often pray'd unto God, for a mercy, which He still Deny'd me; at Length I grew Angry at God: whereupon I grew slack in my Secret</HI> P<HI>rayers, and abated my Acquaintance with the Lord: ever since which, He hath dreadfull, forsaken me, and I know that He hath now no mercy for me.</HI> Now, Let all Hear and <HI>Fear.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly▪ As for P<HI>rayer</HI> with your <HI>Families,</HI> Let F<HI>ear</HI> drive you to That also. There was an <HI>Earth-quake</HI> in <HI>Switzerland,</HI> that Shook down all the Houses in a Town, ex∣cept one piece of one House, where∣in a good man was then at <HI>Prayer</HI> with his Family. Suppose an <HI>Earth-quake</HI> in our <HI>Boston</HI> should quickly shake down all the Houses that have not <HI>Family</HI> P<HI>rayer</HI> constantly going in them, count me not uncharita∣ble for saying, <HI>I am Jealous there
<PB N="44" REF="000652_0022_0FA99F82D7D14270"/>
would be a very terrible Desolation!</HI> How few <HI>Ohed Edoms</HI> are there, that are with their <HI>Families</HI> paving a dai∣ly Respect unto the <HI>Ark,</HI> the <HI>Christ</HI> of God? Ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> few <HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rnelius's</HI> are there, that Calling their <HI>Families</HI> to∣gether more than once every day, do <HI>Pray in the midst of their Houses?</HI> How few Parents and Masters, do <HI>Continue in</HI> P<HI>rayer,</HI> with a frequency like that of the <HI>Continual Offering</HI> under the Law? And how few do like those in Math. 19. 13. <HI>Bring their Little Ones</HI> unto the Lord Jesus Christ, that He may Bless them? You that thus do say unto the Most High, <HI>Depart from our Dwellings!</HI> may justly <HI>Fear</HI> lest by <HI>Death</HI> and <HI>Fire,</HI> He quickly Turn <HI>you</HI> out of them. Yea, you may <HI>Fear</HI> lest the <HI>Flying R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll</HI> of C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rses, do <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly into those Dwellings, where there is no <HI>Prayer</HI> for Blessings to keep them out. The very <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>arks</HI> themselves, do uphold something of a <HI>Family-Worship</HI> among them; and what may those pretended <HI>Christians</HI> then
<PB N="45" REF="000652_0022_0FA99F82D7D14270"/>
<HI>Fear,</HI> whose Houses are upon this Impious Account, F<HI>ar from Fear?</HI> It is an eager and a raging pursuit after, <HI>the World,</HI> which thus Choaks the <HI>Family-Prayers</HI> of our Neighbour∣hood: But I would gladly be at the pains to write that Admonition, in Capitals, on the Walls of every such Habitation, WHAT IS A MAN PROFITED IF HE GAIN THE WHOLE WORLD▪ AND LOOSE HIS OWN SOUL! One would F<HI>ear</HI> to Live in the House of such a <HI>Philist<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n,</HI> whereof one may say, <HI>Sure∣ly the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> is no Fear of God in this place.</HI> And one would think, the Owner of such an House may <HI>Fear</HI> the E∣verlasting Regret that will be upon him, when his Domesticks at last shall follow him, in the Fiery Burn∣ing Lake below, hideously Crying in his Ears, <HI>Why did you never teach us to pray? Your never praying with us, has brought us to this horrid place of Torment after you!</HI> But</P>
<P>Thirdly, Let every manner of
<PB N="46" REF="000652_0023_0FA99F8355C2BD60"/>
<HI>Person</HI> be put upon all manner of <HI>Prayer,</HI> in the <HI>Fear</HI> of God.</P>
<P>You might indeed upon this To∣pick be argued with: <HI>Let the privi∣ledge and advantage of Prayer, inspire you with a very prayerful Disposition of Soul.</HI> The <HI>Priviledge</HI> of Prayer, how high is it! P<HI>rayer,</HI> it is, as we read in Heb. 10. 22. <HI>A Drawing Near to God.</HI> The Immortal King of Hea∣ven, when He bids us to pray, does hold out His <HI>Golden Scepter</HI> unto us, and say, S<HI>inners, you may Draw Near; tho' you have by your</HI> S<HI>ins Forsaken me; yet you may by your</HI> P<HI>rayers Draw Near again unto me; and ask me now far more than the Half of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Kingdom, I am ready to bestow it upon you. A</HI>c∣cordingly, The <HI>Advantage</HI> of Prayer, how <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ich is it! Our God has Assured us, in <HI>Isa.</HI> 45. 19. <HI>I said not unto the Seed of Jacob, Seek ye me in vain.</HI> In vain! Truly No: most Gracious Lord; Thou hast said, S<HI>eek the Lord, and ye shall Live.</HI> There is in the Covenant of God, and <HI>Ensurance-Of∣fice</HI>
<PB N="47" REF="000652_0023_0FA99F8355C2BD60"/>
Erected; where, every one, that Ventures in the Ship of <HI>Prayer,</HI> has the Returns of his Ventures glorious∣ly secured unto him. I may call you, That our Merciful God, will rather work <HI>Miracles</HI> of Mercy, than Leave the Prayers of His Children Unanswered. <HI>Fires</HI> have bin Quen∣ched, <HI>Lions</HI> have been Muzzled, P<HI>ri∣sons</HI> have been Opened, <HI>Dead men</HI> have been Raised, <HI>Rains</HI> have been fetch'd, and the <HI>World</HI> it self has bin stop'd in its Diurnal Whi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l, at the <HI>Prayers</HI> of men <HI>Subject unto like pas∣sions with our selves. Prayer,</HI> tis that which gains a sort of a Victory, e∣ven over the <HI>Invisible World;</HI> the Al∣mighty God Himself says to <HI>P</HI>rayer, <HI>Except thou Let me alone, I cannot pro∣ceed with Destroying Dispensations;</HI> and Prayer says to the Almighty God Himself, <HI>I will not Let thee Go, except thou Bless me.</HI> Let our Distress be what it will, <HI>That</HI> is the Relief, in Psal. 50. 15. <HI>Call upon me, and I will deliver thee.</HI> What sorts of Blessings
<PB N="48" REF="000652_0024_0FA99F83EE428F50"/>
have we a value for? Why, P<HI>rayer</HI> would fetch them all. Would we have our <HI>Souls,</HI> to be <HI>Blessed in very Deed?</HI> A P<HI>raying</HI> Soul, will be a <HI>Thriving</HI> Soul. Much <HI>Prayer,</HI> as it were keeps the Soul in a Breathing <HI>Sweat,</HI> which by Degrees does con∣sume all the Distempers of it. In our <HI>Prayers,</HI> all our <HI>Graces</HI> come to be Exercised, and so to be Strength∣ened, so to be Perfected. <HI>Prayer▪</HI> 'tis taken in 3 Joh. 2. for the <HI>Fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Wind,</HI> which will bring a <HI>Prosperous Voyage</HI> to the Heaven-born, Heaven-bound Soul. Again, A P<HI>raying</HI> Soul, will be a <HI>Joyful</HI> Soul When <HI>Daniels</HI> perplexities drave him to Prayer, there was that Cheering Message brought from Heaven unto him, in Dan. 10. 23. <HI>Thou art greatly Beloved.</HI> There is an Island in the Mediterranean, whereof they say, The Sun will be sure to shine upon it once every every day throughout the year. Truly if you Pray much, you will be Likely thus to have the
<PB N="49" REF="000652_0024_0FA99F83EE428F50"/>
L<HI>ight of Gods Countenance</HI> upon you every day. Once more, A <HI>Praying</HI> Soul will be a <HI>Saved</HI> Soul. O the vast Gains of Pray∣er! It is that whereof we are advised, in Rom 10. 13. <HI>Whosoever shall call on the Name of the Lord, shall be Saved.</HI> So then, Salvation, Spiritual and Eternal S<HI>alvation</HI> it self is ou<HI>r</HI>s, if we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll pray hard for that S<HI>alvation!</HI> Yet further; would we have our <HI>Bodies,</HI> our <HI>Estates,</HI> and all our <HI>Af∣fayrs,</HI> under the perpetual Blessings of Heaven? <HI>Prayer</HI> would befriend our U∣niversal Welfare. These are the proffers of our God unto us, in Psal 91. 15. <HI>He shall call upon me, and I will deliver him, and Honour Him, and with Long</HI> L<HI>ife will I satisfie him.</HI> When S<HI>aul</HI> perceived how much D<HI>avid</HI> was in Prayer, he said, <HI>Thou shalt do great Things.</HI> Thus to those of us, that are keeping the Wheel of P<HI>rayer</HI> in a perpetual motion, it may be said, <HI>Great Things are to be done for such a man▪</HI> Finally, would we have Blessings to be Showred from on High upon our <HI>Fami∣lies?</HI> No Children are more known to be the <HI>Blessed of the</HI> L<HI>ord,</HI> than the Chil∣dren of the most <HI>Praying Parents:</HI> We cannot Lay up a better Portion for our Children, than a Stock of <HI>Prayers.</HI> Yea,
<PB N="50" REF="000652_0025_0FA99F84B03BE298"/>
By <HI>Prayerfulness</HI> we may not only <HI>Get</HI> Blessings, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>at <HI>Be</HI> Blessings too. A pray∣ing <HI>Noah,</HI> a Praying <HI>Job,</HI> a Praying <HI>Da∣niel,</HI> these are the <HI>Gap men</HI> of the places where they <HI>L</HI>ive; these are they who <HI>Deliver Islands.</HI></P>
<P>But if none of <HI>This</HI> move you, then let <HI>Fear</HI> do it. O be <HI>Afraid</HI> of the Mise∣ries, the Inexpressible, the Inconceivable Miseries, whereto a <HI>Prayerless Life</HI> Expo∣ses you. Don't you <HI>Tremble?</HI> To such <HI>Leviathans,</HI> I would speak in the words of <HI>Austin,</HI> Man, <HI>It should make thee Tremble, that thou hast not an Heart to Tremble.</HI> If <HI>Prayerless,</HI> then <HI>Wicked;</HI> for 'tis said, in <HI>P</HI>sal. 18 4. <HI>The Wicked, will not seek after God</HI> But are you not then <HI>Afraid</HI> of the <HI>Woes</HI> that belong unto the <HI>Wicked? Wo to them, it shall be Ill with them.!</HI> They L<HI>ive</HI> under the direful <HI>Curse</HI> of God all their Days; and at last, un∣der that <HI>Curse</HI> they <HI>Dy.</HI> But what will then become of them? Read and again <HI>Tremble!</HI> We are told, in Psal 9. 17. <HI>The Wicked shall be Turned into Hell, and all▪ the Nation: that Forget God</HI> The <HI>Prayerless</HI> to God, are the <HI>Forgetful</HI> of God. But are you not <HI>Afraid?</HI> We
<PB N="51" REF="000652_0025_0FA99F84B03BE298"/>
are Warned, <HI>It is a Fearful Thing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Fall into the Hands of the Living God.</HI> They that while they Lived, would not Lift up their <HI>Hands</HI> in Prayer to God, shall when they <HI>Dy,</HI> fall into the <HI>Hands</HI> of that Living God: <HI>Then!</HI> They that never <HI>Pray'd</HI> before, shall <HI>Pray,</HI> and Cry, and Beg, for the Compassions of the Great God, for whom they once cared not▪ they shall unsuccessful∣ly do it, <HI>With the Groans of a Deadly Wounded Man.</HI> But will you not <HI>Fear</HI> such a <HI>Fearful Thing</HI> as this? O be not a People, <HI>So Foolish and Unwise!</HI> And now, I pass on to say,</P>
<P N="2">II Let us not <HI>Cast off</HI> those <HI>General Fears,</HI> that should prevent the <HI>Restraint</HI> of those <HI>General Prayers,</HI> which ought generally to be going every where a∣mong us. I need not quote <HI>Nazian∣zen</HI> as my Authority for that Asserti∣on, <HI>That there is nothing so Fearful as to be without Fear.</HI> But I will add, That our being without <HI>Fear,</HI> will ren∣der <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s without <HI>Prayer,</HI> and then our Condition would be <HI>Fearful</HI> indeed un∣to Extremity. Wherefore, in one word, O Let not FEARLESS and
<PB N="52" REF="000652_0026_0FA99F8571C2A5C0"/>
PRAYERLESS, be the Character of <HI>New▪ England.</HI></P>
<P>This <HI>Fearless</HI> and P<HI>rayerless</HI> Temper, (D<HI>istemper,</HI> I should rather say,) is that SECURITY, which is the usual Fore-runner of the most Horrible De∣solations. Tho' <HI>Job</HI> could say, <HI>The Thing which I greatly Feared is come up∣on me,</HI> yet with us it is mostly other∣wise; The Thing which we <HI>Least Fear</HI> is most Likely to come upon us; and the Thing is then most Ready to come, when we do <HI>Least Fear</HI> it. Mark what I say, You cannot in all the Book of God, pitch upon any Peo∣ple Remarkably secure, but presently you'l and a Remakable Stroke of Hea∣ven, in Judgment upon those unhappy Sleepers When the <HI>Old World</HI> was Drowned in Security, then 'twas that their <HI>Foundation was Overflown with a Flood.</HI> And so still 'tis, in <HI>Our</HI> World; That men are never so near cutting <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> pieces, as when they sing, <HI>The Bit∣terness of Death <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI> See <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Thes. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 3. Indeed I cannot easily, forbear <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Outcry, which Honest <HI>G. Parisiensis</HI> made Long ago <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Security. Thou
<PB N="53" REF="000652_0026_0FA99F8571C2A5C0"/>
art my first Enemy, and my worst Ene∣my; for thou killest way</HI> Fear, <HI>which is my best Guardian.</HI> But let me then with a just Revenge, assay the Killing of that <HI>Enemy!</HI> For the Cure of this fatal S<HI>ecurity,</HI> and as well, for the Di∣recting, as for the Reviving, both of our <HI>Fears,</HI> and of our P<HI>rayers,</HI> I have two things to Lay before you. I say first,</P>
<P N="1">I. We are in such <HI>Fearful Circum∣stances,</HI> as may justly give <HI>L</HI>oud Ala∣rums unto the Blackest of our <HI>Fears,</HI> and because unto our <HI>Fears,</HI> therefore also unto our <HI>Prayers.</HI> 'Tis not only the Threatning D<HI>rought</HI> now upon us, that bespeaks our <HI>Fears</HI> and our <HI>Pray∣ers;</HI> tho' <HI>that</HI> be something. As they of old once, <HI>Trembled for the Great Rain,</HI> we are this Day, <HI>Trembling for want of Rain.</HI> The Inhabitants of <HI>Tyre</HI> and <HI>Sidon</HI> were afraid of being in Ill Terms with <HI>Herod,</HI> because, <HI>Their Country was nourished by his Countrey.</HI> We seem this Day to be in Ill Terms with that Great King, <HI>By whose Coun∣try our Country is nourished:</HI> And are we not <HI>Afraid?</HI> But we have other
<PB N="54" REF="000652_0027_0FA99F862C74C490"/>
things, which have an Aspect upon us very formidable. We should be glad, of, <HI>Tokens for Good;</HI> but instead there∣of it may be said, as in Psal. 65. 8. <HI>They who dwell in the uttermost parts, are afraid at thy Tokens:</HI></P>
<P>Particularly,</P>
<P>First, <HI>Let not Fear be east off:</HI> Are we not <HI>Afraid,</HI> Lest the <HI>Confusions</HI> which are to over-set and overwhelm, the whole World, in these Latter Dayes, do <HI>Come hither</HI> also. There is yet a <HI>Third Wo,</HI> wherewith Mankind is to be most horribly plagued, for its Opposition to the <HI>Kingdom</HI> of our Lord Jesus Christ; a <HI>Wo,</HI> in compa∣rison whereof, all the horrendous De∣solations, brought first by the <HI>Sar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>acen Locusts,</HI> and then by the <HI>Turkish Hors∣men,</HI> upon the Roman Empire, were but easy things. And what? Is that <HI>Kingdom</HI> of our Lord so Loved, so Studied, so Embraced among our selves, that we need not Fear being reached by that astonishing <HI>Wo?</HI> I would to God it were so. Tho' it will be a <HI>Joyful</HI> D<HI>ay</HI> for them that
<PB N="55" REF="000652_0027_0FA99F862C74C490"/>
are to be <HI>Refreshed by the presence of the Lord,</HI> yet it will be a <HI>woful</HI> Day for them that <HI>Know not God, and obeynot His Gospel.</HI> The Fields will grow loth to nourish those Rebels; T<HI>here shall be Famines.</HI> The Air will grow Loth to let them Breathe; <HI>There shall be Pestilences.</HI> The Eyes of Heaven will grow loth to behold them: T<HI>he Lights of Heaven shall be</HI> D<HI>arkened.</HI> The <HI>E</HI>arth will grown under the Bur∣den of them; <HI>There shall be Earth-quakes in divers places.</HI> There is to be Expe∣cted indeed, a further Accomplishment of that word, in Heb. 12. 26. <HI>Yet once more, I</HI> S<HI>hake, not the Earth only, but</HI> H<HI>eaven also.</HI> It is a Day of <HI>Earthquakes,</HI> and should it not be a Day of <HI>Heart-quakes</HI> too? Literal and Natural <HI>Earth-quakes</HI> are like to be multiplied in the approaching Age. The Subterranean <HI>Fires</HI> that are shortly to assist the Con∣flagration of this Globe, will get head apace, and <HI>Earth-quakes</HI> more stupen∣dous than the Late one upon our mi∣serable Neighbours, will be thereby occa∣sioned. As it was with a Burning Moun∣tain, that our God gave our His <HI>Law</HI> unto the Jewish World, so He terrify'd the World, with another Burning Moun∣tain,
<PB N="56" REF="000652_0028_0FA99F86EBB6A0C8"/>
when He gave out His <HI>Gospel</HI> un∣to the Gentile World. Throughout <HI>Europe</HI> and <HI>Asia</HI> and <HI>Africa,</HI> people were then f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>led with Horrid Conster∣nations, at the Fiery Eruptions of Mount <HI>Ves<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>vius,</HI> as the Historians of those Times Report unto us. Why, our God is now coming to Judge the World for the Contempt of His <HI>Law,</HI> and of His <HI>Gospel;</HI> and He will in a more affrighting manner set the World in a Burning <HI>Fire,</HI> at His Coming: <HI>A Fire shall devour before Him, and it shall be very Tempestuous round about Him.</HI> Proper <HI>Earthquakes,</HI> will probably abound in the Near Advances of That <HI>Notable Day of the</HI> L<HI>ord.</HI> But be sure, <HI>Meta∣phorical Earthquakes,</HI> there will be E∣now; State-quakes, Church-quakes, Na∣tion-quakes, will now Rage at a migh∣ty rate. As <HI>Jonah</HI> ran through <HI>Nini∣ve,</HI> proclaiming, <HI>Yet Forty</HI> D<HI>ays and the Great City shall be Overthrown.</HI> So do I now run thro' N<HI>ew-England,</HI> and pro∣claim, T<HI>here is a Great City going to be Overthrown; and yet within less than Twenty Years, the greatest Shakes are like to be given unto the World, that ever happened from the first Foundation of it.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="57" REF="000652_0028_0FA99F86EBB6A0C8"/>
Secondly. <HI>Let not Fear be cast off:</HI> Are we not <HI>Afraid,</HI> Lest when the S<HI>torms</HI> of Divine Vengeance do burst and break upon our own Sinful Nation, some <HI>Drops</HI> of the Storms do fall up∣on <HI>our</HI> Heads. The Profanity, the Debauchery, the Superstition, wherewith our Nation has been infected, have Long been making a Loud Cry in the Ears of the L<HI>ord God of Sabaoth;</HI> So that he seems to say, as in Jer. 5. 9. <HI>Shall not I visit for these things, saith the Lord: Shall not my</HI> S<HI>oul be avenged on such a Nation as this?</HI> And when the Holy God shall <HI>visit</HI> for those things, it will be well, if <HI>Showers</HI> of <HI>Blood</HI> be not Rained on a Land, where the <HI>Blood</HI> of His Dear Son has been treated as an <HI>Unholy Thing.</HI> Hence 'tis that many Thinking Men, in the Nation at this Day, are Looking upon one another with paleness in their Fa∣ces▪ and wishing, <HI>O that we had Wings like a Dove!</HI> But especially, when they Look back upon the fierce <HI>Persecutions,</HI> which formerly flamed in that Land against the Pure Worship of our Lord, they conceive that they may see, <HI>Wrath coming unto the uttermost.</HI> And how
<PB N="58" REF="000652_0029_0FA99F87AD6A7700"/>
shall a share in that <HI>Wrath</HI> upon the <HI>Mo∣ther,</HI> be now avoided, by the most Re∣sembling of all her D<HI>aughters?</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly. <HI>Let not</HI> F<HI>ear be cast off:</HI> Are we not <HI>Afraid,</HI> Le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t the <HI>Cup</HI> of that <HI>Fury,</HI> which has already dissipated as Glorious <HI>Churches</HI> as any of <HI>Ours,</HI> be likewise given unto <HI>ours.</HI> We have most Appalling In∣timations given unto us, not only in the Wasting and the Doleful Disasters that have come upon the other Plantations of the English <HI>America;</HI> such Disasters as cause the most considerable Personages a∣mong them, to write from thence unto us, <HI>The Divine Providence almost seems to have forsaken this side of the World, and Left us unto the Treasures of Wrath, which we have been Long Laying up!</HI> But also in the S<HI>catterings,</HI> that have elsewhere befallen, <HI>The Holy People.</HI> We may value our selves upon our Ecclesiastical S<HI>ettlements</HI> &amp; <HI>Ornaments,</HI> &amp; upon the wonderful Ap∣pearances of God, in the first production of them: whereof a CHURCH HIS∣TORY might indeed most profitably be [and is] Endeavoured Yea, but our Lord may say unto us, <HI>I have not found thy Works perfect before God!</HI> And who
<PB N="59" REF="000652_0029_0FA99F87AD6A7700"/>
can say, How far that Holy God, may proceed in punishing us, <HI>yet seven times more for our Iniquities?</HI> in punishing us, <HI>above the Rest of the Families of the Earth?</HI> When we see what has befallen others, our Lord says to us, as in Luc. 13. 3, 5. <HI>Except ye Repent, ye shall all Likewise per∣rish.</HI> Let me then say to you, <HI>Go to Shi∣loh!</HI> and again, <HI>Go to Asia!</HI> and once more, <HI>Go to the European Churches!</HI> espe∣cially Go to <HI>France,</HI> where the greatest Scourge of the World, more than seven years ago, coined <HI>Medals,</HI> on which 'twas brag'd, <HI>That he had then Reduced no less than twenty Hundred</HI> T<HI>housand Calvinists, from the Protestant Religion.</HI> A worse, thing surely than the Cutting of so many Throats! Behold, the Warnings of God unto <HI>Us</HI> in these Ends of the Earth, by <HI>the Desolations thus made in the Earth.</HI></P>
<P>Fourthly. <HI>Let not Fear be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ast off:</HI> Are we not <HI>Afraid,</HI> Lest we come our selves to <HI>See.</HI> The mischiefs which our Ancient S<HI>eers</HI> have often foretold unto us. Every <HI>Wise man,</HI> is a <HI>Prophet:</HI> We have had such <HI>Wise men,</HI> on many Opportunities, especially some Anniversary Ones, here <HI>Prophesying,</HI> I assure you, <HI>No Smooth things</HI> unto us: in all which, it has not been a
<PB N="60" REF="000652_0030_0FA99F886D8628D8"/>
rash <HI>Enthusiasm,</HI> it has been <HI>Scripture,</HI> it has been <HI>Reason,</HI> that has Inspired them. They have done according to their Com∣mission, in Isa. 58 1. L<HI>ift up thy voice like a Trumpet.</HI> And what has been the <HI>Voice of the Trumpet?</HI> Not <HI>Uncertain,</HI> but Universally concurring in this thing. <HI>Reformation, or Desolation! Reformation, or</HI> D<HI>esolation!</HI> and, I pray, where do we find much of the demanded <HI>Reformation?</HI> Besides this, our <HI>Old</HI> Men, without any vain <HI>Dreams,</HI> have made their moral Prog∣nostications upon our manners. We have had an <HI>Hooker,</HI> long since Prophesy∣ing unto us, T<HI>hat God would punish the Wanton</HI> S<HI>pirit of the Professors in this Country, with a sad want of Able men, in all Orders among them.</HI> We have had a S<HI>hepard,</HI> long since Prophesying unto us, T<HI>hat such a Dismal Night was towards us, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Afflictions, as would fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l our Heart with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Anguish equal to the worst, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Days.</HI> We have had a <HI>Norton,</HI> Sighing over us, <HI>What is the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of the Lord concerning the Churches of New England, is a matter of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and awful Meditation.</HI> And some other persons, not inferiour, have not stock to say, <HI>We fear the Gospel will go,
<PB N="61" REF="000652_0030_0FA99F886D8628D8"/>
the Lord Jesus will depart from <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, within <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> little while.</HI> Let thy Heart <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, <HI>O New-England,</HI> Lest th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <HI>Day of thy Watchman</HI> come upon thee▪</P>
<P>Fifthily. L<HI>et not Fear he cast off:</HI> Are we not <HI>Afraid,</HI> Lest our Unreformed Iniquities, bring down upon us, most Irret<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ievable <HI>Calamities.</HI> What are our <HI>Iniquities?</HI> Even those very Crimes for which, 'tis said, <HI>The Wrath of the Lord arose against His People</HI> of Old, <HI>until there was no Remedy</HI> You have them, in 2. Chron. 36. 14, 16. First, <HI>The People Transgressed very much, after all the Abominations of the Heathen.</HI> And have not we shamefully <HI>Indianized,</HI> by being one of the most <HI>Lying</HI> (if not like the Indians, also the most <HI>Idle</HI>) People almost in the Universe? Again, <HI>They polluted the House of the</HI> L<HI>ord.</HI> And have not the Scandalous, Damnable, Miscarriages in multitudes of our <HI>Church-Members</HI> done so too? Or, is not the cursed Contempt cast upon the <HI>Table</HI> of the Lord by such multitudes as Turn their Backs thereupon, a further doing so? Once more, <HI>They misused the Pro∣phets.</HI> And how feelingly might many
<PB N="62" REF="000652_0031_0FA99F8932A0E448"/>
of our Discourag'd, Revil'd, Cheated and Starved <HI>Ministers</HI> complain of such Usage, if they Lov'd Complaining? Yea, may not we <HI>Boston,</HI> even call S<HI>o∣dom</HI> our Sister, for our <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> our <HI>Ful∣ness of Bread,</HI> our <HI>Abundance or Idleness,</HI> and our <HI>Oppression of one another?</HI> See whether thy Face, O Town <HI>Once</HI> (and well if not justly <HI>still▪</HI>) <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> L<HI>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</HI> T<HI>own,</HI> to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers, be not, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI> S<HI>ororum:</HI> For my part, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> confess, my particular indisposition <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> mov∣ed by many things that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> ac∣counted, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> out <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> These <HI>Iniquities</HI> are the worst <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> A thousand <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> Blazing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, or views of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mies</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of Impending Evils, man <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> I<HI>niquities.</HI> But <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> our Faults <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> most <HI>Natural<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 paragraph" DISP="〈1 paragraph〉"/> Instru∣ments
<PB N="63" REF="000652_0031_0FA99F8932A0E448"/>
of Saving the <HI>Lands,</HI> the <HI>Lives,</HI> the most precious <HI>Liberties</HI> of this People, are acknowledged but with the worst of Abu∣ses for all their Services; cruel <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> and <HI>Slander,</HI> is now commonly known by the Name of <HI>Country-Day</HI> for the most of them that Lay this People under the most Eternal Obligations. What now can follow <HI>Naturally,</HI> but this; That our <HI>Ti∣red Benefactors,</HI> will make all the sensible part of Mankind joyn with them in say∣ing, <HI>We will never be the Healers of such a People!</HI></P>
<P>Sixthly, <HI>Let not</HI> F<HI>ear be cast off:</HI> Are we not <HI>Afraid,</HI> Lest <HI>Indian Hatchets</HI> are to fetch yet more Blows at the <HI>Root of our Tree?</HI> When the <HI>Philistines</HI> bore hard upon <HI>Saul,</HI> 'tis said, <HI>His Armour bearer was sore afraid:</HI> and what shall <HI>we</HI> be, that are surrounded with Bloody <HI>Philistines?</HI> Our God has been doing to us what He denounced, in Deut. 31. 25. <HI>I will move them to Jealousie with those who are not a People. I will provoke them to Anger with a Foolish Nation.</HI> And those <HI>Foolish Nati∣ons</HI> that yet <HI>S</HI>urvive of that <HI>No People,</HI> seem Reserved for a further Scourge unto us, who have been so <HI>Foolish,</HI> as to neglect ve∣ry much of the <HI>Gospellizing</HI> of those <HI>Nati∣ons.</HI>
<PB N="64" REF="000652_0032_0FA99F89EB821790"/>
Had we done as much, as the <HI>French</HI> have done, for the Proselyting of the <HI>In∣dians,</HI> in our <HI>East,</HI> we had not seen <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> whole Province there Consumed by their Depredations; and God knows, how far we may at some time or other <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e so Chastised, for our like Omissions, in some other Quarters! A twentieth part of the Treasure spent in our <HI>Wars</HI> with the Salvages, would have gone far to∣wards the <HI>Civillizing,</HI> and the <HI>Christianiz∣ing</HI> of them all: and then we had been delivered from such <HI>Wars</HI> for ever. God is to be praised indeed that so many of His Dear Servants have Travelled so far in that matter. But the most of our Peo∣ple, seem to <HI>Blow</HI> upon such Underta∣kings; or at least, have no S<HI>pirit</HI> for it: So that if Good Old <HI>Gildas</HI> were alive a∣mong us, he would threaten us, as he did his Country-men, when he told them, <HI>That God would make the</HI> P<HI>agan</HI> Saxons, <HI>an heavy plague unto them, for their doing so Little towards the Conversion of those mi∣serable</HI> P<HI>agans.</HI></P>
<P>Seventhly. <HI>Let not Fear be cast off:</HI> Are we not <HI>Afraid,</HI> Lest the <HI>Great Wrath</HI> of the Devil which hath been upon us, do remain for more than a <HI>Short Time</HI> among
<PB N="65" REF="000652_0032_0FA99F89EB821790"/>
us. I Remember, 'tis affirm'd by <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>laber Radulphus,</HI> That about the Time, when <HI>Antichrist</HI> was breaking in upon the World, People were scared almost out of their Wits, with a Fiery D<HI>ragon,</HI> seen sometimes to Fly about the Air. Truly, That Fiery <HI>Dragon,</HI> the Devil, has been most sensibly Flying about us, within this year <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> two, in the matchless <HI>Enchant∣ments</HI> and <HI>Possessions,</HI> that have abounded. in our Neighbourhood. But into what <HI>Passions,</HI> into what <HI>Mistakes,</HI> into what E∣normous <HI>Disorders,</HI> has this D<HI>escent of the</HI> D<HI>evil</HI> precipitated us, instead of <HI>driving</HI> us, to a more Trembling <HI>Walk with God?</HI> The <HI>Evil Angels</HI> being now so much ra∣ted off as they are, 'tis well if the next Stroke be not that in Psal 78 49, 59. <HI>He cast upon them the Fierceness of His An∣ger, Wrath, and Indignatoon, and Trouble, by sending Evil Angels among them.</HI> And what's the Next News? <HI>He made a way to His Anger, He spared not their</HI> S<HI>oul from Death, but gave their Life over to the Pe∣stilence,</HI> We have been in an <HI>Egyptian</HI> D<HI>arkness,</HI> buffeted by <HI>Evil Angels,</HI> and buffeting one another upon the Impulse of those <HI>Angels.</HI> God forbid, that the next Thing should be, such an <HI>Egyptian
<PB N="66" REF="000652_0033_0FA99F8AAB8893B8"/>
Pestilence,</HI> as will hardly Leave an House without one <HI>Dead</HI> Person in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> What if the <HI>Angels of Death,</HI> should next shoot the <HI>Arrows of Death,</HI> in an our Windows, with Epidemical Contagions? This I know; A Learned Man Writing against the Regard of <HI>Omens,</HI> yet about Appari∣tions of S<HI>pectres,</HI> has this passage; <HI>Perhaps God will have these</HI> Apollyons <HI>to be seen, as it were upon the</HI> S<HI>tage before Execution; that men may consider into whose Hands, in likelihood, their Iniquities have Betray'd them.</HI></P>
<P>Lastly. <HI>Let not Fear be cast off:</HI> Are we not <HI>Afraid,</HI> Lest the <HI>Rising Generation</HI> here, do Barbarously Degenerate into the <HI>Plant of a strange Vine?</HI> There is indeed nothing to be more dreaded among us, than that thing, in Judg. 2. 10. <HI>There a∣rose another Generation, which knew not the</HI> L<HI>ord, nor yet the Works which He had done.</HI> Alas, Alas! What becomes of our young People? <HI>O my God, what wilt thou do with my miserable Generation?</HI> As for ma∣ny <HI>Hopeful P</HI>ersons, among our Youth, Such as, the Learned <HI>Shepard</HI> of <HI>Charlstown,</HI> the pious <HI>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>okin</HI> of <HI>Cambridge,</HI> the Excellent <HI>De<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ison</HI> of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> God snatches the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> away to Heaven, with a
<PB N="67" REF="000652_0033_0FA99F8AAB8893B8"/>
premature Mortality. But as for many <HI>Other</HI> persons among them, they became Wild, Lewd, Mad, and every way Ex∣orbitant; They are like the Sons of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> The Sin of the Young Men is very great be∣fore the Lord;</HI> and accordingly, <HI>The Plague of the Lord upon those young men, both at home and abroad, becomes very great!</HI> Yea, in the Edges of the Land, they begin to <HI>Paganize:</HI> 'tis horrible to be spoken, but let the Regret at it, be what it will, it must be spoken; <HI>There are Villages of</HI> New-England, <HI>that have a sort of white Pagans in them.</HI> Here then, are our <HI>Fears!</HI> But</P>
<P N="2">II. Altho' we have these <HI>Fears</HI> upon us, yet our <HI>Fears</HI> are to be mixed with <HI>Hopes:</HI> and if they are vented in <HI>Prayers,</HI> they may very well be mixed with <HI>Hopes.</HI> The <HI>Uplifted Hands</HI> of our <HI>Prayers</HI> this Day, must have <HI>Hope,</HI> as well as <HI>Fear,</HI> for the two Supporters of them As <HI>Paul</HI> said about <HI>Mourning,</HI> so would I say about <HI>Fearing,</HI> in 1 Thes 4. 13. <HI>Do not as others that have no Hope.</HI> The Kind Emperour, of old ordered it, <HI>That none should go</HI> D<HI>ejected from the Presence of the Emperour.</HI> Nor, must I now suffer <HI>you,</HI> to Go <HI>Dejected</HI> from the <HI>Presence</HI> of
<PB N="68" REF="000652_0034_0FA99F8B6E2EFF80"/>
the Eternal King, upon whom we are this Day attending When <HI>Daniel</HI> was, as <HI>we</HI> now are, <HI>Weary</HI> with Fasting, an <HI>Angel</HI> Flew from Heaven, till <HI>he</HI> was even <HI>Weary</HI> too (as the Original has it) with the Swiftness of his Motion, to bring him some comfortable Tidings. As <HI>Weary</HI> as I am, yet I must offer you some Comfortable Things before we part; and I am to tell you, There are <HI>Hopes</HI> as well as <HI>Fears</HI> for our Land.</P>
<P>But, what <HI>Hopes?</HI> I Reply,</P>
<P>First, We have <HI>Hopes</HI> in the <HI>Sove∣raign Grace</HI> of our most Gracious God. O what an Heart-breaking Word is that, in Isa. 57. 17, 18. <HI>For the Iniquity of his Coveteousness, was I wroth, and smote him: and he went on frowardly in the way of his Heart:</HI> And what? must all now be Lost? No; There is yet <HI>Hope in Israel!</HI> You shall see what S<HI>overaign Grace</HI> can do. It follows, <HI>I have seen his Ways and will Heal him.</HI> And now, <HI>Lord, Be it unto thy</HI> P<HI>eople according to this thy Gracious Word!</HI></P>
<P>I Reply, Secondly; We have <HI>Hopes</HI>
<PB N="69" REF="000652_0034_0FA99F8B6E2EFF80"/>
in the Hastning <HI>Time of Reformation,</HI> which our God will Hasten in his Time. If the <HI>Man of</HI> S<HI>in</HI> Entred his Last <HI>Half Time!</HI> or his last Hundred and Eighty Years, as no doubt he did, at the <HI>Refor∣mation,</HI> which Commenced about the Year 1517. We may then have a <HI>Lively Hope,</HI> that we are within a very few years, of a <HI>Reformation,</HI> more Heavenly, more Extensive, more Glorious, than the Church of God has ever yet been favou∣red with. But shall <HI>we</HI> be forgotten in this <HI>Time?</HI> We may presume that neither God, nor the King, will then forget us.</P>
<P>I Reply, Thirdly; We have <HI>Hopes</HI> in the Yearly and Holy Fruits of our <HI>Col∣ledge;</HI> that Blessed Nursery of our <HI>Israel.</HI> The Lord may say unto us, <HI>I have Raised up of your Sons for Prophets;</HI> for which that man among us, who is not now greatly Thankful to God, is not worthy the Name of, <HI>A New-Englandman.</HI> There is a most <HI>Hopeful</HI> produce of S<HI>cholars</HI> a∣rising out of that Society; <HI>Young men,</HI> admirably Accomplished in all parts of Literature; <HI>Young men</HI> of most Enlarged Souls; and, which is better still, <HI>Young Men,</HI> full of Piety; no Strangers to the N<HI>ew-Birth;</HI> nor unacquainted with High
<PB N="70" REF="000652_0035_0FA99F8C2BF0DB08"/>
Experiments in practical Religion; such as know what it is to be continually <HI>Fast∣ing</HI> as well as <HI>Praying</HI> for the Blessing of God, not upon themselves alone, but up∣on all concerned in them. <HI>Destroy not that</HI> P<HI>eople;</HI> saith our God; <HI>is there not a Blessing among them?</HI> And as for <HI>You,</HI> Brethren, that are thus coming on; Be Encouraged and Know, T<HI>hat the God of your</HI> F<HI>athers has a greater work for you to do for Him, than what He has yet Employ'd your Fathers in.</HI></P>
<P>I Reply, Fourthly; We have <HI>Hopes</HI> in the presence of the Lord Jesus Christ on <HI>Board</HI> of our <HI>Bark.</HI> A Little Vessel could not be sunk, by all the Blast of Hell, while our Lord was with His <HI>Dis∣ciples</HI> in it. Why, our <HI>L</HI>ord has very few Disciples in this whole▪ Haemisphere of the World, but what are in this Little Vessel. Shall we then <HI>perish?</HI> No, That we shall not; if we now do, by our Prayers <HI>Awaken</HI> our Lord unto the Sav∣ing of us.</P>
<P>But after all; when the worst comes to the worst: Yet, <HI>Surely I know it shall be well with them that fear God, that Fear before</HI> H<HI>im.</HI> Let us have much of that <HI>Fear</HI> within us, and let that Swallow
<PB N="71" REF="000652_0035_0FA99F8C2BF0DB08"/>
up every other <HI>Fear. Qui Deum timet, cum omnia timent.</HI> The <HI>Fear</HI> of God will give us a Room among His <HI>Alamoth,</HI> or His Hidden Ones; and then we may without <HI>Fear</HI> Sing the <HI>Forty</HI> S<HI>ixth Psalm,</HI> which L<HI>uther</HI> used, when Things Look'd with a bad face abroad; Sing, <HI>We will not Fear, tho' the Earth be removed, and tho' the Mountain be carried into the midst of the</HI> S<HI>ea.</HI> Our God, is now, I believe, upon the <HI>Resurrection</HI> of His <HI>Witnesses:</HI> altho' former Attempts about that <HI>Resur∣rection</HI> have been Abortive, yet now, <HI>with His Dead Body they shall arise</HI> It is therefore likely to be a Day of more than ordinary <HI>Indignation</HI> upon an Impious World; but if we are now fitted and acted by the <HI>Fear</HI> of God, and if that <HI>Fear</HI> carry us forth to to all due <HI>Testimonies</HI> for His Truths and Ways, He will say unto us, <HI>Come, My</HI> P<HI>eople; Enter thou into thy Chambers, and Shut thy</HI> D<HI>oors about thee.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's advertisement">
<PB REF="000652_0036_0FA99F8CEDA79B58"/>
<HEAD>Advertisement</HEAD>
<P>THere is now in the Press, and will speedily be Published, A New Book, Entituled, The Great Blessing of <HI>Primi∣tive Counsellours;</HI> Discoursed in a Sermon Preached in the Audience of the Gover∣nour, Council and Representatives of the Province of the <HI>Massachusetts-Bay</HI> in <HI>New-England, May</HI> 31. 1693. Being the Day for the Election of <HI>Counsellours</HI> in that Province. By <HI>Increase Mather,</HI> President of <HI>Har<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ard-Colledge</HI> in <HI>Cam∣bridge,</HI> and Teacher of a Church at <HI>Bo∣ston</HI> in <HI>New-England.</HI></P>
<P>Sold by <HI>Benjamin Harris,</HI> over-against the <HI>Old-Meeting-House</HI> in <HI>Boston.</HI> 1693.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

