<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-01-03</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for "doubt" tags. Look for misused tilde character entities. Check for blanks. Checked for signatures. Checked for #s. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Corrected 27 $-groups. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N10391">
<STC T="E">13172</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99001677</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="013172_0000_0F91041DA6781178"/>
<PB REF="013172_0001_0F910420853F2B90" MS="y"/>
<P>A POEM ON DIVINE REVELATION; BEING AN EXERCISE DELIVERED At the PUBLIC COMMENCEMENT AT NASSAU-HALL, SEPTEMBER 28. 1774.</P>
<P>By the same Person, who on a similar occasion, Sept. 25. 1771. delivered a small Poem on <HI>the rising Glory of America.</HI></P>
<P>PHILADELPHIA: PRINTED AND SOLD BY R. AITKEN, BOOKSELLER, OPPOSITE THE LONDON-COFFEE-HOUSE, FRONT-STREET.</P>
<P>M.DCC.LXXIV.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="preface">
<PB REF="013172_0002_0F910420A01EBF70"/>
<HEAD>PREFACE.</HEAD>
<P>THE Author of the following Poem, or as perhaps it may be better styled Poetical Ora∣tion, may seem to have been rather unhappy in the choice of his subject, which being a good deal historical, did not admit of much poetic dress or ornament, nor gave much scope to fan∣cy or imagination to exert itself, that in which the great strength of a poet lies. With respect to this he would beg leave to observe, that the subject was chosen perhaps happily enough, as the foundation of an Exercise in an institution under the patronage of gentlemen distinguished as friends to Revelation, and on an occasion when the greater number of them were convened.</P>
<P>In the second place it may be objected, that an imitation of the poet Milton may be traced through the whole of the performance, though the Author has not been able to attain to any thing
<PB REF="013172_0003_0F910421577762A0"/>
of the spirit of that immortal bard. To this he has only to reply, that an imitation of great originals is placed by Longinus among the sources of good writing. He therefore con∣ceives himself free from censure on account of any imitation of the poet Milton, which may be seen in his performance, though he is sensible of his unhappiness in not having been able to at∣tain to any degree of his excellent spirit. This however is a misfortune common to him with many honest writers, and for which he throws himself on the candour of the Public.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="argument">
<PB REF="013172_0004_0F91042283032DE0"/>
<HEAD>ARGUMENT.</HEAD>
<P>The introduction, complimenting the college and the assembly convened on the day of commencement.—The subject proposed.—A view of divine revelation from its earliest dawn after the fall of Adam, to its fuller splendor in the writings of the prophets.—From this source the heathen philosophers received much light and information.—Reason of itself unable to give the knowledge of the truth.—The meridian brightness of divine revelation and its general diffusion at the coming of the Saviour.—Its happy influence at that period, in banishing heathen superstition, re∣straining the ferocity of war, and giving a new range to poesy and eloquence; life and immortality being brought to light.—A short hint of the first opposition to the gospel.—Darkness of Popery which came upon the west.—Mahometan delusion which about the sixth century took place in the east.—Some countries of Eu∣rope emerging from Popish superstition, Bohemia, <HI>&amp;c.</HI>—Refor∣mation in England.—The light of revelation rising on America.—Rekindled in the east.—Mahometan imposture destroyed.—The Jews confessing the Messiah.—Pagan idolatry and ignorance removed —The glory with which revelation shall yet appear on this continent.—Divine knowledge covering the earth as the wa∣ters the sea.—Its streams flowing back at the last scene of things to their first source, and mixing with the bright floods of celes∣tial day·—The conclusion valedictory to NASSAU-HALL, the place of the author's education.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<PB REF="013172_0005_0F91042383C65EA0"/>
<HEAD>AN EXERCISE DELIVERED At the PUBLIC COMMENCEMENT AT NASSAU-HALL,
<DATE>September 28. 1774.</DATE></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>THIS is a day of happiness, sweet peace,</L>
<L>And heavenly sunshine; upon which conven'd</L>
<L>In full assembly fair, once more we view,</L>
<L>And hail with voice expressive of the heart,</L>
<L>Patrons and sons of this illustrious hall.</L>
<L>This hall more worthy of its rising fame</L>
<L>Than hall on mountain or romantic hill,</L>
<L>Where Druid bards sang to the hero's praise,</L>
<L>While round their woods and barren heaths was heard</L>
<L>The shrill calm echo of th' enchanting shell.</L>
<L>Than all those halls and lordly palaces</L>
<L>Where in the days of chivalry, each knight,</L>
<L>And baron brave in military pride</L>
<L>Shone in the brass and burning steel of war;</L>
<L>For in this hall more worthy of a strain</L>
<L>No envious sound forbidding peace is heard,</L>
<L>Fierce song of battle kindling martial rage</L>
<L>And desp'rate purpose in heroic minds:</L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="013172_0006_0F9104239EC7C6A8"/>But sacred truth fair science and each grace</L>
<L>Of virtue born; health, elegance and ease</L>
<L>And temp'rate mirth in social intercourse</L>
<L>Convey rich pleasure to the mind; and oft</L>
<L>The sacred muse in heaven-breathing song</L>
<L>Doth wrap the soul in extasy divine,</L>
<L>Inspiring joy and sentiment which not</L>
<L>The tale of war or song of Druids gave.</L>
<L>The song of Druids or the tale of war</L>
<L>With martial vigour every breast inspir'd,</L>
<L>With valour fierce and love of deathless fame;</L>
<L>But here a rich and splendid throng conven'd</L>
<L>From many a distant city and fair town,</L>
<L>Or rural seat by shore or mountain-stream,</L>
<L>Breathe joy and blessing to the human race,</L>
<L>Give countenance to arts themselves have known,</L>
<L>Inspire the love of heights themselves have reach'd,</L>
<L>Of noble science to enlarge the mind,</L>
<L>Of truth and virtue to adorn the soul,</L>
<L>And make the human nature grow divine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh could the muse on this auspicious day</L>
<L>Begin a song of more majestic sound,</L>
<L>Or touch the lyre on some sublimer key,</L>
<L>Meet entertainment for the noble mind.</L>
<L>How shall the muse from this poetic bow'r</L>
<L>So long remov'd, and from this happy hill,</L>
<L>Where ev'ry grace and ev'ry virtue dwells,</L>
<L>And where the springs of knowledge and of thought</L>
<L>In riv'lets clear and gushing streams flow down</L>
<L>Attempt a strain? How sing in rapture high</L>
<L>Or touch in vari'd melody the lyre</L>
<L>The lyre so long neglected and each strain</L>
<L>Unmeditated, and long since forgot?</L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="013172_0007_0F91042457C2B3E0"/>But yet constrain'd on this occasion sweet</L>
<L>To this fam'd hall and this assembly fair</L>
<L>With comely presence honouring the day,</L>
<L>She fain would pay a tributary strain.</L>
<L>A purer strain though not of equal praise</L>
<L>To that which Fingal heard when Ossian sung</L>
<L>With voice high rais'd in Selma hall of shells;</L>
<L>Or that which Pindar on th' Elean plain,</L>
<L>Sang with immortal skill and voice divine,</L>
<L>When native Thebes and ev'ry Grecian state</L>
<L>Pour'd forth her sons in rapid chariot race,</L>
<L>To shun the goal and reach the glorious palm.</L>
<L>HE sang the pride of some ambitious chief,</L>
<L>For olive crowns and wreaths of glory won;</L>
<L>I sing the rise of that all glorious light,</L>
<L>Whose sacred dawn the aged fathers saw</L>
<L>By faith's clear eye, through many a cloud obscure</L>
<L>And heavy mist between: they saw it beam</L>
<L>From Judah's royal tribe, they saw it shine</L>
<L>O'er Judah's happy land, and bade the hills,</L>
<L>The rocky hills and barren vallies smile,</L>
<L>The desert blossom and the wilds rejoice.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This is that light and revelation pure,</L>
<L>Which Jacob saw and in prophetic view,</L>
<L>Did hail its author from the skies, and bade</L>
<L>The sceptre wait with sov'reignty and sway</L>
<L>On Judah's hand till Shiloh came. That light</L>
<L>Which Beor's son in clearer vision saw,</L>
<L>Its beams sore piercing his malignant eye;</L>
<L>But yet constrain'd by the eternal truth</L>
<L>Confess'd its origin and hail'd its rise,</L>
<L>Fresh as a star from Judah's sacred line.</L>
<L>This, Amos' son touch'd with seraphic fire</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="013172_0008_0F910425D34F11C8"/>In after times beheld. He saw it beam</L>
<L>From Judah's royal tribe; he saw it shine</L>
<L>O'er Judah's happy land, and bade the hills,</L>
<L>The rocky hills and barren vallies smile,</L>
<L>The desert blossom and the wilds rejoice.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This is that light which purifies the soul,</L>
<L>From mist obscure, of envy, hate, and pride;</L>
<L>Bids love celestial in the bosom glow,</L>
<L>Fresh kindling up the intellectual eye</L>
<L>Of faith divine, in beatific view</L>
<L>Of that high glory and seraphic bliss,</L>
<L>Which he who reigns invisible, shall give</L>
<L>To wait on virtue in the realms of day.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This is that light which from remotest times</L>
<L>Shone to the just; gave sweet serenity,</L>
<L>And sunshine to the soul, of each wise sage,</L>
<L>Fam'd patriarch, and holy man of God,</L>
<L>Who in the infancy of time did walk</L>
<L>With step unerring, through those dreary shades,</L>
<L>Which veil'd the world e'er yet the golden sun</L>
<L>Of revelation beam'd. Seth, Enos, and</L>
<L>The family of him preserv'd from death</L>
<L>By flood of waters. Abram and that swain</L>
<L>Who erst exil'd in Midian did sing</L>
<L>The world from chaos rising, and the birth</L>
<L>Of various nature in the earth, or sea,</L>
<L>Or element of air, or heav'n above.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This is that light which on fair Zion hill</L>
<L>Descending gradual, in full radiance beam'd</L>
<L>O'er Canaan's happy land. Her fav'rite seers</L>
<L>Had intercourse divine with this pure source,</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="013172_0009_0F910425F28CEEE8"/>And oft from them a stream of light did slow,</L>
<L>To each adjoining vale and desert plain,</L>
<L>Lost in the umbrage of dark heathen shades.</L>
<L>'Twas at this stream the fabling poets drank</L>
<L>And sang how heav'n and earth from chaos rose;</L>
<L>'Twas at this stream the wiser sages drank</L>
<L>And straightway knew the soul immortal lives</L>
<L>Beyond the grave and all the wrecks of time.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>From Judah's sacred hills a partial ray</L>
<L>Extraneous, visited and cheer'd the gloom</L>
<L>Spread o'er the shaded earth; yet more than half</L>
<L>In superstition and the dreams of night</L>
<L>Each hoary sage by long experience wise,</L>
<L>And high philosopher of learning fam'd</L>
<L>Lay buried deep shut from the light of day.</L>
<L>Shut from the light of revelation clear</L>
<L>In devious path they wandered oft,</L>
<L>Nor could strong reason with the partial beam</L>
<L>Of revelation, wholly dissipate</L>
<L>The midnight horrors of so dark an age.</L>
<L>Vain were their searches, and their reason vain,</L>
<L>Else whence the visionary tales receiv'd,</L>
<L>Of num'rous deities in earth, or heav'n</L>
<L>Or sea, or river, or the shades profound</L>
<L>Of Erebus, dark kingdom of the dead.</L>
<L>Weak deities of fabled origin</L>
<L>From king or hero, to the skies advanc'd</L>
<L>For sanguinary appetite, and skill</L>
<L>In cruel feats of arms, and tyranny</L>
<L>O'er ev'ry right, and privilege of man.</L>
<L>Vain were their searches, and their reason vain,</L>
<L>Else whence the sculptur'd image of a god,</L>
<L>And marble bust ador'd as deity,</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="013172_0010_0F91042696791128"/>Altar and hecatomb prepar'd for these,</L>
<L>Or human sacrifice when hecatomb</L>
<L>Consum'd in vain with ceremony dire,</L>
<L>And rites abhorr'd, denied the wish'd success.</L>
<L>Reason is dark, else why heroic deem'd</L>
<L>Fell suicide, as if 'twere fortitude</L>
<L>And higher merit to recede from life,</L>
<L>Shunning the ills of poverty, or pain,</L>
<L>Or wasting sickness, or the victor's sword,</L>
<L>Than to support with patience fully tried</L>
<L>As Job, thence equall'd with him in renown.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Shut from the light of revelation clear</L>
<L>The world lay hid in shades, and reason's lamp</L>
<L>Serv'd but to show how dark it was; but now</L>
<L>The joyous time with hasty steps advanc'd,</L>
<L>When truth no more should with a partial ray</L>
<L>Shine on the shaded earth; now on swift wings</L>
<L>The rosy hours brought on in beauty mild,</L>
<L>The day-spring from on high, and from the top</L>
<L>Of some fair mount Chaldean shepherds view</L>
<L>That orient star which Beor's son beheld,</L>
<L>From Aram east, and mark'd its lucid ray,</L>
<L>Shedding sweet influence on Judah's land.</L>
<L>Now o'er the plain of Bethl'em to the swains</L>
<L>Who kept their flocks beneath the dews of night,</L>
<L>A light appears expressive of that day</L>
<L>More general, which o'er the shaded earth</L>
<L>Breaks forth, and in the radiance of whose beams,</L>
<L>The humble shepherd, and the river-swain</L>
<L>By Jordan stream, or Galilea's lake,</L>
<L>(a see each truth and paradox explain'd,</L>
<L>Which not each wise philosopher of Greece,</L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="013172_0011_0F910427565D1900"/>Could tell, nor sage of India, nor the sons</L>
<L>Of Zoroaster, in deep secrets skill'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Such light on Canaan shone but not confin'd</L>
<L>With partial ray to Judah's favour'd land,</L>
<L>Each vale and region to the utmost bound</L>
<L>Of habitable earth, distant or nigh</L>
<L>Soon finds a gleam of this celestial day:</L>
<L>Fam'd Persia's mountains and rough Bactria's woods</L>
<L>And Media's vales and Shinar's distant plain:</L>
<L>The Lybian desert near Cyrene smiles</L>
<L>And Ethiopia hails it to her shores.</L>
<L>Arabia drinks the lustre of its ray</L>
<L>Than fountain sweeter, or the cooling brook</L>
<L>Which laves her burning sands; than stream long sought</L>
<L>Through desert flowing and the scorched plain</L>
<L>To Sheba's troop or Tema's caravan.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Egypt beholds the dawn of this fair morn</L>
<L>And boasts her rites mysterious no more;</L>
<L>Her hidden learning wrapt in symbols strange</L>
<L>Of hieroglyphic character, engrav'd</L>
<L>On marble pillar, or the mountain rock,</L>
<L>Or pyramid enduring many an age.</L>
<L>She now receives asserted and explain'd</L>
<L>That holy law, which on mount Sinai writ</L>
<L>By God's own singer, and to Moses giv'n,</L>
<L>And to the chosen seed, a rule of life.</L>
<L>And strict obedience due; but now once more</L>
<L>Grav'd on the living tablet of the heart,</L>
<L>And deep impress'd by energy divine,</L>
<L>Is legible through an eternal age.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>North of Judea now this day appears</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="013172_0012_0F91042817BE5E80"/>On Syria west, and in each city fair</L>
<L>Full many a church of noble fame doth rise.</L>
<L>In Antioch the seat of Syrian kings,</L>
<L>And old Damascus, where Hazael reign'd.</L>
<L>Now Cappadocia Mithridates' realm,</L>
<L>And poison-bearing Pontus, whose deep shades</L>
<L>Were shades of death, admit the light of truth.</L>
<L>In Asia less seven luminaries rise,</L>
<L>Bright lights, which with celestial vigour burn,</L>
<L>And give the day in fullest glory round.</L>
<L>There Symrna shines, and Thyatira there,</L>
<L>There Ephesus a sister light appears,</L>
<L>And Pergamus with kindred glory burns:</L>
<L>She burns enkindled with a purer flame</L>
<L>Than Troy of old, when Grecian kings combin'd</L>
<L>Had set her gates on fire: The Hellespont</L>
<L>And all th' Egean sea shone to the blaze.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But now more west the gracious day serene</L>
<L>On Athens rising, throws a dark eclipse</L>
<L>On that high learning by her sages taught,</L>
<L>In each high school of philosophic fame;</L>
<L>Vain wisdom, useless sophistry condemn'd,</L>
<L>As ignorance and foolishness of men.</L>
<L>Let her philosophers debate no more</L>
<L>In the Lyceum, or the Stoics porch,</L>
<L>Holding high converse, but in error lost</L>
<L>Of pain, and happiness, and fate supreme.</L>
<L>Fair truth from heav'n draws all their reas'ning high</L>
<L>In captive chains bound at her chariot wheels.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Now Rome imperial, mistress of the world</L>
<L>Drinks the pure lustre of the orient ray</L>
<L>Assuaging her fierce thirst of bloody war,</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="013172_0013_0F9104291F258E78"/>Dominion boundless, victory and fame;</L>
<L>Each bold centurion, and each praetor finds</L>
<L>A nobler empire to subdue themselves.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>From Rome the mistress of the world in peace,</L>
<L>Far to the north the golden light ascends;</L>
<L>To Gaul and Britain and the utmost bound</L>
<L>Of Thule famous in poetic song,</L>
<L>Victorious there where not Rome's consuls brave,</L>
<L>Heroes, or conquering armies, ever came.</L>
<L>Far in the artic skies a light is seen,</L>
<L>Unlike that sun, which shall ere long retreat,</L>
<L>And leave their hills one half the year in shades.</L>
<L>Or that Aurora which the sailor sees</L>
<L>Beneath the pole in dancing beams of light,</L>
<L>Playing its gambols on the northern hills.</L>
<L>That light is vain and gives no genial heat,</L>
<L>To warm the tenants of those frozen climes,</L>
<L>Or give that heav'nly vigour to the soul,</L>
<L>Which truth divine and revelation brings;</L>
<L>And but for which each heart must still remain,</L>
<L>Hard as the rock on Scandanavia's shore,</L>
<L>Cold as the ice which bridges up her streams,</L>
<L>Fierce as the storm which tempests all her waves.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus in its dawn did sacred truth prevail,</L>
<L>In either hemisphere from north to south,</L>
<L>From east to west through the long tract of day.</L>
<L>From Shinar's plain to Thule's utmost isle,</L>
<L>From Persia's bay to Scandanavia's shores.</L>
<L>Cheer'd by its ray now ev'ry valley smiles,</L>
<L>And ev'ry lawn smote by its morning beam.</L>
<L>Now ev'ry hill reflects a purer ray,</L>
<L>Than when Aurora paints his woods in gold,</L>
<L><PB N="10" REF="013172_0014_0F91042AB44BFC38"/>Or when the sun first in the orient sky,</L>
<L>Sets thick with gems the dewy mountain's brow.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The earth perceives a sov'reign virtue shed</L>
<L>And from each cave, and midnight haunt retires</L>
<L>Dark superstition, with her vot'ries skill'd,</L>
<L>In potent charm, or spell of magic pow'r;</L>
<L>In augury, by voice, or flight of birds,</L>
<L>Or b<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ding sign at morn, or noon, or eve,</L>
<L>Portent and prodigy and omen dire.</L>
<L>Each oracle by Demon, or the craft</L>
<L>Of priests, made vocal, can declare no more</L>
<L>Of high renown, and victory secure,</L>
<L>To kings low prostrate at their bloody shrines.</L>
<L>No more with vain uncertainty perplex</L>
<L>Mistaken worshippers, or give unseen</L>
<L>Response ambiguous in some mystic sound,</L>
<L>And hollow murmer from the dark recess.</L>
<L>No more of Lybian Jove; Dodona's oaks,</L>
<L>In sacred grove give prophecy no more.</L>
<L>Th' infernal deities retire abash'd,</L>
<L>Our God himself on earth begins his reign;</L>
<L>Pure revelation beams on ev'ry land,</L>
<L>On ev'ry heart exerts a sov'reign sway,</L>
<L>And makes the human nature grow divine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Now hideous war forgets one half her rage,</L>
<L>And smoothes her visage horible to view.</L>
<L>Celestial graces better sooth the soul,</L>
<L>Than vocal music, or the charming sound</L>
<L>Of harp or lyre. More than the golden lyre</L>
<L>Which Orpheus tun'd in melancholy notes,</L>
<L>Which almost pierc'd the dull cold ear of death,</L>
<L>And mov'd the grave to give him back his bride.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="11" REF="013172_0015_0F91042C2DE64268"/>Peace with the graces and fair science now</L>
<L>Wait on the gospel <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ar; science improv'd</L>
<L>Puts on a fairer dress; a fairer form</L>
<L>Now ev'ry art assumes; bold eloquence</L>
<L>Moves in a higher sphere than senates grave,</L>
<L>Or mix'd assembly, or the hall of kings,</L>
<L>Which erst with pompous panegyric rung.</L>
<L>Vain words and soothing flattery she hates,</L>
<L>And feigned tears, and tongue which silver-tipt</L>
<L>Moves in the cause of wickedness and pride.</L>
<L>She mourns not that fair liberty depress'd</L>
<L>Which kings tyrannic can exto<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, but that</L>
<L>Pure freedom of the soul to truth divine</L>
<L>Which first indulg'd her and with envious hand</L>
<L>Pluck'd thence, left hideous slavery behind.</L>
<L>She weeps not loss of property on earth,</L>
<L>Nor stirs the multitude to dire revenge</L>
<L>With headlong violence, but soothes the soul</L>
<L>To harmony and peace, bids them aspire</L>
<L>With emulation and pure zeal of heart,</L>
<L>To that high glory in the world unseen,</L>
<L>And crown celestial, which pure virtue gives.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus eloquence and poesy divine</L>
<L>A nobler range of sentiment receive;</L>
<L>Life brought to view and immortality,</L>
<L>A recent world through which bold fancy roves,</L>
<L>And gives new magic to the pow'r of song;</L>
<L>For where the streams of revelation flow</L>
<L>Unknown to bards of Helicon, or those</L>
<L>Who on the top of Pindus, or the banks</L>
<L>Of Arethusa and Eurotas stray'd,</L>
<L>The poet drinks, and glorying in new strength,</L>
<L>Soars high in rapture of sublimer strains;</L>
<L><PB N="12" REF="013172_0016_0F91042D6D1588D0"/>Such as that prophet sang who tun'd his harp</L>
<L>On Zion hill and with seraphic praise</L>
<L>In psalm and sacred ode by Siloa's brook,</L>
<L>Drew HIS attention who first touch'd the soul</L>
<L>With taste of harmony, and bade the spheres</L>
<L>Move in rich measure to the songs on high.</L>
<L>Fill'd with this spirit poesy no more</L>
<L>Adorns that vain mythology believ'd,</L>
<L>By rude barbarian, and no more receives,</L>
<L>The tale traditional, and hymn profane,</L>
<L>Sung by high genius, basely prostitute.</L>
<L>New strains are heard, such as first in the morn</L>
<L>Of time, were sung by the angelic choirs,</L>
<L>When rising from chaotic state the earth</L>
<L>Orbicular was seen, and over head</L>
<L>The blazing sun, moon, planet▪ and each light</L>
<L>That gilds the firmament, rush'd into view.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus did the sun of revelation shine</L>
<L>Full on the earth, and grateful were its beams:</L>
<L>Its beams were grateful to the chosen seed,</L>
<L>To all whose works were worthy of the day.</L>
<L>But creatures lucifuge, whose ways were dark,</L>
<L>Ere this in shades of paganism hid,</L>
<L>Did vent their poison, and malignant breath,</L>
<L>To stain the splendour of the light divine,</L>
<L>Which pierc'd their cells and brought their deeds to view</L>
<L>Num'rous combin'd of ev'ry tongue and tribe,</L>
<L>Made battle proud, and impious war brought on,</L>
<L>Against the chosen sanctified by light.</L>
<L>Riches and pow'r leagu'd in their train were seen,</L>
<L>Sword, famine, flames and death before them prey'd.</L>
<L>Those faithful found, who undismay'd did bear</L>
<L>A noble evidence to truth, were slain.</L>
<L><PB N="13" REF="013172_0017_0F91042E22E95CD8"/>Why should I sing of these or here record,</L>
<L>As if 'twere praise, in poesy or song,</L>
<L>Or sculptur'd stone, to eternize the names,</L>
<L>Which writ elsewhere in the fair book of life,</L>
<L>Shall live unsullied when each strain shall die:</L>
<L>Shall undefac'd remain when sculptur'd stone,</L>
<L>And monument, and bust, and storied urn</L>
<L>Perpetuates its sage and king no more.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The pow'r of torture and reproach was vain,</L>
<L>But what not torture or reproach could do,</L>
<L>Dark superstition did in part effect.</L>
<L>That superstition, which saint John beheld,</L>
<L>Rise in thick darkness from th' infernal lake.</L>
<L>Locust and scorpion in the smoke ascend,</L>
<L>False teacher, heretic, and Antichrist.</L>
<L>The noon day sun is dark'ned in the sky,</L>
<L>The moon forbears to give her wonted light.</L>
<L>Full many a century the darkness rul'd,</L>
<L>With heavier gloom than once on Egypt came,</L>
<L>Save that on some lone coast, or desert isle,</L>
<L>Where sep'rate far a chosen spirit dwelt,</L>
<L>A Goshen shone, with partial-streaming ray.</L>
<L>Night on the one side settles dark; on Rome,</L>
<L>It settles dark, and ev'ry land more west</L>
<L>Is wrapt in shades. Night on the east comes down</L>
<L>With gloom Tartarean, and in part it rose</L>
<L>From Tartary beneath the dusky pole.</L>
<L>The ruthless Turk, and Saracen in arms,</L>
<L>O'er-run the land the gospel once illum'd;</L>
<L>The holy land Judea once so nam'd,</L>
<L>And Syria west where many churches rose.</L>
<L>Those golden luminaries are remov'd,</L>
<L>Which once in Asia shone. Athens no more</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="013172_0018_0F91042EE264DEE0"/>For truth and learning fam'd. Corinth obscur'd,</L>
<L>Ionia mourns through all her sea-girt isles.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But yet once more the light of truth shall shine</L>
<L>In this obscure sojourn; shall shoot its beam</L>
<L>In morning beauty mild, o'er hill and dale.</L>
<L>See in Bohemia and the lands more west</L>
<L>The heavenly ray of revelation shines,</L>
<L>Fresh kindling up true love and purest zeal.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Britannia next beholds the risen day</L>
<L>In reformation bright; cheerful she hails</L>
<L>It from her snow-white cliffs, and bids her sons,</L>
<L>Rise from the mist of popery obscure.</L>
<L>Her worthier sons, whom not Rome's pontiff high,</L>
<L>Nor king with arbitrary sway could move.</L>
<L>Those mightier who with constancy untam'd,</L>
<L>Did quench the violence of fire, at death</L>
<L>Did smile, and maugre ev'ry pain, of bond,</L>
<L>Cold dark imprisonment, and scourge severe,</L>
<L>By hell-born popery devis'd, held fast</L>
<L>The Christian hope firm anchor of the soul.</L>
<L>Or those who shunning that fell rage of war,</L>
<L>And persecution dire, when civil pow'r,</L>
<L>Leagu'd in with sacerdotal sway triumph'd,</L>
<L>O'er ev'ry conscience, and the lives of men,</L>
<L>Did brave th' Atlantic deep and through its storms</L>
<L>Sought these Americ shores: these happier shores</L>
<L>Where birds of calm delight to play, where not</L>
<L>Rome's pontiff high, nor arbitrary king,</L>
<L>Leagu'd in with sacerdotal sway are known.</L>
<L>But peace and freedom link'd together dwell,</L>
<L>And reformation in full glory shines.</L>
<L>Oh for a muse of more exalted wing,</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="013172_0019_0F91042F980FDDC8"/>To celebrate those men who planted first</L>
<L>The christian church in these remotest lands;</L>
<L>From those high plains where spreads a colony,</L>
<L>Gen'<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd free, from Massachusett-shores,</L>
<L>To the cold lakes margin'd with snow: from that</L>
<L>Long dreary tract of shady woods and hills,</L>
<L>Where Hudson's icy stream <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lls his cold wave,</L>
<L>To those more sunny bowers where zephyrs breath,</L>
<L>And round which flow in circling current swift</L>
<L>The Delaware and Susquehannah streams.</L>
<L>Thence to those smiling plains where Chesapeak</L>
<L>Spreads her maternal arms, encompassing</L>
<L>In <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> embrace, full many a settlement</L>
<L>Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pulence, with hospitality,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> manners, and the living plant</L>
<L>Of scien<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ooming, sets their glory high <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><P>The author has a principal reference to an infant Seminary at Back-Creek Somerset County Maryland, where a handsome building is erected, capable of accommodating with the greatest convenience, near 100 Scholars.</P>
<P>This institution, though of few years standing has risen to considerable eminence, and is still carried on with a spirit, which does honour to the Province. It is situated in a part of the Colo∣ny very distant from the Seminaries of reputation to the North∣ward, and near the Bay of Chesapeak into which many rivers emp∣ty themselves from Maryland and Virginia on the Western shore and afford an easy communication. It was very much wanted and is of real service to the advancement of virtue and science in that part of America.</P>
<P>It may not perhaps be impertinent to give some view of the ge∣neral plan upon which this School is conducted. A board of Trustees cosisting of 15 Gentlemen of the first reputation in the county, convene once every three months, or oftener if necessa∣ry, in order to inspect the situation and regulate the affairs of the school. A steward is chosen by them who lays in provisions of the best kind and at the lowest rates, for which he brings in his bill at the expiration of a year: This with the wages of the servants and principal Cook is equally assessed on the students. From the great plenty and cheapness of provisions in this settlement, and the oeconomy of the Trustees in managing the School, the expen∣ces of education seldom amount to more than £ 18 per annum—Board £ 13—Tuition £ 5.</P>
<P>The plan of education is the same with that pursued in other schools of character, and therefore needs not be mentioned. With respect to the internal regulation it may suffice to observe, that the Bell rings for prayers generally at sunrise; for study at the inter∣val of half an hour. The remaining part of the day is divided between study and vacation. In the evening the bell rings for prayers, after which the students retire to their chambers.</P>
<P>The school is placed in a genteel neighbourhood, having in view the dwellings of several Gentlemen of considerable property, who are constantly attentive to its wants, and ready to do the students every good office in their power.</P>
<P>It may now be asked why so particular in the account of this institution, and what has it to do with an exercise delivered at Nassau-Hall in the province of New-Jersey? The author has prin∣cipally this to reply, that on residing some time in the county of Somerset, he became acquainted with the merit of the school, and thought himself under an obligation as a wellwisher to mankind, to recommend it to the Public.</P></NOTE>.</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="013172_0020_0F91043076FC5EC8"/>Thence to Virginia, sister colony,</L>
<L>Lib'ral in sentiment, and breathing high,</L>
<L>The noble ardour of the freeborn soul.</L>
<L>To Carolina thence, and that warm clime</L>
<L>Where Georgia south in summer heat complains,</L>
<L>And distant thence towards the burning line.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>These men deserve our song, and those who still,</L>
<L>With industry severe, and steady aim</L>
<L>Diffuse the light in this late dreary land,</L>
<L>In whose lone wastes and solitudes forlorn,</L>
<L>Death long sat brooding with his raven wing.</L>
<L>Who many 'a structure of great fame have rais'd,</L>
<L>College, and school, upon th' Atlantic coast,</L>
<L>Or inland town, through ev'ry province wide,</L>
<L><PB N="17" REF="013172_0021_0F9104321887E840"/>Which rising up like pyramids of fire,</L>
<L>Give light and glory to the western world.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>These men we honour, and their names shall last</L>
<L>Sweet in the mouths and memory of men;</L>
<L>Or if vain man unconscious of their worth,</L>
<L>Refuse a tear when in some lonely vale</L>
<L>He sees those faithful said; each breeze shall sigh,</L>
<L>Each passing gale shall mourn, each tree shall bend</L>
<L>Its heavy head, in sorrow o'er their tombs,</L>
<L>And some sad stream run ever weeping by.</L>
<L>Weep not O stream, nor mourn thou passing gale,</L>
<L>Beneath those grassy tombs their bodies lie,</L>
<L>But they have risen from each labour here</L>
<L>To make their entrance on a nobler stage.</L>
<L>What though with us they walk the humble vale</L>
<L>Of indigence severe, with want oppress'd?</L>
<L>Riches belong not to their family,</L>
<L>Nor sloth luxurious nor the pride of kings;</L>
<L>But truth meek-ey'd and warm benevolence</L>
<L>Wisdom's high breeding in her sons rever'd</L>
<L>Bespeaks them each the children<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Judges viii 48.</NOTE> of a king,</L>
<L>The christian truth of origin divine,</L>
<L>Grows not beneath the shade of civil pow'r,</L>
<L>Riches or wealth accompanied with pride;</L>
<L>Nor shall it bloom transplanted to that soil,</L>
<L>Where persecution, in malignant streams,</L>
<L>Flows out to water it; black streams and foul</L>
<L>Which from the lake of Tartarus break forth,</L>
<L>The sickly tide of Acheron which flows,</L>
<L>With putrid waves through the infernal shades.</L>
<L>This plant of heaven loves the gentle beams,</L>
<L>Of truth and meekness, and the kindly dew</L>
<L>Which sell on Zion hill; it loves the care</L>
<L><PB N="18" REF="013172_0022_0F910432971B40B0"/>Of humble shepherds, and the rural swain,</L>
<L>And tended by their hands it flourishes</L>
<L>With fruit and blossoms, and soon gives a shades,</L>
<L>Beneath which ev'ry traveller shall rest,</L>
<L>Safe from the burning east-wind and the sun.</L>
<L>A vernal shade not with'ring like the gourd</L>
<L>Of him who warned Nineveh, but like</L>
<L>The aged oaks immortal on the plain</L>
<L>Of Kadesh, or tall cedars on the hill</L>
<L>Of Lebanon, and Hermon's shady top.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>High is their fame through each succeeding age</L>
<L>Who build the walls of Zion upon earth.</L>
<L>Let mighty kings and potentates combine,</L>
<L>To raise a pyramid, which neither storm,</L>
<L>Nor sea indignant, nor the raging fire,</L>
<L>Nor time can waste, or from firm basis move.</L>
<L>Or let them strive by counsel or by arms,</L>
<L>To fix a throne, and in imperial sway,</L>
<L>Build up a kingdom shadowing the earth,</L>
<L>Unmov'd by thunder or impetuous storm</L>
<L>Of civil war, dark treason, or the shock</L>
<L>Of hostile nations, in dire league combin'd.</L>
<L>They build a kingdom of a nobler date,</L>
<L>Who build the kingdom of the Saviour God.</L>
<L>This, not descending rain, nor mighty storm,</L>
<L>Nor sea indignant, nor the raging fire,</L>
<L>Nor time shall waste, or from firm basis move.</L>
<L>Founded on earth its head doth reach the skies,</L>
<L>Secure from thunder, and impetuous storm,</L>
<L>Of civil war, dark treason, or the shock</L>
<L>Of hostile nations in dire league combin'd.</L>
<L>This still shall flourish and survive the date,</L>
<L>Of each wide state and empire of the earth</L>
<L><PB N="19" REF="013172_0023_0F9104370A18A7E0"/>Hid in sepulchral monument of kings,</L>
<L>Shall bear an equal date with that true light,</L>
<L>Which shone from earth to heav'n, and which shall shine</L>
<L>Up through eternity, and be the light</L>
<L>Of heav'n, the new Jerusalem above.</L>
<L>This light from heav'n shall yet illume the earth</L>
<L>And give its beams to each benighted land</L>
<L>Now with new glory lighted up again.</L>
<L>Then ruthless Turk and Saracen shall know</L>
<L>The fallacies of him Medina bred,</L>
<L>And whose vain tomb, in Mecca they adore.</L>
<L>Then Jews shall view the great Messiah come,</L>
<L>And each rent tribe in caravan by land,</L>
<L>Or ship by sea, shall visit Palestine</L>
<L>Thrice holy then, with vile Idolatry</L>
<L>No more defil'd, altar on mountain head,</L>
<L>Green shady hill, or idol of the grove.</L>
<L>For there a light appears, with which compar'd,</L>
<L>That was a twilight shed by rite obscure,</L>
<L>And ceremony dark and sacrifice</L>
<L>Dimly significant of things to come.</L>
<L>Blest with this light no more they deviate</L>
<L>In out-way path; distinguished no more</L>
<L>By school or sect, Essene or Saducee,</L>
<L>Cairite or Scribe of Pharisaic mould.</L>
<L>Jew and Samaritan debate no more,</L>
<L>Whether on Gerizim or Zion hill</L>
<L>They shall bow down. Above Moriah's mount</L>
<L>Each eye is raised to him, whose temple is</L>
<L>Th' infinitude of space, whom earth, sea, sky</L>
<L>And heav'n itself cannot contain. No more</L>
<L>The noise of battle shall be heard, or shout</L>
<L>Of war by heathen princes wag'd; There's nought</L>
<L>Shall injure or destroy; they shall not hurt</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="013172_0024_0F91043726956160"/>In all my holy mountain saith the Lord.</L>
<L>The earth in peace and ev'ry shadow fled,</L>
<L>Bespeaks Emmanuel's happy reign when Jew,</L>
<L>And kindred Gentile shall no more contend,</L>
<L>Save in the holier strife of hymn and song,</L>
<L>To him who leads captive captivity,</L>
<L>Who shall collect the sons of Jacob's line,</L>
<L>And bring the fulness of the Gentiles in.</L>
<L>Thrice happy day when Gentiles are brought in</L>
<L>Complete and full; when with its genial beams</L>
<L>The day shall break on each benighted land</L>
<L>Which yet in darkness and in vision lies:</L>
<L>On Scythia and Tartary's bleak hills;</L>
<L>On mount Imaus, and Hyrcanian cliffs</L>
<L>Of Caucasus, and dark Iberian dales;</L>
<L>Japan and China, and the sea-girt isles</L>
<L>The ancient Ophir deem'd; for there rich gems</L>
<L>And diamond pearl, and purest gold is found.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thrice happy day when this whole earth shall feel</L>
<L>The sacred ray of revelation shed,</L>
<L>Far to the west, through each remotest land</L>
<L>With equal glory rivalling the day</L>
<L>Pour'd on the east. When these Americ shores</L>
<L>Shall far and wide be light, and heav'nly day</L>
<L>Shall in full glory rise on many a reign,</L>
<L>Kingdom and empire bending to the south,</L>
<L>And nation touching the Pacific shore.</L>
<L>When Christian churches shall adorn the streams</L>
<L>Which now unheeded flow with current swift</L>
<L>Circling the hills, where fiercest beasts of prey,</L>
<L>Panther and wolf in nightly concert howl.</L>
<L>The Indian sage from superstition freed,</L>
<L>Be taught a nobler heav'n than cloud-topt-hill,</L>
<L><PB N="21" REF="013172_0025_0F910437ED92FE00"/>Or sep'rate island in the wat'ry waste.</L>
<L>The aged Sachem fix his moving tribe,</L>
<L>And grow humane now taught the arts of peace.</L>
<L>In human sacrifice delight no more,</L>
<L>Mad cantico or savage feast of war.</L>
<L>Such scenes of fierce barbarity no more</L>
<L>Be perpetrated there, but truth divine</L>
<L>Shine on the earth in one long cloudless day,</L>
<L>Till that last hour which shuts the scene of things,</L>
<L>When this pure light shall claim its native skies;</L>
<L>When the pure stream of revelation shall,</L>
<L>With refluent current visit its first hills:</L>
<L>There shall it mix with that crystalline wave,</L>
<L>Which laves the walls of Paradise on high,</L>
<L>And from beneath the seat of God doth spring.</L>
<L>This is that river from whose sacred head</L>
<L>The sanctified in golden arms draw light,</L>
<L>On either side of which that tree doth grow</L>
<L>Which yields immortal fruit, and in whose shade</L>
<L>If shade were needed there, the rapt shall sing,</L>
<L>In varied melody to harp and lyre,</L>
<L>The sacred song of Moses and the Lamb:</L>
<L>Eternity's high arches ring; 'Tis heard</L>
<L>Through both infinitudes of space and time.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus have I sung to this high-favour'd bow'r,</L>
<L>And sacred shades which taught me first to sing,</L>
<L>With grateful mind a tributary strain.</L>
<L>Sweet grove no more I visit you, no more</L>
<L>Beneath your shades shall meditate my lay.</L>
<L>Adieu ye lawns and thou fair hill adieu,</L>
<L>And you O shepherds, and ye graces fair</L>
<L>With comely presence honouring the day.</L>
<L>Far hence I go to some sequest'red vale</L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="013172_0026_0F91043899B9BD38"/>By woody hill or shady mountain side,</L>
<L>Where far from converse and the social band,</L>
<L>My days shall pass inglorious away: <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">In these lines the author has not the least reference to the place of his present residence but to some western part of Ameri∣ca, where in the course of his life he may possibly be thrown. Should he ever remove from his present situation, it shall be with equal melancholy and regret, and if the Muse can produce a strain it shall be remembered in song. For though it may seem a vain boast after the preceding poem which is really very moderate, to talk of giving memory to fountain, landscape, or grove, yet it is very certain that love will raise the mind to language and senti∣ment, to which cold weak geneus of itself, could never attain.</NOTE></L>
<L>But this shall be my exultation still</L>
<L>My chiefest merit and my only joy,</L>
<L>That when the hunter on some western hill,</L>
<L>Or furzy glade shall see my grassy tomb,</L>
<L>And know the stream which mourns unheeded by,</L>
<L>He for a moment shall repress his step,</L>
<L>And say, <HI>There lies a Son of Nassau-Hall.</HI></L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>THE END</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

