<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-07-14</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Simon Charles</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Corrected 0 illegibles of 5. Converted 0 illegibles to GAP DESC="illegible".</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K050288.000">
<STC T="C">T056893</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3304933188</BIBNO>
<VID SET="ECSS">0421902000</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>AN
ESSAY
ON THE
History of Parties,
AND
PERSECUTION
IN
<HI>BRITAIN;</HI></P>
<P>Beginning,
With a brief Account of the <HI>Test-Act,</HI>
and an Historical Enquiry into the
Reasons, the Original, and the Consequen∣ces
of the <HI REND="blackletterType">Occasional Conformity</HI> of
<HI REND="blackletterType">Dissenters.</HI></P>
<P>With some Remarks on the several Attempts
already made, and now making for an
<HI REND="blackletterType">Occasional Bill.</HI></P>
<P>Enquiring how far the same may be esteem'd
a Preservation to the <HI>Church,</HI> or an Injury
to the <HI>Dissenters.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI>
Printed for <HI>J. Baker</HI> at the <HI>Black-Boy</HI> in
<HI>Paternoster-Row.</HI> 1711. (Price 6 <HI>d.</HI>)</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>AN
ESSAY, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></HEAD>
<P>IN order to enquire Critically into the
Reason and Justice, as well as Conse∣quences,
of an <HI>Occasional Bill,</HI> or an
Act to prevent the Occasional Conformity
of <HI>Dissenters,</HI> it seems necessary to state
as distinctly, and in a Method as unex∣ceptionable
as may be, the <HI>Nature</HI> and
<HI>Original</HI> of the Thing call'd <HI>Occasional Con∣formity,</HI>
and by what Steps the present
Debates about it, have come upon the
Stage.</P>
<P>That this may be done with as little Of∣fence
as possible, we shall deduce things in
a brief Historical Narration from undoubted
Testimony of Fact, recent to the Memory
of most observing Men in this Age, and
not to be contradicted by the false Glosses
or Misrepresentations of any: And if by
this it should appear, that the following
are undoubted Truths of unquestion'd Au∣thority,
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
then all the Vehemence which some
have used, in presenting the several Acts
against <HI>Occasional Conformity,</HI> will appear so
many Attempts, <HI>Whether knowingly or igno∣rantly,
is not to the Purpose,</HI> against the
Constitution, and against the just Right of
their Country; <HI>That is to say,</HI></P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. If it it appears, That the Act of Par∣liament
called <HI>The Test-Act,</HI> has been in∣verted
by the Sinister Designs of a Party
among us, and being in its true Intent and
Meaning formed against <HI>Popish</HI> Recusants
only, has been turned against our Fellow
Protestants, to the weakning and injuring
the Interest of the Protestant Religion in
general in this Kingdom;</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. If it appears, That it is a Law un∣just
in its own Nature, and inconsistent
with the Native Rights of the Subjects of
<HI>England,</HI> as well as with the Sovereignty
of Conscience, which ought not to be im∣posed
upon;</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. If it appears inconsistent with the
Christian Religion, and with the Princi∣ples
and Doctrine of the Church of <HI>Eng∣land;</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>4.
If the manner in which it is put in
Practice appears to be a Plot against the
Peace of the Nation, and a constant Han∣dle
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
to the Strife of Parties, and Oppressi∣on
of the Innocent.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>If upon an Impartial Enquiry into the
History of this Law, these things should
appear, then it may be worth our Consi∣deration,
whether we should still pursue a
thing so fatal to the General Good, and be
for ever Sacrificing one another to the Re∣sentment
of Parties, robbing each other of
the Peace, Liberty, and Birthright of <HI>Eng∣lish-men,</HI>
under the Forms, but contrary
to the true Intent and Meaning of the
Law.</P>
<P>From this short Introduction, and in or∣der
to lay these Things more plainly before
us, That <HI>English</HI> Protestants may see what
they are doing, and may not sacrifice one
another to the Interests of the Enemies of
both; We proceed to ransack from the
Beginning, the Records of these Things,
that the Truth being brought forth into a
clear Light, and viewed with open unblind∣ed
Eyes, the present Generation may have
none to blame but themselves, if they pull
down the Liberties and Religion of their
Ancestors with their own Hands.</P>
<P>After the Restoration of King <HI>Charles</HI> II.
had been for some Years perfected, and the
Court as well as the Kingdom was gotten
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
over their first Transports, enjoy'd a full
Dominion over the <HI>Puritan-Party,</HI> as they
call'd them, and had for two or three Years
suppressed the Remains of them by severe
Prosecutions of <HI>Dissenters,</HI> suppressing <HI>Con∣venticles,</HI>
Fining, Imprisoning, and Con∣fiscating
the Hearers, and Banishing, as
by the Corporation-Act, their Ministers
or Preachers Five Miles from every consi∣derable
Town, and the like; the Nobility
and Gentry of <HI>England</HI> began to see, that
while their Eyes had been taken up with
pursuing these lesser Evils of <HI>Schism</HI> in Re∣ligion
among Protestants, they had, as the
Consequence of such Proceedings generally
proves, insensibly suffered the secret En∣croachments
of <HI>Rome</HI> and of <HI>France,</HI> and
opened a Door to <HI>Popery</HI> and <HI>Tyranny.</HI></P>
<P>It would be too tedious a thing to un∣dertake
here, what all our Histories are full
of, <HI>viz.</HI> To give an Account by what in∣sensible
Degrees the King (influenc'd by the
Council of his Brother a declared <HI>Papist,</HI>
and by his own Resolutions, himself as ap∣pear'd
at his Death, being secretly a <HI>Papist,</HI>
an Account whereof shall in these Tracts be
at large made Publick) suffer'd himself and
all his Councils to be acted and managed
by the Artifice of <HI>France,</HI> and being him∣self
a Pensioner to the King of <HI>France,</HI>
brought his whole Kingdom to be passively
<PB N="7" REF="6"/>
subservient, and actively assistant to the Ri∣sing
Exorbitance of that Prince, whose
Power so assisted, has since grown too great
for all <HI>Europe,</HI> and has cost this same Nati∣on,
whose Blood and Valour assisted them,
<HI>to rise</HI> so much Blood and Treasure since
<HI>to reduce.</HI></P>
<P>At length, tho' late, the People of <HI>En∣gland</HI>
took the Alarm, when in the Year
1672, the King of <HI>France</HI> made that dread∣ful
Eruption into <HI>Holland,</HI> attacking the
<HI>Dutch</HI> with three formidable Armies at once,
without any Provocation, any Satisfaction
demanded, or Cause assign'd, save that he
was ill satisfied in them.</P>
<P>At the first of this War we wretchedly
assisted <HI>France,</HI> not only by Land, but de∣clared
War against the <HI>Dutch,</HI> and fell up∣on
them by Sea, in a manner too dishonou∣rable
for an <HI>Englishman</HI> to say much of, <HI>viz.</HI>
falling upon their <HI>Smyrna</HI> Fleet, while in
full Peace they might be supposed to come
securely into our Channel, if not into our
very Harbours. The rest we choose to co∣ver
with a Hand of Charity, rather than
expose the Nakedness of those Times, more
than the Necessity of the present Argument
obliges us to.</P>
<P>The Successes of <HI>France</HI> against the <HI>Dutch</HI>
reduc'd the States to the Brink of Ruine,
and <HI>Naerden</HI> being taken by the Duke of
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
<HI>Luxemburgh,</HI> it was expected, that <HI>Amster∣dam,</HI>
which was but 12 Miles off, would
have sent Deputies to make their Submission
to <HI>France.</HI> But in this Interim the Massacre
of the <HI>de Witts,</HI> and the Ruine of the <HI>Barna∣velt</HI>
Faction intervening, the Prince of <HI>O∣range,</HI>
afterwards King <HI>William</HI> of Glorious
Memory, a Prince born for the Rescuing
oppress'd Nations, and for a Refuge to the
Protestant Religion, was restor'd to the Ad∣ministration
of the Affairs in <HI>Holland,</HI> revi∣ved
the Courage of the desponding People,
and in a little time drove the <HI>French</HI> as fast
out of the Country, as they came in.</P>
<P>These things, and the Progress of the
<HI>French</HI> in <HI>Flanders,</HI> alarm'd <HI>England,</HI> as we
hinted above, and put us upon Enquiring
into our State at Home; Endeavours were
us'd to bring <HI>England</HI> over, and the Pulse of
the People in Parliament beat so high against
<HI>France,</HI> that the Court was oblig'd to make
a shew of Changing Sides; Peace was made
with the <HI>Dutch,</HI> an Offer of Marriage of the
Princess <HI>Mary,</HI> afterwards Queen <HI>Mary,</HI> to
the Prince of <HI>Orange,</HI> and several measures
taken, which look'd like a War with
<HI>France,</HI> tho' nothing less intended.</P>
<P>An Army was rais'd, Three Millions se∣ven
hundred thousand Pounds given by Par∣liament
for the Carrying it on; but such
hold had the <HI>Popish</HI> and <HI>French</HI> Councils
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
gotten in the <HI>English</HI> Court, that all the
Means which were possible to be used
could never get the King to Declare War,
but at last ended all in the Treaty of <HI>Nime∣guen,</HI>
a Peace wholly to the Advantage of
<HI>France.</HI></P>
<P>During these Transactions, the Patriots
of the Protestant Interest in this Nation,
finding the Influence which <HI>French</HI> and <HI>Popish</HI>
Emissaries had on the King, and finding
the <HI>Popish</HI> Lords in the House always vigo∣rous
to oppose every thing which was for
the advancing the new Measures, they ap∣ply'd
themselves to several Methods, in
order to weaken the <HI>Popish</HI> Party. They
could not yet obtain an Act to prevent the
<HI>Popish</HI> Lords Sitting in the House, but the
present Case was to prevent <HI>Popish</HI> Officers
in the Army; who were so many, and be∣haved
so Insolently, that the Army then
raised and incamp'd at <HI>Black-Heath,</HI> under
a Pretence of the War with <HI>France,</HI> was
become a Terror to the People, and was
called the <HI REND="blackletterType">Cut-throat Army.</HI></P>
<P>The Earl of <HI>Shaftsbury,</HI> who till then had
been one of the Five Capital Letters, which
formed the Word CABAL, was the
Man who contriv'd and brought in the
Proposal for a Bill to dispossess these <HI>Popish</HI>
Officers: And the Title of the Act expres∣sed
the Meaning and Design of its being
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
brought in. The King, the Court, and all
the <HI>Popish</HI> and <HI>French</HI> Interest, opposed it
with all their Might; but the Popular
Terror, and the just Fear the People were
in of a <HI>Popish</HI> Army, prevailed, and it pass'd
by a great Majority; neither did the King
think fit to oppose himself to the Stream of
the whole Nation at that time, especially
there being a great Money-Bill then de∣pending
in the House, for no less than
1238750<HI>l.</HI> which would have been lost.
So the Bill pass'd, 25 <HI>Carol.</HI> 2. and is Inti∣tled,
<HI>An Act for preventing Dangers which
may arise from Popish Recusants.</HI></P>
<P>This is the Famous <HI REND="blackletterType">Test-Act</HI>; and that
the true Intent and Meaning of this Act,
and the Reason of its making, may more
plainly appear, the Preamble to the Act is
thus; <HI REND="blackletterType">For Preventing Dangers which
may happen from Popish Recusants,
and for quieting the Minds of His
Majesties good Subjects</HI>; The <HI>Ʋneasi∣ness
of His Majesties good Subjects,</HI> was at
that time manifest to be their Fears of the
Army and Court being put into the Hands
of <HI>Papists;</HI> and the People who push'd on
the Act, were those very People, who es∣pousing
Liberty and Property, obtain'd in
Contempt from the Court-Party the Name
of <HI REND="blackletterType">Whiggs.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="11" REF="10"/>
But further to explain this Matter, the
Court, which with all possible Management
and Art opposed this Law, endeavour'd to
alarm the <HI>Dissenters</HI> with their Danger
from this Act; and Alderman <HI>LOVE,</HI> Re∣presentative
for the City of <HI>London,</HI> a Man
of unspotted Integrity, was privately spo∣ken
to, that he might oppose it on behalf
of the <HI>Dissenters:</HI> This at first had some
Effect on the People; but Mr. <HI>Love</HI> seeing
into the Design avoided it, and would not
meddle; on the other hand, the Persons
who brought in the Bill, assured the <HI>Dis∣senters,</HI>
there was no Design to offer them
any Disturbance, and that if they desired
it, they would bring in another Bill after∣wards,
to exempt them from the Penalties
of the said Act, representing to them at
the same time, That if they struck in to
oppose this Act, the Bill against <HI>Popery</HI>
would be lost, and both they and the Church
of <HI>England</HI> should fall together, under the
growing Mischiefs arising from the Power
of <HI>Papists</HI> in the Court.</P>
<P>The <HI>Dissenters,</HI> prevailed upon with these
Arguments, and especially depending upon
the Promises of the <HI>Church-men,</HI> (Unhappy
Credulity!) that the Act had no View
towards them, and should in no wise be
turned upon them, acquiesc'd, and to save
the Church of <HI>England,</HI> sacrific'd themselves
<PB N="12" REF="11"/>
and their Posterity, to the Ingratitude of
those that proposed it to them. Just thus the
<HI>Dissenters</HI> in <HI>Ireland</HI> suffered themselves to
be prevailed upon in the same Case, rather
than to lose that happy Bill last past there
to prevent the Growth of <HI>Popery;</HI> into the
middle of which, a certain Noble Person
then in the <HI>Ministry,</HI> and lately become a
Convert to a <HI>Principle</HI> perfectly new to
what he formerly profest, thrust into the
middle of that Act, thereby to throw out
all the Faithful Subjects of the Government,
who spent their Estates, and some of their
Blood in the Defence of <HI>London-Derry,</HI> a∣gainst
the <HI>Popish</HI> Army of King <HI>James,</HI>
from being trusted with the Magistracy of
the City they defended.</P>
<P>In this manner, and on this Occasion,
and no other, this Act was passed, which is
now become so much the Favourite of a
Party, as to be thought the great Defence
of the Church of <HI>England;</HI> how and by
what Degrees it became so, may not be
improper to enquire.</P>
<P>It was some Years after the first passing
of this Act, 'ere the Effects of it on the
<HI>Dissenters</HI> were much taken notice of; and
during the first 10 Years afterwards, the
Capitulation of those Persons who brought
it in was pretty well observed: And tho'
several Persecutions happen'd in that time
<PB N="13" REF="12"/>
upon the <HI>Dissenters,</HI> by Virtue of other
Penal Laws which were turned against
them, yet this Part of the Law was not
much insisted on till about the Year 82,
and 83, when the <HI>Popish</HI> Plot being turn'd
into Ridicule, and several Plots trumped
up upon the <HI>Dissenters,</HI> partly to turn the
Odium of that Plot upon them, and part∣ly
to suppress them as a Party joyning with
the <HI REND="blackletterType">Whigs,</HI> especially when the Court
undertook the modelling of Corporations,
and brought Writs of <HI>Quo-Warranto</HI> against
the Charters of Towns: Then this Law
was turned full-but upon the <HI>Dissenters,</HI> and
with all imaginable Eagerness insisted upon,
even so much as to the Common-Council
Men of the City of <HI>London;</HI> nay, they be∣gan
to talk, or offer at, allowing no Citi∣zens
to Vote for Common-Council Men
or Aldermen, but such as had taken the
Sacrament; and to run it to all possible Ex∣tremities,
they went this Length, That no
Man should be allow'd a License to keep
an <HI>Ale-House,</HI> unless he had taken the Sa∣crament
of the Church; and several sad
Stories are left upon Record, of Persons
falling into Despair, Melancholy and
Madness, for having acted against their
Consciences in that Case; till at last
it was said, a poor profligate Wretch
found out an Expedient for it, and finding a
Priest with as little Religion as himself,
<PB N="14" REF="13"/>
communicated with him, professing to take
it as no Religious Act, for that he owned
he was not fit to do it; acknowledging him∣self
a Scandalous Sinner, but that being
forced to do it, or lose his License, which
was his Livelyhood, he took it as common
Bread and Wine, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> There are other
Scandalous Instances of the Severity of
those Times, which we omit, being not
willing to aggravate the Grief of those
things.</P>
<P>By the publick Management of these
Times, this Act was thus brought on the
Stage, as if made on purpose for the <HI>Dissen∣ters,</HI>
while at the same time the <HI>Papists,</HI> a∣gainst
whom it had really been made, were
upon every Occasion forborn, conniv'd at,
and overlook'd; and all Attempts to prose∣cute
the Law against them discourag'd and
discountenanc'd.</P>
<P>This continued during the whole Reign
of King <HI>Charles</HI> II. and in King <HI>James</HI>'s
Reign, till the Defeat of the Duke of <HI>Mon∣mouth,</HI>
when the King in his Speech to the
Parliament, fairly told the House, He could
not want the Service of the Gentlemen of
his own Religion, and openly Dispensing
with this Law in the <HI>Papists,</HI> cajol'd the
<HI>Dissenters</HI> with their share of the Liberty.</P>
<P><PB N="15" REF="14"/>
Some of the <HI>Dissenters,</HI> it must be al∣lowed,
were so far partial to their own Ease,
as not to consider that it was given them at
the Expence of the Constitution, and that
their enjoying the Relaxation of Penal Sta∣tutes
by the Breath of the King, was a
stopping their Mouths against the open
Breaches of the Law, and effectually taking
from them any Argument they might use
against the Dispensing Power, or the pulling
down all the Fortifications of our Laws
against <HI>Popery,</HI> and Arbitrary Govern∣ment.</P>
<P>But
their Eyes were soon open'd, and
they saw the Mistake time enough to
joyn heartily with the Church of <HI>England,</HI>
in restoring the Liberties of their Coun∣try,
and overthrowing the projected Esta∣blishment
of <HI>Popery;</HI> and then followed the
<HI REND="blackletterType">Revolution.</HI></P>
<P>During the whole Reign of King <HI>William,</HI>
the <HI>Test-Act</HI> slept in its Native Circum∣stance,
its first Design in keeping <HI>Papists</HI>
out of Publick Employment, out of Par∣liament,
Army, and Civil List, was effectu∣ally
answer'd: But the corrupt turning the
Edge upon the <HI REND="blackletterType">Dissenters</HI> was discoun∣tenanc'd,
as what was <HI>not only</HI> not the
Interest of the Nation, but as what was not
the true Reason or Intent and Meaning
of the Bill. The King, who had a native
<PB N="16" REF="15"/>
Aversion to all Religious Coercion, had
also the less Inclination to push the Se∣verity
of this Law upon the <HI>Dissenters,</HI>
because he knew in the Original Making
that Law, it was not in the View either of
the People, or of the Sovereign, to give them
the least Disturbance on that Account.</P>
<P>Yet here the <HI>Dissenters</HI> committed ano∣ther
Error; for as if they were easier in
their Compliance, in that they were not
at all compell'd, they voluntarily comply'd
with the Law, tho' they were sure no Man
would meet with Encouragement in prose∣cuting
them for the Omission; nor do we
find in all this time any Prosecution com∣menced
against any Protestant Dissenter,
for taking or executing any Office or Place,
whether Civil or Military, without taking
the Sacrament.</P>
<P>This obtain'd the Name of <HI REND="blackletterType">Occasional
Conformity</HI>; but the Freedom with which
the <HI>Dissenters</HI> qualified themselves, at their
entring into such Offices, tho' there seem'd
no Danger in the Omission, gave Offence;
first to their own Friends, especially among
those, who having a more strict regard to
their Principles, look'd upon it as an Incon∣sistency
with their professed Dissent from
the Church, who complained openly, that
such who could on meer Occasion of Pre∣ferment,
and to shun a Penalty Conform,
<PB N="17" REF="16"/>
ought not to be receiv'd again into the
Communion of particular Congregations,
but as Penitents.</P>
<P>There were many who took up the Wea∣pons
against this Objection, and thought to
master it with Arguments drawn from
General Charity: But however they might
prove the Legality of a Communion of
Charity with all Orthodox Christians; or
a General Communion with the whole
Christian Church; yet it is most certain,
no full Answer could be given to that
Part of <HI REND="blackletterType">Occasional Conformity</HI> which
was submitted to by Persons otherwise
Dissenting from the Church, meerly to
quality for Preferment and Places in the
Government, which was the Sum of the
Dispute at that time.</P>
<P>This Argument therefore being directly
against them, became exceeding Popular,
and especially it appear'd a little new to
find the <HI>Dissenters</HI> themselves vigorously Dis∣puting
for <HI>Conformity</HI> to that very <HI REND="blackletterType">Church</HI>
which they statedly separated from.</P>
<P>No sooner was Her present Majesty come to
the Crown, but the Enemies of the <HI>Toleration,</HI>
having as they thought, an opportunity to op∣press
the <HI>Dissenters,</HI> began here; They found
nothing so proper to render them hated
and odious to the People, as the Charge
of Hypocrisy, and therefore immediately
<PB N="18" REF="17"/>
took hold of this, as an Advantage
which offered against the <HI>Dissenters,</HI> and
that would make their Proceeding against
them popular and specious: And this in∣troduced
the first <HI REND="blackletterType">Occasional Bill.</HI></P>
<P>Now as all Extreams in the unhappy Divi∣sions
of this Nation, have been fatal to the
common Liberty of the whole, as well as to
the Parties themselves, who run unadvisedly
into them: So here, as the <HI>Occcasional Confor-</HI>
of those <HI>Dissenters</HI> in general, who run to
the Sacrament in that prophane manner,
meerly for a Qualification, grew scanda∣lous
and hateful, even to their own Bre∣thren,
whose Consciences were more strictly
obey'd; so the absolute restraining the Liber∣ty
of Occasional Conforming, in all that
should enjoy any Publick Employment,
tying them up from ever Communicating,
or so much as hearing a Sermon in a <HI>Dis∣senting
Meeting,</HI> or indeed in any Foreign
Protestant Church, on Pain of losing their
Employments and Livelyhood; this always
carry'd with it such an Air of Cruelty,
such an Invasion of Native-Right, such an
Oppression of Conscience, such a visible In∣consistency
with the <HI REND="blackletterType">Toleration,</HI> and such
a Degree of <HI>Persecution,</HI> that all the mode∣rate
Part, even of the Church of <HI>England</HI>
it self, opposed it.</P>
<P><PB N="19" REF="18"/>
How it was first introduced and pass'd the
<HI>House of Commons;</HI> how it was sent up to the
<HI>Lords</HI> for their Concurrence; how the
<HI>Lords</HI> return'd it but with one Amend∣ment,
relating to some Circumstances
not essential to the Bill, and which the
Commons would gladly have quitted in
their subsequent Attempts; and yet how the
Commons adhering to their first Bill, and
the Lords insisting on their Amendment,
that Bill was lost: How the next Session,
a second Bill was brought in, and sent up to
the Lords, but the Temper of Persecution
having lost Ground, was thrown out by
the Peers by a great Majority: And <HI>lastly,</HI>
how a third Bill was brought into the House
of Commons, and lost in their own House
by the Attempt to Tack it to another Bill;
and how that Tacking Project not only
threw out the Bill, but even overthrew the
Party, that had been all along so forward
to promote it: These are Things so well
known to every Man that has any Con∣cern
upon him for the Publick, and the
Particulars have been made so public, that
we need do no more, than refer the in∣quiring
Readers to the Papers which have
been already published on that Occa∣sion.</P>
<P><PB N="20" REF="19"/>
When after this by the late <HI REND="blackletterType">Court-Revo∣lution</HI>
in <HI>England,</HI> a new Turn was given to
all our Civil Affairs, and new Faces ap∣pear'd
in the Management; as the Warmth
of the <HI>High Church</HI> Party appear'd in se∣veral
Extravagancies so unbounded, as we
had Reason to apprehend, that they could
be deny'd nothing, and knew they
would stick at nothing to raise their New
Party and effectually crush the Old, so it
was expected this old Affair should be re∣vived.</P>
<P>When
we say <HI>expected,</HI> 'tis needful to add
that it was expected by every Party: The
<HI>High Party</HI> expected it; they said one to
another, That now was the happy Moment,
when it was in their Power entirely, not to
establish the Church only, but so effectually
to crush the Interest of the <HI>Dissenters,</HI> as to
render it impossible for them ever to rise
again, at least so as to make themselves
formidable to the Church.</P>
<P>We might add here what that Party pro∣mised
themselves from the Restoration of
their Friends, the Elections having gone
generally in their favour; how they reduc'd
the <HI REND="blackletterType">Toleration</HI> to such a Pitch, that they
would no more have it allow'd to be a <HI REND="blackletterType">To∣leration,</HI>
but an Exemption from the Pe∣nalty
of certain Laws; how the Academies
<PB N="21" REF="20"/>
and Schools of the <HI>Dissenters</HI> were threaten∣ed,
and Prosecutions against some of them
actually begun; and how in all Places, they
began to threaten the <HI>Dissenters</HI> with shut∣ting
up their Meeting-Houses, and in many
Places, rabbl'd, pull'd down, and burnt
their Meeting-Houses; but this may be re∣ferr'd
to a more proper Place; this may, we
hope, sufficiently prove, That the Friends
of that Party made no question, but that an
<HI REND="blackletterType">Occasional Bill</HI> should be immediately
brought in.</P>
<P>The <HI>Dissenters</HI> testify'd early their just
Apprehensions, when in the Hurry of this
Change at Court, and the coming in of a
New Party like a Flood; the Insults in
their Persons, the Injuries in their Houses
and Meetings, the Abusive Railing Pam∣phlets,
and the Tumultuous carrying of all
kinds of Elections, against common Rules
of Modesty and Decency, as well as Right,
made it Rational to them to think, that no∣thing
could be so severe, but what they had
Reason to expect; and therefore that an
<HI REND="blackletterType">Occasional Bill</HI> should be Introduc'd in∣to
the next Parliament, to the Ruin of their
Liberty, was one of the least Things which
they thought it was Reasonable to fear.</P>
<P>Even those Gentlemen, who tho' willing
for other Reasons, to join in the Changes
at Court, were yet of more Moderate Prin∣ciples,
<PB N="22" REF="21"/>
that were willing to have the late
Ministry depos'd, and admitted the New
Ministry, as a Means to such other Ends as
they had in View, whether respecting this
or that View, yet unconcern'd with any
Religious Prospects; These, tho' they did
not approve of the Occasional Bill, as what
they imagin'd needless to the Church, and
tending to encrease the Ʋneasinesses of the
People, which they having settled the New
Management of Civil Affairs, desir'd to
bring to some settled Condition; yet it is
plain, expected the Occasional Bill to be
push'd at the last Session, and as they ex∣pected
it, so they apply'd themselves to pre∣vent
it, and, as by the Consequence appear'd,
did prevent it.</P>
<P>It will be needless to bring the Com∣plaints
of the Hot Men against these last; for
their fatal Moderation, as they call it, is an
Evidence, that these Men of Moderation
did effectually stop the Current of that Zeal,
or Heat, call it what you please, which
would have put forward such a Bill: 'Tis
enough, that the House of Commons go∣verning
themselves by Moderate Councils,
contrary to all the Expectations, Hopes, or
Fears, as above, offer'd nothing to the Pre∣judice
of the <HI>Dissenters,</HI> abridg'd none of
their Liberties, nor encourag'd any of the
Heats without Doors, which would have
<PB N="23" REF="22"/>
push'd at the <HI>Dissenters;</HI> and the Session
pass'd over, with a Calmness, as exceeding∣ly
Mortifying to the Enemies of Peace, as
perhaps Surprizing to those who had been
under Apprehensions of other Usage, as a∣bove.</P>
<P>By
this happy Conduct, the <HI>Dissenters</HI> be∣gan
to take Courage, Re-builded their De∣molish'd
Meeting-Houses, and promis'd to
themselves, that as Her Majesty had pass'd
Her Royal Word, to preserve <HI REND="blackletterType">Inviolable</HI>
their Privileges and Religious Liberty, they
should enjoy the same, notwithstanding the
former Fears, without any farther Interrup∣tion.</P>
<P>When
on a suddain, from a Quarter
whence they expected nothing of that kind;
and from Hands, which they well hop'd
would, as they formerly had been, held up
in their Favour, the Storm seems to be Risen,
by what ever Influence, and with what e∣ver
Design rais'd, is not for us to Enquire
yet, but we shall adjourn it with the Words
of the Apostle, <HI>We have many Things to say,
but you cannot bear them now.</HI></P>
<P>We are now come to that unhappy
Time, That Crisis, when we see the <HI>Dis∣senters</HI>
given up by their Beloved Patriots,
Attack'd by those, who they justly plac'd
their Confidence in, as the People from
whom they expected Protection; and as a∣nother
<PB N="24" REF="23"/>
Author writes, sacrifiz'd to the Par∣ty-Interest
of those, who pretended former∣ly
to espouse them.</P>
<P>This, we say, with Respect to those Peo∣ple,
who to Congratulate the New Converts
that come over to a Party, are pleas'd to see
themselves ruin'd, and the Liberties of their
Posterity taken away, in Matters both Ci∣vil
and Consciencious, in order to form a
Secular Interest, and support their Prospects
relating to Power, Management, and Ad∣ministration:
We are speaking now of Peo∣ple
without Doors, for of the Parliament
and Proceedings within Doors, we may not
now discourse.</P>
<P>But above all, it seems Astonishing to
Unbyass'd Judgments, to find even the <HI>Dis∣senters</HI>
themselves less Allarm'd at their ap∣proaching
Bondage, than they us'd to be;
willing to please themselves with Hopes, that
the Hands that this comes from, cannot be
suppos'd to hurt them; willing to amuse
themselves with the Rumour, that the Bill
now depending, is differing from the for∣mer,
and less severe; that it is qualified with
some Circumstances which makes them a∣mends;
that it includes a farther Security to
the <HI>Tolleration,</HI> and the like.</P>
<P>Alas poor People! When are ye to open
your Eyes? When will Heaven be pleas'd
to restore you to your Understanding?
<PB N="25" REF="24"/>
What are you doing? If the present Bill is
Qualified with some Clauses for your better
liking it; if the bitter Pill is cover'd with a
thin Leaf of glittering Metal; if there are
not all the severe Things which you were
formerly Attack'd with in this; Do you de∣rive
Comfort from this? Or ought you not
the rather to see the certainty of what is to
come, and that your Bondage is made sure
to you, by the Earnest-Peny given you in
the Beginning?</P>
<P>The present Parliament are, perhaps, dis∣pos'd
to gentle Methods, and backward to
bring upon you the Weight you were for∣merly
Threatned with, and you are pleas'd
with the Negative of your Miseries, and
Thankful that it is no worse.</P>
<P>But have you look'd at the Formidable
Power of your Enemies without Doors?
Have you Enquir'd into their New Mea∣sures?
How having, as before, miscar∣ried
in their Attempts on you, by the
Rash pushing all at once upon the whole of
your Destruction, they now see their Mi∣stake,
and are acting wisely with you; <HI>Go
to, let us deal wisely with them,</HI> was the Anci∣ent
Method of God's Enemies; and what
is this Wisdom, but a gradual Encroach∣ment
upon you; and gaining by little and
little, what they would find less likely to
prevail in, if offer'd at once?</P>
<P><PB N="26" REF="25"/>
Fatal is their Policy, to wheedle you in!
they take hold of your Party Animosities,
and send over their <HI>Hushai's</HI> to Counterfeit
a Revolt to you, and to bring in your Easie
and Impolitick Leaders, into Measures with
them, at your Cost; forming a Party to
carry on Temporal Interest, at the Ex∣pence
of your Religious Liberties; and thus
you are drawn in by the Spies and Cheats of
a Party, to be Agents in your own De∣struction.</P>
<P>Poor
unhappy blinded People! Supinely
sitting down pleas'd with the Ruin of your
Liberty, because it comes from Hands that
you think would not hurt you: Perhaps
those People whom you Rely so steadily up∣on,
are your Friends, and would not wil∣lingly
injure you, but they are not <HI>Dissenters,</HI>
their Opinion is not with you, so it can be
no Point of Conscience to them; perhaps
they do not see so far into the fatal Conse∣quences
of your Oppressions, as you may
soon have Cause to do; and are willing to
give up a few Points, which they may not
be sensible are fatal to your Interest; and as
this may form a greater Interest for them a∣nother
Way, they think this the lesser Mis∣chief.</P>
<P>But
is this suitable to the Sincerity of those
Pretences these Men have always made, of
a Disinterested regard to the Concerns of the
<PB N="27" REF="26"/>
<HI>Dissenters?</HI> Is this according to the Stipula∣tions
of the Memorial to the P. of <HI>O . . . ?</HI> Or
is not this opening a Door, at which the ap∣parent
Ruin of the <HI>Tolleration</HI> must infallibly
enter? It is our Duty to suppose, that the
<HI>Parliament</HI> has no such View, has no Pro∣spect
or Intention, but to the better Esta∣blishing
the Interest of the Church, and are
not desirous of Invading the Tolleration,
or taking away the Liberties of the <HI>Dis∣senters,</HI>
or lessening their Native Rights:
But is not the restless pursuit of the Ruin
of the <HI>Dissenters</HI> at the bottom of their Con∣duct,
who prompt these Things without
Doors? And why do they content them∣selves
with this part of their Design at
this time? But perhaps because they fore∣saw
they could obtain no more, and because
they are willing to get up every Step they
can, towards that intire Dominion over
Conscience, which they hope to arrive to.</P>
<P>It cannot be construed a Reflection upon
the Parliament, without manifest Injustice,
to say, that others may have Abhorr'd
Destructive Prospects, in Contriving what
these may have no View but the general
Good in their Enacting; for the Whole∣somest
Laws have been perverted to the most
wicked Purposes; as Establishments of Ci∣vil
Right to Oppression; Corporation-Pri∣vileges
to Monopoly; Royal Prerogative
<PB N="28" REF="27"/>
to Tyranny, and Church Settlements to
Persecution; and therefore while we charge
the Party who aim at the Ruin of the To∣leration,
to be at the Bottom of every At∣tack
against the <HI>Dissenters;</HI> we no more Re∣proach
the Proceedings of the Parliament;
than when we clear the Parliament of any
Evil in such Proceedings, we may be said
to acquit the Contrivers and Party, who
promote on all Occasions the Ruin of the
<HI>Dissenters</HI> Liberty.</P>
<P>That the present Bill depending in the
House, may be with fewer Restrictions than
the last; That there may be some Clauses
in Favour of the Toleration, we cannot
say but all this may be true, and the Mode∣ration
and Justice of the Houses, are so far
your Safety; but are there not Clauses in
the same Law, which lessen the Liberties
which the Act of Toleration either Granted
you, or which were your Right in Conse∣quence
of the Act of Toleration, or which
are the Native Rights of <HI>English-Men?</HI> Are
there no Clauses which break in upon that
Liberty of Conscience, which we have so
long insisted upon as a Right which no
Humane Power ought to Invade? Are there
no Branches of Persecution in it? Are there
no Powers given to your Enemies to Insult
and Oppress your Consciences? Are there
no poor Innocent Men, who must forego
<PB N="29" REF="28"/>
their Employments, and starve their Fa∣milies,
or act against Conscience to feed
them? Are there no innocent People who
must be driven from the <HI>Dissenters</HI> to the
<HI>Church</HI> meerly for Subsistence? Or which
is still worse, are there no Conscientious
<HI>Dissenters</HI> who must now perish and starve,
because they cannot totally Conform, be∣ing
obliged to quit their Employments,
because they cannot in meer Conscience
comply? If none of these Things are in
the Bill it is well: but if there are, Let
the <HI>Dissenters</HI> flatter themselves as much
they will, that those on whose Favour and
Judgment they so much depend, acqui∣esce
in the Bill: Let them please them∣selves
as much as they will in the Nega∣tives
of the Bill, That this or that which
was severe in the late Bill, was not in
this; they will find, let this be as mild
as it will, it is yet so much the nearer
to the Persecution which the Party de∣signs;
'tis yet a Step forwarder to the
approaching Evil that waits behind; the
slower the Poison, the surer the Operation;
the lingring Consumption is most certain
to kill, and the <HI REND="blackletterType">Toleration</HI> which is the
Aim of the Party, is so much the nearer
to its fatal Period.</P>
<P><PB N="30" REF="29"/>
Nor is the Slumber of the <HI>Dissenters,</HI> and
the Lethargy that is upon them as to this
Matter, the least of their Danger, when
they are so divided in Interests, heated
with Animosities, and engaged in Parties,
that too many among them are willing to
give up any thing, and fall in with any Body,
so they can but strengthen the Party Inte∣rest
they pursue: This is a fore-boding
Signal of the Ruin of their Interest, we
speak not meerly with respect to the pre∣sent
Heats that rage among us, but for
several Years past, this has been the pre∣vailing
Temper.</P>
<P>And how else could they now rejoyce in,
and propose Things to themselves from the
seeming Conversion or Revolt, or what you
will call it, of a Person known thro' many
Years of Publick Conduct, to bear a profess'd
Aversion to the <HI REND="blackletterType">Revolution,</HI> to the Per∣son
of the King, to the whole Body, Be∣ing,
and very Name of a <HI>Dissenter?</HI> Is it
for this Man and his very few Dependents,
that we are so willing to Sacrifice the Li∣berties
of Two Millions of Her Majesty's
Subjects? Is it to gain a Man who no Side
ever thought capable of Business, whose
Interest never put an Ounce in the Scale
of Parties, but who has been the Derision
of all Sides, and the Contempt even of his
<PB N="31" REF="30"/>
own House? Is it for this Man's Favour
that a whole Party should deviate from
their Ancient Steadiness, and give up the
Rights and Privileges of their Country∣men?</P>
<P>We look upon an Attempt of this Nature,
to be a Plot upon the <HI REND="blackletterType">Whigs</HI> in general,
and their Interest as a Party, as well as
upon the <HI>Dissenters;</HI> and this Plot is to di∣vide
them, and no doubt but it will have
the desir'd Effect. For will the <HI>Dissenters</HI>
ever trust a <HI REND="blackletterType">Low Church Whig</HI> again,
when they find that these have turned up∣on
them in such a manner as this, and flat∣tering
the other Party, put their Hands to
such a Work as this, smiling to the <HI REND="blackletterType">Tories,</HI>
with <HI>JEHƲ, Come, see our Zeal for the
Church!</HI></P>
<P>Could there ever be a more effectual
Step to divide the Interest of the Whigs?
Can one Party ever betray another but
it lessens their Confidence one in another
for ever after? Will a <HI>Dissenter</HI> ever re∣pose
his Safety again in the Breast of a
<HI>Church Whig?</HI> Or will a <HI>Church Whig</HI> ever
believe a <HI>Dissenter</HI> can trust him with his
Liberty after this? And do not the Enemy
percieve it?</P>
<P>Were there no Man of <HI>Moderation</HI> left
among the whole Body to have recourse to,
to save Us? And when did this happen? Had
<PB N="32" REF="31"/>
it been when a Majority of <HI>High Flying</HI>
Interest had Govern'd in the . . . . . . . it
might have been expected; but when we
boasted of the contrary to an Extream, to
have this Storm arise from that Quarter!
O <HI>Hominem!</HI> O <HI>Mores!</HI></P>
<P>Why should any Man wonder, That a
<HI>Nemine Contradicente</HI> is added to the Ac∣counts
we have, of the Progress of the
Affair we are upon? How should it be
expected that any one should contradict
what those alone, who it was always ex∣pected
should oppose it, had consented to
do, nay and as we are told, were the O∣riginals,
<HI>I had almost said worse,</HI> in the Fa∣mous
Introduction of it into the . . . .</P>
<P>It might be expected here, that some∣what
should be said to the Matter, of the
present Bill depending: But there may be
more time for that, and a Time more pro∣per.</P>
<P>It
may suffice at present, to speak a
little to the General Design of a <HI>Bill,</HI> or
<HI>Act of Parliament,</HI> against <HI>The Occasional
Conformity of Dissenters,</HI> whether it respects
this Bill or no, and a little of that <HI>Occasi∣onal
Conformity</HI> it self, as they relate to
what has been formerly Transacted in
both Houses of Parliament upon that
Head.</P>
<P><PB N="33" REF="32"/>
We have not the least View in this to
plead for the Occasional Conformity of the
Dissenters, as it relates to a meer Qualifi∣cation,
a Practice which it is manifest few
of the Dissenters defend, which they are
very much come off from, and which has
done much more Prejudice to the Dissenters
themselves, than to the Church. But it seems
absolutely necessary in common Justice, to
distinguish here between a voluntary ill Pra∣ctice
of a few, and a Law to divest the Sub∣ject
either of his Civil or Religious Right.</P>
<P>We find many People, who by their con∣stant
Practice, tho' dissenting in Worship,
and in many things relating to Discipline,
Church-Government and Ceremony, have
yet held it as a Point of Conscience, to main∣tain
a Communion of Charity with the
Church; others, tho' they do not choose to
Communicate with the Church, yet in such
Cases where the Law requires it, think them∣selves
bound in Conscience, <HI>as they are to shew
Obedience to the Laws,</HI> to comply with that
Occasionally, which statedly, they cannot do;
these we call <HI>Conscientious Conformers.</HI></P>
<P>If these things are meerly Matter of Prin∣ciple,
then oppressing these Men must be
the highest of <HI>Persecution,</HI> which <HI>Persecution</HI>
was censur'd in the Preamble to the first Oc∣casional
Bill, to be <HI>contrary to the Principle
of the Christian Religion, and the Doctrine</HI>
<PB N="34" REF="33"/>
<HI>of the Church of</HI> England: And it is to be
noted here, as well worth our Reflection,
that both the first and second <HI>Occasional Bills</HI>
were rejected, because they were look'd upon
to be a Degree of <HI>Persecution.</HI></P>
<P>We cannot but think 'tis always reasona∣ble
to distinguish, between preventing an
evil Practice, and taking away a Civil Right,
and that this is the Case here, no Body will
dispute.</P>
<P>The Dissenters have injury enough, in
that they are by the Letter of the Law, <HI>con∣trary
to the Intent and Meaning of the whole
Legislature at the time of its making,</HI> exclu∣ded
from the common Privileges in Society
with their Fellow-Subjects, <HI>viz.</HI> of serving
the Publick, and receiving the Reward of
their Prince, for the Expressions of their
Zeal and Loyalty in the publick Service; ex∣cept
upon the unhappy Condition of doing
that (which as Dissenters) they may be not
supposed capable to do.</P>
<P>But to lay so severe an Injunction, That
if ever they touch any publick Employ, they
shall never go to hear a Sermon again, or to
communicate again in a Meeting-House.
This is Persecution with a witness, to com∣pel
to do any thing, which is against our
Conscience to do, otherwise, tho' lawful in
itself, <HI>is Persecution;</HI> to restrain from doing
what is in it self lawful, and we may think
<PB N="35" REF="34"/>
to be Duty to do, <HI>is Persecution;</HI> and all the
Punishment inflicted in these Cases, <HI>is Per∣secution</HI>
in the Abstract.</P>
<P>It has been so often argu'd, that this is
no Service to the Church, or to the High
Party, that this Argument seems perfectly
useless to be repeated; but we cannot but
take notice, that all the Acts hitherto pro∣pos'd,
have not seem'd to have an Eye to the
Church, but to the Civil Preferments; not
to bring the Dissenters over to the Church,
but to keep them out of the Offices of Profit.
There lies the true Aim in all this matter;
and this has been so visible in all the former
Practice, that it needs little Explanation.</P>
<P>Had the Design been purely the bringing
the Dissenters over to the Church, they would
let it alone where it is, since nothing is more
certain than this, that the Occasional Con∣formity
of Dissenters has done more towards
bringing all their Posterity into the Church,
than all the Coecive Laws, Penal Statutes,
or other Violence in the World could ever
do; and it is most remarkable, that general∣ly
speaking, where-ever the Parents have
been Occasional Conformists, the Children
have been total Conformist. So that this
Liberty taken by the Dissenters, has been
the Ruin of their Strength, the breaking of
the principal Families of their Party, and the
<PB N="36" REF="35"/>
indifferency of one Age has terminated the
dissenting of the next.</P>
<P>This the High Church Men are not igno∣rant
of, and it is mention'd for this Reason,
<HI>viz.</HI> To prove, that were the true Interest
of the Church regarded in this Case, or at
least were that true Interest the End and De∣sign
in these things, they would entirely let
the Dissenters alone. But the Design in these
things is so far from that, is so remote from
a Religious View, that it all centers in ma∣king
Parties, keeping Posts of Profit and Ad∣vantage,
and if possible, keeping the Dissen∣ters
out of them; and which is yet worse,
the Aim is at a dividing the Interest of the
Whiggs, which being link'd to that of the
Dissenters, has been too formidable for them
to deal with; but if the Low Church Men
can be brought to give up the Dissenters—What
then! Why they shall have the Ho∣nour—of
what? Of being devour'd last,
and that is all they can promise themselves.</P>
<P>And will the Low Church Men give up
the Dissenters? Will they make a Sacrifice
of the Consciences of their Brethren, to gain
a small Addition to their Party Interest?
What can be said to them? We crave leave
to remind them of two or three things.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. How long do ye think the New Inte∣rest
you are making will last, upon so
<PB N="37" REF="36"/>
ill a Foundation built? How far can you
go along with the New Converts you are
bringing over, either they must turn
Whigs, or you must turn High Flyers?
The first can never be but by Project,
and purpose to trick and deceive you;
and the last can never be but by unac∣countable
and most judicial Blindness;
and if these cannot be, then you cannot
go far together.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. When they and you part, and they go
back to their own Party, you having in
the highest manner provok'd the Dissen∣ters,
are you able to stand the Ground
against Popery and High Flying mad
Men by your selves?</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Remember the time when you were
last try'd, and consider that two things
will suit your present Case. (1.) That
when you were try'd with Popery and
Slavery, the one from a Popish Prince,
the other from <HI>French</HI> Maxims of Go∣vernment,
what was your Case? Were
you able to stand your Ground alone?
were you not sensible of the impossibility
of it? And (2.) when you were sensible
of the contrary, and made solemn In∣vitations
to the Dissenters to stand by
you, and join with you, did the Dis∣senters
abandon you? Did they make
their Court to King <HI>James</HI> at your Ex∣pence,
<PB N="38" REF="37"/>
as it is evident they might have
done, and were courted by the King to
do? In short, did they serve you then,
as they are served by you? No; they
resisted all the Caresses of Popery and
and Passive-Obedience, Tories, and
chose Affliction and Hazard with that
very Church of <HI>England,</HI> that now are for
denying them the least publick Advan∣tage,
from that Government they have
spent their Blood and their Money to
support?</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>Are these the Men you will now Sacrifice
to the private Views you have of a Party-Strength?
Are these the Returns to the
Dissenters, for the putting themselves into
your Hands? Is this the Temper promised
them at the Revolution? Is this the Justice
to their adhering so vehemently to the per∣sonal
Interest, in the late Changes of those
that are now making a Market of them?
Honest <HI>Coleman!</HI> Thou hast lost the most
effectual and undisputed Axiom of Political
Philosophy that ever was deliver'd at the
Gallows; <HI REND="blackletterType">No Trust in Man!</HI> The Scri∣ptures
concur in it: <HI>Rich Men are Vanity,
and Great Men are a</HI> <HI REND="blackletterType">Lye. Put not your
Trust in Princes.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="39" REF="38"/>
Turn we our Eyes up to Heaven, from
whence cometh Help; and as <HI>Zachariah</HI> the
Son of <HI>Jehojadah</HI> said, when the Rabble
stoned him, after all the great Things his
Father had done for them; <HI>The Lord look
upon it, and require it.</HI></P>
<P>Nor can the Spirit of common Discern∣ning
forbear to say, without Respect or Claim
to Prophecies, This cannot end but in the
sinking of that very Party, who by this
Treatment of an innocent People, seek to
Establish their Interest even with the very
Men they always abhorr'd. They will sink
under the Weight of the Party they Caress,
and this <HI>Egyptian</HI> shall be to them as a Staff,
which whoever leaneth thereon, it shall pierce
thro' their Hand, and the Deliverance of the
Dissenters shall come some other way.</P>
<P>But we are told here several Things, to
buoy us up under the Weight of what we
see coming upon us; such as these.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. The Bill now depending in Parliament,
tho' it may restrain the Occasional Con∣formity
of Dissenters, as to Places, yet
it gives you more than the Equivalent
in many Things; it confirms the To∣leration,
it restores the Act of Exem∣ption
to the Name of the Toleration,
which it had lost; it checks the Jaco∣bites
in <HI>Scotland,</HI> and it is not extended
<PB N="40" REF="39"/>
in many Things, which were included
in the former Act.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. It was brought in from a Prospect of
meer Kindness to the Dissenters, to pre∣vent
the Design of another Party, who
had projected one tenfold worse, and
which had been perfectly ruinous to the
Dissenters Interest, and had in effect
turn'd the Toleration out of Doors.
And both these evidence that the Dis∣senters
are not given up, or betray'd, or
sacrific'd, as above.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>We answer briefly to this, that, <HI>as before,</HI>
We are not debating what Favour the Two
Houses of Parliament may grant in the Bill
now depending. It is not for us to say here
we are speaking <HI>of</HI> or <HI>to</HI> that Bill, or to the
Houses of Parliament; but we are speaking
to those People, whom we call <HI>Whigs without
Doors,</HI> who are concern'd in, or agree to
bringing any Bill in, or putting forward any
Law, to restrain the Consciences of Innocent
Men, and take from them at the severe Pe∣nalty
of the loss of their Employments, the
Liberty of serving God, according to their
Consciences: If the Parliament have sweet∣ned
this bitter Potion with any Negatives;
with any Favours, We are for being thankful
for all Favours, but We are not to think our
selves oblig'd at all to any of those People,
<PB N="41" REF="40"/>
<HI>if any such are,</HI> who having it in their Power
to prevent it, have put us into the Condition
to seek or be glad of such Favours.</P>
<P>And let those Favours be what they will,
if the Clause excluding all those from the
Natural Privilege of <HI>Loyal Subjects,</HI> and from
the Favours of their Sovereign, who cannot,
<HI>how Consciencious soever their Scruples are,</HI> Con∣form
to the <HI>Church:</HI> We may without Offence
say, we should not be at all the less thank∣ful
to be without the said Favours, having
but at the same time the Liberty to be
without the Grievance.</P>
<P>As to what is called <HI>Confirming our To∣leration,</HI>
if we think it sufficiently Confirm'd
before, and in a most Sacred Manner Esta∣blish'd,
besides the Act of Parliament, in
the Sanction of Her Majesty's Solemn Pro∣mise
from the Throne, of preserving it
<HI REND="blackletterType">Inviolable:</HI> We hope it will not be ill
taken, if we say, We do not see how it can
be better Confirm'd, tho' every Session of
Parliament should pass a New Act in its
Favour: Nor is our Confidence less in Her
Majesty's Sacred Promise, than in all the
Acts to Confirm our <HI REND="blackletterType">Toleration,</HI> that
are or can be pass'd, since one Parliament
may Repeal what ever Acts another has
made, <HI>and even their own too:</HI> But Her Ma∣jesty's
Veracity is a Royal Security which
we have so much Dependance upon, as
<PB N="42" REF="41"/>
we cannot prevail upon our selves to say,
We desire any further Confirmation of it.</P>
<P>That the Parliament in their printed
Votes have thrown Dirt in the Face of
that condemn'd Impostor <HI>S . . . . . l,</HI> and
restor'd the Act for the Liberty of <HI>Dissen∣ters,</HI>
to the true Title and Denomination
of it, <HI>viz.</HI> a <HI REND="blackletterType">Toleration, vide</HI> the <HI>Votes,
Die Lunae Decemb.</HI> 18. 1711. It is a satisfy∣ing
Piece of Justice done that Honourable
House, and what we are bound to acknow∣ledge,
is like the Righteous Proceedings of
so August an Assembly, and we should
have been larger in owning the Favour,
did it not come accompany'd with some∣thing
in the Cover of it, which we can by
no means, without the utmost Hypocrisy
be thankful for, <HI>viz. An Act to restrain
the Consciences of Men, in the Affair of pos∣sessing
Offices, without renouncing the worship∣ping
God in their own way, and according to the
Dictates of their Consciences.</HI> For this we
can no more be thankful, than to a Judge
who pronounces Sentence of Death against
us for Crimes we think our selves not guilty
of.</P>
<P>That we had as <HI>Dissenters</HI> a Legal <HI>Tole∣ration</HI>
before, by Act of Parliament, is cer∣tain,
That the Act Intitled, <HI>An Act to Ex∣empt
Her Majesty's Protestant Subjects,</HI> &amp;c.
is a <HI>Toleration,</HI> is out of all question true,
<PB N="43" REF="42"/>
and to prove it, The Title to this Act now
passing is my Authority, being the Words
of the Parliament, Lords and Commons,
in whose Name, and by whose very Mouths
<HI>S . . . . . . l</HI> is thus pronounc'd an Impostor
and a Deceiver.</P>
<P>We might Address our selves now to
speak to the Act it self, and examine Two
Things in it, and which shall be done with
Brevity and Modesty.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. Will this Act answer the End which
is pretended in the Title, <HI>viz. To secure
the Church of England?</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Will it answer the particular View of
those who acquiesce in it, in hopes of
obtaining by it their Party-Ends, a∣gainst
the Measures taken for a Peace?</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Will this Act answer the Two other
Ends, confirm the <HI>Toleration,</HI> and pre∣serve
the <HI>Succession?</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P N="1">1. Will it answer the End which is pre∣tended
in the Title, <HI>viz.</HI> To <HI>secure the Church
of England;</HI> To this I give the Opinion of
all those Gentlemen, whose Speeches are up∣on
Record, against the first and second
<HI REND="blackletterType">Occasional-Bill,</HI> where it seems manifest,
at least, That it was all their Opinion, that
this Law would bring no real Addition to
the <HI>Church,</HI> only serve to keep the Body of
<PB N="44" REF="43"/>
<HI>Dissenters</HI> more united: And if we might
add in this Case, that <HI>Ʋnion</HI> may in time
be found the only Case, in which the <HI>Dissen∣ters</HI>
can be formidable to the <HI>Church:</HI> The
divided Condition of the <HI>Dissenters,</HI> their
vain Trusts in the <HI>Great Men</HI> who they
thought were their <HI>Protectors,</HI> their frequent
Access to Favours and Fortunes; these have
all along been the Foundation of their Dis∣asters;
their Dependance upon <HI>Great Men</HI>
elevated them, made them secure, divided
them, made them despise Caution and Ene∣mies,
and made them self-interested, narrow,
and reserv'd; <HI>in short,</HI> it bury'd what they
call a Publick Spirit among them; this les∣sen'd
them in their Real Strength to that
Degree, that instead of making them For∣midable,
it made them Despicable; so that
indeed the Liberty and Occasional Confor∣mity
of Dissenters, has been their Ruin, has
been the Weakning their Strength, Lessen∣ing
their Numbers, and Destroying their
Interest; and in all these have been, <HI>if the
Prosperity of the Dissenters is the Churches
Danger,</HI> a Safety to the Church. Now
will this Restraint answer the Churches
End, as it is propos'd? It is impossible;
neither is it Calculated for that End, since
as is before Noted, the Design is not to
bring the Dissenters over to the Church,
but to keep them out of Places: But if
<PB N="45" REF="44"/>
alarm'd by this Treatment, the Dissenters
should more firmly Unite, act in Concert,
recover the Reputation of their Integrity
and Sincerity, as if they are wise they may,
they will add weight to their Interest, and
the End of their mighty Struggle will be
quite Defeated.</P>
<P N="2">2. Will it answer the End of those, who
by it push at breaking the Measures of the
Court, as to Peace or War?</P>
<P><HI>Not in the least.</HI> The Interest they had
this way is entirely divided by it; Mutual
Confidence is Destroy'd, <HI>Irretrievably De∣stroy'd,</HI>
and can never be Restor'd. When
Men Trust and Confide in one another, and
then Decieve one another, they <HI>seldom,</HI> but
in Parties and Sets of Men <HI>Never</HI> Trust a∣gain;
they may join Out-sides, tho' that
will be Difficult, but In-sides Never: Now
if the Concert is broken, which <HI>when whole</HI>
could not withstand the Measures above,
how should they do it when Divided?
No Strength encreases by being separated;
<HI>Vis Unita Fortior,</HI> is an Old and True Max∣im,
to say <HI>Vis separata Fortior,</HI> would be a
gross Absurdity; Can any one be so weak
to think that the Interest of the Whigs and
Dissenters, which is miserably Torn and
Dismembred by this Mystery of Politicks,
can be able to do that now which they could
not do before? Where are the Legions
<PB N="46" REF="45"/>
added to their Strength by this New Step?
Where is the Equivalent they Recieve?
<HI>Ridiculus Mus!</HI> A poor empty unaccom∣pany'd
<HI>Hero,</HI> Whose Interest has not been
able to Draw his own Brethren, the Sons of
his Mother, into his Measures. Nay, whose
Measures Unconcerted and Undetermin'd,
have hardly amounted to a Clear Proposal—Where
are the Preliminaries of this mighty
Treaty? Truly the Whigs have done as
the King of <HI>France</HI> was to do, first evacuate
the Towns, and then let the Confederates
make their Demands, so they have first eva∣cuated
their Friends, surrendred the Faith
they had Pledg'd to the Dissenters, and now
the Tories may make their Demands, and if
it be to give up the Toleration next, we do
not see how these can deny them; so that
in short, the End is as Uncertain as it was
before.</P>
<P N="3">3. <HI>Will this Act Confirm the Toleration?</HI>
Because the House says <HI>it shall,</HI> we will not
say <HI>it shall not;</HI> but God forbid we should
say <HI>it will,</HI> while we see not the least room
for any thing of that Kind: This Act and
a Hundred more of this Nature, being all
attended with this Circumstance, That they
may be Repeal'd by the Breath of the House,
who gives them Life. <HI>As to the Succession
being Secured,</HI> by excluding a few <HI>Jacobites</HI>
out of the <HI>Faculty</HI> at <HI>Edinburgh,</HI> where they
<PB N="47" REF="46"/>
are capable of doing little Mischief, unless
they were likewise excluded out of Com∣missions
of the Peace in <HI>Scotland,</HI> where
their Power is capable of doing things Fatal
to the Succession, as may be proved by innu∣merable
Instances, We cannot have so much
value for that Clause as others have. As to
<HI>Confirming the Toleration,</HI> We will not say
that this Act is a direct Breach of the <HI>Tole∣ration,</HI>
and a most Open Invasion of the Li∣berties
Granted to the Dissenters by the To∣leration;
But we must profess our selves
utterly Ignorant of any Discovery to our pre∣sent
Understanding, as to any Clause, Mat∣ter,
or Thing in it, whereby the said To∣leration
is at all Confirm'd as abovesaid;
which Ignorance, we hope, may be Humbly
acknowledg'd, without Offence.</P>
<P>We conclude this with One Only View,
being the last Resort the Dissenters have, and
the Alone Help, which Humane Power can
offer to interpose in this Affair, and <HI>This is
in Her Majesties Royal Goodness and Com∣passion.</HI></P>
<P>And
the Authors of this small Tract, beg
leave, in the Humblest manner, with all
possible Respect, with the utmost sence of
Duty, in the Name of Her Majesties Loyal,
but Distressed, Protestant Subjects, the Dis∣senters;
to whom Her Majesty has so often
promis'd Her Protection; and in whose Zeal
<PB N="48" REF="47"/>
for Her Service, Her Majesty has been Gra∣ciously
pleas'd to express great Satisfaction;
To represent,</P>
<P>That Her Majesty has given Her Royal
and Sacred Promise to Them on several
Occasions, to Preserve their Toleration
<HI REND="blackletterType">Inviolable.</HI></P>
<P>Submitting the rest to Her Majesty's
Consideration.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

