<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-07-06</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Simon Charles</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Corrected 2 illegibles of 2. Converted 0 illegibles to GAP DESC="illegible".</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K077850.000">
<STC T="C">T096670</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3304916822</BIBNO>
<VID SET="ECSS">0292801100</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
ADDITIONS AND CORRECTIONS TO THE FIRST AND SECOND EDITIONS OF Dr. ADAM SMITH'S INQUIRY into the NATURE and CAUSES of the WEALTH of NATIONS.</HEAD>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<HEAD>VOL. I. page 36, line 17, after the words, <HI>purchase or command,</HI> add,</HEAD>
<P>WEALTH, as Mr. Hobbes says, is power. But the person who either acquires, or succeeds to a great fortune, does not necessa∣rily acquire or succeed to any political power, either civil or military. His fortune may, perhaps, afford him the means of acquiring both; but the mere possession of that fortune does necessarily convey to him either. The power which that possession immediately and directly conveys to him, is the power of purchasing; a certain com∣mand over all the labour, or over all the produce of labour, which is then in the market. His fortune is greater or less, precisely in pro∣portion to the extent of this power; or to the quantity either of other men's labour, or, what is the same thing, of the produce of other men's labour, which it enables him to purchase or command. The exchangeable value of every thing must always be precisely equal to the extent of this power which it conveys to its owner.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<PB N="2" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>VOL. I. page 270, line 8, after the words <HI>European market,</HI> add,</HEAD>
<P>IT must be observed, however, that whatever may be the sup∣posed annual importation of gold and silver, there must be a certain period, at which the annual consumption of those metals will be equal to that annual importation. Their consumption must in∣crease as their mass increases, or rather in a much greater propor∣tion. As their mass increases, their value diminishes. They are more used, and less cared for, and their consumption consequently increases in a greater proportion than their mass. After a certain period, therefore, the annual consumption of those metals must, in this manner, become equal to their annual importation, provided that importation is not continually increasing; which, in the present times, is not supposed to be the case.</P>
<P>IF, when the annual consumption has become equal to the annual importation, the annual importation should gradually diminish, the annual consumption may, for some time, exceed the annual im∣portation. The mass of those metals may gradually and insensibly diminish, and their value gradually and insensibly rise, till the annual importation becoming again stationary, the annual consumption will gradually and insensibly accommodate itself to what that annual importation can maintain.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<HEAD>VOL. II. page 31, line 21, after the words <HI>monopoly against their countrymen,</HI> add,</HEAD>
<P>THE variety of goods of which the importation into Great Bri∣tain is prohibited, either absolutely, or under certain circum∣stances, greatly exceeds what can easily be suspected by those who are not well acquainted with the laws of the customs.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>VOL. II. page 57, line 12, <HI>dele,</HI> from the words, <HI>Thus in Great Britain,</HI> &amp;c. to the words <HI>national prejudice and animosity,</HI> line 18. and insert as follows:</HEAD>
<P>THUS, in Great Britain, Silesia lawns may be imported for home consumption upon paying certain duties. But French cambricks and lawns are prohibited to be imported, except into the port of London, there to be warehoused for exportation. Higher duties are imposed upon the wines of France than upon those of Portugal, or indeed of any other country. By what is called the impost 1692, a duty of five and twenty per cent., of the rate or value, was laid upon all French goods; while the goods of other nations were, the greater part of them, subjected to much lighter duties, seldom ex∣ceeding five per cent. The wine, brandy, salt and vinegar of France were indeed excepted; these commodities being subjected to other heavy duties, either by other laws, or by particular clauses of the same law. In 1696, a second duty of twenty-five per cent., the first not having been thought a sufficient discouragement, was imposed upon all French goods, except brandy; together with a new duty of five and twenty pounds upon the ton of French wine, and another of fifteen pounds upon the ton of French vinegar. French goods have never been omitted in any of those general subsidies, or duties of five per cent., which have been imposed upon all, or the greater part of the goods enumerated in the book of rates. If we count the one third and two third subsidies as making a complete subsidy between them, there have been five of these general subsidies; so that before the commencement of the present war seventy-five per cent. may be con∣sidered as the lowest duty, to which the greater part of the goods of the growth, produce, or manufacture of France were liable. But upon the greater part of goods, those duties are equivalent to a pro∣hibition. The French in their turn have, I believe, treated our goods and manufactures just as hardly; though I am not so well acquainted with the particular hardships which they have imposed
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
upon them. Those mutual restraints have put an end to almost all fair commerce between the two nations, and smugglers are now the principal importers, either of British goods into France, or of French goods into Great Britain. The principles which I have been ex∣amining in the foregoing chapter took their origin from private in∣terest and the spirit of monopoly; those which I am going to exa∣mine in this, from national prejudice and animosity.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<HEAD>VOL. II. page 86. line 4. after the words <HI>insignificant and con∣temptible,</HI> add,</HEAD>
<P>IT is in consequence of these maxims that the commerce between France and England has in both countries been subjected to so many discouragements and restraints. If those two countries, however, were to consider their real interest, without either mercantile jea∣lousy or national animosity, the commerce of France might be more advantageous to Great Britain than that of any other country, and for the same reason that of Great Britain to France. France is the nearest neighbour to Great Britain. In the trade between the south∣ern coast of England and the northern and north-western coasts of France, the returns might be expected, in the same manner as in the inland trade, four, five, or six times in the year. The capital, therefore, employed in this trade, could in each of the two coun∣tries keep in motion four, five, or six times the quantity of industry, and afford employment and subsistence to four, five, or six times the number of people, which an equal capital could do in the greater part of the other branches of foreign trade. Between the parts of France and Great Britain most remote from one another, the returns might be expected, at least, once in the year, and even this trade would so far be at least equally advantageous as the greater part of the other branches of our foreign European trade. It would be, at least, three times more advantageous, than the boasted trade with our
<PB N="5" REF="5"/>
North American colonies, in which the returns were seldom made in less than three years, frequently not in less than four or five years. France, besides, is supposed to contain twenty-four millions of in∣habitants. Our North American colonies were never supposed to contain more than three millions: And France is a much richer country than North America; though, on account of the more un∣equal distribution of riches, there is much more poverty and beg∣gary in the one country, than in the other. France, therefore, could afford a market at least eight times more extensive, and, on ac∣count of the superior frequency of the returns, four and twenty times more advantageous, than that which our North American co∣lonies ever afforded. The trade of Great Britain would be just as advantageous to France, and, in proportion to the wealth, popula∣tion and proximity of the respective countries, would have the same superiority over that which France carries on with her own colonies. Such is the very great difference between that trade which the wis∣dom of both nations has thought proper to discourage, and that which it has favoured the most.</P>
<P>BUT the very same circumstances which would have rendered an open and free commerce between the two countries so advantageous to both, have occasioned the principal obstructions to that commerce. Being neighbours, they are necessarily enemies, and the wealth and power of each becomes, upon that account, more formidable to the other; and what would increase the advantage of national friend∣ship, serves only to inflame the violence of national animosity. They are both rich and industrious nations; and the merchants and manu∣facturers of each, dread the competition of the skill and activity of those of the other. Mercantile jealousy is excited, and both inflames, and is itself inflamed, by the violence of national animosity: And the traders of both countries have announced, with all the passionate confidence of interested falsehood, the certain ruin of each, in con∣sequence of that unfavourable balance of trade, which, they pre∣tend,
<PB N="6" REF="6"/>
would be the infallible effect of an unrestrained commerce with the other.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<HEAD>VOL. II. page 89. line 7. <HI>dele</HI> the sentence beginning <HI>Half the duties,</HI> &amp;c. and ending <HI>subsidies and imposts;</HI> and insert as follows:</HEAD>
<P>BY the second of the rules, annexed to the act of parliament, which imposed what is now called, the old subsidy, every merchant, whether English or alien, was allowed to draw back half that duty upon exportation; the English merchant, provided the exportation took place within twelve months; the alien, provided it took place with∣in nine months. Wines, currants, and wrought silks were the only goods which did not fall within this rule, having other and more ad∣vantageous allowances. The duties imposed by this act of parlia∣ment were, at that time, the only duties upon the importation of foreign goods. The term within which this, and all other draw∣backs, could be claimed, was afterwards (by 7 Geo. I. chap. 21. sect. 10.) extended to three years.</P>
<P>THE duties which have been imposed since the old subsidy, are, the greater part of them, wholly drawn back upon exportation. This general rule, however, is liable to a great number of excep∣tions, and the doctrine of drawbacks has become a much less simple matter, than it was at their first institution.</P>
<P>UPON the exportation of some foreign goods, of which it was ex∣pected that the importation would greatly exceed what was neces∣sary for the home consumption, the whole duties are drawn back, without retaining even half the old subsidy. Before the revolt of our North American colonies, we had the monopoly of the tobacco of Maryland and Virginia. We imported about ninety-six thousand hogsheads, and the home consumption was not supposed to exceed fourteen thousand. To facilitate the great exportation which was
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
necessary, in order to rid us of the rest, the whole duties were drawn back, provided the exportation took place within three years.</P>
<P>WE still have, though not altogether, yet very nearly, the mono∣poly of the sugars of our West Indian Islands. If sugars are ex∣ported within a year, therefore, all the duties upon importation are drawn back, and if exported within three years, all the duties, except half the old subsidy, which still continues to be retained upon the exportation of the greater part of goods. Though the importation of sugar exceeds, a good deal, what is necessary for the home con∣sumption, the excess is inconsiderable, in comparison of what it used to be in tobacco.</P>
<P>SOME goods, the particular objects of the jealousy of our own manufacturers, are prohibited to be imported for home consump∣tion. They may, however, upon paying certain duties, be import∣ed and warehoused for exportation. But upon such exportation, no part of these duties are drawn back. Our manufacturers are unwilling, it seems, that even this restricted importation should be encouraged, and are afraid lest some part of these goods should be stolen out of the warehouse, and thus come into competition with their own. It is under these regulations only that we can import wrought silks, French cambricks and lawns, callicoes painted, printed, stained, or dyed, &amp;c.</P>
<P>WE are unwilling even to be the carriers of French goods, and choose rather to forego a profit to ourselves, than to suffer those, whom we consider as our enemies, to make any profit by our means. Not only half the old subsidy, but the second twenty-five per cent., is retained upon the exportation of all French goods.</P>
<P>BY the fourth of the rules annexed to the old subsidy, the draw∣back allowed upon the exportation of all wines amounted to a great deal more than half the duties which were, at that time, paid upon their importation; and it seems, at that time, to have been the ob∣ject of the legislature to give somewhat more than ordinary encou∣ragement
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
to the carrying trade in wine. Several of the other duties too, which were imposed, either at the same time, or subsequent to the old subsidy; what is called the additional duty, the new sub∣sidy, the one-third and two-thirds subsidies, the impost 1692, the coinage on wine, were allowed to be wholly drawn back upon ex∣portation. All those duties, however, except the additional duty and impost 1692, being paid down in ready money, upon import∣ation, the interest of so large a sum occasioned an expence, which made it unreasonable to expect any profitable carrying trade in this article. Only a part, therefore, of the duty called the impost on wine, and no part of the twenty-five pounds the ton upon French wines, or of the duties imposed in 1745, in 1763, and in 1778, were allowed to be drawn back upon exportation. The two im∣posts of five per cent., imposed in 1779 and 1781, upon all the former duties of customs, being allowed to be wholly drawn back upon the exportation of all other goods, were likewise allowed to be drawn back upon that of wine. The last duty that has been par∣ticularly imposed upon wine, that of 1780, is allowed to be wholly drawn back; an indulgence, which, when so many heavy duties are retained, most probably could never occasion the exportation of a single ton of wine. These rules take place with regard to all places of lawful exportation, except the British colonies in America.</P>
<P>THE 15th Charles II. chap. 7. called an act for the encourage∣ment of trade, had given Great Britain the monopoly of supplying the colonies with all the commodities of the growth or manufacture of Europe; and consequently with wines. In a country of so ex∣tensive a coast as our North American and West Indian colonies, where our authority was always so very slender, and where the in∣habitants were allowed to carry out, in their own ships, their non∣enumerated commodities, at first, to all parts of Europe, and after∣wards to all parts of Europe south of Cape Finisterre, it is not very probable that this monopoly could ever be much respected; and
<PB N="9" REF="9"/>
they probably, at all times, found means of bringing back some cargo from the countries to which they were allowed to carry out one. They seem, however, to have found some difficulty in im∣porting European wines from the places of their growth, and they could not well import them from Great Britain, where they were loaded with many heavy duties, of which a considerable part was not drawn back upon exportation. Madeira wine, not being a European commodity, could be imported directly into America and the West Indies, countries which, in all their non-enumerated com∣modities, enjoyed a free trade to the island of Madeira. These cir∣cumstances had probably introduced that general taste for Madeira wine, which our officers found established in all our colonies at the commencement of the war, which began in 1755, and which they brought back with them to the mother-country, where that wine had not been much in fashion before. Upon the conclusion of that war, in 1763 (by the 4th Geo. III. Chap. 15. Sect. 12), all the duties, except 3<HI>l.</HI> 10<HI>s.</HI> were allowed to be drawn back, upon the exportation to the colonies of all wines, except French wines, to the commerce and consumption of which, national prejudice would al∣low no sort of encouragement. The period between the granting of this indulgence and the revolt of our North American colonies was probably too short to admit of any considerable change in the customs of those countries.</P>
<P>THE same act, which, in the drawback upon all wines, except French wines, thus favoured the colonies so much more than other countries; in those, upon the greater part of other commodities, favoured them much less. Upon the exportation of the greater part of commodities to other countries, half the old subsidy was drawn back. But this law enacted, that no part of that duty should be drawn back upon the exportation to the colonies of any commodities, of the growth or manufacture either of Europe or the East Indies, except wines, white callicoes and muslins.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<PB N="10" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>VOL. II. p. 93. line <HI>ult.</HI> after the words <HI>in consequence of it,</HI> add,</HEAD>
<P>IT has happened in France, as well as in England, though in France there was, not only no bounty, but, till 1764, the export∣ation of corn was subjected to a general prohibition. This gradual fall in the average price of grain, it is probable, therefore, is ulti∣mately owing neither to the one regulation nor to the other, but to that gradual and insensible rise in the real value of silver, which, in the first book of this discourse, I have endeavoured to show has taken place in the general market of Europe, during the course of the present century. It seems to be altogether impossible that the bounty could ever contribute to lower the price of grain.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<HEAD>VOL. II. p. 94. line 14. <HI>dele</HI> what follows after the words <HI>any reasonable person,</HI> to the words <HI>affected by the bounty,</HI> line 27. and insert as follows:</HEAD>
<P>BUT it has been thought by many people that it tends to encou∣rage tillage, and that in two different ways; first, by opening a more extensive foreign market to the corn of the farmer, it tends, they imagine, to increase the demand for, and consequently the production of, that commodity; and, secondly, by securing to him a better price than he could otherwise expect in the actual state of til∣lage, it tends, they suppose, to encourage tillage. This double en∣couragement must, they imagine, in a long period of years, occa∣sion such an increase in the production of corn, as may lower its price in the home market, much more than the bounty can raise it, in the actual state which tillage may, at the end of that period, happen to be in.</P>
<P>I ANSWER, that whatever extension of the foreign market can be occasioned by the bounty, must, in every particular year, be al∣together at the expence of the home market; as every bushel of corn which is exported by means of the bounty, and which would
<PB N="11" REF="11"/>
not have been exported without the bounty, would have remained in the home market to increase the consumption, and to lower the price of that commodity. The corn bounty, it is to be observed, as well as every other bounty upon exportation, imposes two dif∣ferent taxes upon the people; first, the tax which they are obliged to contribute, in order to pay the bounty; and secondly, the tax which arises from the advanced price of the commodity in the home∣market, and which, as the whole body of the people are purchasers of corn, must, in this particular commodity, be paid by the whole body of the people. In this particular commodity, therefore, this second tax is by much the heaviest of the two. Let us suppose that, taking one year with another, the bounty of five shillings upon the exportation of the quarter of wheat, raises the price of that commodity in the home-market, only sixpence the bushel, or four shillings the quarter, higher than it otherwise would have been in the actual state of the crop. Even upon this very moderate suppo∣sition, the great body of the people, over and above contributing the tax which pays the bounty of five shillings upon every quarter of wheat exported, must pay another of four shillings upon every quarter which they themselves consume. But, according to the very well informed author of the tracts upon the corn trade, the average proportion of the corn exported to that consumed at home, is not more than that of one to thirty-one. For every five shillings, therefore, which they contribute to the payment of the first tax, they must contribute six pounds four shillings to the payment of the second. So very heavy a tax upon the first necessary of life, must either reduce the subsistence of the labouring poor, or it must occa∣sion some augmentation in their pecuniary wages, proportionable to that in the pecuniary price of their subsistence. So far as it operates in the one way, it must reduce the ability of the la∣bouring poor to educate and bring up their children, and must, so far, tend to restrain the population of the country. So far as it
<PB N="12" REF="12"/>
operates in the other, it must reduce the ability of the employers of the poor, to employ so great a number as they otherwise might do, and must, so far, tend to restrain the industry of the country. The extraordinary exportation of corn, therefore, occasioned by the bounty, not only, in every particular year, diminishes the home, just as much as it extends the foreign market and consumption, but, by restraining the population and industry of the country, its final tendency is to stunt and restrain the gradual extension of the home∣market; and thereby, in the long-run, rather to diminish, than to augment, the whole market and consumption of corn.</P>
<P>THIS enhancement of the money-price of corn, however, it has been thought, by rendering that commodity more profitable to the farmer, must necessarily encourage its production.</P>
<P>I ANSWER, that this might be the case if the effect of the bounty was to raise the real price of corn, or to enable the farmer, with an equal quantity of it, to maintain a greater number of labourers in the same manner, whether liberal, moderate, or scanty, that other labourers are commonly maintained in his neighbourhood. But neither the bounty, it is evident, nor any other human institution, can have any such effect. It is not the real, but the nominal price of corn, which can in any considerable degree be affected by the bounty. And though the tax which that institution imposes upon the whole body of the people, may be very burdensome to those who pay it, it is of very little advantage to those who receive it.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<HEAD>VOL. II. p. 96. line 4. after the words <HI>able to live better,</HI> add,</HEAD>
<P>IN the purchase of foreign commodities this enhancement in the price of corn may give them some little advantage. In that of home∣made commodities it can give them none at all. And almost the whole expence of the farmer, and the far greater part of even that of the landlord, is in home-made commodities.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<PB N="13" REF="13"/>
<HEAD>VOL. II. p. 103. line 13. <HI>dele,</HI> from the words <HI>orders of people,</HI> to the words <HI>The prejudices,</HI> &amp;c. line 24. and insert as follows:</HEAD>
<P>THEY loaded the publick revenue with a very considerable expence; they imposed a very heavy tax upon the whole body of the people; but they did not, in any sensible degree, increase the real value of their own commodity; and by lowering somewhat the real value of silver, they discouraged, in some degree, the general industry of the country, and, instead of advancing, retarded more or less the improvement of their own lands, which necessarily depends upon the general industry of the country.</P>
<P>To encourage the production of any commodity, a bounty upon production, one should imagine, would have a more direct opera∣tion, than one upon exportation. It would, besides, impose only one tax upon the people, that which they must contribute in order to pay the bounty. Instead of raising, it would tend to lower the price of the commodity in the home market; and thereby, instead of imposing a second tax upon the people, it might, at least, in part, repay them for what they had contributed to the first. Bounties upon production, however, have been very rarely granted.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<HEAD>VOL. II. p. 104. line 18. instead of the paragraph beginning with <HI>Something like a bounty upon production,</HI> &amp;c. insert what follows:</HEAD>
<P>SOMETHING like a bounty upon production, however, has been granted upon some particular occasions. The tonnage bounties given to the white-herring and whale-fisheries may, perhaps, be consider∣ed as somewhat of this nature. They tend directly, it may be sup∣posed, to render the goods cheaper in the home market than they otherwise would be. In other respects their effects, it must be ac∣knowledged, are the same as those of bounties upon exportation. By
<PB N="14" REF="14"/>
means of them a part of the capital of the country is employed in bringing goods to market, of which the price does not repay the cost, together with the ordinary profits of stock.</P>
<P>BUT though the tonnage bounties to those fisheries do not con∣tribute to the opulence of the nation, it may perhaps be thought, that they contribute to its defence, by augmenting the number of its sailors and shipping. This, it may be alleged, may sometimes be done by means of such bounties at a much smaller expence, than by keeping up a great standing navy, if I may use such an expression, in the same way as a standing army.</P>
<P>NOTWITHSTANDING these favourable allegations, however, the following considerations dispose me to believe, that in granting at least one of these bounties, the legislature has been very grossly im∣posed upon.</P>
<P>FIRST, the herring buss bounty seems too large.</P>
<P>FROM the commencement of the winter fishing 1771 to the end of the winter fishing 1781, the tonnage bounty upon the herring buss fishery has been at thirty shillings the ton. During these eleven years the whole number of barrels caught by the herring buss fishery of Scotland amounted to 378,347. The herrings caught and cured at sea, are called seasteeks. In order to render them what are called merchantable herrings, it is necessary to repack them with an additional quantity of salt; and in this case, it is reckoned, that three barrels of seasteeks, are usually repacked into two barrels of mer∣chantable herrings. The number of barrels of merchantable her∣rings, therefore, caught during these eleven years, will amount only, according to this account, to 252,231⅓. During these eleven years the tonnage bounties paid amounted to 155,463<HI>l.</HI> 11<HI>s.</HI> or to 8<HI>s.</HI> 2¼<HI>d.</HI> upon every barrel of seasteeks, and to 12<HI>s.</HI> 3¾<HI>d.</HI> upon every barrel of merchantable herrings.</P>
<P>THE salt with which these herrings are cured, is sometimes Scotch, and sometimes foreign salt; both which are delivered free
<PB N="15" REF="15"/>
of all excise duty to the fish-curers. The excise duty upon Scotch salt is at present 1<HI>s.</HI> 6<HI>d.</HI> that upon foreign salt 10<HI>s.</HI> the bushel. A barrel of herrings is supposed to require about one bushel and one-fourth of a bushel foreign salt. Two bushels are the supposed average of Scotch salt. If the herrings are entered for exportation, no part of this duty is paid up; if entered for home consumption, whether the herrings were cured with foreign or with Scotch salt, only one shilling the barrel is paid up. It was the old Scotch duty upon a bushel of salt, the quantity which, at a low estimation, had been supposed necessary for curing a barrel of herrings. In Scot∣land, foreign salt is very little used for any other purpose but the curing of fish. But from the 5th April 1771, to the 5th April 1782, the quantity of foreign salt imported amounted to 936,974 bushels, at eighty-four pounds the bushel: the quantity of Scotch salt, delivered from the works to the fish-curers, to no more than 168,226, at fifty-six pounds the bushel only. It would appear, therefore, that it is principally foreign salt that is used in the fisheries. Upon every barrel of herrings exported there is, besides, a bounty of 2<HI>s.</HI> 8<HI>d.</HI> and more than two-thirds of the buss caught herrings are exported. Put all these things together and you will find, that, during these eleven years, every barrel of buss caught herrings, cured with Scotch salt, when exported, has cost government 17<HI>s.</HI> 11¾<HI>d.</HI>; and when entered for home consumption 14<HI>s.</HI> 3¾<HI>d.:</HI> and that every barrel cured with foreign salt, when exported, has cost government 1<HI>l.</HI> 7<HI>s.</HI> 5¾<HI>d.</HI>; and when entered for home con∣sumption 1<HI>l.</HI> 3<HI>s.</HI> 9¾<HI>d.</HI> The price of a barrel of good merchant∣able herrings runs from seventeen and eighteen to four and five and twenty shillings; about a guinea at an average.</P>
<P>THE two following accounts are subjoined, in order to illustrate and confirm what is said above concerning the tonnage bounty to the white herring fishery. The Reader, I believe, may depend upon the accuracy of both accounts.</P>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="account">
<PB N="16" REF="16"/>
<HEAD>An Account of Busses fitted out in Scotland for Eleven Years, with the Number of empty Barrels carried out, and the Number of Barrels of Herrings caught; also the Bounty at a Medium on each Barrel of Seasteeks, and on each Barrel when fully packed.</HEAD>
<P><TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL>Years.</CELL>
<CELL>Number of Busses.</CELL>
<CELL>Empty Barrels carried out.</CELL>
<CELL>Barrels of Her∣rings caught.</CELL>
<CELL COLS="3">Bounty paid on the Busses.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL>£.</CELL>
<CELL><HI>s.</HI></CELL>
<CELL><HI>d.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>1771</CELL>
<CELL>29</CELL>
<CELL>5948</CELL>
<CELL>2832</CELL>
<CELL>2085</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>1772</CELL>
<CELL>168</CELL>
<CELL>41316</CELL>
<CELL>22237</CELL>
<CELL>11055</CELL>
<CELL>7</CELL>
<CELL>6</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>1773</CELL>
<CELL>190</CELL>
<CELL>42333</CELL>
<CELL>42055</CELL>
<CELL>12510</CELL>
<CELL>8</CELL>
<CELL>6</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>1774</CELL>
<CELL>248</CELL>
<CELL>59303</CELL>
<CELL>56365</CELL>
<CELL>16952</CELL>
<CELL>2</CELL>
<CELL>6</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>1775</CELL>
<CELL>275</CELL>
<CELL>69144</CELL>
<CELL>52879</CELL>
<CELL>19315</CELL>
<CELL>15</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>1776</CELL>
<CELL>294</CELL>
<CELL>76329</CELL>
<CELL>51863</CELL>
<CELL>21290</CELL>
<CELL>7</CELL>
<CELL>6</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>1777</CELL>
<CELL>240</CELL>
<CELL>62679</CELL>
<CELL>43313</CELL>
<CELL>17592</CELL>
<CELL>2</CELL>
<CELL>6</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>1778</CELL>
<CELL>220</CELL>
<CELL>56390</CELL>
<CELL>40958</CELL>
<CELL>16316</CELL>
<CELL>2</CELL>
<CELL>6</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>1779</CELL>
<CELL>206</CELL>
<CELL>55194</CELL>
<CELL>29367</CELL>
<CELL>15287</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>1780</CELL>
<CELL>181</CELL>
<CELL>48315</CELL>
<CELL>19885</CELL>
<CELL>13445</CELL>
<CELL>12</CELL>
<CELL>6</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>1781</CELL>
<CELL>135</CELL>
<CELL>33992</CELL>
<CELL>16593</CELL>
<CELL>9613</CELL>
<CELL>12</CELL>
<CELL>6</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Total,</CELL>
<CELL>2186</CELL>
<CELL>550943</CELL>
<CELL>378347</CELL>
<CELL>155463</CELL>
<CELL>11</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE>
<TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL>Seasteeks</CELL>
<CELL>378347</CELL>
<CELL>Bounty at a medium for each barrel of seasteeks</CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>8</CELL>
<CELL>2¼</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL>But a barrel of seasteeks being only reckoned two-thirds of a barrel fully packed, one-third is deducted, which brings the bounty to</CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>12</CELL>
<CELL>3¾</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>⅓ deducted</CELL>
<CELL>126115⅔</CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Barrels full packed,</CELL>
<CELL>252231⅓</CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL COLS="3">And if the herrings are exported, there is besides a premium of</CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>2</CELL>
<CELL>8</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>14</CELL>
<CELL>11¾</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE>
<PB N="17" REF="17"/>
<TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL>So that the bounty paid by government in money for each barrel, is</CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>14</CELL>
<CELL>11¾</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>But if to this, the duty of the salt usually taken credit for as expended in curing each barrel, which at a medium is of foreign, one bushel and one-fourth of a bushel, at 10<HI>s.</HI> a bushel, be added, viz.</CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>12</CELL>
<CELL>6</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>The bounty on each barrel would amount to</CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>1</CELL>
<CELL>7</CELL>
<CELL>5¾</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE>
If the herrings are cured with British salt, it would stand thus, viz.
<TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL>Bounty as before</CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>14</CELL>
<CELL>11¾</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>—but if to this bounty the duty on two bushels of Scots salt at 1<HI>s.</HI> 6<HI>d.</HI> per bushel, supposed to be the quantity at a medium used in curing each barrel is added, to wit,</CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>3</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>The bounty on each barrel will amount to</CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>17</CELL>
<CELL>11¾</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE>
And,
<TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL>When buss herrings are entered for home consumption in Scotland, and pay the shilling a barrel of duty, the bounty stands thus, to wit, as before</CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>12</CELL>
<CELL>3¾</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>From which the 1<HI>s.</HI> a barrel is to be deducted</CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>1</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>11</CELL>
<CELL>3¾</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>But to that there is to be added again, the duty of the foreign salt used in curing a barrel of herrings, viz.</CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>12</CELL>
<CELL>6</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>So that the premium allowed for each barrel of herrings entered for home consumption is</CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>1</CELL>
<CELL>3</CELL>
<CELL>9¾</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE>
<PB N="18" REF="18"/>
If the herrings are cured with British salt, it will stand as follows, viz.
<TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL>Bounty on each barrel brought in by the busses as above</CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>12</CELL>
<CELL>3¾</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>From which deduct the 1<HI>s.</HI> a barrel paid at the time they are entered for home consumption</CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>1</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>11</CELL>
<CELL>3¾</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>But if to the bounty the duty on two bushels of Scots salt at 1<HI>s.</HI> 6<HI>d.</HI> per bushel, supposed to be the quantity at a medium used in curing each barrel, is added, to wit,</CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>3</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>The premium for each barrel entered for home consumption will be</CELL>
<CELL>£</CELL>
<CELL>0</CELL>
<CELL>14</CELL>
<CELL>3¾</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
<P>THOUGH the loss of duties upon herrings exported cannot, perhaps, properly be considered as bounty; that upon herrings en∣tered for home consumption certainly may.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="account">
<HEAD>An Account of the Quantity of Foreign Salt imported into Scotland, and of Scots Salt delivered Duty free from the Works there for the Fishery, from the 5th of April 1771 to the 5th of April 1782, with a Medium of both for one Year.</HEAD>
<P><TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL ROWS="2">PERIOD.</CELL>
<CELL>Foreign Salt imported.</CELL>
<CELL>Scots Salt deli∣vered from the Works.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Bushels.</CELL>
<CELL>Bushels.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>From the 5th of April 1771, to the 5th of April 1782.</CELL>
<CELL>936974</CELL>
<CELL>168226</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Medium for one Year</CELL>
<CELL>85179 5/11</CELL>
<CELL>15293 3/11</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
<P>It is to be observed that the bushel of foreign salt weighs 84 lb. that of British salt 56 lb. only.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P><PB N="19" REF="19"/>
SECONDLY, the bounty to the white herring fishery is a tonnage bounty; and is proportioned to the burden of the ship, not to her diligence or success in the fishery; and it has, I am afraid, been too common for vessels to fit out for the sole purpose of catching, not the fish, but the bounty. In the year 1759, when the bounty was at fifty shillings the ton, the whole buss fishery of Scotland brought in only four barrels of seasteeks. In that year each barrel of sea∣steeks cost government in bounties alone 113<HI>l.</HI> 15<HI>s.</HI>; each barrel of merchantable herrings 159<HI>l.</HI> 7<HI>s.</HI> 6<HI>d.</HI></P>
<P>THIRDLY, the mode of fishing for which this tonnage bounty in the white herring fishery has been given (by busses or decked vessels from twenty to eighty tons burden) seems not so well adapted to the situation of Scotland as to that of Holland; from the practice of which country it appears to have been borrowed. Holland lies at a great distance from the seas to which herrings are known prin∣cipally to resort; and can, therefore, carry on that fishery only in decked vessels, which can carry water and provisions sufficient for a voyage to a distant sea. But the Hebrides or western islands, the islands of Shetland, and the northern and north-western coasts of Scotland, the countries in whose neighbourhood the herring fishery is principally carried on, are every where intersected by arms of the sea which run up a considerable way into the land, and which, in the language of the country, are called sea-lochs. It is to these sea-lochs that the herrings principally resort, during the seasons in which they visit those seas; for the visits of this, and, I am assured, of many other sorts of fish, are not quite regular and constant. A boat fishery, therefore, seems to be the mode of fishing best adapted to the peculiar situation of Scotland; the fishers carrying the her∣rings on shore, as fast as they are taken, to be either cured or con∣sumed fresh. But the great encouragement, which a bounty of thirty shillings the ton gives to the buss fishery, is necessarily a discourage∣ment to the boat fishery; which, having no such bounty, cannot
<PB N="20" REF="20"/>
bring its cured fish to market upon the same terms as the buss fishery. The boat-fishery, accordingly, which, before the establishment of the buss bounty, was very considerable, and is said to have employed a number of seamen, not inferior to what the buss fishery employs at present, is now gone almost entirely to decay. Of the former ex∣tent, however, of this now ruined and abandoned fishery, I must acknowledge, that I cannot pretend to speak with much precision. As no bounty was paid upon the outfit of the boat-fishery, no ac∣count was taken of it by the officers of the customs or salt duties.</P>
<P>FOURTHLY, in many parts of Scotland, during certain seasons of the year, herrings make no inconsiderable part of the food of the common people. A bounty, which tended to lower their price in the home market, might contribute a good deal to the relief of a great number of our fellow-subjects, whose circumstances are by no means affluent. But the herring buss bounty contributes to no such good purpose. It has ruined the boat fishery, which is, by far, the best adapted for the supply of the home market, and the additional bounty of 2<HI>s.</HI> 8<HI>d.</HI> the barrel upon exportation, carries the greater part, more than two-thirds, of the produce of the buss fishery abroad. Between thirty and forty years ago, before the establish∣ment of the buss bounty, sixteen shillings the barrel, I have been assured, was the common price of white herrings. Between ten and fifteen years ago, before the boat fishery was entirely ruined, the price is said to have run from seventeen to twenty shillings the barrel. For these last five years, it has, at an average, been at twenty-five shillings the barrel. This high price, however, may have been owing to the real scarcity of the herrings upon the coast of Scot∣land. I must observe too, that the cask or barrel, which is usually sold with the herrings, and of which the price is included in all the foregoing prices, has, since the commencement of the American war, risen to about double its former price, or from about three shil∣lings,
<PB N="21" REF="21"/>
to about six shillings. I must likewise observe, that the ac∣counts I have received of the prices of former times, have been by no means quite uniform and consistent; and an old man of great accuracy and experience has assured me, that more than fifty years ago, a guinea was the usual price of a barrel of good merchant∣able herrings; and this, I imagine, may still be looked upon as the average price. All accounts, however, I think, agree, that the price has not been lowered in the home market, in consequence of the buss bounty.</P>
<P>WHEN the undertakers of fisheries, after such liberal bounties have been bestowed upon them, continue to sell their commodity at the same, or even at a higher price than they were accustomed to do before, it might be expected that their profits should be very great; and it is not improbable that those of some individuals may have been so. In general, however, I have every reason to believe, they have been quite otherwise. The usual effect of such bounties is to encourage rash undertakers to adventure in a business, which they do not understand, and what they lose by their own negligence and ignorance, more than compensates all that they can gain by the ut∣most liberality of government. In 1750, by the same act, which first gave the bounty of thirty shillings the ton for the encourage∣ment of the white herring fishery (the 23 Geo. II. chap. 24.), a joint stock company was erected, with a capital of five hundred thousand pounds, to which the subscribers (over and above all other encouragements, the tonnage bounty just now mentioned, the ex∣portation bounty of two shillings and eight pence the barrel, the de∣livery of both British and foreign salt duty free) were, during the space of fourteen years, for every hundred pounds which they sub∣scribed and paid in to the stock of the society, entitled to three pounds a year, to be paid by the receiver-general of the customs in equal half-yearly payments. Besides this great company, the resi∣dence of whose governor and directors was to be in London, it was
<PB N="22" REF="22"/>
declared lawful to erect different fishing-chambers, in all the diffe∣rent out-ports of the kingdom, provided a sum not less than ten thousand pounds was subscribed into the capital of each, to be ma∣naged at its own risk, and for its own profit and loss. The same annuity, and the same encouragement of all kinds, were given to the trade of those inferior chambers, as to that of the great company. The subscription of the great company was soon filled up, and several different fishing-chambers were erected in the different out-ports of the kingdom. In spite of all these encouragements, almost all those different companies, both great and small, lost either the whole, or the greater part of their capitals; scarce a vestige now remains of any of them, and the white herring fishery is now entirely, or al∣most entirely, carried on by private adventurers.</P>
<P>IF any particular manufacture was necessary, indeed, for the de∣fence of the society, it might not always be prudent to depend upon our neighbours for the supply; and if such manufacture could not otherwise be supported at home, it might not be unreasonable that all the other branches of industry should be taxed in order to support it. The bounties upon the exportation of British-made sail-cloth, and British-made gun-powder, may, perhaps, both be vindicated upon this principle.</P>
<P>BUT though it can very seldom be reasonable to tax the industry of the great body of the people, in order to support that of some par∣ticular class of manufacturers; yet in the wantonness of great pro∣sperity, when the publick enjoys a greater revenue than it knows well what to do with, to give such bounties to favourite manufactures, may, perhaps, be as natural, as to incur any other idle expence. In publick, as well as in private expences, great wealth may, perhaps, frequently be admitted as an apology for great folly. But there must surely be something more than ordinary absurdity, in conti∣nuing such profusion in times of general difficulty and distress.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<PB N="23" REF="23"/>
<HEAD>VOL. II. p. 258. line <HI>ult.</HI> after the words <HI>under their govern∣ment,</HI> insert the following Chapter:</HEAD>
<P>CHAP. VIII.</P>
<P><HI>Conclusion of the Mercantile System.</HI></P>
<P>THOUGH the encouragement of exportation, and the dis∣couragement of importation, are the two great engines by which the mercantile system proposes to enrich every country, yet, with regard to some particular commodities, it seems to follow an opposite plan: to discourage exportation, and to encourage import∣ation. Its ultimate object, however, it pretends, is always the same, to enrich the country by an advantageous balance of trade. It discourages the exportation of the materials of manufacture, and of the instruments of trade, in order to give our own workmen an advantage, and to enable them to undersell those of other nations in all foreign markets: and by restraining, in this manner, the export∣ation of a few commodities, of no great price, it proposes to occa∣sion a much greater and more valuable exportation of others. It encourages the importation of the materials of manufacture, in order that our own people may be enabled to work them up more cheaply, and thereby prevent a greater and more valuable importation of the manufactured commodities. I do not observe, at least in our Statute Book, any encouragement given to the importation of the instru∣ments of trade. When manufactures have advanced to a certain pitch of greatness, the fabrication of the instruments of trade be∣comes itself the object of a great number of very important manu∣factures. To give any particular encouragement to the importation of such instruments, would interfere too much with the interest of those manufactures. Such importation, therefore, instead of being encouraged, has frequently been prohibited. Thus the importation
<PB N="24" REF="24"/>
of wool cards, except from Ireland, or when brought in as wreck or prize goods, was prohibited by the 3d of Edward IV.; which pro∣hibition was renewed by the 39th of Elizabeth, and has been conti∣nued and rendered perpetual by subsequent laws.</P>
<P>THE importation of the materials of manufacture has sometimes been encouraged by an exemption from the duties to which other goods are subject, and sometimes by bounties.</P>
<P>THE importation of sheep's wool from several different countries, of cotton wool from all countries, of undressed flax, of the greater part of dying drugs, of the greater part of undressed hides from Ireland or the British colonies, of seal skins from the British Green∣land fishery, of pig and bar iron from the British colonies, as well as of several other materials of manufacture, has been encouraged by an exemption from all duties, if properly entered at the custom∣house. The private interest of our merchants and manufacturers may, perhaps, have extorted from the legislature these exemptions, as well as the greater part of our other commercial regulations. They are, however, perfectly just and reasonable, and if, consistently with the necessities of the state, they could be extended to all the other materials of manufacture, the publick would certainly be a gainer.</P>
<P>THE avidity of our great manufacturers, however, has in some cases extended these exemptions a good deal beyond what can justly be considered as the rude materials of their work. By the 24 Geo. II. chap. 46. a small duty of only one penny the pound was imposed upon the importation of foreign brown linen yarn, instead of much higher duties to which it had been subjected before, viz. of sixpence the pound upon sail yarn, of one shilling the pound upon all French and Dutch yarn, and of two pounds thirteen shillings and four pence upon the hundred weight of all spruce or Muscovia yarn. But our manufacturers were not long satisfied with this reduction. By the 29th of the same king, chap. 15. the same law which gave a bounty upon the exportation of British and Irish linen of which the price
<PB N="25" REF="25"/>
did not exceed eighteen pence the yard, even this small duty upon the importation of brown linen yarn was taken away. In the dif∣ferent operations, however, which are necessary for the preparation of linen yarn, a good deal more industry is employed, than in the subsequent operation of preparing linen cloth from linen yarn. To say nothing of the industry of the flax-growers and flax-dressers, three or four spinners, at least, are necessary, in order to keep one weaver in constant employment; and more than four-fifths of the whole quantity of labour, necessary for the preparation of linen cloth, is employed in that of linen yarn; but our spinners are poor people, women commonly, scattered about in all different parts of the country, without support or protection. It is not by the sale of their work, but by that of the complete work of the weavers, that our great master manufacturers make their profits. As it is their in∣terest to sell the complete manufacture as dear, so is it to buy the materials as cheap, as possible. By extorting from the legislature, bounties upon the exportation of their own linen, high duties upon the importation of all foreign linen, and a total prohibition of the home consumption of some sorts of French linen, they endeavour to sell their own goods as dear as possible. By encouraging the im∣portation of foreign linen yarn, and thereby bringing it into com∣petition with that which is made by our own people, they endea∣vour to buy the work of the poor spinners as cheap as possible. They are as intent to keep down the wages of their own weavers, as the earnings of the poor spinners; and it is by no means for the benefit of the workman, that they endeavour either to raise the price of the compleat work, or to lower that of the rude materials. It is the in∣dustry which is carried on for the benefit of the rich and the power∣ful, that is principally encouraged by our mercantile system. That which is carried on for the benefit of the poor and the indigent, is, too often, either neglected, or oppressed.</P>
<P><PB N="26" REF="26"/>
BOTH the bounty upon the exportation of linen, and the exemp∣tion from duty upon the importation of foreign yarn, which were granted only for fifteen years, but continued by two different pro∣longations, expire with the end of the session of parliament which shall immediately follow the 24th of June 1786.</P>
<P>THE encouragement given to the importation of the materials of manufacture by bounties, has been principally confined to such as were imported from our American plantations.</P>
<P>THE first bounties of this kind were those granted, about the beginning of the present century, upon the importation of naval stores from America. Under this denomination were comprehended timber fit for masts, yards, and bowsprits; hemp; tar, pitch, and turpentine. The bounty, however, of one pound the ton upon masting-timber, and that of six pounds the ton upon hemp, were extended to such as should be imported into England from Scotland. Both these bounties continued, without any variation, at the same rate, till they were severally allowed to expire; that upon hemp on the 1st of January 1741, and that upon masting-timber at the end of the session of parliament immediately following the 24th June 1781.</P>
<P>THE bounties upon the importation of tar, pitch, and turpen∣tine underwent, during their continuance, several alterations. Ori∣ginally that upon tar was four pounds the ton; that upon pitch, the same; and that upon turpentine, three pounds the ton. The bounty of four pounds the ton upon tar was afterwards confined to such as had been prepared in a particular manner; that upon other good, clean, and merchantable tar was reduced to two pounds four shillings the ton. The bounty upon pitch was likewise reduced to one pound; and that upon turpentine to one pound ten shillings the ton.</P>
<P>THE second bounty upon the importation of any of the materials of manufacture, according to the order of time, was that granted by
<PB N="27" REF="27"/>
the 21 Geo. II. chap. 30. upon the importation of indigo from the British plantations. When the plantation indigo was worth three-fourths of the price of the best French indigo, it was by this act entitled to a bounty of sixpence the pound. This bounty, which, like most others, was granted only for a limited time, was con∣tinued by several prolongations, but was reduced to four pence the pound. It was allowed to expire with the end of the session of parliament which followed the 25th March 1781.</P>
<P>THE third bounty of this kind was that granted (much about the time that we were beginning sometimes to court and sometimes to quarrel with our American colonies) by the 4 Geo. III. chap. 26. upon the importation of hemp, or undressed flax from the British plantations. This bounty was granted for twenty-one years, from the 24th June 1764, to the 24th June 1785. For the first seven years it was to be at the rate of eight pounds the ton, for the second at six pounds, and for the third at four pounds. It was not extend∣ed to Scotland, of which the climate (although hemp is sometimes raised there in small quantities, and of an inferior quality) is not very fit for that produce. Such a bounty upon the importation of Scotch flax into England would have been too great a discourage∣ment to the native produce of the southern part of the united kingdom.</P>
<P>THE fourth bounty of this kind was that granted by the 5 Geo. III. chap. 45. upon the importation of wood from America. It was granted for nine years, from the 1st January 1766, to the 1st January 1775. During the first three years, it was to be for every hundred and twenty good deals, at the rate of one pound; and for every load containing fifty cubic feet of other squared timber, at the rate of twelve shillings. For the second three years, it was for deals to be at the rate of fifteen shillings, and for other squared timber, at the rate of eight shillings; and for the third three years, it was for deals,
<PB N="28" REF="28"/>
to be at the rate of ten shillings, and for other squared timber, at the rate of five shillings.</P>
<P>THE fifth bounty of this kind was that granted by the 9 Geo. III. chap. 38. upon the importation of raw silk from the British plant∣ations. It was granted for twenty-one years, from the 1st January 1770, to the 1st January 1791. For the first seven years it was to be at the rate of twenty-five pounds for every hundred pounds value; for the second, at twenty pounds; and for the third, at fifteen pounds. The management of the silk-worm, and the preparation of silk, requires so much hand labour; and labour is so very dear in America, that even this great bounty, I have been informed, was not likely to produce any considerable effect.</P>
<P>THE sixth bounty of this kind was that granted by 11 Geo. III. chap. 50. for the importation of pipe, hogshead, and barrel staves and heading from the British plantations. It was granted for nine years, from 1st January 1772, to the 1st January 1781. For the first three years, it was for a certain quantity of each, to be at the rate of six pounds; for the second three years, at four pounds; and for the third three years, at two pounds.</P>
<P>THE seventh, and last bounty of this kind was granted by the 19 Geo. III. chap. 37. upon the importation of hemp from Ireland. It was granted in the same manner as that for the importation of hemp and undressed flax from America, for twenty-one years, from the 24th June 1779, to the 24th June 1800. This term is divided, likewise, into three periods of seven years each; and in each of those periods, the rate of the Irish bounty is the same with that of the American. It does not, however, like the American bounty, extend to the importation of undressed flax. It would have been too great a discouragement to the cultivation of that plant in Great Britain. When this last bounty was granted, the British and Irish legislatures were not in much better humour with one another than
<PB N="29" REF="29"/>
the British and American had been before. But this boon to Ireland, it is to be hoped, has been granted under more fortunate auspices, than all those to America.</P>
<P>THE same commodities upon which we thus gave bounties, when imported from America, were subjected to considerable duties when imported from any other country. The interest of our American colonies was regarded as the same with that of the mother country. Their wealth was considered as our wealth. Whatever money was sent out to them, it was said, came all back to us by the balance of trade, and we could never become a farthing the poorer, by any expence which we could lay out upon them. They were our own in every respect, and it was an expence laid out upon the improve∣ment of our own property, and for the profitable employment of our own people. It is unnecessary, I apprehend, at present to say any thing further, in order to expose the folly of a system, which fatal experience has now sufficiently exposed. Had our American colonies really been a part of Great Britain, those bounties might have been considered as bounties upon production, and would still have been liable to all the objections to which such bounties are liable, but to no other.</P>
<P>THE exportation of the materials of manufacture is sometimes dis∣couraged by absolute prohibitions, and sometimes by high duties.</P>
<P>OUR woollen manufacturers have been more successful than any other class of workmen, in persuading the legislature, that the pro∣sperity of the nation depended upon the success and extension of their particular business. They have not only obtained a monopoly against the consumers by an absolute prohibition of importing woollen cloths from any foreign country; but they have likewise obtained another monopoly against the sheep farmers and growers of wool, by a similar prohibition of the exportation of live sheep and wool. The severity of many of the laws which have been enacted for the security of the revenue is very justly complained of, as imposing
<PB N="30" REF="30"/>
heavy penalties upon actions which, antecedent to the statutes that declared them to be crimes, had always been understood to be innocent. But the cruellest of our revenue laws, I will venture to affirm, are mild and gentle, in comparison of some of those which the clamour of our merchants and manufacturers has extorted from the legislature, for the support of their own absurd and oppressive monopolies. Like the laws of Draco, these laws may be said to be all written in blood.</P>
<P>BY the 8th of Elizabeth, chap. 3. the exporter of sheep, lambs or rams, was for the first offence to forfeit all his goods for ever, to suffer a year's imprisonment, and then to have his left hand cut off in a market town upon a market day, to be there nailed up; and for the second offence to be adjudged a felon, and to suffer death ac∣cordingly. To prevent the breed of our sheep from being propa∣gated in foreign countries, seems to have been the object of this law. By the 13th and 14th of Charles II. chap. 18. the exportation of wool was made felony, and the exporter subjected to the same pe∣nalties and forfeitures as a felon.</P>
<P>FOR the honour of the national humanity, it is to be hoped that neither of these statutes were ever executed. The first of them, however, so far as I know, has never been directly repealed, and Ser∣jeant Hawkins seems to consider it as still in force. It may, how∣ever, perhaps, be considered as virtually repealed by the 12th of Charles II. chap. 32. sect. 3. which, without expressly taking away the penalties imposed by former statutes, imposes a new penalty, viz. That of twenty shillings for every sheep exported, or attempted to be exported, together with the forfeiture of the sheep and of the owner's share of the ship. The second of them was expressly re∣pealed by the 7th and 8th of William III. chap. 28. sect. 4. By which it is declared that, <Q REND="inline">"Whereas the statute of the 13th and 14th of king Charles II. made against the exportation of wool, among other things in the said act mentioned, doth enact the same to be
<PB N="31" REF="31"/>
deemed felony; by the severity of which penalty the prosecution of offenders hath not been so effectually put in execution: Be it, therefore, enacted by the authority foresaid, that so much of the said act, which relates to the making the said offence felony, be repealed and made void."</Q></P>
<P>THE penalties, however, which are either imposed by this milder statute, or which, though imposed by former statutes, are not re∣pealed by this one, are still sufficiently severe. Besides the for∣feiture of the goods, the exporter incurs the penalty of three shil∣lings for every pound weight of wool either exported or attempted to be exported, that is about four or five times the value. Any merchant or other person convicted of this offence is disabled from requiring any debt or account belonging to him from any factor or other person. Let his fortune be what it will, whether he is, or is not able to pay those heavy penalties, the law means to ruin him completely. But as the morals of the great body of the people are not yet so corrupt as those of the contrivers of this statute, I have not heard that any advantage has ever been taken of this clause. If the person convicted of this offence is not able to pay the penalties within three months after judgment, he is to be transported for seven years; and if he returns before the expiration of that term, he is liable to the pains of felony, without benefit of clergy. The owner of the ship knowing this offence forfeits all his interest in the ship and furniture. The master and mariners knowing this offence forfeit all their goods and chattels, and suffer three months imprisonment. By a subsequent statute the master suffers six months imprisonment.</P>
<P>IN order to prevent exportation, the whole inland commerce of wool is laid under very burdensome and oppressive restrictions. It cannot be packed in any box, barrel, cask, case, chest, or any other package, but only in packs of leather or pack-cloth, on which must be marked on the outside the words <HI>wool</HI> or <HI>yarn,</HI> in large letters not less than three inches long, on pain of forfeiting the same and the package, and
<PB N="32" REF="32"/>
three shillings for every pound weight, to be paid by the owner or packer. It cannot be loaden on any horse or cart, or carried by land within five miles of the coast, but between sun-rising and sun∣setting, on pain of forfeiting the same, the horses and carriages. The hundred next adjoining to the sea coast, out of, or through which the wool is carried or exported, forfeits twenty pounds, if the wool is under the value of ten pounds; and if of greater value, then treble that value, together with treble costs, to be sued for within the year. The execution to be against any two of the inhabitants, whom the sessions must reimburse, by an assessment on the other in∣habitants, as in the cases of robbery. And if any person compounds with the hundred for less than this penalty, he is to be imprisoned for five years; and any other person may prosecute. These regu∣lations take place through the whole kingdom.</P>
<P>BUT in the particular counties of Kent and Sussex the restrictions are still more troublesome. Every owner of wool within ten miles of the sea-coast must give an account in writing, three days after shearing, to the next officer of the customs, of the number of his fleeces, and of the places where they are lodged. And before he re∣moves any part of them he must give the like notice of the number and weight of the fleeces, and of the name and abode of the person to whom they are sold, and of the place to which it is intended they should be carried. No person within fifteen miles of the sea, in the said counties, can buy any wool, before he enters into bond to the king, that no part of the wool which he shall so buy, shall be sold by him to any other person within fifteen miles of the sea. If any wool is found carrying towards the sea-side in the said counties, unless it has been entered and security given as aforesaid, it is for∣feited, and the offender also forfeits three shillings for every pound weight. If any person lays any wool, not entered as aforesaid, within fifteen miles of the sea, it must be seized and forfeited; and if, after such seizure, any person shall claim the same, he must give
<PB N="33" REF="33"/>
security to the Exchequer, that if he is cast upon trial he shall pay treble costs, besides all other penalties.</P>
<P>WHEN such restrictions are imposed upon the inland trade, the coasting trade, we may believe, cannot be left very free. Every owner of wool who carrieth, or causeth to be carried, any wool to any port or place on the sea-coast, in order to be from thence transport∣ed by sea to any other place or port on the coast, must first cause an entry thereof to be made at the port from whence it is intended to be conveyed, containing the weight, marks, and number of the packages before he brings the same within five miles of that port; on pain of forfeiting the same, and also the horses, carts, and other carriages; and also of suffering and forfeiting, as by the other laws in force against the exportation of wool. This law, however, (1 Will. III. chap. 32.) is so very indulgent as to declare, that <Q REND="inline">"this shall not hinder any person from carrying his wool home from the place of shearing, though it be within five miles of the sea, provided that in ten days after shearing, and before he remove the wool, he do under his hand certify to the next officer of the cus∣toms, the true number of fleeces, and where it is housed; and do not remove the same, without certifying to such officer, under his hand, his intention so to do, three days before."</Q> Bond must be given that the wool to be carried coast-ways is to be landed at the particular port for which it is entered outwards; and if any part of it is landed without the presence of an officer, not only the for∣feiture of the wool is incurred as in other goods, but the usual addi∣tional penalty of three shillings for every pound weight is likewise incurred.</P>
<P>OUR woollen manufacturers, in order to justify their demand of such extraordinary restrictions and regulations, confidently asserted, that English wool was of a peculiar quality, superior to that of any other country; that the wool of other countries could not, without some mixture of it, be wrought up into any tolerable manufacture;
<PB N="34" REF="34"/>
that fine cloth could not be made without it; that England, there∣fore, if the exportation of it could be totally prevented, could mo∣nopolize to herself almost the whole woollen trade of the world; and thus, having no rivals, could sell at what price she pleased, and in a short time acquire the most incredible degree of wealth by the most advantageous balance of trade. This doctrine, like most other doctrines which are confidently asserted by any considerable number of people, was, and still continues to be, most implicitly believed by a much greater number; by almost all those who are either un∣acquainted with the woollen trade, or who have not made particular inquiries. It is, however, so perfectly false, that English wool is in any respect necessary for the making of fine cloth, that it is alto∣gether unfit for it. Fine cloth is made altogether of Spanish wool. English wool cannot be even so mixed with Spanish wool as to enter into the composition without spoiling and degrading, in some de∣gree, the fabric of the cloth.</P>
<P>IT has been shown in the foregoing part of this work, that the effect of these regulations has been to depress the price of English wool, not only below what it naturally would be in the present times, but very much below what it actually was in the time of Edward III. The price of Scots wool, when in consequence of the union it became subject to the same regulations, is said to have fallen about one half. It is observed by the very accurate and intelligent author of the Memoirs of Wool, the Reverend Mr. John Smith, that the price of the best English wool in England is generally below what wool of a very inferior quality commonly sells for in the market of Amsterdam. To depress the price of this commodity below what may be called its natural and proper price, was the avowed purpose of those regulations; and there seems to be no doubt of their having produced the effect that was expected from them.</P>
<P>THIS reduction of price, it may perhaps be thought, by dis∣couraging the growing of wool, must have reduced very much the
<PB N="35" REF="35"/>
annual produce of that commodity, though not below what it for∣merly was, yet below what, in the present state of things, it pro∣bably would have been, had it, in consequence of an open and free market, been allowed to rise to the natural and proper price. I am, however, disposed to believe, that the quantity of the annual pro∣duce cannot have been much, though it may perhaps have been a little, affected by these regulations. The growing of wool is not the chief purpose for which the sheep farmer employs his industry and stock. He expects his profit, not so much from the price of the the fleece, as from that of the carcase; and the average or ordinary price of the latter, must even, in many cases, make up to him whatever deficiency there may be in the average or ordinary price of the former. It has been observed in the foregoing part of this work, that, <Q REND="inline">"Whatever regulations tend to sink the price, either of wool or of raw hides, below what it naturally would be, must, in an improved and cultivated country, have some tendency to raise the price of butchers meat. The price both of the great and small cattle which are fed on improved and cultivated land, must be sufficient to pay the rent which the landlord, and the profit which the farmer has reason to expect from improved and cultivated land. If it is not, they will soon cease to feed them. Whatever part of this price, therefore, is not paid by the wool and the hide, must be paid by the carcase. The less there is paid for the one, the more must be paid for the other. In what manner this price is to be divided upon the different parts of the beast, is indifferent to the landlords and farmers, provided it is all paid to them. In an improved and cultivated country, therefore, their interest as landlords and farmers cannot be much affected by such regula∣tions, though their interest as consumers may, by the rise in the price of provisions."</Q> According to this reasoning, therefore, this degradation in the price of wool is not likely, in an improved and cultivated country, to occasion any diminution in the annual produce
<PB N="36" REF="36"/>
of that commodity; except so far as, by raising the price of mutton, it may somewhat diminish the demand for, and consequently the production of, that particular species of butchers meat. Its effect, however, even in this way, it is probable, is not very considerable.</P>
<P>BUT though its effect upon the quantity of the annual produce may not have been very considerable, its effect upon the quality, it may perhaps be thought, must necessarily have been very great. The degradation in the quality of English wool, if not below what it was in former times, yet below what it naturally would have been in the present state of improvement and cultivation, must have been, it may perhaps be supposed, very nearly in proportion to the degradation of price. As the quality depends upon the breed, upon the pasture, and upon the management and cleanliness of the sheep, during the whole progress of the growth of the fleece, the attention to these circumstances, it may naturally enough be imagined, can never be greater than in proportion to the recompence which the price of the fleece is likely to make for the labour and expence which that atten∣tion requires. It happens, however, that the goodness of the fleece depends, in a great measure, upon the health, growth, and bulk of the animal; the same attention which is necessary for the improve∣ment of the carcase, is, in some respects, sufficient for that of the fleece. Notwithstanding the degradation of price, English wool is said to have been improved considerably during the course even of the present century. The improvement might perhaps have been greater if the price had been better; but the lowness of price, though it may have obstructed, yet certainly it has not altogether prevented that improvement.</P>
<P>THE violence of these regulations, therefore, seems to have affected neither the quantity nor the quality of the annual produce of wool so much as it might have been expected to do; (though I think it pro∣bable that it may have affected the latter a good deal more than the former) and the interest of the growers of wool, though it must
<PB N="37" REF="37"/>
have been hurt in some degree, seems, upon the whole, to have been much less hurt than could well have been imagined.</P>
<P>THESE considerations, however, will not justify the absolute pro∣hibition of the exportation of the wool. But they will fully justify the imposition of a considerable tax upon that exportation.</P>
<P>TO hurt in any degree the interest of any one order of citizens, for no other purpose but to promote that of some other, is evidently contrary to that justice and equality of treatment which the sovereign owes to all the different orders of his subjects. But the prohibi∣tion certainly hurts, in some degree, the interest of the growers of wool, for no other purpose but to promote that of the manufac∣turers.</P>
<P>EVERY different order of citizens is bound to contribute to the support of the sovereign or commonwealth. A tax of five, or even of ten shillings upon the exportation of every tod of wool, would produce a very considerable revenue to the sovereign. It would hurt the interest of the growers somewhat less than the prohibition, be∣cause it would not probably lower the price of wool quite so much. It would afford a sufficient advantage to the manufacturer, because, though he might not buy his wool altogether so cheap as under the prohibition, he would still buy it, at least, five or ten shillings cheaper than any foreign manufacturer could buy it, besides saving the freight and insurance, which the other would be obliged to pay. It is scarce possible to devise a tax which could produce any considerable revenue to the sovereign, and at the same time occasion so little in∣conveniency to any body.</P>
<P>THE prohibition, notwithstanding all the penalties which guard it, does not prevent the exportation of wool. It is exported, it is well known, in great quantities. The great difference between the price in the home and that in the foreign market, presents such a temptation to smuggling, that all the rigour of the law cannot pre∣vent it. This illegal exportation is advantageous to no body but the
<PB N="38" REF="38"/>
smuggler. A legal exportation subject to a tax, by affording a re∣venue to the sovereign, and thereby saving the imposition of some other, perhaps more burdensome and inconvenient taxes, might prove advantageous to all the different subjects of the state.</P>
<P>THE exportation of fuller's earth, or fuller's clay, supposed to be necessary for preparing and cleansing the woollen manufactures, has been subjected to nearly the same penalties as the exportation of wool. Even tobacco-pipe clay, though acknowledged to be dif∣ferent from fuller's clay, yet, on account of their resemblance, and because fuller's clay might sometimes be exported as tobacco-pipe clay, has been laid under the same prohibitions and penalties.</P>
<P>BY the 13th and 14th of Charles II. chap. 7. the exportation, not only of raw hides, but of tanned leather, except in the shape of boots, shoes, or slippers, was prohibited; and the law gave a mo∣nopoly to our boot-makers and shoe-makers, not only against our graziers, but against our tanners. By subsequent statutes our tanners have got themselves exempted from this monopoly, upon paying a small tax of only one shilling on the hundred weight of tanned leather, weighing one hundred and twelve pounds. They have ob∣tained likewise the drawback of two thirds of the excise duties im∣posed upon their commodity, even when exported without further manufacture. All manufactures of leather may be exported duty free; and the exporter is besides entitled to the drawback of the whole duties of excise. Our graziers still continue subject to the old monopoly. Graziers separated from one another, and dispersed through all the different corners of the country, cannot, without great difficulty, combine together for the purpose either of im∣posing monopolies upon their fellow-citizens, or of exempting themselves from such, as may have been imposed upon them by other people. Manufacturers of all kinds, collected together in nu∣merous bodies in all great cities, easily can. Even the horns of cattle are prohibited to be exported; and the two insignificant trades
<PB N="39" REF="39"/>
of the horner and comb-maker enjoy, in this respect, a monopoly against the graziers.</P>
<P>RESTRAINTS, either by prohibitions or by taxes, upon the export∣ation of goods which are partially, but not completely manufactured, are not peculiar to the manufacture of leather. As long as any thing remains to be done, in order to fit any commodity for imme∣diate use and consumption, our manufacturers think that they them∣selves ought to have the doing of it. Woollen yarn and worsted are prohibited to be exported under the same penalties as wool. Even white cloths are subject to a duty upon exportation, and our dyers have so far obtained a monopoly against our clothiers. Our clothiers would probably have been able to defend themselves against it, but it happens that the greater part of our principal clothiers are themselves likewise dyers. Watch-cases, clock-cases, and dial-plates for clocks and watches, have been prohibited to be exported. Our clock-makers and watch-makers are, it seems, unwilling that the price of this sort of workmanship should be raised upon them by the com∣petition of foreigners.</P>
<P>BY some old statutes of Edward III., Henry VIII., and Edward VI., the exportation of all metals was prohibited. Lead and tin were alone excepted; probably on account of the great abundance of those metals; in the exportation of which, a considerable part of the trade of the kingdom in those days consisted. For the encou∣ragement of the mining trade, the 5th of William and Mary, chap. 17., exempted from this prohibition iron, copper, and mundic metal made from British ore. The exportation of all sorts of copper bars, foreign as well as British, was afterwards permitted by the 9th and 10th of William III., chap. 26. The exportation of un∣manufactured brass, of what is called gun-metal, bell-metal, and shroff-metal, still continues to be prohibited. Brass manufactures of all sorts may be exported duty free.</P>
<P><PB N="40" REF="40"/>
THE exportation of the materials of manufacture, where it is not altogether prohibited, is in many cases subjected to considerable duties.</P>
<P>BY the 8th George I., chap. 15., the exportation of all goods, the produce or manufacture of Great Britain, upon which any duties had been imposed by former statutes, was rendered duty free. The following goods, however, were excepted: Allum, lead, lead ore, tin, tanned leather, copperas, coals, wool cards, white woollen cloths, lapis calaminaris, skins of all sorts, glue, coney hair or wool, hares wool, hair of all sorts, horses, and litharge of lead. If you except horses, all these are either materials of manufacture, or incomplete manufactures (which may be considered as materials for still further manufacture), or instruments of trade. This statute leaves them subject to all the old duties which had ever been imposed upon them, the old subsidy and one per cent. outwards.</P>
<P>BY the same statute a great number of foreign drugs for dyers use, are exempted from all duties upon importation. Each of them, however, is afterwards subjected to a certain duty, not indeed a very heavy one, upon exportation. Our dyers, it seems, while they thought it for their interest to encourage the importation of those drugs, by an exemption from all duties, thought it likewise for their interest to throw some small discouragement upon their ex∣portation. The avidity, however, which suggested this notable piece of mercantile ingenuity, most probably disappointed itself of its object. It necessarily taught the importers to be more careful than they might otherwise have been, that their importation should not exceed what was necessary for the supply of the home market. The home market was at all times likely to be more scantily sup∣plied; the commodities were at all times likely to be somewhat dearer there than they would have been, had the exportation been rendered as free as the importation.</P>
<P><PB N="41" REF="41"/>
BY the above-mentioned statute, gum senega, or gum arabic, being among the enumerated dying drugs, might be imported duty free. They were subjected, indeed, to a small poundage duty, amounting only to three pence in the hundred weight upon their re-exportation. France enjoyed, at that time, an exclusive trade to the country most productive of those drugs, that which lies in the neighbourhood of the Senegal; and the British market could not easily be supplied by the immediate importation of them from the place of growth. By the 25th Geo. II. therefore, gum senega was allowed to be imported (contrary to the general dispositions of the act of navigation) from any part of Europe. As the law, however, did not mean to encourage this species of trade, so contrary to the ge∣neral principles of the mercantile policy of England, it imposed a duty of ten shillings the hundred weight upon such importation, and no part of this duty was to be afterwards drawn back upon its ex∣portation. The successful war which began in 1755 gave Great Britain the same exclusive trade to those countries which France had enjoyed before. Our manufacturers, as soon as the peace was made, endeavoured to avail themselves of this advantage, and to esta∣blish a monopoly in their own favour, both against the growers, and against the importers of this commodity. By the 5th Geo. III. therefore, chap. 37. the exportation of gum senega from his ma∣jesty's dominions in Africa was confined to Great Britain, and was subjected to all the same restrictions, regulations, forfeitures and pe∣nalties, as that of the enumerated commodities of the British colonies in America and the West Indies. Its importation, indeed, was sub∣jected to a small duty of sixpence the hundred weight, but its re∣exportation was subjected to the enormous duty of one pound ten shillings the hundred weight. It was the intention of our manu∣facturers that the whole produce of those countries should be im∣ported into Great Britain, and in order that they themselves might be enabled to buy it at their own price, that no part of it should be
<PB N="42" REF="42"/>
exported again, but at such an expence as would sufficiently dis∣courage that exportation. Their avidity, however, upon this, as well as upon many other occasions, disappointed itself of its object. This enormous duty presented such a temptation to smuggling, that great quantities of this commodity were clandestinely exported pro∣bably to all the manufacturing countries of Europe, but particularly to Holland, not only from Great Britain but from Africa. Upon this account, by the 14 Geo. III. chap. 10. this duty upon export∣ation was reduced to five shillings the hundred weight.</P>
<P>IN the book of rates, according to which the old subsidy was levied, beaver skins were estimated at six shillings and eight pence a piece, and the different subsidies and imposts, which before the year 1722 had been laid upon their importation, amounted to one-fifth part of the rate, or to sixteen pence upon each skin; all of which, except half the old subsidy, amounting only to two pence, was drawn back upon exportation. This duty upon the importation of so im∣portant a material of manufacture had been thought too high, and, in the year 1722, the rate was reduced to two shillings and sixpence, which reduced the duty upon importation to sixpence, and of this only one half was to be drawn back upon exportation. The same successful war put the country most productive of beaver under the dominion of Great Britain, and beaver skins being among the enu∣merated commodities, their exportation from America was conse∣quently confined to the market of Great Britain. Our manu∣facturers soon bethought themselves of the advantage which they might make of this circumstance, and in the year 1764, the duty upon the importation of beaver-skin was reduced to one penny, but the duty upon exportation was raised to seven pence each skin, without any drawback of the duty upon importation. By the same law, a duty of eighteen pence the pound was imposed upon the ex∣portation of beaver-wool or wombs, without making any alteration in the duty upon the importation of that commodity, which, when
<PB N="43" REF="43"/>
imported by British and in British shipping, amounted at that time to between four pence and five pence the piece.</P>
<P>COALS may be considered both as a material of manufacture and as an instrument of trade. Heavy duties, accordingly, have been imposed upon their exportation, amounting at present (1783) to more than five shillings the ton, or to more than fifteen shillings the chaldron, Newcastle measure; which is in most cases more than the original value of the commodity at the coal pit, or even at the ship∣ping port for exportation.</P>
<P>THE exportation, however, of the instruments of trade, properly so called, is commonly restrained, not by high duties, but by absolute prohibitions. Thus by the 7th and 8th of William III. chap. 20. sect. 8. the exportation of frames or engines for knitting gloves or stockings is prohibited under the penalty, not only of the forfeiture of such frames or engines, so exported, or attempted to be exported, but of forty pounds, one half to the king, the other to the person who shall inform or sue for the same. In the same manner, by the 14th Geo. III. chap. 71. the exportation to foreign parts, of any utensils made use of in the cotton, linen, woollen and slik manu∣factures, is prohibited under the penalty, not only of the forfeiture of such utensils, but of two hundred pounds, to be paid by the per∣son who shall offend in this manner, and likewise of two hundred pounds to be paid by the master of the ship who shall knowingly suffer such utensils to be loaded on board his ship.</P>
<P>WHEN such heavy penalties were imposed upon the exportation of the dead instruments of trade, it could not well be expected that the living instrument, the artificer, should be allowed to go free. Accord∣ingly, by the 5 Geo. I. chap. 27. the person who shall be convicted of enticing any artificer of, or in any of the manufactures of Great Britain, to go into any foreign parts in order to practise or teach his trade, is liable for the first offence to be sined in any sum not exceeding one hundred pounds, and to three months imprisonment, and until the
<PB N="44" REF="44"/>
fine shall be paid; and for the second offence, to be fined in any sum at the discretion of the court, and to imprisonment for twelve months, and until the fine shall be paid. By the 23 Geo. II. chap. 13. this penalty is increased for the first offence to five hundred pounds for every artificer so enticed, and to twelve months imprisonment, and until the fine shall be paid; and for the second offence, to one thousand pounds, and to two years imprisonment, and until the fine shall be paid.</P>
<P>BY the former of those two statutes, upon proof that any person has been enticing any artificer, or that any artificer has promised or contracted to go into foreign parts for the purposes aforesaid, such artificers may be obliged to give security, at the discretion of the court, that he shall not go beyond the seas, and may be committed to prison until he give such security.</P>
<P>IF any artificer has gone beyond the seas, and is exercising or teaching his trade in any foreign country, upon warning being given to him by any of his majesty's ministers or consuls abroad, or by one of his majesty's secretaries of state for the time being, if he does not, within six months after such warning, return into this realm, and from thenceforth abide and inhabit continually within the same, he is from thenceforth declared incapable of taking any legacy de∣vised to him within this kingdom, or of being executor or admi∣nistrator to any person, or of taking any lands within this kingdom by descent, devise, or purchase. He likewise forfeits to the king, all his lands, goods and chattels, is declared an alien in every respect, and is put out of the king's protection.</P>
<P>IT is unnecessary, I imagine, to observe, how contrary such re∣gulations are to the boasted liberty of the subject, of which we af∣fect to be so very jealous; but which, in this case, is so plainly sacri∣ficed to the futile interests of our merchants and manufacturers.</P>
<P>THE laudable motive of all these regulations, is to extend our own manufactures, not by their own improvement, but by the de∣pression
<PB N="45" REF="45"/>
of those of all our neighbours, and by putting an end, as much as possible, to the troublesome competition of such odious and disagreeable rivals. Our master manufacturers think it reasonable, that they themselves should have the monopoly of the ingenuity of all their countrymen. Though by restraining, in some trades, the number of apprentices which can be employed at one time, and by imposing the necessity of a long apprenticeship in all trades, they endeavour, all of them, to confine the knowledge of their respective employments to as small a number as possible; they are unwilling, however, that any part of this small number should go abroad to in∣struct foreigners.</P>
<P>CONSUMPTION is the sole end and purpose of all production; and the interest of the producer ought to be attended to, only so far as it may be necessary for promoting that of the consumer. The maxim is so perfectly self-evident, that it would be absurd to attempt to prove it. But in the mercantile system, the interest of the con∣sumer is almost constantly sacrificed to that of the producer; and it seems to consider production, and not consumption, as the ultimate end and object of all industry and commerce.</P>
<P>IN the restraints upon the importation of all foreign commodities which can come into competition with those of our own growth, or manufacture, the interest of the home-consumer is evidently sa∣crificed to that of the producer. It is altogether for the benefit of the latter, that the former is obliged to pay that enhancement of price which this monopoly almost always occasions.</P>
<P>IT is altogether for the benefit of the producer that bounties are granted upon the exportation of some of his productions. The home-consumer is obliged to pay, first, the tax which is necessary for paying the bounty, and secondly, the still greater tax which ne∣cessarily arises from the enhancement of the price of the commodity in the home market.</P>
<P><PB N="46" REF="46"/>
BY the famous treaty of commerce with Portugal, the consumer is prevented by high duties from purchasing of a neighbouring country, a commodity which our own climate does not produce, but is obliged to purchase it of a distant country, though it is ac∣knowledged that the commodity of the distant country is of a worse quality than that of the near one. The home-consumer is obliged to submit to this inconveniency, in order that the producer may import into the distant country some of his productions upon more advantageous terms than he would otherwise have been allowed to do. The consumer, too, is obliged to pay, whatever enhancement in the price of those very productions, this forced exportation may occasion in the home-market.</P>
<P>BUT in the system of laws which has been established for the management of our American and West Indian colonies, the interest of the home-consumer has been sacrificed to that of the producer with a more extravagant profusion than in all our other commercial regulations. A great empire has been established for the sole pur∣pose of raising up a nation of customers who should be obliged to buy from the shops of our different producers, all the goods with which these could supply them. For the sake of that little enhance∣ment of price which this monopoly might afford our producers, the home-consumers have been burdened with the whole expence of maintaining and defending that empire. For this purpose, and for this purpose only, in the two last wars, more than two hundred millions have been spent, and a new debt of more than a hundred and seventy millions has been contracted over and above all that had been expended for the same purpose in former wars. The interest of this debt alone is not only greater than the whole extraordinary profit, which, it ever could be pretended, was made by the monopoly of the colony trade, but than the whole value of that trade, or than the whole value of the goods, which at an average have been annually exported to the colonies.</P>
<P><PB N="47" REF="47"/>
IT cannot be very difficult to determine who have been the contrivers of this whole mercantile system; not the consumers, we may believe, whose interest has been entirely neglected; but the pro∣ducers, whose interest has been so carefully attended to; and among this latter class our merchants and manufacturers have been by far the principal architects. In the mercantile regulations, which have been taken notice of in this chapter, the interest of our manufac∣turers has been most peculiarly attended to; and the interest, not so much of the consumers, as that of some other sets of producers, has been sacrificed to it.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="addition">
<HEAD>VOL. II. page 342. line 25. after the words <HI>to fall under their displeasure,</HI> insert what follows:</HEAD>
<P><HI>Of the Publick Works and Institutions which are necessary for facilitat∣ing particular Branches of Commerce.</HI></P>
<P>THE object of the publick works and institutions above men∣tioned is to facilitate commerce in general. But in order to facilitate some particular branches of it, particular institutions are necessary, which again require a particular and extraordinary ex∣pence.</P>
<P>SOME particular branches of commerce, which are carried on with barbarous and uncivilized nations, require extraordinary protection. An ordinary store or counting-house could give little security to the goods of the merchants who trade to the western coast of Africa. To defend them from the barbarous natives, it is necessary that the place where they are deposited, should be, in some measure, forti∣fied. The disorders in the government of Indostan have been sup∣posed to render a like precaution necessary even among that mild and gentle people; and it was under pretence of securing their persons and property from violence, that both the English and
<PB N="48" REF="48"/>
French East India Companies were allowed to erect the first forts which they possessed in that country. Among other nations, whose vigorous government will suffer no strangers to possess any fortified place within their territory, it may be necessary to maintain some ambassador, minister, or consul, who may both decide, according to their own customs, the differences arising among his own coun∣trymen; and, in their disputes with the natives, may, by means of his publick character, interfere with more authority, and afford them a more powerful protection, than they could expect from any private man. The interests of commerce have frequently made it necessary to maintain ministers in foreign countries, where the purposes, either of war or alliance, would not have required any. The commerce of the Turkey company first occasioned the establishment of an ordinary ambassador at Constantinople. The first English embassies to Russia arose altogether from commercial interests. The constant interference which those interests necessarily occasioned between the subjects of the different states of Europe, has probably introduced the custom of keeping, in all neighbouring countries, ambassadors or ministers constantly resident even in the time of peace. This custom, unknown to ancient times, seems not to be older than the end of the fifteenth, or beginning of the sixteenth century; that is, than the time when commerce first began to extend itself to the greater part of the na∣tions of Europe, and when they first began to attend to its in∣terests.</P>
<P>IT seems not unreasonable, that the extraordinary expence, which the protection of any particular branch of commerce may occasion, should be defrayed by a moderate tax upon that particular branch; by a moderate fine, for example, to be paid by the traders when they first enter into it, or, what is more equal, by a particular duty of so much per cent. upon the goods which they either import into, or export out of, the particular countries with which it is carried on. The protection of trade in general, from pirates and freebooters, is
<PB N="49" REF="49"/>
said to have given occasion to the first institution of the duties of customs. But, if it was thought reasonable to lay a general tax upon trade, in order to defray the expence of protecting trade in general, it should seem equally reasonable to lay a particular tax upon a particular branch of trade, in order to defray the extraordinary expence of protecting that branch.</P>
<P>THE protection of trade in general has always been considered as essential to the defence of the commonwealth; and, upon that ac∣count, a necessary part of the duty of the executive power. The collection and application of the general duties of customs, therefore, have always been left to that power. But the protection of any particular branch of trade is a part of the general protection of trade; a part, therefore, of the duty of that power; and if nations always acted consistently, the particular duties levied for the purposes of such particular protection, should always have been left equally to its dis∣posal. But in this respect, as well as in many others, nations have not always acted consistently; and in the greater part of the com∣mercial states of Europe, particular companies of merchants have had the address to perswade the legislature to entrust to them the performance of this part of the duty of the sovereign, together with all the powers which are necessarily connected with it.</P>
<P>THESE companies, though they may, perhaps, have been useful for the first introduction of some branches of commerce, by making, at their own expence, an experiment which the state might not think it prudent to make, have in the long-run proved, universally, either burdensome or useless, and have either mismanaged or con∣fined the trade.</P>
<P>WHEN those companies do not trade upon a joint stock, but are obliged to admit any person, properly qualified, upon paying a cer∣tain fine, and agreeing to submit to the regulations of the company, each member trading upon his own stock, and at his own risk, they are called regulated companies. When they trade upon a joint stock,
<PB N="50" REF="50"/>
each member sharing in the common profit or loss in proportion to his share in this stock, they are called joint stock companies. Such companies, whether regulated or joint stock, sometimes have, and sometimes have not, exclusive privileges.</P>
<P>REGULATED companies resemble, in every respect, the corpora∣tions of trades, so common in the cities and towns of all the different countries of Europe; and are a sort of enlarged monopolies of the same kind. As no inhabitant of a town can exercise an incorporated trade, without first obtaining his freedom in the corporation, so in most cases no subject of the state can lawfully carry on any branch of foreign trade, for which a regulated company is established, with∣out first becoming a member of that company. The monopoly is more or less strict according as the terms of admission are more or less difficult; and according as the directors of the company have more or less authority, or have it more or less in their power to manage, in such a manner as to confine the greater part of the trade to themselves, and their particular friends. In the most ancient re∣gulated companies the privileges of apprenticeship were the same as in other corporations; and intitled the person who had served his time to a member of the company, to become himself a member, either without paying any fine, or upon paying a much smaller one than what was exacted of other people. The usual corporation spirit, wherever the law does not restrain it, prevails in all regulated com∣panies. When they have been allowed to act according to their na∣tural genius, they have always, in order to confine the competition to as small a number of persons as possible, endeavoured to subject the trade to many burdensome regulations. When the law has re∣strained them from doing this, they have become altogether useless and insignificant.</P>
<P>THE regulated companies for foreign commerce, which at present subsist in Great Britain, are, the ancient merchant adventurers com∣pany, now commonly called the Hamburgh Company, the Russian
<PB N="51" REF="51"/>
Company, the Eastland Company, the Turky Company, and the African Company.</P>
<P>THE terms of admission into the Hamburgh Company, are now said to be quite easy; and the directors either have it not in their power to subject the trade to any burdensome restraints or regula∣tions, or, at least, have not of late exercised that power. It has not always been so. About the middle of the last century, the fine for admission was fifty, and at one time one hundred pounds, and the conduct of the company was said to be extremely oppressive. In 1643, in 1645, and in 1661, the clothiers and free traders of the West of England complained of them to parliament, as of mono∣polists who confined the trade and oppressed the manufactures of the country. Though those complaints produced no act of parlia∣ment, they had probably intimidated the company so far, as to oblige them to reform their conduct. Since that time, at least, there has been no complaints against them. By the 10th and 11th of William III. c. 6. the fine for admission into the Russian Company was reduced to five pounds; and by the 25th of Charles II. c. 7. that for admission into the Eastland Company, to forty shillings, while, at the same time, Sweden, Denmark and Norway, all the countries on the north-side of the Baltick, were exempted from their exclusive charter. The conduct of those companies had probably given occasion to those two acts of parliament. Before that time, Sir Josiah Child had represented both these and the Hamburgh Com∣pany as extremely oppressive, and imputed to their bad management the low state of the trade, which we at that time carried on to the countries comprehended within their respective charters. But though such companies may not, in the present times, be very oppressive, they are certainly altogether useless. To be merely useless, indeed, is perhaps the highest eulogy which can ever justly be bestowed upon a regulated company; and all the three companies above mentioned seem, in their present state, to deserve this eulogy.</P>
<P><PB N="52" REF="52"/>
THE fine for admission into the Turky Company, was formerly twenty-five pounds for all persons under twenty-six years of age, and fifty pounds for all persons above that age. Nobody but mere merchants could be admitted; a restriction which excluded all shop∣keepers and retailers. By a bye-law, no British manufactures could be exported to Turky but in the general ships of the company; and as those ships sailed always from the port of London, this restriction confined the trade to that extensive port, and the traders, to those who lived in London and in its neighbourhood. By another bye-law, no person living within twenty miles of London, and not free of the city, could be admitted a member; another restriction, which, joined to the foregoing, necessarily excluded all but the freemen of London. As the time for the loading and sailing of those general ships depended altogether upon the directors, they could easily fill them with their own goods and those of their particular friends, to the exclusion of others, who, they might pretend, had made their proposals too late. In this state of things, therefore, this company was in every respect a strict and oppressive monopoly. Those abuses gave occasion to the act of the 26th of Geo. II. c. 18. reducing the fine for admission to twenty pounds for all persons, without any distinction of ages, or any restriction, either to mere merchants, or to the freemen of London; and granting to all such persons the liberty of exporting, from all the ports of Great Britain to any port in Turky, all British goods of which the exportation was not prohibited; and of importing from thence all Turkish goods, of which the importation was not prohibited, upon paying both the general duties of customs, and the particular duties assessed for defraying the necessary expences of the company; and submitting, at the same time, to the lawful authority of the British ambassador and consuls resident in Turky, and to the bye-laws of the company duly enacted. To prevent any oppression by those bye-laws, it was by the same act ordained, that if any seven members of the company conceived themselves aggrieved
<PB N="53" REF="53"/>
by any bye-law which should be enacted after the passing of this act, they might appeal to the Board of Trade and Plantations (to the autho∣rity of which, a committee of the privy council has now succeeded), provided such appeal was brought within twelve months after the bye-law was enacted; and that if any seven members conceived themselves aggrieved by any bye-law which had been enacted be∣fore the passing of this act, they might bring a like appeal, provided it was within twelve months after the day on which this act was to take place. The experience of one year, however, may not always be sufficient to discover to all the members of a great company the pernicious tendency of a particular bye-law; and if several of them should afterwards discover it, neither the Board of Trade, nor the Committee of Council, can afford them any redress. The object, be∣sides, of the greater part of the bye-laws of all regulated companies, as well as of all other corporations, is not so much to oppress those who are already members, as to discourage others from becoming so; which may be done, not only by a high fine, but by many other contrivances. The constant view of such companies is always to raise the rate of their own profit as high as they can; to keep the market, both for the goods which they export, and for those which they import, as much understocked as they can: which can be done only by restraining the competition, or by discouraging new adventurers from entering into the trade. A fine even of twenty pounds, be∣sides, though it may not, perhaps, be sufficient to discourage any man from entering into the Turky trade, with an intention to continue in it, may be enough to discourage a speculative merchant from ha∣zarding a single adventure in it. In all trades, the regular establish∣ed traders, even though not incorporated, naturally combine to raise profits, which are noway so likely to be kept, at all times, down to their proper level, as by the occasional competition of speculative adventurers. The Turky trade, though in some measure laid open by this act of parliament, is still considered by many people as very
<PB N="54" REF="54"/>
far from being altogether free. The Turky company contribute to maintain an ambassador and two or three consuls, who, like other publick ministers, ought to be maintained altogether by the state, and the trade laid open to all his majesty's subjects. The different taxes levied by the company, for this and other corporation purposes, might afford a revenue much more than sufficient to enable the state to maintain such ministers.</P>
<P>REGULATED companies, it was observed by Sir Josiah Child, though they had frequently supported publick ministers, had never maintained any forts or garrisons in the countries to which they traded; whereas joint stock companies frequently had. And in reality the former seem to be much more unfit for this sort of service than the latter. First, the directors of a regulated company have no particular interest in the prosperity of the general trade of the company, for the sake of which, such forts and garrisons are maintained. The decay of that general trade may even frequently contribute to the advantage of their own private trade; as by dimi∣nishing the number of their competitors, it may enable them both to buy cheaper, and to sell dearer. The directors of a joint stock company, on the contrary, having only their share in the profits which are made upon the common stock committed to their management, have no private trade of their own, of which the interest can be separated from that of the general trade of the company. Their private interest is connected with the prosperity of the general trade of the company; and with the maintenance of the forts and garri∣sons, which are necessary for its defence. They are more likely, therefore, to have that continual and careful attention which that maintenance necessarily requires. Secondly, The directors of a joint stock company have always the management of a large capital, the joint stock of the company, a part of which they may frequently employ, with propriety, in building, repairing, and maintaining such necessary forts and garrisons. But the directors of a regulated
<PB N="55" REF="55"/>
company, having the management of no common capital, have no other fund to employ in this way, but the casual revenue arising from the admission fines, and from the corporation duties, imposed upon the trade of the company. Though they had the same in∣terest, therefore, to attend to the maintenance of such forts and garrisons, they can seldom have the same ability to render that at∣tention effectual. The maintenance of a publick minister requiring scarce any attention, and but a moderate and limited expence, is a business much more suitable both to the temper and abilities of a regulated company.</P>
<P>LONG after the time of Sir Josiah Child, however, in 1750, a regulated company was established, the present company of mer∣chants trading to Africa, which was expressly charged at first with the maintenance of all the British forts and garrisons that lie between Cape Blanc and the Cape of Good Hope, and afterwards with that of those only which lie between Cape Rouge and the Cape of Good Hope. The act which establishes this company (the 23d of George II. c. 31.) seems to have had two distinct objects in view; first, to restrain effectually the oppressive and monopolizing spirit which is natural to the directors of a regulated company; and secondly, to force them, as much as possible, to give an attention, which is not natural to them, towards the maintenance of forts and gar∣risons.</P>
<P>FOR the first of these purposes, the fine for admission is limited to forty shillings. The company is prohibited from trading in their corporate capacity, or upon a joint stock; from borrowing money upon common seal, or from laying any restraints upon the trade, which may be carried on freely from all places, and by all persons being British subjects, and paying the fine. The government is in a committee of nine persons who meet at London, but who are chosen annually by the freemen of the company at London, Bristol, and Liverpool; three from each place. No committee-man can be
<PB N="56" REF="56"/>
continued in office for more than three years together. Any com∣mittee-man might be removed by the Board of Trade and Plantations; now by a committee of council, after being heard in his own de∣fence. The committee are forbid to export negroes from Africa, or to import any African goods into Great Britain. But as they are charged with the maintenance of forts and garrisons, they may, for that purpose, export from Great Britain to Africa, goods and stores of different kinds. Out of the monies which they shall receive from the company, they are allowed a sum not exceeding eight hundred pounds for the salaries of their clerks and agents at London, Bristol, and Liverpool, the house-rent of their office at London, and all the other expences of management, commission and agency in Eng∣land. What remains of this sum, after defraying these different expences, they may divide among themselves, as compensation for their trouble, in what manner they think proper. By this consti∣tution it might have been expected, that the spirit of monopoly would have been effectually restrained, and the first of these purposes sufficiently answered. It would seem, however, that it had not. Though by the 4th of George III. c. 20. the fort of Senegal, with all its dependencies, had been vested in the company of merchants trading to Africa, yet in the year following (by the 5th of Geo. III. c. 44.), not only Senegal and its dependencies, but the whole coast, from the port of Sallee, in South Barbary, to Cape Rouge, was ex∣empted from the jurisdiction of that company, was vested in the crown, and the trade to it declared free to all his majesty's subjects. The company had been suspected of restraining the trade, and of establishing some sort of improper monopoly. It is not, however, very easy to conceive how, under the regulations of the 23d Geo. II. they could do so. In the printed debates of the House of Commons, not always the most authentic records of truth, I observe, however, that they have been accused of this. The members of the committee of nine, being all merchants, and the governors and factors, in their
<PB N="57" REF="57"/>
different forts and settlements, being all dependent upon them, it is not unlikely that the latter might have given peculiar attention to the consignments and commissions of the former, which would esta∣blish a real monopoly.</P>
<P>FOR the second of these purposes, the maintenance of the forts and garrisons, an annual sum has been allotted to them by parliament, generally about 13,000<HI>l.</HI> For the proper application of this sum, the committee is obliged to account annually to the Cursitor Baron of Exchequer; which account is afterwards to be laid before parliament. But parliament, which gives so little attention to the application of millions, is not likely to give much to that of 13,000<HI>l.</HI> a-year; and the Cursitor Baron of Exchequer, from his profession and education, is not likely to be profoundly skilled in the proper expence of forts and garrisons. The captains of his majesty's navy, indeed, or any other commissioned officers, appointed by the Board of Admiralty, may enquire into the condition of the forts and garrisons, and report their observations to that board. But that board seems to have no direct jurisdiction over the committee, nor any authority to correct those whose conduct it may thus enquire into; and the captains of his majesty's navy, besides, are not sup∣posed to be always deeply learned in the science of fortification. Removal from an office, which can be enjoyed only for the term of three years, and of which the lawful emoluments, even during that term, are so very small, seems to be the utmost punishment to which any committee-man is liable, for any fault, except direct malversa∣tion, or embezzlement, either of the publick money, or of that of the company; and the fear of that punishment can never be a motive of sufficient weight to force a continual and careful attention to a business, to which he has no other interest to attend. The committee are accused of having sent out bricks and stones from England for the reparation of Cape Coast Castle on the coast of Guinea, a business for which parliament had several times granted an extraordinary
<PB N="58" REF="58"/>
sum of money. These bricks and stones too, which had thus been sent upon so long a voyage, were said to have been of so bad a quality, that it was necessary to rebuild from the foundation the walls which had been repaired with them. The forts and garrisons which lie north of Cape Rouge, are not only maintained at the ex∣pence of the state, but are under the immediate government of the executive power; and why those which lie south of that Cape, and which too are, in part at least, maintained at the expence of the state, should be under a different government, it seems not very easy even to imagine a good reason. The protection of the Mediter∣ranean trade was the original purpose or pretence of the garrisons of Gibraltar and Minorca, and the maintenance and government of those garrisons has always been, very properly, committed, not to the Turky Company, but to the executive power. In the extent of its dominion consists, in a great measure, the pride and dignity of that power; and it is not very likely to fail in attention to what is necessary for the defence of that dominion. The garrisons at Gibraltar and Minorca, accordingly, have never been neglected; though Minorca has been twice taken, and is now probably lost for ever, that disaster was never even imputed to any neglect in the ex∣ecutive power. I would not, however, be understood to insinuate, that either of those expensive garrisons was ever, even in the small∣est degree, necessary for the purpose for which they were originally dismembered from the Spanish monarchy. That dismemberment, perhaps, never served any other real purpose than to alienate from England her natural ally the king of Spain, and to unite the two principal branches of the house of Bourbon in a much stricter and more parmanent alliance than the ties of blood could ever have united them.</P>
<P>JOINT stock companies, established either by royal charter or by act of parliament, differ in several respects, not only from regulated companies, but from private copartneries.</P>
<P><PB N="59" REF="59"/>
FIRST, In a private copartnery, no partner, without the consent of the company, can transfer his share to another person, or intro∣duce a new member into the company. Each member, however, may, upon proper warning, withdraw from the copartnery, and de∣mand payment from them of his share of the common stock. In a joint stock company, on the contrary, no member can demand pay∣ment of his share from the company; but each member can, with∣out their consent, transfer his share to another person, and thereby introduce a new member. The value of a share in a joint stock is always the price which it will bring in the market; and this may be either greater or less, in any proportion, than the sum which its owner stands credited for in the stock of the company.</P>
<P>SECONDLY, In a private copartnery, each partner is bound for the debts contracted by the company to the whole extent of his for∣tune. In a joint stock company, on the contrary, each partner is bound only to the extent of his share.</P>
<P>THE trade of a joint stock company is always managed by a court of directors. This court, indeed, is frequently subject, in many respects, to the control of a general court of proprietors. But the greater part of those proprietors seldom pretend to understand any thing of the business of the company; and when the spirit of faction happens not to prevail among them, give themselves no trouble about it, but receive contentedly such half yearly or yearly dividend, as the directors think proper to make to them. This total exemption from trouble and from risk, beyond a limited sum, encourages many people to become adventurers in joint stock companies, who would, upon no account, hazard their fortunes in any private copartnery. Such companies, therefore, commonly draw to themselves much greater stocks than any private copartnery can boast of. The trading stock of the South Sea Company, at one time, amounted to upwards of thirty-three millions eight hundred thousand pounds. The divided capital of the Bank of England amounts, at present, to
<PB N="60" REF="60"/>
ten millions seven hundred and eighty thousand pounds. The di∣rectors of such companies, however, being the managers rather of other people's money than of their own, it cannot well be expected, that they should watch over it with the same anxious vigilance with which the partners in a private copartnery frequently watch over their own. Like the stewards of a rich man, they are apt to consider attention to small matters as not for their master's honour, and very easily give themselves a dispensation from having it. Negligence and profusion, therefore, must always prevail, more or less, in the management of the affairs of such a company. It is upon this ac∣count that joint stock companies for foreign trade have seldom been able to maintain the competition against private adventurers. They have, accordingly, very seldom succeeded without an exclusive pri∣vilege; and frequently have not succeeded with one. Without an exclusive privilege they have commonly mismanaged the trade. With an exclusive privilege they have both mismanaged and con∣fined it.</P>
<P>THE royal African Company, the predecessors of the present Afri∣can Company, had an exclusive privilege by charter; but as that charter had not been confirmed by act of parliament, the trade, in consequence of the declaration of rights, was, soon after the Revo∣lution, laid open to all his majesty's subjects. The Hudson's Bay Company are, as to their legal rights, in the same situation as the Royal African Company. Their exclusive charter has not been confirmed by act of parliament. The South Sea Company, as long as they continued to be a trading company, had an exclusive privilege confirmed by act of parliament; as have likewise the pre∣sent United Company of Merchants trading to the East Indies.</P>
<P>THE Royal African Company soon found that they could not maintain the competition against private adventurers, whom, not∣withstanding the declaration of rights, they continued for some time to call interlopers, and to persecute as such. In 1698, however,
<PB N="61" REF="61"/>
the private adventurers were subjected to a duty of ten per cent. upon almost all the different branches of their trade, to be employed by the company in the maintenance of their forts and garrisons. But, notwithstanding this heavy tax, the company were still unable to maintain the competition. Their stock and credit gradually de∣clined. In 1712, their debts had become so great, that a particular act of parliament was thought necessary, both for their security and for that of their creditors. It was enacted, that the resolution of two-thirds of these creditors in number and value, should bind the rest, both with regard to the time which should be allowed to the company for the payment of their debts; and with regard to any other agreement which it might be thought proper to make with them concerning those debts. In 1730, their affairs were in so great disorder, that they were altogether incapable of maintaining their forts and garrisons, the sole purpose and pretext of their institution. From that year, till their final dissolution, the parliament judged it necessary to allow the annual sum of ten thousand pounds for that purpose. In 1732, after having been for many years losers by the trade of carrying negroes to the West Indies, they at last resolved to give it up altogether; to sell to the private traders to America the negroes which they purchased upon the coast; and to employ their servants in a trade to the inland parts of Africa for gold dust, elephants teeth, dying drugs, &amp;c. But their success in this more confined trade was not greater than in their former extensive one. Their affairs continued to go gradually to decline, till, at last, be∣ing in every respect a bankrupt company, they were dissolved by act of parliament, and their forts and garrisons vested in the present re∣gulated company of merchants trading to Africa. Before the erection of the Royal African Company, there had been three other joint stock companies successively established, one after another, for the African trade. They were all equally unsuccessful. They all, how∣ever, had exclusive charters, which, though not confirmed by act of
<PB N="62" REF="62"/>
parliament, were in those days supposed to convey a real exclusive privilege.</P>
<P>THE Hudson's Bay Company, before their misfortunes in the late war, had been much more fortunate than the Royal African Com∣pany. Their necessary expence is much smaller. The whole num∣ber of people whom they maintain in their different settlements and habitations, which they have honoured with the name of forts, is said not to exceed a hundred and twenty persons. This number, however, is sufficient to prepare before-hand the cargo of furs and other goods necessary for loading their ships, which, on account of the ice, can seldom remain above six or eight weeks in those seas. This advantage of having a cargo ready prepared, could not for se∣veral years be acquired by private adventurers, and without it there seems to be no possibility of trading to Hudson's Bay. The moderate capital of the company, which, it is said, does not exceed one hun∣dred and ten thousand pounds, may besides be sufficient to enable them to engross the whole, or almost the whole, trade and surplus produce of the miserable, though extensive country, comprehended within their charter. No private adventurers, accordingly, have ever attempted to trade to that country in competition with them. This company, therefore, have always enjoyed an exclusive trade in fact, though they may have no right to it in law. Over and above all this, the moderate capital of this company is said to be divided among a very small number of proprietors. But a joint stock com∣pany, consisting of a small number of proprietors, with a moderate capital, approaches very nearly to the nature of a private copartnery, and may be capable of nearly the same degree of vigilance and atten∣tion. It is not to be wondered at, therefore, if, in consequence of these different advantages, the Hudson's Bay Company had, before the late war, been able to carry on their trade with a considerable degree of success. It does not seem probable, however, that their profits ever approached to what the late Mr. Dobbs imagined them.
<PB N="63" REF="63"/>
A much more sober and judicious writer, Mr. Anderson, author of the Historical and Chronological Deduction of Commerce, very justly observes, that upon examining the accounts which Mr. Dobbs him∣self has given for several years together, of their exports and imports, and upon making proper allowances for their extraordinary risk and expence, it does not appear that their profits deserve to be envied, or that they can much, if at all, exceed the ordinary profits of trade.</P>
<P>THE South Sea Company never had any forts or garrisons to maintain, and therefore were entirely exempted from one great ex∣pence, to which other joint stock companies for foreign trade are subject. But they had an immense capital divided among an im∣mense number of proprietors. It was naturally to be expected, therefore, that folly, negligence, and profusion should prevail in the whole management of their affairs. The knavery and extravagance of their stock-jobbing projects are sufficiently known, and the ex∣plication of them would be foreign to the present subject. Their mercantile projects were not much better conducted. The first trade which they engaged in was that of supplying the Spanish West Indies with negroes, of which (in consequence of what was called the Assiento contract, granted them by the treaty of Utrecht) they had the exclusive privilege. But as it was not expected that much profit could be made by this trade, both the Portugueze and French companies, who had enjoyed it upon the same terms before them, having been ruined by it, they were allowed, as compensation, to send annually a ship of a certain burden to trade directly to the Spanish West Indies. Of the ten voyages which this annual ship was allowed to make, they are said to have gained considerably by one, that of the Royal Caroline in 1731, and to have been losers, more or less, by almost all the rest. Their ill success was imputed, by their factors and agents, to the extortion and oppression of the Spa∣nish government; but was, perhaps, principally owing to the pro∣fusion
<PB N="64" REF="64"/>
and depredations of those very factors and agents; some of whom are said to have acquired great fortunes even in one year. In 1734, the company petitioned the king, that they might be al∣lowed to dispose of the trade and tunnage of their annual ship, on account of the little profit which they made by it, and to accept of such equivalent as they could obtain from the king of Spain.</P>
<P>IN 1724, this company had undertaken the whale-fishery. Of this, indeed, they had no monopoly; but as long as they carried it on, no other British subjects appear to have engaged in it. Of the eight voyages which their ships made to Greenland, they were gainers by one, and losers by all the rest. After their eighth and last voyage, when they had sold their ships, stores, and utensils, they found that their whole loss, upon this branch, capital and in∣terest included, amounted to upwards of two hundred and thirty∣seven thousand pounds.</P>
<P>IN 1722, this company petitioned the parliament to be allowed to divide their immense capital of more than thirty-three millions eight hundred thousand pounds, the whole of which had been lent to government, into two equal parts: The one half, or upwards of sixteen millions nine hundred thousand pounds, to be put upon the same sooting with other government annuities, and not to be subject to the debts contracted, or losses incurred, by the directors of the company, in the prosecution of their mercantile projects; the other half to re∣main, as before, a trading stock, and to be subject to those debts and losses. The petition was too reasonable not to be granted. In 1733, they again petitioned the parliament, that three-fourths of their trading stock might be turned into annuity stock, and only one-fourth remain as trading stock, or exposed to the hazards arising from the bad management of their directors. Both their annuity and trading stocks had, by this time, been reduced more than two millions each, by several different payments from government; so that this fourth amounted only to 3,662,784<HI>l.</HI> 8<HI>s.</HI> 6<HI>d.</HI> In 1748,
<PB N="65" REF="65"/>
all the demands of the company upon the king of Spain, in conse∣quence of the Assiento contract, were, by the treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle, given up for what was supposed an equivalent. An end was put to their trade with the Spanish West Indies, the remainder of their trading stock was turned into an annuity stock, and the company ceased in every respect to be a trading company.</P>
<P>IT ought to be observed, that in the trade which the South Sea Company carried on by means of their annual ship, the only trade by which it ever was expected that they could make any consider∣able profit, they were not without competitors, either in the foreign or in the home market. At Carthagena, Porto Bello, and La Vera Cruz, they had to encounter the competition of the Spanish mer∣chants, who brought from Cadiz, to those markets, European goods, of the same kind with the outward cargo of their ship; and in Eng∣land they had to encounter that of the English merchants, who im∣ported from Cadiz goods of the Spanish West Indies, of the same kind with the inward cargo. The goods, both of the Spanish and English merchants, indeed, were, perhaps, subject to higher duties. But the loss occasioned by the negligence, profusion, and malversa∣tion of the servants of the company, had probably been a tax much heavier than all those duties. That a joint stock company should be able to carry on successfully any branch of foreign trade, when private adventurers can come into any sort of open and fair compe∣tition with them, seems contrary to all experience.</P>
<P>THE old English East India Company was established in 1600, by a charter from Queen Elizabeth. In the first twelve voyages which they sitted out for India, they appear to have traded as a regulated company, with separate stocks, though only in the general ships of the company. In 1612, they united into a joint stock. Their charter was exclusive, and though not confirmed by act of parlia∣ment, was in those days supposed to convey a real exclusive privi∣lege. For many years, therefore, they were not much disturbed by
<PB N="66" REF="66"/>
interlopers. Their capital, which never exceeded seven hundred and forty-four thousand pounds, and of which fifty pounds was a share, was not so exorbitant, nor their dealings so extensive, as to afford either a pretext for gross negligence and profusion, or a cover to gross malversation. Notwithstanding some extraordinary losses, occasioned partly by the malice of the Dutch East India Company, and partly by other accidents, they carried on for many years a successful trade. But in process of time, when the principles of liberty were better understood, it became every day more and more doubtful how far a royal charter, not confirmed by act of parliament, could convey an exclusive privilege. Upon this question the decisions of the courts of justice were not uniform, but varied with the authority of government and the humours of the times. Interlopers multi∣plied upon them; and towards the end of the reign of Charles II. through the whole of that of James II. and during a part of that of William III. reduced them to great distress. In 1698, a proposal was made to parliament of advancing two millions to government at eight per cent. provided the subscribers were erected into a new East India Company with exclusive privileges. The old East India Company offered seven hundred thousand pounds, nearly the amount of their capital, at four per cent. upon the same conditions. But such was at that time the state of public credit, that it was more con∣venient for government to borrow two millions at eight per cent. than seven hundred thousand pounds at four. The proposal of the new subscribers was accepted, and a new East India Company esta∣blished in consequence. The old East India Company, however, had a right to continue their trade till 1701. They had, at the same time, in the name of their treasurer, subscribed, very artfully, three hundred and fifteen thousand pounds into the stock of the new. By a negligence in the expression of the act of parliament, which vested the East India trade in the subscribers to this loan of two mil∣lions, it did not appear evident that they were all obliged to unite
<PB N="67" REF="67"/>
into a joint stock. A few private traders, whose subscriptions amounted only to seven thousand two hundred pounds, insisted upon the privilege of trading separately upon their own stocks and at their own risk. The old East India Company had a right to a separate trade upon their old stock till 1701; and they had likewise, both before and after that period, a right, like that of other private traders, to a separate trade upon the three hundred and fifteen thousand pounds, which they had subscribed into the stock of the new company. The competition of the two companies with the private traders, and with one another, is said to have well nigh ruined both. Upon a subsequent occasion, in 1730, when a pro∣posal was made to parliament for putting the trade under the ma∣nagement of a regulated company, and thereby laying it in some measure open, the East India Company, in opposition to this pro∣posal, represented in very strong terms, what had been, at this time, the miserable effects, as they thought them, of this competition. In India, they said, it raised the price of goods so high, that they were not worth the buying; and in England, by overstocking the market, it sunk their price so low, that no profit could be made by them. That by a more plentiful supply, to the great advantage and conve∣niency of the publick, it must have reduced, very much, the price of India goods in the English market, cannont well be doubted; but that it should have raised very much their price in the Indian market, seems not very probable, as all the extraordinary demand which that competition could occasion, must have been but as a drop of water in the immense ocean of Indian commerce. The increase of de∣mand, besides, though in the beginning it may sometimes raise the price of goods, never fails to lower it in the long-run. It encou∣rages production, and thereby increases the competition of the pro∣ducers, who, in order to undersell one another, have recourse to new divisions of labour and new improvements of art, which might never otherwise have been thought of. The miserable effects of
<PB N="68" REF="68"/>
which the company complained, were the cheapness of consumption and the encouragement given to production, precisely the two ef∣fects which it is the great business of political oeconomy to promote. The competition, however, of which they gave this doleful account, had not been allowed to be of long continuance. In 1702, the two companies were, in some measure, united by an indenture tri∣partite, to which the queen was the third party; and in 1708, they were, by act of parliament, perfectly consolidated into one company by their present name of the United Company of Merchants trading to the East Indies. Into this act it was thought worth while to insert a clause, allowing the separate traders to continue their trade till Michaelmas 1711, but at the same time empowering the di∣rectors, upon three years notice, to redeem their little capital of seven thousand two hundred pounds, and thereby to convert the whole stock of the company into a joint-stock. By the same act, the capital of the company, in consequence of a new loan to go∣vernment, was augmented from two millions to three millions two hundred thousand pounds. In 1743, the company advanced an∣other million to government. But this million being raised, not by a call upon the proprietors, but by selling annuities and contracting bond-debts, it did not augment the stock upon which the proprietors could claim a dividend. It augmented, however, their trading stock, it being equally liable with the other three millions two hun∣dred thousand pounds, to the losses sustained, and debts contracted, by the company in prosecution of their mercantile projects. From 1708, or at least from 1711, this company, being delivered from all competitors, and fully established in the monopoly of the English commerce to the East Indies, carried on a successful trade, and from their profits made annually a moderate dividend to their proprietors. During the French war, which began in 1741, the ambition of Mr. Dupleix, the French governor of Pondicherry, involved them in the wars of the Carnatic, and in the politics of the Indian princes. After
<PB N="69" REF="69"/>
many signal successes, and equally signal losses, they at last lost Madras, at that time their principal settlement in India. It was re∣stored to them by the treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle; and about this time the spirit of war and conquest seems to have taken possession of their servants in India, and never since to have left them. During the French war, which began in 1755, their arms partook of the general good fortune of those of Great Britain. They defended Madras, took Pondicherry, recovered Calcutta, and acquired the revenues of a rich and extensive territory, amounting, it was then said, to upwards of three millions a-year. They remained for several years in quiet possession of this revenue: But in 1767, ad∣ministration laid claim to their territorial acquisitions, and the re∣venue arising from them, as of right belonging to the crown; and the company, in compensation for this claim, agreed to pay to go∣vernment four hundred thousand pounds a-year. They had before this gradually augmented their dividend from about six to ten per cent.; that is, upon their capital of three millions two hundred thousand pounds, they had increased it by a hundred and twenty∣eight thousand pounds, or had raised it from one hundred and ninety-two thousand, to three hundred and twenty thousand pounds a-year. They were attempting about this time to raise it still fur∣ther, to twelve and a half per cent. which would have made their annual payments to their proprietors equal to what they had agreed to pay annually to government, or to four hundred thousand pounds a-year. But during the two years in which their agreement with government was to take place, they were restrained from any fur∣ther increase of dividend by two successive acts of parliament, of which the object was to enable them to make a speedier progress in the payment of their debts, which were at this time estimated at upwards of six or seven millions sterling. In 1769, they renewed their agreement with government for five years more, and stipu∣lated, that during the course of that period they should be allowed
<PB N="70" REF="70"/>
gradually to increase their dividend to twelve and a half per cent. never increasing it, however, more than one per cent. in one year. This increase of dividend, therefore, when it had risen to its utmost height, could augment their annual payments, to their proprietors and government together, but by six hundred and eight thousand pounds, beyond what they had been before their late ter∣ritorial acquisitions. What the gross revenue of those territorial acquisitions was supposed to amount to, has already been mentioned; and by an account brought by the Cruttenden East Indiaman in 1768, the nett revenue, clear of all deductions and military charges, was stated at two millions forty-eight thousand seven hundred and forty-seven pounds. They were said at the same time to possess an∣other revenue, arising partly from lands, but chiefly from the customs established at their different settlements, amounting to four hundred and thirty-nine thousand pounds. The profits of their trade too, according to the evidence of their chairman before the House of Commons, amounted at this time to at least four hundred thousand pounds a-year; according to that of their accomptant, to at least five hundred thousand; according to the lowest account, at least equal to the highest dividend that was to be paid to their proprietors. So great a revenue might certainly have afforded an augmentation of six hundred and eight thousand pounds in their annual payments; and at the same time have left a large sinking fund sufficient for the speedy reduction of their debts. In 1773, however, their debts, instead of being reduced, were augmented by an arrear to the treasury in the payment of the four hundred thousand pounds, by another to the custom-house for duties unpaid, by a large debt to the bank for money borrowed, and by a fourth for bills drawn upon them from India, and wantonly accepted, to the amount of upwards of twelve hundred thousand pounds. The distress which these accumulated claims brought upon them, obliged them, not only to reduce all at once their dividend to six per cent. but to throw themselves upon the mercy of government, and to supplicate, first, a release from the
<PB N="71" REF="71"/>
further payment of the stipulated four hundred thousand pounds a-year; and, secondly, a loan of fourteen hundred thousand, to save them from immediate bankruptey. The great increase of their fortune had, it seems, only served to furnish their servants with a pretext for greater profusion, and a cover for greater malversation, than in proportion even to that increase of fortune. The conduct of their servants in India, and the general state of their affairs both in India and in Europe, became the subjects of a parliamentary in∣quiry; in consequence of which several very important alterations were made in the constitution of their government, both at home and abroad. In India, their principal settlements of Madras, Bombay, and Calcutta, which had before been altogether independent of one another, were subjected to a governor-general, assisted by a council of four assessors, parliament assuming to itself the first nomination of this governor and council who were to reside at Calcutta; that city having now become, what Madras was before, the most im∣portant of the English settlements in India. The court of the mayor of Calcutta, originally instituted for the trial of mercantile causes, which arose in the city and neighbourhood, had gradually extended its jurisdiction with the extension of the empire. It was now re∣duced and consined to the original purpose of its institution. In∣stead of it a new supreme court of judicature was established, con∣sisting of a chief justice and three judges to be appointed by the crown. In Europe, the qualification necessary to entitle a proprietor to vote at their general courts was raised, from five hundred pounds, the original price of a share in the stock of the company, to a thou∣sand pounds. In order to vote upon this qualification too, it was declared necessary that he should have possessed it, if acquired by his own purchase, and not by inheritance, for at least one year, instead of six months, the term requisite before. The court of twenty-four directors had before been chosen annually; but it was now enacted, that each director should, for the future, be chosen for four years; six
<PB N="72" REF="72"/>
of them, however, to go out of office by rotation every year, and not to be capable of being re-chosen at the election of the six new directors for the ensuing year. In consequence of these alterations, the courts, both of the proprietors and directors, it was expected, would be likely to act with more dignity and steadiness than they had usually done before. But it seems impossible, by any alter∣ations, to render those courts, in any respect, fit to govern, or even to share in the government of a great empire; because the greater part of their members must always have too little interest in the prosperity of that empire, to give any serious attention to what may promote it. Frequently a man of great, sometimes even a man of small fortune, is willing to purchase a thousand pounds share in India stock, merely for the influence which he expects to acquire by a vote in the court of proprietors. It gives him a share, though not in the plunder, yet in the appointment of the plunderers of India; the court of directors, though they make that appointment, being necessarily more or less under the influence of the proprietors, who not only elect those directors, but sometimes over-rule the appoint∣ments of their servants in India. Provided he can enjoy this in∣fluence for a few years, and thereby provide for a certain number of his friends, he frequently cares little about the dividend, or even about the value of the stock upon which his vote is founded. About the prosperity of the great empire, in the government of which that vote gives him a share, he seldom cares at all. No other sovereigns ever were, or, from the nature of things, ever could be, so perfectly indifferent about the happiness or misery of their subjects, the im∣provement or waste of their dominions, the glory or disgrace of their administration; as, from irresistible moral causes, the greater part of the proprietors of such a mercantile company are, and necessarily must be. This indifference too was more likely to be increased than diminished by some of the new regulations, which were made in consequence of the parliamentary inquiry. By a resolution of the
<PB N="73" REF="73"/>
House of Commons, for example, it was declared, that when the fourteen hundred thousand pounds lent to the company by govern∣ment should be paid, and their bond-debts be reduced to fifteen hun∣dred thousand pounds, they might then, and not till then, divide eight per cent. upon their capital; and that whatever remained of their revenues and nett profits at home, should be divided into four parts; three of them to be paid into the exchequer for the use of the publick, and the fourth to be reserved as a fund, either for the further reduction of their bond-debts, or for the discharge of other contingent exigencies, which the company might labour under. But if the company were bad stewards, and bad sovereigns, when the whole of their nett revenue and profits belonged to themselves, and were at their own disposal, they were surely not likely to be better, when three-fourths of them were to belong to other people, and the other fourth, though to be laid out for the benefit of the com∣pany, yet to be so, under the inspection, and with the approbation, of other people.</P>
<P>IT might be more agreeable to the company that their own ser∣vants and dependants should have, either the pleasure of wasting, or the profit of embezzling, whatever surplus might remain, after pay∣ing the proposed dividend of eight per cent. than that it should come into the hands of a set of people with whom those resolutions could scarce fail to set them, in some measure, at variance. The interest of those servants and dependants might so far predominate in the court of proprietors as sometimes, to dispose it to support the authors of depredations which had been committed in direct viola∣tion of its own authority. With the majority of proprietors, the support even of the authority of their own court, might sometimes be a matter of less consequence than the support of those who had set that authority at defiance.</P>
<P>THE regulations of 1773, accordingly, did not put an end to the disorders of the company's government in India. Notwithstanding,
<PB N="74" REF="74"/>
that, during a momentary fit of good conduct, they had, at one time, collected, into the treasury of Calcutta, more than three mil∣lions sterling, notwithstanding, that, they had afterwards extended, either their dominion, or their depredations, over a vast accession of some of the richest and most fertile countries in India; all was wasted and destroyed. They found themselves altogether unpre∣pared to stop or resist the incursion of Hyder Ali; and, in conse∣quence of those disorders, the company is now (1784) in greater distress than ever; and, in order to prevent immediate bankruptey, is once more reduced to supplicate the assistance of government. Different plans have been proposed by the different parties in parlia∣ment, for the better management of its affairs. And all those plans seem to agree in supposing, what was indeed always abundantly evi∣dent, that it is altogether unfit to govern its territorial possessions. Even the company itself seems to be convinced of its own incapa∣city so far, and seems, upon that account, willing to give them up to government.</P>
<P>WITH the right of possessing forts and garrisons, in distant and barbarous countries, is necessarily connected the right of making peace and war in those countries. The joint stock companies which have had the one right, have constantly exercised the other, and have frequently had it expressly conferred upon them. How un∣justly, how capriciously, how cruelly they have commonly exercised it, is too well known from recent experience.</P>
<P>WHEN a company of merchants undertake, at their own risk and expence, to establish a new trade with some remote and barbarous nation, it may not be unreasonable to incorporate them into a joint stock company, and to grant them, in case of their success, a mono∣poly of the trade for a certain number of years. It is the easiest and most natural way in which the state can recompense them for hazarding a dangerous and expensive experiment, of which the
<PB N="75" REF="75"/>
publick is afterwards to reap the benefit. A temporary monopoly of this kind may be vindicated upon the same principles upon which a like monopoly of a new machine is granted to its inventor, and that of a new book to its author. But upon the expiration of the term, the monopoly ought certainly to determine; the forts and garrisons, if it was found necessary to establish any, to be taken into the hands of government, their value to be paid to the com∣pany, and the trade to be laid open to all the subjects of the state. By a perpetual monopoly, all the other subjects of the state are taxed very absurdly in two different ways; first, by the high price of goods, which, in the case of a free trade, they could buy much cheaper; and, secondly, by their total exclusion from a branch of business, which it might be both convenient and profitable for many of them to carry on. It is for the most worthless of all purposes too that they are taxed in this manner. It is merely to enable the company to support the negligence, profusion, and malversation of their own servants, whose disorderly conduct seldom allows the di∣vidend of the company to exceed the ordinary rate of profit in trades which are altogether free, and very frequently makes it fall even a good deal short of that rate. Without a monopoly, how∣ever, a joint stock company, it would appear from experience, can∣not long carry on any branch of foreign trade. To buy in one market, in order to sell, with profit, in another, when there are many competitors in both; to watch over, not only the occasional variations in the demand, but the much greater and more frequent variations in the competition, or in the supply which that demand is likely to get from other people, and to suit with dexterity and judgment both the quantity and quality of each assortment of goods to all these circumstances, is a species of warfare of which the ope∣rations are continually changing, and which can scarce ever be con∣ducted successfully, without such an unremitting exertion of vigi∣lance and attention, as cannot long be expected from the directors
<PB N="76" REF="76"/>
of a joint stock company. The East India Company, upon the redemption of their funds, and the expiration of their exclusive privilege, have a right, by act of parliament, to continue a cor∣poration with a joint stock, and to trade in their corporate capacity to the East Indies in common with the rest of their fellow-subjects. But in this situation, the superior vigilance and attention of private adventurers would, in all probability, soon make them weary of the trade.</P>
<P>AN eminent French author, of great knowledge in matters of political oeconomy, the Abbé Morellet, gives a list of fifty-five joint stock companies for foreign trade, which have been established in different parts of Europe since the year 1600, and which, accord∣ing to him, have all failed from mismanagement, notwithstanding they had exclusive privileges. He has been misinformed with re∣gard to the history of two or three of them, which were not joint stock companies and have not failed. But, in compensation, there have been several joint stock companies which have failed, and which he has omitted.</P>
<P>THE only trades which it seems possible for a joint stock com∣pany to carry on successfully, without an exclusive privilege, are those, of which all the operations are capable of being reduced to what is called a Routine, or to such a uniformity of method as ad∣mits of little or no variation. Of this kind is, first, the banking trade; secondly, the trade of insurance from sire, and from sea risk and capture in time of war; thirdly, the trade of making and main∣taining a navigable cut or canal; and, fourthly, the similar trade of bringing water for the supply of a great city.</P>
<P>THOUGH the principles of the banking trade may appear some∣what abstruse, the practice is capable of being reduced to strict rules. To depart upon any occasion from those rules, in consequence of some flattering speculation of extraordinary gain, is almost always extreme∣ly dangerous, and frequently fatal to the banking company which
<PB N="77" REF="77"/>
attempts it. But the constitution of joint stock companies renders them in general more tenacious of established rules than any private copartnery. Such companies, therefore, seem extremely well fitted for this trade. The principal banking companies in Europe, ac∣cordingly, are joint stock companies, many of which manage their trade very successfully without any exclusive privilege. The Bank of England has no other exclusive privilege, except that no other bank∣ing company in England shall consist of more than six persons. The two banks of Edinburgh are joint stock companies without any exclusive privilege.</P>
<P>THE value of the risk, either from fire, or from loss by sea, or by capture, though it cannot, perhaps, be calculated very exactly, admits, however, of such a gross estimation as renders it, in some degree, reducible to strict rule and method. The trade of in∣surance, therefore, may be carried on successfully by a joint stock company, without any exclusive privilege. Neither the London Assurance, nor the Royal Exchange Assurance Companies, have any such privilege.</P>
<P>WHEN a navigable cut or canal has been once made, the ma∣nagement of it becomes quite simple and easy, and is reducible to strict rule and method. Even the making of it is so, as it may be contracted for with undertakers at so much a mile, and so much a lock. The same thing may be said of a canal, an aqueduct, or a great pipe for bringing water to supply a great city. Such under∣takings, therefore, may be, and accordingly frequently are, very successfully managed by joint stock companies without any exclu∣sive privilege.</P>
<P>To establish a joint stock company, however, for any undertak∣ing, merely because such a company might be capable of managing it successfully; or to exempt a particular set of dealers from some of the general laws which take place with regard to all their neigh∣bours,
<PB N="78" REF="78"/>
merely because they might be capable of thriving if they had such an exemption, would certainly not be reasonable. To render such an establishment perfectly reasonable, with the circumstance of being reducible to strict rule and method, two other circumstances ought to concur. First, it ought to appear with the clearest evidence, that the undertaking is of greater and more general utility than the greater part of common trades; and secondly, that it requires a greater capital than can easily be collected into a private copartnery. If a moderate capital was sufficient, the great utility of the undertaking would not be a sufficient reason for establishing a joint stock com∣pany; because, in this case, the demand for what it was to produce would readily and easily be supplied by private adventurers. In the four trades above mentioned, both those circumstances concur.</P>
<P>THE great and general utility of the banking trade, when pru∣dently managed, has been fully explained in the second book of this Inquiry. But a publick bank which is to support publick credit, and upon particular emergencies to advance to government the whole produce of a tax, to the amount, perhaps, of several millions, a year or two before it comes in, requires a greater capital than can easily be collected into any private copartnery.</P>
<P>THE trade of insurance gives great security to the fortunes of private people, and by dividing among a great many that loss which would ruin an individual, makes it fall light and easy upon the whole society. In order to give this security, however, it is neces∣sary that the insurers should have a very large capital. Before the establishment of the two joint stock companies for insurance in Lon∣don, a list, it is said, was laid before the attorney-general, of one hundred and fifty private insurers who had failed in the course of a few years.</P>
<P>THAT navigable cuts and canals, and the works which are some∣times necessary for supplying a great city with water, are of great and general utility; while, at the same time, they frequently require
<PB N="79" REF="79"/>
a greater expence, than suits the fortunes of private people, is suffi∣ciently obvious.</P>
<P>EXCEPT the four trades above mentioned, I have not been able to recollect any other in which all the three circumstances, requisite for rendering reasonable the establishment of a joint stock company, concur. The English copper company of London, the lead smelt∣ing company, the glass-grinding company, have not even the pretext of any great or singular utility in the object which they pursue; nor does the pursuit of that object seem to require any expence unsuit∣able to the fortunes of many private men. Whether the trade which those companies carry on, is reducible to such strict rule and method as to render it fit for the management of a joint stock company, or whether they have any reason to boast of their extraordinary profits, I do not pretend to know. The mine-adventurers company has been long ago bankrupt. A share in the stock of the British Linen Company of Edinburgh sells, at present, very much below par, though less so than it did some years ago. The joint stock compa∣nies, which are established for the publick spirited purpose of promot∣ing some particular manufacture, over and above managing their own affairs ill, to the diminution of the general stock of the society, can in other respects scarce ever fail to do more harm than good. Notwithstanding the most upright intentions, the unavoidable par∣tiality of their directors to particular branches of the manufacture, of which the undertakers mislead and impose upon them, is a real dis∣couragement to the rest, and necessarily breaks, more or less, that natural proportion which would otherwise establish itself between judicious industry and profit, and which, to the general industry of the country, is of all encouragements the greatest and the most effectual.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

