<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2009-09-01</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Check for blanks. Checked for signatures. Checked for #s. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N02618">
<STC T="E">3103</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99012768</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="half title">
<PB REF="003103_0000_0FEFA66CB8CBEEA8"/>
<PB REF="003103_0001_0FEFA6386A9F1A30"/>
<P>Mr. <HI>Sewall's</HI> SERMON <HI>On a Day of Prayer</HI> For the Rising Generation.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="003103_0002_0FEFA639F8AF4AA0"/>
<P><HI>The Holy Spirit</HI> THE Gift of GOD Our Heavenly Father, To them that Ask Him.</P>
<P>A SERMON Preach'd on a Day of <HI>PRAYER</HI> with <HI>FASTING,</HI> kept by the South Church in <HI>Boston,</HI> to Ask of GOD the Effusion of His SPIRIT on the Rising Generation, <HI>Novemb.</HI> 13th. 1722.</P>
<P>By <HI>Joseph Sewall,</HI> A. M. Pastor of a Church of CHRIST in <HI>Boston.</HI></P>
<BIBL>Isai. 44 3 —</BIBL>
<Q>I will pour my Spirit upon thy Seed, and my Blessing upon thine Offspring.</Q>
<BIBL>Mar. 7.11 —</BIBL>
<Q>How much more shall your Fa∣ther which is in Heaven give good things to them that ask him.</Q>
<P><HI>BOSTON:</HI> Printed for <HI>D. Henchman,</HI> at the Corner Shop over against the Brick Meeting-House in Cornhill, 1728.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="sermon">
<PB N="1" REF="003103_0003_0FEFA63D15EEF5B0"/>
<HEAD>GOD will give His Holy SPIRIT to them that ask Him.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>LUKE XI. 13.</BIBL>
<Q>If ye then, being evil, know how to give good gifts unto your Children: how much more shall your heavenly Father give the Holy Spirit to them that ask Him.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>IN the beginning of this Chapter, one of Christ's Disciples ask'd our Lord to teach them to Pray; in answer to which request, this great Prophet and Teacher of His Church, gives His Disciples an excellent Form or Pattern as a Rule for their Direction in Prayer; which is re∣corded in this and the Evangelist <HI>Matthew,</HI> with some considerable difference. And He encourageth them to continue instant in Prayer, with persevering Importunity, by declaring that if they Ask it shall be given them; that if they seek, they shall find, and that if they Knock it shall be
<PB N="2" REF="003103_0004_0FEFA66E46379D20"/>
open'd to them. And our Lord illustrates and confirms this Truth by a double simi∣litude or comparison. The first is that of a <HI>Friend,</HI> who is moved by importunity to grant his friend's request, being urg'd to that which his kindness as a friend was not sufficient to incline him to. The second is taken from an <HI>earthly Father,</HI> whose pa∣rental love to his Child will not by any means, suffer him to give that which he knows to be hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tful, when his Child asks what is needful and proper to be given, <HI>ver.</HI> 11, 12. And then follows my <HI>text,</HI> in which we have the similitude form'd into an Argument by way of Comparison, from the less to the greater, <HI>If ye then being evil, know how to give good gifts to your children: how much more shall your heavenly father give his holy Spirit to them that ask him?</HI> If ye who are evil, who have, even the natural Affection God hath given you towards your Children impair'd and vitiated by Sir; and compard with God, have no goodness in you; <HI>for there is none good but God;</HI> if ye have both knowledge and will to give good things to your Children; and who is there that hath not, who is not a monster, with∣out natural affection; <HI>How much more shall your heavenly. Father:</HI> God who is your Fa∣ther not only by Creation, but also by A∣doption in Christ; and hath his Throne in
<PB N="3" REF="003103_0005_0FEFA63F5E816320"/>
Heaven above, whence cometh down every good and perfect giving? How much more shall He <HI>give his Holy Spirit,</HI> (in <HI>Mat.</HI> it is, <HI>good things,</HI> <NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">Mat. 7. i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> the Gift of the Holy Ghost comprehends in it <HI>formally,</HI> or <HI>virtually</HI> and <HI>causually</HI> all good things) <HI>to them that ask him:</HI> And therein express a silial disposi∣tion and frame of spirit. The <HI>Dutch</HI> ten∣der the text, <HI>those that pray to Him</HI> The word signifies, says Mr. <HI>Leigh,</HI> humbly to beg any thing, and earnestly to desire it.</P>
<P>DOCT. <HI>GOD our Heavenly Father will most certainly give His Holy Spirit to them; that Ask Him.</HI></P>
<P N="1">1. <HI>WHO is intended by the Holy Spirit?</HI> 2. <HI>What is implied in His being given?</HI> 3. <HI>What is intended in Asking the Holy Spirit?</HI> 4. <HI>Why should we Ask the Holy Spirit?</HI> 5. Prove the Doctrine, <HI>That God our Heavenly Father will most certainly give the Holy Spirit to them that Ask Him.</HI></P>
<P N="1">I. <HI>WHO is intended by the Holy Spirit?</HI></P>
<P>Ans <HI>THE Third person in the Godhead.</HI> The word here us'd for Spirit signifies <HI>Breath</HI> or <HI>Wind:</HI> And it is observ'd by a learned Man, that the Word for Spirit in the <HI>Hebrew, Greek</HI> and <HI>Latin,</HI> signifies Breath.
<PB N="4" REF="003103_0006_0FEFA671FB5CCAE8"/>
Now by this Word the Divine <HI>Essence</HI> which is pure and spiritual, immaterial and invi∣sible, is sometimes signified, in which the Father, Son and Holy Ghost are <HI>One.</HI> But then, as this Name is in a peculiar manner given to the Holy Ghost, so it declares His especial manner and order of subsistence in relation to the Father and the Son, as He proceeds from them. Now it is very ob∣vious that the Third Person in the <HI>Trinity</HI> is often call'd by this Name in the <HI>New Testament,</HI> and by a Name of the like signi∣fication in the <HI>Old.</HI> Thus in the old Testa∣ment, Gen. 1.2. <HI>The Spirit of God moved on the face of the waters, Psal.</HI> 336. <HI>Gen.</HI> 6.3. In the New Testament this word is fre∣quently us'd to signify this Divine Person, <HI>Joh.</HI> 3.5,—8. <HI>&amp;c.</HI> And the Epithet <HI>Holy,</HI> is frequently given Him, <HI>Psal.</HI> 51.11. in our text and in many places in the New Testa∣ment, which may be, not only to denote the holiness of His Nature as He is God, but especially in that it is <HI>His peculiar Work</HI> to sanctify, and <HI>make us holy.</HI> He proceedeth from the Father and the Son, Joh. 15.26. <HI>But when the Comserter is come, whom I will send from the Father, even the Spirit of truth, which procce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eth from the Fa∣ther.</HI> He is call'd <HI>the Spirit of the Son,</HI> Gal 4.6. Now, that the Holy Ghost is an <HI>in∣telligent Subsistend or Person</HI> is evident from
<PB N="5" REF="003103_0007_0FEFA641ACB9CC70"/>
the things ascribed to Him in Scripture, if vou take them together, as Understanding, Will &amp;c. He is said to divide to every Man <HI>as He will,</HI> 1 Cor. 12. 11. And there are those Works attributed to Him, which declare the same thing, Job 33.4. <HI>The Spi∣rit of the Lord hath made me.</HI> He is said to <HI>teach us,</HI> 1 Joh. 2.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> To make Overseers or Bishops over the Flock at <HI>Ephesus,</HI> Act. 20.28. As also to be the Object of those Actings of Men which declare the same thing. He is said to be vexed, and we read of the <HI>Sin against the Holy Ghost.</HI> A∣gain, the Holy Spirit is a <HI>Divine Person.</HI> He is God, One with the Father and the Son in all the Essential Properties and Glo∣ries of the Divine Nature, I Joh. 5.7. <HI>There are Three that bear record in Heaven, the Fa∣ther, the Word, and the Holy Ghost: and these Three are One.</HI> He is called God, <HI>Act.</HI> 5.3. Why hath Satan filled thy heart <HI>to lie unto the Holy Ghost?</HI> ver. 4. Thou hast not lied unto men, <HI>but unto God.</HI> He inspired those holy Men who spake and wrote the holy Scriptures, 2 <HI>Pet.</HI> 1.20, 1. Now it is said, <HI>All Scripture is given by Inspiration of God,</HI> 2 Tim. 3.16. The <HI>Incommunicable Attributes</HI> of God are ascribed to Him. He is <HI>Omni-present,</HI> Psal. 139.7. <HI>Whither shall I go from thy Spirit, Omniscient,</HI> 1 Cor. 2. 10, 11. <HI>But God hath revealed them unto us by his Spirit:
<PB N="6" REF="003103_0008_0FEFA67386F4F1E0"/>
for the Spirit searcheth all things, yea, the deep things of God. For what man knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of man which is in him? even so the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God.</HI> We are <HI>Bap∣tized in his Name,</HI> Mat. 28.19. And there∣fore devoted to His Faith and Service, as our Covenant God. And we are also <HI>so∣lemnly Blessed in His Name,</HI> 2 Cor. 13.14. Not to mention His Agency in the <HI>Super∣natural Works</HI> of <HI>Creation,</HI> and of <HI>Grace,</HI> the latter of which may be Considered under the following Head.</P>
<P N="2">II. <HI>IN what respects is God said to give, the Holy Spirit?</HI> Or thus, <HI>What is intended in God's giving the Holy Spirit?</HI> The Holy Spirit is in Scripture call'd the <HI>Gift of God,</HI> Joh. 4. 10. God is said to give Him; <HI>Joh.</HI> 14.16, 17. <HI>I will pray the Father, and he shall give you another Comforter, even the Spirit of truth.</HI> And agreable to this, such as are made Partakers of this rich Gift, are said to receive the Holy Ghost. 1 Cor. 2.12. <HI>We have received the Spirit which is of God.</HI> Our Heavenly Father gives His Spi∣rit to His Son our Lord Jesus Christ, as He is the Head of His Church, Joh. 3.34. —<HI>God giveth not the Spirit by measure unto him.</HI> He is the <HI>first Receiver,</HI> and thro Him God bestows this great Gift upon His Peo∣ple
<PB N="7" REF="003103_0009_0FEFA699CA0E4B88"/>
Act. 2.33. Therefore being by the right Hand of God exalted, and <HI>having received of the Father the promise of the Holy Ghost, be hath shed forth that which ye now see and hear.</HI></P>
<P>Here I may say,</P>
<P N="1">1. GOD's giving the Holy Spirit denotes <HI>His Authority and free Grace.</HI> This is a free Favour, and is of meer Grace, not of Debt. When we Pray for the Holy Ghost, we must come to the Throne of Grace with∣out Money, and without Price. God hath Power to bellow Him, and He acts herein with Authority and the greatest Freedom. We can do nothing to Purchase this Gift, or to oblige God to bestow it upon us as a reward of Debt. No, we are unworthy of the least of God's Mercies, much less can we in any measure deserve this Com∣prehensive Gift. Ability to Ask aright, and the thing bestow'd in answer to our humble Petition, are both of the free Mercy of God thro' Jesus Christ.</P>
<P N="2">2. THE Spirit is said to be given <HI>res∣pecting His Office, as He is the Dispenser of all Good to God's People.</HI> The Spirit is <HI>Essentially One,</HI> with the Father and with the Son, and as God acts with Sovereign Liberty. But then respecting His <HI>Office</HI> He
<PB N="8" REF="003103_0010_0FEFA676C4EE9A90"/>
is said to be sent and given<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">"In the Communication of the Spirit, respect i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> had unto his Effects, or the Ends for which he is given. The Authority of this Giving respects principally his Gifts and Graces. Dr. <HI>Owen</HI> of the Holy Spirit, p. 81.</NOTE>. The Appli∣cation of the Redemption purchased by Christ is peculiarly attributed to Him, <HI>Tit.</HI> 3.5, 6.— According to his mercy he saved us, <HI>by the washing of regeneration, and re∣newing of the holy Ghost; which was shed on us abundantly thro' Jesus Christ our Saviour.</HI> He is the Good Spirit of God, and all good is from Him. And accordingly He is said to be given with an especial Regard to those excellent Gifts, Graces and Comforts which are Communicated by Him. The Holy Spirit is in His Divine Nature one and <HI>the same,</HI> without variableness: But in His Gifts and Operations He is <HI>various,</HI> 1 Cor. 12.11. <HI>But all these (gifts) worketh that one and self same Spirit—.</HI> Agreably we read of the <HI>seven Spirits of God,</HI> Rev. 4.5. i. e. the Holy Spirit in His manifold Dispensations of Gifts and Graces. "Va∣riety of Gifts,<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">Dr. <HI>Thomas Goodwin,</HI></NOTE> And in this respect the Spirit of God may be said to be given more sparingly, or poured out more plentifully, according to the degree and measure in, which He is Communicated. It is said, that the Holy Ghost <HI>was not yet given—,</HI> or as in the Original, <HI>was not yet, because
<PB N="9" REF="003103_0011_0FEFA69C15B05670"/>
Jesus was not yet glorified,</HI> Joh. 7.39. The Holy Ghost existed from Eternity; but He was not respecting that <HI>peculiar Dispensati∣on</HI> and manifestation of Him, which the Church was favour'd with, after Christ's Ascension.</P>
<P N="3">III. <HI>WHAT is implied in Asking the Holy Spirit? How must we attend this Duty?</HI> Now as we have already observed, the Word signifies earnestly to desire any thing, and humbly to beg it. It intends humble and earnest Prayer. And thus the Word is us'd, Jam. 1.5. If any of you lack wisdom, <HI>let him ask of God—</HI> And then, we must Ask in a right manner, from a right principle, and for a right end.</P>
<P N="1">1. IN Asking of God His Holy Spirit, <HI>we must offer up our hearty Desires to Him.</HI> When we come before God to Ask His Holy Spirit, we must be duly sensible how needful and excellent a Blessing this is, and accordingly express to God the inward desires and breathings of our Souls after it. We must obey that Word, Psal. 62, 8—. <HI>Pour out your hearts before him—.</HI> We must desire and value this great Blessing, other∣wise our Asking it will be but an empty Compliment, yea a mocking of God. We must thirst for this living Water, the plentiful Effusions of the Holy Spirit. As <HI>David</HI> longed, and said, <HI>Oh that one would
<PB N="10" REF="003103_0012_0FEFA6784C43D0F8"/>
give me drink of the water of the well of Beth∣lehem</HI><NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">2 Sam. 23.15.</NOTE> So must we long for these holy Waters, and from our Hearts say, O that God wou'd Pour out His Spirit upon us! And then express our hearty Desires to God in Prayer. The thirsty are invited to Come and drink, <HI>Job.</HI> 7.37. There may be true Prayer without the <HI>Voice,</HI> but not without the <HI>Heart;</HI> there must be the Voice of the inward man.</P>
<P N="2">2. <HI>WE must Ask of God His Holy Spirit in a due sense of our own Sinfulness and Un∣worthiness.</HI> God gives Grace to the Hum∣ble, but knows the Proud afar off: And therefore when we come before Him with our Requests and Petitions, we must come under an abasing sense of our own empti∣ness and unworthiness. We must be sen∣sible that we are empty of all spiritual Good, till the Holy Spirit is Communica∣ted to us, and that we are less than the least of God's Mercies, and therefore most unworthy of so great a Blessing. We must ask as Beggars ask an Alms. Thus the Word is used, <HI>Act.</HI> 3.2. As we are spiri∣tually poor, so we must have a gracious Poverty of Spirit while attending this Duty.</P>
<P N="3">3. WE must Ask <HI>in the Name of our Lord
<PB N="11" REF="003103_0013_0FEFA69DB4B3D240"/>
Jesus Christ, and in the exercise of Faith upon God as our Father in Him,</HI> Joh. 16.23.— Verily, verily, I say unto you, <HI>Whatsoever ye shall ask the Father in my Name, he will give it you.</HI> ver. 24. — <HI>Ask, and ye shall re∣ceive —.</HI> Our Saviour here requires His Disciples to make an explicit and express mention of His Name in Prayer. When we come before God, we must not come in our own name; but make mention of the Name of Christ, who is worthy, and hath purchased the Gift of the Holy Ghost to be Communicated to His People. Now asking in the Name of Christ doth not intend meerly our making mention of the Name of Christ in our Prayers, but also our believing and intire Dependance on Him, His Merit and Mediation, for audi∣ence and acceptance with God. He is our great <HI>High Priest,</HI> and our <HI>Advocate</HI> with the Father. He appears in the Presence of God for us, as a Lamb that had been slain; His Blood was offer'd once for all, and it hath a Voice to plead for us; it speaks <HI>better things than the blood of Abel.</HI> He sits in Heaven as a Priest on a Throne, and is that <HI>Angel who offers much incense with the Prayers of the Saints</HI> upon the golden Altar which is before the Throne. And when the smoke of the Incense with the Prayers of the Saints,
<PB N="12" REF="003103_0014_0FEFA67DB827CB20"/>
ascends up before God out of the Angel's Hand, God smells a sweet savour in these spiritual Sacrifices, and hath a gracious regard unto them for His Son's sake. See Rev. 8.3, 4. We then who are Sinners, and have our best Duties defil'd with this accursed thing, must take our Encourage∣ment from the Merits of Christ, who hath a just Claim by Purchase, to this Compre∣hensive Blessing; and ask in His Name who is the Mediator between God &amp; Man. And then, having such an High Priest, Je∣sus the Son of God, we should <HI>come boldly to the Throne of Grace, thot we may obtain mercy, and find grace to help in time of need,</HI> Heb. 4.16. We must thro' Christ have our Faith in God, and come in humble Confi∣dence as Children to a Father, believing that God is able and ready to bestow a Fathers Blessing upon us. He that cometh to God must <HI>believe that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently seek him,</HI> Heb. 11.6. We must believe that God is such an One as He reveals Himself in His Word, and in the face of Jesus Christ. Particularly, that He is rich in Mercy to all that Call upon Him. Without Faith we cannot please God in this Duty of Prayer, Jam. 1.6. <HI>Let him ask in Faith no∣thing wavering—.</HI> Believe, and you shall receive what you ask agreeable to God's
<PB N="13" REF="003103_0015_0FEFA67AAF4C7D70"/>
Will, either <HI>in specie,</HI> or in <HI>true value.</HI></P>
<P N="4">4. <HI>WE must he servent, and continue in∣stant in this Duty.</HI> This we are taught in our Context, ver. 9, 10. We must ask, seek and knock. We must be importunate, as ver. 8. Jam. 5.16. —<HI>The effectual servent prayer of a righteous man availeth much.</HI> The <HI>inwrought Prayer.</HI> He that asks coldly, asks a dental<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">Qui srigide rogat, docet negare.</NOTE> We must be servent in Spirit if we would obtain the gracious Answer of our Prayers. We must strive and wrestle in holy earnestness, as <HI>Jacob</HI> did, whose wrestling was accompanied <HI>with weeping and supplication,</HI> Hos. 12.4. And thus he had power over the <HI>Angel,</HI> over the <HI>Son of God,</HI> who is Jehovah, and pre∣vailed. If we would not seek in vain, we must approve ourselves the genuine Sons of <HI>Jacob,</HI> and refuse to let the Lord go till He bless us. I may say with great reve∣rence that God delights to be thus over∣come by His People, i, e. <HI>He who is Almighty, is most willing to yield to their importunate Prayers,</HI> Again, we must continue instant in this Duty: As we are commanded. <HI>Rom,</HI> 12.12. We <HI>must pray always, watching there∣unto with perseverance.</HI> Eph, 6.18. If God seem to shut out our Prayers, we must Pray the more earnestly, and never cease till we obtain the Answer of Prayer. Such
<PB N="14" REF="003103_0016_0FEFA68006391420"/>
Petitions never return empty, but always obtain of God either the very thing we ask for, or that which is better for us.</P>
<P>FROM what hath been said of the nature of the Duty, and of the right manner of attending it, it is plain that the Asking here spoken of is a Duty which none but the Children of God, who have the Spirit of Adoption, can discharge aright; and they are oblig'd to ask that they may receive the Holy Ghost in more plentiful measures, which seems nextly intended in our Text, However, unregenerate Persons are also in∣dispensibly obliged to attend this moral Duty of Prayer, and to ask of God the Spirit of Grace and Supplication, that they may do it in a light manner. That moral impotency which is natural to us since the Fall, and consists very much in the rebel∣lion of our Wills against God &amp; His Law doth not abridge God's Power to Command. And then there are those general Promises, If I may so call them, made to the Children and People of God, of the plentiful Effu∣sions of the Spirit, as are a gracious en∣couragement even to such as are now desti∣tute of saving Grace, to ask of God His Holy Spirit. Who knows, but you may be the happy Subjects of this great Bene∣fit? It is not only possible, but probable, if you are now under the Convictions of
<PB N="15" REF="003103_0017_0FEFA69F411CF150"/>
God's Holy Spirit, O seek then, God is not wont utterly to forsake such, unless they resist His holy Spirit st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iving with them. I may further say, it is a much less evil to fail in the manner of our at∣tending this Duty of Prayer, than wholly to neglect it.</P>
<P N="4">IV. <HI>WHY should we Ask of God His Holy Spirit?</HI></P>
<P N="1">Ans. 1. <HI>BECAUSE this is God's Will and Command. God's Will</HI> reveal'd in His Word is to be made <HI>our Rule</HI> and Directory in Prayer, and in every part of Religious Worship. If we ask any thing of God it must be agreable to his Will, I <HI>Job.</HI> 5 14. This is the Confidence that we have in Him, <HI>that if we ask any thing according to his will, be he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reth us</HI> Now that this is the Will of God, our next and context snew us. And in those Eva gel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cal Pro∣mises which we have, <HI>Ezek</HI> 36. among which is that good Word, ver. 27. <HI>I will put my spirit within you.</HI> It is added ver. 37. Thus faith the Lord God, <HI>I will for this he inquired of by the house of Israel to do it for them.</HI> — God would do it; but in such a manner that He would be acknowledged as the hearer of Prayer. The Blessing promised must be sought of God, that it might be given in answer to Prayer. The Spirit of God is promis'd as a <HI>Spirit of Sup∣plications,</HI>
<PB N="16" REF="003103_0018_0FEFA682749C8568"/>
Zech. 12. 10. And then it is promis'd in the beginning of the 13th. Chap. <HI>In that day there shall be a fountain open'd—.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. <HI>THE Advancement of the Glory of God and the Kingdom of Christ in the World, very much depends on this; and therefore we should ask of God this great Blessing.</HI> Our Saviour hath directed us to Pray for the Advance∣ment of God's Honour and Glory in the first place—. <HI>Hallowed be thy Name, thy Kingdom come, &amp;c.</HI> Now when we ask of God His Holy Spirit to be poured out upon us, upon our Children, and upon all Flesh, we do in effect ask that God's Name may be hallowed, for we are utterly unable and indisposed, yea averse to this since the Fall, and must be formed by the Spirit of God to shew forth his Praise, if ever we give glory to Him in a right manner. We shall never sanctify the Lord, unless He renew and sanctify us by His Spirit. And then in order to the increasing and flourish∣ing of Christ's Kingdom, the Spirit of God must be poured out to qualify Ministers to Preach the Gospel of the Kingdom, and to make the Ordinances effectual to Salvation. Agreably our Saviour directed His Disci∣ples to wait for the promise of the Father; assu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing them they should receive Power after that the Holy Ghost was come upon
<PB N="17" REF="003103_0019_0FEFA6A302016D80"/>
them, <HI>Act.</HI> 1.4,—8. And promis'd to send His holy Spirit, <HI>to reprove the World of Sin, of Righteousness, and of Judgment,</HI> Joh, 16. 7, —11. If Sinners are convinced of the deadly evil of Sin, particularly of the Sin of <HI>Unbelief,</HI> and of the suitableness and sufficiency of Christ's Righteousness for their Justification in the sight of God, it is the Holy-Spirit of God that wrought the Conviction. The Apostles themselves were in this respect, <HI>but Ministers by whom God's People believed, even as the Lord gave to every man,</HI> 1 Cor. 3.5. The quickning Influences of the Spirit are necessary to make the Ordinances a favour of life unto life. Men will not fear God, and give Glory to Him unless the Spirit of Grace come mightily upon them. When the, Word of God is accompanied by the Spirit, then the Son of God rides prosperously, and such as were His Enemies fall down∣under Him, being subdued to the Obedience of Faith. Act. 2.41. <HI>Then they that gladly received his word, were baptized; and the some day there were added unto them about three thousand souls.</HI> Surely then, we are oblig'd to ask of God His Holy Spirit, as we are oblig'd to seek the Glory of God, and the Advancement of His Kingdom among Men, God's Honour should be nearer to us than any temporal Interest of our own.</P>
<P N="3"><PB N="18" REF="003103_0020_0FEFA684C528B978"/>3. <HI>THIS is the most needed and excellent Blessing.</HI> When God gives His Spirit, He blesseth His People with all spiritual Blessings in Heavenlies in Christ Jesus, It is of the Spirit that God's People are <HI>born again,</HI> Joh. 3. 5. By the Spirit they are united to Christ, and so obtain an interest in all the saving Benefits He hath pur∣chased. When God gives His Spirit, He gives Grace and Glory, and every good thing. All good things are either formally or virtually included in this Gift. And therefore we should ask it of God, otherwise we shall he greatly wanting to our selves, and not consult our best good and advan∣tage.</P>
<P N="4">4. <HI>THIS is the way to obtain Outward good things with God's Blessing.</HI> If we do thus seek first the Kingdom of God, other things shall be added, "as far as shall be for God's Glory and our own good", and we shall have God's fatherly Blessing with them. Thus when God had promised of old to put His Spirit within His People, it follows,<HI>ye shall dwell in the land I gave to your fa∣thers—</HI>Ezek. 36.27, 28, 29. <HI>I will call for the Corn, and increase it.</HI> But now tem∣poral Prosperity without this Blessing will prove that of fools which destroys them. It God give a People fulness of Bread and take His Spirit from them, they will de∣clare
<PB N="19" REF="003103_0021_0FEFA6A539EB4158"/>
their Sin like <HI>Sodom,</HI> abusing God's good Creatures to His dishonour, and their own destruction, <HI>Psal.</HI> 106.15.78, 29, 31. Thus God threatned them, Mal. 2.2. <HI>I will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urse your Blessings—.</HI> But when God gives His Spirit He blesseth His People indeed; for then the Creatures of God are good to them, <HI>being sanctified by the word and prayer,</HI> I Tim. 4.4, 5,</P>
<P N="5">V. WE come now to prove the Doctrine; <HI>That our Heavenly Father will give His Holy Spirit to them that Ask Him.</HI> Now this is evident in that <HI>Christ the faithful Witness <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stifies it.</HI> He is the only bego-ten Son of God, and was sent to declare His Fathers Will<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">Joh. 1.18</NOTE>; and seeing the Father and He are One, He can't be deceived, nor deceive us. I shall here just hint at a few things.</P>
<P N="1">I. <HI>GOD is our Heavenly Father, &amp; therefore He will give His Holy Spirit to them that ask Him. — How much more shall your heavenly Father —</HI> Hath God put such a strong and invincible Affection in Parents towards their Children, that they think nothing too good or too much for them, nothing that they judge is convenient and proper for them; and shall not God our Heavenly Father much father give His Holy Spirit,
<PB N="20" REF="003103_0022_0FEFA68714D52140"/>
and in and with Him all good things to His Children? Most certainly He will <HI>He hath not spared his own son, but delivered him up for us all, how shall be not with him also freely give us all things?</HI> Rom. 8 32, Is God our Father in this peculiar sense; why then; God hath sent forth His Son made of a Woman — that we might <HI>re∣ceive the Adoption of Sons,</HI> Gal. 4.4, 5. And because ye are Sons, <HI>God hath sent <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orth the sprit of his son into your hearts, crying Abba Father,</HI> ver. 6. And will not God hear the Cries of His Children, when the Holy Spi∣rit himself helps their Infirmities, and make Intercession in them, Rom. 8.26, 27. most certainly He will; they shall have the Holy Spirit more abundantly. God's coming into this Relation of a Father in Christ, is the most wonderful testimony of His Love, I Joh. 3.1. <HI>Behold what manner of love the father hath bestowed upon us, that we should be called the sons of God.</HI> God is the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ in an appropriate sense, as He is His only be∣gotten by eternal and ineffable Generation <Q>He is such a Son as was begotten of the substance of His Father, even as he that is said to be a Man's own natural Son, useth to be</Q> <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Dr.</HI> Goodwin.</NOTE> And then, He is our
<PB N="21" REF="003103_0023_0FEF966D40CE3CE0"/>
Father by the Grace of Adoption in Him: We being united to Christ, and spiritu∣ally one with Him according to the tenour of the New Covenant; He being our Lord and Husband, we may call His Father our Father, Joh 20.17. I ascend to <HI>my Father,</HI> and <HI>your Father,</HI> &amp;c. And surely when such Children ask the Holy Spirit that they, may more and more resemble their Hea∣venly Father, and do His Will more per∣fectly, He will not deny them. No! they are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eirs of God, and in giving His Spirit God gives a Fathers Blessing, a Child's Portion.</P>
<P N="2">2. I might further Confirm this Truth by considering <HI>the great and precious Promises made to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of God.</HI> I shall give one text instead of many, <HI>Isai</HI> 44.3. I will pour Water upon h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m that is thirsty,—<HI>I will pour my sprit upon thy seed, and my blessing upon thine s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing.</HI> This is the great New-Testament <Q>Promise, that God having sent His Servant Christ, and upheld Him, would send His Spirit to uphold us.<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">Mr. Henry.</NOTE></Q> The words may denote a plentiful <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffusion of the Sprit in his purifying re∣freshing and fructisying influences, even as when the Heavens pour down abundance of Rain, and the thirsty Earth is enriched
<PB N="22" REF="003103_0024_0FEFA6895031B4C8"/>
with the River of God which is full of Water, <HI>Psal</HI> 65. <HI>Isai.</HI> 32.15. God that cannot lie hath pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mised this great Blessing to His People. Surely then, God will not deny His Spirit to such as express the longing Desires of their thirsty Souls in Prayer to God for Him, Mat. 5.6 <HI>blessed are they which do hunger &amp; thirst after righte∣ousness: for they shall be filled.</HI></P>
<P>Again, 3. <HI>GOD is a God hearing Prayer.</HI> This is one of the Titles given Him in Scripture, Psal 65.2. <HI>O thou that hearest Prayer—.</HI> God is rich in Mercy to them that call upon Him— I said not to the <HI>Seed of Jacob, seek ye me in vain,</HI> Isai 25.19. ver. 11. <HI>Thus saith the Lord, the holy One of Israel, and his Maker, Ask me of th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ngs to com<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, concerning my sons, &amp; concerning the work of my hands command ye me.</HI><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The gracious Answer w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ich God is giving, is we may hope, to the Prayers of his People, in the <HI>good <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> made and reviv'd on many, particularly of our Young Peo∣ple, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Earthquake,</HI> hath been an Encouragem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt to me to publish t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is small <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> at this time. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> God, and be Excited to pray more earnestly for his Spirit, to work a gene<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>al and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Reformation. O that such as are un<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> might not draw back to P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ition, but believe to th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> saving of their Souls! Prov. 1.23 <HI>Turn you at my r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>proof, behold, I will pour <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> unto you.</HI></NOTE></P>
<DIV2 TYPE="application">
<HEAD>APPLICATION</HEAD>
<P>USE. I. <HI>LET us believe the Divinity of the Holy Ghost, &amp; Worship Him as God.</HI> The
<PB N="23" REF="003103_0025_0FEFA6A92D0EF150"/>
Holy Ghost is God. This the Scriptures testify, as we have heard, and this his Works declare. He that is the Sanctifier of God's People; the Author and Dispen∣ser of all divine Grace &amp; Consolation, must be a Divine Person. Let us then ascribe Divine Honours, Blessing, Glory &amp; Power to the Father, the Son, &amp; the Holy Spirit. Three Persons; but One God. And let it not discourage us that this great Mystery of our holy Religion is to us incomprehen∣sible; for the God whom we Adore is Infi∣nite, &amp; therefore incomprehensible to our finite minds; And He who is the Truth, plainly reveals this to us in His Word, and the Children of God that receive this Re∣velation of God concerning Himself, they live by it, and their enlightned minds do Acquiesce in it, which cou'd not be if it offer'd Violence to any Faculty, or Contra∣dicted right Reason.</P>
<P N="2">2. <HI>LET us give the Holy Spirit the Glory of His Works.</HI> We have heard that in giving the Spirit, God Communicates all saving Good to His People, and therefore we must in a Religious manner Ascribe the effectu∣al Application of the Redemption Pur∣chas'd by Christ to the Holy Spirit. We must give Him the Glory of all His Gifts and Spiritual Operations on the Souls of Men, and take heed we do not ascribe them
<PB N="24" REF="003103_0026_0FEFA68AD6CA07B8"/>
to another either in whole, or in part. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> we savingly Converted? This is the work of the Spirit, and we must say. <HI>Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy Name be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Glory.</HI></P>
<P N="3">3. <HI>LET us bless our Heavenly Father for the Gese of the holy Ghost.</HI> As we ought to bless God for that <HI>unspeakable Gist, His only Son,</HI> so we must bless Him or this <HI>Compre∣hensive Gist of the Holy Ghost,</HI> without which we could never obtain the Benefits pur∣chased by Christ, being dead in Sins, and altogether without strength. Let us then Adore the God and Father of our Lord Je∣sus Christ, for this New Testament Blessing beltow'd on His Church and People in an eminent manner after Christ's Ascension. The Disciples of Christ were directed by our Lord to wait for the promise of the Father, <HI>Even the Baptism of the Holy Ghost,</HI> Act. 1.4, 5. And we find they did not wait in vain; for when the Day of Pentecost was fully come — <HI>they were all filled with the holy Ghost,</HI> Act. 2. which <HI>Peter</HI> declares was spoken of by the Prophet <HI>foel. And it shall come to pass in the last days (saith God) I will pour out of my spirit upon all flesh: and your sons and your daughters shall prophesie, &amp; your young men shall see visions—,</HI> Act. 2. 16,— 18. And when we bless God for what He
<PB N="25" REF="003103_0027_0FEFA6AD02FB2F00"/>
hath done in this regard, let us encourage our selves to Pray &amp; Wait for the further and more full Accomplishment of His Pro∣mises towards the close of the Gospel-Day.</P>
<P N="4">4. <HI>LET us be Exhorted &amp; Encouraged to Ask of God His Holy Spirit.</HI> We are met together this Day to seek to God, that He would pour out His Spirit upon us, in par∣ticular upon the <HI>Rising Generation.</HI> And surely if we duly consider the Awful with∣drawments of the Spiritual Presence of God, the lamentable decay of the Power of Godliness, and the great abounding of Iniquity among us, we shall find gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t reason to say, as Hos. 10.12. — <HI>It is time to seek the Lord, till he come and rain righte∣ousness upon us.</HI> Our Heartsmay well trem∣ble for the Arkof God, &amp; we had need cry to Him that He would not utterly forsake us. We have in a dreadful manner vexed the Holy Spirit that hath been striving with us by Ordinances and Providences. And now it seems as if the Holy Spirit did in a great measure cease striving with Men. Few comparatively have any remarkable Convictions under the Preaching of the Word. Conversions are rare, and dubious. God spake the last Year to us, espe∣cially to our Young People, by His
<PB N="26" REF="003103_0028_0FEFA690B7797E08"/>
Word, and by His Rod<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">The Small-Pox: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> which, the <HI>Minister</HI> that carried on the <HI>Thursday Lecture in Boston</HI> were <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a <HI>Course of Sermons on Early Piety:</HI> I hope to the saving advantage of not a few who d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d by that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</NOTE>. The Visitation was very general, and the Slain of the Lord were many; but alas! it is not followed with a <HI>General Reformation.</HI> Indeed I hope there hath been some good fruit of this grievous Chastisement visible on the <HI>Survi∣vours,</HI> for which we owe our humble Thanks to the God of all Grace; but alas! there is but little compar'd with what God may justly expect. We find by sad experience. that outward means are in themselves in∣sufficient to reform us: Notwithstanding them we shall grow worse &amp; worse, unless God send His Holy Spirit to work with and by them. O then let us seek of God His Holy Spirit to revive His Work among us and that importunately and incessently, be∣ing sensible of our great need of His saving Influences.</P>
<P>AND here I wou'd direct the Exhortation, 1. To Parents and Elder Persons. 2. To Children and Young People.</P>
<P N="1">1. <HI>TO Parents, and Elder Persons, Be you Exherted to Cry to God for the plentiful <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ssu∣sions of the Holy Spirit.</HI> Seek to God to pour out His Spirit upon you, and then upon your Children. In the first place, <HI>Ask of
<PB N="27" REF="003103_0029_0FEFA68D2D7C39E0"/>
God His Holy Spirit for your selves,</HI> and take heed you do not continue secure in a graceless state, destitute of this great Bles∣sing. If you are not concerned about this your selves, how shall you seek it for your Children? If you have not the Holy Spi∣rit your selves, how shall you Pray aright for them, or instruct them, or set them a good Example? If you are <HI>sensual not having the Spirit;</HI> Worldly, Proud, Passio∣nate; this will be a sore Temptation to them, and may be a means to harden them in Sin. If you reglect to seek after <HI>Baptism,</HI> or to <HI>renew your Baptismal Covenant,</HI> this may dreadfully hinder their entring into Cove∣nant with God. If you live in the neglect of the <HI>Ordinance of the Supper,</HI> this may lay a dreadful stumbling block in their way, and embolden them to neglect that great Command which our Lord hath given to His Disciples, Luk. 22.19. <HI>Do this inre∣membrance of me.</HI> O be you then Exhorted to Cry to God for the Holy Spirit your s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lves, that you may be in all the Com∣mandments and Ordinances of the Lord blameless. If you obtain the Spirit of Grace, then you will be enabled to seek to God for your Childien. And then, <HI>Ask of God His Spirit for your Children,</HI> your own Bowels. Travail in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>irth again with them till Christ be formed in them Pray without ceasing,
<PB N="28" REF="003103_0030_0FEFA692F481ECD0"/>
and with holy importunity! Bring them to God, and cry to Him to Convert &amp; heal their Souls. Imitate the <HI>Woman of Canaan</HI> who cryed to our Lord to heal her Daugh∣ter that was vexed with a Devil. At first Christ answered not a word; but still she cried after Him. Then He seem'd to up∣braid her, — <HI>It is not meet to take the chil∣dren's bread, and to cast it to Dogs.</HI> Instead of being discouraged, she makes a Plea of this; <HI>Truth Lord, yet the Dogs eat of the Crumbs that fall from their masters table</HI> Up∣on which our Saviour answered, <HI>O woman great is thy faith: be it unto thee even as thou wilt,</HI> Mar. 15.22, —28. A bold Faith truly, but not so bold as welcome. You can remember how much you were con∣cerned for their outward man when endan∣gered by the late Sickness: And will you not be as much concerned for their Souls, which are under a more dangerous Distem∣per by the Fall, and that an hereditary one which you have been instrumental of con∣veying to them? most certainly you shou'd. As Children of the first <HI>Adam</HI> they are un∣der the Curse of God's broken Covenant, and in danger of the second Death which is eternal. O be earnest with God then to give them His Holy Spirit, that being united to <HI>Christ the second Adam,</HI> they may obtain the Blessings of the New Covenant.
<PB N="29" REF="003103_0031_0FEFA6AF47159558"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> this way yen should carry your little Ones to the Great God our Saviour for His Blessing, who hath said, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uffer little Children and forbid them not, to come unto we, for of such is ibe kingdom of heaven,</HI> Mat, 19.14, And thus you should bring your Chil∣dren that are grown up, and ask of God His Holy Spirit to renew and change their Hearts. As <HI>David</HI> prayed for <HI>Solomon,</HI> I Chron. 29. 19, <HI>Give unto Solemn my son a perfect heart.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. LET this Exhortation be directed <HI>to our Children and Young People.</HI> O be you Exhorted &amp; Encouraged to Ask of God His Holy Spirit. It is with an especial regard to you that we are Assembled this Day: Your Parents and Pastors are concerned for you, and earnestly desirous that you may be the Offspring which the Lord hath blessed; and therefore they unite in seek∣ing to God for His Spirit to be given to you. And will not you join with them in asking this most needed Blessing? Cer∣tainly you should with great importunity; for you will be accursed for ever unless you obtain it. You were by Nature dead in Trespasses and Sins, and Children of Wrath even as others, and stand in abso∣lute need of the Holy Spirit to renew a right Spirit in you. Unless you are born from above, born of the Spirit, it had been
<PB N="30" REF="003103_0032_0FEFA694812F63F8"/>
better for you that you had not been born. However, you are generally the Children of the Covenant, and to you <HI>pertaineth the Adaption,</HI> Rom. 9.4. You have been <HI>Bap∣tized—</HI> O seek to God then that He would Baptize you with the Holy Ghost. You have heard how ready our Heavenly Father is to give His Spirit to them that ask him. Ask then, and you shall receive. O dear Children! Go to your Heavenly Fa∣ther in the Name of Christ, say, My Father! <HI>be thou the Guide of my Youth.</HI> O give me thy Spirit to unite me to thy Son, &amp; to form thine Image on my depraved Soul. I am blind, Open the eyes of my Understanding by the anointing of the Holy Spirit; my carnal mind is enmity against God, it is not subject to thy Law, neither can be, O subdue it: my Affections are vile, O purify them! Thus Call upon God &amp; Cry to Him. And do not cease 'till a saving Change be wro't on your Souls. You mult turn from all Sin unto God, and receive the Lord Jesus Christ by Faith, or perish forever. Do not then depend on this, that you have <HI>Abraham to your Father,</HI> and are the Children of the Covenant, as if your Parents Faith would save you. But remember that awful word, Mar. 8.11, 12. <HI>Many shall come from the east and west &amp; shall sit down with Abraham, Isaac and Jacob in the kingdom of heaven, But the
<PB N="31" REF="003103_0033_0FEFA6B0CD0509D0"/>
children of the kingdom shall be cast out into outer darkness: there shall be weeping and. g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ashing of teeth.</HI> Seek to God then to save you by the washing of Regeneration, and the renewing of the Holy Ghost. You must bear good fruit, or be cut down and cast into the fire, <HI>Mat.</HI> 8.9, 10. Don't satisfy your selves with the blaze of an outward Profession, but bring your empty Vessels that they may be fill'd with the Oyl of saving Grace. Open your Mouths wide, enlarge your Desires, and God will fill them. You are not straitned in God; O be not straitned in your own bowels! Now seek, and you shall find. The time of Youth is probably the <HI>Accepted time</HI> with the most that are Converted, &amp; who enjoy Gospel-Priviledges from their Child hood, And it may be your <HI>only time</HI> for working out your Salvation. Many of your Age hare lately been removed by Death; Do you then Re∣member now your Creator in the Days of Youth, and seek Christ early.</P>
<P>I might offer many M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tives to Excite and Quicken you to this Duty; but shall further only say:</P>
<P>Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sider, <HI>You can't serve your Generation accord∣ing to the Will of God, unless He give you His Holy Spirit.</HI> Our <HI>Fathers</HI> are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Stage; you are rising up and coming upon the S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r of Action. In a little time the Aftairs of Chist's Visible King∣dom mutt he dev<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ved upon you. And let me tell you, an awful Trust this is, and wo <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o you if you betray it. Our Fore-fathers came into this Land when
<PB N="32" REF="003103_0034_0FEFA696D81C1A98"/>
it was an how<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g Wilderness, that they might Own Christ as the only Lord and Lawgiver of His Church, and enjoy Communion with Him and His People in the Purity of His Ordinances, without the Corrupt mixture of humane I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ventions in Religious Worship. And no doubt they had an especial regard to their Posterity herein; for they themslves were not in so much danger of being defi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d. God was eminently with them. God own'd the Ministry of this Country by many Seals of it, in the great Numbers that were born to God here. Many were declar'd to be the Epistle of Christ written not with ink, but with the Spirit of die living God, 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 33. However, in this degenerate Day, it is probable you will be tempted to break the Second Commandment; for the purity and power of Godli∣ness commonly decay together. Yea, in this Evil Day, there are dreadful Temptations utterly to forsake the God of your Fathers. Now there is nothing can pre∣serve you from this Apostacy but the Spiritual Presence of God with you by His Spirit. Unless He enlighten your Minds, you will not know the God of your Fa∣thers; Unless He renew and sanctify you, you will not feel the power, nor taste the Sweetness of Religion. You will account the great Things of God's Law a strange thing: you will preser the World and your Lusts before Christ and His Unsearchable Ric<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, and will fall an easy Prey to them who lie in wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to de∣ceive. O seek to God then to give you His Holy Spirit. And now <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>-Him as your <HI>Sanctifier Guide,</HI> and <HI>Comforter.</HI> T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er God will be with you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s He was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> our Fathers, He will never leave you, nor forsake you. I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Rev 22 17 <HI>The Spirit and the Bride say come and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, say Come and let him that is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, Come: And who∣soever will, let him take the water of life freely.</HI> Ep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 3 20, 21. <HI>Now unto him that is able to d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> exceed∣ing abundantly above all that we <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>work<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> think, accor∣ding to the power that worketh in us, Unto him be glory in the church by Christ Jesus throughout all ages, world without end. Amen.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

