<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2010-02-25</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Did text and markup review.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N26590">
<STC T="E">35364</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99027832</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="035364_0000_1004A13147D5C878"/>
<PB REF="035364_0001_1004A13401107218" MS="y"/>
<P><HI>The present Times perilous.</HI></P>
<P>A SERMON, PREACHED AT <HI>SULLIVAN,</HI> ON THE NATIONAL FAST, APRIL 25, 1799.</P>
<P>BY ABRAHAM CUMMINGS, A. M.</P>
<P>Printed for DAVID J. WATERS, CASTINE.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="sermon">
<PB REF="035364_0002_1004A1371AC31300"/>
<HEAD>A SERMON.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><BIBL><HI>2 TIMOTHY iii. 1—9.</HI></BIBL>
<P>In the last days perilous times shall come: For men shall be lovers of their own selves, covetous, boasters, proud, blas∣phemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy, without natural affection, truce-breakers, false accusers, incontinent, fierce, despisers of these who are good, trai∣tors, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleasures more than lovers of God; having a form of godliness, but denying the power thereof: from such turn away. For of this sort are they who creep into houses, and lead captive silly wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>n laden with sins, led away with divers lusts; ever learning, and never able to con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> to the l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>dge of the truth. Now, as Jannes and Jambres with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Moses, s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> do these also, resist the truth: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>n of corrupt minds, repr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rning the faith. But they shall proceed <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> farther; for th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r folty shall be manifest unto all men, as theirs also was.</P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>THE works of the Lord are great, sought out of all them who have pleasure therein. How fre∣quently and plainly are we enjoined by the voice of Scripture to behold the works of the Lord and consid∣er the operation of his hands—To consider how Infi∣nite Wisdom determines the character and condition of men and the different ages of the world. Our Lord reproved the Jews for not discerning the signs of the
<PB N="4" REF="035364_0003_1004A13AEA8909C0"/>times. Hence the advice before us. This know also that in the last days perilous times shall come, &amp;c.</P>
<P>If it was necessary for Timothy to know this, it can∣not be less necessary for us to know it, who are so much more interested in the events of the last days than Timothy could be, or any other person in that age of the world. Let us then consider,</P>
<P><HI>What time is here intended by the last days:</HI></P>
<P>And, <HI>How it appears that the character of men in the last days fulfils the prophecy in view.</HI></P>
<P N="1">I. What time is here intended by the last days.</P>
<P>The scripture mentions, at least, two important pe∣riods by this appellation: The last days of the Jews and the last days of the Christians. <HI>Gather yourselves together,</HI> said Jacob to his sons, <HI>that I may tell you that which shall befal you in the last days,</HI> i. e. the last times of the Jewish dispensation. <HI>God, who at sundry times and in divers manners, spake in time past unto the fathers by the prophets,</HI> says Paul, <HI>hath in these last days spoken unto us by his Son.</HI> Here also it is plain that the phrase means <HI>the last days of the Jewish dispensation.</HI> But in our text the phrase is spoken in the future tense, and therefore must signify the last days of the Christian dispensation. Such are the present days. It is allow∣ed by the most excellent commentators, that the mo∣ment is very near when time shall be no longer; when the mystery of God shall be finished; when the Millen∣nium, the third dispensation of the gospel, shall com∣mence, and when Christ will destroy the man of sin by the brightness of his coming; but this will further appear if we consider,</P>
<P N="2">II. How it appears that the character of mankind in these days fulfils the prophecy in view. The pro∣phecy begins by declaring that perilous times shall come, times of great danger. And cannot the friends of religion now see the fulfilment? How perilous are the present times, with regard to the spiritual welfare of mankind! Our father and fathers' fathers never saw such a day as this: such a day of delusion in the
<PB N="5" REF="035364_0004_1004A13C88AD0DD8"/>Christian world. Universalism, Deism and Atheism have set their mouths against the heavens, and laughed at the solemn threatenings of Jehovah. They say unto the wicked, It shall be well with him, and cry, <HI>Peace, peace,</HI> where there is no peace.</P>
<P>The Apostle Peter, writing to Christians in general, foretels this our dreadful apostasy: <HI>There were false prophets also among the people, even as there shall be false teachers among you, who privily shall bring in damnable heresies, even denying the Lord who bought them, and bring upon themselves swift destruction. And many shall follow their pernicious ways, by reason of whom the way of truth shall be evil spoken of.</HI> Those among us, who have the proper use of their eyes, can clearly see the accom∣plishment of those predictions, which tell us that the Christian world, in the last days, shall be filled with all manner of delusions, and pernicious, foolish errors. Our false teachers are now performing the work long since assigned for them, that the scripture may be ful∣filled. Some of them have crept into houses, and led captive silly women, laden with sins, led away with di∣vers lusts. When the infidel false teachers in France published their infamous writings, Mr. Pirie tells us, that the <HI>poisardes</HI> or fish-women of Paris were the first objects of their seduction; and by their means the whole fabric of Church and State was o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> hrow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in an instant.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Weishaupt, the founder of the Illuminees, has given to his regents partic∣ular secret instructions for seducing the women. He says, That the fair sex, having the greatest part of the world at their disposition, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o study was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>re wor∣thy of the adept,</HI> than the art of slattery, in order to gain them.—<HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Consp.</HI> p. 25.</NOTE></P>
<P>Now I ask, what can render the times more perilous than these pernicious and damnable errors, which al∣lure such multitudes to everlasting ruin? 'He who flattereth his neighbour, spreadeth a net for his feet. There is a way which seemeth right unto a man, but the end thereof is the way of death.'</P>
<P>These horrid delusions are the source of horrid im∣moralities, which render the times perilous with regard to temporal life, peace and property! <HI>For men shall be lovers of their own selves,</HI> says the text.</P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="035364_0005_1004A13E54669C48"/>
Men were always lovers of their own selves, in all ages of the world; but now this evil of evils shall greatly prevail. Selfishness is the essence of sin; the fountain of all immorality; and as some wicked men are more selfish than others, so it is not unreasonable to suppose that some wicked ages of men are more self∣ish than others. Accordingly the present age exhibits abundant selfishness. How many are there among us, sus∣taining public offices, and under solemn oaths to main∣tain the cause of virtue and the authority of the laws, who can trample on both to accomplish their own sinister purposes. Innumerable are the forms in which this base principle appears; but I shall particularly attend to those which the text presents to our view.</P>
<P>To shew how self-love should operate in the last days, the text declares that men shall be <HI>covetous, boasters, proud, blasphemers.</HI> Covetousness now appears every where among all ranks of people, each one looking for gain from his quarter. Such horrid robbery and extensive violation of property have lately afflicted the earth and the sea, as were seldom known in former times.</P>
<P>And what age of the world ever heard such boasting as the present? What great swelling words of vanity do we hear from the lips of our infidel sons of liberty! What a treat Patriot was Robespiere in profession, ready to die for his country and the cause of virtue! and was there ever a greater Tyrant? I shall plant the tree of liberty in London next summer, said Dumourier. These are but two, among innumerable instances of this kind, which may be quoted from the history of the present times. The rulers of France have undertook to regenerate the world, and diffuse liberty, peace and happiness every where; and more swelling language never was heard from the tongue of man than has proceeded from the leading part of that infidel assem∣bly, respecting the great good which the world are to receive by their means. The eloquent Abbe Maury, speaking of the great and dreadful change of <HI>times and
<PB N="7" REF="035364_0006_1004A14001167528"/>laws</HI> among them, called it a <HI>b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ed</HI> revolution.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Swelling behaviour is one remarkable property of the frog. Under the sixth vial, now running, John saw 'three <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>lean spirit, like frogs, come out of the mouth of the beast, dragon, and false pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>et<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> enenties to civil society, mor∣ality, and the true religion: 'For they are spirits of devils, working <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> A p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>in allusion to the frogs of Egypt working miracles to overthrow divine revelation as exhibited by Moses. And our frogs hate Moses, with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> whole volume of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>paration, and great are the moral miracles which they are now performing; miracles of wickedness, as foreign to the common course of things in the moral world, as the appearance and conduct of the frongs of Egypt were foreign to the common cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> of things in the natural world. The frogs of Egypt went fort<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, is a plague, unto the chambers of their kings; and our mod∣ern frogs <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> go forth as a plague, unto the kings of the earth, to gather the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>tle of that great day of God Almighty' now at hand.
<P>The language of frogs <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tering a king's palace is this: <HI>We are of a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> importance yet a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; we are all e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>al.</HI> And when we see a company of frogs in their loathsome c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lls, the type of illumi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>m, we obser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>der, no d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣tion with respect to power. They all appear <HI>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ual, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="6 letters" DISP="••••••"/>,</HI> and ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ess. A frog was the ancient hiero<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iyp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> for all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="5 letters" DISP="•••••"/>or.</P></NOTE> And what high, pompous prosessions of patriotism and philanthropy, bubble forth in the gazettes, from one year to another. These we know are the effects of pride; for men shall be <HI>proud</HI> in the last days. Who more proud than he who is wife in his own conceit? and who more wife in his own conceit than he who is wife above what is written, as all our insidels are, while they ridicule every doctrine, every proposition, which a creature of yesterday, a vile worm of the dust cannot comprehend. Accordingly they set their mouth in blasphemy against the heavens, and their tongue walketh through the earth: For men shall be <HI>blasphe∣mers,</HI> says the text. Never before was there so much blasphemy known among mankind as sounds in the world at this day. 'We have no other religion but the Constitution, and no other God but Liberty;' said the infamous Marat, when the petition of the Baptists in France to be released from bearing arms was rejected. The impious Cerutideclared in his expiring moments that the only thing which was matter of regret with him in leaving the world was, that he left a religion on the earth.</P>
<P>Blasphemous catechisms have been published in France, in which the Constitution of the Republic was substituted for God, and the National Assembly for the Saints. Our Saviour's incarnation has been the sub∣ject
<PB N="8" REF="035364_0007_1004A142126BAED8"/>of printed ridicule in the base language of the dregs of the people.</P>
<P>The horrid Massacre at Lyons in the year 1793 was introduced by a procession, which set Heaven and an hereafter at desiance. An ass was dressed in the vest∣ments of Priests, with the Old and New Testament tied to his tail, and made to drink out of the sacramental cup: and, when the procession had arrived to a certain spot of ground prepared for the purpose, the Bible was publickly burnt amid the shouts and rejoicings of the blasphemous assistants. The impious courtezan of Hebert at Paris was on a certain public occasion bril∣liantly dressed, placed on a throne of ivory, and wor∣shipped as the <HI>goddess of Reason;</HI> all with a view to cast contempt on the worship of JEHOVAH. The rulers of France have declared our blessed Lord and Redeem∣er to be an impostor; have prohibited the acknow∣ledgment of him and the exercise of his worship.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">A comedian, during the French revolution, appeared personally attacking Almighty God; saying: "No, thou doit not exist. If thou hast power over the thunder-bolts, grasp them; aim them at the man who dares set thee at de∣fiance in the face of thy altars But no, I blaspheme thee, and I still live. No, thou dost not exist."—<HI>Antisocial Consp.</HI> p 129.</NOTE></P>
<P>But to proceed,</P>
<P>Another evil here predicted is disobedience to pa∣rents. How visible is the difference between family government fifty years since, and that which appears at the present time! There was such a thing as family prayer in former times; it was nothing wonderful for a child to hear his father pray and give religious in∣struction; but now family worship and government are generally neglected, and disobedience in children is the natural consequence. The present age is fa∣voured with great light, abundant knowledge, impor∣tant privileges; but ah! the ingratitude every where manifest! how great their damnation with whom such blessings remain unsanctified! But the text must be fulfilled, <HI>Unthankful, unholy.</HI></P>
<P>The next prediction demands particular notice: <HI>With∣out natural affection.</HI> The prevalence of this evil is now clear to every discerning eye. Kinsmen were more re∣garded
<PB N="9" REF="035364_0008_1004A1481B7CF108"/>formerly than brethren are at present; I think any person may be challenged to find in the whole histo∣ry of mankind so many instances of this depravity, in so short a period, as have disgraced human nature within the last ten years. What person, possessed of natural affection, could murder his whole family at once, as that infidel<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Mr BEABLE, of Weathersfield.</NOTE> did in Connecticut? A similar species of murder was lately attempted in the State of Vermont, by another Deist. For more instances of this kind, look into France, where infidelity reigns triumphant. There hundreds of fathers and mothers have been lately led to prison, and publickly accused by their own chil∣dren, that they might be put to death, for some differ∣ence of sentiment in politics or religion. Our Lord has foretold this as one sign of his second coming— 'Children shall rise up against their parents, and cause them to be put to death.'</P>
<P>Montsoy tells us, that a certain child, about ten years old, having been corrected by his mother for some fault, repaired to the revolutionary tribunal, and accused her of favouring the Christian Religion. The accusation was admitted, the boy recompensed, and the mother executed in a few hours. One Philippe, in Paris, cut off the heads of his father and mother, while they were asleep, and carried them to the Jacobin Club, as a proof of his patriotism. One Goutin, of Nantz, beat his father on his death bed. Many chil∣dren, in that infidel country, have been known not only to despise and ridicule their parents, but to beat and lacerate them in a cruel manner, because they re∣fused the precepts of the new infidel system of politics. The same want of natural affection has been expressed against other relatives. The Abbé Barruel, in his His∣tory of the French Clergy, mentions a father who led his son to death; of one O'Sullivan, who led his brother to the guillotine, after he had cast himself into his arms for protection. And we know that a brother of the late King of France was one of those who sought his destruction.</P>
<P><PB N="10" REF="035364_0009_1004A149EDA71A70"/>
Some of the French officers, when they ravaged Swabia and the banks of the lake of Constance, we are informed, drowned their own children, which they had by their wives and concubines, to avoid the trou∣ble of providing for them.</P>
<P>That infernal Society, styled the <HI>Illuminati,</HI> or <HI>Illumi∣nces,</HI> maintain it, as one of their important doctrines, that natunal affection ought to have no existence, and that marriage, the source of all natural affection, is not only useless but injurious to society,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">It is the modern doctrine of the Ency<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lopedists and the Illuminees, "That the paternal authority ceases with the wants of the children: The father would wrong his children, should he pretend to any authority over them after this pe∣riod." —"All th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ties of nature, as well <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> those of government or religion, says Abbe Ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="5 letters" DISP="•••••"/>" <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>re to be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="6 letters" DISP="••••••"/>d <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>upt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> last My<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="6 letters" DISP="••••••"/>."—<HI>Antise <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI> p. 164. 165.</NOTE>—And the dread∣ful <HI>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>otte</HI> oath spares neither parents, friends, nor relations. How clearly, then, is this prediction veri∣fied before our eyes!</P>
<P>Another character of men which the text mentions are, <HI>truce breakers.</HI></P>
<P>The word <HI>truce,</HI> here means any stipulation, cov∣enant, or agreement, which two or more persons may form with each other. Look now through the land and through the world: do we not find that truces, stipulations, oaths and promises are violated every where? The merchant can tell you how few there are at this day, whose words are more than wind. I do not believe that there was ever a time in which cov∣enants, oaths and promises were more impudently vi∣olated than they are at this day. Are not thousands of oaths broken in America and England annually? Some late French publications inform us, that the con∣stituent assembly of France broke their oaths and promises in the most public manner. The deputies were all furnished with written instructions, in which they were positively enjoined to make no innovations as to the form of government; yet they framed a con∣stitution, by which the government was totally chang∣ed. So every individual of the convention in the year 1792, took an oath to maintain the authority of the
<PB N="11" REF="035364_0010_1004A14E4A69AA28"/>king. What was the consequence? In a few months after, they declared France a republic, and murdered the king. And it would be tedious to enumerate the instances of perfidy which the French have exhibited towards the numerous towns in Europe, which have fallen within the grasp of their insatiable rapacity.</P>
<P>But why should oaths and promises be less regard∣ed now than formerly? The answer is easy: The present age is the age of <HI>reason,</HI> the age of infidelity. Only believe that there is no future misery, no Bible, or no God, and what need you care for oaths or prom∣ises? For the same reason, <HI>false accusers</HI> are multipli∣ed, and the <HI>incontinent, levers of pleasures more than lov∣ers of God.</HI> Here is the figure <HI>meiosis;</HI> q. d. <HI>They shall wallow in carnal pleasures, and be filled with enmity against God.</HI></P>
<P>It is impossible for any discerning person, who has lived forty years, not to perceive how much more nu∣merous intemperate and lascivious persons now are, than formerly, in proportion to the number of people; ruining property, family, body, soul and all forever.</P>
<P>Another characteristic of the last days is expressed by the word <HI>fierce:</HI> What terrible fierceness has ap∣peared in the conduct of our infidel sons of liberty, in promoting the cause of their licentious politics! It would be tedious to enumerate, and horrible to describe the cruelties, the assassinations and massacres in France and other parts of Europe, by which the savage ferocity of these wicked men has been diverted and delighted. In the term of three years, Mr. Harper tells us, that be∣sides those slain in the war, no less than three millions of persons were destroyed in France; of which there were two hundred and fifty thousand women, and two hundred and thirty thousand children.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">My authorities are not particularly quoted; for they are not with me. If the reader desires more contirmation, he may consult <HI>The Cannibal's Progress —The History of Mon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>y—Abb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Barrud's History of the French Clergy—The l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> side View of the Prisons of Paris—The Cruelties of the Jacobins—Robison's Pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s of a C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>spira<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y</HI>—and <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>: Lectures.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P>But we hasten to the next prediction: <HI>Despisers of those who are good.</HI> Good people have always been
<PB N="12" REF="035364_0011_1004A151157EDE60"/>despised in every age; but there is one new doctrine peculiar to these last days, which our infidels are rap∣idly propagating; which is, that <HI>piety, in a candidate for any political office, is no qualification or recommendation at all. Good men, as such, are of no use at all in any public employment of the State.</HI> Can such a doctrine as this gain ground among a people, unless good men are de∣spised as they never were before?</P>
<P>The ministers of the Christian religion too, whether they are Papists or Protestants, are reproached and scoffed at as they never were before, in any former period. They are considered by multitudes as a nui∣sance in society, and a constant impediment to that great <HI>something,</HI> which the boasting and licentious politicians of our age have in store for the liberty and regenera∣tion of mankind.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">What a parsimenious disposition prevails, at this day, with respect to the support of the gospel. This presents a melancholy aspect. The regular and honourable support of religious teachers is opposed by a number who appear conscientious. Little do they consider what they are doing; how much they help the devil; what assistance they afford to our modern enemies of all good order, civil and religious.</NOTE> But believe the prophecy, my hearers; the day, the dreadful day, is near, even at the door, when God will teach the world, by an awful lesson, that our patriotic insidels are as great enemies to the true welfare of civil society as they are to re∣ligion. For the prophecy before us declares, that men shall be <HI>traitors</HI> in the last days. The Apostle Peter, describing the apostasy of the last times, more especial∣ly marks out those for destruction who walk in the lust of uncleanness and despise government. Presump∣tuous are they, he says, self-willed, they are not afraid to speak evil of dignities. He represents them as speaking great swelling words of vanity, and promis∣ing liberty, while they themselves are servants to cor∣ruption. The same are the prophetic ideas of the text: <HI>Traitors, heady, high-minded;</HI> which clearly pre∣signify that men shall countenance licentious politics, and be filled with pride and self-importance. They shall trample on the laws of men, as well as the laws of God, and oppose the best principles of government and sound policy. Accordingly it is impossible for
<PB N="13" REF="035364_0012_1004A15419D60B50"/>any one, who has the proper use of his eyes, not to see what a traitorous, rebellious spirit breathes among mankind at the present day. We are a young people, favoured by Infinite Goodness with some of the best constitutions of government that any nation ever en∣joyed; but, young as we are, and happy as we are in this respect, we are already disgraced by three insurrec∣tions. Many there are among us filled with disgust against the wise measures and even the foundation of our government. Ungrateful people! we know not our privileges—we cannot enjoy them: such is our unreasonable jealousy and discontentment: like the man to whom God has given riches, wealth and hon∣our, so that he wanteth nothing of all that his soul de∣sireth, yet God giveth him not power to eat thereof.</P>
<P>As the minds of men, at this day, are polluted with wicked and licentious principles respecting religion, so they are with respect to politics. The false doctrines of <HI>liberty and equality,</HI> which have contaminated mill∣ions of mankind, have certainly a most pernicious influence in society, and are introductory to all those horrid scenes of insurrection and anarchy, distress of nations and perplexity, which must fulfil the prophetic scriptures in the last days. There are many in our land, who behave as if they esteemed it their indispen∣sable duty to oppose government and reproach the ru∣lers, whenever the mode of administration happens not to coincide with their political ideas. What violent reproaches and misrepresentations have some gazettes poured forth against the principal rulers of our nation, for that course of administration which demands our warm approbation!</P>
<P>But what saith the scripture? 'Thou shalt not speak evil of the ruler of thy people. Thou shalt not revile the gods, nor curse the ruler of thy people.' When the Roman officer demanded tribute of our Lord and Pe∣ter, did they, like some of our great patriots, refuse or oppose the tyranny of the tax? No: 'Lest we should offend,' said Christ to Peter, 'go thou to the sea and cast in a hook, and take up the fish that cometh up first,
<PB N="14" REF="035364_0013_1004A155C33384E0"/>and when thou hast opened it, thou shalt find a piece of money: that take and give unto them, for me and thee.'</P>
<P>Subjection to the powers that be is enjoined by the Apostle upon Christians, as their indispensable duty. Whereby, I think, it is plain, that Christians should never appear the first in political revolutions. That mankind every where should enjoy as much liberty as can be consistent with salutary government, must be con∣sonant to the feelings of every benevolent mind; but insurrection is the last mode of redress that even an oppressed people should ever contemplate.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">When our states suffered that oppression from Britain which occasioned the revolution, petition after petition was sent to the British court, while we suffered injury upon injury, before the sword was unsheathed on our part Every mild method for obtaining relief was adopted. And after all, the ruler of Britain, and no we, were the rebels against the C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nstitution of their gov∣ernment, which plainly prohibited <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>cation without representation.</NOTE> We find in the scriptures very little which can be construed to favour political rebellion. 'The Most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will, and setteth up over it the bas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st of men.' So long as the plurality of mankind are exceedingly de∣praved and wicked, all governments will be afflicted with wicked men and wicked measures, in a less or greater degree. The hand of piety <HI>for the most part</HI> has not swayed the civil sceptre in time past, and we may believe never will, while the present dispensation of the gospel remains. To what purpose then can it be for Christians to be eager in the business of revolu∣tion; to exchange one form of government for anoth∣er? since <HI>true</HI> Christianity, perhaps, will have no more influence under the latter government than under the former. What great benefit can it be to exchange one mode of tyranny for another, and one mode of persecution for another? Political revolutions are fre∣quently political judgments, their circumstances and consequences being far more dreadful than the oppres∣sion which occasioned them. The ten tribes complain∣ed and had reason to complain of the tyranny of Re∣hoboam. Accordingly they revolted. What did they gain by it? Their history declares that their character
<PB N="15" REF="035364_0014_1004A1580146F720"/>was far more abominable, and their condition far more miserable, than they ever were before.</P>
<P>How happy were the Christians in their own view in the days of Constantine, when the old empire was de∣stroyed. Their prospect was all tranquillity and peace: Nothing to do now but to bask in the vernal sun of their great revolution. But clouds, O how black and dismal! soon obscured all this glory. They soon sound that their new government was not the kingdom of heaven, but nourished the man of sin, and more dreadful scenes of persecution and cruelty were now to follow than ever were known before.</P>
<P>Other revolutions, too numerous to particularize, have been attended with similar consequences.</P>
<P>It is a great truth, that some forms of government are better calculated to promote the welfare of society than others; but it is not enough that a constitution be good: it must be in good hands, in the hands, not of Deists and Atheists, but of those who fear God, and hate covetousness; for 'when the righteous bear rule, the city rejoiceth; when the wicked bear rule, the people mourn.' A good constitution in bad hands tends to far greater evils than a bad constitution in good hands.</P>
<P>When therefore a nation are become exceedingly corrupt and degenerate, the mere change of their gov∣ernment will accomplish but a poor purpose. There must be a change of morals as well as government; otherwise their revolution will prove a curse and not a blessing: For still the wicked will bear rule, and still the people will mourn.</P>
<P>It is, therefore, in ordinary cases, not only great wickedness, but extreme folly, for Christians to seek a kingdom in this world by political insurrection; to seek that by insurrection, which Christ has plainly told them they never shall obtain by any means whatever. It is the future kingdom of heaven which Christians are to look for: a kingdom, which will very soon be established on the earth: for the Judge stands before the door, the Millennium is at hand; and then 'the
<PB N="16" REF="035364_0015_1004A15C1D206008"/>greatness of the kingdom under the whole heaven shall be given to the people of the saints of the Most High.' Accordingly we sind that the first disciples were peaceable citizens: we have no account that either Paul, Peter, James, or John, belonged to any republi∣can society or Jacobin Club; though they had far more reason to complain than any class of white people now have, either in America or Britain. They never swore hatred to royalty; but 'submit, say they, to every or∣dinance of man for the Lord's sake; fear God, honour the KING.'</P>
<P>If the observations now made be just, the principles and conduct of multitudes, at this day, are clearly traitor∣ous, and amply fulfil this solemn prediction of the text.</P>
<P>But I hear the voice of objection: "What busi∣ness have the ministers of the gospel with politicians in their preaching!" The answer is, Because politicians have business with them. The ministers of religion in France have had business with infidel politicians, drowning boats and assassinations, because all these have had business with them. Among the many devices of Satan at the present day, this is one, that the teachers of religion have no concern with polities. But had Jeremiah, Ezekiel, and other prophets, no concern in these affairs? Had the Apostles no concern with them, when they taught subjection to rulers? Read your Bibles, and determine. Indispensable is the duty of the watchmen, on the walls of Zion, as they are ena∣bled to discern the signs of the times, to warn the churches and people of their approaching danger.</P>
<P>But to proceed. While many blaspheme the Lord of glory, others oppose him secretly, by the form of god∣liness, while they deny the power, slumbering on the principles of false religion, as on a bed of down; from such, we are exhorted by the text, to turn away, deny ourselves, and take up the cross. Gog and Magog sig∣nify <HI>covered and uncovered,</HI> secret enemies, and open enemies: these are the two grand persecutors of the church, in the last days.</P>
<P><PB N="17" REF="035364_0016_1004A1606B223898"/>
We now attend to the next prediction. <HI>Ever learn∣ing, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth.</HI></P>
<P>The present age exceeds all others for learning; many have run to and fro, and knowledge is increased. Yet vast multitudes are not only destitute of the spirit∣ual knowledge of Christ; but they wander more and more in the mazes of strong delusion, that they all might be damned, who believe not the truth, but have pleasure in unrighteousness. For, says the text, 'Evil men and seducers wax worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived.' For 'as Jannes and Jambres with∣stood Moses, so do these also resist the truth; men of cor∣rupt minds, reprobate concerning the faith.' Jannes and Jambres endeavoured to represent Moses as an im∣postor: so do these men also resist the truth, endeav∣ouring to represent all the prophets as impostors. 'But they shall proceed no further: for their folly shall be manifest unto all men, as theirs also was.' Jannes and Jambres were magi, wise men, who became fools, and were shewn to be such. And our modern magi are wise men, in reality, with regard to the sciences; but professing themselves to be wise with regard to relig∣ion, they become fools; and it will not be long, before God will exhibit them as such to the view of the whole world.</P>
<P>There were giants in the earth, in those days of wickedness which preceded the flood; and there are giants in the earth in these days, with respect to litera∣ture, exerting their wisdom against Heaven. The for∣mer were destroyed by water, and these will be destroy∣ed by fire. 'Be patient, therefore, brethren, unto the coming of the Lord'—'For they shall proceed no fur∣ther.' This is the last effort which the man of sin shall exert. He was first a Pagan,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Antiochus Epiphan.</NOTE> then a Christian, and now this son of perdition has become a son of <HI>liberty.</HI> And the characteristics by which he is known are as visible now as formerly. He has committed sacrilege in the temple of God; robbed the churches of their
<PB N="18" REF="035364_0017_1004A1627186F868"/>sacred utensils. He has magnified himself above every god, and spoken marvellous things against the God of gods. He corrupts by flatteries, promising liberty. He thinks to change <HI>times and laws.</HI> He is a revolu∣tionist, with a new calendar and constitution. He has not regarded the desire of 'women;' but his laws and license prostrate their honour. He has seized the mo∣nasteries, and 'divided the land for gain.' Formerly, the man or sin opposed Christ under the covering of religion; but now he meets Christ in the open field; and Christ will soon meet him in the open field, and destroy him by the brightness of his coming.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> coming. Not t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> by fire. Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> by Nebucha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and the whole world. This <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> cut out of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>narch, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>archy, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.
<P>If there <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> who is h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> may per∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> in the Mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="6 letters" DISP="••••••"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the time of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ple who <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ned <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> a bright<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ll of m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>kind.</P></NOTE> Then the Deists will see a miracle, and believe the Bible. Ah! infidel, your anarchy is short: soon will your scoffing mouth cry to the mountains, Fall on us, and to the rocks, Cover us. Happy, long-expected day! Ye saints, lift up your heads, and look up; for your re∣demption draw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th nigh.</P>
<P>INFERENCES.</P>
<P N="1">1. Observe the remarkable analogy between the last days of the Jews, and these last days of the Chris∣tians. The Jews of that time had more knowledge than their ancestors. There were great <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>vivals of true religion among them, while the body of the people sun more <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> more in d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ion and immorality: they had great <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iv<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>on<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ng them, with respect to relig∣ion and politics. There were many who had the form of godling, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="5 letters" DISP="•••••"/> the power, and many sceptics and infid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> among th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m. There w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> much talk of
<PB N="19" REF="035364_0018_1004A16598316F88"/>liberty among them<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>spun; while they were falling into a state of anarchy. The same is our condition in all these respects. Josephus tells us, that the young peo∣ple among them were fond of innovations: that som∣ilies were greatly divided among themselves, and the dearest connexions broke through all restraints, with respect to each other.</P>
<P>How remarkable the resemblance between the Jew∣ish zealots and the infidel Jacobins of Europe! The zealots were great patriots. "They exhorted one an∣other to assert their liberty," says Josephus. "They trampled on the laws of men, and laughed at the laws of God. They ridiculed the oracles of the prophets, as the tricks of jugglers." "They disannulled the succession of the priesthood, and ordained vile, ignoble, and undeserving persons for that office, that they might have their assistance in their wicked undertakings." Such has been the conduct of the Jacobins, with re∣spect to the laws of men and the laws of God. The conscientious Catholic priests were driven from their places and livings, and were succeeded by licentious and perjured persons, who favoured the Jacobins, and taught the religion of reason.</P>
<P>The zealots murdered many of the priests, and de¦stroyed the remains of political government. "They erected tribunals," says Josephus, "for the destruction of those who were obnoxious to their n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious de∣signs. Their thirst was chiefty after the blood of good families. And while they were destroying the people, their terror was so great, that no one had cour∣age enough openly to weep for his deceased friend or relation, or to bury him." Just like the conduct of the Jacobins, in Robespiere's reign of terror; with this difference, that the tyranny and wickedness of the latter have been far more extensive. And as the last days of the Jews were more and more perilous, till the time of their destruction; so we may expect that our days will be more and more perilous, till the Chris∣tian world are destroyed by fire from heaven: Christ has expressly told us, that there shall now be such a time
<PB N="20" REF="035364_0019_1004A16A6DDEF738"/>of trouble 'as was not from the beginning of the crea∣tion; distress of nations and perplexity, the sea and waves roaring, men's hearts failing them for fear, and for looking after those things which are coming on the earth.' Many will tell you that the coming of Christ is far off, and that the Christian world will soon be filled with holiness and happiness. Believe them not; for these perilous times are allowed by all to be the times of the seven last plagues. What is the conse∣quence of these plagues? Is it reformation? No; but blasphemy. Under the fourth vial,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The fourth vial was poured out upon the sun. The civil powers of our modern infidels, under the sixth vial, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> called the kings of the East, for as the ancient kings of the East, the Medes and Persians, destroyed old Babylon; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se are now destroying mystical Babylon. I car<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> but think there is an implicit allusion to the same people, under the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>urth vial. What can be a more lively resemblance of the sun than re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>son? The sun is the great foun∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> of light in the material world, and reason is the great fountain of light in the intellectual and philosophical world. The ancient P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rsians worshipp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> the fan, and ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> modern Persians worship reason. The radiance of reason, in our Fer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tious, infidel philosophers, <HI>is,</HI> by the judgment of God, perverted, and, in∣s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>d of enlightening the world, has scorched mankind with the wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ment heat of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> fury and contention.—The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of all the vials. I sup∣p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> now <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ne measure, and will be m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te and more so to the end.</NOTE> 'men blasphem∣ed the name of God, who hath power over these plagues? Under the fifth, 'they blasphemed God, be∣cause of their pains and their fores, and repented not of their deeds;' and under the seventh, they 'blasphemed God, because of the plague of the hail.' How neces∣sary then it is, that we should be weaned from this world, and set our affections on things above, that we may enjoy the best friend in the worst times, and be hid in the chambers of divine love, till these calamities be overpast.</P>
<P N="2">2. Hence we may expect that the church must drink one more bitter cup of persecution, before Christ's second coming. This will be the battle of Gog and Magog, the battle of the great day of God Almighty, when the beast, and the kings of the earth, and their armies, shall make war against him who sitteth upon the white horse, the emblem of purity and victory, and against his army. At the introduction of our dispen∣sation, when we know that Christ personally appeared, he was represented as appearing upon a white horse.
<PB N="21" REF="035364_0020_1004A16C19C58CA8"/>Rev. vi. 1, 2; so now, at the introduction of the next dispensation, he is represented as appearing upon a white horse, as the WORD OF GOD, and, AS SUCH, op∣posed by the kings of the earth and their armies. Christ is the essential Word, whence the written word proceeds; opposed by the armies of infidels. This word will then be fulfilled in their destruction. This fulfilment they will see and feel with ineffable anguish, and thus be slain by the sword proceeding out of his mouth. Then they will laugh no more, but soberly believe that the word of God, fulfilled in their ruin, is quick and powerful, sharper than any two-edged sword, piercing even to the dividing asunder of soul and spirit, of the joints and marrow.</P>
<P>Some will tell you there is too much knowledge in the world for the existence of persecution. But this is a great mistake. When Christ and the first disciples were persecuted, there was more knowledge both among the Jews and Romans than ever there had been in any for∣mer period. The true source of persecution is neither ignorance nor knowledge, with respect to the sciences; but wickedness of heart, joined with ignorance of the∣ological truth and the rights of conscience. The inno∣cent blood in France, which has run in torrents on ac∣count of religion as well as politics within seven years past by means of the men of knowledge, is a glaring evidence that there may be such a creature in the world as a patriotic, persecuting philosopher. In that age of the world, which resembled this, the infidel Romans first persecuted and destroyed a persecuting church, and then turned their fury against the saints; so our mod∣ern infidels are now persecuting and destroying a perse∣cuting church.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">This must <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> understood of Papists, as individuals. Excellent char∣acters are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ound <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> church, for piety and liberality, entirely opposed to the perticuting spirit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ery Babylon. And they are now suffering as true martyrs for the Christian cause. <HI>Come out of h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r, my people;</HI> this strongly inti∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>s, that some of God's people may remain in her, and partake of her plagues. Babylon is now burning with the fire of liberty, I mean licentious∣ness. It is woud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> to observe how it catches and blazes in various coun∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es, notwithstanding all the pains used to extinguish it. Clearly verified are the following <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ures with respect to mystical Babylon. 'When thou shalt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to deal treacherously, then they shall deal treacherously with thee.' 'He who kills with the sward <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill I with the sword.' In the cup which sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> has fis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> to you, sill to her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> It re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ares a sort of men ex∣tra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for wicked <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>fur to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> double what she has mea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ed to either. Have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Atheist, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="5 letters" DISP="•••••"/>tinet, in popish count<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="5 letters" DISP="•••••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on is fallen and is become the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of devils, the hold of every <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oul spirit, the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>age of every <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>dem and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>esel bird? There is dis∣truction, I think, between Pab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ed the man of sin. Babylon is merely the Roman cla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> The m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> he who was the for∣mer hyp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>erits and th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</NOTE> And soon, we may expect, they will
<PB N="22" REF="035364_0021_1004A16DB6DD16F8"/>turn their fury against the saints of all communions: yea, is not this work already begun?</P>
<P>The loud cry of this sort of men against persecution, like that of the Jews, when they garnished the sepul∣chres of the righteous, is a solemn evidence that such a fiery trial is at hand. The old persecuting Papists were under some restraint, because they believed the Bi∣ble and future punishment; but these new persecutors with triumph over all restraint, denying future punish∣ment, denying the Biole, and some of them even the existence of the D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ity. But this fierce persecution will be very short; 'for a short work will the Lord make upon the earch.'</P>
<P N="3">3. Hence learn the wickedness and folly of those Christians, who are now promoting infidels, by their suffrages, to important employments in the State, and putting a sword into their hand to stay us. They prom∣ise you liberty, and loud is their cry in favour of reason and the rights of man. Believe them not; for they themselves are servants to corruption. They appear harmless, at present; but in a few years longer, their power will be great, and the people in general exceed∣ingly corrupt and degenerate. Then it will be sound that our calendar, churches, and clergy are attended with loss to the public—loss of time and loss of money —and are utterly inconsistent with the wisest political economy. And then the churches, the clergy, and the observers of the Sabbath, must be punished as enemies to the State. These or similar abominations may cer∣tainly be expected as soon as the people shall become sufficiently licentious and degenerate. Such corrupt trees cannot but yield such deadly fruit wherever the soil will admit of it. The base examples, which some
<PB N="23" REF="035364_0022_1004A170CC9B43B0"/>of them <HI>now</HI> exhibit, are exceedingly pernicious to so∣ciety. <HI>But if we refuse the suffrage,</HI> you say, <HI>the infidel will turn Christian, and obtain his purpose after all.</HI> What then? The fault in that case is not your own, but his. There is a wide difference, in the sight of God, between our electing an insidel whom we esteem a Christian, and our freely elevating to political authority the known and open enemies of God and of Jesus Christ. The wicked walk on every side, when the vilest men are exalted: then certainly we should never use our influ∣ence to exalt the vilest of men, as all infidels are, in the view of every true follower of Cln</P>
<P>For the same reason, it is the indispensable duty of all Christian churches to discipline and excommunicate such of their members as obstinately persist in favour∣ing the political elevation of such licentious charac∣ters.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Have we not observed, in our country, the Deist favouring some Chris∣tians, and using his influence to obtain certain privileges for them? What was the consequence? Were not his votes more numerous? Now, I pray, consider, Is it right or wrong? Is it, or is it not, agreeable to the will of Christ, to promote and insided to publy authority, because he has accomplished for you some favourite pur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>? O what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>grace to the Christian name▪ Alas▪ must Christians themselves have a hard in promoting that persecution, not only of religion, but of the mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> virtues, which appears so rapidly ap∣proaching? T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> it not in Gath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> pu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>sh it not in the street, of Ai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cion!</NOTE> But how lamentable the neglect of discipline in churches! 'I will take away the hedge thereof, and in shall be eaten up; and break down the wall thereof, and it shall be trodden down?</P>
<P N="4">4. Hence learn the necessity of watchfulness and spiritual-mindedness. How careful! how zealous should we be, to avoid all appearance of those crimes which must constitute the vil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> character of men in the last days! 'See that ye walk circumspectly, not as fools, but as wife, redeeming the time, because the days are evil? The abounding of iniquity in the world is apt to be attended with coldness and indifferency among professors of religion; so Christ has told us. 'Because iniquity shall abound, the love of many shall wax cold? Let us then, 'with purpose of heart, cleave unto the Lord, and keep the word of his patience,' that he may
<PB N="24" REF="035364_0023_1004A1738EC8E980"/>'keep us in that hour of temptation, which shall come to try all them who dwell upon the earth? Be this our temper of mind, and what can we fear? Let per∣ilous times come, distress of nations and perplexity; let the sea and waves roar around us; our feet are safe on the Rock of ages; our souls shall survive these days of vengeance, "The wreck of ages, and the crush of worlds."</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

