<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-11-02</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs. Corrected 5 $-groups. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N19193">
<STC T="E">24979</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99007193</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="024979_0000_0FCDEF1E4EE310D0"/>
<PB REF="024979_0001_0FCDEF215AE65270" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>PAINTING IN GENERAL. By James L. Walker, MARKET-STREET, NEAR THE COURT-HOUSE BALTIMORE, SIGN OF THE PAINTING MUSE.</HEAD>
<P>HE returns thanks to the Public for the generous Encouragement he has met with, since his commence∣ment in this Town; and hopes, by his continued attention and punctuality to merit their continued FAVOUR: He has employed the best Hands in different Branches, particularly <HI>Coach, Sign,</HI> and <HI>Rooom Painting</HI>; which last he proposes to do in the <HI>European Taste,</HI> not heretofore much practised in this Country: Also deception Pieces, <HI>Chimney, Fire,</HI> and <HI>Candle Screens; Landscapes,</HI> either from Nature or Fancy; <HI>Floor Cloths</HI> of various patterns, &amp;c.</P>
<P>HE HAS also opened a <HI>Looking Glass Manufactory,</HI> in <HI>Calvert-Street,</HI> under the Inspection of WILLIAM FARIS, where he makes <HI>new</HI> and foliates <HI>old Glass; Picture Frames, Square, Round,</HI> and <HI>Oval,</HI> made on the shortest notice.</P>
<P><HI>He has a constant supply of</HI> Painters' Colours, Oil, <HI>&amp;c. which he continues to sell by</HI> Wholesale <HI>and</HI> Retail, <HI>viz.</HI>
<LIST>
<ITEM>WHITE-LEAD, ground,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Yellow-Ochre, do.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Venetian-Red, do.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Spanish-Brown, do.</ITEM>
<ITEM>White-Lead, dry;</ITEM>
<ITEM>Yellow-Ochre, do.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Venetian-Red, do.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Spanish-Brown, do.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Brown-Ochre,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Patent-Yellow,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Naples-Yellow,</ITEM>
<ITEM>King's-Yellow,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Stone-Ochre,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Umber,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Verdigrise,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Prussian-Blue,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dutch-Pink,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rose-Pink,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ivory-Black,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lampblack, of two qualities,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Whiting and Chalk,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Carmine,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lake of three qualities,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Flake-White,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vermillion,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Paint-Oil properly boiled,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Paint-Oil, unboiled,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Spirits of Turpentine,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sugar of Lead,</ITEM>
<ITEM>White-Vitriol,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Litharge, of two qualities,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Painters' Brushes and Tools,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Camel-Hair Pencils,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pumice-Stone,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rotten-Stone,</ITEM>
<ITEM>GOLD and SILVER LEAF,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dutch-Metal, white and yellow, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P>ALL which, from his knowledge of COLOURS, he is enabled to lay in of the best qualities, and will sell on the lowest Terms, with directions for their use; a generous allowance to those who buy to sell again.</P>
<P><HI>ALSO,</HI> COACH GLASS, Large PICTURE and WINDOW GLASS, Patent Water Colours, Crayons, Chalks, and Port-Crayons, in setts; Varnishes, Lacker and Japan, with a variety of Copperplates by the first Masters.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="colophon">
<P>BALTIMORE: Printed by PHILIP EDWARDS, in Market-Street, nearly opposite the CARD MANUFACTORY.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

