<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The continvation of ovr weekely avisoes, since the 19. of this present. Certaine late and very remarkable passages twixt the Pope, and the embassadours of the Emperour and King of Spaine, concerning the excommunication of the King of Sweden and his adherents. A resolute and very religious speach of the King of Sweden, vpon occasion of a danger escaped. The last and certainest passages of Maestricht, in manner of a diurnall, by which you may guest of the event of that siedge. The names of certain English and French commanders lately hurt and slaine before Maestricht. A proclamation of the King of Spaine against Count Henry of Vandenberg, one of the revolted lords of that state. Conditions proffered by the Emperour to draw the Duke of Saxonto his side: ineffective. Besides divers other particulars of note.</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2=" ">Continuation of our weekely avisoes, since the 19. of this present.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">B14962</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 18507.259</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S102672</IDNO>



<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99838443</IDNO>


<AVAILABILITY><P>This text has been selected for inclusion in the EEBO-TCP: Navigations collection, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities. To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication ( http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14962)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177409)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1087:16b)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The continvation of ovr weekely avisoes, since the 19. of this present. Certaine late and very remarkable passages twixt the Pope, and the embassadours of the Emperour and King of Spaine, concerning the excommunication of the King of Sweden and his adherents. A resolute and very religious speach of the King of Sweden, vpon occasion of a danger escaped. The last and certainest passages of Maestricht, in manner of a diurnall, by which you may guest of the event of that siedge. The names of certain English and French commanders lately hurt and slaine before Maestricht. A proclamation of the King of Spaine against Count Henry of Vandenberg, one of the revolted lords of that state. Conditions proffered by the Emperour to draw the Duke of Saxonto his side: ineffective. Besides divers other particulars of note.</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2=" ">Continuation of our weekely avisoes, since the 19. of this present.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[1], 14 [i.e. 15] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by I.D. for Nathaniel Butter and Nicholas Bourne,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1632.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>At head of title page: Iuly 25. Numb. 35.</NOTE><NOTE>Printed by J. Dawson. Cf. STC.</NOTE><NOTE>Page number 1 is on verso of title page; page number 7 is repeated in page numbering.</NOTE><NOTE>Formerly STC 25198.</NOTE><NOTE>Identified on UMI microfilm as STC 25198.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</NOTE><NOTE>With: The continuation of ovr weekely avisoes, since the 30. of the last moneth to this present. Iuly 6. Numb. 32. London : Printed by I.D. for Nathaniel Butter and Nicolas Bourne, 1632.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2016-01-28.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2014-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Kate Allen</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Kate Allen</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="B14962">
<STC T="S">18507.259</STC>
<STC T="C">S102672</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99838443</BIBNO>
<VID>177409</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P><HI>Iuly</HI> 25.</P>
<P><HI>Numb.</HI> 35.</P>
<P>THE CONTINVATION OF OVR WEEKELY <HI>Avisoes,</HI> since the 19. of this present.</P>
<P>Certaine late and very remarkable passages twixt the <HI>Pope,</HI> and the Embassadors of the <HI>Emperour</HI> and King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> concerning the excommunication of the King of <HI>Sweden</HI> and his adherents.</P>
<P>A Resolute and very Religious speach of the King of <HI>Sweden,</HI> vpon occasion of a danger escaped.</P>
<P>The Last and certainest passages of <HI>Maestricht,</HI> in man∣ner of a diurnall, by which you may guest of the e∣vent of that siedge.</P>
<P>The names of certaine <HI>English</HI> and <HI>French</HI> Commanders lately hurt and slaine before <HI>Maestricht.</HI></P>
<P>A Proclamation of the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> against Count <HI>Henry</HI> of <HI>Vandenberg,</HI> one of the Revolted Lords of that <HI>State.</HI></P>
<P>Conditions proffered by the <HI>Emperour</HI> to draw the Duke of <HI>Saxon</HI> to his side: Ineffectiue.</P>
<P><HI>Besides divers other particulars of Note.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON.</HI> Printed by <HI>I. D.</HI> for <HI>Nathaniel Butter</HI> and <HI>Nicholas Bourne</HI> 1632.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Continuation of our Weekely NEWES.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>From <HI>Rome</HI> the <HI>2.</HI> of <HI>Iune, 1632.</HI></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">O</SEG>N Munday last the Cardinall of <HI>Strigonia,</HI> parted from hence homeward with little or no satisfaction; The Pope never vsed nor acknowledged him as an <HI>Imperiall</HI> Ambassa∣dor, and after his first audience, his Holi∣nesse would never haue him heard in the Consistorie, and to that end he never did call the same toge∣ther; so that at last, the said Cardinall being out of hope to haue any publike audience more, and having spent all his mo∣nies, resolved (being inforced so to doe) to returne home a∣gaine, without any order for the desired monies for his <HI>Im∣periall</HI> Majestie. For although there was sent some order for 60000. Crownes vnto the <HI>Nuncio Grimaldi,</HI> yet was there such care vsed, that the said money is not yet paid, and is not like to be paid so soone.</P>
<P>Before the said Cardinall parted, he did remonstrate by a writing the wrong his Holinesse had done vnto him in seve∣rall poynts, especially in not having him approved and vsed as an <HI>Imperiall</HI> Ambassador, which dignity other Cardinals in time past haue enjoyed. Therevpon the Pope said if the like hath beene granted in times past, now We haue reasons to the contrary, which moue vs to graunt that honour neither to you, nor to any other. True it is, We haue given way and leaue to the Cardinall <HI>de Richelieu</HI> to bee a Generall of an Ar∣my, but he doth exercise that charge for the publicke good of <HI>Christendome,</HI> of <HI>France,</HI> and of the <HI>French</HI> King, which reasons neither you nor Cardinall <HI>Borgia</HI> can pretend.</P>
<PB N="2" REF="2"/>
<P>The Pope hath caused a Bull to bee prepared, (though not yet published) whereby he doth anatematize and excommu∣nicate all that take Armes against the <HI>Catholike</HI> Religion. And this the Pope hath done to ridde himselfe of the importunity of the <HI>Austrian</HI> faction; The which neverthelesse doth still vrge him to excommunicate the King of <HI>Sweden,</HI> that after∣wards no <HI>Catholikes</HI> would follow and serue him. Yea they say (though most impertinently) the Pope should not onely excommunicate those that warre against the <HI>Catholicke</HI> Re∣ligion, but also those that warre against the house of <HI>Aū∣stria,</HI> because who warreth against the same (say they) doth warre against the foundation and ground of the said <HI>Catho∣licke</HI> Religion; so as doe the Kings of <HI>France</HI> and of <HI>Sweden:</HI> the one publickly and directly, and the other by his money and assistance; without the which encouragement, the King of <HI>Sweden</HI> would never haue come forth out of his North-Corner, and haue over-runne all <HI>Germany.</HI></P>
<P>At this proposition the Pope did but laugh, saying: Wee that are the head of the <HI>Catholicke</HI> Religion, doe take care for the defence thereof, to preserue the same without harme. And to excommunicate and curse the King of <HI>Sweden,</HI> we doe see no reason, his warre tending not to the destruction of the <HI>Ca∣tholicke</HI> Religion, but onely to performe what he hath pub∣lished by his Manifest about two yeares since: and we see, he hath taken innumerable Townes and Cities, where the <HI>Ca∣tholicks</HI> haue all kind &amp; loving vsage, and no hostilitie at all. Oh! that the <HI>Austrian</HI> Armies had done the like in the <HI>Ca∣tholickes</HI> townes they haue taken, where they haue accompli∣shed such cruelties and impieties, as never were heard of a∣mongst the <HI>Swedish</HI> Armie: <HI>Mantoua</HI> is a fresh example of the pietie of the <HI>Austrian</HI> Armie, which house you call the ground of the <HI>Catholicke</HI> Religion: there hath beene com∣mitted such cruelties against all ages and sexes, such disho∣nour and wickednesse against the women, even those that were consecrated to God; such impiety against God &amp; his Sa∣ments, and all in such an excesse of abomination, that the like the King of <HI>Sweden</HI> can never thinke nor dreame of, against whom you doe so storme, &amp;c.</P>
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
<P>On the latter end of the last weeke, the Ambassador <HI>Borgia</HI> received his royall Patent or Commission, to remaine yet three yeares Ambassador for <HI>Spaine:</HI> whereat the Pope was exceedingly displeased. Saturday last was the day hee desired to haue audience, but the Pope sent him word, that he should not come before him as Ambassador. And indeed the Pope hath now oftentimes said, Wee will not that Cardinals bee Ambassadors of Princes <HI>(Lais)</HI> without our expresse order and licence, &amp;c.</P>
<P>True it is, that they playing on another string, doe in some sort moue the Pope, when they tell him, that the King of <HI>Swe∣den</HI> hath desired of the <HI>Switzers</HI> the passage into <HI>Italy,</HI> &amp; that his Forces draw neere to the borders thereof. But on the o∣ther side, the Most Christian King doth assure his Holinesse for the King of <HI>Sweden,</HI> and doth promise him all safetie and friendship from that part. But because every mans death is vncertaine, and mans will changeable, His Holinesse there∣fore will take such resolution for the <HI>Papall Sea,</HI> and for the safety of his person, as he shall thinke sittest, and hath given order, that <HI>Orivetto</HI> a City in the middle of <HI>Toscany,</HI> and al∣most vnaccessible, the old <HI>Papall Pallace</HI> (where in former troubles the Popes were wont to retyre themselues) should be againe prepared.</P>
<P>Cardinall <HI>Ʋbaldine,</HI> who had beene the maker of Cardinall <HI>Borgia</HI> his protest, hath beene driven out of <HI>Rome,</HI> and confi∣ned vnto <HI>Zagarola,</HI> belonging to Cardinall <HI>Ludovisio,</HI> where both out of griefe and feare, the poore man hath since lost his wit: The Pope having told him before he went out of <HI>Rome,</HI> We haue so much against you, that we might cause your head to be laid before your feete, if we shall doe justice, &amp;c. But in∣deed the Pope is naturally not vindicatiue, else there would haue beene cut off divers heads before this. More I dare at this time not tell you.</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>Farewell.</SALUTE></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="speech">
<HEAD>A Speech made by his Majestie of <HI>Sweden</HI> vnto those of his Court before <HI>Ingolstadt,</HI> vpon occasion of his deliuerance from a Canon-shot.</HEAD>
<P>The death which so vnhappily happened to the Marquis of
<PB N="4" REF="3"/><HI>Baden,</HI> (whose death I am extreamely grieved at, for those rare vertues which were in him, not vnsit to be published to the world) and that thundering bullet, the fatall instrument of his decease, do advertise me and put me in mind that I am mortall, and subject to the same accidents the very poorest and meanest of my Souldiers are subject vnto. It is a generall Law from which my Crowne, my birth, my victories are not able to rescue and exempt me. There remaineth nothing else therefore, but that I must resigne my selfe to the providence of the Almighty, who, if it please him to call me out of this world, heneverthelesse, will not abandon and leaue a cause so just as that which I haue vndertaken for the re-establish∣ment of the <HI>Germane</HI> liberties. He will doubtlesse raise vp some other more wise, more couragious and valiant then my selfe, who shall put a period vnto this warre. I know that the good successe which it pleased God to afford me in my en∣prises, hath made some to be envious, who labour to per∣swade the simple, that I endevour nothing more then mine owne gaine, and the robbing and spoyling of others. But I call to witnesse in this case the Princes who were thus spoy∣led, which I haue againe established in their owne right and estates; the Creditors of which I haue borrowed such extra∣ordinary summes at <HI>Franckford,</HI> and else where; &amp; the great dangers which I doe expose my selfe daily vnto: whether I haue left mine owne Kingdome, and the dearest I haue in the world to any other end, and with other intention, but onely to destroy the tyranny of the house of <HI>Austria,</HI> and to obtaine a profound and setled peace vnto all. This discourse was bro∣ken off by the joyfull acclamations of the hearers, &amp; promise of assistance, all of them with many teares intreating his Ma∣jestie to be more carefull in time to come of his owne preser∣vation, and to continue his first resolution, as they for their parts will continue their fidelitie.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="letter">
<HEAD>Extract of a Letter written from the Armie be∣fore Maestricht, <HI>the</HI> 17. <HI>of</HI> Iuly, <HI>wherein are contained those things of Note which haue lately passed.</HI></HEAD>
<P>I haue in my letter dated the 28. of Iune acquainted you
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>with seuerall passages, concerning both the arriuall of the e∣nemy, and the onset which hee gaue without, as also those within the Citie but neverthelesse: not daring to attempt any thing against the Quarter of his Excellencie, perchance because they perceiued the same to bee to strong for them, on the 29. day they began to march downward toward the <HI>Mase</HI> vntill some 3. or 4. houres march from the Lord of <HI>Berode</HI> his Quarter, and behind a Nunnes Cloister by the <HI>Mase</HI> encamping their Army, the next day being the 30. they began to ensure and strengthen themselves with one retreachment, and to cast vp or raise two batteryes by the dyke, the better to passe over the <HI>Mase</HI> vnder the favour of their Cannon.</P>
<P>On the first of Iuly yet being busied about this worke, and taking care to provide all things readily, shalloupes and boates, and Canons on the battery. The 2. day of Iuly the next morning they began to put their designe in practise, and transported 250. <HI>German</HI> souldiers with spades and mat∣tocks in boates and shallops, and so landed on the other side. But his Excellencie hauing the night before established good order and well guarded the dyke, both with horse and foote and also planted some Ordnance, and hee himselfe being at hand, had vppon this place caused the regiment of the Duke of <HI>Sandall</HI> to keepe watch, commanded by the Lieutenant <HI>Colonell</HI> Marquis <HI>De Thiau</HI> who hauing suffered the enemy to land, and the boates being gone backe againe to fetch ouer more men hee with his forces which were vp∣pon the dike fell vppon them that were landed with great strength and furie, and in despite of the enemies Canon and Muskets which playd continually, they slew most of the enemies forces, and many were drowned all of them went to the pot except onely 103. prisoners, which they brought with them into the Princes Quarter, among these priso∣ners were diuers which last yeare were taken by <HI>Bergen</HI> in the great defeat. This expedition happened not without some losse of our men, by reason of the Canon, and Musket shott. Among the rest inferiour officers voluntaryes and
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>common soldiers, we lost Captaine <HI>Foullion</HI> who receiued three wounds of Musket shott and at the last after the victo∣rie in the retreat hauing brought of his men on the other side had his shoulder taken of with a Canon bullet. Also was slaine the Marquis <HI>De Thiau</HI> whose death is much bewail∣ed of many, for many ra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e vertues and qualities that appear∣ed in him, his place of Lieutenant Colonell is bestowed vp∣pon Major <HI>Buad,</HI> and the Majorship; to Captaine <HI>Ʋerne∣uille.</HI></P>
<P>The next day being the third of <HI>Iuly,</HI> the Kings forces did againe attempt to come over, but somewhat lower; but our horse vnderstanding so much, and they fearing least too ma∣ny of our forces were vpon the Dyke, durst not come over, but with the boates returned backe vnto their former place. The same time were by 25. of our Horse-men brought 13. prisoners, and many horse, among them was one Wagoner, and one that was in commission for the obtaining of victuals, this man had about him 500. Rix-Dollars, to buy victualls in the Villages for the enemie, this proved good bootie for our Souldiers.</P>
<P>Vpon the 4. <HI>ditto</HI> some of our horse tooke and brought pri∣soners 106. Boores, 16. or 17. Carts, and 60. Horses; all these Boores, Carts, and horses were well laden with bread, beere, cheefe, &amp; other provant, to victuall the enemies Camp. There was a greater Convoy then this behind, but our Horse∣men were too weake and durst not assault them.</P>
<P>Here are divers other imprisoned, who daily when some of our men are taken on the other side, are released.</P>
<P>As concerning our approaches, we in time having brought our workes even to the <HI>Counter-Scharp</HI> of the City Moat; The enemy did begin to raise a Travers against our outermost worke, by this meanes to hinder our progresse, which Tra∣vers informe of an halfe Moone being very hinderfull &amp; pre∣judiciall to our proceedings, we endeavoured to possesse the same by force; when this exploit was to be effected, the <HI>Eng∣lish</HI>
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>had the watch that night in the approches, vnder the commaund of the Earle of <HI>Oxford,</HI> being the Regiment of my Lord <HI>Vere.</HI> The Earle for the exploit had commanded 40. <HI>English,</HI> all Gentlemen of very good descent and qualitie, be∣ing voluntaries; These very couragiously assisted with some other Officers and common Souldiers, tooke in this halfe Moone two severall times most manfully: but the enemy with all his might comming against them, vnder favour of their Canon, they tooke the same againe, and caused the <HI>English</HI> to forsake it, with the losse of fiue of the said voluntary Gentle∣men, 7. fouldiers, and 7. labourers, with another <HI>English</HI> Cap∣taine, and 23. or 24. souldiers more were hurt and sore mai∣med. Sir <HI>Simon Harcourt</HI> Knight was shot through the face and hurt with a Granado. Captaine <HI>Rockwood</HI> is also dange∣rously hurt and runne through the arme. The Lieutenant of the Lieutenant Colonell <HI>Herbert,</HI> was shot quite through the body. Those one the other side went not shot-free, and per∣chance haue more of them slaine then were on our side, for we know of some which we saw lying starke dead.</P>
<P>Yesterday also was shot in a batterye in the <HI>English</HI> appro∣ches, the Lieutenant Colonell <HI>Leueston</HI> in the head, and a few dayes before Colonell <HI>Pagnam</HI> in the cheeke, but wee trust that they will escape both of them well cured of their wounds.</P>
<P>The Enemy in three dayes hath made but few shottes out of <HI>Maestricht,</HI> wee know not what may bee the reason, ex∣cept he hath all the while beene removing of his Ordnance on another side: we shall ere long be certified, perchance they wanted something.</P>
<P>Our fire-workers day and night doe throw granadoes into the Towne, which doe great mischiefe.</P>
<P>The <HI>Spanish</HI> in the meane time with their Army are neere vnto the <HI>Mase.</HI> It is thought they will build a Sconce there, but we know no certainety, our best hope is that want of vi∣ctualls will driue him thence.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
<HEAD>Antwerp the <HI>18.</HI> of July <HI>1632.</HI></HEAD>
<P>As for newes it is certaine that Count <HI>William</HI> of <HI>Nassau</HI> yesterday hath taken from vs our strong Fort which we had in the polthen of <HI>Naemen</HI> not very farre from <HI>Hulst</HI> where he hath found or taken from vs eleuen great peeces of Ord∣nance, amongst them were two double Canons, &amp; great store of mansvelders or small peeces vsually so called, the soul∣diers were permitted to depart with their weapons, assoone as this Fort was deliuered or taken by the enemy, they did cut the dikes and drowned the enemies polther, and the pol∣ther of <HI>Naemen,</HI> and put all vnder water, and very like it is that they will doe so with all the dikes till before this Town of <HI>Antwerp,</HI> euen before the paslage on the <HI>Franders</HI> side, the which they may very well doe for men can send them so that this Citie is molested on both sides, on the <HI>Brabant</HI> side it is like a sea to the very gates of <HI>Antwerp,</HI> and now wee feare the other side as much.</P>
<P>As for <HI>Mastricht</HI> those of the Towne defend themselues very valiantly, so that it is supposed that it will hold out yet this Moneth, and as for releiuing of it there is little newes, for our Army can get no victuals, neyther cau they get ouer the <HI>Mafe,</HI> so that it is generally supposed that <HI>Mastric<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</HI> will be lost, and that chiefly for want of victuals, and if our Army were ouer the Riuer of <HI>Mase,</HI> their victuals would be more scanty for them And as for forcing the Prince of <HI>Oranges</HI> Campe there is no meanes, and it is iudged by men of vnderstanding to bee a thing impossible the Prince his Campe, being defended with three or trible workes against our Army, the Prince of <HI>Orange</HI> vsed no great force against the Towne: The besieged haue great store of powder and they shoot continually &amp; defend themselues couragiously, it is a hard Nut to cracke for the Prince of <HI>Orange,</HI> for hee loo∣seth there a great number of men.</P>
<P>Those of <HI>Callen</HI> haue taken truce with the <HI>Swedes</HI> for sixe weekes, and in <HI>Germany</HI> all things prospers for the Emperor, the Generall <HI>Freidland</HI> hath taken all <HI>Bohemia,</HI> and aduances towards the <HI>Swodes</HI> who hath retyred himselfe before <HI>No∣rimbergh</HI>
<PB N="8" REF="6"/>where he entrenches himselfe and maketh him∣selfe strong with his ordnance, he sends for all his troupes from all pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts to come to him <HI>Gustavus Hoorn</HI> his Field Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>shall is gone out of the <HI>Palatinate</HI> to him it is like to be a Generall Field Battell but the <HI>Emperials</HI> and <HI>Freadlan∣ders</HI> haue the greater number because it is supposed that the Duke of <HI>Saxon</HI> is agreed with the Emperour for it is said that the Emperour hath caused Proclamation to be made by the sound of Drumme &amp; Trumpet that no Hostility or hurt shal be done to any of the subjects of the Duke of <HI>Saxon</HI> vpon paine of death. the Duke of <HI>Saxon</HI> hath in his Army as some say 40000. men. And the Duke of <HI>Freedland</HI> 60000. men it is supposed they both will ioyne there forces together and come vpon the <HI>Sweden</HI> to ouercome him if they can. But the truth of these things are vncertaine.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>From <HI>Sitert 18.</HI> July <HI>1632.</HI> in the afternoone.</HEAD>
<P>My last vnto you was the 16. I haue ben since againe in the Army before <HI>Mastricht,</HI> and I came this morning from thence I write you that which I my selfe haue seene.</P>
<P>Notwithstanding they haue vsed great force vpon the halfe Moone at the <HI>Winberger</HI> Gate and wee haue had it in often; the besieged out of the time of Truce which they had on the dicke haue euer taken it from vs againe and beaten vs out of it. And againe one the fifteenth hereof they blew vp a Mjine at the same Gate against the English to their great advantage and one Fryday being the sixteenth be∣tweene three and foure of the clocke in the afternoone and other against the <HI>French</HI> and therevpon about 400. strong they sallyed out getting the Fort of them, and well three rodds of their approchings which they held that day and night following and defended it manfully. During the fight his Excellencie stood in the quarter of Grave <HI>Hen∣dr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k</HI> with 30. horse and I was by him vpon the Hill. The fight lasted till late in the night &amp; in the interim a great bul∣let came out of the Citty which flew betweene the Horses Leggs without hurting any body.</P>
<P>The charging of muskets lasted all night vntill that fi∣nally
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>the <HI>French</HI> being Chaffed in their blood on the 17. put the besieged to flight into the halfe moone which by the seconding of the <HI>English</HI> they tooke in, fighting man fully, the Enemie de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ended them<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elues stoutly, that I be∣leeue there was slaine 400. on both sides they knocked one the other downe with their muske<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s for want of powder and because they could not charge them fast enough this morning our men remained masters of the h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lfe Moone and of the counterverse on the dicke from whence the besieged haue very much hindred the approches.</P>
<P>Fifty Soldiers of the Garrison of <HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wburgh</HI> haue taken in the Castle of <HI>Erckenteell</HI> for from thenc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to hinder the Car∣riage of the victualls to the Army. And they had already sunck two flat bottomed boates: wherefore his Excellency sent thither the Duke of <HI>Boul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on</HI> with seauen Companies of Horse some Footemen and two peeces of Ordnance who got the same without discharging one shot of Ordnance and haue taken prisoner the Commander of the Castle. Tis a p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of importance and situate vpon a Rocke.</P>
<P>This day there was a woman brought before the Prince who came out of the Citty hauing letters to <HI>Don Cordua</HI> al∣so a <HI>Spaniard</HI> of the Regiment of <HI>Alonsa</HI> carrying letters to the Gouernour of <HI>Gulicke</HI> Tis all kept secret. Also yest∣erday a Cittizen came out of the Towne whom his Excel∣lencie caused to be strictly examined and amongst other things hee should haue sayed that there was great discord betweene the soldiers and the Citizens and that certainely they wanted powder which wee find to be so because they shoote but seldome.</P>
<P><HI>Don Cordua</HI> lies with his Army yet in the place where he lay first he cannot come out: The Prince hath also intercep∣ted Letters from the <HI>Infa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ta</HI> to <HI>Parenhyem.</HI> All the workes of the Army are many, and larger and stronger then before <HI>Hertogen Bush.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
<HEAD>Conditions offered by <HI>Wallstein</HI> to the Elector of <HI>Saxony</HI> since the Truce of the 5. of <HI>Iune</HI> sent by Colonell <HI>Sparr.</HI></HEAD>
<P N="1">1 The Elector should cast with himselfe those domages done in his owne countryes of <HI>Saxony</HI> by the warres a∣bout <HI>Leipsich,</HI> and set those against the spoiles that him∣sel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> had lately made in <HI>Bohemia.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. The Elector shall pay 2. Monthes meanes vnto <HI>Wal∣steyns</HI> Army.</P>
<P N="3">3. The Elector shall freely giue over those Bishopricks Church-Lands, and Cloysters.</P>
<P N="4">4. The Elector shall endevour to get the King of <HI>Sweden</HI> out of <HI>Germany:</HI> For which the Emperour will engage himselfe to grant free exercise of the Enangelicall Religion throughout <HI>Bohemia.</HI></P>
<P>These Articles being sent to the Elector he neuer accep∣ted of them. And so there was noe agreement made, nei∣ther is there yet any newes come, that the Elector should forsake the King of <HI>Sweden.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>A Proclamation by the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> concerning the revolt of Count <HI>Henry Vanden Bergh.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SIGNED><HI>Philip</HI> by the Grace of God. King of <HI>Castill,</HI> of <HI>Leon, Ar∣ragon,</HI> both the <HI>Sicells,</HI> of <HI>Jerusalem, Portugall, Nauarre, &amp;c.</HI></SIGNED></OPENER>
<P>As soone as our Sergeant at Armes, vpon the request and on the behalfe of our beloued and faithfull Counsellor and Protector generall did remonstrate to vs, that it is noti∣fied and knowne vnto all men how many seuerall wayes Count <HI>Henry De Bergh</HI> is obliged vnto vs, not onely being our subiect and vassall, but moreover hauing receiued at our liberall hands many extraordinary fauors, benefits and ma∣ny rewards besides all the payments due vnto him vpon a∣greement as well by standing meanes, as money of the Army comming in yearely in great summes, being moreouer ho∣nored with honorable and Principall titles: such as Counsel∣lor of our Counsell of state, Gouernour and Captaine gene∣rall
<PB N="11" REF="7"/>of our Dukedome and Country of <HI>Gelder,</HI> Maister of the Camp. And generall of our Army, and before that, Generall of the Cauallary or horse, and other dignities. The least of all which did oblige him to a firme and constant fidelitye to his Prince, and which is more, his owne oath which he tooke when first he was enstalled into these foresaid digni∣tyes. But hee casting by and slighting all this, and forget∣ting his duty and obedience due vnto vs from him; hee hath greatly enterprised and attempted against vs and our seruice, and the rest and welfare of our state and Countryes. Being so farre transported with his euill and pernitious plots and machinations, that on the 18. of the last Moneth hee pub∣lished printed bills and caused them to be scattered and dis∣persed into many places as well without as within our do∣minions, that all soldiers of what quality or nations (the <HI>Spanish</HI> onely excepted) should bee acceptable and wel∣come vnto him: exhorting and inciting them to rank them∣selues and shelter vnder him, and be led by his command, making vnto them many faire &amp; plausible proffers, by that meanes to draw them to mutiny and rebellion, from their owne colours vnder the which they are Militant for our seruice. Pretending himselfe to bee Master of our Camp and Generall of the Army, but in effect doing that which is al∣together contrary, hauing also the same day written to most of the Magistrates of the Cities in those parts letters signed with his owne hand conformable and agreeable to the other letters which hee published or caused to be published &amp; dis∣persed, which also he caused to be Printed &amp; scattered abroad, &amp; sent to the Prelates, Nobles, Cities &amp; Prouinces of the Low-Countries, labouring by that meanes to dispose them to a generall revolt against vs, and by seditious propositions, as farre dissonant from the truth as from reason. Nay and which is most of all, wrote a letter (also afterward printed) to the Princesse <HI>Jsabell Clara Eugenia,</HI> by the grace of God <HI>Infanta</HI> of <HI>Spaine</HI> our very good <HI>Aunt,</HI> full of abusiue and deceitfull inuentions trickes, and deuices, pretending, and willing to make her beleeue (against all truth) and perswade her that all his actions had no other end or scope but onely her seruice,
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>and the good and tranquility of those Countryes. Of which letters hauing by his Chamberlaine dispersed a great num∣ber of Coppies, and afterwards vnderstanding that his said Chamberlaine was taken prisoner by an oshcer of our coun∣trey of <HI>Braband,</HI> he wrote vnto the said officer the 24. day of the same Moneth a Letter particularly written signed, and sealed with his owne hand and seale contayning an euident and manifest affirmation of the aforesaid letters, to be his, &amp; that hee had sent them by his said seruant or Chamberlaine, and ouer and aboue this added many threats against our O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h∣cer that in case he did not let him free and let him escape, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e would doe thus and thus to him. All these things being to manifest declaring his euili designes against his owne Prince vnto whom is obliged by so many t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, and that he had con∣ceiued abunda<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce of poisonous mischiefe in his heart, which he doth but expect opportune occasion and put in executi∣on. To which end he had found it very conuenient to serue his turne <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith this present occasion, to wit the present siege which our rebels haue durst to lay vnto our city of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ric<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI> which by all likelihood they durst neuer haue done, nor pre∣sumed to atte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pt, had they not beene well assured that the sayd Count <HI>Hen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y</HI> would second thē, but were animated by the wayes and treatie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> &amp; correspondencie which they must needs haue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d with him or his. And being that this is not tolerable in a countrey of Iustice, but all these actions or crimes of Felonies and treason in the highest degree and at∣tempts of mutiny, rebellion, sedition, reuolt, and perturbati∣on of the publike rest and peace of these our Dominions, wherefore shewing vnto him for the discharge of his dutie and office, and the charge giuen vnto him by the Princesse our worthy <HI>Aunt</HI> to appeare before vs, and our trusty and welbeloued the President &amp; rest of our Priuy Counsell they hauing also charged him (to w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t our said Counsellour, and Proctor generall) to doe good &amp; vpright Iustice in this pre∣sent cause, and being thereunto authorized so farre as is re∣quisite, requesting also most hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bly, that all such prouision for Iustice to be executed against Count <HI>Henry,</HI> as shall be found meritoriously due vnto such foule and enormious
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>crimes as his are, with clauses of authorization. Thus it is therefore, that all these things considered, we will and com∣mand by these presents, at the request of our said Counsellor and Proctor generall, that with such ayd and assistance as you shall sind fitting and conuenient, you doe take &amp; apprehend the body of Count <HI>Henry Ʋanbergh</HI> wheresoener, and at what time soeuer you shall be able, to take and apprehend him within our Countries and Dominions, and that you doe carry or conduct him vnder good and sure guard into the prisons of our said Counsell, to be brought before the afore∣said President and Lords of our couusell to answer to Law, and receiue punishment and Iudgement for the said crimes, according to the same, and as shall bee found meete and convenient in such a case, and if so bee that you cannot take him, you shall adiourn him, and call him by edict and open publication, vpon paine of perpetuall banishment and con∣fifcation of goods, to appeare in person within three fifteen dayes. The first fourthnight you shall assigne him for the first day. the 2. for the second day. And the third for a 3, day and last peremtory day. Without any longer expecta∣tion, before our Counsell there to answer to such things as shall be objected and read against him, or aleaged by our P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>octor generall about the aboue mentioned causes &amp; crimes and other matters which hee more amply out of his owne charge shall propound and declare. And so proceed farther and see things ordered as reason shall require, signifying vn∣to him that if hee appeare not the first second and 3. sum∣mon there shall bee proceeded against him in his absence as as shall be fit to bee done in such a case. Certifying vnto the same our Counsell sufficiently what is to bee done. Which counsell of ours wee command, and charge, that vnto the parties (they being heard) they shall doe and ad∣minister good and speedy right Reason and Iustice as in such a case is necessary and convenient, and that in case of de∣fault and contempt of the said Couut <HI>Henry</HI> they shall pro∣ceed vnto the declaration of the said banishment, and the said confiscation, or otherwise as they shall find fit to bee done and proceeded in the like case. In the proceeding of
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>the confiscation you shall note, and set downe vnder your hands, by a good and true Inventarye, all and whatsoeuer goods shall bee found to bee belonging vnto the said Count <HI>Henry Van Bergh,</HI> and commit the keeping and tuition of them vnto such sufficient men as shall bee able to Answer and giue account of them, and the remainder of them when need shall require, and they therevnto called. And for the performance of all this wee giue you full power, Au∣thority, and speciall commandement. And wee doe far∣ther will charge and command. All our officers, and sub∣jects, that therein they doe obey you, and attend you dili∣gently, affording vnto you, counsell, aid and assistance, har∣bour and prison (if need bee) they shall also afford, when by you it is required. For thus it pleaseth vs.</P>
<P>And because (as we vnderstand) that the said Count <HI>Henry</HI> is retyred, and hath absented himselfe out of our Countries, wee therefore will that in that case the adiournement and summons which shall be made by publike Proclamation and edict, shall bee proclaymed at the Court and City of <HI>Bruxels,</HI> and the house of assembly for our Counsell, as also in the Ci∣ty of <HI>Namur,</HI> as being the neerest places vnto his last place of residence, causing the Copy thereof to be affixed vpon the gates of our great Counsell, and of the Court of <HI>Bruxels,</HI> as also the City of <HI>Namur,</HI> as also Coppies shall be affixed vp∣on the doores of the chiefest Churches of the said Cities, to the end that he may not plead or pretend ignorance, but ra∣ther may be of such effect and validity in the publication as if it had beene done to the person of the said Count <HI>Henry,</HI> to which end we doe authorize the said edict and publica∣tion by these present.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Giuen at our City of <HI>Malines</HI> <DATE> the 15, day of <HI>Iuly,</HI> in the yeare of grace 1632 and in the 12. yeare of our raigne.</DATE></DATELINE> These letters were sealed with the broad Seale By the king to the Counsell
<SIGNED>Signed <HI>De Rinevelt,</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

