<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Newes from the Great Turke. A blasphemous manifestation of the Grand Seignior of Constantinople, against the Christians; of his entrance into Christendome, and the particulars of his great armie. As it was sent to a merchant of note in London. As also what forces are preparing against him by the Venetians, and other Christian princes, viz. the Duke of Florence, and Duke of Parma; the Great Master of Malta. / All faithfully translated out of the Italian and French copies. Published by authoritie; that all Christians may take notice of the great pride and horrid blasphemy of the Turkes..</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">B27386</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing N1008</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason E.295[6]</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.114.d.5[21]</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R200195</IDNO>



<IDNO TYPE="proquest">ocm99883212</IDNO>


<AVAILABILITY><P>This text has been selected for inclusion in the EEBO-TCP: Navigations collection, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities. To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication ( http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B27386)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 193607)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C27:1[8])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Newes from the Great Turke. A blasphemous manifestation of the Grand Seignior of Constantinople, against the Christians; of his entrance into Christendome, and the particulars of his great armie. As it was sent to a merchant of note in London. As also what forces are preparing against him by the Venetians, and other Christian princes, viz. the Duke of Florence, and Duke of Parma; the Great Master of Malta. / All faithfully translated out of the Italian and French copies. Published by authoritie; that all Christians may take notice of the great pride and horrid blasphemy of the Turkes..</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 5, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Jo. Handcock in Popes-head-Alley,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1645.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2016-01-28.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM TYPE="personal name">Ibrahim, --  Sultan of the Turks, 1615-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM TYPE="topical term">Islam --  Relations --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Turkey --  History --  1453-1683 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Venice (Italy) --  History --  Turkish Wars, 17th century --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2013-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Colm MacCrossan</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Colm MacCrossan</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="B27386">
<STC T="W">N1008</STC>
<STC T="T">E.295[6]</STC>
<STC T="G">C.114.d.5[21]</STC>
<STC T="C">R200195</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99883212</BIBNO>
<VID>193607</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>NEWES FROM THE GREAT TURKE. A Blasphemous Manifestation of the Grand Seignior of <HI>Constantinople,</HI> against the Christians; of his entrance into Chri∣stendome, and the Particulars of his Great ARMIE. As it was sent to a Merchant of note in <HI>London. AS ALSO</HI> What Forces are preparing against him by the <HI>Venetians,</HI> and other Christian Princes, <HI>viz.</HI> The Duke of <HI>Florence,</HI> and Duke of <HI>Parma;</HI> The Great Master of <HI>Malta.</HI> All faithfully Translated out of the <HI>Italian</HI> and <HI>French</HI> Copies. <HI>Published by Authoritie;</HI> that all Christians may take notice of the great Pride and horrid Blasphemy of the <HI>Turkes.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON;</HI> Printed for <HI>Jo. Handcock</HI> in <HI>Popes-head-Alley.</HI> 1645.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="account">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>NEVVES FROM THE GREAT TURKE.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>ULTAN BRAIN, Might<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="keyers" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Emperour, Son and Nephew of God, the Invincible King of the <HI>Turkes,</HI> of <HI>Greece,</HI> of the <HI>Valticke,</HI> of <HI>Salmuria,</HI> of <HI>Damas∣cus,</HI> of <HI>Phrygia,</HI> of the Great and Lesser <HI>Aegypt,</HI> of <HI>Alexandria,</HI> of <HI>America</HI> and <HI>A∣frica;</HI> King of all the Kings in this World, chiefe Saint of Paradise; Bishop of whole <HI>Asia, Africa,</HI> and <HI>America,</HI> and of the most part of <HI>Eu∣rope;</HI> chiefe head of <HI>Linco;</HI> Guardian of the Se∣pulchre of <HI>Mahomet,</HI> and that of God; Lord and King of all Kings, Prince of all Princes; Terrour and scourge of all Christians; of the <HI>Ottomans,</HI> and of the Circumcised Hope, and Inestimable precious Stone, and most gracious Jewell.</P>
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
<P>The immortall memory of <HI>Sultan Murat,</HI> Grand Seignor of the <HI>Turkes,</HI> our Predecessour and beloved Brother, did alwayes intend to take from the Christians their little Rocke, which is possessed by those that are called by the name of <HI>Religion of Malta;</HI> and withall to sup∣presse their Gallies, because of the continuall damage which they doe upon our Seas. And whilest the said Grand Seignor was busie to bring his designe about, he dyed; Charging us to take this care upon us, which so much the more willingly wee doe resolve to put in exe∣cution, because the said Gallies not regarding our displeasure, tooke not long since a Ship of ours, where the <HI>Sultan Sesera</HI> was, with the <HI>A∣ga,</HI> who dyed in the fight, to our great griefe: therefore Wee Command all our <HI>Bashaes</HI> in <HI>Con∣stantinople,</HI> and all the Kings, to be with their Gallies in a readinesse the first day of the full Moone, in the moneth of <HI>Aprill;</HI> And that all those Gallies which are in our River of <HI>Arcenall,</HI> be set out armed and ready at the same time; together with all the Shippes that are in our Harbours, and our whole <HI>Militia</HI> is to doe the same; for our Will is, That this our Armie shall be the terrour, not onely to Christendome, but
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>to the whole World, that by the multitude of our Gallies and Shippes, the Sunne, Moone, and Starres, in admiration thereof shall be changed; the Fishes shall hide themselves in the deepest bottome of the Sea, for the fearefull noise of our Ordnance, that the Beasts and the Forrests shall be afraid, and the very trees rooted out and bea∣ten downe; And all Christendome shall by this our great might feele our anger and wrath, for the losse of our <HI>Sultan</HI> and the said <HI>Aga.</HI></P>
<P>The said <HI>Sultan,</HI> by this his blasphemous ma∣nifestation, declares as if he meant wholly to bend his force towards the Isle of <HI>Malta,</HI> not∣withstanding is entred in <HI>Candia,</HI> being the Do∣minion of the <HI>Venetians,</HI> where he hath already taken some Forts, whereof some upon Compo∣sition; and notwithstanding, after he had taken possession of them, hath put them most treache∣rously to the sword without any mercy, which is not to be wondred at, by reason that the great <HI>Sultans,</HI> his Predecessours, when they made warre against the <HI>Venetians</HI> and <HI>Hungarians,</HI> did alwayes put them most cruelly to the sword, whether they delivered their Townes up by Composition, or otherwise. It is credibly re∣ported by some that have been eye-witnesses
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>thereof, that this Great <HI>Turkes</HI> Army consists of above 300000 men, whereof most of them are Janisaries; 6 great Galliones, that are of 1000 tunne each; 600 Gallies, 1000 small Boats to land men and ammunition with; 1500 Camels laden with Powder; Besides divers Ships from <HI>Algier,</HI> laden with all sorts of Ammunition, as stakes, nailes, Iron-workes, and such things as they commonly make use of, insomuch as it is thought that they never came out with such a great Armie, as at this time. It is much to be wished, that all Christian Princes were reconci∣led together, and endeavoured to joyne their Forces together, to oppose that cruell enemy that seekes to make himselfe Monarch of the World, and to bring the Christians under his usurping power.</P>
<P>By Letters from <HI>Venice</HI> it is certified, that their Shippes have met with some part of the <HI>Turkes</HI> Fleet, which were coming from <HI>Algier,</HI> and have fought with them, and have sunke twenty of their Gallies and foure of their men of Warre.</P>
<P>They make great preparations at <HI>Venice</HI> a∣gainst the <HI>Turke;</HI> many Christian Princes offer their help to the utmost. By Letters from thence
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>it is certified thus; That the <HI>French</HI> Ambassadour the Lord of <HI>Gremovilie,</HI> having made his pub∣lick entry the 14<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>Iuly</HI> last, the next day after had Audience in the Councell, where he was received with great honour and having shewed his Letters of Credit, made an Oration, offering in the behalfe of the King of <HI>France</HI> his Master, his utmost helpe in this Warre, which was re∣ceived thankfully.</P>
<P>The great Duke of <HI>Florence</HI> hath likewise pre∣sented by his Ambassadour, all his power, as well by land as by water, his Gallies, Shippes, Men, and his own person. The Duke of <HI>Parma,</HI> that is there at present, offers 1500 Dragoones; 500 horse, and 3000 foot; it is said he shall be Gene∣rall, and sent towards <HI>Palma.</HI> The great Master of <HI>Malta</HI> offers likewise 8000 Souldiers, and 2000 slaves. In the meane time, the Great <HI>Turke</HI> goeth on his way, bringing all under his Power where he comes, whilest they feed themselves with these offers.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="5"/>
<PB REF="5"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

