<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2009-07-08</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Check for blanks. Checked for signatures. Checked for #s. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Corrected 10 $-groups. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N07023">
<STC T="E">8927</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99029886</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="008927_0000_10308726FA364090"/>
<PB REF="008927_0001_1030872AE5632AC0" MS="y"/>
<P>THE MECHANICK'S ADDRESS TO THE FARMER: Being a short REPLY to some of the LAYMAN'S Remarks on the Eighteen Presbyterian Ministers Letter to the Arch-bishop.</P>
<P>PHILADELPHIA: Printed by ANDREW STEUART, at the Bible-in-Heart, in Second-street. 1761.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="3" REF="008927_0002_1030872C99B41BD0"/>
<HEAD>THE Mechanick's ADDRESS, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">H</SEG>AVING perused your wonder∣ful Remarks on the Eighteen Presbyterian Ministers Letter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Archbishop, and therewith your Declaration of your Zeal for the Cause of the LORD, and your Desire to open the Eyes of your Fellow-Christians; it kindled in me a Desire of Access to you, in Order to my clearer Instruction: As I may ven∣ture to say, I have nothing more at Heart, than to be truly enlightened in the Path of Duty. But as you are pleased to conceal yourself under the general Characters of <HI>Lay-Man</HI> and <HI>Farmer,</HI> of which we have vast Numbers; I could devise no other Method to obtain my Desire, than by send∣ing out this Address among the Farmers, hoping thereby, to find out the famous Farmer: For it is a Pity that so famous a Talent as his, should be hid; or that such a Candle should be put under a Bushel.</P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="008927_0003_1030872E47E44768"/>As several strange Things are presented to me, dispersed here and there, through your none-such Performance, and I intend to be very brief; I shall set a few of those Mysteries in one View.</P>
<P>To begin then with your wonderful Ar∣guments gathered from the aforesaid Letter, you observe;</P>
<P><HI>First,</HI> That the A—hb—p is a Prelate of the Church of England; therefore he cannot be supposed to have any Grace.</P>
<P><HI>Second,</HI> The Eighteen Presbyterian Mi∣nisters allow the A—hb—p to have Grace, and the Church of England to be Christian; therefore they are secret Enemies to Presby∣terians.</P>
<P><HI>Third,</HI> The A—hb—p denies a Parity of Gospel-Ministers, and holds Episcopal Ordination to be Apostolical, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> there∣fore he can be no Friend at all to Truth.</P>
<P><HI>Fourth,</HI> These Eighteen Ministers say, they were providencially convened at <HI>Phila∣delphia;</HI> therefore they insinuate to the A—hb—p, that the Subscribing said Let∣ter, was a Synodical Act.</P>
<P><HI>Fifth,</HI> These Men signed that Letter; therefore they presumed to sap the very <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oundation of Presbyterian Discipline.</P>
<P><HI>Sixth,</HI> They say, a very remarkable Bles∣sing attended Mr. <HI>MecClanachan</HI>'s Ministry; therefore they bring a hard Charge against Presbyterianism in general.</P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="008927_0004_1030873357176C38"/><HI>Seventh,</HI> They assure the A—hb—p, that they will not be accountable for any Man's Prudentials in every Part of his Con∣duct; therefore they insinuate, that they think themselves qualified to be Bondsmen for other Peoples Goodness.</P>
<P><HI>Eighth,</HI> They tell the A—hb—p, there are Fundamental Doctrines of the Christian Religion and Protestant Reformation pro∣fessed by the Church of England, in which they can agree with that Church; therefore they are <HI>Church-Betrayers.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ninth,</HI> They say, the A—hb—p pre∣sides over the English Church; therefore they are hypocritical double-dealing Men, and allow him Precedency; whereas, had they been Christians, they would have dealt plainly with him,—and told him, that he was in a damnable State, till he condescended to the Level of his Brethren.</P>
<P><HI>Tenth,</HI> These Men say, that a disinterest∣ed Regard to the Fundamentals of Religion, and the Cause of Virtue and practical Piety, constrained them to engage in this Affair; therefore they have given up with every Objection, that has been advanced against the English Church; for which the Meet∣ing-House Doors should be shut against them.</P>
<P>THESE, <HI>Sir,</HI> are some of your very rare Arguments, which, I confess, I should
<PB N="6" REF="008927_0005_1030873506A3B500"/>
never have thought of, being as little ac∣quainted with the Subtilities of School-learning as yourself, if not less.</P>
<P>I fear, all the Schools will deny, that such Logick is taught in them; so that you are like to have the Honour of that noble Invention to your self. Besides, I fear it will not find Credit among the greatest Part of those, you call dear Fellow-Christians, till you have afforded clearer Light to open their Eyes, than you have yet done.</P>
<P>THE next Point I want Clearness in, is about those new Opinions you hold, of the English Church; namely, that she is not Christian: That if she be possessed of Truth, the Presbyterians must be possessed of Error: And finally, that the Dragon and his Angels, spoken of in Revelation, are her Prelates and their cursed Curates. These Things, <HI>Dear Sir,</HI> I am afraid will ruffle the Temper of some of the angry Fellows of the English Church, and will not go well down with the Bulk of Presby∣terians, unless they are better proven; for we have been used to think otherwise. You tell us, they are not new, but were held by <HI>Calvin</HI> and <HI>Knox,</HI> and our Godly Reformers; but as we have nothing to support these As∣sertions but your bare Word, they will hardly believe for us. They allow, that some Ministers of that Church have been
<PB N="7" REF="008927_0006_10308736B3AF9140"/>
eminent and pious, and preached and wrote soundly: such as Bishop <HI>Usher,</HI> Mr. <HI>Harvey,</HI> and others, that I might mention; but I think, they have just Reason indeed to la∣ment, that it is too evident to be denied, that a great Number of them, especially in this Country, are vain and vicious in their Lives, as well as insipid and unsound in their Doctrine; by which Means many poor Souls have neither proper Example nor Instruction to lead them in the Paths of Piety. The Presbyterians would be glad, and I am well persuaded, the Eighteen Mi∣nisters are not of those among them, who would be least glad, if all, or any of that Church, would truly preach, and warmly inculcate those Articles of the Church of England, in which they have the Happiness to agree with that Church; for they desire the Welfare of others, as well as of them∣selves. And sundry of my Neighbours are of Opinion, that [:let Mr. <HI>MecClanachan</HI> be what he will otherwise:] yet if he had not preached and vindicated those Gospel-Doctrines so clearly, and inculcated them so warmly as he did, there would not have been such an Uproar made about him; nor would the Remarks on the Ministers Letter have had so many Abettors, who secretly rejoice, that they have them to make a Handle of, to promote their own low, and
<PB N="8" REF="008927_0007_1030873AB246A6B8"/>
some perhaps, their malicious Designs, to blacken those Ministers Characters, and destroy their Influence, if possible.</P>
<P>BUT I must proceed a little farther, and enquire with Respect to those Eighteen Mi∣nisters Character, who, you say, are Hypo∣crites, false-hearted Presbyterians, Church∣men in Heart, illeterate Mechanicks, vainly expecting to be noticed by Men of high De∣gree either in Church or State, and have been boxing the Compass for a Living, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> Will they not be apt to charge you with Lying and Slander? And the Truth is, I know not how you will be able to free your∣self from the Charge, unless you can sup∣port your Allegations by some better Proof than your bare SAYSO. Will they not be apt to tell you, that you have not only be∣lied them in saying, they denied, that their Brethren had Grace, and that they had a Method of judging a Man's State by his Face? with many other Things of like kind; but that you likewise belied <HI>Calvin</HI> and <HI>Knox,</HI> and the whole Body of Presby∣terians, in telling the World, that these never believed, that the Church of Eng∣land was Christian, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> And yet you have not produced one Proof for your As∣sertion, notwithstanding you said, you would give an Hundred. But no Doubt you think your Word is sufficient Proof,
<PB N="9" REF="008927_0008_1030873D84666760"/>
being a Man of such superior Abilities, as not only to judge a Man's State by his Face, but to judge the A—b—ps State at some thou∣sand Miles Distance. Will they not be apt to enquire, who told you their Conduct in Synod last Year? and to charge you with Slander in asserting, that they endeavoured to introduce Innovations into Synod? For I am well inform'd, they only attempted to have good Regulations formed, in Order the better to preserve the Decorum of the Body, in their judicial Transactions, which Regu∣lations were at length agreed upon without a Dissenting Vote. Will they not think that insatiable Malice, of some ill Design or o∣ther, moves you and your Abettors, to stir up an antient Spirit of Partyism and Slan∣der? Do not a Number of your Expressi∣ons too evidently lean that Way? Will not they and the World judge, that they are as fit to send a Letter to a Person in higher Sphere of Life, as a Number of weak and scandalous Creatures have been to appear before such in Person, to receive Orders for the holy Ministry? If these Men are so much inclined to the Church, as you would represent them, why have not any of them, or of that Side they were formerly united to, whom you seem to strike at thro' them, why, I say, have not one of these gone to, and been received by the Church as well as
<PB N="10" REF="008927_0009_103087405EDEB9A8"/>
other Presbyterians? Is not a Gown as ready for them, as it was for <HI>Hindman, Bell, Lion, Evans</HI> and <HI>Carlisle,</HI> Men of in∣famous Character, with sundry others that I might mention? Except the Bishop would chose to reject Men of good Character, while he received the weak and the wicked, which I believe you will not venture to as∣sert. You say they have been boxing the Compass for a Living. I believe you did not consider, when you wrote these Expres∣sions, nor do others, that are fond to use them. What if these Gentlemen should enquire, who boxed the Compass, when a Number of them left their native Land, not for their best Deeds, and some not for their great Abilities, and boxed the Com∣pass here to screen themselves, and fish for a Living among Presbyterians? What would you think, if they should ask, who boxed the Compass, when a certain Gentle∣man wrote to <HI>England</HI> respecting his Ex∣ploits in defending our Frontiers? Exploits done by others, which he called his own, [:as he did the Sermon he printed, which was done by another Gentleman:] for which Lie he got Twenty Pounds annexed to his Salary. What if they should farther enquire, who boxed the Compass, when one of this Gentleman's Fraternity, being too vain and dull to be acceptable to Presby∣terians,
<PB N="11" REF="008927_0010_103087424D3B5C10"/>
applied to the Study and Practice of the Law; but finding himself too great a Dunce for that Profession, he forged Cre∣dentials, went and preached to an ignorant People, till he got some Money, after which he marched to the Bishop for Orders. What if they should put these and many other Questions, which I believe they might with Justice do, till I were weary writing and you with reading them? You repre∣sent them as-illiterate Mechanicks; but the World is too well acquainted with their Abilities, to conclude them such clownish scurrilous Flings, that they either want Sense or Learning. Were an Acquaintance with Mechanism a Crime, by far the great∣est Part of them are innocent of it. If two or three did understand something of it, will this prove, they had not a regular Education? Your clumsy Calumny equally strikes at the great Apostle PAUL himself, as an illiterate Dunce; for he was a Tent-maker. But perhaps if the Eighteen Mi∣nisters had been Dupes and Dunces, or even Debauchees, they might have escaped all these Charges.</P>
<P>I would now conclude this Address, only I can not help taking Notice of the prodigious Agitation you seemed to be put in by these Men praying the A—hb—p. And I do not wonder at it, when you found
<PB N="12" REF="008927_0011_10308743F880B4D8"/>
out such horrible Idolatry in it, as I know not, if ever any of the Children of Men made such a rare Discovery of before your own penetrating self. The most of us used to think, that they might pray a Man to grant a Favour, without so much as sup∣posing, they were chargeable with Idolatry. But then you have not only found these Men, together with the greatest Part of the present Generation, guilty of this hor∣rible Crime, but your Assertion would in∣volve the Patriarch ABRAHAM in the same Guilt; for he not only prayed, but bowed down to the Children of HETH. But may not some of them enquire, how much bet∣ter is your Conduct, if it is not much worse, in praying [:perhaps some may call it swearing:] in the Name of <HI>Calvin</HI> and <HI>Knox,</HI> who are at best but departed Saints?</P>
<P>These are a few of the Things, that are so difficult to me, and to many others, and if you do not come from your Concealment and explain them to us a little better, I be∣lieve there will not be one real Presbyterian on your Side; consequently you will lose your Labour in attempting to open Eyes. But that is not all; for I fear, great Num∣bers will be tempted to think, that you are so far from being a Friend to Presbyterians, that you are one of their most inveterate
<PB N="13" REF="008927_0012_103087490F605720"/>
Enemies, endeavouring to represent them as a very odious and uncharitable Sort of People, scarcely fit to live in a civilized Na∣tion. Or if you are a Presbyterian by Pro∣fession, they will conclude, that you are an Enemy to them in Practice, and that Ma∣lice has prompted you to write your Re∣marks; and perhaps some Episcopal is joined with you in the Affair. I believe, many will conclude, not only from these Gentlemens apparent Disinterestedness in the Affair, but from their thorough Ac∣quaintance with them, that they had a single View to promote Religion, however they may not have so duly considered all the Circumstances of the Case, and particularly the ill Use that spightful Persons would make of their Letter. But they will be obliged to conclude, that pre-conceived Ma∣lice against these Men, because perhaps you did not find, that they were <HI>Dunces,</HI> or wil∣ling to be <HI>Dupes</HI> to you, moved you to re∣mark. Or perhaps that you gladly and greedily snatched at this Opportunity; to prepare the Way for carrying on some ma∣licious Plot, by attempting to destroy, if possible, these Mens Influence by Sophis∣try, Calumny and Lies. And if this be the Case, have you not Reason to fear, that the Blast of Divine Providence will
<PB N="14" REF="008927_0013_1030874AC2094168"/>
consume your Designs, as Snow melts off the Fields by warm Sun-Beams. But what∣ever your Profession is, if this poor Attempt of mine, or any other Invitation of like kind that may be given, may be a Means of bringing you forth to Light, and you can confirm and establish these Remarks of yours, then I doubt not, but you will meet with sufficient Encouragement to sweep you from the Plough-Tail, seeing that is such a despicable Business, and without boxing the Compass, set you in a Sphere large enough to employ your Talent of opening Eyes.</P>
<P>IF you enquire after me, <HI>Sir,</HI> I can as∣sure you, you will neither find me in the Pulpits, nor in the Schools of Learning, nor have any of those employed in such Places, moved me to this Attempt, or dic∣tated to me while I wrote. The Truth of what I now assert, the unpolished Plainness of my Address will confirm. But you may find me among the Black-Smiths Shops, belonging to the Presbyterians in Chester-County.</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>Sir,</SALUTE> <SIGNED>Your very humble Servant, MECHANICK.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

