<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2009-03-25</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Check for blanks. Checked for signatures. Checked for #s. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Corrected 4 $-groups. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N12446">
<STC T="E">15719</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99024208</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="015719_0000_0F99DFB093D42048"/>
<PB REF="015719_0001_0F99DFB40A630AD8" MS="y"/>
<P>AN ANIMADVERSORY ADDRESS TO THE INHABITANTS OF THE STATE OF VERMONT; WITH REMARKS on a PROCLAMATION, under the Hand of his Excellency GEORGE CLINTON, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> Governor of the State of NEW-YORK.</P>
<P>BY ETHAN ALLEN.</P>
<P><HI>HARTFORD:</HI> Printed by WATSON and GOODWIN, near the Great Bridge. M.DCC.LXXVIII.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="015719_0002_0F99DFB521A48C80"/>
<HEAD>An Animadversory ADDRESS, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>GENTLEMEN and FRIENDS,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I SHALL make no apology for writing this pamphlet; sure I am it was meant for your good: Besides, this is not the first time I have mov∣ed my quill in your behalf. Many times have I hazarded my life for you, as well as for my own property; and if occasion shall in future require, will freely do it again.</P>
<P>ON my return from a barbarous captivity, (part of which extraordinary sufferings was for your sakes) to <HI>Bennington,</HI> the latter end of May, 1778, and having received the congratulations of a large circle of friends, and returned them the mutual ex∣change of compliment and friendship, and had agree∣ably entertained ourselves in commemorating the surprizing success of the last campaign; —the down∣fall of a whole British army, with a BURGOYNE at their head: And after moving the flowing bowl, expatiated on the ever-memorable battle and victory of <HI>Bennington,</HI> the forerunner and grand typical fi∣gure of the destruction of the Northern army; we then took a retrospective view of our old <HI>New-York</HI> quarrel, and entered into a discussion on the politi∣cal
<PB N="4" REF="015719_0003_0F99DFB5A3C4E028"/>
events of forming the new State of VERMONT, it then appeared to me to be a very political move∣ment. I have since, upon mature deliberation, ex∣patiated on the good effects which cannot fail of re∣dounding to the inhabitants, in so extensive a fron∣tier country, from the blessings of a well established civil government; and think it worth my trouble to communicate my sentiments and reflections to the public, with a view of encouraging the good and virtuous inhabitants of this State, to persevere and be happy in the further confirming and establishing the same.</P>
<P>TO live in a state of anarchy, has been found to be inconsistent with the wisdom and practice of mankind in all ages and nations, particularly the civilized; and savage tribes have certain maxims, customs or traditions, which are substituted instead of written laws. Indeed, the state and condition of men urgeth, nay, necessitates them to adopt some form of government for their mutual protection and defence: And, inasmuch as a long course of expe∣rience has, or in truth may convince every capable judge in the said state of <HI>Vermont,</HI> that the govern∣ment of <HI>New-York</HI> never desired to exercise jurisdic∣tional authority over the inhabitants of said state, for any other purpose but to oppress and deprive them of their lands and labours; therefore, it is our duty and interest to yield them no subjection. Sure∣ly, it was not because they loved us or we them; for, the hatred subsisting between us, is equivalent to that which subsists between the Independent States of <HI>America</HI> and <HI>Great Britain.</HI> Every overture of
<PB N="5" REF="015719_0004_0F99DFB663BD8558"/>
pretended peace and friendship to us, is big with mischief and secret design to entrap and ensnare the unwary among us, to divide us, and overturn our new government. This may be learnt from their late proclamation, as well as from many other ways and arts used particularly in the south-east corner of <HI>Cumberland</HI> county, where there are many Tories, who, to a man, through the whole state, are using their influence and intrigues against our new state, in favour of the government of <HI>New-York,</HI> which, for certain motives they prefer.</P>
<P>BUT, to take a retrospective view of the conduct of that government towards us, from four to six, or seven years ago, and we shall find that the <HI>New York</HI> patentees got judgment against those under <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> at trials at common law; but the claim∣ants under <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> appealed to club law, and, in this mode of trial, they beat the claimants under <HI>New-York;</HI> and, in those days, a sort of mob go∣vernment, in the now county of <HI>Bennington</HI> took place, which, however deficient in most respects, was nevertheless the terror of the government of <HI>New-York,</HI> and the only means by which we could possibly maintain the possession of our lands. In the mean the then counties of <HI>Cumberland</HI> and <HI>Glouces∣ter</HI> were greatly oppressed by the venality and cor∣ruption of the government of <HI>New-York:</HI> This I re∣fer to the knowledge of the inhabitants in those counties; though it is altogether probable, that pro∣vided <HI>New-York</HI> government had conquered the Green Mountain Boys, and monopolized their lands, those on the east side of the mountain would have
<PB N="6" REF="015719_0005_0F99DFB74A8B3800"/>
shared the same fate. I have only to add, in this place, that in those days civil government could not be assumed; but I now rejoice to see it established. This is the happy aera which our worthy and de∣ceased friend, Doctor <HI>Thomas Young,</HI> beautifully ex∣pressed himself to the inhabitants of the state of <HI>Ver∣mont,</HI> in these words: <Q>As the supreme Arbiter of right has smiled on the just cause of <HI>North-Ame∣rica</HI> at large, you in a peculiar manner have been highly favoured; God has done by you the best thing commonly done for our species; he has fairly put it in your power to help yourselves.</Q> Our constitution is very much approved of in such parts of the eastern states, where it has been circu∣lated; and though it be difficult, nay, impossible to form a mode of government to the entire satisfac∣tion of the whole body politic; yet I am appre∣hensive, that there are as little, I may say less dissa∣tisfaction in the state of <HI>Vermont,</HI> as to matters of government, as in any of the eastern states, <HI>Connecti∣cut</HI> excepted. Probably, there are some in every state who are averse to any mode of government at all; and such, I fear, are out of the reach of argu∣ment and reason; such are untractable and barba∣rous souls, who enjoy no satisfaction in the happi∣ness of their species, or in the effusion of domestic peace, order, and social virtue: But all good and wise men, will exert themselves in establishing and supporting good government and order, which are inseparably connected together: And though, in the tumults and confusions of a cruel war, the present formed constitutions and modes of government may, and undoubtedly are, more or less imperfect; yet
<PB N="7" REF="015719_0006_0F99DFBB8AAE44A8"/>
they may, in future, be corrected and amended as time of leisure, cool deliberation, and experience may dictate.</P>
<P>CERTAIN I am, that our frontier country was un∣der the greatest necessity of forming into a civil and political government. They were obliged to exer∣cise, not only an internal policy among themselves, but an external policy against a foreign invasion. This they could not trust to <HI>New-York,</HI> who would have been rejoiced to have our inhabitants cut off, that their lands might have fallen into their hands; an object which they have been pursuing for more than seven years last past. In this extreme situation government was formed, and General <HI>Burgoyne</HI> at the same time advancing into the country. The Council of our new state was very busy and zealous in forming the militia into regiments, under brave officers, to face Mr. <HI>Burgoyne:</HI> At the same time Ge∣neral <HI>Schuyler</HI> ordered our militia to march to <HI>Sara∣taga;</HI> but the Council would not allow it, as they viewed <HI>Bennington,</HI> and the adjacent country, to be the object of destruction by the enemy, at least, if not so, by their old adversaries. The Council, fur∣thermore, sent an express to the Council of the state of <HI>New-Hampshire,</HI> acquainting them of the distressed situation of the state of <HI>Vermont,</HI> and imploring their assistance, which <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> generously afforded, sending their hero General <HI>Starks,</HI> with a brigade of valiant men, which being joined by the Green Mountain Boys, terminated in the memorable and twice glorious battles and victories of <HI>Bennington.</HI> This proved the salvation of our new state, and had
<PB N="8" REF="015719_0007_0F99DFBCC3955008"/>
its salutary influence on the pending cause of the In∣dependent States of <HI>America</HI> at large, and is a strik∣ing proof of the good policy of assuming govern∣ment.</P>
<P>ANY one who is acquainted with mankind and things, must know, that it is impossible to manage the political matters of this country without the as∣sistance of civil government. A large body of peo∣ple destitute of it, is like a ship in the sea without a helm or mariner, tossed by impetuous waves. We could not enjoy domestic peace and security alone, set aside the consequences of a <HI>British</HI> war and <HI>New-York</HI> strife, without civil regulations. The two last considerations do, in the most striking manner, ex∣cite us to strengthen and confirm the government already set up by the authority of the people, which is the fountain of all temporal power, and from which the subjects of the state of <HI>Vermont</HI> have alrea∣dy received such signal advantages. This puts us on an equal footing with our old <HI>New-York</HI> adver∣saries, and will enable us to baffle all their schemes; and this the General Assembly of the State of <HI>New-York</HI> well knew, when they sent forth their Procla∣mation from <HI>Poughkeepsie,</HI> dated the 23d day of <HI>Fe∣bruary,</HI> 1778, and signed by his Excellency <HI>George Clinton,</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> Governor of that state: Which Pro∣clamation I do here insert, (for the purpose of in∣forming the inhabitants of the state of <HI>Vermont</HI> of the designs of the new legislature of the state of <HI>New-York</HI>) together with my observations on the same.</P>
<Q><PB N="9" REF="015719_0008_0F99DFBD94D15C68"/>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="proclamation">
<HEAD>By his Excellency GEORGE CLINTON, <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> Gover∣nor of the State of <HI>New-York,</HI> General of all the Militia, and Admiral of the Navy of the same.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">A PROCLAMATION.</HEAD>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">L. S.</NOTE>WHEREAS the Senate and Assembly of this state, did, by their several resolutions passed the twenty-first day of this instant month of February, declare and resolve, That the disaffection of many persons, inhabiting the north eastern parts of the county of <HI>Albany,</HI> and certain parts of the counties of <HI>Charlotte, Cumberland</HI> and <HI>Gloucester,</HI> clear∣ly included within the ancient, original, true and lately established bounds of this state, arose from a contest, about the property of the soil of many tracts of land, within those parts of the said counties re∣spectively.</P>
<P>THAT the said contest was occasioned partly by the issuing of divers interfering patents or grants, by the respective governments of <HI>New-York,</HI> on the one part, and those of <HI>Massachusetts-Bay</HI> and <HI>New-Hampshire,</HI> on the other, antecedent to the late esta∣blishment of the eastern boundary of this state; part∣ly by an higher quit rent reserved on the said lands, when re-granted under <HI>New-York,</HI> than were reserv∣ed in the original grants under <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> or <HI>Massachusetts-Bay,</HI> and the exorbitant fees of office accruing thereon; and partly by a number of grants made by the late government of <HI>New-York</HI> after the establishment of the said eastern boundary, for lands which had been before granted by the governments
<PB N="10" REF="015719_0009_0F99DFBDE36412E8"/>
of <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> and <HI>Massachusetts-Bay,</HI> respectively, or one of them; in which last mentioned grants by the late government of <HI>New-York,</HI> the interest of the servants of the Crown, and of new adventurers, was, in many instances, contrary to justice and po∣licy, preferred to the equitable claims for confirma∣tion of those who had patented the lands under <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> or <HI>Massachusetts-Bay.</HI></P>
<P>THAT the aforesaid disaffection has been greatly increased, by an act passed by the Legislature of the late colony of <HI>New-York,</HI> on the ninth day of March, in the year of our Lord one thousand seven hun∣dred and seventy-four, entitled, "An Act for pre∣venting tumultuous and riotous assemblies in the places therein mentioned, and for the more speedy and effectual punishing the rioters." That many of the aforesaid disaffected persons, though unjustifiable in their opposition to the authority of this state, la∣bour under grievances arising from the causes above mentioned, which in some measure extenuate their offence, and which ought to be redressed.</P>
<P>THAT therefore the Legislature of this state, while on the one hand, they will vigorously maintain their rightful supremacy over the persons and property of those disaffected subjects, will on the other hand, make overtures to induce the voluntary submission of the delinquents.</P>
<P>THAT an absolute and unconditional discharge, and remission of all prosecutions, penalties and for∣feitures, under the above-mentioned act, shall be an
<PB N="11" REF="015719_0010_0F99DFBEB0AA2910"/>
established preliminary to such overtures; which o∣vertures are as follow, <HI>viz.</HI></P>
<P N="1">1st THAT all persons actually possessing and im∣proving lands, by title under grants from <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> or <HI>Massachusetts-Bay,</HI> and not granted un∣der <HI>New York,</HI> shall be confirmed in their respective possessions.</P>
<P N="2">2d. THAT all persons actually possessing and im∣proving lands, not granted by either of the three governments, shall be confirmed in their respective possessions, together with such additional quantity of vacant land, lying contiguous to each respective possession, as may be necessary to form the same in∣to a convenient farm; so as the quantity to be con∣firmed to each respective person, including his pos∣session, shall not exceed three hundred acres.</P>
<P N="3">3d. THAT where lands have heretofore been granted by <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> and <HI>Massachusetts-Bay,</HI> or either of them, and actually possessed in consequence thereof, and being so possessed, were afterwards granted by <HI>New-York,</HI> such possessions shall be con∣firmed, the posterior grant under <HI>New-York,</HI> not∣withstanding.</P>
<P><HI>Provided always,</HI> That nothing in the above regu∣lations contained, shall be construed to determine any question of title or possession, that may arise between different persons claiming under <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> or <HI>Massachusetts-Bay,</HI> or between persons claiming un∣der <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> on the one, and under <HI>Massachu∣setts-Bay</HI>
<PB N="12" REF="015719_0011_0F99DFBF75298710"/>
on the other part, independent of any right or claim under <HI>New-York.</HI></P>
<P N="4">4th. THAT with respect to all such cases, concern∣ing the aforesaid controverted lands, as cannot be decided by the rules exhibited in the aforegoing ar∣ticles, or some or one of them, the Legislature of the state of <HI>New-York,</HI> will provide for the determina∣tion of the same, according to the rules of justice and equity arising out of such cases respectively, without adhering to the strict rules of law.</P>
<P N="5">5th. THAT in all cases where grants or confirma∣tions shall become necessary, on acceptance of the above overtures, such grants or confirmations, shall issue to the grantees, at and after the rate of five pounds for a grant or confirmation of three hun∣dred acres or under, and for every additional hun∣dred acres, the additional sum of sixteen shillings, except in cases, where lands shall be granted or con∣firmed to divers persons in one entire tract, in which case the grants shall issue, respectively, for fifteen pounds each, which allowances shall be in lieu of all other fees or perquisites whatsoever.</P>
<P N="6">6th. THAT whenever, agreeable to the above re∣gulations, new grants or confirmations shall become necessary under this state, for lands heretofore grant∣ed by <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> or <HI>Massachusetts-Bay,</HI> the same quit rent only shall be reserved, which was reserved in the original grants, under <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> or <HI>Mas∣sachusetts-Bay.</HI></P>
<P N="7"><PB N="13" REF="015719_0012_0F99DFC032FDDD10"/>7th. THAT where lands heretofore granted by <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> or <HI>Massachusetts Bay,</HI> have been since confirmed to such grantees by new grants under <HI>New-York,</HI> the quit rents on such lands, shall be re∣duced to what they were in the original grants, un∣der <HI>New Hampshire</HI> or <HI>Massachusetts-Bay.</HI></P>
<P N="8">8th. THAT in order to encourage the settlement of the aforesaid disputed lands, in a peaceable sub∣jection to the authority and jurisdiction of this state, and also of all other lands, held within and under this state, the following commutation for the quit rents, shall be allowed, <HI>viz.</HI> That on payment, at the rate of two shillings and six-pence lawful money of this state, into the treasury of this state, for every penny sterling of quit rent reserved, or on delivery into the same, of seventeen times the quantity of grain, or other commodity reserved for such quit rent, the same shall thence forward be utterly discharged, and for ever cease and be extinguished.</P>
<P>THAT these overtures should be offered with a view, not only to induce the aforesaid discontented inhabitants, of the counties of <HI>Albany, Charlotte, Cum∣berland</HI> and <HI>Gloucester,</HI> to return to a lawful and right∣ful obedience to the authority and jurisdiction of this state; but also in favour of all others whom the same may concern; and to be of no avail to any person or persons whatsoever, who shall after the first day of May next, yield or acknowledge, any al∣legiance or subjection to the pretended state of <HI>Ver∣mont,</HI> the pretended government thereof, or to any power or authority, pretended to be held or exercis∣ed thereunder.</P>
<P><PB N="14" REF="015719_0013_0F99DFC0F1100B18"/>THAT the aforegoing overtures, on the condition above expressed, be tendered for acceptance to all persons, to whose case the same, or any or either of them, do, or shall apply, upon the public faith and assurance of the legislature and government of this state of <HI>New-York,</HI> pledged to such person and per∣sons for the purpose.</P>
<P>THAT the several branches of the Legislature of the state of <HI>New-York,</HI> will concur in the necessary measures for protecting the loyal inhabitants of this state, residing in the counties of <HI>Albany, Charlotte, Cumberland</HI> and <HI>Gloucester,</HI> in their persons and estates, and for compelling all persons, residing within this state, and refusing obedience to the Government and Legislature thereof, to yield that obedience and al∣legiance, which, by law and of right, they owe to this state.</P>
<P><HI>And whereas,</HI> The said Senate and Assembly of this state of <HI>New York,</HI> have also, by their resolution requested me to issue my Proclamation, under the privy seal of this state, reciting their aforesaid decla∣rations and resolutions, and strictly charging and commanding all manner of persons, in the name of the people of the state of <HI>New-York,</HI> to take due no∣tice thereof, <HI>at their peril,</HI> and to govern themselves accordingly.</P>
<P>I DO THEREFORE <HI>hereby, in the name of the people of the state of New York,</HI> publish and proclaim the aforesaid declarations and resolutions; and I do hereby, strictly charge and command all manner of
<PB N="15" REF="015719_0014_0F99DFC1E7BCF940"/>
persons, within this state, at their peril, to take due notice of this proclamation, and of every article, clause, matter and thing therein recited and con∣tained, and to govern themselves accordingly.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Given under my Hand, and the Privy Seal of the State of <HI>New-York,</HI> at <HI>Poughkeepsie,</HI> in the County of <HI>Dutchess,</HI> <DATE>the Twenty Third Day of <HI>February,</HI> in the Year of our Lord One Thousand Seven Hun∣dred and Seventy Eight.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>GEO. CLINTON.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
<CLOSER>GOD save the PEOPLE.</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P>THIS proclamation, after mentioning a disaf∣fection of many persons inhabiting the northeast parts of the county of <HI>Albany,</HI> and certain parts of the counties of <HI>Charlotte, Cumberland</HI> and <HI>Gloucester,</HI> proceeds to affirm that these tracts of country were clearly included within the antient, original, true and lately established bounds of the state of <HI>New-York.</HI></P>
<P>THAT many, nay almost the whole of the inhabi∣tants in those counties, <HI>alias,</HI> the state of <HI>Vermont,</HI> are disaffected to the government of <HI>New-York,</HI> will not be disputed. This is a fact: But it is not fact, that the ancient, original and true bounds of <HI>New-York</HI> included those lands. The first intimation that ever saluted the ears of the public, asserting this doctrine, was, from a proclamation of Governor <HI>Tryon</HI>'s, dat∣ed the 11th day of December, 1771, which begins thus: <Q>Whereas, it is the ancient and incontesti∣ble
<PB N="16" REF="015719_0015_0F99DFC5F3F79AA8"/>
right of this colony, to extend to <HI>Connecticut</HI> River as its eastern boundary.</Q> This assertion hath been answered at large in my Treatise on the Conduct of this Government towards the <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> Settlers, to which I refer the reader, and at present observe, that as the quoted assertions in these proclamations, are wholly without foundation, they need only to be as positively denied as they are asserted. The fact is, that the tract of land which now comprehends the state of <HI>Vermont,</HI> was universally known to be in the government of <HI>New-Hampshire.</HI> Thus it was placed by all Geographers in their maps, 'till the year 1764, when the now <HI>English</HI> King, for certain political reasons, which I shall mention, extended the jurisdiction of <HI>New-York</HI> over the premises, by his special royal authority. At the time of the alteration of this jurisdiction, jea∣lousies had fir'd the minds of King and Parliament against the growth and rising power of <HI>America,</HI> and at this time they began to advance men and govern∣ments into power, with a political design to crush the liberties of <HI>America. New-York</HI> had ever been their favourite government: They could almost vie with <HI>Great-Britain</HI> in the art of vassalaging common people, and in erasing every idea of liberty from the human mind, by making and keeping them poor and servile. This <HI>Great-Britain</HI> well knew; and therefore sliced a large territory from <HI>New-Hampshire,</HI> and added it to <HI>New York,</HI> to depress the power of the one, and enlarge and extend the other. A well concerted plan: But the Green Mountain Boys disconcerted it, by throwing their weight in to the
<PB N="17" REF="015719_0016_0F99DFC729E791D0"/>
scale of Congress, which, thank God, has fairly ponderated. Thus may be seen the design, as well as date, of the original, ancient and true bounds of the state of <HI>New-York</HI>'s being extended over the state of <HI>Vermont;</HI> and, for the same reason it was thus ex∣tended by <HI>Great-Britain,</HI> it will undoubtedly be cur∣tailed by Congress.</P>
<P>AS to the acts of outlawry, mentioned in the Pro∣clamation, they died a natural death the first day of January, 1776, as may be seen from the act itself, here quoted:
<Q>And be it further enacted by the authority aforesaid, that this act shall remain and continue in full force and effect, from the passing thereof, until the first day of January, which will be in the year of our Lord, one thousand seven hundred and seventy-six.</Q></P>
<P>THE subjects of the state of <HI>Vermont</HI> were under no apprehensions from these old, lifeless acts: Nor do I conceive, that the present Legislature of the state of <HI>New-York</HI> have laid them under any obliga∣tion, in granting them a pardon. It was a matter which formerly respected Governor <HI>Tryon,</HI> the old Legislature of <HI>New-York,</HI> and the Green Mountain Boys; and the party last mentioned, choose to settle that old quarrel with Mr. <HI>Tryon,</HI> and resent it, that the Legislature of the state of <HI>New-York</HI> have, so late in the day, undertook to give an <Q>Unconditional discharge and remission of all penalties and for∣feitures incurred,</Q> under an act, which had been long dead; and which, when alive, served only to discover to the world, the wickedness and depravi∣ty
<PB N="18" REF="015719_0017_0F99DFC89BCF6280"/>
of that legislative body which enacted them. In the lifetime of this act, I was called by the <HI>Yorkers</HI> an outlaw, and afterwards by the <HI>British</HI> was called a rebel; and I humbly conceive, that there was as much propriety in the one name as the other, and I verily believe, that the King's Commissioners would now be as willing to pardon me for the sin of rebel∣lion, provided I would afterwards be subject to <HI>Bri∣tain,</HI> as the Legislature abovementioned, provided I would be a subject to <HI>New-York;</HI> and, I must con∣fess, I had as leave be a subject to the one as the other, and, it is well known, I have had great ex∣perience with them both.</P>
<P>NEXT, I propose to consider that part of the pro∣clamation called Overtures, which are contained in the three first articles. Article 1st. <Q>That all per∣sons actually possessing and improving lands, by title under grants from <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> of <HI>Massa∣chusetts-Bay,</HI> and not granted under <HI>New-York,</HI> shall be confirmed in their respective possessions.</Q></P>
<P>THIS first article cannot be considered of any ma∣terial consequence, inasmuch, as among almost the whole possessions referred to in the article, there are but very few, if any, but what are covered with <HI>New-York</HI> grants.</P>
<P>THE second article is as follows: <Q>That all per∣sons possessing and improving lands, not granted by either of the three governments, shall be con∣firmed in their respective possessions, together with such additional quantity of vacant land, ly∣ing
<PB N="19" REF="015719_0018_0F99DFC8AF0907E8"/>
contiguous to each respective possession, as may be necessary to form the same into a conve∣nient farm, so as the quantity of land to be con∣firmed to each respective possession, shall not ex∣ceed three hundred acres.</Q></P>
<P>NEITHER of these two first articles, called Over∣tures, affect the controversy, except in some very few instances, inasmuch as all, or in a manner all the possessions spoken of, were first granted by <HI>New-Hampshire,</HI> except some few which were granted by <HI>Massachusetts-Bay;</HI> and then, lastly, almost the whole of those possessions regranted by <HI>New-York.</HI> This being the case, what has been hitherto proposed, does not reach the essence of the controversy, as the <HI>New-Yorkers</HI> very well know; besides, it is not in the power of the government to confirm any of those possessions which have been already granted, and therefore become the property of the grantees, as will be more fully discussed in its proper place. I proceed to the third article of the much boasted O∣vertures.</P>
<P><Q>THAT where lands have been heretofore grant∣ed by <HI>New-Hampshire</HI> and <HI>Massachusetts-Bay,</HI> or ei∣ther of them, and actually possessed in consequence thereof, and being so possessed, were afterwards granted by <HI>New-York,</HI> such possession shall be con∣firmed, the posterior grant under <HI>New-York</HI> not∣withstanding.</Q></P>
<P>THOUGH it is absolutely out of the power of the said legislative authority, to confirm the possessions
<PB N="20" REF="015719_0019_0F99DFC93499C648"/>
mentioned; yet, to discover their want of generosi∣ty in their proposal, I shall, in the first place, consi∣der what a trifling proportion of those possessions could be confirmed upon their own stating, inas∣much, as the confirming clause in the article, only confirms the possessor, who being so possessed at the time that the <HI>New-York</HI> grant was laid, and has no respect to any additional possession carried on after the grant took place: The identical words are, <Q>And being so possessed, were afterwards granted by <HI>New-York;</HI></Q> <HI>viz.</HI> After such possession was ac∣tually made, and the possessor being so in possession, at the time the grant took place, such possession shall be confirmed, but any later possession cannot be included in the condition of "being so possessed;" for, a later possession was no possession at all at the time the condition of possession took place; and con∣sequently, every possession which has been begun in the state of <HI>Vermont,</HI> since the lands were granted by <HI>New-York,</HI> must be lost to the possessor, and fall into the hands of the <HI>New-York</HI> grantees, with all other uncultivated lands in the state; and all our pur∣chases of those lands from <HI>New Hampshire</HI> and <HI>Mas∣sachusetts-Bay,</HI> fall to the ground, together with our possessions, which have been increased an hundred fold.</P>
<P>THESE Overtures have hitherto been considered only in a grammatical and logical sense, allowing them their own construction; I now proceed to con∣sider them in a law sense. A legislative authority, within its own jurisdiction, may confirm a possession on vacant land, by making a grant of the same to
<PB N="21" REF="015719_0020_0F99DFC9EC878558"/>
the possessor: But, for the legislative authority of the state of <HI>New York,</HI> to pretend as they do in their proclamation, to vacate any grants made by their own authority, in favour of any possession, and to confirm such possessions, by nullifying and defeating their own grants, is the height of folly and stupidi∣ty: For, the lands being once granted, the proper∣ty passeth to the grantee, who is become the sole proprietor of the same; and he is as independent of that legislative authority which granted it, as any person may be supposed to be, who purchaseth a farm of land of me by deed of conveyance; and it is as much out of the power of that legislature to vacate a grant made by them, or the same authori∣ty, in favour of any possessor, as it is out of my power to vacate my deed of conveyance in favour of some second person. It is contrary to common sense, to suppose, that the property of the subject is at the arbitrary disposal of the Legislature: If it was, they might give a grant to-day, and vacate it to-morrow, and so on, <HI>ad infinitum.</HI> This would de∣stroy the very nature and existance of personal pro∣perty, as the whole would depend on the sovereign will and last act of the Legislature: But the truth of the matter is, the first conveyance will, and ought to hold good; and this defeats all subsequent con∣veyances.</P>
<P>FROM what has been said on this subject, it ap∣pears, that the Overtures in the Proclamation set forth, are either romantic, or calculated to deceive woods people, who, in general, may not be suppos∣ed to understand law, or the power of a legislative authority.</P>
<P><PB N="22" REF="015719_0021_0F99DFCAD1E82AE0"/>I HAVE further to evince my arguments on this subject, by the concurring opinion of the Lords of the Board of Trade, on complaint made to them from those very persons, possessing the lands we are speak∣ing of. That clause of their report which is simi∣lar to what I have argued, is in these words: <Q>Such subsequent grants made by the government of <HI>New York,</HI> however unwarrantable, cannot be set aside by any authority from his Majesty, in case the grantees shall insist on their title.</Q></P>
<P>THUS it appears, in a trial (of the same case we are treating of) before the Board of Trade, that the King, under whose authority the government of <HI>New-York</HI> had, in an oppressive manner granted those very lands, could not, by his royal authority, vacate or set aside the grants; yet the present legislative authority of the state of <HI>New-York,</HI> proclaim to the world, and pledge the faith of government, that they will do it: But enough has been said on the impossibility of it, as well as on the ungenerousness of the proposal: And as to the quit-rents, the Ge∣neral Assembly of the state of <HI>Vermont</HI> will determine their expediency, and probably release them all.</P>
<P>WHAT has been observed, answers every part of the Proclamation worth notice, as the five last arti∣cles had an entire reference to the three first; though, it may be worth observing, that the time of compli∣ance with those Overtures are run out, and, it is my opinion, that but few of the subjects of the state of <HI>Vermont</HI> have closed with them. The main induce∣ment
<PB N="23" REF="015719_0022_0F99DFCB8DA170E0"/>
I had in answering them was, to draw a full and convincing proof from the same, that the short∣est, best, and most eligible, I had almost said, the on∣ly possible way of vacating those <HI>New-York</HI> interfer∣ing grants, is, to maintain inviolable the supremacy of the legislative authority of the independent state of <HI>Vermont:</HI> This, at one stroke, overturns every <HI>New-York</HI> scheme which may be calculated for our ruin, makes us free men, confirms our property, "and puts it fairly in our power to help ourselves," in the enjoyment of the great blessings of a free, un∣corrupted and virtuous civil government. You have fought, bled, and hitherto conquered, and are as de∣serving these good fruits of your valour, hazard and toil, as any people under heaven.</P>
<P>YOU have experienced every species of oppressi∣on, which the old government of <HI>New-York,</HI> with a <HI>Tryon</HI> at their head, could invent and inflict; and it is manifest, that the new government are minded to follow nearly in their steps. Happy it is for you that you are fitted for the severest of tryals, you have been wonderfully supported, and carried through thus far in your opposition to that government. Formerly you had every thing to fear from it: But now you have little to fear, for your public character is established, and your cause known to be just. In your early struggles with that govern∣ment you acquired a reputation of bravery; this gave you a relish for martial glory, and the British invasion opened an ample field for its display, and you have gone on conquering and to conquer until
<PB N="24" REF="015719_0023_0F99DFCC292660C8"/>
TALL GRENADIERS are dismayed and tremble at your approach. Your frontier situation often obliges you to be in arms and battles; and by repeated marchings, scoutings and manly exercises, your nerves have become strong to strike the mortal blow. What enemy to the state of <HI>Vermont,</HI> or <HI>New-York</HI> land monopolizer, shall be able to stand before you in the day of your fierce anger!</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>BENNINGTON,
<DATE><HI>August</HI> 9, 1778.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>THE END.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<P>ERRAT. In page 5, line 25, <HI>after</HI> mean <HI>add</HI> time.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

