<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A narrative of the miseries of New-England, by reason of an arbitrary government erected there. Under Sir Edmond Andross. To which is added, some account of the humble application of the pious and noble Prelate, Henry Lord Bishop of London, with the reverend clergy of the city, and some of the dissenting ministers in it, to the illustrious Prince William Henry, Prince of Orange on Fryday [sic], September 21. 1688. : Also the address of the noncomformist ministers (in and about the city of London) to His Higness [sic] the Prince of Orange.</title>
            <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-03">2005-03.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N00368</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N00368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 450</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1231A</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX3030</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">450</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99019794</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 450.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N00368)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 450)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 450)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A narrative of the miseries of New-England, by reason of an arbitrary government erected there. Under Sir Edmond Andross. To which is added, some account of the humble application of the pious and noble Prelate, Henry Lord Bishop of London, with the reverend clergy of the city, and some of the dissenting ministers in it, to the illustrious Prince William Henry, Prince of Orange on Fryday [sic], September 21. 1688. : Also the address of the noncomformist ministers (in and about the city of London) to His Higness [sic] the Prince of Orange.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p. ;  (4to) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>London, printed, for Richard Janeway in Queen's-Head-Court, in Pater Noster-Row. And reprinted at Boston in New-England, by Richard Pierce.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Boston] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688 [i.e., 1689, New Style].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Increase Mather by Holmes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Territory and Dominion of New-England. --  President (1686-1689 : Andros).</term>
               <term>New England --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09</date>
            <label>AEL Data (Chennai)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="unknown:000450_0000_0FA5B18FEA66ACE0"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:000450_0001_0FA5B19091AB9EE0"/>
            <head>A Narrative of the MISERIES of NEW-ENGLAND, by Reason of an ARBITRARY Government Erected there. Under Sir Edmond Andross.</head>
            <p>To Which is added, <hi>Some Account of the Humble Application of the pious and noble Prelate,</hi> Henry <hi>Lord Bishop of</hi> London, <hi>with the Reverend Clergy of the City, and some of the</hi> Dissenting Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters <hi>in it, To the Illustrious Prince</hi> William Henry, <hi>Prince of</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range <hi>on Fryday, September</hi> 21. 1688.</p>
            <p>Also <hi>The Address of the</hi> Nonconformist Ministers (<hi>in and about the City of</hi> LONDON) <hi>to His Higness the Prince of</hi> ORANGE.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <head>The Narrative of the Miseries of N. England, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THat a Colony so considerable as <hi>New-England</hi> is, should be discouraged, is not for the Honour &amp; Interest of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Nation;</hi> in as much as the People there are generally Sober, Industrious, Well-Disciplin'd, and apt for Martial Affairs; so that he that is Sovereign of <hi>New-England</hi> may by means thereof, (<hi>when he pleaseth</hi>) be Emperour of <hi>America:</hi> Nevertheless, the <hi>whole English</hi> Interest in that Territory has been, of late, in apparent Danger of being <hi>lost</hi> &amp; <hi>ruined,</hi> and the Miseries of that People by an Arbitrary Government erected amonst them, have been, beyond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression great.</p>
            <p>The Original of all which has been the <hi>Quo Warranto</hi>'s issued out against their <hi>Charters,</hi> by means <hi>whereof</hi> they have been deprived of their <hi>ancient Rights and Privileges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Massachusets Colony</hi> (whose Patent beareth date from the year 1628) There was in the year 1683, a <hi>Quo warranto</hi>; and after that, in the year 1684, a <hi>Writ</hi> of <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> against them, and they were required to make their Appearance at <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in October, when they knew nothing <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the month before, so that it was impossible for them to answer at the <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> appointed; yet Judgment was entred against them.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="2" facs="unknown:000450_0002_0FA5B1918A0AA208"/>
alledged) had all their Priviledges at once taken from them. There was a <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> against <hi>Connecticut Colony</hi> (whose <hi>Charter</hi> was granted to them by King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second) only Letters were sent to them in the King's Name, signifying, that (incase they did resign their Charter) they should take their Choice of being under <hi>New-York</hi> or <hi>Boston.</hi> Several of the Magistrates there returned a most humble &amp; supplicatory Answer, praying, That their former Government might still continue; but that if it must be taken from them, they had rather be under <hi>Boston</hi> than <hi>New-York:</hi> This was by some at Court interpreted a <hi>Resignation of their Charter,</hi> and a <hi>Commission</hi> sent to Sir <hi>Edmond Andross,</hi> who <hi>went</hi> to <hi>Hartford,</hi> (their principal Town) and declared their Charter and former Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be void. As for <hi>Road-Island,</hi> they submitted themselves to His Majesties pleasure.</p>
            <p>Before these Changes happened, <hi>New-England</hi> was, of all the Forreign Plantations (their enemies themselves being Judges) the most flourishing and desireable.</p>
            <p>But their Charters being all (one way or another) declared to be void and insignificant, it was an easy matter to erect a <hi>French</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in that part of the Kings Dominions, (no doubt intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Evil Counsellours) as a specimen of what was designed to be here in <hi>England,</hi> as soon as the times would bear it. According<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sir <hi>Edmond Andross</hi> (a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> man) was pitched on, as a fit In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument to be made use of; and a most illegal Commission given him, bearing date June 3, 1686. by which he, with four of his Council, (perhaps all of them his absolute <hi>Devotees</hi>) are impowered to make Laws and raise moneys on the Kings Subjects, without any Parliament, Assembly, or Consent of the People.</p>
            <p>It was thought by wise men, that the Remembrance of <hi>Dudley</hi> and <hi>Emp<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>son,</hi> who in the dayes of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8<hi>th</hi> were executed for acting by a like Commission, would have deterred them from doing so, but it did not, for Laws are made by few of them, and indeed what they please: nor are they printed: as was the Custom in the former Governments, so that the people are at a great loss to <hi>know what</hi> is <hi>Law and what <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Olny, <hi>one</hi> Law they are sensible of, which doth prohibit all Town-Meetings, excepting on a certain day once a year; whereas the Inhabitants have occasion to meet once a <hi>Week<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> for the Relief of the Poor; or other <hi>Town-Affairs.</hi> But it is <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to penetrate into the Design of this Law, which was (no Question) to keep them in <hi>every Town</hi> from Complaining to 
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:000450_0003_0FA5B1934933CDF0"/>
to <hi>England,</hi> of the Oppression they are under: And (as Laws have been establishst) so <hi>Moneys</hi> have been raised by the Government in a most illegal and Arbitrary way, <hi>without</hi> any <hi>consent of the People.</hi> Sir <hi>Edmond Andross</hi> caused a Tax to be levied of a <hi>Peny in a Pound</hi> on all the <hi>Towns</hi> then under his Government: and when at <hi>Ipswich</hi> and other places, the <hi>Select Men</hi> (as they are stiled) voted, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as it was against the common Priviledges of <hi>English</hi> Subjects to have money raised without their own Consent in an Assembly or Parliament; That therefore they would petition the King for Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of an Assembly before they made any Rates; the said Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Andross</hi> caused them to be imprisoned and Fined, some 20 <hi>l.</hi> some 30 <hi>l.</hi> as the Judges, by him instructed, should see meet to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine; yea, and several Gentlemen in the Country were Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned and bound to their Good Behaviour, upon meer suspicion, that they did incourage their Neighbours not to comply with these Arbitrary Proceedings. And that so they might be sure to effect their Pernicious Designs, they have caused Juries to be pick'd of Men who are not of the Vicinity, and some of them meer Strangers in the Country, and no Freeholders; which actings are highly ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal. One of the former Magistrates was committed to prison with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Crimes laid to his Charge, and there kept half a Year with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Fault; and though he petitioned for a <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> it was denied him. Also inferiour Officers have extorted what Fees they please to demand, contrary to all Rules of Reason and Justice. They make poor Widows and Fatherless pay 50 <hi>s.</hi> for the Probate of a Will, which under the former easy Government would not have been a Tenth part so much. Six Persons who had been ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally imprisoned, were forced to give the Officers 117 <hi>l.</hi> when as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Computation, they found that here in <hi>England</hi> their Fees would not have amounted to 10 <hi>l.</hi> in all. And yet these things (tho bad enough) are but a very small part of the Misery which that poor people have been groaning under, since they have been governed by a Despotick and Absolute Power. For, their new Masters tell them, that their Charter being gone, their Title to their Lands and Estates is gone therewith, and that all is the Kings? and that they represent the King; and that therefore all Persons must take Patients from them, and give what they see meet to impose, that so they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Houses which their own Hands have built, and the Lands, which at vast Charges in subduing a Wilderness; they have for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years had a rightful possession of, as ever any People in the world
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:000450_0004_0FA5B193DD3BF688"/>
had or can have; Accordingly the Governour ordered the Lands belonging to some in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to be measured out, and given to his Creatures, and Writs of <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be issued out against others: And the Commons belonging to several Towns have been given to some of the Governours <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, who begged them, to the impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing, if not utter ruining of whole Townships: And when an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sland belonging to the Town of <hi>Plimouth</hi> was petitioned away from them by one <hi>Nathaniel <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> whom Sir <hi>Edmond Andross</hi> made his Property <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> because the Agents of the said Town obtained a volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Subscription to maintain their Title at Law, they were compelled to come not only out of their own Country, but Colony, to <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, to answer there as <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the next Assizes, and bound to their good Behaviour: The Officers in the mean time extorting 3 <hi>l.</hi> per Man for Fees, These were the miserable Effects of <hi>New-England's</hi> being deprived of their Charters, and with them of their English li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties: They have not been altogether negligent. as to endeavours to obtain some relief in their sorrowful Bondage; for several Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen desired <hi>Increase Mather;</hi> the Rector of the Colledge at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> to undertake a Voyage for <hi>England,</hi> to see what might be done for his distressed Country, which Motion he complied with; and in <hi>June</hi> the 1st 1688: he had the favour to wait on the King, and privately to acquaint him with the enslaved and perishing Estate of his Subjects in <hi>New-England.</hi> The King was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gracious and kind in his Expressions; then, and often after pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mising to give them ease as to their Complaints and Fears; amongst other things the said <hi>Mather</hi> caused a petition from the Town of <hi>Cambridge</hi> in <hi>New-England</hi> to be humbly presented to his Majesty; which because it doth express the Deplorable Condition of that People, it shall he here inserted.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>To the King's Most Excellent Majesty</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Petition and Address of <hi>John Gibson,</hi> aged about 87, and <hi>George William,</hi> aged about 86 years; as also on the behalf of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours the inhabitants of <hi>Cambridge</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>In most humble wise sheweth,</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>THat Your Majesties good Subjects, with much hard Labour and great <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>, have subdued a Wilderness, built our Houses, and
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:000450_0005_0FA5B194723D82E0"/>
planted Orchards, being encouraged by our <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> Right to the Soil, by the <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="2 words">
                                 <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> granted unto the first <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>, together with our Purchase of the Natives; as also by sundry <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> and Declarations sent to the late Governour, and Company, <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> His <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> Majesty Your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Brother, assuring us of the full enjoyment of our <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> and Possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as is more especially contained in the declaration sent when the</hi> Quo Warranto <hi>was issued out against our Charter.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But we are necessitated to make this our Moan and Complaint to Your Excellent Majesty, for that our Title is now questioned to our Lands, by us quietly possessed for near</hi> 60 <hi>years, and without which we cannot subsist. Our humble <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> to our Governour</hi> Sir <hi>Edmond Andross, shewing our just Title, <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> and peaceable Possession, together with the claim of the <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> of Your Majesty's Letters and Declarations, assuring all your good Subjects, that they shall not be molested in their Properties and Possessions, not availing.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Royal Sir, We are a poor People, and have no way to procure money to defend our Cause in the Law; nor know we of Friends at Court, and therefore unto Your Royal Majesty, as the Publick Father of all Your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects do we make this our humble Address for Relief, beseeching Your Majesty graciously to pass Your Royal Act for the Confirmation of Your Majesties Subjects here in our Possessions to us derived from our late Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour and Company of this Your Majesty's Colony. We now humbly cast our selves, and distressed Condition of our Wives and Children; in Your MAJESTY's feet, and conclude with the Saying of Queen</hi> Esther, If we perish; we perish,</p>
                        <closer>Thus that Petition,</closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Besides this, Mr. <hi>Increase Mather,</hi> with two <hi>New-England</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, presented a Petition and humble Proposals to the King, wherein they prayed, that the Right which they had in their Estates before the Government was changed, might be confirmed; and that no Laws might be made or moneys Raised, without an Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, with sundry other particulars; which the King referred to a Committee for Foreign plantations, who ordered them into the hands of the Attourney-General to make his Report. The Clerk, <hi>William <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> sent to the Attourney General a Copy, wherein the Essential Proposal of an <hi>Assembly</hi> was wholly left out: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing spoke to about it, he said the Earl of <hi>Sunderland</hi> blotted out that with his own hand. Likewise a Soliciter in this Cause related that the said Earl of <hi>Sunderland</hi> affirmed to him, that it was by <hi>his</hi> Advice
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:000450_0006_0FA5B195336C2B58"/>
that the King had given a Commission to Sir <hi>Edmond Andross</hi> to raise moneys without an <hi>Assembly,</hi> and that he knew the King would never consent to an Alteration, nor would he <hi>propose</hi> it to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty. When of late all Charters were restored to <hi>England,</hi> it was high time for <hi>New</hi>-England to expect the like; for if it be an ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal and unjust thing to deprive good Subjects here of their Laws and Liberties, it cannot be consistent with Justice and Equity to deal so with those that are affar off. Applications therefore were made to the King, and to some Ministers of State: It was urged, that if a Foreign Prince or State should, during the present Troubles send a <hi>Friggot</hi> to <hi>New</hi>-E<hi>ngland,</hi> and promise to protect them as under their Former Government, it would be an unconquerable Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; yet no Restoration of Charters would be granted to <hi>New</hi>-E<hi>ngland,</hi> which has opened the Eyes of some thinking men. Thus has <hi>New</hi>-E<hi>ngland</hi> been dealt with: this has been and still <hi>is</hi> the bleeding state of that Countrey: they cannot but hope that E<hi>ng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> will send them speedy relief; especially considering that throw the ill Conduct of their present Rulers, the <hi>French Indians</hi> are (as the last Vessels from thence inform) beginning their cruel Butcheries amongst the E<hi>nglish</hi> in those parts. And many had fears that there is a Design to deliver that Countrey into the hands of the <hi>French</hi>-King, except His Highness the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> whom a Divine Hand has raised up to deliver the Oppressed, shall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and speedily prevent it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="application">
            <head>The humble Application of Henry Lord Bishop of London. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HE declared in excellent Words that they came to pay Him their humble Duties and most grateful Respects for His very great and most hazzardous Undertaking for their Deliverance, &amp; the Preservation of the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> and the Ancient Laws and Liberties of this Nation. <hi>He addeth,</hi> That they gave up daily ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Thanks givings to Almighty GOD, Who had hitherto been gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously pleased so <hi>wonderfully</hi> to preserve his Person, and prosper &amp; Favour his good Design: and they promised the continuance of the serventest of their Prayers to the same GOD, and to use all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current Endeavours in their Circumstances for the promoting, yet
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:000450_0007_0FA5B195CABE03E8"/>
further, that Work which was so happily begun; and also for the perfecting of it, not only in this Kingdom, but in other Christian Kingdoms. <hi>He likewise suggested to the Good Prince,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That some of the Dissenting Ministers and their Bretheren were there present, who having the same sense of His Coming hither with themselves, adjoined themselves with them, by him, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their humblest and most grateful Resentments.</p>
            <p>His Highness was pleas'd to declare, That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He thanked them for their Attendance, and acquainted them very briefly with the cheifest ends of His Difficult and Chargeable Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That indeed it was to preserve and secure the protestant Religion, (His own Religion, and their Religion) and assureing them, He should not think any thing (not Life it self) too <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to hazzard in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting and</hi> Perfecting <hi>so good a Work. Also He offered up (with great Devotion) his solemnest Acknowledgements to Almighty GOD for His Presence with him and Blessing upon his Endeavours &amp; Arms hitherto. And asked the Continuance of all their Prayers to God for him,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="address">
            <head>The Address of the Nonconformist Ministers &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WEdnesday, <hi>January</hi> the 2<hi>nd.</hi> Diverse of the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting Ministers in and about <hi>London,</hi> that go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Denomination of Presbiterial and Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational, to the Number of <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or upwards. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended His Highness the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> at St. <hi>James's,</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced by the Earl of <hi>Devonshire,</hi> the Lord <hi>Wharton,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Wiltshire,</hi> their Sense was represented by one of these Ministers to this Effect. <abbr>
                  <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>That they professed their grateful Sense of His Highness's hazzar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous &amp; Heroical Expedition which the Favour of Heaven had made so surprisingly prosperous.</p>
            <p>That they esteemed it a common Felicity that the worthy Patriots of the Nobility and Gentry of this Kingdom had unanimously concurred unto His Highness's Designs, by Whose most pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Advice, the Administration <gap reason="illegible: torn page" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Affairs
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:000450_0008_0FA5B19695995BA0"/>
devolved in this difficult Conjuncture into the Hands which the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and World <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be apt for the greatest <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and so suitable to the present <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="3 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>That they promised the utmost <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which in their Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they are capable of affording for <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> promoting the excellent and desireable Ends, for which his Highness had declared.</p>
            <p>That they added their continual fervent Prayers to Almighty, <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for the Defence and Propagation of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Interest throughout the Christian World.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (which some of them <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and which <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="5 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊◊◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to make mention of to His Highness) had their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of that intended Application been so early as to make <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>more general</hi> Attendance possible to them at that time.</p>
            <p>That therefore tho they did now appear in a distinct <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they did it not <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> distinct Account, but that only which common to them and to all Protestants.</p>
            <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="2 paragraphs">
               <desc>〈2 paragraphs〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> printed for <hi>Richard <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in Queen's-Head-Court, in <hi>Pater Noster-Row.</hi> And Reprinted at <hi>Boston</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> by <hi>Richard <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
