<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doctrine of the covenant of redemption. Wherein is laid the foundation of all our hopes and happiness. Briefly opened and improved. / By Samuel Willard, teacher of a church in Boston. ; [Three lines from Psalms]</title>
            <author>Willard, Samuel, 1640-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 174 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N00556</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N00556</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2274</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APZ0589</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">684</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99038208</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 684.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N00556)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 684)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 684)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doctrine of the covenant of redemption. Wherein is laid the foundation of all our hopes and happiness. Briefly opened and improved. / By Samuel Willard, teacher of a church in Boston. ; [Three lines from Psalms]</title>
                  <author>Willard, Samuel, 1640-1707.</author>
                  <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 165, [1] p. ;  15 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Benj. Harris over against the Old-Meeting-House.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Increase Mather.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Redemption.</term>
               <term>Covenant theology.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:000684_0000_0FA9A40E6E73FF90"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:000684_0001_0FA9A40F31691FC8"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Doctrine OF THE COVENANT OF REDEMPTION. Wherein is laid the Foundation of all our HOPES and HAPPINESS.</p>
            <p>Briefly Opened and Improved.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Willard,</hi> Teacher of a Church in <hi>BOSTON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Psal. 89.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I have made a Covenant with my Chosen, I have Sworn to <hi>David</hi> my Servant.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Boston,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benj. Harris</hi> against the <hi>Old-Meeting-House.</hi> 1693</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="unknown:000684_0002_0FA9A40FF20BFB30"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THE Great and Glorious God who has an absolute Dominion over his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, might (had he pleased) have dealt with Men in a way of Soveraignty only, requiring Duty and Obedience from them, without any promise of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. But he has seen Good to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sact with them in a Covenant way. There are but Two Covenants essenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally differing which the Most High has made with men, <hi>Viz.</hi> That of <hi>Works,</hi> And that of <hi>Grace.</hi> The first Covenant which man whilst in Paradise, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in, is rightly termed a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works,</hi> because <hi>Works or Doing,</hi> was the Condition of it. This was soon broken, and so made Null; but then the Lord out of his Infinite Goodness, was pleased to establish another Covenant, The first was made with a Righteous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and so a <hi>Covenant of Works,</hi>
               <pb facs="unknown:000684_0003_0FA9A410B33CE9B0"/>
between the Holy God and him. This latter was made with sinners and is therefore a <hi>Covenant of Reconciliation.</hi> And it is fitly stiled the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi>: Not but that there was Grace in the First Covenant, for His Divine Majesty did infinitely condescend in binding himself to his Creature: but to do thus to a fallen, forlorn sinful Creature, is <hi>by way of Eminent Grace.</hi> The Scripture speaketh expresly of <hi>Two Covenants, Gal 4.24.</hi> And that not only as <hi>Diverse,</hi> but as <hi>Opposite</hi> and differing in their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The Law of Faith is set in direct opposition to the Law of Works. <hi>Rom. 3.27. For a man to find the Life of his hands,</hi> to live by his own Righteousness; and for him to depend solely upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Righteousness of another, that is, of Jesus Christ for Life and Salvation, are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things. And from thence it is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a man to be under both the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants at the same time: he cannot be the Child of two Mothers, the Child of <hi>Hagar,</hi> and of <hi>Sarah</hi> too.</p>
            <p>That the Covenant of Grace has for
<pb facs="unknown:000684_0004_0FA9A411728194A8"/>
the substance of it been the same in all Ages, differing only in Circumstances &amp; as to the manner of dispensations is denied by the <hi>Old Pelagians,</hi> and by <hi>Socinians, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians,</hi> and some <hi>Baptists</hi> at this day. But the Scripture assureth us, <hi>That Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers under the Old-Testament were not made perfect without us. Heb. 11.40.</hi> They &amp; we are saved by the same Christ &amp; by the same Covenant, the Mediator of the Covenant has always been the same, <hi>Yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, to day, &amp; for ever the same. The Son of God was an Intercessor for his People before his Incarnation.</hi> Zach. <hi>1:12. Believers under the Old-Testament</hi> were <hi>secured by him.</hi> Neither is there salvation in any other. <hi>If then the Partriarchs were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ved (as we know they were) it was by Jesus Christ: No man was ever saved since the world began but by him. Under the Old-Testament Faith in Christ was neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary in order to Justification &amp; Salvation</hi> To him give all the Prophets Witness that through his Name, whoever believeth in him shall receive remission of sins. <hi>Promises which do concern Spiritual and Eternal
<pb facs="unknown:000684_0005_0FA9A4123312D440"/>
as well as Temporal blessings, were made to Old-Testament believers.</hi> Our Saviour proveth that the bodys of Saints shall have a Glorious Resurrection to Eternal Life from the Covenant made with Abraham. <hi>They of old, Looked for a City which has Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, whose maker and builder is God.</hi> Which, if Heaven (and not Temporal Blessings only) had not been Promised them, they would not have done. Now if there is an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as to the Mediator, the Condition, the promises of the Covenant made with Believers in the days of the Old Testament and of the New, the Covenant must needs be effectually the same. When therefore by the <hi>Old &amp;</hi> the <hi>New-Covenant,</hi> that of Works and of Grace are intended, the distribution is of the <hi>Genus</hi> into its <hi>Species.</hi> But when the Covenant of Grace as under the Legal or Evangelical dispensation, is meant (&amp; so it often is in the Scripture) the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction is of the same subject according to its various adjuncts.</p>
            <p>There is another Covenant which that of Grace is built upon, Viz. <hi>The Covenant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi> That there have been blessed Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sactions between God the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ther and the Son from the Days of Eternity, concerning the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Elect, is a glorious Truth, which (not the light of nature but only) the written word of God has revealed; That speaketh of <hi>Gods Purpose
<pb facs="unknown:000684_0006_0FA9A412F4CAD0F8"/>
and Grace given us in Christ Jesus before the world began,</hi> and of <hi>Eternal Life pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised before the world began.</hi> These tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sactions were Foederal. The father said of the Son [<hi>im Tasim, si posuerit] If he shall make his Soul an offering for Sin,</hi> Isa. <hi>53.10.</hi> Whatever is required to a compleat formal Covenant between two distinct Persons is to be affirmed, concerning what has passed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Christ with respect unto the Redemption of those that were from Eternity gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him; Articles of Agreement (to speak after our Nature) have been concluded, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and exactly kept unto by them both. On this account the Lord Christ is said to be a <hi>Surety.</hi> He is not only <hi>Fidejussor</hi> but <hi>Expromissor.</hi> He has so undertaken to answer for his Elect, as that they were many of them set at liberty before the price of their Redemption was actually payed &amp; that by vertue of this Covenant, wherein the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did take the word of his Son Jesus Christ, that the thing should in due time be performed. As to the Efficacy of his Death, <hi>He was slain from the Foundation of the World.</hi> Believers that dyed in the beginning of time went to heaven because the Son of God had promised to lay down his life to satisfy divine justice in their behalf. Concerning the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> this Author has Published a judicious Treatise ten years since, whereby the Churches have been edified. He has
<pb facs="unknown:000684_0007_0FA9A413AF0959F0"/>
with the like s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lidity discoursed on the <hi>Covenant of Redemption,</hi> shewing himself a workman that needs not be ashamed. The Reader will find therein Gospel Mysteries, with <hi>Brevity</hi> and yet Perspicuity (which is rare) explained, confirmed, applyed, so as that both Learned and Unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (God has made us Debtors unto both) may thereby be built up in their most Holy Faith; in some more disputable Points, He expresseth his own Judgement without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting on those whom He differs from. It has been controverted amongst very Learned men, whether it is consistent with the Rectoral Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness of that God who cannot look upon ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, to pardon sin without satisfaction made to his injured justice. <hi>Grotius, Vos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius, Voetius, Turretin, Heidan,</hi> and of our own Divines, the great <hi>Owen</hi> and Mr. <hi>Burgess</hi> have inclined to the Negative in the Question mentioned. But others of great name and worth, (and in particular Dr. <hi>Twiss</hi> concerning whom our Mr. <hi>Norton</hi> in his Life of Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> does truly affirm that he was if any of this age a Star of the first-Magnitude) are for the Affirmative; with whom the Worthy Author does concur, but with such Modesty and Candor as no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious person tho' of a differing Sentiment, can be offended at him. In Questions so Extrafun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental, (as long as the best of us know but in
<pb facs="unknown:000684_0008_0FA9A414740AF3C8"/>
part) we may (to use <hi>Austins</hi> expression) be diversly perswaded <hi>Salve fide et Caritate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the God of truth, bless these endeavours for glory to his own Name, the edification of his People, and the rejoicing of his Servant, and Grant that both Speaker and Hearers, Writer and Readers, may have Joy toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Day of Christ.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Boston, New-England.</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>February 6</hi>th. <hi>1693.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Increase Mather</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="unknown:000684_0009_0FA9A4153154FF70"/>
            <head>CHAP I. An Introduction.</head>
            <p>THE Unparallel'd and Incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensible Love of God to Sinful Man, displayed in the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Affair of his <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi>; is the great thing celebrated in the Scriptures; and is that which invites our most frequent, and raised Meditations. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore prays for his <hi>Ephesians,</hi> that they, together <hi>with all Saints, might be able to comprehend it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Eph.</hi> 3.17, 18, 19. Nor is there one passage in this whole Transaction, but what is admirable and precious; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the foundation of our hope to enjoy Eternal Life, who are by <hi>Nature Children of Wrath</hi>; and but for it, the whole forfeited Race of <hi>Adam</hi> must have perished hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly
<pb n="2" facs="unknown:000684_0010_0FA9A415F2425540"/>
and everlastingly. The Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this is truly surprizing: Time is too short; Eternity but long enough to spend in the Survey of it. This Love is a Fountain which sprang up in, and runs down to Eternity. It never knew a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor shall ever come to an end.</p>
            <p>Now there are two general heads, unto which our Speculation of this Glorious My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery may be reduced.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Provision which God made for our deliverance before time, in the days of Eternity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The things which are done in time for the actual Accomplishment of it. They that would Search the Love of God to the Original, and follow it up to the Well-head of it, must ascend beyond the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the World, and look for it in that Eternity which had no Beginning. Not only the <hi>things</hi> that he hath done for us, but the <hi>thoughts</hi> also which he had of us, do Recommend his Transcendent Good Will unto us; the Meditation of them was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry choise to <hi>David, Psal.</hi> 139.17. That God bare Love to his People <hi>of Old,</hi> He Himself assures them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3. These Thoughts of his had lain hid from us, but that he was pleased to Reveal them to us in his Word, from whence we must bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:000684_0011_0FA9A416AE9A5BE0"/>
our Information: and it is our Duty and will be our Advantage to enquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, so far as we have Scripture Light to direct us. The former of these is that which is Designed in the Ensuing <hi>Treatise,</hi> by Divine Assistance. and in truth, all our Speculations about the latter will be dark, short, and confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, except we trace them hither. We shall neither know where our Salvation began, nor what Security there is for it, or how to act our Faith aright about it. Here is the <hi>Idea</hi> or <hi>Exemplar</hi> of all that is done in bringing of Fallen Man to Glory: here is the Ratification or Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment of the whole concern: here we are acquainted with the leading Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to, and unfailing Assurances of the <hi>Vocation, Justification, and Glorification</hi> of all Gods Chosen Ones: for here we find the first Link of that Chain, and that which fastens all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30. The best and most suitable notion under which this great Affair may be represented to us for our Information, and satisfaction, is that of a <hi>Covenant</hi>; which being of so much use a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, is the more easily understood: and because it carries in it the strongest confirmation of things that Humane Nature is capable of, must needs be most accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to the establishing of our Faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="4" facs="unknown:000684_0012_0FA9A4176F1CEDA8"/>
Nor is this a meer notion of mans In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, but that which hath clear and firm footing in the Word of God, as will in its due place appear. Now this Covenant, is by some Divines called the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Suretyship</hi>; by others, the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Redemption</hi>; because there was in it a full Suretyship given for, and a firm Compact made about the Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a number of Mankind, in order to their Salvation.</p>
            <p>The enquiry into, and right stating of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of this <hi>Covenant,</hi> is of excellent advantage for our better understanding of the whole tenour of the Scriptures; the avoidance of many pernicious Errors which the ignorance of it, hath given advantage to take rooting among such as call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves <hi>Christians</hi>; the true apprehension of the Terms of the Gospel Covenant; and the comforting of the Hearts of Gods Children, against the many Temptations which assault them. I shall therefore, as God shall please to assist me, endeavour to pursue it in this method.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To state the right notion of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>To prove from the Word of God, that there is such a Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>To Explain it in those several things wherein the special nature of it may be rightly concerned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="5" facs="unknown:000684_0013_0FA9A41830447DB8"/>4 <hi>To shew the necessity of it in order to Fallen Mans Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>To shew the Influence which it hath into the Covenant of Grace which is made with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>To draw some practica Inferences from it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAPTER 2. The right Notion of the Covenant of Redemption Stated,</head>
            <p>THere are two enquiries apt to be made about a matter of Discourse, <hi>viz. Ansit,</hi> and <hi>Quids<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> whether the thing be, and what it is. If the thing it self be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for granted to be, the former is Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perseded; but if it be Suspected, it must be Cleared: and either of these seems to claim the Precedency: for, though words be to signify things, yet they are often Dark, Ambiguous Aequivial; and till we know what they Indigitate, how shall we determine whether the thing be? And yet on the other hand, till we are satisfied that the thing is, it is superfluous to enquire into the nature of it, lest our dispute
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:000684_0014_0FA9A4195CD18870"/>
should prove to be about a non-entity. To avoid both of these, I shall here only give some brief general account of the thing intended by the <hi>Covenant of Redemption,</hi> in order to the proof of the Assertion that there is such a thing; leaving the full ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of it till afterwards.</p>
            <p>Let it then be here observed. It is certain that the whole concern of Mans <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> had it conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and determination in Gods eternal Decree. It is a sure rule, <hi>That whatsoever God doth in time, he purposed to do it before time</hi>: for he <hi>worketh all things according to the counsel of his will, Eph.</hi> 1.11. God is a wise Agent; he must therefore know his own works; and this knowledge must be eternal, or else it could not be Divine, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.18. <hi>Known unto God are his works from the foundation of the world.</hi> He is a free Agent, and so he doth nothing but what he will do: And that will had no beginning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing <hi>Immutable, Job</hi> 23, 13. <hi>he is of one mind and who can turn him</hi>? Now although the <hi>Decree</hi> of God, be with respect to him Decreeing, but one simple and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided act; yet, in reference to the things Decreed, it is various, or hath many parts, in it: for which reason the scripture speaks of many <hi>thoughts</hi> and many <hi>purposes</hi> of his.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="unknown:000684_0015_0FA9A41B248D50A8"/>Among these <hi>Decrees,</hi> Those of <hi>Predestina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> deserve to be peculiarly remarked by as; because they contein in them the Idea of that special government by which God leads all reasonable creatures to an everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing state of happiness or misery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And among these, that of <hi>Election</hi> carries in it matter of si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>lar and eminent comfort to all true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, who by the knowledge of their Faith, come to be acquainted with their Interest in, and Title to it. In which <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree</hi> of <hi>Election,</hi> there was not only the designation of the end, unto which the Creature was appointed, but also the laying out of the whole way in which they were to be brought unto the Attainment of that end. The end to which men are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by <hi>Election,</hi> is <hi>Eternal Life.</hi> That which is the end of our Faith, is the Design of Gods <hi>Election,</hi> and that is our <hi>Salvation,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.9. Among the means, that which shines forth most illustriously, is mans deliverance from Sin and Wrath by the <hi>Obedience</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> who is the Eternal Son of God, and in fulness of Time was made man, in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der to his Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us. This way of mans <hi>Redemption,</hi> had a room in Gods Eternal Purpose: Our <hi>Election</hi> therefore was <hi>in him,</hi> and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Creation <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4. Not that
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:000684_0016_0FA9A41B38DC5DB0"/>
Christ as Mediator was the Meritorious procuring Cause of our <hi>Election</hi>; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in and by him we were to be made partakers of all the benefits which were to be the Fruits of this Electing Love to us. Hence then the Son of God was appointed to do those things for us, which were to procure all these benefits to be bestowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n us; and for this reason is he said to be <hi>Slain from the Foundation of the World,</hi> Rev. 13.8. not that he was actually so, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the Designation of it; and so the Apostle expounds it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.20. <hi>who was verily Foreordained before the Foundation of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Article in the Decree, is in the Scripture represented unto us, under the notion of a <hi>Covenant</hi> between <hi>God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and <hi>God the Son</hi>; as will appear af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, together with the reason why it is exhibited under such a notion. So that by the <hi>Covenant of Redemption,</hi> under our consideration, we are to understand, <hi>An E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting Compact clearly made, and firmly Ratified, between</hi> God <hi>the Father, and God the Son, about the Redemption and Salvation of a number of the Children of Men</hi>; and this is a Covenant distinct from that which we call the <hi>Covenant of Works,</hi> which past between God and Man at the first in <hi>Adam</hi>;
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:000684_0017_0FA9A41BF356FD78"/>
as also from the <hi>New Covenant,</hi> or that <hi>of Grace,</hi> which is Indented between God and Man, in Christ as the <hi>Mediator</hi> of it. This is the thing about which our Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is, and which may be laid open in the Sequel.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 3. Scripture Evidence that there is such a Covenant of Redemption.</head>
            <p>THat the Word of God doth not in Terms mention such a Covenant by such a Title, must be acknowledged: but that it doth give us the account of a <hi>Covenant,</hi> which cannot be Interpreted of any other, yea which fully amounts to the thing, may safely be affirmed. We read, Psal. 89.3. <hi>I have made a Covenant with my Chosen, I have Sworn to David my Servant.</hi> There are divers Texts in Scripture, especially in the Old Testament, which have a double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erence, partly to the <hi>Type,</hi> partly to the <hi>Antitype</hi>; or to the <hi>Antitype</hi> under the <hi>Type</hi>: This Psalm is one of those portions of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure, in which <hi>David</hi> is made a notable <hi>Type</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="unknown:000684_0018_0FA9A41CB502A208"/>
of Christ: Him therefore it mainly aims at. The Covenant wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, is here made the foundation of all Consolation to the People of God: Here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en we have.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Subject Matter, <hi>viz. A Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The firmness of it; <hi>I have made</hi>; Hebr. <hi>Cut,</hi> alluding to that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, in <hi>Jer.</hi> 34.18. which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ratification; and <hi>I have</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Immutability of it, according to <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17, 18.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Parties in it; God on the one hand; I: God is the Speaker, Christ on the other hand, expressed in two words: <hi>My Chosen</hi>: noting both his <hi>Excellency,</hi> and his <hi>Election; David my Servant</hi>; which must needs ultimately aim at Christ, as many Expressions in the Psalm will unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably evince, especially those in <hi>verse</hi> 19.22, verse 28, 29.35, 36. Christ is therefore elsewhere called <hi>David,</hi> see <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.9. <hi>Ezek</hi> 34.34, 37.24. and if we would know what Covenant this is, the Context clearly indicates it, to be that which concerns the <hi>Redemption</hi> and Salvation of the People of God: for it was that wherein he was made helpful to his People, <hi>verse</hi> 19. wherein he was Anointed to his Offices of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diating Redeemer, <hi>verse</hi> 19, 20. made Gods <hi>First-born,</hi> verse 27. and hath an abiding
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:000684_0019_0FA9A41D732C9218"/>
Seed, <hi>verse</hi> 36. we also read, Zech. 6.13. <hi>The Counsel of Peace shall be between them both</hi>; which clearly points to this Covenant under consideration.</p>
            <p>But I shall essay a little more particularly to make the thing evident. I will not here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> on the opening of the nature of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in general having done it in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; the sum whereof is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is a mutual obligation between two parties.</hi> That which I have now to do, is to make it manifest, that there is such a transaction between those two glorious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, which amounts to, or is suitably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by a <hi>Covenant</hi>; and that with respect to fallen mans <hi>Redemption.</hi> In order to the clearing up of which, let it be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>That God in discovering of his mind to us, is pleased to accommodate his language to our capacity, clothing divine truths with such words, as may best suit our understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. When therefore we say, there is such a Covenant, it intends that there is that which is <hi>Analogous</hi> unto, and holds a full proportion with such a thing; and is best accommodated to our understanding and faith by such a resemblance. For evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of this, let us lay together these par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and they will amoun to a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="12" facs="unknown:000684_0020_0FA9A41E317B9270"/>1. That God hath from all Eternity <hi>Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> a number of Mankind to Glory. The Scripture is so fall and clear for this, that it would be superfluous to insist upon it. This is the beginning of all saving good which comes to any of the Children of Men. From hence it is that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> its rise, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5. 1 Thes. 1.4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto is the application of grace in Effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Vocation restrained, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46. <hi>Ro.</hi> 11.7. and what else can be designed in that <hi>Everlasting Love</hi> that God bears to men, from whence their Conversion proceeds? <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3. nor can all the Evasions of men, elude the application of these, and many more Scriptures, to <hi>Eternal Election.</hi> If Redemption and Salvation belong to the Works of God, then there was a <hi>Decree</hi> that past concerning them, unless we will deny that God works in them as a Cause by Counsel.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in this <hi>Decree</hi> of <hi>Election,</hi> God hath appointed for his Chosen, not only the end to which he will bring them, which is Glory; but also the means which are requisite in order thereunto. For this reason it is called the <hi>Counsel of his Will, Eph.</hi> 1.11. now <hi>Counsel</hi> hath a proper and next reference unto the means. <hi>Counsel</hi> according to our conception of the thing,
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:000684_0021_0FA9A41EF35AE960"/>
               <hi>is a deliberate enquiry after the most suitable way for the accomplishing of a Design which one hath in his thoughts</hi>; and is ascribed to God after the manner of men. Wise Agents will contrive their Business in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their setting about it. Gods Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses are displayed unto us under the consideration of end and means. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines with himself, both what to do, and how to do it: and this properly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to the Eternal <hi>Idea</hi> of his; and for this reason he assures his people that he <hi>knows what his own thoughts are,</hi> Jer. 29.11. <hi>i. e.</hi> what methods he hath contrived for the management of their Affairs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Gods ultimate end in this Design, being the advancement of the glory of his Grace; hence by a wise and blameless Counsel, he ordered the permission of man to fall into such a State of Misery, as to put him into an absolute need of a <hi>Redeemer.</hi> That mans Fall came within the compass of the Decree, must needs be concluded, except we will assert some things to come to pass against or beside Gods Will; which is to deny his actual Supremacy over the whole Creation; or how is that <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11. true? Man there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore had not Fallen, if he had not pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>posed to permit it; In which he acted
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:000684_0022_0FA9A41FB34F50A0"/>
his holy Soveraignty beyond the capacity of any Impeachment by the Creature. His spotless Holiness so ordered it, that no Iniquity could be laid to his Charge on this account, <hi>Psal.</hi> 141.17. That the glory of his <hi>Grace</hi> was the end of this, so far as his Elect were involved in it, herein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, because he took the occasion from hence, for the Illustration of that precious Attribute, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.20. and but for it the whole concern of <hi>Gospel Grace</hi> had been excluded; and that this Fall of Man put him into an absolute need of a <hi>Redeemer</hi> is manifest, both from the rigour of the Law, exacting death of all its Transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, without any abatement, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.4. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.17. the utter impotency of man, by the deadly influence of the <hi>Apostasy,</hi> to do any thing towards his own delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, being left by it <hi>without strength, Rom.</hi> 5.6. and the dreadfulness of the misery which he was under the efficacy of, and must undergo, if there were no Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. either he must perish with an <hi>Everlasting Destruction,</hi> or there must be a powerful <hi>Redemption</hi> laid in for him. This is the fearful condition in which this whole Race is involved.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Hence, among the means, the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Son of God was set apart in the
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:000684_0023_0FA9A420715D5828"/>
               <hi>Decree,</hi> to be a <hi>Redeemer.</hi> The Son of God was not only an <hi>actual</hi> Redeemer in time, but a <hi>chosen</hi> Redeemer from Eternity, and for that reason is called Gods <hi>Chosen One, Psal.</hi> 89.3. and his <hi>Elect,</hi> Isa. 42.1. That the Son of God came within the compass of the <hi>Decree,</hi> and had his Name written there, as one who was to become a <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some</hi> for his People, is manifest by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Testimony, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.23. <hi>I was set up from Everlasting.</hi> It is the Son who is the true Wisdom, that is brought in speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here: the word [<hi>Set up</hi>] denotes the constituting of one in some Office; and therefore a noun from it signifies a <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour.</hi> It doth not design his natural Coessentiality with his Father, but his being ordained to some Employment; and what was that but this of a Redeemer? hence is he called <hi>A Lamb slain from the Foundation of the World,</hi> Rev. 13.8. which must be intended with respect to the <hi>Decree.</hi> Hence our Election is involved in his, Eph. 1.3, 4. Christ was not sent in haste into the World: it was not a rash and indeliberate Undertaking of his, but it was all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the Counsel of God, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> every passage relating to it, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.23.8.4.27, 28. when therefore he came in the Flesh, he professeth that it was <hi>to do his Fathers Will,</hi> Psal. 40.7.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="16" facs="unknown:000684_0024_0FA9A421345A09E0"/>5 The Decree of God is a firm, stable, Immutable Purpose of his. A very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then could say, <hi>Nulla est Litura in De. cretis Sapientum.</hi> The <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Persians,</hi> under a proud opinion of their infallible Wisdom, set a Stamp of Immutability upon all their Laws. But this is peculiar and proper to the Purposes of God. Gods Wisdom is like himself, Infinite: he can never be wiser than he was, then when he established his Decree. He did it in Counsel, and his after thoughts can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not mend his former. It was his Will that things should be so, and he hath but <hi>one Will,</hi> which is not to be <hi>altered, Job</hi> 23.13. Nor can he ever want for Power to put that in Execution, which he hath purposed; for he can do every manner of thing. The Records of Eternity shall stand unshaken; what he hath said shall certainly come to pass, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.21. <hi>Psal.</hi> 102.27.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Son of God, who was thus constituted Redeemer in the Decree, is a Person in the God-head, infinitely free and uncompellable. Though the Doctrine of a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Persons in the <hi>Unity</hi> of the Divine <hi>Essence,</hi> be a Mystery beyond the capacity of our short Understandings to fathom; yet in as much as these are
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:000684_0025_0FA9A421EE4C91D0"/>
exhibited to us under the notion of three <hi>Persons,</hi> each one having a distinct <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistence,</hi> (though all have but one and the same <hi>Essence</hi>) we must therefore allow to each of them all that is <hi>Essential</hi> to the God-head: and thus we are to conceive of each of them to have a <hi>Divine Will</hi>; though it be one and the same in all. The Son of God, being God, is in this respect <hi>Coequal</hi> with the Father; for this reason he challenged this <hi>Equality</hi> as his due, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. and God calls him <hi>his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> Zech. 13.7. He is thereupon incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Compulsion. So that, upon an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible supposition, that the Son had not complied with his Fathers Will in this matter, he could not have been Decreed to be a Redeemer; and from this very Argument the Apostle proves, that what Christ did upon this account was his own voluntary act, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5, 6, 7. The Father no sooner proposed it to him, than he readily complied with it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Hence, to the firm and immutable constituting of the Son of God a Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the <hi>Decree,</hi> there past an Eternal <hi>Transaction</hi> between the Father and him, which is best shadowed to us, by the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Covenant</hi>: and because it had a proper respect to the Ransoming of his
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:000684_0026_0FA9A422B1055100"/>
Chosen from sin and misery, it may there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore well be called the <hi>Covenant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi> If the Son of God became a Redeemer by his own Consent freely, and was determined unto it before the World began, it infers, according to our Capacity, that there was something pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to him, and that he did accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly accept of it.</p>
            <p>The Transactions between the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Divine Persons, Infinitely Transcend our Understandings: but if we will form a Conception of them, it must be after this manner: and God is pleased so to declare it unto us, that we may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to entertain it in our <hi>Faith</hi>; and in as much as this stands among the <hi>Decrees</hi> of God, in which there is the whole I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea of this work, and it is in all of it ratified unchangeably; there must to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the mention of all those things which relate to it, be also a final and determinate conclusion about it, all must be ratified. In this regard the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel of Peace</hi> is said to be <hi>between them both,</hi> Zech. 6.13. hereupon also, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posal of it by the Father to the Son, is represented under the form of a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Hypothetically</hi> propounding both a <hi>Condition</hi> and a <hi>Reward</hi> Isa. 53.10. and
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:000684_0027_0FA9A4237249DEF0"/>
in Psal 110.7. there is a Connexion which amounts to the same thing, for in a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulate Axiom,</hi> where there are things joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, that are consequent the one upon the other, it bears the force of a <hi>Connex</hi>; and so it is in the Text; and this may suffice for the evidence of the thing, or that there is such a Covenant.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 4. Of the Parties in the Covenant of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
            <p>IT follows now that we come a little nearer, &amp; make a more distinct Survey of this Covenant, according to the Light afforded us concerning it in the Word of God. I shall therefore here explain it in such things wherein the special na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it, and its difference from other Covenants may be discerned; especially the <hi>Covenant of Works,</hi> and the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi>; and here may these things be Enquired into.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Who are the Parties in this Covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whence this Covenant had its rise, or what was the ground of its being made?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="20" facs="unknown:000684_0028_0FA9A4242FB2DC78"/>3. <hi>When it was made?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Whether it be a Covenant of Works or of Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Who are Covenanted for?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>What are the Articles of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Who are the Parties in this Covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a general Observation that in all Covenants there are two Parties, and there can be neither less or more; for the notion of a <hi>Covenant</hi> belongs to the Head of <hi>Relation,</hi> which hath but the <hi>Relate</hi> and the <hi>Correlate,</hi> and cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed. If then there are divers parties, they suppose divers Covenants. In the Covenant of Works, God and Man im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately were the Parties: In the New Covenant they are God and Man, thro' the Interposition of a Mediator, unto whom both Parties have a respect. But in the Covenant of Redemption they are <hi>God &amp; the Son.</hi> This is agreed on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all those that acknowledge such a Covenant, but under what consideration, it is depa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with reference to each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and may be here particularly Ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plained.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God is one Party, <hi>Psal.</hi> 89.3. <hi>I have made:</hi> The Party that speaks there is God himself. But it may be asked, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be to be considered <hi>Essentially</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="unknown:000684_0029_0FA9A424F0AD8C40"/>
or <hi>Personally</hi>; and so is to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Father</hi>? In the former Descrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> given of this Covenant, I have expressed it as belonging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o God the Father. There are some Divines who would have it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Essentially,</hi> and assigned to the <hi>Deity,</hi> considered in the <hi>Essence,</hi> and not in any particular <hi>Subsistence,</hi> left otherwise the Holy Spirit, the Third Person in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Trinity should be excluded from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing personally concerned in this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. This Debate needs not be eagerly pursued, being easily reconcileable: here then observe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Decree in which this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is to be found, is properly an Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sential Act, or belongs to all the Three Persons in common, as they are one in the Essence. Acts properly personal are only such as flow from their <hi>Relative Properties,</hi> or at least have their <hi>Foundation</hi> in these <hi>Relations.</hi> The Decrees is an act of Divine Counsel, exerted by the Divine Will, which is undivided, and common to the three persons: and thus the Deity is the one party Covenanting, because <hi>the Essential acts of the Trinity are undivid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Joh.</hi> 5.17, 19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in these <hi>Essential</hi> Works, the Scripture frequently observes a <hi>personal</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="unknown:000684_0030_0FA9A425AE2CB590"/>
propriety, and an order of working ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of their Subsistence and manner of working: so that in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever work, any one persons order of Subsistence, and manner of working doth principally appear, it is, by way of spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialty, ascribed to that person; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that person is alone in it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God doth herein manifest himself to us most clearly in such a manner of being or <hi>Subsistence.</hi> The Father is the first Person, hence <hi>beginning</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Works are Attributed to him, as <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.</hi> The Son is the Second Person, and therefore secondary works are ascribed to him, such as <hi>Redemption.</hi> The Holy Ghost is the Third and Last Person, and therefore finishing works are given to him, such as <hi>Application.</hi> The Father works of himself, by the Son and Spirit. The Son works from the Father by the Spirit. The Holy Ghost works from them both; <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.19.16.13. and this Order is to shew the <hi>Oecononomy</hi> of the Divine Persons. Now in this regard, Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sential Works may have a peculiar Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priation to a person not exclusive, but inclusive of the other.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Jesus Christ in making mention of this Covenant, acknowledgeth the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:000684_0031_0FA9A4266F778510"/>
to be the Party whom he had In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented withal. See <hi>Psal.</hi> 2.7, 8. the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning of the Son here spoken to, and owned, points us to the Father under the <hi>Personal Relation.</hi> So also in Psal. 89.26. which <hi>Psalm</hi> hath a proper reference to this Covenant; and how often in the Gospel have we Christ declaring his Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to be from his <hi>Father</hi>? more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in <hi>John</hi> 17. he challengeth of him the performance of the Promises of this Covenant, and truly, as this Covenant is the beginning of all our Salvation, and the spring or Original from which all the good that we hope for, so it is fitly attributed to him, who is the first of the persons.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The other Party is the Son of God, the Second Person in the Trinity, who is Coeternal with the Father. The Covenant being Eternal, there could not be any party in it, but one who was an <hi>Eternal Person.</hi> Whosoever is engaged in a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which is a voluntary act, must be presumed to <hi>Exist,</hi> cither in himse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f, or in his <hi>Representative.</hi> Nor is this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted whether the Son of God be the other party: but yet there is no little difference in the notions about the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or respect in which he stands as a
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:000684_0032_0FA9A4272D9E44B8"/>
party in this Covenant. The Son of God is considered under a treble notion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Meerly as he is a Divine Person, and so is only <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As he hath assumed our Nature into Union with his Person, and so is <hi>God-Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As he hath a Mystical Union with all the Members of his Church, or with all Believers, in which sense he is also called <hi>Christ,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.12. and under which of these considerations, he is a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this Covenant, is variously appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended. Here then we may conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Christ Mystical is not the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this Covenant; my meaning is, that the Members of Christ, or his Spiritual Seed, were not joyntly Covenanters with him here. The People of God are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered as a party in the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> with whom God Indents through a <hi>Mediator</hi>: but they have no such consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration here. It is true, they are taken notice of in this Covenant, yea, it is for them that Happiness was contrived and secured in it, but that is as they stand related to the Terms of it. The Elect are not <hi>Agents,</hi> but <hi>Patients</hi> here. There is nothing in it required of them to be done <hi>by them,</hi> but all is to be done <hi>for
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:000684_0033_0FA9A427ED65FE78"/>
them.</hi> They are not <hi>Undertakers,</hi> but are <hi>Undertaken</hi> for, <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.10. and this is one difference between these two Covenants.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence it is the Person of Christ alone that is the Party. It must be either Christ <hi>personal,</hi> or Christ <hi>Mystical:</hi> not the latter as is already declared. He was alone in this Undertaking. He only was to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the work of Redemption, and had no Coadjutor, <hi>Isa.</hi> 63.3. Redemption-work is appropriated to him. As he was to have the whole honour of our deliverance paid unto him, so that none might share with him in the Glory of it, he took none into Partnership with him in the work, but took it wholly upon himself: nay there was none in Heaven or Earth to be found to Undertake in this Business besides him, and therefore he stood alone in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Christ meerly considered as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Son of God, and the Second Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in the Blessed Trinity; and not as God and Man, by the Assumption of our Nature, is the other party in this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. I know there are weighty Divines of another Perswasion, who labour by many arguments to prove that the Son of God, was looked upon as in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or with respect to the <hi>Futurition</hi> of
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:000684_0034_0FA9A42952EDCF58"/>
his assuming it, in the Indenting of this Covenant: But I suppose that conception will overthrow the very notion of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in this matter. The present con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion that hath now been laid down, will be apparent by these things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This is (as hath already been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served) called a Covenant only by way of <hi>Analogy,</hi> as it is accommodated to our understanding; it being nothing else but that <hi>Article</hi> in the <hi>Decree,</hi> which concerns the <hi>Redemption</hi> of Man by Christ. There must therefore be such an <hi>Analogy</hi> obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in our conceptions of it, and it must be Interpreted by notions proper to a <hi>Covenant.</hi> Now, though the Father and the Son be one in <hi>Essence,</hi> and so have not two Wills, but one undivided; yet they are Two Persons, and as such, are conceived by us as consulting, deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and concluding about things: hence the Divine Persons are so represented, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. and the reason of it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the things done are, to our manner of conception, the Fruits of Counsel. That there was not only a Divine Will in the Father sending, but also in the Son consent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be sent by him, we must needs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain; else we can have no rational and regular notion of a person sending, and of
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:000684_0035_0FA9A4296E05B918"/>
a Person sent. Although these are but one Will, yet it comes under a distinct conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration by us, though the manner of it be above our conception.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Christ, not only as he is Man, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so as he is Son, is in the <hi>Oeconomical</hi> Dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation of things, <hi>Subordinate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to his Father. Though in the Divine Essence he is Equal as he is God, (for, where there is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat fameness, there must needs be a perfect equality) yet in the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration of the Affairs of his Kingdom, he is Subordinate; The meer <hi>Assumption</hi> of our <hi>Humanity</hi> did not make him so; for his Person was not degraded by his <hi>Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>: he was still, in regard of that, <hi>In the Form of God, and counted it no Robbery to be Equal with him,</hi> Phil. 2.6. but he volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily complied with his order. This is the common consent of Orthodox Divines, and that according <hi>to Scripture,</hi> Gal. 14.29. <hi>My Father is greater than I.</hi> Not as he is God, for so he asserts, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.30. <hi>My Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and I am one</hi>; but as he is the Father; considering Christ, not as man, but as Son. For this reason he is said to be <hi>Sent</hi> by the Father: which must needs have reference to the Eternal Covenant; and that this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to his Person, therein appears, because
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:000684_0036_0FA9A42A2E04E240"/>
how else can we Terminate the <hi>Incarnation</hi> upon the Son, as the Person assuming.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though it be true, that without the Humane Nature Assumed by the Son of God, the work of Redemption could not have been performed by him (which is the main stress of the reasonings for the other assertion) yet the Son of God both could and did undertake for the doing of this work, without the Humane Nature Assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. The Incarnation therefore of the Son of God is rather a <hi>Condition</hi> of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, or a thing requisite in him who was to be a Redeemer, in order to his fitness to go through with that great Undertaking; than a <hi>quality</hi> needed to render him a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Though the Son of God could not actually Redeem us, but in our Nature; yet without our Nature he could Covenant to Redeem us. Though he could not perform Obedience, active or passive, to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but in our Nature; which was only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ncerned in this Obedience, as to the actual performance of it, yet he could Undertake without it, to obey the Law in it; and that is sufficient with respect to his Covenanting about it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Son of God became man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Covenant</hi>; and therefore is not to be considered as man in the act of <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="unknown:000684_0037_0FA9A42AEE944160"/>
The Incarnation of the Son of God was one <hi>Article</hi> in this Covenant, as will be afterwards observed; it was one of the things undertaken by him, and for which he engaged. The futuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefore of his being man depended upon this proposal and undertaking; and for that reason must needs presuppose it. Nor was it necessary that the person Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting must so be looked upon as man, for the Saving of the Elect before his actual coming in the Flesh; it was suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>n was designed to this before time by promise or Covenant.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Covenant of Redemption was an <hi>Eternal Covenant</hi>; and therefore the party as such must come under an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal consideration, and that could only be in regard of his being the Eternal Son of God, or with respect to his Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonality. Though in the Decree, Christ is no sooner appointed to be a Redeemer than he is designed to be man, and therefore this also had an Eternal consideration in that; because the Decree was <hi>from Everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> and though in Eternity there be no <hi>Priority</hi> or <hi>Posteriority</hi> of time; for that would be to confound <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Eternity:</hi> yet in the things themselves, there may be considered a priority and Posteriority of
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:000684_0038_0FA9A42BADF6A5B8"/>
               <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Order.</hi> Thus the cause is in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nature before the effect: thus the Persons Covenanting are in order before the Covenant it self: and hereupon the <hi>Undertaking</hi> of the Son of God to be man, is in order before the <hi>faturition</hi> of his <hi>Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> It hath a Causal Antecedency to the futurity of this Assumption, because that which made it future from Eternity, was the Compact which past between his Father and him about it in the Days of Eternity.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 5. Of the Rise of this Covenant, or the Grounds of its being made.</head>
            <p>IT now follows, in the next place, that we enquir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>from whence this Covenant had its Rise,</hi> or what was the ground of the making of it.</p>
            <p>This will be best understood by our care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful observing where this Covenant is pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ced; and that is under the head <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Election</hi> and it refers unto the <hi>means</hi> which were in it Ordained for the accomplishment of it in
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:000684_0039_0FA9A42C6E3711E8"/>
the Salvation of such as were Chosen. In the Decree (as in the prudent purposes of all wise Agents) there is the resolving of the End, and the laying out of the means by which it is to be advanced. These are inseparable in <hi>Gods Purposing,</hi> but distinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the <hi>things purposed.</hi> In the Decree we find such a thing as <hi>Election,</hi> wherein God hath appointed men unto Salvation, and also contrived the way in which he will accomplish it; and to this way doth the <hi>Covenant of Redemption</hi> appertain: and therefore the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ise of it was the <hi>meer good Pleasure of God, to advance the glory of the Riches of his Grace, by the Redemption of his Chosen, and bringing of them to Enjoy Eternal Life</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for which end, he appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his own Son to be the Redeemer, and Indented about it in a free Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p>Here let it be observed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That a Covenant is not a <hi>Natural</hi> but a <hi>voluntary</hi> act. In every Covenant there is a consent of the parties Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting, to the Articles upon which it is built. Now consent is performed by the Will: and therefore there was no natural necessity of any such Contract as this between these glorious Persons: so that it was Gods mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good pleasure that gave
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:000684_0040_0FA9A42D2E2C57D0"/>
Being to it. The very thing about which it is concerned was arbitrary with God. There was no necessity lying upon him to save any of the race of fallen man, who had by their own fault destroyed themselves: and therfore there could be no necessity lying upon him to contrive and fix a way in which this sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation was to be brought about. God doth nothing <hi>necessarily</hi> but what he doth <hi>naturally</hi> all his other acts are free. <hi>Election is a voluntary thing.</hi> Eph. 1 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The consideration when this Covenant past, tells us that there could be nothing in the Creature to move these glorious persons to indent it. It must be meer good pleasure and nothing else, whatsoever can be said of the creature which men can suppose to have argument in it to move towards such a thing, is Posteriour to, and Consequent upon the Decree, to which this Covenant belongs. The object of it was a possible being; which as it had no being in it self, so was here ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to have a being, and to pass through all these changes that have befallen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, being Predestinated thereunto. So that we can look at no consideration on this account, but what falls behind of having any possible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence into the Covenant. Not the state of integrity, in which man was at first; for in that state, had he continued in it, he
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:000684_0041_0FA9A42DEE086898"/>
had not needed a Redeemer. Not the miserable Estate he fell into by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stasy; for, though that was a step towards his Redemption, because it put him into a capacity for it, and brought him under a necessity of it; yet it could not put God upon thinking of his Recovery; because his Misery was deserved, and the Justice of God was concerned in it: and besides, this fell under the Decree of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as a <hi>Medium</hi> towards the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods rich mercy in saving him. Not the prevision of any good nature or inclination in him; for there is not any such thing truly in any sinner by nature, nor the least <hi>disposition</hi> towards the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of this Redemption on <hi>Gospel-terms,</hi> unless God do work it in him: nor is this always wrought in such as are supposed to be naturally best inclined, but at Gods plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. God therefore could have nothing out of himself to move him.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The ultimate end of Gods design in this Covenant, was the Illustration of the Glory of his Rich Grace in them that are saved, so we are told. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.6. God is his own last end in all his works of Efficiency, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> therefore had that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>imate respect in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Decrees. There are several respects
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:000684_0042_0FA9A42EAEC35FE0"/>
to his Glory which his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> do bear: that of Fallen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> was peculiarly designed for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Praise of his Grace</hi>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Article might have a special <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by it. Hither then Election had an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and consequently, all the Contrivances that were laid for the bringing about of the Salvation to which men were Elected, were measured accordingly. Infinite Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom sought out the best way to make this <hi>Attribute</hi> to shine in its Lustre so as might be <hi>admirable</hi>; and it contrived this, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in this Covenant.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Because there was a wonderful <hi>Love</hi> at work in it, to those that were Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed; hence the rise of this Covenant may well be a signed to the <hi>love of God</hi> which he bare from Eternity to his Elect. He Chose them, and so Covenanted with his Son that he should Redeem them; and why did he so? it was <hi>because he loved them.</hi> The reason of this love is his good pleasure. The first act wherein this love was exprest, was in Chusing us in Christ, and Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him to Redeem us; in which he laid a sure and firm foundation for our Sal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vation: Gods sending of Christ is for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reason ascribed to his unparalell'd love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 3.16. 1. <hi>Joh</hi> 4.10.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="35" facs="unknown:000684_0043_0FA9A42F6F047408"/>5. That which streins this love up to the highest degree, is that it was a free and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate act, both on the part of God the Father deputing, and of God the Son ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting and undertaking in this business, we cannot conceive how there should be any other way in which grace could possibly more shine forth than in Christ's Coming upon mans necessity, to do and dy for him. <hi>A greater love than this</hi> cannot possibly be thought of, than that God should not <hi>spare His Own Son,</hi> &amp; that Christ should not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold himself. The Apostles argument con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes this to be the greatest gift, <hi>Rem.</hi> 8.32. Now the putting of this into a Covenant addes Emphasis to it: that it should not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be thought of, but indented for, and firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ratified in an Everlasting and unchanga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Compact: that thus the sinners eternal salvation should be made sure against all that might be supposed to offer to prevent it. It was therefore that <hi>Grace</hi> might appear to be <hi>Grace</hi> indeed, and his love might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to us as most surprizing, that he put it into such a method, which <hi>Infinite wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> concluded upon as most proper to set it off by: and therefore, when God would call us to the contemplation of his great love to us, he leads us up thus far. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="36" facs="unknown:000684_0044_0FA9A4302ECF4AA8"/>
            <head>CHAP. 6. When this Covenant was made.</head>
            <p>THE next enquiry is when this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was made? This question seems to be here super<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uous, since we have already taken notice that it was an Eternal Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action: and being <hi>before time,</hi> it must needs also be <hi>without beginning:</hi> Jesus Christ therefore speaking of this design, saith, <hi>I was set up from Everlasting,</hi> Prov. 8.23. and for this reason it is said of him, that he was <hi>Foreordained before the Foundation of the World,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.20. It was agreed upon <hi>before time</hi> was between God the Father and the Son, that he should <hi>in time</hi> accomplish the Salvation of the Elect; but yet because, though in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Acts there is no succession, yet, as we before observed, there is an order, it may not be unprofitable to consider in what order this Covenant stands, and that for two reasons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Because of the <hi>Sublapsarians,</hi> who though they acknowledge the Eternal
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:000684_0045_0FA9A430EF8465F0"/>
Predestination of men to an Everlasting State of Happiness or Misery, do yet place it in order after mans <hi>Apostasy,</hi> and build it upon that.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Because of the forementioned Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of those who presuppose the Decree of Christs Incarnation, in order to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this Covenant with him consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as God and Man; wherein they do evidently make that Decree <hi>Antecedent</hi> to, and wholly <hi>distinct</hi> from this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Both of these do certainly mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place the Covenant, and give it a wrong station.</p>
            <p>As to the former of these it may suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to make these few Remarks.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he who will rightly conceive of a Decree, must reduce all that refers to it to the two heads of <hi>End</hi> and <hi>Means.</hi> There is nothing that belongs to any Purpose, but it is either the thing purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, or the way in which it is to be compassed: and therefore one of these two will take in whatsoever can be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned concerning it. But this is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple against which I apprehend no ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional objection can be made, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted to the common sentiments of Mankind.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Gods design in his Decree
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:000684_0046_0FA9A431AE2172C0"/>
was his own Glory; and that which Election had a peculiar respect to, was the Glory of his Grace. All Gods works of Efficiency were to set forth his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and thereby exalt his <hi>Declarative Glory</hi>; which he accordingly disposed in his Eternal Decree, and hath a respect to in his Efficiency, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. In the choise which he made of men to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he contrived the advancement of that precious Attribute of Grace. This is pointed to as the end of all, Eph. 1.4, 5, 6. <hi>It was to the praise of the Glory of his Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the object of this Decree was <hi>Ens possibile,</hi> a possible Being. All Beings are either the first, or from the first. The first Being can be but one, and that is God. He only enjoyed a never Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning Eternity; all other are the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring of time, before which they had no Existence: and because they were to be from him, not by any necessity, but by a voluntary act, hence, God being a Cause by Counsel in all his free and transient acts, there must a Purpose pass with him in order to their Being: <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent</hi> to which purpose, in our concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, there could be no other considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the thing but as a <hi>meer possibility</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="unknown:000684_0047_0FA9A4326E20B740"/>
for it was by vertue of this purpose that it Past into a <hi>Futurition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 All therefore that concerns this possible being in order to its rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing the designed end, belongs to the means. Hitherto, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the Subject under our present con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration, viz. man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>His Creation; the state of integrity in which he was made; the Covenant of wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks which God put him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; the permission of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Apostasy by which he fell under the Curse of that Covenant, and so came to stand in need of Redemption.</hi> Either these things belongs to the Decree, or else there was no Decree about them; and so they fell out besides Gods intention; or else we must assign two Decrees to God, and so two ends, and two orders, of <hi>Media</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specting the same <hi>Subject</hi>; and so we must suppose that God lost his end in the First, which put him upon a new contrivance in the latter. How unbecoming it is to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain such conceptions about the great God, let any Christian Judg. If then they apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the Decree, it must be either to the end or the means: not to the end, for that is the glory of Grace, which is not the things themselves, but that which Results from them: they then are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> steps to it, and so must be of the means.</p>
            <p n="5">5. All the <hi>means</hi> as they refer to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree,
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:000684_0048_0FA9A4332E0478C8"/>
are <hi>Coordanate.</hi> In the <hi>execution</hi> indeed they are <hi>Subalternate,</hi> but not so in the <hi>purpose</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I mean that though they are put into an order in the Decree, yet in the act of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeing they are all together. They are a Chain linked in one, and do all together make but one entire Medium; nor can we rationally conceive them to be here separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. If we consider the Permission of Man to fall, antecedent to the Future Coming of Christ to Redeem him, we can in no sence allow it to be a designed medium of the exaltation of free grace. If we consider of Christ as appointed to the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, without the consideration of Mans Apostasy, we cannot conceive what he should come for. And for this reason the <hi>Covenant of Redemption</hi> cannot in order follow the Decree of permitting man to fall, but must be together with it.</p>
            <p>As to the Second, let it be remembred, that it hath already bin made to appear, that the Covenant was made with the Second Person, and that his <hi>Incarnation</hi> was one thing put into the Covenant: so that it was this Covenant which gave Futurition to it: and therefore to suppose a <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for the son of God to become man, antecedent to, and distinct from this Covenant, is not only <hi>Superfluous</hi>; for what need is there of
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:000684_0049_0FA9A433EEED65B0"/>
two acts to pass for one and the same thing? but it is indeed to <hi>vacate the very Notion of the Covenant,</hi> by taking away the whole that belongs to it, and assigning it to a Decree supposed to be distinct from it: for if we look upon Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t as God-Man, or Decreed to be so, we must conceive that he hath voluntarily Undertaken it, for he was not so necessarily: and then we must also suppose it was for some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and that must be in order to his being a <hi>Redeemer</hi>; for on no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count did he ever design it: and if this be the <hi>Covenant it self,</hi> how should it be before it? Besides, the <hi>Decree</hi> being (as hath already been observed) not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal but essential act, we may therefore safely and intelligently say, <hi>That one God in Three Persons, in Decreeing of the means of mans Salvation, stated and ratified this Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="42" facs="unknown:000684_0050_0FA9A434AF02B6B8"/>
            <head>CHAP. 7. Whether it be a Covenant of Works, or of Grace.</head>
            <p>IT may furthermore be Enquired, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Covenant of Redemption is to be accounted a Covenant of Works, or of Grace; and here let me premise: That it is certainly a <hi>Covenant distinct</hi> from both of those which ordinarily come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der these Denominations among us. It is neither that which was made with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in <hi>Innocency</hi>; nor that which is made with us in and through a <hi>Mediator,</hi> for in both of these man is of one party; whereas he is not so in this, but only a Subject in respect of which it is made: But if the enquiry be, under whether of these considerations it is to be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on in it self, it may be readily replied, that acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rding to its respects, it may be accounted either the one or the other. Here then we are to look upon it, either with reference to the <hi>matter</hi> of it, and the <hi>terms</hi> between the parties, or to the <hi>end</hi> and <hi>design</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="43" facs="unknown:000684_0051_0FA9A4356F7260A8"/>1. If we consider the <hi>matter</hi> of it, and the <hi>terms</hi> which were agreed on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Parties Covenanting, it fully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to a <hi>Covenant of Works</hi>; and indeed it bare a proper respect to the Covenant of Works which past between God and man at first. for Christ was to be the <hi>Second Adam</hi>; and therefore he was to do that for us which the other failed of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to restore us from that misery, which he by his failure brought upon us: hence that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. <hi>As in Adam all dy even so in Christ shall all be made alive.</hi> But yet it was not the same Covenant with that; not only because he was a <hi>diverse party,</hi> but also because he was <hi>differently concerned</hi>: for <hi>Adam</hi> was only to obtain the Blessing by his <hi>Active Obedience</hi> and to fall under the Curse by his <hi>Disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and that irrecoverably as to any power in himself, whereas the Son of God was to merit by his <hi>doing,</hi> and to make Satisfaction by his <hi>Suffering.</hi> But yet it ran in the tenor of a <hi>Covenant of Works,</hi> in which there is a work to be done, and a Reward to be given on the account of it. He was to purchase and pay for what he had, and that to the full price: on which account the <hi>Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> is said to be <hi>Purchased,</hi> Eph. 1.14.
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:000684_0052_0FA9A4362D536C90"/>
and he is said to <hi>give himself a ransom,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim</hi> 2.6. but this will be more fully spoken to, with the reason of it hereafter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we consider the end and whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of this Covenant, it issues in being a <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi> Though it were so laid that <hi>Grace</hi> might appear consistent with <hi>Justice,</hi> and therefore there was a work to be done for the making way for it, yet it carried Grace in the aim of it, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The last end of it was for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Rich Grace. Eph.</hi> 1.5.6. and the very Satisfaction made unto Justice in order to it, puts a great lustre upon this Grace, in as much as Christ was to remove that obsta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle out of the way by his obedience which mans sin had thrown into it. It was that God might express his free and undeserved favour to a number whom he had Chosen to be made partakers in it: that he might bestow upon man a <hi>Salvation</hi> which he never <hi>Laboured for</hi>; bring him to an <hi>heaven</hi> he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>earned</hi>; enrich him with a <hi>portion</hi> which he could never have <hi>Purchased</hi>; and free him from a <hi>Misery</hi> which would else have <hi>Swallowed</hi> him up for ever, &amp; which he had <hi>Procured</hi> to himself.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence all the means which were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon between these parties for this
<pb n="45" facs="unknown:000684_0053_0FA9A437965F8230"/>
end, were the contrivances of this <hi>Grace.</hi> The whole Plot was so laid out, that in all of it there should be the Beams of <hi>Divine-Love and Favour</hi> shining forth: for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The whole provision of a Redeemer was of <hi>Grace:</hi> whether we consider it on the Fathers part <hi>Proposing</hi> the thing, &amp; <hi>accepting</hi> of the way: He was under no necessity to offer such a Proposal; it was absolutely free, yea, that he would be reconciled to sinners in such a way, was <hi>Grace</hi> The case is <hi>Criminal,</hi> man by his fall becomes a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent</hi>; justice might have fallen upon him, and refused to have taken any other in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change. Though the Satisfaction be valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enough, yet the receiving it thus is <hi>voluntary,</hi> therefore it is <hi>Grace.</hi> Had God said the sinner himself shall Die, it had been just: or if we consider it on the Sons part undertaking it; he had no obligation lying upon him by any kind of necessity; he was <hi>God blessed for ever</hi> before: his Divine Essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Glory could not be augmented by it in the least, he had no Consanguinity to move him, for it was the Son of God that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted, he took up the kindred or relation by Covenant: see for this <hi>Phil</hi> 2.6.7. it was therefore of meer grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The work it self which he undertook to perform, considered with relation to this
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:000684_0054_0FA9A437AE2A1D80"/>
those for whom he was to do it, was also <hi>Grace.</hi> The Covenant of works requires of those that are under it, either to <hi>Do</hi> or to <hi>Suffer</hi>: but that when we fell short of doing, and have therby exposed ourselves unto Suffering, another should interpose, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to do and Suffer for us, this it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires not. The Son of God was in himself naturally under no Law, and therefore his putting of himself into such a condition as to be under it, and this that so he might do the greatest kindness, must needs be of <hi>Grace</hi>; and that was the very design of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.8. <hi>God Commendeth his love, in that whiles we were yet sinners, Christ Died for us. so, Gal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>he was made of a woman, made under the Law, to Redeem them that were under the law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 All the proffers of Salvation, which are in the Gospel made unto Sinners, are the results of this Covenant: Here they have their <hi>Foundation.</hi> We find that all the good that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to Fallen men in the <hi>Gospel,</hi> is offered <hi>freely.</hi> We must indeed come for it; but <hi>without money, and without price,</hi> Isa. 55.1. we must take it indeed; if we will have it, but it must be <hi>freely,</hi> Rev. 22 27. But whence is it that there are such liberal offers made to the children of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n? why it flows
<pb n="47" facs="unknown:000684_0055_0FA9A4386EEC7380"/>
from the <hi>Covenant of Redemption,</hi> and had it not been for this, there had never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such news been heard of in the World. Here was the Foundation laid for all, the <hi>Saving Grace</hi> which is Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensed in time to any of the children of men; and so it must needs be a <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 8. Who are Covenanted for?</head>
            <p>THE Title put upon this Covenant, viz: of Redemption, supposeth a <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> unto whom this <hi>Redemption</hi> is to be <hi>applied,</hi> and consequently for whom it was <hi>undertaken.</hi> But it is requisite that we Fix the due limits here, or else we shall be at a great loss in an Essential Point relating un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Covenant, for only the Redeemed, and all of them are to receive the benefits of it; here then let these things be considered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It supposeth subject that stands in need of Redemption. To have undertaken it for any other, had been Supervacaneous. And
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:000684_0056_0FA9A43930AF1E98"/>
there could be no other such monument but such a creature as is forfeited, and fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to misery, and cannot get out of it again, till it be bought out, and rescued from it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There are two sorts of creatures that are reduced to this exigency, viz: <hi>fallen An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and men.</hi> As to the <hi>Angels</hi> which kept their first station, though they needed <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation,</hi> yet not <hi>Redemption</hi>: and that this Confirmation of theirs doth derive from this Covenant to them, is no-where in Scripture so much as insinuated. But those once <hi>Angels,</hi> now <hi>Devils</hi> are become miserable by their woful revolt from God, being fallen under a Righteous Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and therefore they so far need Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, as that without it they must needs be Eternally miserable, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind are by the <hi>Apostasy</hi> come under this infelicity: they are a company of <hi>dead Creatures,</hi> by vertue of that sin, the Guilt whereof lieth heavy upon them, Rom. 5.12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Fallen <hi>Angels,</hi> or <hi>Devils,</hi> stand no way related unto this Covenant: but only men. God never thought of, or contrived a way for the Jayl-Delivery of Devils, but hath left them hopelesly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sentence which fell upon them
<pb n="49" facs="unknown:000684_0057_0FA9A439EF8807A0"/>
when they rebelled against him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their misery is beyond all hopes of remedy: they are said to be <hi>Reser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Everlasting Chains,</hi> Jude, 6. But God had more Gracious thoughts for man: and in this respect we find, that the Son of God in pursuit of this Covenant, med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not with the <hi>Assumption</hi> of the <hi>Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> nature, but took that only of <hi>Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> Heb. 2.16. And the reason of this was because he had not covenanted to redeem <hi>Angels</hi> but only <hi>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That all mankind universally were not included in this Covenant, so as that the Son of God undertook to pay the Redemption price for them. How far there was some benefit to redound from it to mankind, I here dispute not: But that Christ became <hi>Surety</hi> to pay the <hi>Price</hi> for all, is not to be believed. As to the notion or distinction, of his redeeming all <hi>Sufficiently,</hi> and only some <hi>Effectually,</hi> it cannot be reconciled to sense, how then shall it be believed? It is one thing to pay a Price of sufficient value to redeem all, and another thing to pay it for their Redemption: and to suppose that he did it for this end, and yet they should pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish at the last, is not only besides, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Scripture, Joh. 6.39. <hi>This is the
<pb n="50" facs="unknown:000684_0058_0FA9A43AADF31F60"/>
Fathers Will that hath sent me, that of all that he hath given me, I should Lose no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi>; yea, if we consider the nature of the Covenant, it will evidence it to be inconsistent. The end of it hath been shewn to be for <hi>the Glory of Gods Grace, in the Salvation of his Redeemed:</hi> this Covenant was a <hi>Medium</hi> to that end, and therefore all that were so Covenanted for must certainly attain it, or else the Covenant so far loseth its design. This therefore is that which Christ Intercedes for in behalf of those whom he hath Redeemed, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. these are they whom <hi>his Father gave him,</hi> that he might Redeem them.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That Those whom he Covenanted for, were a Definite Company of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular persons. Not only was the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them agreed upon in this Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, but the individuals also were De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined. Here observe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The Covenant did not run <hi>Illimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> That he should pay a price for all, and that offers should be made to all, and that as many as would accept of them, might be made to partake in the benefits of it, was not the form in which this Covenant ran: There is indeed such an offer made in the <hi>Promulgation</hi> of the
<pb n="51" facs="unknown:000684_0059_0FA9A43B6EE12CC8"/>
               <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> by the <hi>Gospel,</hi> to all unto whom it comes on such a condition: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut, neither is this to all men, nor yet doth the Covenant of Redemption run so. and there is this reason for it among others, because it is one <hi>Article</hi> in this <hi>Covenant,</hi> that whom Jesus Christ doth <hi>Redeem,</hi> he shall <hi>save,</hi> and in order to it bring them to himself, <hi>John.</hi> 6.37. and but for this, none would come to him, <hi>vorse.</hi> 44. and then where would be the <hi>seed that should serve him, and be counted to him for a generation</hi>?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor did this Covenant run upon the <hi>Previous qualities</hi> of men before Conversion. It did not say that such sorts of persons should be redeemed, and others not: but it took in, as God saw meet, all sorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, <hi>Jews and Greeks, Barbarians</hi> and <hi>Scythi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>; of every age, sex and disposition, some that proved civil before they were savingly changed; others who before they were brought home to Christ, were the vilest and most debauched of mankind. This appears to have been so, by the event, for which we have plentiful Scripture Testimony; and therefore it assures us, that it was not upon these terms that it stood.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But it took in so many <hi>Individual</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, chosen according to the Sovereign pleasure of God. Hither the Apostle limits
<pb n="52" facs="unknown:000684_0060_0FA9A43C2E1AEEC8"/>
it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11. The <hi>Lambs Book of Life,</hi> in which <hi>names</hi> are <hi>written,</hi> mentioned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. refers properly to this <hi>Covenant:</hi> and they are persons who are <hi>written</hi> here; they have their <hi>names</hi> in it. The Son of God <hi>knew</hi> from eternity whom he was to Redeem, and God <hi>knew</hi> them. This is the <hi>Foundation</hi> of which the Apostle speaks, which hath such a <hi>Seal</hi> upon it, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>who are his,</hi> this Indigitates the very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons: Our <hi>High Priest</hi> therefore had their <hi>names written upon his brest plate</hi> when he was to offer the Sacrifice for them, and make expiation in <hi>their behalf</hi> in the <hi>Holy Place.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 9. What are the Articles of the Covenant?</head>
            <p>IT Belongs to the nature of a Covenant that there are <hi>terms agreed</hi> upon, and <hi>concluded</hi> between the parties in it; or something in which each obligeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to the performance of: and by the distinct knowledge of these it is, that we come to have an insight into the particular nature of any Covenant. It is therefore
<pb n="53" facs="unknown:000684_0061_0FA9A43CEDF3EE68"/>
needful that we take the account of the <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>Covenant of Redemption,</hi> that so we may discover the main and essential difference between that and the Covenant of Grace, to prevent our confounding of them one with the other. Here let it be observed that this is one of those <hi>Covenants</hi> which is made between <hi>equals</hi> &amp; therein is divers from the other, which is made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a <hi>Superiour,</hi> and <hi>inferiour.</hi> They are equal, whether we consider them in their <hi>nature,</hi> Phil. 2.6. or if we consider the <hi>things arising from it</hi>; the Glory of One God in Three Persons is the design which was laid in it: or if we consider the <hi>mutual obligation</hi>: they stand equally bound each of them to the terms which he Undertakes. Now for a more distinct and particular view of these <hi>Articles,</hi> it may be Enquired,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What were the common Terms between both the Parties?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>What were the Obligations lying upon each Party by himself?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What were the common Terms between both Parties?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They were such as these that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That a certain number of Mankind should be made the Monuments of Rich
<pb n="54" facs="unknown:000684_0062_0FA9A43DADFCEB30"/>
Grace: or, That the Glorious Attribute of Grace should be exalted in the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Salvation of a <hi>Definite</hi> Company of men; and to this <hi>Article</hi> belongs the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of mans being <hi>Created in his Integrity; put under a Covenant; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to fall from it, and make himself miserable,</hi> in order to the making way for the Illustration of this Grace. That such a thing should be, was voluntary on Gods part, and therefore there past a Decree for it: and this being <hi>Essential,</hi> it belongs to all the Three persons. Hence the Scripture speaks of mens being <hi>Ordained</hi> or appointed to Glory, and of their being <hi>Elected</hi> or Chosen to the Kingdom: which expressions, denote this eternal designation, which was agreed upon, and so past between God, Father, Son, and Spirit; see<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 5, 9. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.20. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.4.2. <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.13. and all this was with an eye to the glorifying o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Grace of God, <hi>Eph</hi> 1.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That in order to the Illustration of this Grace in mans Salvation, the first Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant should be Satisfied in all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of it, That whatsoever that required should be fully responded. The considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mans being under a <hi>Law Covenant,</hi> and forfeiting himself to the <hi>Curse</hi> of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing supposed in the former <hi>Article</hi>; there is
<pb n="55" facs="unknown:000684_0063_0FA9A43E6EFBF828"/>
a Proviso, that the Covenant shall not be baulked, and that therefore the Salvation intended should make no breach upon, nor offer any violence to the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Justice</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but that it should in all points be complied withal, and mans Salvation be so effected as that no <hi>jot or tittle of the Law should pass</hi>: for so it is brought about, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.18. and that <hi>Justice and Peace should agree in one, Psal</hi> 85.10. that <hi>God should be Just in Justifying of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Rom.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That in order to the accomplishment of this great affair, there should be a sutable and sufficient<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Redeemer provided, who should undertake this work, and accomplish it in all things that were requisite for the compleating of it. The agreement about a Redeemer still belongs to the common consent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ong the three Divine Persons, according to our distinct conception of it; for it is an act of absolute Divine Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccept of Satisfaction at the hands of any besides the proper Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the case being <hi>Criminal:</hi> it must therefore proceed from that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>overaign Will of his to determine that it should be so, from whence alone it could be a thing acceptable to God, when therefore Christ appeared in the Execution of his Work, God declared his acceptablenes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to
<pb n="56" facs="unknown:000684_0064_0FA9A43F2F027450"/>
him by a <hi>voice from Heaven,</hi> Mat. 3.17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>What were the Articles peculiar, or the Engagements lying upon each party by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Such there were, and here in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral we are to observe: That though the Parties were equal in their <hi>Covenanting,</hi> yet in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> one Party Indented to be Inferiour to the other. The Son of God was to take to himself a Nature, in which he was to be his Fathers <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> hence he is so called, <hi>Isa.</hi> 42.1. and because there was something to be done by him first, in order to his meriting of that which he was to receive of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for it; this may first come under our consideration: Here then</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may consider the Engagement which the Son took upon himself. The work of <hi>Redemption</hi> was laid upon his Shoulders, he was the party agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and consenting to take that Province upon him in his own person: and it may suffice to speak generally of this, and so his Undertaking may be compriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He accepted of and took upon him to perform th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> work of <hi>Redemption,</hi> and thereby he received the Relative Title of <hi>Redeemer</hi> from <hi>Eternity.</hi> To this the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="57" facs="unknown:000684_0065_0FA9A43FF03C8E78"/>
bears witness, when it tells us, that he was the <hi>Lamb slain from the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the World, Rev.</hi> 13.8. and when it saith that we are <hi>Chosen in him, to obtain Redemption by him,</hi> Eph, 1.4, 7. which Scriptures clearly express his designation to this Office and Work, and this being personal, hence there was, not only the Father <hi>Propounding,</hi> but the Son also <hi>consenting</hi> and <hi>accepting</hi>: so that this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts properly to one <hi>Article</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi>: for we cannot rationally sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose a person free, sovereign, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no natural obligation to it, to be designed, constituted, and set apart to an Office, without his own free and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary consent. Hereupon it follows, that on this very score or account, all the <hi>old Testament</hi> believers, dying before his appearing in the flesh, went to heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the credit of his undertaking; having their sins discounted, and their happiness conferred upon them, in the merit of that satisfaction and obedience which he had engaged for.</p>
            <p n="2">2 He undertook and engaged to do all that which was requisite for the performance and accomplishment of this Redemption, and this is necessarily inferred upon the former. He who takes upon him to do any
<pb n="58" facs="unknown:000684_0066_0FA9A440AF70DA08"/>
work, engageth himself to do all that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the work cannot be done. What this was will appear, both by taking a view of that which was needful for mans reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very from misery, and being restored to favour and happiness; and by observing what it was that the son of God did actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally perform. Whatever Christ did go thorough here, was <hi>according to the fore know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and determinate Counsel of God; i. e.</hi> the Covenant between God the Father and the Son<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and this was summarily in two things</p>
            <p n="1">1 That he would assume to his person the nature of man, and thereby put himself into a capacity of performing Redemption work. That the Covenant was made with the Son of God not considered as God man, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as Son, hath been already made to app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar. This undertaking then is to be considered as an <hi>Article</hi> belonging to it, and it must needs be so, for the Son of God could not be appointed to be a Man but by a Covenant, because his consent was abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely requisite in such an appointment, it being a Covenant between equals, as is granted on all hands: hence we must either unnecessarily multiply Covenants, or else assign it unto this. The <hi>Scripture</hi> mentions no more but <hi>three covenants</hi> in which God is concerned about man; viz: that of <hi>works</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="unknown:000684_0067_0FA9A4416D4829C0"/>
that of <hi>Grace</hi> and this of <hi>Redemption</hi>; and it must belong to this, if to any of these; for in the other two, men themselves are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Besides, the Humane Nature to be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed needs not to be respected as <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting,</hi> but only as <hi>Covenanted</hi> for, inas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the Divine Nature assuming the Humane, wrought it into a perfect s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to itself: for it was not to have an <hi>Humane Personal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity,</hi> but to be of the <hi>Person</hi> of the Son of God, and to be an organ or instrument in and with which the Son of God was to do this work. It was a body, <hi>i. e.</hi> (an Humanity) <hi>Prepared for him, Heb.</hi> 10.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That in this nature he would become <hi>sponsor</hi> or <hi>surety</hi> for Gods Elect, and so put himself under the law, and stand responsible to it for all that was demanded of them whether of <hi>active</hi> obedience as they were Gods <hi>subjects,</hi> or <hi>Passive,</hi> as they were <hi>sinners.</hi> Hence that <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4.5. He was not only to be in our <hi>nature,</hi> but also in our <hi>stead,</hi> he was to <hi>do</hi> that we might be happy, and to dy that we might be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from misery. This is included in <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.10. Thus he became a surety by way of exchange, not as bound joyntly with us, but as bound alone for us. Gods Holiness did expect <hi>Obedience,</hi> and his Justice did exact <hi>Satisfaction</hi> from him upon our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="60" facs="unknown:000684_0068_0FA9A442D4D4BF98"/>
for this reason is he called, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Lamb,</hi> but a <hi>Lamb slain from the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Rev</hi> 13.8. for then was his death agreed upon and fully concluded: hence when they who were the instruments of it, had wreak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their malice upon him, the Spirit of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>quaints us that it was according to Appointment, a thing <hi>determined</hi> long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.23. the whole work that Christ did upon Earth, was nothing else but a fulfilling of this Covenant: he did not do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any compulsion, but volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> so he tells us, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.17, 18.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The obligations which God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bound himself in, in this Covenant, were of two sorts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such as relate to Christs help and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement in the Undertaking and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the work of mans Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption: and these are principally three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Investing him with such <hi>Offices</hi> as were needful for the discharge of this g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at Work. It was meet that the Son of God should come with <hi>Authority.</hi> There were great things to be done in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this Business; and the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of all depended on the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of God: The <hi>Redeemer</hi> therefore must not only be <hi>designed</hi> but <hi>Invested.</hi> The Son of God was, in our Nature to be <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>augurated</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="unknown:000684_0069_0FA9A442EE25ACC8"/>
in his Mediatorly Function; hence his being <hi>Anointed King,</hi> was according to the <hi>Decree,</hi> Psal. 2.9, 8. and hereupon also he is said to be an <hi>Everlasting Priest,</hi> Psal. 110.7. and a designed <hi>Prophet,</hi> Isa. 42.6, 7. for these Prophetical Predictions concerning him, were discoveries of the Tenour of this Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The fitting of him for this work, with all the things which were requisite for his being every way furnished for the discharge of it, else his Offices had been in vain. God is not wont to send a <hi>Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger</hi> without Legs. If God <hi>calls</hi> any to special Service, he <hi>furnisheth</hi> him, and this was promised to the Son: he was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to have an Humane Nature <hi>Hyposta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically</hi> United to his Person, without which he could not have actually appeared in the Business of mans Redemption, or possibly have stood our Surety, according to the Tenour of the first Covenant. This is by a Synecdoche called a <hi>Body,</hi> and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is said to prepare it for him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5. and this refers to that ancient Covenant in which there was such a provision made as is exprest in <hi>Psal.</hi> 40.7. He was also to have this Humane Nature fitted and qualified with all the necessary Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whereby it might be capacitated
<pb n="62" facs="unknown:000684_0070_0FA9A443AF704980"/>
for the doing of what was requisite, and to this end was his <hi>Unction</hi> promised, Isa. 61 1, 2 whereby he was not only <hi>Inaug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rated</hi> in his O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fices, but also his Humane Nature was <hi>Sanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fied,</hi> and all those Graces which were needful for him in his active and passive Obedience, were put into him in an overflowing measure, <hi>Psal.</hi> 45.8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.34.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to him all the supplies of all constant assistance in his Work, that so it might not fail in his Hand. It was a great work, and it was a frail na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in which it was to be performed; for this cause it would need mighty as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance to support or uphold it so as not to fail. There was Infinite Wrath which our Nature was to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and therefore a <hi>mighty arm</hi> must be underneath to bear it up, else it would have been broken in pieces by it. Almighty Power therefore did stand engaged for him, whereby a good issue of this Affair was secured. God promised him that he should not sink under the weight of it, <hi>Psal.</hi> 89.21. Isa. 42.4, 6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such as relate to the Fruit and Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his Undertaking: and these are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The acceptance that this work should
<pb n="63" facs="unknown:000684_0071_0FA9A4446F186968"/>
find at the Fathers Hands. We have already observed, that not only the <hi>Valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleness</hi> of the Satisfaction offered, but also the <hi>Acceptance</hi> of it with God, is to be considered in the making of it a <hi>Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption</hi>: because it is at Gods liberty whether he will let the Prisoner of Justice go free, and receive another to stand in his room. Now God promised to his Son in this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, that he would take content in this Satisfaction of his; that it should be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grateful or pleasing thing to him; and accordingly it is expressed concerning him, <hi>Isa.</hi> 42.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Reward which he should receive for this work of his. There was a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Indented for, and Christ had an Eye to it in this Work, and Improved it for his Relief, when he was under the forest Agonies of Temptation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. and that was.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of himself personally; that he should receive the highest honour and glory in our nature, <hi>Psal.</hi> 89.27. this therefore was propounded after the nature of a reward, <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8, 9. Yea, such a Reward is promised, as shall give him full content, <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.11. we find that his Work and Recompence are put together, <hi>Psal.</hi> 110. <hi>ult.</hi> He was to have
<pb n="64" facs="unknown:000684_0072_0FA9A4452F361710"/>
the Everlasting Honour of this Work as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to him, and to Triumph gloriously</p>
            <p n="2">2. In regard of those who were to be Redeemed by him. As he <hi>Sanctified himself for their Sakes,</hi> and undertook to Redeem them by Satisfying for them, as a fruit of his Everlasting Love to them, so the Father promised him that he should Enjoy them as a <hi>Purchase,</hi> and that they should be a <hi>Generation</hi> of his <hi>Praise,</hi> Psal. 22.30. Isa. 53.10. He was assured that not one of all those whom he was to Dye for, should ever be Lost, or finally miscarry, but they should all of them be brought to the Possession of that Glory which he should procure for them: that they should be his <hi>Spouse</hi>; and therefore we have him claiming this Reward, as that which he had Indented for, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. and these are the Summary Articles of this Wonderful Covenant.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="65" facs="unknown:000684_0073_0FA9A445EE12B938"/>
            <head>CHAP. 10. The necessity of this Covenant, in order to Mans Salvation.</head>
            <p>IT may be enquired what ground there was for such a Covenant as this? or, what reference Mans Salvation hath to it, and dependence upon it? and the enquiry into this will serve to set forth the Rich Grace of God to man, in those Ancient Thoughts he had for him; and here in general it may be asserted, That there was a necessity for such a Transacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to pass. But that this necessity may be rightly stated; I shall first obser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e what sort of necessity it is, and then clear it up.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A thing may be said to be necessary in a double respect, <hi>viz. Absolute</hi> and <hi>Hypothetical</hi>; and there is a great difference between these.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Absolute Necessity, which may also be called <hi>Natural,</hi> is such as flows from the very nature and being of the thing.
<pb n="66" facs="unknown:000684_0074_0FA9A446AEFB38C0"/>
Thus we say the fire burns necessarily, because it is a natural quality of it, and inseparable from the form.</p>
            <p>Thus it is natural and necessary for God to Love Himself; for the Father to Beget the Son, for the Holy Ghost to proceed from them both. Whereas there are other acts of God which are not Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, but meerly voluntary; as the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the World, the making these and those sorts of Creatures, and many the like.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hypothetical or <hi>Conditionate</hi> Necessity is, when upon the supposition of one thing to be done, there is something necessary in order to it without which it cannot be done: so that though it be not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to do the thing, yet if he will do it, he must needs do thus or so in order to the accomplishing of it; and this necessity flows from the <hi>connexion</hi> of things one with another. An end is not attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without the use of means; and there are means that are proper, on which the attaining of the end hath dependance, or without which it cannot be reached; so that if he will not miss of his design, a person must necessarily use the means that are so connected unto it; and when there are various means or divers ways to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass
<pb n="67" facs="unknown:000684_0075_0FA9A447706E50C0"/>
the design, the necessity is more loose and disjunct, it being indifferent as to this or that, but yet it must of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity be one of them. But when the <hi>Medium</hi> is but one, it is then a restrained necessity; either this way or not at all. Now the <hi>Necessity</hi> under consideration is not of the first sort, or <hi>Absolute,</hi> but of the Second, <hi>viz. Conditionate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. For the more clearing up of this, let it be considered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God was under no natural necessity to Save any of Fallen Mans Posterity. There was no tie of Nature upon him, to give a pardon to, and bestow Salvation upon any of that Ruin'd Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. He might have Damned them all, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any injury to himself, or wrong done to them; and that he did not so do, is a fruit not of <hi>Compulsion,</hi> nor of <hi>Nature,</hi> but of his meer <hi>Good Will,</hi> Rom. 9.18. No man can give any other reason of the thing it self, than that which he gives of the choice of the Subject in particular. The same reason why he chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth this man, and not the other, is to be assigned why he chuseth any at all, and that is, <hi>because it so seemed good unto him,</hi> Mat. 11.24. for they were all equally ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="68" facs="unknown:000684_0076_0FA9A4482E242628"/>2. That hence God was not under any natural necessity of engaging in this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, for the bringing about the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of men. If the effecting of the thing were arbitrary to him, then the Inden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing about the doing of it must needs be so too. If God might have left the whole Race of Mankind to have perished for ever; and that he doth not so do is <hi>contingent,</hi> i. e. <hi>free and voluntary</hi>; than whatsoever refers unto the designation or appointment of it in the Decree must pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> of his Will: and hitherto this Covenant is to be referred. Yea, indeed if it had been natural, the notion of a Covenant made about it had been impertinent; the fixing of a Decree concerning it, had been super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous; for what occasion is there for a Decree about natural actions?</p>
            <p n="3">3. That natural Necessity destroys the very nature of a Covenant. For, a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is a voluntary obligation between persons about things wherein they enjoy a freedom of Will, and have a power to choose or refuse. It is a deliberate thing wherein there is a Counsel and a Consent between Rational and free Agents. It is true, a person may be a Subject, and so under the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Consenting</hi> in
<pb n="69" facs="unknown:000684_0077_0FA9A448EDFDC208"/>
a Covenant; so was <hi>Adam</hi> at the First but still the act of <hi>consent</hi> it self, is the act of a <hi>Cause by Counsel</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and therefore it is not absolutely necessary, so as that he could not but do it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether there be a natural or abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute necessity, in regard of the Nature of Gods Justice and Holiness, that there should be a counterprice paid to make satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for sin, in order to the sinners salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may be disputed, I know this assertion is by some defended against the <hi>Socianians,</hi> &amp; as stifly denied by other who are no <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> &amp; suppose that there are other things in Scripture sufficient to confute them. That because God is naturally <hi>Holy</hi> &amp; <hi>Just,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he must needs <hi>punish</hi> sin either in the <hi>Sinner,</hi> or in his <hi>Surety,</hi> seems not to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident. To say that God could not by his absolute Lordship have Saved a Sinner without a <hi>Mediator,</hi> looks as if it laid him under a necessity beyond what the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will warrant. It is true;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Holiness and Justice are Divine Essential Perfections. Every Attribute of God, is God displaying of himself to us after such a manner: and though these are manifold as they come to our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings, yet they are in him one and the same undivided Being. They are the
<pb n="70" facs="unknown:000684_0078_0FA9A449AEE67070"/>
things by which he maketh himself known to the Creature: and if he were not such an one in himself, they would be a false Representation, which is blasphemy to suppose. If there were no Creature to be the Subject of the Application of these, yet God would be, and is everlastingly <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Just</hi>: for if he will make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self appear to be so in his Works, it is because he is so in his Nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in all his Works of Efficiency, he aims at the Declaration of the Glory of his own Perfections. What else is the <hi>Declarative Glory</hi> of God, but a display of his <hi>Essential Glory</hi> to the Creature, so far as he sees meet? He had all in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self before there was a World; but he would have a World to be a Mirrour of his Perfections; and those to be in it who should be able to read them, and acknowledge him therein; and therefore these are to declare it, <hi>Psal.</hi> 19. and he is said to be <hi>known</hi> by them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That hence he contrived all in a <hi>condecency</hi> for the expressing of his Essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Natural Perfections, and that by his Infinite Wisdom. It must needs be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged and asserted, that God had a respect to those <hi>Attributes</hi> of his, which he would make known to the World, in
<pb n="71" facs="unknown:000684_0079_0FA9A44A6E6267A8"/>
the laying out of all his Works of Ef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficiency in the <hi>Eternal Decree.</hi> Hence we have eminent displays of Gods <hi>Holiness,</hi> in the Displeasure that he discovers against Sin; and of his <hi>Justice</hi> in that he will not let it go unpunished. He therefore orders his Works so as these shall have their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable manifestation, <hi>Psal.</hi> 145.17.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the nature of Sin, as Sin, most properly appears in that it is against God, and therefore cannot but be hateful to him in regard of his <hi>Holiness.</hi> Holiness is God bound for his own Glory, and therefore set against whatsoever stands in the way of it. We cannot then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, but that upon supposition of Sin <hi>committed,</hi> God is <hi>provoked,</hi> and cannot possibly approve of it, bat abhors i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Psal.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.4, 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.13.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That there is an eminent display of Gods <hi>Holiness</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> in the witness which he bears against Sin, by resolving to punish it either in the Sinner or his Surety. Certainly God doth herein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be Glorious in Holiness, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently Just. It gives a clear and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest declaration of it to the Conviction of all: and indeed, were it not for that it so doth, God would never have put things in this way; for the Affair was
<pb n="72" facs="unknown:000684_0080_0FA9A44B2E09E380"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for this very end: and Gods ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold and unsearchable Wisdom appears in his contriving these means, so admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly suit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to the advancement of his end, <hi>Psal.</hi> 9.16.</p>
            <p>But that f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om hence the <hi>Punishment</hi> of Sin with Eternal Death, proceeds from a <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cessity,</hi> is a further enquiry. That Sin deserves it, is not to be doubted, but that God is naturally obliged to punish it so, and cannot be God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he doth, needs further consideration: and there are these things which may be thought of about it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Holiness and Justice are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dered in Efficiency as <hi>Relative Attributes.</hi> Divines distinguish of those Attributes which appear to us in the consideration of Gods <hi>Suffic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ency,</hi> and those that are discovered in his <hi>Efficiency.</hi> These latter are called <hi>Relative,</hi> because there is a <hi>Relation</hi> to the Creature evidently appears in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of them; and such are t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>se. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liness</hi> is seen in Gods managing all the Affairs of the Creature so as to gain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lory to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by all. <hi>Justice,</hi> in Gods standing by his own Law, and the terms of the Covenant which past between him, and Ration<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Beings: so that these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o suppose the Reasonable Creature
<pb n="73" facs="unknown:000684_0081_0FA9A44BEEFE6928"/>
as the Subject in which they are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested, and a Transaction between God and them, as the ground of that proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and therefore the declaration or di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lay of them terminates on the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the punishment of Sin according to these, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> also terminate on the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For God to <hi>Hate</hi> Sin, may be conceived to be in himself: but to <hi>punish</hi> it, must have a Subject on which it falls, and that is a Creature, who is punished: and thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proceeds from the <hi>Relative</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of these <hi>Attributes,</hi> with regard to the <hi>Declaration</hi> of them. <hi>Punishment</hi> is the Execution of a just Sentence un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a delinquent: and we may conceive <hi>Justice</hi> to be in God Essentially as a Perfection; and consequently <hi>anger,</hi> which is nothing else but his just displeasure at Sin: but not so <hi>punishment,</hi> which is a transient thing, and passeth on the Subject punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That hence <hi>punishment</hi> is to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned to Gods works of <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciency,</hi> of which the Rule given by Divines is, <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne opus ad extra est Contingens.</hi> That all Gods Acts or Works out of himself are Contingent, as they are opposed to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of nature; <hi>i. e.</hi> they might have
<pb n="74" facs="unknown:000684_0082_0FA9A44CAE016F70"/>
been, or they might not have been. That they are voluntary acts of Choise, and depend on his Will. Whatsoever concerns any Second Being, was at Gods pleasure, as to his treating with it, and his Dispensations of himself unto it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hence all the Works of Efficiency are the Executions of a <hi>Free, Decree,</hi> Eph. 1.11. It refers to all Gods Dispensati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both of Creation and Providence: whatsoever God doth by necessity of nature, needed not to have past into a Decree. The Decree is acknowledged by all the Orthodox, to be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>luntary Deliberation and Determination of a most free agent, prescribing to himself an <hi>Idea</hi> or method for the order and way in which he will carry on those Affairs he intends to manage, and although there is a sort of freedom which is consistent with necessity; yet a thing cannot be both naturally <hi>necessary,</hi> and yet <hi>arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> because these two are contradistinct.</p>
            <p n="5">5. There was Gods absolute Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty or Lordship in making of the <hi>Decree.</hi> We may see Infinite <hi>Wisdom, Holiness, Justice, Grace,</hi> in the contrivance it self: and reason good, for it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived on purpose for the Declaration of these: but in the contrivance it self, his
<pb n="75" facs="unknown:000684_0083_0FA9A44D6D390AA8"/>
Supream absolute Liberty was asserted: and therefore the Apostle reduceth the answer to all the Disputes and Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mens hearts, unto this, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 22. If God Decree, he cannot do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> otherwise than as God; But yet he useth his holy pleasure in it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the Punishment of Sin must have some referrence to the person, and terminate there. If we consider Sin ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stractly and separately, as it is an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, we cannot conceive how or after what manner it can be punished: The <hi>penalty</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of it therefore must bring it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the consideration of a <hi>Guil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which it leaves upon the Sinner, and by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of it exposeth him to <hi>punishment.</hi> The Sinner is the guilty person, and the Sin is his, and therefore if Sin be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily punished, it would consequently follow, that the Sinner in person must be punished, because the Sin i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pot of it cannot be Translated. If then this Guilt may be removed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, it argues that there is an arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariness in the punishing of it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Hence the transferring of the guilt and punishment of Sin from the Sinner to his Surety, seems to plead against this natural necessity: because, if the penalty
<pb n="76" facs="unknown:000684_0084_0FA9A44E2E3CF9A0"/>
be removed, the Offender may escape and therefore Sin may go unpunished in him: and that God will not remove it from him but in a way of Translation seems to be voluntary, because he hath contrived it as a way most suitable to advance the Declarative Glory of his <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>Grace.</hi> It is most certain, that Christ in suffering for Sin, suffered <hi>Arbitrarily</hi>; there was the highest Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty expressed in it. The pardoning of the Sinner hereupon is equally <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,</hi> and refers to the <hi>Covenant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi>: and how this should be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with <hi>Relative Justice,</hi> except God had a Soveraignty in regard of the thing it self, is very hard for any to tell.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> are also Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perfections. These are equally God with the other. They are Divine Attti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, and are as much Essential to God, as his <hi>Holiness</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> though they are also <hi>Relative</hi> in the manifestation of them. When God shews himself merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and gracious in pardoning Iniquity, Transgression, and Sin, he shews himself to be God, which he should not do, if these were not his <hi>Innate Perfections.</hi> These are therefore <hi>Letters of his Name,</hi> Exod.
<pb n="77" facs="unknown:000684_0085_0FA9A44F968409C0"/>
34.6, 7. and by these he gives us to know him.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Hence we may seem to argue as strongly, that God <hi>Pardons</hi> Sin by necessity of nature, as well as <hi>Punisheth</hi> it. For surely he is gracious as well as Holy and Just; and then by consequence God could no more have avoided pardoning than punishing of Sin: but we are assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that his Grace proceeds according to his good pleasure, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18.21, 22. Besides, it is to be remarked that Gods <hi>Holiness</hi> appears in the Illustration of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of his Attributes, and getting himself a Name thereby.</p>
            <p>These considerations seem to have their weight. But it must be confessed that Gods Judgments are a great deep, and Sobriety becomes us in our enquiry into the grounds and causes of them. Sin is nothing less because God pardons it, and the necessity of the interposing of a Surety for the procuring of this pardon, will be built upon another sure <hi>Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis,</hi> which the Scripture is full for, and this leads to the next thing, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Positively; there is a <hi>Connex</hi> or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Necessity of this Covenant, which
<pb n="78" facs="unknown:000684_0086_0FA9A45003925268"/>
which we may take the account of in a few Conclusions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God, by his Relative Justice, stands firmly engaged to punish Sin. Here let it be observed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there is a <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Justice.</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice appears in doing that which is right. There must be something that must fix the bounds betwixt right and wrong, or else there is no scope for Justice to exert it self. Justice appears in the manifestation of Gods Righteousness: but that cannot be manifested, nor can the Creature be brought to confess it to him, in respect of his Works, but by being convinced that he doth that which is right: and that must be by reducing it to a <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Righteousness.</hi> God in <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty</hi> may do what he will with the Creature; and that is <hi>Just</hi> in it self, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he can do no wrong. But <hi>Justice</hi> is here considered in distinction from his <hi>Arbitrary Supremacy,</hi> and therefore must have respect to a Rule; this is implied, in <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Gods Decreeing Will is the Rule of his Relative Justice. The <hi>Decree</hi> laid out the <hi>Rule</hi>: for God is <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Law-giver.</hi> The Law of <hi>Gubernation,</hi> is the Rule of <hi>Government.</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns <hi>Laws</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="unknown:000684_0087_0FA9A4506F5124D8"/>
are called their <hi>Decrees,</hi> because they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate about them, and then Decree them, and so make them authentick. Gods <hi>Decrees</hi> are <hi>Laws,</hi> because in them he hath voluntarily determined how to Govern the Creature: and though his Wisdom hath suited them to the natures of the Creatures to be Governed; whence the Light of Nature may make great discoveries; yet his <hi>Fiat</hi> makes them au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick: and there are some <hi>positive</hi> ones too. We Define Justice, to be a <hi>constant resolution to do that which is right:</hi> now Gods Will is the measure of that which is right: and as in the Decree he laid out his <hi>own Efficiency,</hi> so also the <hi>Creatures Duty</hi>; and hither the Rule must refer. The Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is his, and therefore he may prescribe to it, and it ows him Obedience. It is therefore observable, how often when God publisheth his Edicts, he gives no other reason for them but, <hi>I am the Lord,</hi> q. d. it is my will and pleasure, and who dare to Cavil at it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the first Covenant made with <hi>Adam,</hi> and the Law therein given him, was an <hi>express</hi> of this Decree concerning the duty of men, and the rewards of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Sin. It was because God had purposed thus to proceed with man, that
<pb n="80" facs="unknown:000684_0088_0FA9A4512FEC5F20"/>
he published to him this Law, with the <hi>Sanctions</hi> of it; wherein he assured him, that if he obeyed he should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but if he transgressed, he should <hi>die,</hi> Gen. 2.17. and therefore what God hath said on this account, he is resolved to pursue it, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.4. This Transaction is represented under the notion of a <hi>Covenant,</hi> to signify that there was a <hi>mutual obligation</hi>: not only did God oblige man in it, but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self too; and here was, as it were, a publication of the Edict or Decree, that man might know what God was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved on, and upon what ground he himself stood.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hence man by his fall coming un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Law of Death, Justice is strongly engaged to see the Law Executed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the true intent of it. God having given to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a Law, according to which he was to stand or fall, he must in Justice judge him by the Law. Now Gods <hi>Holiness, Justice, Truth, Righteousness, Immutability</hi> stand all concerned in it. Upon this account, Christ assures us of the necessity that not one syllable, Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or point of the Law must fall to the ground, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18. yea, God himself swears that he will do Justice, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.40. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and indeed, because
<pb n="81" facs="unknown:000684_0089_0FA9A451EEF7C208"/>
God was resolved to make sin a foil, on which he would draw the Colours of his Holiness, in the displays both of his Justice and Grace, he therefore inviolably fixed this Law or Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That hence Relative Justice requires that if sinning man be pardoned, his sin must be satisfied for according to this Law, in a Surety. Here lies the ground of the necessity. If any ask, why need God to lay a ground for such a necessity, if he could by his Lordship have pardoned Sin without a Mediator? it is easily replied, who are we to call him to an account? and it may as well may be demanded, why did God let man fall into sin to necessitate the Intervention of a Surety? surely he could have kept him from it, as he did the preserved Angels It is enough, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wisdom cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ived the way for his own Glory, and <hi>Who shall teach hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, who is most High.</hi> Here then let it be observed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Covenant of Works did not exclude the Intervening of a <hi>Redeemer</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to take up the matter between God and the Sinner. It is true, it did not make mention of such a thing; nor was it then meet to tell man, that if he should undo himself, he should be repaired by another: that was not an <hi>Article</hi> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated
<pb n="82" facs="unknown:000684_0090_0FA9A452AED7D240"/>
to a Covenant of Works; but it was reserved for another Covenant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> that of Grace. But there was no obstacle there, or provision against it; for indeed that Covenant was one of the <hi>Media</hi> for the Illustration of the Glory <hi>of Grace,</hi> and therefore it could not in Wisdom be made obstructive to it. God is the best Interpreter of his own mind, and he hath thus expounded it, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring that he hath ordained his Son to be the <hi>Repairer of the Breach, and to Redeem us from the Law, Gal.</hi> 4.4, 5. That when the Law could not Save us, he should, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. and by making of so many precious Promises to all that believe in his Son, of Pardon, Peace, Salvation; of delivering them from the Curse of the Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God therefore purposed this when he gave the First Covenant, though he did not reveal it till after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Yet the Covenant of Works posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively and inexora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly requires <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for all the breaches made upon it. It will have Reparation for all damages, and Thunders Curses upon all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Transgressors of it in any one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. and God, whose honour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ands engaged to it, to see that there
<pb n="83" facs="unknown:000684_0091_0FA9A4536E125B78"/>
be no injury offered to it, will take care that it shall be answered to the least punc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.18. This Law being at first given for a Rule of <hi>Relative Justice,</hi> must be exactly kept to: so that there is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence to be expected.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence without the coming in and undertaking of a sufficient Surety, there can be no discharge to man who is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>Delinquent.</hi> The Scripture tells us that the Sinner is <hi>Guilty</hi>: that he is <hi>bound fast</hi>; that he is <hi>concluded or shut up under Sin.</hi> The word that is Translated, is <hi>in danger,</hi> Mat. 5.21. Signifies, <hi>is held fast.</hi> It is a <hi>Metaphor</hi> from a condemned man, who is manacled or fettered against the day set for his Execution. Now the Law sets no such at liberty, but by an exchange. If it remove the Curse by taking it off from the Sinner, some other must become a Curse in his room, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> and it must be one that is sufficient; one that can and will make reparation for that Sin; otherwise the Sin is not legally punished.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That none but the person of the Son of God could be a suitable and sufficient Surety for sinning man. This will best ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, if we consider, what was requisite in such a Surety, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="84" facs="unknown:000684_0092_0FA9A4542EF4E3A8"/>1 He must be one that might be both God and Man in One Person. The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this Suretiship, having a reference to the Law of the first Covenant, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that he must be Man, because it was <hi>Man that had sinned, Heb.</hi> 2 14. The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the work to be done in this state of Suretiship, made it necessary that he should be God, as will appear in the following Considerations. Now, though the reason why this best suited the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond person in the Trinity, rather than any other, be abst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>se to us, yet in the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of these affairs, it better became the Son than any of the other persons. It was meet that the Father should appoint the person, and that the Holy Ghost should finish this Affair, which is done in <hi>Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi>: but <hi>Redemption,</hi> which must Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene, best suited the Order of personality, to be the Province of the Second Person.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He must be one whose Obedience must be of equivalent worth to that of all those for whom he became a Surety, and whatever may be pleaded in point of <hi>Active Obedience,</hi> that that of a meer man might answer the Covenant; for the First <hi>Adams</hi> would have done, if he had stood, who was but a meer man: yet as to <hi>Passive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> or Suffering, <hi>Adam</hi> could not expiate his
<pb n="85" facs="unknown:000684_0093_0FA9A454EEF92198"/>
own Guilt by suffering, much less that of his posterity, who are every one of them become guilty. It could not be any less a personage that might engage on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count than the Son of God, the Law else could not have been satisfied, but vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence must have been done to Relative Justice, if the Debtor be discharged before all his Debts are paid. He must be one that could put an <hi>Infinite merit</hi> into his Obedience, who could do this: and who but the Son of God had this ability?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence he must be one able to bear and not sink under the weight of all the wrath which man had pulled down upon himself by his Sin. Now this was <hi>Infinite Wrath,</hi> and therefore the power that was requisite for the sustaining of it, must needs exceed that of a meer Creature. This was the Glory of his Redemption, that the Work was l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id upon one who was <hi>mighty to Save,</hi> Isa. 63.1. <hi>Psal.</hi> 89.19. If he had broken under it, the design had surely miscarried, and the Salvation of Fallen Man had still been left an hopeless thing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He must be one whom God the Father could accept of, and take content in. None could force a Surety upon him; no Law tied him to accept of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;
<pb n="86" facs="unknown:000684_0094_0FA9A455AF7959D0"/>
it was his meer pleasure to do it: had he refused it from one that was never so sufficient, it had been no Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice. Needs therefore must it be one in whom he could confide, whom he could trust, and devolve this work upon: and such only was his own Son. There was none found in <hi>Heaven or Earth</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides; but of him he gave that Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, Math. 3.17.</p>
            <p n="5">5 He must be one who bare us good will, and took delight in the work of Redemption. It was certainly a very great Love to Mankind that could move him to engage in such an Undertaking as this; to expose himself to so sore a <hi>Travail of Soul,</hi> and submit to undergo such grievous things as it was requisite for him to do in the making of satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Justice of God, and answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the demands of the Law, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere was none but the Son of God that entertained such a respect for poor man in his misery: but he did, <hi>Prov..</hi> 8.31. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ezek. 26.5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Son of God could not become actually engaged to be mans Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, so as that our Redemption should be secured by it, but only by a Covenant:
<pb n="87" facs="unknown:000684_0095_0FA9A4566E03D8A0"/>
and this will be manifest in the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of these things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It was absolutely free for the Son of God to chuse whether he would be a Redeemer, and Surety, or no. The Son of God is a Divine Person, and hath all personal propertios belonging to him: Now one thing proper to a Person is, to be <hi>Intelligent,</hi> and by consequence to have a <hi>power of Election.</hi> Christ was no Surety by nature; it was none of his either Essential or Personal Properties: and he could not be so by Coaction, for he is the <hi>Eternal Jehovah,</hi> and therefore cannot be compelled. The Apostle plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly asserts his full liberty in this matter, in <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2 God the Father was not absolutely bound to accept any satisfaction at the hands of a surety. Had the Son offered it, yet his Suretiship could not have been authentick, but by the intervention of the Fathers voluntary consent. If God had said, and resolved, that fallen man should bear his own puni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hment, and there should be no substitute accepted in his room, who should have opposed him? he had Justice on his side; man was the sinner, yea and he did so say con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fallen <hi>Angels,</hi> and therefore
<pb n="88" facs="unknown:000684_0096_0FA9A4572DFB4168"/>
they are all of them <hi>reserved in everlasting Chains.</hi> The case was criminal, and an exchange of an offender for an innocent person to suffer in his room, is scarcely allowable among men, to be sure, the Judge may righteously refuse it. Nor did it flow from Gods natural love to mankind; for he had as much for the Angelical nature, and for the residue of men who were not included in this Covenant: it must then be of his free choice.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Hence it follows, that neither could the work be sure to be done, nor the reward of the work be certain to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but upon mutual compact or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement. There could have been no security on any hand without it; and therefore witho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t this it could not have been a certain truth from eternity, that the Son of God should, in fulness of time, come into the world, and become a Saviour; the contrary to which the Scripture assures us. Now to sum up all that hath been said on this account; the <hi>Necessity</hi> of this <hi>Covenant</hi> lies in these few following Conclusions.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That mankind stands under a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of works, which requires Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="89" facs="unknown:000684_0097_0FA9A457EDDF0AC0"/>
of him, and threatens disobedience with death. This Covenant being made with <hi>Adam,</hi> as the head of mankind, it included all his posterity, who were to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and or fall with him, in the first tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of his Obedience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Divine Justice stands enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to this Covenant to see it rigorously performed according to the true intent of it. Hereby was man reduced to that exigency, that in case of Disobedience, he must unavoidably dy, either in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self or in his surety, Justice, lying in the way, must be satisfied, if mercy appear.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That man is fallen under, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by became forfeited to the law, and liable to the execution of the sentence of it. it was not his <hi>Original state,</hi> but his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stasy</hi> that reduced him to this exigency: but by reason of that, Divine Justice hath him in chase, and is pursuing him to Death.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That God will save a residue of that company, and <hi>deliver them from the wrath to come.</hi> For, if God had purposed in himself to have destroyed all mankind, and to make his wrath known in their personal eternal sufferings, there could have been no necessity for a Covenant of Redemption. Justice had its full scope
<pb n="90" facs="unknown:000684_0098_0FA9A458AD63B488"/>
to take place upon man, being exposed unto it by sin; but mercy had that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in its way which left it no room for the exerting of it self without such a Transaction.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That for this end he will provide a Redeemer for men. He will lay in to make this Salvation sure, and open a way wherein he may not deny himself, but <hi>be both Just, and the Justifier of all those that believe in his Son</hi>: and that, when mans case shall call for it; when his misery shall stand in need of such a course to be taken for its succour, the remedy may not be to seek: In all these respects it was necessary, and that because.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Without a Redeemer <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> could not have met in agreement in the salvation of fallen man, either there must have been a Clashing between these two <hi>Attributes,</hi> or else man must have been for ever under the wrath of God. If there had been no Redeemer, there could have been no salvation according to the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of the dispensation of the first Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>Futurition</hi> of a Redeemer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended absolutely on this Covenant. Here it had its foundation and rise, as hath
<pb n="91" facs="unknown:000684_0099_0FA9A4596D3B0A60"/>
been already proved. Those promises, compacts, and engagements between God the Father and God the Son, gave the futurition to Christs coming into the World, doing the work of Redemption, and receiving all the Rewards consequent upon it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If this Redeemer had not come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, and performed the work of mans Redemption, then</p>
            <p n="1">1. Man had continued for ever in a state of Condemnation. He had remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the same condition with Fallen Angels, an hopeless, forlorn, miserable Creature. If Christ had not died, we had been <hi>without any Hope,</hi> for it is by his Death that we are delivered, Rom. 8.14. But for this, the Condemnation which fell upon us for sin, must needs have remained irreversible, and we must all have perished indubitably.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Grace had been without its declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Glory. That Attribute, which he had a design signally to advance, and to make himself known in and by, to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Admiration, had mist of this Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration, and never been thus spoken of. <hi>Socinians</hi> indeed labour to perswade us, that the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of Christ for Sin, destroys the notion of Grace appearing
<pb n="92" facs="unknown:000684_0100_0FA9A3852E043660"/>
in the Salvation of Sinners, and denies the freedom of his mercy in his saving of them; and therefore they will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no such <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> But i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is a very great mistake, for this is the very thing which enhaunceth this Grace of God, and puts a great many wonders into the Declaration of it; for though it is not to be denied, that for God to have ordained that sinful man should, upon the Confession of his Sins, and voluntary submitting of himself to Gods Soveraignty, have received a free pardon of all his sins, would have been a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous declaration of free Grace, and so a wonderful condescendency in God, thus to have past by the high affronts which are by mans sin offered to his glorious Name; yet, to consider, that when man was become so involved or intangled by a righteous, and yet a rigorous Law, as that there was no possibility of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing saved without the Death of a Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for him; and that no less a perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage would serve for this than the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Son of God; that the Father should voluntarily spare him out of his own bosome, yea and freely appoint him to this Office, that he should by submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Law, yea doing and dying
<pb n="93" facs="unknown:000684_0101_0FA9A385EF8BB120"/>
in our nature and stead, become a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour for us, that so we might not die but live, and mercy might flow down to us, through his being made a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for us, and suffering the whole weight of Gods wrath on our account; this makes <hi>Grace</hi> to be the more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously resplendent, yea, and raiseth it up to the highest pitch of admiration that can be imagined.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 11. Of the Influence that the Covenant of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption hath into the Covenant of Grace, which is made with us.</head>
            <p>THE Foundation of Fallen Mans Salvation is laid in the Covenant <hi>of Redemption</hi>: here was the price pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to buy him out of the hands of Revenging Justice, and purchase for him the Eternal Inheritance. Here also was security given that all those for whom it was provided should be made happy par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers
<pb n="94" facs="unknown:000684_0102_0FA9A386AF4B4CC0"/>
in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of it. But still there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in order to the bringing of them into the actual enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this <hi>Title,</hi> and having this Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver unto them, and for this the Scripture points us to another <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> distinct from this, which is by some called the <hi>Covenant of Reconciliation</hi>; but is more generally known by the name of the <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi> Not as if the former were not of meer Grace; but here, the Grace which was laid up in the former, breaks forth and is applied effectually unto them, who were before the heirs of it. Nor can these Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants be confounded, without greatly darkning the knowledge of the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Mystery</hi> of the Love of God to men. These Covenants are Essentially diverse one from the other, having neither the same <hi>Parties,</hi> nor the same <hi>Articles</hi> in them. In the former the Father and the Son are the parties, in this latter, God and Man. In the former, the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of God was to be satisfied; in the latter, the Grace of God, which was so made way for, is to be applied. In the former, the <hi>Law</hi> was to be fulfilled by Christ; in the latter the <hi>Gospel</hi> is to be complied with by man. In the
<pb n="95" facs="unknown:000684_0103_0FA9A3876F8534F8"/>
former, Christ was made one party; in the latter he stands as the <hi>Mediator</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween both parties, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2.5. In the former, God Covenanted <hi>for us,</hi> in the latter he Covenants <hi>with us</hi>: there he promised us to his Son; here he promiseth himself to us. But though these are two Covenants, yet there is a near Conjunction between them, and the latter hath a manifold dependance on the former: yea, such, as all the Believers solid comfort, and permanent hope a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riseth from it: yea indeed, all the Grace that there is in this Covenant derives from that, as a stream from a Fountain; and this may be observed more especially in five respects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Covenant between God the Father and God the Son, was that which opened the way for his Covenanting with his people. Had not that Covenant been first made, this would never have been heard of. The Covenant which God Indents with his people is wholly of Grace, in all the parts of it, as it is made by him: from the foundation to the top-stone of it, there is no other voice to be heard but that of Grace. Now, had there not been an <hi>Antecedent Covenant,</hi> which man had some relation
<pb n="96" facs="unknown:000684_0104_0FA9A3884158B618"/>
unto, this might immediately, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any previous p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation have entred into. Grace is free, else it were not Grace; and God might have exprest it to whom he saw meet. But when we consider how it was with man when this Covenant was declared; <hi>viz.</hi> that he stood under an Old Covenant of Works, and was related to it as a Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressor; the <hi>Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pt</hi> of it being violated by him, and the <hi>Curse</hi> of it having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken place on him, and the <hi>Justice</hi> of God standing obliged to the fulfilling of the <hi>Articles</hi> in that Covenant which God had engaged in: it stood up as an high <hi>Wall of Separation between God and Man,</hi> and called for vengeance to be executed upon him according to his Earnings; nor could it be appeased without full satisfaction given to it for the Injuries done it by the sinning Creature. All mankind stood thus Condemned, and Men of Death. Hence it was necessary, that without a <hi>Covenant of Reparation</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terposing, there could not be a <hi>Covenant of Salvation.</hi> Had not this great Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action past, the Covenant of Works must of necessity have taken place, and we must have been judged and condemned, and for ever destroyed by it. <hi>God must
<pb n="97" facs="unknown:000684_0105_0FA9A388EEF53D80"/>
be Just, in being gracious</hi>: he must not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>himself</hi> or any of his <hi>Attributes: Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and truth must correspond</hi>; and how could that be as the case stood, had there not been such a transaction as this? If Justice had not interposed, Grace might have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded without any more ado; but because <hi>God must be Just in Justifying a sinner,</hi> there must be provision made that he may be so: So that this Covenant of Redemption may be looked upon as the <hi>procuring cause</hi> of the Covenant of Grace: it opened the door to it, removed the obstructions that would else have impeded it, and made the way for God to be gracious to poor sinning man, and save him, without any injury done to his justice, or violence offered to his law. Here it was that all was laid in that needed to satisfy that to the utmost farthing: and when that is once appeased and its mouth stopt, so that it hath no more to say, Grace hath now its full and free scope. In this regard we shall find, the Apostle redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of our Salvation to this Covenant which was made with Christ before time, as the Root and Original of it. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The Application of the Grace of the <hi>Covenant of Reconciliation,</hi> whereby any of the children of men are brought into
<pb n="98" facs="unknown:000684_0106_0FA9A389AFB15DA8"/>
that Covenant, and truly entituled to all the good which is therein promised to the Children of God, bears an entire re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to the Covenant of Redemption. That all the Children of men are not taken into the New and Everlasting Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>venant, is certain. That all those to whom it is offered in the Gospel, do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally embrace it, is also evident upon ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation. So that the reason of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nnot be because some do hear of it, and others do not. That any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to come into this Covenant, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in their unbelief, when they are outwardly called, is their own fault, and it will be charged upon their <hi>wilfulness,</hi> Joh. 5.40. But that an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do entertain it, and actually close in with the terms of it, and believe in Christ for salvation, <hi>is not of themselves</hi> or by any power of their own, <hi>but of God,</hi> Eph. 2.8 And if he should have done no more towards their believing, than he did to the other, they would have been for ever under their unbelief. Now there must be some reason assigned why God applies it to this and not to the other. This cannot be in the Creature, because all are alike <hi>Children of wrath,</hi> and equally guilty and filthy in their natural state as born, Eph.
<pb n="99" facs="unknown:000684_0107_0FA9A38A6EE7D3E8"/>
2.3. It must then be in God. And as the Covenant of Redemption was a result of his meer good pleasure, so the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Grace of the New-Covenant, is an act, of his faithfulness to his promise to Christ in that Covenant. Hence, when God comes with his Converting Grace, to bestow it upon any; when he powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perswades the man to <hi>receive the word of truth,</hi> and accept of Jesus Christ upon his offer and terms; and passeth by that other who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>its by him, and leaves him to despise, and make light of the Grace exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to him; he evermore hath his eye upon, and proceeds according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this Covenant. So that those who were Covenanted for by Christ, and given him of his Father, are brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Covenant of Grace by the Holy Ghost. The Spirit of God, when he comes to make the Gospel Efficacious unto the salvation of sinners, by putting them into the Covenant of Grace, he takes his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures by this Covenant: <hi>he reads these ancient records,</hi> observes who they were by <hi>name,</hi> that were given to the Son of God in that transaction; he address<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th these with his power, and causeth them <hi>to hear his voice</hi> that they may live; we have such an expression in <hi>Acts</hi> 15.48. <hi>as many as
<pb n="100" facs="unknown:000684_0108_0FA9A38B2E75EBC0"/>
were ordained to Eternal life believed.</hi> Yea and our Saviour Christ lays that down as a Rule which never fails, <hi>John</hi> 6.37. <hi>All that the Father giveth me, shall come unto me.</hi> Christ first redeems them by <hi>Price,</hi> and then the spirit delivers them by <hi>Power:</hi> he first buys them out of the hands of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,</hi> and then the Holy Ghost comes and fetcheth them out of the <hi>Prison of Sin,</hi> and from under the <hi>Power of Satan,</hi> and enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them. So that the Covenant of Grace in respect to the extensiveness of it, to the Subject, is made just as large as the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Redempti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, that being the pattern according to which it is made, and the reason of this is grounded in the former consideration: for till men are bought out of the hands of the Law they are not free to be indented with in a way of Grace they are not <hi>Sui Juris,</hi> they cannot Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant for themselves; they are the <hi>servants of sin and satan,</hi> and prisoners of the Law: except therefore Christ have paid the price for them, they are in no capacity for this Grace, but must abide under their former state of Condemnation.</p>
            <p n="3">3 All the encouragement which an awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened sinner hath to embrace &amp; take hold of the Grace which is exhibited in the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb n="101" facs="unknown:000684_0109_0FA9A38BEE193D30"/>
Covenant, ariseth, or is fetched from the Covenant of Redemption. There is a previous <hi>Conviction</hi> which is wont to be wrought in the heart or conscience of a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, in order to the proposal of the Terms of the Gospel to him: and this is requisite, for without this <hi>Conviction</hi> he cannot be brought to see any need that he stands in of the benefits of the New-Covenant; and consequently cannot be perswaded to give them entertainment. Now in the working of this <hi>Conviction,</hi> he is made to see and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend his forlorn wretched state, and how he came to fall into it: that an holy law hath been broken by him; that by vertue hereof he lies under guilt, and is fast bound by a Sentence of Condemnation, to suffer the wrath of God, and vengeance of hell: that he hath to do with a God who is a just and a righteous Judge, who will stand to his word, and is unchangeable, and will give accomplishment to all that he hath said with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fail. So that when he is under the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of these Convictions, and now the Grace of God is tendered him in the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and he is spoken to, and treated with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the things of his peace: he is told that God is Gracious, ready to pardon, willing to receive him into favour, and to bestow salvation upon him; although these things
<pb n="102" facs="unknown:000684_0110_0FA9A38D7599CD40"/>
are glad tidings in themselves, yet there will arise demurs and enquities in him about the matter, and he will be ready to say <hi>how can these things be</hi>? he will presently demand, how then shall the Justice of God be satisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for me? how shall the mouth of the law be stopt? how shall the first Covenant be fully answered and stand inviolable? nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it to be supposed, that such an one can believingly cast himself upon the Gospel Grace, and place his reliance upon Christ, till he be well satisfied upon this account. That is not to be accounted for a true <hi>faith</hi> which rashly adventures upon accepting of tendred me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cy, and never considers how it comes, or in what way his sin may be so pardoned, as that God may salve the honour of his Justice in the Applying of Justification unto him. Now this discovery is to be made in the Contemplation of the <hi>Covenant of Redemption</hi>: here alone it is that this is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seen: for in that it was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t this provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion was made: Here is the great disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Surety<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ip of Christ, in which he put himself in the sinners room and undertook to satisfie for him, and God accepted of him in that Relation; and accordingly all that he did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the work of his Humiliation was on this score, and in the Accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="103" facs="unknown:000684_0111_0FA9A38E35646948"/>
of this Undertaking of his, and so it was done on the account of <hi>us Sinners</hi> 2 Cor. 5.21. Nor indeed could all that Christ actually did and suffered give us a through satisfaction on this account, without our being able to refer it to this Covenant, in which it is that we come to know what is the Efficacy and Acceptableness of it. We cannot then enter into the Covenant of Grace, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having an eye on the Covenant of Redemption: <hi>for in the exerting of Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Faith, we do not only believe that we shall be Saved, but we believe in Christ for Salvation, to come to us from his merit, by the application of the vertue of his active and passive Obedience to us for our Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: and the acceptance of our persons and duties in him, being Sprinkled with his Blood:</hi> and all this is a proper result from the Covenant we are now treating of.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A true Believer, who is entred into the Covenant of Grace with God, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not strongly plead for any Covenant-mercy at his hands without running up hither. It is true, the Covenant of Grace is sure: it hath its firm and inviolable promises belonging to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and every one that hath entertained it by a true and
<pb n="104" facs="unknown:000684_0112_0FA9A38EF493ABC8"/>
living Faith, is under the promises of it, and hath such a Title to them as can never fail him. But let us observe, The Covenant of Grace hath its <hi>Conditions</hi>; and it is certain upon daily experience, that the best Believers do but poorly on their part perform that which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them, and are often failing in, and falling short of their Duty in this regard: if therefore they must always fix their eye upon that, and look no farther than themselves, they would not seldom, be driven off from Prayer, and lose their active hopes of acceptance with God; especially when they are over-ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with gross prevarications, and woful scandalous failures in their Covenant Obligations: and these things have some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld them under doubts, and fears, and darkness: and where shall they have their Souls lifted up again, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to go to God for the Grace and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lp which they need, but by remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the Covenant made with Christ, in which they are given to him, and undertaken for by him? and not only so, but it is to be remembred, that there i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no <hi>Meritorious</hi> vertue in the best Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce or Covenant keeping which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> attain unto, to impetrate any mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="105" facs="unknown:000684_0113_0FA9A38FB2F85700"/>
at the hands of God for them. Their <hi>Righteousness</hi> when it is best, is but <hi>ragged and defiled.</hi> There is something in all they do which wants a pardon, or else it cannot be accepted of them; and all the right that we have in any of that good which is laid up in the Promises of the Covenant of Grace, is derived to us from the merit of Christs Obedience and Satisfaction; and we can believing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ask for it upon no other score. When therefore <hi>David</hi> pleads with God for <hi>good,</hi> he begs of him to be his <hi>Surety, Psal.</hi> 119.122. All the Encouragement that a Child of God hath to be impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate with God, and wait on him with expectation to be made to partake in his favours, which derive through the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, is in this, that he knows, or is made to have an active hope, that his name is written in the Covenant of Redemption; and therefore he may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ask it for Christs sake; because he hath both purchased this good at the hands of God, and also that he did it for him in particular.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is the Covenant of Redemption that establisheth, or maketh unchangeable, all the mercies and promises of the Covenant of Grace. For; although it is so that God,
<pb n="106" facs="unknown:000684_0114_0FA9A39072FBA6A8"/>
who is one party in the Covenant he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, and cannot falsify his word which he hath past; yet we who are on the other party, are mutable, and consequent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly might violate the condition, and so come under a forfeiture, and lose the Promises: and therefore such as look no farther than the Covenant of Grace, and consider the conditions of it, and the threatnings annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to it, such as, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.38. <hi>&amp; the like,</hi> have been ready to deny the Doctrine of <hi>Perseverance</hi>; and set up the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable Doctrine of total and final <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stasy</hi> whereas this Covenant affords us a compleat <hi>Salvo</hi> for all this, because in it, there is a security provided for the people of God, and a promise made to the Son that none of those whom his father hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him shall be lost, or be suffered to draw back to perdition. The <hi>mercies</hi> of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace are <hi>sure mercies,</hi> because they are the mercies of <hi>David, Isa.</hi> 55.3. <hi>i. e.</hi> They are such as were promised to him; <hi>viz.</hi> to Christ, of whom <hi>David was a Type.</hi> The promises indeed are invaria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but if it be enquired how they came to be so, it is to be observed that they are said to be <hi>in him,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.20. It is he who gives them their confirmation: on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it is that when God speaks of his
<pb n="107" facs="unknown:000684_0115_0FA9A391338A7540"/>
continuing his mercy to his people, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all their falls and false dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in his Covenant, he Comemorates an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther Covenant as the ground of his so doing, <hi>Psal.</hi> 89.33, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Not the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which was made with <hi>Davids</hi> Children<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which intends the Covenant of Grace, but that which was plighted with <hi>David</hi> himself, <hi>i. e.</hi> with <hi>Christ,</hi> and that is the Covenant of Redemption. Emblematical of this are these observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Scriptures, 1 Kings 15.3, 4, 5. 2 King. 8.16.34. and a clear distinction is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made between these two Covenants in that memorable place, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.60. There is the <hi>Covenant made with them in the days of their youth, i. e.</hi> in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness, which was a Covenant of Grace, under Ceremonies, Signs and Types: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is God saith he <hi>will Remember, i. e.</hi> graciously; he will perform the good for them which was held forth in it, notwithstanding all they had done to provoke him to the contrary. Put how will he do this? he will <hi>establish unto them an Everlasting Covenant,</hi> i. e. the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Redemption<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and therefore observe, he doth not say he will establish it <hi>with them</hi>; but <hi>unto them</hi>; i. e. he would make them receive the application
<pb n="108" facs="unknown:000684_0116_0FA9A391F196A420"/>
of all the good which was provided for them in it: yea, indeed, this is it which sets God on work, to bring about the mercy intended for his Chosen, when they are doing all they can to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand it, and lay the greatest blocks in the way to it; because he hath enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to do this in the Eternal Transacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that past between him and his Son about it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb n="109" facs="unknown:000684_0117_0FA9A392AEF42058"/>
            <head>CHAP. 12. The Application of this Truth by way of Information.</head>
            <p>THE Doctrine of the Covenant of Redemption is not meerly <hi>specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> but exceeding <hi>practical</hi> and it will not be amiss, to subjoin some brief improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, and here;</p>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>USE I.</head>
               <p>May be by way of <hi>Information:</hi> there are several inferences which may be drawn from and confirmed by it: let a few be here taken notice of:</p>
               <div n="1" type="inference">
                  <head>INFERENCE I.</head>
                  <p>We may here see the ground of the certainty, and infallibility of the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and Salvation of all Gods Elect. The
<pb n="110" facs="unknown:000684_0118_0FA9A3936DDBBF00"/>
right conception and consideration of this Covenant, will take away all doubts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, and afford many undeniable evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of it; and in particular.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. We may strongly argue from the inexpressible love of God, which herein discovers it self abundantly. The same love which gave Christ for us in the ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ness of time, provided him for us in the days of Eternity; and that is set forth as incomparable, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.16. <hi>God so loved,</hi> &amp;c: there is no <hi>reddition.</hi> Nay here is the <hi>Emphasis</hi> of it; he not only gave him for us when we needed him but he provided him for us before we needed him: that he made sure of this salvation for us <hi>before all ages and generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> This Covenant was the Lords own <hi>Doing</hi> every way, and may well be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous <hi>in our eyes.</hi> He first thought of it, when there was none to put him in mind of it in his Infinite Wisdom; and he In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented it: and sure he would never have done all this if his heart had not been set upon the Salvation of his Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen. It was he who propounded, and ratified this Covenant with his own Son, <hi>Psal.</hi> 89.3. and would he have made it and so ratified it, with such firm and inviolable engagements, if he had no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="111" facs="unknown:000684_0119_0FA9A3942F516F10"/>
been fully resolved upon the unfailing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment of it?</p>
                  <p n="2">2 This will be farther pleaded: because the <hi>Individual names</hi> of those who were thus to be redeemed by Christ, were put into the <hi>Articles</hi> of this Covenant. There was not only an agreement made, that there should be a Common price paid, a Common stock laid in, which might be sufficient for as many as would make improvement of it; It might then have been uncertain whether any at all should have been saved by it: but the very persons were covenanted for; and this is evidently intended by the <hi>writing of their names in the Book of life,</hi> of which mention is made in the Scripture, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13 8.17.8. Which is nothing else but the book of the Covenant of Redemption, in which provision was made for the resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of dead sinners to life again by Jesus Christ, it is therefore called the <hi>Lambs book,</hi> because these were given to him to redeem. And <hi>Names</hi> must needs indigitate persons: so that the individuals were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented for, and this is a book which hath no blots in it: those that are here written must needs be saved: what saith Christ himself about it? <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. <hi>All that the Father hath given me shall come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="112" facs="unknown:000684_0120_0FA9A394EE9E0D30"/>3. All these are firmly promised and engaged to Christ in this Covenant, they shall be his Seed, upon the performance of the Articles that were proposed unto him. This was one Encouragement that his Father offered to him, see <hi>Isa.</hi> 13.10 Psal. 22.30. and how do they come to be the Seed of Christ, and consequently the Children of God, but by being brought into the Covenant of Grace, and under the Promise of Eternal Life, Gal. 3.26. Now this was the Word and Promise of God himself; The <hi>Unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> God, the God that <hi>cannot Lie</hi>: and it is made to his own Son; and upon it he undertook the work, and went through it, in expectation of the compleat Accomplishment of it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. <hi>for the Joy that was set before him, &amp;c.</hi> and what can we possibly conceive to be more firm?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Sufficiency of the Redeemer must needs make this Salvation sure to those for whom it was provided. In this Covenant God took care to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide one who was every way able to do the work which he was to Engage in; and therefore it was utterly impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that it should fail in his hands. For this reason he is said to be a <hi>strong Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer</hi>
                     <pb n="113" facs="unknown:000684_0121_0FA9A395B017B0F8"/>
Jer. 50.34. and <hi>Mighty to save.</hi> Isa. 63.1. see also for this, Deut. 33.23 <hi>Psal.</hi> 83.19. He is able to bear down all Opposition that can be made against him and there is no adverse power that can so interpose as to obstruct this Salvation, but it is carried on with a strong hand: needs then must it be without fail brought about.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 By this Covenant, that which lay in the way as the great Obstacle or hindrance of mans Salvation, is altogether removed, so as it shall no longer impede it: <hi>viz. the justice of the first Covenant.</hi> Fallen man is by a Righteous Law condemned, and Jus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice demands the life of the sinner for its satisfaction: but <hi>in the Covenant of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, Justice it self is not only pacified, but stands as deeply engaged for the Salvation of Gods Redeemed, as any other of the Divine Attributes:</hi> it is in Combination with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyin this business, <hi>Psal.</hi> 85.10. and by vertue of this transaction, not only Grace and Mercy, but Justice also appears glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously, and triumphantly in the sinners de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, 1 Joh. 1.9. and what is there then that should impede this business? Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes here breaks forth with Lustre, and God no way wrongs either his Truth or his Holiness, in saving the chief of
<pb n="114" facs="unknown:000684_0122_0FA9A3966F8884A0"/>
sinners by Jesus Christ. For the Son of God becoming a surety for miserable man, who was by the fall undone, and became insolvent to the Law, he dischargeth him of all his Obligations to that Covenant; &amp; having given compleat satisfaction to it in all its demands, the sinner is, <hi>by the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Act of Justice,</hi> discharged of that debt: and now God declares his <hi>Righteousness</hi> in Justifying of him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.26. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the Apostle makes a Challenge, he strengthens it by forming such an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as this, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 34. <hi>Who is he that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth? It is Christ that Dyed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6 Hence if any of Gods Elect should fail of being brought into the Covenant of Grace, and so being saved; this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant would so far be defeated and made void. For, if the Covenant were so made as that the Names of those who were to be Redeemed, were all put into it, then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all these must be brought into the possession of the good Provided for them or else there must be some of those lost whom the Father had given to Christ, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst which he himself declares, and it would certainly tend greatly to his Disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Those then who have attained to be able to read their names written in the
<pb n="115" facs="unknown:000684_0123_0FA9A3973220BF98"/>
book of <hi>Life,</hi> and have so <hi>made their Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on sure,</hi> may hereby be assured, of their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure standing in this Covenant, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort themselves in the confident expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the unfailing assistance of the Grace of God, to Preserve them unto Life Eternal, according to <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="inference">
                  <head>INFERENCE II.</head>
                  <p>Here we see where and whence those <hi>Absolute promises</hi> Recorded in the Scripture, have their Originall. There is a great dispute in the world about <hi>Absolute Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</hi> The <hi>Arminians</hi> do wholly deny any such to be at all. The <hi>Antinomians</hi> do err as much on the other hand in asserting them to be made to <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as sinners.</hi> A right understanding of this Covenant, and the true rela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion which these promises have to it, will give us light for the clearing of all these doubts. Here then take these following Asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That there are no promises of Gods special favour Recorded in His Word, but what do belong unto some Covena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. All Gods d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lings with mankind, which refer to their Everlasting Estate, are in the way of a Covenant. As soon as God had Created man, he plighted a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="116" facs="unknown:000684_0124_0FA9A397F0958BB8"/>
with him, in which <hi>Life and Death</hi> were set before him: and when the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant was violated by mans sin, and he had forfeited the Life that was promised, and purchased the Death threatned in that God having a design of saving a number of this unhappy race, made the discoveries of an <hi>Hope</hi> to him, by bringing in a New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, &amp; this was revealed unto man im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately upon his <hi>Apostasy.</hi> This indeed is a way best suited to the nature of man; and God hath vouchsafed thus to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate himself thereunto, see, <hi>Psal.</hi> 111.9. <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.3. And elsewhere frequently.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 That it is of the nature of a Covenant Promise to be joyned with some Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This Conclusion follows from the consideration of a Covenant in General, which is a <hi>Mutual Obligation,</hi> wherein there are two parties engaged each to the other: so that the engagement on one part, stands related to the engagement on the other part, &amp; thereupon it is <hi>Hypothetical.</hi> A Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant Promise is a Promise which is made with a <hi>relative respect</hi> to something that is expected from him to whom it is made, on the performance whereof the <hi>Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the Promise stands and on the fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure
<pb n="117" facs="unknown:000684_0125_0FA9A398AE9DCAC8"/>
whereof it becomes void: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is sometimes expressed, always intended, a <hi>Threatn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng</hi> to take place instead of the <hi>Promise,</hi> in case of such a failure: and a person hath no farther hold on the Promise, than as he is under the <hi>Condition</hi> of it. So was the promise of the first Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Isa.</hi> 56.2. And therefore there was also a Threatning, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. Thus also is the Gospel Covenant Promise <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> pressed and connected, <hi>Mark,</hi> 16, 16.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 That these <hi>Absolute Promises</hi> are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called <hi>Absolute,</hi> because they have no <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending Condition</hi> in the Covenant of Grace. Hither we are to refer all such Promises as do engage the <hi>giving of the conditions of the Covenant of Grace</hi> to these or those. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such as these are to be found in the Book of God, particularly in <hi>Isa.</hi> 57.18 <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25, 26, 27. And several more of the same Tenour.</p>
                  <p>These Promises can have no conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on depending in the Covenant of Grace, for so they would argue a contradiction; for God to say, I will <hi>Convert</hi> you, if you will <hi>Convert</hi> yourselves; I will give <hi>you a New heart,</hi> if you will <hi>make a New Heart to yourselves</hi>; I will give you <hi>Faith to believe,</hi> if you will <hi>believe</hi> in your own strength. These promises re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present
<pb n="118" facs="unknown:000684_0126_0FA9A39979C8B598"/>
God plainly undertaking, freely and fully to work that in sinners, which is required in the <hi>Gospel Covenant,</hi> in order to their being made partakers in the good therein promised; and for that reason are they said to be <hi>Absolute,</hi> with respect to the Gospel Covenant, because they bear no respect to the Condition which is therein propounded and required so as to engage for it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That all these promises have their <hi>Conditions,</hi> and the performance of them, contained in the Covenant of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Hence it is that they are given in the Word of God, to be the discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the great Efficacy of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and to assure us of the certain and unfailing fulfilment of it: that no sin or unworthiness of the Creature, shall be able to obstruct it, how much soever they have done to throw blocks in the way, and to provoke God to reject them, yet it shall not prevent the breaking out of his grace in the Accomplishment thereof; because all that Gods Elect do or can do, to hinder their own Salvati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, and bring wrath upon themselves, is taken care about, and full satisfaction is made for it in that Covenant by our
<pb n="119" facs="unknown:000684_0127_0FA9A39A330B9C98"/>
Surety: and hereupon do these Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions follow.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That those Promises are not of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversal Application. They do not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage God to all men universally: they are not made to <hi>Sinners as Sinners; i. e.</hi> none can challenge the application of them to themselves on that account, or for this reason, because they are <hi>Sinners.</hi> But they are confined to the <hi>Election of God,</hi> or to those who are comprehended in the Covenant of Redemption; and they only do <hi>obtain them,</hi> Rom. 11.7. <hi>The Election hath obtained.</hi> It is not for every one that reads these Promises, to confide and lot upon it, that they are made unto him, and to take them to be the ground of his Faith, and to conclude that by vertue of them, he shall be Saved. God only knows whom they belong to, before such time as there is a particular application made of them by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.6.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That no man can challenge thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Promises as his own, till he be brought under the Covenant of Grace, and the Conditions of it are wrought in him. These Promises do not discover any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way of <hi>Salvation</hi> unto men, than that which is Revealed in the Gospel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="120" facs="unknown:000684_0128_0FA9A39B6AA20830"/>
which is by Faith in Christ, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance unto Life: and therefore though these promises are not annexed to the Gospel Condition, or depend upon it, yet they do engage for it, <hi>viz. to give a New Heart</hi>; to bestow Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance upon them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and upon this account, they discover themselves to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to this or that man in particular, in the application which the Spirit of God doth make of these conditions to him: When therefore the Condition is wrought in the Soul, then the man may and ought to apply them, and take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self the comfort of them, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Love of God to him, and his Faithfulness to his own purposes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises which he made to Christ in the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erlasting Covenant: but till then we have no assurance. Our <hi>Election</hi> is only made sure, by securing our <hi>Calling,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This notwithstanding, these pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises are useful to be looked upon by the <hi>Awakened,</hi> though at present <hi>Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted</hi> Sinner, to Engage him to wait upon, and hope in God for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the work in him, and that notwithstanding his own sinful unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiness and weakness: since they declare
<pb n="121" facs="unknown:000684_0129_0FA9A39D7A6B17E8"/>
to him, that <hi>Gods Grace is absolutely inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent on any qualifications in the Creature,</hi> and cannot be obstructed by the absence of them; and may thereupon direct him whither to go for Grace to believe, and for Sanctification; and whence he must derive it, if ever he partake in it. They say that God is the Author of all and therefore all the Objections and Dis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>couragements which they are ready to gather from the conditions in that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, and their own inability <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> perform them, are here recovered, by shewing them who is the Author of this Grace: and because he hath abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely said that he will do it for some, it gives us hope that if we wait upon him for it, he will do it for us.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Yea these promises signify to all where the Gospel comes, that there is no hindrance <hi>on Gods part,</hi> why he may not come and pardon and heal the sinner nor any impediment on our part by rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son of Impenitency, unbelief, or great trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions, but that he may look over, break through, and for all them come to us, and afford us this Salvation for his own Great Names Sake, and by vertue of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which he hath made with his own
<pb n="122" facs="unknown:000684_0130_0FA9A39DF5A8B1C0"/>
Son; and that notwithstanding all our unworthiness, and indisposedness to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it. In a word, these Promises signify that the business of Redemption is secured, and that God hath already taken up, &amp; is satisfied in the Suretiship of His Son, and accounts himself under an inviolable bond to perform the Good promised, for all those who were appointed to be the Heirs of this great Salvation: and how much of encouragement is there in this for poor guilty sinners that have no other hope before them?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="inference">
                  <head>INFERENCE III.</head>
                  <p>Here we see upon how strong a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation a believers hopes for Glory are laid. We have observed that there is a neer connection between the Covenant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and that of Grace: and here is one principal inference which is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from the connection that he who by Faith in Christ is brought into the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>venant of Grace, may derive the strength of hope and holy confidence to himself from the Ancient Covenant of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; because <hi>his being in this undeniably sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth him to have been included in that:</hi> and
<pb n="123" facs="unknown:000684_0131_0FA9A39EB8B07B50"/>
then, no wonder if his faith be often sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and his hopes unsetled, if he do not keep his eye continually upon this. But a right speculation here will wonderfully nourish and strengthen him. <hi>Hope</hi> is a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers <hi>Anchor,</hi> with which he keeps himself from running adrift in hours of Temptati: on: it is that which he <hi>Lives upon</hi> till he comes to Heaven, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24. How much then may he strengthen this by such a contemplation? for from this Covenant there flow down to him these Glorious discoveries.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Here he sees that <hi>satisfaction</hi> is made to the Justice of God for his sins; and that his <hi>happiness</hi> is bought and paid for. He may here discern, not only a <hi>sufficient</hi> price, but a <hi>Covenant</hi> price laid down; such as was indented for by God himself, and therein all his demands answered; and therefore it is accepted by him: so that the law hath nothing, as a Covenant, to implead him for; whereby all the charges of satan and his own misgiving heart that are made against him are fully confuted: and it no ways dasheth his Hope to reflect and consider what he hath been in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, (though it humbleth and abaseth him) considering what he now is in Christ
<pb n="124" facs="unknown:000684_0132_0FA9A39F80E9C3C0"/>
Jesus, <hi>Rom</hi> 8.1. Here he knows where he hath a right and title to the Glorious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and how it was procured for him: that it is already bought and paid for in his name, and for that reason it shall assuredly be bestowed upon him in due time.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Here he sees all the hard conditions of life, which are propounded in the Law, to be fully satisfied and performed. The Law saith <hi>do this and Live, i e.</hi> do it perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and constantly, without any failure or defect: though this were fair and easy to man in integrity, when he had the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God upon him, yet now he finds it hard, yea an impossibility in himself to comport with all; &amp; the more he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, the more apprehensive he is of his sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> coming: and this makes a legal life to be an horrible slavery. But he here is certified that Christ became surety for all this, and that he hath fully performed those terms to a tittle, and this upon his account; so that hereupon he hath brought him to stand upon better terms of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.5. and now, his dayly defects, though they grieve him, yet they do not hinder or damp his expectation of the life which is Promised.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Here also he sees Jesus Christ to be
<pb n="125" facs="unknown:000684_0133_0FA9A3A032EADDC8"/>
the <hi>undertaker</hi> for all that which is to be do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e by him in order to Salvation <hi>i e.</hi> for the performing and accomplishing of the very Gospel Covenant. When the law is satisfied for our offences, there is yet some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be <hi>done</hi> by us in order to Salvation The new Covenant requires <hi>Faith, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, and Perseverance</hi>: and as we could not put the First Grace into our selves, by conversion, so neither can we carry the work on when it is begun, nor withstand all the powerful Temptations that ly in our way, and be <hi>Faithful unto the Death,</hi> that we may <hi>receive the Crown of Life:</hi> and yet all this must be, according to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>our of the Covenant, and the lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>king meerly upon this, makes a Child of God some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be afraid whether he shall hold out, he finds so much strength set against him, and so much infirmity attending on him. But here is his <hi>Hope</hi> setled; in this Covenant Jesus Christ was the undertaker for this also; for he is to <hi>bring</hi> his Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to <hi>Glory Heb,</hi> 2.10. hence that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Joh</hi> 6.37. <hi>He gave himself for his Church,</hi> not only to <hi>satisfy</hi> for them, but also to <hi>sanctify</hi> them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> so that now he knows whither to go, and where to ask for all the help that he stands in need of where it cannot be denied him.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="126" facs="unknown:000684_0134_0FA9A3A0EEE3B150"/>4 Here he also sees all his Objections satisfactorily answered, and Doubts resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. When any thing offers to perplex him he brings it hither, and here he finds a full relief against it. If the Terrible Aspect of Gods <hi>Justice</hi> Terrifies him, he comes hither and finds it to be satisfied, and <hi>kissing of Mercy.</hi> If the consideration of Gods spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Holiness startles him, he sees it glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Jesus Christ, and mightily advanced in bringing so much Honour to God by this way of Salvation thus laid out. If the thoughts of his Sins Amaze him, and the Terrible Threatnings against them become a Terrour to him, here he finds the Curse exacted, and all his Sins satisfied for, and the whole penalty of them born: when his sins look never so great and formidable to him, here he finds, a sacrifice provided which is of infinite value. If his own <hi>Righteousness</hi> ashame him, by reason of the woful imperfection of it, and the many blemishes that there are upon it, here he discovers One that is Perfect and Everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid in for him. If his own <hi>Weakness</hi> discourage him, and he be ready to sink under the sense of it, here he finds a strength prepared for him, Even an <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Arm underneath</hi> to support him. So that in nothing that can carry any appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="127" facs="unknown:000684_0135_0FA9A3A1B59CABA0"/>
of a Discouragement in it, is he at a loss in this Covenant to find a full relief against it.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. And here he hath strong grounds of Confidence against all the Enemies of his Salvation. He need not be afraid of any accusations they can bring in against him, before God, though he knows that there is too much that can be truly said against him, by reason of his daily<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> follies, short comings, aberrations: because he knows that, his name being in the Covenant, that will speak more for him, than all they can do against him; and his <hi>Redeemer</hi> at the Right Hand of God is his Advocate, to answer all that can be brought in against him by way of accusation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34. Nor needs he be afraid of their underminings, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible opposition, though he knows that they are too subtile for him, and a great deal stronger than he is; because he is assured of this, that his Redeemer is <hi>Strong,</hi> and <hi>Faithful,</hi> and must answer for him to God, being in that Covenant engaged to bring him to Salvation. And what should im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the hopes of such an one? Or who shall be able to make him asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of this <hi>Hope</hi>?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="inference">
                  <pb n="128" facs="unknown:000684_0136_0FA9A3A27AA03590"/>
                  <head>INFERENCE IV.</head>
                  <p>Here we see the True and proper ground or reason of the Justification of a sinner. This <hi>Article ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h a great deal of Mystery in it,</hi> and many are lost in their Speculations about it, for want of a Clue to lead them through it. But the consideration of the Covenant o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Redemption, will clear this great Truth from all difficulties which men are pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>plexed with about it. <hi>The Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of a sinner,</hi> though as it is conferred upon him in a way of <hi>Imputation,</hi> it is an act of <hi>Rich Grace</hi>; yet in it self it is a <hi>Law act,</hi> and ought to proceed according to Truth and Equity; it is a Scripture As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.15. And the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this oftentimes makes an awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned soul to stumble and haesitate: he is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to say, <hi>shall not the Judge of the Earth do right</hi>? now I have sinned, I have trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressed the Law, and it can never cease to be a truth, that I have so done: how then shall God Pronounce me just, righteous, acquitted, who am a sinner. What <hi>Truth</hi> can there be in such a sentence? for my Faith cannot make the least satisfaction for my sins; and my obedience is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, &amp; if God should be <hi>strict to mark</hi> the
<pb n="129" facs="unknown:000684_0137_0FA9A3A339BBCCE8"/>
iniquity mixing with it, <hi>I could not stand</hi>: where then is the Righteousness of God, which is so much celebrated in Scripture, how doth he stand to his own Law, which saith that <hi>the sinner shall dy?</hi> Now all these scruples will come to be fully taken off, and the Soul will be aboundantly satisfied in the Contemplation of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. for;</p>
                  <p n="1">1 If faith in Jesus Christ were only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in the Covenant of Grace, for our Justification, we could not possibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> if there were no farther discovery made of the reason and ground of this. If God had not stood in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the first Covenant to the terms of it, and his <hi>Holiness</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in that engagement, it had not been so hard to understand how he might acquit the sinner by bestowing of a Free Pardon upon him, and there would have been no need for us to look any farther than to Grace in it, supposing it consistent with So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign <hi>Holiness</hi> thus to have done. But when we remember that there was such a Covenant, and that both Gods <hi>Holiness</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> were deeply concerned in it, to see to the compleat performance of it, and that therfore the breach of it must be satisfied for, or else there can be no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="130" facs="unknown:000684_0138_0FA9A3A3F0625270"/>
or acquittance given; how shall we take up satisfied in such an Offer, until we see how or in what way this satisfaction can be made? and when we are Convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that neither our Faith nor Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can be Meritorious, or answer the Demands of the Law, we must needs look yet farther?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Hence, in the Covenant of Grace, the Obedience of Christ is propounded to a sinner, as the <hi>Matter</hi> of the <hi>Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> which he is to believe in him for. Christs Righteousness is exhibited as both the <hi>Meritoorius,</hi> and also the <hi>Material</hi> cause of our being acquitted before God. To perswade us to Embrace it, and Cast ourselves upon it, it presents it before us as a <hi>Perfect Righteousness,</hi> which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way full, and answerable to the Law in all points, having enough in it to answer all the Demands of that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, hence we read, <hi>Rom:</hi> 5:18, 19. How compleatly this makes up all that which was procured by <hi>Mans Offence:</hi> but,</p>
                  <p n="3">3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The way how this Righteousness came to be ours by <hi>Imputation,</hi> and so accepted for us unto our <hi>Justification,</hi> is discovered in and by the Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="131" facs="unknown:000684_0139_0FA9A3A4B7F59790"/>
of the Covenant of Redemption; in which we may Observe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That we were there Covenanted for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This Covenant was not made <hi>with</hi> us but <hi>for</hi> us. Though Christ were the only <hi>Party</hi> Covenanting with his Father, yet we were the <hi>Subjects</hi> of the Covenant. That great Transaction was made with respect to us, and in order to the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about of our Salvation: so that, as Christ was the <hi>Redeemer,</hi> so we were the Persons to be <hi>Redeemed</hi> by Him; <hi>Galatians,</hi> 4:5.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That hence all that Christ did in that Great Work, was for us, or upon our account. <hi>He Lived not for Himself, neither Dyed He for Himself, but for us, Gal.</hi> 2.20. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Ult·</hi> He had no occasion to put himself into the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Redeemer upon his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: He Owed no Active Obedience to the Law for himself, being the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Son of God: nor did he deserve to suffer any Penalty for himself, for he <hi>was without sin</hi>; it was therefore for such as did need all this to be done for them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4.5.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="132" facs="unknown:000684_0140_0FA9A3A573A494C0"/>3 That what he thus did was upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement between his Father and him. That there first past a firm Covenant about it, before he engaged actually in the doing of it: so that there was a firm Foundation laid for the securing of the Fruit and Benefit of it, and for this reason, the Blood of Christ is called <hi>the Blood of the Everlasting Covenant, Hebr.</hi> 13:20. Because it was Shed upon this Compact.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That he had a firm and inviolable Promise from his Father, that all this should be made ours, and that we should reap the fruit and benefit of it, <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.10. It was a Promise made by God <hi>who cannot lie,</hi> and it was sealed by <hi>Two Immutable things, Hebr.</hi> 6.18. There was Gods <hi>Purpose</hi> and his <hi>Oath</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it. Now when all these things are put together, they clear up the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness of Gods Proceeding: for though it be a sinner that stands at the Bar, and one who is in himself by Law a man of Death; yet when it is made to appear that he was redeemed by an Everlasting Covenant. That <hi>Temporary</hi> Covenant of Works cannot infringe it, but must be subservient unto it. And since he is Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="133" facs="unknown:000684_0141_0FA9A3A633FDB528"/>
in <hi>his surety,</hi> how Unrighteous so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he is in himself, God is Righteous in Justifying of him, and no injustice can justly be charged upon him, in declaring him to be Righteous, by vertue of this Righteousness. So that our Justification is built upon a Foundation which is stron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the Earth or Heavens.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="inference">
                  <head>INFERENCE V.</head>
                  <p>Here we Learn that mans whole Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion proceeds from God himself, It plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tells us how little hand poor man hath in his own deliverance from misery, and obtaining of blessedness, and this will be discovered in two Propositions.</p>
                  <p n="1">I That the foundation of mans Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was laid in this Covenant. From hence it is that it derives its rise and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, that any of the undone Children of Adam are brought to Inherit eternal Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, they owe the whole acknowledgment of it hither. Fallen man could not have bin saved without such a Covenant: his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness absolutely depended upon the good will of God; and these are the first thoughts that God enterteined in himself about mans delivery; and here began
<pb n="134" facs="unknown:000684_0142_0FA9A3A6F913B990"/>
the <hi>futurition</hi> of it. If God had not <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen them first,</hi> they would never have <hi>Chosen him.</hi> If Christ had not come to be a Redeemer, all the children of men must have died hopelesly in their sins, and if God the Father had not Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted with his Son about his coming on this great errand, he had certainly never come. again, if Christs obedience had not been <hi>accepted</hi> with God upon the account of those for whom he both Did and Died, it could never have been <hi>Imputed</hi> to them so as to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the procuring cause of their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and if God had not thus Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted with his Son about it, it had never been thus <hi>accepted.</hi> No one of these things could have been left out, in this great affair. Now all this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from God himself, it is his own doing, The creature that is to be saved by it, was not there to speak for it self<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for it was before the Creation; so that neither was there any other Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated being to speak unto God in its behalf. If God had not thought of it and done it, it had never been; for this was an eternal act; it past in the Divine Counsel, and was ratified there before the world was.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="135" facs="unknown:000684_0143_0FA9A3A7B671AAF8"/>II That all that which contributes to mans Salvation, ariseth and flows down from this Covenant whatsoever else can be mentioned or thought of, that hath any influence into the eternal Salvation of the children of men, is hither to be reduced, as to the <hi>Original</hi> of it, Here were the contrivances and ways for the accomplishment of all this business laid out, and most wisely delineated: Here was all that was needful to bring sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to the actual possession of eternal life prepared: yea the very Covenant of Grace in and by which the Treaty is held and carried on between God and Sinners under the Gospel Dispensation is here fountained. Not only the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> it self, but the <hi>Application</hi> of the Redemption is wholly derived from hence in all the parts and <hi>steps</hi> of it: in this Covenant it was that Christ was <hi>made all for us,</hi> that he might be so to us 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. All the Promises which were made, of providing the Ordinances for, and giving them to men, of send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them the means of Grace and the calls of the Gospel; of sending the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit to them, and into them, of drawing sinners home to Jesus Christ, &amp; making <hi>them</hi> to comply with him on his
<pb n="136" facs="unknown:000684_0144_0FA9A3A8708F6968"/>
terms, of keeping them in him, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving them from Falling away from Grace after they are in him; and of bringing them to, and making them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit Eternal Glory at the last, they are all the promises of this Covenant, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> engaged benefits of Christs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> were made to him upon it, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fulfilled eminently upon his havi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> done the Work, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that all this is of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> because it is all of it laid up in Gods Covenant; yea in such a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant wherein there were none engaged as Parties undertaking, but such Persons as were God.</p>
                  <p>Hence also the Application of this good to us must needs be acknowledged to this, and here must be assigned the reason why any of us do <hi>believe that we may be saved:</hi> it was not because we were enclined or disposed to it more than others, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause our Salvation was <hi>Secured</hi> for us in that Covenant, and must be in this way <hi>Promoved:</hi> and how may this serve <hi>to hide pride from man,</hi> and lead him up to an humble acknwoledgment of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all his hopes?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="137" facs="unknown:000684_0145_0FA9A3A943C40CE0"/>
            <head>CHAPTER XIII. The Farther Application by Way of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and Consolation.</head>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>USE II. For <hi>EXHORTATION,</hi> and <hi>DIRECTION,</hi> to the People of God; and that in Four Respects.</head>
               <p>LAbour to Clear up and to be satisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your Interest in and Relation to this Covenant. Rest not Contented till you have gotten some good Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that your Names were written in the Book of Life, and to move you hereto, Consider these Two Things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a Thing that may be known. Although the Eternal Transaction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween GOD the Father, and GOD the Son, be a Secret Hidden from the World, and no Man can have any particular
<pb n="138" facs="unknown:000684_0146_0FA9A3AB69EDCF78"/>
knowledge of it referring to himself, till he be made partakers in the special fruits of it: yet the Believer in regard of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, may obtain a clear acquaintance with it: he may be able to discern and read it. There is a way Revealed in the Scripture whereby we may come to know what was contrived about us in the days of Eternity, and be assured that Jesus Christ hath paid the full Price of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: not only that he hath done so for some, but for us in particular. Were it not so, that Precept in, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. had been superfluous: yea all the Commands given us to <hi>Prove</hi> and <hi>Try</hi> our own State were vain: For unless our Trial Issue here we are still left at a loss. But there is a Promise made to the People of God that fear him, that <hi>He will show them His Covenant, Psal.</hi> 25.14. <hi>i. e.</hi> The Great secret of the Covenant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, shall be discovered to them, by making of them to know that God loved them with an Everlasting Love.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The foundation of all your <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation</hi> is laid in this Covenant. All the Comfort of the Children of God resolves ultimatly into this, that <hi>Christ
<pb n="139" facs="unknown:000684_0147_0FA9A3AB8841A5C0"/>
Loved us and gave himself for us:</hi> but this he did not do for all the world but only for a select company, whom his Father had given unto him, and these are they whom he Covenanted for before the world was made. If ever we be saved, it must be by the vertue and application of the satisfaction of Christ to us; this is applied to none but those whom he indented for, and was appointed by his Father to Redeem: so that if we would know whether our sins are Pardoned, and Justice be atoned to us, it must be by knowing that Christs death is become ours, and accepted for us: and the way to be satisfied in this, is by finding our names in that roll or list, which was entred in the record: of Heaven before time was: and till we come to understand this, how can we be free from the fears and terrors of the wrath to come!</p>
               <p>Now the Scripture way wherein we are directed to arive at this knowledg, is by following of the streams up to the fountain. There are some streams of common bounty, which flow from God the Fountain of Goodness, to all the World; he being the common Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor to all his Creatures; and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e are
<pb n="140" facs="unknown:000684_0148_0FA9A3AC388CFD60"/>
none but do partake more or less of his <hi>Benignity,</hi> Psal. 145.9. Mat. 5.45. But yet a man may swim in the fulness of all these favours, yea be glutted with them, and yet be an utter stranger to this Covenant, <hi>Psal.</hi> 17.14. These are kindnesses which God can allow to his Enemies. But there are other distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishing favours, which the great King reserves to bestow only on those whom he hath set his heart upon, &amp; is resolved to make them his special favourites: so that whosoever is made to enjoy any of these, he may hereby certainly know that God hath a mind to <hi>honour him,</hi> and intends Eternal Life for him. There are peculiar tokens of the Love of God which he gives to none but such as have found Grace in his sight; and those that enjoy them, may from thence unerringly conclude that they were giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to Christ in an Everlasting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. We may read the descent of these in Rom. 8:29.30. There is a <hi>white Stone, and a new Name which is not Legible by any but him who hath it.</hi> This God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stows upon none other but those who were thus Covenanted for. There is a powerful work of Conversion wrought in the Soul, by causing the man to pass
<pb n="141" facs="unknown:000684_0149_0FA9A3ACF1E0A188"/>
from death to life, the donation of the Spirit of Adoption by which we are enabled to <hi>Cry, Abba Father,</hi> the infusion of the Grace of Sanctification, in which there is a wonderful change made, a <hi>New Creature</hi> brought forth, <hi>all old things past away, and all things become new</hi> in him. Now these are all the gifts of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Grace, they are the secret convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from the Well-head of Electing Love, they are the <hi>Covenant Mercies,</hi> and <hi>things that Accompany Salvation</hi>: if then you are called by his power, seized by his Spirit, sanctified by his Grace; you may by this be assured that you were Chosen in Christ, and Covenanted for with him. These benefits are not scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered promiscuously, but are given pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly. Labour therefore to have and discover such Operations as these in your hearts, and to be more and more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the reality of them: this will be the way to derive joy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation from the Fountain, and fetch down comfort into your Souls as far as from Eternity.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Be exhorted to make improvement of your interest in this Covenant, for your establishment against the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations which may assault you. We may
<pb n="142" facs="unknown:000684_0150_0FA9A3ADB9763868"/>
safely determine, that all the shakings or unsettlings of a believers faith, and all the discouragements under which he La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours at any time, do arise either from a want of his being fortified in this Covenant, or from a neglect of applying and improving it seasonably: For this hath enough in it to dissolve all doubts, and answer all objections, if it be wisely improved by us: use it therefore;</p>
               <p n="1">1 To silence all the accusations which may arise from the Covenant of Works. A Believer is sometimes greatly Puzled, and in a Shock of sore Temptation he is hurried to the <hi>Old Covenant,</hi> where sin is declared against, and the sinner is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and Justice stands engaged to do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution accordingly: and now he is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perplexed to think how the Law and Grace can consist, and so how such a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as he is can be Saved, and he is ready to sink under it. Indeed in the Covenant of Grace he hears of pardon and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, which are assured to the Sinner up on believing, and that is a precious thing; but he knows not how to reconcile this to what the Law saith; that <hi>God is Holy and of purer eyes than to behold Iniquity,</hi>
                  <pb n="143" facs="unknown:000684_0151_0FA9A3AE77AA1388"/>
that <hi>Sinners shall not stand in his sight</hi>; &amp; such an one hath he notoriously been; and how should he make those things to bear? Now Repair to the Covenant of Redemption, and take a through view of it, and there you shall find that all this is sufficiently taken care about, and every difficulty that you can think of, is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether removed. The Covenant of Grace indeed speaks of favour and mercy to Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, freely to be bestowed upon them by God through Christ, but in the Covenant of Redemption you may see how all this is brought about, and be satisfied in it: for in this Covenant there is an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering provided, a compleat Sacrifice laid in: here is the Blood of a Saviour to be shed, his precious life to be laid down in exchange for the life of the Sinner, in which there is infinitely more value than in the lives of all the World; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Law requires at the hands of the Sinner is here answered. Here is Justice sitting in Triumph, Holiness glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously Exalted, the Law fulfilled to the utmost of all that it can demand: here God declares his hatred against Sin suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, and all that was demanded in the Covenant of Works, is made good to the utmost farthing; and now what
<pb n="144" facs="unknown:000684_0152_0FA9A3AF3B6C0940"/>
should hinder the flowing down of the Grace of the New Covenant to the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Gods Elect, since it appears, that <hi>he can be both Just and the Justifier of them that believe</hi>?</p>
               <p n="2">2 To remove all the doubts that may arise: in you respecting the Covenant, of Grace. In this very Covenant, Satan the adversary of Gods People seeks to find many flaws, and thereupon to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster their minds and disturb their tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, so as that many times they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with that quietness repose them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves upon it, or suck that sweet and comfort out of it, which is therein provided for them: and the usual stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem which he is wont to entangle them by, is the consideration that though there are very great and Precious Promises held out to the Children of God in that Covenant, enough to satisfy their most enlarged desires, if they could appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate them to themselves; yet in the Gospel all these Promises come with conditions annexed to them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are no farther ours than the condition is to be found wrought in us, and we can no more use Them for our Establishment, than we are able to make out these conditions &amp; these conditions are
<pb n="145" facs="unknown:000684_0153_0FA9A3B0005C7FB0"/>
two sorts; <hi>viz.</hi> either such as are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in order to our being made Partak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in these Promises, or such as are requisite in order to our coming to the compleat fruition of the good laid up in them. Respecting the former, there is so much Counterfeit in the world, and it is a thing so easy to be mistaken about: and led into a vain presumption, yet he troubles them with doubts whether they are indeed true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, or have sincerely Repented and Turned to God. Now for the clearing up of this, they are to confer the <hi>Rules</hi> given in the Scriptures, and wait for the <hi>Co-Witness of the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to the latter, the trouble is, a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever finds Satan filling him with fears whether he shall ever be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them: his faith is so <hi>weak,</hi> and the Temptations which Assault him are so <hi>strong,</hi> that he shall fail, and his faith give in: his Obedience is so poor and une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that it will never find acceptance with God: and this Perseverance is a Terrible thing; how shall he ever be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hold out against all the Furious Shocks which he is to encounter, and be faithful to the Death, and if he do
<pb n="146" facs="unknown:000684_0154_0FA9A3B0B214EC40"/>
not, he must expect to lose the Crown: It is an hard thing to maintain his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, in the midst of all the Allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and affrightments that are in his way, and if he fail or fall short he is lost after all: Now if you find your selves to be at any time thus shaken, your business is, presently to repair to the <hi>Everlasting Covenant,</hi> and there you shall find satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and good security against these fears. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1 You shall here find all these conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are thus required of you in the Covenant of Grace to be firmly and faithfully undertaken for by the Lord Jesus Christ. For, we observed before, that in the Covenant of Redemption, one <hi>Condition</hi> that was laid upon and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of the Son of God, was that he should <hi>bring many Sons to Glory</hi>; and for that end he undertook to do all that for them and in them, that was requisite for the accomplishment of it: so that he stands obliged not only to answer the <hi>Law</hi> for them, but the <hi>Gospel</hi> too. The fulfilment of every condition that is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary in order to their Participation in Life Eternal, is incumbent on him to see to; If there be any thing, which is a <hi>necessary medium</hi> to Glory, required of us,
<pb n="147" facs="unknown:000684_0155_0FA9A3B180919D58"/>
he is engaged to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it done in us and for us, else it would not be a Compleat work of Redemption. If He should deliver us from the <hi>Law,</hi> so far as to make it a possibility for us to be saved by Grace, and yet leave us to Perish for want of the <hi>Evangelical Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> without which there is no Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we were in a miserable state; for we can no more do this of our selves than we could the other: but it is far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise. That would be an <hi>Arminian mock Redemption</hi>; and it would be but to save us from one <hi>Hell,</hi> to throw us into a <hi>Worse.</hi> But, as the Son of God was to answer the <hi>Law</hi> for us, so was he to give us the Grace and Strength to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer the <hi>Gospel</hi> in all the Demands of it: and therefore the security is in him, whose Strength will Manifest and Magnify it self in our Weakness</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence you shall here find all those <hi>Absolute Promises</hi> which are upon Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Record, given for your comfort. It is true an Unbeliever can make no challenge of them to himself, or make a living of them: they are not a <hi>Dish</hi> that is set before every one to <hi>feed</hi> upon: but a believer may and ought to reckon
<pb n="148" facs="unknown:000684_0156_0FA9A3B238FC9B98"/>
them to be his own, and to suck all the <hi>Marrow and Fatness</hi> out of them. And when you have well pondered of these Promises you may strengthen your Faith by arguing after this manner; <hi>viz.</hi> That although in the Covenant of Grace all these things are required of you, and they must be found in you if ever you be saved; yet in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Redemption all this is un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dertaken for: for this is the proper lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of these Promises. When God saith <hi>He will give you a New Heart, and put his Spirit upon you, and put his Fear into your Hearts, and you shall never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from him, and the like</hi>; these Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises belong to some, there are they who are designed &amp; pointed at by them, and who are they but such as are <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to Salvation from Eternity</hi>? and these are they who are <hi>Effectually called in Time.</hi> You may therefore upon the consideration of your <hi>vocation</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Accomplishment of them in you; for though you might fail, yet God cannot.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence also Jesus Christ hath Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to send his Spirit into the hearts of his people, to dwell in them, to teach
<pb n="149" facs="unknown:000684_0157_0FA9A3B2FAD606E8"/>
them, to keep <hi>them by his Power, and that through Faith to Salvation.</hi> When Jesus Christ left this earth as to his bodily presence, he then gave his Spirit to be the Guardian of his People, that they might not be left Orphans: and it is he who hath undertaken to do all that in them and for them which they need: to keep their weak Grace alive; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent its being quenched by the many waters of Temptation that would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise swallow it up, and utterly extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish it in them: and this is a Fruit al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of the Covenant of Redemption. And hence it comes to pass, that though Adam in his integrity, lost all his stock by the prevelancy of a Temptation, that was too hard for him, yet a believer in the hand of the Spirit of God, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing all the frailties that attend upon him, shall never lose his little stock, but both keep and encrease it. So that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, when we look upon the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> required in the One Covenant, we lay by it, the consideration of the <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking and Provision</hi> that is made for the performance of it in another Covenant, that may quiet and satisfy our souls in this regard, and enable us to
<pb n="150" facs="unknown:000684_0158_0FA9A3B3AF3B7228"/>
Triumph over all Doubts and Fears, which Assaults us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Be therefore directed whither to go for all the strength and assistance, for the discharge of the Duty which is ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon you, and required of you in your place and station; and for comfort in the doing of it. We are often dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the weight of Duty, and are ready to sink under it, upon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience we have of our own imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; whereas if we look back unto this Covenant we shall there find that taken care for effectually; for here we may observe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Perfect Obedience which was required, and was to Merit our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God, was laid upon Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t; and hereupon it is taken off from us.</p>
               <p>He was to do as well as to Dy. We have taken notice that his <hi>Active Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> was required in, and became a Condition of this Covenant, as well as his Passive; and God hath respect to it: he looks upon it, and imputes it to us: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the Law is answered, and all the happiness which man once forfeited
<pb n="151" facs="unknown:000684_0159_0FA9A3B476983628"/>
is purchased. What though we cannot perfectly obey? yet because he hath done it for us, there is our Security, and we may account it ours, because it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in our Name.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That <hi>Sincerity,</hi> under our greatest <hi>imperfections</hi> render our performances <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable</hi> to God. If our <hi>hearts be right</hi> in the Duties we do, if they are True and Faithful to God, if we can truely plead <hi>Uprightness and Integrity</hi>; they shall <hi>preserve us.</hi> No weakness that influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth our Obedience, shall cut it off from his favour, or prevent his <hi>smelling a sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of rest in it.</hi> He that had not a <hi>Lamb</hi> to offer, might offer <hi>Two Turtle Doves.</hi> The ground of this is here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Christ is accepted for us in the Covenant of Redemption, and so we come to be accepted through him in the Covenant of Grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That Christ is engaged not only to do <hi>for us,</hi> but <hi>in us,</hi> too, all the works that are needful. All that is requisite to our pleasing of God, and obtaining of Glory. His Almighty power stands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it: hence <hi>Pauls Prayer</hi> for his <hi>Colossians, Col.</hi> 1.9, 10, 11. In a word,
<pb n="152" facs="unknown:000684_0160_0FA9A3B5B13A4B80"/>
This Covenant hath provided a Christ for us to go to for all that we can stand in need of, in order to the bringing of us home to the Kingdom: <hi>For the Subduing of all our Enemies the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering of our Corruptions, the Recovering of us from our Apostasies, the Establishing of our Grace, the Perpetuating of our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severance</hi>; So that there can nothing be wanting for the satisfaction of a belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Soul, but here it is to be had ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and the encouragement to go to him with boldness for it, is fetched from the consideration of this Covenant; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause GOD the FATHER stands firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Engaged to His SON, for the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all this for us; and he cannot deny us when we come and humbly and believingly claim it at his hands, upon this scope.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Labour we to <hi>see, admire and Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify</hi> those riches of Grace that are laid up for poor man in this Covenant. The Covenant of Redemption hath matter enough in it for us to study upon and contemplate for ever. A believer, when himself, cannot look upon this Covenant without admiration, and Extasy: it is full of unsearchable wonders. Here are the
<pb n="153" facs="unknown:000684_0161_0FA9A3B7BAD81E10"/>
greatest engagements imaginable to oblige us to love and serve God. Here is matter enough to Elevate our Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to the highest strain! for,</p>
               <p n="1">1 Here we learn what were the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting thoughts of God concerning us, even <hi>thoughts of mercy and peace,</hi> when we find our names written in That Book, we are sure that God Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membered us before we were or any other creature to make mention of us to him: and what a sweet and ravish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contemplation is here. <hi>The Physician was provided before the Malady was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted,</hi> when we were not, God thought of us for good, and made the way of this good sure and unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable: he enrolled a Covenant for us in the Records o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eternity. The Father and Son did, of their own accord, thus consult for the Everlasting welfare of a company of worthless Worms: they contrived the matter between them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, resolved to build the Declarative Glory of Divine Grace upon so mean a Subject as sorry man. Here we see what a difference was put between us and the <hi>Children of Wrath; how precious Gods thoughts of us were,</hi> that among such multitudes whom he passed by, he
<pb n="154" facs="unknown:000684_0162_0FA9A3B83236E390"/>
should fix his heart upon us, and mark us out for a Kingdom, and how asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonishing a thing is this?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here also we may observe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely Wise Contrivance of mans Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. There are all the Mysteries of Wisdom concerned in this Covenant. Here is a way found out to Save Fallen Man, which would altogether have puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and non-plust the Understandings of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>men</hi>; if they had sat them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to study about it, it would never have come into their thoughts. Nay, the <hi>Angels</hi> themselves are still amazed at it, and desirous to be <hi>Gazing</hi> into the <hi>Mystery</hi> of it, although it be Revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Who could ever have told God, had he seen meet to enquire of him, how a Sinner should be Saved, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice remain Inviolated. Now in this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, we see that all things are so contrived as that there is no flaw, nor any the least disagreement between the Covenant of Works, and the Covenant of Grace, but both have their honour and glory, and yet the sinner is saved out of the hands of the Law, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from Wrath and Vengeance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.26.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="155" facs="unknown:000684_0163_0FA9A3B8F3DBC5A8"/>3. Here we see how sure a ground and foundation there is laid for the certain Salvation of all Gods Elect; in that every thing which was requisite to it, in all the parts of it, is here fully provided: and all that might possibly have hindred it, is taken care about that it be removed out of the way. The <hi>Guilt</hi> of Sin lay as a great Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to separate between God and us; and as long as it there lay, there was no coming at him: he was a consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Fire; but now this Guilt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved away, and this Mountain is thrown into the depths of the Sea. The pollution of sin lay as a woful obstruction to mans happiness, and whilst it abode, he must needs be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable: but here is a washing and a cleansing prepared, a Fountain opened for it, which can take it all away. There was a Legal Obedience required as the Condition of mans happiness, and without such a Righteousness, he could not be entituled to it: but here is an Everlasting Righteousness brought in, and whatsoever else might be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, here it is to be found: so that there is now nothing to hinder the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
<pb n="156" facs="unknown:000684_0164_0FA9A3B9B6EA8C48"/>
Salvation of every Believer.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Here we may read the Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of God to his own Word and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise made to his Son; when we find our selves Converted, and made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in saving Grace; and so we may be led up to the true reason of our accepting of Christ, by faith in him, not to be in us, or any natural good dispositions of ours, but in the fidelity of God. If he should have let us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to our selves, and not have sought us up and brought us home to Christ, as we should never have come to him, so we could never have accused him of falshood; for we did not know our selves to be the Subjects of those promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, till by the effect he made it known to us. But because he had promised it, therefore he fulfilled it: and this is the reason why the <hi>Gospel</hi> which became a <hi>savour of Death</hi> to others, was made a <hi>savour of Life</hi> to us: the same means that <hi>hardened</hi> others in their sins, <hi>soft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> us, and brake us off from our sins, and brought us home to God; and this will help to confirm us in the assurance that the same <hi>Faithfulness</hi> will do the rest that remains to be done for us, in
<pb n="157" facs="unknown:000684_0165_0FA9A3BA78F7E878"/>
the accomplishment of our compleat Salvation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Here also we may acquaint our selves with what deep engagements Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ hath laid upon us to love, and fear, and serve him, in that he undertook for our Redemption and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from Eternity; and that which serves more especially to set forth our Obligation and Debt to him in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, is the consideration how he was circumstanced in this Covenant, in three or four respects.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it was a free and voluntary engagement on his part. He was under no tie of natural necessity to do this work. He was a person at full and free liberty in himself to be engaged or not engaged for us. It was at his own pleasure whether he would become a <hi>Surety,</hi> and give himself up for our Redemption: Hence that <hi>Job.</hi> 10 18. <hi>I have Power, &amp;c.</hi> the word implies a <hi>Liberty or a Right to a Thing.</hi> He was a Divine Person, and therefore enjoyned in himself the highest Liberty and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty over his own actions. If he had refused to do this for us, he had
<pb n="158" facs="unknown:000684_0166_0FA9A3BB37526638"/>
not injured us at all. And needs must it be a very great bond which is laid upon us, by one that doth us the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est kindness, who was no farther obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to it, than he himself pleased to make himself to be: for the more free the love is, the greater doth it appear to be.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That he thus engaged for us before we desired it of him. He did not tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be asked by us; he did not wait for our petitions to be put up to him requesting him that he would put in for us, and become our <hi>Propitiation</hi>: but before we had a being, or were in any capaci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of enquring after him, he then put in, undertook, and made himself fast by a Covenant and a Promise. It had been incomparable love for him to have undertaken such a thing for us, upon our most ardent and importunate entreaties: yea it would have looked like a thing that was unreasonable, for us ever to have requested him to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage himself in our behalf: but for him to interpose, and take up our cause, and become responsible for us, <hi>Unsought</hi>! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is carries the greatest Force in it, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.9.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="159" facs="unknown:000684_0167_0FA9A3BC036308F0"/>3 That the engagement that he has took upon him, was the greatest, and most condescending that could have been,; <hi>viz</hi> that he would stand in the sinners room and place, when he had provoked the <hi>Holiness</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> of God against him, and lay open to <hi>Infinite Wrath</hi> and all the Curses of the Law were now fallen upon him. For him now to take the whole <hi>Guilt</hi> of our sins upon himself, resign himself up to the <hi>Law</hi> and undertake to answer it for us, to do all that it required of us, to suffer all that it had denounced against us, even the most Ignominious and dreadful imprssions of the wrath of God, and endure his furious displeasure in <hi>making his Soul an Offering for sin.</hi> Who ever would have done any thing like unto this? These were astonishing things and therefore they require our at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4 9.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The Persons whom he thus enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for, were not <hi>Good men,</hi> nor <hi>Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous men,</hi> nor <hi>Friends,</hi> but <hi>wicked ungodly enemies Rom.</hi> 5.6. and <hi>verse</hi> 8.9. A little kindness shewn to a Mortal enemy, is a great one, because it is to such an one. They were those that had been
<pb n="160" facs="unknown:000684_0168_0FA9A3BCC27FE098"/>
treacherous against the throne of God, that had <hi>Sinned against Heaven,</hi> Pulled down a Righteous Curse and Misery on their own heads; and the Son of God kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w what they would be, when he took this Province upon him; for it was under the very consideration of their Being such that he became their <hi>Redeemer.</hi> For all this he did not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, but took this occasion of his undertaking to be so, that so he might give the most surprising instance of his Grace.</p>
               <p n="5">5 That if he had not done it, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len man must of necessity have Perished for ever. There was no other way left for him to be Saved. There was not any other person to be found either in <hi>heaven</hi> or <hi>earth,</hi> that did or could appear for him. No other course could be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to work out his deliverance. The Curse must have taken place, and swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him up with everlasting miseries, if the Son of God had not come and removed it from him by bearing of it in himself, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.12. Acts 3.12. and now you that are the Children of God by Faith in his Son, say; are not these <hi>cords of love</hi> strong? and do they not bind us to <hi>Love, Serve, Praise and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="161" facs="unknown:000684_0169_0FA9A3BD7B5FA948"/>
him</hi> all the days of our lives? out of doubt, there are no stronger Ties imaginable than what are made by this Covenant, to Holiness; the Apostle thus improves it, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.15. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That was a great design in this Covenant, that Christ might <hi>Purchase to himself a Peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> that he might have a <hi>Generation to Serve him.</hi> It is therefore our work to study Holiness by all these incentives; and to that end, let us reflect upon all the Good that ariseth from this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and deriveth by it unto us, and acknowledge all our comforts and hopes to it. Remember that if this Covenant had not been made, <hi>The Precious Gospel had never been Preached to us; the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of it had never been administred; the Good News of God reconcil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng the world to himself had never been talked of in the world.</hi> All the fruits that you taste in the Love of God, all the hopes you have of escaping Hells Miseries, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entertained in heavens felicities, acknowledge the original of them to this Covenant: and let the consideration of this put a Glorious Lustre upon them. Consider and think, they are not mercies which come by casualty or peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
<pb n="162" facs="unknown:000684_0170_0FA9A3BE382E9950"/>
they are not occasional favours, but benefits which were provided for you before the world had its begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and then made as sure for you, as the Covenant of a God could make them. What then remains but that we enquire solemnly, <hi>what shall we Render to the Lord for all these his benefits to us</hi>? Let such speculations as these, raise us up to the highest ardours of the Divine Love, and engage us in the most fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and sedulous endeavours to live all <hi>the rest of our time</hi> to the Glory of His Great Name.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="application">
               <head>USE 3.</head>
               <p>For <hi>Consolation</hi> to the People of God. To all such as are in Covenant with God in Christ through Grace; or are made to Partake in the Grace of the new-Covenant: Everlasting Consolaltion flows down to you from this Covenant. Every Attribute of it distributes abundant comfort to the Souls of the Children of God. It is a <hi>Free Covenant</hi>; there was nothing to engage God to the making of it, but his own meer good pleasure:
<pb n="163" facs="unknown:000684_0171_0FA9A3BF00C795C0"/>
and free applications are the most Potent and secure of any; because if they did not intend the Performance of them, there can be no reason given why they should bring themselves under the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of doing it. It is a <hi>Gracious Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi>; there was nothing in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to move God to it: it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he would Gloriously Exalt His Grace in the pursuance of it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though we are unworthy of, and can no way deserve the good which is provided in it, yet we may be confident, because it was the very aim and design of it to set forth the riches of Grace for ever. It is an <hi>Everlasting Covenant</hi>; it never had any beginning: and was contrived and concluded before time, and therefore it cannot have any end, but will last to Perpetuity. It is an <hi>Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Covenant,</hi> being made between Parties that are unchangeable, <hi>in whom there is no variation or shadow of turning</hi>: and hence whatever we have been and done, they can never repent of, or alter one syllable in it. It is a <hi>well ordered Covenant</hi> having provided every thing that is requisite to make us everlastingly happy, in the compleat deliverance of us from sin and hell, and bringing of
<pb n="164" facs="unknown:000684_0172_0FA9A3BFBB74BFB8"/>
us to the perfect fruition of God to all eternity. It is a <hi>stable Covenant</hi> that cannot fall, being made with one in whom all the fulness of the Godhead dwells; and was therefore furnished to answer all the demands of it to the uttermost. Hence therefore, you have no need to be afraid of the <hi>Law,</hi> and all its terrors and threatnings, for that is fully answered, and hath nothing to say against you: Nor of the <hi>Devil,</hi> for all his accusations are taken off, and by it rendered altogether insignificant: Nor of <hi>your own sins,</hi> how many and weighty soever they have been; for they are all of them satisfied for, and the acquittance is taken out: Nor of your <hi>impotency to do Evangelical Duties,</hi> for there is everlasting strength provided in him to supply it, and that which shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fail you, you may Challenge all enemies, despise all adverse powers, and Triumph in your assured hope of Glory.</p>
               <p>And now, what can you do less than Celebrate the remembrance of this your Redeemers love and kindness to you; as with a <hi>Soul humbling</hi> consideration of your own unworthiness; so with <hi>heart
<pb n="165" facs="unknown:000684_0173_0FA9A3C07B664898"/>
ravishing joyfulness,</hi> and <hi>inexpressible thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness,</hi> for all this kindness and Grace of his expressed to you? let it make his <hi>Name Precious</hi> in your thoughts, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>as an oyntment poured out,</hi> and help you to <hi>remember his love more than wine,</hi> and when you look inward, and find the beginings of this Glorious work so engaged in, to be applied unto you, and that this <hi>Redeemers satisfaction</hi> is brought home to your Souls, by the Spirit of God enabling you to believe in him, and working of you up to a begun conformity unto him; let this strengthen your faith cheerfully and triumphantly to wait for the full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment of what remains; believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>he who hath begun a good work for you will Perfect it in you to the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
