<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pillar of gratitude. Or, A brief recapitulation, of the matchless favours, with which the God of heaven, hath obliged the hearty praises, of his New-England Israel. A sermon delivered in the audience of His Excellency, the Earl of Bellomont, captain general, and governour in chief, and of the Council &amp; Representatives, of the General Assembly of the province of the Massachusetts Bay, convened at Boston, in New England. On May 29 1700 the day, for the election of counsellors, in the province. / By Cotton Mather. ; Whereto there is appendixed, an extract of some accounts, concerning the wonderful success of the glorious Gospel, in the East-Indies. ; [One line of Latin quotation]</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-02">2006-02.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N00772</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N00772</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1139</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX2651</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">930</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99019394</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 930.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N00772)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 930)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pillar of gratitude. Or, A brief recapitulation, of the matchless favours, with which the God of heaven, hath obliged the hearty praises, of his New-England Israel. A sermon delivered in the audience of His Excellency, the Earl of Bellomont, captain general, and governour in chief, and of the Council &amp; Representatives, of the General Assembly of the province of the Massachusetts Bay, convened at Boston, in New England. On May 29 1700 the day, for the election of counsellors, in the province. / By Cotton Mather. ; Whereto there is appendixed, an extract of some accounts, concerning the wonderful success of the glorious Gospel, in the East-Indies. ; [One line of Latin quotation]</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
                  <author>Massachusetts. General Court.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p. ;  13 cm. (12mo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B Green, &amp; J Allen.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Massachusetts --  Politics and government --  To 1775</term>
               <term>Election sermons --  Massachusetts --  1700.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:000930_0000_0FACA3586DEF52B8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:000930_0001_0FACA35570121F30"/>
            <p>A Pillar of Gratitude.</p>
            <p>OR, A brief Recapitulation, of the <hi>Match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Favours,</hi> with which the God of Heaven hath obliged the HEARTY PRAISES, of His <hi>New-Engliſh</hi> ISRAEL.</p>
            <p>A SERMON deliverd in the Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of His EXCELLENCY, the Earl of BELLOMONT, Captain General, and GOVERNOUR in Chief, and of the COUNCIL &amp; Repreſentatives, of the GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAL ASSEMBLY of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of the <hi>Maſſachuſetts Bay</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened at <hi>Boston,</hi> in <hi>New England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> 29 1700 the Day, for <hi>Election</hi> of <hi>Counſellers,</hi> in that Province.</p>
            <p>By <hi>COTTON MATHER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereto there is <hi>Appendixed,</hi> an Extract of ſome Accounts, concerning the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Succeſs of the Glorious Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Nemo non haec vera dicit.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Boston,</hi> Printed by <hi>B Green,</hi> &amp; <hi>J Allen.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="unknown:000930_0002_0FACA35744525A90"/>
            <head>A Pillar of Gratitude. At the Opening of the Grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Aſſembly, of the Province of Maſsachuſet-Bay, New England. 29 <hi>d.</hi> 3 <hi>m.</hi> 1700.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. CXLVII.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He hath not ſo dealt with any Nation!</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THere was a people, of whom the God of Heaven ſaid, <hi>This people have I formed for my ſelf, they ſhall ſhew forth my praiſe</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there be ſuch a people any where under the Cope of Heaven at this Day, 'tis in the <hi>Engliſh Nation.</hi> But of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gliſh Nation,</hi> certainly there is no Colony or Plantation that hath more cauſe it
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:000930_0003_0FACA357A7A63908"/>
               <hi>Shew forth the praiſe</hi> of the Almighty, than that which is now and here Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened What more agreeable or profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Addreſs,</hi> can be made, unto a <hi>Great and General Aſſembly</hi> of this Province, than an Invitation to the <hi>Praiſes</hi> of our Good God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who as <hi>He is worthy to be praiſed,</hi> ſo, Deſires to <hi>Inhabit our Praiſes,</hi> and reckons Himſelf <hi>Glorified,</hi> when we <hi>Offer</hi> them? The <hi>Royal Charter</hi> of our <hi>King,</hi> has made this, <hi>A Day of Election,</hi> for no ſmall part of our <hi>Government</hi>: And though the <hi>Civil Affairs</hi> now to be atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, will not al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow this to be, <hi>A Day of Thank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>giving,</hi> Yet no Thoughts were mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e proper for a people rejoycing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Protecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Government,</hi> than thoſe which would well become, <hi>A Day of Thanksgiving.</hi> Indeed, that <hi>Angel,</hi> who <hi>Flew thro the midſt of Heaven, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng, with a loud voice, Fear God, and give Glory to him,</hi> would not be able fully to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et off the <hi>Glory</hi> due to our God, for His matchleſs <hi>Favours</hi> unto us: But inſtead hereof a poor, ſhallow, ſinful <hi>Mortal,</hi> muſt come to you, with this Meſſage, <hi>Praiſe God, and Give Glory to Him</hi>! And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et it will be a <hi>Melody</hi> unto the very
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:000930_0004_0FACA35928EDF760"/>
               <hi>Angels</hi> or Heaven, to hear <hi>Mortals</hi> on Earth, Singing and Shouting forth, <hi>Glory to God in the Higheſt, for His Good Will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A people there has been, of whom that Account may be given, <hi>O Lord, Thou haſt brought a Vine, thou haſt cast out the Heathen, and planted it: Thou didſt cauſe it to take deep Root, and it filled the Land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> She ſent out her Hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> unto the Sea, and her Branches unto the River.</hi> My Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers all this while know not, whether I am giving an Account of <hi>Old Iſrael,</hi> or of <hi>New-England</hi>: So Surprizing has been the <hi>Parallel</hi>!</p>
            <p>The <hi>Matchleſs Favours</hi> of God unto <hi>Old Iſrael,</hi> are here C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>brated in one of the <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lelujatic Pſalms</hi>; and a <hi>Pſalm</hi> on ſuch a Subject, very fitly, both begins and concludes with; <hi>Hallelujah</hi>! The <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphonema</hi> which crowns all, is this, <hi>He hath not ſo dealt with any Nation; Praiſe ye the Lord.</hi> It gives us this <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> That when the Bleſſed God Endows a people with <hi>Matchleſs Favours,</hi> it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>comes that people to bleſs Him with <hi>Hearty Praiſes.</hi> This is an <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> ſo plain, ſo evident, and ſo practical, there needs
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:000930_0005_0FACA359E7A615E0"/>
no operation thereupon, to prepare it, for its <hi>Application</hi> unto our ſelves. The <hi>Matchleſs Favours</hi> of God unto <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are now to be ſet before you, in a <hi>Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re Catalogue</hi> of them: I ſay, a <hi>Short</hi> one, for who can in a piece of an Hour, Compoſe a <hi>Full</hi> one, or one that ſhall not fall <hi>ſhort</hi> in many Inſtances? Behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo much of <hi>New-England,</hi> from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Quarter, under ſuch Characters, here come together, I ſhall take this opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to beſpeak your <hi>Hearty Praiſes</hi> to the Almighty God, for <hi>So Dealing with</hi> New-England <hi>as not with any Nation.</hi> And I have now choſen a Subject, that one, would think ſhould be of all, the leaſt liable to Cavilling Objections, and Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. For, if any man ſhall object unto any one <hi>Article,</hi> in all my <hi>Catalogue, We owe no Hearty Praiſes to God upon that Article,</hi> give me leave to ſay it, It ſhall be an <hi>Hyperb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le</hi> of <hi>Ingrati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ude</hi>; and, That man ſhall be a <hi>prodigy</hi> of <hi>Profanity,</hi> and <hi>Stupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I cannot introduce the <hi>Catalogue</hi> of the <hi>Matchleſs Favours,</hi> wherein our God <hi>hath ſo dealt with us, as not with any Nation.</hi> Until you have had ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:000930_0006_0FACA35AADD89668"/>
upon the Nature, and Meaning, and Ingredients of thoſe <hi>Hearty Praiſes,</hi> which we are to render unto the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty for His <hi>Matchleſs Favours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will Remember then, That in our <hi>Hearty Praiſes</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, for His <hi>Match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Favours,</hi> we are to Confeſs, to Admire, to Adore thoſe <hi>Glories</hi> of God which are Conſpicuous and Illuſtrious in His <hi>Favours.</hi> The <hi>Power,</hi> the <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> the <hi>Mercy,</hi> and the <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> of the Great God, gloriouſly <hi>Shine forth</hi> in His <hi>Dealing ſo with us, as not with any Nation.</hi> The <hi>Glories</hi> of God, that His <hi>Dealings,</hi> do teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie and certifie, and ſignalize unto us, <hi>Theſe</hi> we muſt very diſtinctly <hi>Sound forth,</hi> with <hi>His High Praiſes in our mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, you will alſo Remember, that we are utterly <hi>unworthy</hi> of theſe <hi>Matchleſs Favours,</hi> for which we offer up unto God our <hi>Hearty Praiſes.</hi> When we Reflect on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Dealings</hi> of our God with us, we fearfully add unto our own <hi>unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs,</hi> if we don't ſenſibly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſay with our Father <hi>Jacob<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lord, we are not worthy of the Leaſt of all theſe Mercies.</hi> Truly, 'tis not becauſe we are better than any <hi>other Nation,</hi> that our God hath <hi>ſo dealt with
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:000930_0007_0FACA35B69984CD8"/>
us, as not with any Nation.</hi> We are more <hi>vile</hi> than every <hi>other Nation,</hi> if we don't own our ſelves <hi>as vile,</hi> as <hi>any Nation</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> When God had <hi>ſo dealt</hi> with His people of old, as <hi>not with any Nation,</hi> He, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>und and confound the <hi>vain Thoughts</hi> of <hi>pride</hi> in them, told them, Deut. 7.7, 8. <hi>The Lord did not ſet his Love upon you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye were more in Number than any people, (for ye were the fewest of all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) but becauſe the Lord Loved you.</hi> Such in <hi>Idem per Idem,</hi> is very good ſenſe, in he Language of <hi>Soveraign Grace; The Lord Loved you, meerly becauſe He Loved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou!</hi> Even ſo; 'Tis the meer <hi>Soveraign Grace</hi> of the God, <hi>who does all things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ording to the Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l of his own Will,</hi> that hath <hi>ſo Dealt with the Engliſh Nation as n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t with any Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion.</hi> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Anceſtors were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, wretched, rue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul Pagans, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur <hi>Indians</hi>; and there are now the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in our <hi>Nation</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that there are in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hore <hi>Enſlaved Neighbours,</hi> that are under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Houſes of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> or of <hi>Auſtria</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Why as the Lord <hi>ſo Dealt</hi> with thee, O <hi>New-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngland, as not with any Nation!</hi> The very <hi>Iottantots</hi> of <hi>Africa,</hi> and <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iba's</hi> on <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>da</hi> are a <hi>Nation</hi> as worthy of the Divine
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:000930_0008_0FACA35C2C8B1F38"/>
ties as thou art; and thou haſt <hi>Sins</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to bring upon thee as many plagues and woes as the <hi>Greek Churches</hi> themſelves are Languiſhing under. But, <hi>It is even ſo, O our Heavenly Father, meerly becauſe it pleaſes thee!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally; You will Remember, That we don't offer up <hi>Hearty Praiſes</hi> unto God, for His <hi>Matchleſs Favours,</hi> if they be not <hi>Active Praiſes.</hi> When we Reflect on the <hi>Dealings</hi> of our God, with us, there is that ingenuous Queſtion to be thought upon; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12. <hi>What ſhall we render to the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for all His Benefits!</hi> Hath our God <hi>ſo dealt with us, as not with any Nation?</hi> We are then to ſtudy fit <hi>Returns</hi> of <hi>Gratitude,</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> wherein we ſhall exceed every <hi>other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> 'Tis not a formal ſaying, <hi>Thanks be to God!</hi> that will ſerve to Expreſs our <hi>Thanks</hi> unto Him, for <hi>ſo dealing with us, as not with any Nation.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Thanks doing,</hi> and <hi>Thanks living,</hi> that muſt Expreſs our <hi>Thanks.</hi> Without ſome agreeable <hi>Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> in our Converſations, we have no True <hi>Thankfulneſs.</hi> We are then to think, <hi>What are the Fruits now Expected from a Nation, with whom God hath ſo dealt as,
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:000930_0009_0FACA35CE4DDCE20"/>
not with any Nation?</hi> What muſt be our <hi>Fruitfulneſs,</hi> that we may ſtill <hi>Enjoy,</hi> and not <hi>Forfeit</hi> the <hi>Bounties</hi> of God?</p>
            <p>But let us now proceed unto the <hi>Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Favours</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God unto thee, O <hi>New England,</hi> which call for ſuch <hi>Hearty Praiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here, concerning the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of the <hi>Country</hi> it ſelf, where <hi>the Moſt High hath divided, unto us our Inheritance,</hi> I will not ſay, God hath <hi>ſo dealt with us, as not with any Nation</hi>; But this If may ſay, There is many a <hi>Nation</hi> that is not near ſo well accommodated. Of the <hi>Land</hi> where our Lott falls unto us, our Good God may ſay, as in Ezek. 20.6. <hi>It is a Land that I had Eſpied for them.</hi> And tho' it be not, <hi>The Glory of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lands,</hi> yet <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> could not have met with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er <hi>Lands.</hi> Deſervedly is it called, <hi>New England</hi>; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or <hi>England,</hi> that braveſt Lady of <hi>Europe,</hi> has no where in <hi>Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> a Daughter that ſo much Reſembles her. The <hi>Comforts</hi> of the <hi>Climate,</hi> abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly outweigh the <hi>Hardſhips</hi> of it. The <hi>Poor</hi> find a more comfortable Subſiſtence in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, than alm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt in any other. Almoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>very where elſe the <hi>Poor</hi> do rather <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="unknown:000930_0010_0FACA35DA7D0D730"/>
Life, than <hi>Enjoy</hi> it. But, the <hi>Poor</hi> of this Land, may ſay, <hi>God hath not ſo dealt with the reſt of the poor in our Nation, or ſcarce in any Nation.</hi> And where the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of it uſe <hi>Diſcretion</hi> and <hi>Induſtry,</hi> they moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly furniſh themſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, not only with <hi>Neceſſaries,</hi> but alſo with <hi>Convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> Indeed <hi>New England</hi> is not <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: That</hi> we are ſure old. But for my part, I do not ask to Remove out of <hi>New England,</hi> except for a Removal into <hi>Heaven.</hi> 'Tis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me Troubles, but thoſe rather in the <hi>Mora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> than the <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Circumſtances of the Country, have often cauſed our moſt E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ent. <hi>Elijahs,</hi> to wiſh, <hi>Oh! If they had the wings of a Dove, whither would they flee away</hi>! And, Whither, Syrs, I beſeech you? I doubt, you don't know the <hi>World</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Certainly, you'l find it <hi>Old Adams World,</hi> go w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere you will. There grow <hi>Briars</hi> &amp; <hi>Thorns,</hi> in other parts of the World, as well as <hi>New England.</hi> But, O Good pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ple of <hi>New England,</hi> Tho' you are by the <hi>Royal Charter,</hi> delivered from the Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ions of thoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that once demanded of you, <hi>Quitrents</hi> for all the <hi>Good Land</hi> unto the poſſeſſion whereof your <hi>Titles</hi> are now
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:000930_0011_0FACA35E636DE688"/>
Confirmed, yet Hear now thy Great Landlord, calling for <hi>His Quitrents,</hi> in thoſe terms. Deut. 8 10, 11. <hi>When thou haſt eaten and art full, then thou ſhalt bleſs the Lord thy God, for the Good Land, which he hath given thee; Beware that thou forget not the Lord thy God in not keeping His Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us paſs on to thoſe <hi>Favours</hi> of Heaven, that are more <hi>Distinguiſhing,</hi> &amp; <hi>Conſiderable,</hi> and without which, the beſt Countreys in the World, would be as undeſitable as <hi>Italy</hi> it ſelf: A Country that is the <hi>Garden</hi> of the World, and yet an <hi>Hell upon Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Firſt, Let not the <hi>Method</hi> be charged with any <hi>Rudeneſs,</hi> if <hi>Religion</hi> take the <hi>firſt place,</hi> in our Enumeration of thoſe <hi>Matchleſs Favours,</hi> wherewith our God hath obliged us infinitely This, This was the grand point wherein the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of old, were the <hi>Favourites</hi> of Heaven <hi>The Lord ſhewed his words, [i e.</hi> the Ten Commandments of the Moral Law] <hi>unto Jacob, his Statutes</hi> (or the Ceremonial Law) <hi>and His Judgments</hi> (or the Judicial Law) <hi>unto Iſrael:</hi> And <hi>Then</hi> it follows, <hi>He hath not ſo dealt with
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:000930_0012_0FACA35F25755330"/>
any Nation; Praiſe ye the Lord.</hi> God in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>avouring</hi> us (and the <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi>) with the Knowledge of the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſo dealt with us as not with any Nation.</hi> As it was ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.14. <hi>He Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>teth the Horn of His People, even of the Children of Iſrael, a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple near unto Him.</hi> When God makes a forlorn Race of <hi>Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiles,</hi> to become his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and by His Holy <hi>Religion</hi> brings them <hi>near unto Him,</hi> it becomes them to <hi>Exalt the Horn,</hi> that is to ſay, to utter His <hi>Praiſes</hi> with <hi>Higher Notes</hi> than ordinary. 'Tis done for the <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſingularly done for thee, O <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Iſrael</hi> How much ought we to <hi>Praiſe the Lord,</hi> for that <hi>Religion,</hi> which alone teaches us how to <hi>Praiſe the Lord!</hi> When the Herald of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed the Greatneſs of his Maſter, by more than <hi>Forty</hi> ſeveral Titles, the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald of the King of <hi>France,</hi> as often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated that one Title, <hi>The King of France, France, France!</hi> In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting, that this <hi>One,</hi> was more than all the <hi>other</hi> This I will ſay, Tell me not of more than <hi>Forty</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſings and Stapl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and Pleaſures of other Countreys. My <hi>New England</hi> has
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:000930_0013_0FACA35FE566E3E0"/>
one Thing that will weigh down more than <hi>Forty</hi> of the beſt things that other Countreys on brag of; That is, <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Religion, Religion!</hi> The <hi>Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> is indeed a <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them that have it <hi>Revealed,</hi> and publiſhed among them. By this <hi>Religion</hi> men are <hi>Lifted up to Heaven,</hi> and have <hi>Heaven</hi> coming down to <hi>them.</hi> We have the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of our Lord JESUS CHRIST, which is moſt juſtly called, <hi>The Glorious Goſpel of God</hi>: And this <hi>Goſpel</hi> will make a <hi>Glorious People</hi>: But, O <hi>Goſpellized Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> then <hi>Glorify God</hi>! They are moſt <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Myſteries</hi> that the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion,</hi> does Enrich us withal, and they are moſt <hi>Noble Directions</hi> with which it counſils us. O <hi>New-Englanders,</hi> While you have a Bible in your Habitations you <hi>Eat Angels Food</hi>! A man that <hi>Feeds</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> upon the principles of this <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> is a <hi>Noble Creature,</hi> and a <hi>Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date</hi> of the <hi>Angelical Life.</hi> The <hi>Regions</hi> that have not our <hi>Goſpel,</hi> are the <hi>Regions that Sit in Darkneſs,</hi> and in the <hi>Valley of the Shadow of Death</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If we receive this <hi>Goſpel</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> in the <hi>Love of it,</hi> it will infallibly bring us to
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:000930_0014_0FACA360AB878A18"/>
Everlaſting Bleſſedneſs. If this our <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel be Hid,</hi> it is <hi>Hid unto them that be lost.</hi> The Strangers to this <hi>Religion,</hi> are <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the World,</hi> and <hi>without Hope</hi> of Bleſſedneſs in another World. The Lands that have not our <hi>Goſpel,</hi> what are they, but the <hi>Habitations of Devils,</hi> and all the year long, in a more lamentable plight, than the furtheſt and frozen Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of the <hi>North,</hi> which have <hi>all Night</hi> for many months together? In the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of our <hi>Christian Religion,</hi> we have, in one word, A CHRIST, A CHRIST, in whom our <hi>Hungry Souls</hi> have the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> and in whom our <hi>Thirſty Souls</hi> have the <hi>Water of Life</hi>: and our <hi>Naked Souls,</hi> the Splendid <hi>Garments of Salvation.</hi> Out of Heaven, hath, <hi>God, the perfection of Beauty ſhone upon</hi> us. Our CHRIST, He is the <hi>Way</hi>; without Him, we were <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabonds,</hi> and <hi>going aſtray in the greatneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Folly;</hi> He is the <hi>Truth</hi>; without Him, we are a prey to the <hi>Father of Lies,</hi> and our <hi>Deceived Heart</hi> can't be Sav'd from a <hi>Lye in our Right Hand:</hi> He is the <hi>Life</hi>; without Him, we are <hi>Dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins</hi> Bleſſed JESUS, <hi>'Twere better we ſhould not be at all, than be without
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:000930_0015_0FACA361644654C8"/>
Thee</hi>! But, that bright <hi>Sun of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> hath dart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d His <hi>Healing Beams</hi> down upon thee, <hi>O New England</hi>; when ſo many millions of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, are left unenligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened. Above hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Children of men, I ſuppoſe, are <hi>Idolaters</hi> to this Day; and almoſt a <hi>Quarter,</hi> if I miſtake not, are <hi>Mahometans</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Aſtoniſh'd at the <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> of God, that has made us <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> Let us Employ our Pitty, and Prayer, &amp; Care, for thoſe that are Expoſed unto <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion</hi> every day, by their<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Lack</hi> of our <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> Bleſſed be God, that has Crown'd the Labours of His <hi>Dutch Ministers</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt Indies</hi> of late years, with ſuch rare Succeſſes, that Hundreds of Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of the Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ives, are Converted from their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and their <hi>Mahometaniſm,</hi> &amp; are <hi>Baptiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> into the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Strike on, O Arm of the Lord</hi>! What we have done, for the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vangelizing</hi> of our <hi>Indians,</hi> has been as great an Honour to <hi>New England,</hi> as any that ever befel it. The like H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nour in ſome regards has not befall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>any, Nati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on; Praiſe ye the Lord!</hi> I veh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, Let not that <hi>Evangelical Work</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="unknown:000930_0016_0FACA362297D0478"/>
now come to <hi>nothing.</hi> Reſcue it from the Decayes, and Choak weeds which do Threaten it; and ſee whether we can't extend it even unto the <hi>Five Nations</hi> of the <hi>Weſt,</hi> as well as that in the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> If they be not by our mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s made <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> we can tell who will uſe all means to make them, <hi>twofold more Children of Hell,</hi> than they are already.</p>
            <p>Well, but when our God has granted us the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> there is a <hi>Second Flight</hi> that our Thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hts are to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke, into the <hi>State of the Caſe</hi> which renders it a <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> of God; And this is, That it is <hi>Truly Chriſtian.</hi> Two Hundred years ago, were the <hi>Dark Times</hi> of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtaſy.</hi> Wherein <hi>Satan,</hi> by his <hi>Vicar</hi> and <hi>Viceroy</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> rendred a very <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinnom,</hi> that which was called <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me.</hi> The <hi>Unſearchable Judgments</hi> of God, gave up all <hi>Europe,</hi> unto the <hi>Chains of Darkneſs,</hi> which <hi>Popery,</hi> that is but a <hi>Diſguiſed,</hi> and <hi>Revived Paganiſm</hi> laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: Except here an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there ſome <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in Sackl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th,</hi> which by barbarous <hi>Cruſades,</hi> &amp; Cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s againſt them, were made <hi>Sheep for the ſlau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hter all the day long.</hi> But about one hundred and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:000930_0017_0FACA362E8C65AC0"/>
years ago, God Showred a <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Reformation,</hi> upon the <hi>Nations</hi> of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi>; and <hi>Antichriſt</hi> Loſt <hi>Half</hi> his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. God in ſome things then dealt with our <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> as not <hi>with any Nation</hi>: For the Myſtical <hi>Jericho</hi> being then demoliſhed before the Evangelical Shouts of the <hi>Reformation</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Curſe</hi> of our Bleſſed JESUS, hath ever ſince in a ſtupendous manner fallen on the Heads of all that have gone to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>build</hi> it, and blaſted all their Enterprizes. And God hath Raiſed up a <hi>Golden Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of men in the <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> who notwithſtanding many diſcouragements and diſadvantages, from the Maſquera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Adverſaries of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> as they have kept the <hi>Lords Day</hi> more ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo, for all the other ſtrictneſs of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſtianity,</hi> and for the <hi>Power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> and for mighty Elevations of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> have none to equal them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (or not many, I am ſure) among the Sons of <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis no <hi>Small</hi> Thing that God has done for our <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> in delivering it from, the <hi>Political Miſchiefs of Popery,</hi> under which the Nations yet <hi>Intoxicated</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="unknown:000930_0018_0FACA363A67513D8"/>
with the <hi>Popiſh Abominations</hi> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. The <hi>Proteſtant Religi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> hath not been ſet up ſcarce in <hi>any Nation,</hi> but it has made them, even in Temporals, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a very little while, twice as <hi>Rich</hi> and as <hi>Great</hi> as they were before; And one, ſomewhat curious in his Calcula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions, has demonſtrated, That the Aboliſhing of <hi>Popery</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> is worth at leaſt Eight Millions of Pounds Sterling, yearly profit unto it. But this is a <hi>Small</hi> Thing, in compariſon of what has been done by God for the <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> in its Deliverance, from the <hi>Spiritual Miſchiefs of Popery</hi> For 'tis peculiarly concerning the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> that the Spirit of God uttered that Oracle in 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Theſ. 2.11, 12. <hi>God ſhall ſend them strong Deluſion, that they ſhould Believe a lie, that they all might be Damned, who Believed not the Truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Praiſes,</hi> where are you? Let Heaven ring wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h our <hi>Praiſes</hi> unto our God, for the <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Praiſed be God, That the <hi>Treaſures</hi> of His Bleſſed <hi>Word</hi> are not lock'd up from us! That we are not <hi>Prieſt ridden</hi> by the <hi>Janizaries</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt</hi>! That we have not <hi>Non ſenſical Figments,</hi> thruſt down our Throats
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:000930_0019_0FACA36467E499C8"/>
with Burning Fire brands<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That we may uſe our own <hi>Deſcretion</hi> in the concerns of our own <hi>Salvation</hi>! That we are not by bloody Inquiſitions, or Drag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings, or Faggots, and Gibbets, driven to worſhip the <hi>Works of mens Hands!</hi> Truly, There are <hi>many Nations,</hi> that are not ſo <hi>Dealt</hi> withal. But you, O dear People of <hi>New-England,</hi> have your Share in this amazing Deliverance.</p>
            <p>Aſtoniſh'd a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> of God, which has made us <hi>Proteſtants</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Let us put on all Bowels of <hi>Charity,</hi> for our Brethren, that are <hi>Confeſſors,</hi> and <hi>Refugees,</hi> for the <hi>cauſe of God.</hi> Let us annex the <hi>Cries</hi> of our <hi>Prayers,</hi> unto the <hi>Cries</hi> of the <hi>Souls under the Altar,</hi> for a ſpeedy and rapi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Thunder ſtorm,</hi> upon thoſe, who have the Cry of all the <hi>Righteous Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od</hi> that has been <hi>Shed</hi> from to the <hi>Blood of Abel,</hi> to the Blood <hi>of</hi> Bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, whom they lately broke upon the <hi>Wheel,</hi> going up to God againſt them: <hi>Ut convert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> percan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, aut confundantur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t noce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Yea, Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more than all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; Let us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Efficacy</hi> of our <hi>Holy Religion</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> upon our own Hearts, and L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ves, Let us <hi>Live</hi> up to the <hi>Maxims</hi> of our <hi>Holy Religion,</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:000930_0020_0FACA36524A67A10"/>
               <hi>Live</hi> under the awful and joyful <hi>Force</hi> thereof. Otherwiſe a prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ked God, may put us upon Severe <hi>Trials,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it: but if we have not had the <hi>Holy Reliſh</hi> of it, we ſhall, when we are <hi>Tried,</hi> ſoon give it away.</p>
            <p>But are there no <hi>Specialties</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> in which <hi>New England</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hath received the <hi>Matchleſs Favours</hi> of God, even beyond the reſt of the <hi>Engliſh Nation.</hi> This is a <hi>Third Flight,</hi> that we are now to take in the <hi>Praiſes</hi> of God. I am not indeed ſo inconſiderate, as to <hi>boaſt</hi> of my Country: and, Ah, <hi>New England,</hi> thou haſt enough and enough to <hi>Humble</hi> thee. Yea, I will readily grant, That in one City of the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> (I mean, the <hi>Capital</hi>) there is a greater Number of <hi>Pious People,</hi> than in all this whole Province. And I am no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo Abſurd &amp; M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roſe and Little, as to <hi>dream,</hi> that there are no <hi>Pious People,</hi> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what are in leſſer points of my own perſwaſion. But the <hi>Favours</hi> of God muſt not be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Our Degeneracies are horrible: they Expoſe us to the Dreadful Wrath of the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, who when Churches <hi>Leave their firſt Love,</hi> does <hi>Quickly come</hi> ſorth againſt
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:000930_0021_0FACA3669406A9C8"/>
them, with Horrible Deſolations. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, As they tell me, That the <hi>Peaſants</hi> in moſt other Countreyes are meer Bruits to what they are in <hi>England</hi>: I ſuppoſe, <hi>Ours</hi> are not worſe than <hi>Englands.</hi> Yea, I have heard unprejudiced ſtrangers own, That there is yet left proportionably more of <hi>Piety</hi> in this Land, and the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people</hi> are for the moſt part, better inſtructed, than in any that they know of under Heaven. And I hope they will have cauſe to ſay, that they ſee more <hi>Honeſty</hi> too; or Elſe the <hi>Piety</hi> is worth nothing at all. He that is but a <hi>Publican</hi> at the Second <hi>Table,</hi> is but a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> as to the Firſt. <hi>Modeſty</hi> forbids me, to ſay <hi>much</hi> of This; though I wiſh I could ſay <hi>More</hi>; and, <hi>Compariſons</hi> are <hi>Odious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there are ſome further <hi>Specialities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Doctrinal Articles</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> through the <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> of God, are more univerſally Hold, &amp; Preach'd in the Churches of <hi>New-England,</hi> than in <hi>any Nation,</hi> and far more than in our own It is more than I know, That there is <hi>One Socinia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in all the Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ey; And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the <hi>Pastors</hi> of <hi>our Churches,</hi> I do not know that there is one <hi>Arminian</hi> The
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:000930_0022_0FACA366B8CD07E8"/>
               <hi>pure Doctrines of Grace,</hi> which are a <hi>Match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Favour</hi> of God unto the <hi>Churches</hi> that have them, are the <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſant,</hi> and <hi>publick</hi> Doctrines of the Countrey. Yea, The <hi>Neonomian,</hi> and the <hi>Antinomian</hi> Errors, about that Great Point<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of, <hi>A Sinners Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification before God,</hi> which have bred ſuch a Scandalous Contention, among the <hi>Non Conformiſts</hi> beyond Sea, have not yet Straggled over the <hi>Atlantic,</hi> among this people of God. The two <hi>Covenants,</hi> that of <hi>Works,</hi> and that of <hi>Grace,</hi> are not here ſo confounded, as in many other places. <hi>The Everlaſting Goſpel,</hi> is here Preach'd with Purity, more univerſally, than in <hi>any Nation. God hath not ſo dealt with any Nation; Praiſe ye the Lord</hi>! We don't pretend here, that we have taught our Neighbours, <hi>The whole Duty of man</hi> when we have Leſt out the <hi>Main Dut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of all. And give me leave to ſay, There is CHRIST Preach'd in thy Churches, O <hi>New England</hi>; and the <hi>Shout of that King is heard in the midſt of thee.</hi> I hope, there is nothing of <hi>Religion</hi> among us, but ordinarily you ſhall hear ſomething of CHRIST in it, before you have done and you have the <hi>Truth as it is in Jeſus</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="unknown:000930_0023_0FACA3678FF9C090"/>
Our Preachers don't value their <hi>Sermons,</hi> upon being as <hi>Auſtin</hi> complain'd, the Writings of <hi>Tully</hi> were, <hi>Without ſo much as the Name of CHRIST in them</hi>: and would not have you be like thoſe whom the writings of the Ancients do brand, <hi>ſine Chriſto Chriſtians.</hi> A <hi>Nation</hi> full of Preachers, that will contrive to make Hara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gues upon <hi>Moral Vertues,</hi> but baniſh CHRIST as much as they can out of all their <hi>Treatiſing,</hi> muſt needs be very obn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xious to the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: I will ſay with <hi>Luther, Quicquid O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur, Docetur, Vivitur extra Chriſtum, eſt Idolo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atria coram Deo, et peccatum.</hi> Yea, to uſe the Expreſſion of an Excellent perſon, <hi>If I were in a Church full of Kings, I would ſay ſo</hi>! But God has not <hi>ſo dealt with this our little Nation.</hi> How will you now <hi>Praiſe God</hi> for this <hi>Matchleſs Favour?</hi> How? But by prizing of His CHRIST, and loving of His CHRIST, and yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l poſſible Obedience to the CHRIST who is the <hi>Author of Eternal Salvation, to as many as Obey Him.</hi> I'l drive that Nail, with one ſtroke of Hiſtory. There had been much of CHRIST, at <hi>Capernaum</hi> of old: A CHRIST was a Reſident at
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:000930_0024_0FACA368237ECEA8"/>
               <hi>Capernaum</hi> Yea, but our CHRIST was grievouſly undervalued there; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Lord fore-told, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.23. <hi>Thou ſhalt be brought down to Hell.</hi> Now I find in the Jewiſh <hi>Talmuds</hi> that <hi>Capernaum</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this given up to the moſt <hi>Helliſh Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs</hi> that ever was: The Town of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaum,</hi> was a meer <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ground. There was not a more <hi>Helliſh</hi> place for Filthineſs, and Sorcery, on the Face of the Earth. Oh, Conſider of it!</p>
            <p>Moreover, Is it not a <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> to Sit under the <hi>Wings</hi> of <hi>Churches,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Primitive Diſcipline</hi> is <hi>Reſtored</hi>: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> that <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and <hi>Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> and other Great <hi>Lights</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> wiſh'd for, and wrote for, &amp; would gladly have <hi>Dy'd</hi> for? A <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> wherein all Things are Conformed, as well as we can underſtand, unto the Word of the Lord JESUS CHRIST, &amp; wherein the <hi>Elders</hi> have their <hi>Authority</hi> upheld, the <hi>Brethren</hi> have not their <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> over laid, and all things Conſpire to Repreſent the <hi>Holineſs</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven</hi> unto the World; it is a <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> of Heaven, to the <hi>Nation</hi> that is
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:000930_0025_0FACA368E7CB3D98"/>
               <hi>Illuminated</hi> with it. In whatſoever we may want of <hi>this,</hi> may the <hi>Great Shepherd of the Sheep</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead us, and make our <hi>Works perfect</hi> before Him. In whatſoever we have attained of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, it will be a very ſad <hi>unhappineſs,</hi> for any man to be ſo Left of God, as to be the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of Diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it: it were better to <hi>Dy,</hi> than come under that <hi>unhappineſs.</hi> God grant we may hear that, which they tell us, was one of the <hi>Songs,</hi> at the <hi>Feaſt of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles, Bleſſed be our Youth, that have not made our Old men Aſhamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is it not a <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> of our God unto us, that for the Propagation of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Civility</hi> among us, there has been a COLLEDGE Erected in theſe <hi>Ends of the Earth?</hi> Truly, God hath not <hi>ſo dealt with</hi> any Out-goings of <hi>our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on!</hi> Had it not been for ſuch <hi>Miniſters</hi> as have Shone in moſt of our Towns, the <hi>Wild Beaſts of the Deſart,</hi> in a little while would have <hi>Lien there, the Houſes would</hi> moſtly have been <hi>full of doleful Creatures,</hi> and <hi>Owles</hi> would <hi>have dwelt there.</hi> A Learned and a Godly <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> hath been the <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> of God unto <hi>New-England</hi>: Men of whom that Account
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:000930_0026_0FACA369AC191BB8"/>
might be given, which the Great <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> in his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irs gave of one, for whom he deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gn'd preſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment, <hi>Nihil ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit, nihil ardet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mniat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; Men, of whom it might be ſaid, as it was of a certain Scotch Divine, <hi>That he di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eat and Drink, and Sleep the Kingdom of Heaven</hi>: Men that have been <hi>Timothies</hi> in their Houſes, <hi>Chryſostomes</hi> in their Pulpits, and <hi>Auguſtines</hi> in their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations. <hi>Impoſtors</hi> have but ſeldome got in, and ſet up among us; and when they have done ſo, they have made but a <hi>Short Blaze,</hi> and <hi>Gone out in a Snuff</hi>; and ſome Hand or other, hath done ſuch a Service for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as to <hi>Scourge the Thieves out of the Temple</hi> But <hi>Miniſters</hi> that have been <hi>Pastors after the Heart of God,</hi> theſe have ſtill <hi>Flouriſhed like a Green Olive tree in the Houſe of God,</hi> and have been the means for their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with them. If any under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value this <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> of God, I will mind them of a Speech uſed by the Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi> when he heard ſome underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing the Miniſters of the Goſpel; <hi>Well, God Bleſs them, by whom God Bleſſeth us</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This could not eaſily have been, if it had
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:000930_0027_0FACA36A78467E80"/>
not been for the <hi>Seminary</hi> of <hi>Good Letters</hi> and of <hi>Good Manners</hi>; for which our God may ſay unto us, as unto His <hi>Iſrael, I Raiſed up of your Sons for Prophets, and of your young men for Nazarites: Is it not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thus, O ye Children of</hi> New England? The Reverend <hi>Chauncey,</hi> once Prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dent of our <hi>Colledge,</hi> publiſhed a Sermon on thoſe words of the Prophet, wherein he has a line or two, not improper now to be Repeated. Saies he,
<q>This Great Bleſſing is not regarded by <hi>Covetous Earthworms,</hi> and many make wicked Returns for the Bleſſing, and ſeek to pull down <hi>Schools of Learning.</hi> How hateful unto the Lord is this <hi>Unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Do ye thus requite the Lord, ye foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh people and unwiſe?</hi>
               </q>
Thus the Renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Old man Exclaimed in <hi>his Day.</hi> All that I ſhall add <hi>this Day</hi> upon it is, That except we do immediately ask and take the Advice of our Excellent GOVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOUR, for the obtaining of a Good Eſtabliſhment of this our <hi>Colledge,</hi> it is much to be fear'd it will preſently be broken up; Without his Direction and Countenance we can do nothing to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; &amp; it is a <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> of God
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:000930_0028_0FACA36B27AD1AC0"/>
that we may have it. If meerly thro' <hi>our Neglect,</hi> an <hi>Ominous Ruine</hi> come now upon our Colledge, monſtrous, and ſhameful, and ſenſeleſs will be our <hi>Unthankfulneſs</hi> unto God, who hath <hi>ſo Dealt</hi> with us, as not with <hi>Every Nation</hi>; and they that wiſh well unto <hi>New England</hi> will ſay, <hi>Surely no other Nation would have been ſuch</hi> Felones de ſe, <hi>or have dealt ſo by its own greateſt Intereſt!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, if we now make our Tranſition in the <hi>Second place,</hi> unto our <hi>Civil State,</hi> We ſhall therein ſee much of That which hath ſecured unto us, the Enjoyment of our <hi>Holy Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igion,</hi> and find our ſelves further followed with the <hi>Matchleſs Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours</hi> of our God. When we look either upon our <hi>Subſiſtence</hi> heretofore and hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or upon the <hi>Government</hi> under which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we do now Subſiſt, <hi>New England</hi> may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by the <hi>Angels,</hi> whom the moſt High God has uſed in conveying theſe His <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unto us, as in Luk 1.28 <hi>Hail <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Highly Favoured, the Lord is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>!</p>
            <p>Though I am no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> has our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince any one that is. He, who in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Common wealth is called, <hi>The
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:000930_0029_0FACA36BE8714580"/>
Divine of the Star<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>; Yet I may ſo far take notice of what Occurs in our <hi>Civil State,</hi> as to ſay:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Our <hi>Subſiſtence,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt by <hi>Miracle</hi>: Our God has <hi>not ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with any Nation.</hi> How ſtrangely was the Settlement of <hi>New England</hi> at firſt brought forward, and at laſt brought about; When God <hi>brought a Nation out of the midſt of a Nation!</hi> There were ſome Occurrences in that Thing, which would make that Challenge not unreaſonable, Deut. 4.32 <hi>Ask now of the Dayes that are paſt, which were before thee, ſince the Day that God Created man upon the Earth, and ask from the one ſide of Heaven unto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whether there have been any ſuch thing as this great thing is, or hath been heard like it?</hi> And ever ſince the Settlement, how ſtrangely have we been Relieved, Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, Supplied in our frequent, and frightful Exigencies? We have often been in very ſore <hi>Distreſſes</hi>; but being Diſtreſs'd, <hi>This poor people has cried unto the Lord, who hath heard and ſav'd,</hi> with moſt ſeaſonable and unexpected Salvations. Hath God <hi>ſo dealt with every Nation?</hi> Truly No! I muſt ſay unto you, as in
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:000930_0030_0FACA36CA748EE38"/>
Deut 4 7. <hi>What Nation is there, that hath God ſo Nigh unto them, as the Lord our God is in all things, that we call upon him for?</hi> There have been formidable Attempts of Satan and his Sons, to <hi>Unſettle</hi> us: But what an overwhelming <hi>Blast</hi> from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven has, defeated all thoſe Attempts? And very particularly, When the <hi>Carel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Perſecution</hi> ſo raged againſt our Brethren in the Engliſh Nation, That a late Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter affirms, <hi>More were then Starv'd, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe Dy'd in noiſome Priſons th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> what I care to mention</hi>; We felt nothing of it; but were ſo <hi>dealt withal,</hi> as not at that very Time our Brethren in <hi>our Nation.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, and after, a vaſt number of <hi>Ebene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers,</hi> Erected by <hi>New-England</hi> upon all its various Intereſts, whole <hi>Nations</hi> of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages from one end of the Land unto the other, took up Arms againſt us. But the <hi>Sword of God,</hi> in one years time, cut off thoſe Nations: for, O <hi>New England,</hi> Thou didſt <hi>not get the Land in poſſeſſion, by thy own Sword, neither did thine own Arm Save thee</hi> At length it was propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>That a Colony of Iriſh might be ſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ck the growth of this Countrey</hi>: An <hi>Happy Revolution</hi> ſpoil'd <hi>that Plot</hi>:
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:000930_0031_0FACA36D70B1B6A8"/>
and many an one of more general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence than <hi>That</hi>! But the <hi>Tribulation for Ten Dayes,</hi> which we then had, in a variety of <hi>Calamities,</hi> afforded us a vaſt variety of <hi>Experiences,</hi> upon which we might ſet up our further <hi>Ebenezers.</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped <hi>New-England,</hi> may with exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wonderment, cry out, <hi>Having obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Help from God, I continue to this Day</hi>! The Ancient Hiſtorian could ſay, <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam majori Triumpho vicimus, quam cum Decem Annorum ſtrage vinci non potuimus</hi>: Thus may we ſay, 'Twas a <hi>Matchleſs Favo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of our God unto us, that when this <hi>Little Veſſel</hi> was in a direful <hi>Storm</hi> for <hi>Ten years</hi> together, it has after all out liv'd the <hi>Storm.</hi> And I may add hereupon, though we drank Deep of the <hi>Cup of Trembling,</hi> which the Hand of God carried about unto the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> in the Late <hi>War</hi>; yet there were ſeveral Merciful Diſpenſations of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, wherein God <hi>ſo dealt with us, as not with any Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, Secondly, In the <hi>Government</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et over us, we may and muſt ſay it, <hi>Our God has done Great Things for us</hi>!</p>
            <p>It is no Little Bleſſing of God, that
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:000930_0032_0FACA36E257D1390"/>
we are a part of the <hi>Engliſh Nation.</hi> Our Dependence on, and Relation to, that brave <hi>Nation,</hi> that man deſerves not the Name of an <hi>Engliſh man,</hi> who deſpiſes it. There is no <hi>Engliſh man</hi> but what has for his <hi>Birthright</hi> thoſe <hi>Liberties,</hi> which are a rich <hi>Inheritance</hi>: When all the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of the <hi>Northern Europe,</hi> of late years fooliſhly Loſt their <hi>Liberties,</hi> the brave <hi>Engliſh,</hi> (tho' with ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uggle enough, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Unnatural Conſpiracies</hi> of the <hi>Late Reigns</hi>) have ſtill preſerved <hi>Theirs</hi>: They are none but the Sons of <hi>Edom,</hi> that undervalue thoſe <hi>Liberties</hi>: and who do not ſee, that God <hi>hath not ſo dealt with any Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if it be a <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> of our God unto us, that we have our claim to <hi>Engliſh Liberties,</hi> (though our <hi>Task maſters</hi> Twelve years ago, told us we had <hi>None!</hi>) Let us not be inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of His <hi>Matchleſs Favour</hi> unto us, (for it is <hi>Now ſo</hi>!) that we have a claim to the KING of <hi>England,</hi> as having theſe Dominions alſo under His Auſpicious Influences.</p>
            <p>GOD, by a wondrous <hi>Revolution</hi> hath brought unto the Throne of <hi>Three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="unknown:000930_0033_0FACA36EF0E1DEC8"/>
by the Voice of all the good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple therein, a KING, whoſe <hi>Royal Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> are ſuch, that we may truly ſay, <hi>God hath not ſo dealt with any Nation</hi>: As the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> is the moſt Glorious of any under Heaven, ſo there is no <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that can boaſt of ſuch a KING, as ours! A KING Raiſed by Heaven, to ſave <hi>Three Kingdoms</hi> from the <hi>Chains</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> that were <hi>Treacherouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> prepared for them, and break thoſe that were apace putting upon all <hi>Europe</hi> alſo: A KING us'd by Heaven, to put an Hook in the <hi>Noſtrils</hi> of a <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and make him diſgorge at the Peace of <hi>Ryſwick,</hi> Cities and Countreys, which contain as much in Bigneſs, as all the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi>: A KING, whoſe <hi>Royal Aſſent</hi> unto ſundry <hi>Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> has advanc'd the <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> unto <hi>Priviledges,</hi> richly worth all the millions of Money, that have been ſpent ſince the <hi>Revolution</hi>; and the <hi>Scotch Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is likewiſe Reſtored unto its Deſired Faelicity. As <hi>New England,</hi> was the Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt of all the <hi>Plantations</hi> in Declaring for this Illuſtrious PRINCE, thus from <hi>New England</hi> alſo there go up as Lively
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:000930_0034_0FACA36FA7F85C60"/>
Acclamations, as from any whatſoever, <hi>Long, Long may we have ſuch a KING to Reign over us</hi>!</p>
            <p>When the KING, Reſolving to <hi>Favour</hi> us, with a moſt Exact <hi>Image</hi> of His own <hi>Royal Vertues,</hi> in a GOVERNOUR, gave His Commiſſion unto the truly No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Earl of BELLOMONT for the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> of theſe Plantations, we were from almoſt every Quarter told, That the Nobility of <hi>Three Kingdoms</hi> could not have afforded a perſon more charming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Agreeable: But ſince His Excellency's Happy Arrival, we now find, <hi>That the One half was never told us.</hi> You will pardon me, <hi>My Lord,</hi> if I call upon my people to Bleſs God, and Thank the King, for Your EXCELLENCY, when I am reckoning up the Things, wherein we are <hi>ſo Dealt withal, as not any Nation.</hi> I do not forget that I am ſtanding in a place, very near Heaven, in which, more than in any under Heaven, <hi>Flatter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> would be offenſive: to <hi>My Maker.</hi> Yea, I do Believe, our<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> GOVERNOUR Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, hath ſo much of the Great <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> in him, that I could not more <hi>Offend</hi> Him, than by going to <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter</hi> him.
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:000930_0035_0FACA3706A1E5170"/>
Nevertheleſs, I Judge, it would be no leſs than a <hi>Sinful Omiſſion</hi> in me, if I ſhould not reckon our GOVERNOUR, among the <hi>Matchleſs Favours</hi> of our God unto us. I am not <hi>Praiſing</hi> of Him; for in the Langua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of a <hi>Divine,</hi> I muſt call to mind, that he is <hi>Nothing,</hi> but what GOD makes him to be: But I am urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, to the <hi>Praiſing</hi> of GOD for Him. Yea I will ſay [<hi>And I wiſh I could ſo ſpeak it, that all</hi> New England <hi>might Hear it!</hi>] That as we made our GO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERNOUR, a Great Article of our <hi>Prayers</hi> to GOD, before we Received Him, So, now we ſee our <hi>Prayers</hi> thus remarkably anſwered, if we don't make him an Article of our <hi>Praiſes</hi> to GOD, not only in publick, but alſo in private, every where throughout the Land, we deſerve the Diſaſter which the Enemies of the <hi>Kings</hi> Intereſts d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſire to ſee befall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us; that is to ſay, to be Deprived of ſo great a Bleſſing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But I am the more Excuſed from inſiſting on this <hi>Matchleſs favour</hi> of God unto us, becauſe I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, our people Generally have ſome affectionate Reſentments of it. It was of old ſaid, Pſal. 144.14, 15. <hi>Let there be
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:000930_0036_0FACA371283B5CB8"/>
no Complaining in our Streets; Happy is that people that is in ſuch a caſe.</hi> Now, tho' I muſt freely own it, That no people has been more prone to <hi>Complain</hi> than we, yet I have heard perſons that converſe among all ſorts of people, ſay, <hi>That they never yet could ſee the man, who uttered, or muttered, the least Complaint againſt His EXCELLENCY'S Government.</hi> Say, O <hi>New England</hi>; Has the Lord <hi>ſo dealt with any Nation</hi>? The only <hi>People,</hi> that <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain</hi> of Him, ſo far as I can Learn, are thoſe worſt of <hi>People,</hi> the mortal Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of all <hi>People,</hi> the <hi>Pyrates,</hi> and their <hi>Abettors.</hi> The Inflexible <hi>Juſtice</hi> of our GOVERNOUR, perpetually and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully, purſues thoſe Horrid <hi>Sea-Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi>; But for thoſe Bloody <hi>Harpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and thoſe that are in <hi>Confederacy</hi> with them, to <hi>Complain</hi> of the <hi>Vengeance</hi> that follows them, is <hi>Muſick</hi> in the Ears of all that would not ſee theſe Plan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ations Ruined. All <hi>Honeſt men,</hi> Rejoice when ſuch are <hi>Grieved, That</hi> there is come a <hi>Man, that ſeeks the Welfare of this Little Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall we now Petition His EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CELLENCY to do for this his people I Shall we petition Him, to Look with a
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:000930_0037_0FACA371F3AF2BB0"/>
Gracious, and Fatherly <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> upon our Weakneſſes? To Improve his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the Court of <hi>England,</hi> ſo that <hi>His</hi> Great Friends, may for his ſake be <hi>ours</hi>? To <hi>Defend</hi> us from Injuries, to <hi>Direct</hi> us in Difficulties, to Countenance our juſt <hi>Liberties,</hi> and the beſt Friends of them?</p>
            <p>EXCELLENT SIR, You <hi>prevent</hi> us, in all our Petitions: You <hi>Do</hi> for us, whatever we would <hi>Ask</hi> for: You leave us, nothing to Do, but to <hi>Study</hi> how we may Show <hi>all Thankfulneſs,</hi> for the <hi>Great Quietneſs</hi> we Enjoy by You, and the <hi>Worthy Deeds</hi> which are <hi>done to this Nation by your Providence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ELECTIONS, for which the <hi>Province</hi> this Day ſends in a <hi>General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly,</hi> Exemplify to us thoſe our <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> wherein God hath <hi>ſo dealt with us,</hi> as hardly <hi>with any Nation.</hi> Indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what <hi>New England</hi> had from the Beginning done, to deſerve ſingular <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,</hi> and conſidering what precious <hi>Liberties</hi> had been raviſhed from <hi>New-England,</hi> it was a fruit of the Royal <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> as well as <hi>Goodneſs</hi> in His Majeſty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Endue <hi>New England</hi> with a <hi>Charter</hi> of <hi>Liberties,</hi> above the reſt of the Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:000930_0038_0FACA372AE7ECD30"/>
We have a <hi>Royal Charter,</hi> which Effectually Secures unto us, all <hi>Christian Liberties,</hi> and all <hi>Engliſh Liberties,</hi> for which, I may ſay with the <hi>Rabbi; If the Heavens were Parchment, and the Seas were Ink, they would not ſuffice to write the Juſt Praiſes of God.</hi> We have a <hi>Royal Charter</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo Shel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ering us, That no <hi>Counſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ors,</hi> nor <hi>Judges,</hi> nor <hi>Juſtices,</hi> can hereafter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Arbitrarily Impoſed upon us. Yea, we have ſome Advantages not only above <hi>any other Nation,</hi> but alſo above any part of <hi>our own Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Syrs, I cannot more Emphatically tell you, What <hi>Praiſes</hi> are due to the God of Heaven, for theſe His <hi>Matchleſs Favours,</hi> than in thoſe words, Gal. 5 13 <hi>Brethren, ye have been called unto Liberty, only uſe not your Liberty for an occaſion to the fleſh.</hi> God forbid. That in the uſe of our <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Elections,</hi> we ſhould be acted by any <hi>Spirit,</hi> but that of Reſpect unto the <hi>Publick Welfare.</hi> I hope, we are a people of more underſtanding, than to think, That the <hi>Saving a little Money,</hi> is <hi>New-England's</hi> greateſt Intereſt. God will ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us, That this evil principle will be the <hi>Root of all Evil.</hi> And almoſt all our
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:000930_0039_0FACA37369AD24C8"/>
               <hi>Loſing,</hi> has uſually been by improper <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi> I will humbly take leave to add, Let us Beware of <hi>Narrow,</hi> and <hi>Little,</hi> &amp; <hi>Selfiſh</hi> Deſigns; Beware of unjuſt <hi>Cenſures,</hi> and <hi>Slanders,</hi> upon <hi>Perſons of Merit</hi>; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of all <hi>Self-undoing prejudices,</hi> in our <hi>Elections.</hi> And eſpecially Beware of counting thoſe perſons our <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> that are of all the moſt <hi>Able,</hi> and the moſt <hi>Willing</hi> to be our <hi>Benefactors.</hi> I am not afraid of telling You, That I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much perſwaded, the <hi>Factious Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> with which our <hi>Elections</hi> were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times managed, were not the Leaſt of thoſe <hi>Provocations,</hi> againſt which, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven teſtified by taking away our <hi>Charter</hi> from us. It is poſſible, That at this very Time, there may be peculiar cauſe for ſome caution; That our <hi>Elections</hi> may be ſo manag'd, as to demonſtrate, that we are not a <hi>Contemptible,</hi> but a <hi>Wiſe,</hi> and a <hi>Good people,</hi> and that we are <hi>not Ignorant</hi> of our true Intereſt.</p>
            <p>But You that have <hi>hitherto</hi> been the <hi>Elected</hi> RULERS of this <hi>Province,</hi> will bear with me, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> of all, I mention You, as not the <hi>Laſt,</hi> nor the <hi>Leaſt</hi> of thoſe <hi>Matchleſs Favours,</hi> which our God
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:000930_0040_0FACA375A8D1DFF8"/>
hath given us. In your <hi>Piety,</hi> in your <hi>Faithfulneſs,</hi> in your Zeal to <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Good,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have ſeen in ſome Good meaſure <hi>Judges as at the Firſt, and Counſellors as at the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</hi> If you ſhould meet with any <hi>Ostraciſms,</hi> You will reſent it no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than the Heroic <hi>Lacademonian,</hi> who rejoyced, <hi>That Sparta had ſo many men more worthy than himſelf</hi>: Tho' for my own part, I know not where we can mend our ſelves. If God continue your <hi>Opportunities,</hi> we make no Doubt, that He will continue your <hi>Inclinations</hi>: and if a Pagan <hi>Cicero,</hi> much more will a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Magistrate,</hi> Look upon his place in the Government, <hi>Velut Tutela, ad Utilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Eorum qui Commiſſi ſunt.</hi> Nor will you Lay aſide thoſe two <hi>Remembrances,</hi> wherein the Great <hi>Lord Chancellor</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> once obſerved, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he precepts for the Duties of Rulers to be ſummed up; <hi>Remember that you are Gods,</hi> and, <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that you are men.</hi> But it will remain to be wiſh'd for you, That you may be fortified with an Exemplary <hi>Patience.</hi> To contribute whereunto, I will at this Time only Remember, a memorable paſſage in the Jewiſh Records. There
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:000930_0041_0FACA375C3EA7100"/>
was a publick Officer, at whoſe Houſe many people every day <hi>gratis</hi> received Reliefs and Soccours. One Day he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Well, what do our people ſay to day?</hi> They told him, <hi>Why, the people partook of your Kindneſſes, and Services, and then they Bleſs'd you very fervently</hi> Did they ſo? Said he: <hi>Then I ſhall have no great Reward for this Day.</hi> Another Day, he asked, <hi>Well, and what ſay our people now</hi>? They told him, <hi>Alas, Good Syr, the people En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd your Kindneſſes and Services to day, and when all was done, they did nothing but Rail at you.</hi> Indeed! ſaid he; <hi>Now for this Day, I am ſure that God will give me a great and a good Reward.</hi> Much Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; May the Lord hear you joyfully going before Him with that Requeſt, Neh. 5.19. <hi>Think upon me, for Good, O my God, according to all that I have done for this people.</hi> And may you think, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the words of that Eminent perſon; who was rewarded with Baniſhment by the Ungrateful <hi>Genevians,</hi> after he had been among them, the moſt Serviceable man, that ever they ſaw, <hi>Certe ſi homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſerviviſſem, Certainly, If I had ſerv'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one but men, in what I have done, I were
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:000930_0042_0FACA3766A2C7688"/>
very ill Rewarded; but it is well, that I have Serv'd Him, who alwayes well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quites thoſe that Serve Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Enough and Enough hath now been ſaid, for to beſpeak our <hi>Hearty Praiſes</hi> unto God. If theſe <hi>Matchleſs Favours</hi> of God unto us, will not, what will beſpeak our <hi>Hearty Praiſes</hi>? Truly, ſince our God hath ſo <hi>Dealt with us,</hi> as rarely with <hi>any Nation,</hi> it becomes us, in <hi>Chooſing thoſe things that pleaſe Him,</hi> to Exceed <hi>Every Nation.</hi> Hath <hi>more</hi> been <hi>done</hi> for us, <hi>than for others</hi>? Common Ingenuity will make this Inference; Then, in all <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> and <hi>Honeſty,</hi> and in all thoſe things that may <hi>Adorn the Doctrine of God our Saviour,</hi> Let us <hi>Do more than others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, as I find both <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Auſtin,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to ſpeak, <hi>What they could not Finiſh within the ſpace of an Hour,</hi> I am ſenſible, the Occaſions before the <hi>Great and General Aſſembly</hi> this day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> do forbid me to <hi>Speak</hi> what I can't <hi>Finiſh</hi> in <hi>an Hour,</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me <hi>to Finiſh</hi> what I <hi>Speak</hi> with the <hi>Hour.</hi> My Diſcourſe is now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be concluded, Leſt you ſhould have the Inconvenience that <hi>Nazianzen</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="unknown:000930_0043_0FACA377277925F8"/>
would complain of, namely, <hi>Satiety in a Sermon.</hi> But I muſt conclude, with an earneſt proteſtation, that we are a people, under more than Ordinary Occaſions, to <hi>Tremble at that word of God</hi>: Amos 3.2. <hi>You only have I known of all the Families of the Earth: therefore I will puniſh you for all your Iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="45" facs="unknown:000930_0044_0FACA377EE103C80"/>
            <head>An Appendix. Giving a more particular Account of the Glorious and Wonderful Succeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which the Goſpel hath had in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies.</hi> [Touched in the foregoing Sermon]</head>
            <p>THE Praeſident of <hi>Harvard</hi> Colledge in <hi>New England,</hi> having written to the Learned Dr. <hi>Leusden,</hi> the Hebrew Profeſſor at <hi>Utrecht,</hi> a true and brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, of what ha's been done towards the Goſpellizing our <hi>American Indians</hi>; that Letter was publiſhed not only in the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue, wherein it was written, but alſo in the <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>High Dutch,</hi> the <hi>Hungarian,</hi> and other Tongues; and gave much ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>isfaction to the Churches of the Reformation, in many Nations.</p>
            <p>On this Occaſion, (and becauſe that Letter had requeſted ſatisfaction, in this point,) the Profeſſor of <hi>Utrecht,</hi> ha's
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:000930_0045_0FACA378AB5F12B8"/>
publiſhed an Extract of diverſe Letters from Credible and Reverend Perſons in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> relating the Succeſs of the Goſpel, with which the <hi>Dutch</hi> Proteſtant Miniſters in, thoſe remote Regions, have ſeen their Holy Labours Rewarded. A <hi>Seminary</hi> (or, Colledge) erected at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labar,</hi> for the Education of Young men, to be made <hi>Proponents,</hi> and <hi>Paſtors,</hi> is it ſeems of no little Conſequence to the Evangelical Intereſts. But more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly.</p>
            <p>D. <hi>Hermanuus Specht,</hi> Miniſter in <hi>Colombo,</hi> Writes,</p>
            <p>
               <q>In the Kingdom of <hi>Jaffanapatnam,</hi> There were found in the year, 1684. One hundred and forty one thouſand, four hundred and fifty ſix, of the Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tives, Converted unto the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. And within four years mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, there were Forty thouſand more added unto the Number.</q>
            </p>
            <p>D. <hi>Adrianus de Mey,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel, and Praeſident of the Colledge here Erected; Writes;</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Young men of <hi>Malabar,</hi> in the Colledge there Erected, are diligent, &amp; make notable progreſs in the <hi>Dutch</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="unknown:000930_0046_0FACA37969B6C1B8"/>
                  <hi>Tongue</hi>: In one years time, they Learnt to Read and Write. They know how to Pray, as the Chriſtians do: and they can recite by Heart, the Queſtions in <hi>Borſtius</hi>'s little Book, and tranſlate them out of the <hi>Dutch Tongue,</hi> into that of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labar.</hi> They alſo Sing Pſalms in our Church I hope God will beſtow His Grace upon them, and fill them with His Spirit, that ſo theſe Young men, may in Time prove bleſſed Inſtruments, to Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pagate the Kingdom of Chriſt among theſe Heathens. <hi>Jaffanapatnam, Jan.</hi> 22. 1692.</q>
            </p>
            <p>D. <hi>Franciſcus Valentinus,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Amboina,</hi> writes.</p>
            <p>
               <q>It hath pleaſed the moſt High God, to ſend me, unto the Service of the <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Churches in <hi>Amboina</hi>; in the Chief City whereof the Reverend <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius Vander Sluys</hi> of <hi>Utrecht,</hi> fed about Thirty Thouſand Souls, preaching the Word of God, with ſingular Alacrity, and invincible Labour, among the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans. God ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h given him to Convert both <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Mahometans</hi> (for here are many <hi>Mahometans,</hi>) and bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſubjection unto Chriſt, thoſe that
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:000930_0047_0FACA37A2E40AED8"/>
were miſerably periſhing in their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. An Hundred Infants at a Time are ſometimes here Baptiſed; who as they grow up, give notable proofs of their Diligence, and Ingenuity, and Piety. Religion flouriſhes here, the <hi>Colledges</hi> alſo flouriſh: God is known, and by the <hi>Pagans</hi> Worſhipp'd; and abandoning the Gods, which their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors Worſhipp'd, and taught them to do ſo, theſe once moſt Superſtitious <hi>Ambomians,</hi> not only Embrace the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the True God, but even the <hi>Mahometans</hi> alſo (which is wonderful!) deſiring to be <hi>Baptiſed,</hi> moſt gladly give themſelves up unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and obey his Laws.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amboina W. Id. Jun.</hi> 1686.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Jurieu</hi> adds hereupon, <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no noſtrorum interest, ut haec omnibus patefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, et in publicum evulgentur.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
