<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unreasonableness and danger of a peoples renouncing their subjection to God. A sermon, preached at the General Court of election, at Hartford in the colony of Connecticut on May the tenth 1711. / By Stephen Buckingham M.A. and Pastor of the church in Norwalk. ; [Text]</title>
            <author>Buckingham, Stephen, 1675-1746.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N01255</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N01255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 1495</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW8945</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">1495</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99015216</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 1495.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N01255)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 1495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 1495)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unreasonableness and danger of a peoples renouncing their subjection to God. A sermon, preached at the General Court of election, at Hartford in the colony of Connecticut on May the tenth 1711. / By Stephen Buckingham M.A. and Pastor of the church in Norwalk. ; [Text]</title>
                  <author>Buckingham, Stephen, 1675-1746.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37, [1] p. ;  15 cm. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Short, printer to the governour &amp; Company of the colony of Connecticut.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New London [Conn.] in N.E. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1711.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian ethics.</term>
               <term>Election sermons --  Connecticut --  1711.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>AEL Data (Chennai)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:001495_0000_0FB34E10A8D8E4D8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:001495_0001_0FB34E1221D05B58"/>
            <p>The Unreaſonableneſs and Danger of a Peoples renouncing their ſubjection to God.</p>
            <p>A Sermon, Preached at the General Court of Election, at Hartford in the Colony of Connecticut on May the Tenth 1711.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Stephen Buckingham</hi> M. A and Paſtor of the Church in <hi>Norwalk,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jer. 25.</bibl> 
               <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, what Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty have your Fathers found in me, that ye are gone far from me and have walked after vanity and are become vain.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>NEW LONDON</hi> in N E Printed by <hi>Thomas Short,</hi> Printer to the Governour &amp; Company of the Colony of Connecticut. 1711<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="unknown:001495_0002_0FB34E13A5F1AB38"/>
            <head>The Unreaſonableness and Danger of a Peoples Renouncing their Subjection unto GOD.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Jer. II. XXXI<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>O Generation, ſee ye the Word of the Lord: have I been a Wilderneſs unto Iſrael? a Land of darkneſs? whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>efore ſay my people, We are Lords, we will come no more unto thee?</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Lords Viſible Profeſſing people, having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een, by ſundry fore-going <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned of their horrible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and invited to Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Reformation, left they ſhould Invol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e themſelves under his heavy Judgments, but all this in great meaſure in vain, and to no purpoſe, the people being ſo greatly hardened; He do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h at laſt raiſe up this <hi>Prophet,</hi> whoſe name, as the <hi>Learned</hi> obſerve, denotes the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or the Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Lord,</hi> a name well becoming one, by whoſe Miniſtry the Lord was ſo Exalted, in many cloſe and ſharp <hi>Reproof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of ſins terrible <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciations</hi> of approaching Judgments, and alſo Divine <hi>Promiſes</hi> of Mercy, I ſay, He raiſes up this <hi>Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> not ſo much to <hi>invite</hi> thoſe hopeleſs ones to Repentance, as to <hi>Denounce</hi> the Deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="2" facs="unknown:001495_0003_0FB34E15D5422380"/>
of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the <hi>Temple,</hi> and the peoples Seventy Years Captivity in <hi>Babylon,</hi> for their Incorrigible perſiſting in their Sins. Whether this <hi>Chapter</hi> contains in it the firſt <hi>Sermon,</hi> that the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> Preached directly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this People, or not as it is not poſitively determine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, ſo neither is it Material for us to inquire, altho' it be the firſt that we have upon Record</p>
            <p>The former Chapter contains in it the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, which God gave him to this Office of a <hi>People,</hi> together with ſome neceſſary Inſtructions and Directions, in order to the right diſcharge thereof, and being ſet upon ſo great a piece of ſervice, attended with many Difficulties &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, and Weight being added to all theſe by his being <hi>Call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> to this Work in his <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d doth as there was occaſion, preſent him with ſome ſtrengthening, and ſupporting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations. The Prophet being thus called, furniſhed, and fortified to his Work, is in this Chapter manifeſtly ſet about it: which chiefly conſiſts of matters of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>icti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> laid before this people (which were viſibly Gods Profeſſing peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) of the greatneſs of their evil in departing away from God: the <hi>Unreaſonableneſs</hi> of their ſo doing he manifeſts, in that God never gave them any real Occaſion ſo to do. <hi>v</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have your Fathers found in me, that they are gone far from me, and have walked after v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> become vain?</hi> In the words now read the Lord doth return to his former <hi>Expoſtulation</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="unknown:001495_0004_0FB34E16A1924CA0"/>
with them, and therein puts them upon ſhewing, wherein<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He had by neglecting, or wronging them, laid them under any <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> or given them any <hi>Occaſion,</hi> to depart away from Him: And therein makes it evidently, and beyond all queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to appear, that if Reaſon, Experience, or Gratitude had born any ſway with them, they would not have forſaken Him In the Words we may obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Lords clearing Himſelf from blame, in what He had been to, and done for this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, propounded by way of <hi>Interrogation:</hi> Which Interrogation implies a <hi>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>errent negation,</hi> Have <hi>I been a Wilderneſs unto Iſrael?</hi> &amp;c. q. d I have not been ſo, but on the contrary, like a pleaſant fruitful Land to them</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Lords Charge drawn up againſt them by way of <hi>Expoſtulation. Wherefore ſay my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, we are Lords, we will come no more unto the?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Particularly 1. A Compellation. <hi>O Generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Their ſerious attendance to what he had to propoſe to them, Required, <hi>ſee ye the Word of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Principal thing proposed. Wherein we have</p>
            <p n="1">1 An account of the great care which the Lord had had of, and the great kindneſs He had ſhewed to them, <hi>Have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c</hi> &amp;c</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their Evil from hence argued, and aggravat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Wherefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay my people,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>O Generation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſome would have this to be a <hi>Note of Admiration,</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:001495_0005_0FB34E18E12EEB38"/>
               <hi>Exclamation,</hi> and Read it thus, <hi>Oh Generation!</hi> or Oh what a ſtrange Generation is this, into what Times are we fallen! But it rather ſeems to be a <hi>Note of Compellatic</hi> calling upon and inviting the People then living, ſeriouſly to conſider what he was now about to deliver to them, preſſing that upon them now, which he had upon their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. v. 5. <hi>See ye the Word of the Lord.</hi> i. e. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſider it To ſee, the Word is a Phraſe not much unlike to the <hi>Hearing the Rod,</hi> MIc 6: 9. For the heart hath an <hi>Eye</hi> to ſee the one, as well as an <hi>Ear</hi> to hear the other, there is an <hi>Inward,</hi> as well as an <hi>Outward</hi> Eye <hi>Dent.</hi> 29, 2, 3, 4. <hi>And Moſes called unto all Iſrael and ſaid unto them, ye have ſeen all that the Lord did before your Eyes in the Land of Egypt unto Pharaoh and unto all his Servants and unto all his land; The great Temptations which thine Eyes have ſeen, the ſigns, and thoſe great Miracles: Yet the Lord hath not given you an heart to perceive, and Eyes to ſee, and Ears to hear, unto this day</hi> Pro. 20. 11. <hi>The hearing Ear, and the ſeeing Eye, the Lord hath made even both of them. Have I been a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto Iſrael? Iſrael</hi> was a Name firſtly given unto <hi>Jacob</hi> on occaſion of his wreſtling, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing for a Bleſſing <hi>Gen</hi> 32. 28. <hi>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſaid, thy Name ſhall be called no, more Jacob, but Iſrael: for as a Prince thou hast power with God, and with Men, and hast Prevailed.</hi> From hence his Poſterity were called <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l;</hi> of them conſiſted the <hi>Viſible</hi> Church of God, until the coming of Chriſt <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76. I. <hi>In Iudah God is known, his Name is great in
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:001495_0006_0FB34E1A6121B850"/>
Iſrael.</hi> And from thence the Holy Ghoſt hath ſeen meet to make it a name of the whole <hi>Invi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Catholick</hi> Church, <hi>Col,</hi> 6. 16. <hi>And as many as walk according to this Rule, peace be on them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mercy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and upon the Iſrael of God. Have I been a Wilderneſs</hi> ? Have I held My People to hard fare, as Cattle that are kept on ſome barren Heath? Have My People ſerved Me and Reaped no Fruit thereby, as if they had tilled a Barren piece of Land? Have I not rather bleſſed them, and abundantly Rewarded them, while they were Loyal and Faithful to Me? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Your wants were not ſuch, while you kept cloſe to Me, as to enforce you to leave Me, and to look out for new Quarters. <hi>A Land of Darkneſs?</hi> A Land of extream miſery; Darkneſs is ſometimes put for miſery, <hi>Lam.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 2. <hi>He hath led one, and brought me into darkneſs but not into Light.</hi> A lateward Land, that is very ſlow in yielding fruit; Have I not been bountiful and forward in doing you good? <hi>Wherefore ſay my People</hi>  
               <hi>Say,</hi> Why do they entertain ſuch Thoughts? as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. I. <hi>We are Lords,</hi> We have gotten that ſtrength that we have no more need of thy ſupport. <hi>We will come no more unto thee?</hi> We will be ruled no longer by Thee, q. d. We will caſt off dependance upon, and Renounce Obedience to God.</p>
            <p>DOCT. <hi>That when the Lord, Viſible profeſſing peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, under the deepeſt Bonds, and Obligations revolt from, and renounce Obedience unto Him, it is moſt unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in them, and highly provoking unto Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="unknown:001495_0007_0FB34E1C2F1D9988"/>
This was a people highly favoured by the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He calls them His People, and He had done very much for them, yea ſo much as that He might ſay, <hi>what could have been done more?</hi> He <hi>drew them with the Cords of a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> and <hi>with Bands of lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Now by how much the more kind, and obliging He had been unto them; ſo much the more unreaſonable muſt their revolt from God be, and conſequently very provoking unto God. <hi>Jer</hi> 8. 5. <hi>Why then is this people of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> back, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perpetual back ſlidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi> This Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains many things in it, which for brevity ſake may be comprehended in theſe two Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>PROP I. <hi>That the Lords Viſible profeſſing people, under the deepeſt Bonds and Obligations, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> liable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt from and renounce Obedience to Him. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>PROP. II. <hi>That when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that ſuch a people do revolt from the God of their Mercies, and renounce Obedience to Him; it is moſt unreaſonable in them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> highly provoking to Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PROP. I. <hi>That the Lords Viſible profeſſing people, under the deepeſt Bonds &amp; Obligations, are liable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt from and renounce Obedience to Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What an undeniable inſtance have we of this in our Context <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. <hi>Thus faith the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, what in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quity have your Fathers found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that they are gone far from me, and have walked after vanity, and are become vain? Neither ſaid they, where is the Lord this bro't us up out of the land of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that led us through the Wilderneſs &amp;c</hi> Yea the Truth of this Truth may be undeniably argued from the many,
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:001495_0008_0FB34E1EE210BFB8"/>
and ſolemn cautions, which the Lord gave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old againſt their ſo doing, when they came to their fulneſs and grandure in the land of Canaan, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 12. <hi>Then beware leaſt thou forget the Lord, which bro't thee forth out of Egypt, from the houſe of Bondage.</hi> And again, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8, 10, 11. <hi>When thou haſt eaten, and art full, then thou ſhalt bleſs the Lord thy God, for the good land which he hath given thee, beware that thou forget not the Lord thy God, in not keeping his Commandments, and his Judgments, &amp; his Statutes, which I command thee this day.</hi> And yet ſo it was, that notwithſtanding all theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they forgat, and carried it very undutifully and ungratefully to the God of their Mercys. Some of the great things which the Lord did for them, which if rightly conſidered were very binding and obliging, together with the great abuſe of thoſe mercies, which they were guilty of, we have an account of <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>He found him in a deſert land, and in the waſte bowling Wilderneſs: He led him about, He inſtructed him, he kept him as the apple of his eye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As an Eagle ſtirreth up her neſt, fluttereth over her young, ſpreadeth abroad her Wings, taketh them, bareth them on her Wings; So the Lord alone did lead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and there was no ſtrange God with him. He made him ride on the high Places of the Earth, that he might eat the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and he made him to ſuck honey out of the Rock, and oyl out of the flinty Rock<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Butter of kine</hi> &amp;c <hi>But Jeſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>un waxed fat and kicked: Thou art waxen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at, thou art covered with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:001495_0009_0FB34E2068902BA8"/>
ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d which made him, and lightly eſteemed the rock of his Salvation.</hi> Thus the Lord had led them, &amp; ſed them, he had skilfully guided them, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guarded them; and after many trials and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties bro't them to a comfortable ſettlement; and yet we ſee, what ill requital He met with from them. When <hi>Jeſhurun</hi> was by the doles of Divine bounty <hi>Waxen fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he in a Beaſt like or worſe manner <hi>kicked,</hi> grew maſterleſs, and <hi>forſook</hi> the <hi>God that made him, and lightly eſteemed the Rock <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his Salvation.</hi> God was of no account with him: a proſperous is a dangerous Condition: and a People bro't into it, are ſet in ſlippery places from whence too often they ſlide away from God, and are caſt down into deſtruction, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 22. <hi>And the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſperity of Fools ſhall deſtroy them</hi> If it be here asked whence it is that the Lords viſible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing people under the Bonds of deepeſt obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, are liable to revolt from, and renounce Obedience unto God? I anſwer</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe <hi>all that are the Lords viſible profeſſing people, are not really what they profeſs themſelves to be.</hi> Rom. 9. 6. <hi>For they are not all Iſrael which are of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> There are many that have the name of God called upon them, who do not as in Duty bound depart from iniquity: among the many that have a name to live, there are but compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively a few, that are alive: Many for ſome low and Siniſter ends liſt themſelves in Chriſts ſervice, who are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et are far from being cordial to him; and from hence <hi>after the hardneſs</hi> and <hi>Imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="unknown:001495_0010_0FB34E21E36D9C50"/>
of their <hi>hearts, Treaſure up to themſelves wrath againſt the day of wrath, and the Revelation of the Righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Judgments of God; not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ing that 'the goodneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God leadeth them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Becauſe <hi>Thoſe who are truly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are but in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> There is a body of ſin dwelling in them, which will not be wholly rooted out of them; during their ſtate of imperfection The great Apoſtle, who had truth of, and a great meaſure of Grace, yet declares that of himſelf, which truly gracious ones may ſeal to themſelves, <hi>Rom</hi> 72<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſee another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in my Memb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, warring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the law of my mind, and bringing me into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the law of ſin, which is in my members</hi> From hence it is that we read of <hi>David, Peter,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that had deſervedly the characters of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, that yet were left to grievous falls. Thus we ſee the firſt Propoſition made good, which affores ſolemn warning to all Profeſſors of their danger, and to adviſe them to bear in mind that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>fore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et him that thinketh be ſtandeth take heed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be faſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PROP 11 <hi>That when it is ſo, that the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible profeſſing people, under the Bonds of deeped <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions revolt from, and renounce Obedience unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; it is moſt unreaſonable in them; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to him</hi> When becauſe the Lord dea's <hi>Well</hi> with a people the, deal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with Him, ſee how the Lord upbraid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> People with their ill requiting Him, <hi>Deut</hi> 32 6. <hi>Do you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> people, and unwiſe? Is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t be thy Father, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="unknown:001495_0011_0FB34E23DA989FD0"/>
bought thee? hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e not made thee, and eſtabliſhed thee?</hi> It is a moſt unreaſonable thing, it would better become Unreaſonable than Reaſonable Creatures, Yea it is in ſome reſpects to act be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low unreaſonable Creatures, for they do in their way, and according to their capacity, pay ſome kind of acknowledgements and reſpects to their benefactors, <hi>Iſa.</hi> I. 3. <hi>The Ox knoweth his owner, and the Aſs his Maſters Crib: But Iſrael doth not know, my people doth not conſider,</hi> That thus to do is very unreaſonable, on the part of the Lords profeſſing people, and likewiſe very provoking unto God, will appear from theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Reaſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>I. Becauſe the <hi>Revolting</hi> of ſuch a people <hi>muſt needs be ſpontantous and very willful.</hi> This is laid to their charge in the context, <hi>v</hi> 25. <hi>With h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld thy foot from being unſhod, &amp; thy throat from thirſt: but thou ſaidſt, there is no hope. No, for I have loved ſtrangers and after them will I go.</hi> It could not be, becauſe the Lord had been harſh and ſevere to them, and ſo had laid them under Neceſſity to revolt from Him; there was no ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity to be found in God ſee <hi>v.</hi> 5. of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text God did not begin to for ſake them. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50. 1. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, where is the bill of your Mothers divorcement, whom I have put away?</hi> A Woman that deſerted her Husband, and had not a bill of Divorcement under his hand, was to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the peccant party, ſo ſaith the Lord, if I have laid you under any neceſſity to forſake Me, bring forth the evidence; if I have put you away, then
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:001495_0012_0FB34E24E15AE508"/>
ſhew the Bill of Divorce. Moreover it could not be from Ignorance, becauſe this was a place of great light, it was a place where God had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded His name, unto whom He had given good ſtatutes and right Judgments, He had unto this People above any other ſhewed what was right<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 147. 19, 20. <hi>He ſhoweth his word unto Jacob, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and his judgments unto Iſrael. He hath not dealt ſo with any Nation and for his judgments; they have not known them.</hi> They were compar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with other Nations, as ſitting in <hi>Gothen,</hi> and the reſt groping in the dark. Now if the revolt of ſuch a People be neither of neceſſity, nor Ignorance, then it muſt needs be Spontanious, and wilful, &amp; ſo very unreaſonable, and highly provoking.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Reaſ. Becauſe this <hi>is to deal very ungratefully with God.</hi> Ingratitude is condemned by the light of Nature, the very Heathen have look't upon it as a grievous ſin, yea as the Mother of many other ſins; and much more is it Condemned by God, who has joyned the <hi>Unthankful,</hi> and <hi>Unholy</hi> together, 2 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Unthankfulneſs</hi> was one of the ſins mentioned, <hi>Rom</hi> 1. 21. For the ſake of which, God was provoked <hi>to give them up to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e mind, and vile affections.</hi> To requite <hi>Evil for Evil</hi> is very ſinful: But to requite <hi>Evil for Good</hi> Oh how hainous! The Lord may in a Wrathful way ſay to ſuch a People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om</hi> ſaid to <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Sam</hi> 16. 17. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> friend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Such a people for whom the Lord hath done ſo much, are under greater and ſtronger Bonds to
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:001495_0013_0FB34E278EF33D70"/>
walk with and obey God, than any others, Yea, ſuch bonds one would think Holy Ingenuity would feel, and be Commanded by, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32 6. God had cared for them as a tender hearted Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, He had bought them with a great price, He had <hi>given men for them, and people for their life,</hi> He had well formed them, both as to Civils and Eccleſiaſticals. This People were riſen higher in their Profeſſion, and raiſed higher in their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, than the reſt of the Nations, a People therefore, from whom the Lord might claim great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Loyalty, than from any others What Prodigious Ingratitude muſt it needs be for ſuch a people to be diſloyal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch a people for whom the Lord had done ſo much, to lay aſide all holy Ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to caſt off all bonds of Love, &amp; to bring forth the <hi>Chapes</hi> of <hi>Sodom</hi> and the <hi>Cluſters of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah,</hi> is very unreaſonable, and alſo provoking, <hi>Iſa,</hi> I. 21. <hi>How is the faithful City become an Harlo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? it was full of Judgment, Righteouſneſs lodged in it; but now Murderes.</hi> Amos 3. 2. <hi>You only have I known of all the Families of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore I will puniſh you for all your Iniquities.</hi> To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight againſt God with ſuch Weapons given for no ſuch end, is for ſuch a people to ſhew themſelves worſe than the very <hi>Publican<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> of whom we find it Recorded, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> 5 46. That they <hi>love them that love</hi> them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reaſ. Becauſe thus to do is for <hi>a people to run a bead of their own Experience and to give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and feeling the lie.</hi> Paſt experiences may rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be expected, to afford preſent counſel: and
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:001495_0014_0FB34E28A26F5690"/>
ſo to be improved by Men, who are capable of being guided by reaſon, &amp; much more by Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now there never was a profeſſing people taken near to God, but he gave them ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the Good of keeping cloſe to him: He has very liberally, and richly rewarded them, they have been no looſers while they have been faithful to God; He has given them to ſee, that His ſervice is the moſt profitable, and occaſion to ſay, when they have revolted from Him as <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2. 7. <hi>I will go and return to my firſt husband, for then was it better with me than now.</hi> God remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and expects that His People ſhould not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the kindneſs that he ſhews to them, while they walk with Him. vid, <hi>Context. v.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, I remember thee, the kindneſs of thy Youth, the lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of thine eſpouſals, when thou wenteſt after me in the Wilderneſs; in a land that was not ſown. Iſrael was holineſs unto the Lord, and the firſt Fruits of his Increaſe: all that devour him, ſhall offend: Evil ſhall come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith the Lord.</hi> In a Word God was with them, while they were with Him, ſo that their own experience might teach them other and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than to revolt from God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Reaſ. Becauſe ſuch a People in ſo doing are <hi>ſadly regardleſs of their own Interſt.</hi> It is a part of the Covenant which God hath made with His People, and which He <hi>will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> alter or break,</hi> that if they do tranſgreſs. He will Chaſtiſe, that He <hi>will viſit their tranſgreſſions with the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, and their Iniquities with ſtripes,</hi> Pſal. 89 32. And when
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:001495_0015_0FB34E2A2092EDA0"/>
once the Lords Profeſſing people revolt from Him, it is not long before He takes His Rod into His hand. Now for a people to revolt, while Divine Judgments are hanging over their heads, and fairly within their view, is very unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and to be more brutal, than the Feaſts, who are not eaſily driven into Places, where danger is ſeen, <hi>Balaams Aſs</hi> would not go forward, when ſhe ſaw the <hi>Angel</hi> ſtand in the way with a <hi>drawn Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many hardſhips, and ſorrows do a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing people expoſe themſelves unto, while they forſake God, vid context, <hi>v.</hi> 25. <hi>Withold thy Foot from being unſhod, and thy Threat from thirſt: but thou ſaidst, there is no hope,</hi> q. d Do you not ſee, how that by departing from Me You do for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake Your own Mercies, croſs and oppoſe Your own Intereſt? How greatly are You Impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by it? Did You while You were Loyal to me, want Shoos for Your Feet, and Water to quench Your Thirſt? &amp; now how do You groan for the want of what You then had? Oh how unnaturally cruel to themſelves are a revolting people and even contrary to nature hating their own fleſh!</p>
            <p n="5">5 Reaſon, Becauſe thus to do is an argument that <hi>They do not ſuitably improve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Inſtructions, which from the harms of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> has have been offered unto them.</hi> Is it not <hi>highly</hi> Irrational for any Man to <hi>go</hi> on in ſuch a way, which to his own obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on has been fatal to others. It was an <hi>aggravat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="unknown:001495_0016_0FB34E2D2174E548"/>
of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e'ſhazzars</hi> ſin in that he had had a proſpect of his Fathers Puniſhment, by which he migh have been warned, and yet he made no good improvement of it, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. 22. <hi>And thou his ſon, O B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſhazzar, hast not humbled thine heart, tho' thou kneweſt all this;</hi> tho' thou kneweſt that pride was the overthrow, and downfal of thy predeceſſor, yet thou waſt not humbled Oh the harms of others will (if rightly improved) make thoſe who are obſervers thereof, cautious.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Reaſon, <hi>Becauſe a profeſſing people in thus doing, Croſsite Lord, what in them lies, of his reaſonable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation.</hi> Where much is given anſwerable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns may reaſonably be expected: Hence the Lord to ſpeak after the manner of Men promiſes to himſelf more, and better from a people for whom he has done more and greater things than for others, <hi>Iſa</hi> 41. 21. <hi>This people have I formed for my ſelf, they ſhall ſhew forth my praiſe.</hi> The Lord doth, and reaſonably may expect, that his people ſhould be ſuch as will not lye, and he falſe to him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63 8. <hi>For he ſaid, ſurely they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> children that will not lie: ſo he was their Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 Reaſon, <hi>Becauſe thus to do is to deal worſe by a good God, than the beathen do by their dumb Idols</hi> As it is an argument of their folly, to truſt in them, which are but <hi>the works of mens hands, they have mouths but they ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, yes have they but they ſee n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Pſal 115. 4, 5, 6, 7. ſo this their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>fide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce in &amp; lovalty to their Idols reproves a Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſſing peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for their revolt from the true God Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="unknown:001495_0017_0FB34E2E9FB1B178"/>
the Context, <hi>v</hi> 11, 12, 13. <hi>Hath a Nation changed their gods, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> no gods? but my people have chang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> glory, for that which doth not profit.</hi> To change a Fountain for a Fountain, may not ſome times be diſadvantagious: but to change a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain for a Ciſtern, Oh how unreaſonable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> A profeſſing people are highly unreaſonable in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting from the true and living God, when the Heathen clave to their Idols which will appear from theſe Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Heathens Gods are <hi>Impotent,</hi> &amp; unable to afford help to them They can neither do <hi>Good nor Evil,</hi> they can neither <hi>Comfort nor Afflict, Iſa</hi> 41. 23. Hence the Heathen have no real occaſion, either to love them, or to be affraid of them. But the true God can do every thing: His hand is under no other limitation but his own <hi>Job</hi> 42. 2. <hi>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that thou canſt do every thing.</hi> He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n do good and he can do evil, i. e. Afflictive evil, <hi>Iſa</hi> 45. 7. <hi>I form the Light, and create dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: I make peace, and create evil: I the Lord do all theſe things</hi> Now ſeeing the Heathen do not part with their Gods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who they think can, tho' indeed they cannot help them, a profeſſing peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt needs be very unreaſonable in revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from God <hi>All ſufficient</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Heathens gods are <hi>dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> but the true God is abſolutely <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endent</hi> They neither have their beings of themſelves nor can they up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their own beings: But the true God hath his being of himſelf, and by himſelf doth ſuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in his own being</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="17" facs="unknown:001495_0018_0FB34E30204D7090"/>
3. The Heathen have not experienced any thing from their gods, that might oblidge them unto them, but a profeſſing People have had manifold obligations laid upon them by the true God, even their and Gods <hi>Enemies being judges.</hi> Pſal. 126. 2, 3. <hi>Then ſaid they among the Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n, the Lord hath done great things for them.</hi> Deut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1. <hi>For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir Rock is not as our Rock, even our enemies them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves being judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Reaſon <hi>Becauſe ſuch a people are Gods People, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in the</hi> Text <hi>wherefore ſay my People:</hi> They are Gods people not only by <hi>Crea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> but alſo by <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nant,</hi> hence for them to make alienation of <hi>themſelves</hi> from God and to revolt from God muſt be to rob God of his due.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Reaſon, <hi>Becauſe the Revelting of ſuch a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from God caſts in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olerable reflexion upon G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</hi> It is practically to ſay, that they had found iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in God; it is to charge him with being an hard Maſter; Yea, that he had been to them, what a Wilderneſs is to them that dwell therein. The Language of their forſaking, God is that he had by the ſtraits that they were bro't into neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated them to look out for ſome better quarters. What Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>exion of impotency and Weakneſs, or unfaithfulneſs may be expected to be caſt upon God by the World, when a profeſſing People depart away from him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>USE</hi> Having confirmed the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> I would proceed as the time, and particular occaſions of
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:001495_0019_0FB34E31AFBEEE50"/>
this day will allow, to make ſome <hi>Improvement</hi> of it, which may be principally by way of <hi>Reflexion</hi> upon our ſelves</p>
            <p>Whether we in theſe parts of the World have not reaſon to look upon our ſelves a people ſo circumſtanced, as that the Truth we have now heard, affords us a Glaſs, wherein we may ſee the merciful obliging bonds we have been under unto God, and at the ſame time, how unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able we have been in revolting from, &amp; renounc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedience to God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Have we not been laid under the Bonds of deepeſt obligations? has not the Lord been far from being a Wilderneſs, or a land of darkneſs to us?</hi> So that we have had reaſon in ſome meaſure, from what the Lord has done for us, to ſeal to what is ſaid <hi>Deut.</hi> 23 29 <hi>Happy art thou O Iſrael: who is like unto thee, O people ſaved by the Lord, the ſhield of thy help, and who is the ſword of thy excellency!</hi> There hath been a time when we were in a Wilderneſs, and the Lord was not a Wilderneſs to us. What our own eyes have ſeen, and our Fathers alſo have told us, ſhew<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that we have been greatly favoured by the Lord, ſo that it may be ſaid to u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to <hi>New England,</hi> to <hi>Connecticut,</hi> to this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at <hi>Aſſembly</hi> containing as much of it, as may be expected to be ſpoken to at once, <hi>See ye the word of the Lord.</hi> The Lord has not in that reſpect put us off with Words which we can only hear, and ought to believe, but he has made his words to be things, ſuch as we might ſee, yea and others alſo might ſee;
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:001495_0020_0FB34E33201B5470"/>
God hath not only <hi>ſet New-England as a ſeal upon his Heart, but as a ſeal upon his Arm;</hi> There have been practical, viſible Teſtimonies of his love to this Wilderneſs; Yea the time hath been, that the Heathen could ſay, that the Lord was with us, and that he had done great things for us; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126 2. <hi>Then ſaid they among the heathen, the Lord hath done great things for them</hi> Oh they were good times with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when their enemies could ſee, that the Lord was among them, <hi>Num.</hi> 23. 21<hi>The Lord his God is with him, and the ſhout of a King is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The time was (and it may be for a Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we are ſo much forced to ſay, it was!) that God was with us; It is ſeldom to be found that a people have had more clear and uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted experience of Divine bounty, that <hi>New-England</hi> has had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore ſuffer me to make uſe of what <hi>Samuel</hi> once ſaid to the General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of <hi>Iſrael</hi> with particular application to this Great and Honourable Aſſembly 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 7. <hi>Now therefore ſtand ſtill, that I may reaſon with you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, of all the righteous acts of the Lord, which be did to you and to your fathers.</hi> I have ſtudied bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and may not here enlarge, but only hint at things briefly.</p>
            <p n="1">1 How wonderfully did the Lord appear for the firſt Settlement of this land, when our Fathers followed God into this Wilderneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Lord did as it were gather<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a nation out of the midſt of a Nation, and ſpirit them upon a Religious
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:001495_0021_0FB34E34AEFA5A18"/>
account, to follow the Lord into a land not ſown, ſo that what is ſaid in the <hi>Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> may be in ſome reſpect applied for the Lords Juſtification and our Humiliation <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>Yet I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lanted thee a noble Vine, wholly a right ſeed: how then art thou turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the degenerate pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt of a ſtran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Vine unto me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, it may not be forgotten, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Settlement, of this Land had <hi>be Royal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The Kings heart is in the hand of the Lord,</hi> And he was pleaſed to turn it toward this Good deſign; when <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a chap.</hi> 6 <hi>v.</hi> 22 had obtained the Royal favour for carrying on the building of the Houſe of the Lord, they do joyfully acknowledge it to be the work of the Lord <hi>For the Lord had made them joyful, and turned the heart of the King of Aſſyria unto them; to ſtrengthen their hands in the work of the Houſe of God the God of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. How has the Lord taken the part, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared on the behalf of His People againſt thoſe who ſought our Ruine? How were thoſe who attempted to devour us, look'd upon and dealt with by Heaven as offenders, and how did evil come upon them! How early did the Devil ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate his vaſſals the Heathen to make inrode upon this Land with Malice, Murder, and Cruelty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet how manifeſtly did Gods Hand appear againſt them and <hi>made room</hi> for his People? <hi>How could one</hi> as it were <hi>chaſe a Thouſand and two put Ten Thouſand to flight?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, how many endeavours have there been at home, and abroad to diſturb our quiet
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:001495_0022_0FB34E3625003E88"/>
Settlement, and yet thoſe <hi>Counſels</hi> have been <hi>turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fooliſhneſs,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Weapons form'd against</hi> us, have not <hi>Proſpered.</hi> And altho' God has many ways, and many times ſorely chaſtned us; Yet he hath <hi>ſtay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d his rough wind in the day of his Eaſt wind,</hi> ſo that God has not <hi>been a Wilderneſs</hi> to us, by laying us open without being our Protection.</p>
            <p n="3">3 How has the Lord been far from being <hi>a land of darkneſs</hi> to us, in that there have been, and ſtill are <hi>Nurſeries of Learning, and Piety</hi> amongſt us. What a <hi>land of darkneſs</hi> would this otherwiſe have been? From thoſe wholſom Fountains how many <hi>Streams</hi> have Iſſued forth to <hi>make glad the Cities of our God?</hi> The Lord may in this reſpect appeal to us, as in <hi>Amos</hi> 2. 11. <hi>And I raiſed up of your ſons for Prophets, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Young Men for Nazarites Is it not even thus, O ye Children of Iſrael? ſaith the Lord.</hi> Yea how may we not only ſee the Churches of our Land Illuminated by hopeful Perſons thus Trained up among ourſelves; But alſo the Seats of our Civil Government, and places of Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance filling up with Perſons of Worth, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their other good Accompliſhments have the additions of a Liberal Education?</p>
            <p>And here we may not in ſilence paſs over the <hi>Tokens for good</hi> in this Colony in that ſome Pious and well diſpoſed perſons have moved for &amp; have had the Approbation, Countenance and Support of this Government, in order to the obtaining a School of the Prophets among us, the flouriſhing of which (as it hath not for the Time been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful)
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:001495_0023_0FB34E37A150D6D0"/>
we hope will not only encourage the Publick (whoſe advantage is Principally aimed at therein) to continue their ſupport: But alſo Particular Perſons of Ability to follow the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of ſome, who already by their Liberal Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations have done Worthily for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Foundation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What ſmiles of Providential encouragements hath this Land been favoured with? Altho' it cannot be denied, but that there have been days wherein God hath Afflicted us, and Years where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have ſeen evil; Yet what great mixtures of mercies have we had? The Peace we have had when ſurrounded with the Heathen, Health and Plentiful Proviſion in a Wilderneſs are mercies not to be forgotten For how long a Time were our fields unacquainted with <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,</hi> &amp; the Trees ſtrangers to devouring Worms, and our Plantations to many Diſeaſes which now are come among us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that the Inquiry may be made <hi>Joel</hi> 1. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Hear this, ye old men, and give ear, all ye the Inhabitants of the land: hath this been in your days?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. And above all, how has the time been, that we have had the glory of God in the midſt of us, His preſence in, and with his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances? How has there been to be ſeen <hi>the goings of our God and King in his Sanctuary,</hi> ſo that there was Reaſon rejoycingly to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay of our Zions, <hi>this and that man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as born in
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:001495_0024_0FB34E395E537D20"/>
them?</hi> How did God own his own Ordinances, to the convincing and converting, of Sinners the edifying and building up of Saints? How many were there that did <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as a Cloud, and as the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ves to their windows?</hi> ſo that that eminent Servant of God who Preached on this occaſion many years ſince<note n="*" place="bottom">ſee Mr <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s Election <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> reflecting on the firſt glory of <hi>New England,</hi> had ſuch expreſſions as theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Multitudes were converted to thee, even to thee O H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ford, to thee O New Haven, &amp; to thee O Windſor, and the like might be ſaid of many of the Churches in New England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely theſe things being ſeriouſly thought of, may be ſufficient to convince us that we are the People that have been under the bonds of deepeſt obligations. We proceed to inquire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>II <hi>Whether the Lords way to us be as it hath been?</hi> We have indeed great reaſon to bleſs God, that things are ſo well with us as they are, that forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and undeſerved Mercies are ſo plentifully heaped upon us; But yet how often, how many ways, and for how long a Time, has the Lord born aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul Teſtimony againſt us, and loudly proclaimed that he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> controverſie with us; and if God be with us as formerly, why are we thus? Has not the Lord been Teſtifying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us by the Sword of a Cruel and Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, Enemy unto the Diminiſhing and greatly Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhing of us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wnin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon our M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:001495_0025_0FB34E3AA1ADB058"/>
enterpriſes <hi>ſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to cauſe our enemy</hi> to laugh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves; by amazing Droughts ſo as to make it a time of great diſtreſs; by <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſtings, Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpilars;</hi> &amp; more lately by unuſual <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Fruits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the field?</hi> And what can be the reaſon of all this? Truly it would be for us to flatter our ſelves and to ſhut our Eyes againſt the Light, if we do not conclude that it is our revolting from God, that doth lie at the bottom of all this, according to our <hi>Context v.</hi> 17. <hi>Hast thou not procured this unto thy ſelf, in that thou haſt forſaken the Lord thy God, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thee by the war?</hi> While we duty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully owned God to be our Leader, he did not fail to be our protector If we had been true to God, and had not <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed</hi> to him, can it be ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he would have become our enemy, and ſo many ways have fought againſt us? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſaid ſurely they are my people, Children that will not lie: ſo he was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir Saviour. But they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled, and vexed his holy Spirit: Therefore he was turned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> enemy, and he fought againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Things being thus, is it not high time for us to be Redecting upon our Revolt from God, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve we not too much practically ſaid, <hi>we are Lords we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> time been when New Englands walk was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> than it is?</hi> I do not here ſpeak any thing that is liable to Controverſy or Diſpute; But purely of the beautie of Holineſs. Are the Commands of God ſo weighty with us as they have been heretofore? are the Ordinances
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:001495_0026_0FB34E3D1B840970"/>
of God of that eſteem as they have been? Is there now ſo much of the Fear of God, ſo much zeal for God, ſo much Righteouſneſs among men, as always is needful, and as ſometimes hath been viſible among us? What coldneſs and remiſſneſs is there to be found in Religious concerns? what neglect of Family Inſtruction and Government? Is o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r way and Walk ſo becoming &amp; adorning the Goſpel, as our Predeceſſors? We are, it may be, too ready to find fault with ſome things that they did; but it were well, if we were not in many more things to blame— <hi>Truly,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If our pious Predeceſſors ſhould come from the Dead, how juſtly and greatly would they blame our revolt from God? Might they not ſharply ſay to us, <hi>Is this according to thee good Counſels and Inſtructions we have given You, and the good examples we have ſet before You? When did you ſee us make ſo light a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>matter of Prophaning the Name or day of God? Were we ever ſo Wordly, ſo voluptuous<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo regardleſs, of our duty to God and Man? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Is our Poſterity come to this! Aſſuredly our ſins muſt needs be greatly aggravated in turning quickly out of the good ways, which our Fathers walked in,</hi> Judg. 217. <hi>They turned quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the way, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Fathers walked in, obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Commandments of the Lord; but they did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are we not become greatly degenerate? look we into Hearts, Families, Plantations, the Land, and think what hath been, and what is? are not our Hearts more Carnal, and our ways more Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive than formerly <hi>Particularly,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="26" facs="unknown:001495_0027_0FB34E3E628BC7D0"/>
1 <hi>Is there not among is a great neglect of Chriſt, the Goſpel and Goſpel Ordinances?</hi> The Tender of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſpel to the World is the greateſt tender, that ever God made: hence he is called <hi>the gift of God</hi> Joh 4 10 Now in the Goſpel and Goſpel Ordinances there is the moſt clear, plain and affectionate Tender of him It is there that he ſtands, and cries Himſelf unto poor Sinners <hi>John</hi> 7. 37. <hi>Jeſus ſtood and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of any Man thirſt, let him come unto me, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drink.</hi> There he ſtands <hi>Beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eching</hi> poor Sinners to be <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ciled to God,</hi> 2 <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi> 5. 20. There he <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>and &amp; kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of poor Sinners h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arts,</hi> uſing the moſt powerful Arguments, and offering the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Encouragements unto them to <hi>open to him, Rev.</hi> 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. Yea there it is, that he preſents poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with a lively proſpect of his direfull Paſſion, thereby to perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vade them to open unto him, <hi>Cant</hi> 5 2 <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, my Siſter, my Love, my Dove, my undefiled: For my head is filled with dew, and my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> There he proclaims himſelf every way able to afford help and relief to poor periſhing Sinners, that he has <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to cloath thoſe that are naked, <hi>Gold</hi> to enrich thoſe that are poor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye ſolve</hi> to make thoſe that are born blind to ſee: And that all this with whatſoever they ſtand in need of he ſtands ready to beſtow upon thoſe that will accept of it, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Terms ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are very agreeable to their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, <abbr>
                  <hi>viz.</hi>
               </abbr> moſt <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, John</hi> 6 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m that cometh to me, I will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> Rev 22. 17.<hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="unknown:001495_0028_0FB34E3FE3747E08"/>
And the Spirit and the Bride ſay come, and let him that heareth ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> come. And let him that is a thirſt, come: And whoſoever will, let him take the water of Life freely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the neglecting, diſregarding, &amp; under valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e offers muſt needs be very provoking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 37, 38. <hi>How often would I have gathered thy Children together, even as a hen gathereth her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> under her Wings, and ye would not! Behold your hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is left unto you deſolate.</hi> Heb. 2. 3. <hi>How ſhall we eſcape, if we neglect ſo great ſalvation?</hi> How is the deareſt love of God the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt trampled upon by Goſpel neglecters, and the alone Remedy refuſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And is there not a great deal of this to be found among us, and is not this that which lies at the bottom and is the very Fountain of the reſt of our ſins and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eries? If the greateſt love be ſlighted greateſt Grace rejected, what but proportionable Wrath may be expected? And ſurely the Lord hath a great Controverſie with us on this account<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wounds God more, than a regardleſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Goſpel; <hi>Will not God viſit for theſe things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what abundance of evidence can there be brought in againſt us on this account? The Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Goſpel which we have been ſo long favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, beings in plentiful evidence againſt us, and we may hear it <hi>plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing againſt us, Where is the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, which I have ſo plainly revealed, ſo freely offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo ſtrictly Commanded you to receive, ſo earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeched
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:001495_0029_0FB34E4171DAF468"/>
you to give Entertainment to?</hi> Where is the prizing of the <hi>Pearl of great price?</hi> Where is there a deſire of him, <hi>that is deſirable for all N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover the Miniſters of the Goſpel have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant reaſon to renew that Ancient Complaint, <hi>We have laboured in vain, who hath believed our Report?</hi> When poor Sinners have been <hi>Piped unto,</hi> they have <hi>not danced;</hi> When they have been <hi>Mourned</hi> over, they have <hi>not lamented.</hi> How much cauſe have they had to fear, that much of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial labour has been in vain? Yea the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of Sinners do Teſtifie againſt them for their <hi>Goſpel neglects,</hi> and aſſure them, that often when Chriſt ſpeaks they ſtop their Ears, when the Spirit ſtrives they quench its motions; And are <hi>like the deaf Adder that ſtoppeth her ear: Which will not hearken to the voice of Charmers Charming <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ever ſo wiſely</hi> Pſal. 58. 4, 5. Aſſuredly Goſpel Sinners are the greateſt Sinners, and will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>y be found to be the moſt inexcuſable. It will be more Tolerable for the blind Heathen in the lay of the Lords Vengeance than for them <hi>Job.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 22 <hi>If I had not come, and ſpoken unto them, they had not had ſin: But now they have no clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>How much Worldly mindedneſs is there to be found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g us?</hi> And this Generally follows upon the former: for it is not to be wondered at where the <hi>Kingdom of God and his Righteouſneſs</hi> are ſet light by, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>add<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ional</hi> things are too much ſet by How manifeſtly is the deſign of the firſt Settlement
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:001495_0030_0FB34E42E129B730"/>
of this Land very much forgotten, and a <hi>Worldly</hi> deſign come in its place? <hi>Un lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> there were higher, more nob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and excellent <hi>Things</hi> in the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and much upon the Hearts of thoſe, who left a pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant land and under went many hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips in coming to this Wilderneſs Thoſe who were the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of this motion, their <hi>Deſign</hi> was the following of the Lord, the promoting of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion the free enjoyment of God in the <hi>Purity</hi> of all his Ordinances; They ſoon did expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> did leave <hi>Greater Things</hi> from whence <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> came than <hi>Thy</hi> could attain unto here: not but that ſome of them might too much forget, what they came <hi>out into the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſee:</hi> But I ſpeak of them that were Leaders in that <hi>Great Undertaking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what is the <hi>Deſign</hi> that now bears <hi>Sway?</hi> how light do men make of the <hi>Things</hi> of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom?</hi> And the <hi>Thing</hi> that is moſt minded is the World. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ming,</hi> and <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>chandizing, i. e.</hi> ſecular affairs how violently purſued by almoſt all, except thoſe, who are apparently ſlothfal? From whence elſe is it, that there is ſo much Covetouſneſs, <hi>ſoaring more than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> meet, Grudging at Publick and Neceſſary Charges?</hi> Oh! Is it not to be feared, that the love of the World will leave us as little room in Gods Heart, as it hath done him in ours?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Is not there much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ride to be found among us?</hi> From whence elſe is it, that Perſons know not or keep not their proper places? <hi>The Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d behaves him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf proudly againſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cient, and the baſe againſt the
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:001495_0031_0FB34E446EA0B4E0"/>
Honourable?</hi> Whence alſo but from pride is it, that there is ſo much ſtout Heartedneſs, which tranſports men to an awleſſneſs of men veſted with Gods Authority? <hi>Pride goe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h before deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and ſurely our Circumſtances <hi>loudly</hi> call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us to walk <hi>humbly</hi> with God</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Is there no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> much ſenſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lity to be found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi> How much Precious Time ſpent, Eſtates waſted Families Impoveriſhed, &amp; which is worſt of all Bodies and Souls wounded and deſtroyed, by means of <hi>prevailing Inſobriety,</hi> Intemperance, and Exceſs?</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Is there not great formality and outſideneſs in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of God and Godlineſs?</hi> We are indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in external acts of Worſhip, but inſide God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and that which is indeed the Life and Soul of it how Rare to be found? How much do the <hi>generality</hi> take up ſatisfyed with <hi>having a name to live,</hi> if ſo much be attained) with having <hi>as form of Godlineſs, not regarding the power there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f?</hi> In a Word how doth <hi>Iniquity greatly abound, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve of many wax cold</hi> Things being thus be we all of us <hi>Solemnly,</hi> Admoniſhed of our great revolt, <hi>warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> of our <hi>great danger</hi> and Counſelled to our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant duty. Our Sins are too viſible to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, our dangers greatly to be feared: Therefore before the decree bring forth, let us fall to our duty, and Return wherein we have Revolted, and take heed that we be not farther Unreaſonably <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> And this we had need to be very ſerious and buſie about, becauſe it is neither caſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:001495_0032_0FB34E4604463530"/>
keep from revolting, nor yea to recover when we have Revolted. <hi>It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not eaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to keep from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking:</hi> It is a thing natural unto men to draw off from and forſake God. It is that, which the nature of man doth not need to be Inſtructed in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hence we are ſaid to <hi>go aſtray from the Womb, Pſa.</hi> 58. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Now to get an head of Nature (which there is too much of even in thoſe that are in part ſanctified) this Requires Labour this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires Work.</p>
            <p>Moreover, <hi>It is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to recover from hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from God.</hi> This will be found to be up hill work, Afflictions though they be ſharp and heavy, yet will not of themſelves prevail <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 4. 6. &amp;c. The Lord doth there reckon up ſeveral heavie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which he had bro't upon them, and tell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ffectual they had been, five times he doth compl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion. <hi>And yet ye have not returned into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing ſhort of the ſpecial work of God will Recover ſuch a people. Let all Friends all Providences, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all Ordinances agree to do what they can, yet all of them will do nothing, except God be pleaſed to put to his hand. Therefore we had need with utmoſt earneſtneſs to joyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with the Church in <hi>Pſal</hi> 80. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, 7, 19. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> O God.</hi> To ſtir us up hereunto, let us Conſider.</p>
            <p>I. <hi>That our Sins are greatly, aggravated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>We have fallen from an high pitch of Profeſſion, and Priviledges.</hi> It is indeed a great mercy for a people to be taken nigh to God, and to be dealt with in a diſtinguiſhing way as to religious privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges:
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:001495_0033_0FB34E4763E82768"/>
But it is no leſs dangerous to Revold un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch Circumſtances. Duty and Priv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ledge do or ſhould go together<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a neglect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the former forfeits the latter, or expoſes to diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing judgments. <hi>Amos</hi> 3. 2. <hi>You <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have I known of all the families of the Earth: Therefore I will puniſh you for all your iniq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Have we not Revolted under, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> been reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ries of rebu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es? Have we not</hi> Revolted yet mere and more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 1. 5.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Are not our Revoltings become very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> There are indeed and it would be very ſad if there were not ſome who do <hi>Sigh and cry for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that are done in the Land,</hi> Ezek 4. 9. But are not the generality Revolting?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Conſider that our con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>g to Revolt from God may be expected to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> followed with the Lord, ſevere an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>madverſions:</hi> What might we expect upon ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> going on to abuſe the goodneſs of God, but that he ſhould turn and do us hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t and conſume us, after that he hath done us good.</p>
            <p>How juſt would it be for the Lord to be a <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>derneſs and a Land of darkneſſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> to that people who practically <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we are Lords and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> come no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> There is no greater miſery th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to have been happy. It is more afflicting to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> than to be <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orn</hi> low.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Conſider, How ſad it would be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhould i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come this, that the Lord ſhould be to us, what a Wilderneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe that dwell there.</hi> Should he leave us unhedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unwalled, not be our Protection and Defence,
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:001495_0034_0FB34E48E02C4460"/>
what people can there be found more helpleſs than we ſhould be?</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing our danger, let every one fall to their duty Oh is there Room for us to hope for ſuch a comfortable word as that, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi> 2. 22. <hi>Retur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ye back ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ding Children, and I will heal your back ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ding</hi> let us then heartily ſay, <hi>behold, we come unto the, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or thou art the Lord our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For which end it is neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That each o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and reflect upon his own Particular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Indeed the diſeaſe is general, but the Recovery muſt be wrought by dealing with particulars So long as we content our ſelves with a general c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, Oh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is a declin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apoſtatiſing time, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> abounds, and love wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and,</hi> and all this without any particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion upon what each of us have done, this doth nothing toward Amendment So long as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> buſy our ſelves in complaining and caſting ſtones at the ſins of others, and remain inſenſible of our own guilt we are far from making the caſe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo long as no man <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> what have I done? No man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> one will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi> 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſel of the King of Nineveh was good, <hi>Jon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> 3. 8. <hi>Let them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> every one from his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> way, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in their hands.</hi> This is the promiſing bleſſed frame of a People Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ized, but yet not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtroyed. <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k.</hi> 7. 16. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Untill we come to this we do nothing to purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="34" facs="unknown:001495_0035_0FB34E4A6219E390"/>
2. <hi>It is needful that true and unfeigned Repentance be laid a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the bottom of our ret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnings</hi> If Judah do not <hi>return with their whole heart,</hi> The Lord looks upon what they do to be done <hi>feignedly.</hi> Jer. 3. 10 <hi>Our uncircum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> hearts muſt be humbled within us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 41. If the Spirit of God with converting, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dirving Influences may be given to us, this is the Catholieon, that will cure us of our ſins and for rows too, yea it will enſure bleſſings to us, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39 19 <hi>Neither will I bide my face any more from them: for I have poured out my Spirit upon the houſe of Iſrael ſaith the Lord God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>It is needful that each be vigorous to improve their proper Talent, and Station.</hi> There is no Perſon,' to whom any truſt is committed whether Civil, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, or Domeſtical, but are thereby advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to forward our return to God, and indeed very much of ſucceſs doth depend upon our lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together Particularly,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Let it be propoſed as incumbent upon thoſe Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Perſons, that may be this day Eſtabliſhed, or Reſtabliſhed Rulers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>over this People in the Civil Authority, to be concerned to prevent our farther Revolt, and to help us to return wherein we have backſidden</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You need not, right Honourable and Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be informed, that it is the property as well as the duty of Pious Rulers to ſeek the welfare of the people over whom they are ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and methinks our declined condition, and the danger we are in of perpetuating our Revolt from God, doth with utmoſt earneſtneſs beſpeak your Honours in thoſe
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:001495_0036_0FB34E4BE0100200"/>
words <hi>Ezra</hi> 10. 4 <hi>Ariſe for this matter belongeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</hi> It is your greateſt Honour that you are betruſted with ſo much of the charge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Religion in the Civil concerns of it, if you may be Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to prevent our farther backſliding, that ſo the Lord may not be <hi>a Wilderneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> it will be your and our hapineſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gods honour, your honour and our ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ety do much depend upon it. Much of our way is to be choſen out by you, Right Honourable, whom, we have the priviledge to ſee ſetting chief among us. We have indeed abundant reaſon, Reflecting upon your indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable and unwearied endeavours to promote the Publick Weal of this Colony by ſuppreſſing grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vice and Immorality, by bearing up againſt the ſins of the times, &amp; by <hi>giving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>moſt encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> unto Godlineſs, <hi>to accept it always and in all places w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h all Thankfullneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> And we do with deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſubmiſſion beſeech your Honours, that ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue <hi>to be ſtrong, and let n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t your hands be weak, for your work ſhall be rewarded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your being ſet over a declined people, and that alſo in a Stormy time, make<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> your work to be the more hard and difficult: But you have the Prayers of all whoſe prayers are worth the having<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea the Gods of Gods will be with you; and may <hi>he think upon you for good, according to all that you have done, and ſhall do, for this people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Thoſe, to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m the miniſtration of the Goſpel is committed, are alſo greatly concerned in this matter</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is high time for ſuch to lift up <hi>their voices like
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:001495_0037_0FB34E4D6118E298"/>
a Trumpet, to ſhew the Lord people their Tranſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſſing, and the houſe of Iſrael <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> If a declining peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are flattered this makes their breach like the Breach of the Sea and their wound Incurable. <hi>Lam.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 13, 14. The Lord help all ſuch to deal plainly and faithfully and though men will not hear, yet you ſhall reap the fruit of your faithful labourers, ſurely your <hi>Judgment ſhall be with the Lord, and your work with your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Moreover the Station, in which thoſe, who are the Repreſentatives, of this Colony, do ſtand advantages them to help our return.</hi> The truſt (Gentlemen) which is put into your hands is great, you may do much for the preventing our farther Revolt from God, Oh if any thing farther can be done to cruſh growinging iniquity it will be well worth your deepeſt conſultation!</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Head<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Families ought to look upon themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to prevent our farther Revolt from, and to help <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Return unto God.</hi> Families are the Nurſeries out of which Common-Wealths, and Churches are Repleniſhed; If there be <hi>Degenerate Plants</hi> and <hi>Strange Children,</hi> can it be expected but that more Publick Societies ſhould bare <hi>Sowre fruits</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You that are Parents and Maſters betray not your Authority, ſet good examples, Watch, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, ſtrive Pray againſt the Sins of the Times Let not your Houſes be receptacles of vain men, and ſon of Belial, left you ſhould give occaſion for your Children and Servants to <hi>riſe up and call you
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:001495_0038_0FB34EDFC0F3B8"/>
curſed;</hi> But reſolve by the help of God, that <hi>You and Your houſes will ſerve the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally,</hi> Let us beg the down pourings of the Spirit of God, the Reviving of his work, the ſtrengthening of thoſe things that remain, which are ready to die; Then might we hope that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the Lords being to us a Wilderneſs or a Land of Darkneſs, we might have the Lord mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good to us ſuch comfortable words as thoſe. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51. 3. <hi>For the Lord ſhall comfort Zion, He will comfort all her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt places, and he will make her Wilderneſs like Eden, and her D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſort like the Garden of the LORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
