<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God's sovereign government among the nations asserted in a sermon preached before His Excellency the governour, the Honourable Council, and representatives of the province of the Massachusetts-Bay in New-England, on May 28. 1712. Being the day for election of Her Majesties Council for that province. / By Samuel Cheever, Pastor of the church in Marblehead. ; [Six lines from Psalms]</title>
            <author>Cheever, Samuel, 1639-1724.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N01294</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N01294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 1541</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW6306</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">1541</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99012440</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 1541.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N01294)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 1541)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 1541)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God's sovereign government among the nations asserted in a sermon preached before His Excellency the governour, the Honourable Council, and representatives of the province of the Massachusetts-Bay in New-England, on May 28. 1712. Being the day for election of Her Majesties Council for that province. / By Samuel Cheever, Pastor of the church in Marblehead. ; [Six lines from Psalms]</title>
                  <author>Cheever, Samuel, 1639-1724.</author>
                  <author>Massachusetts. Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 53, [1] p. ;  15 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Green: sold at the booksellers shops.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1712.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Election sermons --  Massachusetts --  1712.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:001541_0000_0FB3AAA98266CEA0"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:001541_0001_0FB3AAAB31325C40"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GODS Sovereign Government Among the NATIONS Aſſerted in a SERMON Preached before His Excellency the GOVERNOUR, the Honourable COUNCIL, and Repreſentatives of the Province of the <hi>Maſſachuſetts-Bay</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> on <hi>May</hi> 28. 1712. being the day for Election of Her Majeſties Council for that Province.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SAMUEL CHEEVER,</hi> Paſtor of the Church in <hi>Marblehead.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. xcv.3, 6</hi>
               </bibl>
For the Lord is a great God and a great King above all gods: O come let us Worſhip, and bow down, let us kneel before the Lord our Maker.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. ii.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
Kiſs the Son, leſt he be angry, and ye periſh in the way, when his wrath is kindled but a little: bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON</hi>: Printed by <hi>B. Green:</hi> Sold at the Bookſellers Shops. 1712.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="unknown:001541_0002_0FB3AAACE2E20208"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PRinted by Order of His Excellency the GO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERNOUR and COUNCIL.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Iſaac Addington,</hi> Secr.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="unknown:001541_0003_0FB3AAAE31846C10"/>
            <head>GODS Sovereign Government Among the NATIONS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM XXII. 27, 28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
All the ends of the World ſhall remember, and turn unto the LORD: — For the Kingdom is the LORDS: and he is the Governour among the Nations.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Eternal GOD, for whom, and by whom all things in the World were made, and are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and governed, having in his everlaſting Counſel (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Primitive Apoſtacy and Revolt from Him, fore-known to Him with all His Works from the beginning of the World) purpos'd from the Ruins of fallen
<pb n="2" facs="unknown:001541_0004_0FB3AAB273D3E608"/>
man, to take out of them a People for his Name, and to reduce them to Subjection and Obedience to Him, from whom they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted; that they might ſhew forth, &amp; might be to the Praiſe of the Glory of his Grace: was pleaſed accordingly to pitch upon his bleſſed SON, to be the great undertaker in this Matter, and called therefore <hi>the Captain of their Salvation,</hi> Heb. 2.10. Appointed to bring the Children unto Glory. Chriſt Jeſus being therefore deputed to this difficult task, the deſert of Sin was ſuch, and the Juſtice of God ſo immutable, that there was no way to bring the matter to an iſſue, but by the Death &amp; Sufferings of the Lord Jeſus; Sin being ſuch a crime and offence againſt the Crown of Heaven, that without ſuitable Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction made to Divine Juſtice, the honour of Gods Law and Government could not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be upheld and maintained in the World: Chriſt Jeſus having therefore conſented here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and willing to aſſume that Nature which had Sinned, and to offer up Himſelf a Sacrifice to ſatisfy Divine Juſtice, it was very congruous to Divine Wiſdom, that for ſo deep a Humiliation He ſhould have as illuſtrious an Advancement, and a peculiar Honour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:001541_0005_0FB3AAB42DB0E258"/>
upon him, ſo as to be made King and Lord of all, and have a <hi>Name given Him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove every Name,</hi> and ſuffer firſt, and ſo enter into Glory; according to the Prediction of the Prophets, and by Chriſt applyed to Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Luk</hi> 24.25. It being that which he Prayes for, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.5. That the Glory which he had, as to his Divine Nature, with God from Eternity, might be communicated ſo to his Humane Nature, as that his whole Perſon might be glorious, and by that way have a joynt Rule with God over all the Works of his hands, which as in other Places of Scripture, ſo particularly is plainly hinted in the Book of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and eſpecially in this <hi>Pſalm</hi> where the Text lyes: the two great Truths reſpecting the Humiliation and Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Chriſt, and his Exaltation afterward being exactly Predicted by the Spirit of God, for the directing and ſtrengthning the Faith and Hope of the Church of God in all Ages of the World. This <hi>Pſalm</hi> is a Prophetical Pſalm, and ſhould the queſtion be asked as was by the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> Act 8.34. <hi>Of whom ſpeaks the Prophet this, of himſelf, or ſome other man?</hi> It muſt be underſtood of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> in whom many of the Paſſages were literally accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed;
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:001541_0006_0FB3AAB5ABA6B690"/>
as appears by comparing it with <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.35, 46. &amp; <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.24. The former part of the <hi>Pſalm</hi> holding forth his Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the latter part hinting out his Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and gracious Promiſes made to Him in this Eſtate; and is a Propheſy of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of his Kingdom by the acceſſion of the Nations from one end of the World to the other, who ſhould remember, and turn to him. The words may be conſidered as a Propheſy, and a Promiſe made to Chriſt, for his incouragement in diſpatching that ardu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affair he was intruſted withal. And alſo it implies a ſtrong Obligation on the ends of the World, <hi>to Remember and turn to the Lord</hi>; and the more effectually to perſwade them ſo to do, we have laid down in the latter part of the verſes read, a moſt undeniable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>For the Kingdom is the Lords, and he is the Governour among the Nations.</hi> Now this Kingdom of Chriſt admits of a two-fold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration; The firſt is that Univerſal King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by which Chriſt, together with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Holy Ghoſt, reigns over all things; this being common to every Perſon in the God-head. And Chriſt on this account hath power over all fleſh, and <hi>He is King of Nations
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:001541_0007_0FB3AAB75DC0A360"/>
as well as Saints.</hi> And ſecondly, there is a ſpecial peculiar Kingdom which Chriſt exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes over his Church, his Mediatory King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by ſpecial diſpenſation committed by the Father to him over the Hearts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men to bring the Soul to a free, and voluntary Subjection to him, hinted in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 110.3.</p>
            <p>But its the firſt of theſe two, which ſhall eſpecially be taken notice of, not wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the other; the univerſal Kingdom and Government, common to the whole God-head. There being but One GOD, though Three Perſons, and all equal in Power and Glory: This Truth therefore as it hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the calling of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reward promiſed to Chriſt. I ſhall wholly wave any further conſideration of, and the Reaſon given in the Twenty-eight Verſe, is that I ſhall principally confine my Diſcourſe to. In which Verſe, we have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the Univerſal Kingdom of the Lord, and his Government of all the Nations in the World: The deſign of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe being to perſwade, and if poſſible to prevail with us in theſe ends of the World to a humble ſubjection and ſubmiſſion to the
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:001541_0008_0FB3AABA8420EA50"/>
Sovereign Government of GOD, whoſe we are, and whom we ought to Serve, and in all things readily obey.</p>
            <p>
               <label>DOCTRINE.</label>
GOD the Lord (or Chriſt Jeſus) is certainly the King and Supreme Governour among the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the World, and ought to be Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and acknowledged as ſuch by all; and eſpecially by His Profeſſing People, at what end of the World ſo ever by His Providence they are caſt, and placed to dwell in.</p>
            <p>This Truth is that, which we find ſo often aſſerted, and by irrefragable arguments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, ſo univerſally implanted in the light alſo, and law of Nature, that without offering violence to Reaſon, and blowing out this candle of the Lord the Spirit in man; all muſt yield to the belief of it: If we own there is a GOD in the World, we muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly own Him as the King and Governour of it; it is what we are taught in the <hi>Lords Prayer, Thine is the Kingdom the Power and the Glory,</hi> Mat. 6.13. And which every one, every day ought to ſay, <hi>Amen</hi> unto. That which
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:001541_0009_0FB3AABBC3A161E0"/>
               <hi>David,</hi> that great King over Iſrael, did moſt readily in his Life, and at his Death humbly acknowledge, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.11, 12. And that he held his Crown from him; all his Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries over the Nations were ſuch as God gave him, who was exalted as head over all. How often in the Pſalms do we find <hi>David</hi> owning and proclaiming this Truth? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.2, 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 66.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 103.19. It's one of the Royal Titles given to God, That He is the <hi>Moſt High, Pſal.</hi> 83. <hi>ult.</hi> God is the Supreme: Other Perſons may be high in their Stations and Poſts of Honour, which Providentially they are advanced to; but the Title really of the Moſt High belongs peculiarly to God alone; ſo he is called by <hi>Abram, Gen.</hi> 14.18. Power and Highneſs is originally and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally in God. He is a <hi>Great King,</hi> Mal. 1.4. <hi>The Only Potentate,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.15. But not to ſpend time in averring a Truth ſo plainly demonſtrated, and which I hope none need to be taught, by the terrible works of God, as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was, by turning him <hi>a grazing among the beaſts, till ſeven times paſſed over him, that he might know that the Moſt High rules in the Kingdom of men,</hi> Dan. 4.32. I ſhall therefore diſpatch in a few
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:001541_0010_0FB3AABD358F8470"/>
Propoſitions this Truth, and illuſtrate the ſame by a few Concluſions reſulting from them, for the clearing up of the ſame, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Application of the whole, and to conclude all with all convenient brevity.</p>
            <p>PROP. I. <hi>God the Lord is certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in, and about the affairs of all Nations, all the World over.</hi> And here we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Being and Conſtitution of Nations is really from God.</hi> The wiſe God, though he had the reſidue of the Spirit, and could at once, if he had ſo pleaſed, made the whole Stock and Race of Mankind, and repleniſh'd the Earth with a ſufficient Number of Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, as God did do at the Creation of ſome parts of the World; yet notwithſtanding He choſe rather to diſplay his manifold Wiſdom and Power in this great affair, to frame, and make immediately but One Man, and One Woman, deſigning from that One Stock, all Mankind ſhould be Propagated, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.26. Of one Blood, from one Family, all ſhould have one Father, be all Adams Children, who was to be the repreſentative of all his Seed: Whereas among the Angels the Inhabitants
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:001541_0011_0FB3AABEB3E54740"/>
of the Higheſt Heaven, God made the whole number at firſt; and in the Starry Heaven, God at once garniſhed them with thoſe Lights which continue to this day according to his Ordinance: but in this lower World it is otherwiſe. All came from duſt, in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time God had a multitude of Nations in the firſt Age of the World before the Flood; and afterward when they were brought to Eight Perſons in the Ark, yet God in a few years repleniſhed the Earth, and from thoſe three Sons iſſued a multitude of Nations; it was the bleſſing Promiſed to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 12.2. Though he was but one individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, <hi>Of thee, Gen.</hi> 15.5. He was the father of many Nations, they were as the Stars of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; in Aegypt, in the ſpace of Two hundred and fifteen years became a great Nation, ſix hundred thouſand Males, from twenty years old and upwards.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>As God is the Maker of the Nations, ſo all the Motions of the Nations, are all ordered by God, from one part of the World to another.</hi> We find at Babel, how God by the confuſion of Languages, ſcattered them up and down, when they were building to prevent their being ſo ſcattered, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.5. And indeed its
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:001541_0012_0FB3AAC035AEB0E8"/>
the Lord who bounds every ones Habitation; In Him we <hi>Move,</hi> as well as <hi>Live, Act.</hi> 17.26. <hi>It is not in man to direct his ſteps,</hi> as <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.23. Gods ways and thoughts are not as mens; God made for man a large houſe to dwell in, a great body of Earth, though part of it be a Wilderneſs, and a barren Land, for the wild Aſs to dwell in, as we read, in <hi>Job</hi> 39.6. Yet a very great part of it is very fertile, as Aegypt watered by the River <hi>Nilus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Canaan</hi> counted the glory of all Lands, and by God allotted to be the Place of his Peoples abode, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.8. Though at firſt poſſeſſed by the Poſterity of Canaan, and improved for many Ages, yet God for the Sins of that People rooted them out, and brings Iſrael in their room: As God gave them the grant of that Land, ſo in that grant he ſets down their bounds and limits: in <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.31. and <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.4. Though Iſrael poſſeſſed not the whole till Davids time. God is indeed the Lord of the Soyl, and removes Nations as he ſees meet. As <hi>Joſeph</hi> did by the Egyptians from one end of the Land to another, never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that all the Nations ſhould be penned up in one Corner of the World, nor drove to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in heaps, when he hath room enough
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:001541_0013_0FB3AAC2785C96C0"/>
for all, without encroaching upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Proprieties: He brought up the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines from <hi>Caphtor,</hi> and the Syrians from <hi>Kir, Amos</hi> 9.7. Gave <hi>Mount Seir</hi> to <hi>Edom,</hi> would not let Iſrael diſturb him in his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion. And by the Wiſe Orderer of all, it was that this little handful of People came to dwell in this Wilderneſs, God moving on the hearts of our Predeceſſors to leave a fruitful Land, and come to this <hi>Jeſhimon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>All the Changes that happen among the Nations are all Over-ruled by this God, and Lord of all.</hi> It is the Great GOD who doth moſt certainly order all events, and iſſues of affairs which to men, and ſecond cauſes may be unknown and unexpected, yet ſo brought about, that no man can alwayes foreſee or prevent: Gods Peculiar is that He Himſelf is JEHOVAH, and changes not, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. There is not the ſhadow of turning, or any variableneſs: but the World is full of chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. It is with Political Bodies as with Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Natural, at ſuch times when Perſons have the Fever &amp; Ague, one day ſick, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day tolerably well: and as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaking of himſelf, in his 10. <hi>Chap</hi> &amp; 17. <hi>v. Changes &amp; War are againſt me</hi>; is very applicable to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:001541_0014_0FB3AAC3EF97B358"/>
God ſometimes bleſſes a Nation with a great deal of Proſperity, ſome conſiderable time: at another time, vexes them with all manner of adverſity. In <hi>Solomon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime, Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el had very happy dayes: as we read 1 <hi>King.</hi> 4.25. Iſrael dwelt ſafely, every man under his vine; and it was durable all the dayes of <hi>Solomon</hi>; ſo that there was no adverſary, or evil occurrent, as Solomon acknowledges to <hi>Hiram,</hi> 1 <hi>King</hi> 5.4 But as ſoon as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> head was laid in the duſt, what an ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing change and turn of affairs, Ten tribes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel againſt the houſe of David, and <hi>Solomon</hi> with all his Wiſdom could not prevent it, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.15. God gave up <hi>Rehoboam</hi> to ſo fooliſh and fatal a miſtake, as to alienate the very hearts of his Subjects from him; &amp; what abundance of changes in both the Kingdoms fell out, the Hiſtory of their Reigns in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Writ do abundantly evince: And indeed Nations are very prone to tranſgreſs againſt the Lord, and change their glory for that which doth not profit, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.11. And no wonder if God change his diſpenſations to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them: Sin brings trouble in a Nation, and God hath very often a controverſy with Nations, <hi>with all the Inhabitants of the Land,
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:001541_0015_0FB3AAC5AC4E9B08"/>
Hoſ.</hi> 4.1, 2. We read, <hi>of a Sinful Nation, Iſa.</hi> 1.4. <hi>&amp; Jer.</hi> 7.28. <hi>This is a nation that obeys not the voice of the Lord</hi>: and this will cauſe God to take other meaſures, and vex ſuch with all manner of adverſity, as we find, in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.5, 6. God hath his time to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, and bring a People low, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.39. So alſo to take away the Peace of a People, as you have it, in <hi>Jer.</hi> 16.5. He can draw out his Sword out of the Sheath of his Patience, give it a large commiſſion to paſs through a Land; and its God alone who can give quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. How much of Gods Sovereignty is ſeen in this matter in the times of the Judges? the Land ſometimes reſted many years, but they had alſo long times of Servitude. And indeed in our times, what Multitudes of changes have paſſed over us? and what a long calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous War have we laboured under? As from the Heathen behind us, thoſe pricks &amp; thorns left to prove &amp; afflict us by; and alſo a Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Enemy: and it muſt be God only that makes Wars to ceaſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.9. That can give us quietneſs. And had we been more careful to have pleaſed the Lord, He could before this day have made our Enemies to be more at Peace with us.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="14" facs="unknown:001541_0016_0FB3AAC70AD20500"/>4. <hi>The Government of the Nations is moſt certainly Ordered by this God and Lord of all.</hi> As God hath made the Nations of one bloud, ſo he hath and doth take care in his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that all may be under rule &amp; govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and as he hath given Laws, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rules to all, ſo He is pleaſed to Set up Perſons, who ſhall be entruſted in a great meaſure, with the Execution of them; and to govern men by men, putting that honour on ſome to Rule, ſo on others to obey, and be Ruled by them; Civil Government being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Gods Ordinance, to be obſerved in his Realm every where. God endoweth ſome with particular gifts of Wiſdom and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge above others, that they may be the more Serviceable in their Generation to others. God ordered a ſpecial Education for <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was to be King in <hi>Jeſhurun,</hi> to be trained up in the Court of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and well learned in all the Wiſdom of the Egyptians, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.22. And mighty in Words as well as Deeds, one that could <hi>do,</hi> as well as <hi>ſay</hi> what became him. And <hi>Saul</hi> the firſt King of Iſrael, God gave him another ſpirit, of Government to fit him for the Place he was called to, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.6. Civil Government being the great Inſtrument
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:001541_0017_0FB3AAC86B4B8AB8"/>
in Gods hand, appointed for the preſervation of humane Society, that men might not live as Beaſts, but live civilly and orderly as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Rational Intellectual Beings. And Gods care is ſuch, as that he layes down rules for Governours as well as for the Governed; we may read their Character, what they ought to be, given by <hi>David</hi> by the order of the God of Iſrael, and directed by the Spirit of God, in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3. To make and leave a Record of the ſame; for the direction of all in after Ages, and God orders alſo the King to write out a Copy of the Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.18, 19. And <hi>Johojada</hi> gave to <hi>Joaſh</hi> the Teſtimony with the Crown, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.11. When he anointed him King: And ſo all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Officers alſo are by the Orders of Gods Realm, to be Men <hi>Fearing God</hi>; and ſuch as muſt <hi>Judge not for man, but for the Lord, who will be with them in the Judgment</hi>; to obſerve their carriages, ſo alſo to defend them againſt all thoſe Perſons whom the impartial exerciſe of Juſtice might provoke and exaſperate their Spirits: God hath therefore kindled this light in the minds of all men, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſee the neceſſity of upholding &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it in the World: and altho Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:001541_0018_0FB3AACA0BED2578"/>
have been in the World, and Rebellions againſt Governours, yet it hath been only to put it into others hands; and if one hath been thrown out of the Sadle, another hath been put in; Licentious Nature doth not love to be controlled, &amp; would have no Lord over it: but ſound reaſon will tell every man that there is no living where every man may do what he will without controll. The moſt barbarous Nations who never ſaw a Bible, have their Governours, to whoſe Edicts and Wills, they do moſt unaccountably ſubmit. The old <hi>Perſians</hi> had a cuſtom, when their old Prince dyed, to indulge the People with five dayes miſrule, in which they might do what ever they would without controll; that ſo by the Rapine, and Out-rages committed, they might be brought in love more with the Perſon and Government of the Succeeding Prince: A ſad way, but a ſure one, as the Author calls it. But our holy Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion hath taught us a better way; let us be the more thankful to God for his holy Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and ſtudy to do our part, and duty of ſubmiſſion to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, who is our King, and Lives for ever, though ſuch as are ſent by him, may &amp; will die like men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="unknown:001541_0019_0FB3AACBEB7CA120"/>PROP. II. <hi>What ever Rulers are by Divine Providence ſet over men, yet God the Lord is certainly the moſt Abſolute Supreme Governour, and King over all.</hi> The great God, though he entruſt Mortals with a Power to Rule, yet he keeps the Government in His Own Hands. Chriſt tells <hi>Pilate, Joh.</hi> 19.11. When he was telling of his Power, That <hi>he could have no Power at all againſt him, except it were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him from above</hi>: his Power muſt come from God, though <hi>Caeſar</hi> had put him in the Place; there was One above <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and without the permiſſion of this God, he could neither condemn him, nor ſee execution done upon him. The Lord is that King, who will never part with his Sovereignty to any of his Subſtitutes whatever; as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> tells <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, In the Throne I will be greater than thou, Gen.</hi> 41.40. In the account given of Iſraels conduct in the Wilderneſs: Pſal. 77.20. <hi>Thou leddeſt thy People, like a flock by the hand of Moſes &amp; Aaron.</hi> We find that God is the greateſt Principal Leader; <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were but Inſtrumental under God; as in the Natural Body, the head guides the hand, ſo alſo in all Political Bodies: God could indeed, but he puts in Men, not that God needs their
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:001541_0020_0FB3AACCEB8B56C0"/>
help, for He can do all of it alone. Though Men cannot do all alone, the Number &amp; Care is too great, <hi>Moſes</hi> complains, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.11, 14. But God doth it as an Act of favour, to put honour on the Creature, as in his Preſerving Providence He often uſes Inſtruments, not out of neceſſity, as when he imploys the poor Widow of <hi>Zarephath,</hi> to take in his Prophet to her Table, but puts a ſingular honour on her, and ſends Himſelf Proviſion enough for both of them; ſo it is alſo in his Governing Providence, God uſes Inſtruments, but it muſt alwayes be remembred by ſuch as Rule for Him, and ſuch as are to be Ruled by them, That God is the Supreme, and his Laws and Rules muſt be by both, carefully obſerved and kept, and its God who concurs with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments; and without Him the builder builds in vain and the watch-mans care would be inſignificant; God never therefore gives Commiſſion to any, but he gives and limits their Commiſſion with ſuch particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions as He ſees meet. And for the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration of this, we may conſider a few Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions which reſult from this Propoſition laid down. As,</p>
            <p>Conclu. 1. <hi>God the abſolute Supreme Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver,
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:001541_0021_0FB3AACE98244C40"/>
as He is the Governour of the Nations, ſo He gives Laws to all of them, to Regulate all Perſons in all their Actions.</hi> In all Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there is a Legiſlative Power; and in <hi>Judahs</hi> bleſſing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. The <hi>Scepter,</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver</hi> are joyned together; and the Church very readily owns this Lord of all, to be her <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> as he was her <hi>King, Iſa.</hi> 33.22. And its an argument uſed by the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> to diſſwade Perſons from rigid cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and raſh condemning of men for thoſe things which the Law doth not condemn in them, becauſe there is One Supreme univerſal Lawgiver, who can directly bind mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and make Laws for their Souls, and is able to Save, and to deſtroy mens Souls, which no other Lawgiver can do, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.12. This God hath his Throne prepared in the Heavens, and is ſo repreſented as Sitting on it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4 21. And as there he receives ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from all, ſo from thence he gives forth his Laws and Commands to all men whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. The Eternal God, having the whole Model of the World in his Own Mind, as he propoſed to make Man the chief of all his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Works, ſo he reſolved how all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſhould be governed; and pitched upon a
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:001541_0022_0FB3AAD17A0D1198"/>
Rule according to which all ſhould walk, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. Never deſigning to make any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture who ſhould be abſolute Lord of his own Actions, to live, ſpeak, act or do as he pleaſed; but that all their ways ſhould fall under Law and Rules congruous and ſuitable to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of that Being, He was pleaſed to give them.</p>
            <p>Conclu. 2. <hi>God having therefore in his own hand drawn up a body of Laws, hath been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to proclaim and declare to man, what is his great duty, God expects from him; and what God hath revealed, ought carefully to be ſtudyed and practiſed.</hi> Promulgation of Laws, being what is ordinarily practiſed in all Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Deut. 29. <hi>ult. Secret things belong to the Lord, but thoſe things which are revealed, belong to us and our Children</hi> for ever. There are indeed <hi>Arcana imperii,</hi> Myſteries of State, and many Secret events of Providence, which God in his own time will bring to paſs; but the things revealed by God are the proper objects of mans inquiry, ſtudy and practice. <hi>Micah</hi> 6.8. <hi>He hath ſhewed thee O man, what is good, and what the Lord requires of thee, &amp;c.</hi> At mans firſt Creation, God making of him in His Image, He gave him the full know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:001541_0023_0FB3AAD2F0DB9180"/>
of his Mind &amp; Duty, and by Oral Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in the firſt Ages of the World, His Law was ſafely handed down, and communicated by one to another, till God after mans Life was ſo exceedingly ſhortned, was pleaſed to commit his Laws of the Government to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and at Mount Sinai gave the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, the Moral Law, to his People, and wrote them on Two Tables of Stone with his Own Finger; as we are certifyed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> his Secretary of State, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.18. It being a new Edition of what was firſt given to <hi>Adam,</hi> and an univerſal Rule to oblige all Perſons in all Ages to obſerve and do; and in after Ages this God inſpired holy Men to write down, &amp; leave upon Record ſuch Rules, as might be ſufficient to make men wiſe to Salvation, and compile that compleat Canon, by which men might be throughly furniſhed unto every good Work: the Scriptures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe Sacred digeſts, where God diſcovers his Imperial Power, as well as his Wiſdom and Juſtice; and though indeed the Wiſe God hath been pleaſed to give ſome more oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to know his Will, than others; yet all have the Light and Law of Nature, a <hi>Law written in their hearts,</hi> as its called, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15.
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:001541_0024_0FB3AAD4861436A0"/>
The non-improvement of which will clear up the Juſtice of God in Puniſhing ſuch, and leave all without excuſe in the Great Day of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; when God will render to every one according to his Deeds.</p>
            <p>Conclu. 3. <hi>As God hath Publiſhed the Laws of his Government, ſo he doth poſitively Enjoyn and Command Obedience to all his Laws.</hi> God doth not leave the Creature at liberty, to comply, or not; but layes a ſtrict charge on all, Speaks with authority; and although the Word is ſometimes called <hi>Gods Counſel,</hi> and God (tho' the Sovereign Governour) conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends to reaſon, and debate with poor Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, makes them Judges as it were in their own caſe, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.3. <hi>&amp; Jer.</hi> 26. <hi>Iſa</hi> 5.3. Yet it is to convict them of the equity and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſs of all his demands &amp; expectations, and the unreaſonableneſs of their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in any thing there-unto. At Mount Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai, with what authority did God ſpeak, ſuch words, that they entreated might not be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to them any more; but Prayed that <hi>Moſes</hi> might ſpeak with them, and they would hear, but <hi>let not God ſpeak with us, leſt we dye,</hi> Exod. 20.19. And Chriſt Jeſus in the day of his Humiliation, under the form of a Servant, yet
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:001541_0025_0FB3AAD602CB9F38"/>
had this teſtimony given of him by the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ſent to apprehend him: Joh. 7.46. <hi>That never man ſpake like this Man.</hi> And the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt Matthew in the Hiſtory of Chriſts Life, declares, That Chriſt taught them as <hi>One having Authority, and not as the Scribes;</hi> as you may Read in <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.29. In the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical Law, God enjoyns them to do this and that, <hi>I am the Lord,</hi> Lev. 19.3, 12, 14, 30, 37. Never any Laws delivered with that Majeſty, and in that Style, as the Laws of this God are, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.15, 16. Without any exception in both Covenants, in the firſt <hi>Do</hi> and <hi>Live;</hi> and in the ſecond Covenant, <hi>Believe</hi> and <hi>Live</hi>: Act. 17.30. He <hi>Commands all men to Repent.</hi> 1 Joh. 3.23. <hi>And this is his Commandment that we belive on the Name of his Son Jeſus Chriſt</hi>; and what we cannot do without Supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral aid, He binds us to ſeek the help of his Grace to enable us to do it, and therefore in ſo many Places binds us to <hi>Bow down &amp; kneel before the Lord our Maker,</hi> acknowledge our conſtant dependance on Him, for all we need.</p>
            <p>Conclu. 4. <hi>As this God gave us the Copy of his Laws, and enjoyns Obedience to them; ſo He hath given the higheſt Sanction that is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> He Promiſes the greateſt Rewards, to
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:001541_0026_0FB3AAD7935D9C70"/>
allure and perſwade to Obedience, no leſs than <hi>Everlaſting Life</hi>; God is the <hi>Rewarder of ſuch as diligently ſeek him,</hi> Heb. 11 6. He hath E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Salvation to give to ſuch as <hi>Obey him, Heb.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. A Crown, a Kingdom for ſuch as love him, <hi>James</hi> 2.5. No Potentate in the World can give ſuch a Reward. Satan made the higheſt offer to Chriſt when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him the Kingdoms of this World, and the Glory of them; but it was far more than ever he could have made good: The higheſt reward men give is ſome earthly preferment; but in Gods Government, He will give a Crown which fades not away.</p>
            <p>Concl. 5. <hi>In this Sanction, God as he Promiſes a Reward of Eternal bleſſedneſs, ſo he threatens, for contempt of his Laws, he will inflict Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Puniſhment.</hi> Mat. 25.46. <hi>Theſe ſhall go into Everlaſting Puniſhment</hi>: God will puniſh both here and hereafter. Kings can condemn a Traitor but to death, kill the body; but can do no more: but this King of Kings can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath killed the body caſt into Hell the Soul alſo, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.5. He hath prepared a <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi>; He hath <hi>Everlaſting Burnings,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Mark</hi> 9.44. He hath an Everlaſting Priſon to throw ſuch into, who trample
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:001541_0027_0FB3AAD8F0854B90"/>
upon his Authority, and riſe up againſt their Maker.</p>
            <p>Conclu. 6. <hi>God being Supreme, will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call all men to an account at his Bar, for all the contempt of his Laws, &amp; Government; and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence every one according to the Merits of their Offences.</hi> The Ancient of dayes will Sit on the Throne of his Glory, the Books will be opened, and the Judge of all the Earth will paſs Sentence, which will never be reverſed, and from which there lyes no Appeal; He is the Moſt High over all the Earth, and his Laws are ſetled in Heaven, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.89. <hi>v.</hi> Such as dy in their Sins, found guitly, will not be cleared; tho' God be <hi>Gracious,</hi> yet he is <hi>Juſt</hi> alſo. God did upon mans firſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the Law provide indeed a remedy, and paſſed an Act of Grace, for ſuch as would ſubmit to the Terms of it; <hi>Gracious</hi> being one of Gods eſſential Attributes, to be <hi>Good</hi> as well as <hi>Great,</hi> as in the Proclamation made by God of Himſelf, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34 6, 7. will readily appear: God did in the ſecond Covenant, let his Subjects know, that by the interpoſition of Chriſt, and ſatisfying his Law, Sinful man might by Faith, and Obedience to Chriſt as their Lord for the future, be Saved;
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:001541_0028_0FB3AADA875C1C08"/>
but where theſe Terms of Grace are neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſlighted, and Sinners will not accept of the Man Chriſt Jeſus to Reign over them; ſuch will be treated as Rebels, find no favour, but the Sentence of the Law will remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken off, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.36. There being no proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Book of Statutes for the Salvation of ſuch as deſpiſe the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> tho' there be for Sins againſt the <hi>Law,</hi> on Mens repenting and believing, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16.</p>
            <p>PROP. III. <hi>As God is the Supreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of all, ſo He is to be Remembred, and Owned as ſuch by all; but eſpecially by his Profeſſing People, on what Spot of the Creation ſo ever they are got.</hi> And here firſt of all.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The whole World, and all the Nations of it are under his Government.</hi> Gods Dominion is Univerſal, it certainly reaches to all the Ends of the Earth; there is no created Being, but its under the Rule of this Great GOD: All the Angels good &amp; bad were in <hi>Micaiahs</hi> viſion, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.19. He had a repreſentation of the Divine Preſence in the Air, attended with good and bad Angels, ſtanding in the poſture of Servants, ready to receive Gods Commands; and in the Starry Heaven, <hi>Iſai.</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="unknown:001541_0029_0FB3AADBEC6251E8"/>
48.13. — <hi>When I call to them, they ſtand up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi>: As Servants to their Maſter: every Creature, Wind &amp; Seas obey him; and all is to teach man his leſſon and duty to God, much more of ſubjection to Him; but its the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of Rational Beings to the Great God we are ſpeaking of; this is that which all ought to acknowledge, tho' all have not the Laws of Gods Kingdom ſo clearly made known, having not the Goſpel among them; yet, if they ask the beaſts, they would tell man a great deal of his duty, as <hi>Job</hi> 12.7. <hi>The crane and ſwallow,</hi> Jer 8.7. Will teach man to know the time of Judgment, and the time of Mercy. But to come to our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Gods Profeſſing People ought moſt eſpecially to Remember and Turn to the Lord.</hi> Such whom God hath eſpecially known of all the Families of the Earth, theſe are under eſpecial bonds to Own &amp; Submit to his Government; ſo God tells Iſrael, <hi>He had formed them for himſelf,</hi> Iſai. 43.21. <hi>and they ſhould ſhew forth his Praiſe</hi>: God did more for them than any others; they are called his Peculiar People, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.14, 15. The Lords by a ſpecial Profeſſion, and the objects of his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar care, priviledged with his ſpecial Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:001541_0030_0FB3AADF865CE800"/>
It is therefore their duty and intereſt to acknowledge, and moſt readily ſubmit to his Government. It is the unhappy lot of a Multitude of the Nations, to live in darkneſs, and in the region of the ſhadow of Death; but where God irradiates any dark corner of the Earth by the Sun of Righteouſneſs, and takes poſſeſſion of it as a ſpecial part of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſuch tho' they dwell in a Wilderneſs ought to bow down before him, and ſerve him; and they ought to be peculiar in their Recognition, and acknowledgment of his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Authority over them; and the Name, Nature, Titles and Attributes of God, not Notionally only, but Practically to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred and improved; and this in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever part of the World ſo ever they are got, all being under the Juriſdiction of the Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent God: There being no Place in the World where God is not, no Privileged Place where any offenders can take Sanctuary, <hi>Amos</hi> 9.2, 3. <hi>Job</hi> 34.22. Which hints to us our duty in theſe ends of the World, and will be found our beſt Method, aſſoon as we hear of him to obey him, and ſubmit our ſelves to him. But more of this in the Application of this truth, which I muſt haſten to; but before that, I
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:001541_0031_0FB3AAE116A86E28"/>
would ſay a little for the confirmation: And if it be asked,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How God comes to be the Supreme, and why He muſt be owned, and ſubmitted to as ſuch?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The equity and reaſonableneſs of it will appear, if we conſider the following Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p>Reaſon 1. <hi>God by the right of Creation hath a moſt unqueſtionable title to this Government, and may well challenge it as his due.</hi> The World and Nations in it had never been, if God by his Almighty Power had not given them their Exiſtence; It is an argument uſed in all Ages; the Church looks on it as her duty to Serve Him, Pſal. 100.2, 3 <hi>He made us, and not we our ſelves</hi>: had the Nations been their own Maker, there might have been ſome Pretence not to have ſerved him; but all muſt acknowledge they have their Being from God; Fear and Worſhip appertains to Him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as his due, who made the Earth by his Power, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13 <hi>verſes</hi>: He is the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of the ends of the Earth, <hi>Iſai</hi> 40 28. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part, the utmoſt ends of it. God was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed from all Eternity, the firſt Being that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was, and all others muſt own themſelves but of yeſterday, but God is <hi>from Everlaſting
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:001541_0032_0FB3AAE2758C9E40"/>
to Everlaſting,</hi> Pſal. 90.2. It is this God, who formed the earth, and laid the foundations of it alone; and He therefore hath the higheſt reaſon to govern it: Fathers of the fleſh, who give but (under God) a Being to their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and but the leſs noble part, the fleſh, are to be reverenced, and ſubmitted to, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9. The Father then of their Spirits may much more challenge ſubmiſſion &amp; ſubjection. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy Creator,</hi> Eccl. 12.1. carries with it an irrefragable argument, and motive, as well as duty.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 2. Conſider, <hi>That God is not only the Maker, but Preſerver of all.</hi> He nouriſhes, and brings them up; they are all at Gods finding; this is what the Church declares &amp; owns, in Neh. 9.6. <hi>Thou preſerveſt them all, &amp; the Hoſt of Heaven worſhippeth thee</hi>; and its a ſtrong argument why things on the Earth alſo ſhould do it, being all under the ſame Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Hand of Providence. It was the great aggravation of Iſraels Sin in the Wilderneſs, that when God had furniſhed a Table for them in that deſart Land, Opened the doors of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, rained down Manna upon them to eat, and given them of the Corn of Heaven, gave them Fleſh, and feathered Fowl; that yet for
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:001541_0033_0FB3AAE36E1F1D18"/>
all this, they ſhould Sin ſtill, and not believe, for his wondrous works, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.23. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In this great Family of the World, God takes care even of the bruit Creatures, provides for the Raven his food, fills the Appetite of the young Lions; and doth much more for Man, and hath therefore the greateſt reaſon to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that man ſhould be willing to ſerve Him, who is the great Benefactour: and therefore God enters his complaint againſt Iſrael, refers the equity of it to the ſenſeleſs creatures, to make judgment of it, <hi>That he had nouriſhed and brought up Children, &amp; they had rebelled againſt him,</hi> Iſai. 1.2, 3. Doing that which the bruit Beaſts in their kind would not do to their benefactour, but gave their labour to ſuch as provided a Crib for them.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 3. <hi>Gods Government muſt be owned, Becauſe He is indeed the beſt Governour in the World.</hi> He is as the firſt, ſo the beſt good: He is <hi>Optimus Maximus</hi>; He hath the moſt tranſcendent excellencies, and perfections i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginable, all in the higheſt degree, and it is impoſſible there ſhould be a better. We may without the leaſt ſhadow of flattery, and we ought to aſcribe to Him, the higheſt Encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums; and when we have ſaid all, it is but a
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:001541_0034_0FB3AAE507CD6408"/>
very little part of his Glory that we know or can expreſs: Whatever Wiſdom &amp; Conduct, is in Mortal Potentates here, falls infinitely ſhort of the Wiſdom of this Great GOD. <hi>Heman</hi> and <hi>Chalchel,</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf, tho' men of great Wiſdom, yet no way to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with God's, who is Wiſe in heart, and called the Onely Wiſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. Wiſe at all times, never did a fooliſh act; and as his Wiſdom excels the Wiſdom of all, ſo his Strength alſo, <hi>Job</hi> 9.4. None hath Arm like God; never was God put to a nonplus, but was able to do whatever he pleaſed to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Inhabitants of the World: He is in a Word, the Onely ONE, in whoſe Reign never any blemiſh could be really found, ſo Holy &amp; Juſt in all His Adminiſtrations, that nothing ever done by Him can be excepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.2. The leaſt thought of any ſuch thing was that which <hi>Elihu</hi> abhorred, <hi>Job</hi> 34.10, 12. And challenges any that could ſay, That God wrought ever any iniquity, <hi>Job</hi> 36.23. His own Will is indeed the higheſt Rule, by which God governs, but its ſo holy and juſt, that it is as impoſſible, that God ſhould do any wrong to any Creature, as it is for God to act againſt Himſelf contrary to His
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:001541_0035_0FB3AAE700BFE500"/>
Own Mind &amp; Will; and therefore tho' wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men complain ſometimes, as thoſe did in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18 29. To be puniſhed for the Sins of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> but God vindicates his own Act, &amp; declares, That their ways were unequal, and not the Lords<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that if they would repent and turn, iniquity ſhould not be their ruine. Gods judgment being a great deep, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways righteous, <hi>Pſal</hi> 36 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33.</p>
            <p>But to cloſe this head:</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 4. <hi>Its moſt certain, that Gods Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the Eaſieſt Government; His Laws are the moſt Juſt &amp; Equal.</hi> And if this be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, ſound Reaſon as well as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in every man will give its ſuffrage that God ſhould be Governour in Chief over all, and all deference, and ſubmiſſion ſhould be given to Him above and before any other; its ſo equal, that God reaſons the caſe, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.2, 3. And would have his People teſtify a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, if they knew any juſt cauſe to be weary of him: And in <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.5. Would have Iſrael tell, What iniquity they found in Him, to go far from Him. God governs indeed by Law, and will uphold the honour of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, not let his Authority be trampled upon, but will puniſh the contempt of it; but
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:001541_0036_0FB3AAE800631730"/>
He impoſes no grievous burdens, as men ſometimes do, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.46. Chriſts commands are not grievous, 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 5.3. And hence Chriſt aſſures us, <hi>That his Yoke is eaſy,</hi> and will be ſo where it is lined with love, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.30. And a new Nature given, which our bleſſed Lord hath purchaſed by his blood, and is One among the <hi>All things</hi> delivered Him by the Father, as is hinted, in <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.27. He being made of God to us, <hi>Sanctification,</hi> as well as Righteouſneſs, as we find inſerted, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. Its only therefore corrupt Nature that will complain, not Grace: And theſe Laws of Gods Government are the moſt beneficial, uſeful, and every way profitable to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: <hi>Godlineſs being profitable to all things, having the promiſe of this life, as well as that to come</hi>; ſo that upon the whole, it may be well called, a <hi>reaſonable Service,</hi> Rom. 12.1. And the eaſieſt in the World. And here, I might ſummon the experience of Chriſts faithful Subjects: <hi>David</hi> invites the faithful, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.8. <hi>O taſte and ſee that the Lord is good</hi>: What ſweetneſs did he find in Gods Laws! Read, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.10. <hi>They were ſweeter than honey</hi>; and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.16. It was his <hi>delight</hi>; and ſo 24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 72. <hi>verſes.</hi> And as God hath among us a
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:001541_0037_0FB3AAE969C98E38"/>
number of faithful &amp; loyal Subjects, ſo there are ſuch as have lived under both Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; Once were in a State of Nature, Now in a State of Grace; other Lords have had dominion over you, but thro' Grace you have ſubmitted to Gods Name, and His only; Surely you can ſpeak well of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and would not change this God, nor yield your ſelves to be Servants of Sin, and Satan again; you never repented your choice, but grieved only that you ſubmitted no ſooner thereto, and can readily give your Affidavit to the World, that it is the eaſieſt, and beſt Government, and far more eligible than to be under the Tyranny &amp; Bondage of Sin and Satan. But I muſt not enlarge any further, but come to the APPLICATION: Briefly, in a threefold USE; and firſt by way of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</p>
            <p>USE, I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We may hence learn, That if God be the Supreme Governour, and hath, as you have heard, ſuch an indubitable Right to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the World, <hi>That Sin, and eſpecially wilfull Sin, what ever Advocates it may have in the World, is certainly the moſt Malignant &amp; Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Evil, that can poſſibly be.</hi> The Laws of Gods Realm are ſo holy, juſt &amp; good, that
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:001541_0038_0FB3AAED44470438"/>
Sin which is the tranſgreſſion of ſuch Laws muſt needs be very Evil; and will be very bitter at laſt, how light a matter ſo ever men make of it; and ready to ſay, as <hi>Lot</hi> of his <hi>Zoar, Is it not a little One</hi>? When he would have it ſpared: But yet where it reigns, it is rebellion againſt the Lord, as it is a departing and wandring from the beſt Rule; ſo its diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to the higheſt Authority, it is a Traitour to the Crown, and dignity of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and deſerves exemplary Juſtice to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted upon it, uſurps the Government which is the Lords only due, its a ſlighting and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing of God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. Makes light of Gods Commands, ſets at nought his Counſel, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.25. Strikes at the very Being &amp; Eſſence of God; every ſuch reigning Sin would have no God. Its <hi>Deicidium,</hi> as the Schools call it, contrary to God as Lawgiver, Enmity in the abſtract to the Law of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. An act of diſloyalty to the Eternal God, like <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaloms</hi> Treaſon againſt his own Father, &amp; like <hi>Sheba</hi> lifts up its hand againſt the King, and therefore not to be dealt gently withal, but purſued, and brought to condign Puniſhment: It is Satans work who Sinned from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8. And was the <hi>Arch-rebell</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="unknown:001541_0039_0FB3AAEF9076EF70"/>
againſt Gods Government, would not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Gods Rule, and made it his work to draw man into that horrid conſpiracy, to take the Government on himſelf, and break off that yoke? And among men, we find Treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Government made ſuch a crime, that mens Lives and Eſtates are little enough to atone for ſuch an offence, and ſatisfy for ſuch a tranſgreſſion: the Law of Rebellion of Children againſt their Parents was in the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical Law a Capital offence, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. <hi>verſes.</hi> What then is Rebellion againſt the Living GOD: God hath proclaimed it to be the great enemy of His Government, and that ought not to reign in our Mortal Bodies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12. It being that abominable thing which his Soul hates, <hi>Jer.</hi> 44 4. And which he charges every one to have no fellowſhip with, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11. To hold no correſpond with this Rebellion, SIN, but bring it forth, that it may be ſlain, and deſtroyed, as <hi>Jehojada</hi> did with <hi>Athaliah,</hi> the uſurper of the Crown of <hi>Judah,</hi> 2 King. 11.15.</p>
            <p>But by way of Enquiry,</p>
            <p>USE, II. This Truth ſhould put us on ſearching our own hearts, and inquiring, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed we have really Owned, and in our
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:001541_0040_0FB3AAF10352EBF0"/>
hearts Submitted to God as we ſhould, &amp; ought to have done?</hi> Whether his Sovereign Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Government hath been ſo far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded among us in theſe ends of the World, as it ought, and ſhould have been. It is not enough to come as <hi>Huſhai</hi> ſometimes did to <hi>Abſalom</hi> with good words, <hi>Let the King Live</hi>; when in his heart it was King <hi>David,</hi> and not King <hi>Abſalom</hi> he meant. God knows all our hearts; Let us then ſee that our hearts be right in this matter. It is moſt certain, that we are by Profeſſion the Lords People: Our Predeceſſors openly profeſſed themſelves the Servants of the moſt High God, and that their Errand hither was to enjoy the Worſhip and Ordinances of God in their Power and Purity; and we are now a ſmall handful got into theſe Corners of the Earth, where I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume there are none amongſt us, that can poſſibly think themſelves out of Gods Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, but do certainly owe a duty of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and Allegiance, as to our Gracious QUEEN: ſo alſo to the KING of Heaven; and here GOD hath Mercifully increaſed and bleſſed us, He hath been accommodating us with all neceſſaries, and furniſhed our Tables in this Wilderneſs: Let us take heed of
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:001541_0041_0FB3AAF2A58F8A20"/>
               <hi>Jeſhuruns</hi> Sin, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.18. To be unmindful of, and forget the God who formed us; and made us His People: We have profeſſedly taken God for our King and Governour; He hath given us his book of Statutes, the Laws of His Kingdom; if we have not the firſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, what was written by His own hand, and the hands of his faithful Secretaries; yet we have well atteſted Copies of the ſame: and as He hath given us this to be the Rule of our Lives, ſo He hath told us, on what terms we may expect, that He will own and bleſs us; and I hope none of you are without a Copy of theſe Laws; You all have, or may eaſily get the Holy BIBLE to Read in, all the days of your Lives. The Enquiry then ſhould be, How far we have been careful as to call Chriſt our Lord; So to do what He hath ſaid to us, and enjoyned us to do? to allude to <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.46. He hath ſhewn us what is good, and what he requires of us; He hath the moſt inconteſtable right, and authority o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us; its not matter of indifferency, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we will obey or not, but of abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity on pain of his everlaſting diſpleaſure. I am ſatisfyed, God hath among us a great many good and faithful Subjects to His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:001541_0042_0FB3AAF3EBB97F28"/>
and Government, who readily, ſincerely and willingly ſubmit to His Laws &amp; Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among us, upright Men who would on no account be falſe &amp; treacherous, but care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to keep themſelves unſpotted from the World, and would not harbour Sin that ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Gods Government, nor countenance or ſuffer to their power, <hi>Wickedneſs to dwell in their Tabernacles</hi>; but are Mourners for the Sins which they cannot Reform. But I fear upon Enquiry, that there are too many who are too ſlight in this matter, and have cauſe to be aſhamed becauſe they have not a reſpect to, and for all our Lords Commandments: Many may be ready as <hi>Saul</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Amalek,</hi> to tell <hi>Samuel,</hi> that he had performed the Commandment of the Lord, which was to ſlay utterly that People, Young and Old, ſpare nothing, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.3. And yet had ſpared <hi>Agag,</hi> the beſt of the Sheep and Oxen, only the vile and refuſe they deſtroyed utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And its well if there be not ſome ſuch like evil among us, to allude to that Hiſtory; its well if there be not a great many groſs Corruptions. If you have been ſo faithful; What means the bleating of the Sheep and lowing of the Oxen in our Ears? What means,
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:001541_0043_0FB3AAF593735AD8"/>
I Pray, all that <hi>Pride</hi> in the Land, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo many humbling and impoveriſhing Providences by Sea and Land? So many <hi>Oaths</hi> and direful Imprecations? Such little regard to fear that dreadful <hi>Name, The Lord thy God?</hi> What Poyſon of Aſps is under the Lips of ſo many? What bruitiſh <hi>Drunkenneſs?</hi> Breaches of the <hi>Seventh Commandment</hi>? What a deal of Profanity, neglect of the Worſhip of God? How much Senſuality, Worldlineſs? Rules of Sobriety, Temperance and Juſtice are Violated. How many <hi>Agags,</hi> Maſter Sins ſpared, which ſhould have been hewed in pieces before the Lord? And all this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Warnings given by God in His Word and Works. What a terrible ſevere <hi>Mulct</hi> did God lay the laſt year on this poor Land, by thoſe fearful Judgments at Sea and Land: The ſore diſappointment at <hi>Canada,</hi> breaking our Ships with his Eaſt-Wind: And that deſolating <hi>FIRE</hi> in our Metropolis, laying ſo much of our Glory in Aſhes, deſtroying ſo many goodly Edifices, turning us out of doors, where theſe Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities have been ſo many years formerly Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated; both the Places, as if God were angry with both Orders among us: Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:001541_0044_0FB3AAF6F9EB6C50"/>
theſe with many other remarkable occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; and the continuance of the Heathen, and other Enemies rage againſt us, do moſt evidently indicate the Lords great diſpleaſure againſt this Land, and call aloud on all to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, What means the heat of this great anger? and to Reform &amp; Amend what ever is amiſs: Leſt God puniſh us yet ſeven times more for our walking ſo contrary to Him, and refuſing to ſubmit to His Government and Laws, ſo clearly Publiſhed, and ſo often Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, and urged on us to obſerve. But I muſt now haſten. In the laſt Place.</p>
            <p>USE, III. A word then of EXHOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TATION; and firſt of all to the Shields of this part of Gods Earth which belong to, and are put in by God to be the Fathers and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors of His People; and defend them from all Wrongs and Oppreſſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it then pleaſe Your</hi> EXCELLENCY;</p>
            <p>The Supreme Governour and Lord of all hath in kindneſs to this Land, Seated you in this Poſt of Honour, and made you under our gracious QUEEN, His Chief Miniſter of State, entruſting you with the Care &amp; Charge
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:001541_0045_0FB3AAF8810A53B0"/>
of His People, and furniſhed you with ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Accompliſhments for the diſcharge of the ſame, and ſent you for the Puniſhment of Evil Doers in His Realm, and for the Praiſe alſo and incouragment of ſuch as do well. Give me leave then with all due reſpect, to requeſt that your Excellency would pleaſe to lay out all your Talents for the upholding and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Honour of Gods Government, and His Laws, that He hath given out for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulating of all the Actions of the Children of Men. Let not Gods Authority be trampled upon; Its the Lord of all, who hath Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully continued you in this Poſt ſome years longer than your former Predeceſſors, whom the King of Heaven was pleaſed long ago to ſend for home. Permit me then to be your humble Monitor, and put you in Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, (though you know theſe things,) from whom it is you hold your Place; the King of Kings: and though our Governour, and ſo to be honoured, regarded, and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to, yet the God of Heaven is your Lord and Governour, to whom You and all of us muſt give an account for all our Betruſtments. Men in the higheſt Poſts on Earth are yet Servants to the Great GOD, and its certainly
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:001541_0046_0FB3AAFBF6675E40"/>
a Privilege as well as a duty ſo to be. Among men its a great honour to Serve in Kings Courts: All Officers about them are honourable; much more in Gods Court. The Epitaph on <hi>Moſes</hi> his Grave, and the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle given him by God was, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Moſes my Servant is Dead.</hi> Give me leave then only to Requeſt, You would be good and faithful to God, and His Intereſt, and Gods <hi>Euge</hi> will be better than all the Acclamations of Men whatever. Imitate good <hi>Nehemiah</hi>'s Pattern, <hi>Seek the welfare of this People</hi>; with <hi>Joſhua, Be Strong and very Couragious, and God will not fail nor forſake you.</hi> And that God who was with <hi>Moſes, Joſhua, David,</hi> lives ſtill, and is among us, and can make His Service a Place of Profit, as well as Honour, and in another World however, bountifully Reward ſuch as are careful to do the things which are pleaſing in His ſight in this World.</p>
            <p>Secondly. Thoſe Honourable Perſons, The Lieutenant GOVERNOUR and COUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SELLOURS, into whoſe Lap the Lot for Election of them may fall this day, to aſſiſt in Government. Let me entreat all of you, to tender the Honour and Glory of God above
<pb n="45" facs="unknown:001541_0047_0FB3AAFE0E80CC90"/>
all; Stand for and maintain the Honour of Gods Laws, which muſt be obſerved to the End of the World. Be careful to make no Laws repugnant to the Statutes of Gods Realm, diſpenſe with none of thoſe immutable Rules which God the Governour of all hath ſet down in His Word; no Mortal can make that Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful which God hath forbidden. Let all of you what Place ſo ever in the Government you ſuſtain, in the Legiſlative Power, or the Executive part of it; Be Men of Integrity and Truth; anſwer the great Expectation of God and His People: In all Emergencies what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, put to your helping hand. Say as <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caniah</hi> did to <hi>Ezra, We alſo will be with thee, Ezra</hi> 10.4. Take notice of all the diſorders in Gods Realm, do your utmoſt to Reform and Amend what poſſibly can be done; You are Gods Warrant-Officers; be Men fearing God at all times: Do Gods Work faithfully, and He will ſtand by you. <hi>Rehum</hi> the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, and the Enemies of the Jews, pretend to <hi>Artaxerxes, Ezra</hi> 4.14. Becauſe they had Maintenance from the Kings Palace, it was not meet for them to ſee the Kings diſhonour; What they pretended, it is certainly your duty with reſpect to the King of Heaven, and
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:001541_0048_0FB3AAFF2B1236F0"/>
is no way meet for you to ſee His great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, nor His Authority trampled on, who is King of all the Earth, and from whoſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace all have their Maintenance. Let no af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Popularity, or fear of Man, which brings a ſnare, impede you in Gods work: Let not Vice and groſs Immoralites go Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed: Be juſt in all your Adminiſtrations; You are called <hi>Gods, Pſal.</hi> 82.6. by God and by Men. Your Title is Worſhipful, Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to imitate your Maker, and Credit that Poſt God hath put you in.</p>
            <p>Third <hi>Branch of the Exhortation</hi>: To the Repreſentatives, and Worthy Gentlemen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the Government. Remember, you have a great Truſt committed to you. Let me requeſt that you would be faithful to God and His People. What was lodged formerly in the hands of a conſiderable body of People, is now devolved upon your Care &amp; Prudence. Be careful then in your choice, to chooſe ſuch as are really friends to the Government, (I mean) to the Great GOD and LORD of all. Chooſe none who are diſaffected to Gods Government; do not imagine your Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages are your own; there is a God among
<pb n="47" facs="unknown:001541_0049_0FB3AB00DADA38C8"/>
you, to whom you ſtand accountable for this, and every dayes work. Let all ſiniſter ends and by-reſpects be laid aſide: You muſt chooſe for God, as <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> told his Judges, <hi>They judged not for Man, but for the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6. For it muſt be remembred, You are under Gods Government, chooſing for God: Chooſe able Men, and ſuch as will do good Service for God and His People. And Remember, the Laws of Gods Realm are by a Multitude miſerably neglected; and you are entruſted with the Execution of them. You have done well to give your Civil San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and if any thing more can be done, it will be very pleaſing in the Lords ſight, for the Suppreſing thoſe groſs Vices which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound ſo much among us. We have indeed good Laws againſt Vice and Immorality, but there is certainly a fault among us, that they are not better Executed. I know Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, Juſtices of the Peace cannot be every where: God alone is Omnipreſent. I know alſo that care is taken, that annually Under Officers, <hi>Grand-jury-men, Tything-men,</hi> and <hi>Conſtables</hi> are Choſen, and all put under the Oath of God, to inquire after, and not let Criminals go Unpreſented for favour or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection;
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:001541_0050_0FB3AB0236E24330"/>
and were ſuch Under Officers ſo faithful as they ought, much Sin might doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs be Prevented &amp; Suppreſſed. But whilſt Offenders are ſo ſtudious, as to ſhift from one Town or County to another, and tarry but their year and day; and Officers take ſo little notice, to exhibit timely complaints; and are ſo dull of hearing, ſo ready to cloſe their eyes, as the Jews of old, with reſpect to Spiritual Truths: Sin abounds exceedingly. I confeſs, the burden is too heavy to be thrown too often on a few, and ſuch Places are what Men decline as much as may be, having from Men moſtly, the ill will of their Neighbours only, ſo that iniquity ſo prevails that its very difficult to find a faithful Man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.6. And this is our wound, and will be our wo; we may cry to God with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 12.1. <hi>Help Lord, for the Godly man ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, for the faithful fail from among the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Men.</hi> And indeed could any Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent be yet found, or remedy diſcovered, which might be equal to the miſchief, it is likely to bring upon us; it would certainly be a piece of good Service to the Crown of Heaven, and might be advantagious to the lengthening out the Tranquillity of this Land. But,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="unknown:001541_0051_0FB3AB03CAA904E8"/>Fourth <hi>Branch of this Exhortation,</hi> to the Lords Stewards, and Miniſters in His Houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Fathers,</hi> in many reſpects, and <hi>Brethren.</hi> It is indeed one part of our Miniſterial Work to put our Hearers in Remembrance of their duty, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.14. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6. If we would be good Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, but we our Selves alſo need to be put in mind of our Duty, and Place; though we know it, and are eſtabliſhed in the Truth: It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore very meet to Remember the Poſt we are in, and by whom it is we are put in, in this Supreme Government of God over the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and among his People; It hath been the pleaſure of His Grace to put us in as Stewards of the Myſteries of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. By Him entruſted to diſpenſe the Word of Truth, and give every one their Portion, according to thoſe Orders we have received from God our Maſter, rightly dividing the Word of Truth, as Workmen that need not be aſhamed; if we are but careful to approve our Selves to God, more than to pleaſe men, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. But who is ſufficient for theſe things? Its of ſuch Stewards moſt eſpecially required, <hi>That
<pb n="50" facs="unknown:001541_0052_0FB3AB05611CAB58"/>
they be found Faithful,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.2. Our Worthy Predeceſſors are gone off the Stage, ſent for home by their Lord and Maſter; Let us who are left behind, follow their faith, and conſider the End of their Converſation; and as in Doctrine, ſhewing Uncorruptneſs, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and Sincerity; ſo in all things, to ſhew our Selves Patterns of Good Works. Its the care of Souls, the nobleſt and beſt part of Man which is committed to us, and we muſt certainly give account to Him who will Judge both the Quick and Dead at His Appearing: but let us attend to Gods order to <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> with reſpect to his Hearers, <hi>Let them return to thee, but return thou not to them, and I will make thee unto this People, a fenced brazen Wall. And they ſhall fight againſt thee, but they ſhall not prevail, for I am with thee to ſave thee, and to deliver thee, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Jer. 15.19, 20. Let us endeavour to anſwer the Character given of <hi>Tychi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, A beloved Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and faithful Miniſter of the Lord,</hi> Eph. 6.21. And <hi>Epaphras, Col</hi> 1.7. If God ſay to us its <hi>Well Done,</hi> though men ſhould ſay it was <hi>ill done, unadviſedly ſpoke.</hi> We Serve a good God, who will paſs by, what a cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, critical Ear will find fault withall.
<pb n="51" facs="unknown:001541_0053_0FB3AB06F7F783C0"/>
We have a great many diſorders in Gods Houſe; We want a great deal of Wiſdom to know how we ought to behave our Selves in it, our difficulties and diſcouragements are many; We are expoſed to cenſures and hard Speeches; We live in a time of great Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy; but nothing muſt daunt or diſmay us; Let nothing put us, who are the Lords Commiſſion Officers, to throw up our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, or lay down our work, till God give us an honourable diſmiſſion out of the Field at laſt. Our Lords Joy will abundantly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſate all our Sorrows and Troubles. But I muſt not enlarge on theſe things.</p>
            <p>I have only One Word more to the Body of this People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>That they would all Remember and Turn to the Lord.</hi> Own Him as your Lord, Submit readily to His Government, Obey Him in all things, and hearken to His Voice. Let me pray that what ever hath been amiſs may be humbly Lamented over, and really and ſincerely at laſt Reformed. I preſume we have no ſuch Independents a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, but will moſt roadily Own their great Dependance is certainly on this God for all we need, for Time, and for Eternity.
<pb n="52" facs="unknown:001541_0054_0FB3AB0846D6FDE8"/>
Let all then ſhew themſelves Loyal Subjects to this Great KING, and Walk ſuitably as ſuch: We are now on our good Behaviour, and its only <hi>Quam diu ſe bene geſſerint,</hi> that God will own us and bleſs us. And here I might bring in all the reaſons of the Doctrine, to be improved as ſo many Motives to preſs you to a chearful and willing Subjection to this Government; but I ſhall be too tedious. I have only one more Motive to proſs and compel you to come in; and this is to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that our Protection and Safety in this day of Trouble, this time of Battel and War, depends moſt certainly on our Obedience</hi>: Kings do protect their Subjects: but a Subject may ſo tranſgreſs, as to be Out-lawed by Him: We have moſt certainly done enough to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord, to do ſo by us, to Out-law us, and throw us out of His Protection: But God is a Patient, and a good God, but it is our Wiſdom not to Provoke Him too far: We are a naked People: What terrible work do the Heathen (a contemptible Enemy as we accounted them,) make among us every Year? How many ever and anon cut off, and deſtroyed? and how eaſily can God hiſs for the fly; to allude to what we find, <hi>Iſai</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="unknown:001541_0055_0FB3AB0A6B1849A0"/>
7.18. That is in the uttermoſt part of the Rivers of Aegypt, to come upon us; and the Bee of Aſſyria to infeſt our Coaſts? And what this Summer will Produce, we know not: God hath indeed made many gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in His Word, but there are Conditions to be performed on our part; and if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe and rebel againſt Him, He will deliver us into the Hands of Men, Proclaim a liberty to the Sword, as He threatned <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Jer. 34.17. He can break down the Hedge, take away the Wall, let us be a prey to any who will devour us. Let all therefore Remember and Turn: Make God our friend, and He can ſoon ſubdue our Enemies, and turn His Hand againſt our Adverſaries; He can cauſe us to dwell in ſafety alone, and it then may be ſaid of us, with which I cloſe, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.29. <hi>Happy art thou O Iſrael: Who is like unto thee, O People! ſaved by the Lord, the ſhield of thy help, and who is the ſword of thy excellency: and thine enemies ſhall be found liars unto thee, and thou ſhalt tread upon their high places.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
