<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nepenthes evangelicum. A brief essay, upon a soul at ease; in what piety will bring both parents and children to. : A sermon occasion'd by the death of a religious matron, Mrs. Mary Rock. Who having entred the eighty first year of her age, withdrew from us. 30d. 7m. 1713. / By Cotton Mather, D.D. ; [One line from Matthew]</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N01367</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N01367</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 1624</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX2558</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">1624</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99019293</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 1624.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N01367)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 1624)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 1624)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nepenthes evangelicum. A brief essay, upon a soul at ease; in what piety will bring both parents and children to. : A sermon occasion'd by the death of a religious matron, Mrs. Mary Rock. Who having entred the eighty first year of her age, withdrew from us. 30d. 7m. 1713. / By Cotton Mather, D.D. ; [One line from Matthew]</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p. ;  (12mo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Fleet, for Daniel Henchman at his shop in King-Street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1713.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: A soul at ease.</note>
                  <note>Running title: A brief essay upon a soul at ease.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rock, Mary, 1633-1713.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  1713.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:001624_0000_0FB3E355A9B80208"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:001624_0001_0FB3E35727CD4908"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEPENTHES <hi>Evangelicum.</hi> A brief ESSAY, UPON A SOUL at EASE; In what PIETY will bring both PARENTS and CHILDREN to. A SERMON Occaſion'd by the DEATH of a Religious Matron, <hi>Mrs.</hi> Mary Rock. Who having entred the Eighty firſt Year of her Age, withdrew from us. 30 <abbr>d.</abbr> 7 <abbr>m.</abbr> 1713.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Cotton Mather,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Matth. XXVI. 13.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>It ſhall be told for a Memorial of her.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Fleet,</hi> for <hi>David Henchman</hi> at his Shop in <hi>King-Street.</hi> 1713.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="unknown:001624_0002_0FB3E358A70F7B30"/>
            <head>A SOUL at EASE.</head>
            <head type="sub">BOSTON-Lecture, 1 d. 8 m. 1713.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſal. XXV. 13,</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>His Soul ſhall dwell at Eaſe; and his Seed ſhall inherit the Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Text I now Read, had not been Readd unto you, if the Providence of God had not furniſhed me with an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Commentary</hi> upon it. Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day there took her Flight from us, an Excellent Handmaid of the Lord, in whoſe <hi>Diſpoſitions</hi> and <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> my Text had a moſt Emphatical, and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable <hi>Commentary.</hi> And I ſhall do but what is required in the <hi>Fifth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> if I take this Opportunity of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:001624_0003_0FB3E35A2574F570"/>a Juſtice to the <hi>Memory</hi> of a <hi>Juſt One,</hi> whom we all agree to Honour as a <hi>Mother Iſrael:</hi> And for whom we are this Day, <hi>Bow'd down heavily, as One that Mourneth for his Mother.</hi> A Perſon, who was One of the <hi>Firſt-born,</hi> if not the <hi>very Firſt</hi> of her Sex that was Born, in this famous <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh-America:</hi> And who deſerves to be Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably Mentioned, as long as <hi>BOS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON</hi> ſhall endure, which, I hope, will be unto the ſecond Coming of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. May it be an happy Omen, that <hi>Many Daughters</hi> of this our <hi>New-Engliſh Jeruſalem</hi> will <hi>do Virtuouſly,</hi> when we ſee the <hi>Firſt</hi> of them, like another <hi>M<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>am,</hi> (her Names-ſake) leading them in the Praiſes of God.</p>
            <p>I will not loſe the Sight of <hi>Her,</hi> tho' I will for an Hour ſeem to addreſs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Text, that I have choſen on her Occaſion: A Text, wherein I ſee both the <hi>Bleſſings of the Upper-Springs,</hi> and the <hi>Bleſſings of the Nether-Spring,</hi> flowing unto us. Our God has this in His Order for our Meeting this Day; <hi>Gather the People together, and I will give them Water.</hi> O Congregation, Sing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:001624_0004_0FB3E35BB07C0878"/>the Song of <hi>Iſrael; Spring up, O Well; Sing ye unto it!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I verily believe, that Bleſſings to be received in <hi>another World,</hi> are here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged unto the <hi>Fear of God.</hi> But, I find, Interpreters do generally underſtand certain Bleſſings to be received in <hi>this World.</hi> And I know, That <hi>Godlineſs</hi> has <hi>the Promiſe of the Life that now is,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Life that is to come.</hi> I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſo far to comply with the <hi>Voice of the Board</hi> of Interpreters, as to employ firſt a Diſcourſe on certain Bleſſings, which Piety will obtain for us, in the <hi>Life that now is.</hi> But I foreſee, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have done, the Bleſſings which Piety will obtain for us in the <hi>Life that is to come,</hi> will break in upon our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations. We ſhall be unavoidably, and as it were by Surprize, led into the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations of them.</p>
            <p>You may behold here, a <hi>Conjunction</hi> of Bleſſings: An <hi>Aſpect</hi> full of Happineſs. One is, An <hi>Eaſy Soul.</hi> The other is, An <hi>Happy Seed.</hi> Indeed there is a very great <hi>Adaptation</hi> in the mention of theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. They are very <hi>Aptly</hi> joined. Our departing <hi>Soul</hi> does not fall into <hi>Uneaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="unknown:001624_0005_0FB3E35D2F001AC0"/>on any Point more ſenſibly, than the Condition of our <hi>Seed.</hi> That which makes us very <hi>Uneaſy,</hi> is, our Thoughts, <hi>What may become of our Children.</hi> O God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fearing Man, <hi>Fear nothing;</hi> let thy <hi>Soul dwell at Eaſe;</hi> thy <hi>Offspring</hi> ſhall be well provided for.</p>
            <p>This is the DOCTRINE that is now ready for you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To Live in the true Fear of God, is the way to Lodge in a ſweet Eaſe of Soul: And they that fear God have this good Thing particularly to make them Eaſy, that their Children after them ſhall fare the better for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ We will begin with the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age which our Piety will bring to <hi>Our ſelves:</hi> The Advantage of, <hi>An eaſy Soul The Fear of the Lord will be the Eaſe of the Soul that has it.</hi> Piety will reſcue the Soul from <hi>Diſturbance,</hi> from <hi>Vexation,</hi> from ſuch Troubles and ſuch Tumults, as will elſe Diſcompoſe it wonderfully.</p>
            <p>We will firſt of all take Notice of ſome <hi>General Inſtructions,</hi> about the <hi>Eaſe
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:001624_0006_0FB3E35EB2391228"/>of Soul</hi> which Piety will be attended withal. If Miniſters would accurately conſult the Languages wherein our God has written His Oracles unto us, they would often find ſuch <hi>Hints,</hi> as would otherwiſe paſs unobſerved, tho' moſt highly worthy of Obſervation. Here is an Inſtance. There is an Inſtructive Elegance and Emphaſis, yea, a Variety of Inſtructions, in that Expreſſion, <hi>His Soul ſhall dwell at Eaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt. The <hi>Eaſe</hi> of Mind obtained by Piety, will be a <hi>Laſting Eaſe.</hi> Our Soul will <hi>Dwell</hi> in it. Our <hi>Abode</hi> will be in <hi>Eaſe.</hi> We ſhall have an <hi>Abiding Eaſe.</hi> There will be a <hi>Continuance</hi> of our <hi>Eaſe.</hi> We enter into it, at our <hi>Firſt Converſion</hi> unto Piety; we ſhall remain in it, unto all <hi>Eternity.</hi> It won't be the ſhort Blaze of <hi>Thorns Crackling under a Pot.</hi> When, I pray, when will it come to an End? Not until the <hi>Soul</hi> it ſelf come to an End: A Lamp of God, that ſhall Burn forever. The Account is a <hi>Joyful</hi> One, a <hi>Pleaſant</hi> One: Pſal. XVI. 11. <hi>Fulneſs of Joy, and Pleaſures forevermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly. The <hi>Eaſe</hi> of Mind attain'd by Piety, is to be enjoy'd in the <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:001624_0007_0FB3E36037877FF8"/>Time</hi> that paſſes over us. Our Soul ſhall <hi>ſpend the Night</hi> in it. This is the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Word uſed here. When 'tis with us, a <hi>Night</hi> of Darkneſs and Sorrow, even <hi>then</hi> we ſhall be <hi>at Eaſe.</hi> There ſhall ariſe unto us <hi>Light in Darkneſs.</hi> We ſhall meet with ſuch Things as will give us <hi>Eaſe,</hi> and <hi>Revive us, when we Walk in the midſt of Trouble.</hi> When 'tis a very <hi>Dark Time</hi> with us, and a <hi>Midnight</hi> of Confuſion is on our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and our Fleſh can <hi>See nothing</hi> but Hazard and Horror on every ſide, <hi>Now</hi> is the Time that Piety will give <hi>Eaſe</hi> unto us. It will do that Thing; Job XXXV. 10. <hi>Give Songs in the Night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly. The <hi>Soul</hi> is the <hi>Seat</hi> of that <hi>Eaſe</hi> which is attain'd by Piety. Our <hi>Body</hi> may be <hi>ill at Eaſe,</hi> notwithſtanding our Piety. A Pious Man may have a <hi>Diſeaſed Body;</hi> a <hi>Body,</hi> that ſhall be as they ſaid the Laborious <hi>Calvin's</hi> was, <hi>An Hoſpital of Diſeaſes;</hi> a <hi>Body</hi> that ſhall <hi>Feel,</hi> as <hi>Timothies</hi> did, <hi>Often Infirmities. Lord, One whom thou Loveſt, is Sick!</hi> But the <hi>Soul</hi> may be <hi>at Eaſe,</hi> when the <hi>Body</hi> is in Pain. When the <hi>Outward Man</hi> is even broken to Pieces, Piety will enable us to
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:001624_0008_0FB3E361B3776E28"/>ſay ſtill, <hi>My Mind is Eaſy!</hi> Our <hi>Soul</hi> ſhall be <hi>Sedate,</hi> yea, <hi>Solac'd,</hi> when our <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man</hi> is never ſo much off the Hinges. If Piety would only Eaſe the <hi>Body,</hi> we ſhould call it, <hi>A Phyſician of no Value.</hi> 'Tis the <hi>Soul,</hi> the <hi>Soul,</hi> that moſt wants to be made <hi>Eaſy. Eaſineſs</hi> in the <hi>Outward Man</hi> indeed cannot be expected here: This is a World that has <hi>Thorns</hi> every where growing in it. But now, the Boaſt of Piety is that; <hi>Luk.</hi> I. 46, 47. <hi>My Soul does Magnify the Lord; my Spirit has Rejoiced in God my Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We will now go on in the next Place, to <hi>Enquire</hi> more Particularly. What is that <hi>Eaſe</hi> which Piety brings to the <hi>Soul?</hi> And, Whence that <hi>Eaſe</hi> of the <hi>Soul</hi> ariſes? Diverſe MAXIMS of PIETY are to be taken into our Conſideration, and for our Encouragement in the courſe of Piety. By theſe MAXIMS, the <hi>Enquiry</hi> will be ſufficiently anſwered.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Piety brings us to <hi>Dwell</hi> in a <hi>Good State:</hi> And, Oh! the Glorious <hi>Eaſe</hi> which belongs to the <hi>Soul</hi> of that Man, who finds himſelf to be fixed in a <hi>Good State</hi> for Perpetuity! What we render, <hi>His Soul ſhall Dwell at Eaſe,</hi> is in the
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:001624_0009_0FB3E36337D28318"/>Original, <hi>His Soul ſhall dwell in Good.</hi> It is an <hi>Eaſe</hi> flowing from a Senſe of <hi>Good.</hi> A <hi>Good State</hi> makes the Mind <hi>Eaſy.</hi> By the <hi>Fear of God</hi> we are brought into a <hi>Good State.</hi> And that our Mind may <hi>Dwell at Eaſe,</hi> the <hi>Fear of</hi> God will bring us to <hi>Dwell in a Good State.</hi> We ſhall be fixed in it. The <hi>New Covenant</hi> is a <hi>Good</hi> Covenant. It is called, <hi>The Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Covenant.</hi> Piety ſettles us under the <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi> A Soul <hi>ſettled</hi> under the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> may Sing that Song; Pſal. CXVI. <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Return to thy Reſt, O my Soul, for the Lord has deals Bountifully with thee.</hi> My Friend, what is there now to <hi>Diſquiet</hi> thy Soul? Thou art in a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> which makes over the Alſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient GOD unto thee for thy Portion: Surely a moſt <hi>ſufficient Portion!</hi> A <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> that puts thee into the Hands of a moſt Powerful and Merciful <hi>Saviour:</hi> And none can <hi>Pluck thee out of thoſe Hands!</hi> A <hi>Covenant,</hi> that provides a full Supply of all thy <hi>Wants,</hi> a full Relief of all thy <hi>Fears,</hi> a Defence from all <hi>Damage</hi> in this World, and a Perfection of all <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> in the World to come. Soul, Do but now ſincerely ſay, <hi>Great GOD,
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:001624_0010_0FB3E364AD157D18"/>Be then my God; And Glorious JESUS, let me by thy Merit, and thy Conduct, be brought home unto God!</hi> So from this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this will be <hi>thy Covenant.</hi> A Soul in ſuch a <hi>Covenant,</hi> may <hi>Dwell at Eaſe;</hi> and always think, <hi>I am well, I am well; I have all that my Soul can wiſh for!</hi> 'Tis a <hi>Soul</hi> that <hi>Inherits all Things:</hi> A Soul that has GOD for a <hi>Father:</hi> One whoſe <hi>Father</hi> is, <hi>The High Poſſeſſor of Heaven and Earth:</hi> To be the <hi>Heir</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Care</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Father; Soul, take thine Eaſe; thou haſt Goods laid up,</hi> not <hi>for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years,</hi> but for Eternal Ages!</p>
            <p n="2">II. To <hi>Dwell</hi> in CHRIST and in GOD, is to <hi>Dwell at Eaſe:</hi> Piety brings us to ſuch a <hi>Dwelling.</hi> It brings to what may be the Verſion of the Clauſe we are upon; <hi>His Soul ſhall dwell with the GOOD ONE.</hi> And who that is, we know very well. By the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> we come to <hi>Dwell</hi> in the Glorious ONE, who is <hi>Goodneſs</hi> it ſelf. The Note of the <hi>Fear of God</hi> is that; <hi>Lord, Toon haſt been our Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling I lace in all Generations.</hi> Oh! moſt <hi>Eaſy Dwelling Flace!</hi> Piety brings us to Dwell in a CHRIST; And ſo to do, is to <hi>Dwell in a Rock.</hi> The Believer flies
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:001624_0011_0FB3E36638334888"/>to a <hi>Chriſt</hi> as to a <hi>Rock,</hi> and ſays, <hi>Here will I Dwell, for I have deſired it!</hi> Such an one, <hi>Dwells in me, and I in him,</hi> ſaith our Lord. It may be ſaid unto the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, what we Read; Num. XXIV. 21. <hi>Strong is thy Dwelling-Place, and thou put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thy Neſt in a Rock.</hi> Oh! the <hi>Safety</hi> of ſuch a Dwelling! Oh! how exceeding <hi>Wiſe</hi> the Soul that makes Choice of ſuch a Dwelling! A <hi>Feeble</hi> Soul, that has made an <hi>Houſe</hi> in ſuch a <hi>Rock,</hi> may well be an <hi>Eaſy Soul!</hi> O <hi>Soul in Chriſt;</hi> What, what ſhould hinder thy being a <hi>Soul at Eaſe?</hi> The Great GOD becomes the <hi>Habitation</hi> of ſuch a Soul. We Read, 1. Joh. III. 24. <hi>He that keeps His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, dwells in Him.</hi> And how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently Accommodated muſt the Soul be, which <hi>Dwells in God!</hi> Certainly, in the Infinite GOD, there is enough to make an <hi>Happy Soul;</hi> and therefore an <hi>Eaſy Soul.</hi> A Soul in GOD, is a <hi>Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheltered Soul.</hi> He who <hi>Dwells in the ſecret Place of the moſt High,</hi> and <hi>abides under the Shadow of the Almighty,</hi> ſuch an one will ſay of the Lord, <hi>He is my Refuge, my God; in Him I will truſt.</hi> The Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all this Metaphor is thus much;
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:001624_0012_0FB3E367AEBAD460"/>(for I will uncloath it:) By Piety we <hi>Repair</hi> to God in Chriſt; We <hi>Secure</hi> His Friendſhip, His Favour, His ready Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour; We <hi>Converſe</hi> with Him continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; We are taken under His Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. A Soul dwelling <hi>here;</hi> may <hi>Dwell at Eaſe.</hi> What can there be to Annoy ſuch a Soul?</p>
            <p n="3">III. To <hi>Dwell in Peace</hi> is to <hi>Dwell at Eaſe.</hi> Piety brings us to <hi>Peace:</hi> The <hi>Pathes</hi> thereof are <hi>Pathes of Peace.</hi> To be at <hi>Peace with God,</hi> This, this is to be <hi>Eaſy;</hi> and hereby, <hi>Good ſhall come unto thee.</hi> Now, by the <hi>Fear of God</hi> we come into it. We Read; Pſal. CXIX. 165. <hi>Great Peace have they which love thy Law, and nothing ſhall Offend them.</hi> Piety brings us to the <hi>Pardon</hi> of our Sin. The <hi>Guilt of Sin,</hi> is the moſt heavy <hi>Load</hi> that ever was heard of; A <hi>Load</hi> enough to break the Back of an <hi>Angel!</hi> What would a Soul thoroughly Awakened, and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Terrified with the <hi>Guilt of Sin,</hi> give to <hi>be Eaſed</hi> of ſuch a ponderous <hi>Load?</hi> Piety carries the <hi>Laden Soul</hi> to the <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> of that Saviour, who ſays, <hi>Come to me, and I will give thee Reſt!</hi> O Soul coming to Piety and Repentance: The
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:001624_0013_0FB3E36A295EB6A8"/>Voice of Heaven to thee, is that; Math. IX. 2. <hi>Be of good Cheer, thy Sins are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given thee.</hi> 'Tis; <hi>Be at Eaſe, the Lord has put away thy Sin; Thou ſhalt not Die.</hi> A Soul Glorifying the Holy God in the ways of Piety, is a Soul <hi>Reconciled</hi> unto GOD. The <hi>Wrath</hi> of GOD is <hi>turned away</hi> from that Soul: That Soul, being <hi>Juſtified by Faith, has Peace with GOD.</hi> The Song of that <hi>Eaſed Soul</hi> may be, <hi>I will Praiſe Thee, O Lord, becauſe tho' thou waſt Angry with me, Thine Anger is turned away.</hi> And what follows? <hi>Thou doſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me.</hi> A <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Conſcience!</hi> A <hi>Soul dwelling at Eaſe,</hi> is a <hi>Pacified Conſcience,</hi> a <hi>Peaceable Conſcience;</hi> A <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which from the <hi>Blood</hi> of a Saviour ſprinkled upon it ſpeaks <hi>Peace</hi> to the pardoned Sinner. In the Wiſdom of the Ancients, the Note was, <hi>Haec eſt Animae Suaviſſima ut Saluberrima Requies.</hi> A <hi>Conſcience</hi> Rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Roaring with Guilty Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, is of all things the moſt Into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable: Such a <hi>Wounded Spirit, who can bear it? who can bear it?</hi> The Soul is <hi>Eaſed,</hi> when the Painful and Grievous <hi>Wounds</hi> of the <hi>Conſcience</hi> are healed. A <hi>Conſcience</hi> quieted, by the <hi>Blood of the Son
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:001624_0014_0FB3E36B786053C8"/>of God Cleanſing from all Sin,</hi> this renders an <hi>Eaſy</hi> Soul. Piety brings a <hi>Quiet</hi> unto the <hi>Conſcience.</hi> It ſpeaks <hi>Peace</hi> to the Soul. Soul, <hi>Dwell at Eaſe,</hi> when thy <hi>Conſcience</hi> has in it, that <hi>Peace of God that paſſes Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</hi> A Soul at a <hi>continual Feaſt,</hi> ſurely is a Soul <hi>dwelling at Eaſe.</hi> A <hi>Good Conſcience</hi> is a <hi>continual Feaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>Holineſs</hi> brings <hi>Eaſe</hi> to the Soul, by <hi>Healing</hi> the <hi>Diſtempers</hi> of the Soul. The Fruit of Piety is an <hi>Healed Soul;</hi> therefore an <hi>Eaſy</hi> one. An <hi>Holy</hi> Soul, is an <hi>Healed Soul.</hi> The <hi>Fear of God</hi> is <hi>Health</hi> to the Soul, and <hi>Marrow</hi> to the Mind; It makes an <hi>Healthy</hi> Soul. The <hi>Paſſions</hi> of the Soul, are the Things which will not let it be <hi>Eaſy;</hi> Things which break the <hi>Reſt</hi> of it. Hence 'tis that we Read; Iſa. LVII. 20, 21. <hi>The Wicked are like the troubled Sea, which cannot Reſt; There is no Peace, ſaith my God unto the Wicked.</hi> Piety <hi>Cures</hi> our <hi>Paſſions;</hi> Moderates them; Regulates them. In Piety the Soul is brought into <hi>Order;</hi> The <hi>Diſorders</hi> of the Soul are mightily Rectified. This makes an <hi>Eaſy Soul.</hi> A <hi>Luſt</hi> in the Soul, is a <hi>Thorn</hi> in the Soul. The Soul cannot be at <hi>Eaſe,</hi> while a <hi>Luſt</hi> is Inflaming and
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:001624_0015_0FB3E36CF3949318"/>Enraging of it. Piety pulls out the <hi>Thorn.</hi> Our Holy Saviour does in the Piety which He Works in us, <hi>Redeem us from all Iniquity.</hi> Piety will teach the Soul to <hi>Love</hi> nothing in this World <hi>Inordinately,</hi> and makes us willing to <hi>deny our ſelves</hi> of every thing that God would have us go without. Piety will teach the Soul to lay aſide all <hi>Inordinate Care;</hi> It will help us to <hi>caſt all our Care upon God,</hi> and put our Truſt in Him for the Iſſue of all. Oh! the <hi>Eaſe</hi> of the Soul, that can do ſuch things! <hi>Content</hi> makes an <hi>Eaſy Soul;</hi> yea, it is an <hi>Eaſy Soul.</hi> A Soul <hi>Dwelling at Eaſe,</hi> is a Soul <hi>contented</hi> with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which God has appointed for us. Piety brings us to <hi>Contentment.</hi> A Grand Leſſon which Piety teaches the Soul, is that; <hi>Be content with ſuch Things as you have.</hi> It brings the Soul to this Eaſy Frame; <hi>Lord, Not my Will, but thy will be done.</hi> We Read; 1. Tim. VI. 6. <hi>Piety with Contentment is great Gain. Piety</hi> will be with <hi>Contentment;</hi> and therefore it will bring us to <hi>great Eaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. Piety puts the Soul upon that <hi>Courſe,</hi> which <hi>Uſually,</hi> yea, <hi>Naturally</hi> brings <hi>Eaſe</hi> to the Soul. The <hi>Fear of God</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="unknown:001624_0016_0FB3E36E70309BE0"/>will always produce and excite <hi>Prayer</hi> to God. <hi>Every one that is Godly will Pray.</hi> Now <hi>Prayer</hi> is the trueſt <hi>Hearts-Eaſe.</hi> When the Soul is not well at <hi>Eaſe,</hi> the kind Invitation of Heaven unto us, is that; Pſal. LV. 22. <hi>Caſt thy Burden on the Lord.</hi> Piety will do this thing; and this throws off the <hi>Burden;</hi> This <hi>Eaſes</hi> the Soul. Whatever <hi>Diſtreſs</hi> be upon the Soul, Piety will ſay, <hi>Well, I will go tell my Father of it!</hi> If the Soul be in any Grief, Piety will <hi>Vent</hi> the Grief, in a <hi>Prayer</hi> to the Father of <hi>Mercies;</hi> A <hi>Prayer</hi> to the God who does <hi>not willingly Afflict or Grieve the Children of Men.</hi> The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of Piety is, <hi>To be careful for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but in every thing to preſent a Requeſt unto the Lord:</hi> Then follows, Phil. IV. 7. <hi>The Peace of God ſhall Garriſon your Heart and Minds thro' Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> at ſuch a rate, that the Enemies of your Tranquility ſhall not be able to break in up<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on you. Indeed, the <hi>Heart knows its own Bitterneſs;</hi> and we often know <hi>the Plague of our own Heart;</hi> A <hi>Grief</hi> that is known to none but our <hi>own Heart;</hi> none but <hi>we our ſelves</hi> are privy to it. But now, Piety will put this <hi>Grief</hi> into a
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:001624_0017_0FB3E36FE7BE5CB8"/>
               <hi>Prayer,</hi> and ſo carry it unto the Lord. A <hi>Grief</hi> carried thither, is <hi>eaſed</hi> by being ſo. Either the <hi>Ground</hi> of the Grief is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, or elſe the <hi>Senſe</hi> of <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Grief is aſſwaged; when it is by <hi>Prayer</hi> ſpread before the Lord. We Read of one who was of a <hi>ſorrowful Spirit,</hi> 1. Sam. I. 18. She could ſay, <hi>I have poured out my Soul unto the Lord;</hi> And anon, <hi>Her Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was no more Sad.</hi> Oh! No ſuch <hi>Anodyne,</hi> for an unquiet Soul! A <hi>Praying</hi> Poſture is an <hi>Eaſy</hi> Poſture for the Soul. To fall down on the Knees, this <hi>eaſes</hi> the Soul. It was urged, Pſal. LXXXVI. 4. <hi>Rejoice the Soul of thy Servant; for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, O Lord, I do lift up my Soul.</hi> Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, To <hi>lift up the Soul unto the Lord,</hi> this Comforts the Soul, Gladdens the Soul, <hi>Eaſes</hi> the Soul: A <hi>Praying Soul</hi> takes the way to be an <hi>Eaſy Soul.</hi> There is no Caſe but <hi>Prayer</hi> will ſuit it: It is the <hi>Univerſal Medicine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. Piety <hi>Aſſures</hi> the Soul, that thoſe Things, which moſt threaten the <hi>Eaſe</hi> of the Soul, ſhall but promote the <hi>Good</hi> of it. The <hi>Fear of God</hi> will bring us to <hi>Dwell in Good,</hi> becauſe it aſſures us, that nothing ſhall befal us, but what ſhall
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:001624_0018_0FB3E3716C282F18"/>
               <hi>do us Good.</hi> So to <hi>Dwell in Good,</hi> is to <hi>Dwell at Eaſe.</hi> That which will not let us be <hi>Eaſy,</hi> is the <hi>Calamity</hi> whereto we are obnoxious. Our <hi>Diſaſters</hi> do ſpoil and break our <hi>Eaſe.</hi> We think we are <hi>Hurt,</hi> or we fear that we <hi>ſhall</hi> be ſo. But Piety brings us under the covert of that Word; Rom. VIII. 28. <hi>All things ſhall work together for Good, unto them that love God.</hi> Ah, Soul, that cannot be <hi>Eaſy!</hi> The Affliction which Diſcompoſes thee, and will not let thee be at <hi>Eaſe,</hi> will do thee no <hi>Hurt.</hi> It is a <hi>Faithful God,</hi> who ſends thy Affliction upon thee; One who ſays, <hi>I will do thee no Hurt:</hi> And thou ſhalt certainly find, <hi>That God has meant it unto Good.</hi> An excellent Servant of God, ſadly tortured with the Stone, would in the midſt of his Affliction cry out, <hi>I am upon my Fathers Rack.</hi> Child, Tho' thou mayſt be upon a <hi>Rack,</hi> yet it is thy <hi>Fathers Rack!</hi> Afflicted Soul, Conſider this; Realize this; <hi>My God is doing of me Good, by all His afflictive Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations!</hi> Why ſhouldeſt thou not be at <hi>Eaſe,</hi> when thou art ſure, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non thy Experience will be that; Pſal. CXIX. 7. <hi>It is good for me that I have
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:001624_0019_0FB3E372E77768A8"/>been Afflicted.</hi> Oh! <hi>Be at Eaſe;</hi> Thy <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty</hi> comes to make thee <hi>Rich in Faith.</hi> The <hi>Reproaches</hi> on thy Name, are to fit thee for a <hi>Crown of Glory.</hi> The <hi>Loſs of thy Friend,</hi> is that thou mayſt have the <hi>Good part that cannot be taken away. Be Eaſy;</hi> This <hi>Affliction,</hi> which <hi>for the preſent is not Joyous but Grievous,</hi> will <hi>Afterwards, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards!</hi>—be found for thy Benefit. The <hi>Fruits</hi> of it, will be ſuch as will Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and Faithfulneſs of God, in all His Dealings with thee: <hi>Peacable Fruits:</hi> Oh! let thy Soul be at <hi>Eaſe,</hi> and in <hi>Peace,</hi> from the Proſpect of them! That Hope, <hi>All for the Beſt, All for the Beſt!</hi> Methinks, it may always keep a Soul <hi>at Eaſe.</hi> A Soul ever Sailing on the <hi>pacific Sea;</hi> while Bound unto the <hi>Port</hi> which I am now preſently to tell you of.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Piety will provide a <hi>Dwelling</hi> for the SOUL, <hi>after Death;</hi> and ſo <hi>good</hi> a <hi>Dwelling,</hi> that the <hi>Eaſe of Soul</hi> in it, will be <hi>Wonderful! Wonderful! Wonderful!</hi> The Bleſſings of the <hi>Life to come,</hi> are now, as I foretold, come unto us. The <hi>Fear of God</hi> provides an <hi>Eaſy Dwelling</hi> for the Soul of the Good Man, at the
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:001624_0020_0FB3E37493D1EDC8"/>Time when his <hi>Seed Inherits the Earth.</hi> At the time of our <hi>Death,</hi> it is that our Children enter upon the <hi>Inheritance</hi> that we leave unto them, and make their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of it. At <hi>this time</hi> the Soul of a Good Man ſhall have a <hi>Dwelling in Good;</hi> It ſhall dwell in a <hi>good State,</hi> and in a <hi>good Place,</hi> and therefore <hi>dwell at Eaſe.</hi> I am obliged unto the Famous <hi>Alting</hi> the Younger for this Illuſtration. The <hi>Immortality of the Soul</hi> is plainly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and Aſſerted in this Expectation. The <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> has moſt plainly Teſtified this Article of our Faith: It is not poſſible for any Words to be plainer or fuller for this Purpoſe, than thoſe Words of our Saviour; Matth. X. 28. <hi>They that Kill the Body, are not able to Kill the Soul.</hi> But Sirs, you ſee the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> alſo acknowledges it; An <hi>Eaſy Dwelling</hi> for a prepared Soul, when it leaves the <hi>Body.</hi> Let no Man be now ſo Bruitiſh, as to make any Doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he has an <hi>Immortal Soul</hi> or no. There is a late Infamous Bigot, whom they will needs have to paſs for a very <hi>Learned</hi> Man; that for a notable Proof of his Learning, has written a Diſcourſe
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:001624_0021_0FB3E375E920B3A8"/>to prove <hi>from the Scriptures and the Firſt Fathers, that the Soul is a Principle natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Mortal.</hi> You have ſeen the <hi>Scriptures</hi> Condemn that Fooliſh Man; and one cannot well Imagine, with what Face, he could call in the <hi>Fathers</hi> to Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize his wicked Opinion. I may not be allow'd here to Digreſs for the Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of an Aſſertion made with ſo much of an Impudence, that cannot be accounted for: But I hope, <hi>Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> may paſs for one of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> who in his <hi>Apology,</hi> over and over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain aſſerts, All <hi>Departed Souls</hi> to be in a <hi>ſtate of Senſibility;</hi> All of them to have a <hi>Senſation</hi> continued unto them. Well, but what comes of a God-fearing, and ſo a prepared Soul, when it muſt no longer <hi>Dwell</hi> in the <hi>Body?</hi> The <hi>Soul</hi> is by Death, turned out of its <hi>Dwelling;</hi> turned out of Doors. But a <hi>Regenerated</hi> Soul, a Sanctified Soul, a Purified Soul, finds a <hi>Dwelling</hi> at its Departure hence; A Comfortable <hi>Dwelling;</hi> A <hi>Dwelling</hi> where it ſhall <hi>be comforted.</hi> Our Saviour who is gone to prepare them for us, has told us, Luk. XVI. 9. <hi>When ye fail, they ſhall receive you into everlaſting Habitations.</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="unknown:001624_0022_0FB3E377725FB8B0"/>Our Sin has brought us into <hi>Debt</hi> unto the Juſtice of God. When we <hi>Die,</hi> the Creditor comes upon us for the <hi>Debt.</hi> Then <hi>we fail;</hi> we are <hi>Broke;</hi> we are <hi>Bankrupts.</hi> Our <hi>Dwelling</hi> is taken from us. We are turned out of All. But <hi>Then!</hi> our Compaſſionate Saviour has <hi>Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> for us, in His <hi>Heavenly Manſions.</hi> An Excellent Miniſter in <hi>Hereford-ſhire,</hi> not very long ago, uttering theſe Words, <hi>We know, that if our Earthly Houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, we have,</hi>— There he ſtopt; There he faltered; There he expired. Inſtead of Speaking the reſt, he went unto it. I will now ſpeak it.— <hi>A Building of God, an Houſe not made with Hands, Eternally in the Heavens.</hi> Would you know where the <hi>Dwelling</hi> is? Our Saviour ſaid unto the Dying Penitent; Luk. XXIII. 43. <hi>This Day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> Piety will bring to <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> The <hi>Dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of a Soul diſtinguiſhed by Piety, ſhall be in the <hi>Paradiſe</hi> of God: That which <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls <hi>Locum Divinae Amae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis recipiendis Sanctorum Spiritibus De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatum.</hi> Soul, During the <hi>Sleep</hi> of Death, and in the <hi>Days of Darkneſs,</hi> This, this
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:001624_0023_0FB3E378F8108DE8"/>will be the <hi>Lodging</hi> of the Soul: A <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe,</hi> where no <hi>Sin,</hi> and by Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, no <hi>Sorrow</hi> will cleave unto the Soul. A <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> where the Soul will be elevated unto ſuch <hi>Contemplations</hi> of Him, as to render it after ſome ſort, <hi>preſent with the Lord:</hi> A <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> where the Soul ſhall <hi>Feed on the Tree of Life,</hi> and be refreſhed by the Principle of <hi>Grace,</hi> which God has planted in it. O moſt <hi>eaſy Dwelling!</hi> We Read of the Dying Saints; Iſa. LVII. 2. They <hi>enter into Peace, they reſt in their Beds.</hi> Of the Soul Dwelling in ſuch a <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> we Read, <hi>It is Comforted.</hi> There is nothing to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Dwelling of ſuch a Soul <hi>Uneaſy,</hi> but only its remaining under that part of the <hi>Curſe;</hi> Its <hi>Body</hi> left Rotten in the <hi>Grave;</hi> and the Delay of the <hi>Reſurrection of the Dead,</hi> which it is waiting and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for. But even this Matter of <hi>Uneaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> is made <hi>Eaſy,</hi> by ſome Viſions of a Glorious CHRIST in the mean time enjoy'd, and the glad Aſſurance of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing er'e long Raiſed, and then taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the City of God.</p>
            <p>¶ But we will proceed now, to the Advantage which our Piety will bring
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:001624_0024_0FB3E37A70BCE208"/>to <hi>Ours:</hi> The Advantage of an <hi>Happy Seed. Good Men have this good Thing to make them Eaſy; their Children after them ſhall fare the better for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us Inform our ſelves upon what Account!</p>
            <p>Firſt. The Piety of <hi>Parents</hi> does bring their <hi>Children</hi> into the <hi>Covenant</hi> of God. Pious Parents give up <hi>Themſelves</hi> unto God, in His <hi>Covenant.</hi> But then, they give up their <hi>Children</hi> as well as <hi>Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;</hi> their Children as <hi>a part</hi> of Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The Reſult is that; Gen. XVII. 7. <hi>An everlaſting Covenant, to be a God unto thee, and unto thy Seed after thee.</hi> Oh! the <hi>Rich Inheritance</hi> of the <hi>Children</hi> thus brought into the <hi>Covenant</hi> of God, and of Grace! To <hi>Inherit the Earth,</hi> yea, to Inherit the whole World, is not ſo much as to have the great God in <hi>Covenant</hi> with us, for our <hi>Inheritance.</hi> It follows; If theſe Children Die in their <hi>Infancy,</hi> they have a Claim to all the Bleſſings of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> in the Eternal World. When the great GOD ſays, <hi>I will be the God of theſe Children,</hi> He intends, <hi>I will bring them to a part in the Heavenly City.</hi> O Pious Parents, your Dead Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:001624_0025_0FB3E37C0203C328"/>are but gone before you, into the Suburbs, and ſome Foretaſtes of that <hi>Inheritance,</hi> which you have ſecured for them. Yea, this Clauſe, <hi>They ſhall Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the Earth,</hi> muſt be a little more nicely thought upon. There is an <hi>Earth</hi> to be <hi>Inherited</hi> by theſe <hi>Children:</hi> Even that <hi>New Earth,</hi> wherein ſhall <hi>dwell Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs;</hi> that <hi>New Earth,</hi> over which they ſhall <hi>Reign, of whom is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Theſe <hi>Children of Abraham,</hi> are to be <hi>Heirs of the World;</hi> But in the <hi>World to come.</hi> When you Read of, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heriting the Earth,</hi> O Saints, look for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as far as <hi>that</hi> World, for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining, and the Fulfilling of it. If theſe Children ſhould ſurvive their <hi>Infancy,</hi> the <hi>Covenant</hi> has enſured this, That they ſhall have an <hi>Offer</hi> of the Goſpel; That Chriſt, and Grace, and Heaven, ſhall be <hi>Offered</hi> unto them. <hi>Unto them firſt</hi> is that Saviour ſent, that would <hi>Bleſs them in turning them from their Iniquities.</hi> O In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuable Priviledge!</p>
            <p>Secondly. Piety in Parents, does diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to purſue a <hi>Good Education</hi> for their <hi>Children.</hi> Of a Pious Parent, it was ſaid in Gen. XVIII. 19. <hi>I know him,
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:001624_0026_0FB3E37E34A6E990"/>that he will Command his Children, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord.</hi> Even ſo, Such a Parent, <hi>I know him;</hi> He will inſtil the <hi>Principles of Religion</hi> into his Children: They ſhall be well Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized Children. Such a Parent, <hi>I know him,</hi> He will inform his Children how to fly from <hi>Sin,</hi> and turn to <hi>God,</hi> and cloſe with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and walk in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the Doctrines of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi> Such a Parent, <hi>I know him,</hi> He will Adviſe his Children againſt the Pathes of the Deſtroyer, and reſtrain them and reſcue them with all poſſible Agony from thoſe Deſtructive Ways. 'Tis a vaſt Felicity, to have ſuch an <hi>Education!</hi> But there is one Point of <hi>Education</hi> more, that ſuch a Parent will beſtow upon his Children. He will find out a fit <hi>Employment</hi> for his Children: He will have them taught ſome <hi>Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> by which they may <hi>Inherit</hi> as much of the <hi>Earth</hi> as may be needful for them, and they may be Uſeful in their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: He will not bear, that they ſhould be brought up in <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> and prove meer <hi>Drones</hi> in the Hive of the Common-wealth. He makes to the
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:001624_0027_0FB3E37FC57AF058"/>World, an Honourable Preſent of <hi>Well-educated Children!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly. Piety is a <hi>Prayerful</hi> ſort of a Thing. Pious Parents will <hi>Pray</hi> for their <hi>Children.</hi> Pious Parents are <hi>Praying</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. They lay up a <hi>Stock of Prayers</hi> for their Children. We Read of ſuch an One; Job I. 5. <hi>He offered Sacrifices accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Number of all his Children.— Thus did Job continually.</hi> The Prayers of an <hi>Abraham</hi> for his <hi>Iſhmael, O my God, That my Son may Live in thy Sight!</hi> The Prayers of a <hi>David</hi> for his <hi>Solomon, O my God, That my Son may have a perfect Heart given to him!</hi> There is a mighty Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in theſe Prayers. They <hi>avail much;</hi> Pious Parents are always <hi>Travailing</hi> for their Children with them. Children, Theſe <hi>Prayers</hi> will not be loſt. It will be <hi>your Fault,</hi> if they be! The <hi>Relations</hi> that have been given in the Hiſtories of the Church, concerning the Succeſs of Prayer made by Pious Parents for their Children, before and after the Days of <hi>Monica</hi> have been many and Marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. I will now ſingle out One, which perhaps you have not met withal. I know the Name of a Worthy Man, who liv'd
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:001624_0028_0FB3E381365A5A38"/>ſome while ſince in the County of <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wal;</hi> and who had a Son wandring from God, and from him, under a very Vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Character. He procured a Number of Miniſters to join with him, in a <hi>Day of Prayer</hi> for the Converſion of that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal Son.</hi> On <hi>that very Day,</hi> Behold, the Prodigal returned, with a new Temper and Biaſs of Soul given to him. God bleſſed a Calamity that befel him, for his Awakening and Converſion; And from <hi>that very Day</hi> he became a New Creature, and a Servant of God. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this Worthy Man, when he lay a Dying, ſaid, <hi>I have Ten Children, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Nine are in Chriſt; God has converted Nine of them to ſerious Piety. I Die Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving for the Tenth; He alſo ſhall be brought home unto God.</hi> And this alſo was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed. Verily, The Children of ſuch Parents, are not ſoon to be deſpaired of!</p>
            <p>Fourthly. The <hi>Piety</hi> of <hi>Parents,</hi> does often beſpeak <hi>Proſperity</hi> for their <hi>Children.</hi> We Read; Prov. XX. 7. <hi>The Juſt Man walketh in his Integrity; His Children are bleſſed after him.</hi> 'Tis often ſo; Pious Parents have their Piety often <hi>Rewarded</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="unknown:001624_0029_0FB3E382B4F76AF0"/>in the Proſperity of their <hi>Children.</hi> They get their Eſtates Honeſtly; they wear well; their <hi>Children Inherit the Earth</hi> which they leave unto them; the <hi>Third Heir</hi> it may be Rejoices in what was left by his Grandfather. More than this; <hi>Pious Parents</hi> devote a <hi>Good Portion</hi> of their Eſtates to <hi>Pious</hi> Uſes. Yea, I muſt ſay unto you, They ALL do ſo! <hi>I</hi> ſay again, whatever Havock the Aſſertion may make among ſome <hi>Covetous Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites,</hi> They ALL do ſo. Now, this lays up a <hi>Good Portion</hi> for their <hi>Children.</hi> The Parents <hi>deviſe Liberal Things;</hi> the Children reap the Harveſt of that Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality. The <hi>Alms</hi> diſpenſed by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, are a <hi>Seed</hi> ſown in the Earth for the Children. 'Tis to <hi>caſt the Bread-corn into moiſt Ground,</hi> [which we are directed to do, Eccl. XI. 1. For 'tis to be Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated ſo:] It will <hi>be ſeen after many Days.</hi> The Children will have the Crop. After their <hi>Parents</hi> are laid in the <hi>Earth,</hi> even then the Children, as the Reward of their Piety, do <hi>Inherit the Earth.</hi> If the knowledge of their Children do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well, ſhould arrive unto the <hi>Souls</hi> of the Parents <hi>Dwelling at Eaſe,</hi>— But
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:001624_0030_0FB3E384293DCCE0"/>theſe are <hi>Secret Things.</hi> And I know, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>His Sons come to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and he knoweth it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>APPLICATION.</head>
               <p n="1">I. Let the Antitheſis now be call'd in; An Admonition Hearken'd to, that is to be Trembled at. <hi>The Soul of a Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man may not be at Eaſe;</hi> nay, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be at Eaſe. Ah, Impenitent Sinner, Where, where is thy <hi>Dwelling?</hi> Thy <hi>Dwelling</hi> is under an <hi>Old Covenant,</hi> which ſpeaks to thee none but very <hi>Uneaſy Things;</hi> even thoſe Things, Iſa. III. 10. <hi>Wo unto the Wicked, it ſhall be ill with him.</hi> It was of Old ſaid, <hi>Wo to them that are at Eaſe in Zion.</hi> But, O Sinner in <hi>Zion,</hi> How can you be at <hi>Eaſe</hi> when you think on the <hi>Wo</hi> that lies upon you? Is it not an <hi>Uneaſy</hi> Thing, to lye under the <hi>Wrath</hi> and <hi>Curſe</hi> of God? An <hi>Uneaſy</hi> Thing, to be a <hi>Slave</hi> unto <hi>Sin,</hi> unto <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> unto the moſt Cruel of all Task-maſters? An <hi>Uneaſy</hi> Thing, to be in hourly Danger of being ſiezed by the <hi>Meſſengers of Death,</hi> and forced away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Tribunal of a Righteous and a
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:001624_0031_0FB3E385B06DE748"/>Terrible God? Ah, poor Soul, Unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto God; There is Danger, leſt thy <hi>Dwelling</hi> be quickly in a Place of <hi>Torments;</hi> in the Place of <hi>Dragons!</hi> The Revelation which never deluded any Man, has forewarned thee of ſuch a <hi>Place:</hi> 'Tis no Deluſion! Oh! <hi>Who can dwill with everlaſting Burnings?</hi> But Sinful, and ſecure Soul, thou are in hourly Danger of going down to ſuch an <hi>uneaſy Dwelling.</hi> How, how canſt thou <hi>Dwell at Eaſe,</hi> in this Condition? It was demanded of ſuch as you, Jam. V. 1. <hi>Weep and Howl for the Miſeries that ſhall come upon you.</hi> Verily, The firſt and the beſt Thing to be deſired for you is, That you may not have a Soul <hi>dwelling at Eaſe</hi> in this Condition. I Wiſh thee very well, my Friend; But I cannot expreſs a more Charitable Wiſh for thee than this; That thou mayſt feel <hi>no Eaſe</hi> in thy Soul, till thou art got out of this Condition. <hi>Good God, make thou the Souls of our Unconverted Children, very Uneaſy, while they continue ſo!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. But now, let none that <hi>Fear God,</hi> be <hi>Enemies</hi> to the <hi>Eaſe</hi> of their <hi>Souls.</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="unknown:001624_0032_0FB3E3872B7A2468"/>O Pious ones, don't <hi>refuſe to be Comfored.</hi> Don't reject the <hi>Legacy</hi> of your <hi>Dying Saviour.</hi> Don't give way to any Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelming and Unreaſonable <hi>Uneaſineſs</hi> of Soul. That the <hi>Exhortation</hi> which now <hi>ſpeaks unto you, as unto Children,</hi> may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, you have three Things incumbent on you.</p>
               <p>One thing you have to do, is this. Your <hi>Title</hi> to an <hi>Eaſy Soul</hi> ſhould be cleared up. You ſhould get a clear Sight of it, and a well-grounded Aſſurance, <hi>That you are in good Terms with Heaven.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Examine</hi> your ſelves; with an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial <hi>Examination</hi> faithfully Search and Try your ſelves. Ask, <hi>Have I ſo Renounc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all my Idols, that the great God is now on the Throne in my Soul, above them all? And that He ſways more with me than any of them?</hi> Ask, <hi>Have I embraced my Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Saviour in all His Offices, and earneſtly Repaired unto Him for all the Benefits of His Great Salvation?</hi> Ask, <hi>Do I walk in the Fear of God, aw'd by His Eye upon me, lothe to Diſpleaſe Him? Have I an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſembled Love unto my Neighbour, and a Joy in his Wellfare? Is this World of leſs Account with me than the World to come?</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="unknown:001624_0033_0FB3E388B65685C0"/>To put it out of Doubt, that theſe Things are in you, Renew, Repeat, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> of the Soul, which may make you feel the Preſence of them. Do thoſe Things in a way of <hi>Mourning</hi> for Sin, and <hi>Turning</hi> to God, which when they are done, your Souls may &amp; ſhould then <hi>Dwell at Eaſe;</hi> The <hi>Things which accompany Salvation.</hi> And now ſay; Pſal. XLIII. <hi>5. Why art thou caſt down, O my Soul? And why art thou diſquieted within me? Hope in God, for I ſhall yet Praiſe Him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another thing you have to do, is this; Don't liſten to <hi>Temptations</hi> that would give <hi>cauſeleſs Diſturbance</hi> to the <hi>Eaſe</hi> of your Souls. A buſy Tempter, who <hi>ſeeks Reſt and finds none,</hi> is he who breaks yours as much as he can. But as you Read; Pſal. XI. 1. <hi>In the Lord I put my Truſt. How ſay ye to my Soul, Flee as a Bird unto your Mountain?</hi> Thus Repel them who <hi>Trouble</hi> you:
<q>
                     <hi>How ſay ye to my Soul,</hi> Thy <hi>Sins</hi> are too many, too heinous, to be Forgiven? <hi>I put my Truſt</hi> in the <hi>Blood</hi> of the Son of God, which <hi>cleanſeth from all Sin? How ſay ye to my Soul,</hi> The <hi>Spirit of God</hi> is utterly departed from
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:001624_0034_0FB3E38A24ACC758"/>thee? <hi>I put my Truſt,</hi> That I have the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> at Work upon me, even in my <hi>Fears</hi> of His Departure? <hi>How ſay ye to my Soul,</hi> Thou haſt ſuch an <hi>hard Heart,</hi> as carries the Mark of one Rejected of God? My <hi>Truſt</hi> is, That my Heart begins to <hi>Soften,</hi> inaſmuch as I begin to feel the <hi>hardneſs</hi> of it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>A third Thing you have to do is this; Lye down upon a <hi>Pillow</hi> ſtuff'd with the <hi>Promiſes.</hi> A Soul ſupplied with, and applying of the <hi>Promiſes,</hi> may ſoon come to this <hi>Eaſineſs?</hi> Pſal. IV. 8. <hi>I will lay me down in Peace, and Sleep; for O Lord, thou alone makeſt me Dwell in Safety.</hi> In the Poetical Antiquity and Mythology, there was a Celebrated <hi>Nepenthes,</hi> [or <hi>No-Grief</hi>] an admirable Remedy, which put an end unto all Sorrow and Anger, and cauſed People to forget all their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes. No Man could Weep (ſaid the Poets) in the Day that he taſted it, tho' he had loſt the Deareſt Friend in the World. The Phyloſophers try to have the Properties of it anſwered in <hi>Opium.</hi> No, Sirs, 'Tis nothing but our <hi>Glorious Goſpel,</hi> that will after all, afford the true <hi>Nepenthes.</hi> In the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:001624_0035_0FB3E38BD16994A0"/>our <hi>Glorious Goſpel</hi> alone it is, that we have a genuine Cure for all that brings any of our <hi>Uneaſineſs</hi> upon us. My Brethren, There are <hi>Promiſes</hi> that will ſuit all your Occaſions of <hi>Uneaſineſs.</hi> Are you <hi>Uneaſy,</hi> becauſe you ſee <hi>Poverty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in like an Armed Man</hi> upon you? Take that <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and make a Living upon it; Pſal. XXXIV. 10. <hi>They that ſeek the Lord, ſhall not want any good Thing.</hi> Does the Death of any <hi>Deſirable Relatives</hi> make you <hi>Uneaſy?</hi> Take that <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and what it brings with it, inſtead of them all: Heb. XIII. 5. <hi>He hath ſaid, I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> Does the view of your own <hi>Approaching Death</hi> make you <hi>Uneaſy?</hi> Take that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> for a <hi>Rod</hi> and a <hi>Staff,</hi> to walk thro' <hi>Hazar-maveth</hi> withal; Pſal. XXIII. 4. <hi>Tho' I walk thro' the Valley of the Shadow of Death, I will fear no Evil; For thou art with me.</hi> Are you <hi>Uneaſy</hi> becauſe of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils</hi> that you are near to, and muſt go thro'? Take that <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and make a <hi>Cordial</hi> of it; Iſa. XLI. 10. <hi>Fear not, for I am with thee; Be not diſmayed, for I am thy God: I will ſtrengthen thee, yea, I will help thee, yea, I will uphold thee with the
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:001624_0036_0FB3E38D2BC202D8"/>Right Hand of my Righteouſneſs.</hi> Do the Thoughſs of the <hi>Orphans,</hi> which you are, you know not how ſoon, to leave in an evil World, make you <hi>Uneaſy?</hi> Take that <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and look on it, as a competent and perpetual <hi>Fund,</hi> for them to ſubſiſt upon; Pſal. XXVII. 11. <hi>When my Father and my Mother forſake me, the Lord will take me up.</hi> Who can be <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſy</hi> in the midſt of ſuch Accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; or be in <hi>Straits</hi> in the midſt of ſuch <hi>Sufficiency?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. The <hi>Children</hi> of Pious Parents, muſt attend unto the Counſils of God. YOU, my Children, have <hi>ſomething</hi> to do, that you may be the better for your <hi>Parents.</hi> And I will tell you, what that <hi>ſomething</hi> is. You muſt lay hold on the <hi>Covenant</hi> of God for your ſelves; and heartily <hi>ſay unto the Lord, Thou art my God.</hi> You muſt come into this Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>O Great GOD, has my Parent cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen thee? I alſo do make Choice of thee, to be my God!</hi> And, Child, <hi>Wilt thou not from this</hi> Time, come into that Reſolution, <hi>Lord, Thou art my Father, and thou ſhalt be the Guide of my Youth?</hi> Truly, the Language now expected from you, is
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:001624_0037_0FB3E38EB81ADAA0"/>that; Exod. XV. 2. <hi>The Lord is my God, and I will prepare Him an Habitation: My Fathers God, and I will Exalt Him.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal, you muſt Conform to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires of your Pious Parents. Thwart them not; Grieve them not; cauſe not an <hi>Heavy Heart</hi> unto them; Don't make them <hi>Uneaſy.</hi> Be not the Sons of <hi>Eli,</hi> who <hi>hearkned not unto the Voice of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> You know the Doom, and the Death of thoſe miſerable Children! Yet more; Your Pious Parents have pray'd for you; have made Thouſands of <hi>Prayers</hi> for you, with <hi>ſtrong Crying and Tears.</hi> But you muſt <hi>Pray for your ſelves,</hi> if you would fare the better for the <hi>Prayers</hi> of your <hi>Parents.</hi> Nor can you fare the better for your <hi>Pious Parents,</hi> except you tread in the Steps of their Piety. Remember Their <hi>Piety</hi> will but aggravate your <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> if you continue <hi>Impious.</hi> We Read of <hi>One in Hell,</hi> which cryed out, <hi>Father Abraham, I am Tormented in this Flame.</hi> O Children whoſe Parents have been the <hi>Friends</hi> of God, If you are found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong His <hi>Enemies,</hi> as your <hi>Impiety</hi> will declare you to be <hi>ſuch,</hi> you will be thrown into <hi>Hell,</hi> and your Damnation
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:001624_0038_0FB3E3903998FAD8"/>there, will be the more Exquiſite and Horrible for the <hi>Parents</hi> which you are deſcended from. Your <hi>Parents</hi> will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come your <hi>Torments:</hi> And the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of what they did for you, and how you have Sinn'd againſt it all, will <hi>Torment</hi> you wonderfully; the Smoak, and the Cry of ſuch <hi>Torments,</hi> will <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend for ever and ever!</hi> So did the Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> warn the Children of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Parents; Matth. III. 9, 10. <hi>Think not to ſay within your ſelves, we have Abraham to our Father. Every Tree which bringeth not forth good Fruit, is hewn down, and caſt into the Fire.</hi> I ſee, I ſee, Oh! what Numbers of our poor Children, in a Courſe of Impiety, throwing themſelves down into that <hi>Unquenchable Fire.</hi> A moſt Lamentable Spectacle! <hi>O Lord, I beſeech thee to deliver their Souls!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶ But it is time for me, in my <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical</hi> way, which one would think ſhould be a very <hi>Significant</hi> way, to Clinch the Nails which I have hitherto been driv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And I may upon a due Reflection, make this Report unto you, That the <hi>Religious Matron</hi> who yeſterday with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew from us, was One, in whom the
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:001624_0039_0FB3E391A8DC8E58"/>Truths which have now been delivered, concerning a <hi>Soul</hi> Dwelling and preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Eaſe</hi> by a <hi>Piety,</hi> and an <hi>Offspring</hi> rendred, and by themſelves and others eſteem'd, Happy, in <hi>Pious Parents,</hi> have been in a very Conſpicuous Degree ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplified. Such a <hi>Good Report</hi> ſhe has <hi>of all, and of the Truth it ſelf.</hi> I alſo muſt make a Record of it, and <hi>my Record ſhall be true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are not <hi>Bribed</hi> by the <hi>Riches</hi> of them who <hi>Dye and are buried,</hi> for to bear any flattering and fulſome Teſtimonies for them. Nothing without a <hi>Shining Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety</hi> in our Friends, can obtain our Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies: Tho' ſometimes <hi>Public Stations,</hi> or ſuch things as place Perſons in the Light of more <hi>Public Obſervation,</hi> may invite us to Enlarge upon them. <hi>Philip de Comines</hi> complaines of it, That when he expoſtulated with a <hi>Carthuſian,</hi> for putting the Term of a <hi>Saint</hi> on one that had been a Perſon of a very evil Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, his Monk replied upon him, <hi>Syr, We always make a Saint of a Benefactor.</hi> I hope, that you will find <hi>Us</hi> clear of that Scandal; and that you have often found us moſt Expatiate in Commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:001624_0040_0FB3E39331825CB8"/>ſuch <hi>Saints</hi> as have laid us under no <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Perſonal</hi> Obligations.</p>
               <p>The Excellent Father of this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, and of this Country, (whoſe <hi>Life</hi> makes a Great Article among the MAGNALIA of <hi>New-England,</hi>) would in her Childhood, often preſent her to them that came to ſee him, and ſay with a peculiar Satisfaction, <hi>This is my</hi> New-England <hi>Token!</hi> becauſe a good God had ſent her to him, as a <hi>Token</hi> of His Favour to his Family, ſo ſoon after his coming to <hi>New-England.</hi> And I know not why <hi>New-England</hi> ſhould not now preſent her to the World, as a <hi>Token</hi> of the Divine Favour to a Country, which He has adorned with ſuch bright Jewels, as do ſurpaſs thoſe of the Orient. When ſhe lay at the Point of Death in her Minority, and was indeed given over for Dead, while Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> was at Prayer with her, the Heart of her Father was raiſed unto a <hi>particular Faith</hi> for it, which he immediately declared, <hi>That the Child ſhould Live!</hi> And now, having out-lived the Eightieth Year of her Age, I have an Opportunity to tell you, what ſort of a <hi>Life</hi> it was, which that
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:001624_0041_0FB3E394A3716128"/>Prayer of my Grandfather, had its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Anſwer in. It was a <hi>Life</hi> of the moſt exemplary <hi>Piety</hi> in all the parts of it; And my Sermon has all along done little more than tell <hi>her</hi> Story, when it has told you, what the <hi>Fear of God</hi> will do, and what <hi>Eaſe</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> it will bring unto.</p>
               <p>While ſhe was a Wife, to a moſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable Servant of God, Mr. SAMUEL DANFORTH, the Paſtor of <hi>Roxbury,</hi> ſhe was no Stranger to Afflictions; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the Infirmity and Mortality of <hi>many Children.</hi> But by being thus Afflicted, ſhe was but the more improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that <hi>Piety</hi> which made her <hi>Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> in the Eyes of all that have the <hi>Fear of God</hi> at all directing of their Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>As thoſe Holy Women that bore a part in the <hi>Firſt Voyages</hi> to this Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, were thoſe <hi>Good Things,</hi> than which <hi>the World</hi> had not many to ſhow, that were <hi>Better,</hi> or more worthy to be had in <hi>Everlaſting Remembrance:</hi> Thus <hi>our Land</hi> hath not many Things to be more boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, than a ſet of Holy Women found among <hi>their Daughters,</hi> who have been
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:001624_0042_0FB3E3963B539B58"/>
                  <hi>Poliſhed Stones in the Temple of God,</hi> and Patterns of the Things that are <hi>Holy, and Juſt, and Good.</hi> WOMEN, that have moſt entirely given themſelves up unto God, and ſtudied and practiſed <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs in all manner of Converſation: Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> that have known and lov'd a dear SAVIOUR, and <hi>liv'd by the Faith of the Son of God: Women,</hi> that have walk'd with God, in the <hi>Religion of the Cloſet,</hi> and ſet an high Price on Communion with Him in the <hi>Aſſemblies of Zion: Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> that have been Wiſe, and Good, and moſt Obliging in all <hi>Relations,</hi> and beſtow'd upon their Children an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Education: Women,</hi> that have with incomparable Patience and Meekneſs, entertained the <hi>Croſs</hi> that has been or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered for them: <hi>Women,</hi> that have been <hi>Bleſſings</hi> to their Neighbours, and been helpful in a Thouſand kind of Offices among the Diſtreſſed in their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood. <hi>Such</hi> was this Handmaid of the Lord; and among <hi>ſuch, a Star of the firſt Magnitude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For near Twice ſeven Years before ſhe Died, her <hi>Sight</hi> was utterly taken from her. But, Oh! the <hi>Light ariſing to
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:001624_0043_0FB3E397D0961FD0"/>her in all her Darkneſs!</hi> Some that have been <hi>Blind all their Days,</hi> have yet been ſuch <hi>Illuminated Perſons,</hi> that they have been Eminent <hi>Preachers</hi> of the Goſpel, yea, moſt notable <hi>Writers,</hi> for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and Service of it. Among ſuch Sons of <hi>Bartimaeus,</hi> I know not that the <hi>Armies of the Living God,</hi> ever had a more Illuſtrious Champion than that moſt accompliſhed Literator, the preſent <hi>Profeſſor of Hiſtory</hi> in the Univerſity of <hi>Glaſgow:</hi> [Mr. WILLIAM JAMESON.] A <hi>Sampſon</hi> by whoſe Hand God pulls down the Temple of the <hi>Romiſh Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines!</hi> I ſnatch at an Occaſion to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this Miraculous Man, becauſe I have really wiſh'd and fought an Occaſion to Expreſs my Deſires that his Learned Books were more Common among us Others there have been, who have only lain <hi>Blind in their Latter Days;</hi> but yet have in the <hi>Light of God</hi> ſo <hi>ſeen Light</hi> that they have been able to <hi>Guide others</hi> in the ways of God, and <hi>ſhew them the Pathes of Life.</hi> And ſuch an One was this Handmaid of God; One under <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Blindneſs,</hi> yet Gloriouſly Reſembling the <hi>Living Creatures that are full of Eyes!</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="unknown:001624_0044_0FB3E3992CF189F8"/>When the acute <hi>Milton</hi> had loſt his Eyes, he Comforted himſelf with this; <hi>Orbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem certe Luminis quidni leniter feram, quod non tam amiſſum, quam Revecatum intus atque Retractum, ad acuendam potius mentis Aciem quam ad hebetandam ſperem.</hi> 'My <hi>Sight</hi> is only call'd <hi>Inward,</hi> that it 'may be <hi>ſharpened</hi> there. And he argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That as <hi>Man lives not by Bread alone, but by the Word of God,</hi> we ſee not with our <hi>Eyes alone,</hi> but by being under the Wiſe and Kind Conduct of God. Thus this Pious Perſon had her <hi>Sight,</hi> but as it were turned the more <hi>Inward</hi> and <hi>Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> by her <hi>Blindneſs,</hi> and fixed upon thoſe Things which had hitherto been the Object of her <hi>Faith.</hi> She gained a <hi>ſtronger Sight</hi> of <hi>Him that is Inviſible;</hi> a <hi>clearer View</hi> of the <hi>Things which are not ſeen and are Eternal. Cicero</hi> affirms, <hi>Democ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus</hi> eaſily comforted himſelf under the loſs of his Ey-ſight by this; That if he was not able to diſtinguiſh <hi>Black</hi> from <hi>White,</hi> yet he could perfectly well diſcern <hi>Good</hi> from <hi>Ill, Right</hi> from <hi>Wrong.</hi> This Pious Perſon, One <hi>more Wiſe unto Salvation</hi> than any that the Roman Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor had ever heard of, when God call'd
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:001624_0045_0FB3E39AB05A0958"/>her to make her <hi>Sight</hi> a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> unto Him, had this Reparation of her Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that ſhe had the more <hi>Lively Sight</hi> of Things in the Kingdom of God; ſhe more diſtinctly view'd thoſe Things, which if they could be ſeen with our Eyes, we would find the <hi>Love</hi> of them <hi>Wondrouſly raiſed</hi> in us. Every one will Delight and Wonder ſaw, <hi>A Soul dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Eaſe!</hi> Her <hi>Submiſſion</hi> to the <hi>Will of God:</hi> Her Admirations of what <hi>ſhe ſaw</hi> in a moſt endeared JESUS: Her <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> to them who brought the <hi>Word of God</hi> unto her, which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually done by one or other, almoſt all the Day long; Her <hi>Chamber</hi> a very <hi>Chappel</hi> wherein ſomething of Devotion was ever going on; A little <hi>Anti-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of Heaven! The unexpreſſible Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſhe took in <hi>Prayer</hi> to God: Her Fruitfulneſs in <hi>Religious Conferences:</hi> Her <hi>Affectionate Love</hi> to the Children of God: Her profound <hi>Humility,</hi> perpetual Self-Abaſement, Self-Abhorence: And her lively Anhelation after the <hi>Heavenly World,</hi> with a moſt finiſhing <hi>Reſignation</hi> to her Saviour, for His own <hi>Time,</hi> and His own <hi>Way</hi> to bring her unto it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="unknown:001624_0046_0FB3E39C292825E8"/>
It was impoſſible to ſee her in her <hi>Dying Hours,</hi> without ſeeing the ghaſtly Viſage of DEATH Gloriouſly altered; and the meaning of, <hi>O Death, Where is thy Sting?</hi> tendered in a moſt noble Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of it. And now, when her ſenſe of every Thing in this World, was in a manner gone, if either CHRIST, or HEAVEN, were but mentioned, it ſeem'd as if the mention of thoſe <hi>Two Words,</hi> infus'd a <hi>New Life</hi> into her. She made me think of that Excellent Lady, <hi>Olympia Fulvia Morata,</hi> who in her laſt Moments declar'd, <hi>That ſhe had now got the Sight of a moſt Excellent Place, and a very Delightful one; ever Shining with an Aſtoniſhing Light and Brightneſs;</hi> Haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereto, her Triumph was, <hi>Tota ſum laeta;</hi> I am now <hi>as full of Joy as I can hold;</hi> A Singular Happineſs did ſhe <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ow and long enjoy in her <hi>Children,</hi> and their Tender and Helpful Behaviour. Her Two <hi>Sons,</hi> have long been Faithful and Painful and eminently Serviceable Miniſters of the Goſpel: Her Two <hi>Sons-in-Law</hi> have been as well <hi>Sons-in-Love</hi> unto her: And her <hi>Daughters</hi> have been worthy to be call'd <hi>Hers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="unknown:001624_0047_0FB3E39DB322C648"/>
And now her <hi>Soul</hi> is gone to <hi>Dwell in Eaſe,</hi> her dutiful Offspring, will doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Inherit</hi> ſo much of the <hi>Earth,</hi> as will Reward the Duty which they have ſo Examplarily paid unto her. But <hi>this</hi> is not what they ſo much propoſe: 'Tis the <hi>leaſt</hi> of their Deſires; as it was of <hi>Hers</hi> for them. An <hi>Heavenly Inheritance</hi> will be theirs; <hi>A Better and a Laſting Subſtance in Heaven!</hi>— If they go on to prefer and purſue <hi>That,</hi> as I hope they do, and walk in the ſteps of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who have laid up ſo many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Prayers, That they <hi>may do wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily in Iſrael.</hi> And their Experience, how remarkably God has been a <hi>Father</hi> to them, ſince their Excellent <hi>Father</hi> left them <hi>Orphans</hi> in a difficult World, I hope, will be conſidered as an Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement for all Godly <hi>Parents,</hi> and for their <hi>Children.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
