<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Gospel ministry the rich gift of the ascended Saviour unto his church. As it was represented in a sermon preached August 2. 1715. / By Mr. Benjamin Colman, on a day of prayer kept by his congregation, to implore the divine conduct and blessing with them, in their election of another into the pastoral office among them.</title>
            <author>Colman, Benjamin, 1673-1747.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N01458</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N01458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 1732</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW6426</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">1732</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99012561</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 1732.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N01458)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 1732)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 1732)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Gospel ministry the rich gift of the ascended Saviour unto his church. As it was represented in a sermon preached August 2. 1715. / By Mr. Benjamin Colman, on a day of prayer kept by his congregation, to implore the divine conduct and blessing with them, in their election of another into the pastoral office among them.</title>
                  <author>Colman, Benjamin, 1673-1747.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p. ;  15 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Fleet and T. Crump, for Samuel Gerrish, on the north side of the Town-House.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1715.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: The precious gifts of the ascended Saviour.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C^8 (A3, C1 missigned B3, B).</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 3 misnumbered 1.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church in Brattle Square (Boston, Mass.).</term>
               <term>Sermons --  1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:001732_0000_0FB778FAE48F15C8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:001732_0001_0FB77901B4DAD688"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Goſpel Miniſtry</hi> The rich GIFT of the <hi>Aſcended</hi> SAVIOUR Unto His CHURCH.</p>
            <p>As it was Repreſented in a SERMON preached <hi>Auguſt</hi> 2. 1715. By Mr. BENIAMIN COLMAN, On a <hi>Day of Prayer</hi> kept by <hi>His</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, to implore the Divine <hi>Conduct</hi> and <hi>Bleſſing</hi> with them, in their <hi>Election</hi> of <hi>Another</hi> into the <hi>Paſtoral Office</hi> among them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Fleet</hi> and <hi>T. Crump,</hi> for <hi>Samuel Gerriſh,</hi> on the <hi>North</hi> Side of the Town-Houſe. 1715.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="unknown:001732_0002_0FB77908C89B8978"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>IT ſeems to me but a piece of Juſtice to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the <hi>free <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I have made of Mr. <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s <hi>Expoſitions,</hi> thro' the following <hi>Diſcourſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="unknown:001732_0003_0FB7790E216B5BE0"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Goſpel Miniſtry</hi> The rich GIFT of the <hi>Aſcended</hi> SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIOUR unto His <hi>Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EPH. IV. 8, 11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Wherefore he ſaith, When he aſcended up on high, he led Captivity Captive, and gave Gifts unto Men.—</p>
                  <p>And he gave ſome Apoſtles: and ſome Prophets: and ſome Evangeliſts: and ſome Paſtors and Teachers.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE <hi>Text</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>Aſcention</hi> of our Lord JESUS CHRIST into Heaven, where He is ſet down at the right hand of the Majeſty on high; the Glory of which Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent is here meditated in the bleſſed Fruits and Effects of it to the ſinful Children of Men.</p>
            <p>Three things here offer to our Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="4" facs="unknown:001732_0004_0FB77912DDE35630"/>
1. <hi>A Prophecy</hi> of our Saviour's Aſcenſion is referr'd to; and a very Illuſtrious one it is, in the 68. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. <hi>Thou haſt aſcended on high, thou haſt led Captivity captive; thou haſt received Gifts for Men, yea for the Rebellious alſo, that the Lord God might dwell among them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the Text quotes theſe words of <hi>David,</hi> who ſaw the day of our Lord's Aſcenſion, and ſpake of it in Spirit as a thing <hi>paſt,</hi> it was ſo ſure and certain to be in God's appointed time.</p>
            <p n="2">2. IN the Text the <hi>Accompliſhment</hi> of this Prophecy is ſuppoſed and taken for granted, which amounts to an <hi>Aſſertion</hi> of its. Fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the perſon of Chriſt. To Him the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> here applies it, as one of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances wherein the Spirit of Chriſt in the Prophets did teſtify before the Glory that ſhould follow his Sufferings.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> had ſpoken of Chriſt <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically</hi> in the <hi>ſecond</hi> Perſon. <hi>Thou</hi> haſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended, <hi>&amp;c</hi>—. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> applies it to him <hi>Hiſtorically</hi> in the <hi>third</hi> Perſon; when <hi>He</hi> aſcended up on high, <hi>He</hi> led <hi>&amp;c</hi>—.</p>
            <p>AND to ſatisfy us that the Prophecy of the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> was of Chriſt truly, and can bear no other Application ultimatly, the Apoſtle argues in a <hi>Parentheſis</hi> between the
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:001732_0005_0FB779184D3E6180"/>two Verſes of my <hi>Text;</hi> which I have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd to omit in the reading them juſt now to you; <hi>Now that he aſcended, what is it but that he alſo deſcended firſt into the lower parts of the earth? He that deſcended is the ſame that aſcended up far above all Heavens, that he might fill all things.</hi> Which is as much as to ſay, that <hi>David</hi> in Spirit ſpake of <hi>Him</hi> who firſt came down from Heaven to our Earth, and here in our fleſh deſcended into the Grave, from whence he roſe and aſcended bodily far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all viſible Heavens; unto the preſence and Throne of God. Thus we ſee the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> and its <hi>Accompliſhment;</hi> that <hi>David</hi>'s words did indeed mean Chriſt's Aſcention, and were fulfilled in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. LET us obſerve the <hi>glorious things which are ſpoken</hi> concerning the Aſcention of Chriſt:
<list>
                  <item>1. That <hi>he led Captivity Captive.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. That <hi>he received and gave Gifts to men.</hi> And</item>
                  <item>3. Theſe <hi>Gifts are ſpecify'd, He gave ſome A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>THERE is doubtleſs and <hi>Alluſion</hi> in the words unto the Uſages and Cuſtom of <hi>Generals</hi> and <hi>Conquerors,</hi> who after great and illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Victories</hi> obtained by them were wont to <hi>Triumph;</hi> and in their triumphant <hi>Entries</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="unknown:001732_0006_0FB77925B7E96A60"/>into the Capital City of the Empire to which they belong'd and for which they fought, they us'd to be follow'd by the <hi>Captives</hi> whom they had taken in the War; and to make ſhew of the Riches, the <hi>Spoils</hi> they had taken from the Enemy, and to add unto the pomp of the day they made public "<hi>Largitives</hi> and <hi>Donatives</hi> to their Souldiers, and ſcatter'd their Magnificence and Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty among the Crouds.</p>
            <p>IT may ſeem probable that theſe ſort of <hi>Triumphs</hi> were in uſe in <hi>David</hi>'s time, and the moſt <hi>famous One</hi> of his Reign might be on that occaſion whereon the 68. <hi>Pſalm</hi> was compoſed, namely the <hi>Tranſlation of the Ark</hi> (the Type of Chriſt's Mediation) into the Tent which he had pitched for it in <hi>Sion.</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> Triumphs were of a later Date, but anſwer'd ſo exactly to the Deſcription here given by <hi>David,</hi> of the leading the Captives in proceſſion, and the ſcattering Gifts among the Multitude that we may think the <hi>Nations</hi> received the Cuſtom from <hi>him;</hi> whoſe Victories in war well deſerv'd a Triumph; and were ſingled out by God to be the <hi>Types</hi> of the Spiritual Victory of Chriſt over the powers of Darkneſs. This ſeems to me more worthy to be ſaid, than
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:001732_0007_0FB77927364B8D28"/>that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> manifeſtly alludes unto the <hi>Roman Conquerors:</hi> which tho' it might have paſs'd had our Text been firſt deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> who liv'd under the <hi>Roman Empire;</hi> yet what Alluſion to <hi>their</hi> Triumphs cou'd <hi>David</hi> make who liv'd ſo long before them, unleſs you will allow too that he <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>DAVID</hi> was a famous <hi>Type of Chriſt,</hi> and that <hi>Great Solemnity of his Reign,</hi> the carrying of the <hi>Ark</hi> in pomp to <hi>Sion,</hi> was an illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Type of our Lord's <hi>Aſcention</hi> into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>David</hi> on that triumphant Occaſion celebrated <hi>all the Victories</hi> that God had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him over His and his Church's Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and aſcribed all the Glory of them to God and to the <hi>Ark of his ſtrength. This</hi> was now <hi>aſcending on High,</hi> even the <hi>Ark,</hi> from a humble and obſcure ſtate wherein it had long been, into a <hi>Royal Tent</hi> which he had pitch'd for it in that Hill of Sion which God had choſen, the Mount which he lov'd. Now to grace that Proceſſion and Aſcent of the Ark, we may ſuppoſe that the King bro't forth the train of <hi>Captives,</hi> even <hi>ſuch</hi> as before had often led many an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> into <hi>Captivity.</hi> Thus Captivity was led Captive, and the <hi>Spoils</hi> taken from them
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:001732_0008_0FB779288FC552B0"/>were carry'd to <hi>Sion,</hi> and there <hi>Dedicated</hi> to God, for the building of the <hi>Temple</hi> in after days, where the <hi>Lord God</hi> might dwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. Of <hi>Him</hi> David had <hi>receiv'd</hi> theſe Victories and theſe Spoils; and to Him he <hi>aſcribes</hi> the glory of the one, and to His ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and ſpicial honour he <hi>Conſecrates</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Of which Spoils that <hi>David</hi> gathered and Dedicated, which were of Silver and Gold and Braſs, <hi>Solomon</hi> afterwards adorn'd the Temple, and made its holy Veſſels.</p>
            <p>THESE things, tho' the <hi>Glories</hi> of the Kingdoms of this world were but a <hi>low fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure</hi> and ſhadow of the Aſcention of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the Son and Lord of <hi>David.</hi> When He aſcended <hi>on high,</hi> even to the <hi>right Hand of God,</hi> above all Heavens, He did as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors us'd to do and <hi>more; He led Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity Captive;</hi> He led thoſe Captive that had led us ſo, and if He had not interpos'd would have led us ſo for ever; He made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly a ſhew of Principalities and Powers, of Satan, Sin and Death ſpoiled of their power over His Subjects; utterly broken for ever and led in Chains: He appear'd then <hi>more than a Conqueror,</hi> for every Conqueror was not allow'd a <hi>Triumph,</hi> and all <hi>Believers</hi> too who follow. His Chariot with their <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna</hi>'s
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:001732_0009_0FB7792A53FB4F88"/>are more than Conquerors thro' Him, they too are <hi>Triumphers;</hi> for thanks be to God who cauſeth us always <hi>to Triumph in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>THOU haſt received Gifts for men, yea for the Rebellious;</hi> ſays the <hi>Pſalmiſt; He gave Gifts unto men;</hi> ſays the <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> He received and and He gave; He gave that which He had received; for it was given Him to beſtow: <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.2, 22. <hi>As thou haſt given him,— that he ſhou'd give—: and the glory which thou gaveſt me I have given them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>GIFTS for <hi>Men,</hi> not for <hi>Angels: Henry.</hi> For <hi>Men</hi> in General, not for the <hi>Jews</hi> only, but for the <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo. Gifts <hi>in Man,</hi> as the <hi>Margin</hi> reads it in the <hi>Pſalms; i. e.</hi> in the <hi>humane Nature,</hi> which the Son of God was pleas'd to cloath Himſelf in, in whom (as Mediator) <hi>all fulneſs dwells,</hi> that from His fulneſs we all might receive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>YEA for the Rebellious:</hi> for thoſe that had been Rebels, and now were in Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion; had forfeited any claim to the leaſt Favour, but had deſerv'd and incurr'd wrath to the uttermoſt; for Rebels of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in particular who had been <hi>Enemies in their minds by wicked works;</hi> even theſe has He reconciled. So they ſay, the <hi>Generous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="unknown:001732_0010_0FB7792FA2B8E698"/>of old in the day of their Triumph, were wont not only to reward their <hi>Friends and faithful Souldiers</hi> with munificent Gifts, but to ſhow <hi>Acts of Grace alſo to their very Captives.</hi> The aſcending <hi>Saviour</hi> gave His Divine Gifts even for and to His <hi>Crucifiers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>THAT the Lord God might dwell among them;</hi> ſays the <hi>Pſalmiſt.</hi> That He might <hi>ſet up a Church</hi> in a rebellious world,<note place="margin">Henry.</note> in which He would dwell by His Word and Ordinances, as of old in the Sanctuary. So ſays the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the verſes after our Text; theſe Gifts from the Aſcended Saviour were given <hi>for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of the Saints, for the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, for the Edifying the body of Chriſt; till we all come in the unity of the faith,</hi> &amp;c—. That is in one word, for the building up a Church, and for the Edification of Souls in Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Faith and Holineſs unto Salvation.</p>
            <p>AND now we come more particularly to conſider what theſe Gifts of the Aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Saviour to His Church were, and thoſe the <hi>Apoſtle ſpecifies and enumerates:</hi> He gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, <hi>&amp;c</hi>—.</p>
            <p>YOU obſerve that only <hi>Offices</hi> are named, but <hi>Qualifications</hi> are ſuppoſed; Chriſt never gave Offices without a ſuitable
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:001732_0011_0FB77939491E51F0"/>meaſure of Gifts for the diſcharge of them; which are here therefore repreſented in their <hi>variety</hi> and <hi>diverſity;</hi> ſome <hi>Ordinary,</hi> others <hi>Extraordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Extraordinary Offices</hi> and divine Gifts agreeable to them: <hi>ſome Apoſtles, ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſome Evangeliſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had an Immediate Call to their Office,<note place="margin">Pool.</note> a Univerſal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, Infallibility in teaching, and the power of working Miracles; they were Prophets and more than Prophets, being commiſſioned and gifted in an excellent manner for the firſt founding of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church in all parts of the World.</p>
            <p>NEXTLY <hi>Prophets:</hi> Theſe alſo were Extraordinary Officers, whom God endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to foretel things to come, and expound the writings of the old Prophets; they In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted Scripture by Immediate Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly <hi>Evangeliſts.</hi> Theſe likewiſe were Extraordinary Officers, ordained by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles as their Companions and Aſſiſtants in preaching the word and planting Churches in the places where they had travelled. Such we eſteem <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Apollos</hi> and <hi>others</hi> to have been.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="unknown:001732_0012_0FB77942392F2900"/>
THESE <hi>Extraordinary Gifts and Officers</hi> were neceſſary in the firſt planting of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and ceaſed with that Extraordinary Occaſion for them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. THE <hi>Ordinary and ſtanding Officers</hi> of the Church of Chriſt follow: <hi>Paſtors and Teachers:</hi> Biſhops and Elders: who are ſet over the Churches as Guides and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, to <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>teach.</hi> They are <hi>one</hi> and the ſame <hi>Office,</hi> and accordingly <hi>joyned</hi> by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN ſhort, The <hi>Inſtitution of a Goſpel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry</hi> is the thing here taught, and that it is <hi>the Gift of our Aſcended Saviour</hi> to His Church, and to continue in it to the End of the World.</p>
            <p>I will only add, to carry on the <hi>Harmony</hi> between the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Prophecy</hi> and its <hi>Fulfilment;</hi> That this <hi>variety</hi> of Offices and Gifts; Superior and Inferior,<note place="margin">Mollierus.</note> Ordinary and Extraodinary, the one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling ſo much the other in Glory, for the building of the Spiritual Temple of Chriſt; do well anſwer unto the <hi>Princely Gifts</hi> which <hi>David</hi> dedicated for the building of <hi>Solomon's Temple,</hi> and the <hi>Ark</hi>'s. Aſcent thereinto and final Reſt therein. The Apoſtles, Prophets
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:001732_0013_0FB779441E302258"/>and Evangeliſts, and the Gifts of Inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Tongues, Prophecies, Miracles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe ſhine like the <hi>Conſecrated Gold;</hi> and let it ſuffice Us the Ordinary Miniſters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and be accounted too great Riches committed to us, if we may but be uſed and ſerve as the <hi>Silver Veſſels</hi> in the houſe of God, and may but be able to bring our Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of <hi>Braſs</hi> or <hi>Hair.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT I haſten to the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> hoping you will forgive me that I have been ſo <hi>tedious</hi> in commenting upon ſuch a <hi>Copious Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>DOCT. <hi>That the Inſtitution of a Goſpel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and Qualification of perſons ſmith are to be eſteemed among The Rich Gifts of our Aſcended Saviour to a ſinful World, and the glorious Fruits of His Aſcention.</hi> When he aſcended on high, He gave Gifts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WE may take the <hi>Doctrine</hi> into theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Propoſions.
<list>
                  <item>1. That our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt has Inſtituted and Ordained a Goſpel Miniſtry.</item>
                  <item>2. That He furniſhes and qualifies Men for it, with a variety of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Heavenly Gifts.</item>
                  <item>3. That they are the rich Gift of Chriſt unto a ſinful World.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="14" facs="unknown:001732_0014_0FB7794CFB1D9B20"/>
4. That it is the glorious Fruit of His Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>OUR Lord Jeſus Chriſt has Inſtituted and Ordained a Goſpel Miniſtry, to continue in His Church, and for the Edification of it unto the End of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Saviour of Men has had, hath, and ever will have a Church in the World. This has exiſted the ſame, under the various Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and Diſpenſations of Religion and of the Covenant of Grace, which have been from <hi>Adam</hi> to this day, and ſo will it be by the power and grace of God unto the End of Time. In this Church of the Living God there ever has been <hi>the Miniſtry of Men,</hi> and of ſome particular perſons whom God has called, endowed, and in diverſe manner authorized to Miniſter in holy things unto others, for their Souls Good. Of the <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archal Age</hi> we can ſay but little more than this, that the venerable <hi>Fathers</hi> of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Religious Families and Tribes have been eſteemed both <hi>Princes and Prieſts</hi> to them; no doubt <hi>praying</hi> with and <hi>bleſſing</hi> their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſholds, <hi>inſtructing</hi> and <hi>charging</hi> them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of God, receiving their Offerings and <hi>offering</hi> up Sacrifices, and <hi>lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in the Spiritual Sacrifices of praiſe unto
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:001732_0015_0FB7795001FB9568"/>God. No doubt too, but there were Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary <hi>Prophets</hi> raiſed up and inſpired and ſent by God with His will in their mouths upon Occaſion; as well as more Ordinary Revelations of Heaven to the <hi>Holy Men</hi> that walked with God, as <hi>Enoch, Noah</hi> and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ENOCH</hi> prophecy'd in his day of the <hi>Judgment</hi> yet to come, the ſecond Coming of our Lord; as the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> informs us. <hi>Noah</hi> was a <hi>Preacher of Righteouſneſs</hi> in his Generation, and the Longſuffering of God endured them for a great while under the Endeavours of his holy Miniſtry. <hi>Abraham</hi> we know was a faithful Father to his nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Houſhold, to inſtruct them in and command them after him <hi>to keep the way of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND thus things continued untill the Deſcent of the Houſe of Iſrael into <hi>Egypt;</hi> where neither were their Poſterity left al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together we may think without Inſtruction; but when God viſited them by the Miſſion of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and had bro't them thence by an outſtretched Arm, He then came down on <hi>Sinai,</hi> and gave them the Law by the diſpoſition of Angels, in thunders and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; which threw them into ſuch terrors
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:001732_0016_0FB7795E2AF43358"/>that they humbly beſo't of God that He would no more ſpeak unto them immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Himſelf, but by the Mouth and Miniſtry of <hi>Moſes;</hi> ſolemnly promiſing that they would obediently hearken unto all that he ſhould ſpeak to them in the Name of the LORD. GOD approv'd of this diſcreet and wiſe Motion which they made, and took up <hi>Moſes</hi> into the Mount, and there and thence forward inſtructed him in His whole Mind and Will for the Religion and Government of that His choſen People.</p>
            <p>HE then Inſtituted among them, as His <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Worſhip and <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> ſo the Miniſtry of the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites;</hi> who were to ſerve at His Altar, and to teach thro' the Land in their ſeveral Diſperſions the Statutes and Commandments of God. Their lips were to preſerve Knowledge, and the people were to <hi>ſeek the Law at their Mouth.</hi> God inſpired alſo His <hi>Holy Prophets;</hi> and ſent them with <hi>particular Revelations</hi> and Meſſages, as it pleaſed Him; and thus the Miniſtry of Religion continued in the Houſe of <hi>Aaron,</hi> even till the coming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>OUR <hi>LORD JESUS</hi> was that <hi>Great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> which God had promis'd to His people
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:001732_0017_0FB7795F54A2E9C8"/>
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> that He would <hi>raiſe up of their Brethren, like unto Moſes,</hi> and put his words in his mouth, and require it of them that ſhould not hearken unto him.</p>
            <p>NOW as ſoon as our LORD began His <hi>publick Miniſtry,</hi> He alſo called and Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>twelve Apoſtles,</hi> and ſent them forth to preach the Kingdom of God; and after them the Lord appointed other <hi>Seventy alſo,</hi> and ſent them two and two before His face, into every City and Place, whither He him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wou'd come. Thus they miniſtred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt all the time that the Lord went in and out among them, unto the day that they ſaw Him taken up into Heaven. Juſt before which, He renewed His Commiſſion unto them, and extended it unto all whom He ſhou'd call to miniſter in holy things e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the End of the World. <hi>Mat. ult. And Jeſus came and ſpake unto them ſaying; All power is given to me in Heaven and in Earth; go ye therefore and teach all nations, Baptizing them in the name of the Father and of—.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HERE our Lord firſt <hi>aſſerts</hi> His own Commiſſion and Authority, and then <hi>ſeals</hi> His to us. He did not go beyond His power, nor did He aſſume or uſurp any; but all power is given to Him in Heaven and Earth.
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:001732_0018_0FB77960E44A40B0"/>He has a legal Title, and a full Poſſeſſion; He is Inveſted in it, Inaugurated and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned for ever. And He gives Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion not only to the Apoſtles, tho' to them primarily, as the chief Miniſters of His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; but to their ſucceſſors alſo, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel from age to age, to the worlds End. He aſſures them of His Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Preſence with them in their preaching His Word, and adminiſtring His Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and that it ſhall be conſtant and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual; lo, I am with you always even to the End, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His Spirit is with His ſervants to aſſiſt them, and in His Ordinances to give them Succeſs and Efficacy.</p>
            <p>AGREEABLY to this Commiſſion the whole <hi>New Teſtament</hi> abounds with the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of the Miniſtry of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> &amp; <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts,</hi> their Ordaining and Inſtructing and ſending others to preach the Goſpel; the Qualifications Duties and Labours incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon Miniſters are laid down, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations and Charges given unto fidelity in this ſacred Office; many Titles and Names of honour and truſt are given them; they are called Miniſters of Chriſt, Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards of the Myſteries of God, Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, Overſeers, Watchmen for Souls
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:001732_0019_0FB77968CC93F880"/>that muſt give an Account, and Labourers in the Word and Doctrine, and Angels of the Churches; And finally, Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are upon all theſe Accounts required to Acknowledge them and highly Eſteem them in love, to count them worthy of double Honour, to Communicate for their Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and to obey and ſubmit to them.</p>
            <p>THUS our Lord Jeſus has Inſtituted a <hi>Goſpel Miniſtry</hi> in His Church.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>He furniſhes and qualifies Men for it with a variety of Divine and Heavenly Gifts;</hi> He <hi>gifts</hi> them for His Church, and <hi>gives</hi> them to His Church.</p>
            <p>HE is the <hi>True Light</hi> which lighteth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man that cometh into the World: the Original and Fountain of every kind and degree of worthy Gifts, wherewith one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and another are Adorned and Enriched. Whether they be common Gifts or ſaving Graoes, they are all derived and received from Jeſus Chriſt. The Endowments of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> as well as thoſe of Men are ſo; <hi>In Him was life, and the life was the light of Men.</hi> "That <hi>life</hi> which is the <hi>light</hi> of Men comes "from Jeſus Chriſt: the life <hi>in Man</hi> is light, for he is made a <hi>living Soul.</hi> The light of Reaſon is common to Men and all reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:001732_0020_0FB7796CD06EA270"/>Creatures, and derived from the <hi>Eternal Logos or Word,</hi> by whom and for him, the Thrones and Dominions in Heaven were created as well as Man upon Earth. By the Publication of the Goſpel, and by the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of His Spirit, He lighteth all thoſe that are enlightned to Salvation. Our Lord Jeſus both in His Eternal God-head, and alſo as Mediator and Redeemer, is the giver of every good Gift to us, and of <hi>His fulneſs we all have received and Grace for Grace.</hi> All <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and all <hi>Believers</hi> after them: both the favour of <hi>Apoſtleſhip,</hi> and fitneſs for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CHRIST</hi> calls none to any Truſt and Office in His Kingdom whom He does not gift and qualify for their place in it. If Qualifications be wanting, we may be ſure they have no Divine Call and Separation of God thereunto. I mean here ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent meaſure of Gifts, for whoſe are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to this high and holy Service? When God has called men to Extraordinary Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Service, He has gifted them in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary manner; as He did the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles. But a more common and ordinary Meaſure of ſuitable Gifts may ſuffice for more common and ordinary Truſts and Services; which therefore are to be
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:001732_0021_0FB77972A5DAC7D8"/>acquired in the uſe of ordinary Means, by diligent ſtudy and prayer, under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon gracious Influences of the <hi>Holy Spirit.</hi> Inſpiration is not to be look'd for on any ordinary Occaſion, nor the gift of Tongues, nor the working of Miracles.</p>
            <p>CHRIST will give that which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite where He calls any one to His Miniſtry; but He requires and expects too Diligence and Labour with many Prayers and humble Dependance on Him on our part; and that we have an awful ſenſe of the great Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Learning neceſſary, eſpecially in the Holy Scriptures; and greater meaſures yet of Sanctity and Holineſs, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Divine Influence to Incline, Spirit and Animate us, and alſo to ſucceed and proſper us; that our ſtudies and labours may not be in vain in the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>HE</hi> the Head of all glorious Influence to the Church chuſes whom He will ſend and imploy in it, He makes men to differ in Gifts, which in various Manner and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures He beſtows as pleaſes Him, on whom He will; and then by whom He will He worketh.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Holy Spirit of Grace</hi> is pour'd out on the Church for that End; to furniſh <hi>ſome</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="unknown:001732_0022_0FB77978F11F8FC0"/>for the Edification of others, and by their Miniſtry to bring in the Elect to believe and be ſaved. The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is ſubſtituted <q>and given forth by our <hi>Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> Perſonally to promote and effectuate His Mediation for God with Men.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Scot.</hi>
                  </note> He is now the <hi>other Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate</hi> to inforce the Miniſtry of Men on Chriſt's behalf:</q> even the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> which abides with His Church for ever to this End. He qualify'd and furniſh d the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> for their ſervice, and ſo He does <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Miniſters</hi> for theirs till the worlds End. As long as Chriſt ſhall have a Church up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth, the Holy Ghoſt is <hi>vitally uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it,</hi> as <hi>One</hi> ſpeaks well, even as the Soul to the Body; for as there is <hi>one Body,</hi> the Church, ſo there is <hi>one Spirit;</hi> as our <hi>Context</hi> has it: and this one bleſſed Spirit of Grace works every ſaving and gracious Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that is produced by the Miniſtry of Men; Enlightning, Sanctifying, Quickning and Comforting the Souls of His choſen and called, and being in them the Spirit of Supplication. He is <hi>the Spirit of the Son ſent forth into the hearts</hi> of the Elect.</p>
            <p>BUT He works in and by the <hi>Miniſtry of Men.</hi> Not that He needs them or their
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:001732_0023_0FB779840F945B88"/>Miniſtries to him, but this is the Reaſonable and Gracious way which He Himſelf has ordained and ſanctify'd unto our Uſe. We muſt look and wait for Him in His own way, and therein expect His free and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Operations. He will work by whom He will work, and whom He will uſe He prepares for the uſe which He pleaſes to make of him.</p>
            <p>AS the Father <hi>ſanctify'd and ſent Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world,</hi> and gave Him the Spirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Meaſure; ſo Chriſt hath ſent His Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and furniſh'd them with meaſures of Gifts and Graces from His Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>HEAR how graciouſly and with what Solemnity our Saviour ſpeaks of it in His Prayer for His Apoſtles, and in them for all that ſhould believe in him thro' their word: <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.17, 18, 19. <hi>Sanctify them thro' thy truth, thy word is truth. As thou haſt ſent me into the world, even ſo have I ſent them into the world; and for their ſakes I ſanctify my ſelf, that they alſo might be ſanctify'd thro' the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE bleſſed Prayer is, Sanctify them <hi>as Miniſters</hi> to thy Service; <hi>qualify</hi> them with Chriſtian Graces and Miniſterial Gifts; <hi>own</hi> them in the Office and let thy Hand go with them: For this cauſe I <hi>Sanctify,</hi> i. e.
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:001732_0024_0FB77984C1F1D550"/>
               <hi>devote</hi> my ſelf an Offering that they may be qualified from above and accepted with God both as Saints and Miniſters. Thus Chriſt <hi>gave Himſelf for His Church to ſanctify it.</hi> And for the Sanctification of <hi>Believers</hi> He ſanctifies His <hi>Miniſters: Joh.</hi> 21, 22. <hi>Jeſus ſaid again to them, Peace be unto you; as my Father hath ſent me, even ſo have I ſent you</hi> (Qualify'd and Furniſh'd as well as Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riz'd and Commiſſion'd;) <hi>and when he had ſaid this, he breathed on them, and ſaid unto them, receive the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>THE Miniſters of Chriſt, whom He qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifies and furniſhes with Miniſterial Gifts and Graces are a very rich Gift of Chriſt to a ſinful World.</hi> Manifold is the Riches of His Grace unto them whom He qualifies, and when He has ſo Inriched them Great is the Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of His Gift in them unto the Souls of Men. All His <hi>Gifts</hi> to them is ſo much <hi>Grace</hi> to His Church, and to render them a <hi>Gift worthy of Himſelf,</hi> and of His love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Souls.</p>
            <p>LET me lay before you <hi>two Texts</hi> here; for I cannot pretend to enter into a proper Method or Enlargement on this head, on which a great many worthy things might be copiouſly ſaid: The <hi>firſt</hi> Text ſhall ſpeak
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:001732_0025_0FB7798678D5B690"/>the <hi>greatneſs of the thing</hi> for God to <hi>furniſh</hi> a Miniſtry, the <hi>ſecond</hi> to <hi>give</hi> it to His Church. The firſt is in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5, 6. Not that we are ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing, as of our ſelves; but our ſufficiency is of God; <hi>Who alſo hath made us able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the New Teſtament.</hi> The other is in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> Therefore let no man glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in man, <hi>for all things are yours; whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas—, all are yours, and ye are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods.</hi> Thus God <hi>forms</hi> a glorious Miniſtry in the world, to be His glorious <hi>Gift</hi> to it.</p>
            <p>AND do but conſider the <hi>End</hi> to which He forms it, and the glorious <hi>Effect</hi> which under His Bleſſing it produces, and it will appear to be an <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> and <hi>Magnificent Gift</hi> of Heaven. It is inſtituted in the hand of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and under that <hi>Revelation</hi> which God has made of Himſelf and of His Will and Grace to men, to be <hi>the means of the Illumination, Converſion and Salvation of the World.</hi> And what can be more Noble or Important than this End? at leaſt what more glorious in <hi>our</hi> Eyes, to whom is the word of this Salvation ſent, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of Reconciliation committed? One Soul is of an Invaluable Price; but what then is
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:001732_0026_0FB7798BAD905650"/>the Salvation of Millions of Immortal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that were periſhing in Ignorance, Corruption and Spiritual Bondage and Death!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MEN and Brethren,</hi> if your Souls are of any worth in your own Eyes, ſo muſt you value and ſet a price on the means of your Inſtruction unto the Kingdom of God, the means of their Sanctification, and Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in Grace unto Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THESE are the Servants of the moſt High God, which ſhew you the way of Salvation:</hi> God has Endowed, Commiſſioned and ſent them on that ſervice to you; at the urgent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and on the account of the periſhing Condition of your Souls, and their own too, and a Million Millions of others beſides you: and will you not <hi>reverence this Gift</hi> of Chriſt to you? how ſhould you <hi>believe</hi> in Chriſt and be ſaved, if theſe were not <hi>ſent</hi> to preach Him to you, and as <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> from Chriſt to <hi>beſeech and pray</hi> you in Chriſts ſtead to be reconciled to God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WE then as workers together with God beſeech you not to receive His Grace in vain:</hi> not to make light of it, not to treat it with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. Look not upon Us nor our Office as a mean or inſignificant thing, but ſuffer
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:001732_0027_0FB7798DD2FB0DF8"/>me to ſpeak in God's behalf and to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy my Office, <hi>this Miniſtry which we have receiv'd of the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SAY not,— this <hi>fooliſhneſs of Preaching,</hi> ſeeing iſ pleaſes God by it <hi>to ſave them that believe. Weak</hi> as it is, by it God has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded the <hi>pride</hi> of the world, for <hi>the world by wiſdom knew not God.</hi> But in the preached Goſpel, God and the way of your Recovery from Sin and Hell, to Holineſs and Heaven, is revealed; and the glory both of His Grace and Juſtice is ſeen in the face of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Let a man therefore ſo account of us as of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of God;</hi> if ſo be that we may but be <hi>found Faithful;</hi> which we are while we ſtand to and act up to our Commiſſion. And I will juſt read to you how the Apoſtle teaches us to <hi>ſtand</hi> by it, and <hi>triumph</hi> in it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in commends our Miniſtry to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of our People: It is in the Cloſe of the 2 <hi>Chap.</hi> of the 2 <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and the beginning of the 3. <hi>Chap. Now thanks be to God which always cauſeth us to triumph in Chriſt, and maketh manifeſt the ſavour of his Knowledge by us in every place. For we are unto GOD a ſweet ſavour of Christ, in them that are ſaved, and in them that periſh: To the one we
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:001732_0028_0FB77993E9773430"/>are the ſavour of Death unto Death, and to the other the ſavour of Liſe unto Life: and who is ſufficient for theſe things? For we are not as many which corrupt the word of GOD; but as of Sincerity, but as of God, in the ſight of God ſpeak we in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>DO we begin again to commend our ſelves? or need we as ſome others Epiſtles of Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to you, or Letters of Commendation from you? Ye are our Epiſtle written in our hearts, known and read of all men: for as much as ye are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly declared to be the Epiſtle of Chriſt, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by us, written not with Ink, but with the Spirit of the living God; not in Tables of Stone, but in fleſhly Tables of the Heart. And ſuch Truſt have we thro' Chriſt to God-ward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O might <hi>We</hi> beſpeak You after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, who are our reſpective <hi>Charges,</hi> and had we this <hi>proof of our Miſſion</hi> to you from God in your Conſciences; we ſhould <hi>need</hi> no more to <hi>convince</hi> you, we ſhould <hi>deſire</hi> nothing more to <hi>ſatisfy</hi> you of the <hi>greatneſs of the Gift</hi> of Chriſt to His Church in the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> which He has Ordained in it.</p>
            <p>IT only remains now in the <hi>fourth and laſt place</hi> to Obſerve,</p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>THAT this bleſſed Gift of God to His Church, an Inſtituted Goſpel Miniſtry, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:001732_0029_0FB779954748E228"/>qualify'd by Him for the Miniſterial Office, are the glorious Fruit of the Aſcention of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> When he <hi>aſcended on high, He gave</hi> &amp;c. He <hi>purchas'd</hi> them by His Death, He <hi>received</hi> them at His Aſcention, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet down at the right hand of God He <hi>ſhed forth</hi> of His Holy Spirit. So while He was here on Earth He inform'd His Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that it <hi>was to be,</hi> and ſo He <hi>fulfilled</hi> His glorious Promiſe after He was taken from them. I will only lay before you the <hi>Prophecy</hi> and Promiſe, and the <hi>Event.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>FOR the <hi>firſt</hi> let us look into the <hi>parting gracious Diſcourſes</hi> of our Lord to His Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, juſt before His Apprehenſion and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixion, and His <hi>Divine Prayer</hi> with and for them, as it is recorded by the <hi>Evangeliſt John.</hi> There our Lord tells His Diſciples, that <hi>He would pray the Father, and He ſhould give them another Comforter to abide with them for ever; even the Spirit of Truth. Joh.</hi> 14.15. This "was the Great <hi>New Teſtament</hi> promiſe, as that of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> was of the <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi> Chriſt was the <hi>Conſolation of Iſrael</hi> which the faithful were waiting for before He came into the world, and now that He was leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the world and going to the Father He promis'd His Church <hi>another Comforter</hi> to
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:001732_0030_0FB77996F7CEAEA0"/>ſupply His Bodily Preſence, and to abide with them in His Abſence. Another <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clete,</hi> another <hi>Advocate,</hi> another <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Teacher,</hi> or <hi>Exhorter;</hi> another <hi>Patron</hi> as ſome render it; This bleſſed Gift He promis'd upon His <hi>leaving</hi> them; the Spirit of Truth in all His ſaving Gifts and Operations. <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>I will not leave you Comfortleſs, I will come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</hi> Not only viſit and comfort them once and again after His <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> but after His <hi>Aſcention</hi> be coming daily to them in His bleſſed Spirit, the viſits of His Grace. Again, <hi>v.</hi> 25. <hi>Theſe things have I ſpoken to you, being yet preſent with you; but the Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which is the Holy Ghoſt, whom the Father will ſend in my name, He ſhall teach you all things.</hi> Here He bids them expect another <hi>Teacher</hi> on His Departure: one that ſhould come <hi>in His name;</hi> as His <hi>Subſtitute, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, Repreſentative;</hi> for He is <hi>the Spirit of Chriſt,</hi> to carry on his undertaking: He was to teach them all things, and be in them the Spirit of Wiſdom and Revelation; to <hi>accompliſh</hi> them for, <hi>aſſiſt</hi> them in, and carry them thro' their Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>AGREEABLY we read again, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.26, 27. <hi>When the Comforter is come, whom I will ſend unto you from the Father, even the Spirit
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:001732_0031_0FB7799D655EE500"/>of Truth which proceedeth from the Father, He ſhall teſtify of me; and ye alſo ſhall bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>—&amp;c. Mr. <hi>Henry</hi> ſays, That we have more in this Verſe concerning the <hi>HOLY GHOST,</hi> than in any one Verſe beſides in the <hi>Bible.</hi> Here is an account of him in his <hi>Eſſence</hi> or Subſiſtence rather, He the Spirit of truth which proceedeth from the Father: The Emanation of Divine Light, the Ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of Divine Power: as Heat and Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence are of the Sun and yet are one with it. Again here is an account of this <hi>bleſſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> in his <hi>Miſſion, Office</hi> and <hi>Operations.</hi> He was ſpeedily then to come in a more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Effuſion of his Gifts, Graces and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, than had ever yet been. <hi>Chriſt</hi> had been long the <hi>O Ercomenos, He that ſhould come,</hi> but now the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> was He. <hi>I will ſend him,</hi> ſaid Chriſt, <hi>ſcil:</hi> upon my Aſcention. <hi>I will pray the Father and he ſhall give him.</hi> It was to be the fruit of his Dominion, and Interceſſion within the vail. The Spirit was promis'd to come from Chriſt the Mediator, upon the Apoſtles, to inſtruct them in their preaching, to enable them for working, and to carry them thro' their Sufferings and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony. He teſtifies of Chriſt to this day in the preached Goſpel, and by the mouth of his Miniſters.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="unknown:001732_0032_0FB779A14CF2AE98"/>
BUT there is yet a farther paſſage of our Saviours, wherein he told his Diſciples that his own Departure was <hi>neceſſary</hi> unto the Coming of the Comforter, and that the Coming of the Spirit was abſolutely <hi>neceſſary</hi> to the carrying on his Intereſt on Earth; for that he was to receive of him and to ſhew it unto them. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.7, 14. <hi>Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, I tell you the truth, it is expedient for you that I go away; for if I go not a way, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter will not come unto you; but if I depart I will ſend him unto you. And when he is come, he will convince the world</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He ſhall not ſpeak of himſelf—but he ſhall glorify me, for he ſhall receive of mine and ſhew it unto you. All things that the Father hath are mine, therefore ſaid I, that he ſhall take of mine and ſhew it unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THUS the Spirit of Grace was to come <hi>from the glorify'd Redeemer,</hi> to glorify him on Earth, by converting the world to him, by the Miniſtry of Men. The Gifts and Graces of the Spirit in the Apoſtles, and their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and writing under his bleſſed Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, were to diſplay the power and glory of the Aſcended Saviour; for <hi>in Operation</hi> as well as Eſſence <hi>He derives from the Son;</hi> He communicates and applies what Chriſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd; as Chriſt therefore has purchas'd
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:001732_0033_0FB779A2E76576E8"/>all Spiritual Bleſſings and they are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <hi>to</hi> him by the Father, ſo they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered <hi>by</hi> him to the Holy Spirit to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to us, and conferred according to the Divine Eternal Purpoſe and Council, both as <hi>to perſons,</hi> and as to ways and <hi>means;</hi> both foreknown; the one <hi>Choſen</hi> in Chriſt, the other <hi>Ordained</hi> by him.</p>
            <p>TO have done, the laſt Order that our Saviour left with his Apoſtles juſt before his Aſcention was that, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.49. <hi>Behold I ſend the promiſe of my Father upon you; but tarry you at Jeruſalem till ye be endued with power from on high.</hi> And <hi>Act.</hi> 1.4. <hi>He commanded them to wait for the promiſe of the Father, which ſaid he ye have heard of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND thus you ſee that <hi>this was the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> and <hi>Prediction</hi> of our LORD while he continued here on Earth with his Diſciples, that <hi>after his Aſcention the Holy Spirit ſhould be poured out</hi> to qualify his Miniſters for, and carry them through, and ſucceed them in their Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>AND now let us ſee the <hi>Event,</hi> the Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Event, wherein this glorious Promiſe was <hi>fulfilled;</hi> which was upon this famous day of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> ten days after our Lord's Aſcention: when the Diſciples being met
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:001732_0034_0FB779A64D082A98"/>together in <hi>one place,</hi> aſſembled on the <hi>firſt Day of the Week</hi> for Worſhip, (as no doubt they had continued in Supplications and Prayers night and day, waiting obediently for the Deſcent and Supply of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) <hi>ſuddenly there came a ſound from Heaven, as of a ruſhing mighty wind, and it filled all the houſe where they were ſitting; and there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared cloven Tongues like as of fire and ſat upon them; and they were filled with the Holy Ghoſt, and began to ſpeak with Tongues as the</hi> Spirit <hi>gave them utterance.</hi> This miraculous Event made a great Noiſe inſtantly in the <hi>City,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo great a <hi>Feſtival,</hi> and the multitude gathered together, <hi>diſperſed Jews out of every Nation under Heaven,</hi> who were amazed and confounded to hear theſe <hi>unlearned Galileans ſpeak to them the wonderful works of God,</hi> in the ſeveral Languages of the Nations where they were diſperſed. But <hi>Peter</hi> ſtood up, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired and filled with the Deſcended Spirit of Truth and Grace, and explain'd the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing Occurrence to them: He told them in ſhort, <hi>That God had raiſed up the Crucified Jeſus from the Dead, and had exalted him to his own right hand in the higheſt Heavens;</hi> for they had often ſeen and convers'd with Him after his Reſurrection, and at laſt they ſaw
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:001732_0035_0FB779A78B92EFB8"/>him aſcend bodily into Heaven; and that now <hi>having receiv'd of the Father the promiſe of the Holy Ghoſt, he ſhed Him down upon them in what they now ſaw and heard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THUS the <hi>Holy Ghoſt was given when Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus was glorified,</hi> i. e. after his Aſcention, and not till then; <hi>i. e.</hi> in the fulleſt Effuſion of his Heavenly Gifts and Graces. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are to eſteem the inſtituted, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd and proſperous Miniſtry of the Goſpel, to be <hi>the Gift of Chriſt as Aſcended,</hi> reigning and Interceding for us at the right hand of God, and made the Head and fountain of all divine Influence and ſaving Bleſſings to the Church: as we read, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.22, 23. <hi>And hath put all things under his feet, and gave Him to be the Head over all things unto his Church; Which is his body, the fulneſs of Him that filleth all in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND thus I have in the plaineſt manner I could, but I fear too tedious, opened and prov'd the <hi>Doctrine; That the Inſtitution of a Goſpel Miniſtry, and the Qualification of Perſons for it are to be eſteemed among the rich Gifts of the Aſcended Saviour.</hi> And now I ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to apply the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>BUT ſuch a world of awful and juſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections</hi> offer themſelves upon the <hi>great Truths</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="unknown:001732_0036_0FB779B1BA849740"/>that have been ſet before you, that I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to venture even upon the hinting at them after this length which I have already allow'd my ſelf. And yet I needs muſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>We ſee</hi> (my Brethren) <hi>the Glory of the Lord Jeſus, and his Grace to us:</hi> 1. <hi>His Glory:</hi> in the verity of his Reſurrection and Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the perfection of his Sacrifice, the height of his Exaltation, the dignity of his State, his high Dominion, Supremacy, and Exerciſe of Rule and Government, both in the Kingdom of Providence and Grace. Let us look to Him where he is, and where we hope e're long to be, and behold his Glory.</p>
            <p n="2">2. WE ſee his <hi>gracious care of, and love and mercy to a miſerable ſinful world,</hi> that He has inſtituted a Miniſtry of Religion in it, that he has given forth his Holy Spirit to ſanctify Perſons thereunto, gift and qualify them for it; incline and ſpirit, ſucceed and proſper them in it. <hi>He is the Rock, his work is perfect.</hi> To Him we muſt aſcribe all the Glory that there is to be ſeen in Men or Means. They that are qualify'd and call'd and us'd by him, muſt put it far from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and people muſt turn off their Eyes from their Miniſters, to their <hi>Aſcended Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, for who is Paul or who is Apollos, ſave
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:001732_0037_0FB779B423F9C720"/>Miniſters by whom ye believed.</hi> If <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were here to preach to you by Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to work Miracles, and which is more to convert Thouſands at a time to Chriſt; yet would they not ſuffer you to look ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly at them, as if by their power or holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs any thing were done; no, they would tell us, but <hi>God has glorified His Son Jeſus,</hi> and to his <hi>Name, thro' Faith in his Name,</hi> muſt every Divine Effect be ſolely attributed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>OUR Doctrine does great Honour to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Office, and to them that are in it, or are deſigned for it.</hi> Who would not deſire to be a part of <hi>this precious Gift</hi> to a periſhing world for the Salvation of Souls! <hi>I thank Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord,</hi> ſaid Holy <hi>Paul, who hath enabled me, for that he counted me faithful, putting me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Miniſtry!</hi> O the <hi>glorious Goſpel of the bleſſed God</hi> (ſays he) <hi>committed to my truſt.</hi> Miniſters are <hi>Angels,</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> in the Church; high and awful is their Station; they muſt ſerve with fear, and rejoice with trembling.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>THE means of Education are a bleſſed Gift of Heaven to a Land:</hi> Our <hi>Schools,</hi> our <hi>Colleges</hi> and the <hi>Sons of the Prophets</hi> there that excell in Diligence, in Science and in early Piety. The Schools had <hi>Elijahs</hi> laſt Viſitation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Aſcention, and ever ſince our <hi>Lord</hi>'s
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:001732_0038_0FB779B58A6CB380"/>Aſcention they have His. There he ſelects the <hi>happy favourite Youth,</hi> adorns him with Gifts and Graces, inclines and devotes him to ſacred Services, deſigns him his eminent Uſe and Services in the World, and calls him forth from thence into his Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom among Men, makes him a burning and a ſhining Light and ſets him up in his Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtic, to give light in the world. How many ſuch <hi>rich Gifts</hi> of Chriſt have the Churches receiv'd from our <hi>College?</hi> how ſingular a Bleſſing has it herein been made unto the Land?</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>OUR Doctrine would put perſons on dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating themſelves to the Holy Work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and Parents on devoting their goodlieſt Sons thereunto:</hi> Give <hi>them,</hi> O give <hi>your ſelves,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſervice of your Aſcended Lord, that he may make you worthy Gifts unto his Church. And O what <hi>Diligence</hi> ſhould <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didates</hi> for the Miniſtry be put upon in the uſe of proper means, ſtudy, prayer, humility, with purity of Aim and Intention at the glory of God, uſefulneſs in the world, the benefit of others, and the ſaving your own Souls? Yea how <hi>thankful</hi> ſhould they be for the Gifts of God to them, natural and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired Parts, the love of Study, an Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:001732_0039_0FB779B6FA824968"/>to his Service, a hearty and fervent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to do good in the world, and eſpecially to labour in the Salvation of Souls. Again, how <hi>careful</hi> ſhould they be to do nothing which may provoke God to deny unto them his Gifts, or to take them away from 'em? but to do every thing whereby they may keep themſelves in the love of God, and <hi>come behind in no Gift.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>THE Doctrine would direct people in chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a Miniſter or Paſtor, to be over them in the Lord:</hi> which as it is their undoubted <hi>right,</hi> ſo they are <hi>accountable</hi> to Chriſt <hi>how</hi> they improve it for the good of their own Souls and their Families. They ought ſurely to <hi>covet earneſtly the beſt Gift of Heaven</hi> they can find prepared for them and offer'd to them. Chuſe One who may be indeed a Gift of Heaven to you: One whom Chriſt has gifted and accompliſht for his work, One that moſt viſibly ſhines in the Spirit of Chriſt and of Grace, One whom you may hope Chriſt will own, One that has a zeal for Chriſt and Holineſs, and for the Souls of Men.</p>
            <p>TOO many there are that are ready to <hi>intrude without either Gifts or Graces</hi> into the ſacred Work of the Miniſtry; and too many
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:001732_0040_0FB779BDD8E2D980"/>ſeem <hi>careleſs</hi> whether the Perſon whom they chuſe have either, if ſo be they may but have him <hi>cheap.</hi> Such a Perſon may be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated to the Miniſtry of the Goſpel by the <hi>hands of Men,</hi> and I may add by the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane will</hi> of a People, but Chriſt never <hi>gave</hi> nor <hi>ſent</hi> him. Great care ſhould be taken that unqualify'd perſons be not received into this Holy Office, for Chriſt will diſown and diſclaim their being his Gifts to men.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>OUR Doctrine would comfort and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage thoſe that are in the Miniſtry, and deſire to be found Faithful in the wighty Truſt:</hi> You have (my Reverend <hi>Brethren and Fathers</hi>) the glorious LORD and SAVIOUR in the Heavens to be looking to and relying on, to ſupply you with Gifts and Graces, to ſupport and comfort you in all your Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, to protect and defend you in his Service, and to ſucceed you in his Work. He <hi>reigns</hi> above, and has ſaid to you, <hi>All power is given to me in Heaven and Earth, go ye therefore.</hi> In this his Might and Name <hi>go forth</hi> therefore and <hi>go on.</hi> You and your work are his ſpecial Care, and while he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns the World, his gracious Eye is upon the <hi>little Flock</hi> his Church therein. This Man at the right hand of God ſtands alſo among
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:001732_0041_0FB779C197683000"/>the <hi>Myrtle trees in the bottom;</hi> and Angels re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Orders and make their Motions as the Needs of his humble and feeble Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant do require. He walks in the midſt of his golden Candleſtics, and he holds the Stars in his right hand. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1. In his <hi>hand</hi> which ſpeaks his tender <hi>Care</hi> of them, his <hi>right</hi> hand which ſpeaks his <hi>power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>HOW Diligently ſhould Miniſters improve all their Gifts for Chriſt; labouring to approve themſelves as the Gifts of ſo glorious a Lord unto His Church:</hi> For Men do not <hi>light a Candle to put it under a Buſhel.</hi> How lamentable was it that the <hi>Shield of Saul</hi> was at laſt vilely thrown away as tho' He had not been <hi>Anointed with Oyl!</hi> 
               <q>Having therefore <hi>gifts differing</hi> according to the Grace of God which is given to us, let us wait on our Miniſtring, on Teaching, on Exhortation, and on the Rule committed to us, with Diligence. Let us, as becomes our Relation to God and Souls, follow after Righteouſneſs, Godlineſs, Faith, Love, Patience, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; fight the good Fight and lay hold on Eternal Life. Let us ſtudy to be Examples to the flock, in Word, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, in Spirit, in Faith, in Purity. Let us preach the word, be inſtant, in
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:001732_0042_0FB779C6AF893850"/>ſeaſon <hi>&amp;c.</hi> reprove, rebuke <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let us hold faſt the faithful word, and feed the flock of God that is among us, his Lambs and his Sheep, willingly and of a ready mind.</q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>LET us ſtudy how to behave our ſelves in the houſe of God, and to ſhew our ſelves approved workmen that need not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let us be ſound in the Faith, always ſpeaking the things which become ſound Doctrine; with meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves; being gentle unto all men, apt to teach. Let us labour to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come mighty in the Scriptures; and to preach not our ſelves but Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, and our ſelves the ſervants of Souls for Jeſus ſake. Let us give attention to Reading, to Exhortation, to Doctrine; ſhewing Uncoruptneſs, Gravity, Sincerity, and ſound Speech which <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let us o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our mouths boldly, to make known the Myſtery of the Goſpel; that thereof we may ſpeak ſo as we ought to ſpeak; as able Miniſters of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> not of the Letter, but of the Spirit. Let us meditate therefore on divine things, and give our ſelves to Prayer and to the Miniſtry of the word; let us give our
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:001732_0043_0FB779C799273580"/>ſelves wholly to them and continue in them, that we may both ſave our ſelves and thoſe that hear us.</p>
               <p>Let us remember how we have been charged awfully unto all this, and have obliged our ſelves, before God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; who ſhall judge the quick and the dead, at his Appearing and Kingdom: And when the chief Shepherd ſhall appear, ye ſhall receive a Crown of Glory which fadeth not away.</p>
            </q>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>WITH what Thankfulneſs and Eſteem ought perſons to entertain the Miniſtry of Chriſt? and reverence their faithful Paſtors, as the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gift of the Aſcended Saviour to them?</hi> Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and places ſhould carefully ſeek the ſettlement of the Goſpel among them, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably ſupport the Miniſtry thereof, give a hearty welcome and receive gladly the Salvation bro't to their Houſes; and every way encourage and comfort the Hearts of their Miniſters in the work of the Lord; eſpecially by <hi>eſteeming them highly in love for the Words ſake,</hi> and yielding a willing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to their Inſtructions, Admonitions, Counſels, and profiting under the ſame.</p>
            <p>LET it not be that Heaven <hi>caſts its Pearls before Swine,</hi> that do but <hi>turn and rend</hi> inſtead
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:001732_0044_0FB779C91F94C720"/>of <hi>reverencing the feet</hi> of them that bring the glad Tydings of Peace. Too many are the places that put far from them the Miniſtry of Chriſt, and count themſelves <hi>unworthy of Eternal Life;</hi> they ignorantly and profanely deſpiſe the Goſpel, for they do not know the Gift of God: they abuſe, revile and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify him that wears the name of a Miniſter. But this is as Chriſt himſelf was rejected of Men, and if they have <hi>called the maſter of the Houſe Beelzebub, what ſhall they not call them of his Houſhold?</hi> But Chriſt reſents highly the Contempt done unto his Heavenly Gift: <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.10, 11. <hi>Into whatſoever City ye enter and they receive you not, go out into the ſtreets of the ſame and ſay, Even the very duſt of your City which cleaveth on us, we do wipe off againſt you: notwithſtanding be you ſure of this, that the Kingdom of God is come nigh unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VERILY there are too many that do not ſeem to <hi>eſteem their Miniſters,</hi> however fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd and faithful they be, <hi>as the rich Gift of Chriſt</hi> to them: in ſome places they <hi>ſtarve</hi> them, rating them and their Labours at a <hi>vile and cheap price;</hi> in ſome places they <hi>grieve</hi> and break the hearts of their Miniſters by perſonal diſreſpects, in others by Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Quarrels among themſelves; and
<pb n="45" facs="unknown:001732_0045_0FB779D31F30B9D8"/>let me add, that if it be only by <hi>Unprofitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> under the Labours of your Miniſters you ſhow the little regard you have, and the ſmall account you make of them and of Him that ſends them. But beyond all, How evil is it to revile, diſparage and expoſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, to bely and ſlander the <hi>Miniſtry of a Land;</hi> and thro' the Grace of God too a Body of Miniſters ſecond but to few places of like numbers, for Miniſterial Gifts and Graces, Diligence and Labours both as to Study and Preaching, and other Inſtances of a Paſtoral Fidelity and Watch; to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them in <hi>Satyr</hi> to their Churches thro' the Land as <hi>Traitors</hi> to Chriſt and to the Churches, ignorantly or knowingly betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in their beſt Intereſts which they ought to defend and maintain; to repreſent them as a part of the <hi>Army of Gog and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog compaſſing about the Camp of the Saints of God and the beloved Gity;</hi> to make the Churches believe (if they can indeed be made to believe it) that their Miniſters are <hi>dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Perſons,</hi> not to be truſted by reaſon of their corrupt Principles or Deſigns: how Evil muſt this be? For indeed were this true, it muſt then be confeſſed that the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Miniſtry</hi> of this Land is <hi>no Gift of Chriſt</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="unknown:001732_0046_0FB779D5115CB3C0"/>unto theſe Churches, but a <hi>ſore and heavy Judgment</hi> on them. The word of God unto his <hi>Miniſters</hi> under this preſent trial is that, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 8. <hi>Approving your ſelves as the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt in much Patience;— by honour and diſhonour, by evil report and good report, as deceivers and yet true, as unknown and yet well known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. AND laſtly, We learn from our Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine <hi>the Reaſonableneſs of our preſent Prayers to God this day.</hi> We are come together to <hi>ask a great and bleſſed Gift from our Aſcended Saviour to this ſinful Flock of His;</hi> even the Union of our hearts in the <hi>Election of ſome Perſon into the Paſtoral Office among us,</hi> whom He ſhall pleaſe to qualify and accompliſh herefor, encline and ſpirit unto fidelity herein, and make a rich and ſingular Bleſſing to us and our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren after us: to the <hi>Town</hi> alſo together with us, and to the <hi>Land.</hi> Such <hi>Gifts</hi> are with our <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> to beſtow, and he diſpenſes them from Heaven freely even to the <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious.</hi> He himſelf has bid us <hi>pray the Lord of the Harveſt that he will thruſt forth Labourers into His Harveſt:</hi> and he has promis'd to <hi>give the Holy Spirit to them that ask him,</hi> and to give his people (and his repenting back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding people too) <hi>Paſtors after his own Heart. Jer.</hi> 3.15.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="unknown:001732_0047_0FB779D684F973E8"/>
WE come this day to pray for all our <hi>Holy Brethren,</hi> both Miniſters and People together, that the <hi>Lords Miniſters may be cloathed with Righteouſneſs and Salvation, and his Saints be made to ſhout for joy:</hi> to pray for the <hi>Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates</hi> for the Miniſtry in particular, that our <hi>Colleges</hi> may be repleniſhed with every good and perfect Gift from God the Father of Lights, and that the Spirit of Grace may reſt in double Portions on the Sons of the Prophets.</p>
            <p>WE are here this day to confeſs our utter <hi>unworthineſs</hi> to receive any ſuch <hi>Gift</hi> from God, which yet he has bid us moſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to covet and to ſeek. We are here to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail all the <hi>forfeitures</hi> we have made of ſuch a Mercy. We therefore ſeek it only in the Name of our Aſcended <hi>Saviour,</hi> and from his gracious Hands, of his fulneſs, and the riches of his glorious Grace. If we do not ask amiſs, ſurely we may receive; for it is a Petition every way agreeable to his Holy Will. Why has Chriſt received ſuch Gifts for Men but to beſtow them? Why has he gifted Men but to give them to his Church? or why elſe has he inclined them whom he has gifted to give themſelves to the Service of the Church? Ask then with Humiliation,
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:001732_0048_0FB779DF53BFCD28"/>Faith and true Deſire, and receive, that your Joy may be full. Such a Gift was always meant to be ſought and obtain'd by Prayer; and the Gift is greatned to us when it is thus obtained.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>united</hi> Prayers of our <hi>Brethren</hi> with us this day ſhould ſtrengthen our Faith and fervency in the Prayers of the day. For has not our Lord ſaid unto us concerning the Acceptableneſs and Efficacy of <hi>joynt Prayer</hi> with God, with which words I will <hi>Conclude, Mar.</hi> 18.19. <hi>I ſay unto you, that if two of you ſhall agree on Earth, as touching any thing that ye ſhall ask, it ſhall be done for you of my Father which is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IF <hi>two</hi> agree it ſhall be done, how much more if <hi>many</hi> agree in the Petition. Let us <hi>Agree</hi> my Brethren. God unite our hearts to make one Voice in <hi>Prayer;</hi> and God unite our hearts to his own Glory in the <hi>Choice</hi> propoſed by us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
