<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fair dealing between debtor and creditor. A very brief essay upon the caution to be used, about coming in to debt, and getting out of it. Offered at Boston-lecture; 5. d. XI. m. 1715/16. / By Cotton Mather, D.D. &amp; F.R.S. ; [Two lines of quotation]</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04">2009-04.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N01536</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N01536</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 1823</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW6051</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">1823</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99012184</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 1823.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N01536)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 1823)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 1823)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fair dealing between debtor and creditor. A very brief essay upon the caution to be used, about coming in to debt, and getting out of it. Offered at Boston-lecture; 5. d. XI. m. 1715/16. / By Cotton Mather, D.D. &amp; F.R.S. ; [Two lines of quotation]</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p. ;  15 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Green, for Samuel Gerrish, at his shop over against the north side of the Town-House.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1716.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: The honest debtor.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Debtor and creditor.</term>
               <term>Sermons --  1716.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:001823_0000_0FB83DE09F2FFE58"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:001823_0001_0FB83DE1EDE70D88"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FAIR DEALING <hi>between</hi> Debtor <hi>and</hi> Creditor. A very brief ESSAY UPON The CAUTION to be uſed, about <hi>coming</hi> in to DEBT, And <hi>getting</hi> out of it. Offered at BOSTON-Lecture; 5. d. XI. m. 1715/16.</p>
            <p>By Cotton Mather, D.D. &amp; F.R.S.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Stultus eſt Debitor, qui gaudens Pecunias acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, et Tempus quo reddere debeat, non attendit.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gregor. in Moral.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON:</hi> Printed by <hi>B. Green,</hi> for <hi>Samuel Gerriſh,</hi> at his Shop over againſt the North ſide of the Town-Houſe. 1716.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1"
                facs="unknown:001823_0002_0FB83DE39D7B0328"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Honeſt Debtor.</head>
            <head type="sub">BOSTON-Lecture 5. d. XI. m. 1715, 16.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. XIII. 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Owe no Man any thing, but to Love one another.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT was a ſad Complaint of Old, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding a People, who had made an high <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of the true <hi>Religion;</hi> Ezek. V. 7. <hi>You have not done according to the Judgments of the Nations which be round about you.</hi> It ſeems, other Nations, who had not been ſo well-inſtructed as this People, yet had <hi>more Equity</hi> in their Dealings, and were People of <hi>Better Morals,</hi> than theſe who had been under the Covenant of God.</p>
            <p>It has been complained, That tho' the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> of God, be Profeſſed with an uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Show among our ſelves, yet among us,
<pb n="2" facs="unknown:001823_0003_0FB83DE4EAB79BA0"/>there are too often found ſuch <hi>Iniquities</hi> in the Dealings of Men, as are condemned even in the <hi>Judgments of the Nations;</hi> and there are <hi>Better Morals</hi> to be found in Places, which yet may have the Cenſure of the Patriarch upon <hi>Gerar</hi> too much belonging to them, than ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times occur in what makes the moſt flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pretences to be a <hi>Land of Rectitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, I hope, it will never be complained, That the Miniſters of the Goſpel, are by any Sinful Silence acceſſary to the Tranſgreſſions, which <hi>Deny</hi> the <hi>Doctrine of God our Saviour,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a People, that are under peculiar Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to <hi>Adorn</hi> it. It ſhall not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, That the Miniſters do ſo confine themſelves to Preach <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> that the People forget <hi>Moral Honeſty,</hi> thro' any Default of ours. It ſhall be aſſerted, That with a due <hi>Frequency,</hi> as well as <hi>Fervency,</hi> we inculcate upon our Neighbours, the Duties of <hi>Moral Honeſty,</hi> and remonſtrate unto them, that without <hi>This,</hi> all their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> is but a <hi>Counterfeit; God will reject it, and they ſhall not proſper in it!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One <hi>Point of Morality,</hi> wherein we are told, that many People are defective, is, The Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with which Peoples <hi>Running into Debt,</hi> and <hi>Lying</hi> in it when they have run into it, ought for ever to be regulated. People there
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:001823_0004_0FB83DE85CC8B2B8"/>are, too many, who do bring <hi>Debts</hi> upon themſelves, in ſuch a manner, and in ſuch a meaſure, that a <hi>Folly</hi> nothing ſhort of <hi>Criminal,</hi> is to be charged upon them. And when they have brought ſuch <hi>Debts</hi> upon themſelves, their <hi>Delay</hi> to get from under them, is what alſo amounts unto a <hi>Crime,</hi> for which they are to be Indicted, as <hi>not having the Fear of God before their Eyes.</hi> There are ſome Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Day, which may render a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe on this <hi>Point of Morality,</hi> ſingularly Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable. But indeed it were never out of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And, I would humbly hope, that not only the <hi>Creditors,</hi> but even the <hi>Debtors</hi> too, will anon be Thankful, for the Advice which is now Faithfully to be diſpenſed unto them.</p>
            <p>To check the Errors too often committed by <hi>Contracting</hi> of <hi>Debts,</hi> and by <hi>Continuing</hi> in them, I now read unto you a Sentence of the Sacred Oracles, before which we ought all to tremble as before the Vibrations of a Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolt. It is the <hi>Voice of the ETERNAL,</hi> that is now convey'd unto us, by the Pen of an Inſpired Apoſtle. <hi>The God of Glory Thunders</hi> in it; May His <hi>Voice</hi> be ſo <hi>Powerful,</hi> as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce an univerſal Compliance among us, an univerſal Obedience unto it.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of God, who is a <hi>Righteous Lord,</hi> and <hi>Loves Righteouſneſs,</hi> does firſt of all direct
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:001823_0005_0FB83DEA35E4A950"/>us, to pay a <hi>Debt</hi> which People owe unto their <hi>Superiours;</hi> That they who ſerve the <hi>Publick,</hi> and have their <hi>Thought</hi> and their <hi>Time</hi> taken up, in watching for the Safety of the <hi>People,</hi> may be handſomely Subſiſted in their Station. A <hi>Debt</hi> this is, which is not always duely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, nor ſo honeſtly paid as it ought to be! But then, the Direction goes on; That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Debt</hi> People may owe to <hi>one another,</hi> in the way of their Dealing with <hi>one another,</hi> be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo duely anſwered. People muſt not be in <hi>Debt</hi> unto one another, any further than what is <hi>anovoidable.</hi> 'Tis true, there is One <hi>Debt,</hi> which tho' it ſhould be ever <hi>Paying,</hi> yet it will be ever <hi>Owing.</hi> A <hi>Debt</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Of this, as <hi>much as you pleaſe!</hi> But for any other <hi>Debt,</hi> even for that which is a proper <hi>Debt,</hi> Here you cannot be too Cautious. Let Chriſtians <hi>come Slowly</hi> into it; and let them <hi>get Quickly</hi> out of it. Let Chriſtians Exerciſe their <hi>Wiſdom</hi> in coming in, and their <hi>Juſtice</hi> in getting out. Come into it, with the Pace of a <hi>Tortoiſe,</hi> and get out of it, with the Flight of an <hi>Eagle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The DOCTRINE, which I have a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Commiſſion to inſiſt upon, is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a proper Caution, about coming into DEBT, and getting out of DERT, which is a conſiderable Point of Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="unknown:001823_0006_0FB83DEBB6F8EBF8"/>
A Due <hi>Caution,</hi> to <hi>Owe no Man any thing,</hi> is what <hi>every Man</hi> ſhould Labour in. 'Tis the Duty of Chriſtians, to have as few <hi>Creditors</hi> as ever they can, and owe as little to their <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors</hi> as ever they can, and give none of their <hi>Creditors</hi> any cauſe to complain, <hi>That they are not fairly dealt withal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe, There is no need of any Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Eſſay, to give a Definition of the DEBT, againſt which we are now to be caution'd. The <hi>Lexicons</hi> of the <hi>Lawyers</hi> are needleſs to be conſulted on this Occaſion, which will tell us, <hi>Debitor tuus eſt, qui tibi non reddit quod tuum eſt.</hi> A <hi>Debtor</hi> is One, who does not let another Man have his own; One who does not ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a Neighbour, what he has a claim un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. They will tell us, A Debt, is what a Man is under Obligation to accommodate another Man withal. Or, <hi>Quod ab Invito Exigi poteſt;</hi> What a Man may by <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Right,</hi> be forced whether he will or no, to part withal. The meaning of a DEBT, is too well known, yea, on both ſides too <hi>feelingly underſtood,</hi> for us to want any Explication of it. Every body knows, That a Man is in <hi>Debt,</hi> when he is <hi>under Obligation to deliver up any Poſſeſſions unto another Man, upon the Demand thereof.</hi> There are many Ways, in which a Man may come under ſuch an Obligation; and particularly
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:001823_0007_0FB83DED2E423190"/>ſuch Ways as thoſe wherein <hi>Oneſimus</hi> came in <hi>Debt</hi> unto his Maſter. But the moſt uſual Way, and that which I have now my Eye moſt upon, is, that of <hi>Agreement with the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor.</hi> The <hi>Debt</hi> is indeed, but as an <hi>Embryo,</hi> in its Formation, while the <hi>Time</hi> is not yet come for the Creditor to make his Demand. But it is more fully formed, and makes a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry audible Cry, when a Man witholds from another Man, the <hi>Poſſeſſions,</hi> which ought <hi>Now</hi> to be delivered. This is not only <hi>Being</hi> in <hi>Debt,</hi> but alſo <hi>Lying</hi> in <hi>Debt:</hi> And it is to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided with all the <hi>Caution</hi> imaginable. <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> You do not anſwer your <hi>Worthy Name;</hi> nor come up to that Neceſſary Character of <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Genuine Chriſtians,</hi> Heb XIII. 18. <hi>Having a Good Conſcience, in all things willing to Live Honeſtly;</hi>—If this <hi>Caution</hi> be a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with you.</p>
            <p>I hope, no Man will Excuſe any Mans not <hi>Paying</hi> what he <hi>Owes,</hi> by the Example of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who <hi>Borrowed</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any Reſtitution. If the Great GOD, who was now become the King of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> gave His injur'd People a ſort of <hi>Letters of Mart,</hi> for them to make Repriſals on the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> it was but according to the <hi>Law of Nations.</hi> But ſome will maintain, in reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did not <hi>Borrow</hi> any thing of
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:001823_0008_0FB83DEEB1E06EC0"/>the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> Our Tranſlation may be mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. They did not <hi>Borrow,</hi> but <hi>Beg</hi> of them. The ſame Word is Tranſlated elſewhere, To <hi>Requeſt.</hi> The Things which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> were not <hi>Lent,</hi> but <hi>Given</hi> to them. When its ſaid, <hi>They Lent unto them,</hi> it ſhould be only taken ſo, <hi>They Accommodated them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am aware, That for People to bring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into <hi>Debt,</hi> is not a Thing always For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden of God Our Apoſtle himſelf, who writes to the <hi>Romans, Owe no Man any thing,</hi> yet was willing to bring himſelf into <hi>Debt,</hi> upon a Good Occaſion Yea, and into a <hi>Debt</hi> of <hi>Suretiſhip</hi> too, which is a Sort of <hi>Debt,</hi> that calls for more <hi>Caution</hi> than any in the World. On the behalf of his Convert, he writes unto <hi>Philemon;</hi> (Ver. 8.) <hi>If he owes thee any thing, put that on mine Account.</hi> It was of Old required by God; Deut. XV. 8 <hi>If there be a poor Man, thou ſhalt ſurely lend him ſufficient for his Need.</hi> Our Saviour has Commanded us. To <hi>Lend</hi> one unto another; Saying, <hi>From him that would Borrow of thee, turn thou not away.</hi> And in His Word, He has Commended, the <hi>Good Man, that Shows Favour and Lendeth;</hi> with an Hint indeed at the ſame time, <hi>That we ſhould guide our Affairs with Diſcretion.</hi> But we can't <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> without our Neighbour coming into <hi>Debt</hi> unto us: Which renders it plain. That
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:001823_0009_0FB83DF3A4002408"/>ſome <hi>Debt</hi> is to be allowed of. Yea, without ſome <hi>Debt,</hi> there could no <hi>Trade</hi> be carried on. It would ſtrangely Cramp the <hi>Trade</hi> of a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, if it might be no more than the <hi>Caſh</hi> that is running among them. There may be much <hi>Conveniency</hi> in <hi>Buying,</hi> and ſometimes there may be a <hi>Neceſſity</hi> for <hi>Buying,</hi> when People cannot immediately <hi>Pay</hi> for what they <hi>Buy.</hi> Yea, ſince the World ſo much reſolves to <hi>Trade upon Credit,</hi> I will Grant, That a Man of <hi>Capacity</hi> and <hi>Integrity,</hi> that has nothing elſe, may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times have his <hi>Capacity</hi> and <hi>Integrity</hi> a <hi>Sufficient Fund,</hi> for him to take up thereupon, if his <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors</hi> will pleaſe to have it ſo. Our <hi>Books of Accounts,</hi> are a very Material part of our <hi>Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;</hi> and an Excellent Proviſion they are, to carry on a <hi>Lucriferous Buſineſs,</hi> when 'tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to have <hi>Caſh</hi> at hand, in Proportion to the <hi>Trade</hi> that mult be proſecuted. And there, if <hi>Diſcount</hi> paſs for <hi>Good Pay,</hi> I pray, what Hurt is done to any Body? No Body is hurt, if the <hi>Debt</hi> wherewith <hi>Trade</hi> is carryed on, be kept under a <hi>Suitable Regulation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, that <hi>Suitable Regulation!</hi> This is what I am now to treat upon.</p>
            <p>I Confeſs my ſelf leſs competent for a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe on ſuch a Subject, than perhaps many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the Auditory, For, <hi>I am neither a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, nor the Son of a Trader.</hi> And yet I am a
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:001823_0010_0FB83DF570DA0EC8"/>Maſter of certain MAXIMS, which will En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able me &amp; Embolden me, to attempt now a very brief Treatiſe upon it. MAXIMS which I can maintain with Victorious Demonſtrations, and have more than a <hi>Thouſand Preachers</hi> in the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, to ſtand by me; I mean, The CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SCIENCE of every Man that I Speak unto; MAXIMS, which if well hearken'd to, ther would be fewer of thoſe <hi>Debts,</hi> which multiply among us <hi>Uneaſy Circumſtances;</hi> and this Place would be much more, <hi>A Mountain of Holineſs, and a Dwelling of Righteouſneſs,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Bleſſed of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="maxim">
               <head>The firſt MAXIM.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Man that is going into Debt, ſhould keep the Eye of Prudence Open, upon every Step that is before him.</hi> To run in the <hi>Dark,</hi> when One is going into <hi>Debt;</hi> This is <hi>Folly in the Exaltation of it:</hi> One going into <hi>Debt,</hi> ſhould with a <hi>Rational Proſpect,</hi> be able to ſee his <hi>whole way Plain</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. People without <hi>Foreſight</hi> ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver go into <hi>Debt;</hi> without <hi>Foreſight,</hi> of what in the Progreſs of their way they may meet withal. It was an ancient Prayer; Pſal. V. 8. <hi>Becauſe of my Obſervers, make thy way ſtrait be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Face.</hi> My Friend, Becauſe of thy <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors,</hi> Be ſure of a <hi>Strait way,</hi> and go not into <hi>Debt,</hi> without a <hi>Way</hi> lying Plain <hi>before thy Face,</hi> for every ſtep of thy Motions. The Jews have
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:001823_0011_0FB83DF6EDA4D080"/>a Tradition, that our Father <hi>Adam</hi> was the Author of that Saying, <hi>No Man would Sin if he ſaw from the Beginning to the End.</hi> Moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly very many among the Children of <hi>Adam,</hi> would not run into <hi>Debt,</hi> as they do, if they did but <hi>ſee from the Beginning to the End.</hi> Going into <hi>Debt,</hi> make a Pauſe, and think, <hi>Will it not be Bitterneſs in the Latter End?</hi> The conduct of <hi>Prudence,</hi> is that; Prov. XX<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>A Prudent Man foreſees the Evil and hides himſelf.</hi> Sirs, When you are going into <hi>Debt,</hi> thoroughly weigh the Matter. If you can <hi>foreſee</hi> any remarkable <hi>Evil,</hi> in which you are like to be Entangled by what you do; <hi>Then</hi> Stop; <hi>then</hi> ſtay; <hi>then</hi> look about you. If you are So <hi>Simple,</hi> as to <hi>paſs on,</hi> you deſerve to be <hi>Puniſhed</hi> for what you do. The Thing I preſs for is, That before you go into <hi>Debt,</hi> you adviſe with an Ingenious Man that once prevented a deal of Miſchief at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> I mean him, who did a World of Good by that Memorable Saying, <hi>Ye ought to do nothing Raſhly.</hi> When the <hi>Temptation</hi> of going into <hi>Debt</hi> comes upon you, [And, there often appears too much cauſe to Juſtify my Term, when I call it, <hi>of Temptation!</hi>] it will be but <hi>Prudently</hi> done of you, to think; <hi>What will be the Conſequence of what I am now a doing? Shall not I run my ſelf into inextricable Snares? Am not I pulling on my ſelf inſupportable Miſeries? Cares
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:001823_0012_0FB83DFA6A593B78"/>that will be too heavy for me? Cheats upon thoſe have truſted me? The wrath of diſappoinied Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors? Diſgrace &amp; Contempt among all my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours?</hi> If upon Mature Deliberation, you have a <hi>Clear View</hi> of Eſcaping all this <hi>Evil;</hi> Then 'tis <hi>Well!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prudence</hi> is the Thing that is urged upon you. Now, that you may keep within the Limits of <hi>Prudence,</hi> Methinks, it were no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper Propoſal; <hi>Conſult with a Prudent Friend, about what you do, before you do it.</hi> A <hi>Friend</hi> whoſe <hi>Prudence</hi> you may rely much upon; Such a <hi>Friend</hi> is a <hi>Treaſure.</hi> And on this Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, he may be very <hi>Literally</hi> ſo, <hi>Emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> ſo! If you have any <hi>Doubt,</hi> about going into any <hi>Debt;</hi> Ask the Counſil of ſuch a <hi>Friend,</hi> Whether it be well for you to do it, or no? You know who ſaid; Prov. XIII. 10. <hi>With the Well-adviſed is Wiſdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am ſure, if you Conſult with one Friend, whom I ſhall Name unto you he will give you a Dictate of <hi>Prudence,</hi> about one Sort of <hi>Debt,</hi> where with many Thouſands do moſt <hi>Unadvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly</hi> ruine themſelves, and their Families. A <hi>Solomon</hi> is the Friend, I intend; and the <hi>Debt</hi> is that of an Inconſiderate <hi>Suretiſhip,</hi> an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable <hi>Suretiſhip.</hi> He tells us; Prov. XVII. 18. <hi>A Man void of Underſtanding ſtriketh hands, and becomes a Surety in the preſence of his
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:001823_0013_0FB83DFB75339548"/>Friend.</hi> He tells us; Prov. XI. 15. <hi>He that is Surety for a Stranger ſhall be ſore Broken for it; and he that hateth Suretiſhip is ſure.</hi> For a Man to Vow, <hi>That he will never be Surety for another,</hi> 'tis to make a <hi>Raſh Vow.</hi> A Man may thus Enſnare himſelf in Engagements to decline a <hi>Duty</hi> which God may call him to. There is a Violation of the <hi>Third Commandment,</hi> as well as Breach upon <hi>Charity,</hi> in ſuch Engagements. But then, If you will be <hi>well-adviſea,</hi> forget not that Caveat; Prov. XXII. 26. <hi>Be not One of them that are Sureties for Debts.</hi> Uſe abundance of Deliberation, when a <hi>Suretiſhip</hi> ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded unto you; Think over &amp; over again; <hi>Am I Safe? Does God call me into any Sponſorial Hazards? Do not the Circumſtancies of my Family forbid my coming into them? Shall not I by'nd by Repent moſt bitterly, and even tear my Hair for the Vexation of my coming under theſe Encumbrances?</hi> Theſe are Thoughts, which I ſuppoſe, do not come into the Minds of them, who are moſt eaſily drawn into <hi>Ruining Suretiſhips.</hi> The <hi>Cups</hi> that ſometimes Mellow Men into this <hi>Folly,</hi> don't afford Room for ſuch Thoughts as theſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="maxim">
               <head>The Second MAXIM.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Man that would not be Sinfully in Debt ought to have a Spirit reconciled unto a Low and Mean Condition in the World, if this be what the Glorious GOD ſhall call him to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="unknown:001823_0014_0FB83DFD088F1DC8"/>
A grand Cauſe of Peoples running into <hi>Debt,</hi> is this; They cannot bear the Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a <hi>Low and a Mean Condition</hi> in the World. Eſpecially, They that have ſometimes Lived in more of Splendor; theſe oftentimes find themſelves very unable to bear a <hi>Reduced Condition.</hi> This 'tis, that cauſes them to run into <hi>Debt.</hi> for the Supply of their <hi>Carnal Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites.</hi> Hence 'tis, that Some who <hi>Live upon other Mens Eſtates,</hi> go ſo far in their Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, as to Live Higher than their <hi>Creditors</hi> themſelves can do. Thoſe <hi>Flags of Pride,</hi> if I may be ſo bold, <hi>Are they Paid for?</hi> With what Face can you pretend unto them, while they are not ſo?</p>
               <p>But, firſt, it is a Poſition, which I hope, no Good Man will queſtion; If a Man cannot keep out of a <hi>Low and Mean Condition,</hi> without a plain <hi>wrong to the Eſtates of other Men,</hi> he is then moſt Evidently called of GOD into a <hi>Low and Mean Condition.</hi> Man, The Glorious GOD, <hi>whoſe thou art, and whoſe are all thy wayes,</hi> now Stakes thee down to a <hi>Low and Mean Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi> Thy <hi>Straits</hi> are what the Glorious GOD has ordered for thee. It ſhould be a Principle with a Good Man, <hi>I may not have, what I cannot have.</hi> And in Purſuance of this Principle he ſhould go on; <hi>I cannot have what it will be a wrong unto other People for me to have.</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="unknown:001823_0015_0FB83E02257D03F0"/>The ſhort of it is; <hi>If there be any thing that I cannot have without forcing and keeping my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour out of his Right for it, the Great GOD Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders me to go without it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well; but what ſhall we then do, if a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ſuch <hi>Creepling Circumſtances</hi> be ordered for us?</p>
               <p>The Anſwer is, <hi>Lower your Sails.</hi> For there is another Poſition, of which I am ſure no Good Man will make any Queſtion. If GOD conſine a Man unto <hi>a Low and Mean Condition,</hi> the Man ſhould Labour for a ſweet <hi>Contentment</hi> with his <hi>Low and Mean Condition. Confinement</hi> and <hi>Contentment</hi> muſt go together. <hi>You have not forgotten the Exhortation that ſpeaketh unto you, Be Content with ſuch Things as you have.</hi> Let a Man get a <hi>Spirit</hi> ſuited unto his <hi>Condition.</hi> It is the Firſt mark of Bleſſedneſs; Mat. V. 3. <hi>Bleſſed are the Poor in Spirit.</hi> Who are the <hi>Poor in Spirit?</hi> They that have a <hi>Spirit</hi> willing to be <hi>Peor</hi> if God call them to it. It is injoined upon you; Jam. I. 10. <hi>Let the rich rejoyce in that he is made low.</hi> How ſhall he <hi>Rejoyce in being made Low?</hi> Let him cheerfully entertain the Opportunities which his being <hi>made Low,</hi> and falling into Decay, gives him to expreſs his Patience, his Humility, his Reſignation, and Glorify God. A <hi>Low and a Mean Condition</hi> is perhaps, the <hi>Croſs</hi> which our Saviour has
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:001823_0016_0FB83E02F7AE2E50"/>aſſigned unto us; <hi>The Thing appointed for us.</hi> It becomes us now to be <hi>Crucify'd unto the Would:</hi> A Man upon a <hi>Croſs</hi> troubles not himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Wealth</hi> of this World. Remember, Sirs, It won't be long that you are to languiſh in this <hi>Low and Mean Condition.</hi> The Prophet ſaid, Ezek. VII. 12. <hi>The Day draweth near, let not the ſeller mourn.</hi> Since the <hi>Day draweth near,</hi> that you are to be Stript of all, don't lay it much to Heart, tho' you muſt <hi>Sell</hi> all you have, and Strip your ſelves of every thing, rather than ly in <hi>Debt</hi> for what you have.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="maxim">
               <head>The Third MAXIM.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Man to run into Debt, when he has no Proſpect, and perhaps no Purpoſe of ever getting out; This is a Diſhoneſty by no means to be Countenanced.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are thoſe who puſh themſelves into <hi>Debt,</hi> when they know, 'tis utterly <hi>Improbable,</hi> they ſhall ever <hi>Pay</hi> what they <hi>Owe.</hi> Yea, with a <hi>Probability,</hi> there is alſo an <hi>Intention</hi> in them, never to Pay. In the mean time, how are the <hi>Creditors</hi> impos'd upon! O <hi>Diſhoneſt People,</hi> 'Tis one ſort of <hi>Stealing,</hi> and a very groſs one too, which is to be charged upon you. 'Tis as bad at Picking the Pockets of your <hi>Creditors!</hi> In this Tribe are to be ranked the <hi>Shameleſs Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers;</hi> I ſay, <hi>Shameleſs Borrowers;</hi> The <hi>Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers</hi> whom the <hi>Thirty Seventh</hi> Pſalm and the Twenty firſt Verſe, hath Stigmatized. A Sort
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:001823_0017_0FB83E047060DF58"/>of Bold People, who carry on a down-right <hi>Beggary</hi> under the more Specious Form of <hi>Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing;</hi> —People, from whom you Save no leſs than <hi>Four Pounds</hi> in <hi>Five,</hi> by not <hi>Lending</hi> but <hi>Giving</hi> of <hi>One</hi> unto them, when they would have borrowed <hi>Five.</hi> What ſayes the Word of God? Prov. XIX. 22. <hi>A Poor man is better than a Lyar.</hi> It were better to be <hi>Poor,</hi> and Conflict with a very Straitning <hi>Poverty,</hi> than to run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Debt,</hi> with ſuch <hi>Lies,</hi> as they who <hi>Promiſe</hi> to <hi>Pay</hi> at ſuch a Time, and <hi>Pay</hi> at ſuch a Time, and have no Faith in all their Promiſes; There is no Believing a Word they ſay!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="maxim">
               <head>The Fourth MAXIM.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Men ought often and nicely to Examine the State of their Buſineſs, if they would not find themſelves irrecoverably Plunged into Debt, before they are aware, but it comes in unexpectedly like a Traveller upon them; and then holds him like an Armed Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a very Dangerous, and therefore a very <hi>Culpable</hi> Thing, for People to let their <hi>Buſineſs</hi> go on from Year to Year, in Muddy <hi>Uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> There are no wiſe People, but what will be fond of often ſeeing <hi>Where-abouts</hi> they are in their <hi>Buſineſs.</hi> It was directed; Prov. XXVII. 23. <hi>Be thou diligent to know the ſtate of thy Flocks, and look well to thy Herds; For Riches are not for ever.</hi> People ſhould uſe much <hi>Diligence,</hi> frequent En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, exact Inſpection, into the <hi>State</hi> of their
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:001823_0018_0FB83E099C182768"/>Affairs. For ſome <hi>Rich</hi> Men, have ſoon come to nothing by their <hi>Inadvertency.</hi> Dealers of the Beſt Faſhion among us, have uſed conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Once a Year,</hi> to Settle their <hi>Books of Accompts,</hi> and find their Account in doing ſo. And for want of it, there may be ſome of whom we may ſhortly ſay, as <hi>Paul</hi> to the Shipwreck'd Mariners; <hi>Ye ſhould have hearkened unto me, and not have gain'd the Harm &amp; Loſs, which you are like to ſuffer by your Negligence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, if upon the Scrutiny, Men find, That they <hi>Over-trade their Stock;</hi> and if they find, That they <hi>run behind hand;</hi> Or, in a word, if they find, that their <hi>Expences</hi> do exceed their <hi>Revenues;</hi> They ought <hi>Seaſonably,</hi> I ſay, <hi>Seaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably,</hi> to take all due Meaſures, and <hi>Early</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, put a Stop to the Torrent of <hi>Debt,</hi> which elſe like Waters at a Breach, is breaking in upon them.</p>
               <p>Upon this Head, I have One Thing more to ſay; which I ſuppoſe all that would lead <hi>Lives in all Godlineſs &amp; Honeſty,</hi> will Juſtify. I will not now diſcuſs the Queſtion, <hi>How far, or how ſoon a Debtor is bound in Conſcience to diſcover his Difficulties unto his Creditors?</hi> Yet it may be truly affirmed; That ſometimes People fail and break, who are guilty of Great Iniquity, in that they did it not <hi>ſome Years before.</hi> They ought <hi>ſome Years before</hi> to have ſeen, how Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:001823_0019_0FB83E0B5FC502C8"/>were going with them, and been much more <hi>Early</hi> in doing what ſhould have been done, that their <hi>Creditors</hi> might not have been ſuch heavy <hi>Sufferers.</hi> They have brought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into ill Terms with Heaven, by ſuch a <hi>Miſmanagement</hi> as is to be charged upon them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="maxim">
               <head>The Fifth MAXIM.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Man that is got into Debt, ought to get out of it, as faſt as be can, and as if it were for his Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Unto a Man that is fallen into the Toils of <hi>Debt,</hi> there is this Advice given; Prov. VI. 5. <hi>Deliver thy ſelf as a Roe from the hand of the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and as a Bird from the hand of the Fowler.</hi> What is a <hi>Debt,</hi> but a <hi>Load:</hi> An honeſt Man ſhould feel it as a <hi>Load,</hi> and groan under the <hi>Load;</hi> But not cry for, <hi>more Weight!</hi>—as the Miſerables that are <hi>Preſſing to Death</hi> uſe to do. He that is in <hi>Debt,</hi> ſhould be in <hi>Pain,</hi> to get out of it. Eſpecially, if the <hi>Time</hi> when the <hi>Payment</hi> becomes due, be arrived, it ſhould be like the <hi>Pain</hi> of a <hi>Broken Bone</hi> unto him. For indeed, it is a very true Aſſertion; <hi>Minus Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit qui minus tempore Solvit;</hi> A Man does not Pay the <hi>Sum,</hi> if he don't pay it in the <hi>Time</hi> that is agreed for. <hi>Debtor,</hi> Be thou ſo Solicitous in <hi>Complying with Time</hi> for every Payment; and be ſo Indefatigable in turning every Stone for the Satisfaction of thy <hi>Creditor,</hi> that he may have no manner of reaſon to Reproach thee, for
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:001823_0020_0FB83E0D59356A38"/>any <hi>Careleſsneſs,</hi> and <hi>Slothfulneſs,</hi> any Tendency to the leaſt <hi>Appearance of Evil</hi> in thee. And here occurs one thing to be more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly animadverted on. When a <hi>Poor Man</hi> has done any Work for a <hi>Rich Man,</hi> whom he has much dependance on, and he comes for his Dues; the <hi>Rich</hi> ought not now to <hi>anſwer him roughly,</hi> and put him off time after time, and make him Loſe, I know not how much Time, in giving Attendance on him. <hi>Detained Wages</hi> will anon make a Cry that will reach the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens. 'Tis Enjoined, Prov. III. 28. <hi>Say not unto thy Neighbour, go and come again, and to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row I will give, when thou haſt it by thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="maxim">
               <head>The Sixth MAXIM.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>If a Man be ſo far brought into Debt, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Inſolvent, there is a Behaviour agreable to <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Holy Religion, both by God and Men to be expected from him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let our <hi>Debtors</hi> pay ſome Regard unto the <hi>Admonition of God our Saviour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be thro' any <hi>Real Default of yours,</hi> that ſuch a <hi>Debt</hi> be come upon you. 'tis moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, you ought with a deep <hi>Repentance,</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe your ſelves before God, and the World. Your Acknowledgments unto your <hi>Creditors</hi> particularly, ought to have ſuch a ſenſible, and Ingenuous, and ſelf abuſing <hi>Repentance</hi> in them, that <hi>their</hi> Hearts towards you may be
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:001823_0021_0FB83E0E38663798"/>
                  <hi>mollified,</hi> by their ſeeing the <hi>Brokenneſs</hi> of <hi>yours.</hi> It is preſcribed unto one in <hi>Debt;</hi> Prov. VI. 3. <hi>Do tois now, my ſon: when thou art come into the hand of thy Friend, Go humble thy ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if it be the <hi>meer Hand of God</hi> that has by Impoveriſhing <hi>Loſſes</hi> brought this <hi>Debt</hi> upon you, ſtill there is very much <hi>Self-Abaſement</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for. 'Tis a <hi>Rebuke</hi> of God upon you, that has thus <hi>Emptied</hi> you, and <hi>Enfeebled</hi> you; And a very <hi>Humbling Rebuke</hi> it is. Under it, you ought to be ſo Humble, ſo Modeſt, ſo Penſive, and ſo Submiſſive, that your <hi>Creditors</hi> as well as other Spectators, inſtead of Upbraiding you and Inſulting you, ſhall but <hi>Sympathize</hi> with you in the Diſaſters that have befallen you. The Exhortation to ſuch as are thrown into <hi>Debt,</hi> is that; 1 Pet. V. 6. <hi>Humble your ſelves under the mighty Hand of God, that he may Exalt you in due time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Fine,</hi> Let the <hi>Debt</hi> come which way it will, your <hi>Creditors</hi> muſt be fairly dealt withal. An Inſolvency muſt not be complicated with any <hi>Under-hand Practices,</hi> any <hi>Fraudulent Practices,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Unjuſt <hi>Concealments,</hi> that ſhall <hi>withold more than is meet,</hi> from the Injured <hi>Creditors.</hi> There was a Poor Widow, very much in <hi>Debt;</hi> But ſhe was one who diſcovered a very <hi>Honeſt Mind</hi> that the <hi>Creditors</hi> might be ſatisfy'd. God ſtrangely enabled her to ſatisfy them; Yea,
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:001823_0022_0FB83E0FAF335408"/>but ſee how the Direction ran, 2 King. IV. 7. <hi>Go, and pay thy Debt, and live thou and thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the reſt.</hi> The Firſt Thing to be look'd after was, <hi>Go and pay thy Debt;</hi> And, Rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Providence of God for the reft. There have been ſome <hi>Debtors,</hi> who have taken ſuch <hi>Indirect Methods</hi> upon an Inſolvency, that a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Series of Diſappointments has after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards been Entail'd upon them; Nothing would ever after ſtick upon their Bread; The Doom from the Throne of God upon them, has been that; Jer. XXII. 30. <hi>Write you this Man, A Man that ſhall not proſper in his Days.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="maxim">
               <head>The Seventh MAXIM.</head>
               <p>A Wholeſome Antidote againſt the Miſchiefs of Debt, it would be for a Man to Conſider Seriouſly what he does, when he wrongs other Men by lying in Debt unto them.</p>
               <p>CONSIDERATION: O thou <hi>Preſervative</hi> of Mankind. A wake thou, Ariſe, Affect, and mightily go to Work, on the Occaſion that is now before us.</p>
               <p>Firſt, A <hi>Debtor,</hi> (one that is, or would be ſo) will do well to Conſider, how much he may be Condemned by that <hi>Royal Law; Let a Man do as be would be done unto.</hi> The Law that ſhines as a Star of the Firſt Magnitude, in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of our Saviour; Mat. VII. 12. <hi>All things whatſoever ye would, that men ſhould do to you, do
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:001823_0023_0FB83E1145964470"/>ye even ſo to them.</hi> A Law, which God has En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven as with a <hi>Pen of Iron, and the Point of a Diamond,</hi> on the Hearts of the Children of Men. A Law, than which none more <hi>Confeſſed,</hi> and yet none more <hi>Tranſgreſſed</hi> among the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Men. <hi>Debtor,</hi> Think with thy ſelf, <hi>Were I the Creditor, ſhould I like to be dealt withal as I now deal with my Creditor?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I now make a <hi>Motion</hi> that is full of <hi>Equity;</hi> And if this Our <hi>Motion</hi> may more generally take, my <hi>Sermon</hi> will have a very Deſirable &amp; Comfortable <hi>Harveſt,</hi> tho' all the reſt of it ſhould be but as the Rain falling upon a Rock. 'Tis this; When the <hi>Debtor</hi> puts off his <hi>Creditor</hi> from time to time, Let him think with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; <hi>Were I the Creditor, could I care or bear to be ſo deals withal?</hi> How many <hi>Shufflings,</hi> would ſuch a Thought as this in the Power of it, put an end unto?</p>
               <p>Again, A <hi>Debtor</hi> will do well to <hi>Conſider,</hi> what is the <hi>Eighth Commandment;</hi> What is implied in it; What is Required in it; And how far the <hi>Eighth Commandment</hi> will bear him out. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, To keep a Man out of his <hi>Right,</hi> when 'tis poſſible to help him to it; I may uſe thoſe Words upon it, Job XXXV. 2. <hi>Thinkeſt then this to be Right?</hi> The <hi>Eighth Commandment</hi> will never conſent unto it.</p>
               <p>This is the rather to be ſpoken, becauſe
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:001823_0024_0FB83E15323AB038"/>very many of the <hi>Debts</hi> in the World, are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Thefts,</hi> curſed <hi>Thefts.</hi> And the <hi>Flying Roll</hi> that is to <hi>Enter into the Houſe of the Thief,</hi> will find the way to thoſe that make nothing of them.</p>
               <p>Once more; The <hi>Miſcries</hi> which <hi>Debt</hi> is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied withal; ought not theſe alſo to be Conſidered? Oh! <hi>Cotiſider</hi> of it. Is it nothing, to be in ſuch continual <hi>Perplexities,</hi> that One muſt conclude a <hi>Pillow</hi> to have Some uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Stuffing in it, that ſo <hi>Perplexed</hi> a Man ſhould be able to <hi>Sleep</hi> upon it? Is it nothing, to be Deſpiſed of ones Neighbour, and be annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a blaſted Reputation? Is it nothing, to be expoſed unto the Rage, of Provoked <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors,</hi> &amp; feel many Effects of their Indignation? To be <hi>Dun'd</hi> with repeated Indignities; To be <hi>Vex'd</hi> with legal Proſecutions; At length to have that Story come in for the iffue of all; Marth. XVIII 28 <hi>The Creditor laid hands on him; &amp; tool him by the Throat, ſaying, Pay me what thou oweſt. And he caſt him into Priſon, till he ſhould pay the Debt.</hi> Oh! Miſerable Caſe! It is mention'd as the Lamentable caſe of <hi>Davids</hi> Followers; 1 Sam. XXII. 2. <hi>Every one that was in Diſtreſs, and every one that was in Debt.</hi> Verily, Tis <hi>Distreſs</hi> enough to be in <hi>Debt;</hi> Enough to Pall &amp; Spoil all the Delights of a Man that has any Ingennicy What? For him on every Turn to think, <hi>There we ſuch and ſuch Good Neighbours. that Suffer no
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:001823_0025_0FB83E1708E46DA0"/>little Damage from me!</hi> How much Regret in a Reflection on it!</p>
               <p>For indeed, There is this in it, worſe than all the reſt. Oftentimes a Man in <hi>Debt,</hi> muſt have the <hi>Guilt</hi> of much <hi>Wrong</hi> lying upon him. This <hi>Guilt</hi> will bring a Cloud upon the Soul, be <hi>Chains of Darkneſs</hi> upon it, and much interrupt Communion with God. Yea, the <hi>Guilt</hi> will arm the <hi>Conſcience</hi> with Scourges grievouſly to laſh the Soul that ſhall be under it. In Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity we find many Cuſtomes, of Severe Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments inflicted by <hi>Creditors</hi> on their <hi>Debtors</hi> when in a courſe of Law, they had them delivered up unto them. <hi>A. Gellius</hi> among others makes a mention of them. What the Roman Laws of the XII <hi>Tables</hi> allow'd, for the <hi>Creditors</hi> to tear the <hi>Debtors</hi> Limb from Limb without a Metaphor, was hard enough. But for the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> of a <hi>Debtor</hi> to take him in hand, and with angry Strokes to tell him, <hi>You have wronged ſuch &amp; ſuch Neighbours; they feel themſelves the worſe for you every day that comes over their heads; and what Reſtitution can you make unto them!</hi> Verily, This will be worſe than any of the ancient <hi>Puniſhments,</hi> that <hi>Bankrupts</hi> had aſſigned for them. I ſay, Again &amp; again, <hi>Conſider</hi> of it!</p>
               <p>And now, having built a <hi>Watch-Tower</hi> upon <hi>Seven</hi> MAXIMS, as upon ſo many Unſhaken <hi>Pillars,</hi> from whence you have diſpenſed unto
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:001823_0026_0FB83E18B62FB828"/>you thoſe <hi>Warnings,</hi> which may prevent the <hi>Debts,</hi> wherein too many <hi>detain</hi> the Poſſeſſions of their Neighbours, without the <hi>Conſent,</hi> &amp; unto the <hi>Damage,</hi> of the Rightful Owners; I think, I have Purchaſed the Liberty to addreſs the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors</hi> a little in Favour of their <hi>Debtors,</hi> and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat that as much <hi>Favour</hi> as can be, may be ſhown unto them. Sir, It may be your Poor <hi>Debtors,</hi> come to you after that manner; Matth. XVIII 29 <hi>He fell down at his Feet, &amp; beſought him, ſaying, Have Patience with me, &amp; I will pay thee all.</hi> Now, if theſe <hi>Debtors</hi> give you any Indications of an <hi>Honeſt Mind,</hi> I alſo Pray you, to have as much <hi>Patience</hi> with them as you can. I have not a word to ſay, againſt <hi>Compelling</hi> of People to be <hi>Honeſt.</hi> But if you ſee, they would fain be <hi>Honeſt,</hi> &amp; Struggle &amp; Wreſtle for it, and have any Merit in them, then, I ſay, uſe them with all the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> &amp; <hi>Mercy</hi> of a Brother; Let them find all <hi>Brotherly Kindneſs</hi> from you. You have them in <hi>Debt</hi> unto you, for ſo much <hi>Money;</hi> Bring them into a further <hi>Debt,</hi> for ſo much <hi>Kind Uſage</hi> of them; Tho' on this head, Let them ſtand charged for nothing, but, <hi>Love to a Benefactor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It pleaſes me very much to find this preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in a famous <hi>Lexicon Juridicum;</hi> 
                  <q>That before a <hi>Debtor</hi> be Sued, <hi>Adeundus eſt, et civiliter inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſſandus, ſemel at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> iterum,</hi> He ſhould be civilly Addieſſed once again, by the <hi>Creditor,</hi> &amp; then
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:001823_0027_0FB83E1A493EC688"/>by ſome of his Friends, and be Admoniſh'd of the Damage that he will bring upon himſelf, and eſpecially the Wounds upon his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> if he don't fairly pay what he owes. [Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to, Matth. XVIII. 15, 16.]</q> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> the Lawyer, obſerves, That this way of Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing a <hi>Debtor,</hi> before the Arreſting of him, <hi>Certum crit, quod ex jure Divino et Humano omnibus modis ſit Obſervanda.</hi> And that there are Places, in which a <hi>Plantiff</hi> cannot have his Cauſe heard, if he can't prove that he has uſed the <hi>Urbanity,</hi> of theſe Preliminary <hi>Admonitions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doubtleſs you Obſerve, That the Precept, <hi>Owe no Man any thing,</hi> has a Twin-Brother born with it; <hi>But to Love one another.</hi> Of this <hi>Debt,</hi> the <hi>Debt</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> which we muſt always <hi>Pay,</hi> and yet alwayes <hi>Owe,</hi> to one another, I cannot but make this Obſervation. This <hi>Debt</hi> well follow'd, would regulate the other wonderfully! If this MAXIM, <hi>To Love our Neighbours as our ſelves,</hi> were cloſely kept to, Things would be carried on between <hi>Creditors</hi> and their <hi>Debtors,</hi> with a moſt wondrous eaſineſs.</p>
               <p>Did Men <hi>Love one another,</hi> they would be loth to be <hi>Debtors,</hi> be <hi>ſlow to Owe, and ſwift to Pay;</hi> They would have a mighty Horror of <hi>Owing</hi> more than they can make <hi>Payment</hi> of; They would reſolve, <hi>I will undergo any thing, rather than damnify my Neighbour, that lives peaceably &amp; ſecurely by me, &amp; is ready to let me have, what I aſk him for,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="unknown:001823_0028_0FB83E1C1BCD5710"/>
Did Men <hi>Love one anotber,</hi> they would not ſeck to make others become their <hi>Servants,</hi> which you know, <hi>Debtors</hi> are. And where they are ſo, they would not be <hi>Cruel</hi> in <hi>Exactions</hi> and <hi>Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> upon them. No; They would ſometimes <hi>Remit</hi> unto the extremely Neceſſitous, what they might have Exacted &amp; Extorted from them.</p>
               <p>I will particularly ſay, Tho' <hi>Uſury</hi> be Lawful in a Country where Lands may be <hi>Mortgaged</hi> and forever <hi>Alienated;</hi> as they might not in the Land of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> yet there are ſome Hard Uſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in the <hi>Uſury,</hi> between the <hi>Creditor</hi> and the <hi>Debtor</hi> among our ſelves, which the Law of <hi>Love</hi> will never juſtify.</p>
               <p>And now, the Minds of People throughout the Country, are greatly engaged in <hi>Projections,</hi> how we ſhall become furniſhed with ſuch a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> of <hi>Trade,</hi> as may prevent an undue Growth of <hi>Debt</hi> among us, I will take the Opportunity to ſay; My Brethren, I be ſeech you, Let not this <hi>Debt</hi> be forgotten, <hi>To Love one another.</hi> There is a <hi>Variety</hi> of Apprehenſions upon the matter. This Variety, begins to grow into too much <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimony.</hi> But, <hi>My Brethren Theſe Things ought not ſo to be.</hi> Your Miniſters are too Wife, I hope, to offer you any of their Sentiments upon your Various <hi>Projections.</hi> And they do not count themſelves Wiſe enough, to pronounce any <hi>Judgment</hi> upon that Spirit of <hi>Over-trading</hi> and <hi>Over-doing</hi> that ſome ſuppoſe very much to
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:001823_0029_0FB83E1D37E63DE0"/>threaten us. Or Wiſe enough to propoſe what <hi>Retrenchments</hi> may be moſt Expedient for us. But we will all make you an ofter, of what our <hi>Bible</hi> has in it, relating to your Conduct. There we find it ſaid; Jam. IV. 11 <hi>Speak not Evil One of another, Brethren.</hi> There we find it ſaid; Eph. IV. 31. <hi>Let all Bitterneſs, &amp; Wrath, &amp; Anger, and Clamour, &amp; Evil-ſpeaking be put away from among you.</hi> Sirs, you have a Great Eſteem for One another; and they are very worthy Men, who now thwart One another in their Apprehenſions. But, Oh! Don't grow <hi>Strange</hi> to One another. If once your Spirits be at all <hi>Exaſperated,</hi> the Malady againſt which we would all provide, will but come under an <hi>Exaſperation. Animoſities</hi> will make all good <hi>Projections</hi> Impracticable; our Caſe Deplorable &amp; Incurable. <hi>Conſider what I ſay, &amp; the Lord give you underſtanding in all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I ſhall go off in <hi>Debt,</hi> if I leave another Thing Unmentioned. I may not leave off, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til I have done my Beſt, that <hi>every Soul</hi> in the Aſſembly may have a <hi>Portion</hi> to carry home. It may be ſome of the Hearers will count them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Unconcerned,</hi> [tho', <hi>I know not why they ſhould</hi>] in what has been hitherto inſiſted on. But I am ſure, I have now ſomething to ſay, that <hi>every Soul</hi> in the Aſſembly has Infinite Cauſe to give Attention to. The Diſtinction of a, <hi>Debitor ex contractu;</hi> &amp; a, <hi>Debitor ex delicto,</hi> is to be thought upon; A <hi>Debt</hi> of <hi>Contract,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Debt</hi> of <hi>Treſpaſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="unknown:001823_0030_0FB83E1EB674F6B8"/>
'Tis a Thing that calls for the moſt awful, Conſideration of <hi>Every Soul</hi> among us; That our <hi>Sins</hi> have brought us into <hi>Debt</hi> unto the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the Infinte GOD. There is a <hi>Debt</hi> of <hi>Sufferings,</hi> which we owe to the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite GOD. The <hi>Fenalty</hi> of the <hi>Divine Law,</hi> to which our Sins have made us obnoxious, muſt be Executed. The Honour of the <hi>Holy One,</hi> whom we have Denied &amp; Blaſphemed by our Sins, muſt be Vindicated. For the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this <hi>Debt,</hi> there are <hi>Sufferings</hi> to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, which are, Oh! how Exceedingly to be trembled at! Our <hi>Sins</hi> are called, our <hi>Debts,</hi> becauſe they render us fearfully <hi>Indebted</hi> unto the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of God. Sinner, Thou haſt a <hi>Debt</hi> lying upon thee, which were ponderous enough to break the Backs of all the Angels in Heaven. <hi>Ten Thouſand Talents</hi> are but a ſmall Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the <hi>Debt</hi> which is oppreſſing of thee; the <hi>Debt,</hi> which may make thee cry out, <hi>Lord, I am oppreſſed, undertake for me!</hi> Ten Thouſand <hi>Mountains</hi> were leſs than the light Duſt of the Balance, compared unto it. <hi>Thouſands of Rams, Ten Thouſands of Rivers of Oyl;</hi> a Sacrificed Off-ſpring; a Sacrifice of Myriads of Angels; the whole World made a Sacriſice; all Creatures turn'd into a <hi>Burnt-Offering,</hi> would not make a full Payment of the <hi>Debt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, Oh! What an aſtoniſhing thing has been done for us on this tremendous Occaſion! The Eternal
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:001823_0031_0FB83E20F62A3DD0"/>Son of God has aſſumed our <hi>Nature;</hi> and therein He has become our <hi>Surety.</hi> On a Compact with His Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Father agreeing unto it, He has taken our <hi>Debt</hi> upon Him. He ſaid, <hi>Lo, I come to anſwer the Debt.</hi> He has done ſo, in the <hi>Expiatory Sufferings,</hi> wherein He became <hi>Obedient unto Death, even unto the Death of the Croſs:</hi> And He received an <hi>Acquittance,</hi> as having done it, at His <hi>Roſurrection from the Dead.</hi> Oh! wonderful! Oh! wonderful! Our Saviour now invites us, to come, &amp; plead the <hi>Payment</hi> which He has made, that we may be Releaſed from our <hi>Debt,</hi> and <hi>lay hold on Enternal Life.</hi> Oh! Let us now with a lively Faith, make that Prayer to our Saviour, Pſal CXIX. 122. <hi>Be Surety for thy Servant for Good.</hi> Plead it with the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious GOD, <hi>Lord, my Saviour has anſwered the Demands of thy Law in my Room. Oh! Bring my Soul out of Priſon, that I may praiſe thy Name, &amp; Oh! deal bountifully with me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then, what a <hi>Debt</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> to Him, who has thus paid our <hi>Debt,</hi> ſhall we have lying for ever upon us! We muſt own that <hi>Debt</hi> for ever, and the <hi>Love</hi> of our Saviour, in thus <hi>Ranſoming</hi> our Souls, it muſt <hi>Conſtrain</hi> us to love Him, &amp; prize Him, &amp; ſeek Him, &amp; ſerve Him, and be ſwallowed up in all poſſible Endeavours to Glorify Him. O ye <hi>Ranſomed of the Lord;</hi> what will you do now for Him, who has diſcharged a <hi>Debt</hi> for you; wherein if He had not appeared for you, you muſt have been caſt into an horrible, and an infernal <hi>Priſon,</hi> from whence you could not have come out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til you had <hi>Paid the uttermoſt Farthing:</hi> — But that,— What Ages muſt it have called for? — What will you do, but moſt heartily declare unto him; <hi>Truly, O Lord, I am thy Servant, I am thy Servant, ſince thou haſt looſed my Ponds; Oh! may I be entirely Thine forever more!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let this be the <hi>Concluſion of the Matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
