<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A familiar guide to the right and profitable receiving of the Lord's Supper. Wherein also the way and method of our salvation is briefly and plainly declar'd. / By Theophilus Dorrington.</title>
            <author>Dorrington, Theophilus, d. 1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 120 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04">2009-04.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N01646</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N01646</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 1954</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW7115</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">1954</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99013269</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 1954.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N01646)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 1954)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 1954)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A familiar guide to the right and profitable receiving of the Lord's Supper. Wherein also the way and method of our salvation is briefly and plainly declar'd. / By Theophilus Dorrington.</title>
                  <author>Dorrington, Theophilus, d. 1715.</author>
                  <author>Anne, Queen of Great Britain, 1665-1714, dedicatee.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The seventh edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[6], 114 p. ;  14 cm. (12mo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed by J. Franklin, for Eleazer Phillips at Charlstown [sic], and sold at his shop.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1718.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedicated to Queen Anne.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper.</term>
               <term>Salvation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:001954_0000_0FBA42A89C929728"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:001954_0001_0FBA42AA2244DF78"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FAMILIAR GUIDE TO THE Right and Profitable Receiving OF THE LORD's SUPPER. Wherein alſo The Way and Method of our SALVATION is briefly and plainly Declar'd.</p>
            <p>By THEOPHILUS DORRINGTON.</p>
            <p>The Seventh Edition.</p>
            <p>BOSTON: Re-Printed by J. FRANKLIN, for ELEAZER PHILLIPS at <hi>Charl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stown,</hi> and Sold at his Shop. 1718.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="unknown:001954_0002_0FBA42ABB8BD44C0"/>
            <head>TO THE QUEEN's MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it Pleaſe Your <hi>MAJESTY</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O permit me, most thankfully to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, that it is Your MAJESTY's very gracious Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of another Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, to revive the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay'd PIETY and VERTUE of the Age; which as it animates me to proceed in that, and has almost brought it to Perfection, ſo it was the great Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of this. In which I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd
<pb facs="unknown:001954_0003_0FBA42AD19C66B50"/>
to perſuade and direct to the right uſe of this bleſſed SACRAMENT; which is perhaps the best and most effectual M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eft in his Church, to promote and maintain in it the Love of GOD and of our Neighbour. And may it pleaſe Your SACRED MAJESTY to give leave, that I may encourage myſelf from the Favour mention'd, to implore and hope for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Your MAJESTY's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage to this ſmall Piece alſo. I am, and deſire to be as long as I live,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſty's moſt Obedient and Dutiful Subject, <hi>Dorrington.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="unknown:001954_0004_0FBA42AE91E004F0"/>
            <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have in this little Book diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinctly stated and repreſented that ſolemn Covenant with Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, which we all of us enter into at our Baptiſm. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſince the receiving of the <hi>LORD's SUPPER</hi> is deſign'd for a Reward and Confirmation of that Covenant, the distinct Knowlege of that is neceſſary to our Fitneſs for this Sacrament; and I have fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſpers'd through the whole, many weighty Arguments to induce Men to keep cloſe to that Covenant; it being to us the only way to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that ſo I might at once promote in many a Religious and good Life, a fitneſs for this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the attainment of their everlasting Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="unknown:001954_0005_0FBA42B0614E3EC0"/>And having made this the Subject and Scope of this Book, I think it way not be amiſs to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest, that it is very fit to be recommended and preſented by thoſe who have taken upon them the charitable Office of being God-fathers, or God mothers to ſuch as they have preſented to God at the Font. It is the certain Duty of theſe ſpiritual Parents, and the Charge laid upon them by the Church, to concern themſelves afterwards, and take all the Care they can, that the Child may be taught, as ſoon as it is able to learn, what a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Vow, Promiſe and Profeſſion, it has made by them. This Duty and Charge they would hereby in ſome meaſure perform; eſpecially if they would alſo concern themſelves after a time to know what uſe their ſpiritual Children have made of it. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, if the Duties and Charge of this most uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſpiritual Relation were conſcientiouſly mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in this and the like ways perform'd; we ſhould not ſee ſo much deplorable Wiekedneſs among Profeſſors of Christianity as there is, and we might reaſonably hope to ſee the next Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration at furthest, deliver'd from the Vices and Madneſs of this.</p>
            <p>And ſince this Covenant is implied in Baptiſm, when it is not expreſs'd in our way; this Book will be uſeful to read in all Families, in order to train up young People in the knowledge of their Ingagements to God, and in the way of their Salvation, and to a fitneſs for this bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they may be confirm'd in that way. To adapt it the better to ſuch an uſe, I have added in the end a Prayer, which is proper to be uſed after the reading of any part of the Book in the Family or Cloſet.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="unknown:001954_0006_0FBA42B207984278"/>
            <head>A FAMILIAR GUIDE TO THE Right and Profitable Receiving OF THE LORD's SUPPER.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. I.</hi> The <hi>INTRODUCTION.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <hi>Christian</hi> READER,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOU haſt here repreſented to thee in a little room, I think, all that is neceſſary to render thee a meet and profitable Receiver of the holy and comfortable Sacrament of the Body and Blood of JESUS CHRIST our Lord. And I ſuppoſe it is in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner repreſented, as is moſt fit and likely, with the Bleſſing of God to poſſeſs thee with all
<pb n="2" facs="unknown:001954_0007_0FBA42B8288CFB40"/>
the Qualifications requiſite to him that comes to this Sacrament, if thou wilt afford this little Book a ſerious and frequent peruſal. If thou haſt been ſo unhappy, and ſo much miſtaken in thy true intereſt as never to have laid theſe things to heart before, and to have liv'd in the neglect of this bleſſed Ordinance; I would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, I would entreat thee often to read and ſtudy theſe things, till thou art familiarly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, and deeply affected with them; that thou mayeſt to thy advantage come well prepared to this Sacrament. If the things here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained have already affected thy Heart, and had a good Influence on thy Life, and thou art a frequent Attendant on this Sacrament, it may ſuffice to read this Book as often as thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt on the Week before thou comeſt to it, as a good Week's Preparation for it. And for thoſe who communicate every Lord's Day (as I wiſh all Chriſtians did) it may ſuffice, commonly, to retire ſome time on the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or get up the ſooner on the Sacrament-day, and ſeriouſly meditate on the Exerciſes herein propos'd, which are deſignd' to excite him that has an habitual fitneſs for this Sacrament into an actual one, &amp; are uſeful for that purpoſe. I ſay commonly this may be enough for ſuch; but yet even they alſo may find it neceſſary and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſometimes, when leiſure allows, to read the whole.</p>
               <p>Becauſe what is requiſite to render a Man a meer Receiver of this Sacrament is alſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and is ſufficient to conſtitute a good Chriſtian, and to bring him to Heaven: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:001954_0008_0FBA42B9DDDC3210"/>
I have ſaid in the Title, that the whole Method and Way of our Salvation is herein plainly declar'd. So that if any Soul be Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous about that grand and moſt important QUESTION, <hi>What must I do to be ſaved?</hi> he may find it herein reſolv'd. And whether this holy Sacrament may be accounted and uſed as a means of Converſion to a good Life or not; yet I hope, that by the Bleſſing of God, this little Book may be ſuch a Means to many, if Men will but think it worth their while to do ſo much to their own Everlaſting Happineſs, as to read and conſider ſo ſmall a Treatiſe.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The <hi>PRAYER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MAY the God of all Grace, Lover of Souls, to whom the Redemption and Salvation of Mankind is ſo very dear; and who invites us to this Sacrament is the way to Heaven, and that he may herein give us the happy foretasts of it: Bleſs this my weak Endeavour, and give it a Succeſs according to the greatneſs of his Power and Love; to the promoting in many Hearts the Love of this Sacrament, and their frequent and comfortable Attendance upon it; and to the bringing many Souls to Happineſs and Glory, for the ſake of <hi>JESUS CHRIST</hi> our Mediator and Advocate, <hi>AMEN.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> The Creation of <hi>MAN.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHEN it is ſaid in the firſt Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that <hi>God ſaw every thing that he, had made, and behold it was very good:</hi> This means, that the Creator, upon the review of
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:001954_0009_0FBA42BB4E1E7C98"/>
his Works, was pleaſed and delighted herein; and that he hated nothing that he had made: For, what we hate, we wiſh that it were not, eſpecially not ſuch as it is. If therefore the Creator had hated any thing that he had made, he had made it to be ſuch as he would not have it to be; which is not to be ſuppoſed of Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom and Goodneſs, and of ſuch Power as is able to make every thing what he pleaſes it ſhall be. Mankind therefore, among the other Works of God, were made very good, and were pleaſing to our Maker. Indeed he made Man a very Noble and Excellent ſort of Creature, ſuch as muſt be peculiarly pleaſing to Himſelf, above all things in this lower World: As we may judge, by thoſe words in Gen. 1.27. <hi>God created Man in his own Image.</hi> This was the peculiar Glory of Man, and that which chiefly advanced him above the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures about him. And it did principally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in theſe things following: That as he had Faculties capable of knowing, loving, and obeying God, he was diſpoſed to do ſo; He knew God to be the moſt Excellent Being, and did accordingly reverence and eſteem him: He knew him to be the Fountain of Good, and his chief Good, and did accordingly fix the choice of his Will upon him; and valued his Favour and Love, by which he enjoy'd God as his greateſt and only felicity. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e was then no Error or falſe reaſoning in his Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, no perverſe Choice in his Will, no Innordinacy in any of his Appetites, no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in them contrary to his Reaſon. In No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:001954_0010_0FBA42BCD76ACFE0"/>
was Man inclin'd to contradict his Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to God, or any of the Eternal Laws of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs. Upon this Account it was that Man was very good, and belov'd of his Maker. And being ſo belov'd. he liv'd in perfect Peace and Happineſs: He was not encumbred with any Evil; he wanted nothing that he had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for. It appears his kind Creator would not ceaſe doing for him, till he had provided for all his Neceſſities and Deſires; that ſo he might be compleatly happy. Man then enjoy'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the willing and ready Service of all Creatures about him. He enjoy'd himſelf, and could with pleaſure conſider and praiſe God for the Noble and Excellent Nature which God had given him: He had an eaſy and quiet Mind, had no conflicts with himſelf, had no occaſion to rebuke or fall out with himſelf. He énjoy'd then his God too, being aſſur'd of his Favour, and receiving the conſtant communications of it. He could with great delight, contemplate and praiſe the glorious Attributes of God; and the Divine Wiſdom, Power, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Goodneſs and Truth, were very plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant to him, while he was aſſur'd that all theſe were friendly, and would be favourable to him. This was Man's firſt Condition; a very excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and happy one: But alas! through his own default it did not laſt long.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> The firſt <hi>COVENANT</hi> between <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>MAN.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is very probable, that all the particular Dealings of God with Man in this Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:001954_0011_0FBA42BE50D7EB90"/>
are not told us in that ſhort account which <hi>Moſes</hi> gives us of the beginnings of the World. It being enough for us to know in general, what is the Spring and Source of all that Sin and Miſery which is now found among Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; the knowledge of which is of ſome Uſe and importance towards our getting free from both. But what is told us of the Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons between God and Man in that State, we may think we ſhall moſt truly underſtand, and moſt rightly interpret, if we guide our ſelves herein by the Tenour of his dealing with Mankind ſince that. From what is told us then of that Time, and from what appears ſince, we may learn, That it pleaſed the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor when he had made Man, and had ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oblig'd him, to take upon him the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Governour to his Creature, as he had the undoubted right of one; and he very juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thought fit to exerciſe a Dominion over him for his good. It was therefore, we may ſuppoſe, promiſed to Man, that he ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Favour of his Maker, and a perfect Happineſs both of Body and Soul, upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that he would continue in the due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and love of his Maker, and obey his Commands. And it was made known to him, that he ſhould fall from the beſt of his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, from that wherein he was ſo pleaſing to his Maker; and from all his Happineſs, if he did not continue ſtedfaſt in his Duty, and perfectly perform it, as God had enabled him to do. And this is that which is commonly called, <hi>The First</hi> COVENANT.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="unknown:001954_0012_0FBA42BFDFFBB2C8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> The <hi>SACRAMENTS</hi> of That.</head>
               <p>MOREOVER, God having made Man to conſiſt of a Body and Soul, and knowing that it is natural to him, for the Objects of his Senſes to make great Impreſſions, and to have a mighty Influence upon his Mind: His Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Goodneſs order'd Matters ſo, as that his Senſes might help to admoniſh him of his Duty, and to aſſure him of his Happineſs in the performance of it. And this we may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was the reaſon and Ground of God's ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating two Trees in the Garden where he had placed our firſt Parents, for a peculiar and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>common Uſe: The one call'd, <hi>The Tree of Knowlege of Good and Evil</hi>; the other call'd, <hi>The Tree of Life.</hi> Theſe we may reckon to have been the Sacraments of the firſt Covenant: For in theſe were Spiritual things by God's appointment repreſented by outward and viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Signs and Actions: Man was aſſiſted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his Duty and Obligations to his Maker by that Tree, call'd, <hi>The Tree of Knowledge of good and Evil</hi>: For we may ſuppoſe that the Fruit of this Tree was ſet apart by God whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the following purpoſe: Man was to take care to cultivate this Tree as well as others; but he was to offer the Fruit of it at ſet times ſolemnly and religiouſly to God, as a viſible ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment that he own'd him the Maker of all things, and the ſupreme Lord, and the Proprietor of all. This was reſerved, as we
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:001954_0013_0FBA42C199DF36F8"/>
may ſay, by God, to be a devoted thing, and Man's Thank-offering to him for all the reſt of his Gifts. And for this reaſon Man was forbid to eat of it himſelf. For we find in later Times, it was always held a very heinous and guilty thing for Men to ear of, or uſe what God had ſeparated and reſerved to himſelf. Now for ſuch a ſenſible outward performance, as the ſolemn offering of this Fruit to God, and the looking upon it, and uſing it only as a Devoted thing, was an excellent and fit means to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Mankind for ever to acknowlege their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator and Preſerver as the ſupream Lord and Proprietor of all things; as it was a ſenſible Declaration that they did make this acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, ſo it was a ſenſible Obligation of themſelves that they would continue to do ſo; and the more a help to them to continue it, &amp; to anſwer all the Obligations which naturally reſult from it in the Courſe of their Lives.</p>
               <p>And then the other Tree was appointed to aſſure Man, upon his perfect Obedience, of his Immortality and everlaſting Happineſs. So that whilſt he continued ſtedfaſt in his Duty, he had right to take and eat the fruit of this Tree: And he might take it as God's viſible and ſenſible pledge, and as an Inſtrument of Conveyance of Eternal Life and Happineſs to him, in like manner, as now we have leave from God to look upon the Rain-bow, not only as the natural effect of the Sun ſhining up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a falling Shower, but, as God's viſible pledge and aſſurance to Mankind, that he will never again deſtroy the World with a Deluge of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="9" facs="unknown:001954_0014_0FBA42C45F1AA580"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. V.</hi> Of the Sin and Fall of <hi>MAN.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THIS Account ſhews the exceeding great Guilt and Wickedneſs of the Sin of our firſt parents. Their Sin was, that they did cat of the forbidden Fruit; and ſo they uſed and took to themſelves what was reſerved and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to God: It was the bringing to a common uſe, that which was ſeparated by his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to a religious one, and was the profaning of a hallow'd or holy thing. But let it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd a little how monſtrous and vile this Sin of our firſt Parents was! How ſoon had they forgotten the mighty obligations which the Creator had ſo lately laid upon them! How bountiful had he been unto them! And he witheld and reſerv'd but one Fruit to himſeif; &amp; this, we may ſay, they grudg'd &amp; envy'd him: They would not be content with ſo vaſt a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion as he had made for them, but would needs have this afforded too. The poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending Creature, that deriv'd his Being, and all he had, would needs be ſole proprietor and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Lord of all things on the Earth, &amp; would acknowledge no Superiour! They had no need of this Fruit, were perfectly happy without it; &amp; might have contined ſo happy, if they would have abſtained from this; but they moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonably deſpiſed their Happineſs, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded the loſing it for the ſake of the Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and Advantage which they expected from this ſingle Fruit. The Creator indeed
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:001954_0015_0FBA42C617E733A0"/>
had been ſo good to them, they would not be lieve he would ſo ſeverely puniſh their eating this Fruit as he had threatned to do; and ſo that which ſhould have oblig'd them to be ſtedfaſt in their Duty, was moſt perverſly turn'd into an encouragement to Sin. O vile and ſhameful Wickedneſs! Let us conſider from what a vile original we all ſpring, and be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and aſhamed.</p>
               <p>In yielding to this foul act, they loſt that Holineſs and Righteouſneſs which they had been endow'd with, and by which eſpecially they had been pleaſing to their Maker.</p>
               <p>In this alſo they broke the Condition of the firſt Covenant, which required that they ſhould conſtantly reverence and love their Creator, and obey him in all things. And the ſad Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of this was, That they hereby loſt the Favour of God, and forfeited all their own Happineſs. They loſt all right to the good things of this World; to the Obedience and Servicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of the Creatures which God had made for them. They became liable to the penalty which God had threatned to inflict, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately upon the Tranſgreſſion did deſerve to have been put to Death, and to be thrown into the place of everlaſting puniſhment, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd for the Devil and his Angels.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> The <hi>NEW COVENANT.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND the utmoſt Severity of the Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning had been immediately executed in that manner upon them, we may believe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:001954_0016_0FBA42CBCC6249C0"/>
as it was ſaid, <hi>In the Day thou eatest thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely die</hi>: If the Son God had not become a Mediator on their behalf. And he freely undertook to do whatever might be neceſſary to tender it conſiſtent with the Honour of God to receive his rebellious Creatures into Favour again, to releaſe their obligation to everlaſting Puniſhment, and reſtore them to perfect Happineſs. What he then undertook to do to this purpoſe, we may learn and conclude from what he did in the fulneſs of time: And that was, That he would unite himſelf to the Humane Nature, and would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Man. In that nature he would perf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m a perfect obedience to God the Father, that he might merit for Mankind the Happineſs which was ſetled to be the reward of perfect Obedience. And to excuſe Man from the eternal Death which he had deſerved by his Sin, he undertook to ſuffer Death in his ſtead, and ſo to make his Death a Sacrifice for the Sin of Mankind. Thus much did he, very kindly and of his own accord, undertake to do for us; and he was accepted of the Father, and aſſur'd that he ſhould, by doing thus, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Favour for us which he deſir'd. So he procur'd for Man that he ſhould not be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly caſt off and thrown into endleſs Miſery; but have other Terms of Favour appointed him: And this diſpenſation or Appointment, is that which is called the NEW COVENANT: And it is called the New Covenant in his Blood, becauſe it was procur'd by his undertaking to ſhed his Blood in the Humane Nature as a
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:001954_0017_0FBA42CDDA083710"/>
Sacrifice for Sin. Upon this our firſt Parents were permitted to live, to enjoy, in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the good things of this world for a while, and had ſpace allow'd them to make their Peace with God, to recover his Favour, and their own Happineſs.</p>
               <p>We muſt know, that ſince it was a ſetled Law before the Fall of Man, that he ſhould propagate ſuch as himſelf; and his poſterity ſhould be reckon'd in the ſame ſtate and relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards God with their Father, who began them: Therefore when the firſt Parents o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mankind thus became polluted by their Sin, and were fallen into the ſtate of guilty Rebels againſt God; all their poſterity muſt needs come polluted into this world, as unclean things out of unclean, muſt be <hi>born Children of Wrath,</hi> as the Scripture ſpeaks. We therefore have the ſame Taſk upon us which our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents had; that is, to recover the Favour of God and our Everlaſting Happineſs, by perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now the Terms and Conditions of this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Covenant</p>
               <p>Let us ſee then, what are the Duties which it requires to be perform'd on our part: and what are the Promiſes of it on God's part; the Bleſſings which it offers to make us partakers of, upon the condition of performing thoſe Duties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VII.</hi> On our <hi>PART.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIRST let us take notice of our own part of this Covenant, and obſerve what it is that
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:001954_0018_0FBA42CFBAB60398"/>
God requires of us, to whom the Goſpel is preached, which we muſt do to be ſaved. And becauſe all mankind are now conſider'd by God as guilty and polluted Creatures; as having ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and being diſpoſed to do wickedly; there is firſt required of us, That we repent and turn from Sin. In the next place, becauſe we muſt return to God; it is required, That we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith: And laſtly, That we engage our ſelves, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keep God's Holy Will and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, &amp; walk in the ſame all the days of our life. But becauſe the Heart of Man is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and wicked, and we are ſo backward to do our Duty, that we are unwilling to know it; therefore it will be requiſite to mention ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what particularly, the Things contain'd under theſe three general heads.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The first</hi> main Branch of our Duty is, that we repent and turn from ſin: To which purpoſe we muſt ſtand at a defiance with all the cauſes of ſin, and reſolve they ſhall not govern us. Therefore has the Church been wont to expreſs this Branch of our Duty thus: We muſt renounce the Devil, and all his works; the Pomp and Vanities of this wicked World, with all the covetous Deſires of the ſame: And all the ſinful Deſires of the Fleſh, ſo as that we will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, nor be led by them.</p>
               <p>We muſt renounce the Devil and all his Works. It was by the Craft and Inſtigation of this Apoſtate Spirit, the Enemy of our Happineſs, that Mankind were at firſt drawn into Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:001954_0019_0FBA42D12FD0BCE8"/>
againſt God. We muſt reſolve therefore never to have any Correſpondence with him; to abhor and abſtain from all thoſe guilty ways of conſulting him, or ſeeking his Aſſiſtance, which the ungodly World have ever practiſed. We muſt never knowingly, or willingly, obey any of his Commands, nor comply with his Temptations. We muſt reſolve to fight againſt all thoſe Spiritual Wickedneſſes in our ſelves, which he infects the humane nature with, ſuch as Pride, Anger, Envy, Treachery, Lying, Malice, and Cruelty. Muſt abhor to imitate or follow him in the tempting of others to wickedneſs; or in the Hatred and Perſecution of good men for the ſake of their Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>We muſt alſo renounce the Pomp and Vanities of this wicked World, and all covetous Deſires of the ſame. That is, we muſt reſolve and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage that we will not let the love of the World rule in our Hearts, which is oppoſite to the Love of God. We will not let our Hearts fix on the Wealth, the Pleaſures, or the Dignities, and Honours here below: Nor will make the getting of them the Aim and Scope of our chief En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour and care; nor let the Enjoyment of them be our cheifeſt Delight and Satisfaction. That we will not be guided by the Cuſtoms of the World, nor follow a multitude to do evil: That our deareſt Relations, or our moſt neceſſary and moſt uſeful friends and Benefactors, ſhall not be able to influence us againſt the Will of God, and the Dictates of our Conſcience: That we will be ready to part with all that is dear, all is neceſſary to us, and which we might
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:001954_0020_0FBA42D298A07180"/>
otherwiſe lawfully keep and enjoy, when they ſtand in Competition with our Love and Duty to God. And we will ſubmit to any Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in the want even of neceſſary things, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to do any thing to gain them, which is contrary to the Laws of Divine Love.</p>
               <p>We muſt further renounce, mortifie, and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all ſinful Deſires of the Fleſh: All the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular &amp; diſobedint Inclinations of our corrupt Nature muſt be mortified and ſubdued. We muſt chace away thoſe fleſhly Luſts which war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Soul; the Love of ſlothful Eaſe, and Idleneſs, all Intemperance, and Laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. We muſt forſake and abſtain from all thoſe ſenſual Sins, which abuſe and prodigally waſte God's good Creatures; which enſlave the Thoughts and Faculties of the Soul to the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites of the Body; and which render the Soul unfit for the due Exerciſes and Operations of its Faculties; and which tend to clog and encum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er the Body with Diſeaſes. We muſt renounce all theſe three Sources of Evil, the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh, and muſt reſolve we will not follow nor be led by them. And this is the Firſt main Branch of our Duty under the New Covenant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Second</hi> is this: We muſt believe all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith. And this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uires of us to promiſe and perform the Things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ollowing: That we will ſeriouſly apply our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elves, as our leiſure and opportunity will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow us, to make the beſt improvement that we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an of the means of Divine Knowledge which the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rovidence of God affords us; that ſo we may
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:001954_0021_0FBA42D41F541C70"/>
gain as much of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſtimable Treaſure as we can: That we will not through Negligence or Hatred of the Truth be ignorant of any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant revealed Truth. That whatever does ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to us to be revealed from God concerning himſelf and our way to Happineſs, we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it as a certain truth, becauſe it comes from him who is infinite in Wiſdom, &amp; cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; and is a God of Truth, and therefore cannot deceive.</p>
               <p>Theſe Articles of our Faith are ſummarily comprehended in that <hi>Form of ſound Doctrine,</hi> which is commonly called the Apoſtles Creed, among which theſe are chief ones. That we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in God the Father, who hath made us and all the World. That we believe in God the Son, who hath redeemed us and all Mankind; which implies theſe things: We muſt believe that all Mankind are guilty before God, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to his Eternal Wrath and Puniſhment. That Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God, died as a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crfice for the Sins of Men: That he ſubmitted to an accurſed Death, as the Puniſhment of Sin in our ſtead, and to excuſe us from ſuffering it for ever: That his Death is accepted with the Father as an Atonement for Sin, and ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the advantage of all thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and believe on him: Who being heartily ſorry for their Sins, and fallen out with them, do forſake them and turn to God; and do expect and rely upon the Merit of his Death, to find fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our with God. We muſt believe, that as Jeſus Chriſt died for our Sins, ſo he roſe again for our Juſtification<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Having made a full Attonement,
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:001954_0022_0FBA42D59C16B838"/>
he was releaſed from the Bonds of Death: and is aſcended into Heaven; and that he ever lives there to make Interceſſion for us; that is, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and beſtow upon wretched Mankind, all the bleſſed Benefits which his Death has pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for them. And we muſt believe in God the Holy Ghoſt, who graciouſly applies all thoſe Bleſſings to us, and who ſanctifies us and all the Elect People of God.</p>
               <p>Further: We alſo are bound and required to make our open Profeſſion of the Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in theſe Articles; and to own it to the World, that we are, and will be the Worſhipers of the one only true and living God, by one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator between God and man, the Man Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. And we muſt chuſe rather to ſuffer any loſs, or to die, than to renounce or deny our Faith. And we are bound alſo to lead a Life ſuitable to theſe Articles of Faith, to let them govern our Converſations as they ought to do: And our Faith muſt work or operate in the Exerciſes of Love. This is the Second main Branch of our Duty under the New Covenant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Third</hi> is this: That we muſt engage and endeavour to keep God's Holy Will and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and to walk in the ſame all the Days of our Life. And this obliges us to the Things following, That we will diligently ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and learn the Will of God, as it is expreſs'd in the Laws which he has given us; will not cavil nor diſpute againſt our Duty, when we ſhould perform it; will endevour to know our Duty, that we may do it. That we will love his Law, and it ſhall be our conſtant Aim and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:001954_0023_0FBA42D71DC16E80"/>
to conform to it in all things: We abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely bind our ſelves, and are bound to live in no willful, known, and preſumptous Sin. That we will not deliberately and knowingly treſpaſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of God. This Covenant indeed does not require of us to <hi>preform</hi> a perfect Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for that is a thing now above our power: but it binds us to <hi>endeavour</hi> a perfect Obedience; that is, not to be willingly guilty of any known Sin. There is, alas, no meer Man now, that can conſtantly &amp; perfectly keep the whole Law of God but <hi>in many things we offend all:</hi> And 'tis one Bleſſing of the New Covenant, that it par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons Sins (as we ſhall ſee preſently) which ſuppoſes Defects in our beſt Obedience. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo our Saviour has taught us to pray as daily for the pardon of Sin, as for our daily Bread. But this Covenant bears with none but involuntary Sins; ſuch as we commit through Ignorance or Surpriſe, and for want of Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, on a ſudden, when our Ignorance and Inconſideration are not wilful, nor due to the neglect of our ſelves. And as for known, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and Preſumptuous Sins, and ſuch as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberately committed; they put us out of this Covenant, and loſe us all right to the Favours and Bleſſings of it, till they are bitterly repented of, and utterly forſaken.</p>
               <p>Thus much we muſt heartily &amp; ſincerely bind &amp; engage our ſelves to do; and this is our part of the New Covenant. This is alſo called the Covenant of Grace or Favour; and we may ſee that it has juſtly that Name, in that it admits of Repentance for Sin, and accepts of that poor
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:001954_0024_0FBA42D925493E08"/>
imperfect Obedience, which is all that we can now perform: And we ſhall ſee that Name fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther juſtified, in that it will appear to be one of the Bleſſings and Favours of it, that it affords us ſtrength to perform our Duty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VIII.</hi> On <hi>GOD's</hi> Part.</head>
               <p>AND now I come to repreſent and ſhew what are the Favours and Bleſſings on God's Part, of this New Covenant. What he offers, and promiſes, and will beſtow, upon our Performance of the Duties and Conditions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us. And theſe may be comprehended under theſe three rich and important Heads.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The First</hi> is a full and free Pardon of all our Sins. God will blot our Iniquities, as it were, out of his Remembrance; will forget that we were Sinners, and will treat us as righteous, Will lay aſide his moſt juſt Wrath againſt us: and embrace us with the Arms of Mercy and Love. He that might moſt Righteouſly have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd us with an Everlaſting Deſtruction, will rejoyce over us to do us good. He will pardon our moſt numerous Sins; will pardon the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Offences; will pardon even our known, wilful and deliberate Sins, and our Cuſtoms of Sinning, upon our Repentance and forſaking of them. And a general Repentance and a humble Behavour towards God, will obtain the Pardon of thoſe infirmities and involuntary Sins which we do not obſerve our ſelves to be guilty of, and cannot be perfectly free from. And having thus pardoned all our Sins, the Courſe
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:001954_0025_0FBA42DAD099FC18"/>
of Mercy is free; all Obſtruction of it is remov'd and we may addreſs to God with Boldneſs in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, as to a reconciled Father; and believe him ready to afford us all that is neceſſary to our Salvation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The next</hi> Favour and Bleſſing of this Covenant is, The reſtoring of the Divine Image in us in our Sanctification. If upon the Propoſal of this Covenant to us we do accept of it, and are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to yeild to the Conditions it requires, and to give up our ſelves to a Life of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs according to the Laws of God, He will give us Spiritual ſtrength to perform our Duty ſo far, as that we ſhall be accepted through the Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt. If we will not undertake, we ſhall not be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form; but if we will undertake and bind our ſelves to do our Duty, he will enable us to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it. It might ſeem a ſtrange thing that God ſhould require of us to bind our ſelves and undertake to do that which we cannot do of our ſelves, (as we do in obliging our ſelves to all thoſe things fore-mentioned) if it were not that the very binding our ſelves to this does entitle us by the Tenour of this Covenant to Grace ſufficient for us. In all the Exhortations of the Goſpel to an Inſtance of Duty, we may reckon there is comprehended alſo the Offer of Divine Aſſiſtance, which ſhall be afforded to him who yeilds, in the purpoſe and deſire of his Soul, to comply with thoſe Exhortations. No Man therefore ſhall have ground to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, that he would leave his known Sins, and do the Duties which he knows he omits,
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:001954_0026_0FBA42E05C1871A0"/>
but cannot do ſo: For if a man ſincerely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to leave his Sins, devotes himſelf to his Duty, and Diligently uſes the Means that may enable him to do it: That is, If he waits on God for this Grace in earneſt and perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Prayer, and a due attendance on the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word and the Sacraments, that Man ſhall infallibly come to be able to do what he thus wills and deſires. For, <hi>He that hungers and thirsts after Righteouſneſs, ſhall be filled,</hi> as our Saviour ſays; And <hi>God will give the Holy Spirit to them that ask him.</hi> It is the Favour of this New Covenant to help us to do what it requires us to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The last</hi> Favour and bleſſing of this Covenant, is an Everlaſting Happineſs both of Body and Soul in Heaven. We are left by it indeed ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to a natural Death; to mind us of our guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Rebellion againſt God: That we may not forget we are Sinners, and do deſerve an Eternal Death: On purpoſe that the ſence of this might quicken our deſire and concern to recover the Divine Favour, and make us the more ready and willing to ſubmit to the terms of recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. But Death ſhall not long have Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over us: God will not leave the Soul in Hell; that is, it ſhall not be always ſeperated from the Body; nor ſhall the Body be always ſubject to the Ignominy and Puniſhment of its Diſſolution. Since the Sins are pardon'd which did deſerve Death, the Creature ſhall be releaſed from it: And our Savour's Reſurection from the Dead does eſpecially aſſure the Reſurection of thoſe that believe on him, He has alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:001954_0027_0FBA42E30DE37350"/>
that he will <hi>give them Eternal Life, &amp; raiſe them up again at the last day.</hi> The Body, then, however ſcatter'd and diſpers'd, and loſt to all knowledge of Men, ſhall be gather'd together by the Wiſdom of God, and be raiſed to Life by his Almighty Power: And it ſhall be raiſed with great advantage; <hi>It was ſown a Natural Body, it ſhall be raiſed a Spiritual Body; It was ſown in Corruption,</hi> but <hi>it ſhall be raiſed Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</hi> And the Soul ſhall be again united to it, never to be ſeperated more: But both ſhall be taken up to dwell in a glorious happy place, where is <hi>fulneſs of joy, and pleaſure; for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more:</hi> To live in the Fellowſhip and Communion of kind, happy, and glorious Angels: To dwell in the Preſence of God, and contemplate, and praiſe, and love him, and rejoyce in his love for ever. This is now the whole Tenour of the New Covenant, which was procur'd for us by the precious Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, our kind and powerful Advocate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IX.</hi> The <hi>SACRAMENTS</hi> of this Covenant.</head>
               <p>AND this Covenant alſo hath its Sacaments. God has appointed ſenſible Actions and Signs, in and by which it is to be made between Him and Us. In the Uſe of theſe Sacraments, we muſt teſtifie our Conſent to this Covenant, and ſignifie, that we own our ſelves engag'd in it. And in the uſe of theſe muſt we wait for, and expect the Bleſſings and Favours on God's part to be afforded us. It is by theſe that he
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:001954_0028_0FBA42E48DE35028"/>
has determin'd to convey thoſe <hi>Favours</hi> which we can at preſent receive, which are the Pardon of our Sins, and the Sanctification of our Natures; and alſo to aſſure that which we are to hope for, our Everlaſting Happineſs and Glory. Theſe we muſt neceſſarily uſe, then, if Means &amp; Opportunity be afforded us to do ſo, that we may be Partakers of his Favours: And in uſing them, we muſt ſincerely purpoſe and bind our ſelves to the Performance of our Duty. The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments appointed to be, as we may ſay, The Inſtrument of this Covenant ſince the coming of Chriſt, which are all that nearly concern us, are Baptiſm, and the Supper of the Lord. Theſe, and theſe only, are now generally neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
               <p>By Baptiſm we are admitted into this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and make our firſt ſolemn Acceptance of it. By the Lords Supper we renew it, if it has been broken on our part by any wilful Sin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> committed ſince we were baptiſed: Or elſe we therein teſtifie and declare our continuance ſtill in it, and our purpoſe and deſire to do ſo; if any of us have liv'd ſo happily ſince we were baptized, as never to violate or break this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant by any wilful known Sin.</p>
               <p>It is true, when we are baptized in our Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, we are not capable expreſly to intend &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign the performances of our part in this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, becauſe we cannot then underſtand or know it. But this Sacaament is in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God deſign'd for the Scrament of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into this Covenant, ſince the appearance of Jeſus Chriſt in the World. And as that which
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:001954_0029_0FBA42E62402B448"/>
was the Sacrament of this Admiſſion under the Jewiſh Diſpenſation, was by God's Appointment adminſtred to Children at eight days old; ſo the Chriſtian Church has been wont, even from the Apoſtles times, to adminiſter Baptiſm to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, from whence it is not to be doubted but they learn to do this from the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And our Saivour gives a plain Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the Practice, when he ſays, <hi>Suffer little Children to come unto me, and forbid them not; for of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Our Church therefore, as without doubt it ought to do, adminiſters Baptiſm to Infants that they may partake of the Bleſſings of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to their Salvation.</p>
               <p>But becauſe there is an Ingagement on the part of the Baptized Perſon <hi>implied</hi> in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Baptiſm; the Wiſdom and Piety of the Church has thought fit that it ſhould be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd</hi> too: That ſo the baptiſed Perſon may be better convinced afterwards, That he did thus engage himſelf at his Baptiſm. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the infant it ſelf cannot expreſs this, the Church has provided, that ſome Chriſtian Friends ſhould do it for us, who are alſo Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes that the thing is done. And they are bound to take care, that as we grow up to the Uſe of our Reaſon, we may grow alſo in the Knowledge of our part in this Covenant, and may come to underſtand what we are bound to.</p>
               <p>And that the baptiſed Perſon himſelf may ratifie and confirm his baptiſmal Engagement, he muſt, when he can exerciſe his Reaſon, and
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:001954_0030_0FBA42E7913405B0"/>
know his part of this Covenant, readily chuſe and conſent to it, and ſolemnly renew it; and ſo he muſt make it his own Act &amp; Deed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote himſelf to God. This our Church has very juſtly ordered ſhould be ſolemnly and publickly done in the recieving of Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. A thing, alas, too much neglected, to the great Decay of Chriſtian Piety among us: But if this were duly and generally practiſed, we ſhould in all likelihood ſee more Perſons live according to their baptiſmal Vow, and as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Chriſtians, than commonly do.</p>
               <p>But this Diſcourſe is deſign'd cheifly to bring Men prepar'd to the Lords Supper, that they may worthily and profitably receive that; &amp; therefore it muſt not be diverted ſo as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt long on any other Subject but what is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and ſerviceable to that deſign and end of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. X.</hi> The <hi>LORD's SUPPER</hi> a Confirmation of this Covenant.</head>
               <p>I SHALL now therefore bring the Diſcourſe more cloſe to the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, which has been all this while leading and aiming towards it. And I ſhall begin to diſcourſe particularly of that, by ſhewing, That it is appointed by God as a Faederal Rite, and is to be uſed as ſuch by us; As a Ceremony wherein this New Covenant between God and Man is renew'd and confirm'd. This, by a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſearch, we ſhall ſoon find to be very evident in Holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="unknown:001954_0031_0FBA42E9FA5958F0"/>Our Saviour himſelf, when he firſt inſtituted this Sacrament, ſpeaks thus of it, as he was delivering the Cup to his Diſciples, <hi>This Cup <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the New Covenant in my Blood,</hi> Luke 22.20. For what our Tranſlation renders <hi>Testament</hi> there, had been more exactly &amp; properly rendred <hi>Covenant,</hi> Our Saivour's plain meaning is this: Take this Cup as the Inſtrument of Conveyance to you of the Divine Bleſſings of the Covenant of Grace, which are the ineſtimable Purchaſes of my precious Blood. Again, when our Lord ſays of the Bread in this Sacrament, <hi>This is my Body which is given for you</hi>; and of the Cup, <hi>This is my Blood of the New Covenant which is ſhed for many for the Remiſſion of their Sins:</hi> He plainly means, That this Sacrament is intended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o renew to us the Bleſſings &amp; Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, which are the Purchaſes of his meritorious Death, &amp; his Sacrifice which he offer'd to God in dying for us. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> plainly teaches us to underſtand our Lord thus: For he ſays of the <hi>Bread</hi> this Sacrament, It <hi>is the Communion of the Body of Christ</hi>; and of the <hi>Cup,</hi> It <hi>is the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.16. By Communion, he means the Communication of theſe. It is faithfully intended by God that in the Uſe of this Sacrament, thoſe who are fit Receivers, ſhall partake of the Body and Blood of Chriſt; and this Bread and this Cup ſhall be the Communication of the Body and Blood of Chriſt to them: Theſe outward Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Broken Bread, and Wine poured out ſhall bring with them, to thoſe humble and prepared Souls which receive them, this Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:001954_0032_0FBA42ED8D9E7728"/>
Grace: By which means they ſhall be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Bleſſings purchaſed by the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or wounding of the Body, and the ſhedding of the blood of our Saivour, the bleſſings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by the valuable Sacrifice of his Death; which are the Bleſſings of the New Covenant fore-mention'd.</p>
               <p>This Sacrament is ordain'd of God to be a Pledge &amp; Conveyance of theſe bleſſings, &amp; ſhall actually &amp; infallibly be ſo to meet Receivers: God will ne'er be wanting to his Sacraments, nor leave them without the Efficacy he deſings them for, if the Receivers be not wanting to themſelves. He faithfully intends the Renewal, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this Covenant with us in this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and will actually do it if we ſincerely intend the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>And that the Renewal of our part of the Covenant at this Sacrament is expected and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by God, cannot chuſe but be very eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apprehended. When God offers good things upon Terms and Conditions, he requires the binding our ſelves to perform thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, if we will partake of thoſe good things; and our embracing the Offers he makes, implies, and ought to imply, the accepting of thoſe Terms, and the engaging our ſelves to perform thoſe Conditions. To be ſure God never intends we ſhall be partakers of thoſe good things, without performing thoſe Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. When 'tis ſaid, God <hi>gives the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to them that aſk him,</hi> 'tis imply'd that <hi>aſking</hi> is the neceſſary Condition and Means of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; <hi>God gave his only begotten Son, that
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:001954_0033_0FBA42F40C1BEE08"/>
they who believe in him ſhould not periſh, but have Everlaſting Life</hi>; 'Tis required Men <hi>believe</hi> as a Condition of their obtaining Everlaſting Life, So when it is ſaid, <hi>Jeſus Christ is the Author of Salvation to them that obey him</hi>; and <hi>Repent that your Sins may be blotted out</hi>: Theſe things evidently imply, that our Sins ſhall not be forgiven, unleſs we <hi>repent</hi> of them; not will the Bleſſed Jeſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be a Saviour to us, if we do not <hi>devote our ſelves to his Service,</hi> and give up our ſelves to follow his Example and Conduct. Now this being the conſtant Tenour of the Goſpel; We muſt needs Conclude, that when we are offer'd to be made partakers of theſe Bleſſings in this Sacrament, it is required, that if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them, we muſt bind our ſelves to perform ſuch Conditions.</p>
               <p>Our receiving therefore of thoſe things which are God's Pledges and Coveyances of thoſe Bleſſings upon Conditions, is an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Profeſſion and Declaration that we bind our ſelves to do what is required of us! And if that outward profeſſion be not attended with an inward and ſincere Intention, it is hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Hypocriſie, and makes a Man undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>guilty of the Body and Blood of Christ:</hi> He is reckoned to have abuſed &amp; profaned the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood of Chriſt, as did the wretched Men that ſlew him. The receiving thoſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this Sacrament is an outward profeſſion and Declaration that we accept of God's Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and it certainly bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds us ſincerely to
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:001954_0034_0FBA42F68BDC5C98"/>
intend our performance of the Conditions of it.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle plainly gives this Inſtruction in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. in that he intimates the parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this Sacrament to be a Rite of the ſame Nature and Signification with the eating of the Sacrifices which had been offer'd to any god. As the Eating of thoſe Sacrifices therefore ſignified the owning him for God, to whom the Sacrifice had been made, and ſo the obliging of themſelves to worſhip and obey him; and the Reliance upon that Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to find Favour and obtain a Bleſſing from him; ſo the Eating of the Lords Supper muſt be reckon'd to imply and declare the ſame profeſſions and engagements. This is the Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Sacrifice made to God, even the great Sacrifice of the Body and Blood of Chriſt; and therefore muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tended with Faith or a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance upon that Sacrifice to find Favour with him; the owning him to be God, and the binding our ſelves to honour, love and obey him. For this reaſon it is that the Apoſtle forbids in that Chapter thoſe who would par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of this Sacrament the Eating of any Feaſts upon Sacrifices whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> been offer'd to the Heathen Idols; which Sacrifices he ſays were offer'd to Devils: <hi>Ye cannot drink the Cup of the Lord and the cup of Devils<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ye cannot be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Lord's Table and of the Table of Devils</hi>; ſays he, <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>Ye cannot,</hi> may mean, <hi>'tis impoſſible,</hi> you ſhould ſincerely intend what is ſignified by both theſe things; that is, the owning the true God as God, and the owning
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:001954_0035_0FBA42F82B657B58"/>
thoſe Devils as God, for in owning one, you do imply the renouncing of the other To be ſure the true God requires, if you own him, that you do renounce all other. Or it muſt mean, <hi>You ought not</hi> to do thus. If you partake of the Cup and Table of the Lord, you muſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely intend thereby the owning of him; and then you muſt not ſo much as ſeem to own thoſe filthy Devils in eating of the Sacrifices which have been offer'd to them. Therefore he adds in the 22d Verſe, That in doing thus, they did <hi>provoke the Lord to Jealouſie</hi>; becauſe they made a ſhew and appearance of departing from, and of renouncing him herein. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle then plainly teaches us, that in receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Sacrament, we do make profeſſion and ſhow of honouring and covenanting with God; and therefore that we ought really and ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to intend it.</p>
               <p>I might ſhow that the Name of <hi>Sacrament</hi> was given to this Ordinance by the firſt Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians, becauſe they reckon'd the Celebrating this Supper to ſignifie the Binding our ſelves to ſerve and honour, love and obey and truſt in God; to be his faithful Subjects and Servants. And ſo notorious was it, that they uſed it as a Ceremony of covenanting with God; that even the Heathens knew this, and therefore one of them ſpeaking of the Chriſtian Aſſemblies in his time for Worſhip (at which they always Celebrated this Sacrament) ſays; They met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether on a fixed Day before it was light, (this was for fear of their enemies) and did there bind themſelves by an Oath or Sacrament not to
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:001954_0036_0FBA42F99F42FDA0"/>
commit any Thefts or Adulteries, nor to betray any Truſt, or deal deceitfully with their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and the like. They then took this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament as an Engagement to be of the Religion of Jeſus, and ſo to perform the Terms and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the New Covenant: We therefore muſt, when we receive it, ſincerely intend the Confirmation of that Covenant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XI.</hi> An Earneſt Perſuaſive to come to the <hi>LORD'S SUPPER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I SHALL now inſiſt a little upon an earneſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſive to the frequent Attendance upon this Sacrament, which the woful &amp; deplorable Neglect of theſe times, and the ſad conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of that Neglect, do make but too neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>Let all Men know then, that when they are come to years, and are capable to know and to renew their Vow and Covenant which they made in Baptiſm, they are commanded by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in this way to renew and confirm it. They are indiſpenſably bound to receive this Sacrament in Confirmation of that Covenant. No Man is left at Liberty whether he will receive this Sacrament or not; but if the Providence of God affords him Means and Opportunity to do ſo, he is bound to prepare himſelf for, and receive it. If a Man any time neglects to prepare himſelf for it, and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unfit, and abſents himſelf becauſe he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: in that caſe he will be judged to have neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:001954_0037_0FBA42FBF4E32F40"/>
the Sacrament it ſelf. He that does not endeavour to be prepared, &amp; receive it as often as Opportunity is afforded him to do it in that Congregation of Chriſtians, which the Order of the Church and Obedience to the Governours of it does oblige him to join with; He does ſo often neglect and refuſe it, as he thus ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents himſelf from it. But the neglect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal of this, we muſt know, is the neglect &amp; refuſal of the incomparble Bleſſings of the New Covenant; of having the pardon of our Sins renewed and Sealed; the Bleſſed Influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Holy Spirit tenewed upon us; and our Title confirmed to Everlaſting Bleſſedneſs, and our Hopes of it increaſed and ſtrengthened; 'tis to neglect our own Intereſt, and to provoke the Diſpleaſure of God, more than by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sins, in neglecting the Offers of his Grace and Mercy.</p>
               <p>Let all thoſe who never mind this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor do ever prepare themſelves for it, nor receive it, know, That they do therein in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate the renouncing of their Covenant with God, and do cut themſelves off from all Hopes and Expectations of the Favours and Bleſſings of the Covenant of Grace, till they repent of this guilty Omiſſion of their Duty, and ſo come to this Sacrament prepared for it. Oh wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Creatures! They chuſe to remain in a ſtate of Damnation. To be ſure a Man that has contradicted his Covenant ſince he was Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, by living in any wilful Sin; if that Man does not reſolve to forſake his Sin, and come to this Sacrament, and hereby bind himſelf to his
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:001954_0038_0FBA42FD9D7AC4A8"/>
Duty, he will be in the fight of God, account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to renounce his Chriſtianity, to deny the Lord that bought him, to trample upon the Blood of the Covenant; the Blood of Chriſt, and to deſpiſe his dying Love: And as ſuch, a Man muſt inevitably periſh; ſo he will fall under the heavieſt and ſoreſt Perdition.</p>
               <p>Whatever pretended Wiſhes a Man may have to forſake his Sins, whatever Regret and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe for them, and whatever Reſolutions he makes to forſake them, they will not be acc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>epted with God, not bring him into a Title to the Favour of this Covenant, if he has Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity and Means to Partake of this Sacrament, and refuſes to do it: Becauſe 'tis <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by</hi> this Sacrament that God expects &amp; requires the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newal of this Covenant after we have broken nit: Our Repentance is not compleated accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Will of God till this is done, if he Affords us Means and Opportunity to do this. We are not Allowed to expect that he will Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept our Reſolutions and Vows in any other way, when he has Appointed us this way of preſenting them to Him.</p>
               <p>Beſides, Is it not a wonderful thing that Men ſhould forget that this Sacrament is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God as the Means to Convey to them the ſtrength to perform their good Vows and Reſolutions? And then he that Neglects this Sacrament, lays himſelf under the Power and Tyranny of his Sins, by Neglecting the Mighty Help which Heaven kindly affords him againſt it: And he binds upon himſelf the Guilt of all his Sins, and as it were Seals Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:001954_0039_0FBA42FF1EF47040"/>
to Damnation in refuſing and neglecting this Ordinance, whereby he might be Sealed to the Day of Redemption.</p>
               <p>Let all Men know, that the Wilful Neglect &amp; Refuſal of this Sacrament is a Damnable Sin of Omiſſion, and puts every Man that is Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it out of a State of Grace &amp; Salvation: And they that Neglect to come to this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance when 'tis prepared for them, may very juſtly Fear that God will not Bleſs any other to them: For what Ground have they to think He will Bleſs one of his Ordinances to them, while they Neglect another, or let them Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain by Prayer &amp; Hearing the Word what he Commanded them to uſe this Sacrament for too, that they may Obtain it; And then they that live in Neglect of this, are in great Danger Never to be Saved by any other Means of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p>Men may perhaps think themſelves very Good Chriſtians if they keep their Church, attend the Publick Prayers, and ſometimes Hear, ſometimes Sleep away a Sermon: But if they Neglect this Sacrament, they muſt Expect God will Reject all there other Performances: <hi>He that breaks the Law, in one Point,</hi> the Scrip-ſays, <hi>is guilty of all</hi>; And then he that Neglects his Obedience to any one of God's Commands knowingly &amp; willfully, will be lookt upon and treated by Almighty God as if he had Fulfill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed none of them. Oh that Men would Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly lay theſe things to Heart, and Conſider the Terrible Danger which they put themſelves into by this Neglect!</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="unknown:001954_0040_0FBA43005FD615E0"/>Let us be aſſured, that whatever it is that hinders us from preparing our ſelves, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Sacrament, it is a Snare &amp; Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Devil the Great Adverſary of our Souls: Who knows the Great and Saving Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of this Sacrament, and therefore would not have Men uſe it: Who knows that if we Seriouſly and Frequently Attend upon this Means of our Salvation he muſt Deſpair of ever Accompliſhing our Deſtruction. Oh let us Defeat the Malicious Deſigns of our Enemy, and Reſiſt all Suggeſtions that would bear us off from this Practice.</p>
               <p>Let us Conſider how Kindly &amp; Lovingly the Lord Jeſus, the great Lover of Souls Invites us to it: <hi>Come unto me,</hi> ſays he, <hi>all ye that are weary and heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> Let us not give him cauſe to complain of us, and ſay, <hi>Ye will not come unto me that ye may have Life.</hi> Let us conſider what noble and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting Entertainment he has provided for us at this heavenly Feaſt: He deſigns to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain us with aſſurances of his Love, with the Divine Influences of his Holy Spirit, with the joyful Pledges and foretaſts of Heaven? and is this what is but fit to be deſpiſed! Conſider at what a coſtly Rate and Price he has provided us this Entertainment! Even at the Price of his own cruel Sufferings, and bitter Death, and of his moſt precious Blood. If we love our Souls then, and have any Concern for their Salvation, let us prepare our ſelves and come to this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as often as we can: If we have any true Love to the Lord Jeſus, our beſt Friend, our
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:001954_0041_0FBA4302189B1668"/>
kind Saviour, who loved us and laid down his Life for us; Let us earneſtly deſire and ſeek the Purchaſes of his Blood, and ſeek to be made partakers of them in that way in which he has appointed us; as we ſhall certainly do, if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally &amp; ſincerely deſire them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XII.</hi> Of Fitneſs to come to this <hi>SACRAMENT.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUT the common Pretence and Excuſe that hinders Men from coming to this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is, That they are not ſit for it, and they are afraid of Eating &amp; Drinking unworthily, &amp; of incurring their own Damnation thereby. It is therefore the Deſign of this little Book to ſhew what fitneſs is requiſite for a worthy &amp; profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Receiving of this Sacrament; and to help Men to that Fitneſs by the Bleſſing of God; which they ſhall not fail to obtain of him by earneſt Prayer, and the ſerious and frequent pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſal of what is here preſented.</p>
               <p>And ſince in celebrating this Sacrament of the Body and Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, we are to renew and confirm this Covenant which we we have been ſpeaking of between God and us? This will abundantly direct what Preparation and Fitneſs is requiſite, that we may be meet Partakers of it to our Profit and Comfort. And it is neceſſary that we know what the Terms and Conditions of it are which God requires to be performed on our Parts, and what it offers and promiſes on God's Part. This Matter therefore has been already for that Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:001954_0042_0FBA43035A613068"/>
diſtinctly and ſomewhat particularly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented.</p>
               <p>In the next place, we muſt unfeignedly and ſincerely chuſe and lay hold on this Covenant: It muſt be the hearty deſire, the ſincere purpoſe of our Souls to be engaged in it: To be bound in thoſe happy Bonds which ſet our Souls at Liberty from the Bonds of Sin and Death: We muſt deſire the Bleſſings, and ſeek the Favours of it, and readily accept and ſubmit to the Terms and Conditions; and declare, that we will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect our Salvation upon thoſe Terms.</p>
               <p>And alſo we muſt, certainly, be very thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Son of God at this Memorial of his Death, ſince he became the Mediator of this Covenant, and has by his Death procured the Favour of New Terms of Salvation, and the offer of Peace and Reconcilement with God upon ſo gentle and eaſy Terms.</p>
               <p>And he who has the Knowledge of this Cov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enant, and this good diſpoſition of Mind there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, that Man is fit for this Sacrament, and if he comes, he ſhall be a welcome Gueſt at the Lords Table. Now as I have repreſented the Knowledge neceſſary to this, I ſhall go on to repreſent alſo more particularly the good Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Mind which we ought to come with. And I ſhall repreſent this in ſuch a way as will be fit to form it in Men where it is not, or to exite and actuate it, and ſet it into exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe where it is. I ſhall repreſent it in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Acts or Exerciſes of it: Which you may take notice are a lively Deſcription of a very meet Receiver of this Sacrament. So that
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:001954_0043_0FBA4304D0F74300"/>
he who would <hi>become</hi> fit for this Sacrament, muſt read and meditate on thoſe things, till he finds thoſe diſpoſitions and Affections rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in him, which are therein expreſſed. And he that would know or find himſelf fit for this Sacrament, muſt examine himſelf by them, and ſee whether they repreſent the State and Diſpoſition of his Mind or not. And if a Man be <hi>habitually</hi> poſſeſſed with ſuch a good State of Mind, as theſe things will be, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, very agreeable to him, ſo they will be of uſe to <hi>ſtir up that Diſpoſition</hi> into Excerciſe, and to an <hi>actual Fitneſs</hi> for this Sacrament; As Fire is wont to kindle fire in matter that is apt and diſpoſed to receive it. Further, he that would <hi>behave himſelf rightly and duely at this Sacraments</hi> to his Comfort and Benefit, as he muſt have his mind then filled with ſuch Thoughts and Affections as are here repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo the reading of theſe things there, if he has leiſure, will be uſeful to poſſeſs him with ſuch Thoughts and Affections. And laſtly, he that would maintain the good Diſpoſition of Mind which he has at the Sacrament, may very profitably for that purpoſe, read and meditate on theſe things afterwards; which will be as uſeful to cheriſh and maintain, yea, &amp; to improve in us this Diſpoſition of Mind, as they are to form it. All this uſe, I dare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, may be made of theſe Exerciſes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
               <pb n="39" facs="unknown:001954_0044_0FBA43065A666858"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XIII.</hi> An Exerciſe of Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Remembrance of the Death of <hi>JESUS CHRIST.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LORD, I am not worthy to live, if I do not always remember the exceeding great Love of my Lord and only Saviour Jeſus Chriſt in dying for me; and if I do not moſt affectionately conſider and obſerve the many and incomparable Benefits, which by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood ſhed, he hath obtained for Sinners. My ſoul; that thou mayſt know, in ſome meaſure, the wondrous heighth, the breadth, the depth, the length of the Love of God in Chriſt Jeſus: That thou mayſt entertain the larger apprehenſions of that Love, which exceeds all finite Knowledge; Thou muſt enlarge thy Thoughts, and take in all thou canſt of theſe dimenſions of it. Conſider what a Depth of Wretchedneſs and Miſery Jeſus reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cues poor loſt Mankind from! Conſider what a glorious heighth of Honour and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs he deſigns to advance them to! Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider who the excellent Perſon is that has done all this for us! Conſider what it coſt him to procure for us ſuch a Redemption! Behold the moſt amazing, but moſt pleaſing proſpect in the World, Redeeming Love! Dwell in the Contemplation of this; for ſurely it is good to be here!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As for the Condition</hi> into which thou wert ſunk, it was the vileſt and the moſt miſerable
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:001954_0045_0FBA4308086A3878"/>
that a Creature could fall into: It was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly diſerable, for thou hadſt utterly loſt the Favour of thy Maker the Fountain-Good, and forfeited all right, and loſt all hopes of ever being happy: Thou wert become a vile Sinner, odious to the pure and holy God; and wert as contemptible as miſerable: Thou wert obnoxious to the Eternal Wrath and juſt vengeance of the Almighty: Thou didſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be thrown into the deep Lake of Fire and Brimſtone, where is eternal Woe and Sorrow, weeping and Gnaſhing of Teeth; where the wrath of God burns for ever, and the Fire will never be quenched; from whence there ſhall be no returning. Where wretched Creatures are furies to themſelves, and more than double all the Torments of Hell with this tormenting Thought, that they muſt all endure for ever: They will know no intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or reſpite; they will never come to an End. This is the ſad portion of Sinners: And this muſt all Mankind after a few Complaining Days, ſpent in this low mortal Life, have been thrown into; And there was no creature in Heaven or Earth could poſſibly have prevented his Doom; no, it could never have been avoided if Jeſus had not concerned himſelf to help us. And he has taken away the neceſſity of our Deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; has rendred this Woe and Miſery now an avoidable Thing; Is not this a glorious Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit?</p>
               <p>Look down, my Soul, in ſerious thoughts into that horrid dungeon and lake of Fire! Imagine as thou mayſt well, that many wretched
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:001954_0046_0FBA430A21C2EDD8"/>
Souls are already plunged into it, who ſqan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred away the Day of Life, the precious Time allowed them of making their peace with God, and to avoid theſe Miſeries! think thou ſeeſt them wallowing in Flames, pierced through with Fire, and in all parts themſelves on a Flame! And beſure, if thou couldeſt hear them, thou ſhouldeſt hear the moſt diſmal Howlings, bitter Complaints; ſome curſing the Day that ever they were born, and all, at times, curſing themſelves as cauſes of their own ruin. And think now if one of theſe deſpairing Souls ſhould have an Angel ſent to it, that ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Priſon-doors and let him out, and ſend him into this world again to be in a condition and poſſibility of avoiding all this Miſery, would he not account this a wonderful Favour! Such as he could never praiſe enough: Such as could never be worthily requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: It is, in truth, not leſs than this that thou art beholden to the Love of Jeſus for: It is not a leſs favour to be kept from this Miſery, than to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from it into the ſtate wherein thou now art.</p>
               <p>And thou art kept from this by the tender compaſſionate, and moſt patient Love of the Lord Jeſus! Long ago, if thou hadſt ſuffered thy deſerts thou hadſt been thrown into this Miſery: Long ago have thy Sins deſerved it: It is of the Lord's Mercy that thou art not conſumed. Jeſus has repreived thee by his powerful Interceſſion: he has procured that thou art hitherto ſpared; yea, he has procured that thou mayſt, if thou wilt, be pardoned; &amp;
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:001954_0047_0FBA430FC8CBF7E8"/>
mayſt for ever be exempted from enduring thoſe intolerable Miſeries. Oh, how much art thou obliged! Say how uſeful, how neceſſary, how great is your Redeemers Love; Oh, what Love, what Praiſe can reach it! Oh compaſſionate Love, how ſhall I find Expreſſions ſuitable to thy kindneſs! Why was my Life ſo dear to thee! Why haſt thou not ſuffer'd me to periſh! Me, who am as unworthy of thy Favour, as I am in diſtreſs and need of it!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And does this</hi> engage thy wonder ſo much, my Soul? It may indeed well do ſo; but this alone muſt not detain it: There are yet more occaſions for thy Admiration and Praiſe in the Redeemer's Love! And this thou wilt ſee, if thou conſider what a Glorious Heighth of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Happineſs he deſigns to advance poor, vile, contemptible Sinners to. Thoſe that have render'd themſelves unworthy of this Earth, and even of this low, mortal Life, he intends to advance them to Heaven, and give them E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life. Thoſe that are unworthy of any thing that is good and comfortable, he intends to make them perfectly happy. Thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the utmoſt contempt of their Maker; that are fallen under the Inſults and Scorn of the abject Devils, he intends for the Honour of ſeeing God, and dwelling in his bliſsful Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence for ever. O rich and bounteous Love! Nothing leſs will ſerve him, but that where he is, we ſhould alſo be. Think, my ſoul if thou canſt, what Heaven is.</p>
               <p>Think of a bright and glorious Place, where this Sun would be aſhamed and even diſappear,
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:001954_0048_0FBA4314A92493D8"/>
as now the ſtars do at his Riſing. Think of an innumerable Company of glorious Creatures, each of them more bright than he. Think thou ſeeſt them all in Joy, all raviſht and tranſported with Pleaſure, and thy ſelf among them parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of that Joy and Pleaſure. Think thou wert now in the Preſence of the Fountain-Good, receiving immediately from himſelf the Teſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imonies and Communications of infinite Love! That thou wert there, where no Fear or Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row can ever come! Where the Joy is pure without allay! Where the Pleaſure is ſolid and abiding, not likely to leave thee in diſcontent and diſtaſt! Where the Joy and Pleaſure ſhall never End! Oh how glad wouldſt thou be to ſee thyſelf there! Thou mayſt believe it is not: poſſible for thy Heart now to conceive the mighty Joy, which would poſſeſs thee: And to this Happineſs, even to this, does the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer's Love deſign to bring thee. He would have thee attain this Happineſs: He offers it thee on gentle Terms: He offers to guide and help thee thither, if thou wilt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> give up thy ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o his kind and gracious Conduct. And is not this amazing and obliging Love!</p>
               <p>All the Joy and Happineſs of Heaven may be, my Eternal Portion if I will; and ſhall be ſo if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m not wanting to my ſelf. Jeſus has not been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or will be wanting to do all that in him lies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o bring me to it. He does not grudge me the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igheſt Bliſs that my Nature is capable to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain, or that my own kindeſt Wiſhes to my ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an deſire. He loves me, then, as much as I can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ove my ſelf, and is willing to make me as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:001954_0049_0FBA4316A41F73A8"/>
as I can deſire to be; and more happy than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can conceive or imagine. Such is the Love o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jeſus to a Wretch, that deſerves only his Ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred and Contempt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But doſt thou</hi> know, my Soul? Canſt thou think who the <hi>Perſon</hi> is that has done theſe great Things for thee? I am ſure, if thou hadſt not been told, thou couldſt never have imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it. Infinite Love indeed might be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be in the Son of God; but he has infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Greatneſs, Majeſty and Glory too; he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> exalted ſo far above us, that it were even Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Condeſcenſion for him to regard or concer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf about the Miſery which ſuch low thing as we, had pulled upon our ſelves. Beſides, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is Infinitely pure and Holy too, and has an ete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal hatred of all Sin and Wickedneſs; and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> became miſerable by our Sin. And he love the Father with an Infinite Love; and he mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mankind to love, and honour, and praiſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Father; but they have forſaken the end o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Being, and turned to hate, and deſpiſe eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Good and Glorious God. And could it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> imagined, that ever ſuch Perſons ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deemed then, by the Son of God?</p>
               <p>But be aſtoniſh'd, Oh ye Heavens! Sing Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Oh ye glorious Hoſts of Angels! Produc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your loftieſt Hymns, and help, Oh help poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feeble Mortals to praiſe the Son of God! Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it was he that became our Mediator: He too<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon him the kind Office of being our Saviour It was the Son of God that did us this kind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs: The Eternal, the Only-begotten Son o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="unknown:001954_0050_0FBA4319454211C0"/>
God; who is the <hi>expreſs Image</hi> of the Father's <hi>Perſon,</hi> and <hi>the brightneſs of his Glory.</hi> This Perſon, my Soul, whom thou muſt own to be the true and Eternal God, by whom the Worlds were made; who ſuſtains all things; who is the Glory of Heaven, and the ſtability of Earth; who is incomprehenſible in his Greatneſs; and to be ſure, Mighty to ſave, is he who regarded, us in our vile Miſery, and moſt deſpicable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
               <p>Who pitied us in the Miſery which we had madly pull'd upon our ſelves which we had deeply deſerv'd! Who lov'd Sinners, the moſt hateful things that are! Oh the wonder! that he ſhould retain Kindneſs, and think Thoughts of Love towards us after the Abuſe of great creating Love; to us who are altogether unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to him! whoſe Happineſs is not at all neceſſary, nor can make any addition to his! He had been eternally happy, if we had been for ever loſt and miſerable: Yet he would not ſee us loſt; he afforded his help, when all other help utterly failed us, and we muſt have pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, if he had not helped us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But go on,</hi> my Soul, for the way is ſtill plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and ſtrowed with new and various de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights; and conſider too, in what way and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod this glorious Perſon the Son of God accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed this great Salvation! what he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to do, and what to ſuffer, that he might ſave thee.</p>
               <p>Thou muſt know then, that this excellent Perſon meditated and deſigned no leſs conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion, when he undertook to ſave thee, than
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:001954_0051_0FBA431AC6F41720"/>
to become man for thy ſake. He intended it then, and in the fulneſs of time ſubmitted to it. <hi>The word was made Fleſh.</hi> The Son of God took a Humane Nature, and became the Son of <hi>David</hi>: For he was born of a Virgin, who was of the Houſe and Family of <hi>David</hi>: A Royal Family indeed; but in this branch of it, at eaſt, ſunk into poverty and contempt. He who made the World, condeſcended to be made of a Woman! He who is Lord of Life and Glory, became ſubject to the Law that obliges Creatures! He whom the Angels account it their honour to attend and worſhip, made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of no reputation, took upon him the form of a Servant, and expoſed himſelf to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſcorn of Men. O Son of God, how couldſt thou endure to live upon this earth ſo defiled with Sin, to converſe with Sinneri? We muſt needs wonder, that when thou wert in our guilty world, thou didſt not ſhew thy terrible hatred and reſentment of the Sins of Men in ſending Plagues and Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about the rebellious world. It is an amazement that thou ſhouldeſt here go about doing good! But this was thy conſtant prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice: It was glorious Love, O adorable Son of God, which brought thee down among us; and Love ſpake in every Word of thine; Love attended all thy ſteps; Love to mankind was exerciſed in all thy Actions. What exceeding honour, gracious Lord, haſt thou done our mean Nature, in taking it into a perſonal Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with thy ſelf! Thus haſt thou exalted it above the Angels, and abundantly vindicated
<pb n="47" facs="unknown:001954_0052_0FBA431C0DF6E3E0"/>
it from the contempt of Devils; who firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, and then utterly deſpiſed it: So low and mean is thy condeſcenſion, and ſo glorious our exaltation! Behold, my Soul, the Son of God become our brother! And as he is our brother, he does exalt us to become the Sons of God, together with him: And his Father becomes our Father. Oh, <hi>what manner of Love is this, that we ſhould be called the Sons of God!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this is not all the condeſcenſion of the Son of God to ſave mankind, that he took to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the humane nature: No, tho' this was much, yet he did more, much more than this. He undertook to die a Sacrifice for the Sins of men, which as God, he could not do; and therefore he became man, that he might be capable of dying: And in humbling, he <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the Croſs.</hi> And here, if ever, my ſoul, thou wilt be loſt in aſtoniſhment, in conſidering thy Saviours love to mankind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thou wilt ſurely deſpiſe all things beſide. Thou wilt like his great Apoſtle and Lover, be forced to value no knowledge but that <hi>of Chriſt, and him crucified</hi>; and to account all things but <hi>droſs and dung,</hi> that thou mayſt gain an Intereſt in this Love. That it may thus engage thee, conſider now the death which Jeſus underwent for thee.</p>
               <p>Was it the Death of the Croſs? Was my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour crucify'd? And what kind of Death was this; his Enemies, the unbelieving Jews, choſe it for him, and the Heatheniſh <hi>Roman</hi> Soldiers executed it. And this Death was the vileſt
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:001954_0053_0FBA431DF5DDAC40"/>
and the moſt ignominious one in the account of the <hi>Romans</hi>; ſuch as they put none to but the moſt contemptible Abjects, and the baſeſt Malefactors. And this Death was, in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Jewiſh Law, an accurſed one: he was reckoned accurſed of God that was <hi>hanged on a Tree.</hi> But let me conſider the Indignities, the contemptuous uſage which attended my Saviour's Death, and how painful and afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it muſt needs have been to him.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as the bleſſed Jeſus was condemned to die, he was committed to rude Soldiers who made it their ſport to injure and abuſe him. They ſtript him of his Cloaths, tied him to a Pillar and cruelly ſcourged him on his naked Back. Oh Jeſu! I love and adore thee, whom thoſe Wretches thus vilely abuſed! I grieve for thy Injuries, and am afflicted with thy pain! After this they platted a Crown of Thorns, and forced it, to make it ſit faſt up on his Head wounding and tearing thereby his Sacred Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and then, my Soul, had I been there, I might have ſeen his own Blood running down and diſguiſing his Bleſſed Face, Oh what an diſguiſe of that Majeſty and Meekneſs, of that venerable Sweetneſs, that awful goodneſs which had always dwelt there! They then found out ſome contemptible Purple Garment, and put it on him, and put a Reed in his Hand to imitate a Scepter; and then mockt him with the bowing the knee before him, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Hail King of the Jews.</hi> And to ſhew how little Honour or Reverence they intended him in this, they moſt diſdainfully ſpit in his Face,
<pb n="49" facs="unknown:001954_0054_0FBA43223B9163C0"/>
and buffeted him about, among them, from one to another: And with out doubt, he thought himſelf the wittieſt of the Company, who could deviſe the greateſt Affront. Thus was he injur'd and abus'd, who came into this World on the Kind Deſign of ſaving loſt Sinners: Thus was the King of Glory, the King, not of the Jews only, but of Heaven and Earth, mockt and deſpiſed by the vileſt of Men.</p>
               <p>When they had tired themſelves with this barbarous Sport, and how much rather him? They put his own Cloaths on him again, and led him away to crucifie him. And on him they laid the heavy and ignominious burthen of his Croſs, &amp; he muſt carry a long way, the Inſtrument of his Shame and Death to the place of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, but they had uſed him too ill before to leave him ſtill able to carry ſo heavy a Load; and after he had hardly carried it a little way, he fell under it. I ſee, O Son of God, in this thy; Fainting under the Croſs, a manifeſt proof that thou didſt really take our Nature upon thee, with the innocent Infirmities of it: And I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but admire and praiſe ſo wondrous a Condeſcenſion of the Almighty for our ſakes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They who uſed him ſo cruelly before, I muſt needs imagine, did not exerciſe any Compaſſion to him upon this occaſion. I abhor to think, how inhumanly, 'tis probable, they uſed him now. But they laid at laſt the Burden upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Shoulders; for now their Malice was in haſt to be rid of him.</p>
               <p>When he was come to the place of Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixion, they ſtript him of all his Cloaths, and
<pb n="50" facs="unknown:001954_0055_0FBA43271CF3F4F0"/>
expoſed the freſh Wounds which the rud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Scourge had given him, to the cold Air. They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid him upon his croſs, and violently ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out his Arms, and then drove a great Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> through each Hand: Thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faſtning to the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Beam of the Croſs, thoſe bleſſed Hands which had been uſed in the working many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> kind Miracle, but had never done any harm, and certainly deſerv'd a better uſage. Then they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e one or two great Nails through his Feet, and faſtned them to the upright Beam of the Croſs; thoſe Feet which had carried him di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently about his kind Buſineſs in the World<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which was to ſeek and to ſave loſt Sinners. This being done, they ſet the Croſs upright, that he might hang upon thoſe Nails, drove through thoſe very ſenſible Parts of his Body, in exquiſite Pain and Torture, and expoſed to the view and ſcorn of the Spectators: And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe reviled, inſulted over him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ided him here. It would even wound a Heart that has any tenderneſs to think that any one ſhould be uſed ſo cruelly: and one could ſcarce forbear to feel ſome pity and trouble at ſeeing even the moſt odious Malefactor in ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. But this was not a Malefactor, my Soul, but as thy Sins had made him one!</p>
               <p>This was the innocent Jeſus, who had done no Iniquity, neither was Guile found in his Mouth! This was thy Lover, thy Saviour, thy Friend that hung here; and all this he endured For thee. My Soul; if thou hadſt ſeen the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Jeſus thus hanging upon theſe Nails, and bleeding from his Head, and from his Hands,
<pb n="51" facs="unknown:001954_0056_0FBA43281741B088"/>
and from his Feet; and heard his Enemies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling him there, what Reſentments would'ſt thou have felt! Would not ſo ſad an Object have made thy Tears keep pace at leaſt with the drops of his moſt precious Blood? Would it not have made thee alſo ſmite thy Breaſt as ſome of the Spectators did? Couldſt thou ſee this, and not feel thoſe Wounds, and ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize with thoſe Pains he indured? When eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Wound might be underſtood to ſay, Sinner, behold how I love thee: All this I endure for thee: How then ſhould this Sacrament affect thee, which is a lively Memorial of his Death? What a deep ſence of thy Saviour's Love and Sufferings ſhould this create in thee? When he is here, as it were, evidently ſet forth cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified before thee; I ſee here his pale, wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, bloodleſs, broken Body; I ſee his Blood poured out, &amp; ſeparated from it. Canſt thou ſee this, and ſay, my Love is crucify'd, and think thou ſeeſt him crown'd with Thorns, All over daub'd with Dirt, and his Enemies filthy Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and his own Blood, and not be ſadly griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to think he was put to endure all this by his love of thee? Oh, crucified Jeſus, there was never Grief, there was never Love like thine! All this endured for me! This commands and &amp; deſerves, Oh let it cauſe my great Grief for, and my ardent Love to thee.</p>
               <p>But all this which afflicted his Body, was the leaſt part of the Sufferings he felt; he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r'd more, abundantly more, then all this in the Suffering of his Soul: For I muſt conſider fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that this Death of his was an accurſed
<pb n="52" facs="unknown:001954_0057_0FBA4329915D2120"/>
one in the account of the Jewiſh Law; that is, in the account of God himſelf; for it was he that had ordered and taught them to account it ſo; on purpoſe that it might foretel and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie before-hand, that the Redeemer of the World ſhould bear in his Death the Curſe and Puniſh- which the Divine Law had juſtly threatned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sins of Men. This then muſt call to thy mind the Sufferings of his Soul, <hi>He was made a Curſe for us,</hi> and <hi>God laid on him the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of us all.</hi> By men was he treated as a Malefactor, and by God too. The light of his Father's Countenance, and the pleaſing Aſpects of his Love, which had been always the Joy of his Soul, and the Reward of all his Labours in his ſervice, and till now had been conſtantly enjoy'd, was now, when he wanted it moſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn; when he was under his ſharp outward Sufferings, and when he was at the point of Death. And in making his Soul an Offering for Sin, he was afflicted and terrified with God's Almighty Wrath and Diſpleaſure. This made him cry out, who was ſilent before, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> He felt the Wrath which our Sins had deſerved. O terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing! Who can concieve what he endured? We may believe no Torments can exceed thoſe he felt in his Soul, except it be thoſe of Hell, if they do.</p>
               <p>Oh wounding Thought! This ſtabs and pierces my Soul: This tells me, It was not the cruel <hi>Jew</hi> or barbarous <hi>Roman</hi> Soldier that tormented, and killed the loving Jeſus, as the vile Sinner: It is I, among the reſt of Sinners,
<pb n="53" facs="unknown:001954_0058_0FBA432B116E8640"/>
gave him his cruelleſt Wounds his ſharpeſt Sorrows: It was I that wounded, that killed my Saviour and Friend: I ſhed his Life's moſt precious Blood. Was there ever ſuch a thing known beſides this? O Jeſu, there was never any Love like thine; and there is nothing ſo vile, ſo baſe as a Sinner: Greater love than this hath no man; that one lay down his Life for his Friend: But thou haſt laid down thine for Enemies, for thoſe that hated thee, yea for thoſe that killed thee: Thou art there on the Croſs deſpiſed, that I might be honoured: Thou art there in Pain, that I might be at eaſe: Thou art there hungry and thirſty, that I might be ſupplyed with all good things: Thou art there accurſed, that I might be bleſt; Thou art there deſerted by thy Fathers Favour and Love, that I might enjoy the Everlaſting delights of it: Thou art there dying, that I might live an everlaſting Life in Joy and Glory unſpeakable and eternal. O Jeſu! Was I more dear to thee than thine own Life? Was I to be rather indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged than thine own Eaſe, and more to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected than thine own Honour; What am I, Lord? Oh, what is Man, that thou art thus mindful of him? There was never Love like thine; none but a God could love thus! Oh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorable Myſtery! Oh Wonder of Wonders. Thy Greatneſs is unſearchable, thy Love is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, and thy ways are paſt finding out! With profoundeſt reverence I adore thy Incomprehenſible Love: I leave off to fathom what I can never reach, and will give up my ſelf to praiſe and admire for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb n="54" facs="unknown:001954_0059_0FBA432CA9BA57B0"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XIV.</hi> An Exerciſe of <hi>REPENTANCE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAve I indeed given my kind and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Saviour ſo much Grief by my Sins, and ſhall they give me none? <hi>Oh that my Head were Waters, and my Eyes a Fountain of Tears,</hi> to drench my filthy polluted Soul! But alas! it is not all the Tears that I am able to ſhed which could ever make me clean, or waſh out the ſtain of any, the leaſt of my Sins! Oh! I am become, it ſeems, ſo exceeding foul, and have contracted Stains of ſuch a nature, that nothing but this precious Stream, my Saviours Life's Blood, can cleanſe me! How am I fallen from the Dignity and Honour of my Creation; I was made little lower then the Angels by my bounteous Creator; but I have made my ſelf more vile than the Beaſts that periſh. I was made ſubject to no Creature, not bound to pay any Homage or Service towards the glorious Angles, though made lower than them; but alas, I have made my ſelf a Slave to the abject, Devil, I have refuſed to ſerve God my Maker and Friend, and have drudged for my mortal Enemy. Oh wretched Man that I am! I have ſought his Service, while I have declined thine; and run after his Temptations, while I have endeavoured to evade thy Commands. Oh, I have been forward to Evil, and backward to all that is Good: I have combined with my Soul's great Enemy, to haſten and increaſe my Damnation.</p>
               <p>Infinite Goodneſs! How unjuſtly, how baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="55" facs="unknown:001954_0060_0FBA432E465F60D0"/>
art thom requited for all thy bounteous Love to Mankind! Who can conceive or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the vileneſs, the Enormity of Sin! Which is a Contempt of thy infinite Majeſty, a Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt thy unqueſtionable Authority, and Abuſe of thy free Goodneſs, a Defiance of thy Almighty Power, a denial of thy incomparable Wiſdom, and an Affront to all thy Glorious Attributes: Which is contrary to that Honour and Homage whieh I owe thee as thy Creature. Wo is me that I ſhould ever offend my Maker! So liberal and ſo gracious a Father! Wo is me that I ſhould ſlight and affront the Love of Jeſus my Redeemer, as I have done in cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe vile Sins that he came to deſtroy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Oh Jeſus, at what a coſtly Rate haſt thou lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, and merited my Love! And how loth, how ſlow am I to entertain the Love of thee: Thou haſt loved, where thy Hatred has been deſerved; and I, vile wretch, have hated him that has infinitely deſerved my Love. Thy Love to me me has been a vaſt Condeſcenſion, and has cauſed thy Humility and Abaſement; yet wouldeſt thou love the Unworthy: But my Love to thee would have been my Honour and Glory, my everlaſting Advancement; yet have I been unwilling to love thee. Wo is me, I have been obſtinate in Wickedneſs! Oh, how have I grieved the Holy Spirit, in neglecting, reſiſting, and oppoſing his good and kind Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in my Soul; turning a deaf Ear to his gentle Admonitions, and refuſing to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and healed, Oh my God, in our Sins we deſpiſe thy Will, and do our own! We diſown
<pb n="56" facs="unknown:001954_0061_0FBA432F8CB9FEE0"/>
thee, and make Gods of our ſelves. In our Sins we believe the great Deceiver before the God of Truth; and follow his deluſive Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, rather than thy rich and faithful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. In our Sins we prefer Earth before Heaven, the Creature before the Creator; and reckon there is more Happineſs in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome of them, than in the Enjoyment of Thee, the infinite Fountain of Good.</p>
               <p>Oh how vile, how enormous a thing is Sin! Who can ſufficiently hate it! I ſee O Lord, in the terrible Sufferings of my Saviour, thy migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Diſpleaſure againſt the Sins of Men, and it terrifies me to think of it. I plainly ſee how odious they are to the Divine Purity; in that ſo worthy and great a Perſon, he who is ſo well and juſtly beloved of the Father, was ſorely afflicted by the Father himſelf, when he bore the Sins of Mankind. I ſee thy hatred, O Lord, againſt my Sins; I believe it very juſt, and I cannot chuſe but hate them too, I will hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth <hi>hate every falſe way, but thy Law will I love.</hi> I will love thy Righteouſneſs and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and utterly abhor what is ſo contrary to it, as my Sins. I will account it my greateſt Honour to conform to thee, and will abandon and be aſhamed to be found in the moſt credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, or moſt applauded Sins in the World. Henceforth will all Sin have a moſt deformed and ugly Viſage to my Eye; I ſhall never think any one charming; I ſhall never account any one worthy to be deſired.</p>
               <p>But when I conſider, O Lord, the courſe of my paſt Life; when I look into thy Commands,
<pb n="57" facs="unknown:001954_0062_0FBA43323AC8EB70"/>
and compare with them my Thoughts, and Words, and Actions, Oh what a mortifying View does this Examination preſent me! Oh wretched Creature, I am confounded, I am fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Indignation againſt my ſelf, when I ſee how much I have had to do with this vile, this odious thing! Wo is me, and how many are my Tranſgreſſions! They are, alas, <hi>more in number than the Hairs of my Head, and my Heart</hi> even <hi>fails me</hi> when I review them. I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in every Age of my Life, ever ſince I could know or chuſe my Actions! Oh wretched Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, how early did I begin to Sin againſt thee! How many have been the unheeded Actions of my Life! The moſt of which, I much fear, have been wicked, ſince they proceeded from one ſo prone to do Evil as I. And how many more muſt the Sins of my words in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood have been, eſpecially while I did not ſet any watch upon my Tongue, nor keep the door of my Lips. And when I think how eaſie and abundantly the light Mind multiplies thoughts, I tremble to think how my vain, fooliſh, vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Mind has multiplied Trangreſſions too. Lord, <hi>who can underſtand his Errors</hi>! I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed at the Number of my Sins: I have ſinned, alas, againſt thee in every Circumſtance and Condition of my Life. I have ſinned in every Relation towards Men; not doing that Honour, not paying that Juſtice, not exerciſing that charity to my Neighbour which I ought. I can view none of thy Commands, but it calls to mind many Sins I have been guilty of. Very often have I repeated the ſame Sins; <hi>returning</hi> to
<pb n="58" facs="unknown:001954_0063_0FBA4333A3DBB3E8"/>
them, <hi>as the Dog to</hi> the filthineſs of <hi>his vomit</hi>; and, <hi>as the Swine wallowing in the mire.</hi> I have ſinned againſt thy Law, and againſt the Goſpel: Oh, how cold reception have I given to the Offers of thy Grace and Mercy! How have I neglected the great Salvation! Trampled upon the Blood of the Covenant, and deſpiſed my Saviour's dying redeeming Love! Oh how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of other Mens Sins have I been guilty of! By my ill Example; by giving them needleſs and unjuſt Provocation; by tempting and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring them to Sin; by aſſiſting what I ought to have hindred; by conniving where I ought have beſtowed reproofs; and by countenancing and abbetting what I ought to have corrected and diſcouraged. I cannot, alas, pretend to have done any good Action without a Mixture of Evil in it: My beſt Works need the Blood of Chriſt to cleanſe them, and make them fit to be preſented unto thee: And indeed I want that Blood to waſh even the Tears of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. What a mighty Charge am I able to draw up againſt my ſelf! [<hi>Here thou may'ſt particularly mention thoſe Sins thou art ſenſible of</hi>] But thou, O Lord, knoweſt me better than I do my ſelf; and I dread to think how much more thou canſt add to the heavieſt Charge that I can bring againſt my ſelf.</p>
               <p>I have been ſo vile as to Sin deliberately a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee; to do Evil, knowing that I did Evil. I have been eaſily induced to Sin; the ſlighteſt Temptations have prevailed with me; I have been, alas, accuſtomed to do Evil. O Lord, thou haſt exerciſed wonderful Patience
<pb n="59" facs="unknown:001954_0064_0FBA433803455378"/>
and Forbearance towards me in a long train and courſe of ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing; and I have been ſo baſe and ungrateful as to encourage my ſelf to tranſgreſs by that Patience which ſhould have led me to Repentance.</p>
               <p>O wretched and vile Creature that I am, I have greatly ſinned, I am become exceeding guilty! What ſhall I ſay unto thee; Oh thou preſerver of Men. I will lay myſelf down in the Duſt before thee. I am at thy Mercy, O Lord, and muſt own that I have deſerved the utmoſt ſeverity of thy Wrath. In the ſad Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Jeſus I ſee what my Sins have deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I ſee in his Contempt how I have deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be deſpiſed. I ſee in his Thirſt upon the Croſs how I have deſerved the want of all things comfortable. I ſee in his Agony, and by his Groans under the Divine Wrath, what Diſpleaſure and Puniſhment I have deſerved to ſuffer. I ſee in his accurſed Death that I have deſerved to die, and be Eternally accurſed and caſt out of the Divine Favour. O Lord, I am unworthy, utterly unworthy to breath in this Air of thine, to inhabit this Earth; to enjoy this chearful Light. I am leſs than the leaſt of all thy Mercies. I muſt judge, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn my ſelf, I muſt own thou wert juſt, and I ſhould have but my deſerts, if I were now ſhut up in gloomy darkneſs; if I were now wrapt in everlaſting Flames; if I were feeling the Torments of the never-dying Worm, and of endleſs bitter Deſpair.</p>
               <p>Lord, I will puniſh, I will take vengeance on my ſelf for my Sins. I will lead a life of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification
<pb n="60" facs="unknown:001954_0065_0FBA433D0F1BEF68"/>
rather than Indulgence; I will never allow again any high or admiring Thoughts of my ſelf. It ſhall always keep me humble, to think how great diſparagement and vileneſs I have contracted! To conſider my ſelf a Sinner, and that there is Imperfection and Sin mixed with the beſt of my Actions.</p>
               <p>But, O Lord, I beſeech thee do not thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Judgment with thy Servant, for in thy fight ſhall no man living be Juſtified. Oh deal not with me after my Sins; neither reward me after my Iniquities. Bleſſed is the Man whoſe Iniquity is forgiven, whoſe Sin is covered. Spare me, good Lord; ſpare thy Creature whom thou haſt redeemed with thy moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood! Oh ſpare the miſerable Wretch that confeſſes his Faults; reſtore thou him that is penitent. Pity thou him that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite: Revive the Spirit of the humble; chear the contrite Heart: <hi>A broken and a contrite Heart, O God thou wilt not deſpiſe. Give me,</hi> then, <hi>the joy of thy Salvation; uphold me with thy free Spirit: Then will I teach Tranſgreſſors thy ways, and Sinners ſhall be converted unto thee. Open thou my Lips, O Lord, &amp; my Mouth ſhall ſhew forth thy Praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XV.</hi> An Exerciſe of good Reſolutions.</head>
               <p>OH Crucified Jeſus! Great Martyr of Love! I cannot chuſe but acknowledge, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire and praiſe the exceeding Greatneſs of thy
<pb n="61" facs="unknown:001954_0066_0FBA433ED6F9AB08"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ying Love! Much it is, O Lord, that I reckon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſelf beholden to thee: and what, O what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall I render unto the Lord for all his Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs and Benefits! Lord, when I ranſack my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore, I am aſhamed, I am utterly abaſht to find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow poor it is. Oh, what can a Creature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urn to his Maker? What can I give, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave nothing to give? who am nothing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat I derived from thee? Thy Goodneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eed is ſuch, that thou requireſt no more than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e are able to render, and with that thou art <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell pleaſed: But that, O Lord, is ſo little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat I cannot be ſatisfied with it. O let thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulneſs of all Excellent Grace, thy Fulneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ove fill me with all true Excellency and Love, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat I may be the better and the worthier Gift to thee.</p>
               <p>Deareſt Jeſu! For the Love of thee I readily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enounce all the flattering Vanities of this World, all the moſt neceſſary Enjoyments of it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat I may ſteadily honour and enjoy thee: I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccount all things but Loſs and Dung, &amp; will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot count my Life dear, that I may finiſh my Courſe of Duty with Joy, and may win Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But eſpecially, O Lord, for love of thee I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o here utterly renounce, abdicate and abhor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my moſt darling Sins. And it grieves me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat I ſhould ever be ſo baſe as to entertain any Rivals of the Loving Jeſus in my Heart. O Lord, I hate them ſo much the more now, by how much the more I have formerly loved them. I will utterly caſt them out of my Heart; no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore ſhall they harbour there; no longer will
<pb n="62" facs="unknown:001954_0067_0FBA43401CEFF198"/>
I entertain, no longer cheriſh thoſe thine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. What! Can I be kind to the bloody Crucifiers of my Lord! See, my Soul; ſee theſe Murderers all daubed with the Blood of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy Saviour. Away from me ye hateful Things: We will now inſtantly part, never, I hope, to meet again, never to be accquainted more. Be gone without delay; I will thruſt you out of my Soul; you have no right to abide here. Jeſus alone has right to poſſeſs and rule me. Away vile Envy, I cannot endure the ſight of thee: Be gone my Covetouſneſs: My Malice I hate thee: My Senſuality I will ſtarve thee:, My Pride I will humble thee; My Idleneſs thou haſt made me ſo much work to do, that I am reſolved, I ſee it abſolutely neceſſary, to baniſh thee forever from me. All my Luſts &amp; vile Affections be gone; ye ſhall have no more kind uſage here; do not expect it.</p>
               <p>Jeſus has all my Love, I have none for you, I am all his, I am no more for ye. Be gone, ye hateful Tyrants of my Soul. Jeſus, a kind and gracious Maſter, impoſes gentle Tasks, but you lay heavy burdens upon me: His <hi>Yoke is eaſie, and his Burden light</hi>; but your Commands are rigorous and intolerable. Jeſus has ſhown me great and wondrous Love: Ye promiſe me much ſatisfaction and kindneſs, but perform nothing. No, ye have cheated and deceived me: Ye have robbed me of my Peace, robbed me of my Dignity, and Glory, and which is more, ye have robbed me of the Favour of my God. What can you do for me, if you ſhould do all that you promiſe, which is never to be
<pb n="63" facs="unknown:001954_0068_0FBA43419F68E8A8"/>
expected, that is comparable with what he can do for me; what he is willing, and has faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully promiſed to do for me, if I will but hate and forſake you; or with what Jeſus has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done to teſtifie his Good-will and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to me. Jeſus made himſelf of no Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for my ſake, and that he might advance me to the Higheſt Honour: But ye would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe me to the utmoſt Contempt of God, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Devils: Jeſus has died for me that I might live for ever, but ye would kill me; Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus rules to ſave, but you to deſtroy. His Rewards are Eternal Life and Happineſs, but your Wages is Death and Miſery everlaſting. When I come to die, what fruit, what comfort can I expect from you? Alas, all that you could ever gain will leave me then, if it be not gone before, and I muſt go a poor, naked, friendleſs Stranger into the Eternal World; yea, for your ſakes I muſt, if I do not caſt you off, appear a hated guilty Rebel before my Lord and Judge, and be expoſed to all the Terrours of Divine Wrath. But the Love of Jeſus will not then forſake me: Neither Tribulation, Diſtreſs, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, nor Death it ſelf ſhall ever ſeperate me from the Love of Jeſus if I will but be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced from you. And Jeſus is King of the other World, and will ſend his kind Angels to receive my departing Soul, out of the mean Tabernacle of my Body, and to conduct it to a glorious Manſion: To welcome it from the Miſeries of this ſinful World, to congratulate my happy Victory over you my Enemies, and carry me in Triumph to a Place of Bliſs, and
<pb n="64" facs="unknown:001954_0069_0FBA434332CC8440"/>
to be with Chriſt. Can I then ſo much abandon my Reaſon, ſo much miſtake my Intereſt, as to have any more to do with you.</p>
               <p>Oh Lord, the great Redeemer have Mercy upon me, and deliver me from theſe tyrannous Maſters. Thy Service is perfect freedom; in keeping thy Commands there is greater Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Set my Soul, I pray, at liberty to run the ways of thy Commandments. As for theſe thine Enemies and mine, bring them forth and let them be ſlain before thee: Root them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly out of my Heart. Let them from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth be in a decaying languiſhing Condition, never thrive more, and quickly die. I will never be ſatisfied till I ſee them utterly depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of all Motion, Senſe and Life. Oh Jeſu, thy Croſs, thy Nails. thy Spear are due to theſe: Let them from thence receive many mortal Wounds, that thou mayeſt never be diſpleaſed, nor I troubled or diſparaged with them any more.</p>
               <p>O crucified Love, thou haſt prevented me by thy Love, and infinitely exceeded all that I can return: But I will learn of thee to love, and follow thee as well as I can. Thou haſt given thy ſelf for me on the Croſs, and giveſt thy ſelf to me in this Sacrament: Behold, O Lord I offer my ſelf to thee, my whole ſelf, I offer and bring thee all the Faculties of my Soul, all the Members of my Body· I offer my Senſes and my Paſſions: I offer all my Thoughts, my Words, and my Actions,: I offer all my Deſigns and Endeavours: All the Labours of my worldly Calling: all the Adorations of
<pb n="65" facs="unknown:001954_0070_0FBA43448E432F20"/>
my Worſhip and Devotions. I offer thee all my Poſſeſſions in the World; all the Perſons that I can command and influence to worſhip, honour and ſerve thee. I offer thee all the Days of my Life; I offer thee my Death when thou wilt pleaſe to require it; and both li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and dying I deſire to be thine. I deſire to be intirely thine. Oh how dearly haſt thou bought this poor Gift! Never was ſo great a Price, beſide this, paid for any Creature. I will live to my Love that dyed for me. I will henceforth look upon my ſelf as a devoted conſecrated thing, and will ever <hi>endeavour to remain ſo,</hi> and to carry my ſelf as ſuch. I will <hi>never</hi> be willingly employ'd but as thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeſt and as thou alloweſt. Lord, for thy ſake I will love thy Law, and it ſhall be my meditation all the day. I will love thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments above Gold, and all falſe ways I will utterly abhor. Dearer ſhall thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments be to me than thouſands of Gold and Silver, and ſweeter than Honey from the Comb. I will love nothing but what <hi>Thou loveſt,</hi> and will hate whatever is diſpleaſing to thee.</p>
               <p>I am heartily grieved, O Lord, that I have <hi>ever loved any thing</hi> but thee, while I neglected to love thee. I am heartily aſhamed to think that I ſhould place no Affection, where all I could offer is but due, and beſtow all where little or none is due. Eſpecially does it <hi>vex</hi> and <hi>grieve</hi> me that I ſhould be ſo monſtrouſly ungrateful and miſtaken, as to love any thing more than the <hi>loving Jeſus.</hi> Hereafter deareſt
<pb n="66" facs="unknown:001954_0071_0FBA4346483E5618"/>
Lord, I purpoſe to love nothing but far below thee, and for thy ſake whatever I do love: And what is moſt like thee, or moſt ſerviceable to thy Honour and Glory, ſhall have the moſt of my <hi>Love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Henceforth it ſhall be my honour that I am a <hi>Servant of Jeſus</hi>; it ſhall be my delight and pleaſure to be a <hi>Lover of Jeſus</hi>; it ſhall be my moſt valued Wealth that he is mine, and I am his. <hi>Whom have I in heaven but thee, O Lord, and there is none in Earth that I can deſire in compariſon to thee.</hi> And therefore nothing can be ſo ſweet to me; nothing can afford me ſo much ſatisfaction and joy, as to be able to ſay of thee, <hi>My beloved is mine and I am his.</hi> For me to be thine, O Jeſu, is my Honour, my Security, my Peace and Happineſs everlaſting. For thee to be mine is health to my Soul, ſtrength to do thy Commandments; it is Joy unſpeakable and full of Glory; it is Heaven on earth, and the Heaven of Heaven; It is Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption to me, O rich and bouuteous Love. I am thine, O Lord, with all my Soul, that thou mayſt be mine. Oh how much ſhall I gain by giving my ſelf to thee; I ſhall gain myſelf, and be ſaved from everlaſting Perdition, and I ſhall gain everlaſting happineſs in the enjoyment of thee.</p>
               <p>I am thine, O Jeſu; ſave me, I have ſought thy Precepts, Lord, ſanctifie me wholly, that in Body, Soul and Spirit, I may be thine: Take a full poſſeſſion of me for the future; and let not any other Lord have dominion over me.
<pb n="67" facs="unknown:001954_0072_0FBA4347E63A7408"/>
O Lord, <hi>I have ſworn and I will perform it, that I will keep thy righteous Judgments.</hi> I purpoſe to be <hi>stedfast unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, as knowing that my labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord.</hi> I am thine, diſpoſe of me as thou pleaſeſt: I will bear thy Yoke, I will not decline thy Croſs, I will not deſpiſe thy ſhame: The reproach of Chriſt ſhall be to me greater riches than the proſperity of this World. Let but thy Grace be ſufficient for me, and then call me to what thou ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt: I can do all things through Chriſt's ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of me. Lord, I ſhall not, I hope, fear or decline to ſuffer for thy ſake: No: though I ſhould die for thee, I purpoſe not to deny thee. But, alas, it troubles me to think how weak and vain all my reſolutions are, and how ſoon they will come to nothing without thy conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual ſupport and aſſiſtance. This troubles me; but it is my comfort, that thy Grace is eaſily obtained; it may be now had for asking of it: O ſhield me with thy Grace againſt all tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: <hi>Hold up my goings in thy word, that my footſteps ſlip not: Guide thou me by thy counſel, till thou haſt brought me to thy glory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XVI.</hi> An Exerciſe of <hi>FAITH.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Believe there is only one true and living God; who is the Father, the Son, and Holy Ghoſt; an infinite, eternal, perfect being; the Maker and Preſerver, Owner and Governour of all things. Who has right to the Homage, Worſhip and Obedience of Mankind: Who
<pb n="68" facs="unknown:001954_0073_0FBA434E08081378"/>
has laid upon us his Laws, and takes notice of our Behaviour; that his eyes behold all the Dwellers upon Earth, and try the children of men; That he is always nigh to every one of us, for it is in him that we live, move, and have our being. I believe, O Lord, that thou <hi>art, and art a Rewarder of thoſe that diligently ſeek thee:</hi> Thou haſt appointed a day wherein thou wilt judge the World in Righteouſneſs, and render to every man according to his works: That thoſe who are found wicked in that Day ſhall go away into everlaſting Puniſhment, but the righteous into Life Eternal.</p>
               <p>But I believe alſo, that <hi>to the Lord our God belong Mercies and forgiveneſſes, though we have rebelted againſt him,</hi> if in the way of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment we ſeek his pardoning Mercy. Thou haſt, O Lord, bleſſed be thy Name, proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy ſelf a God, forgiving Iniquity, Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion and Sin: And declareſt, that thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt not the Death of a Sinner, but had rather that he ſhould turn from his wickedneſs and live. O wonderful condeſcenſion and goodneſs! O how ſweet is thy mercy! How glorious and great! The exceeding vileneſs, and the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of our Sins, do magnifie thy Mercy beyond all comprehenſion and praiſe. Favour and Forgiveneſs to a baſe Sinner, is that the Sinner could not expect till thou hadſt decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it ſhould be obtained, and didſt graciouſly offer it.</p>
               <p>When we here ſunk into the moſt abject miſery by a moſt vile rebellion againſt thee; had rendred our ſelves obnoxious to thy Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="69" facs="unknown:001954_0074_0FBA434FEA0B36D0"/>
Hatred and Wrath, and deſerved to follow the Apoſtate Angels in their Fate and Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as we had followed them in rebellion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then did thy infinite Wiſdom contrive how to ſhew us favour in a way conſiſtent with thine own honour: Thou didſt find out a way to ſpare us, and to puniſh our Sins; to glorify thy Juſtice in taking vengeance on our inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and thy Mercy in ſaving the wretched Sinners: And <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believes in him, ſhall not periſh but have everlaſting Life.</hi> Thou gaveſt, O Father, thine only begotten Son to the condeſcenſion and meanneſs of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our Nature upon him; and to die a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for our Sins; and on him thy well beloved Son, didſt thou lay the iniquities of us all. And in his death thou haſt received a full, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and ſufficient Sacrifice, Oblation and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for the Sins of the whole world. Thou haſt laid our help on one that is mighty, and able to ſave to the utmoſt all that come unto God by him. We adore thy incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible Goodneſs and Compaſſion to Sinners! Thou art abundant, O God, in Goodneſs and Truth!</p>
               <p>Thy Mercy is over all thy works: In Mercy thou haſt great delight: We remember the glorious Exerciſes of it: We know, O Lord thou canſt pardon the greateſt Offences; for thou haſt pardon'd very great Sinners: <hi>David</hi> was forgiven his baſe Murder and Adultery; <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh</hi> his horrid Idolatry, and filling <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> with innocent Blood; The vile Adultereſs
<pb n="70" facs="unknown:001954_0075_0FBA435150D0B7D0"/>
                  <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi>; The Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied and diſowned thee with an Oath; the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Saul,</hi> who blaſphemed thee himſelf, and being exceedingly mad againſt thee, compelled others to blaſpheme: All theſe are Monuments of thy glorious forgiving Mercy. O what comfortable, what joyful hopes have we in ſuch Goodneſs!</p>
               <p>We know, that having given us thy Son, thou wilt not deny us any thing that is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to our Salvation: But if we ask, we ſhall receive; if we ſeek, we ſhall find; if we knock it ſhall be opened to us. On that ranſome which my Saviour has paid for me, and on all thy gracious promiſes which for his ſake thou haſt made, I do wholly and firmly rely. With an humble confidence, O Lord, that we may find favour wïth thee, we remember before thee in this Sacrament the bleeding Wounds of thy dear Son and his precious Death, our rich Sacrifice for Sin. We remember before thee, and preſent unto thee, him whom thou haſt ſet forth to be a propitiation thro' Faith in his Blood. And in his Name, relying upon the value and acceptance of his Sacrifice. I, thy poor unworthy Servant, humbly preſent my ſelf before the Throne of thy Grace to ſeek thy favour, begging leave that I may claim thy gracious promiſes, which in him are <hi>Yea,</hi> and in him <hi>Amen</hi>: And that I may now entertain and delight my ſelf with the glorious Hopes which they afford. I deſire, I hope that thou wilt fully forgive my manifold and great Tranſgreſſions. I deſire, I hope that thou wilt
<pb n="71" facs="unknown:001954_0076_0FBA4355DB1ABC68"/>
give me thy holy Spirit, which thou haſt promiſed to give to them that ask thee. O grant me that Spirit to cleanſe me from all unrighteouſneſs, to purifie my polluted Soul; to take away all the filthy ſtains of my Sins; to ſtrengthen my weakneſs in Temptations; to be my ſupport and comforter under Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements and Afflictions; to aſſiſt me in all my Duties; to guide my way and ſecure my perſeverance to the end. Thou, O Lord, who ſearcheſt the hearts, and tryeſt the reins of Men, well knoweſt, wherein my greateſt weakneſs lies; Lord ſtrengthen me in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, I beſeech thee, againſt mine own Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. I deſire, I hope thou wilt graciouſly keep me unſpotted from the world: Keep me from following any of the Errors and Vices that ſhall ever be in Vogue with the giddy and wicked Multitude. I deſire, I hope, that thou wilt mercifully defend me againſt the Wiles &amp; Devices of my Soul's great Adverſary the Devil. I humbly commit my ſelf to thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious keeping, Oh faithful Creator.</p>
               <p>I deſire, I hope, O Lord, that thou wilt bleſs me with health, and with a competent proviſion of what is needful for me of the good things of this World; and defend me, if it pleaſe thee, from poverty, dependance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. Give me neither poverty nor riches, but feed me with food convenient for me. I know, O Lord, Man is <hi>born to trouble as the ſparks fly upwards</hi>; that Sin entering into this World, has brought miſery and affliction with it; and that our folly and perverſeneſs
<pb n="72" facs="unknown:001954_0077_0FBA43575FE106A8"/>
commonly needs ſuch diſcipline to make us wiſe and good. I deſire to ſubmit to whatever it ſhall pleaſe thee to order for me; to ſay always after the example of my Saviour, <hi>Lord, not my Will, but thine be done.</hi> I hope thou wilt deal with me according to thy Mercy, and lay upon me no more than thou wilt inable me to bear. I believe thou mayſt do me great good by my afflictions; I pray thee ſanctify them all to the promoting my Soul's health, and my everlaſting happineſs: And give me, I pray thee, an humble reſignation, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible patience, that I may neither deſpiſe the chaſtning of the Lord, nor faint when I am rebuked of him: Let me always incourage my ſelf with this aſſurance, that theſe light afflictions, which are but for a moment, if they be patiently born, ſhall <hi>work for me a far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory.</hi> I deſire, I hope thou wilt direct and enable me ſo to paſs thro' things Temporal, as that I may not finally loſe the things Eternal. That by thy conduct and guidance I may at laſt arrive ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to that happy World where the weary are at reſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here the wicked ceaſe from troubling, where ſorrow and ſighing, and pain and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and fear and care ſhall all be baniſhed; all tears ſhall be forever wiped from our eyes, and we ſhall enjoy thee, and all that we can deſire in perfect Bliſs, and eternal Safety and Quiet.</p>
               <p>This is a true ſaying, and worthy of all men to be received, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave Sinners.</hi> Lord, I receive it;
<pb n="73" facs="unknown:001954_0078_0FBA435CF7E65D20"/>
Lord, I believe, help thou my unbelief, I believe O Jeſu, thou art Chriſt the Son of the living God, that ſhould come into the World. O tender and condeſcending Love, how dear is that bleſſed Name to me! Jeſus my Saviour; O how full of ſweetneſs is it, as a rich perfume! Thy Name is as oyntment poured forth! O be thou ever <hi>Jeſus</hi> to me. To thee, O Lord, I fly as a refuge from the juſt wrath of God I have deſerved; as able to conquer all my ſpiritual Enemies; as willing to receive into thy protection all that come unto thee. <hi>Oh Lamb of God that takeſt away the ſins of the world,</hi> have mercy upon my poor Soul; grant me thy peace. Thou inviteſt thoſe that are weary and heavy laden to come unto thee: Behold, Lord, I come, let me find reſt to my Soul.</p>
               <p>I come to partake of the happineſs of being united to thee in this Sacrament. I believe, O Lord, the Truth of all thy promiſes, and the vertue and power of all thine Ordinances: And that the Bread we break, and the Cup we drink in this Sacrament, are not bear Signs, but real Inſtruments of conveyance, and the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of thy Body and Blood; I come then, that I may receive thy Body and Blood; may be intereſted in the Merits of thy paſſion; that I may partake of thy Spirit, and be intituled to the Heavenly Inheritance, which thou haſt purchaſed for poor loſt Sinners. I come to make a thankful remembrance of thy Death, which thou didſt kindly ſubmit to for the advantage of Mankind: And by thy Death I hope to have Life everlaſting.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="unknown:001954_0079_0FBA435EDD73A088"/>I gladly embrace, O Lord, the offers of thy Goſpel. I deſire thee to ſubdue in me all my rebellious Luſts and vile Affections, and as a King to rule over me, I will account it my honour to be thy meaneſt ſubject. I deſire thee to afford me thy heavenly Inſtructions; teach me as a Prophet, and make me wiſe to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thro' Faith that is in thee. I deſire thee to interceed for me as a Prieſt in the vertue of thy moſt valuable Sacrifice; and to beſtow upon me the large Bleſſings which thou haſt purchaſed for ſinners. I believe, O Lord, thou haſt died for our ſins and art riſen again for our Juſtification, I deſire thy death may ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly crucifie and kill all my ſins; and that thy Reſurrection may revive my hopes. By thy Reſurrection I deſire, I hope for mine: By thy Aſcenſion into Heaven, I deſire thee to draw my heart and affections from this vain empty World, to the hearty love and earneſt deſire of heavenly things: And I hope thou wilt raiſe me up at the laſt day, and bring me to be where thou art, and give me an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life. I take this Sacrament as a pledge of thy everlaſting Love; as the evidence of Love already ſhown me, and the earneſt and aſſurance of yet greater communications to come.</p>
               <p>My Soul thirſts for God, even for the living God: Oh when ſhall I come and appear before God! When ſhall I ſee thy Face, O dear Jeſus, without a veil; be kiſs'd with the Kiſſes of thy Mouth, enjoy thy ſelf immediately? When ſhall theſe ſhort and faint glimpſes of thy Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be exchanged for a full abiding ſight of
<pb n="75" facs="unknown:001954_0080_0FBA436051BD8CB8"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hee? When ſhall I leave not only to viſit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut to dwell with thee, and to receive, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anſient taſts, but drink large draughts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elight and joy from an infinite fountain of liſs and joy: For in thy <hi>preſence is fulneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oy, and at thy right hand are pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore.</hi> Oh, how I long that this my weary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilgrimage were done: That I were abſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom the Body, that I might be preſent with the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That I might have no neceſſary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, deareſt Jeſu, from perpetual contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating, praiſing, loving and enjoying thee. For this, however, I do wait; This I do thro' thy merits, and from thy infinite love expect; and that expectation ſhall encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage me to labour in thy Service, to bear thy Croſs, and to follow thee whitherſoever thou ſhalt call me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XVII.</hi> An Exerciſe of <hi>CHARITY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Jeſu, thou art infinite Love! I cannot but with great delight and wonder con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template thee; and when I do ſo, I feel a pleaſing conſtraint upon me to love. I muſt account this a moſt excellent and divine Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification, which is ſo eminent in thee: I muſt reckon it my greateſt honour to be conformed to the Son of God; and therefore I muſt ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſlike and hate my ſelf for any defect of Love I find in my ſelf. Beſides, when I think how much I am loved; how much th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and bounteous Love has given, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="76" facs="unknown:001954_0081_0FBA4361D4D97A88"/>
it has forgiven to me, I am forc'd to account my ſelf baſe and extreamly unworthy of this, if I do not love much.</p>
               <p>I will put on, then, the moſt extenſive Charity that I can: I will wiſh well, and do good to all men as far as I have power, and as oft as I have opportunity to do it: I will love my Neighbour as my ſelf; and account him my Neighbour who has any need of my kindneſs, and to whom I have it in my power to do any office of kindneſs, whoſoever he be. Thou, O bleſſed Jeſu, haſt loved the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Wretches! I then, will account none unworthy of my love and good will. Thou haſt loved thoſe that were infinitely below thee, and haſt mightily condeſcended to do them kindneſs. I will never account it below me therefore to do an Office of kindneſs to my meaneſt Neighbour; but rather the greater the condeſcenſion is in the doing it, the more I will value the opportunity of ſhowing therein the greater likeneſs and gratitude to thee. Thou, Lord, haſt loved thoſe that are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unprofitable to thee; and from whom thou canſt never receive a parallel return of Love: I will be aſhamed, then, as I moſt juſtly may, to beſtow no Benefits but where I have received, or expect to receive ſome.</p>
               <p>Thou, O Jeſu, haſt loved even thine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and prayed for thoſe that <hi>deſpitefully uſed and perſecuted thee</hi>: And this is a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious pattern which I intend by the aſſiſtance of thy Grace, to imitate. As for all that have injur'd me by word or deed, O Lord, I
<pb n="77" facs="unknown:001954_0082_0FBA4365916F93C8"/>
forgive them, and I pray thee to forgive them. I am more ſorry for their Error and Sin, than I am at any loſs or damage, which is come, or may come to me by their injury: Lord have mercy upon their Souls; forgive my enemies, perſecutors and ſlanderers, and turn their hearts. I deſire no harm to any that are my enemies, if any be ſo: Nor will I rejoyce over them when they fall, but rather grieve to ſee it; much leſs will I ever ſeek their harm or miſchief. And I purpoſe on the contrary, notwithſtanding all their unkindneſs, to do them all the good Offices which I can; conſiſtently with a due care of my own ſafety, and with other obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and duties to thee, or to others of my Neighbours. I purpoſe to ſtudy, and ſeek to do them good: To return bleſſing for curſing, reſpect for contempt, and good for evil: That I may, if it be poſſible, <hi>overcome evil with good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As it is the character of Charity, not to be forward to think evil, I will take care that no uncharitable Jealouſies or Suſpicions of my Neighbour may repreſent him my enemy who is not ſo: I will take care not to interpret a miſtake into a malicious deſign; or that which is intended as a kindneſs into an injury: But will always endeavour to take all his words and actions in the beſt ſenſe, and put the beſt interpretation upon them all that I can: Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially will I do thus by the Magiſtrate, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bound to it by the obligation to reverence and honour him, as well as by the Laws of Charity; and becauſe it is neceſſary and uſeful
<pb n="78" facs="unknown:001954_0083_0FBA4366B0FA7F78"/>
to the publick peace and welfare, and ſo is in its effects a Charity to others of my Neighbours too.</p>
               <p>I thank thee, O Lord, for all the kindneſs of my friends, and for thoſe that have done me any good: I pray thee, O bounteous Love, abundantly to requite them in this world and the next; in temporal and eternal Bleſſings continue or encreaſe their ſtore and worldly proſperity, if it may be good for them; and eſpecially bleſs them with Spiritual Bleſſings in heavenly things. I will endeavour as far as lies in my power, in what I can do for their outward eſtate, or for their Souls, always to expreſs a moſt grateful ſenſe of their kindneſs. I will not deſpiſe the love of the meaneſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, much rather will I thakfully reſent the condeſcending favours of thoſe that are above one.</p>
               <p>I make my humble ſupplications to thee now, O Lord, at a good time, for all Mankind: I recommend to thy infinite Mercy all <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi> Oh let them that ſit in darkneſs ſee thy marvellous light, and be turned from the power of Satan unto God: That the earth might be filled with the knowledge of the Lord, as waters cover the ſea. Let thy Goſpel of Holineſs, Peace and Love. O Jeſu, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n and be glorified, from the riſing of the Sun unto the going down of the ſame.</p>
               <p>With great trouble and concern, O Lord, I conſider how much of the wretched world lies in wickedneſs! O how ſad a thought is it,
<pb n="79" facs="unknown:001954_0084_0FBA436A2E855CE0"/>
that ſuch a Saviour ſhou'd be offer'd to men, and ſo few receive him! How ſad is it to think, that ſo many thouſands of Souls, for whom Chriſt died, are likely to go down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the diſmal Caves of Hell! That ſo many who might be eternally happy, and praiſe thee for ever, will deſtroy &amp; throw themſelves into everlaſting Miſery: <hi>Rivers of Waters run down mine eyes, becauſe men make void thy law:</hi> A Law ſo rich in Love, and ſo condeſcending in Grace. I am troubled, O Lord, becauſe they do not love thee, and becauſe they will deſtroy themſelves: Becauſe they affront and rebel againſt thy moſt obliging Goodneſs, and neglect ſo great Salvation as it offers them.</p>
               <p>O that I could ſave many precious ſouls from their deſtruction; Oh that I could pluck them as brands out of the burning! As far as I am able, and as becomes me to do in my place and ſtation, I will endeavour to cure the epidemical wickedneſs of the times I live in: I will earneſtly endeavour to keep thoſe that are under my authority and power, and that are of my neighbourhood and acquaintance, and whom I can have any influence over from going down to everlaſting perdition. I will follow all that I may with advice and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel; and thoſe that I may not pretend to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, I will endeavour to intreat, that they would be ſaved: And thoſe whom I ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> do this to, I will reprove and correct for any wickedneſs that I obſerve in them. I will propagate, as well as I can, the ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and the love of thee among the ignorant
<pb n="80" facs="unknown:001954_0085_0FBA436C6B47C1F8"/>
and Careleſs, and thoſe whom their Poverty hinders from providing for themſelves; by giving among them, according to my Ability, ſuch means of their Inſtruction and Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as thy Favour has afforded the Publick.</p>
               <p>I am greatly troubled and concern'd at the Miſeries and Calamities which I hear of or ſee in the World: That thy Creatures whom thou didſt make, that thou mighteſt love them, and that they might be happy, ſhould pull upon themſelves ſo much Miſery from thy juſt Wrath, and deſerv'd Vengeance. Oh how ſad is it to think of Thouſands of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple going down alive into the Pit, ſwallow'd up by ſudden Earthquakes, and in a moment ſnatch'd hence into Eternity, without any time to prepare for their Departure. How it grieves me to think of the ſad Effects of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Famine in ſome Places; of infectious and peſtilential Diſeaſes in others. It wounds my Soul to conſider the woful Calamities and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations that attend horrid Wars! Oh how deplorable a thing is it that Men ſhould ſeek to ſpill the Blood of Men, and give the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſes of their own Kind for a Prey to Birds and wild Beaſts. Lord, rebuke the proud Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of the World, abate their Pride, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage their Malice, and confound their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices. Grant that Wars may ceaſe in all Lands, and gentle Love and happy Peace abound! Proſper, good Lord, thoſe that endeavour for a juſt and ſafe Peace, that they may attain it: and <hi>ſcatter thou the People that delight in War.</hi> Oh that thy Judgments which are abroad in
<pb n="81" facs="unknown:001954_0086_0FBA436F68475720"/>
the Earth, might make the Inhabitants of the World to learn Righteouſneſs, and turn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to thee who haſt ſmitten them, that thou mayſt heal them.</p>
               <p>As a Member of thy bleſſed Church I am particularly concern'd for the Tranquility and peace, and the true Spiritual Glory and proſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity of that. O Lord, purge out of thy Church whatever does diſpleaſe thee, and is deſtructive to the Souls of men. Purge out of it whatever is an Offence to thoſe without: Poſſeſs all Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians with this, that they are oblig'd to Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that their carriage may adorn &amp; recommend their Religion in the ſight of the Infidels; and to take care their <hi>Light may ſo ſhine before Men, that they ſeeing their good works, may Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie their Father which is in Heaven.</hi> Purge thy Church, we pray thee, from all falſe Doctrines and Hereſies; from profaneſs and Perſecution; from Superſtition and Cruelty; from Envy, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Malice, and all uncharitableneſs. Bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way of truth all ſuch as have erred, and are deceivied: Raiſe up them that are fallen; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, and ſtrengthen thoſe that ſtand in Piety and Vertue, and Profeſſion of the Truth, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thoſe Parts of thy Church that mourn, and are oppreſt under a barbarous Perſecution: And let thine own Right Hand, and Holy Arm, in thy due time, give them a mighty Salvation.</p>
               <p>O God of Love, O Prince of Peace, and God of Order, we pray thee, let thy Goſpel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote theſe good things in thy Church. Grant that there may be <hi>no hurting nor destroying in all thy Holy Mountain</hi>: That all the Members
<pb n="82" facs="unknown:001954_0087_0FBA4370F1B0F280"/>
of the Church, as Members of the ſame Body, and of one another, may have a Cordial Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to each other: Carrying themſelves with <hi>all lowlineſs and Meekneſs</hi> to each other; and with <hi>long ſuffering, for bearing one another in Love.</hi> Grant that as there is but <hi>one Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ,</hi> whom we all pretend to Love and Reverence, as there is but <hi>one</hi> true <hi>Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of us all,</hi> ſo we may all <hi>with one Mind and one Mouth glorifie thee our God.</hi> Grant that every Member of the Church may ſo know and keep its proper Place, that there may be <hi>no Shciſm in the Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Jeſu, King of Love, ſill with thy kind and gentle Spirit all Chriſtian Kings, Princes, and Governours. Let no proud wrath, no malicious Envy, no greedy Covetouſneſs, no turbulen Ambition reign in any of them: Grant that they all, knowing whoſe Miniſters they are, may above all things ſeek thy Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Glory: And that they may ſtudy to preſerve the People committed to their Care in Wealth, Peace and Godlineſs. That they may truly and indifferently adminiſter Juſtice to the Puniſhment of Wickedneſs and Vice, and and to the Maintainance of thy true Religion and Vertue.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially, O Lord, we intreat thee to regard with peculiar Favour, thy Servant <hi>GEORGE,</hi> our moſt Gracious King. Let thy Wiſdom direct him in all his Adminiſtrations; thy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Pov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> promote his good Deſigns, that under him we may be Godly and Quietly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd. Let thy bounteous Goodneſs ſhower
<pb n="83" facs="unknown:001954_0088_0FBA437251E62F10"/>
upon him abundantly all Perſonal Bleſſings, for his Body, and for his Soul, to his long Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity in this Life, and his everlaſting Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the next. Since by his Wiſdom and Care, by his Love to thee and Goodneſs to us, with thy Bleſſing upon his Endeavours, we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the happy Liberty of thy Houſe, and theſe thy bleſſed Ordinances, to the Joy and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of our Souls, we will never fail to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber him in all our Prayers and Supplications unto thee.</p>
               <p>Pour down an Abundance of thy Spirit, we pray thee, O gracious Jeſu, upon all Biſhops and Paſtors of thy Church. Repleniſh them with all right and ſound Knowledge, and a true Underſtanding of thy Word. Oh let not their Hearts be governed, or their Actions be guided by the Deſigns of Covetouſneſs or Ambition: but do thou poſſeſs and rule them by a great Zeal for thy Glory, and for thy great Deſign, the Salvation of Souls: Grant that they may by their Holy Doctrine, and anſwerable Lives, be mightily ſucceſsful in turning many to Righteouſneſs; and that they may ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and many of thoſe that are committed to their Charge.</p>
               <p>Since my Goodneſs, O Lord, extends not to thee; and thou art above the receiving of any Advantage by the beſt returns that I can make for all thy Bounty to me: It ſhall be my Charge and Care to requite thy Kindneſs upon thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to whom I may be profitable. I will love them, O Lord, that love thee, and do all the Good I can, to thoſe eſpecially that <hi>are
<pb n="84" facs="unknown:001954_0089_0FBA4373ED85FDE0"/>
of the Houſhold of Faith</hi>: I will gladly relieve the Neceſſities of thy Servants which are made known to me; will feed the Hungry, cloath the Naked, inſtruct the Ignorant, reduce the Wandring, viſit the ſick and Impriſoned, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and help the Weak-hearted, and vindicate and aſſiſt, the Fatherleſs and Widows in their Diſtreſs, according as I have Opportunity and Power to do ſo. And give me, I beſeech thee, O loving Jeſu, a juſt and large Notion of <hi>the Houſhold of Faith,</hi> that I may not confine this my Charity within too narrow bounds. Let me always be afraid of reſtraining it within too narrow Limits, never of extending it too far among Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>I love thee, O Lord Jeſus, for making ſo ſweet and pleaſant a thing as Charity my Duty, and do account even this an Inſtance of thy Charity to me. If there be any other Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of this Divine Vertue, O Lord, which I have not thought of, I deſire thee, the gteat Fountain of Love, to admoniſh me of it, and always to diſpoſe me to it. Grant that in the pleaſing Exerciſe of Love I may paſs the Time of my ſojourning here in this malicious, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable World; till I come at length to that happy One. Where ſincere, abundant and unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable Love, and Joy, and Glory dwell for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XVIII.</hi> Prayers for Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>I.</hi> O God of Love, Father of all Mercies, and Giver of every good an perfect Gift: It
<pb n="85" facs="unknown:001954_0090_0FBA437B07AB9F80"/>
is thy command, and I reckon it a kind and a juſt One, that I ſhould celebrate this Sacrament in Remembrance of the Death and Sacrifice of thy dear Son, our only Saviour and Redeemer, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; to make me thankful for his Love, and for the Benefits of his Paſſion and Death, and that I might be made a partaker of thoſe incomparable Benefits: Thou haſt command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me in this way to renew my Covenant with thee; to declare my ſelf thy Creature and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and bind my ſelf to continue thy faithful Servant, and to live as becomes one that had his Being from thee. O Lord, I muſt acknowledge it is but too neceſſary for me to renew the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which I am ſo apt to tranſgreſs. I am therefore heartily willing: I deſire to ſtrengthen the Bands of Love, that they may hold me the faſter to my Duty. I would never be exempted from the Yoke of thy Service! Oh do not thou caſt me out of it for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt. And I am willing to remember my dear Saviour's dying Love, to be deeply affected with it, and therefore to uſe ſo lively a Repreſentation of his Death, as he has provided in this Sacrament. I must indeed own my ſelf infinitely unworthy of ſo great a good, but yet cannot chuſe but be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſirous, O Lord, to partake abundantly in the Merits and Benefits of my Saviour's Death: There is nothing ſo dear to me as to have all mine Iniquities pardoned; and to recover thy Favour. To enjoy the excellent Graces of thy Holy Spirit, and be conſecrated for a Sacred Temple to him: To receive Earneſts and Pledges, yea and Foretaſts of my future Joy and Happineſs: all which are
<pb n="86" facs="unknown:001954_0091_0FBA437D9E735960"/>
the matchleſs Bleſſings he has purchaſed for me, and which thou haſt directed thy Church to ſeek and partake of in and by this Sacrament. All this I humbly ſeek and crave, through the Merits of Jeſus Christ my Lord, to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour and Glory, World without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>II.</hi> Almighty and moſt merciful God, I bleſs thee for this Sacrament, and would come to it with a hungring and thirſting Soul. But alas, how ſhall I, a poor mean Creature, approach thy Majesty! How ſhall I a guilty polluted Sinner, dare to approach thy Purity and Holineſs! O Lord, I am infinitely unworthy to come ſo near thee: Yet it ſeems, thou doſt not regard my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs, elſe thou wouldſt never have invited me. Thou inviteſt poor ſinful Creatures in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to this Feast; thy Gueſts can be none but ſuch: if all therefore that are unworthy to come, ſhould abſent themſelves, none of us would be there; and thy vaſt and kind Preparations would be in vain; I come therefore, moſt gracious God, in Obedience to thy Command and Invitations. But I will come with the lowliest Reverence and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; for thou haſt regard unto the lowly: I will come as a returning Prodigal, for thou art willing to receive ſuch. I will come, hoping in thy infinite Mercy; for there is Mercy with thee, through Jeſus Chriſt. My great Concern, O Lord, is that I may be in ſome good meaſure fit to approach thee, though I can never be worthy; and that I may have and exerciſe thoſe Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations in my attendance on thee which are ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to this Sacrament, and which thou requireſt.
<pb n="87" facs="unknown:001954_0092_0FBA437F21ABC040"/>
I have therefore earneſtly endeavour'd to find thoſe Qualifications in my ſelf: But alas, O Lord, I dare not trust to my own Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Endeavours. Do thou, O Heart-ſearching God, examine and try me: do thou, I pray thee, prepare me. I fly to thy Grace and Bleſſed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence; Lord, give me, I pray, what thou requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to be in me. It is my great Encouragement to make this Requeſt, that I know I ask herein what thou art willing to give. Thou, Lord, art always more ready to hear, than we to pray; and art wont to give more than either we deſire or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. Thou knowest I cannot have theſe Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications but from thee: Since therefore thou haſt commanded me to come poſſeſs'd with them, I am ſure thou art willing to give them. Thou art deſirous we ſhould come prepar'd, and ſuitable Gueſts to this heavenly Entertainment; art de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſee thy Houſe fill'd with ſuch. Fill me then, good Lord, and many other Souls, with thoſe Graces which it becomes us to appro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ach thee with, for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt our Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator and Advocate. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>III.</hi> O Lord of inſtnite Bounty and Power, I humbly pray thee, give me a ſincere and unfeigned Repentance for all my Sins: Oh let the Remembrance of them be grievous unto me, the Burden and Influence of their Power intolerable. Poſſeſs me with a hearty ſhame and Sorrow, for that I have ſo baſely and unworthily af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted thy infinite Majeſty, and put my kind Saviour to ſo much grief and ſuffering to ſave me. Poſſeſs me with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n earneſt hatred of what is ſo diſpleaſing to thee as my Sins juſtly are; that I may earneſtly and ſteadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavour to caſt them from me. Turn thou my fooliſh Heart from the Love of all Sin, to the Love of thee, Do thou, O Lord, who beſt knoweſt all the dark
<pb n="88" facs="unknown:001954_0093_0FBA4381294C8668"/>
Corners of my Heart, diſcover to me every lurking ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Evil, which I have not been able by my Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to obſerve; and let it now be brought forth and ſlain before thee.</p>
               <p>Increaſe in me, O good Lord, I humbly pray, a lively Faith in thy Mercy, through the Merits and Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt. Help me firmly to believe thy readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to receive and pardon Sinners that repent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to thee: To rely with all Aſſurance on the Sacrifice and Atonement of thy Son's precious Death: Raiſe in me the comfortable Hopes of all Mercy and Favour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſure Foundation; and grant me to rejoyce in hopes of ſeeing thy Glory.</p>
               <p>Oh that my Heart may be all on a Flame of Divine Love, even a whole Burnt-offering, when I remember and conſider my Saviour's dying Love to Sinners. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when I ſee him in this Sacrament, as it were evidently ſet forth Crucified before me. When I ſee there his broken Body, and his Blood poured out; and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that all this he ſuffer'd for me. Oh let ſuch a ſight affect me, as it ought to do, beyond all expreſſions. Oh let it transform me into Love. Let it make ſuch ſtrong and laſting impreſſions upon me, that I may ev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er afterwards be under the ſweet and mighty influences of Love; always be guided by the Laws, and aiming at the Ends of Love. Let Love and Thankfulneſs to him be greatly employing my Soul when I am at this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and be from henceforth the great Concern and Buſineſs, the very Form and Character of my whole Life for ever.</p>
               <p>And ſince my Love cannot redound to his Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, make it flow abundantly upon thoſe that love him. Give me a free Heart and Hand, and Power to do much good to them. According to my Power I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to exerciſe my Charity towards them, and towards all Men, in thought, Word, and Deed at this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I pray that the Memorial of my dear Saviour's Love, may effectually inſpire me to do ſo; And I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and deſire, and pray, that thou wilt be pleaſed to enable me to abound in Love and good Works towards all men, through the whole Courſe of my Life.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="unknown:001954_0094_0FBA4382CDA149D0"/>Put, I beſeech thee, O Lord, my Soul in all reſpects into ſuch a poſture as becomes the Remembrance of a crucified Saviour, that I may be well pleaſing and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted with thee; that thou mayſt delight over me to do me good; that I may have Communion with thee to the Joy and comfort of my Soul, to the increaſe of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Strength, to the ſecuring of my Perſeverance in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs all my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ays. All which I humbly ask in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, and further <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rave whatever is comprehended in his moſt abſolute Form of Prayer, ſaying,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XIX.</hi> Directions for a devou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Behaviour at the <hi>COMMUNION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THanks be to God we have ſo good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made by our Church for the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of this bleſſed Sacrament; that any good Soul may receive it with great Devotion and Comfort, who will but ſeriouſly attend to what is appointed to be ſaid and done in that Adminiſtration; as indeed many ſuch Souls: <hi>accuſtomed</hi> to it, have found by very Comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Experience: Upon which account it were much to be deſired, and very adviſable that thoſe who are wont to attend this way but once in a Year, when they enter into an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, would perſwade themſeves to come more frequently to it, that they might do ſo with the more comfort and advantage to their Souls when that occaſion requires them to do it: For the whole buſineſs is ſo order'd, that 'tis very apt and fit to ſtir up in us the lively and vigorous Exerciſe of all thoſe Graces which
<pb n="90" facs="unknown:001954_0095_0FBA43844FF5CCD8"/>
are required to attend it. So that the beſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which can be given for our due and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Behaviour at the Holy Communion is this: That the Communicant do very cloſely attend to what is order'd to be ſaid and done by him that Miniſters, or by the Communicant himſelf, while they are upon this duty.</p>
               <p>But becauſe the Communicants, eſpecially where the Number is great, (as I wiſh it were every where) will have ſome ſpaces wherein they may employ themſelves in ſome private Ejaculations and Devotions; I ſhall not think it contrary to the propoſed Brevity of this Book to afford them ſome ſuch Devout Prayers and Ejaculations as they may uſe; and I ſhall put them in their proper Places. But theſe muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>monly very ſhort, that they may not be diverted from joining with the Publick Office.</p>
               <p>To begin then, where we uſually begin this Adminiſtration.</p>
               <p>When He that Miniſters is reading thoſe Sentences of Holy Scripture, which are deſign'd to Exhort and Encourage the making our Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings to Almighty God: While you have your Offering in your hand, or when you have given it, ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord of Heaven and Earth, Maker and Owner of all Things! All that I hvae and am is from Thee, &amp; all is Thine. Thou doſt give, and thou haſt right to take and uſe what thou pleaſeſt of it: I humbly preſent This according to my Ability; as an Acknowledgement of thy right in me, and in all that I have; and of thy Bounty in giving it. I preſent, and I humbly intreat Thee to accept This as a token and Pledge of the Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of my ſelf, and all that I have, to ſerve and honour Thee. Sprinkle me, O Lord Jeſus, and this my
<pb n="91" facs="unknown:001954_0096_0FBA4389D7053FE0"/>
duty with thy precious Blood, and obtain for me, by thy Merits, a great Encreaſe of all Spiritual Gifts and Graces to thy Glory and my Salvation.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>When the Offerings are all receiv'd and ſet upon the Altar: He that Miniſters proceeds to make Interceſſions to God for the Whole State of Chriſt's Church Militant here on earth: In which it becomes every Devout Soul, as a liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Member of than Church, to join with him with very hearty Affections.</p>
               <p>After this He proceeds to the immediate Exhortation, which is deſign'd to deter all thoſe from drawing near to this Holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, who are conſcious to Themſelves that they have been negligent to prepare for it; &amp; who live in any known Sin. And then it goes on to Encourage thoſe Humble Penitents, and Faithful Souls, who have been careful to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Themſelves; and to excite in them thoſe Diſpoſitions with which they ought to come. It will be very proper for the Communicant, while the Miniſter is reading this, to join with Him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd to turn it into a Prayer.</p>
               <p>In the next Place you are to join with the Miniſter with Humility and true Godly Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in a Confeſſion of Sins, and to receive by Him Gods Abſolution.</p>
               <p>To the Sentences of Holy Scripture which He next recites to encourage our Faith and Hope in God, it may be proper to make in your Hearts ſome ſuch Anſwers as theſe,</p>
               <p>To thoſe Words of our Saviour, <hi>Come unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Anſwer. <hi>Behold, O Lord, I come: Jeſus thou
<pb n="92" facs="unknown:001954_0097_0FBA438C0341B998"/>
Son of</hi> David, <hi>have Mercy upon me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To thoſe Words, <hi>God ſo loved the World,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Anſwer. <hi>O Father of Mercies, have Mercy upon me, and give me that Faith in thy Son, that I may not Periſh, but have Everlaſting Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the Words of St. <hi>Paul, This is a true Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> &amp;c,</p>
               <p>Anſwer. <hi>Lord, I believe the truth of this, &amp; thankfully embrace ſo Important a Truth: O Christ, ſave me, one of the Chiefeſt of Sinners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the words of St. <hi>John, If any Man ſin,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Anſwer. <hi>Be thou, O Jeſus the Righteous, my Powerful Advocate with the Father: O Father, accept of his Death as a Propitiation for my Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To what the Miniſter ſays next, you are to make the Anſwers directed, and to join with Him in the Praiſes and Prayers following</p>
               <p>After the Bread and Wine is by Prayer of Conſecration ſet apart to repreſent the Body and Blood of Chriſt; and the Miniſters are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, you muſt look upon the Elements with an Holy, Awful Reverence, and ſadly call to mind the Scourging, the Buffetings, the Crown of Thorns, the cruel Nails and ſpear which wounded and bruiſed, which tore and kill'd the Loving Jeſus: You may remember the more terrible Sufferings and ſharp Agonies of his Soul; which he endur'd eſpecially when He made his Life an Offering for Sin. And you ſhould call to mind it was for your Sins that gave Him all theſe Sufferings and Griefs; that yet He endur'd them for your Advantage And he was Scourged, that by His ſtripes you
<pb n="93" facs="unknown:001954_0098_0FBA438DA7F821C8"/>
might be healed; He ſhed His Blood to ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome you from Hell and Miſery; and died, that He might obtain for you Everlaſting Life and Happineſs. And while the reſt of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are receiving, if they are a good Number, you will have leiſure, and may very profitably entertain yourſelf with reading over the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Exerciſes of thankful Remembrance, Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in reading them, you may Exerciſe thoſe Graces as you ought to do. If there will not be time to repeat them all, you may do well to chuſe ſome ſuch a one or more of them as is moſt ſuitable to the preſent ſtate, and diſpoſition of your mind. For the Devout Soul may be at one time more taken up in Admiration &amp; praiſe of the dying Love of Jeſus Chriſt: At another time it may be eſpecially poſſeſt with a deep Humiliation and Repentance; at another time it may be eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Hopes and Joys of believing; Or engag'd in making Earneſt Reſolutions of Love, Obedience, and Gratitude to the Great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer: Or in Exerciſes of Charity to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable World; And your Entertainment at this ſpare time may be choſen accordingly. Only this muſt be adviſed, in relation to this matter, That you ſhould make Obſervation of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelf, whether you do not too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly fix your Meditations upon one and the ſame of theſe Exerciſes, and ſo neglect the reſt: For this muſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be allow'd; But you muſt conſtrain your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lf, if need be, to uſe ſometimes one, and ſometimes another of theſe, that ſo you may at times Exerciſe every Grace, and by the Exerciſe encreaſe in all.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="unknown:001954_0099_0FBA4163235BC9D0"/>When you go to Receive, and ſee the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter approaching with the Sacred Bread, which repreſents the broken body of our Lord, look on it, and ſay:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold,</hi> my Soul, <hi>the Lamb of God, which taketh away the Sins of the World. Worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain to receive Power, and Riches, and Wiſdom, and Strength, and Honour, and Glory, and Bleſſing. Oh come Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, take poſſeſſion of my Soul, and dwell Thou for ever with me; that I may be the more fit for ſuch a Happineſs, transform me into thy Likeneſs, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of my Mind. Open ye everlaſting Doors of my Heart, that the King of Glory may come in.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When He delivers it to you, join with Him, and ſay:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which was given for me, preſerve my Body and Soul unto Everlaſting Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as you are eating it, ſay within yourſelf:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Jeſu, Thou art the Living, and Life-giving Bread, which cometh down from Heaven; which, whoſoever eateth, he ſhall live for ever. Thy Fleſh is Meat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and thy Blood is Drink indeed: On Thee my hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Soul ſhall feed, by my Faith, with hearty Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Let me taſte and find, that thou, Lord, art Gracious; Thou that filleſt the Hungry with good things, repleniſh me abundantly with thy Grace. Oh let this Divine and Spiritual Food afford me much Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Strength and Refreſhment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When he delivers the Cup, Join with Him, and ſay:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which was ſhed for me, preſerve my Body and Soul unto Everlaſting Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when you have drank it, ſay:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thy Love, O King of Saints, is better than Wine. As the Apple-tree among the Trees of the Wood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo is my
<pb n="95" facs="unknown:001954_0100_0FBA416556D8B588"/>
Beloved among the Sons: We will remember thy Love more than Wine: The remembrance of thy wondrous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve ſhall be the frequent and the moſt pleaſant Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of my Life: Thy Love, O Jeſu, ſhall comfort me in my Sorrows; ſhall ſtrengthen me in my weakneſs; ſhall quicken and cure my Sloth: and Backwardneſs to my Duty: Oh let thy Love even transform me into Love.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Father of Mercies, and of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, whom thou haſt ſet forth to be a propitiation through Faith in his Blood, behold, I beſeeth thee, this precious Sacrifice of thy Son! Behold it, I pray thee, and turn away from me, thy poor feeble Creature, all the wrath and Vengeance which my Sins have deſerv'd. This is that on which I firmly and ſolely rely to find favour with thee; and this is that in which I know thou art well pleaſed: O Father of Mercies, have Mercy upon me. Deal always with thy ſervant according to thy Mercy; and teach me thy Statutes, that I may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſerve and pleaſe thee in Newneſs of Life: And I humbly hope and deſire to be accepted with thee, thro' the merits and mediation of thy beloved Son, who died for our Sins, and roſe again for our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; is now ſet down at thy right hand, and ever lives to make Interceſſion for us.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>Taking notice of the Sacrament delivered to others you may thus improve it.</p>
               <p>Jeſus, the rich and bounteous Lover, has good things in ſtore for as many as come unto them: Jeſus is able to ſave to the uttermoſt all that come unto God by him. Of his fulneſs do we all receive, and Grace for Grace. See, my Soul! ſee here thy Maſter's Bounty and Love! See Him here giving even Himſelf to His Friends.</p>
               <p>My Soul, if Jeſus ſo lov'd us all, we ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to love one another. This Commandment has He left us, that He, who loves God, ſhould
<pb n="96" facs="unknown:001954_0101_0FBA4167436D7100"/>
love his Brother alſo. Study, then, what Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Love and Kindneſs it may lie in thy Power to do to any of theſe thy fellow Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants, and reſolve upon it, for the kind Jeſus will take it as even done to him. If thou love him truly, thou muſt needs love thoſe whom he loves: Thou muſt pity them in all their Diſtreſſes, Spiritual and Temporal, whom he has pitied in their miſery at ſo coſtly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate: Thou muſt learn to forgive thoſe whom he forgives: Thou muſt be liberal according to thy power, and their neceſſities, to thoſe whom thou ſeeſt the objects of his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Love. And eſpecially thou muſt charge thy ſelf not to hate, not to do any deſpite or injury to any of theſe; for even that too wou'd he take as done to himſelf: Thou muſt not deſpiſe any of theſe for their mean Condition in this world: He may have made the poor of this world rich in Faith: Thou muſt not envy nor grudge at any of them whom the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God has favour'd more than he has done thee in the bleſſings of this world. Thou muſt take heed always that thy carriage be not a ſcandal and occaſion of Sin to any of theſe; that thou deſtroy not him whom Chriſt died for. And bleſſed be thy name, O Lord, for theſe ſweet and pleaſant Laws. I willingly bind my ſelf, O Jeſu, to obſerve theſe thy Laws of Love. Oh thou great pattern of Love, learn me to love.</p>
               <p>O kindeſt Jeſu, thy Body was broken, and is divided amongſt us to unite us to thee, and to one another. Let it be among us a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="97" facs="unknown:001954_0102_0FBA41685FFDED18"/>
incentive of mutual Charity: Let it be in its effects, unity of ſpirit among us, a bond of peace, and all righteouſneſs of life in our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage one towards another. O thou the great fountain of Love, pour it abundantly into my heart, and into the hearts of all thy faithful people; that we may abound in love one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another; and by thus bearing thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Character and Likeneſs, in Love, may ſhow to all men that we are indeed thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When all have communicated, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter begins the Prayers that remain, you are to leave off all private Devotions, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to join with him and the Congregation to the end.</p>
               <p>After he has pronounced the bleſſing, you may privately ſay:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To him that loved us, and waſh'd us from our Sins in his own Blood, and hath made us King's and Prieſts unto God &amp; his Father: To h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m with the Father and the Holy Ghost, be Glory and Dominion for ever, and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>Then riſing from your knees, kindly and courteouſly ſalute your fellow-communicants, at the parting of the Congregation.</p>
               <p>Private Devotions after the <hi>Communion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XX.</hi> A Meditation on the <hi>COMMUNION,</hi> to be uſed at Church or at Home.</head>
               <p>OH my Soul, ſeriouſly conſider how thou haſt been honour'd, how thou haſt been
<pb n="98" facs="unknown:001954_0103_0FBA416A39D1CDB8"/>
entertain'd in the houſe of God this day? Thou haſt been a gueſt to the King of Saints, the Lord of Life and Glory: Divine Love has been thy heavenly entertainment, and Man did eat Angels food. Thy Saviour, thy Friend has brought thee into his banquetting houſe, his banner over thee was Love. Thou canſt not ſurely very ſoon forget the pleaſures of this Feaſt: Has it not left behind it a very pleaſing reliſh? Has it not put thy mouth quite out of taſte towards the things of this world? It is very fit that it ſhould be ſo: It would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thee for ſome time after this, to account this world's delights ſour and inſipid; and certainly if thou meditate upon the good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment thou haſt had, it will be ſo.</p>
               <p>Jeſus, the glorious Son of God, was Maſter of the Feaſt thou haſt been at ſo lately, and he was himſelf the Feaſt, Jeſus prepar'd it out of love to thee. And becauſe his great love could not (as we may eaſily imagine) provide any thing better, he provided Himſelf to be thy rich and coſtly entertainment. He has feaſted thee with his Body and Blood. He has, in giving thee that Bread and Wine, which was by the Miniſter according to his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conſecrated and ſet apart to repreſent his broken Body, and his Blood ſhed for mankind, made the partaker of the Spiritual Bleſſings and Benefits of his Death and Paſſion. O how great things has he then beſtowed on thee! Where canſt thou find again ſuch entertainment? What enjoyments of this poor world could afford it? And if he has given thee never ſo
<pb n="99" facs="unknown:001954_0104_0FBA416B946C4D50"/>
much of this poor world, he has he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thee that which is of infinitely great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> And if he has given thee but little of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> world, thou haſt no reaſon to complain of him who has been ſo free, ſo bounteous to thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o much better things. Say then to him, Oh, how plenteous, how rich is thy goodneſs, Lord, which thou haſt in reſerve for thoſe that fear thee, and that hope in thy mercy!</p>
               <p>He has treated thee with the pardon of all thy Sins, however numerous, however heinous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d guilty. Canſt thou forbear to admire and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo great a Favour? Is it not wondrous that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vaſt a debt ſhould be ſo freely forgiven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Does not this forgiveneſs reſtore thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the almighty favour and love of God? And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thee le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k, and ground to expect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> heaven, all that is good for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to thy Salvation? Oh ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Bleſs the Lord, On my Soul: All that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> praiſe his holy Name; who hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> my life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m deſtruction, who forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s: Who crowneth me with loving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſs and tender mercies: O bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man whoſe tranſgreſſion is forgiven, whoſe ſin is cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d: Bleſſed, O Lord Jeſus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the man that put<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n his trail in thee.</p>
               <p>He hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtow'd on thee, my ſoul, his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit to dwell with, and to ſanctify thee, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thee with all Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o heal all the diſtemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of thy Soul, thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſy, ſhameful diſtemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to make th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tolerable and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy ſelf, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iable and well pleaſing to him. O happy Souls, that are the Temples
<pb n="100" facs="unknown:001954_0105_0FBA416CD3F150F0"/>
of this Holy Spirit! Where he dwells all things ſhall be in a beautiful Order; all things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and calm, and peaceful; all full of joy: There is a peace which the world cannot give, and a joy unſpeakable and full of glory. In them heaven dwells already; they ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with its incomparable felicities here on earth; and are ſeal'd hereby to the day of Redemption.</p>
               <p>Thy Loving Lord, then, has given thee at this Feaſt, too, the Pledges and Earneſts of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure Glory and Bleſſedneſs. He has even uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee to himſelf after a wonderful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; he looks on thee as a Member of his own Body; has made thee Partaker in his Death, and intends thee to partake in his Reſurrection. He will not leave thy Soul in Hell, nor ſuffer thy dead Body to lie always under Diſſolution. He will <hi>ſhew thee the Path of Life,</hi> and thou ſhalt dwell <hi>at his right Hand, where are Pleaſures for evermore.</hi> Thou ſhalt dwell in his Preſence, where is <hi>fulneſs of Joy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh how like a God has thy Glorious and kind Saviour entertained thee! None could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver beſtow ſuch things on thee but he. Thou haſt been treated as a Favourite of Heaven, who canſt not chuſe but acknowledge thy ſelf a poor, vile and contemptible Sinner. All theſe bleſſings and favours he hath confer'd upon thee, and given thee in this Sacrament ſenſible pledges and tokens of them; tho' thou art un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the very meaneſt and commoneſt of his gifts to mankind. Aſſure thy ſelf, it was not for any merit or worthineſs in thee, that he
<pb n="101" facs="unknown:001954_0106_0FBA416E5137F580"/>
has been ſo bountiful, but of his own free mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: There is nothing of debt in his love, but thou muſt look upon it as altogether obligation.</p>
               <p>And now, my Soul, thou muſt conſider too the mighty obligation he has laid upon thee. Thou art able to promiſe, to do nothing in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn for his love, but what he has infinitely oblig'd thee to. Should ſuch a love as this ever be forgotten; or rather ſhouldſt thou not reſolve that thou wilt always retain a grateful ſenſe of it? And that ſuch a love ſhould be the greateſt joy and the ſweeteſt delight of thy life: That ſuch a love ſhould make an entire conqueſt of thee; and make thee ſubject to the pleaſant laws of it, thro' the whole courſe of thy Life. Thou canſt not ſure, for ſhame, think of a leſs return, than to give up thy ſelf to him; to live to him that died for thee; to ſtudy and love what will pleaſe him, and do it in all things. No; thou canſt not think of any thing leſs than of being his ſervant, who has bought thee with ſo great a price: Who has ranſom'd thee from hell and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miſery, and that by his own cruel ſufferings and accurſed death.</p>
               <p>And will it ever become thee, thinkeſt thou, after thou haſt conſider'd the cruelleſt ſufferings of Jeſus for thy ſake, to ſhrink or murmur at ſufferings, or guiltily decline them? Wilt thou pretend to be a follower, a diſciple of Jeſus, and yet not be able to endure any thing grievous or inconvenient<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Has he ſuffer'd very grievous things for thee, worſe by far
<pb n="102" facs="unknown:001954_0107_0FBA416FD9DB79F0"/>
than thou art able, or will ever be call'd to ſuffer for his ſake? And wilt thou ſuffer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for him? Was his way to heaven in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbred with ſharp thorns, and will it become thee to murmur if thine be not ſtrow'd with roſes? Was the great and glorious Jeſus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpis'd in the world, and muſt thou be mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſpected and honourd'd? Was Jeſus, the Son of <hi>David,</hi> (a rich and mighty King) mean and poor, and will nothing ſerve thee but to be vaſtly and ſuperfluouſly rich? For ſhame, my Soul! Theſe deſires cannot become thee. It is enough for the diſciple to be as his maſter; and ſurely 'tis an honour that the ſervant be as his Lord, If thou wilt be a follower of Jeſus, thou muſt expect, as the world hated him, ſaw no form or comelineſs in him; ſo it will hate, and it will ſcorn thee: It will not ſee any thing to admire in thee. Conſider the ſufferings of Jeſus and harden thy ſelf; learn from him to deſpiſe the inconveniencies of this life; learn to deſpiſe its allurements. From his indifferency towards it, 'tis thy duty and honour to be very indifferent too. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his, as all thy duty, thou wilt find pleaſant upon the tryal of it, and a reward to thy ſelf. This will give thee an invincible compoſure and peace of mind, a happy command and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of thy ſelf, under all the viciſſitudes and changes of this mutable, uncertain World.</p>
               <p>Conſider further, my Soul; has he bleſt thee with the pardon of all thy Sins? and does not this oblige thee to take the utmoſt care that thou ſin no more? Know, he that had much
<pb n="103" facs="unknown:001954_0108_0FBA4174840678C8"/>
forgiven him, ſhould love much; and love will not let thee do any thing willingly, that is ſo diſpleaſing and hateful to the kind and holy Jeſus, as the leaſt Sin would be. Conſider, thy ſins were pardon'd to oblige thee to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them for ever; and this does greatly oblige thee to it: It were horrid and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous ingratitude then, if the pardon of what is paſt ſhould encourage thee to begin a new ſcore. O abhor the thoughts of this, and reckon thou art oblig'd to live with great care of thy ſelf, to take great heed to thy ways, to ſhun even the appearances of evil, to abhor and avoid all temptations to wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>Conſider, my Soul, the Holy Spirit is come to dwell with thee; to conſecrate thee to be a ſacred Temple to himſelf! O divine gueſt! O how great is thy honour and thy happineſs! Wilt thou not let him know, that thou doſt account it both? Wilt thou not ſtudy to be eaſy to ſuch a gueſt? To ſhew him the greateſt reſpects? Know then, that he muſt rule in thy heart; he muſt be, not in compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only, but in reality maſter of the houſe. He is honourable enough, ſurely, to have ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect done him: And it will be thy advantage to give it him. And thou muſt take care, that thou never admit thy luſts and vile affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions again: He will not dwell with ſuch vile company; if thou wouldſt retain the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of his preſence, they muſt be for ever baniſh'd from thy Soul: And ſure it would be very eaſy for thee to ſee, 'tis not fit that they ſhould be allow'd ſo much as a competition with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="unknown:001954_0109_0FBA4175F12D33F0"/>Conſider too, how it becomes a Soul to live that is deſign'd an Inhabitant of Heaven; that is already made free of the <hi>New Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> which is above. Should you not now conform your manners to that bright company? Should you not conſider what a kind of life they liv'd when they were here on earth; and ſet your ſelf to follow them, as they were followers of Jeſus? The vertues which were ſo eminent in their lives, muſt alſo ſhine in yours. They were not many of them Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and Kings, and Queens on earth, becauſe that Fortune, ſhall I ſay, or rather that Burden, falls to the ſhares of but few among mankind: Neither were they, it may be, many of them vaſtly rich, and more than they needed to be: But, which is better, and of more advantage to themſelves than either of theſe, they were poor in ſpirit; they were humble and meek; they were temperate and ſober; they were very good and merciful; all their zeal and concern was to advance the glory of God. Theſe are the ſteps thou muſt tread in; this the way thou muſt follow, to follow them to bliſs; thou canſt not come to their end in any contrary way: Thou muſt <hi>not be conform'd to this World, but be transform'd by the renewing of thy mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou muſt not eagerly hunt after the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, the wealth, and the preferments of this world. It would become thee to be ever very indifferent towards them, as having already taſted and enjoy'd far better things than they: What is capable to afford thee incomparably
<pb n="105" facs="unknown:001954_0110_0FBA4177B34FDD40"/>
more pleaſure and ſatisfaction: And eſpecially would this become thee, as being intituled to far better things: To more durable and uſeful riches, more ſolid and laſting pleaſures, and to far higher dignities and preferments. Theſe the Saviour and Friend has given thee pledges and aſſurances of at this Sacrament; and theſe he will beſtow at the laſt day to thoſe that love and fear him.</p>
               <p>For thou mayeſt expect that this Jeſus, whoſe humble ſufferings and death thou haſt now commemorated, will come again in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with the Hoſt of glorious Angels attending them, to judge both the Quick and the Dead. He will come to <hi>take vengeance in flames of fire, on them that obey not his Goſpel.</hi> And will come to reward all his faithful Servants, to be glorified and admir'd for his bounty and rewards to all them that believe. Oh conſider well, my Soul, that awful, certain Day! and ſuch as thou wouldſt then be found, endeavour now to be; if this life be diligently employ'd in thy maſter's work, the performance of thoſe duties which belong to thy ſtation, and cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling, and relations; he will then ſay to thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Well done good and faithful ſervant, enter thou into thy maſter's Joy.</hi> It will be more to thy advantage, then, to have denied thy ſelf now for thy maſter's honour and ſervice, than to have indulg'd and pleas'd thy ſelf in all things; it will be of greateſt advantage to thee, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be found to have been ſober, and temperate, and good, and religious: When all the honours and all the favour and applauſe of that Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="106" facs="unknown:001954_0111_0FBA417A959494F8"/>
will be given to ſuch; and no other diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ences among men ſhall be regarded, but their differences in theſe things. Be ſure, my Soul, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t will not then repent thee, whatever it does <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow coſt to gain the rewards and honour of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat Day. Reſolve firmly then for a good and holy Life; be never weary of well doing, for here is an everlaſting reſt which ſhall receive thee at the end of it, and the time before thou wilt reach it is but ſhort. Be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouraged by any difficulties thou mayſt meet with; if thou wilt boldly ſtrive, thou ſhall overcome them all, thro' Chriſt ſtrengthening thee: To whom with the Father and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, One ever bleſſed God, be all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory, World without End. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XXI.</hi> Prayers for a ſuitable <hi>CONVERSATION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>I. O</hi> God, the Strength of all them that put their Truſt in thee; mercifully accept my Prayers; and becauſe through the Weakneſs of our mortal Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we can do no good thing without thee, grant me the help of thy Grace, that in keeping thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I may pleaſe thee both in Will and Deed, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord: <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>II. O</hi> Lord, the Fountain of all Power and Might, grant, I beſeech thee, to me thy Servant, Grace, to withſtand the Temptations of the World, the Fleſh, &amp; the Devil; and with a pure Heart and Mind to follow and ſerve thee, the only true and living God; and let me be accepted with thee in all my Service, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="107" facs="unknown:001954_0112_0FBA417BE9EE7770"/>
                  <hi>III. O</hi> Almighty God, who alone canſt order the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly Wills and Affections of Sinful Men, grant unto me thy Servant, that I may Love the things which thou commandeſt, and Deſire thoſe glorious things which thou doſt promiſe; that ſo among the ſundry and manifold Changes of this World, my Heart may ſurely there be fixed, where true Joys are to be found, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>IV.</hi> LOrd of all Power and Might, who art the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and giver of all good Things: graft in my Heart the Love of thy Name; encreaſe in me true Religion; nouriſh me in all Goodneſs, and of thy great Mercy keep me in the ſame through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>V. O</hi> Lord, who haſt taught us, that all our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, without Charity are nothing worth: Send thy holy Spirit, I beſeech thee, and pour into my heart that moſt excellent gift of Charity, the very Bond of Peace, and of all Vertues; without which, whoſoever liveth, is dead before thee. Grant this for thy only Son Jeſus Chriſt's ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>VI.</hi> ALmighty God, who haſt given thy only Son to be unto us both a Sacrifice for Sin, and alſo an Example of Godly Life; give me Grace that I may always moſt thankfully accept that his inneſtimable Benefit, and alſo daily endeavour my ſelf to follow the bleſſed ſteps of his moſt holy Life, through the ſame Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>VII.</hi> GRant, I beſeech thee, Almighty God, that like as I do believe thy only begotten Son, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to have aſcended into the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens; ſo I may alſo in heart and mind thither aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend, and with him continually dwell, who liveth and reigneth with thee and the Holy Ghoſt, One God, World without End. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="108" facs="unknown:001954_0113_0FBA417D828562C0"/>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> MAY the Peace of God, which paſſeth all Underſtanding, keep my heart and mine in the knowledge and love of God, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, and the Bleſſing of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, be upon me, and remain with me always. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>IX.</hi> GLory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghoſt: As it was in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, is now, and ever ſhall be, World without End. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XXII.</hi> Prayers of Recollection.</head>
               <p>THeſe contain the Sum of this Book, and are made fit to be uſed after the reading any parts of it in the Family or Cloſet.</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">I. O Moſt great and glorious God! Lord of Heaven and Earth, infinite in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty &amp; Glory, and in thy Greatneſs unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. And as thy Greatneſs is infinite, ſo is alſo thy Goodneſs; which thou haſt exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in a manner ſuitable to thy excellent Greatneſs: For thou art in all things like thy ſelf, and there is none beſides thee like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee. In wondrous Wiſdom and Goodneſs haſt thou made the World, bounteouſly communicating Being and Happineſs among thy Creatures. But thy Goodneſs has pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly ſhown it ſelf in thy dealing with Mankind, and appear'd in amazing Glories. It appears within us, and in all things that are round about us. Thou haſt made Man a Noble Creature, little lower than the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.
<pb n="109" facs="unknown:001954_0114_0FBA417ED5FCF3B8"/>
Thou didſt endow him with thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Image in righteouſneſs and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Thou crownedſt him with honour and dignity, giving him dominion over all the works of thy hands. Thou haſt built this beauteous world for his habbitation, and plentifully furniſh'd it with all things neceſſary and delightful to him. All our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes preſent us with many inſtances of thy goodneſs to us, the earth is full of it; day unto day uttereth ſpeech, and night unto night ſheweth knowledge of this. We cannot without the greateſt and the moſt wilful blindneſs, fail to ſee it; nor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the moſt unworthy and diſingenuous ingratitude, forget or neglect to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it.</p>
                  <p>But this, O Lord, is that which we muſt, with ſhame and ſelf abhorrence, accuſe our ſelves of. All thy Goodneſs, and the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it, were ſoon forgotten by our Firſt Parents, and they rebell'd againſt thee: And we are their true and vile Off-ſpring, going aſtray from the Womb, living in Enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, and deſpiſing thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. All the Wickedneſs of the World, and the Affronts haſt received from it, thou didſt foreſee; and yet of thy great Patience and Forbearance didſt ſpare our firſt Parents, and permit them to propagate their baſe and corrupt nature! And this gives us occaſion, O Lord, to reflect upon the greateſt and moſt glorious exerciſe of thy goodneſs to mankind.
<pb n="110" facs="unknown:001954_0115_0FBA41820F09DE68"/>
When we were all guilty before thee, and obnoxious to thy eternal wrath; and thy honour, and thy juſtice did require our utter rejection and perdition: Yet even then did then did thy wiſdom and goodneſs contrive and afford us a way and means of Salvation: And thy infinite greatneſs, tho' ſo exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affronted, did condeſcend to a concern to ſave us I and a way was found out ſuitable to thy greatneſs and our neceſſity. Even then did God the Father ſo love the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believes in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life: And then did God the Son, in his infinite compaſſion to mankind, offer himſelf to be our Mediator; and he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to purchaſe for us the divine favour which we had loſt, at the coſt of his own abaſement, in taking our nature, and dying a ſacrifice for the ſins of men. O how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied, Lord, has thy kindneſs and mercy been towards us! And how odious and deteſtable are all our tranſgreſſons againſt thee! When we conſider, O Lord, the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations thou haſt laid upon us! we are even confounded to think of the exceeding vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and enormity of our Sins. We are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forced, O Lord, to abhor our ſelves; we humble, we abaſe our ſelves before thee. We acknowledge thy greateſt diſpleaſure againſt us to be juſt and righteous, and muſt own, that we have deſerv'd thou ſhouldſt throw us into everlaſting fire, which is prepar'd for the Devil and his Angels. But,
<pb n="111" facs="unknown:001954_0116_0FBA41846ED60550"/>
bleſſed be thy name, there is mercy with thee, and thou art, through the undertaking of our bleſſed Mediator, a God forgiving iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſin. We praiſe thee, we magnifie thee, O Lord, for thine ineſtimable love in the redemption of the world by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Encouraged, O Father, by the Sacrifice of thy Son, and the merits of it, we return unto thee: We deſire to return to our duty. We gladly and thankfully accept of the new offers of Grace and Favour with thee, which thou art pleaſed to make us; we ſubmit to the gentle and eaſy terms thou requireſt of us; and we humbly ſeek thy favour upon theſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. We were, O Lord, by the kind diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of thy providence, in our early infancy, dedicated to thee, and engag'd in that happy Covenant, which thou affordeſt us as the way of our Salvation: but we muſt with ſhame confeſs, that we have broken this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and liv'd too great a neglect of it; and have added to the other Heinouſneſs and Wickedneſs of our vile Sins, the great guilt of breaking our Vows and Promiſes to thee. As ſenſible of our unworthy Behaviour here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: again, O Lord, we deſire to renew thoſe Bonds, and we earneſtly deſire they may be ſo confirm'd by this renewal of them, as that they may never be broken any more. We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce this wicked World, our own corrupt Nature, and thine Adverſary the Devil; we purpoſe not to ſuffer our ſelves to follow, nor be led by them. We will receive, Lord,
<pb n="112" facs="unknown:001954_0117_0FBA4185965237D8"/>
what thou requireſt us to beleive; and we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote our ſelves to keep and obey thy Holy, Juſt and Good Commandments, through the whole courſe of of our lives: to be always under the Influence and Power of Love to thee, and to our Neighbours: To love thee with all our Heart, and with all our Soul, and with all our Might; and our Neighbour as our ſelves. O Father of Mercies, graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly accept of our repentance, and return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: Look upon the Death of thy Son, and turn from us all thy wrath: Juſtifie us freely by thy Grace; pardon all our Sins upon the account of it; take us into thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and grant that we may ever hereafter pleaſe thee in newneſs and holineſs of life, for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt, to whom with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, be all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory, for ever and ever.
<hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p n="2">II. O Eternal Son of the Eternal Father, who inheriteſt the infinite Wiſdom, Power and Glory, and the infinite Love and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Father! Jeſus, thou Son of God, have mercy upon us, O Chriſt hear us; be thou our Advocate with thy Father; By thy Holy Nativity and Circumciſion; by thy Meritorious Croſs and Paſſion; by thy precious Death and Burial; by thy Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, take us into thy Care and Protection: Thou that haſt done all theſe things for us, have Mercy upon us: O be thou Jeſus to us, and ſave us from our Sins: Give us, according to thy Promiſe, to them that receive thee, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="113" facs="unknown:001954_0118_0FBA4187351DFDF0"/>
Privilege to become the Sons of God? We accept of thee, O Lord, as a King to rule us, and will Study to know and endeavour to obey thy Commands: We earneſtly deſire thy teaching as our great Prophet; and will receive and comply with thy Divine Inſtructions, however contrary they are to the corrupt Byaſs of our Nature and our Love of this World. Lord, we purpoſe to conform our ſelves to them by the Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thy excellent Example, and not to be conformed to this World. And we will always acknowledge our utter unworthineſs of the leaſt Good, and place all our Hopes in thy Merits and Interceſſion as our great High prieſt. Oh let us find by the good Succeſs of all our humble Addreſſes, that thou haſt Compaſſion on our Miſeries, and doſtever live to make Interceſſion for us. So we whom thou haſt redeem'd with thy moſt precious Blood, will give up our ſelves to thy Service, and ſhew forth thy Praiſe, not only with our Lips but in our Lives, by walking before thee in all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Righteouſneſs of Life and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, to the Glory of God the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, in this and the other World, even for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p n="3">III. O Infinite and Eternal Spirit, the Lord and giver of Life, who proceedeſt from the Father and Son, who with the Father &amp; the Son together art Worſhipped and Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed! We pray thee to have Mercy upon us.
<pb n="114" facs="unknown:001954_0119_0FBA418A1DE050C0"/>
We have promiſed and reſolved what is due from us; but alas, more than we are able to perform without thy Influence and Aſſiſtance: We therefore addreſs our ſelves to thee, O bleſſed Spirit: Come down we beſeech thee, into our Hearts; repleniſh us abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly with thy Grace; let us become thy Sacred, &amp; conſecrated Temples, and do thou evermore dwell in us: Baniſh and purge out of us for ever all that is contrary and diſpleaſing to thee. Teach us that denying all Ungodlineſs, and worldly luſts, we may live Soberly, and righteouſly, and Godly, in this preſent World. Write thy Law in our Hearts, that we may never depart from it. Increaſe and maintain our Faith; Increaſe and continue our Love; cheriſh all Grace in us; and cauſe us to perſevere in Holineſs, and Vertue, and well-doing, to the End of our Lives. Keep us in the Knowledge and Love of God, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. We purpoſe, O Holy Spirit, duly to wait for thy bleſſed ſaving Influences in a diligent Attendance on thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Ordinances, the Word and Sacraments: O let us be always in due fitneſs to attend them, when the happy Opportunities of doing ſo are offered us; and let them be always bleſt to us, and be effectual to promote our Sanctification and Salvation.</p>
               </q>
               <p>[Inſert this when this Prayer is uſed in the Morning.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We give thanks to the God of all Mercies for the ſafe Protection, the quiet and Comfortable Reſt of the laſt Night: We devote this day and all our Lives to thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, in the Duties which thou giveſt us to do; aſſiſt us mercifully,</hi> O Lord, <hi>in all, and accept us in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[Inſert this when this Prayer is uſed at Night.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Enlighten our dark Souls we beſeech thee,</hi> O Lord, <hi>with all the Knowledge that is neceſſary to our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eon: Fill us with devout Affections, and let thy</hi> Love <hi>always poſſeſs and rule us: Be thou, we pray, our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections this Night from all the Perils and Dangers of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Father which, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
