<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of Presbyterian ordination. In answer to a pamphlet, entituled, A modest proof, of the order and government settled by Christ, in the church. / By Jonathan Dickinson, M.A. Minister of the Gospel at Elizabeth-Town, New Jersey. ; [Six lines of Scripture texts]</title>
            <author>Dickinson, Jonathan, 1688-1747.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-08">2004-08.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N02125</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N02125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 2525</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APY3617</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">2525</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99030736</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 2525.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N02125)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 2525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 2525)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of Presbyterian ordination. In answer to a pamphlet, entituled, A modest proof, of the order and government settled by Christ, in the church. / By Jonathan Dickinson, M.A. Minister of the Gospel at Elizabeth-Town, New Jersey. ; [Six lines of Scripture texts]</title>
                  <author>Dickinson, Jonathan, 1688-1747.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], iii, [1], 44 p. ;  18 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Daniel Henchman, and sold at his shop, over-against the Brick Meeting-House in Cornhill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1724.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Mr. Dickinson's defence of Presbyterian ordination.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Checkley, John, 1680-1754. --  Modest proof ...</term>
               <term>Ordination.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy.</term>
               <term>Apostolic succession.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>AEL Data (Chennai)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-05</date>
            <label>AEL Data (Chennai)</label>Re-keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:002525_0000_0FDB44B9A033D5E0"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:002525_0001_0FDB5F4B15628878"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Dickinson's</hi> DEFENCE OF Presbyterian Ordination.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:002525_0002_0FDB5F5010A6A648"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF <hi>Presbyterian Ordination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ANSWER to a Pamphlet, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, A MODEST PROOF, OF THE Order and Government settled by Christ, in the CHURCH.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Jonathan Dickinson,</hi> M.A.</p>
            <p>Minister of the Gospel at <hi>Elizabeth-Town, New Jersey.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>1 Cor. III. 5.</bibl>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who then is Paul, and who is Apollos, but Ministers, by whom ye believed?</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <bibl>Eph. IV. 14.</bibl>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>That we henceforth be no more Children, tossed to and fro, and carried with every wind of Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, by the slight of Men, and cunning craftiness, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they lie in wait to deceive.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Daniel Henchman,</hi> and sold at his Shop, over-against the Brick Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-House in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1724.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="i" facs="unknown:002525_0003_0FDB5F511D8D75D0"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THOUGH the preaching of the Cross, be to them that perish foolishness; <hi>and the Ministry of the Gospel, is by the World esteem'd a mean and contemptible Thing: Tet</hi> Infinite Wisdom <hi>has contriv'd, and</hi> Infinite Grace <hi>improv'd this Engine, for the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down the strong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olds of Sin and Satan, in the Hearts of Men, for the rescue of Sins miserable Captive's, for the advancing the kingdom of Grace, and erecting Trophies, on the Ruines of Satan's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in the World. This it is, that has dissipated that Darkne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Heathenism, which heretofore co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd the face of the Earth: This, that has demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished the Temples, laid waste the Altars, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpated the Votaries of the Heathen Gods; and seat the Gentile Worship packing to Hell: This, that notwithstanding its Original mean Appearance, has conquer'd and baffled all the proud Philosophy of</hi> Greece <hi>and</hi> Rome: <hi>This, that so stoutly withstood, and finally triumph'd over the fiercest Opposition of the haughty</hi> Monarchs <hi>and</hi> Potentates <hi>of the Earth: By this, are</hi> Christ's Ways made known in the Earth, and his saving Health among the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <hi>And in a Word, By this,</hi> are the Eyes of
<pb n="ii" facs="unknown:002525_0004_0FDB5F52EB6FDF80"/>
poor perishing Sinners open'd, and they turned from Darkness unto Light, and from the power of Satan unto God, that they may have an Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance among them that are sanctified.</p>
            <p>AND <hi>as this</hi> sacred Institution, <hi>is of last Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to the Souls of Men; so it is of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, that</hi> they th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> take this Office upon 'em, are called of God, as was Aaron. <hi>For, as on the one Hand,</hi> it has pleased God, by the foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of preaching, to save them that believe; so <hi>is it an awful Truth on the other Hand,</hi> That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever entreth not by the Door, into the Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; but climbeth up some other way, the same is a Thief, and a Robber. <hi>He that appointed</hi> the Ministry of Reconciliation, <hi>as the ordinary Means of Salvation, That</hi> we cannot believe in him, of whom we have not heard nor hear without a Preacher; <hi>has also hedged in this weighty Trust, from the Intrusion of vain Pretenders, that</hi> none may Preach, except they be sent.</p>
            <p>HENCE <hi>it appears a most d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ring Usurpation, for any to assume the Character of</hi> Christ's Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadors, <hi>that have not their Mission from him. And it would therefore be a commendable Zeal, in the </hi> High Church Party, <hi>to depreciate our Ministry, and to decl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> against our</hi> Invasion of the sacred Function; <hi>if their Arguments were answerable to their</hi> Confidence. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for such a small upstart Sect, gravely to attempt, by Arguments a hundred times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed, to Unchurch all the</hi> Protestant <hi>World, but themselves; and to nullify all their</hi> Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;
<pb n="iii" facs="unknown:002525_0004_0FDB5F52EB6FDF80"/>
               <hi>Rather exposes their Bigottry to Contempt, than their</hi> Zeal and Charity, <hi>to the envy of any thinking Person.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have no Sollicitude, to find out more of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Discourse herein impugned, than is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd p. 5. by his</hi> Jacobi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Principles, of</hi> Passive Obedience, <hi>and Non-resistance: nor should I have esteem'd his Arguments worthy of Notice, were it not for the malign Influence, they may have upon the</hi> Laity, <hi>for whose Use they were calculated, and into whose Hands, they are so carefully put. But for their sakes, an</hi> Antidote <hi>was thought Need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AN Apology <hi>may be justly expected from me, for undertaking a Task, that should have been left to some abler Hand: But I have none but this to make, That I could bear of no other, like to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the Cause; and therefore thought it neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, to hold up the</hi> Shield.</p>
            <p>IF <hi>some Arguments occur in this Dissertation, that have been used before, in the same Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy, it must be remembred, that</hi> Truth is always the same; <hi>and that</hi> the same Thing must be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, to those that are dull of hearing.</p>
            <p>I <hi>know that this Discourse must stand or fall, by the Reader's Censure; and therefore shall say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing about it, but that I hope, it won't be wholly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="defense">
            <pb n="1" facs="unknown:002525_0005_0FDB5F5643234C88"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE OF Presbyterian Ordination.</head>
            <p>THERE is nothing more necessary, in the right managing of Controversy, than a fair stating the Debate; that Men fight not with their own Shadows, nor combate in the Dark: But of this, our Author had especial Reason to be cautious, since he design'd his Discourse for the Use of the <hi>Laity,</hi> who are not to be startled with such Questions, least they stumble at the Thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shold.</p>
            <p>BUT though his Province was to <hi>Harrangue,</hi> and not to <hi>Argue,</hi> on which score, he may be excused from once mentioning the Question in debate; yet it may be of some Service to the clear understanding of this choice Discourse, to know the state of the Controversy. I shall therefore briefly, and fairly state the Case, in these two Propositions.</p>
            <p n="1">I. WHETHER <hi>Bishops</hi> are by <hi>Divine Right,</hi> Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and have by vertue of that Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, the sole Power of <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>Jurisdiction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="unknown:002525_0006_0FDB13AEA63D5E20"/>II. WHETHER the English <hi>Diocesan Bishops,</hi> that have some scores, and even hundreds of Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions under their Inspection; with their <hi>lordly Dignity,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Power,</hi> are the only Scripture <hi>Bishops,</hi> on whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ministerial Authority,</hi> and <hi>sacred Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o necessarily depend.</p>
            <p>BOTH of these, should have been most clearly, and fully prov'd in the Affirmative, before ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Author had erected his <hi>Trophies,</hi> and concluded his Pamphlet, with such confident Boasting, and pathetical Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions.</p>
            <p>IT's my present Business to examine his Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, and if in the Conclusion it appears, that he cannot find one Word in the Bible, to support this <hi>Prelacy;</hi> nor add<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce any <hi>Commission</hi> from the <hi>King</hi> of the Church, for this extensive <hi>Dominion,</hi> or <hi>lordly Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> I hope <hi>Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>by<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er,</hi> may yet deserve, a more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Character in the World, than <hi>Intruders into the sacred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unction,</hi> or <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the sacred Service;</hi> as the <hi>Prefacer</hi> of this Discourse, modestly stiles them.</p>
            <p>THE first Thing that offers to our Consideration, (after some Account of the noble Views of this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor is a remarkable piece of <hi>History,</hi> which take in his own Words. p. 2. <q>Now the Church, however <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rassed and disquieted, with a great variety of Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes and Debates, about Points of Doctrine and Discipline; yet heard little or no Noise made, for above 1400 Years, about this Point of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. One <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erius</hi> sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed a Debate, but had so few to second him, that it died with himself, and left his Name on Record among Hereticks.</q> This deserves particular Consideration; for he would doubtless hereby insinuate, that <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cesan Epis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opacy,</hi> universally obtain'd in the Church, for the first four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred Years; and met with no Opposition, but by <hi>Aerius,</hi> who got nothing by his upstart Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:002525_0006_0FDB13AEA63D5E20"/>
but the infamous Character of <hi>Heretick.</hi> But</p>
            <p n="1">1. WOULD it not have been more to his Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, to have proved, that <hi>Diocesan Episcopacy</hi> of the modern Stamp, was ever known in the Church for the first three hundred Years, or ever once asserted by any Author of Note, within that Time? This would have been an acceptable Performance; such I dare say, as the World was never yet blessed with. But what occasion of Proof? He no doubt conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the <hi>Laity</hi> were obliged to take his Word.</p>
            <p n="2">2. WAS there <hi>no Noise about this Point of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, for fourteen hundred Tears?</hi> Can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e have the Front, to publish such a Story to the World! I'm sure, he is not exceedingly well qualified to write upon this Subject, if ignorant, that <hi>Jer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> one of the most <hi>learned,</hi> and <hi>judicious</hi> of all the <hi>Fathers;</hi> did as exprestly assert, and vindicate the co-ordinacy of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> as ever <hi>Aerius</hi> did. Does he not in his Epistle to <hi>Evag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> expresly tell us, that <hi>the Apostle clearly teches, that Presb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters are the same with Bishops; and that afterw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rds, One was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lected, and put before the Rest, for the remedy of Schism?</hi>—And does he not in his Commentary on <hi>Titus,</hi> largely prove the Identity of <hi>Bishop</hi> and <hi>presbyter,</hi> by the very same Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that are used by the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> now? and plainly affirms, that <hi>a Presbyter is the same with a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop; and before that by the Devil's Instin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, there were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arties in Religion, and it was said among the People, I am of Paul, I of Apollo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and I of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rches were govern'd by the common Council of Presbyters, &amp;c.</hi> And was <hi>Jerom</hi> the only Person among the Ancients, who maintain'd this Doctrine? Don't our Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries themselves acknowledge, <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Morton's</hi> Apol. Cath Lib. 1. P 118, 119, 120. Dr. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Letter to <hi>Wadsworth,</hi> in Dr. <hi>Burnet's</hi> Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dei. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Iren. P. 276.</p>
               </note> That St. <hi>Ambrose, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:002525_0007_0FDB5F57D7F04BC0"/>
Seduli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Crysost<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, Theo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oret <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilact,</hi> all of 'em asserted the parity of <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Presb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters?</hi> Don't the World know, that the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> and <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ckle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in England, with his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, were persecuted for this very Doctrine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Peri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d he Speaks of? Hear <hi>Medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> on the whole, as cited by <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ermine</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter. Cap. 15. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Sanctum <hi>Hierony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> idem omnino cum <hi>Aeranis</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eque solum <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; sed etiam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> que ita (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>quit <hi>Medma)</hi> istiviri, alioqui Sanctissimi, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rarum consuiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>imi, quorum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sententiam, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nde in <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldens<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bus,</hi> postremo in <hi>Johanne Wickl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Michael <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> affir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, that S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Jerom,</hi> was altogether of the same Opinion with the <hi>Aerians,</hi> and that <hi>Jero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was not alone in that Heresy; but also <hi>Ambrose, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustin, Sedul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s, Primasi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, Crysostom, Theodoret, Oec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meniu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> And though these were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise very holy Men, and most studious of the holy Scriptures, yet the Church condemned their Opinion, first in <hi>Aerius,</hi> then in the <hi>Waldenses,</hi> and la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly in John <hi>Wickle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I could besides, bring him sufficient <hi>Documents,</hi> from Authors much more Ancient than any of these, to disprove this Assertion: But he not putting the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e upon this Iss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, I shall net spend Time to heap up Authorities; but only enquire, whether <hi>Prelacy</hi> when it did obtain in the Church, was so very grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that there was <hi>no Noise made about it.</hi> Hear <hi>Gregory N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zienz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> on that Point. <q>Would to God, (says he) there were no <hi>Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cy,</hi> no Prerogative of Place, no Tyranical Privelleges, that by Vertue alone we might be discern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. Now this right and left Hand, and middle Rank, these higher and lower Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and this state like Precedence, have caused ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:002525_0007_0FDB5F57D7F04BC0"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruitless Conflicts and Bruises, have cast many into the Pit; and carried away Multitudes to the Place of the Goats.</q> And just Cause there was for this Complaint; for does not every one, that has the least Acquaintance with <hi>Ecclesiastical History</hi> know, what dread<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul Convulsions, the primitive Churches were thrown into, by the Pride and Emulation of the Clergy, after this <hi>prelatick</hi> Power and Superiority had obtain'd among them: And what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umultuary Uproars, and blood<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sacres, those who would be deem'd the <hi>Ambass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dors</hi> of the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> have occasion'd, by their ambitious Pursuit of <hi>Ecclesiastical Dignities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND now let the Reader judge, how agreeable, is the Title of <hi>A mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st Proof,</hi> to a Pamphlet which begins, with so bold and notable an Escape.</p>
            <p>THUS I'm come to consider the Character of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s;</hi> whose Name, he tells us, is left on Record a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Hereticks, for his Opposition to <hi>Prelacy.</hi> But who has recorded him among Hereticks? It was <hi>Epip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anius,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Constanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in <hi>Cyprus;</hi> a bright Instance of the Pride, Emulation, and Ambition of the Clergy, at that Time; as appears from his haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and malicious Conduct, towards <hi>Crysostom,</hi> Bishop of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Vid. <hi>Soc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at.</hi> Eccles. His<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Lib. 6. Cap. 9. 11.</note> and a most pitiful, weak, tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing Author: That <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Episcopal</hi> Writers themselves own, that <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e spake Nonsense, on the Subject before us;</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Reignolds</hi> Letter to Sir <hi>Francis Knolls.</hi>
               </note> and that <hi>he was of acknowledged Injudiciousness, and Unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curacy</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Brok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sby</hi> Hist. of the Govern. of the Prim. Church. P. 108.</note>
            </p>
            <p>BUT was it only for his Opposition to <hi>Prelacy,</hi> that <hi>Aerius</hi> was left on Record among Hereticks? Were there not greater Articles against him than this? <abbr>
                  <hi>viz.</hi>
               </abbr> His condemning of <hi>Lent,</hi> of <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices</hi> for the <hi>Dead;</hi> and the like Superstitions, then
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:002525_0008_0FDB5F5C56631828"/>
received in the Church: which <hi>Epiphanius</hi> attempts to justify against him; and thereby proves him more <hi>Orthodox,</hi> than himself.</p>
            <p>I should now take my leave of this <hi>Historical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction,</hi> were it not for a pleasant Continuation, (or rather Contradiction) of this Story, in the very next Word: <q>The goodly Order, (says he) and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment instituded by Christ, stood firm for many Ages, and under it the Church flourished, and the Christian Religion mightily prevail'd, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the violent Persecutions of those Times: But at length it was invaded and suppressed, by the <hi>Usurpation</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> of the <hi>Roman Papacy,</hi> a secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Power and Dominion was set up, &amp;<hi>c.</hi>
               </q> Was there <hi>no Noise for fourteen hundred years, about this Point of Church Government,</hi> and yet this Government invaded and suppressed, by the <hi>Usurpation</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> of the <hi>Roman Papacy;</hi> and a secular Power and Dominion erected upon its Ruines? These Consequences do then, most naturally follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. THAT the Church Government he contends for, is the same with the <hi>Papal Hierarchy,</hi> according to the Pattern of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> before the Year of Christ 1400. For until that Period, there was <hi>no Noise about this Point of Church Government;</hi> nor was it <hi>suppressed by the Roman Papacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. THAT the <hi>Usurpation and Tyranny of the Roman Papacy,</hi> did not commence till the fifteenth Century. For by this, the Government he propugns, <hi>was sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, and a secular Power and Dominion set up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT it's time I dismiss this <hi>History,</hi> and consider another, no less Remarkable; which I find in p. 3. where after a just Lamentation of the unhappy Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, by which the Church at the <hi>Reformation,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="unknown:002525_0008_0FDB5F5C56631828"/>
was disturb'd, and the common Enemy diverted; he proceeds to tell us, that <q>among other Differences, this was one, that while the greatest and most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Part of the reformed Church, retain'd the ancient Order and Government; and vindicated it from the Usurpations, and Encroachments of the <hi>Papacy;</hi> others, (upon what Consider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions I shall not en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uire) were pleas'd to set up a new Form, and Model of Policy.</q>
            </p>
            <p>HAVE I quite mistaken this Author all this while, and supposed him pleading for <hi>Prelacy,</hi> whilst it's the An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of the <hi>Presbyterian Government,</hi> which he a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asserts? Truly this Paragraph, That <hi>the greatest and most considerable Part of the reformed Church, retaind'd the ancient Order and Government,</hi> would tempt me to think so; had it been reconcileable to the rest of his Discourse. For does not every Body know, that the <hi>Divine Right of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy,</hi> was a <hi>Doctrine</hi> unknown in all the foreign Churches, at the Time of the <hi>Reformation?</hi> and that they uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally maintain'd the Identity of <hi>Bishop</hi> and <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an't the bitterest of our Adversaries, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged this? Hear one of them, <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Howel. Famil, Letters.</hi> vol. 3. P. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> who after he had proposed <hi>Calvin,</hi> as the first Founder of the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> Principles, proceeds, <q>Thus <hi>Geneva</hi> Lake swallowed up the <hi>Episcopal See;</hi> and Church Lands were made Secular, which was the White they le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled at. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>Geneva</hi> Bird flew therice to <hi>France,</hi> and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> which make about a tenth Part of that People, it took Wing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>so to <hi>Bobemia,</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> High and Low, as the <hi>palatinate,</hi> the Land of <hi>Hesse,</hi> and the con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Provinces of the States of <hi>Holland, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> I would therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this Author to read the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, French, Dutch, Scotch, Helvetian,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Confession<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Faith;</hi> with all their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:002525_0009_0FDB5F5DEC5A1C58"/>
of Note upon this Subject, whether Systemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, or Polemical. And he'll find, that he has once (whether willingly or not) spoken Truth; That <hi>the greatest and most considerable Part of the reformed Church, retain'd the ancient,</hi> (that is the Presbyterian) <hi>Order and Government.</hi> Some of the foreign Churches, did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed early set up <hi>Superintendents;</hi> but never once dream'd of their Superiority by <hi>Divine Right,</hi> over their Brethren. But even these (as Dr. <hi>Stillingfle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> testifies, <note n="*" place="bottom">Iren. P. 411.</note>) <hi>stifly maintain Jerom's Opinion, of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quality of Gospel Ministers.</hi> And in <hi>Sweden, Denmark,</hi> and <hi>Norway,</hi> they have nominal <hi>Bishops.</hi> But as for those of <hi>Denmark,</hi> they have their Succession from <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who was but a <hi>Presb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, according to our Authors Scheme, are so far from <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cesan Bishops,</hi> that they are not so much as <hi>Gospel Ministers.</hi> And they of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Norway,</hi> will no better serve his Purpose; for the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Religion, has deprived those of Ecclesiastical Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; and these are but <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imi inter pares,</hi> says the Author of <hi>Present State of Europe,</hi> for the Year 170<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. P. 134, and 147.</p>
            <p>THUS we see, that the <hi>Divine Right of Episcopacy,</hi> was not known in the primitive Church; nor once profess'd by any of the foreign Reformers; and I may add, as little believed by the <hi>Church of England</hi> her self, in the beginning of the Reformation.</p>
            <p>AND now, since we find o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Authors <hi>Confidence,</hi> thus far outgoing his <hi>Mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sty</hi> in this; we'll see how he acquits himself, in his following Essays.—And the next thing that offers, worthy of particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration, is his Account of <hi>the Order and Government, institued by Christ and his Apostles, in the Christian Church</hi> Which being cast into four Heads, I shall consider them each distinctly.</p>
            <div type="consideration">
               <pb n="9" facs="unknown:002525_0009_0FDB5F5DEC5A1C58"/>
               <head>The First HEAD consider'd.</head>
               <p>HE first undertakes, <hi>To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> what sacred Offices were instituted by Christ and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Apostles, in the Church.</hi> And the Sum of what he offers on this Head is, That these Offices were threefold.(I) <hi>The Twelve Aposties, whose Commission</hi> (he tells us) <hi>we have at large,</hi> Mat. X. (2) <hi>The Seventy Disciples, sent forth with the same Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ission, and the same Power: But though; their Commission was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uch the same, with what was given to the Apostles, (who had not as yet receiv'd their full Commission) yet it is most certain, that they were two distinct Orders of Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Ministers. (3). Deacons, who were invested with some share of the Apostolick Office, particularly of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as well as managing the publick Stock of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I shall first take Noti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of his Instance of the <hi>Twelve Apostles,</hi> and the <hi>Seventy Disciples.</hi> Is it <hi>most certain, that they were two distinct Orders of Gospel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters?</hi> How does this appear? <q>The <hi>Twelve</hi> (says he, P 10.) were particularly honour'd with the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of APOSTLES; but the <hi>Seventy,</hi> though they were sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> forth immediately by Christ, are no where so called.</q> But what is the meaning of the Word APOSTLE? Does it not signify a <hi>Messenger,</hi> or one Sent? And was it not because they were <hi>sent forth,</hi> that our Lord gave to the <hi>Twelve,</hi> the Title of APOSTLES? And were not the <hi>Seventy</hi> also said to be APOSTELEIN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sent,</hi> Luk. X. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? Which every Body that understands any Greek, knowns to be the Word, from whence APOSTLE is deriv'd. And does not the <hi>Evangli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t,</hi> with Allusion to the Mission of the <hi>Twelve,</hi> tell us, fore cited Luk. X. 1. That <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter these things, the Lord appointed other Seventy also, and</hi> SENT <hi>them?</hi> Other <hi>Seventy</hi> What? N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <hi>Disciples:</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="unknown:002525_0010_0FDB5F5F56AC2360"/>
he did not appoint 'em such now, they were so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: But other <hi>Seventy Apostles,</hi> or <hi>Messengers,</hi> which is the same thing. These indeed, were not sent out as the <hi>Twelve,</hi> to Gospelize the Nations after Christ's Resurrection. And therefore, were never APOS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TLES, in the Gospel Dispensation: But for this Temporary Mission, had the same Commission, the same Powers, and the same Denomination with the <hi>Twelve.</hi> If they were not expresly called <hi>Messengers,</hi> they are said to be SENT, which implies it.</p>
               <p>BUT there's one invincible Argument yet to be consider'd; and that is, <q>When a Vacancy falls in the College of <hi>Apostles,</hi> by the Apostacy of <hi>Judas,</hi> what a solemn Work was there, at the translation of one from the Number of Disciples, (of the <hi>Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> I suppose he means) that he might be reckon'd and numbered with the Eleven.</q> But who told him, that <hi>Matt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ias</hi> was one of the <hi>Seventy?</hi> Is it possible to prove this? If not, it is not <hi>put beyond all Question,</hi> as he vainly boasts: But on the contrary, it's beyond all Question with me, that instead of being two dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct Orders of <hi>Gospel Ministers,</hi> they were neither of them <hi>Gospel M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nisters</hi> at all, by vertue of the <hi>Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> he speaks of. For how could they be <hi>Gospel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters,</hi> before there was any <hi>Gospel Church?</hi> Certain it is, that they were then under the <hi>Jewish Oeconomy;</hi> and that the Christian Church was founded on Christs Resurrection, &amp; therefore, could not have <hi>Officers,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it had a Being. But what need I insist? These Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ages are effectually answer'd, beyond all possibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Reply, by two of his own Party. Hear what they say.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>WHEREAS (saith Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Anno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. on Luk. X. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>) some compare the <hi>Bishops</hi> to the <hi>Apostles,</hi> the <hi>Seventy</hi> to the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="unknown:002525_0010_0FDB5F5F56AC2360"/>
of the Church; and thence conclude, that divers Orders in the Ministry, were instituted by Christ himself. It must be granted, that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients did believe these two to be divers Orders; and that those of the <hi>Seventy,</hi> were inferior to the Order of the <hi>Apostles;</hi> and sometimes they make the Comparison here mentioned: But then it must also be granted, that the Comparison will not strictly hold. For the <hi>Seventy</hi> receiv'd not their Mission, as <hi>Presbyters</hi> do from <hi>Bishops;</hi> but immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from the Lord Christ, as well as the <hi>Apostles;</hi> and in their first Mission, were plainly sent on the same Errand, and with the same Power.</q> Thus he. And</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Sage</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Vind. of the Prin. of the Cypr. Age, Cap. 6. Sec. 5.</note> has more plainly and fully clear'd the Cause. <q>It is obviously observable (says he) in the Evangelical Records, that the Christian Church was not, could not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ounded, till our Saviour was risen; Seeing it was to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ounded on his Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. Our Martyr <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>rian,</hi> as appears from his Reasonings on divers Occasions, seems very well to have known, and very distinctly to have observed, that the <hi>Apostles</hi> themselves, got not their <hi>Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to be Governours of the Christian Church, till after the Resurrection; and no Wonder, for this their Commission is most observably recorded Joh. XX. 21, 23, 23. No such thing any where recorded, concerning the <hi>Seventy.</hi> Nothing more certain, than that <hi>that</hi> Commission which is recorded Luk. X. did constitute them only <hi>Temporary</hi> Missionaries, and that for an Errand, that could not possibly be more than <hi>Temporary.</hi> That <hi>Commission</hi> contains in its own Bowels, clear Evidences, that it did not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stall them, in any standing Office at all, much less,
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:002525_0011_0FDB5F667433C118"/>
in any standing Office in the Christian Church; which was not yet in being when they got it. Could that <hi>commission</hi> which is recorded Luke X. any more constitute the <hi>Seventy,</hi> Standing Officers in the Christian Church, than the like <hi>Commission,</hi> recorded Mat. X. could constitute the <hi>Twelve</hi> Governours of the Christian Church? But it's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that the <hi>Commission</hi> recorded Mat. X, did not constitute the <hi>Twelve,</hi> Governours of the Christian Church; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, what need of a new <hi>commission</hi> to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, after the Resurrection?</q>
               </p>
               <p>NOW let the Reader judge, whether the disparity of the <hi>Twelve</hi> and <hi>Seventy,</hi> ben't a very tottering Foundation, to build their <hi>Episocopacy</hi> upon.</p>
               <p>BUT it's Time I take notice of his Third sort of Officers; and consider whether <hi>Deacons</hi> were invested with some share of the <hi>Apostolick Office,</hi> particularly of <hi>pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ching</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> The only way to know what was their Office, and what their Power, is to have recourse to their Original Institution; we find it in Acts VI. 2, 3. <hi>It is not reason, that we should leave the Word of God, and serve Tables; therefore Brethren look you out, seven Men of honest Report, full of the Holy Ghost and Wisdom, whom we may appoint over this Business.</hi> Is here the least shadow of Authority, for their <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>?</hi> Is not is propos'd as the whole of their Work, to <hi>serve Tables?</hi> And is it not plainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuated, that they had no Authority to <hi>preach</hi> or <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize,</hi> in that the care of the Church Stock, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed unto them on purpose, to disentangle those from secular Encumbrances, whose Business this was; that they might not be forc'd <hi>to leave the Word of God?</hi> I would therefore, with respect to these <hi>Deacons,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind this Author of the Apostles Challenge, Rom. X. 15. How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> except they be sent?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="unknown:002525_0011_0FDB5F667433C118"/>BUT he tells us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> That <hi>Philip by his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, converted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and initi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ted the Converts there, into the Christian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> by Baptism.</hi> To which it's sufficient Answer, that <hi>philip</hi> was an <hi>Evangelist.</hi> Acts XXI. 8. and in that Capacity, <hi>preach'd</hi> and <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ptized.</hi> He infinuates indeed, that he was dignified with that honourable Title, on account of his <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing:</hi> But I'm sure he can't find the least hint in the Bible, to countenance such an Insinuation. But were it granted, that <hi>Deacons</hi> as such, may be <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists;</hi> they must then have Power of Ordination and Jurisdiction: For <hi>the Work of an Evangelist</hi> (saith Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi> from <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>) was this, to lay the Foundations of the Faith in barbarous Nations, to constitute them Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> &amp;c. and so at length, according to his own Scheme, <hi>Deacons</hi> are become superiour to <hi>Presbyters,</hi>and even co-ordinate with the <hi>Apostles</hi> themselves.</p>
               <p>THUS we see, that there is not such a difference as he pretends p. 12. <hi>between these Gospel Deacons, and those so named under the Presbyterian Model.</hi> If any of these want <hi>Ordination,</hi> it is in those Congregations, where there is not Church Stock to commit to their Care. And I confess, we are not very fond of ordaining Men to a Work, that we know 'em not furnished to discharge.</p>
               <p>HAVING thus undermin'd his Foundation, his Fabrick must necessarily fall. I'll however take the Pains to pull it to pieces, and see what Materials it's made of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remarks">
               <head>REMARKS on the Second HEAD.</head>
               <p>HIS next Business, he tells up P. 13. is, <hi>to make it appear how these Offices were distinguished, and to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate an Imparity among them.</hi> This he essays, by such a tedious and impertinent Harrangue; that <hi>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="8 letters">
                        <desc>〈8 letters〉</desc>
                     </gap>s
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:002525_0012_0FDB5F67926D3190"/>
estinvenire, quam vincere.</hi> It's much more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to know what he would be at, than to answer his Arguments, if there be any thing under this Head, which deserves that Name.</p>
               <p>BUT that I may make way for a distinct Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of what he ought to have prov'd under this Head, I'll state the Case particularly.</p>
               <p>THE Office of <hi>Apostles,</hi> was either <hi>Extraordinary</hi> and Temporary, or <hi>Ordinary</hi> and Perpetual. 'Twas by vertue of their <hi>extraordinary</hi> Office, that they were denominated APOSTLES. Which appears from this, that this Title was given them, on Account of their being sent abroad, of their unfixed Charge, and iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerary Circumstances; and therefore, none but these thus <hi>extraordinarily</hi> sent forth, are any where in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, distinguish'd by that Appellation. But even they themselves, as ordinary Officers in the Church, are stiled <hi>Presbyters.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> V. 1. and 2 <hi>Feb.</hi> V. 1. and 3 <hi>Job.</hi>V. 1.</p>
               <p>THAT the <hi>Apostles</hi> were <hi>extraordinary</hi> Officers, he himself grants; and tells us, p. 33. (as such) what their Powers and Gifts were, which take in his own Words. <q>'Tis acknowledged, that some Things peculiar to the first <hi>Apostles,</hi> were <hi>Extraordinary</hi> and Temporary, and expired with their Persons: such as, their hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been Eye and Ear Witnesses of Christ's Life, Doctrine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Miracles, Suffering, Resurrection, and Ascentio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; their having received their Commission immediately from Christ, their being infallible Guides, in delivering the Doctrines of the Gospel, their unlimitted commission to all the World, and Jurisdiction over all churches, their Power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer miraculous Gifts on others, to discern, Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>its, and to back their Censures with corporal Puni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as on <hi>Annanias</hi> and <hi>Sapp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ira,</hi> and <hi>Elimas.</hi>
                  </q> Thus for their <hi>extraordinary</hi> Power. But besides this,
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:002525_0012_0FDB5F67926D3190"/>
they had <hi>ordinary</hi> Functions, common to other <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> of the Gospel; Such as Preaching, dispensing the Sacraments, ordaining others to the Work of the Ministry; and governing the Church. These things premised, I come now to consider the Question, which should have been,</p>
               <p>WHETHER the <hi>Apostles</hi> in the exercise of their ordinary Function were <hi>Bishops,</hi> superior to <hi>presbyters.</hi> This he ought to have demonstrated, if he would have done any thing to the Purpose: But what his Performance is, we shall see by the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uel.</p>
               <p>THE first Method he proposes for clearing the Cause, is indeed the only right one, and if duly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted, will infallibly answer. It is to consider their <hi>Commissions.</hi> Let us then consider them.</p>
               <p>As for the first <hi>Commission</hi> he speaks of, I've alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy shewn, all Discourse upon that subject to be meer tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing. But true it is, that <hi>when Christ was to leave the Earth, having finished the Work of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be gave the Apostles their Commission, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t 'em into the actual Exercise of their Apostolick Power and office.</hi> Mat. XXVIII. 18, 19, 20. and Joh. XX. 21. Upon this he makes a long <hi>common-place,</hi> in which he dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trously acquits himself. But it's to be observ'd, that he all along considers the <hi>Apostles,</hi> as acting by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this <hi>Commission,</hi> in the exercise of their <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi> and temporary Power; and therefore, (as we heard before) spends his Breath to no Purpose Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, since I have no Controversy with him, about their <hi>extraordinary</hi> Power, I shall not waste Time, in animadverting on the Imperfections of his Discourse, on that Subject: But immediately consider, whether he finds any distinct <hi>Commission</hi> for <hi>Presby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their Authority appears subordinate to that of the <hi>Apostles<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in their ordinary Function. He promises P. 18. <q> To consider the <hi>Commission,</hi> given to the other
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:002525_0013_0FDB5F6FE3B042D0"/>
Order of Church-Officers instituted by Christ, the <hi>Seventy Disciples,</hi> in whom the Order of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and ordinary <hi>Pastors</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> is suppos'd to be founded.</q> And why does he not produce it? If there were any such <hi>Commission,</hi> it is easy to tell us where we may find it. But the plain Truth is, had he search'd till <hi>Dooms-day</hi> for a <hi>Commission</hi> for <hi>Presbyters</hi> distinct from what was given to the <hi>Apostles,</hi> he must have return'd with a <hi>Non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> inventus.</hi> And <hi>where it is not to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad, the King must lose <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THIS Consideration, of the Unity of the <hi>Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> furnishes me with an Argument, unto which I challenge the whole Tribe of the <hi>Prelatists,</hi> to give a Rational Answer. It is this.</p>
               <p>THEY <hi>that are authorized by the same Commission, have the same Office and Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>BUT <hi>all the Ministers of the Gospel,</hi> (the Apostles themselves, in their ordinary Capacity not excepted) <hi>are authorized by the same Commission.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THEREFORE, <hi>it necessarily follows, that they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the same Office and Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THE <hi>Major</hi> of this Argument is self evident; and the <hi>Minor</hi> must stand good, until our Adversaries can produce two <hi>Commissions,</hi> by which Gospel <hi>Ministers</hi> are authorized to the discharge of their Trust.</p>
               <p>ENOUGH has been said already, about the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of ordinary <hi>Pastors</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> to the <hi>Seventy;</hi> that there needs no more Words about it.</p>
               <p>BUT he has one old thread-bare Argument, to prove the Imparity he pleads for, which has been so often exploded by those of his own Party, and so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten resuted by the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> that the mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it at this time of Day, is perfectly ridiculous. However, let's hear what he has to say. <q>From the Account we have (says he, P. 19, 20.) of them, and their Ministry, in the Sacred History; we can't
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:002525_0013_0FDB5F6FE3B042D0"/> 
frame a more just and true Notion of this second Order of Church Officers, than that they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted to be Assistants and Helpers to the Apostles in the Work of the Gospel. And I know nothing which will give us a better Reason for this Notion, than this Consideration; that as it is the same <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> the same <hi>Master-builder,</hi> who had framed the Civil and Ecclesiastical Policy among the Jews, under the Legal Dispensation, who does erect this new Fabrick of the Gospel Church; so it's reasonable to expect as great Symmetry and proportion between the one and the other, as the Difference of the two Dispensations will allow, &amp;<hi>c.</hi>
                  </q> Unto which he adds Instances of <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons, install'd in the Priests Office, and the <hi>Levites</hi> subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate unto them; and <hi>Moses</hi> in the State, and the <hi>Seventy Elders</hi> subordinate unto him.</p>
               <p>THIS Argument, (as indeed most others, adduced by the Party) was consecrated in the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> School <note n="*" place="bottom">Vid. Bellarm. de Cler. Cap. 14.</note>. And the <hi>Romanists</hi> have more Reason to be fond of it, than our <hi>Episcopalians;</hi> unless they also, are for an Universal <hi>Papacy.</hi> For as the <hi>High Priest</hi> in the Jewish Church, and <hi>Moses</hi> in the State, were but one; with the other Orders under them, so should there be (by this Argument) but one <hi>Bishop</hi> (the <hi>Pope</hi>) in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Church; to whom all others should be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</p>
               <p>BUT let the Cause be duly weighed, and I think neither of these can get much by it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. THEN, has not our Lord dissolv'd the Jewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Polity, chang'd their Priesthood, and erected another Constitution? Hear the <hi>Apostle</hi> on this Head, Heb. VII. 12. <hi>For the Priesthood being changed, there is made of necessity, a change also of the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="18" facs="unknown:002525_0014_0FDB5F715567B4B0"/>2. THE Jewish <hi>High Priest</hi> was appointed for a particular Function, which no Officer in the Gospel Church, has any Concern with. <hi>He was daily</hi> (saith the Apostle) <hi>to offer up Sacrifices, first for his own Sins, and then for the People.</hi> Heb. VII. 27. and <hi>to enter into the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>berna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e alone, once every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ear, not without Blood; which be offer'd for himself, and the Errors of the People.</hi> Heb. IX. 7. Whence it necessarily follows, that the Occasion of the Office ceasing, the Order must be abolished.</p>
               <p n="3">3. THE whole <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nick Priestbood</hi> was Typical, and had its full Accomplishment in Christ the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type; it cannot therefore, have any Continuance under the Gospel. The <hi>Apostle</hi> call's this Legal <hi>Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> with all its Appendages, <hi>a Shadow of Good things to come.</hi> Heb. X. 1. And when the Substance is come, the Shadows are done away. But after all,</p>
               <p n="4">4. I'm willing to grant, that <hi>the same Lord and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver,</hi> (to use this Authors Words) and <hi>the Same Master Builder,</hi> who appointed his Worship and publick A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration in the <hi>Jewish Synagogue,</hi> has translated the same into the Christian Church; and thereby has maintain'd a great <hi> Symmetry and Proportion,</hi> between the one and the other. But this is so far from being any Service to the impleaded <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> that it utterly destroys it. Let us hear what two of the most learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and judicious Divines the Church of <hi>England</hi> could ever boast of, say on this Subject.</p>
               <p>THE first is Dr. <hi>Bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Observat. on the 1 Can. p. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>. <q>Among the <hi>Jews,</hi> (saith he) he who was the chief of the <hi>Synagogue,</hi> was called CHAZAN HAKENESETH, <hi>The Bishop of the Congregation,</hi> and SHELIACH TSIBBOR, <hi>The Angel of the Church.</hi> And the Christian Church being model'd, as near the Form of the <hi>Synagogue,</hi>
                     <pb n="19" facs="unknown:002525_0014_0FDB5F715567B4B0"/>
as they could be; as they retain'd many of the Rites, so the Form of the Government was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, and the Names remain'd the same.</q> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain <note n="†" place="bottom">Observat. on the 2 Canon P. 83.</note>,<q>In the <hi>Synagogues,</hi> there was first one, who was called the <hi>Bishop of the Congregation;</hi> next the three Orderers and Judges of every thing about the <hi>Synagogue;</hi> who were called TSEKENIM, and by the Greeks <hi>Presbuter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i,</hi> or <hi>Gerontes,</hi> that is <hi>Elders;</hi> These order'd and determin'd every thing that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the <hi>Synagogue,</hi> or the Persons in it. Next them, were the three PARNASSIN, or <hi>Deacons,</hi> whose Charge was to gather the Collections of the Rich, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tribute them to the Poor.</q> Thus he, than which, nothing can be a more exact Description of the <hi>Pres<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yterian</hi> Form of Government.</p>
               <p>THE second is Dr. <hi>Stillingsleet</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Iten. P. 257.</note>, <q>What shew of Reason (says he) can be given, why the Apostles should slight the Constitution of the Jewish Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, which had no dependance on the Jewish Hierarchy, and subsisted not by any Command of the Ceremonial Law? The Work of the Synagogue not belonging to the Priests as such, but as Persons qualified for instructing others. And again, <note n="†" place="bottom">bid. p. 264.</note> We are to take Notice, that the Rulers of the Church under the Gospel, do not properly succeed to the Priests and Levites under the Law; whose Office was Ceremonial, and who were not admitted by any solemn Ordination, unto their Function.</q> Thus he, with much more to the same Purpose. By which we see, that if our Author <hi>Knows nothing that will give us a better Reason of his Notion,</hi> of the <hi>Imparity</hi> of <hi>Gospel Ministers</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> than the different Orders in the <hi>Jewish Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ood,</hi> (as he tells us P. 19. he does not) we are not like to be much distress'd with his Arguments.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="unknown:002525_0015_0FDB5F72E77D44A8"/>THUS having done with the Consideration of the <hi>Commissions</hi> given to the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and those of a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct Office and Order, he promises P. 23. <q>To shew next, the <hi>Apostles</hi> Authority over other <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>astors</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> in the Church, from Several Instances of their exercising it, in several Respects and Ways, as is recorded in the sacred History.</q> And he grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undertakes for eight Pages together, to exemplify this. But what need of this Pains? Since it's what was never yet called in Question; nor ever like to be, unless his weak trifling Reasons on the Subject, give occasion for it. But has he brought one single Instance to prove, that the <hi>Apostles</hi> as <hi>Bishops,</hi> in the Exercise of their ordinary Office, were superior to other <hi>pastors</hi> and <hi>Teachers?</hi> Not one Syllable to this Purpose! But on the contrary, we find him P. 25. mentioning <hi>Timothy,</hi> (a <hi>Bishop,</hi> as he afterwards tells us) as an Instance to prove, that those inferior <hi>Pastors</hi> serv'd with the <hi>Apostles in the Work of the Gospel, as Sons with their Fathers.</hi> And also bringing in the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the Church</hi> among these inferior Orders, P. 29. And what then becomes of the Succession in the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>post<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate,</hi> if his <hi>Bishop Timotby</hi> was inferior to the <hi>Apos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles?</hi> Or what becomes of his <hi>Diocesan Episcopacy,</hi> if <hi>Presbyters</hi> were <hi>Rulers</hi> in the Church?</p>
               <p>THERE's no need I should longer attend upon his impertinent Discourse on this Subject; I will therefore hasten to some</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversions">
               <head>ANIMADVERSIONS on the third HEAD.</head>
               <p>WHICH is <hi>to examine, whether any of these Offices were Extraordinary and Temporary; and to prove that they were not: But design'd to be perpetual, and standing in the Church.</hi> And this he tells us P. 32. is <q>The Hinge, on which the whole Controversy depends;
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:002525_0015_0FDB5F72E77D44A8"/>
ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, all the Authority and Obligation of Christ's Institution, as to the present Church.</q> One would think, that we are now in a fair way for compromi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing all the Controversy between the <hi>Prelarists</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> and of procuring general Releases from both Parties; for he acknowledges, <hi>That the Apostles extraordinary Powers</hi> (as we have heard him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore describe them) <hi>are ceased;</hi> and <hi>that it was only the ordinary Power and Authority of the Apostles, which was to serve the Edification, good Order and Government, of the constituted Church in all succeeding Ages;</hi> which he pleads for. And if the perpetual Permanence of the <hi>Apostles</hi> ordinary Office, will satisfy; I'll be Security for all the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in the Realm, that they shall heartily acknowledge it: And demand no other Terms in order to their Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ormity, than this very reasonable one; that the <hi>Episcopalians</hi> shall plead for no other Powers, as belonging to the <hi>Apostles</hi> ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Function, but what they can prove from Scripture. But it's well, if this don't prove a Bone of Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at last; for I find this Author, without the least Shadow of Proof, P. 34. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erting it to be part of their ordinary Office, <q>To superintend both Pastors and People, to settle good Constitutions, agreeable to the Word of God, for the orderly and decent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of all the Ordinances of Religion, publick Worship, and other Affairs of Discipline, as the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igence of the Church should require, &amp;<hi>c.</hi>
                  </q> And if these things be not granted him, all his fine Scheme will come to nothing, and his <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aborate Treatise</hi> may be even used for waste Paper. And yet the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> can by no Means by brought into these Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. THEY can't allow, that the <hi>Apostles</hi> as ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Officers, were to <hi>superintend</hi> both <hi>Pastors</hi> and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; because there is not one lisp in the Bible, of
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:002525_0016_0FDB5F747026EB68"/>
such a <hi>Superintendency</hi> belonging to any ordinary Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer. But on the contrary, the whole Government is committed to <hi>Presbyters,</hi> without any to <hi>superintend</hi> them. See 1 Pet. V. 1, 2. <hi>The Elders who are among you I ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ort, who am also an Elder,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Feed the Flock of God which is among you, taking the Oversight</hi> (Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copountes) <hi>thereof.</hi> Whence I argue,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF presbyters are not only to Feed the Flock of God; but to take the Oversight thereof, or to discharge the Bishops Office over it,</hi> as the Original Word signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies. <hi>They are under the Superintendency of no ordinary Officer in the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>BUT <hi>the former is the Words of the Text; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the latter true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. NOR can the <hi>Presbyterian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> grant, that Christ has left it with any ordinary Officers, to settle any <hi>Constitutions</hi> in his Church. Because (as our Author himself truly tells us p. 39.) <hi>We know what a dreadful curse is pronounced against them, who either add to, or take away from, the Institutions of Jesus Christ, in the</hi> 18 <hi>and</hi> 19 <hi>Verses of the </hi> XXII <hi>Chap. of the Revelations of St. John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>BUT if the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are so incredulous, as not to take his bare Word in this Case, though given with the most positive Air; yet they have such Sparks of good Nature left, as to agree with him in this Conclusion; That <hi>there is nothing more evident, upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Examination; than that Christ in instituting these Orders and Offices</hi> (in their ordinary Exercise) <hi>design'd, that they should be standing and unalterable Constitutions in his Church, to continue to the end of the World.</hi> And we will allow him too, the unalterableness of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Office; if he intends no more, (as he tells us P. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. he does not) than <hi>their ordinary Power and 
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:002525_0016_0FDB5F747026EB68"/>
Authority, which was to serve the Edification, good Order and Government of the constituted Church, in all succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ages.</hi> But is he means, as it seems he does, that the <hi>Apostolate</hi> (properly speaking) is a standing Order in the Church; here we must part ways, and he must bring very good Arguments to prove it, before he can make me his Proselyte. And whether he has such to offer, I'll now particularly consider.</p>
               <p>HIS first Argument is taken from their <hi>Commission,</hi> and the Promise subjoyn'd, <hi>Lo I am with you alway, to the end of the World! But how could that be,</hi> (says he) <hi>if their Office was to expire with themselves?</hi> How indeed? <hi>We must therefore</hi> (as he says) <hi>understand it as a Promise not to them only; but to their Successors also.</hi> But the Question is, What is this Succession, unto which the promise is made? Is it a Succession in the <hi>Apostolate</hi> only? If so, there is then no <hi>Commission</hi> given, nor Promise made, to any but <hi>Apostles,</hi> and so consequently, there is but one Order of Gospel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters in the Church; none but <hi>Apostles,</hi> to discharge any Ministerial Function. But I hope he will allow us enough of these, to <hi>Disciple all Nations, to Baptize and to Teach 'em, whatsoever Christ has commanded.</hi> And I'M sure, the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will be no loosers by that Bargain, let these <hi>Paroc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ial Apostles</hi> be called <hi>Bishops, Presbyters,</hi> or what else our Author pleases. In a Word, this Argument is so far from establishing an Impari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty among the Ministers of the Gospel, that it plainly proves, that there is but one Order in the Church, since the <hi>Commission</hi> is but one; and the succession to the <hi>Apostles</hi> by vertue of that <hi>Commission,</hi> but one. If <hi>Bishops</hi> be the <hi>Apostles</hi> Successors; there are no <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi> inferior to them. If <hi>Presbyters</hi> be the <hi>Apostles</hi> Successors, there are no <hi>Bishops</hi> Superior to them. Let which will be assum'd, the Consequence is the same. Thus we are prepar'd to attend his second Argument.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="unknown:002525_0017_0FDB5F7C073FBA68"/>WHICH is taken from 1 Cor. XII. 28. <hi>God hath set some in the Church, first Apostles, secondarily Prophets, thirdly Teachers, after that Miracles, then Gifts of Healing, Helps, Governments, diversities of Tongues.</hi> Whence he triumphs, <q>God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ath Set,—even he who settled the Ordinances of Heaven, which none can alter, hath fixed these different Orders in the Church.</q> If this be so, that these Orders are fixed in the Church, these Consequences must necessarily follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. THAT there are not only <hi>Apostles</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> but also <hi>Prophets</hi> distinct from both, fixed in the Church: For these are not only named with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but forced into a Class, distinct from them both. First <hi>Apostles,</hi> SECONDARILY <hi>Prophets,</hi> thirdly <hi>Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</hi> And thus, he who the last page, would allow us but <hi>One</hi> Order of <hi>Ministers,</hi> has now furnish'd us with <hi>Three,</hi> and by both spoil'd his own Scheme.</p>
               <p n="2">2. IT will also follow, that <hi>Miracls, Gifts of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and diversities of Tongues,</hi> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Church, and of perpetual Permanence. This Consequence cannot be evaded, by saying; that <hi>they are not distinct Offices from these, but extraordinary Gifts confer'd on them.</hi> For (to use his own Words) <hi>God hath Set, even he who settled the Ordinances of Heaven,</hi> which none can al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, hath as well set <hi>Miracles, Gifts of Healing, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versities of Tongues,</hi> as <hi>Apostles, Prophets</hi> and <hi>Teachers.</hi> To say that these are <hi>Extraordinary,</hi> the others not, is to quite destroy his Argument, from God's having SET those in the Church. For the Text assures us, that he hath SET these there also.</p>
               <p>HIS third Argument, is taken from Eph. IV. 11, 12, 13. <hi>He gave some Apostles, some Prophets, some Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and Teachers; for the perfecting the Saints, for the Work of the Ministry, for the edifying the Body of Christ; till we all come in the Unity of the Faith,</hi> &amp;c, <q>where it is plain, (says he) these Offices were
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:002525_0017_0FDB5F7C073FBA68"/>
to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>inue till the Church should be perfected, fully brought in, and fully advanced; and till it should be beyond all hazard of being seduced; that is to say, until the end of the World.</q> This Text is very agreeable to the former, and the Answer may be the same; that if these Offices are to continue to the end of the World, they are all of 'em to continue so long, and then we shall have four Orders of Church-Officers, besides <hi>Deacons,</hi> when he pleads for but three in all. And were that absurd, and even ridiculous Assertion of his p. 38, granted him, That <hi>these different Designations, dont import diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Offices, but different Exercises of the same Office:</hi> yet the Text makes these as permanent as the other. His <hi>Apostles</hi> therefore, must (according to that Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) be <hi>Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Evangdists,</hi> to the end of the World, as well as <hi>Bishops.</hi> And when we find these fixed <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cesan Bishops,</hi> whilst such, not only endowed with the Gift of <hi>Prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> but travailing through the World, to <hi>Evanmgelize</hi> the Nations; we'll allow 'em to be the Apostles Successors.</p>
               <p>BUT the plain Truth of the Business is, that the <hi>Apostolate</hi> was a Temporary Office, calculated only for the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant State of the Church; and as Such, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of in both these Texts. And the ordinary Office of <hi>Pastor</hi> and <hi>Teacher</hi> only, to continue <hi>until we all come in the unity of the Faith.</hi> That the <hi>Apostolick Office</hi> was <hi>Extraordinary,</hi> and admitted of no Succession, I thus Prove.</p>
               <p n="1">1. THE <hi>Apostles</hi> had an <hi>extraordinary</hi> Call to their Office; and were never brought into it, in an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Way, and therefore when a Successor was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to <hi>Jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> Act. I. they chose him by <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that the Affair might be left wholly to God's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision; and did not presume to separate him to the Work, by <hi>Ordination.</hi> Nor indeed, did the <hi>Apostles ever ordain</hi> any, to their own Office and Order. I 
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:002525_0018_0FDB5F7E2330F4F8"/> 
Challenge the World to produce one Instance of such an <hi>Ordination.</hi> But on the contrary, it is essential to the <hi>Apostolical</hi> Character, that they be <hi>Apostles, not of Men, nor by Men: but by Jesus Christ, and God the Father, who raised him from the Dead,</hi> Gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I. 1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. THERE were <hi>extraordinary</hi> Qualifications ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to the Apostolick Office. We have them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly mentioned, when a Successor was to be chosen to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Acts I. 21, 22. <hi>Wherefore of these Men which have companied us, all the time that the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus went in and out among us, beginning from the Baptism of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, unto that same Day, that he was taken up from us; must one be crdain'd, to be a Witness with us, of his Resurrection.</hi> Whence it plainly appears, that none could be admitted into the <hi>Apostolate,</hi> but such as had seen Jesus, both before his Death, and after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection.</p>
               <p n="3">3. THE <hi>Apostles</hi> had an universal and <hi>unlimited Commission;</hi> and were sent to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Kingdoms, to Gospelize the Infidel Nations. On which account especially, they are distinguish'd by the Title of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>POSTLES, as we heard before. It is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but Nonsense, to talk of <hi>Diocesan Bishops</hi> succeeding them, whose <hi>Power</hi> is limited.</p>
               <p n="4">4. THERE were <hi>extraordinary</hi> Gifts confer'd on the <hi>Apostles,</hi> to qualify them for the Exercise of their extraordinary Power and <hi>Commission;</hi> such as the Gifts of Miracles, of Tongues, infallibility of Doctrine, transcendent E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>icacy and Energy in Preaching, &amp;<hi>c.</hi> And as <hi>Spanbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius</hi> truly affirms <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 3. Num. 25 &amp; Seq.</note>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Every one that was e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dued with a proper Apostolick Power, had, and could give visible Proof, and occu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar Demonstration of these Gifts.</hi> I'll therefore conclude this Argument, with his Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to the <hi>Pope,</hi> with but little Variation. <hi>Let the
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:002525_0018_0FDB5F7E2330F4F8"/>
Bishops as did the Apostles, declare, that they have the Gifts of Tongues divinely insused; let them bring visibly the Gifts of the Holy Ghost from Heaven, let 'em work like the Apostles, such illustrious Miracles, and then we shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ield, that they have Apostolick Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THUS having seen, what Cause of Triumph our Author has on this Subject. I'll leave him to clap his Wings, and crow over the poor ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>led <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> and proceed to some.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remarks">
               <head>REMARKS on his Fourth HEAD.</head>
               <p>Which is <hi>to shew, who succeed in these Offices, and rightly execute them to this Day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>HE teils us p. 41. That <hi>be need but do it, of the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessers to the Apostles; for when that is done, the other come in of course.</hi> But I enquire, how do they come in? Do they come in <hi>at the Door,</hi> or <hi>climb over the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld?</hi> I'm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure, except they are Successors to the <hi>Apostles,</hi> in their ordinary Office, he can find no <hi>Commission</hi> in the Bible, to bring them in. However, let us follow him in his own Path.</p>
               <p>AFTER a triumphant Narrative of the Feats he has perform'd, under the former Heads; (which I think I have sufficiently animadve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed upon already) he proceeds to this Argument:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>EITHER <hi>Bishops</hi> must be the true Successors to the <hi>Apostles,</hi> or else they have no successors at all; and the <hi>Apostolick</hi> Order and Office is quite extinct; and the Church is totally depriv'd of the prime and chiefest Office, instituted by Christ, for its Edi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, good Order, and Government.</q>
               </p>
               <p>THIS Argument I acknowledge, is invincible; and therefore, I must yield the Cause, that <hi>Bishops are the Apostles true Successors;</hi> and that none but they have any Powers from the <hi>Commission,</hi> or any Claim to the
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:002525_0019_0FDB5F7FF7E31160"/>
Promise given to the <hi>Apostles.</hi> But then, the Ques<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, who these <hi>Bishops</hi> are, whether the <hi>Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> who su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintend many hundred Congregations; and none but such: Or whether it be the <hi>Pastor</hi> of each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregation. If the latter be granted, we have no Quarrel with him on this Subject. If the former be supposed, he would have done well to have offered some Proof upon that Head. For though the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> do allow the Succession of <hi>Bishops,</hi> to the Apostles; they are not so good humour'd as to grant, what he in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inuates P. 44. Without the least shadow of Proof; that these <hi>Bishops</hi> are superior to ordinary Pastors and Teachers; or that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly succeed to the <hi>Apostolick Office.</hi> But whether we'll allow it or not, he is resolved to stand by the Cause, and defend it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> possible. And could he justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy what he further offers, as an Argument for his <hi>Episcopal Succession,</hi> he would I confess, bid very fair for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>IT's evident(says he) also from Scripture, that the <hi>Apostles</hi> in their own Time, did con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er on others the <hi>Apostolick</hi> Power and Authority.</q> But how is this evident? He makes it evident to any Man that is resolved to believe it, from the Election of <hi>Matthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> to the <hi>Apost<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>late.</hi> 
                  <q>Their (the Apostles) first work (says he P. 45.) was to ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se one to succeed <hi>Judas;</hi> and by the direction of God, <hi>Matt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> is receiv'd into the Number of the Apostles.</q> Did the <hi>Apostles</hi> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er on <hi>Matth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> the postolick Power? No! It plainly appears that they neither did, nor could do it; in that they so solemnly refer the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>se to God, by a <hi>Lot,</hi> and depend upon his immediate Direction. If they could (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inuates) have committed the <hi>Aposto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ck</hi> Office, into the Hands of other faithful Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, why did they lot <hi> ordain Matthias</hi> to the Charge,
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:002525_0019_0FDB5F7FF7E31160"/>
without referring the Election to God's immediate Decision? or why did they number him among the eleven <hi>Apostles,</hi> without <hi>Ordination?</hi> The Reason of this plainly is, because this Office was <hi>Extraordinary,</hi> and the Call to it must therefore be so too.</p>
               <p>BUT he has more Evidence to produce, well wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of our most serious Attention! It is this. <q>So when <hi>James</hi> the Brother of John, is killed by <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rod,</hi> another of that Name, was <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Jerusalem.</hi>
                  </q> And is not this an invincible Argument, to prove, that the <hi>Apostles</hi> (who according to him were all of 'em Bishops) did confer upon others, the <hi>Apostolick Power</hi> and Authority, because <hi>James,</hi> who was one of the Apostles, was <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Jerusalem?</hi> But he tells us. <hi>That this James, some will have to be another, than James commonly called the les<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, one of the first Twelve Apostles.</hi> But who are these some? and why will they have it so? I'm sure no Man living can give a good Reason, why this <hi>James</hi> he speaks of, was not the Son of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus,</hi> numbred with the <hi>Twelve.</hi> Mat. X. 3. And I'm as sure, that there is not one Word in the Bible to support this chimerical Notion, of his <hi>Episcopacy.</hi> And this, I think every body will be convinced of, when they see what is offer'd for the Proof of it. I will therefore give the Reader the Entertainment, of every Word this Author offers, to confirm this Point. And</p>
               <p>FIRST he tells us <hi>'Twas be, to whom St. Peter</hi> (as <hi>Bishop of Jerusalem) notifies, his miraculous Deliverance.</hi> Acts XII. 17. A most convincing Argument! For we know, Peter could not notify his Deliverance, to any but Bishops.</p>
               <p>HE subjoins, 'Twas <hi>he, who presided in the Council of Jerusalem.</hi> Acts XV. But how does that appear? I'm certain, there is not the least li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p of that kind, in the place refer'd to, unless his declaring his <hi>Sentence,</hi> or Opinion, of the Affair debated, be supposed an Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:002525_0020_0FDB5F811803F300"/>
of it; and if so, <hi>Peter</hi> must also be <hi>President</hi> of that <hi>Synod;</hi> for he, as well as <hi>James,</hi> declares his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the Case before them. But were it granted, that <hi>James presided</hi> in the <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> what will he get by it? Is every <hi>Moderator</hi> of a <hi>Synod</hi> a <hi>Bishop,</hi> in the Sense he pleads for? If so, there are many more <hi>Bishops,</hi> than he is willing to allow.</p>
               <p>THUS we are come to the last Proof, of <hi>James's Episcopacy,</hi> and that is, <hi>It was He to whom St. Paul made his Address, when he came thither; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of whom he speaks, in the 19 Verse of the first Chap. of the Epistle to the Galations, whom he calls an Apostle, and the Lord's Brother.</hi> The Argument stands thus, <hi>Paul went in unto James;</hi> therefore <hi>James</hi> was a <hi>Bishop Paul</hi> calls him <hi>an Apostle, and the Lord's Brother;</hi> therefore he was <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Jerusalem. Risum ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>s amici.</hi> Can Men pretend to found their Faith upon such ridiculous Whimsies, the very mention whereof, is enough to excite Mirth, in the most <hi>fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gmatick Complexion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>AND now let us see, what more he can offer to make it <hi>evident, that the Apostles did in their own time, con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er the Apostolick Power on others.</hi> 
                  <q>Certain it is, (saith he) that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> were received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Apostolick Office; Paul</hi> immediately called there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by Christ, at his Conversion; but <hi>Barnabas</hi> in the ordinary manner, when he received that new Name from the <hi>Apostles,</hi> which signifies Son of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation.</q> I hope he won't pretend, that the <hi>Apostles</hi> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er'd the <hi>Apostolick</hi> Power on <hi>Paul,</hi> since he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges his immediate Call: And the <hi>Apostle</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self informs us, 1 Cor. XV. 8. That <hi>Christ was seen of him, as of one born out of due time.</hi> By which it appears, he had that necessary Qualification for the <hi>Apostolick</hi> Office, a <hi>Sight of Christ.</hi> Though his Vision of Christ, and Commission of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, were late, and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, on which account h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> stiles himself <hi>an Abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="unknown:002525_0020_0FDB5F811803F300"/>
And as to <hi>Barnabas,</hi> does he bring the least hint from Scripture, to prove his <hi>mediate</hi> Separation to the <hi>Apostolate,</hi> though he so confidently asserts it? Did he think, that his bare Word would be taken in this Case, without the least pretence of Proof? Or that it was a sufficient Argument, to prove his <hi>mediate Call,</hi> that <hi>he receiv'd a new Name from the Apostles, which signifies Son of Consolation?</hi> By a like Argument, this Author may expect to be an <hi>Apostle</hi> himself? he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving so famously merited the Name of <hi>Boanerges,</hi> by his Thunder against the Schismaticks. But I'm weary of such trifling, and will therefore see, if he can find any thing more to the purpose; when he comes to give <hi>Instances of some raised from among the ordinary Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, to the Apostolical, or Episcopal Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>HIS first Instance is, The most Reverend Father in—, his Grace, <hi>Timothy,</hi> Lord <hi>Arch-Bishop</hi> of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.</hi> Of whom he tells us, p. 47. <hi>That Paul actually gave him an Episcopal power, over the Church of Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sus, and the Presbyters and Pastors thereof.</hi> To which I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer:</p>
               <p n="1">1. THE <hi>Scriptures</hi> no where give so much as the Title of <hi>Bishops,</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus;</hi> and how then came they by that Character? The <hi>Postscripts</hi> do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed call 'em <hi>Bishops;</hi> but every one conversant in Books, knows, that they are no part of the Canon of Scripture, nor to be found in any ancient Copy of the <hi>New Testament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Timotby</hi> was so far from being <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Epbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that it's abundantly evident from Scripture, he never was fixed there at all. Particularly, it's unaccountable if <hi>Timothy</hi> was there, that <hi>Paul</hi> should make no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him, in his <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Ephesians;</hi> as he does in all his other <hi>Epistles</hi> to the Churches, that to the <hi>Galati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns</hi> only excepted . It's a sure Evidence, that he was neither <hi>Bishop</hi> there, nor <hi>resident</hi> there. But let us
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:002525_0021_0FDB5F8294718158"/>
take a particular View of his <hi>Peregrinations,</hi> as we find them recorded in the Scriptures; and it will thence plainly appear, that if he was a fixed <hi>Bishop</hi> at any place, he was a pattern of <hi>Nonresidency.</hi> We find him at <hi>Corinth,</hi> when <hi>Paul</hi> wrote from thence, his <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Romans.</hi> Rom. XVI. 21. He was with <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Phillippi,</hi> when he wrote his first <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians.</hi> 2. Cor. I. 1. He was with <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> when he wrote his <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Phillippians</hi> from thence. Phil. II. 19. And also when he wrote his <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Collossians.</hi> Col. I. 1. He was also his Companion when he wrote both his <hi>Epistles</hi> to the <hi>Thessalonians;</hi> as appears from the first <hi>Verse</hi> of each <hi>Epistle.</hi> We find him likewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e invited by the <hi>Apostle</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> to be helpful to him in the <hi>Ministry.</hi> 2 Tim. IV. 9, 10, 11. From whence, he intened to take him along with him, <hi>to visit the Churches of Judea.</hi> Heb. XIII. 23. To all which I may add, he was a <hi>preacher</hi> for some con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable time, to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> 2 Cor. I. 19. And now, would it not make a Man smile, were he never so serious; to hear of a <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> who has the whole World for his <hi>Diocess;</hi> especially, when there is not the lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Word in the Scripture, to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance his having any fixt Charge there. Ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries</hi> do indeed urge to that purpose, 1 Tim. I. 3. <hi>As I besought thee to abide still in Ephesus, that thou might<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est charge some, that they preach no other Doctrine.</hi> But the Argument is the quite contrary way. For to what end should the <hi>Apostle</hi> entreat a <hi>Bishop,</hi> to tarry in his own <hi>Diocess,</hi> when he could do no other, without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending God, and neglecting his Duty?</p>
               <p n="3">3. IT's certain, he was no Bishop of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> when the <hi>Apostle Paul</hi> took his last leave of that Church. For then he commits to the <hi>Presbyters</hi> the oversight thereof, and gives 'em a most solemn Charge of the <hi>Church,</hi> as the proper <hi>Bishop</hi> of it. Acts XX. 17. 28.
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:002525_0021_0FDB5F8294718158"/>
And yet this is the last time they ever saw the <hi>Apos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle's</hi> Face, as is evident from Verse 25. But it's time I consider, what our Author adduces, to prove this <hi>Episcopacy</hi> of <hi>Timothy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>HE is instructed (says he) in all the Exercises of the <hi>Episcopal</hi> Power, particularly to command and charge them, (the <hi>Pastors</hi>) that they <hi>Preach sound Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</hi>
                  </q> And han't every <hi>Minister</hi> Authority, as <hi>Christ's Ambassador,</hi> to charge his Brethren as well as others, to be <hi>faithful?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>HE was also (says he) to prescribe <hi>Rules</hi> for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worship; particularly that <hi>Prayers</hi> be offered up for all in Authority.</q> That is, he was exhorted, 1 Tim. II. 1, 2, <hi>To Supplications, Prayers, and giving of Thanks, for all Men; for Kings, and for all that are in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> Therefore was to prescribe <hi>Rules</hi> for publick Worship. The meaning no doubt is, that he was by his <hi>Episcopal Authority,</hi> to put out a New <hi>Common Prayer Book;</hi> since there is no praying for <hi>kings, and all in Authority</hi> without.</p>
               <p>ANOTHER Instance of his <hi>Episcopal</hi> Power, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd by this Author, is, That he was <q>to examine and judge, Persons duly qualified for the <hi>Sacred</hi> Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pel; and give imposition of Hands to, or to <hi>ordain</hi> none, but such as are found duty qualified&amp;<hi>c.</hi>
                  </q> And what Inferrence would he make from hence? But that <hi>Timothy</hi> had the Power of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,</hi> which he would have had, were he but a common <hi>Presbyter.</hi> If he would infinuate, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>Timothy</hi> was admonished, <hi>to lay Hands suddenly on no Man;</hi> he had the sole Power of <hi>Ordination;</hi> it's just as much to the purpose, as if he should argue, that he had the sole Power of <hi>exhorting and teaching,</hi> because the <hi>Apostle</hi> charges him, to <hi>be instant, in sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and out of season, in preaching the Word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="unknown:002525_0022_0FDB5F8BC552D2D0"/>A further Argument of this <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Authority, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thus proposes. <q>He was to guard di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gently against false Doctrines, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>educing Spirits, and to put the Brethren in mind, and command them, that they give not heed to such Doctrines and Seducers.</q> And is not this the Duty of every Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pel <hi>Minister,</hi> without this superior <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Authority?</p>
               <p>HE was also (saith this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <q>To judge, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, and confute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> after due Examination, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</q> But is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here a Word of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ering Pres<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ters, in the Text <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to? He is indeed there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>no to receive</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> But were i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> granted, that he had this Authority, and what further is plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed for, of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Deac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> This will nothing distinguish him from other <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> who in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with others of their Order, might exercise all these Powers. After all, if we low, (what I'm sure can never be prov'd) that he had a Power over other <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vested <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his own Person, he was an <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>2 Tim. IV. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and as such, was desir'd to carry a while at <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to regulate Affairs in that <hi>instant Church,</hi> and give a check to those <hi>Wolves,</hi> which the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> foresaw Acts XX. 29. would <hi>enter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> as well as to direct and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> who wanted the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of such an <hi>extraordinary</hi> Person. How vain therefore, is all Argument from such an <hi>extraordinary,</hi>to an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Church Officer?</p>
               <p>OUR Author foresaw this <hi>Objection,</hi> and attempts the removal of it, by telling us, P. 49 <q>Tis altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther groundless; for we find no such Office of an <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> instituted, distinct from that of <hi>Apostle,</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="unknown:002525_0022_0FDB5F8BC552D2D0"/>
Presbyte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>;</hi> but that it was a common De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signation to all, who were the first Planters of the Gospel, among <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Heathens.</hi>
                  </q> What Doctrine is this? Does not the Apostle plainly tell us, Eph. IV. 11. That our ascended Lord gave to his Church, not only <hi>some Apostles, some Prophets, same Pasters and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> but some Ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngelists also? And agreeably, the Ancients always esteem'd <hi>Ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngelists</hi> to be <hi>extraordin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Officers, distinct from other <hi>Past<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs.</hi> Hear what <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> says of them <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <q>They obtaining (says he) the first Step of <hi>Apostolick</hi> Succession; and being as divine Disciples of the chief and principal Men, builded the Churches every where, plan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed by the <hi>Apostles.</hi>—Next taking their Journey, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Work and Office of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> that is, they preached Christ unto them, that had not yet heard of the Doctrine of Faith; and publish'd earnestly the Doctrine of the holy Gospel. These Men, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving planted the Faith in sundry new and Strange Places, <hi>ordain'd</hi> there, other <hi>Pasters,</hi> committing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>illage of the new Ground, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ght of such as were lately converted unto the Faith; passing themselves, unto other People and Countries, &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>THUS I've gone through what he has to offer for the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> And now let us hear, how he proves <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to be <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 
                  <q>The like Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority (says he) is confer'd on <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Churches of <hi>Crete,</hi> that he should <hi>set in order the things that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and ordain Elders,</hi> or Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters <hi>in every City;</hi> and that he should stop the Mouths of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, who taught things which they ought not; and that he should <hi>rebuke them sharply, that they may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </q> To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer,
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:002525_0023_0FDB5F8D16E97E68"/>
                  <hi>crete</hi> being at this time unsetled with Pastors, the very Errand he was left there upon, was to <hi>ordain Elders in every City;</hi> and these <hi>Elders</hi> so ordin'd, were all of 'em <hi>Bishops,</hi> Tit. I. 6, 7. And therefore, there was no need of his continuance with them, under the Character of a <hi>Bishop;</hi> nor did he tarry long with them, as Dr. <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>by</hi> not only acknowledges, but proves from <hi>Scripture.</hi> 
                  <q>As for <hi>Titus,</hi> (Says he) he was only left a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Crete,</hi> to <hi>ordain Elders in every City,</hi> and <hi>to set in order the things that were wenting;</hi> and having done that Work, he had done all that was assign'd him in that Station; and therefore, St. <hi>Paul</hi> sends for him the very next Year, to <hi>Nicopolis,</hi> Tit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll. 12.</q> Thus he, to which nothing need be added, since whatever occurs on this Head, has been parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly answer'd already.</p>
               <p>THUS having quit out Hands, of the <hi>Episcopacy</hi> of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> his <hi>Hierarchy</hi> has but one Refuge more to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to, and that is the <hi>Apocaliptick Angels,</hi> who I suspect will also fail him, and not prove his Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians in this conflict.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>What has been hitherto observ'd, makes it to me very evident, (says he) and I think, may make it to any other unprejudiced Person, at least highly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the <hi>Angels</hi> of the Seven Churches of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> were Persons of the <hi>Apostolical</hi> and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Order. For since there was such an Order of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and <hi>Bishops</hi> instituted by Christ in his Church—who else could these <hi>Angels</hi> be, but Officers of this higher Order?</q> In answer to which, I'll endeavour to imitate his Brevity, and waving all other Arguments, to disprove this fond conceit; will only offer plain <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that these <hi>Angels</hi> are (as the Word <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> frequently is) taken in a collective Sense, as including not only the <hi>Ministers</hi> of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> but even the whole <hi>Churches</hi> themselves. Thus
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:002525_0023_0FDB5F8D16E97E68"/>
the <hi>Epistles</hi> are directed, <hi>unto the Seven</hi> CHURCHES <hi>in Asia,</hi> Rev. I. 4, 11. and always concluded with this <hi>Epiphonema, He that bath a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ear to bear, let him bear, what the Spirit saith unto the</hi> CHURCHES. And thus in the <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Angel</hi> of the Church of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi> is there such a commendation for <hi>Labour and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> such a Complaint <hi>of the lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of their first Love,</hi> such an Exhortation to <hi>Repentance,</hi> and threatning to <hi>remove their Candlestick out of its place,</hi> as are altogether incompatible to a single Person. And what clears this Case, beyond all possibility of Reply, is the <hi>Plural</hi> Expressions, so frequently applied to these <hi>Angels.</hi> For Instance; When the <hi>Angel</hi> of the Church of <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rna,</hi> is exhorted <hi>to fear none of there things,</hi> &amp;c. it is subjoined; <hi>The Devil shall cast some of</hi> YOU, <hi>into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, that</hi> YE <hi>may be tried, and</hi> YE <hi>Shall have Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> &amp;c. Chap. II. Verse 10. Was it some of the <hi>Bishop,</hi> that was to be <hi>cast into Prison,</hi> and a number of him, to be <hi>tried,</hi> and to <hi>have Tribulation?</hi> So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e verse 13. <hi>Antip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> faithful Martyr, was stain among</hi> YOU, <hi>where Satan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>welleth.</hi> Was he slain among the <hi>Bishop,</hi> and had the <hi>Bishop</hi> only, such bad Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, where <hi>Satans seat was?</hi> And to the same purpose, Verse 24. <hi>But unto</hi> YOU <hi>I say, and to the rest in Thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atira.</hi> With several other like Passages, which can by no means agree to a single Person. And how then did it become so very evident to this Author, that <hi>these Angels were of the Episcopal Order?</hi> I confess, I can't envy him the Satisfaction he obtains from such Evidence, but will leave him to the fruition of it, while I take a short View of the <hi>History,</hi> with which he concludes his Arguments, and see, whether he has been more happy in this, than in that, with which he began his <hi>Dissertation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>ALL the <hi>Records</hi> (saith he) we have of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and primitive Church, do harmoniously attest,
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:002525_0024_0FDB5F8F0115B9A8"/>
that this <hi>Order,</hi> and these <hi>Offices</hi> instituted by Christ, were inviolably preserv'd for many Ages, and so po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitive are they, as to that prime Office of <hi>Apostles</hi> and <hi>Bishops,</hi> that they give us particular <hi>Catalogues</hi> of the <hi>Bishops,</hi> who succeeded the <hi>Apostles,</hi> in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning the most famous and principal Churches in the World.</q> It would have been a needles Toil, for this Author to have given his Reader any <hi>Docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of this, or to have produc'd one of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Records,</hi> or so much as one of the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the Church, to prove this bold Assertion; for he knows that the <hi>Laity</hi> are easily put off with Confidence and Assurance. And it is also needless for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to heap up contrary Authorities, against <hi>bold</hi> and <hi>blind</hi> Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. I shall therefore only propose to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration, the Answer of their own Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Iren. part, 2 cap. 6.</note>, to these frivolous Pretences. Who observing, that <hi>Eusebius</hi> makes it a most hard Matter to know, who succeeded the <hi>Apostles,</hi> in the Churches they plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; adds, <q>Say you so, is it so hard a Matter to find out, who succeeded the <hi>Apostles,</hi> in the Churches planted by them, unless it be mentioned in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Paul,</hi> what becomes then, of our unquesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable Line of Succession, of the <hi>Bishops</hi> of several Churches, and the large <hi>Diagrams</hi> made of the <hi>Apos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolick</hi> Churches, with every one's Name set down in his Order, as if the writer had been <hi>Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>renceaul</hi> to the <hi>Apostles</hi> themselves? Is it come to this at last, that we have nothing certain, but what we have is Scripture? And must then the Tradition of the Church be our Rule, to interpret <hi>Scripture</hi> by? An excellent way to find out the Truth doubtless, to bend the Rule to the crooked Stick.</q> And the same Author justly observes<note n="†" place="bottom">Ibid. p. 300.</note> 
                  <q>That from such Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonings
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:002525_0024_0FDB5F8F0115B9A8"/>
of the Fathers, and their mentioning of Successions of <hi>Bishops,</hi> it can never be prov'd, that <hi>Bishops</hi> were of a higher Order, or had any Power over <hi>Presbyters;</hi> nor that in all places, there was so much as any Difference at all between them; nor that they mean'd ought, save a <hi>succession of Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</hi>
                  </q> Thus Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> unto which nothing need be added.</p>
               <p>I will therefore proceed to consider <hi>Calvin's</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, whom he brings for his Voucher in this Case, and would no doubt by this, and several other Quotations from him, have his <hi>Lay Reader</hi> suppose he is wholly on his side. He indeed finds him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging, that the Ancients had <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Bishops;</hi> and he might have added, <hi>Lectors</hi> and <hi>Acolyths,</hi> for <hi>Calvin</hi> mentions these too among the rest, in the place refer'd to. But why did he not tell us, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Calvin,</hi> 
                  <q>The <hi>Bishop</hi> had no Dominion over his Colleagues, the <hi>Presbyters;</hi> but was among them as the <hi>Consul</hi> in the <hi>Senate,</hi> to propose Matters, to enquire the Votes, to preside in Counsels, Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, and Exhortations; to direct the Affair by his Authority, and to put in Execution, what was decreed by common Council. And that even this is introduced by <hi>Humane Consent,</hi> is confessed by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients themselves.</q> I say, why did he not inform us of this also? The Reason is obvious, it would quite have spoiled his Argument, and who would be an Evidence against himself?</p>
               <p>THUS, I've gone through all his Arguments, for the Proof of the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of <hi>Prelacy;</hi> and must submit it to the Readers Judgment, whether any of 'em remain unanswer'd.</p>
               <p>HIS next Business is, to propose three <hi>Objections,</hi> against the Doctrine he propugns; and he discovers his Prudence and Caution, in proposing 'em as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:002525_0025_0FDB5F902D1B9798"/>
as possible to his own Cause, that he might find something to answer. But it would have been kindly done of him, to have allow'd the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> to state their own <hi>Objections:</hi> And I dare say, if he had undertaken to have given any satisfying Answer to the <hi>Reasons</hi> brought by them, against his Doctrine; he would have found Work enough for his Life time. I'll take liberty to propose some few to them, which he may consider at his Leisure.</p>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>Arg. 1. IF the Scriptures ascribe, not only a communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Names; but also of Office and Order, to Bishops and Presbyters; they are necessarily co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate.</head>
                  <p>BUT <hi>the Scriptures do ascribe, a Community both of Names and Office, to Bishop and Presbyter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. THEY ascribe a <hi>Community of Names,</hi> Acts XX. 17, 28. Where those called <hi>Presbyters,</hi> in the 17 Verse, are stiled <hi>Bishops</hi> in the 28. And the same thing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears with meridian Lustre, from <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 5, 7. Where those called <hi>Presbyters</hi> in the 5th Verse, are also de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominated <hi>Bishops</hi> in the 7th. And</p>
                  <p n="2">2. THE <hi>Scriptures</hi> also ascribe, an Identity of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, to <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters.</hi> Thus 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> V. 1, 3. <hi>The Elders which are among you I exhort, who am also an Elder, &amp;c. Feed the Flock of God which is among you, taking the Oversight thereof.</hi> I'm sure, the Consequence is inevi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>able, that if <hi>Presby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ers</hi> are to take the Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight of the Flock, or as the Original Word signifies, to discharge the <hi>Bishops</hi> Office over it; there is a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of Order</hi> and <hi>Office,</hi> as well as of <hi>Name,</hi> between <hi>Bishop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter,</hi> which was the thing to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>Arg. 2. IF there be no Gospel Ministers in a regularly constituted Church, but Bishops; then Bishop and Presbyter, must be the same Order and Office.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="unknown:002525_0025_0FDB5F902D1B9798"/>BUT, <hi>there are no Gospel Ministers in a regularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitued Church, but Bishops.</hi> As is abundantly evident, from Phil. I. 1. <hi>Paul and T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s the Servants of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us Christ, to all the Saints in Christ Jesus, which are at Phillippi, with the Bishops, and Deacons.</hi> From which Text, we not only find <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> all the Officers belonging to the Church of Phillippi; but it also appears, that there was a plurality of <hi>Bishops</hi> in that Church; and that they were therefore such <hi>Bishops,</hi> as would make but a very <hi>whiggish Figure,</hi> in our Times.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>Arg. 3. IF Presbyters are the only ordinary Ministers of the Gospel, given unto the Church by our ascended Lord, for the Perfecting of the Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, for the work of the Ministry, and for the edifying the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Christ; then Bishops and Presbyters are co-ordinate.</head>
                  <p>BUT that <hi>Presbyters are the only ordinary Ministers of the Gospel, given unto the Church by our ascended Lord,</hi> appears true, from Eph. IV. 11, 12. Where <hi>Pasters</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> are enumerated, as the only ordinary Gospel <hi>Ministers.</hi> And therefore the Consequence is unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iable, that there are no <hi>Bishops</hi> given by Christ to the Church, distinct from these <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and <hi>Teachers.</hi> Enough has been said already, to satisfy any Man, that won't shut his Eyes against clearest Convictions, that the Offices first enumerated in this Text, were <hi>Extraordinary</hi> and <hi>Temporary.</hi> I need therefore take no Notice of that <hi>Objection</hi> now.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="argument">
                  <head>Arg. 4. IF Presbyters have power of Ordination; Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops and Pesbyters are co-ordinate.</head>
                  <p>BUT that <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ters have power of Ordination,</hi> is most undeniably Prov'd, from 1 Tim. IV. 14. <hi>Neglect not the Gift that is in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, which was given thee by pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>esy, with the laying on of the Hands of the Presbytery.</hi> Our Author raises two mean and trivial <hi>Objections,</hi> against
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:002525_0026_0FDB5F98B0E0D140"/>
the pertinency of this Text, to the Purpose for which it's adduced. The first is, that <hi>the presbytery is not to be understood of the Assembly, or Consistory of Presbyters; but of the Mun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, or Office it self.</hi> Very pretty! Then <hi>Timothy</hi> was <hi>ordain'd by the leying on of the Hands</hi> of the Office of a <hi>Presbyter.</hi> The first Office I presume, that ever had Hands. His second <hi>Objection</hi> is, that <hi>the Presbytery did but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> and assist, at the Ordination of Timothy, as is evident, from</hi> 2 Tim. I. 16. <hi>Where the Apostle says, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Gift was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> on him, by laying on of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> But does not the Text expresly say, that he received this Gift by <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of the Hands of the Presbytery?</hi> And I know of no Consequence, that can be drawn from the <hi>Apostle's joyning in this O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> but this; that he was himself a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and therefore not a <hi>Bishop</hi> of the modern Stamp. Which brings me to</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="argument">
                  <head>Arg. 5. IF the Apostles themselves, as ordinary Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of the Gospel, were Presbyters; then Bishops are not Superior to Presbyters.</head>
                  <p>BUT <hi>the Apostles themselves, as ordinary Gospel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, were Presbyters.</hi> Thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pet. V.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>The Elders which are among you, I ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ort, who am also an Elder. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Joh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>The Elder, unto the El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ct Lady.</hi> And 3 Joh. 1. <hi>The Elder, unto the well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>loved Gains</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="argument">
                  <head>Arg. 6. IF there be no mention of Bishops superior to Presbyters, in the whole Book of God; then Bishops and Presbyters are co-ordinate.</head>
                  <p>BUT <hi>I challenge the World to shew any mention, of Bishops Superior to Presbyters, in the Book of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IT <hi>is therefore a just Conclusion, that there is no such thing.</hi> Since it can't be found in the <hi>sacred Records;</hi> especially, since the Word <hi>Bishop</hi> no where occurs in the <hi>New Tes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ment,</hi> but in direct Opposition to <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>acy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="43" facs="unknown:002525_0026_0FDB5F98B0E0D140"/>BUT whither do I run? It's high time to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that my Province is to be a <hi>Respondent,</hi> and not an <hi>Opponent;</hi> I will therefore only besp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>k my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Patience, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> I just propose two or three <hi>Scruples,</hi> with respect to the <hi>Modern Bishops,</hi> which I can by no means get rid of. Hoping this Author will be so Charitable, as to resolve 'em in his next.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. THE first is, How the <hi>Ambassadors</hi> of our <hi>lowly Jesus,</hi> and the Successors of his humble self-denying <hi>Aposties,</hi> came by a <hi>Lordly Dignity,</hi> when expresly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd from being <hi>Lords over Gods Heritage.</hi> 1 Pet. V. 3.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. HOW <hi>Bishops</hi> came by secular Business and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, when expresly requir'd to <hi>give themselves wholl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to the Work of their Ministry.</hi> 1 Tim. IV. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. WHETHER those <hi>Bishops</hi> that are found so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry seldom in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> are the proper Successors to Timothy, who was so strictly charg'd, <hi>To preach the Word, be instant, in Season, and out of Season.</hi> 2 Tim. IV. 2.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
               <p>AND now, having finish'd my Remarks upon this Pamphlet, I shall only add by way of <hi>Conclusion,</hi> a short <hi>Expost<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lation</hi> with the <hi>High-Church</hi> Party.</p>
               <p>WHOSE Interest <hi>Gentlemen, do you think you are driving on, while you are not only <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mning</hi> almost all the <hi>Pretestant Churches,</hi> for want of a <hi>regular Ministry;</hi> but what in you lies, bringing a Contempt upon the Persons, and a Blast upon the Labours, of so many of Christs <hi>faithful Servants?</hi> Is it a light thing, to wound the Consciences of the <hi>weak,</hi> to strengthen the Infidelity of the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rtine,</hi> and to give such matter of Triumph to the <hi>Papis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> by rend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing the very <hi>Baptisms,</hi> and all other sacred Institutions in most <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:002525_0027_0FDB5F9D32EFFE48"/>
Churches,</hi> matter of Question and Debate; and even sapping the <hi>Reformation,</hi> at the very Root? Would not <hi>Mode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> oblige you to question your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, since <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> against so considerable a Part of Christ's Mystical Body; so often refuted by the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and all of 'em condemn'd, by some or other of the most eminent of your own Party? Is not the condemning of <hi>Presbyterian Ordination,</hi> an egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Reflection upon the <hi>Legislature</hi> of the Nation, who have establish'd <hi>Presbytery</hi> in </hi>North Britain?</hi> Nay, is it not an equal Reflection upon the Fidelity of our <hi>Blessed Saviour,</hi> that he should leave so great a Part of his Church, without either <hi>Ministry</hi> or <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances?</hi> Do you think that our Lord Jesus Christ will disown his faithful Servants, in <hi>the Day of his Kingdom,</hi> for their want of external State and Grandeur, and for not submitting to a Government, whereof there is not one Word in the <hi>Scriptures?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>TRULY Gentlemen, some small Allay of <hi>Charity</hi> in your Principles, would render 'em nothing less amiable, to the Protestant World; who maugre all the <hi>Anatbema's</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> or Imputations of <hi>Schism</hi> from HIGH-CHURCH, will Suppose, that <q>The Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which wants <hi>Charity,</hi> is not from God, but that the Error is of the damning side.</q>
               </p>
               <p>OUR Comfort is, that we are not to stand or fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, by your Judgment; but can chearfully go on in our Work, with a refreshing Expectation, that <hi>when the chief Shepherd shall appear, we shall receive the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised Crown of Glory, that fadeth not away.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
