<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three discourses concerning the reality, the extremity, and the absolute eternity of Hell punishments. By William Cooper, A.M. One of the Pastors of the Church in Brattle-Street, Boston. ; Publish'd by desire of many of the hearers. ; [Five lines of Scripture texts]</title>
            <author>Cooper, William, 1694-1743.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 144 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N02941</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N02941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 3526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 3523</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW1085</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">3526</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99006830</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 3526.</title>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 3523.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N02941)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 3526)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 3526; 3523)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three discourses concerning the reality, the extremity, and the absolute eternity of Hell punishments. By William Cooper, A.M. One of the Pastors of the Church in Brattle-Street, Boston. ; Publish'd by desire of many of the hearers. ; [Five lines of Scripture texts]</title>
                  <author>Cooper, William, 1694-1743.</author>
                  <author>Cooper, William, 1694-1743. Divine teaching to be sought ...</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 114, [2], 26 p. ;  16 cm. (12mo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. Kneeland and T. Green, for Joseph Edwards, at the corner shop on the north-side of the town-house.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCCXXXII. [1732]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 50, 70 misnumbered 34, 34.</note>
                  <note>"Divine teaching to be sought, that we may be led into Divine truth. A sermon preach'd February 27th. 1731,2. By William Cooper ... Boston, Printed for J. Edwards. 1732."--[2], 26 p. at end, with separate title page (Evans 3523). Apparently not issued separately.</note>
                  <note>Errata notes, p. 114 and p. 26, 2nd count.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hell.</term>
               <term>Future life.</term>
               <term>Sermons --  Collections.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="unknown:003526_0000_0FF856CB146592A8"/>
                  <pb facs="unknown:003526_0001_0FF812C04E06D200"/>
                  <p>THREE DISCOURSES CONCERNING The <hi>Reality,</hi> the <hi>Extremity,</hi> AND the abſolute <hi>Eternity</hi> OF Hell Puniſhments.</p>
                  <p>BY WILLIAM COOPER, A. M. One of the Paſtors of the Church in <hi>Brattle-Street, Boſton</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Publiſh'd by Deſire of many of the Hearers.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2 Cor. v. 11.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Knowing therefore the terror of the Lord, we perſwade men.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 Cor. xv 11.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>So we preach, and ſo ye believed.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Heb iii. 12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Take heed, Brethren, leſt there be in any of you an evil heart of unbelief.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BOSTON,</hi> Printed by S. KNEELAND and T. GREEN, for JOSEPH EDWARDS, at the Corner Shop on the North-ſide of the Town-Houſe. MDCCXXXII.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="1" facs="unknown:003526_0002_0FF856DCD9327850"/>
                  <head>The Reality <hi>OF</hi> Hell Puniſhments.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>LUKE XVI. 23.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>AND in Hell be lift up his eyes being in torments.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE words belong to that aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and awakening diſcourſe of our Saviour, commonly called the parable of the rich man and <hi>Lazarus;</hi> tho' ſome don't ſo well approve of calling it a parable, for there is no ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude uſed in it. It is rather a narrative or deſcription of the different ſtate of good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> had men in the other world. To illuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> this deſcription, and make it the more
<pb n="2" facs="unknown:003526_0003_0FF812C30B2F24D8"/>ſolemn and affecting, two particular perſons, whoſe circumſtances were very different in this world, are ſuppoſed, and made the ſubjects of it. What is deſign'd to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in the whole, is true in fact; and there are many inſtances and examples of it, in this and in the other worlds. The wicked are, ſome of them, rich, great, and proſperous in this world; but extremely and everlaſtingly miſerable in the next. The godly are, ſome of them, poor, afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, deſpiſed in this world, but infinitely and everlaſtingly happy in the other. This is the ſubſtance, ſcope, and end of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of our Saviour.</p>
                  <p>The words of our text are ſpoken of the wicked rich man. He <hi>died,</hi> as well as the poor beggar; for riches cannot deliver from death. And was <hi>buried,</hi> which is not obſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v'd of the other; had a pompous and coſtly funeral, ſutable to his worldly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tate and degree. But his condition after death, was moſt wretched and miſerable: <hi>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>el <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e lift up his eyes being in torments.</hi> O ſad end of a ſoft and delicate, a careleſs and ſtupid, a ſenſual and voluptuous life!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In hell</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>; in <hi>Hades,</hi> the ſtate of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked dead, the region of damned ſpirits. <hi>He
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:003526_0004_0FF856DF171E6948"/>lift up his eyes:</hi> Not the eyes of his body, for that was buried in the grave; but the eyes of his mind. For (as ſays a judicious writer on the place,<note n="†" place="bottom">Mr.<hi>T. Cruſo,</hi> in his pious and accurate diſcourſes upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Rich Man</hi> and <hi>Lazarus.</hi>
                     </note>) bodily members and ſenſible acts, are aſcrib'd in ſcripture to ſeparate ſouls, by way of alluſion; as they are likewiſe many times aſcrib'd to God himſelf, tho' he be a pure and perfect Spirit. The eyes of his mind, which were ſhut while he liv'd, were opened after death; his underſtanding and conſcience were now awakened, and he was convinc'd of thoſe things which he did not apprehend, or wou'd not believe before. <hi>Being in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> The pains of hell had now actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally got hold upon him; he felt ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the wrath of God upon his ſoul, as were not to be match'd with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt bodily torments in this world.</p>
                  <p>The DOCTRINE I would now offer from theſe words is this, viz.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is a moſt certain and awful truth, That there is a HELL, a place of miſery and torment, in which the wicked ſhall be puniſh'd after this life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="unknown:003526_0005_0FF856AAC2797BE0"/>
Under this Doctrine I propoſe only theſe two things.
<list>
                        <item>1. To give the <hi>proof</hi> and <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> that there is ſuch a place and ſtate of miſery, as we call <hi>hell,</hi> for the puniſhment of wicked and unholy perſons after this life.</item>
                        <item>2. To ſpeak of the awful <hi>ſeaſons</hi> or <hi>periods</hi> at which ſinners paſs into this place of puniſhment.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. To give the <hi>proof</hi> and <hi>evidence</hi> that there is ſuch a place and ſtate of miſery, as we call <hi>hell,</hi> for the puniſhment of the wicked and ungodly after this life.</p>
                  <p>This is indeed no pleaſing ſubject for us to inſiſt upon, but a neceſſary one for you to hear of, which we, who are put in truſt with the goſpel, muſt not baulk. A part of the counſel of God which we muſt not ſhun to declare to you, as we would be found faithful to your ſouls, and to our own, and to our maſter that ſends us. Our LORD JESUS CHRIST frequently preach'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ſubject in the days of his miniſtry. How often and earneſtly did he tell his hearets of <hi>the damnation of hell</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Mat. xxiii 33.</note>, <hi>the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of fire</hi> into which the wicked ſhall be caſt<note n="†" place="bottom">Mat. xiii. 42.</note>, <hi>the place of darkneſs</hi>
                     <note n="‖" place="bottom">Mat. viii. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>where there is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth;</hi> of <hi>the worm
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:003526_0006_0FF856E0A8BC0250"/>that dies not, and the fire that ſhall never be quenched</hi>
                     <note n="‡" place="bottom">Mark ix. 45.</note>, <hi>the everlaſting fire prepared for the devil and his angels</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Mar. xxv. 41.</note>? How many ſuch paſſages might I gather up, and you eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remember, from his ſermons recorded in the holy goſpels? And <hi>we</hi> ſhou'd learn of <hi>Him</hi> how to preach, and fulfil our miniſtry. Surely men need to hear of this now as much as then. Men have within them an evil heart of unbelief, that inclines them to queſtion this truth. Satan endeavours to perſwade them out of the belief of it, as he did our firſt parents. He ſaid to the woman, Tho' ye do eat, <hi>ye ſhall not ſurely die,</hi> Gen. iii. 4. So he ſays to ſinners now, Tho' you do tranſgreſs you ſhall not be damn'd; ye ſhall not ſurely go to hell. He promiſes them impunity, and ſo makes them the ſervants of ſin. Men had need therefore be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in the belief of this truth now, leſt their infidelity be cur'd by woful experience. Hell torments are not a melancholy fancy, no cunningly deviſed fable, nor empty threatning; but an awful truth, a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reality. For</p>
                  <p n="1">1. This is a doctrine that does but agree with the <hi>majeſty</hi> and <hi>authority</hi> of the great God as the <hi>king</hi> and <hi>judge</hi> of the world.
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:003526_0007_0FF856AC95F4BA40"/>The Lord is a great God, and a great king above all gods. He is the king eternal, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, inviſible; the bleſſed and the only potentate: The king of kings, and lord of lords; with whom is terrible majeſty<note n="*" place="bottom">1 Tim. vi. 15. Job xxxvii. 22.</note> Now the kings and princes of the earth you know, have not only their royal pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for themſelves, and for their nobles and attendants, but alſo their <hi>priſons, jails,</hi> and <hi>dungeons,</hi> into which they caſt and ſecure criminals and malefactors, traitors and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators. And this is needful to keep up the greatneſs and ſecure the honour of their government. And ſhall not the great king, whoſe name is dreadful<note n="†" place="bottom">Mal. 1.14.</note>, have a place wherein to ſecure and puniſh thoſe who are ſo hardy and inſolent as to break his laws, and rebel againſt his authority? How wou'd his government be expos'd and weakn'd if it ſhou'd be otherwiſe? This wou'd encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage mutiny in heaven, and rebellion on earth. To what purpoſe would it be for him to call ſinning angels and men to an account, if he had no where to puniſh them for their offences? Thus, 'tis but ſutable to the divine majeſty and authority that there ſhou'd be a hell for the puniſhment of the wicked.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="7" facs="unknown:003526_0008_0FF856E2D906C0E8"/>
2. It is neceſſary for the maintaining and vindicating the divine <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>holineſs.</hi> We know that the Lord is <hi>not a God that hath pleaſure in wickedneſs, neither ſhall evil dwell with him: The fooliſh ſhall not ſtand in his ſight; for he hateth all the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Pſal. v. 4, 5.</note>. He is infinitely oppoſite in his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, will, and works to all moral impurity. And as he has forbidden it in his law, juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice requires him to puniſh it according to its deſerts. <hi>Shall not the judge of all the earth do right</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Gen, xviii. 23.</note>; and therefore make a difference in his diſpenſations, between the righteous and the wicked, between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not? This is not viſibly done in the preſent world. Now wickedneſs ſeems to be conniv'd at, and ſinners to be countenanc'd, rather than otherwiſe, by being indulg'd with outward eaſe, pomp, and proſperity, as was the rich man the text ſpeaks of. This was an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent difficulty, which the people of God ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, and were ready to ſtumble at. Jer. xii. 1. <hi>Righteous art thou, O Lord! Yet let me talk of thy judgments: Wherefore doth the way of the wicked proſper?</hi> Job xxi. 7—13. <hi>Wherefore do the wicked live, become old, yea, are mighty in power? Their ſeed is eſtabliſhed
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:003526_0009_0FF856AF851C4DC8"/>in their ſight with them, and their off-ſpring before their eyes. Their houſes are ſafe from fear, neither is the rod of God upon them.— They ſend forth their little ones like a flock, and their children dance. They take the tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brel and harp, and rejoice at the ſound of the organ: They ſpend their days in wealth —.</hi> The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> was in the like anxiety, being preſs'd with the ſame temptation. Pſal. lxxiii. Init. <hi>As for me my feet were almoſt gone, my ſteps had well-nigh ſlipt. For I was envious at the fooliſh, when I ſaw the proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the wicked. For they are not in trouble as other men, neither are they plagued like other men. — Their eyes ſtand out with fatneſs, they have more than heart can wiſh. — Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold theſe are the ungodly who proſper in the world, they increaſe in riches.</hi> But now that which eaſes the difficulty, and ſatisfactorily clears up the matter is, That 
<hi>the Lord knows h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>w to reſerve the unjuſt</hi> to future puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note n="*" place="bottom">2 Pet. ii. 9.</note>, whom he forbears for the preſent, or touches but lightly. The <hi>rod</hi> of God is not <hi>upon</hi> them now, becauſe his <hi>fury</hi> is to" <hi>reſt</hi> upon them hereafter. We are therefore bid to <hi>judge nothing before the time, until the Lord come</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">1 Cor. iv. 5,</note>. And hence the day of wrath is call'd the day of <hi>the revelation of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:003526_0010_0FF856E5B4DF37A0"/>judgment of God</hi>
                     <note n="‖" place="bottom">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>. ii. 5.</note>. Thus the preſent impunity of the wicked, plainly refers us to a future puniſhment. Pſalm xcii. 7. <hi>When the wicked ſpring as the graſs, and all the workers of iniquity do flouriſh: it is that they ſhall be deſtroyed for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. CHRIST'S <hi>coming into the world, his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and death,</hi> are a convincing argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and proof that there is a hell. Why did He come into the world, but to ſave his people from this place of miſery? "He did not come to ſave them from the leſſer conſequences of ſin, ſuch as the calamities of this preſent life, and bodily death; for to theſe they are ſtill expos'd, tho' he is made redemption to them. It can't rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably be tho't a deſign great eno' for the ſon of God to come from heaven to earth upon, and to lay down his life for, to ſave us only from bodily and temporal evils. Surely our Lord had not come from the <hi>higheſt heavens,</hi> but to ſave us from the <hi>low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt hell.</hi> The ſalvation of Chriſt is call'd <hi>a deliverance from the wrath to come,</hi> 1 Theſ. 1.10. But (as one obſerves upon it) if that wrath be imaginary, ſo muſt our deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from it be too<note n="*" place="bottom">See the Author before reſer'd to, p. 57.</note>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="10" facs="unknown:003526_0011_0FF856B260A3BE50"/>
Moreover, They were the very <hi>pains of hell</hi> which our Lord ſuffered. Indeed, he did not lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally deſcend into hell, to ſuffer there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the damned<note n="†" place="bottom">We are not ſo to underſtand that article of the creed <hi>He deſcended into hell.</hi> The meaning is, That h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> went into the ſtate of the dead, and continued un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of death, till the third day.</note>; nor did he ſuffer after the ſame manner as they do. No, theſe things were abſolutely inconſiſtent with the holineſs, purity, and dignity of his perſon. The ſufferings of Chriſt and the ſufferings of the damned, were therefore neceſſarily different in ſeveral circumſtances of them. Nevertheleſs our Lord did ſuffer in his ſoul ſuch <hi>pains, horror, agony,</hi> and <hi>terror,</hi> as were of the ſame nature and kind with the ſufferings of hell<note n="‖" place="bottom">After this manner very judicious Divines, the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Calvin</hi> and others, ſpeak of the ſufferings of Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>; ſuch as none ever ſuffer'd on this ſide hell, and carried in them the eſſence of the puniſhment of the ſecond death. For the wrath of God due to the elect for their ſins, was poured into his ſoul, and he bore the curſe of the law in the full weight of it. <hi>Gal.</hi> iii. 13. How inconceivably great were his ſufferings in the garden? In his <hi>agony</hi> there <hi>he was afraid, and amazed, and fell flat on the ground:</hi> He
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:003526_0012_0FF856E7393F1B08"/>began to be <hi>ſore amazed,</hi> and to be <hi>very heavy;</hi> and ſaid to thoſe that were with him, <hi>My ſoul is exceeding ſorrowful, even unto death: And his ſweat was as it were great drops of blood falling down to the ground</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Mat. xxvi. 37, 38. Mark xiv. 32. Luke xxii. 44.</note>. And muſt not this ariſe from ſuch a ſenſe of the wrath of God, as is, for the ſubſtance of it, like that ſuffer'd in hell. He felt the ſame in the time of his crucifixion, when that bitter outcry was extorted from him, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou ſorſaken me</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Mat. xxvii 46.</note>? The ſufferings of Chriſt were anſwerable to the pains of hell, and therefore call'd ſuch in ſcripture. For to Chriſt the ſon of <hi>David,</hi> of whom <hi>David</hi> was a type, we may apply thoſe words of the Pſalmiſt, Pſalm xviii. 5. <hi>The ſorrows of hell compaſſed me about.</hi> Pſalm cxvi. 3. <hi>The ſorrows of death compaſſed me about, the pains of hell gat hold upon me.</hi> Chriſt did not feel the ſorrows of hell <hi>after</hi> death, but he felt them in his ſoul while he liv'd, before his death; the very ſame (as has been ſaid) for kind and ſubſtance, tho' not after the ſame manner, and in the ſame circumſtances.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="unknown:003526_0013_0FF856B3E75FA6A0"/>
Here now is another <hi>proof</hi> or <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi> of this truth, That there is a hell for the wicked. If Chriſt did feel and ſuffer the very pains of hell, when he bore the wrath and curſe of God due to the elect for their ſins, then certainly there is a hell, a place provided and prepared, in which the wicked ſhall ſuffer his wrath and vengeance for ever. As our Lord was going to ſuffer and die, he turned himſelf to the company which followed him, and ſaid, <hi>If they do theſe things in a green Tree, what ſhall be done in the dry?</hi> Luke xxiii. 31. As much as if he had ſaid, "If God deliver me up to ſuch ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings as theſe, becauſe I am made a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for ſin, what will he do with ſinners themſelves"? Truly from the bitter ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt, we may juſtly infer what <hi>ſhou'd</hi> have been done to the whole race of mankind, if he had not interpos'd; and what <hi>ſhall</hi> be done to thoſe who die in their ſins, unſanctified and unpardoned. If God did this to the ſon of his love, when he found ſin but imputed to him, what ſhall he do to the children of his wrath, whom he will find under the guilt and reigning power of ſin? The apoſtle argues after this manner in another caſe, 1 Pet. iv. 17. <hi>If judgment begin at the houſe
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:003526_0014_0FF856E98A990728"/>of God, what ſhall the end be of them that obey not the goſpel of God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Men have the <hi>intimations</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages</hi> of this truth within themſelves: <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural conſcience</hi> bears witneſs to it. There are implanted in the minds of men by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, apprehenſions and expectations of a ſtate of miſery after this life, for them that do wickedly. The very heathen have had the apprehenſions of it without the light of revelation<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>What elſe made the Heathen</hi> Emperour <hi>when he lay a dying, cry out,</hi> O animula vagula blandula, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> O my wretched wandring ſoul, whither are thou now haſtning? What will become of me? Live I cannot, die I dare not!</note>. It would take up too much time, and be not ſo fit for the holy ſabbath, nor for a chriſtian and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular audience, to mention what ſome of their <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and <hi>Poets</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">
                        <l>Gnoſſius haec Rhadamanthus habet duriſſima regna:</l>
                        <l>Caſtigatque, audit<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> dolos: ſubigit<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> fateri</l>
                        <l>Quae quis aſud ſuperos, furto laetatus inani,</l>
                        <l>Diſtulit in ſeram commiſſa piacula mortem.</l>
                        <l>Continuo ſontes ultrix accincta flagello</l>
                        <l>Tiſophone quatit inſultans: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>voſque ſiniſtra</l>
                        <l>Intentans angues, vocat agmina ſaeva ſororum.</l>
                        <bibl>Virg. <hi>Aeneid. lib. 6 lin. 566.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <l>Saxum ingens volvunt alij, radiiſque rotarum</l>
                        <l>Diſtricti pendent: ſedet, aeternumque ſedebit</l>
                        <l>Infelix Theſeus; Phlegyaſque miſerrimus omnes</l>
                        <l>Admonet, et magna teſtatur voce per umbras:</l>
                        <l>Diſcite juſtitiam moniti, et non temnere Divos.</l>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>lin. 616.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </note> have ſaid of future puniſhments: Wherein tho' for want of ſcripture revelation their imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations have been vain, yet they give e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to the thing it ſelf written in their conſciences, about which the word of God doth inform us more fully and clearly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="unknown:003526_0015_0FF856B570A798D0"/>
They that are loth to believe this truth, and try to diſpute themſelves out of it, yet can't deliver themſelves from the fears of it. An <hi>awakened conſcience</hi> will ſuggeſt it, let ſinners ſtrive what they can to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence it. Doubtleſs they were the fears of this which caus'd <hi>Belſhazzer</hi> the king to <hi>change his countenance,</hi> and <hi>his knees to ſmite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>neagainſt another,</hi> in the midſt of his impious feaſt, when he ſaw <hi>the hand-writing on the wall.</hi> Dan. v. 5, 6. And this is what the Apoſtle calls <hi>a certain fearful looking for of judgment and fiery indignation,</hi> Heb. x. 27.</p>
                  <p>Nay, not only have all men the fears and apprehenſions of a wrath to come, but ſome have had the very <hi>fore-taſtes</hi> of it. The pains of hell have even gat hold up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them in this world. The <hi>worm</hi> that never dies has <hi>began to bite</hi> them here. "Some have felt ſuch a hell <hi>within</hi> them,
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:003526_0016_0FF856EBB8DEA7A0"/>as has been a plain indication of one <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> them"<note n="‖" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Cain, Lamech, Saul,</hi> and <hi>Judas; Spiva,</hi> and other ſuch affecting inſtances.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. If there is a <hi>heaven</hi> for the good, doubtleſs there is a <hi>hell</hi> for the wicked. The belief of future rewards for good men, does neceſſarily dra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> after it the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of future puniſhments for the wicked. The arguments that prove the one, do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually prove the other alſo. So that if there be a heaven, a place of light, joy, and bleſſedneſs, where the godly are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd and comforted after this life, there is likewiſe a hell, a place of darkneſs, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and miſery, into which the wicked are carried when they leave this world.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The <hi>ſcriptures of truth</hi> do plainly and clearly <hi>reveal</hi> this to us. Here is at laſt the proper proof of the thing. Other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments are ſtrongly preſumptive, but this puts the matter out of doubt, renders the thing beyond all diſpute true; and by this we are to regulate our faith. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is reveal'd in the word of God, challenges the honour of being believ'd becauſe it is there contain'd. Not to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit what is there deliver'd, is to affront the divine veracity, and make God a liar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="unknown:003526_0017_0FF856B90FBDD4B8"/>
The ſcriptures are a <hi>ſure word of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> They have all the evidences that can <hi>reaſonably</hi> be deſir'd, that they are indeed from God. They have been <hi>confirm'd</hi> by numerous ſurprizing miracles; which were all well atteſted, being openly ſhewed in the ſight of the world. And can it be ſuppos'd this <hi>divine ſeal</hi> wou'd be affix'd to a lie? Beſide this outward atteſtation of miracles, the ſcripture has all <hi>internal tokens</hi> and <hi>characters</hi> of divinity. It car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in it ſuch impreſſions of wiſdom, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, majeſty &amp;c. as are nothing leſs than divine. It appears to us in a ſelf-evidenc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing light. They that look into it with a mind rightly diſpos'd, muſt needs find a difference between this and all other books in the world. <hi>For what is the chaff to the wheat? ſaith the Lord God. Is not my word like as a fire, ſaith the Lord? And like the hammer that breaketh the rock in pieces?</hi> Jer. xxiii. 29, 30. The word of God is <hi>quick and powerful, ſharper than any two edged ſword, piercing even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, of joints and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the tho'ts and intents of the heart.</hi> In the reading and hearing of it, many have been <hi>convinced of all, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of all,</hi> and had <hi>the ſecrets of their hearts made manifeſt;</hi> and ſo <hi>falling down on their
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:003526_0018_0FF856EDE85FC120"/>face, have acknowledg'd, God is in it of a truth.</hi> Heb. iv. 12. 1 Cor. xiv. 24, 25.<note n="*" place="bottom">The learned <hi>Francis Junius,</hi> in the account he gives of his own life, tells us how he was in his youth infected with looſe notions in religion, and by the grace of God was wonderfully recover'd, by reading accidentally in a bible, which his good father had deſignedly laid in his way, the 5 firſt verſes of the goſpel of <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hn.</hi> He ſaith, That he obſerv'd ſuch a <hi>divinity in the argument,</hi> ſuch <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> authority and majeſty in the ſtile,</hi> that his fleſh trembled, and he was ſtruck into ſuch an amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that for a whole day he ſcarce knew where he was, and what he did, and from thence he dates the beginning of his being religious.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>In ſhort, If the bible be not the word of God, then there is no divine revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on now in the world; no diſcovery at all of God's mind concerning our duty and happineſs: And can it be ſuppos'd God has left the world wholly deſtitute of what it ſtands in ſo much need of? If therefore there are any who deſpiſe the ſacred ſcriptures, who wou'd contradict and bear down the divine authority of theſe holy books, and laugh at thoſe who regulate their faith, and govern their lives by them; as do ſome of the <hi>ſcoffers</hi> of theſe <hi>laſt days,</hi> affecting to be tho't faſhionable, and to have more ſenſe than the reſt of mankind: There is juſt cauſe to fear their
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:003526_0019_0FF856BB4343AD98"/>
                     <hi>antipathy</hi> to the bible is ſuch as that they will not read it at all; or if they do, that their luſts and prejudices darken their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, and hinder them from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the truth in the love of it: That they try to perſwade themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that it is not true, only becauſe they wou'd not have it to be ſo; for if it be, then <hi>wo, wo, wo,</hi> to ſuch ſcepticks and unbelievers; whoſe peculiar and aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated <hi>condemnation</hi> will be <hi>this,</hi> That <hi>light is come into the world, and they have loved darkneſs rather than light, becauſe their deeds were evil,</hi> John iii. 19.</p>
                  <p>But we know and are aſſured, that the ſcriptures are the word of God, and conſequently the word of truth. And in them the curtain between this and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible world, is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it were drawn back, and we are ſhewn <hi>things that are to come hereafter.</hi> How plainly and abundantly do they tell us, that there is a place of everlaſting miſery and torment, in which the wicked ſhall have their portion aſſign'd them after this life. Both teſtaments are full of it. It is needleſs, and wou'd be almoſt endleſs, to turn you to the ſeveral texts that ſpeak of this. Yea, they tell us of many who are <hi>already</hi> turned into this dreadful place, and are now actually ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:003526_0020_0FF856F0C9C52CC8"/>in it. So are the <hi>ſinning angels.</hi> 2 Pet. ii. 4. <hi>God ſpared not the angels that ſinned, but caſt them down to hell, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered them into chains of darkneſs, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved unto judgment.</hi> So are the ſinners of the <hi>old world:</hi> Their <hi>ſpirits</hi> are now <hi>in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which ſome time were diſobedient, when once the long-ſuffering of God waited in the days of Noah, while the ark was preparing</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">It is the opinion of ſome of the learned, That theſ: ſinners are referr'd to in ſome places of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Proverbs, where hell is call'd <hi>the congregation of the dead.</hi> As in chap. xxi. ver. 16. <hi>The man that wandreth out of the way of underſtanding, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the congregation of the dead.</hi> And in ch. ii. 18. ſpeaking of the ſtrange and fooliſh women, he ſaith, <hi>That her houſe inclines to death, and her paths to the dead.</hi> And ch. x. 18. That <hi>the dead are there, and that her gueſts are in the depths of hell</hi> The hebrew word here us'd and tranſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ed <hi>dead,</hi> is, <hi>Rephaim,</hi> which properly ſignifies <hi>Giants</hi> and is rendred by the ſeventy <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> The meaning ſeems to be this, that the ſtrange woman will bring thoſe who are her gueſts to hell, to keep the apoſtate Giants company. Thoſe mighty men of renown of the old world, (Gen vi. 4, 5) whoſe wickedneſs was ſo great in the earth, that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented and grieved God that he had made man, and to take vengeance upon whom he brought the general deluge upon the earth: Theſe great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors were firſt drown'd, and then damn'd, and ſent to that accurſed place which was appointed for them. And to that place and condition in which they are; the Spirit of God by <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, the harlot will bring her gueſts, thoſe who to follow her, wander out of the way of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. See to this purpoſe, an <hi>Exercitation</hi> upon Prov. xxi. 16. by the very learned <hi>Joſeph Mede,</hi> Vol. 1. p. 41.</note>,
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:003526_0021_0FF856BD27B4EAC0"/>1 Pet. iii. 19, 20. So alſo are the ſinners of <hi>Sodom,</hi> Jude 7. ver. <hi>Even as Sodom and Gomorrha, and the cities about them, giving themſelves over to fornication, and going af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtrange fleſh, are ſet forth for an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſuffering the vengeance of eternal fire.</hi> They were for their abominable and unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural wickedneſs conſum'd out of the earth by fire from heaven, and are now ſuffering the vengeance of hell fire. To this place was committed the ſoul of the <hi>rich man</hi> the text ſpeaks of. And thither went the ſoul of miſerable <hi>Judas,</hi> when he had diſpatch'd himſelf out of this world. Acts i. 25. <hi>From which Judas by tranſgreſſion fell, that he might go to his own place,</hi> i. e. to hell, which was his place by divine appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and his own demerit.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things are enough to prove the Doctrine, and ſet it beyond all ſober con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction. A hell there is; and they that will not be convinc'd of it by ſuch argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:003526_0022_0FF856F24F49D950"/>as theſe, will have a dreadful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of it at laſt by ſenſe and feeling.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. We come now to ſpeak a little of the awful <hi>ſeaſons</hi> or <hi>periods</hi> at which ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners paſs into this place of puniſhment. Theſe are <hi>two:</hi> At death, and after the general judgment.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>ſouls</hi> of the wicked go into the place of puniſhment at <hi>death.</hi> The ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture gives us to apprehend a particular judgment to which the ſouls of all men go immediately after death. Heb. ix. 27. <hi>It is appointed for all men once to die, and after this the judgment;</hi> the latter follows upon or immediately after the former. When the <hi>duſt returns to the duſt as it was, the ſpirit goes to God who gave it,</hi> Eccl. xii. 7. It goes to him as a judge, to be by him determin'd to its eternal ſtate. And this way looks that of the Apoſtle, Rom. xiv. 12. <hi>So then every one of us will give account of himſelf to God;</hi> every one ſingly and alone will do ſo, at the end of this life. Then a judgment paſſes upon every ſoul, previous to that which will be at the end of the world, tho' there is the ſame event as to both: For the particular judgment <q>at the end of this life, determines the ſoul to that happineſs or miſery, which
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:003526_0023_0FF856C0288C0528"/>the general judgment at the end of the world will determine ſoul and body to.</q> There is therefore a <hi>firſt damnation,</hi> ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent to the reſurrection, and that treads upon the heels of death, which reſpects the ſoul only. This is repreſented to us in viſion, Rev. vi. 8. <hi>And I looked, and behold a pale horſe; and his name that ſat on him was death, and hell followed with him.</hi> The ſouls of ſuch as die in their ſins are adjudg'd to hell by God, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried there by devils, as ſoon as they leave their bodies; and while their bodies lie in the grave, their ſouls are in torment there. This is plain from our text, and the <hi>whole narrative</hi> which it is a part of. The wicked rich man, was no ſooner dead, but <hi>in hell he lift up his eyes being in torments: and cried out, I am tormented in this flame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The reward of the <hi>righteous</hi> begins at the hour of death: ſo does the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the wicked. It would be a favour indeed if ſinners might have their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuſpended till the reſurrection, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the long interval between their death and the judgment day: but it will not be ſo. When the ſouls of the wicked go to God at death, he <hi>delivers them to the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors,</hi> Mat. xviii. 34. And therefore we have the Pſalmiſt praying and depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating,
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:003526_0024_0FF856F48A7AF008"/>as in Pſalm xxvi. 9. <hi>Gather not my ſoul with ſinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. After the <hi>reſurrection</hi> they will be caſt into it in their whole perſons, <hi>body and ſoul</hi> united as they are now. When the trial of the great day is over, that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence will be pronounced upon the wicked, Mat. xxv. 41. <hi>Depart ye curſed into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire, prepared for the devil and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> This ſentence will be executed as ſoon as paſs'd. The holy angels, thoſe miniſters of his that do his pleaſure, being arm'd with power ſufficient, ſhall be the executioners of it. Mat. xiii. 41, 42. —<hi>So ſhall it be in the end of the world. The ſon of man ſhall ſend forth his angels, and they ſhall gather out of his kingdom all things that offend, and them which do iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and ſhall caſt them into a furnace of fire: there ſhall be wailing and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> We are told what the iſſue of the laſt judgment wil be, in Rev. xx. 14. <hi>And death and hell</hi> (the wicked whoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were rais'd out of the grave, and whoſe ſpirits were fetch'd from the infernal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) <hi>were caſt</hi> (body and ſoul together) <hi>into the lake of fire which is the ſecond death.</hi> So we read, Job xxi. 30. <hi>The wicked is reſerved to the day of deſtruction; they ſhall be brought forth to the day of wrath:</hi> As
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:003526_0025_0FF856C256C58F30"/>malefactors are brought forth out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in order to their execution. Agreably our Saviour has forewarn'd us, Mat. x. 28. <hi>Fear not them which kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoul; but rather fear him which is able to deſtroy both ſoul and body in hell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon this account damned ſpirits do now dread the judgment day, and think of it with horror. The devils do ſo; for then their miſery and torment will be greater than now it is. <hi>Mat.</hi> viii. 29. And, doubtleſs, 'tis the ſame with damned ſouls: For tho' their miſery is now inexpreſſibly great, yet not ſo great as it will be after the judgment day, when body and ſoul together ſhall be caſt into hell, and they will ſuffer in their whole man. Hence the <hi>unjuſt</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>reſerved unto the day of judgment to be puniſhed;</hi> becauſe that will be the day of their compleat puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> ii. 9.</p>
                  <p>If now it ſhould be ask'd by any, Where is the hell you have been diſcourſing of? And is the place of miſery the ſame now that it will be after the day of judgment? I anſwer, This is what the ſcripture hath not clearly reveal'd; and it becomes us to beware of vain curioſities; of <hi>intruding into thoſe things which we have not ſeen,</hi> as
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:003526_0026_0FF856F764646800"/>the Apoſtle's phraſe is, Col. ii. 18. It concerns us but little to know now, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hell be in the air, or in the concave of the earth. It is enough that we know there is ſuch a place; and it concerns us to ſpend our tho'ts, and time, and pains how to keep out of it, rather than to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe our ſelves with needleſs inquiries about it.</p>
                  <p>Let therefore the preſent diſcourſe come to us upon the ſame errand, the rich man deſir'd <hi>Lazarus</hi> might be ſent upon to his brethren in his father's houſe, namely, <hi>to teſtify unto</hi> us <hi>leſt we come into this place of torment.</hi> O let all of us be convinc'd of that now, which none of us will be able to doubt of hereafter. Let us take heed leſt there be in any of us an evil heart of unbelief. This is indeed a place to us now unſeen; there is a vail between us and it. But <hi>hell is naked before God, and to him deſtruction hath no covering,</hi> Job xxvi. 6. And he cou'd have laid it open, and expos'd it to common view, if he had ſo pleas'd. But beſides his ſovereign plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in this matter, it is eaſily apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this would not be ſo ſutable to our ſtate of trial and probation in this world, where we are to <hi>walk by faith, and not by
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:003526_0027_0FF856C4881C1490"/>ſight.</hi> Therefore <hi>by faith being warned of God, of things not ſeen as yet,</hi> let us be ſo <hi>mov'd with fear, as to prepare an ark to the ſaving of</hi> our ſouls. Let us make haſte to CHRIST, and ſee that we are in him by a true faith; for <hi>there is no condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="27" facs="unknown:003526_0028_0FF856F99B63B030"/>
                  <head>The Extremity <hi>OF</hi> Hell Puniſhments.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>MATTHEW XIII. 42.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>AND ſhall caſt them into a furnace of fire: there ſhall be wailing and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OPE and fear are the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive paſſions of humane nature: And the bleſſed God having made us with them, deals with us according to our frame, and makes uſe of theſe affections, to bring us to himſelf, and keep us within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of our duty. He has therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to them ſuch objects, as when
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:003526_0029_0FF856C6BAA1FAB0"/>believ'd and duely conſider'd, can't but powerfully move and excite them. To encourage and raiſe our <hi>hopes,</hi> he in his word propounds a reward infinitely great; and to awaken and alarm our <hi>fears,</hi> he threatens us with a puniſhment inconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vably dreadful: And that this threatning may be the more regarded, the infliction and execution thereof, in the full extent and extremity of it, is as certain as eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal truth can make it.</p>
                  <p>In the words of our text we are told, what will be the final portion of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and ungodly in the other world; what will be the certain end and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of a life of irreligion and impiety perſiſted in. And this is told us by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, who is <hi>the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true witneſs; who liveth, and was dead, and behold he is alive for evermore; and has in his own hand the keys of hell and of death</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Rev. i. 18.</note>.</p>
                  <p>In this chapter we have Chriſt preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the goſpel of the kingdom, to great multitudes which were gathered together to hear him. He ſpake many things to them in <hi>parables;</hi> in a way of continued ſimilitude or compariſon, by which ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:003526_0030_0FF856FB43535180"/>and eternal things, are deſcrib'd in language borrow'd from the things of this life. Our text belongs to the parable of the <hi>tares.</hi> We have the parable it ſelf from the 24th to the 30th verſe. And the expoſition which Chriſt gave of it to his diſciples at their requeſt, from the 37th to the 43d verſe.</p>
                  <p>The drift of the parable, is to let us know the preſent and future ſtate of the goſpel church. At preſent there are in it a mixture of good and bad, who are to continue together to the end of the world. Then a ſeparation will be made, and the place of their everlaſting abode, will be as far diſtant as heaven is from hell.</p>
                  <p>The particulars of the application or reddition of the parable, as our Saviour gives them to us, are theſe. <hi>He that ſows the good ſeed is the ſon of man,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Lord of the harveſt. <hi>The field is the world,</hi> the viſible church, ſcattered all the world over, and not confin'd to any particular nation. <hi>The good ſeed are the children of the kingdom,</hi> true ſaints, the godly and righteous, form'd and made ſuch by the Spirit of Chriſt, ſcatter'd here and there like precious ſeed, the planting of the Lord that he may be glorified. <hi>The tares are the children of the wicked one,</hi> the
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:003526_0031_0FF856C8EA12B0E0"/>devil, ſuch as bear his image, and do his luſts; who makes men wicked and keeps them ſo; who takes unwearied pains, watcheth all opportunities, and lays hold on all advantages, to corrupt mens minds and manners, to propagate error and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, wickedneſs and profaneneſs. Who is therefore ſaid in the 25th verſe, to ſow theſe tares, <hi>while men ſlept;</hi> before the Lord's ſervants and labourers were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd of it. <hi>The harveſt is the end of the world,</hi> the great day of judgment, when time ſhall be no longer. <hi>The reapers are the angels,</hi> who ſhall be employ'd by Chriſt in the great day, as the miniſters of his juſtice. And <hi>the fire</hi> into which the tares ſhall then be caſt, is hell-torments The 40, 41, and 42. verſes. <hi>As therefore the tares are gathered and burnt in the fire; ſo ſhall it be in the end of this world. The ſon of man ſhall ſend forth his angels, and they ſhall gather out of his kingdom all things that offend, and them which do iniquity: And ſhall caſt them into a furnace of fire: there ſhall be wailing and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The words of our text, are a very awful and moving deſcription of the miſery and torment, which the wicked are to undergo in the other world. The place in which they muſt have their abode, is call'd <hi>a
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:003526_0032_0FF856FE3B709D20"/>furnace of fire:</hi> And what a horrible and frightful idea does this convey to the mind? <hi>Who can dwell with devouring fire? Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s burning fiery furnace, heated ſeven times, was but a faint image of it<note n="†" place="bottom">Dan. 3. ch.</note>. Into this dreadful place they are not barely ſent or put, but <hi>caſt,</hi> with force and violence, againſt their wills, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their loud ſhrieks and crys, and the utmoſt reſiſtance they are able to make. And the extremity of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they are here to undergo, is ſet forth by the effects thereof, which are <hi>wailing and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> Theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are the effects of extreme intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pain and anguiſh, rage and horror; and are deſign'd to ſet forth the intenſe degree of the torment of the wicked in the coming world; eſpecially of ſuch as pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh from under the goſpel, and go to hell out of the viſible church. And as <hi>Joſeph</hi> told <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his dream was doubled, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the thing was eſtabliſh'd by God, and God wou'd ſhortly bring it to paſs, (<hi>Gen.</hi> xli. 32.) ſo for the greater confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of this awful truth, the words of our text are <hi>thrice doubled,</hi> repeated no leſs
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:003526_0033_0FF812BC9ECEB030"/>than ſix times by this evangeliſt <hi>Matthew</hi> in his goſpel<note n="‖" place="bottom">Chap. viii. ver. 12. Chap. xiii. ver. 42 &amp; 50. Chap xxii ver. 13. Chap. xxiv. ver. 51. Chap. xxv. ver. 30.</note>.</p>
                  <p>The DOCTRINE now from the words is this, <hi>The miſery and uniſhment of ungodly ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in the future world, will be</hi> EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TREME <hi>and</hi> INTOLERABLE.</p>
                  <p>On the laſt ſabbath I gave you a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning the <hi>reality</hi> or <hi>certainty</hi> of hell puniſhments; endeavour'd to ſet before you the proof and evidence of this awful doctrine of our holy religion, That there is a hell, a place of miſery, for the puniſhment of obſtinate finners in the next world. This I did as a foundation for the diſcourſes that were to follow. The <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>extremity</hi> of the miſery of the damned in hell, is to be the ſubject of the preſent diſcourſe. For if ſatan, the great enemy of man's happineſs, can't prevail to make men think there is no hell, his next endeavour is to ſoften future puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and repreſent them with as little
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:003526_0034_0FF857009791E3C8"/>terror as may be. It ſhall therefore be my endeavour at this time, as God ſhall help, to repreſent them to you in their nature, weight and terror, from the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which are a ſure word of prophecy, whoſe intimations I wou'd follow, and lay aſide uncertain conjectures. And O! that we might all employ our moſt ſerious and attentive tho'ts to this important ſubject, and ſo mix the word with faith that it may ſavingly profit us! In ſpeaking to this Doctrine, I ſhall take the following method.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. To <hi>explain</hi> what I mean, and wou'd have you underſtand, when I ſay the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the damned in hell will be <hi>extreme</hi> and <hi>intolerable.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Offer <hi>ſome conſiderations</hi> from whence their puniſhment muſt be tho't to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely great.</item>
                     <item>3. Inquire into the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>kind</hi> of this puniſhment, from whence the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and extremity of it will ſtill further appear.
<p>And</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. Mention ſome <hi>heavy circumſtances,</hi> which help to render their puniſhment ſo extreme and intolerable.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. To <hi>explain</hi> what I mean, and wou'd have you underſtand, when I ſay the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:003526_0035_0FF856CD4F592360"/>of the damned in hell will be <hi>extreme</hi> and <hi>intolerable.</hi> And by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of extremity and intolerableneſs, which are inſeparable from hell torments, I would be underſtood to mean the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>That they far exceed all the moſt heavy afflictive evils of the preſent life and world.</hi>
                        <p>There are various kinds of evils and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, which men ſuffer in this world, from the righteous hand and providence of God, as the fruit and puniſhment of ſin. There are particularly many painful <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous diſtempers</hi> to which we are liable; burning fevers, corroding cancers, the tormenting gout, ſtone and ſtrangury. How many miſerables have we ſeen, who have been chaſtened with pain upon their bed, and the multitude of their bones with ſtrong pain, ſo that their life has abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red bread, and their ſoul dainty meat: who have been full of toſſings to and fro to the dawning of the day; ſaying in the evening, would God it were morning, and in the morning, would God it were even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing! Who have like <hi>Job</hi> complain'd even of life, and expoſtulated, <hi>Wherefore is light given to him that is in miſery, and life to the bitter in ſoul? Which long for death, and it cometh not: Who would rejoice exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:003526_0036_0FF857021CF70618"/>and be glad to find the grave!</hi> Job iii. 20, 21. And many <hi>exquiſue puniſhments</hi> have been invented for the torturing great and public offenders; ſuch as burning in the fire, breaking upon the wheel, and boiling in oil or lead. But the torments in hell do far exceed any of theſe, or whatever other can be invented by the wit or malice of men. What the Apoſtle ſays of the glory of heaven, may as well and truly be ſaid of the miſery of hell, All <hi>the afflictions of the preſent time,</hi>
                           <note n="†" place="bottom">Rom. viii. 18.</note> 
                           <hi>are not worthy to be compared</hi> therewith.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. That <hi>they are ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> great that the wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſubjects of them cou'd not endure them, without being utterly conſum'd, were they not upheld in being for this end by the mighty power of God.</hi>
                        <p>Gracious ſupports the damned in hell have none. God does not ſupport them in their miſery, as he does his children in this world, under the fatherly afflictions he lays upon them for their good; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are kept from fainting in the day of adverſity, and are enabled to bear his hand with meekneſs, patience and reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; with a filial ſubjection to him the father of ſpirits. No; the damned in hell
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:003526_0037_0FF856CF8F8D27C8"/>have no ſuch ſupports as theſe; if they had, their puniſhment would not be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable. They are only ſupported in being by a continu'd act of God's power. Without this ſupport, the extremity of their miſery wou'd be the extinction of their being. If this ſhou'd be withdrawn, the ſpirit wou'd fail before him, and the ſoul which he has made. The damned are ſaid to be <hi>veſſels of wrath fitted to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in which God makes his power known,</hi> Rom. ix. 22. They are by the power of God rendred capable to bear ſuch tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as would elſe utterly conſume them, Once more,</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. That <hi>the greatneſs of them cannot be fully comprehended in tho't, nor expreſs'd by words.</hi>
                        <p>After all the terrible repreſentations made hereof in ſcripture, our moſt terrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed tho'ts do not equal the horror and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. Here all tho'ts as well as words are ſwallow'd up. Pſalm xc. 11. <hi>Who knows the power of thine anger?</hi> Alas! none does. It <hi>paſſes knowledge. Eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither have entred into the heart of man, the things which God has prepared for them that</hi> hate him. If one ſhou'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from the dead, and come to us from the place of torments, he cou'd not in full
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:003526_0038_0FF857044E59BC90"/>declare and deſcribe to us what a ſtate of miſery it is; becauſe the torments thereof are unutterable. As the things of heaven are unutterable to mortal ears by a mortal tongue, (as one who had been caught up to the third heavens has told us<note n="†" place="bottom">The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> 2 Cor xii 4.</note>,) ſo are the things of hell, the <hi>wondrous plagues</hi> there prepared, the <hi>ſtrange puniſhments</hi> there reſerv'd for the workers of iniquity. Thus extremely and intolerably great are the puniſhments of hell.</p>
                        <p>Yet will there be <hi>degrees of miſery</hi> there. Tho' the puniſhment of all will be intoler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ſome will have a heavier puniſhment than others. <hi>Some will have the capacities of their ſouls more enlarg'd than others, to receive proportionable degrees of inflicted wrath.</hi> As the veſſels of glory will be all full, tho' ſome by being larger than others, will hold more glory; ſo the veſſels of wrath, will have as much inflicted on them as each of them can bear, yet ſome will have their capacities enlarg'd to bear more wrath than others. Mark xii. 40. <hi>Theſe ſhall receive greater damnation.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="2">II. I ſhall in the next place <hi>offer ſome brief conſiderations,</hi> which muſt needs lead
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:003526_0039_0FF856D113415DF8"/>us to think, the torments of hell are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely and intolerably great.</p>
                  <p>And</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>It is but reaſonable the puniſhment of offenders ſhou'd be proportion'd, as to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of it, to the nature of their offenies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is an allow'd rule of equity among men. To apply this now to the preſent caſe. There is an infinite guilt in ſin. An offence riſes in proportion to the dignity of the perſon offended againſt. Now the majeſty of God is truly infinite, againſt whom ſin is committed; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the guilt of ſin exceeds our tho'ts, is immenſe and infinite. O! what an intoler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thing is it, that proud duſt ſhould fly in the face of his glorious maker, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny his authority over him? What an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable provocation, that the reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creature, who is naturally and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily a ſubject, ſhould deſpiſe the divine law and lawgiver! ſhould boldly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolently ſay, <hi>Who is the Lord, that I ſhould obey his voice?</hi> and hardily dare him to do his worſt! Which is indeed the language of every ſinner, as often as he ſins know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly and wilfully. Thus, as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Sin ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>the commandment is exceeding
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:003526_0040_0FF85706B52FA578"/>ſinful</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Rom. vii. 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>. And what but an exceeding great puniſhment muſt then belong to it? Fools make a mock at ſin<note n="‖" place="bottom">Prov. xiv. 9.</note>, carnal minds allevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate it, but when weigh'd in the balances of the ſanctuary, 'tis found ſo heavy, that the moſt weighty and intolerable puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inflicted on ſinners, cannot exceed the deſerts of it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The torments of hell are of <hi>God's own preparing for his enemies that rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him;</hi> and therefore muſt be ſuppos'd to be exceeding great.</p>
                  <p>It may well be expected the extremity of the puniſhment will be in proportion to the preparation that has been made for it. Now <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>phet was ordain'd of old,</hi> Iſai. xxx. 33. And hell fire is call'd <hi>fire prepar'd,</hi> Mat xxv. 41. prepared <hi>for the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t' and his angels,</hi> and his children, even from the foundation of the world, as was the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for the righteous. Prepared for them by God in the greatneſs of his wiſdom and power. Hell's torments as well as heaven's glories, are the product of divine eternal counſels. As there is great prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration made for the entertainment of the ſaints in the kingdom of glory, ſo is there alſo great preparation made for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:003526_0041_0FF856D35E53A430"/>of the wicked in the place of miſery. And ſurely the puniſhment muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great which is thus prepared. The <hi>preparation</hi> ſhews the <hi>extremity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 The puniſhments of hell are alſo <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by God in the greatneſs of his power and wrath;</hi> therefore they are extreme and intolerable.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe none elſe can inflict puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments heavy eno', He will then deal with ſinners Himſelf, take them into His own hands. And what <hi>a fearful thing</hi> muſt it be <hi>to fall into the hands of the living God?</hi> Temporal evils are inflicted by the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſecond cauſes, that are of a limited power to hurt: but in the next world God more immediately torments the damned by his own power. And <hi>who knows the power of his anger? Even according to his fear, ſo is his wrath,</hi> Pſal. xc. II. <hi>God will ſhew his WRATH, and make his POWER known in the veſſels of wrath,</hi> Rom. ix 22. In them, and upon them, God will ſhew to all the world, his puniſhing juſtice, his enmity to ſin, and the ſtrength of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting power. How great then muſt their ſufferings be, which are deſign'd as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of theſe things? Once more,</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>The puniſhment of the damned will be in a proportionable degree to the happineſs of the bleſſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="unknown:003526_0042_0FF85708EB20D908"/>
The ſcripture makes a direct oppoſition between theſe. Therefore as the ſaints in heaven will be infinitely happy and bleſſed, ſo the damned in hell will be infinitely wretched and miſerable. As in heaven there is <hi>fulneſs of joy,</hi> happineſs in perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo in hell there is <hi>fulneſs of wo,</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery in perfection. For <hi>as for God, his work is perfect.</hi> Theſe he has <hi>ſet the one over againſt the other.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. We come to ſpeak of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>kinds</hi> of the puniſhment of the damned; by which the greatneſs and extremity thereof will further appear. And this puniſhment may be ſaid to be of <hi>two</hi> kinds, that of <hi>loſs,</hi> and that of <hi>ſenſe.</hi> We have both theſe in that ſentence to be pronounc'd on the wicked in the great day, Mat. XXV. 41. <hi>Depart ye curſed into everlaſting fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 It is a <hi>puniſhment of l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſs;</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s in the privation of all that's good, comfortable and deſireable; even of the chief, the higheſt, the moſt excellent and everlaſting good. The loſs not only of temporal good things, worldly enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which are comparatively ſmall and inconſiderable things; but the loſs of GOD, of CHRIST, of HEAVEN. O inconceivable
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:003526_0043_0FF856D64A5508E8"/>loſs! The loſs of friends, of eſtate, of health, yea, of life it ſelf is nothing to this. To the loſs of that GOD in whoſe favour is life, and whoſe loving-kindneſs is better than life; who is the only ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate portion of our immortal ſouls, whoſe perfection and ſatisfaction conſiſt in the clear and transforming viſion of his glory! To the loſs of CHRIST, the Saviour, the glorified JESUS, with whom to be, the Apoſtle counted far better than to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in this world; in whom we ſhall ſee God, and who is the very light of heaven: For <hi>the lamb is the light thereof</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Rev. xxi. 23.</note>. And the loſs of whom both aſcertains and includes the loſs of <hi>heaven,</hi> and all the felicities of that bleſſed world, all thoſe great prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations which God has made for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of his ſons and daughters, who by him to be brought to glory. O infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite loſs! What overwhelming ſorrow muſt it bring thoſe into who ſhall ſuffer it?</p>
                  <p>How deeply do ſome reſent temporal loſſes; the loſs of their eſtate and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the loſs of near and lov'd relatives, a conſort, or a child? Many years ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, do not wear out the impreſſion of
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:003526_0044_0FF8570BDFC846B8"/>ſuch loſſes. They that bear them, do as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid he ſhould for the ſuppos'd death of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> go down to the grave mourning<note n="‖" place="bottom">Gen. xxxvii. 37.</note>. This ſorrow of the world works death, breaks the conſtitution, and bring on thoſe diſeaſes that end in death. And if the loſs of creature comforts be ſo hard to bear, what will the loſs of the bleſſed God be? And, as one ſpeaks<note n="‡" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Bates.</note>, If <hi>Cain,</hi> when baniſh'd from the ſociety of the ſaints, wherein God was publickly worſhip'd, and graciouſly made himſelf known, cried out in anguiſh of ſoul, <hi>My puniſhment is greater than I can bear,</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the accent of grief here, <hi>And from thy face ſhall I be hid</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Gen. iv. 13, 14.</note>; how intolerable will the final ſeparation from his glorious and joyful preſence be?</p>
                  <p>I know carnal and earthly minds, are not much affected <hi>now,</hi> with the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this puniſhment of loſs. If the loſs of God, of Chriſt, and of Heaven, was all they were to ſuffer in the next world, they think it wou'd be no ſuch great matter, they cou'd bear this well enough. But they'l have other apprehenſions of this hereafter. The damned in hell will have a conſtant, quick, and lively apprehenſion
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:003526_0045_0FF856D7CFA470B8"/>of the happineſs they have loſt. Their underſtandings will be enlarg'd and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to take a proſpect of it, on purpoſe to aggravate their grief. They will alſo ſee much of the happineſs of the ſaints in the great day: They will ſee with what glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious bodies they are rais'd, how joyfully they are embrac'd by Chriſt, and what honours he puts upon them; ſee how they aſcend ſmiling, triumphing, ſhining, with him their Lord into the higheſt heavens. This will give them a <hi>ſenſible conviction</hi> how great happineſs they have loſt, and this they will always remember to their greater vexation. Thus the puniſhment of hell, is a puniſhment of loſs.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is <hi>a puniſhment of ſenſe.</hi> With the loſs of the greateſt good, will be join'd the ſuffering of the greateſt evil. This part of their puniſhment is ſet forth to us in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by <hi>fire</hi> quicken'd and enrag'd with <hi>brimſtone.</hi> Whether this be material or metaphorical, the intenſeneſs or extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their torment is ſignified thereby.</p>
                  <p>If it be <hi>material</hi> fire, as the ſcripture, in what it ſays of it, wou'd lead us to think; it is of a different nature from ours, and ſuch as can act on a ſpiritual ſubſtance, ſuch as devils and damned
<pb n="45" facs="unknown:003526_0046_0FF8570D65EE53C0"/>ghoſts<note n="*" place="bottom">Indeed it is difficult to conceive how a material fire can act on a ſpiritual ſubſtance. But 'tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable to determine that 'tis impoſſible. For if we conſider what pain is, it is as conceivable how pure ſpirits are capable of it, as ſpirits in conjunction with bodies. The humane ſoul in its nature is ſpiritual as the angels, yet has a painful ſenſe of fire, or other afflictive evils incumbent on the ſenſes. The body meerly feels not pain, but it paſſes thro' the body to the ſoul. If the ſoul by a ſtrong diverſion of tho'ts apply it ſelf to an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the body is inſenſible of pain, as is evident in ſome diſeaſes; and that in the heat of battle deep wounds are not felt. And as God by a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural conſtitution has order'd, that the body ſo touch'd and moved, excites a painful ſenſe in the ſoul; he may have ordained that devils ſhall feel the impreſſions of material fire, in the place to which they ſhall be confin'd. Dr. <hi>Bates.</hi>
                     </note>. "It is a peculiar fire, for a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar terrible purpoſe. It is ſomething which God has created and made by his infinitive power, to be his inſtrument to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and torment his rebellious creatures, to afflict the bodies and ſouls of wicked men, and even ſpirits which have no bodies".</p>
                  <p>But if it be <hi>metaphorical,</hi> and the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hell are only ſhadowed out to us by fire and brimſtone, as the happineſs of heaven is repreſented to us by feaſting, eating bread, and drinking wine, &amp;c.;
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:003526_0047_0FF856DAA68144F0"/>then it will follow, that the torments of hell are unſpeakably greater, than for one to be caſt alive into a furnace or lake of fire. This is but a weak and faint repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of that; is but as painted fire to rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fire.</p>
                  <p>It is but juſt and reaſonable that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſhou'd ſuffer, both in their bodies and in their ſouls. They ſin in both. The body is not only the ſouls partner, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in ſinning. And therefore ſhall be puniſh'd in all the parts, members, and ſenſes of it; which have been all defiled with ſin, and <hi>yielded as members of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>the ſoul</hi> being the chief ſinner in this world, ſhall be the chief ſufferer in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>That</hi> ſhall ſuffer beyond what the body is capable of, from the immediate impreſſions of divine vindictive wrath. The eſſence of the puniſhment of hell lies in this, THE WRATH OF THE ETERNAL GOD, FILLING AN IMMORTAL SOUL, WHOSE FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CULTIES ARE VASTLY INLARGED TO RECEIVE THE IMPRESSIONS OF THAT WRATH. What the moſt enraged fire is to the body, that, and more than that, is <hi>this</hi> to the ſoul. And as the body will be tormented in all its members, ſo will the ſoul in all its faculties.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="47" facs="unknown:003526_0048_0FF8570F97DC3EF0"/>
The <hi>mind</hi> will have preſented to it dreadful viſions of horror. It will then have the moſt diſmal apprehenſions of the evil of ſin, the holineſs, juſtice, power, majeſty and eternity of God. Then the vail of judicial blindneſs will be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and the ſpirit of deep ſleep which is now upon ſinners will go off, and they will be powerfully convinc'd of thoſe things, which here they did not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, or would not realiſe. Nor will they be able to take off their own tho'ts from thoſe things which trouble and torment them.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>will</hi> remains, and ſtrongly wiſhes for good, but finds none; can meet with nothing but what is evil, what it is averſe from and contrary to.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>conſcience</hi> will always be accuſing and condemning, laſhing and ſcourging, for ſins committed, and duties neglected; for the many calls of God which have been refus'd, and the ſtrivings of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which have been reſiſted.</p>
                  <p>The MEMORY will then be employ'd in recollecting what is paſt, for preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet. As old ſins, ſo former mercies will then be bro't to remembrance, which were made an ill uſe of, and can never be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd more. So <hi>Jeruſalem remembred</hi> in
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:003526_0049_0FF8571281023978"/>the days of her affliction and miſery, <hi>all her pleaſant things, which ſhe had in the days of old,</hi> Lam. i. 7. And ſo <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid to the rich man, <hi>Remember that thou in thy life time receivedſt thy good things,</hi> Luke xvi. 25.</p>
                  <p>Finally, All the <hi>tormenting paſſions</hi> of the ſoul will then be mov'd and at work. The moſt confounding <hi>ſhame,</hi> overwhelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſorrow,</hi> pining <hi>envy,</hi> violent <hi>fury,</hi> cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el <hi>hatred,</hi> and ſinking <hi>deſpair.</hi> All theſe tormenting paſſions will then be let looſe upon the ſoul, and be to that, worſe than ſo many gnawing worms upon the vital and moſt tender parts of the body. Thus the ſoul will be the ſeat and ſubject of the greateſt ſuffering, and will be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally its own tormentor.</p>
                  <p>Nor may any one think this is light and eaſy to be born; for great is the power of the mind to torture and torment. Yea, of all torments that of the mind is the worſt. <hi>The ſpirit of a man can ſuſtain his infirmity, but a wounded ſpirit who can bear?</hi> Prov. xviii. 4. Of the intolerable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this there have been ſome unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py inſtances in this world. <hi>Judas</hi> whoſe anguiſh of ſpirit put him upon deſtroying himſelf. <hi>Spira</hi> and others, whoſe breath has ſmelt of the brimſtone of hell fire, in
<pb n="49" facs="unknown:003526_0050_0FF8574AB540B890"/>their direful outcries, and blaſphemous expreſſions. Yea, we have an image of this in the agonies of ſpirit, and troubles of conſcience, which ſome of God's chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren have been in. <hi>Job</hi> was afflicted in ſuch a manner, that he complains, <hi>The ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of the almighty are within me, the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof drinketh up my ſpirits. The ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of God do ſet themſelves in array againſt me</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Job vi. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>David</hi>'s complaint is as bitter, <hi>Thine arrows ſtick faſt in me, thy hand preſſeth me ſore. I have rored by reaſon of the diſquietneſs of my heart</hi>
                     <note n="‖" place="bottom">Pſalm xxxviii. 2, 8.</note> And <hi>Heman</hi> ſeems to exceed, <hi>Thou haſt laid me in the loweſt pit, in darkneſs, in the deeps. Thy wrath lieth hard upon me; and thou haſt afflicted me with all thy waves. Lord, why caſteſt thou off my ſoul, why hideſt thou thy face from me? I am afflicted and ready to die: While I ſuffer thy terrors, I am diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted. Thy fierce wrath goeth over me, thy terrors have cut me off,</hi> Pſalm lxxxviii. 6, 7, 15, 16.</p>
                  <p>And above all, How great were the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of CHRIST in his <hi>ſoul,</hi> in the day when the Lord laid on him the iniquities of his people, and the ſenſe of his father's wrath due to <hi>them</hi> was let into his ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="34" facs="unknown:003526_0051_0FF85714B7523B40"/>He was ſore amazed! His ſoul was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſorrowful! The agonies of his ſpirit threw him into a bloody ſweat; forc'd thro' the pores of his bleſſed body, <hi>great drops of blood falling down to the ground!</hi> What great ſufferings then, muſt we ſuppoſe the ſouls of ſinners to be the ſubjects of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the other world, when the almighty will <hi>render indignation and wrath, tribulation and anguiſh, upon every SOUL of man that doth evil?</hi> Rom. ii. 9. Thus the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the damned in both the kinds of it, that of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and that of <hi>loſs,</hi> will be extreme and intolerable.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. We come now to mention ſome <hi>heavy circumſtances</hi> which heighten their puniſhment, and help to render it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme and intolerable. I might here mention,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. That of the <hi>place.</hi> Than which no place can be more diſmal and uncomfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. It is therefore call'd a <hi>priſon,</hi> a <hi>pit,</hi> a <hi>fiery and ſmoaking furnace,</hi> a place of <hi>utter darkneſs,</hi> where there <hi>is blackneſs of darkneſs for ever.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The <hi>company.</hi> If they muſt ſuffer in ſuch a place, may they not have ſome good company there, to miniſter to their ſupport and relief? O no! their company
<pb n="51" facs="unknown:003526_0052_0FF8574C53E20EB0"/>will add to their miſery. Devils and damned ſpirits will be very vexatious and uneaſy companions to one another. For they are all extremely miſerable and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely wicked both. They will ſuffer from the rage and madneſs of one another. And they will hear from each other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but diſquieting groans, piercing ſhrieks, and horrid blaſphemies. <hi>David</hi> laments himſelf, Pſa. cxx. 5. <hi>Wo is me that I ſojourn in Meſech, and dwell in the tents of Kedar;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a people rude and barbarous, hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and hating. But how miſerable muſt they be, who are everlaſtingly to dwell with ſuch companions and aſſociates as devils and damned ſpirits?</item>
                     <item>3. They <hi>will have nothing to refreſh them under their ſufferings.</hi> There will be none of the delights of ſenſe, for the ſoul to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the tho'ts of its own miſeries with. All former pleaſures are entirely paſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. They'l meet with none of thoſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects which pleas'd and gratify'd them here. They'l indeed carry their ſenſual luſts with them into the other world, but meet with no objects to ſatisfy the ſame. What is ſaid of <hi>Babylon</hi> upon her fall, may be truly ſaid of them in hell, Rev. xviii. 14. <hi>That all things which their ſouls luſted after are departed from them.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="52" facs="unknown:003526_0053_0FF857166186EA90"/>
4. Their <hi>ſufferings will have no intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nor abatement.</hi> This is a furnace in which the fire never goes out, nor ſo much as decays. They'l be ſo far from having a releaſe, that they'l have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxation. <hi>David</hi>'s complaint will be more pathetically theirs, <hi>Day and night thy hand was heavy upon me</hi>
                        <note n="†" place="bottom">Pſalm xxxii. 4.</note>. They <hi>ſhall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is poured out without mixture, into the cup of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation; and be tormented with fire and brimſtone, in the preſence of the holy angels, and in the preſence of the lamb; and have NO REST DAY NOR NIGHT,</hi> Rev. xiv. 11, 12.</item>
                     <item>5. <hi>The apprehenſion of others happineſs will add to their miſery.</hi> That the perception of the ſaints glory, will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a great aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of ſinners miſery, our Lord has told us, Luke xiii. 28. <hi>There ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, when ye ſhall ſee Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac and Jacob, and all the prophets in the kingdom of God, and you your ſelves thruſt out.</hi> They will not be able to bear it, that others are happy while they are miſerable; that others are in the manſions of light and glory above, while they are in the regions of darkneſs and miſery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. Pſalm cxii. 10. <hi>The wicked ſhall ſee it, and be grieved; he ſhall gnaſh with his
<pb n="53" facs="unknown:003526_0054_0FF8574E9775A168"/>teeth, and melt away.</hi> And what will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this part of their miſery more acute and afflictive, will be the conſideration, That this very bleſſedneſs was once offer'd to them, as well as thoſe who are now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying it; and <hi>they</hi> might have been in the preſent actual poſſeſſion of it, if they had not been wanting to themſelves; if they had not neglected and diſobey'd the Saviour who wou'd have bro't <hi>them</hi> to it alſo.</item>
                     <item>6. They <hi>are without pity from any.</hi> Here in griefs that cannot be remedied, ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in others, and pity from them, is ſome ſmall relief, and helps to aſſwage the troubled mind. Therefore <hi>Job</hi> ſays, <hi>To him that is afflicted, pity ſhould be ſhewed</hi>
                        <note n="†" place="bottom">Job vi. 14.</note>. But the damned in hell have not this leaſt of comforts. In their moſt pitious ſtate they are abſolutely unpitied. The <hi>devils</hi> don't pity them: <hi>They</hi> are deſtitute of love, kindneſs, and pity, ſince their fall, and the loſs of their original holineſs; their <hi>tender mercies are cruelties.</hi> Their <hi>fellow-ſufferers</hi> don't pity them; for all humane tender affections are loſt in hell: The wicked there are <hi>hateful and hating one another.</hi> The <hi>holy angels,</hi> and the
<pb n="54" facs="unknown:003526_0055_0FF857189778DD88"/>
                        <hi>bleſſed ſpirits</hi> in heaven, don't pity them; for they are not the <hi>objects of pity,</hi> their miſery being the effect of their own ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate choice. The ſaints in heaven will not pity their neareſt relations in hell. For they now <hi>know them no more after the fleſh.</hi> The love which they once bare to them is now ſwallowed up in the love of God. Neither will the <hi>bleſſed God</hi> pity them. All their agonies and cries will not move his heart. His <hi>compaſſions</hi> now <hi>fail for everm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>re,</hi> and he has <hi>in anger ſhut up his tender mercies</hi>
                        <note n="‖" place="bottom">Pſalm lxxvii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>, 89.</note>.
<p>For we muſt know God's pity is not mov'd as ours is, <hi>naturally</hi> and <hi>neceſſarily.</hi> Others miſery naturally moves our pity, whether we will or no. But God's pity and mercy are never mov'd without an act of his will. Therefore he ſays, <hi>I will not pity</hi>
                           <note n="†" place="bottom">Jer. xiii. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</note>. Inſtead of pitying them, <hi>He will laugh at their calamity, and mock when their fear cometh,</hi> Prov. i. 26.</p>
                        <p>Once more,</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. As they are <hi>without pity from others,</hi> ſo they are <hi>without hope in themſelves.</hi> Hope is the laſt refuge of men in trouble in this world, but it leaves ſinners in hell. They are no ſooner there, but they fall
<pb n="55" facs="unknown:003526_0056_0FF85751847D2B80"/>into total deſparation. For <hi>when a wicked man dieth his expectation periſheth,</hi> Prov. xi. 7. Whatever tho'ts they pleas'd and deluded themſelves with before, now they'l know the decree is irreverſible, their ſtate remedileſs: That as their tree fell, ſo it muſt lie for ever<note n="†" place="bottom">Eccleſ. xi. 3.</note>. They will utterly deſpair of its ever being better with them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n it is: Their preſent miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is inſupportable, and they will always fear more to come. And this is the very heighth of miſery, to have nothing to hope, and much to fear! Pſalm xlix. 19. <hi>They ſhall never ſee light.</hi>
                        <p>But the <hi>Eternity</hi> of hell puniſhments is to be the ſubject of our next diſcourſe, and I wou'd not anticipate it here.—</p>
                        <p>From what has been ſaid in the preſent diſcourſe concerning the <hi>Eternity</hi> of them, Let ſecure ſinners, who are ſleeping as upon the top of a maſt; who are hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the ſlender thread of life, over the lake of fire and brimſtone; be awakened and effectually excited to fly from the wrath to come, and to work out their own ſalvation with fear and trembling!—</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="56" facs="unknown:003526_0057_0FF8571AD006D438"/>
Let all ſerve to make ſin formidable, Chriſt precious, and the goſpel offer of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation acceptable to every ſoul of us?—</p>
                        <p>Let us think no care too much, no pains too great, to eſcape ſuch extreme miſery! Let this be our earneſt and conſtant pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, LORD, <hi>Gather not my ſoul with ſinners!</hi> However thou dealeſt with me in <hi>this</hi> world, let me, by thy mercy and grace, be deliver'd from condemnation in the <hi>next:</hi> that I may never know by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, what it is to <hi>dwell with devouring fire,</hi> and to <hi>inhabit everlaſting burnings!</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="57" facs="unknown:003526_0058_0FF85753B08061C0"/>
                  <head>The Eternity <hi>OF</hi> Hell Puniſhments.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>REVELATIONS XIV. II.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>AND the ſmoke of their torment aſcendeth up for ever and ever.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>EXT to there being no hell at all, the moſt acceptable doctrine to a ſinner wou'd be, that the puniſhment of hell is temporary, and ſhould ſometime or other come to an end. This is what ſatan, that old deceiver, wou'd induce men to believe if he cou'd; and this is what the ſinner wou'd fain flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter himſelf with the hopes of. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can't raſe ſuch words as
<pb n="58" facs="unknown:003526_0059_0FF8571DAA0BE2B0"/>
                     <hi>everlaſting, for ever and ever,</hi> out of their bibles, they'l try what ſoftning interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can be put upon them; whether by ſome weak criticiſm of language, or trifling cavils of carnal reaſon, they can't overthrow a doctrine which gives them ſo much diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance in their ſins, and puts ſuch a block in the way of their unlawful purſuits.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Eternity</hi> of the puniſhment of hell is what above any thing makes it ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. If men did once imagine it to be any thing ſhort of an endleſs duration, their fear of it, and care to avoid it wou'd pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably abate; the threatnings of God wou'd looſe their force and terror; and when men <hi>heard the words of the curſe, they would bleſs themſelves in their hearts, ſaying, We ſhall have peace, tho' we walk the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our hearts</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">xxix. 19.</note>.</p>
                  <p>Leſt therefore there ſhould be any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, flattering themſelves with ſuch deluſive and deſtructive hopes, thro' the ſubtilty of ſatan, the ſlight of men, or the efficacy of natural unbelief, I purpoſe now, by divine help, to diſcourſe to you of the <hi>eternity</hi> of the torments of hell, as I have before of the <hi>reality</hi> and <hi>extremity</hi> of them. And as an introduction to this
<pb n="59" facs="unknown:003526_0060_0FF85755E8697580"/>diſcourſe, I have taken the words now read unto you, <hi>And the ſmoke of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſcendeth up for ever and ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From the 6. ver. of this chapter, we are told of three angels, or meſſengers, ſent from heaven, to give notice of the fall of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and of thoſe things that were antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and conſequent to that great event.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>firſt angel</hi> was ſent on an errand previous to it; and that was to <hi>preach</hi> the goſpel, <hi>the everlaſting goſpel to them that dwell on the earth:</hi> that ſo men might be bro't <hi>to fear God,</hi> and <hi>give glory to him;</hi> becauſe <hi>the hour of his judgment was come,</hi> verſe 6, 7.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>ſecond angel</hi> follows the other, and proclaims the actual fall of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen, that great city; becauſe ſhe hath made all nations drink of the wine of the wrath of her fornication.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A <hi>third angel</hi> follows the other two, and gives warning to all of that divine venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that tremendous puniſhment, which wou'd overtake all that obſtinately adher'd to the antichriſtian intereſt, and perſiſted in their damning idolatries. They ſhou'd <hi>drink</hi> deep <hi>of the wine of the wrath of God, poured out without mixture into the cup of his indignation; and be tormented with fire and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>imſtome, in the preſence of the holy angels,
<pb n="60" facs="unknown:003526_0061_0FF8571FF1D56688"/>and in the preſence of the lamb,</hi> verſe 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> A very dreadful vengeance this! Inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by CHRIST himſelf on his enemies, his holy angels beholding it and approving it. And what gives weight and terror to the puniſhment it ſelf is, the continuance and duration thereof. This is not for any term of time, but for ever and ever. <hi>And the ſmoke of their torment aſcendeth up</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>for ever and ever.</hi> Words expreſſive of an endleſs and interminable duration; as may be ſhewn by and by. And if the <hi>ſmoke</hi> of their torment aſcends for ever and ever, then their <hi>perſons</hi> muſt endure ſo long <hi>in their torment.</hi> This is what is call'd <hi>the ſecond death,</hi> in 20th chapter 14th verſe, and is to be the portion not of <hi>Idolaters</hi> only, but of all obſtinate and impenitent ſinners, of all that retain their pleaſant and profitable ſins, of all ſuch as know not God, and obey not the goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>The point of DOCTRINE to be ſpoken to from the words is this, <hi>The torments of the damned in hell will be ETERNAL, and never never have an end.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="unknown:003526_0062_0FF85758208443B8"/>
Eternity is an amazing thing! O the vaſtneſs of an endleſs duration! Who can meaſure the length of it? While we ſtrive to reach it, it is ſtill further off from us! When we have ſet off as many thouſands and millions of years, as numbers can reckon up, we are no nearer to an end, than before we began! Divines have ſtretch'd their wits to repreſent eternity, that apprehenſions of it might be more ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and affecting, but were never able to reach it.</p>
                  <p>Eternity does not waſte at all as time does. There is not the leſs duration to come for all that is paſt. The damned in hell are not at all nearer an end of their puniſhment, for having lain long in it. It will never be nearer an expiration, than when they firſt went away into it. In a word, They will always have an eternity of torments to expect and endure.</p>
                  <p>This now is the <hi>very hell of hell;</hi> that which is moſt terrible in it. This is what men are moſt loth to believe concerning it; what they wou'd fain argue and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute away the truth of, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd therefore what we ſhall at this time endeavour the confirmation of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="62" facs="unknown:003526_0063_0FF8572175695318"/>
For this end I propoſe to ſhew,
<list>
                        <item>1. How <hi>plainly, ſtrongly,</hi> and <hi>inconteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> this is reveal'd to, and taught us, in the word of God.</item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Why,</hi> or <hi>whence it is,</hi> that the torments of the damned are to be, and muſt be, nothing leſs than eternal. And.</item>
                        <item>3. How <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>inſufficient</hi> the <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections,</hi> or rather <hi>cavils</hi> are, with which ſome wou'd oppoſe it.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. To ſhew you <hi>how plainly, ſtrongly, and inconteſtably, this truth is reveal'd to and taught us in the word of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if the eternity of hell torments is a <hi>ſcripture doctrine,</hi> this is ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince thoſe of the truth of it, who profeſs to regulate their faith by the bible. Now, as this is a moſt important doctrine, ſo God has been pleas'd to reveal and make it known in his inſpired word, in ſuch a manner, ſo plainly, clearly, and ſtrongly, as one wou'd think ſhou'd leave no room for ſo much as doubting, much leſs denial.</p>
                  <p>Here</p>
                  <p n="1">1. We find the words <hi>eternal, everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for ever, for ever and ever,</hi> join'd with the torments of hell, the miſery of the damned, thro'out the book of God. Iſai. xxxiii. 14. <hi>The ſinners in Zion are afraid,
<pb n="63" facs="unknown:003526_0064_0FF85759A361EC20"/>fearfulneſs hath ſurprized the hypocrites there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: who among us ſhall dwell with devouring fire? who amongſt us ſhall dwell with EVERLASTING BURNINGS?</hi> Dan. xii. 2. <hi>They that ſleep in the duſt of the earth ſhall awake, ſome to everlaſting life, and ſome to ſhame and EVERLASTING CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEMPT.</hi> Mat. xxv. 41. <hi>Then ſhall be ſay alſo unto them on the left hand, Depart from me ye curſed, into EVERLASTING FIRE.</hi> Verſe 46. <hi>Theſe ſhall go away into EVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LASTING PUNISHMENT.</hi> 2. Theſſ. i. 7, 8, 9. <hi>When the Lord Jeſus ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed from heaven, with his mighty angels, in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and obey not the goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with EVERLASTING DESTRUCTION from the preſence of the Lord.</hi> 2 Pet. ii. 17. <hi>To whom is reſerv'd the miſt of darkneſs FOR EVER.</hi> Jude 7. verſe, <hi>Suffering the vengeance of ETERNAL FIRE.</hi> Rev. xx. 10. <hi>And ſhall be tormented day and night FOR EVER AND EVER.</hi> And in the words of our text, <hi>The ſmoke of their torment aſcendeth up FOR EVER AND EVER.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is true, the words <hi>everlaſting,</hi> and <hi>for ever,</hi> are ſometimes uſed in ſcripture, as well as in common ſpeech, for a duration
<pb n="64" facs="unknown:003526_0065_0FF85723AC2F7E30"/>that will have an end. But when they are ſo uſed, the ſenſe is obvious, and the nature of the thing ſpoken of, ſufficiently ſhews the meaning in which they are to be taken; and, which is of great weight, they commonly ſignifie too that the thing ſpoken of ſhall endure, as long as the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of it does endure. Thus for inſtance, when the <hi>hills</hi> are called <hi>everlaſting hills,</hi> (Gen. xlix. 26.) every one readily appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends they are ſo called, becauſe while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things periſh out of the world in a number of years, theſe will remain till this lower world it ſelf, which they are ſo conſpicuous a part of, will be diſſolved. Thus alſo the prieſthood entail'd upon <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi>'s family, for his pious zeal in the matter of <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosbi,</hi> is called (<hi>Numb.</hi> xxv. 13.) an <hi>everlaſting prieſthood,</hi> becauſe it ſhou'd continue to the period of the old teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment diſpenſation. So, when 'tis ſaid <hi>the leproſy of Naaman ſhould cleave to him, and his poſterity for ever.</hi> (2 Kings v. 27.) the meaning is plainly this, That ſo long as any of his poſterity remain'd, that evil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe ſhould cleave to them. After the ſame manner, when 'tis ſaid, Eccleſ. i. 4. <hi>One generation paſſeth away, and another generation cometh: but the earth abideth for ever;</hi> the ſenſe is moſt obviouſly this,
<pb n="65" facs="unknown:003526_0066_0FF8575C999F6708"/>That the earth is to remain, till the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral generations of men deſign'd by God to be born, are compleated. In ſuch a way as this, the words <hi>everlaſting,</hi> and <hi>for ever,</hi> are ſometimes us'd for a duration that will have an end. But they can't be ſo underſtood when applied to, and join'd with future puniſhments: And this for the following weighty reaſons.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The <hi>ſame words</hi> are us'd to expreſs the <hi>everlaſting miſery of the wicked,</hi> as are us'd to expreſs the <hi>everlaſting happineſs of the godly</hi> in the other world. Thus when 'tis ſaid, in Mat. xxv. 46. <hi>Theſe ſhall go away into everlaſting puniſhment, but the righteous into life eternal,</hi> one and the ſame word is us'd in the <hi>original.</hi> Our tranſlation indeed gives two words of the ſame import, and of equal extent, <hi>everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>eternal.</hi> But the ſame word is us'd in the <hi>greek</hi> to ſignify the duration of the happineſs of the one, and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the other<note n="†" place="bottom">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>. If therefore the happineſs of the godly in the other world muſt be underſtood to be eternal, and their bleſſedneſs to be ſuch as ſhall have no end, (which none deny) we muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="66" facs="unknown:003526_0067_0FF85725E71B0068"/>the ſame of the miſery and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the wicked. Both are ſpoken of exactly in the ſame manner, without any the leaſt intimation of a difference in the duration of them. And which makes the matter clearer,</item>
                     <item>2. The happineſs of the godly, and the miſery of the wicked, are ſet in <hi>direct oppoſition</hi> one to another. <hi>Theſe ſhall go away into everlaſting puniſhment, but the righteous into life eternal.</hi> The direct op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, between everlaſting puniſhment and everlaſting life, in theſe words of our Saviour, is a convincing argument they are to be underſtood in the ſame extent, for an abſolute eternity.
<p>And which is ſtill more,</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The <hi>eternity of hell torments,</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd in the ſame words that are us'd to expreſs the <hi>eternity of God himſelf.</hi> Thus when we read of <hi>the everlaſting God</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="bottom">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>, in Rom. xvi. 26, the ſame word is us'd as when we read of everlaſting fire, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting puniſhment, and everlaſting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, in the places that have been mention'd. And thus the phraſe in our text us'd to expreſs the eternity of hell torments, viz. <hi>for ever and ever,</hi> is us'd
<pb n="67" facs="unknown:003526_0068_0FF8575E230149D8"/>to expreſs God's own eternity. Rev. v. 14. <hi>Him that liveth for ever and ever:</hi> and in other places. So that if God's own eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity can be prov'd from ſcripture, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of hell torments is to be prov'd from it alſo. The eternity of both is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of juſt in the ſame manner; and there is as much ſcripture proof of this as there is of the other. And indeed the words <hi>for ever and ever,</hi> us'd in our text, and in other places reſpecting the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hell, are us'd no where in the <hi>new teſtament,</hi> where they are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of any thing leſs than an endleſs duration. I find them us'd eighteen or twenty times, and always importing an endleſs duration.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Every thing that relates to the torment of the damned,</hi> is in ſcripture ſaid to be <hi>eternal.</hi> Thus <hi>God,</hi> the author of their puniſhment, is the <hi>eternal God,</hi> the <hi>everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Jehovah,</hi> who ever lives to puniſh. Hence it is ſaid to be <hi>a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Heb. x. 31.</note>. The <hi>fire</hi> that torments them is <hi>everlaſting fire,</hi> that never goes out, as the <hi>worm</hi> that gnaws them is ſaid <hi>never to die.</hi> Which words are repeated three times by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
<pb n="68" facs="unknown:003526_0069_0FF85728174CEB88"/>for their greater certainty, and more heedful obſervation. Mark ix. 44, 46, 48. <hi>WHERE THEIR WORM DI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ETH NOT, AND THE FIRE IS NOT QUENCHED. — WHERE THEIR WORM DIETH NOT, AND THE FIRE IS NOT QUENCHED. — WHERE THEIR WORM DIETH NOT, AND THE FIRE IS NOT QUENCHED.</hi> The <hi>chains</hi> that hold them in their torment are call'd <hi>everlaſting chains,</hi> Jud. 6. ver. And, which is very conſiderable in the preſent argument, the <hi>judgment</hi> by which they are condemn'd to it, is call'd <hi>eternal judgment,</hi> Heb. vi. 2. Now, it cannot be call'd eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal judgment in reſpect of the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of adminiſtration, but only with a regard to the effect and iſſue of it. The act of judgment is not eternal, for the proceſs will be over in time, tho' it may l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt long; but the reſult and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of it are eternal: It determines men's ſtate unalterably and for ever. Thus, not only is the puniſhment of the damned ſaid to be eternal, but <hi>every thing that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and conduces to it,</hi> is ſaid to be ſo alſo.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Agreable to all this, the ſcripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the condition of ſinners in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world to be <hi>hopeleſs</hi> and <hi>deſperate.</hi>
                     <pb n="69" facs="unknown:003526_0070_0FF857600977EB70"/>Thus we are told, <hi>When a wicked man dieth, his expectation ſhall periſh,</hi> Prov. xi. 7. That <hi>the eyes of the wicked ſhall fail, and their hope be as the giving up of the ghoſt,</hi> Job x. 20. That <hi>they that go down to the pit can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hope for God's truth,</hi> Iſai. xxxv. 18. All which expreſſions, are to ſhew the ſinners caſe and ſtate in the other world to be deſperate, and ſuch as admits of no poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of relief. For where any <hi>poſſibility</hi> is, hope will ſtill abide and faſten upon it; and therefore if all hope be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, 'tis a plain ſign there is not any ground to ſupport and encourage it.</p>
                  <p>And hence 'tis that hell is call'd the place of <hi>outer</hi> and <hi>utter darkneſs,</hi> becauſe the condition of thoſe that are in it, is for ever hopeleſs and remedileſs; and they are without the moſt diſtant reſerves of mercy. If there were any hope in hell, it wou'd not be the place of utter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. No, the hope that the torment of it wou'd ever come to an end, tho' thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands and millions of years off, wou'd let down a gleam of light into thoſe dark regions; and be like the ſtar light to the horrors of the night. But becauſe there is nothing of this, therefore 'tis call'd the <hi>blackneſs of darkneſs for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="unknown:003526_0071_0FF8572A50EB4C80"/>
Thus we ſee, how plainly and ſtrongly the doctrine of the eternity of hell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is taught us in the word of God. The ſcripture ſpeaks of the eternity of the puniſhment of the wicked in the other world, in words that import an endleſs duration, in the ſame manner that it ſpeaks of the eternity of the happineſs of heaven, yea of the eternity of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. It ſpeaks of every thing that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to their puniſhment as being eternal. And agreable to this, it every where re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the condition of ſinners in the other world, as hopeleſs and deſperate. After this manner is this doctrine taught us in the holy ſcriptures; ſo plainly and fully, that words can't be found out to expreſs it in a fuller or clearer manner.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. The ſecond thing propos'd was, to ſhew, <hi>why</hi> or <hi>whence it is,</hi> that the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the damned is to be, and muſt be, nothing leſs than eternal. The reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this into the reaſons of it, will not only help to clear the righteouſneſs of God in it, but be ſo many arguments fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to evince the truth and certainty hereof.</p>
                  <p>This indeed might be reſolved into the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>determination</hi> of God; and there
<pb n="71" facs="unknown:003526_0072_0FF85763885AC758"/>is good reaſon why his creatures need look no further: For we are ſure, whatever God wills and determines can't be unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, unjuſt or unholy, but muſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly agree with the excellencies and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of his nature, however it may appear to our depraved reaſon. Yet we have ſeveral things to offer as reaſons of the doctrine, and for the ſhewing how fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, agreable, and juſt it is, for God to puniſh ſin and ſinners everlaſtingly.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A leſs puniſhment wou'd not be a <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſanction to the divine law.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where a law is not guarded and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forc'd by ſutable ſanctions, the wiſdom o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> power of the lawgiver may be call'd in queſtion. The ſanctions muſt be ſuted to the nature and capacity of the ſubject for whom the law is deſign'd. Now, as man is an immortal creature, a creature made and deſign'd by God for an endleſs life, 'tis certainly moſt fit and ſutable for him, to be ruled by a law that promiſes an immo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tal reward, and threatens an endleſs puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Otherwiſe the law wou'd not be fram'd agreable to the nature of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, who will not be fully rul'd by any lower means, than the hopes and fears of everlaſting things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="72" facs="unknown:003526_0073_0FF8572D333E8BA8"/>
Indeed, we find by ſad obſervation and experience, that theſe are not always ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to keep men within the compaſs of their duty, and to reſtrain them from ſin. For the ſake of ſome momentany pleaſure or profit, or for the fear of ſome preſent temporal detriment and inconvenience, men will every day break God's law, and thereby hazard the loſs of eternal good, and incur the enduring everlaſting evils. This makes it plain that ſuch a ſanction is no more than is needed. If it was any thing lower, and the puniſhment threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned was but temporary and limited, how much more bold wou'd ſinners be in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing the divine law? And might they not then with ſome reaſon too, lay the fault upon the lawgiver, for being ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective as not to enforce his law with a ſutable penalty?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A leſs puniſhment wou'd not be <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the guilt of ſin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is an infinite guilt in ſin: it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends againſt an infinite majeſty; it vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates thoſe infinite obligations we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſubjection and obedience to him, and reflects an infinite diſhonour to his laws and government: Therefore an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite puniſhment does but come up to the
<pb n="73" facs="unknown:003526_0074_0FF85765E4C813A0"/>demerit of it. A puniſhment infinite in <hi>duration,</hi> becauſe an infinite weight of wrath at once, cannot be born by a finite creature.</p>
                  <p>And if any think a <hi>temporary puniſhment</hi> may ſuffice for it, this is becauſe they have light tho'ts of ſin, and don't ſee how exceeding ſinful it is. If nothing but the blood of the ſon of God, which was the <hi>blood of God,</hi> inaſmuch as He was God and man in one perſon; and which was a ſatisfaction <hi>infinite in value,</hi> the dignity of his perſon giving ſuch a merit to his ſufferings: If, I ſay, nothing leſs than His blood, cou'd procure a pardon for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving repenting ſinners; what leſs puniſhment than eternal, can reaſonably be ſuppos'd, to be inflicted upon ſinners that are finally impenitent and unbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo cut themſelves off from the benefit of his ſatisfaction?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>truth</hi> of God is now concern'd to make the puniſhment of the damned eternal.</p>
                  <p>For what we read in ſcripture of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal puniſhments, are not <hi>threatnings only,</hi> (and if they were, it is certainly moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable to the divine perfections they
<pb n="74" facs="unknown:003526_0075_0FF8572F7264C990"/>ſhou'd be fully executed;<note n="†" place="bottom">The reader may ſee this argument excellently well purſu'd in Dr. <hi>Wiggleſworth</hi>'s Lecture Sermon, concerning the duration of future puniſhments.</note> for it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming the great Governor of the world to affix penalties to his laws, which he never intends to execute;) but they are <hi>open declarations</hi> of God's purpoſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, <hi>plain predictions</hi> of matters of fact, <hi>ſolemn aſſurances</hi> of what ſhall certainly come to paſs, in the accompliſhment and execution of which the divine veracity is concern'd.</p>
                  <p>That none may perſwade and flatter themſelves, that the judge will in the great day be more favourable than the threatning of the law, He who is to be the judge has told us, that the wicked ſhall not only be ſentenced to everlaſting fire, but that the ſentence ſhall be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Mat. xxv. 46. <hi>THESE SHALL GO AWAY INTO EVERLASTING PU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NISHMENT.</hi> This is no other than a ſtrong and poſitive affirmation: an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs declaration of God's invariable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, will, and purpoſe. Chriſt, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue witneſs, has told us this, as <q>directly and poſitively, as he hath any thing elſe relating to the laſt judgment,
<pb n="75" facs="unknown:003526_0076_0FF8576796798658"/>or concerning any other fact of his goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; and we have as little reaſon to ſuſpect he has a reſerved meaning in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, as in any other whatſoever.</q> So that the truth of God in his word, obliges him to make the puniſhment of the wicked eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. For <hi>God is not a man, that he ſhould lie; nor the ſon of man, that he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent: hath He ſaid, and ſhall he not do it? or hath he ſpoken, and ſhall he not make it good?</hi> Numb. xxiii. 19.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The puniſhment of the damned in hell muſt be eternal, that ſo <hi>the juſtice of God may have its everlaſting diſplay.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Every divine attribute is to ſhine forth with an eternal luſtre; for they are all dear and glorious to him, one as well as another. His <hi>wiſdom, power,</hi> and <hi>goodneſs,</hi> will be eternally manifeſted in the things which he has made in the upper world. His <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> will for ever be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd and magnified in the ſalvation of a remnant of loſt ſinners, who will then be made veſſels of glory. His <hi>juſtice,</hi> that muſt take place, and act its part, in ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring to ſinning angels and men accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their works, in the due and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable puniſhment of their offences, and that is in their ſuffering the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of eternal fire. The glory of this
<pb n="76" facs="unknown:003526_0077_0FF85730F7BE0CD0"/>attribute cannot endure for ever, if there are not ſome to be the everlaſting monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of it.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>The damned in hell are, and for ever will be, utterly unqualified for the divine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour;</hi> therefore their puniſhment will be endleſs and everlaſting.</p>
                  <p>They are filthy ſtill, unholy ſtill, impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſtill; their hearts are as full of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to God, hatred of holineſs, and love to ſin as ever. Their puniſhment works no change in their nature or will. "They have abundant conviction indeed, but no true converſion. They are full of ſorrow, but not godly ſorrow. In all their bitter wailings their is no holy mourning". They grieve for their own miſery, but not for God's diſhonour. If a new life was grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, it wou'd be fill'd up with new ſins and provocations. Nay, they keep on ſinning ſtill. As <hi>Amon</hi> in his affliction, ſo they in their miſery, <hi>treſpaſs more and more.</hi> We have a true repreſentation of the condition and temper of the damned, in what we read of the antichriſtian idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the worſhipers of the beaſt, Rev. xvi. 9, 10. <hi>They were ſcorched with great heat, and blaſphemed the name of God, which hath power ever theſe plagues, and they repented not to give him glory! They gnawed their
<pb n="77" facs="unknown:003526_0078_0FF8576A75584FA0"/>tongues for pain, and blaſphemed the God of heaven, becauſe of their pains and ſores, and repented not to give him glory.</hi> Thus ſoul "in the fire of hell are not melted, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rather hardned. And from hence it ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pears that they are the proper objects o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> divine revenging juſtice for ever and ever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> They are for ever unqualified for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine favour, and therefore muſt neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have it extended to them.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. We proceed to the third thing pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pos'd, To ſhew how <hi>weak and inſufficien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the objections,</hi> or rather <hi>cavils, are,</hi> wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which ſome wou'd weaken this truth.</p>
                  <p>It need not ſurpriſe or ſtumble any, that this truth, how plainly ſoever it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd in the ſcriptures, ſhould be denied by ſome: This does not at all weaken its credit, or bring it under any ſuſpicion with wiſe and conſidering perſons. For which of the truths of the goſpel has not been ſtruck at? Satan has a ſpight againſt them all, and has in the ſeveral ages of the church ſpirited ſome to oppoſe them all in their turns. They have all of them ſtood a trial. And that they are preſerv'd to this day, and ſtill own'd and profeſs'd in the church of God, is a mark of their divinity, an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that they indeed came from heaven. In the days of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> there were
<pb n="78" facs="unknown:003526_0079_0FF857335AF4A668"/>thoſe who <hi>erred concerning the truth,</hi> even in ſuch an important point as that of the <hi>reſurrection,</hi> to the endangering the faith of many, and the <hi>overthrowing the faith of ſome;</hi> their words did <hi>cat as doth a canker,</hi> as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſays of them, in his ſecond epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> ii. 17, 18. And in his firſt epiſtle, chap. i. 6, 7. He ſpeaks of ſome others, who had <hi>ſwerv'd from the faith, and turned aſide unto vain jangling; deſiring to be teachers of the law, but underſtanding not what they ſaid, nor whereof they affirm.</hi> And in another place he tells us, that <hi>evil men and ſeducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe;</hi> which was one thing that wou'd make the <hi>laſt days,</hi> which are now come upon us, ſo <hi>perilous:</hi> Upon this account he gives this needful advice to <hi>Timothy, Continue thou in the things which thou haſt learned, and haſt been aſſured of, knowing of whom thou haſt learned them,</hi> 2 Tim. iii. 14.</p>
                  <p>Having given this general remark, I ſhall now ſuggeſt ſomething, by way of anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to the moſt plauſible cavils or objec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that any bring againſt this truth. And theſe are taken from the <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> of God; from the <hi>love, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> of God; from the <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of God; or from the <hi>redemption
<pb n="79" facs="unknown:003526_0080_0FF8576CDE75E1D0"/>of Chriſt,</hi> which ſome will have to be <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Some take an objection againſt this truth, from the <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> of God; and wou'd repreſent it as inconſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent herewith, for God to puniſh the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient ſins of men in this mortal life, with eternal torments in another.</p>
                  <p>In anſwer to whom it may be ſaid, <hi>We</hi> are but very incompetent judges of what agrees with the juſtice of God, and what does not. That may well eno' agree with this, and other the perfections of God, which we can ſcarcely apprehend to do ſo.</p>
                  <p>But eſpecially are weincompetent judges in the preſent caſe, concerning the deſert of ſin; and this on two accounts. We are both <hi>blind</hi> and <hi>partial.</hi> We are <hi>blind and ignorant,</hi> and don't fully know the deſert of ſin; nor can we, unleſs we fully knew the majeſty and greatneſs of that God it offends againſt, the reaſon and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of that law which it violates, the excellency of that image of God which it defaceth, the preciouſneſs of that blood which it tramples under foot, and counts an unholy thing, and the worth of that ſoul which it deſpiſeth and deſtroyeth. And we are as <hi>partial</hi> as we are blind; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="80" facs="unknown:003526_0081_0FF85736510D8A20"/>we our ſelves are concerned in it. And as reaſonable is it for an offender and criminal, to judge the law and the proceedings of the judge, as for ſinners to determine what is juſt and righteous for God to do in the puniſhment of ſin. But then, tho' the act be tranſient and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary, the injury and offence is objec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively infinite, (as has been already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd) and ſuch as the offence is muſt the demerit be. A permanent guilt may alſo be contracted by a tranſient act. "And, as one has well obſerv'd, no go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the world ever tho't it a rule to be obſerv'd in puniſhing, as required by equity and juſtice, that the pain and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty inflicted, ſhou'd laſt no longer than that ſpace of time which the crime took up in the commiſſion of it. Therefore ſome have been put to death from whence they can never be reſtor'd, and ſome have been baniſh'd or impriſon'd for a long time, perhaps during life, in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of crimes which were committed in a very ſmall ſpace of time, and yet no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice imputed to the law or judges".</p>
                  <p>But that which fully clears the juſtice and righteouſneſs of God here is, That the ſinner has but <hi>his own option and choice,</hi> tho' he ſuffer everlaſting puniſhments.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="81" facs="unknown:003526_0082_0FF8576E63731A90"/>
To uſe here the words of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> 
                     <q>Life and death, ſays he, felicity and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, are ſet before us in the ſcriptures: Felicity is annex'd to obedience, miſery to diſobedience; and God tells us, that accordingly he will judge and execute; and he offereth every man his choice. He therefore that after this doth chuſe the ſin which miſery is annex'd to, doth chuſe the miſery and refuſe the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And therefore it is no wrong to caſt him into miſery, tho' everlaſting, as long as he hath nothing but what he choſe (in the cauſes of it) and loſes nothing but what he rejected, and that with wilful obſtinacy to the very laſt.</q> Thus he. And this is but agreable to what God himſelf ſays, Prov. i. 24, —31. <hi>Becauſe I have called, and ye refuſed, I have ſtretched out my hand, and no man regarded. But ye have ſet at naught all my counſel, and would none of my reproof. I alſo will laugh at your calamity, I will mock when your fear cometh. When your fear cometh as deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and your deſtruction cometh as a whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind; when diſtreſs and anguiſh cometh upon you. Then they ſhall call upon me, but I will not anſwer, they ſhall ſeek me early, but they ſhall not find me. For that they bated knowledge, and did not chuſe the fear
<pb n="82" facs="unknown:003526_0083_0FF85737E5B0A2C8"/>of the Lord. They would none of my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel; they deſpiſed all my reproof. Therefore ſhall they eat of the fruit of their own way, and be filled with their own devices.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Some will argue againſt this truth from the <hi>goodneſs</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> of God, as if theſe cou'd not let any of his creatures be everlaſtingly miſerable.</p>
                  <p>To this it may be replied, Tho' God is good and merciful, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely good and merciful, yet his goodneſs and mercy don't work naturally and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, as theſe ſeem to ſuppoſe they do. There muſt always be an act of his will, for the exerciſe of his goodneſs and mercy. God is a <hi>free agent,</hi> tho' a good and merciful being. He has eſtabliſh'd the order in which theſe attributes ſhall be exercis'd, which he will not depart from: And he has a ſovereign right to chuſe the objects thereof. Agreably he has ſaid, <hi>I WILL HAVE MERCY, ON WHOM I WILL HAVE MERCY,</hi> Exod. xxxiii. 19. And of ſome he has ſaid, <hi>I WILL NOT PITY THEM.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The goodneſs and mercy of God will be exercis'd on the proper objects of it; but the damned in hell are <hi>not the proper objects thereof,</hi> and therefore his mercy may be withheld from them, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
<pb n="83" facs="unknown:003526_0084_0FF85770A6548BB8"/>merciful all the while. It is a very juſt tho't I have met with, "Such things as are <hi>naturally</hi> capable of the divine good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, may be <hi>legally</hi> uncapable of it. And this is the caſe of condemned ſinners in another life. As creatures in miſery they are <hi>naturally</hi> capable of receiving the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine goodneſs and mercy, but as obſtinate impenitent ſinners, they are <hi>legally</hi> and <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially</hi> uncapable to receive them.</p>
                  <p>We read 'tis true, That <hi>mercy rejoiceth againſt judgment,</hi> James ii. 13. A text which theſe ſort of perſons make much uſe of againſt the truth we are upon; fondly imagining from thence that final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mercy alone will be diſplay'd and ſwallow up all in its own embraces. There will indeed be ſome who ſhall be inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the triumph of mercy, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd and qualified to receive it; in <hi>theſe</hi> mercy will rejoice againſt judgment. But that there ſhall be no monuments of juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, as theſe wou'd carry it, this is far from the meaning of the text: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the verſe out of which it is taken confutes them, and ſuch an interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For the former part of the verſe ſpeaks of ſome who <hi>SHALL HAVE JUDGMENT WITHOUT MERCY.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="84" facs="unknown:003526_0085_0FF8573A1B7D52B0"/>
3. Some oppoſe this truth on pretence of advancing the <hi>glory of God's grace:</hi> This they ſay wou'd be mightily diſplay'd, in the final recovery of the <hi>whole apoſtate race,</hi> from their ſin and miſery into a ſtate of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. To this let me ſay,</p>
                  <p>That God certainly beſt knows in what way his grace will be moſt gloriouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play'd, &amp; it becomes us to leave this to infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite wiſdom, &amp; ſpare our own contrivances and projections. But after all, this wou'd <hi>leſſen</hi> and <hi>eclipſe,</hi> and not greaten and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify the grace of God, as is pretended. For it is juſtly obſerv'd, "That the diſplay of the glory of divine grace, does not conſiſt ſo much in the extent of favour to a greater number of perſons, as it does in its being <hi>free</hi> and <hi>undeſerv'd,</hi> and alſo <hi>ſpecial</hi> and <hi>diſtinguiſhing,</hi> and therefore laying the higheſt obligation on ſuch as are concerned in it; which is the moſt known and proper ſenſe of the word <hi>grace.</hi> Surely the everlaſting puniſhment of ſome for their ſins, will render the grace of God to others, to the ſaved rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, the more glorious, and give a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty luſtre to it. So the rejection of the <hi>Jews,</hi> did mightily ſet off the grace of God in the reception of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Rom. xi. 22. <hi>Behold the goodneſs and ſeverity of God; towards them ſeverity, but towards
<pb n="85" facs="unknown:003526_0086_0FF85772DEC11BA0"/>thee goodneſs.</hi> Agreably, the <hi>diſcriminating</hi> grace of God in Chriſt, will be the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the ſong of the redeemed for ever, and be ſounded with the higheſt notes of praiſe. The <hi>new ſong,</hi> which will never wax old, is ſung by them to the <hi>Lamb,</hi> as having <hi>redeemed them to God, OUT OF every kindred, and people, and nation,</hi> Rev. 5.9. They herein conſider themſelves as the objects of diſtinguiſhing love and grace, redeem'd from among the reſt of mankind; and how cou'd they do this, if all the reſt of mankind were ſav'd, or were to be ſav'd as well as they? And this brings me to conſider a <hi>fourth objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>argument</hi> againſt the truth we are aſſerting and vindicating.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. And this is taken from the <hi>work of redemption,</hi> which ſome will have to be of an univerſal extent in the deſign of it, ſo as that the whole apoſtate race of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind ſhall finally have the benefit of it; yea, and the very devils<note n="†" place="bottom">Origines olim univerſalem omnium creaturarum rationalium, uſque ad ipſos diabolos, ſalutem ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, affirmabat: hujus veſtigia, ſuperiori ſeculo, legit Franciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us Puccius, Italus, et Samuel Huberus, Helvetius, ex Reformato Lutheranus; ſed ab ipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Lutheranis, ob enorme placitum, ejectus. <hi>Vid. Maſtric. Theolog. lib. 6. cap prim. §. 17. And he has ſome weak diſciples in our day, who would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ain tamper with the ſame doctrine.</hi>
                     </note> too: For
<pb n="86" facs="unknown:003526_0087_0FF8573C4D09A198"/>which end, they fancy the offers of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Chriſt, will be made to devils and condemned ſinners in hell, which they will embrace, and ſo obtain deliverance. A moſt wild abſurdity, that has no foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in ſcripture nor reaſon; the reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of which one wou'd think ſufficient to explode it: Yet there is <hi>ſome occaſion</hi> to return a <hi>direct anſwer</hi> to it. I ſhall therefore now inquire into theſe two things, 1. Whether Chriſt died for <hi>all men,</hi> and not only for all <hi>men,</hi> but for the very <hi>devils?</hi> Whether God deſign'd the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all mankind, and of the fallen an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, by the death of Chriſt; and this ſhall finally be accompliſh'd in conſequence hereof? And 2. Whether there are any offers of ſalvation by Chriſt, made to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils and condemned ſinners in the place of puniſhment?</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Whether Chriſt died for <hi>all men,</hi> and for the <hi>devils</hi> alſo? There are two different ranks or orders of fallen creatures concerned in this queſtion, and ſo we ſhall conſider them diſtinctly.</p>
                  <p n="(1)">(1.) Let us inquire, Whether Chriſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>all men?</hi> The queſtion is not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="87" facs="unknown:003526_0088_0FF85775DA032248"/>the death of Chriſt was ſufficient to redeem the whole world of mankind, if it had been ſo intended and accepted by God; this is allow'd by all, and reſults from the infinite value of it<note n="*" place="bottom">Nor are we here to conſider the doctrine of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal redemption, as it is held by ſuch as are in the <hi>arminian</hi> ſcheme: For tho' they hold <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal redemption,</hi> they don't hold <hi>univerſal ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> making the <hi>purchaſe</hi> of greater extent than the <hi>application.</hi> How <hi>juſtly</hi> or <hi>conſiſtently,</hi> I may not now ſtay to inquire. But wou'd refer the reader, that is capable, to <hi>Turretine, Van Maſtricht,</hi> and other ſuch authors. And the engliſh reader, that deſires fuller information and better eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to <hi>Cole</hi>'s diſcourſes on the ſovereignty of God; our memorable Mr. <hi>Willard</hi>'s Lectures on the aſſemblies catechiſm, in which he ſhews himſelf a great maſter in ſyſtematical and controverſial divinity; and alſo to a late worthy writer, the reverend Mr. <hi>Ridgley,</hi> a pious and learned miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in <hi>London,</hi> who has wrote upon the <hi>aſſemblies larger catechiſm,</hi> in two volumes in folio; in the firſt whereof, the doctrine of univerſal redemption, as held by the <hi>arminians,</hi> is exploded, &amp; the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures they bring for it particularly examin'd and ſolidly anſwer'd; the oppoſite doctrine of ſpecial redemption eſtabliſh'd on ſcripture foundations, and clear'd from the miſrepreſentations given of it, and the objections bro't againſt it, by thoſe on the other ſide of the queſtion.</note>. But whether the ſalvation of the whole apoſtate race
<pb n="88" facs="unknown:003526_0089_0FF8573F3099A680"/>of mankind was <hi>deſign'd</hi> in the death of Chriſt, and ſhall finally be <hi>obtain'd</hi> in vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue thereof. Now the ſcripture, which reveals the myſtery of our redemption by Chriſt, teaches us quite otherwiſe. They for whom Chriſt died, and to whom the benefits of his redemption are therefore to be applied, are ſpoken of as a ſelect num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber under diſtinguiſhing characters. They are call'd <hi>his church.</hi> Eph. v. 25. <hi>Chriſt loved the CHURCH, and gave himſelf for IT.</hi> Acts xx. 28. <hi>The CHURCH of God which he hath purchaſed wth his own blood.</hi> And ſurely the world and the church are not of equal extent. The church is a company, call'd out of the world, and is in it as a <hi>garden incloſed</hi> from the common fields, <hi>Cant.</hi> iv. 12. They are call'd his <hi>ſheep,</hi> excluſive of the <hi>goats,</hi> John x. 15. <hi>I lay down my life for the ſheep.</hi> And that theſe are a diſtinguiſh'd number, and that the fruits of the purchaſe of his death will be enjoy'd by none but theſe, appears from what he ſays to ſome in verſe 26, <hi>Ye believe not, becauſe ye are not of my ſheep.</hi> They are called <hi>his ſeed,</hi> Iſai. liii. 10. and <hi>his children,</hi> Heb. ii. 13. to diſtinguiſh them from the ſeed of the ſerpent, and the children of this world. In Tit. ii. 14, they are called a <hi>peculiar people.</hi> And in
<pb n="89" facs="unknown:003526_0090_0FF857775E951A00"/>Rev. v. 19. they are ſaid to be <hi>redeem'd by his blood, out of every nation and people;</hi> which neceſſarily ſuppoſes the reſt of thoſe nations and people, not to be equally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd with them. And theſe redeemed ones are ſtiled, the <hi>firſt fruits unto God and the Lamb,</hi> chap. xiv. 4. Which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation inſinuates, that they were ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the reſt, as the firſt fruits, the firſt born under the law were, by God himſelf, who took them for his own por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Numb.</hi> iii. 13. and viii. 16. In fine, Chriſt <hi>died</hi> for none that he did not <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceed</hi> for; and he did not interceed for the world, but for thoſe only who were given him by the father out of the world, to redeem and bring to glory. In this ſtrain runs his <hi>interceſſory prayer,</hi> in the xvii. chap. of <hi>John,</hi> made a little before he left the world, and which is a <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of what he ever lives to make <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the vail. Father! Glorifie thy ſon, that thy ſon alſo may glorifie thee. As thou haſt given him power over all fleſh, that he ſhould give eternal life to as many as thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him. — Thine they were, and thou gaveſt them me. — I pray for them: I pray not for the world, but for them which thou haſt given me, for they are thine. — They are not of the world, — and for their
<pb n="90" facs="unknown:003526_0091_0FF8574167C3EA98"/>ſakes I ſanctify my ſelf.</hi> — Here <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion,</hi> which is of equal latitude with <hi>redemption,</hi> is limited to a certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, excluſive of the world.</p>
                  <p>Indeed, the objects of redemption are ſometimes ſpoken of in ſcripture, in ſuch univerſal terms as theſe, <hi>all men, the world,</hi> the <hi>whole world.</hi> It is needful therefore to inquire into the meaning, the true and genuine ſenſe of thoſe places, which ſeem to aſſert the univerſal redemption of the children of men; and whether diverſe reſtrictions don't properly belong to them. Now, as to the term <hi>all,</hi> it is often us'd in ſcripture, as well as in common ſpeech, when but a part, and ſometimes by far the leſſer part, of the ſubject ſpoken of, is intended. Of this it is eaſy to give many inſtances. Take theſe which follow; Mat. iii. 5, 6. <hi>Then went out to him,</hi> (i. e. <hi>John</hi>) <hi>Jeruſalem, and all Judea, and all the region round about Jordan, and were baptized of him.</hi> Surely none will underſtand this of every individual perſon in thoſe places, but of a conſiderable number only. It is ſaid again, <hi>All men held John as a prophet,</hi> Mat. xxi. 26. "Whereas only a number did ſo; for the ſcribes and phariſees did not, and many others who hated and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted him. We alſo read, John xxv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.
<pb n="91" facs="unknown:003526_0092_0FF8577994EDCDA8"/>that <hi>Jeſus</hi> baptized, and <hi>all men came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</hi> "By which nothing more is meant, than that many among the Jews attended on his miniſtry, which were by far the ſmaller part of that nation.</p>
                  <p>And as to the term <hi>world,</hi> or <hi>the whole world,</hi> divers reſtrictions belong to it, and it has various acceptations in ſcripture. I ſhall not ſtay to give you them all. It is ſufficient for our preſent purpoſe to ſay, that by <hi>the world,</hi> and <hi>the whole world,</hi> is frequently meant nothing more than all ſorts of perſons, without diſtinction of ſex, nation, eſtate, quality, or condition.</p>
                  <p>Thus the <hi>phariſees</hi> ſaid of Chriſt, John xii. 19, <hi>The world is gone after him,</hi> i. e. all ſorts and degrees of perſons. And ſometimes it is to be underſtood of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in diſtinction from the <hi>Jews.</hi> As, to give one inſtance, in Rom. xi. 12, the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>The fall of them,</hi> i. e. the <hi>Jews,</hi> is <hi>the riches of the world,</hi> i. e. the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> as is plain from the next words, which name the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi>Jews.</hi> This will help us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſuch places as that, in 1 John ii. 2, where 'tis ſaid, <hi>Chriſt is the propitiation for our ſins; and not for ours only, but alſo for the ſins of the whole world.</hi> By which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle means nothing more, than that Chriſt
<pb n="92" facs="unknown:003526_0093_0FF8574321AC9B00"/>was the propitiation, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for their ſins on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly who were <hi>Jews,</hi> but for the ſins of the believing <hi>Gentiles;</hi> or of all that ſhould believe in Chriſt, of whatever nation, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or condition in the world. And thus upon a due examination of thoſe ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures upon which ſome found the doctrine of univerſal redemption, and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the various limitations to which they are ſubject, it will appear they are by no means ſufficient for the purpoſe to which they are bro't. I can't, within my preſent limits, enter into a particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of them all; nor is it needful; for what has been already ſaid, may ſerve as an anſwer to many of them. But there are two or three, which I wou'd not paſs over, becauſe they are main texts with ſuch as hold the doctrine of univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal redemption, in oppoſition to that which is ſpecial and particular.</p>
                  <p>One is that, in 1 Cor. xv. 22. <hi>As in Adam all die, even ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive.</hi> And as parallel to this, they mention Rom. v. 18, where 'tis ſaid, <hi>As by the offence of one, judgment came upon all men to condemnation, even ſo by the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of one, the free gift came upon all men to juſtification of life.</hi> From hence they argue, That the benefit by <hi>Chriſt</hi> is equal
<pb n="93" facs="unknown:003526_0094_0FF8577BCD1C79D0"/>to the damage by <hi>Adam;</hi> that juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and life by the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> is as large and extenſive as the condemnation and death by the firſt. And ſo it is, but not in their ſenſe. The Apoſtle runs a parallel between the two <hi>Adams;</hi> and makes the firſt to be a <hi>figure,</hi> or type<note n="†" place="bottom">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> of the other, <hi>of him that was to come.</hi> And they are alike in many reſpects. Thus, <hi>Adam</hi> is a common head, ſo is <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Hence, as <hi>Adam</hi> hath a <hi>natural</hi> ſeed, ſo has <hi>Chriſt</hi> a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> ſeed. And, as <hi>Adam</hi> ruin'd <hi>all</hi> his ſeed, ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> has redeem'd <hi>all</hi> his. But here's the difference, (the not apprehending of which leads into the miſtake) all the natural ſeed of <hi>Adam</hi> are not the ſpiritual ſeed of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but a number ſelected out of the other. There is a <hi>diſparity,</hi> as well as a parallel, between the two <hi>Adams.</hi> This the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> allows, ſaying, as in verſe 15. <hi>But not as the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, ſo alſo is the free gift,</hi> i. e. there is a difference between the communication of death by the firſt, and of life by the ſecond Adam; and, among others, this is one, The gift of righteouſneſs and life by the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> does not extend to all the individuals that were ruin'd by
<pb n="94" facs="unknown:003526_0095_0FF857456E6DDD40"/>the offence of the firſt. So that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon is to be thus ſtated and explained, <hi>Chriſt</hi> as <hi>effectually</hi> conveys life to <hi>all</hi> his ſeed, as <hi>Adam</hi> did death to <hi>all</hi> his.</p>
                  <p>The other is that in Coloſ. i. 20. <hi>And, (having made peace by the blood of his croſs) by him to reconcile all things unto himſelf, by him, I ſay, whether they be things in earth, or things in heaven.</hi> This place is generally look'd upon to be of difficult interpretation, and has pretty much exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis'd annotators, and had various ſenſes put upon it; and yet, if I may be allow'd with all humility to ſhew my opinion, it admits of a very plain and eaſy interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and I am ready to wonder at the difficulty which has been made about it. To <hi>me</hi> the meaning is only this, "That all things which are reconcil'd to God, are ſo by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which things ſo reconciled by him, are in heaven and in earth". For the term <hi>all</hi> is often uſed to ſignifie only thoſe who are the objects of the thing done for them. As for inſtance, when 'tis ſaid, (Pſalm cxlv. 14.) <hi>The Lord upholdeth all that fall, and raiſeth up all thoſe that are bowed down.</hi> It can't be underſtood as if God rais'd up every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual perſon in the world, that is bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down by the weight of trouble and
<pb n="95" facs="unknown:003526_0096_0FF8577E9D480C48"/>affliction; for ſome do ſink under their burden: but the meaning is, that all who are rais'd up when bowed down, are ſo by God. Thus, when 'tis ſaid God has reconciled all things to himſelf by Chriſt; the meaning is not that <hi>all things,</hi> all creatures that ever offended him, <hi>are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually reconciled;</hi> but that all who are made partakers of this bleſſed privilege of reconciliation, are ſo by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who made peace by the blood of his croſs. And theſe <hi>things,</hi> theſe creatures ſo reconciled, are <hi>in heaven &amp; in earth;</hi> one part of them the Apoſtle conſiders as being in heaven, and the other part of them on earth, in their way to it. So that he here means the whole company of redeemed ſinners, who are elſewhere called the <hi>family in heaven, and in earth,</hi> Eph. iii. 15.</p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) It may be inquired, Whether Chriſt died for the <hi>ſinning angels,</hi> or <hi>devils;</hi> whether <hi>their redemption</hi> was at all intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his death? And there is nothing in ſcripture on which to found ſuch an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, but the contrary. The Apoſtle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt (Heb. ii. 16.) ſays, <hi>Verily, He took not on him the nature of angels: but he tock on him the ſeed of Abraham.</hi> Or, as the margin of ſome of our bibles reads it, <hi>He taketh not hold of angels, but of the ſeed
<pb n="96" facs="unknown:003526_0097_0FF857485BF5CA88"/>Abraham he taketh hold.</hi> The angels fell, and he let them go, without putting out the arm of mercy to recover them; and ſuffers them to lie in their fall without hope or help. Chriſt never deſign'd to be the Saviour of fallen angels, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did not aſſume their nature. He is ſaid to <hi>deſtroy</hi> ſatan by his death, but not to <hi>ſave</hi> him. The 14th verſe of that chapter, <hi>That thro' death he might deſtroy him that had the power of death, that is, the devil.</hi> Satan knew that he ſhou'd have no benefit by Chriſt, and this was what made him ſo full of ſpight, rage and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror when Chriſt came into the world. <hi>What have we to do with thee, Jeſus, thou ſon of God? Thou art come hither,</hi> not to ſave, but <hi>to torment us before the time,</hi> Mat. viii. 29. And therefore it is that he ſo oppoſes Chriſt's kingdom and intereſt in the world to this day.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The other thing to be inquir'd into is, <hi>Whether there are any offers of ſalvation made to the devils, and condemned ſinners in the place of puniſhment?</hi> No, verily! They never had, nor never will have any ſuch offer. The ſcripture ſpeaks of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day of life, as the day of grace and probation, as the <hi>accepted time</hi> and <hi>day
<pb n="97" facs="unknown:003526_0098_0FF85780CDF74970"/>of ſalvation</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Heb. iii. 7 xiii. 1. 2 Cor. vi 2. Iſai. lv. 6. Luke xiv. 42.</note> and ſuppoſes this to end at death. Iſai. xxxviii. 18. <hi>The grave cannot praiſe thee, death cannot celebrate thee: they that go down into the pit cannot hope for thy truth.</hi> As the goſpel which we now have in our hands is the <hi>laſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation,</hi> ſo the time of life which we now enjoy is the <hi>only ſeaſon</hi> of grace. Yet ſome would fain have the goſpel preach'd in hell, and try to make the ſcriptures ſay ſo. The places they bring for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, are eſpecially two.</p>
                  <p>One is that, in 1 Pet. iii. 18, 19, 20. <hi>For Chriſt alſo hath once ſuffered for ſins, the juſt for the unjuſt, (that he might bring us to God) being put to death in the fleſh, but quickned by the ſpirit. By which</hi> [Spirit] <hi>alſo he went and preached unto the ſpirits in priſon; which ſometime were diſobedient, when once the long-ſuffering of God waited in the days of Noah, while the ark was a preparing</hi> —. The meaning of which place is this, That <hi>Chriſt,</hi> before his own coming in the fleſh, did ſend <hi>Noah,</hi> that <hi>preacher of righteouſneſs,</hi> and by His Spirit enabled him to preach to the old world, who were diſobedient, and for their diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,
<pb n="98" facs="unknown:003526_0099_0FF857A330E2E480"/>their bodies being drown'd by the flood, their ſpirits were ſent to the priſon of hell, after the long-ſuffering of God had waited on them, while the ark was building. In <hi>Noah</hi>'s time, when they were preach'd to by the Spirit of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his miniſtry, they were on earth, but in <hi>Peter</hi>'s time, when he wrote of them, they were in <hi>hell,</hi> and therefore he calls them <hi>ſpirits in priſon;</hi> and this preaching to them was <hi>while</hi> they were on earth, not <hi>after</hi> they were in hell. See <hi>Gen.</hi> vi. 3. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> ii. 5. compared with this place.</p>
                  <p>The other is that, in 1 Pet. iv. 6. <hi>For, for this cauſe was the goſpel preached to them that are dead, that they might be judged ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to men in the fleſh, but live accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God in the ſpirit.</hi> If by the <hi>dead</hi> here are meant ſuch as are <hi>naturally</hi> dead, by a diſſolution of ſoul and body, it means the faithful of old, to whom the goſpel was preach'd when alive on earth, but are now dead in Chriſt. The words can have no relation to the preaching of the goſpel to any of the dead in <hi>Hades,</hi> in the ſeparate ſtate, for it is ſpoken of as a thing already paſt and over with them. The text ſays the goſpel <hi>was,</hi> or <hi>hath been,</hi> not <hi>is,</hi> or <hi>ſhall be</hi> preached to them
<pb n="99" facs="unknown:003526_0100_0FF857B0401C6D58"/>that are dead<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, praedicatum fuit evangelium.</note> But there is no neceſſity to underſtand the dead here ſpoken of, concerning ſuch as are naturally dead, and gone out of this world, but rather of ſuch as are <hi>ſpiritually</hi> dead while they live. Of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> of whom the Apoſtle is plainly ſpeaking in the <hi>context.</hi> To theſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> who were <hi>alienated from the life of God, dead in treſpaſſes &amp; ſins</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">It was proverbially ſaid by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Doctors, <hi>Populi terrarum,</hi> i. e. <hi>Ethnici non vivunt,</hi> The Heathens do not live. <hi>Whithy</hi> in loc.</note>, to theſe was the goſpel preach'd, for two reaſons menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd 1. That <hi>they might be judg'd according to men in the fleſh:</hi> might be <hi>judg'd,</hi> i. e. condemn'd and reprov'd; <hi>as men in the fleſh</hi>
                     <note n="‖" place="bottom">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. The phraſe <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, in the new teſtament, ſignifies to <hi>live, ſpeak,</hi> or <hi>act,</hi> after the manner of meer natural men, not acquainted with the mind of God, or not aſſiſted by his Spirit. See the Author above.</note>, or as <hi>natural men,</hi> i. e. for their former ſinful fleſhly life, when they wro't the will of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and liv'd in <hi>laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſneſs, luſts,</hi> &amp;c. as in the 3. verſe. And 2. That they might <hi>live according to God in the ſpirit;</hi> might forſake their old ſins, and live a new and ſpiritual life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="100" facs="unknown:003526_0101_0FF812C78752D8F0"/>
But if theſe interpretations ſhou'd not give us the true and genuine meaning of theſe texts, it makes nothing at all for thoſe who wou'd put ſuch a perverſe ſenſe upon 'em as we are now oppoſing. For <hi>their's cannot be the true meaning,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is contrary to the whole current of ſcripture, and the analogy of faith. God has been pleas'd, for wiſe reaſons, to leave ſome difficulties in the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. There are in them as the Apoſtle obſerves, <hi>things hard to be underſtood, which they that are unlearned and unſtable, wreſt, as they do alſo the other ſcriptures</hi> that are plainer, <hi>to their own deſtruction,</hi> 2. Pet. iii. 16. And it is ſometimes much eaſier to ſay what is <hi>not,</hi> and <hi>cannot</hi> be the meaning, than what <hi>is.</hi> But for any to ground opinions of dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, contrary to what the church of God, <hi>the pillar and ground of truth,</hi> has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways held, and againſt a multitude of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther texts, upon one or two dark and doubtful places, this, to ſay the leaſt, ſhews great boldneſs and preſumption. And how eaſy a matter is it for ſuch as regard not the analogy of faith, nor the context of ſcripture, to prove <hi>in their way,</hi> even the wildeſt abſurdities?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="101" facs="unknown:003526_0102_0FF857B276A31750"/>
To conclude this head, The ſcripture gives us to underſtand, that when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall appear in the great day of judgment, his church will be perfected, his myſtical bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy fill'd up with all the members that are to be added to it; the number of his elect compleated; and ſo be preſented to his father in ſuch words as theſe, <hi>Behold, here I am, and the children which thou haſt given me:</hi> and not one will be miſſing of all the ſons and daughters he was to bring to glory. See <hi>Eph.</hi> iv. 12, 13. chap. v. 27. <hi>Heb.</hi> ii. 13. And <hi>John</hi> xvii. 24. Then his <hi>mediatorial kingdom,</hi> which was given him by the father for the good of the elect, and in order to the bringing them to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>ſhall be deliver'd up,</hi> the end and deſign of it being fully anſwer'd, in the ſalvation of his people, and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his enemies. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xv. 24. And the proceſs of this day being ended, and thoſe who had the ſentence of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion paſs'd upon them, being gone into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting puniſhment; and thoſe who had pronounc'd upon them the ſentence of life, having entred into the kingdom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd for them, and <hi>gone in</hi> with the bridegroom <hi>to the marriage, THE DOOR WILL BE SHUT;</hi> as to <hi>ſecure</hi> thoſe that are within, ſo to <hi>ſeclude</hi> thoſe that are
<pb n="102" facs="unknown:003526_0103_0FF812CF93112A20"/>without. <hi>Mat.</hi> xxv. 10. And how doth all this agree with new offers, and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond trial?</p>
                  <p>Thus I have finiſh'd the <hi>doctrinal</hi> part of theſe diſcourſes, in which I have ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died <hi>plainneſs</hi> and <hi>brevity.</hi> It remains to make a ſhort improvement of them,
<list>
                        <item>1. By way of <hi>inference</hi> and <hi>inſtruction.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. By way of <hi>counſel</hi> and <hi>advice.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt USE, by way of <hi>inference</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. How <hi>great</hi> and <hi>terrible a God</hi> is He with whom we have to do! Who is able to puniſh with an <hi>everlaſting deſtruction,</hi> to deſtroy <hi>both ſoul and body in hell for ever!</hi> Surely this God is <hi>great and greatly to be feared.</hi> As his favour is to be valued more than life, ſo his diſpleaſure is to be dreaded more than death. <hi>With God is terrible majeſty,</hi> and this a guilty world will find e're long. <hi>Stand in awe</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>and ſin not. Let us have grace, whereby we may ſerve God acceptably, with reverence and godly fear: For our God is a conſuming fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>How great an evil muſt ſin be!</hi> Hell is the juſt demerit of ſin. It is ſin that
<pb n="103" facs="unknown:003526_0104_0FF857B4B4ACF858"/>has dug the pit of hell, and fill'd it with fire and brimſtone; that turns ſouls into it, and keeps them in it for ever and ever. It muſt then it ſelf be a dreadful evil, of a moſt vile and accurſed nature. Since the puniſhment of ſinners in the next life will be extreme and eternal, ſin is certainly another kind of thing, than is commonly imagined. O! You that have light tho'ts of ſin, look into the place of torments, the bottomleſs pit; behold the treaſures of wrath that are there prepar'd to puniſh the workers of it; hearken to the groans and cries of thoſe who are there reaping the fruit of their doings: And then ſay what is to be tho't of ſin. We muſt look into <hi>hell</hi> to know what ſin is: And even then we ſhan't fully know what an evil it is. For it may be truly ſaid of ſin, <hi>it is deeper than hell, what canſt thou know?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. We learn what it is that <hi>makes death ſo formidable a thing.</hi> It is this, That to the wicked, ſuch as die in their ſins, <hi>hell follows after</hi> it. The <hi>ſting of death</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>ſin,</hi> (1 Cor. xv. 56.) becauſe ſin binds over to a puniſhment after death. If death was not to moſt men an intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to future endleſs miſery, but only an extinction of their preſent being, it
<pb n="104" facs="unknown:003526_0105_0FF8578252DF6008"/>wou'd not be the king of terrors. 'Tis the <hi>ſecond</hi> death which gives the ſting and terror to the <hi>firſt. It is not this I am afraid of,</hi> ſaid a condemn'd criminal with whom I went to the place of execution, as he look'd up upon the gallows; <hi>it is not this I am afraid of, but the wrath of God after death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. We may infer the <hi>wiſdom of ſerious religion,</hi> and the <hi>folly of an irreligious courſe of life.</hi> By ſerious religion I mean, the <hi>denying all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts,</hi> and the <hi>living ſoberly, righteouſly, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the preſent world;</hi> which is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent deſcription of a courſe of piety, given us in <hi>Tit.</hi> ii. 12; and which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes in it, <hi>faith</hi> in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>repentance</hi> towards God, and <hi>new obedience.</hi> This is the courſe which leads <hi>from</hi> the place of everlaſting miſery, <hi>to</hi> the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite place of endleſs joy and happineſs, and is therefore the way of wiſdom; the way which the wiſe walk in, and by walking in which they ſhew that they have <hi>a good underſtanding;</hi> according to that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. xv. 24. <hi>The way of life is above to the wiſe, that he may depart from hell beneath.</hi> On the other hand, an irreligious courſe, a vain, ſenſual, ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life, leads directly down to this place
<pb n="105" facs="unknown:003526_0106_0FF857B7A022F978"/>of miſery. This is the <hi>broad way</hi> which as certainly leads to <hi>deſtruction,</hi> as the <hi>narrow way</hi> leads to <hi>life. They that live after the fleſh ſhall die</hi> eternally. And are the <hi>pleaſures of ſin, which are but for a ſeaſon,</hi> of ſo much worth, that for them we ſhou'd dwell in everlaſting burnings? This is folly in its exaltation! Folly heightn'd into a frenzy! Eccleſ. ix. 3. <hi>Madneſs is in their hearts while they live, and after that they go to the dead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. With what thankfulneſs ſhou'd we admire and adore the divine <hi>patience, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance,</hi> and <hi>long-ſuffering</hi> towards us, in that we have not been turned into hell long before now! We may all ſubſcribe to that, Pſalm ciii. 8. <hi>The Lord is ſlow to anger.</hi> and verſe 10. <hi>He hath not dealt with us after our ſins, nor rewarded us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our iniquities.</hi> We are all of us the children of wrath by nature, and have made our ſelves <hi>ſeven-fold</hi> more ſo than we were before. How oft have we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd him to cut us off in the multitude of our tranſgreſſions? But he has ſtay'd his hand—. And this when he has made quick work with others. — O! what a leſſon of thankfulneſs does this teach us? And how careful ſhou'd we be not to turn his grace into wantonneſs?
<pb n="106" facs="unknown:003526_0107_0FF857848BB49500"/>How thankful wou'd a damned perſon be, if God ſhou'd free him from the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery he is now in, and place him in the ſame condition with us now; and ſhou'd we be leſs thankful that we are not bro't into the ſame condition which they are now in?</p>
                  <p n="6">6. How <hi>thankful ſhou'd we be for the holy ſcriptures,</hi> wherein we are told of this place of everlaſting miſery, and warn'd not to come into it? This is a place to us now unſeen, it lies out of our ſight. But life and immortality are bro't to light by the goſpel. Herein is the wrath of God reveal'd from heaven againſt all ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and unrighteouſneſs of men: And this with a compaſſionate deſign that we may be ſtirred up to <hi>flee from the wrath to come.</hi> The light of nature affords ſome intimations of this, but the goſpel clearly reveals it, ſo that the matter is no longer doubtful, and they that go into it will be without excuſe. Great is their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to eſcape hell, who have the oracles of God committed to them. Luke xvi. 27, 28, 29. <hi>Then ſaid he, I pray thee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore father, that thou wouldeſt ſend him to my fathers houſe: For I have five brethren; that he may teſtifie unto them, leſt they alſo come into this place of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rment. Abraham
<pb n="107" facs="unknown:003526_0108_0FF857B926771B60"/>ſaith unto him, They have Moſes and the prophets; let them hear them.</hi> The ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are ſufficient to keep men out of hell. How thankful then ſhou'd we be who enjoy them, when God has not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them to every people? We ſhou'd ſearch, believe, and practiſe them; ſhou'd <hi>take heed to them as to a light that ſhineth in a dark place;</hi> ſhou'd take them for <hi>a light to our feet, and a lamp unto our path,</hi> that ſo we may <hi>depart from the ſnares of death,</hi> and our <hi>ſteps</hi> may not <hi>take hold on hell.</hi> And <hi>as many as walk according to this rule, peace</hi> ſhall <hi>be on them, and mercy,</hi> as <hi>upon the Iſrael of God,</hi> Gala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. vi. 16.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. How <hi>happy are they who are in a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned juſtified ſtate?</hi> Such are more than once pronounc'd bleſſed by the pſalmiſt, Pſalm xxxii. 1, 2. <hi>Bleſſed is he whoſe tranſgreſſion is forgiven, whoſe ſin is cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Bleſſed is the man unto whom the Lord imputeth not iniquity.</hi> This is the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a pardoned man, he ſhall be fav'd from hell, he ſhall never come under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation in the other world. For there is <hi>no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Rom. viii. 1. A pardon bars up the door of the bottomleſs pit, ſo that he who has it ſhall never be caſt down
<pb n="108" facs="unknown:003526_0109_0FF857877208DA68"/>into that. The pardoned ſoul may ſing, as in Pſalm lxxxvi. 12, 13. <hi>I will praiſe thee, O Lord my God with all my heart: and I will glorifie thy name for evermore. For great is thy mercy toward me; and thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered my ſoul from the loweſt hell.</hi> How thankful then ſhou'd they be, who have a good hope thro' grace, that they are in a pardoned ſtate? And how earneſt and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſhou'd we all be in ſeeking after this bleſſedneſs? Once more here,</p>
                  <p n="8">8. How <hi>great are the obligations of believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers unto JESUS CHRIST?</hi> For his blood is what has quenched the fire of hell, which was burning againſt them. They are <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd from wrath thro' him,</hi> by his being <hi>made of God redemption to them.</hi> What reaſon then has the believer to ſay, "Bleſſed be God for Jeſus Chriſt! Thanks be unto God for the unſpeakable gift of his ſon! To uſe here the apt words of another, <q>The glorious <hi>ſun of righteouſneſs</hi> having put out <hi>this fire,</hi> ought certainly to be the more pleaſant to thoſe whom he is <hi>riſen upon,</hi> and who have experienc'd the benefit of <hi>healing in his wings:</hi> There being not <hi>one ſaint</hi> in heaven, or in earth, but what may truly ſay, <hi>All this miſery had been my everlaſting lot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ng the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rſt of ſinners, if the eternal ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n of God had not been made ſin and a curſe for me.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="109" facs="unknown:003526_0110_0FF857BB547C4B10"/>
Second USE, by way of <hi>counſel</hi> and <hi>advice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Let us be <hi>firmly perſwaded</hi> of theſe awful truths, and <hi>admit no ſuggeſtion</hi> tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſhake our belief of them. It is an age of infidelity, in which temptations of this kind do abound; all had need therefore be upon their guard, eſpecially thoſe who are young. Take the <hi>doctrine of future puniſhments</hi> as it is reveal'd in the word of God, and be <hi>ſtabliſh'd in the faith</hi> of it <hi>as ye have been taught.</hi> The <hi>eternity</hi> of them is what men are moſt apt to quarrel with. But, I think, eno' has been ſaid, to convince and ſatisfie any one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves the word of God, and has not learnt to wrangle away the plaineſt truths. And ſuch as will not believe <hi>God</hi> ſpeaking in his <hi>word,</hi> neither would they believe if he ſhou'd ſend an <hi>angel</hi> from heaven to them. For <hi>his</hi> word might as well be queſtion'd. An angel can ſpeak but the word of God; and if <hi>an angel was to bring any other goſpel,</hi> you are not to receive it, but to hold him accurſed. <hi>Gal.</hi> i. 8.</p>
                  <p>The denial of the eternity of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the wicked, is indeed ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of practical religion. It takes off from men the higheſt reſtraint, and opens a door to all licentiouſneſs. It takes away
<pb n="110" facs="unknown:003526_0111_0FF85789A61F8D50"/>that fear in which we ſhou'd paſs the time of our ſojourning in this world, and with which we ſhou'd be working out our own ſalvation. It tends to make men deſpiſe the preſent offers, and refuſe the preſent calls of the goſpel; and to be careleſs of the things of their peace in this the day of them. They that give into it then, do err concerning the truth in a very <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous point.</hi> The doctrines of the goſpel are all of them <hi>according to godlineſs,</hi> tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to promote that. Whatever doctrine is manifeſtly otherwiſe, carries with it an evident mark of its falſeneſs, and proves it ſelf that it can never be of God, and is therefore to be rejected with abhorrence, and ſuch as would propagate it to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided. 1 Tim. vi. 3, 4, 5. <hi>If any man teach otherwiſe, and conſent not to whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome words, even the words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the doctrine which is according to godlineſs, He is proud, knowing nothing, but doting about queſtions and ſtrifes of words —: From ſuch withdraw thy ſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let us <hi>often remember them,</hi> and have them much in our tho'ts. Let the belief of theſe things produce frequent ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration upon them. The believing realizing conſideration of the puniſhments of hell, if
<pb n="111" facs="unknown:003526_0112_0FF857BD8C64CA60"/>we ſometimes ſet our ſelves to it, might, by the bleſſing of the ſpirit of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, have ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good effects. It would help to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the deceitfulneſs of ſin, and to weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the force of temptations: It might ſerve to awaken us out of carnal ſecurity, and to quicken us in the working out our own ſalvation. Indeed, the <hi>love of God</hi> is the acceptable principle; and is what ſhould <hi>reſtrain</hi> us from ſin, and <hi>conſtrain</hi> us to duty. Yet we <hi>may,</hi> and have <hi>need</hi> to call in and improve the conſideration of the torments of hell. <hi>This motive</hi> the ſinner uſually feels the force of at his firſt converſion, in the beginning of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious life; and it is of uſe to us thro' the whole of our chriſtian courſe, even when we come to act, in the main, from a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and better principle. <hi>Job</hi> was a man of ſingular piety, yet was reſtrain'd from ſin, by this principle: <hi>For deſtruction from God was a terror to me,</hi> chap. xxxi. 23. They that <hi>hope</hi> for God's <hi>ſalvation,</hi> ſhou'd yet <hi>fear</hi> his <hi>deſtruction. "Adam</hi> in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency was aw'd with a threatning.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Let it be the <hi>great concern,</hi> and moſt <hi>ſerious endeavour</hi> of us all, <hi>to eſcape the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments of hell.</hi> For this end they are ſet before us in the word of God. <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore the terror of the Lord,</hi> let us be
<pb n="112" facs="unknown:003526_0113_0FF8578BC83D8710"/>perſwaded to break of our ſins by righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and to turn out of the broad way that leads to deſtruction! — Let us cry earneſtly to God for mercy, and ſue out a pardon at the throne of grace! — Let us flie to the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and take <hi>ſanctuary</hi> in him by faith! For there is no door of eſcape open for a guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſinner, but in and thro' <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and in him there is a <hi>wide and effectual door open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> to one that is flying from the wrath to come. O for a <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or we are undone for ever! O for that believing covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing act to make him ours!</p>
                  <p>And let us do all this ſpeedily and without delay; and not put off the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing the counſels of God to the laſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, leſt we bewail our folly to no purpoſe, as multitudes are now doing, in a miſerable eternity. The door is open to <hi>day,</hi> but it may be ſhut to <hi>morrow;</hi> and being <hi>once</hi> ſhut, it is ſhut <hi>for ever. Wherefore as the</hi> HOLY GHOST <hi>ſaith, To day while it is called to day, harden not your hearts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our bleſſed Saviour after he had <hi>warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> his hearers of <hi>the wrath to come,</hi> and thereupon exhorted them to <hi>bring forth fruits meet for repentance,</hi> enforces all with this ſolemn declaration, wherein he lets them know what terms they ſtood upon, and what continual danger they were in,
<pb n="113" facs="unknown:003526_0114_0FF857BFF0DF17D8"/>
                     <hi>The ax is now laid unto the root of the trees: therefore every tree which bringeth not forth good fruit, is hewn down, and caſt into the fire,</hi> Mat. iii. 10. Profeſſors in the viſible church, are <hi>trees</hi> in God's vineyard, from whom he expects good fruit, fruits meet for repentance, the fruits of righteouſneſs which are by Jeſus Chriſt to the praiſe and glory of God. If they fail his juſt expectations concerning them, are barren and ungodly, bringing forth <hi>no</hi> fruit, or which is worſe <hi>bad</hi> fruit, wild grapes, the grapes of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and the cluſters of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrow,</hi> their ruin is inevitable, and is ſpeedily coming on. They may every moment expect juſtice will <hi>ſtrike the fatal blow,</hi> cut them down as unworthy to ſtand any longer in the vineyard, and caſt them as dry ſtubble into the unquenchable fire of divine wrath. Take therefore the aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful admonition, Jer. xiii. 16. <hi>Give glory to the Lord your God before he cauſe darkneſs, and before your fect ſtumble on the dark moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and while ye look for light, he turn it into the ſhadow of death, and make it groſs darkneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
                     <p>If any now think the doctrine we have been upon to be harſh and grievous, 'tis <hi>not ours</hi> but <hi>God's.</hi> And we muſt ſpeak with <hi>his words,</hi> whether men will hear,
<pb n="114" facs="unknown:003526_0115_0FF8578D8F5F7878"/>or whether they will forbear. Should we tell you otherwiſe, we ſhould but deceive you with a lie, and hurt our own ſouls as well as yours. But when we <hi>ſpeak as the oracles of God,</hi> it is time for <hi>him that hath ears, to hear.</hi> And ſurely 'tis eaſier to <hi>hear</hi> of the puniſhments of hell than to <hi>feel</hi> them. If you don't caſt this truth out of your minds by forgetfulneſs or unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, it may, by the bleſſing of the Spirit, work to your converſion and ſalvation. Then you will have your belief of it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd, and it will be ſo far from being a <hi>terror</hi> to you, that it will furniſh you with matter of <hi>comfort</hi> and <hi>praiſe</hi> to think, that thro' grace, you are deliver'd from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring fire, and from the everlaſting burnings.</p>
                     <p>However let careleſs obſtinate ſinners know to their ſorrow, tho' they may put this truth <hi>out of their minds,</hi> they can't put it <hi>out of their bibles;</hi> but there it will ſtand as a ſealed truth, which they ſhall experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally know in the future world, that the wicked <hi>SHALL GO AWAY INTO EVERLASTING PUNISHMENT, and THE SMOKE OF THEIR TORMENT ASCEND FOR EVER AND EVER.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <p>Page 55. line 19. for <hi>Eternity</hi> read <hi>Extremity.</hi> P. 85. marg. l. 1. r. <hi>Origenes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="unknown:003526_0116_0FF857C263979E38"/>
                  <p>DIVINE TEACHING <hi>to be ſought, that we may be led into</hi> DIVINE TRUTH.</p>
                  <p>A SERMON Preach'd <hi>February</hi> 27th. 1731, 2.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>William Cooper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John xviii. 38.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Pilate ſaith unto him, WHAT IS TRUTH?</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Epheſ. v. 9.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The fruit of the Spirit is in all truth.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 John iv. 6.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Hereby know we the Spirit of truth, and the ſpirit of error.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BOSTON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Edwards.</hi> 1732.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="unknown:003526_0117_0FF857911B9BCF60"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE following <hi>ſhort Sermon</hi> was preach'd after thoſe which have been preſented to your View, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>leaſt Tho't</hi> of its being ever made public. The Subject indeed is <hi>important,</hi> and (perhaps) at this preſent Day not <hi>unſeaſonable:</hi> But it requires a <hi>fuller</hi> Management. — However, to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie ſome of my Friends, it now (ſuch as it is) goes abroad; and may the Bleſſing of Heaven go along with it!</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="unknown:003526_0118_0FF857C49AD727A0"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>DIVINE TEACHING</hi> to be ſought, that we may be led into <hi>DIVINE TRUTH.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>PSALM XXV. 5.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Lead me in thy truth, and teach me: for thou art the God of my ſalvation, on thee do I wait all the day.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HESE words are a prayer of holy <hi>David;</hi> a very needful prayer, ſutably and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately made; and which we ſhou'd all learn of him to make for our ſelves. In it we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, 1. The <hi>matter</hi> of the prayer, or the <hi>bleſſing</hi> pray'd for. 2 The <hi>argument</hi> of the prayer, or the <hi>pleas</hi> with which he urges and enforces his petition.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="2" facs="unknown:003526_0119_0FF857936D49E710"/>
1. The <hi>matter</hi> of the prayer, or the <hi>bleſſing</hi> pray'd for and ask'd; and this is <hi>divine inſtruction.</hi> A bleſſing of no ſmall importance, of no leſs than infinite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment: <hi>Lead me in thy truth, and teach me.</hi> He ſpeaks in the language of one <hi>ignorant,</hi> or of one at <hi>a loſs;</hi> of one in <hi>danger</hi> of being led aſide, of erring and miſtaking; of one ſenſible that if <hi>left to himſelf</hi> he ſhould go out of the way of truth; of one ſincerely deſirous to be <hi>rightly informed,</hi> and who therefore appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf to a <hi>divine inſtructor.</hi> He looks above men, to <hi>the father of lights,</hi> from whom comes down every good and perfect gift, whoſe Spirit is the ſpirit of wiſdom and revelation: <hi>Lead me in thy truth, and teach me!</hi> Let me have a clear underſtanding of thy mind and will! En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able me to <hi>diſcern</hi> truth from error, and then to <hi>embrace</hi> it, and to <hi>practiſe</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it! Leave me not to the <hi>natural darkneſs</hi> of my own underſtanding; but do thou ſhine into my mind, and in <hi>thy light</hi> give me to <hi>ſee light! David</hi> was a knowing intelligent man, yet was ſenſible he needed God to teach him. He <hi>had been</hi> happily taught of God; cou'd ſay, <hi>O God, thou haſt taught me from my youth;</hi> yet was deſirous to be taught <hi>more</hi> and
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:003526_0120_0FF857C7A8785DE8"/>
                     <hi>farther,</hi> to be better <hi>inform'd,</hi> and better <hi>eſtabliſh'd.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>pleas</hi> or <hi>reaſons</hi> with which he urges his petition. 1. <hi>For thou art the God of my ſalvation.</hi> The God on whom he depended for ſalvation, both temporal and eternal: Therefore he came to him for that <hi>inſtruction</hi> which was neceſſary to <hi>ſalvation,</hi> for if he was not inſtructed in the <hi>way,</hi> he cou'd never attain to the <hi>end.</hi> 2. <hi>On thee do I wait all the day.</hi> This ſpeaks a <hi>conſtant attendance</hi> upon God in the way of duty: He <hi>put</hi> and <hi>kept</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſo far as he cou'd, in the <hi>way</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the bleſſing he ſo much deſir'd; and he hop'd and pleaded that this wou'd not be in vain.</p>
                  <p>The DOCTRINE now from the words may be this, 
<q>
                        <hi>DOCT. We ſhould all of us ſeck of God his teaching, that we may be led into his truth.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>In ſpeaking to this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> it may be briefly ſhewn,
<list>
                        <item>1. What we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand here by <hi>God's truth.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. What by our being <hi>led in this truth.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>How God teaches thoſe whom he leads in his truth.</hi> And</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="4" facs="unknown:003526_0121_0FF857959D5E7E60"/>
4. <hi>Why we ſhould ſeek of God thoſe teachings, whereby we may be led in his truth.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. To ſhew what we are to underſtand here by <hi>God's truth.</hi> By God's truth here we are to underſtand his <hi>mind</hi> and <hi>will,</hi> as it is reveal'd in the ſacred ſcriptures, concerning mans preſent duty and future happineſs. REVEAL'D RELIGION, that is God's truth; for it comes from him as the bleſſed author of it, contains <hi>the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of his will,</hi> and is the only true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the only way to heaven and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. John xvii. 17. <hi>Thy word is truth.</hi> This contains <hi>two</hi> main parts, the one <hi>doctrinal,</hi> the other <hi>practical;</hi> and <hi>both</hi> are God's truth.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>doctrinal</hi> part of religion is to be underſtood by God's truth. This is what contains <hi>things which are moſt ſurely to be believed by us.</hi> It is call'd <hi>the faith d liver'd to the ſaints,</hi> as a ſacred truſt, for them to <hi>keep</hi> with care, and <hi>defend</hi> with earneſtneſs, <hi>Jude</hi> verſe 3. It is alſo ſaid to be <hi>one,</hi> (Eph. iv. 1. <hi>One faith</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is what all chriſtians ſhould be united in the profeſſion of; but it conſiſts of <hi>many articles,</hi> all of which are precious, to be receiv'd as <hi>faithful ſayings, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all acceptation;</hi> tho' ſome are of
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:003526_0122_0FF857C92D4DE298"/>greater moment and importance than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yea, of ſuch moment that without the belief of them, we can't be good chriſtians, or intitled to ſalvation. Many of them are <hi>incomprehenſible</hi> by us, <hi>above</hi> reaſon tho' not <hi>contrary</hi> to it; and are therefore called <hi>myſteries, the myſteries of the kingdom of heaven.</hi> Yea, the whole ſyſtem of goſpel truths, is for this reaſon called <hi>the myſtery of faith,</hi> 1 Tim. iii. 9. This is <hi>the truth which the ſpirit leads into,</hi> John xvi. 13. And which is ſaid <hi>to dwell in believers, and to be with them for ever,</hi> 2 John 2.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>practical</hi> part of religion is alſo to be underſtood here by God's truth. This contains in it the <hi>ſtatutes</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments</hi> of the Lord our God; and is the rule of our <hi>life,</hi> as the other is the rule of our <hi>faith.</hi> Pſalm cxix. 142. <hi>Thy law is truth.</hi> By the former we are to regulate our <hi>judgment,</hi> by the latter we are to order our <hi>converſation.</hi> And the former hath a powerful influence upon the latter; and is therefore called <hi>the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine which is according to godlineſs,</hi> 1 Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. vi. 3. which tends to promote godlineſs, to make men live godly in this preſent world. This is the truth which we muſt be <hi>led in,</hi> muſt <hi>walk in.</hi> Agreably, a life
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:003526_0123_0FF8579721CB5248"/>of practical godlineſs is called <hi>a walking in truth, as we have received a command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the father,</hi> 2 John 4. But the former of theſe, viz. <hi>Doctrinal Truth,</hi> is what I wou'd be underſtood chiefly to intend, and ſhall principally refer to in the preſent diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. To ſhew what we are to underſtand by our being <hi>led in this truth.</hi> It means theſe two things at leaſt, our being <hi>bro't into</hi> it, and <hi>kept in</hi> it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Our being <hi>bro't into</hi> the truth. This includes <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>aſſent.</hi> God leads thoſe into his truth, whom he helps to underſtand the truths of the goſpel, with the grounds and reaſons of them, and from an inward perſuaſion of their verity, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly to own and profeſs them: To whom he gives a <hi>ſound judgment,</hi> by which they do diſcern truth from error, and do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly embrace the one, and reject the other.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Our being <hi>kept in</hi> it. To be <hi>led in</hi> God's truth, is not only to <hi>embrace</hi> it, but to <hi>adhere</hi> to it, notwithſtanding any temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to relinquiſh it, or depart from it. Leading is a continual motion. And it is as much our duty to <hi>continue in the faith,</hi> as to own it at firſt. We have
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:003526_0124_0FF857CB9250A4F8"/>therefore that <hi>exhortation,</hi> Heb. x. 23. <hi>Let us hold faſt the profeſſion of our faith without wavering.</hi> And this is the <hi>commendation</hi> given by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the church in <hi>Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Thou holdeſt faſt my name, and haſt not denied my faith,</hi> Rev. ii. 13. And it is the black <hi>character</hi> of the devil, the grand apoſtate, that <hi>he abode not in the truth,</hi> John viii. 44.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. To ſhew <hi>how God teaches</hi> thoſe whom he leads in his truth.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Outwardly by his <hi>word.</hi> This is the ſtanding rule, and the ordinary means. The ſcriptures of the old and new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment contain the outward revelation of God's mind and will; they teach us "what we are to believe concerning God, and what duty God requires of us. And in them God doth as really teach us, as if he were our immediate monitor. For <hi>all ſcripture is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and for inſtruction in righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Tim. iii. 16. It was written by <hi>holy men of God,</hi> as they were <hi>moved by the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and is a perfect revelation, able to <hi>make us wiſe unto ſalvation, thro' faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And they that have it in their <hi>hands,</hi> need not ſay in
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:003526_0125_0FF8579968863CB0"/>their <hi>hearts, Who ſhall go up to heaven for us, and bring the truth of God to us, that we may hear it and know it?</hi> God has indeed appointed a <hi>ſtanding miniſtry;</hi> but the buſineſs of that is to <hi>teach Jacob God's judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Iſrael his law;</hi> to <hi>open</hi> the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word, and to <hi>apply</hi> it, not to add to it, or bring another in its room. Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are therefore to ſtudy this word, and in their preaching to keep cloſe to it. Iſai. viii. 20. <hi>To the law and to the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi> 2 Tim. ii. 15. <hi>Study to ſhew thy ſelf approved unto God, a workman that needeth not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, rightly dividing the word of truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Inwardly by his <hi>Spirit.</hi> John xiv. 26. <hi>But the comforter which is the Holy Ghoſt, whom the father ſhall ſend in my name, He ſhall teach you all things.</hi> He helps to underſtand the word. The ſpirit does not ordinarily teach <hi>without</hi> the word, never <hi>contrary</hi> to it. He does not diſcover new things which have no foundation in the bible, but helps to diſcern the things there reveal'd, by an internal ſpiritual illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Hence <hi>David</hi> prays, Pſalm cxix. 18, <hi>Open thou mine eyes, that I may behold wondrous things out of thy law.</hi> This is what <hi>Chriſt</hi> did for his diſciples after his
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:003526_0126_0FF857CDC14E7130"/>reſurrection, Luke xxiv. 45. <hi>Then opened he their underſtandings to underſtand the ſcriptures.</hi> We need <hi>internal illumination,</hi> as well as an <hi>external revelation,</hi> in order to our ſpiritual diſcerning goſpel truths. The <hi>objects</hi> indeed are fairly preſented in the word, but the <hi>faculty</hi> muſt be prepar'd to receive them; for ſince the fall the underſtanding of man is unapt to receive the rays of divine light; not that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of diſcerning is loſt, but weakned, and, more than ſo, corrupted and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced. The rational mind may diſcern the literal ſenſe of the propoſitions in the goſpel, but the quickening beams of the ſpirit of truth and holineſs, muſt help to diſcern them in their ſpiritual meaning, excellency, and glory, and to ſuch a through conviction of their truth and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, as heartily to receive and embrace them. Reading or hearing alone will not let the doctrines of the goſpel into our underſtandings in their true and proper light. Iſai. vi. 9. <hi>Hear ye indeed, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not; and ſee ye indeed, but perceive not.</hi> Certainly the knowledge of the truth <hi>as it is in Jeſus,</hi> is a different thing from the knowledge of it <hi>as it is in ink and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi> Heavenly things cannot be ſeen in their reality and glory, but by a heavenly
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:003526_0127_0FF8579C54AA4C68"/>light. All the torches and candles we can light up, cannot ſhew us the light of the ſun, unleſs it ſhed down its own light up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us: So the humane underſtanding, tho' never ſo much aſſiſted with outward and rational helps, cannot behold ſpiritual truths in their proper light, but by a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual irradiation. 1 Cor. ii. 14. <hi>The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural man receiveth not the things of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God: for they are fooliſhneſs unto him; neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> Therefore it was the Apoſtle's deſire and prayer in behalf of his beloved <hi>Epheſians, That the God of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the father of glory, would give unto them the ſpirit of wiſdom, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, in the knowledge of him,: that the eyes of their underſtanding being inlightned, they might know the hope of his calling, and the riches of the glory of his inheritance in the ſaints, and the exceeding greatneſs of his power to them ward who believe,</hi> Eph. i. 17, 18. Thus God teaches thoſe whom he leads into his truth, by his <hi>word,</hi> and by his <hi>ſpirit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">IV. We are to ſay, <hi>Why we ſhould ſeek to God</hi> to afford us his teaching, for to lead us into his truth.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="11" facs="unknown:003526_0128_0FF857D0DD88DE08"/>
1. We ſhall <hi>never rightly know the truth,</hi> if God does not teach us and lead us into it. Truth is a precious jewel, a pearl of great price, which the mind of man has a natural deſire after, and is in queſt of; and that we find it, is of the laſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to us. For the knowledge of the truth is the foundation of religion, and is the firſt ſtep to ſalvation. 1 Tim. ii. 4. <hi>Who will have all men to be ſaved, and to come to the knowledge of the truth.</hi> A true chriſtian is one that believes the doctrines, as well as obeys the precepts of Jeſus Chriſt; and the former is as neceſſary as the latter. <hi>With the heart man believes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. x. 9. But we ſhall never know them to a ſaving purpoſe, ſhall never heartily believe, embrace, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce in, and live upon them, without a divine teaching. Neither <hi>natural reaſon,</hi> nor <hi>humane teaching</hi> are ſufficient for this; as has been already hinted. Hence the greateſt maſters of reaſon and learning, are many times moſt ignorant in, or the greateſt deſpiſers of goſpel myſteries. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus, a maſter in Iſrael,</hi> could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt's doctrine of ſpiritual rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. What Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> upon the profeſſion of his faith in that <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental article</hi> of Chriſt's divinity, may be
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:003526_0129_0FF8579DDB4B55D0"/>ſaid to every true believer, reſpecting the ſame and other doctrines of the goſpel, Mat. xvi. 17. <hi>And Jeſus anſwered and ſaid unto him, Bleſſed art thou, Simon Barjona; For fleſh and blood hath not revealed it to thee, but my father which is in heaven.</hi> Without this divine teaching we ſhall but (as it were) grope in the dark; be <hi>ever learning, but not able come to the knowledge of the truth:</hi> Our knowledge will at beſt be but dark and confus'd, our faith weak, wavering, and ineffectual. <hi>The double<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded man,</hi> that is not fix'd in his religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous principles, will be <hi>unſtable in all his ways,</hi> James i. 8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The danger we are in of being led into <hi>contrary errors,</hi> ſhould make us ſeek of God to <hi>teach us and lead us into his truth.</hi> There is truth, and there is error. Every grace (we ſay) has its <hi>counterfeit,</hi> and ſo every truth has it's <hi>oppoſite.</hi> And error is oftentimes ſo dreſs'd up by the ſlight of men, and the artifice of ſatan, ſo colour'd and varniſh'd, that it looks like truth, and is taken for ſuch by too many. We had need therefore ſeek divine teaching, that ſo we may diſcern the things that differ, and may approve only things that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent. Errors in religion are dangerous, tho' ſome more than others; and ſome of
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:003526_0130_0FF857D3119DD788"/>them are fatal and deſtructive. <hi>2 Pet.</hi> ii. 1. Scarce any errors are purely ſpeculative; they do more or leſs affect the heart, and influence the life.</p>
                  <p>Indeed in this day of abounding errors, no little pains are taken by ſome, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade men that truth and error are indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent things; that 'tis no matter what opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions a man holds, if he does but lead, what they are pleas'd to call (in a ſenſe unevangelical eno') an honeſt and good life. In this way ſome late celebrated Writers, have ſhewn their enmity to <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxy,</hi> to <hi>creeds,</hi> and <hi>confeſſions of faith;</hi> and wou'd prepare men to receive their own corrupt opinions. But if it be ſuch an indifferent thing what opinions men are of, as theſe would repreſent, to what end are ſo many <hi>Epiſtles</hi> written to the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to regulate and eſtabliſh their faith? To what end does the Holy Spirit ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly exhort us <hi>not to be deceiv'd; to buy the truth, and not to ſell it;</hi> to <hi>beware of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers;</hi> to <hi>ſhun philoſophy and vain deceit;</hi> to <hi>hold faſt the form of ſound words,</hi> to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the faith, grounded, and ſettled;</hi> and <hi>to take heed leſt being led away with the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the wicked, we fall from our own ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſs;</hi> and therefore to <hi>prove all things,</hi> and to <hi>hold faſt what is good.</hi> And why
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:003526_0131_0FF8579F9EE5B2D0"/>did the Apoſtle ſo fear for the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> leſt as the <hi>ſerpent beguiled Eve thro' his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, their minds ſhould be corrupted from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt?</hi> Surely theſe things imply a great difference between truth and error; and are a plain declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that <hi>doctrines</hi> and <hi>opinions</hi> are of great concern and moment in our religion, and in the buſineſs of ſalvation. And are eno' to make us very careful what prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples we forſake, and what we embrace; eno' to make us earneſtly ſeek of God his teaching to <hi>lead us into</hi> truth, and to <hi>keep us in</hi> it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We are encourag'd to hope <hi>God will teach us, and lead us in his truth,</hi> if we ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely ſeek to him and wait upon him. We have therefore that direction, James i. 5. <hi>If any of you lack wiſdom,</hi> (to guide him in the judgment of things, as well as in the management of affairs) <hi>let him ask of God, who gives to all liberally upbraiding not.</hi> And God is ready to perform that promiſe, Prov. ii. 3, 4, 5. <hi>If thou crieſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowledge, and lifteſt up thy voice for underſtanding; then ſhalt thou underſtand the fear of the Lord, and find the knowledge of God.</hi> Divine teaching is included in the gift of the ſpirit: and what encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement have we to ſeek this bleſſed gift?
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:003526_0132_0FF857D4C6FFDEC0"/>Luke xi. 13. <hi>If ye then being evil know how to give good gifts unto your children: how much more ſhall your heavenly father give the holy Spirit to them that ask him?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. There is <hi>no ſuch teacher as God is;</hi> therefore ſhould we ſeek of him to teach us. <hi>Who teaches like him?</hi> ſaid <hi>Elihu</hi> to <hi>Job,</hi> ch. xxxvi. 22. His teaching are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all other teachings. There are other teachers beſides God, or rather <hi>under</hi> him, <hi>miniſterial teachers</hi> of his own appointment, with whom he vouchſafes to work; but there are none like him: and the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the teacher, ſhould excite us to ſeek his teachings. Here</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) His teachings are the moſt <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>intimate.</hi> They not only inform the <hi>underſtanding,</hi> but reach to the <hi>heart;</hi> are receiv'd into <hi>that,</hi> affect and move <hi>that.</hi> It is truly ſaid, <hi>He has his pulpit in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, who teaches hearts.</hi> This is God's prerogative. 2 Cor. iv. 6. <hi>God who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the light to ſhine out of darkneſs, hath ſhined INTO OUR HEARTS, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Man's light may ſhine into the head, but God's light doth ſhine into the heart. The Pſalmiſt expreſſes the intimacy of divine teachings. Pſalm li. 6. <hi>Behold thou deſireſt truth in the
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:003526_0133_0FF812C4B48311C8"/>inward part, and in the hidden part ſhalt thou make me to know wiſdom.</hi> Pſal. xvi. 7. <hi>I will bleſs the Lord who hath given me coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, my reins alſo inſtruct me in the night ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> The <hi>reins</hi> are the moſt inward parts of the body, and the <hi>night ſeaſons</hi> the moſt private and retired time: both expreſs the intimacy of divine teaching.</p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) His teachings are moſt <hi>plain</hi> &amp; <hi>clear.</hi> Theſe make that plain which the ſoul be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had but a very confus'd notion of. The miracle which Chriſt wrought on the blind man, in Mark viii. 24, 25, might be deſign'd to teach us this. <hi>Chriſt put his hands upon him, and ask'd him if he ſaw ought. The man looked up, and ſaid, I ſee men as trees walking. After that he put his hands again upon his eyes, and made him look up: and he was reſtored, and ſaw every man clearly.</hi> So Chriſt ſaid to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, John xvi. 25. <hi>Theſe things have I ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto you in proverbs: the time cometh when I ſhall no more ſpeak unto you in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs, but I ſhall ſhew you plainly of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> The ſoul taught of God is made to <hi>ſee,</hi> which is more than to hear or barely to apprehend; according to that of <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b,</hi> (chap. xlii. 15.) <hi>I have heard of thee by the hearing of the ear, but now mine eye SEETH thee.</hi> And agreeable to that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:003526_0134_0FF857D6F93DC730"/>(Eph. iii. 9.) <hi>And to make all men SEE, what is the fellowſhip of the myſtery which from the beginning of the world hath been bid in God, who created all things by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">(3.) His teachings are the moſt <hi>convinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>ſatisfying.</hi> Our Saviour therefore ſaid of the Spirit, (John xvi. 8.) <hi>When he is come, he ſhall convince the world.</hi> Under the teachings of God the ſoul cannot but yield an unfeigned aſſent to what is taught. His teachings bring ſuch clear evidence of truth to the mind, as ſets the ſoul beyond all peradventure, and gives it a full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. 1 Theſſ. i. 5. <hi>Our Goſpel came to you not in word only, but in Power, and in the Holy Ghoſt, and in much aſſurance.</hi> And, in Col. ii. 2, we read of <hi>the full aſſurance of underſtanding, to the acknowledgment of the myſtery of God, and of the father, and of Chriſt.</hi> Man's teaching may prevail to ſilence, ſo that the perſon mayn't be able to gainſay or deny, tho' the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may be doubtful ſtill: but the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God not only ſilence but <hi>ſatisfie;</hi> the ſoul freely and ſweetly acquieſces in the things taught, and is fully ſatisfied that they are <hi>the truth and no lie.</hi> So <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. cxix. 75. <hi>I know, O Lord, that thy judgments are right.</hi> So the people anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered to the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> John
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:003526_0135_0FF857A594548F30"/>iv. 42. <hi>Now we believe, not becauſe of thy ſaying: for we have heard him our ſelves, and know that this is indeed the Chriſt, the Saviour of the world.</hi> Divine teachings are ſo ſatisfying to the ſoul, that it can ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture its all upon the truth of what it has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>earn'd of God. So the female martyr ſaid to her perſecutors, <hi>Tho' I can't diſpute for Chriſt, I can die for him.</hi> Prov. viii. 8, 9. <hi>All the words of my mouth are in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, there is nothing froward or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe in them. They are all plain to him that underſtandeth, and right to them that find knowledge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">(4.) His teachings are the moſt <hi>powerful</hi> and <hi>effectual.</hi> Men teach in the Name of God, and by his authority; but it is God only who can give power and efficacy to his word. 2 Cor. iv. 7. <hi>But we have this treaſure in earthen veſſels, that the excellency of the power, may be of God, and not of us.</hi> It was remark'd concerning Chriſt's preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Mat. vii. 29. <hi>That he taught as one having authority, and not as the ſcribes.</hi> There went a mighty power with his Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, perceiv'd and felt by thoſe that heard him. The teachings of God can make their way into the dulleſt and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt capacities. Iſai. xxxv. 8. <hi>An high way ſhall be there, and a way, and it ſhall be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the way of holineſs: the way-faring men,
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:003526_0136_0FF857D9E8AEF678"/>tho' fools ſhall not err therein.</hi> Hence ſome poor illiterate chriſtians, have had more knowledge and greater illuminations in ſpiritual and divine things, than men of good abilities and deep penetration. On this account our Saviour broke forth into thoſe words, Mat. xi. 25. <hi>I thank thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them unto babes:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">(5) The teachings of God are <hi>trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming.</hi> They transform the ſoul into another image than it had before. God <hi>caſts</hi> thoſe whom he teaches into the very <hi>mould</hi> of the truths which he teaches them. Rom. vi. 17. <hi>Ye were the ſervants of ſin, but God be thanked ye have obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine INTO WHICH YE WERE DELIVERED,</hi> (ſo it might rather be read) as into a <hi>mould,</hi> by which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and repreſent the ſhape and figure of it. By the teachings of God the ſoul is transform'd into the likeneſs and ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the goſpel, anſwers it, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd to it. 2 Cor. iii. 18. <hi>We all with open face, beholding as in a glaſs the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame image from glory to glory, as by the Spirit of the Lord.</hi> The <hi>glaſs</hi> wherein we have this ſight of the glory of God, is chiefly the
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:003526_0137_0FF857A72ACD2358"/>
                     <hi>word:</hi> We are helpt to <hi>ſee</hi> the glory of God in this glaſs by the teachings of his Spirit. The <hi>glory</hi> into which we are chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this ſight, is our conformity to that holineſs which ſhineth in the word. And this change is twofold; from <hi>ſin</hi> to <hi>grace,</hi> which is a degree of glory; and <hi>from glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to glory,</hi> i. e. from one degree of glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous grace to another, till grace here be conſummated in glory for ever.</p>
                  <p n="6">(6.) The teachings of God are <hi>abiding.</hi> I John ii. 27. <hi>But the anointing which ye have received abideth in you.</hi> Notional knowledge, where it is no more, is flitting; and the words of men they vaniſh from us: But the words of God they ſtick in the ſoul, and the impreſſions made by his teaching are laſting Impreſſions, Pſalm cxix. 98. <hi>Thou thro' thy commandments haſt made me wiſer than mine enemies: for they are EVER WITH ME.</hi> And in 93, ver. <hi>I will NEVER FORGET thy precepts; for with them thou haſt quickned me.</hi> What God teaches any he writes on their hearts; and what is written <hi>there</hi> remains. Heb. viii. 10. <hi>I will put my laws into their mind, and write them in their hearts.</hi> The teachings of God ſo abide with the ſoul, as to cauſe <hi>perſeverance</hi> in his ways. Pſalm cxix. 33. <hi>Teach me, O Lord, the way of thy ſtatutes,
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:003526_0138_0FF857DB70560600"/>and I ſhall keep it to the end.</hi> He dares pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe perſeverance, if God will undertake inſtruction. And accordingly ſtedfaſtneſs was the fruit of this teaching. Therefore he ſays again, ver. 102. <hi>I have not departed from thy judgments: for thou haſt taught me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Once more</p>
                  <p n="7">(7.) Divine teaching is <hi>ſaving.</hi> All o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther teaching can't ſave a man from hell: Let a man have never ſo much humane learning and notional knowledge, if he has no other, he will never find the way to heaven, but will lie down in eternal ſorrow. But the teachings of God will make the ſoul <hi>wiſe unto ſalvation,</hi> 2 Tim. iii. 15. The ſoul that has them, will not miſs of eternal life: According to the words of our Saviour, John xvii. 2. <hi>And this is life eternal, that they might kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>w thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</hi> They that have the light of grace, ſhall have the light of glory: For the light of grace and glory are of the ſame kind, tho' not in the ſame degree. They that have <hi>this viſion</hi> ſhall not <hi>periſh.</hi> This teaching has <hi>ſalvation</hi> annex'd to, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected with it. This therefore the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt makes an argument in our text, for God to afford him his teaching; <hi>Lead me in thy truth, and teach me: for thou art the God of my ſalvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="unknown:003526_0139_0FF857A964B8E4E8"/>
All the USE I ſhall make of this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is, to <hi>direct</hi> us in ſeeking to God for <hi>his teaching,</hi> that we may be led into <hi>his truth.</hi> The reaſons that have been given why we ſhould do this, are <hi>weighty</hi> and <hi>cogent,</hi> if duely conſider'd. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore add nothing further by way of <hi>motive,</hi> but only by way of <hi>direction,</hi> in a few hints of importance to be obſerv'd.</p>
                  <p>Briefly then,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Be <hi>carneſt</hi> and <hi>importunate</hi> in ſeeking this. A cold wiſh or two, that God wou'd teach us his truth, is not anſwerable to the importance of the thing. This is a matter of <hi>prime importance,</hi> of <hi>infinite concernment,</hi> in which our <hi>ſalvation</hi> is concern'd, as is ſuggeſted to us in the text; and we ſhou'd ſeek it of God with an anſwerable impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon our ſpirits, with ſuch a deep and inward concern as is agreeable to the momentous ſubject. <hi>If thou crieſt after knowledge, and lifteſt up thy voice for under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, then ſhalt thou find the knowledge of God,</hi> Prov. ii. 4, 5.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Continue ſeeking. Continue in prayer and watch in the ſame with thankſgiving.</hi> Our <hi>daily conſtant</hi> prayer ſhould be of this import, <hi>Lead me in thy truth and teach me.</hi> One of the <hi>pleas</hi> with which this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition is urg'd in the text, ſpeaks a <hi>conſtant</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="unknown:003526_0140_0FF857DDDF3935B8"/>
                     <hi>attendance</hi> upon God in the way of duty. <hi>On thee do I wait all the day.</hi> "It ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>all the day long,</hi> and <hi>every day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. To prayer join the <hi>uſe of other God's appointed means.</hi> Study the word of God, for his <hi>word is truth;</hi> and uſe the beſt helps you can for the right underſtanding of it. <hi>Underſtandeſt thou what thou readeſt?</hi> ſaid <hi>Phillip</hi> to the <hi>Eunuch.</hi> He anſwered, <hi>How can I, except ſome man ſhould guide me?</hi> Acts viii. 30, 31. The <hi>expoſitions</hi> of holy and learned men, are to be us'd with thankfulneſs and prayer for our better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the ſcriptures. And thus the <hi>ſtated miniſtry</hi> of the word is alſo to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. It is an apoſtolical cautionary direction, 1 Theſ. v. 20. <hi>Deſpiſe not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyings,</hi> i.e. ordinary preaching, the word opened and applied by miniſters in chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an aſſemblies. God not only gave extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary officers to his church, but ordinary, <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and teachers, for the perfecting of the ſaints, for the work of the miniſtry, for the edifying the body of Chriſt, till we all come in the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the faith, and the knowledge of the ſon of God, unto a perfect man, to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt,</hi> Eph. iv. 10, 11. Theſe ends being to be anſwer'd <hi>now,</hi> as well as heretofore, the office continues: And their miniſtrations are to
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:003526_0141_0FF857AB97096660"/>be attended on as an ordinance of God. As we ſhould not <hi>reſt in</hi> the teachings of men, ſo we ſhould not think our ſelves <hi>above</hi> them. For God is pleas'd to own and bleſs them, for the end whereto he has appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them. Miniſters are <hi>workers together</hi> with God, as <hi>helpers of your faith and joy. Who then is Paul, and who is Apollos, but miniſters by whom ye believed, even as the Lord gave to every man?</hi> 1 Cor. iii. 5.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Indulge nothing that hath a tendency to lead you aſtray from truth;</hi> to byaſs your judgment, and give a wrong bent to your mind. Beware of all <hi>ſecret prejudices.</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to mortifie <hi>pride, ſelf-conceit,</hi> and an <hi>affectation of novelty. Grieve not the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit of God</hi> by any ſin, leſt he be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd to leave you to a ſpirit of deluſion.</p>
                  <p n="5">5, and laſtly, Be very careful to <hi>live up to what you do know, and profeſs to believe. Practical holineſs,</hi> (as one ſays,) is an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent means for the maintaining of <hi>doctrinal orthodoxy. Solomon</hi> tells us, 'tis for the <hi>righteous that God layeth up ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>und wiſdom,</hi> Prov. ii. 7. And again, <hi>He giveth to thoſe that are good in his ſight, wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> Eccl. ii. 26: And our Saviou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf tells us, John vii. 17. <hi>If any man will do his will, he ſhall know of the doctrine, whether it of God, or whether I ſpeak of
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:003526_0142_0FF857E01C0B9890"/>my ſelf.</hi> "Such as follow the guidance of the Spirit in the courſe of their lives, ſhall have him to regulate their judgments: And they that are govern'd by him as a ſpirit of holineſs, ſhall be inſtructed by him as a ſpirit of truth".</p>
                  <p>I ſhall conclude this diſcourſe, with giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you one <hi>ſhort rule,</hi> whereby to try and judge of doctrines whether they be of God. <hi>Thoſe doctrines which tend moſt to debaſe and humble man, and to exalt and magnifie free grace, are moſt likely to be of God.</hi> The reaſon is becauſe this is what God aims at in the contrivance of fallen man's redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. To this the whole frame is admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly fitted, from the firſt <hi>corner ſtone,</hi> to the bringing forth the <hi>top ſtone</hi> thereof. 1 Cor. i. 29, 30, 31. <hi>That no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence. But of him are ye in Chriſt Jeſus, who of God is made unto us wiſdom, and righteouſneſs, and ſanctification, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: That, according as it is written, Let him that glorieth, glory in the Lord.</hi> Eph. ii. 7, 8, 9. <hi>That in the ages to come he might ſhew the exceeding riches of his grace, in his kindneſs towards us thro' Chriſt Jeſus. For by grace are ye ſaved, thro' faith; and that not of your ſelves: it is the gift of God. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t of works, leſt any man ſhould boaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="unknown:003526_0143_0FF857ADC341E490"/>
An excellent writer, upon that anſwer which <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave to <hi>Peter</hi> when he had confeſs'd his divinity, <hi>Fleſh and blood hath not revealed it to thee, but my father in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> hath theſe words which I think worth tranſcribing, <q>It is no recommending character of any doctrine, that it is pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſutable to fleſh and blood. We have reaſon to be jealous that it is no ſpiritual truth, which the natural man very readily receives. The doctrines which are promoted and countenanced by fleſh and blood, have the ſuſpicious mark upon them of accurſed doctrines. 'Tis no argument why I ſhould give credit to this or that opinion, becauſe 'tis grateful to nature, but rather an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt it. The ſwift progreſs of error is owing very much to its ſmooth concurrence with the ſtream of nature. It is ill judging after the fleſh, they judge beſt and moſt wiſely, that judge contrary to it.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now may <hi>the SPIRIT OF TRUTH lead us into all truth,</hi> for His ſake who is <hi>the WAY, and the TRUTH, and the LIFE!</hi>
                     <note place="bottom">Page 3. l. 16. for <hi>could</hi> r. <hi>might.</hi> P. 10. l. 2. dele <hi>the light of.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
