<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dissertation on the image of God wherein man was created. [Three lines from Genesis] / By Benjamin Colman, D.D. ; [Three lines from Van Mastricht]</title>
            <author>Colman, Benjamin, 1673-1747.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N03287</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N03287</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 4001</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APZ0514</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">4001</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99038133</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 4001.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N03287)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 4001)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 4001)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dissertation on the image of God wherein man was created. [Three lines from Genesis] / By Benjamin Colman, D.D. ; [Three lines from Van Mastricht]</title>
                  <author>Colman, Benjamin, 1673-1747.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], xii, 47, [1] p. ;  22 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed &amp; sold by S. Kneeland and T. Green in Queen-Street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCCXXXVI. [1736]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Addenda"--p. 47.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>God --  Attributes.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:004001_0000_10037476469159C8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:004001_0001_100373805DEDF8D8"/>
            <p>A Diſſertation On the <hi>Image</hi> of GOD, wherein <hi>Man</hi> was created.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:004001_0002_1003738A347A8A30"/>
            <p>A DISSERTATION ON THE <hi>Image of GOD</hi> WHEREIN <hi>Man was created.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GENESIS. I. 27.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>So God created Man in his own Image, in the Image of God created He him, Male and Female created He them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Benjamin Colman,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Anima eſt Naturae ſpiritualis, caeleſtis, divinae, indiviſibilis, incorruptibilis, immortalis, Angelis imo Deo proximae.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Van Maſtricht.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON:</hi> Printed &amp; Sold by S. KNEELAND and T. GREEN in Queen-ſtreet. MDCCXXXVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb facs="unknown:004001_0003_1003738D66D05720"/>
            <p>Quoniam deleta eſt Imago Dei in nobis per lapſum <hi>Adae,</hi> ex reparatione judicandum eſt qualis fuerit: Dicit <hi>Paulus</hi> nos per Evangelium transfigurari in Imaginem Dei: Et ſecundum ipſum Regeneratio ſpiritualis nihil aliud eſt quam ejuſdem Imaginis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauratio: quod autem eam conſtituit <hi>in Juſtitia et Sanctitate veraci,</hi> eſt Synecdoche; nam quamvis illud praecipuum eſt, non tamen eſt totum: Hac voce deſignatur totius Naturae Integritas, — in Mente lux rectae Intelligentiae &amp;c—.</p>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Calv. in loc.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="i" facs="unknown:004001_0004_10037394801AB3F0"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> INTROD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CTION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N a late <hi>Diſſertation</hi> on the <hi>three firſt Chapters of Geneſis,</hi> I paſs'd over the <hi>Subject</hi> now before me, with a Deſign (by the Will of God) to give it a more <hi>diſtinct</hi> and full Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration by it ſelf. <hi>This</hi> I now preſent unto the Publick, hoping it may be of ſome <hi>Uſe</hi> and not unacceptable, to <hi>Them</hi> eſpecially whoſe ſpiritual Profit has been the Duty and Aim of my Studies and Miniſtry. And the leſs I am like to viſit and converſe with them in my <hi>advancing Years,</hi> the rather would I now and then put into their Hands ſome of the <hi>Meditations</hi> they have heard with Patience and Pleaſure, and in which when I am dead I may <hi>yet ſpeak</hi> to 'em. And if this <hi>Apology</hi> diſpleaſe any, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke <hi>Reflections</hi> public or private, they will not much move me.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="ii" facs="unknown:004001_0005_1003739D39742140"/>
               <hi>Man</hi> in his firſt Eſtate, and ſo <hi>Angels</hi> in theirs, were very much made for <hi>Contemplation</hi> and <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi> And <hi>theſe</hi> are very much the Exerciſe, Pleaſure and Improvement of <hi>renewed</hi> and enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Minds under the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Admiration</hi> ſeems the firſt Affection of an <hi>Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Creature,</hi> both in the Order of Nature and of Time; and of ſpecial Uſe and Influence in the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, moral and <hi>Divine Life.</hi> We may ſuppoſe <hi>Adam</hi> was ſtruck with vaſt and a moſt pleaſing <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration</hi> upon his firſt coming into Being. What a <hi>World of Wonders</hi> preſented it ſelf before his Eyes! how many ſtrange and beautiful <hi>Objects</hi> ſurrounded him! which ſhould he firſt gaze at, which moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire! and moſt of all (it may be) did he ſurvey and wonder at <hi>Himſelf!</hi> 
               <q>Who and what am I? whence came I into this Form and Circumſtances, and with theſe Powers of Mind and Body? what glorious Wiſdom Power and Goodneſs has made me thus, and all theſe Things about me?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Such we may ſuppoſe were the Emotions of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Mind, upon his firſt View of his <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> the living <hi>Creatures</hi> about him, and of the <hi>Heavens</hi> over him. In the midſt of which holy Aſtoniſhment he fell into a <hi>Trance,</hi> and awak'd with a <hi>new Object</hi> before him, more the <hi>Wonder</hi> and Deſire of his Eyes than all that he had ſeen before! It was <hi>Eve,</hi> form'd in the ſame <hi>Image and Likeneſs of God</hi> that he ſaw and felt within himſelf. How did he gaze on this <hi>crowning Gift</hi> of Heaven to him! <q>
                  <hi>This is now Bone of my Bone, and Fleſh of my Fleſh;</hi> ſaid he, <hi>She ſhall be called Woman.</hi>
               </q>— Immediately God bro't the long Train of <hi>living Creatures,</hi> in beauteous Order, before their <hi>Earthly Lord</hi> and Owner, to give them <hi>Names</hi> according to their various Kind and Nature. What a <hi>Scene</hi> of Admiration was this to <hi>Adam</hi> and alſo to the <hi>Angels</hi> of God! to ſee an
<pb n="iii" facs="unknown:004001_0006_100373A519E1ABE0"/>imbodied Spirit, like <hi>Themſelves</hi> in the Image of God for Knowledge, endowed with an <hi>Inſight</hi> into the various Workmanſhip of God below, into the exquiſite Perfection of every Form, the End &amp; Uſe of every living Thing! Thus his <hi>firſt</hi> Act of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to his <hi>Maker</hi> was Admiration, which juſtifies the Wiſdom of the <hi>Schools,</hi> who have made it the firſt of the <hi>Paſſions.</hi> It certainly is ſo, and <hi>ever</hi> was. But in our preſent <hi>fallen</hi> State, in how <hi>low and feeble</hi> a manner is the <hi>firſt Exerciſe</hi> hereof in our <hi>Infancy!</hi> in what unknown ſort of <hi>Confuſion</hi> are the <hi>firſt</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices of Things now received by us! The ſtate of <hi>Infancy</hi> had no doubt been vaſtly better in a ſtate of <hi>Innocence,</hi> and the <hi>Perception</hi> of Things incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly faſter, more diſtinct, and exquiſitely pleaſant; as the <hi>Chriſtal Glaſs</hi> drinks in the Light and is irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> has made all his wonderful Works to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired; to <hi>be ſought out with Pleaſure</hi> by all rational Beings. He has made <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> to admire them and give him Glory. This is their <hi>Worſhip</hi> and Praiſe to God, and their own <hi>Improvement</hi> in Knowledge and Goodneſs—It had been the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate <hi>Sin and Fall</hi> of our firſt Parents, without their eating of the <hi>forbidden Fruit,</hi> yea before <hi>that</hi> was forbidden to them, if the <hi>firſt</hi> Affection and Exerciſe of their Mind had not been a religious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend <hi>Admiration</hi> of God, in Themſelves, the Heavens and Earth, and in all the living Creatures about them. And holy Admiration ſtill <hi>is,</hi> ever <hi>has been</hi> and ever <hi>will be,</hi> the Imployment and Felicity of Angels and Saints in the <hi>heavenly Places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There</hi> are the <hi>Objects</hi> of Admiration which <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard,</hi> neither can they <hi>enter into the Heart of Man to conceive of;</hi> And the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of Heaven</hi> have greater Capacities and Powers to <hi>look into</hi> the Wiſdom Power and Goodneſs of God in all his Works: How then do we think that
<pb n="iv" facs="unknown:004001_0007_1003588AF9D5CD28"/>
               <hi>They admir'd</hi> and ador'd, look'd on the <hi>Divine Glory</hi> and on one another, and <hi>ſhouted together</hi> in the Day of their <hi>own</hi> Creation! And again we read, that in the Day they ſaw our <hi>Earth</hi> come into its Place Form and Motion, with <hi>Man</hi> and all the Creatures <hi>under his feet</hi> thereon, thoſe <hi>Morning Stars ſang all together</hi> the Praiſes of God. How did they admire the Deſcent of the IMMENSE SPIRIT <hi>on the Face of the Deep,</hi> to bring a World of <hi>Order</hi> and Beauty out of that dark <hi>Void,</hi> and Abyſſe of confuſed Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter! With what awful Reverence and vaſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation did they attend and liſten, when God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>the Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs!</hi> tho' they were moſt acquainted with <hi>Light</hi> before, dwelling in the Fulneſs of it, <hi>in Light unapprochable</hi> by us, where the Light of the <hi>Sun</hi> is not needed, and compar'd with which it is but a <hi>Shade!</hi> Yet they ſaw <hi>our</hi> Light was <hi>good,</hi> inexpreſſibly good <hi>for us,</hi> and they admir'd the <hi>dividing</hi> it from the Darkneſs. They ſaw the <hi>Firmament,</hi> that vaſt Expanſe of <hi>Air</hi> and Region of Light and Darkneſs, a Shadow to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Eyes of the inconceivable <hi>Immenſity</hi> of God, <hi>filling all in all</hi> thro' this his ſeen Univerſe. They beheld from on High the forming of our <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>dry Land,</hi> and the Earth bringing forth <hi>Herbs</hi> and <hi>Graſs</hi> and <hi>Trees,</hi> with all their wondrous <hi>Seeds</hi> and <hi>Fruits,</hi> while as yet there was no <hi>Ray</hi> of the Sun upon them; not knowing, but expecting greatly, for what kind of <hi>Creature</hi> and Creatures this vaſt Profuſion of <hi>Bounty</hi> was prepared. They were the only <hi>Audience</hi> when God bad the <hi>Waters</hi> bring forth the <hi>moving</hi> Creature that hath <hi>Life,</hi> and the <hi>Fowl</hi> that fill the <hi>Air</hi> and fly in the open Firmament; and while they heard God <hi>bleſs</hi> his inferior living Creatures, and bid 'em to increaſe, to <hi>multiply</hi> and propagate their <hi>Kind,</hi> (a Thing altogether <hi>new</hi> to <hi>Angels</hi> and marvellous in their Eyes, for living Creatures to <hi>communicate</hi> Likeneſs and Life, under
<pb n="v" facs="unknown:004001_0008_100373B5B62ED1B0"/>the Power and Bleſſing of God) how were they fill'd with <hi>new</hi> Wonder and Delight at this <hi>new Thing</hi> which the <hi>Lord God</hi> created: whereof their Superiour World had given them no <hi>Idea.</hi> They then turn'd their Eyes on the <hi>dry Land,</hi> and with a growing Surprize ſaw <hi>the Cattle and creeping Things and Beaſts</hi> come forth out of the <hi>Earth</hi> after their Kind; all of them finding their proper <hi>Food</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for them, and all of them made in <hi>Pairs</hi> to propagate their kind! a <hi>Scene</hi> of Beauty and Wonder, and ſuperior Workmanſhip, ſuted to the Element of <hi>Air,</hi> as the <hi>Fiſhes</hi> before were to the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters! and could the <hi>bright Intelligences</hi> above look down on all theſe Things, from Day to Day, as God created them, and not be <hi>raviſh'd</hi> in the Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them?</p>
            <p>But moſt of all, when God proceeded and ſaid, <q>
                  <hi>Let Us make</hi> MAN, <hi>in our Image, after our Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Male and Female; to have Dominion over the Fiſh of the Sea, the Fowl of the Air, and over the Cattel and all the Earth;</hi>
               </q> how did the <hi>Hoſts of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> look (think we) with <hi>all</hi> their Eyes, to ſee what <hi>God-like</hi> Creature, like <hi>Themſelves,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> of all this Earth and of all the Creatures on it, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into Being? When preſently they ſaw the <hi>Lord God</hi> form Man's <hi>Body</hi> of the Duſt of the Ground, and then breathe into his Noſtrils the <hi>Breath of Life,</hi> and he became a <hi>living Soul,</hi> a <hi>Spirit</hi> like Themſelves, but united to Fleſh and Blood! O new and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous <hi>Form!</hi> ſo near <hi>a Kin</hi> unto themſelves and yet how <hi>different!</hi> made <hi>male and female</hi> alſo, to <hi>multiply and fill the Earth,</hi> and eat all the Good of it! How did the Angels of God look on and love the happy <hi>perfect Pair,</hi> and more admire 'em, than <hi>they</hi> were able to admire the Wiſdom and Power of God in themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="vi" facs="unknown:004001_0009_100373BE9609AD88"/>
I no more doubt, my <hi>Readers,</hi> of the Truth of ſomething <hi>like</hi> theſe things that I here write, than I do of almoſt any thing <hi>not ſeen</hi> and not revealed to me in the Word of God. That is to ſay, I do not at all queſtion but that in the Creation of this World of ours, the <hi>Angelic Hoſts look'd on admiring and giving Glory to God,</hi> as the Almighty proceeded from one Part of his Work unto another; and that the Words of God to <hi>Job</hi> out of the <hi>Whirlwind</hi> are to be taken literally; <hi>"When the Morning Stars ſang together, and all the Sons of God ſhouted for Joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Man in his <hi>fallen State,</hi> and in his <hi>Redemption</hi> has been more an Object of the <hi>Admiration</hi> of the <hi>Angels</hi> of God, than he was in his <hi>Creation.</hi> God's Work of <hi>Grace</hi> toward <hi>Sinners</hi> is repreſented to us as more admirable in the Eyes of <hi>Angels,</hi> than all his Works of Nature and Providence, in a ſeparate Conſideration herefrom. Not that Man's <hi>Sin</hi> was a thing ſo <hi>new</hi> to them, for they had ſeen their Fellow-Angels <hi>fall from Heaven;</hi> but the Recovery and <hi>Salvation</hi> of Sinners was a thing altogether <hi>unknown</hi> before. We find 'em therefore <hi>pictur'd</hi> by the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of God, and <hi>ſpoken</hi> of in his Word, as <hi>intently</hi> and for <hi>ever</hi> looking into this <hi>Myſtery</hi> of Grace<note n="*" place="bottom">Exod. xx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 17. 1 Pet. i. 12. Epheſ iii. 10. Iſai. vi. 2. Luke ii. 14. Revel. v. ii.</note>. So the <hi>Cherubims</hi> were made, by the Order of God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> with <hi>their Faces bowed over the Mercy-Seat,</hi> as never able to ſatisfy their pleaſing Wonder on the <hi>ſacred Myſtery.</hi> And St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us, that <hi>theſe Things the Angels deſire to look into.</hi> For as another <hi>Apoſtle</hi> teaches us, <hi>By the Church</hi> on Earth is the <hi>manifold Wiſdom of God made known to the Principalities and Powers above.</hi> And we have their <hi>new Songs</hi> thro' the Book of God, in Admiration of his Power,
<pb n="vii" facs="unknown:004001_0010_100373C9230D4828"/>Wiſdom, Holineſs and Mercy in the <hi>Redemption</hi> and Salvation of fallen Man.</p>
            <p>Only let us never think that the <hi>Admiration of perfected Spirits</hi> ever grows into any <hi>like Surpriſes and Amazements,</hi> as are ſometimes felt by us. The Light which ſhines in and on them in ſo pure clear and diſtinct, the Manner wherein they think and perceive is ſo perfect, the Government of their Tho't &amp; Affection is ſo true and exact, that it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids us to imagine any ſuch Weakneſs and Infirmity in their Admiration, as we find in our own. Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent &amp; holy Minds have a Strength, Steddineſs and Fortitude of Tho't, which we have loſt by our Fall. God of his Fulneſs communicates ſo to them, as is ever filling, refreſhing and ſatisfying 'em. <hi>In his Light they ſee Light.</hi> The Glory of <hi>his Face</hi> is ever ſhining on them in all that they behold. They are able to make an equal and juſt Obſervation of all things. They ſee and ſearch deep, with great Eaſe, into all Things, greater and leſs; and marvellous things occur to them in every one. They live in the World of Wonders, and ſee into the Wonders of all Worlds, ſee nothing little or common in any of them. All is great and good in their Eyes that God has done. We have <hi>Songs</hi> prepared for <hi>us</hi> which <hi>They</hi> take up and Sing: <q>
                  <hi>The Works of the Lord are great, ſought out by all them that have pleaſure in them!</hi>
               </q> 
               <q>
                  <hi>If I would ſpeak of them they are more than can be number'd.</hi>
               </q> Such Language as this becomes the Mouth of <hi>innocent</hi> Creatures, as well as <hi>ours.</hi> So He may be <hi>praiſed from the Heavens, "praiſed in the Heights!</hi> praiſe ye <hi>Him all his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels!</hi> And were the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> ſhining Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences like them, we ſhould call on them to praiſe him in their Courſes, and Stations: Or had the <hi>Deeps</hi> and <hi>Dragons</hi> from the Earth <hi>Minds</hi> to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire Him, and <hi>Tongues</hi> to extol Him, we might call on them to joyn with us in the Work. But ſince
<pb n="viii" facs="unknown:004001_0011_100373D3AAB92628"/>
               <hi>Beaſts and all Cattel, creeping Things and flying Fowl,</hi> have no ſuch Powers for Praiſe; let <hi>Kings of the Earth and all People, Princes and all Judges, young Men and Maidens, old Men and Children, praiſe the Name of the Lord; for his Name alone is excellent; his Glory is above the Earth and Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The great End and Deſign of this Affection of <hi>Admiration</hi> (ſays our admirable Dr. <hi>Watts</hi>) is to fix our <hi>Attention</hi> on the admired Object, to impreſs it more effectually on our <hi>Memory,</hi> and to give a ſenſible <hi>Delight</hi> to our Mind.</q> How good, how pleaſant and neceſſary then is it, to uſe this <hi>Means</hi> of fixing our Hearts on <hi>God</hi> by his Works, which day and night declare his <hi>Glory,</hi> and ſpeak to us of his Eternal Power and <hi>Godhead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, Without the <hi>Admiration</hi> of God in his Works of Nature, Providence and Grace, there neither is nor can be any thing of <hi>Religion,</hi> either among Angels or Men. And there is ſo little Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion among Men on Earth, becauſe there is no more Admiration of the bleſſed God in the Things that are ſeen, or that are revealed to us by him. The more God is admired by us the better He will be worſhiped and ſerved by us. It is becauſe He is ſo perfectly admir'd by the Spirits in Glory, that he is ſo perfectly ſerv'd and obey'd by them. The Admiration of God works by Love to Him, Delight in him, Deſire to pleaſe and glorify him, Fear and Reverence of his excellent Majeſty, and the Hope of ſeeing and ſerving him for ever. It draws all the Affections of the Soul after it, carries them along with it, and is the Spring and Life of all Devotion. It enlarges the Mind and dilates the Heart, and leads it away a willing Captive. It opens the Lips to ſhew forth God's Praiſe, it liſts up the Eyes and Hands to him, with Tranſports
<pb n="ix" facs="unknown:004001_0012_100373DC9749CAC0"/>of Joy: And at times too it ſtops the Voice, and <q>ſtrikes us mute, and Praiſe ſits ſilent on the Tongue.</q> — Such an Inſtrument of Devotion, and Handmaid to it, is true Admiration. It is ſacred and devoted to God, and Man in his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence kept it ſo. It is not only conſiſtent with perfect Tranquility and Happineſs, but indeed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes and advances it. There can be no true State or Reliſh of real Happineſs in created Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, without the free and full Exerciſe of this Affection. If there were nothing to be admir'd in <hi>God and Chriſt,</hi> in Heaven and Glory, how ſhould they be the <hi>Beatific Objects</hi> to us?</p>
            <p>I ſhall add but <hi>two</hi> Words more. The <hi>firſt</hi> is that the <hi>greateſt Admiration</hi> ſeems to be with the <hi>leaſt Surprize.</hi> Nothing is more calm and <hi>tranquil,</hi> I conceive, than the Admirations of Angels and perfected Spirits, in their Viſion and Adoration of God. Our <hi>Surpriſes</hi> at things new and rare and unexpected is from the Weakneſs of Fleſh and Blood, and from the Darkneſs of our Minds. The more feeble the more Surprize, but the ſtronger the Intellect is the more ſerene and placid, even and fix'd is the Admiration. — I know not which was <hi>Eve</hi>'s Fault and the Beginning of her Sin, whether too <hi>much</hi> Surpriſe at the <hi>Serpent</hi>'s ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her, or too <hi>little</hi> Emotion at it. One or other might be the Beginning of her Fall. It was a wonderful Thing that a Snake or Worm ſhould find a Tongue and Voice to ſpeak to her. His curſed Motion to her, to eat of the forbidden Fruit, ſhould have rais'd in her a holy <hi>Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> Her Innocence and Holineſs ſhould have ſo expreſs'd it ſelf, when ſhe heard God contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted, and mean and ill Things ſuggeſted of Him. But the <hi>Marvel</hi> at the Thing, and her Admiration
<pb n="x" facs="unknown:004001_0013_100373E8A55E1210"/>at the <hi>Serpent,</hi> ſeems to have taken up her Mind and drawn her away into a Parley and Talk with him. She was too curious to hear him out (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after our manner) in all he had to ſay, and ſo was beguiled thro' his Subtlety. As the <hi>Snake</hi> to this day charms Birds and Squirrels with its Eye, ſo <hi>Eve</hi> ſeems to have been taken with the <hi>Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> in the Serpent's Management. She ſhould have dropt the Wonder from a Deteſtation of his Words, and have anſwered only as her <hi>Bleſſed Seed</hi> did when he was tempted, "<hi>Get thee hence, Devil!</hi> Were it an <hi>Angel from Heaven</hi> that ſhould ſpeak thus, <hi>let him be accurſed.</hi> Her Wonder ſhould have wro't thus, "<hi>Lord God!</hi> what curſed kind of <hi>Beaſt</hi> is this, that ſpeaks indeed, but to ſlander Thee, and give Thee the Lie! — But <hi>Eve</hi> ſeems to have been <hi>too calm</hi> and unmov'd upon ſo ſtrange an Event, and ſo vile a Motion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>other</hi> thing I would therefore add is, That <hi>an innocent and holy Mind</hi> may be piouſly ſtruck with Admiration at Things <hi>moſt evil and diſagrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to it.</hi> The <hi>Angels that keep their firſt State</hi> were doubtleſs ſtruck with ſacred Aſtoniſhment at the Rebellion of their Fellows; and after they had ſung for Joy at the Creation of <hi>Man,</hi> they were fill'd with a holy kind of Wonder Grief and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at his ſudden Fall. <hi>God</hi> Himſelf ſpake to <hi>Adam</hi> of it after this Manner, "<hi>Who told you, you were naked! have you eaten of the Tree whereof I commanded you that you ſhould not eat of it? Woman, what is this that thou haſt done?</hi> And to affect the ſtupid Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> and Daughters of <hi>Eve,</hi> for their Iniquities after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, God has ſpoken in his Word of our Sins as ſuch, that the very <hi>Heavens</hi> (the heavenly <hi>Spirits</hi> who dwell in them) might even be <hi>ſurpris'd</hi> and
<pb n="xi" facs="unknown:004001_0014_100373F30F2A62A0"/>
               <hi>amazed</hi> at them<note n="*" place="bottom">Iſai. i. 2. Jerem. ii. 12.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Hear O Heavens, I have nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and bro't up Children, and they have rebelled againſt me! Be aſtoniſhed O ye Heavens at this, and be horribly afraid! be ye very deſolate ſaith the Lord.</hi>
               </q> If any thing has ever |caus'd any thing like Surprize and Aſtoniſhment in the ſerene and holy Minds of Angels, it has been and is the <hi>Sin</hi> and Wickedneſs of Men and Devils. But even in this Caſe, the <hi>Difference</hi> is unknown, and it may be inconceivable, between the <hi>Wonder</hi> of a holy Mind above, and that of a Saint on Earth. — It may be repreſented to us from <hi>St. John</hi>'s Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at ſeeing the <hi>great Whore,</hi> and the <hi>Angels Anſwer</hi> to him: Revel. xvii. 1,—7. —<hi>And</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>when I ſaw her I wonder'd with great Admiration! and the Angel ſaid unto me, Wherefore didſt thou marvel? I will tell thee the Myſtery of the Woman and of the Beaſt, her ſeven Heads and ten Horns.</hi>
               </q> See how <hi>ſurpriz'd the holy Man was</hi> at this <hi>horrid Form,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>the Mother of Harlots and Abominations of the Earth, a Woman drunken with the Blood of Saints and of the Martyrs of Jeſus, ſitting upon a ſcarlet colour'd Beaſt, full of Names of Blaſphemy!</hi>
               </q> but ſee again <hi>how calm the bleſſed Angel</hi> was! he even reproves mildly the great Admiration of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> as being too much. Yet the Bloodineſs and Filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> is abominated in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven much more</hi> than it is in the <hi>true Church</hi> on Earth: But it is ſeen there with <hi>leſs</hi> ſurprize. Indeed the <hi>Harlot</hi> is a Wonder and an Abomination both there and here.</p>
            <p>I ask my <hi>Readers</hi> Pardon that I have ſo long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained him with a kind of <hi>new Diſſertation</hi> on the <hi>Admiration</hi> which may agree unto a State of <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi>
               <pb n="xii" facs="unknown:004001_0015_100373FF19583478"/>and Perfection: But the plain <hi>Scope</hi> of it is to direct and fix our <hi>admiring Thoughts</hi> on the Bleſſed GOD and his Works, and on <hi>His Image in our Selves</hi> in a more eſpecial Manner; as they would have been <hi>if we had kept our firſt State,</hi> and as they <hi>will be in Heaven</hi> for Evermore if we regain <hi>it</hi> and get thither; which is the <hi>only Aim</hi> of the preſent <hi>Meditations.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="unknown:004001_0016_1003740A60B736B0"/>
            <head>DISSERTATION. Of the <hi>Image of</hi> GOD wherein <hi>Man was created.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GENESIS. I. 27.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>So <hi>GOD</hi> created Man in his own Image, in the Image of <hi>GOD</hi> created He him, Male and Female created He them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hree</hi> things are here ſaid concerning <hi>Man,</hi> that he is a <hi>Creature,</hi> that he was made <hi>Male</hi> and <hi>Female,</hi> and that the <hi>firſt</hi> Man and Woman were created in the <hi>Image of</hi> GOD. The <hi>laſt</hi> thing is <hi>doubled</hi> in the <hi>Text,</hi> partly to expreſs the double <hi>Pleaſure</hi> of God in his Work, and alſo to put a double <hi>Honour</hi> on it: But more eſpecially to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs on the Hearts of the <hi>Sons</hi> and <hi>Daughters</hi> of Men a high Senſe of the <hi>Dignity</hi> done 'em, and of the great <hi>Love</hi> of GOD to them in their Creation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="unknown:004001_0017_1003741277772090"/>
It is a Matter of great <hi>Importance</hi> to the Children of <hi>Men,</hi> and to be for ever kept by them in a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Remembrance, that God made our <hi>Firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> both <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> in <hi>His own Image, in the Image of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He made them alike <hi>Humane Souls,</hi> which know no Difference of <hi>Sex</hi> when out of the Body, but are <hi>as the Angels;</hi> of <hi>Whom</hi> nothing higher or more <hi>glorious</hi> can be ſaid in their Original bleſſed State, than that God made <hi>Them,</hi> as He did <hi>us,</hi> in his <hi>own Image.</hi> Man was made a <hi>little lower</hi> than the Angels, but like them <hi>crowned</hi> with this <hi>Glory and Honour</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Pſalm viii. 5.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Man</hi> is <hi>Male</hi> and <hi>Female. Neither is the Man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Woman, nor the Woman without the Man in the Lord</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">1 Cor. xi. 7, 11, 12.</note>: That is to ſay, neither in the Day of his <hi>Creation,</hi> nor in thoſe of his <hi>Propagation</hi> thro' all paſt and future Generations: As it follows, <hi>For as the Woman is of the Man, even ſo is the Man alſo by the Woman; but all things of God.</hi> When therefore it is added, that <hi>the Man is the Image and Glory of God, but the Woman is the Glory of the Man,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> explains himſelf only to give the <hi>Man</hi> his Preheminence in point of <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Dominion:</hi> This <hi>one Thing</hi> in the Image of God excepted, the Woman <hi>equally</hi> ſhines in the Glory of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>So are <hi>Mankind</hi> conſtituted &amp; propagated. <hi>Adam</hi> was firſt created, and then <hi>Eve;</hi> he out of the <hi>Duſt</hi> of the Ground, and ſhe taken out of his <hi>Body.</hi> So ſhe became <hi>Bone of his Bone, and Fleſh of his Fleſh.</hi> But their <hi>equal</hi> and greater Glory was, that God made them alike <hi>living Souls,</hi> immortal <hi>Spirits,</hi> in a Perfection of <hi>Knowledge, Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and conſequently of <hi>Happineſs</hi> and Bleſſedneſs, ſuted to their <hi>Earthly</hi> State, with <hi>Dominion</hi> over the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>Moſes</hi> gives us <hi>this</hi> Account of <hi>the Image of
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:004001_0018_1003741F38B3D6B0"/>God</hi> wherein Man was created, if you compare, <hi>Gen.</hi> i. 26, 28. with <hi>Chap.</hi> ii. v. 7.15, 16, 17, 20, 23. And keeping my Eye upon <hi>this pure Word of God,</hi> it appears plain and evident that <hi>the Image of God on Man,</hi> in the Day when God created Him, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted</hi> in the following Things.</p>
            <p n="1">I. GOD made Man a <hi>Spirit,</hi> a <hi>living Soul,</hi> and this was his <hi>Likeneſs</hi> to his MAKER, the <hi>Image</hi> of God upon him.</p>
            <p>If you ask, what God is? <hi>Chriſt</hi> has revealed Him, John iv. 24. <hi>God is a Spirit.</hi> And if you ask, what <hi>Man</hi> is, <hi>Moſes</hi> tells us, He is a <hi>living Soul.</hi> In his <hi>Soul</hi> he bears the <hi>Image of God,</hi> and not in his <hi>Body.</hi> His <hi>Body</hi> is of the <hi>Duſt</hi> and returns to it, when his <hi>Spirit</hi> returns to <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Infinite Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Father of Spirits,</hi> the Lord, Ruler and Judge of <hi>Spirits,</hi> the only Portion and Felicity of <hi>Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God claims the <hi>Soul</hi> for his own, even <hi>all Souls,</hi> the Soul of the <hi>Father</hi> and of the <hi>Son</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Ezek. xviii. 4.</note>. This un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen Part of Man bears the Image of the <hi>Inviſible</hi> and Incorruptible God. Were the <hi>Body</hi> a thouſand times more elegant and <hi>wonderful a Form</hi> than it is, or even as it will be after the Reſurrection, yet it were utterly impoſſible and <hi>unlawful</hi> to conceive of it as any Likeneſs of God. As when God would be ſeen in the <hi>Mount</hi> by the Elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they ſaw <hi>no manner of Similitude</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Deut. iv. 12.</note>. The Face and Eye and Hands of Men are full of <hi>Spirit</hi> and Life, from the <hi>living Spirit</hi> within that animates and acts 'em. Theſe are attributed to <hi>God</hi> in Scripture in way of Accommodation to <hi>Souls</hi> here in the Body. But the <hi>firſt</hi> thing in the Image of God on Angels and Men is <hi>Spirituality.</hi> What ſhould be the Likeneſs of the <hi>Living God,</hi> but a <hi>living Soul</hi> or <hi>Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="unknown:004001_0019_100374255DBB09C8"/>
Indeed we little know what our <hi>Souls</hi> are: Yet we are ſure that we are <hi>ſuch,</hi> becauſe we think, reaſon, remember, reflect, foreſee, hope, fear, &amp;c. What the <hi>Spirituality</hi> of God is, is far more incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable to us. He is <hi>Infinite,</hi> filling Heaven and Earth. <hi>Whither can we go from His Preſence and Spirit</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">Pſalm cxxxix. Prov. xvi. 2.</note>? The <hi>Rays</hi> of Light, <hi>the Wings of the Morning</hi> are not equal to the <hi>Thoughts</hi> of Men, for Brightneſs and Swiftneſs. In one <hi>Moment</hi> of Tho't my poor Mind reaches the <hi>third Heaven,</hi> a million times beyond the <hi>Sun</hi> in its <hi>Zenith.</hi> This Soul is a poor, low feeble Image of the Immenſity, Spiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Omniſcience of God. HE <hi>ſearches</hi> the Heart of Man, <hi>weighs</hi> his Spirit, and knows his Tho't <hi>affar off.</hi> This is <hi>too wonderful for us, it is high and we cannot attain to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let our Souls pauſe and imagine what an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible Spirit GOD is! <hi>What is his Name, and his Sons Name, if thou canſt tell</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Prov. xxx. 4</note>. HE <hi>is that He is, has Life in Himſelf,</hi> and <hi>in Him we live and move and have our Being</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Exod. iii. 14. John v. 26. Acts. xvii. 25.28.</note>. The Worlds of <hi>Spirits,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Corporeal Univerſe,</hi> are his Workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <q>continually ſuſtained and governed by Him. His active Eſſence therefore intimately pervades and penetrates the immeaſurable Frame! GOD is Life, Light, Mind, Self-exiſtence; Glory, Bleſſedneſs, Perfection; incomparable, inconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable. <hi>To Whom can we liken Him, or what Likeneſs can we compare unto Him?</hi> Singularity and Onlineſs is his Glory. <hi>There is One God, and no other than He.</hi>
               </q>
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Religion of <hi>Ieſus</hi> delineated.</note>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhould not have dar'd to ſay of God that He is <hi>a Spirit,</hi> or to have call'd Spirits his <hi>Image and Likeneſs,</hi> if He Himſelf had not ſo ſpoken to us of
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:004001_0020_10037430263C3158"/>Himſelf. Yet is there no other Image whereby our <hi>Minds</hi> can repreſent Him to themſelves, but from their own ſpiritual Nature, Powers, and Operations. This therefore muſt be the <hi>firſt</hi> thing in the Image of God of Angels and Men, <hi>Spirituality.</hi> In this Glaſs we ſee the firſt <hi>Shadow</hi> of God. Our Souls diſcern it by <hi>Reflection</hi> on themſelves. We then look <hi>without,</hi> look abroad, and ſee thro' the Eyes of the Body Images of Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs, in every thing Material and Viſible. We ſee the Work of ſome perfectly wiſe, good, Almighty <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence.</hi> — It is in and from <hi>it ſelf,</hi> that the poor finite <hi>Spirit of Man,</hi> conſcious to its own Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Affections, and enlightned from the Spirit and Word of God, conceives and infers what a tranſcendent Being and <hi>Spirit</hi> God is; the Framer of the Univerſe, and the Former and Father of all Spirits. It is becauſe we in our <hi>Souls</hi> bear ſome <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi> of God, that we can at all apprehend &amp; know that God is a <hi>Spirit.</hi> The <hi>Beaſts</hi> have Eyes to ſee the Fields of Graſs and Corn as much as we, but not having <hi>our Souls</hi> to diſcern the <hi>Eternal Power and Godhead</hi> from the Things that are made, their Spirits are not the Likeneſs of God as ours are.</p>
            <p>And yet the <hi>ſpiritual Nature</hi> of Angels and Men is not to be compared with the Spirituality of God, or the <hi>Simplicity</hi> of his Eſſence. The groſſeſt <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> that our Eyes behold is not ſo much below the <hi>Soul</hi> of Man, as <hi>that</hi> is below the Spirituality of the <hi>Divine Nature.</hi> Never the leſs in the Faculties of the <hi>Humane Soul</hi> we plainly ſee ſome Reſemblance of the <hi>Infinite Eternal Spirit,</hi> the Maker and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of all Things, viſible &amp; inviſible. And this is the <hi>firſt</hi> and moſt obvious part of the Image of God upon us in our <hi>Creation,</hi> that we are Souls or Spirits. God who made us <hi>this Soul</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Jerem. xxxviii. 16.</note>, herein has
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:004001_0021_1003743AEB1D8190"/>made us <hi>in his own Image, after his Likeneſs;</hi> for He is THE SPIRIT, and <hi>the Father of Spirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God is a <hi>Spirit</hi> in a Senſe far ſuperior to that wherein <hi>Angels</hi> are to be ſo called. <hi>He maketh his Angels Spirits</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Pſalm. civ. 4.</note>. I doubt not but God is more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible to them, and in Compariſon of them, than they are to us and in Compariſon of us. <hi>Created</hi> Spirits are <hi>compounded</hi> Beings if compared with their MAKER; they are <hi>made</hi> what they are, and He who made them can if he pleaſe annihilate and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them again. But there is an ineffable, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable <hi>Simplicity of Eſſence</hi> in the Divine Nature, which infinitely diſtinguiſhes His Spirituality from that of all Creatures.— Angels and Souls are <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> but they ſingly occupy a ſpace, and paſs from place to place, with an incredible Swiftneſs, like <hi>Rays of Light;</hi> but the Inviſible God is an <hi>Immenſe Being</hi> filling Heaven and Earth, always preſent and the ſame in all Places. This is as <hi>far</hi> above Souls or Angels, as they are above Bodies.</p>
            <p>It is a moſt juſt and glorious Account that God gave of Himſelf to <hi>Moſes,</hi> I AM THAT I AM. He is what no One elſe is or can be; He is <hi>alone</hi> what He is; what <hi>all</hi> his Creatures can but poorly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent, and leſs can underſtand; even as the <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> of a Man does but poorly repreſent him in his Life, Look, Thought and Speech. — God is <hi>ſingly</hi> the Spiritual BEING, and there is none <hi>like</hi> Him, none <hi>beſide</hi> Him. As there is <hi>none Good but One which is God,</hi> ſo is there but <hi>One only Spirit</hi> in the Univerſe, <hi>who filleth all in all</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Eph. i. 23.</note>.</p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Lord</hi> our God is ONE LORD, and the Knowledge of HIM is <hi>too wonderful for us; it is high, and we cannot attain to it:</hi> yea how little do we know of <hi>our own Spirits,</hi> which are made for
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:004001_0022_100374456D004F38"/>the Knowledge of Him? It is but <hi>as thro' a Glaſs darkly</hi> that we ſee any thing of GOD. The Ideas of <hi>Infinite, Eternal, Unchangeable</hi> and <hi>Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtent</hi> are the Proof and Illuſtration of his <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuality.</hi> We can only explain and confirm the One from the other. As <hi>what Man knoweth the Things of a Man, ſave the Spirit of Man that is in him? even ſo the Things of God knoweth no Man, but the Spirit of God</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">1 Cor. ii. 11.</note>: <hi>Which Things we</hi> therefore <hi>ſpeak, not in the Words which Mans Wiſdom teacheth, but which the Holy Ghoſt teacheth, comparing ſpiritual Things with ſpiritual.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is therefore unto me no Account of the <hi>Spirituality of God</hi> like unto the following <hi>Texts</hi> of Scripture. Exod. iii. <hi>I</hi> AM, <hi>that is my Name.</hi> xxxiii. 20. <hi>Thou canſt not ſee my Face.</hi> 1 Tim. vi. 16. <hi>Whom no Man hath ſeen, nor can ſee.</hi> Heb. iv. 13. <hi>All things</hi> (even all Souls and Spirits) <hi>are naked and open before Him.</hi> Pſalm. cxxxix. <hi>Thou underſtandeſt my Tho'ts afar off.</hi> 1 Cor. xii. 11. <hi>That One and Self ſame</hi> SPIRIT <hi>divideth to every one ſeverally as He will.</hi> So does the <hi>One Immenſe Being</hi> in all Worlds, viſible and inviſible, to every Creature, ſuperior and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, as the one Creator, Preſerver, Governour, Judge, Sanctifier and Saviour of <hi>all.</hi> — This is <hi>Light without any Darkneſs at all, Light unapprocha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and full of Glory.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">1 John. i. 5.</note> There can be no more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and convictive <hi>Light</hi> given us into the <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuality</hi> of God than St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s noble Diſcourſe to the Men of <hi>Athens,</hi> Acts. xvii. While the Eye reads it, the Soul <hi>ſees and feels</hi> what a SPIRIT God is: it <hi>ſeeks</hi> and feels and <hi>finds</hi> Him within it ſelf: "GOD <hi>that made the World and all things in it, Lord of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth! who dwelleth not in Temples made with Hands, nor is worſhiped by us as tho' he needeth
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:004001_0023_100374544EBEE318"/>any thing;</hi> for <hi>He giveth unto all Life and Breath and all things, and hath made of one Blood all Nations of Men, and hath determined the Times and Bounds of every ones Habitation; for He is not far from every one of us, for in Him we live and move and have our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for we are his Offspring.</hi> See here an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, enlightned, ſanctified <hi>Spirit!</hi> that it is ſome <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,</hi> ſome <hi>Shade</hi> of the Eternal, Immenſe, moſt Holy <hi>Spirit,</hi> which is GOD.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>God</hi> made <hi>Man</hi> in his own <hi>Image</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Intellect and Underſtanding, Knowledge and Wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God is the <hi>Only-wiſe</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Rom. xvi. 27. Job xxxvi. 4., Pſalm. cxlvii. 5.</note> 
               <hi>perfect in Knowledge,</hi> and <hi>his Underſtanding is infinite.</hi> So his <hi>Word</hi> ſpeaks of Him, and his <hi>Works</hi> declare it of Him. <hi>He that formeth the Eye, ſhall He not ſee? and He that teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Man Knowledge ſhall He not know?</hi> There is not a Soul ſo <hi>brutiſh</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Pſalm. xciv. 10.</note> as not to allow this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Man,</hi> in his Soul and Body is the moſt eminent Diſplay of <hi>the Knowledge and Wiſdom of God</hi> here on Earth. The Mind and Eye of Man ſurvey the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, Earth, Seas and all the Creatures, and ſee how <hi>in Wiſdom God hath made them all</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Pſalm. civ. 24.</note>. Then we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>our Selves</hi> alone, among all the Creatures here on Earth, capable of <hi>this Underſtanding,</hi> and are led to ſay unto our Selves and unto God, <hi>Where is God my Maker! that teacheth me more than the Beaſts of the Earth, and maketh me wiſer than the Fowl of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Man</hi> in his <hi>firſt State</hi> was happy and glorious in a <hi>Perfection</hi> of Knowledge and Wiſdom, proper for an imbodied Spirit. He had not the Knowledge of <hi>Angels,</hi> for he was made <hi>lower</hi> than they; but he was <hi>wiſe as an Angel</hi> in Fleſh ſhould be. He was created with a due Knowledge of <hi>God</hi> his Maker, of
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:004001_0024_1003745E179BF5E8"/>
               <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and of the <hi>Creatures</hi> about him. God ſpake to our firſt Parents, and they to each other in an admirable manner, as is related by <hi>Moſes.</hi> Their Minds were full of <hi>Light,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> of God was in their Heart, and they were in the <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> of their own Souls and of <hi>Intellectual Happineſs.</hi> They want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no more Knowledge of <hi>Good</hi> at the Time, and to be ſure needed no Knowledge of <hi>Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Underſtanding</hi> of Man was a Beam from the Light of the Knowledge and Glory of God upon him. God made him like Himſelf an <hi>Intellect,</hi> an <hi>Intelligence;</hi> the <hi>Inſpiration of the Almighty</hi> gave him his Underſtanding. <hi>In</hi> his <hi>Light</hi> Man <hi>ſaw Light.</hi> And now Souls are <hi>renewed in Knowledge after the Image of God</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Col. iii. 10.</note>. They are renewed into the Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in part, wherein they were firſt created. As they grow in holy <hi>Knowledge,</hi> they are <hi>changed</hi> more and more into the <hi>Divine Image from Glory to Glory</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">2 Cor. iii. 18.</note>.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Devil</hi> tempted our Parents to aſpire after <hi>more Knowledge,</hi> and ſo they fell. The <hi>Father of Light</hi> had given them as much of this <hi>perfect Gift</hi> as was good and fitting for them. This ſhould have highly contented them, and filled 'em with Delight and Thankfulneſs. And ſo it did, until the falſe <hi>Fiend</hi> perſwaded them to think, that GOD forbid 'em <hi>the Tree of Knowledge</hi> left it ſhould make 'em wiſer and better than they were. Alas! they found nothing by it but the Knowledge of <hi>Sin and Miſery,</hi> of which it was their Happineſs to be ignorant; and they <hi>loſt</hi> the Knowledge of all the <hi>Good</hi> which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore enjoyed. We remain miſerable, and periſh in our Ignorance of God, unleſs we are renewed after Him in Knowledge. True ſpiritual <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored in the Regeneration of Souls. God gives the <hi>Light of the Knowledge of his Glory in the Face of</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="unknown:004001_0025_1003746AADB85498"/>JESUS CHRIST<note n="‖" place="bottom">2 Cor. iv. 6. Rom. xv. 14. Mat. vi. 23. Eph. i. 17. Col. i. 9.</note>. They who were <hi>ſometimes Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are made Light in the Lord.</hi> They are <hi>full of Goodneſs, filled with all Knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>Soul</hi> be without Knowlege, is not <hi>good.</hi> It is very <hi>evil</hi> to it to be ſo. What is a dark and <hi>blind</hi> Soul good for! <hi>the Light that is in it is Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> The Light of Life is from <hi>the Father of Glory,</hi> the Father of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Eyes of our Underſtanding being-enlightned, to know the Hope of his Calling. God gives the Spirit of Wiſdom and Revelation in the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his Son.</hi> This is the <hi>Image of the Father</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored in his Elect. So they become again the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> of God; <hi>filled with the Knowledge of his Will, in all Wiſdom and ſpiritual Underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a <hi>bright</hi> Account is this, given by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> of the <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>God</hi> on the Soul of Man, in reſpect of <hi>Knowledge!</hi> Not only has Man an <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi> which reflects on its own Acquirements, and (as an excellent <hi>Divine</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Mr. <hi>Willard</hi> on the <hi>Catechiſm.</hi>
               </note> of our own ſays) "<hi>reads</hi> its own Knowledge, and <hi>communicates</hi> it to others; but the true and high Glory of this created <hi>Intellect</hi> is, "that it is capable of <hi>knowing God</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Eternal Life; <hi>for this is Life Eternal to know Him the only true God and Jeſus Chriſt whom be has ſent.</hi> And if Souls <hi>regenerated by the Spirit of God</hi> receive from him a <hi>ſanctified Mind,</hi> a <hi>ſpiritual Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning</hi> of Things relating to their own Duty and Happineſs; how much more muſt we ſuppoſe our <hi>firſt Parents</hi> in their ſtate of <hi>Integrity</hi> and Perfection to be bleſs'd with a moſt <hi>holy Knowledge</hi> and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Diſcerning?</p>
            <p>But there is <hi>another</hi> of the <hi>Divine Attributes,</hi> which in the <hi>Scripture</hi> Account of it and in the enlightned <hi>Mind</hi> of Man, <hi>excels</hi> in Glory, and is yet more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:004001_0026_1003737C412C9920"/>the <hi>Divine Likeneſs</hi> on the Reaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and that is <hi>Holineſs, Goodneſs &amp; Righteouſneſs.</hi> I go on therefore to ſay,</p>
            <p n="3">III. Man was eminently created by God in his own <hi>Image,</hi> after his <hi>Likeneſs,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Sanctity</hi> and <hi>Holineſs, Integrity</hi> and <hi>Rectitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a <hi>moral</hi> as well as <hi>intellectual</hi> Perfection. The Bleſſedneſs of God and his Glory lies in <hi>both.</hi> HE is infinitely and unchangeably poſſeſs'd of both. Nor is there any poſſible <hi>Perfection</hi> of Souls or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, but it muſt be both in <hi>Mind</hi> and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and alſo in <hi>Will</hi> and Affections. <hi>This</hi> is to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Dictate of <hi>that,</hi> and then the Light of God rules in the Heart; which is what we are call'd to by the Voice of Reaſon and Scripture<note n="‡" place="bottom">Col. iii. 15.</note>. Then all is regular, wiſe, juſt, perfect.</p>
            <p>There is <hi>none Holy as the Lord.</hi> He is <hi>glorious in Holineſs. Holy, Holy, Holy, is his Name</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Exod. xv. 13. Iſaiah vi. 3. Act iii. 14. Dan iv. 13.</note>. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Holy One</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and all the Angels of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven are <hi>holy Ones.</hi> They proclaim the <hi>equal</hi> Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Father Son and Spirit,</hi> while they <hi>treble</hi> the Praiſes of the Divine Holineſs. What then ſhould be the <hi>Image</hi> of God on the <hi>Seraphims</hi> but their <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs?</hi> while with cover'd Faces they make the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative <hi>Holineſs of God</hi> the Subject of their Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. They never ceaſe from this<note n="*" place="bottom">Rev. iv. 8.</note>, <hi>They reſt not Day and Night ſaying, Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God Almighty! which art and waſt and art to come.</hi> The Work of <hi>Saints</hi> on Earth is juſt the ſame<note n="‖" place="bottom">Pſalm xcix. 9. xcvii. 12.</note>, <hi>Exalt the Lord our God and worſhip at his Footſtool, for the Lord our God is holy.</hi> And again, <hi>Give Thanks at the Remembrance of his Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This renders God <hi>fearful in Praiſes,</hi> that He is glorious in <hi>Holineſs.</hi> "A perfect <hi>Underſtanding</hi> muſt
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:004001_0027_1003747A93D81018"/>have a perfect <hi>Will,</hi> and where the Mind and Will is <hi>perfect</hi> there muſt be perfect <hi>Holineſs.</hi> Therefore is the Name of God moſt holy and reverend. He muſt needs be <hi>Holy in all his Works.</hi> He muſt needs then make Angels and Men <hi>holy.</hi> They could not come <hi>other</hi> out of his holy Hand. The Impreſs and <hi>Stamp</hi> of his Holineſs muſt be upon them. Being <hi>capable</hi> of this Image of God, and it being <hi>neceſſary</hi> to their Perfection, they could not poſſibly be deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of it. If every <hi>Word</hi> of God is <hi>pure,</hi> ſo is every <hi>Work.</hi> He cannot <hi>look</hi> upon Iniquity, he is of <hi>purer</hi> eyes than to behold it, he <hi>hates</hi> and loaths it, and <hi>loves Righteouſneſs.</hi> This bears <hi>his own Likeneſs,</hi> and is therefore <hi>lovely</hi> in his Eyes, for he infinitely <hi>loves Himſelf.</hi> We read, <hi>The Lord loveth the righteous:</hi> why? but becauſe He is <hi>Himſelf</hi> righteous, and thoſe that love and do Righteouſneſs are <hi>like</hi> to Him. This <hi>one Thing</hi> is eaſily found<note n="‡" place="bottom">Eccleſ. vii. 29.</note>, nor is all the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon</hi> needed to find it out, that God <hi>made Man upright.</hi> He could not make him otherwiſe. This <hi>Uprightneſs</hi> in the Creature is the <hi>Image of God</hi> upon it. Men are <hi>Partakers of a Divine Nature,</hi> in the Regeneration of Souls<note n="*" place="bottom">2 Pet. i. 4. Pſalm. xxv. 21.</note>. They are made upright and <hi>ſincere</hi> in the Sight of God. <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and Uprightneſs preſerves them,</hi> and they <hi>eſcape the Corruption that is in the World thro' Luſt,</hi> and <hi>add</hi> to their <hi>Faith, Vertue, Knowledge, Temperance, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Godlineſs, brotherly Kindneſs and Charity.</hi> The Sons of <hi>Men</hi> (you ſee here) are capable of ſuch a <hi>Glory</hi> and Likeneſs to God as to become again Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the <hi>Divine Nature.</hi> This cannot poſſibly mean any thing more or leſs than ſome Reſtoration of the <hi>Image</hi> of God in them. The <hi>Loſs</hi> of that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage is ſuppoſed, and it is ſaid to be <q>the Want of Original Righteouſneſs &amp; the Corruption of his
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:004001_0028_100374813B850B98"/>whole Nature.</q> He has <hi>corrupted</hi> himſelf thro' Luſt, and the <hi>World</hi> lies in this Corruption, it is propagated from Age to Age, and common to all Places. But then there is thro' Grace an <hi>Eſcaping</hi> out of this Corruption, which ſome are made <hi>Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> of, thro' Sanctification of the <hi>Spirit.</hi> That is to ſay, they are made holy, vertuous, wiſe, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, patient, godly by the Power of Divine Grace, making a <hi>glorious Change</hi> in them; whereby they do again partake of that <hi>Divine Nature</hi> which was the <hi>Likeneſs of God</hi> upon Man in his firſt Creation.</p>
            <p>This is the true and genuine Meaning of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Words, repeated in the next <hi>Chapter</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">ver. 20.</note> 
               <hi>They have eſcaped the Pollutions of the World, thro' the Knowledge of the Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Theſe the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> calls<note n="‡" place="bottom">Rom. vi. 6.7.2 Cor. v. 17. Gal. vi. 15. Eph. iv. 22.</note> 
               <hi>new Men</hi> and <hi>new Creatures;</hi> being <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in the Spirit of their Mind;</hi> the <hi>old Man</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>put off,</hi> which is <hi>corrupt</hi> according to deceitful Works, and the <hi>New Man</hi> put on, which <hi>after God is created in Righteouſneſs &amp; true Holineſs.</hi> See here the <hi>Image of God</hi> wherein <hi>Adam</hi> was created, and into which the <hi>Elect</hi> of God are recovered by the Power and Efficacy of the Goſpel, which calls us with a <hi>holy Calling,</hi> from Uncleanneſs unto <hi>Holineſs.</hi> This is <hi>the Image of God's dear Son,</hi> and this is <hi>his</hi> Calling,<note n="*" place="bottom">1 Pet. i. 15.16. Rom. viii. 29.</note> 
               <hi>Be ye Holy, for I am Holy.</hi> So we are made <hi>Children</hi> and adopted in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for the HOLY ONE will put no other among his Children, but thoſe in whom he puts this <hi>Likeneſs to Himſelf, his Son and Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Holineſs</hi> is the eminent Glory of the DEITY. It is not Knowledge or Power that gives Likeneſs to God, ſeparate from Holineſs, Juſtice, Goodneſs and Truth. It is in theſe <hi>moral</hi> Perfections that the
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:004001_0029_1003748947EC9080"/>
               <hi>Lord</hi> paſſes before us, proclaims his <hi>Name</hi> and ſhews his <hi>Glory,</hi> from the Beginning of the <hi>Bible</hi> to the End of it. <hi>Devils</hi> retain a vaſt Knowledge, void of Wiſdom becauſe deſtitute of Holineſs. <hi>Angels</hi> ſhine in the Purity and Wiſdom of <hi>God,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>holy</hi> in all the Uſe they make of their Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And <hi>ſuch</hi> is the Renovation of <hi>Man</hi> after God in Knowledge and Holineſs together, <hi>transform'd by the renewing of his Mind</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Col. i. 9,—15.</note>.</p>
            <p>Pauſe here a Moment and reflect, — It is in our <hi>Souls</hi> and <hi>Spirite</hi> that we muſt look for any <hi>Likeneſs</hi> or <hi>Image</hi> of God, moſt High moſt Wiſe and Holy! and it is <hi>eſſential</hi> to every created <hi>Spirit</hi> in its firſt Exiſtence to be <hi>like</hi> God the Father of Spirits, as his <hi>Offspring,</hi> in Underſtanding and Will, in a <hi>Rectitude</hi> of both; Which is to ſay, in <hi>Integrity and Upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> in moral and intellectual Perfection <hi>together;</hi> for they are inſeparable, are <hi>loſt</hi> together and are <hi>recovered</hi> together: They come from Heaven, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for Heaven, and are unchangeably and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in Heaven — Let <hi>God</hi> be dear and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us, and our <hi>Souls</hi> be dear and prized by us, from the Conſideration of what God at firſt made them; ſo <hi>wiſe</hi> and knowing, <hi>holy</hi> and righteous. God made them <hi>for</hi> Himſelf and <hi>like</hi> Himſelf; <hi>in</hi> his Image and <hi>for</hi> his Glory; and for <hi>their Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in his Likeneſs and Love for Evermore. <hi>This</hi> we ought to have <hi>preſerved</hi> and been ever happy; now let us ſeek to <hi>recover</hi> it in the Way of Goſpel Perfection, (by Regeneration, Repentance, holy O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and by Faith in a better Righteouſneſs than our own) ſetting the Life and Laws of Chriſt ever before us; and we ſhall become <hi>wiſe, holy and bleſſed,</hi> in a Meaſure of Conformity to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is <hi>the Image of the Inviſible God, the Firſt-born of every
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:004001_0030_1003748E74DB9DC0"/>Creature;</hi> which is the whole <hi>End,</hi> Aim and Fruit of the <hi>Miniſtry of the Goſpel,</hi> of <hi>Sabbaths and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> the <hi>Word, Sacraments</hi> and <hi>Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, the moſt full and perfect Reſemblance of <hi>created Spirits</hi> unto the <hi>One</hi> infinitely wiſe and good SPIRIT, theri Former and Father, can be <hi>no other,</hi> either more or leſs than <hi>this,</hi> — the Mind and Will of the <hi>Creature</hi> agreeing perfectly after his Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Manner, to the Wiſdom and Rectitude of the CREATOR: So that the Soul at firſt received a <hi>Stamp</hi> and Impreſs of God, even as the Wax does of a <hi>Seal,</hi> as well in its <hi>Will</hi> and Affections as in its <hi>Intellectual</hi> Powers; even a gracious <hi>Habit,</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe cleave to and proſecute the higheſt and <hi>beſt End,</hi> in the moſt proper and direct <hi>Means:</hi> So that as <hi>God</hi> ever acts for his <hi>own Glory</hi> in his <hi>Creatures Happineſs,</hi> ſo the <hi>Soul</hi> of Man in its Conformity to Him acts for the <hi>Glory of God</hi> and <hi>its own Bleſſedneſs</hi> in his Favour. This muſt be <hi>the firſt and great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> of the Lord God to the Soul that he has made, and its <hi>laſt</hi> Happineſs and <hi>Perfection,</hi> its <hi>Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to God and <hi>Union</hi> with him; "<hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all the Underſtanding and with all thy Heart.</hi> The Soul cannot <hi>cloſe</hi> more with God, nor <hi>receive</hi> more of Him. — As will further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by our going on to conſider,</p>
            <p n="4">IV. God created Man in his own <hi>Image,</hi> after his <hi>Likeneſs,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Dominion.</hi> Theſe are the expreſs Words of <hi>Moſes, "God ſaid, Let Us make Man in Our Image, after Our Likeneſs, and let them have</hi> DOMINION.</p>
            <p>God is LORD <hi>of all!</hi> this is his <hi>Glory</hi> and unalie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <hi>Right,</hi> to reign and rule. He cannot deny Himſelf, and wo to his Creation ſhould his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Providence ceaſe. His is the Power and Kingdom; He is GOD <hi>over all;</hi> the <hi>Moſt High, Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor of Heaven and Earth.</hi> Heaven is his <hi>Throne,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="unknown:004001_0031_100358D8681598C0"/>and the Earth his <hi>Footſtool.</hi> Angels, Authorities and Powers are all under his Feet. He is the One Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver and Judge, the <hi>Lord of Hoſts and King of Glory.</hi> Wiſdom and Might are His: his Dominion is an Everlaſting Dominion, and his Kingdom from Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to Generation.</p>
            <p>Intellectual and moral Creatures carry an Image of God's <hi>Dominion</hi> in their Nature. They are made for Rule and Government in their Places. <hi>Angels</hi> are therefore called <hi>Dominions</hi> and <hi>Thrones, Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities</hi> and <hi>Powers.</hi> And <hi>Man</hi> was in like manner made for <hi>Government</hi> here on Earth. The <hi>Fear</hi> of him was put upon the Creatures, and they herein are put <hi>under his Feet.</hi> God firſt ſaid to him, <hi>Have thou Dominion,</hi> and then bro't them to <hi>Adam</hi> to give them <hi>Names.</hi> So he gave him Poſſeſſion of them all. This is celebrated in the <hi>Eighth Pſalm;</hi> the Glory is given to God and all Pride is hidden from Man: "<hi>What is Man that Thou art mindful of him! Thou haſt made him a little lower than the Angeis, and haſt crowned him with Glory and Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Man</hi> is made for <hi>Dominion</hi> in his Place as <hi>Angels</hi> are in their. Rational and moral <hi>Powers</hi> are given to be ſure to be uſed and <hi>applied,</hi> to great and good <hi>Ends</hi> and Purpoſes, reſpecting <hi>God, Self,</hi> and <hi>Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Creatures,</hi> in one World or other. The Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of theſe Powers muſt be in <hi>Subjection</hi> to God, the <hi>Government</hi> of our Selves, and a righteous <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct</hi> toward others, below or above us, or on a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel with us.</p>
            <p>But principally Man's <hi>Glory</hi> is, that he is made for <hi>Self-Government,</hi> for Rule over himſelf, for <hi>a Poſſeſſion of his own Soul,</hi> the Government of his own <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Will, Deſires</hi> and <hi>Appetites, Thot's, Words</hi> and <hi>Actions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> was the Dominion he was principally deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, and inveſted with. The <hi>Law</hi> of his God put <hi>within</hi> him, and given to him in <hi>Words</hi> as ſoon
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:004001_0032_1003749473285040"/>as he found himſelf in Being, ſufficiently told him this. It ſpake indeed plainly his <hi>Subjection to-God,</hi> that he was made for <hi>Obedience</hi> and a reaſonable Service; But it ſpake alſo his <hi>Preheminence</hi> above the Creatures put under him, in a diſtinguiſhing Power for the <hi>Rule</hi> of his own Actions, with Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and Choice, Liberty and Freedom, and from a Conſcience of right and wrong.</p>
            <p>Underſtanding and Wiſdom, the Power of Tho't and Conſideration was given to Man <hi>for this End. "The Lord God put the Man into the Garden to dreſs and keep it, and He commanded the Man, ſaying</hi> &amp;c. Thus Man was made <hi>under the Law to God,</hi> a Law to himſelf, and was both able and inclined to do the Will of God, and to govern himſelf thereby. And this Power for <hi>Self-Government,</hi> by the Light and Law of God within him, and by the Will of God revealed to him, was the <hi>Image</hi> of his God upon him.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Divine Dominion</hi> and Government is in the Perfection of Wiſdom and Righteouſneſs. <hi>The Sceptre of his Kingdom is a right Sceptre.</hi> He does according to <hi>his Will</hi> in the Armies of Heaven, and among the Inhabitants of the Earth; but his Will is <hi>perfect,</hi> his <hi>Ways are Truth and Judgment,</hi> He is <hi>holy in all his Work, juſt and right is He.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the <hi>Subjection</hi> of Man to <hi>God</hi> is his <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning Himſelf,</hi> in all his Thot's Words &amp; Actions, in a wiſe, righteous and ſuperiour manner; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Creature in the <hi>Likeneſs of God,</hi> and made for Authority and Rule on Earth.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Lord</hi> therefore tells us that he came into our World to recover Man into his Original Freedom and Liberty. "<hi>If the Son make you free, ye ſhall be free indeed</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">John viii. 36. Rom. viii. 21. Luke xvii. 21.</note>. Man by his Fall <hi>loſt</hi> that Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:004001_0033_1003749AA708F738"/>over, and Poſſeſſion of himſelf, wherein God had made him. The Son of God came to <hi>reſtore him into the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God.</hi> The <hi>Image</hi> of the Heavenly Father is reſtored in thoſe Souls, whom his Grace recovers from the Bondage of Sin and Satan, into his own Kingdom, which <hi>Kingdom of God is within us.</hi> It makes Men <hi>Kings and Prieſts to God.</hi> They uſe Themſelves, and all his Creatures, to the Creator's <hi>Glory.</hi> This was that <hi>Original Dominion</hi> in which and for which Man was made. His Original <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> was given Him for <hi>this</hi> End. So God <hi>qualified</hi> him for the <hi>Rule</hi> to which he called him. He gives no <hi>Right</hi> but for <hi>his own Glory</hi> from his Creatures, and for <hi>their Happineſs</hi> in a regular ordering and conducting themſelves.— And this leads me to another Point, wherein the <hi>Image of God</hi> conſiſted in Man's Original Stace of Knowledge Holineſs &amp; Dominion, and that is</p>
            <p n="5">V. His Original State of <hi>Happineſs and Bleſſedneſs.</hi> —God is the <hi>bleſſed Being;</hi> infinitely, eternally and unchangeably <hi>happy;</hi> being poſſeſs'd of all poſſible Perfection and Glory for ever and ever: "<hi>God over all, bleſſed for Evermore</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Pſalm. cxix. 12. Rom. ix. 5.</note>. He made <hi>Man</hi> happy, and for Happineſs everlaſting: He forbad him that which he knew would make him miſerable: For he knew that <hi>Miſery</hi> muſt lie in the <hi>Loſs</hi> of the Divine Likeneſs.</p>
            <p>A <hi>miſerable</hi> Creature could not come out of the Hand of the <hi>bleſſed</hi> God: He could not make a liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Soul ſo <hi>unlike</hi> Himſelf, ſo <hi>contrary</hi> to Himſelf. —The Creature muſt make it ſelf miſerable, if ever if become ſo. Angels and Men have made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo, againſt the Commandment of God, by their own Sin and Tranſgreſſion. They have wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:004001_0034_100358DCF56C21D8"/>choſen Evil under the Notion of Good, and thereby brought Miſery upon themſelves. But God required 'em to chuſe only what is good, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the Evil. God made 'em in the Knowledge of Good, and ignorant of Evil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Man</hi> was made innocent, wiſe and holy, and therefore neceſſarily <hi>happy.</hi> He was made bleſſed for ever, in caſe he did not commit <hi>Sin,</hi> from which Miſery naturally flows, and with which it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily connected.—<hi>Man</hi> was made happy both as to Soul and Body: He wanted nothing for either. He had Wiſdom and Purity within, Peace &amp; Joy, Content and Pleaſure. Without him he had a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, a Garden of God. Every thing grew there, pleaſant to the Eye, to the Smell and to the Taſte. His Eye beheld a Creation of God's in Perfection. He had a charming Tongue and Voice to praiſe Him. The muſical <hi>Birds,</hi> happy in the <hi>Branches,</hi> ſinging and feaſting there, were but an Emblem of their Owners Liberty and Freedom to what was good and joyous. Man was a thouſand fold more a Pleaſure to himſelf in all his Tho'ts and Words! in his Contemplations of God in his Works, in his Knowledge of his Will, in his Senſe of the Divine Favours and Bounties to him, in a Heart full of Gratitude to God, and with a Tongue tuned to his Praiſe, to magnify Him with Thankſgivings.</p>
            <p>Every intellectual and moral Pleaſure attended Man in his Paradiſaic State, as well as every ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Delight. "He feaſted (ſays One) on the Loving-kindneſs of God, better than Life, and on all the Sweets of an untarniſhed Creation.— God <hi>bleſſed</hi> him in the Day he made him, for he ſaw him in a bleſſed State, and required him to keep himſelf in that State and be happy. God bound himſelf to bleſs him, if he kept himſelf in his Love. As a Means of preſerving himſelf herein, God gave him his <hi>Sabbath</hi> and his <hi>Covenant:</hi> He bleſſed every
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:004001_0035_100374A418E73A98"/>
               <hi>Seventh Day</hi> to him, for a Time of ſpecial Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications of his Grace and Love; and none of us can imagine what a <hi>bleſſed Day</hi> every <hi>Seventh</hi> would have been to Man in his State of Innocence &amp; Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; what Viſits and Viſions from Heaven Man had enjoy'd thereon. It may be a <hi>Flavel,</hi> or an <hi>Henry</hi> the Elder, may ſometimes have taſted a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of like Rapture.</p>
            <p>Real and ſenſible <hi>Communion with God</hi> is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Bleſſedneſs of Souls. A meaſure of it remains to fallen recovered Man in his ſecret and publick Devotions. <hi>Becauſe thy Loving kindneſs is better than Life my Lips ſhall praiſe thee: Thus will I bleſs thee while I live, I will lift up my Hands in thy Name: My Soul ſhall be ſatisfied as with Marrow and Fatneſs, and my Mouth ſhall praiſe thee with joyful Lips: My Soul followeth bard after thee, thy right Hand uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Pſal. lxiii. 3, 4, 5. Heb iv. 3.</note>. Believers in Chriſt <hi>do enter into this Reſt,</hi> but it comes vaſtly ſhort of a Sabbath <hi>in Eden,</hi> or the <hi>Heavenly Sabbatiſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No doubt but the Image of God was <hi>viſible</hi> upon Man in his Earthly Paradiſe, and <hi>ſenſible</hi> to himſelf in his inward Frame. His <hi>Mind</hi> was full of Light, his Heart of Joy; which beam'd out in his Eyes and <hi>Face,</hi> and flow'd over from his <hi>Mouth</hi> and Tongue. The Abundance within <hi>irradiated</hi> the whole Body. If <hi>Moſes</hi> Face ſhone in the Mount with God, how did <hi>Adam</hi>'s in the Garden of God! The <hi>Ioy of the Lord</hi> was a Covering of Glory on Him: It fell off in the Hour he ſinned, and he ſaw himſelf <hi>naked.</hi> Our <hi>Parents</hi> look'd aſtonied at one another to ſee the outward Change upon themſelves, as well as from what they felt within. They ran to the <hi>Fig-Leaves</hi> to hide their Shame.</p>
            <p>Thus Man <hi>loſt</hi> the Image of God in the ſenſible Loſs of his Happineſs. <hi>Miſery is the Image of Satan.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="unknown:004001_0036_100358DFD0B8CAD0"/>Such is Guilt to a Soul: Pollution attends it: Grief and Shame are the inevitable Conſequent. The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils of the World, with <hi>Death</hi> in the Rear of the woful Train, ſhows us the Loſs of the <hi>Divine Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> wherein we were created. For we were made for <hi>immortal Life</hi> and Happineſs, and lo Miſery and <hi>Death</hi> have invaded us! Which leads me to add,</p>
            <p n="6">VI. And laſtly, God created Man <hi>in His own Image</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Immortality.</hi> God made <hi>Adam</hi> a <hi>living Soul</hi> that can <hi>never die,</hi> a natural I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of HIM <hi>who only hath Immortality.</hi> And God covenanted with <hi>Adam</hi> that tho' his Body was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible in it ſelf, yet He would preſerve it in Health, Eaſe and Strength, and it ſhould never ſee Death in caſe he never ſinned. God gave him therefore the <hi>Tree of Life</hi> to eat of, a Sign Pledge and Means of Immortality to his Body, and of the Continuance of Happineſs to him in Soul and Body all his Days on Earth; and I doubt not it was alſo a Seal and Aſſurance to him of a Tranſlation to a better World, a better Paradiſe in due Time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Man</hi> could not but <hi>begin</hi> to be becauſe he was a Creature; no more could the <hi>Angels</hi> of Heaven. <hi>God</hi> only is <hi>Eternal,</hi> from Everlaſting to Everlaſting, without Beginning or End. <hi>Spirits</hi> that can never ceaſe to be, yet once were not. By God were the Inviſible Thrones and Dominions above created, and ſo likewiſe the Spirits in Fleſh. Both were made for an <hi>everlaſting</hi> Exiſtence and Duration. The Word of God's Power <hi>upholds</hi> them in Being, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a holy and happy State, or in their ſinful and miſerable Condition. This <hi>Immortality</hi> ſimply conſidered is a ſignal Likeneſs of the <hi>Everlaſting Father</hi> upon his <hi>Offspring. Angels</hi> are in this Image of God upon them for ever and ever: Their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Glory, Bleſſedneſs, Joys are ſure of an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Duration. And <hi>Souls</hi> that are here <hi>ſanctified in
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:004001_0037_100374AE701A8788"/>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> are ſure of going to Him at Death, and of Bleſſedneſs in his <hi>Likeneſs</hi> for Evermore.<note n="*" place="bottom">Pſalm xvi. 9, 10, 11. lxxiii. 23, —26. John xiv. 1,—4. 1 Cor. xv. 16,—23, 45,—ult. 1 Joh iii. 2.1 Pet. i. 3. Rom ii. 7.</note> This <hi>Life and Immortality is bro't to Light by the Goſpel,</hi> and we are <hi>begotten to the lively Hope of it by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead.</hi> The <hi>Promiſe which</hi> GOD <hi>hath promiſed</hi> is this <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> in Soul and Body united, unto all them that by <hi>patient Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in well doing,</hi> ſeek after it.</p>
            <p>And this ſhows us the <hi>Original State</hi> of Man; to what <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi> he was deſigned and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared in his Creation, in Conformity to the Life and Bleſſedneſs of his MAKER, even for an everlaſting ſeeing ſerving and Enjoyment of Him. This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was an eminent Part of the <hi>Divine Image and Likeneſs on our Firſt Parents,</hi> in the Day when they received their Being. They knew themſelves made for Immortality, and that their preſent happy Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances could never ceaſe, but might increaſe for ever and ever, and be changed for better and better, higher and highe: to Everlaſting. <hi>Death</hi> therefore was ſet before them to deter them from Sin; <hi>Death</hi> bodily and ſpiritual; not a Period to their <hi>Exiſtence</hi> but to their <hi>Happineſs;</hi> which alone is to be called <hi>Life;</hi> for to exiſt in <hi>Miſery,</hi> in any great Degree of it, is <hi>Death</hi> rather than Life, and a reaſonable Creature would chuſe <hi>Strangling</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">Job. vii. 15. Pſalm. xlix. 19. Rev. xx. 6, 14. Mark. ix. 44. Jude. v. 6. Luke iii. 17. Iſai: xxxiii. 14.</note>, rather than ſuch an Exiſtence. — We read therefore of the Soul in a State of Miſery, that it <hi>ſhall never ſee Life;</hi> and the <hi>ſecond Death</hi> has power over it. The <hi>Curſe</hi> comes on that Soul in the very <hi>Letter</hi> of it, "<hi>In dying thou ſhalt die.</hi> The miſerable Spirits in <hi>Hell</hi> are for ever dying, and yet never die; never
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:004001_0038_100374B1C082C490"/>ſee an <hi>End</hi> of their Miſery; <hi>their Worm dieth not, and the Fire is not quenched.</hi> Here is the <hi>Loſs</hi> of the Image of God to the uttermoſt. For God lives in the Perfection of <hi>Bliſs,</hi> in ineffable inconceivable Bleſſedneſs, for ever and ever: And ſo do Angels and glorified Spirits in His Likeneſs and Favour: They have an <hi>Eternity</hi> of Happineſs before them: But ſinning Angels, and impenitent damned Souls, are in everlaſting <hi>Chains of Darkneſs, reſerved to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable Fire and everlaſting Burnings.</hi> The Image of <hi>Immortality</hi> upon them is an everlaſting <hi>Curſe!</hi> the <hi>Reverſe</hi> of that Living Happy Soul which God at firſt made us.</p>
            <p>Indeed there is no Image of God's <hi>Self-Exiſtence,</hi> his neceſſary Exiſtence, his Independent Eſſence, his proper <hi>Eternity</hi> and Unchangeableneſs, in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Nature of Angels or Men, or in the happy Immortality of holy Spirits. God is <hi>the High and lofty</hi> ONE <hi>that inhabiteth Eternity;</hi> having <hi>Life in Himſelf.</hi> Only the Eternal <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> who are <hi>One</hi> with the <hi>Father,</hi> are alſo the <hi>Brightneſs</hi> and <hi>expreſs Image</hi> of his <hi>Eternal Glory.</hi> Yet every <hi>immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> Spirit is an Image of the <hi>Vital Being</hi> from Whom it came; in Whom alone is the <hi>Origine</hi> of Life, and <hi>the Life</hi> is the <hi>Light</hi> of Men and Angels: i. e. the <hi>Living God</hi> is the Spring and <hi>Fountain</hi> of it; as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſings, "<hi>For with Thee is the Fountain of Life</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Pſalm xxxvi. 9. John. i. 4. Iſai. lvii. 15.</note>. When Man recovers his firſt and proper <hi>Immortality,</hi> as the Righteous ſhall do at the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> then the <hi>Image of God</hi> will be <hi>perfectly</hi> reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in him, never to be loſt again.</p>
            <p>And thus we have ſaid ſomething (O how little a part) of the <hi>bleſſed Image of God</hi> wherein Man was created: A little <hi>lower than the Angels,</hi> but like
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:004001_0039_100374B9B3293E88"/>them <hi>living Spirits,</hi> in a ſufficient Degree of <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> and Wiſdom, <hi>Purity</hi> and Goodneſs, Greatneſs and <hi>Dominion,</hi> Happineſs and <hi>Bleſſedneſs,</hi> and in <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality</hi> which was the <hi>Crown</hi> of all: For this Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Holineſs and Bleſſedneſs would have remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him <hi>for ever and ever.</hi> Like <hi>GOD</hi> he had been <hi>the ſame,</hi> and his <hi>Years without End;</hi> only there had been a perpetual <hi>Increaſe</hi> in Perfection &amp; Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs, if he had preſerved his Innocence.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>O Sons and Daughters of Men,</hi> contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate this your <hi>Original State,</hi> and mourn the Loſs of it! bewail and condemn your Selves, and give <hi>Glory</hi> unto God who made you <hi>ſuch,</hi> and for an ever-during Felicity.</p>
            <p>DEATH, <hi>Death</hi> is the dreadful Sign and Teſtimony to us of the <hi>Loſs</hi> of God's Image and <hi>Likeneſs!</hi> Bodily Death is ſo, Spiritual Death more! A dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Body,</hi> under miſerable <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> and preſently forſaken by the living Spirit, is a viſible, ſenſible, ſorrowful Spectacle of the Loſs of God's Image: But a <hi>dead Soul,</hi> under the Miſery of ſpiritual <hi>Luſts,</hi> and the Sentence of God to <hi>Eternal</hi> Death, is a thouſand-fold more hideous Spectacle of the Loſs of God's Likeneſs. Let <hi>Senſe</hi> look upon a dead <hi>Corpſe,</hi> and let it ſay if the Image of the Living God is not departed, in this Puniſhment of Sin! but let <hi>Faith</hi> look into the <hi>State</hi> of the Dead, and ſee <hi>Souls</hi> in the Place of Miſery for ever and ever; and then behold the utmoſt Loſs of <hi>Life,</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and of Bleſſedneſs! Here, here is the <hi>Image of God loſt to the uttermoſt!</hi> look on <hi>this</hi> and cry out, on <hi>Adam's Sin</hi> (as ſome have done) <hi>O Adam!</hi> "what haſt thou done! — But rather lay thy Hand on thy own Heart, <hi>O Sinner,</hi> and ſmite on thy own Breaſt, and cry out of thy own Sins, and feel thy own <hi>Plague,</hi> who <hi>wilt not come to Chriſt that thou may'ſt have Life!</hi> wilt not ſubmit
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:004001_0040_100358EEC0CB1830"/>to the Terms of the Goſpel, for the recovery of <hi>this,</hi> and <hi>more</hi> than this, thy Original Knowledge, Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Dominion and Bleſſedneſs in an <hi>Everlaſting Paradiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God is ready to <hi>reſtore our Souls;</hi> the <hi>Means of Grace</hi> and Holineſs teſtify of it to us from Day to Day: What mean our <hi>Sabbaths, Sermons, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> the <hi>Word and Prayer,</hi> but a holy and happy everlaſting State for Soul and Body, if we will but accept of <hi>ſo great Salvation!</hi> Read the Account of a <hi>better Paradiſe</hi> for every One who will but ſeek it, by a timely Submiſſion to the <hi>Son of God,</hi> the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Adam,</hi> the <hi>Lord from Heaven,</hi> who came <hi>to ſeek and ſave that which was loſt,</hi> and to <hi>reſtore that which be took not away:</hi> Your <hi>Bible</hi> cloſes with the Account of this <hi>Caeleſtial Paradiſe,</hi> and of the <hi>Image of God on Man</hi> in the Heavenly Places! and how could the <hi>Revelations</hi> of God to Man end more holily and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly! Revel. xxii. 1,—6. <hi>And he ſhewed me a pure river of water of life, clear as cryſtal, proceeding out of the throne of God, and of the Lamb. In the midſt of the ſtreet of it, and of either ſide of the river, was there the tree of life, which bare twelve manner of fruits, and yielded her fruit every month: and the leaves of the tree were for the healing of the nations. And there ſhall be no more curſe: but the throne of God and of the Lamb ſhall be in it; and his ſervants ſhall ſerve him. And they ſhall ſee his face; and his name ſhall be in their foreheads. And there ſhall be no night there, and they need no candle, neither light of the ſun; for the Lord God giveth them light: and they ſhall reign for ever and ever. And he ſaid unto me, Theſe ſayings are faithful and true. And the Lord God of the holy prophets ſent his angel to ſhew unto his ſervants the things which muſt ſhortly be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="unknown:004001_0041_100374C647062820"/>
But I am not willing to finiſh on a <hi>Subject</hi> ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and profitable as this is, without going into ſome more particular <hi>Reflections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. O what a <hi>brave, good, great</hi> and <hi>happy Creature,</hi> was <hi>Man</hi> in his <hi>firſt</hi> Eſtate!</p>
            <p>See, you Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> and Daughters of <hi>Eve,</hi> what your <hi>firſt Parents</hi> were, and <hi>you</hi> in their Loyns! how <hi>crowned with Glory and Honour,</hi> as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſings! or as the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> ſpeaks, "<hi>Adam, the Son of God! He</hi> that in his <hi>Goſpel</hi> had wrote this, might well in his <hi>Acts</hi> quote that Paſſage of the <hi>Poet. "For we are his Offspring!</hi> — If then we are the <hi>Offspring of God,</hi> and were at firſt created worthy of ſuch a <hi>Style,</hi> being made in <hi>his Image and Likeneſs;</hi> then what <hi>an Angel in Fleſh</hi> was Man in his firſt State! wiſe, holy, happy and immortal! an imbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died Spirit made for the Knowledge and Viſion of God, and in a Dominion over the Earth and all the Creatures on it. <hi>Man</hi> was a Brother of Angels; only in a Body of Fleſh, and a Candidate for their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Glory. He was a grand and <hi>auguſt</hi> Creature in the Eyes of his Maker, good in his Sight, high in the Eſteem of good Angels and the Envy of evil ones.— We talk of <hi>noble and royal Blood</hi> now in our fallen, corrupt and dying Condition; under our Diſeaſes and Pains, Leproſies and Ulcers; but we were indeed in our firſt Eſtate <hi>Children of the moſt High,</hi> Sons of Glory, for immortal Dominion. Here was the <hi>true Honour,</hi> which came <hi>from above,</hi> and had returned to God and Heaven, and left us in high Dignity &amp; <hi>Royalty</hi> everlaſting, with the Image of <hi>the King of Glory</hi> on us, a never fading <hi>Crown.</hi> Our <hi>Bible</hi> does us the greateſt <hi>Honour</hi> in this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our <hi>Original State;</hi> but the Glory is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unto God in the Perfection and Excellency of his own Works. So <hi>God</hi> created us, and unto <hi>Him</hi> be Glory. "<hi>Thine O Lord, is the Greatneſs and the Majeſty!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="27" facs="unknown:004001_0042_100358F4727B6A88"/>
II. <hi>O what a great and good and holy and bleſſed Being is the</hi> LORD OUR GOD, who made Man in his own <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Likeneſs!</hi> Of his <hi>own Heart,</hi> and overflowing <hi>Fulneſs,</hi> He did this! "<hi>O Lord, our Lord; how excellent is thy Name in all the Earth!</hi> So the <hi>Pſalm</hi> begins and ends, which is the Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of <hi>Man</hi> in his State of <hi>Dominion.</hi> The Glory of God herein is alſo <hi>above the Heavens,</hi> above the Praiſes of <hi>Angels</hi> there. We poorly <hi>liſp,</hi> like <hi>Babes</hi> and <hi>Sucklings</hi> at his high Praiſes, for our Souls are not what they once were! yet had we the <hi>Tongues of Angels</hi> we could not render Him the Glory due unto his Name, which is <hi>exalted above all Bleſſing and Praiſe.</hi> It ſhould be a Pleaſure to us, that there are <hi>higher Orders</hi> of Creatures to praiſe and ſerve God better. We ſhould <hi>awake up our Glory,</hi> and do our beſt, and live on the Hope of doing better and better for evermore. "<hi>Be thou exalted, O God, above the Heavens! let thy Glory be above all the Earth</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Pſalm. cviii. 4, 5, 6. cxlviii. 1, 2, 11, 12, 13.</note>.</p>
            <p>[Under this Head I will inſert the learned and pious <hi>Peter van Manſtricht</hi> his <hi>Reaſons</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Theoretico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practica Theologia,</hi> p. 378.</note> of God's making Man in his own Image.
<list>
                  <item>1. To <hi>contemplate</hi> and delight <hi>Himſelf</hi> in Man, as in a Glaſs or <hi>Effigy:</hi> As we read Prov. viii. 31. that in the Day <hi>when He appointed the Foundations of the Earth his Ioy was in the habitable Parts of it, and his Delights in the Sons of Men.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. As it were to <hi>propagate</hi> Himſelf, were any thing like that poſſible, in Creatures bearing his <hi>Likeneſs.</hi> As it is in the Nature of all <hi>Good</hi> to communicate of it ſelf, and propagate its own <hi>Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> It is ſo in every <hi>inferior Life</hi> here known to us, in Conformity doubtleſs to the <hi>Firſt and moſt perfect.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. That he might have on <hi>this Earth,</hi> as in
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:004001_0043_100374D301FB0CB0"/>every other habitable <hi>Globe</hi> he doubtleſs hath, <hi>Thoſe</hi> that ſhould know and love and worſhip Him for what he is <hi>in Himſelf</hi> and is to <hi>them:</hi> which they would never do without an <hi>Impreſs</hi> of Himſelf on them, ſenſible to themſelves.</item>
                  <item>4. That He might have on this Earth of ours Thoſe with whom he may <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe,</hi> as a <hi>Father</hi> Friend and Benefactor, and make <hi>bleſſed</hi> by Communion with Himſelf, thro' <hi>Time</hi> here and to <hi>Eternity:</hi> which <hi>Friendſhip</hi> and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot be without Likeneſs, any more than <hi>Man</hi> can converſe with the <hi>brute Creatures</hi> which are ſo unlike to him. <hi>Simile enim| ſimili gaudet.</hi> Man therefore that is made to live <hi>to</hi> God, and for ever with him, and to find his <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> therein, muſt needs be in the <hi>likeneſs</hi> of God, wiſe, holy, juſt and good.</item>
                  <item>5. That Man may have <hi>within Himſelf</hi> a Perception and Conviction of his <hi>Creator</hi>'s moſt high and infinite <hi>Perfections;</hi> his Simplicity, Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, Immortality, Underſtanding, Will, Wiſdom, Juſtice, Holineſs, Goodneſs and Dominion; and have theſe always in <hi>Remembrance,</hi> and before his own Eyes, in the <hi>Image</hi> of them on himſelf.</item>
                  <item>6. That we may know and be convinc'd that none of our <hi>Evils</hi> come from <hi>God,</hi> but are altogether of <hi>our Selves,</hi> and that in Contradiction to the <hi>Will</hi> of God, and therefore in <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt Him, which the Glory of his Holineſs and Dominion muſt ſee <hi>puniſhed.</hi> Prov. xvi. 4. <hi>The Lord hath made all things for Himſelf, yea even the wicked for the Day of Wrath.</hi>]</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. See the <hi>true Baſis, and a ſtrong Foundation for the whole moral Law,</hi> in both the <hi>Tables</hi> of it; the <hi>Love of GOD,</hi> and of our <hi>Neighbours;</hi> and I may add the true Love of <hi>our Selves</hi> alſo. For if God made Man <hi>in His own Image &amp; Likeneſs,</hi> how ought Man to <hi>love God, Himſelf,</hi> and his <hi>Neighbours?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="29" facs="unknown:004001_0044_100374DC05859AD0"/>
1. He ought <hi>to love the</hi> LORD <hi>his</hi> GOD <hi>with all his Heart, and with all his Soul, and with all his Mind, and with all his Might</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Deut. vi. 4, 5. x. 12, 15, 20. Matth. xxii. 37. Pſalm. cxxxix. 14, 17. lxxiii. 25.</note>. This muſt neceſſarily be the <hi>firſt and great, Commandment</hi> and indiſpenſable, <hi>Duty</hi> of all Creatures, in all Worlds, made in the <hi>Image</hi> of God. For they are made to <hi>love</hi> what is good and lovely; and the <hi>Original</hi> of Good, the Perfection of Beauty, to be ſure <hi>firſt;</hi> the moſt perfect and <hi>ſupreme</hi> Good with the <hi>higheſt</hi> Affection. Deſire and Delight. Beſides, that the Relation of an <hi>Offspring</hi> is a Bond to Love, in the higheſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, by the Acknowledgment of all Mankind. A Child is bound to love his <hi>Parents</hi> with his firſt and beſt Affection, becauſe thro' Them he receives his Being, and is begotten in their Likeneſs. If <hi>God</hi> then be a <hi>Father</hi> (and <hi>have we not One Father? has not one God created us?</hi>) this muſt be the <hi>Honour</hi> due from us; and <hi>our</hi> great Honour it is to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <hi>love</hi> the Greateſt and Beſt of <hi>Beings,</hi> for <hi>this</hi> Reaſon, becauſe He has made us <hi>in his own Likeneſs?</hi> No wonder this is his <hi>Law</hi> to us, and this his Grace and <hi>Favour</hi> to us, to require our <hi>Love? "My Son, give me thy Heart! Is He not thy Father, that hath made thee?</hi> that has <hi>faſhioned thee in the Womb,</hi> with the ſame <hi>wonderful and precious Thot's</hi> unto thee, as to thy <hi>Firſt Parent</hi> when he ſpake firſt of forming him, "<hi>Come let us make Man, in our I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, after our Likeneſs.</hi> O what is there that is lovely in us but <hi>that,</hi> and <hi>who</hi> ſhould be the Object of our Souls Love but this <hi>Bleſſed Being? "Whom have I in Heaven but Thee? and there is nothing on Earth that I deſire beſide Thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Did ever any <hi>Prince</hi> make a Law that his <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> ſhould love Him<note n="‡" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Henry</hi> on Deut. vi.</note>? yet ſuch is the Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:004001_0045_100374E1B72C38C8"/>of the Divine Grace that this is God's firſt Law to Man.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Let me turn the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> and ask — Was there ever any <hi>King</hi> that did not expect and require the Love of his <hi>own Children?</hi> So high and near a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject as a <hi>Child</hi> muſt needs love, as well as fear; and it is the Glory of Kings to be lov'd as well as fear'd.</p>
            <p>But if we are made in God's <hi>Image,</hi> let our <hi>Love</hi> be regulated hereby. <q>Our Deſire muſt be toward Him, out Delight in him, our Dependance on him, and to him we muſt be intirely devoted. It muſt be a comſtant Pleaſure to us to think of Him, hear from him, ſpeak to him and ſerve him. We muſt love him with an intelligent, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and ſuperlative Affection.</q> 
               <hi>We have had Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our Fleſh and we gave them Reverence; ſhall we not</hi> love <hi>the Father of our Spirits and live?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Our being made in the <hi>Image of God</hi> teaches us to <hi>love our Selves,</hi> to love <hi>our own Souls,</hi> with a high <hi>Eſteem</hi> and Value, with a rational <hi>tender and fervent</hi> Affection. God made us to love our Selves for <hi>his ſake,</hi> for his Image on us and Glory from us. God is Himſelf <hi>Love</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">1 John. iv. 8.</note>: What more <hi>amiable Idea</hi> can we have of Him? what a <hi>delectable Object</hi> is He by this Account of Him? How <hi>lovely</hi> is He to Himſelf and to all Intelligent Beings! He is in the firſt place <hi>Love</hi> with Regard to <hi>Himſelf,</hi> in a moſt perfect bleſſed everlaſting <hi>Self-love.</hi> He neceſſarily, infinitely and unchangeably loves <hi>Himſelf;</hi> whether we conſider Him in the <hi>Ineffable</hi> mutual Love of <hi>Three Divine Perſons, One in God-head and Glory;</hi> or in his infinite <hi>Complacence</hi> in his own <hi>bleſſed and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Perfections.</hi> He has revealed Himſelf thus to us, "<hi>I the Lord thy God am a jealous God!</hi> which ſpeaks <hi>Self-Regard</hi> in the higheſt Degree. He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:004001_0046_100374E63528DF18"/>
               <hi>deny himſelf,</hi> nor give away his <hi>Glory.</hi> He has made all Worlds, and all, Rational Beings <hi>for his own Glory.</hi> He has made us like Himſelf, with an invincible Principle of <hi>Self-love,</hi> but firſt for his <hi>own Praiſe</hi> from us, without which we can never be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and happy.</p>
            <p>It is evident that <hi>the Principle of true Self-love</hi> in us is Part of the <hi>Image on God</hi> on us; for by <hi>this</hi> we govern our Selves, our Appetites, our Will and Affections, by the Will of God, for his Glory and our own Good, preſent and future. As ſoon as <hi>Adam</hi> was created he was forbidden <hi>to Sin againſt his own Life;</hi> "In the Day thou eateſt thou ſhalt ſurely <hi>die.</hi>" In our fallen State God addreſſes to this ſame Principle, in its Remains within us, "<hi>Why will ye die?</hi> In Regeneration Souls are recover'd to <hi>the true Love of Themſelves.</hi> As <hi>God</hi> is glorious Self-love, ſo is <hi>Man</hi> in his | primitive and ſaved State. The greateſt <hi>Self-good</hi> we can propoſe to our Selves, is to be <hi>like God,</hi> and to have him well pleaſed with us. That is to ſay, <hi>to be good and do good,</hi> as God is and does.</p>
            <p>We ſhould love nothing in our Selves but what is <hi>agreable</hi> to God, and an <hi>Exhibition</hi> more or leſs of his <hi>Image</hi> on us. We ſhould <hi>hate</hi> and loathe in our Selves whatſoever is <hi>contrary</hi> to God, his Nature and Will made known to us. We muſt <hi>deny</hi> our preſent <hi>carnal Self,</hi> which is <hi>Enmity to God, is not ſubject to his Law, nor indeed can be</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Rom. viii. 2, 6, 7, 13. John iii. 7. Gal v. 24. Col. iii. 5.</note>, without a holy and bleſſed <hi>Change</hi> wro't in us by the Spirit of God. Hence we are required to <hi>mortify our Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> and to <hi>crucify the Fleſh with its Affections and Luſts.</hi> Theſe are not our <hi>Self,</hi> but the Corruption and Enemies of our Soul.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="unknown:004001_0047_100374EFF8DDE838"/>
O that we did but <hi>know our Selves,</hi> and love our own Souls! we ſhould then ſeek the <hi>Image of God</hi> within our Selves, and ſet a juſt Value on it. The Want of this is the real <hi>Hatred</hi> of our Selves and of God: Proverbs. viii. 36. <hi>He that ſinneth againſt Me wrongeth his own Soul, all they that hate Me love Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt <hi>love our Neighbour as our Selves,</hi> for <hi>he</hi> is made like <hi>us</hi> in the <hi>Image</hi> of God. Therefore <hi>honour all Men,</hi> and therefore <hi>love the Brotherhood.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">1 Peter. ii. 17.1 Tim. i. 5. Luke x. 29. Deut. x. 18. Gen. ix. 6. iv. 10 John. xiii 34 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 8, 9. iv. 7, 8. v 1.</note> Have we not all <hi>one Father,</hi> has not <hi>One God</hi> created us? And have not <hi>Saints</hi> One <hi>Redeemer</hi> &amp; <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> whoſe Image is renewed on them all! <hi>The End of the Commandment is Charity</hi> (the Love of God and of our Neighbour) <hi>out of a pure Heart, a good Conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience and Faith unfeigned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Say not, <hi>Who is my Neighbour?</hi> Let <hi>Humanity</hi> be found in us, for the ſake of that <hi>Image of God</hi> wherein Man was created. We muſt <hi>love the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, for the Lord loveth Him. Contempt</hi> of Men is Contempt of God, and <hi>Cruelty</hi> to Men is odious to God. So is all Injuſtice and Unrighteouſneſs. The <hi>laſt</hi> Injury to Man is in his <hi>Life,</hi> and this is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from the Beginning, and revenged by God, for <hi>this</hi> Reaſon, "<hi>For in the Image of God made He Man!</hi> therefore <hi>whoſo ſheddeth Mans Blood, by Man ſhall his Blood be ſhed.</hi> No | wonder that the Blood of <hi>Abel</hi> cried ſo from the Ground againſt wicked <hi>Cain,</hi> and that God has ſet ſuch a <hi>Mark</hi> and Brand upon his Name for ever. <hi>Benevolence</hi> and <hi>Beneficence</hi> ever was and is the Law of Nature, of <hi>Moſes and of Chriſt.</hi> Love is the <hi>fulfilling</hi> of the Law. <hi>As we have Opportunity let us do good to all Men, eſpecially to the Houſhold of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="unknown:004001_0048_100374F79ADAE0C0"/>
               <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are under a more ſpecial Law of <hi>Love</hi> than others, from the Knowledge of God and <hi>his Love in Jeſus Chriſt, that great Love wherewith he has loved us;</hi> and from the Example and Law of Chriſt, "<hi>A new Commandment give I unto you, that you love one another, as I have loved you that ye love one another.</hi> And how is this <hi>new</hi> Commandment inforced and urged on us in the <hi>New Teſtament?</hi> but from the <hi>Image of God</hi> reſtored by Grace <hi>in the Godly.</hi> Therefore we muſt <hi>love the Brethren,</hi> and to <hi>Godlineſs</hi> add <hi>Brotherly Kindneſs.</hi> We ſhould be able to ſee <hi>God</hi> in one another, and we muſt love the <hi>Godly in Chriſt Jeſus</hi> for the ſake of <hi>his Spirit</hi> in them, and their <hi>Likeneſs to Him.</hi> As <hi>Aaron</hi> and the <hi>Elders of Iſrael</hi> looked on the <hi>ſhining Face of Moſes,</hi> when he came down from the <hi>Mount,</hi> with Wonder and great Reverence. The <hi>Apoſtle of Love,</hi> who had lain in the Boſome of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> vehemently urges the Law of <hi>Chriſtian Love</hi> from the <hi>Image</hi> of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in the Saints. <q>
                  <hi>Every one that loveth Him that begat, loveth him alſo that is begotten of Him: Beloved, let us love one another, for Love is of God, and every one that loveth is born of God, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God; he that loveth not, knoweth not God, for God is Love. If we love one another God dwelleth in us, and his Love is perfected in us: We know that we have paſſed from Death to Life becauſe we love the Brethren: he that loveth not his Brother abideth in Death.</hi>
               </q> Such was the Love of this bleſſed <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to the <hi>Elect Lady</hi> and to <hi>Gaius;</hi> for <hi>the Truths ſake, which dwelleth in us and ſhall be in us for ever.</hi> It goes to <hi>Heaven</hi> with us, and is <hi>the Image of God</hi> on Angels and Saints there for ever and ever. <hi>Charity never faileth,</hi> but remains and is perfected <hi>when that which is perfect ſhall come;</hi> when <hi>Prophecies</hi> and <hi>Tongues,</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope ſhall ceaſe and vaniſh away.</hi> 1 Cor. xiii. 8, 10, 13</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="unknown:004001_0049_1003590C95C7AF00"/>
How <hi>odious</hi> then ſhould the <hi>want</hi> of Love be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtian! who as God for <hi>Chriſt's ſake</hi> has loved them, ſo they ought for <hi>his</hi> ſake to love one another. This <hi>Love</hi> ſhould not be <hi>in Word or in Tongue, but in Deed and in Truth, with a pure Heart, fervently.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">1 John. iii. 18 1 Pet. i. 22. Jam. iii. 9. Rom. xii. 9, 14</note> The <hi>Tongue</hi> is an <hi>unruly Evil, full of deadly Poiſon,</hi> when not under the <hi>Law of Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; therewith Men bleſs God even the Father; and therewith curſe</hi> they <hi>Men which are made after the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of God.</hi> Can there be any thing more a Contradiction, and an Abomination than this. <hi>Let Love be without Diſſimulation, bleſs and curſe not. But if ye have bitter Envying and Strife in your Heart, glory not</hi> in Words of feigned Love, <hi>and lie not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Truth.</hi> This is <hi>earthly, ſenſual, deviliſh.</hi> So <hi>diſtant</hi> is it from and <hi>oppoſite</hi> to the <hi>Likeneſs</hi> of God and Heaven.</p>
            <p>How excellent are the Precepts and Directions of our <hi>Holy Religion</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Epheſ. iv. 26, — 37. Col. iii. 8, 9, 12, 13.</note>! <q>
                  <hi>Be angry and ſin not; let not the Sun go down upon your Wrath: Neither give place to the Devil. And grieve not the Holy Spirit of God, whereby ye are ſealed to the Day of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Let all Bitterneſs, and Wrath, and Anger, and Clamour, and evil Speaking, be put away from you with all Malice; and be ye kind one to another, tender hearted, forgiving one another, even as God for Chriſt ſake hath forgiven you.</hi>
               </q> So does the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God</hi> on Man teach him to <hi>love God, Himſelf and his Neighbours,</hi> more eſpecially <hi>Thoſe</hi> in whom the Image of God is <hi>renewed</hi> in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. I go on to infer <hi>the dreadful Loſs to Man by Sinning againſt God, and the poſitive Miſery</hi> that he
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:004001_0050_100375051EA62D18"/>has bro't upon Himſelf. He has loſt the <hi>Likeneſs</hi> of his God! O how vaſt was this <hi>Loſs!</hi> how dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful this natural and inevitable Puniſhment of Sin! He aſpired to be <hi>as God</hi> for Knowledge and he loſt that bright Underſtanding which God had given him. <hi>Sin</hi> got him nothing but the Knowledge of <hi>Evil,</hi> and it loſt him the Knowledge of God. Man loſt his Original Righteouſneſs. This <hi>Glory</hi> depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from him. He was a <hi>living Temple</hi> and Palace of God, and the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> dwelt in him; but he polluted himſelf and became <hi>a Stye of unclean Luſts, the Habitation of Devils.</hi> Sin extinguiſh'd the <hi>Light</hi> of God on him, in Mind and Body; and Darkneſs cover'd him, the <hi>Shadow of Death</hi> ſtain'd him. He loſt the <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> of himſelf, Dominion over him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and became <hi>a Slave of Satan.</hi> The Creatures loſt their <hi>Fear</hi> of him, which the Majeſty &amp; Luſtre of his Face before commanded, and he loſt that <hi>Knowledge of the Creatures</hi> which God had given him for Empire over them. <hi>They</hi> grew ſurly and fierce toward him, as <hi>he</hi> had loſt his Reverence and Fear of God. He loſt his true Happineſs in his Original Rectitude; his Peace within and Joy in God was gone; the Terrors of Guilt ſeiz'd and ſtung him, and he fled from God; <hi>was afraid and hid himſelf.</hi> His <hi>Immortality</hi> indeed remain'd, but what <hi>Joy</hi> in that, when Innocence and Purity was gone! Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality in <hi>Sin</hi> and Guilt, under the Loſs of God's <hi>Image</hi> and Favour, <hi>unlike</hi> God and abominable in his Sight,—it was but the greater <hi>Miſery</hi> to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal in <hi>ſuch</hi> Circumſtances. To ceaſe to be at all, were the thing <hi>now</hi> to be deſired! even to loſe <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality</hi> too with the <hi>Likeneſs</hi> of God! for <hi>in his Favour is Life, and his Likeneſs is better than Life.</hi> We may take to our Selves in our <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from God, thoſe Words of the <hi>Prophet,</hi> Iſaiah. xiv. 12. <hi>How art thou fallen from Heaven, O Son of the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing! thou that didſt ſay in thy Heart, I will be as the
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:004001_0051_1003750B01E244F0"/>Moſt High! how art thou bro't down to Hell, to the ſides of the Pit!</hi> — But then <hi>the Miſery of Man by the Fall is not only the Loſs of God's Image,</hi> but <hi>a Contrariety and Enmity to God.</hi> We are <hi>alienated</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Epheſ. iv. 18.1 Cor ii. 14. Rom. viii. 7. Matth. vi. 23. Joh. iii. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>from the Life of God through the Ignorance that is in us, our carnal Heart is Enmity to God, is not ſubject to his Law, nor indeed can be</hi> of it ſelf. <hi>The natural Man receiveth not the Things of the Spirit of God, for they are Fooliſhneſs unto him; neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned. The Light that is in</hi> the wicked <hi>is Darkneſs;</hi> and <hi>how great is that Darkneſs!</hi> which is lov'd and <hi>choſen rather than Light!</hi> — This is that Corruption of our whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, "which is commonly called <hi>Original Sin</hi>", from which the <hi>Rebellions</hi> of our Lives againſt the Will of God do flow; even all our <hi>Tranſgreſſions</hi> in Tho't, Word and Deed — This is the <hi>Scripture</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Geneſis vi. 5. Jerem. iv. 22. Prov. i. 22. Pſalm. x. 4. xiv. 3. Rom. vii. 18, — 24.</note> Account of our <hi>Contrariety</hi> to God by Nature and wicked Works. <q>We are <hi>wiſe to do Evil,</hi> but to do <hi>Good</hi> we have <hi>no Knowledge.</hi> We even <hi>hate</hi> the Knowledge of <hi>the Holy. God is not in all our Thoughts. The Imaginations of our Hearts are only evil continually. We are all gone aſide, we are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether become filthy, there is none that doeth Good no not one. I know that in me, dwelleth no good thing; the Good that I would I do not, the Evil that I would not that do I! O wretched man that I am. who ſhall deliver me from the Body of this Death?</hi>
               </q> — This Soul-Miſery is the dire <hi>Conſequent</hi> of the Loſs of God's Image. It is the Image of <hi>Satan</hi> on us, who deceived us into our Revolt from God. This is Sin's Dominion and our natural <hi>Bondage.</hi> And our neceſſary <hi>Immortality</hi> is an infinite <hi>Addition</hi> to this State of Sin and Miſery, were there no <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance</hi> from it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="unknown:004001_0052_100375112B153878"/>
In one Word, For <hi>what</hi> is it that the Sons of Men <hi>exchange</hi> the Image of God in their Eſtrangement from Him, and in their Rebellions againſt him! O 'tis for the Image of a <hi>Brute Beaſt</hi> in their <hi>fleſhly</hi> Luſts, and for the Likeneſs of unclean <hi>Devils</hi> in their <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> Luſts! a miſerable Exchange be it <hi>the Filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Fleſh or Spirit.</hi> But there is no avoiding <hi>either,</hi> if we leave God or will not return to <hi>Him;</hi> we muſt take our <hi>Lot,</hi> nay our own <hi>Choice,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come both Brutes and Devils, and <hi>periſh</hi> like 'em.</p>
            <p>Wherefore,</p>
            <p n="5">V. Here is abundant Matter and Cauſe for that <hi>Evangelical Repentance,</hi> Humiliation, holy Mourning, Shame, Fear, Confeſſion, Deprecation, and Agony of Soul after Pardon and Renovation, which the <hi>Goſpel</hi> teaches and requires. The Doctrine of our Salvation muſt be a Doctrine of Repentance &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to God. In this the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven</hi> returns to us. There is no other poſſible Way for it. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance unto Life muſt be granted, revealed and publiſhed to us; and it muſt be wro't in us, we muſt be bro't into it. By what other Means can a Soul ever recover out of a ſtate of Sin? Therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> and the Holy JESUS, came all preaching <hi>Repentance.</hi> We muſt mourn for every ſingle <hi>Act</hi> of Sin committed by us, how then ought we to bewail the Sin of our <hi>Nature,</hi> which is the Spring of all the Impurities of our Life! It is only <hi>Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Pſalm cxxx 4. Rom. iii. 25, 26. Zech. xii. 10. Pſal. li. 1, 5, 7.</note> that draws forth this <hi>Repentance toward God,</hi> ſhewing us that there <hi>is Forgiveneſs with Him that he may be feared; "Whom God hath ſet forth to be a Propitiation, thro' Faith in his Blood, to declare his Righteouſneſs for the Remiſſion of Sin; that he might be juſt and the Juſtifier of him which believeth in Jeſus.</hi> See here the Fountain opened for Pardon and Cleanſing, in the Exerciſe of
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:004001_0053_10037517FA0FCCD0"/>Faith and Repentance! See it decribed by <hi>Zecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah</hi> and exemplified in <hi>David;</hi> The <hi>Prophet</hi> gives the Promiſe of it, the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> practiſes it. "<hi>I will pour</hi> (ſays the Promiſe of God) <hi>upon the Houſe of David, and on the Inhabitants of Jeruſalem the Spirit of Grace and of Supplication, and they ſhall look upon Me whom they have pierced and they ſhall mourn for him, as one mourneth for his only Son, and ſhall be in Bitterneſs for him as one that is in Bitterneſs for his Firſt-born.</hi> So the <hi>Pſalmiſt practis'd</hi> in the Day of his great Repentance. "<hi>Have Mercy upon me, O God, according to thy Loving kindneſs; according to the Multitude of thy tender Mercies blot out my Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion! Waſh me thro'ly from mine Iniquity, &amp; cleanſe me from my Sin; for I acknowledge my Tranſgreſſions, and my Sin is ever before me!— Behold I was ſhapen in Iniquity, and in Sin did my Mother conceive me! Purge me as with Hyſſop and I ſhall be clean, waſh me and I ſhall be whither than Snow!—Create in me, O God, a clean Heart, and renew a right Spirit within me!— Reſtore to me the Joy of thy Salvation, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me with thy free Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. Learn we <hi>the Miſery of Devils,</hi> which to be ſure muſt be equal to, if not much greater than fallen <hi>Man</hi>'s, in the <hi>Loſs</hi> of God's Image &amp; Likeneſs, and in the Infliction of his Wrath and Curſe. And yet not greater than theirs who deſpiſe the Goſpel and periſh under the Light thereof: For <hi>Devils</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſinned againſt an Offer of Mercy or Means of Grace, that we know of. The Son of God took not their Nature, to put them in a Way for the Recovery of their primitive Holineſs and Glory. They <hi>ſaw</hi> him indeed in our Nature, but it was with <hi>Hatred</hi> and Indignation, which added to their Guilt and Judgment. They <hi>tempted</hi> him in Hope to have defeated the Deſign of our Redemption; but finding nothing in Him, and prevailing nothing
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:004001_0054_1003751E84E92FD8"/>againſt him, they <hi>trembled</hi> before him and hated him the more. Math. viii. 29. <hi>What have we to do with Thee, Jeſus thou Son of God? art thou come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to torment us before the Time?</hi> They thus ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor'd from the Brightneſs of <hi>the Image of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> in Him; "<hi>I know thee who thou art, thou holy One of God!</hi> In this their Uncleanneſs, and Enmity to God and Chriſt and Holineſs, they remain odious and accurſed for Ever; and <hi>the Son of God</hi> in our Nature and in our Air will ſentence 'em to the <hi>everlaſting Burnings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">VII. See we then <hi>the Glory of the Man</hi> CHRIST JESUS, <hi>the ſecond Adam.</hi> The <hi>firſt Adam</hi> in all his Glory was not to be likned, or compared to Him. The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was in his beſt Eſtate <hi>of the Earth earthy, the ſecond Man is the Lord from Heaven; the firſt Adam was made a living Soul, the ſecond Adam a quickning Spirit</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">1 Cor. xv. 45, 47. Col. i. 5.2 Cor. iv. 6. John. i. 14. Col. i. 13. Prov. xxx. 4. Col. ii 9.</note>. There is as much Difference between the <hi>Image of God in meer Men,</hi> and that in the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> as there is between Earth and Heaven, between God and his Creature, between a living Soul and Him that made it, between <hi>Him that has Life in Himſelf</hi> and communicates Life natural and ſpiritual, and him that receives it. Accordingly we read of CHRIST, that He is <hi>the Image of the Inviſible God, the Heir of all things, the Brightneſs of the Fathers Glory, the expreſs Image of his Perſon, having by Inheritance a more excellent Name than Angels,</hi> the Object of their <hi>Worſhip;</hi> And yet they are <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Thrones and Principalities and Powers:</hi> To the SON it is therefore ſaid, "<hi>Thy Throne, O GOD, is for ever and ever!</hi> Agreably we read again, of <hi>the Light of the Glory of God in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and that <hi>his Glory was beheld as the Glory of the Only-Begotten of the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="unknown:004001_0055_10037526C28EEC28"/>
Such is the <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>Eternal Father</hi> in his <hi>dear Son,</hi> by an ineffable Communication of Eſſence, or by an unſearchable Self-exiſtence, is not for us to ſay! <hi>for what is his Sons Name? if thou canſt tell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was <hi>Adam</hi> created <hi>wiſe</hi> in the Likeneſs of God? <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Wiſdom of God;</hi> the <hi>Serpent</hi> with all his Subtlety could not <hi>beguile</hi> him, neither in the <hi>Deſart</hi> nor in the <hi>City.</hi> Was <hi>Adam</hi> made <hi>holy</hi> in the Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God? <hi>Chriſt</hi> was the <hi>Holy One of God;</hi> ſeen and confeſſed to be ſo both by Angels and Devils. Was <hi>Adam</hi> made <hi>Lord</hi> of the Creatures on Earth? <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſet down on <hi>the Right Hand of the Majeſty in the Heavens; Angels Authorities and Powers being made ſubject to Him.</hi> And was <hi>Adam</hi> made <hi>bleſſed</hi> and <hi>happy</hi> in the Likeneſs of God? of <hi>Chriſt</hi> we read that God has made Him <hi>moſt bleſſed for evermore.</hi> — In one word, the incommunicable <hi>Glories</hi> of the Eternal and Unchangeable <hi>Godhead</hi> are in <hi>Chriſt, in whom dwelleth the Fulneſs of the Godhead bodily.</hi> — But let us deſcend to the poor <hi>Members of Chriſt</hi> on Earth.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. What muſt we then think and ſay <hi>of the Saints on Earth?</hi> of <hi>Souls Regenerated by the Spirit of God,</hi> converted from Sin and ſanctified to God; adopted in Jeſus Chriſt, pardoned and juſtified; again made Children and Heirs of God! Why, the <hi>Image of God</hi> is in part <hi>reſtored</hi> in them, and will ſoon be <hi>perfected</hi> in 'em. How elſe ſhould God juſtify them, put 'em among his Children, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare them Heirs of Heaven? Well might the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>John</hi> ſpeak with Admiration of this <hi>new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of God, the Conformity of <hi>renewed Souls</hi> to the Image of the <hi>Son of God,</hi> and their Adoption in Him<note n="†" place="bottom">1 John. iii. 1, 2, 3. Rom. xii. 2.</note>; <hi>Behold what manner of Love the Father hath beſtowed on us, that we ſhould be called the Sons of God!
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:004001_0056_1003752D70F60308"/>therefore the World knoweth us not, becauſe it knew Him not: Beloved, now are we the Sons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be; but we know that when He ſhall appear we ſhall be like him; for we ſhall ſee him as he is: And every One that hath this Hope in him, purifieth himſelf even as He is pure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See the Bleſſedneſs of a State of <hi>Grace</hi> here and of <hi>Glory</hi> for ever! the Image of God is <hi>begun</hi> in this Life, and will be <hi>perfected</hi> in the next. The Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in Jeſus Chriſt are <hi>renewed in Knowledge,</hi> and made <hi>Light in the Lord;</hi> they are <hi>after God created in Righteouſneſs,</hi> are made <hi>free from Sin</hi> and are tranſlated into the <hi>glorious Liberty of the Children of God.</hi> They are <hi>begotten to the lively Hope of the Inheritance incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerved in Heaven for them.</hi> Thus does the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify the <hi>Regenerate State,</hi> and ſet it before the Eyes of Men in a <hi>Divine</hi> Light, that all may ſee the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and Excellency of the <hi>true Salvation</hi> of Souls; which is <hi>the Recovery of the Image and Likeneſs of God,</hi> wherein we were at firſt created. So that all the <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Directions</hi> of the Goſpel do at laſt expire in thoſe Words to the <hi>Romans, "And be ye transformed by the renewing of your Minds, that ye may prove what is that good, and acceptable and perfect Will of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">IX. Think and infer from all, <hi>what Heaven is,</hi> and what the <hi>Caeleſtial Glory and Bleſſedneſs</hi> will be found by the happy Partakers thereof! then the <hi>Image of God and Chriſt will be perfected in the Saints!</hi> They will <hi>ſhine forth</hi> in the Kingdom of their <hi>Father, wiſe holy bleſſed dignified</hi> for ever &amp; ever. And this glorious Likeneſs to God will be for ever <hi>growing</hi> in 'em, to their increaſing <hi>Joys</hi> for ever and ever.—This is <hi>Heaven, Paradiſe regain'd,</hi> the <hi>Jeruſalem from above, with the Glory of God upon it.</hi> This is <hi>Viſion,</hi> to be more and more <hi>like God,</hi> by ſeeing Him as he is. This is to <hi>know even as we are known;</hi> to ſee
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:004001_0057_10035928F64F1380"/>the <hi>Face</hi> of God in his <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Image</hi> on us. This is <hi>the Tree of Life,</hi> with <hi>all manner of Fruit;</hi> and this the <hi>Water of Life</hi> from the <hi>Throne of God</hi> and <hi>of the Lamb:</hi> And there can be <hi>no more Curſe,</hi> no more any <hi>Loſs</hi> or Want for ever of the <hi>Likeneſs and Love</hi> of God; but the higheſt Bleſſedneſs in the everlaſting Enjoyment of <hi>both;</hi> and <hi>they ſhall reign for ever and ever.</hi> Revel. xxii. 1,—5.</p>
            <p>And here let us contemplate, for a Moment, the UNITY of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of God; how they <hi>begin</hi> and <hi>end,</hi> and thro' every Part agree and are <hi>one</hi> in <hi>This;</hi> "Man <hi>created</hi> in the <hi>Image</hi> of God and moſt <hi>happy</hi> therein; but preſently <hi>miſerable</hi> by ſinning againſt God in the <hi>Loſs</hi> of God's Likeneſs and Favour: Then the <hi>Seed of the Woman</hi> is revealed, <hi>recovering</hi> Souls into the Favour of God, by <hi>renewing</hi> them in Knowledge and Holineſs, after the <hi>Image</hi> of Him that created them, and ſo making them <hi>meet</hi> for the <hi>Heavenly Paradiſe.</hi>—Whoſoever looks through the <hi>Book</hi> of God, may eaſily ſee this one <hi>Line</hi> drawn thro' the <hi>whole</hi> of it; than <hi>which</hi> nothing can be more worthy of God, nor more neceſſary for us, and level to us.—And I know no more ſhort and plain <hi>Argument</hi> of the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Holy Scriptures than <hi>this View of their Unity</hi> gives unto us. <q>Such a <hi>Unity of Deſign,</hi> in all the Parts of <hi>Scripture,</hi> tho' written by different <hi>Perſons,</hi> in different <hi>Ages,</hi>
               </q> and in ſuch a <hi>Manner</hi> as the Scripture is delivered, Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical, Doctrinal, Legiſlative, Prophetical, Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, and Hortatory; ſeems utterly inconſiſtent with either <hi>Impoſture</hi> or <hi>Enthuſiam;</hi> one or other of which muſt be the <hi>Charge</hi> that <hi>Infidels</hi> bring againſt our <hi>Belief</hi> of their <hi>Inſpiration</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>"Shew if you can (ſays a late learned Writer<note n="*" place="bottom">An <hi>Eſſay</hi> on the ſeveral <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> of God to Mankind.</note>) a ſingle <hi>Enthuſiaſt</hi> that is conſiſtent with himſelf thro'
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:004001_0058_1003753B8B4D0548"/>many Volumes. If then it ſhall appear, that there is <hi>one</hi> worthy and noble Deſign purſued thro' the Books of the <hi>Old and New Teſtament,</hi> by one wiſe plain and ſimple Mean, tho' they had forty or more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Authors and were not written in leſs than ſixteen hundred Years; it will amount to the cleareſt Demonſtration that the <hi>Bible</hi> muſt be from HIM who exiſts thro' all Ages, and ſees all that is paſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and to come, who has always the ſame View, &amp;c." <hi>Thus He.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon all therefore, as the natural <hi>Reſult</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of what has been ſaid,</p>
            <p n="10">X. And laſtly, How <hi>dear and precious,</hi> infinitely ſo, ſhould <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Goſpel</hi> be to us? and what can we think or ſay of <hi>our Selves</hi> if we <hi>refuſe Him in the Propoſals of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Deſign</hi> and End of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s coming into the World is to <hi>reſtore the loſt Image of God</hi> in us, and to <hi>recover us into the Divine Likeneſs,</hi> Love and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; to our primitive Holineſs and Bleſſedneſs, Dominion and Glory, and to <hi>a far more exceeding and eternal Weight of Glory.</hi> He took our Nature and died in it to make us <hi>New Creatures,</hi> ſuch as God at firſt made us; <hi>His Workmanſhip</hi> a ſecond time, <hi>created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good Works.</hi> He came to deliver Souls from the Power of <hi>Satan,</hi> and to <hi>bruiſe the Serpent's Head under the Feet of his</hi> Elect, that they ſhould <hi>trample on the Lion and the Dragon. He gave himſelf for us to redeem us from all Iniquity, and to purify unto himſelf a peculiar People zealous of good Works</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">2 Cor. v. 17. Gal. vi. 15. Eph. ii. 10. Rom. xvi. 20. Pſal. xci. 13. Tit. ii 14. Pſal xl 8. Rom. vii. 22.</note>. This ſhould make Chriſt <hi>glorious</hi> in our Eyes that he ſaves <hi>only in this Way of Holineſs</hi> thro' <hi>Sanctification of the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Obedience to the Truth:</hi> So that every renewed Soul can ſay
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:004001_0059_10037542EC328B70"/>after him, <hi>"Lord, thy Law is within me, I delight to do thy Will, O God.</hi> O what a Change is this! into the Likeneſs of Man's Original State! <hi>"I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the Law of God after the inward Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>this Cauſe</hi> ſhould the written and preached <hi>Goſpel</hi> be very <hi>dear</hi> to us; it being the declared End, Uſe, Power and Efficacy thereof, to reſtore the loſt <hi>Image</hi> of God in us. It is the bleſſed Means of holy Knowledge and ſaving <hi>Illumination;</hi> and of the <hi>Purification</hi> of Souls for Communion with God: <hi>Ye have purified your Souls in obeying the Truth</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">1 Pet. i. 22. Pſal. cx. 2 3. Rom. i 16. Hebrews il. 1, 2, 3. 2. Cor. iv. 3, 4.</note>. It is the Means of <hi>ſpiritual Dominion,</hi> Freedom from Sin and Liberty to what is good and holy: <hi>Thy People ſhall be willing in the Day of thy Power, in the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Holineſs.</hi> It is the Means of infinite <hi>Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> unto Souls in the Likeneſs and Love of God. <hi>He that hath my Commandments and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me, and he ſhall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will manifeſt my Self to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ought therefore to give the more earneſt Heed to the Things which we have heard,</hi> to the Doctrines Precepts and Motives of the Goſpel, <hi>leſt at any Time we ſhould let them ſlip</hi> out of our Minds and Hearts; for <hi>how ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great Salvation?</hi> the Recovery of the loſt <hi>Image of God</hi> in our Souls, and thereby the <hi>Pleaſure and Delight</hi> of God in us, which ſuppoſes and ſecures a ſtate of <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi> everlaſting. What can God himſelf <hi>propoſe better</hi> for us than <hi>ſuch</hi> Salvation? the <hi>ſame</hi> Felicity which he <hi>at firſt</hi> made us for and made us in. What can our <hi>own Souls deſire</hi> or wiſh for beyond this, or any thing beſide it? to have the <hi>Likeneſs</hi> of God reſtored in them, or to be reſtored in <hi>his</hi> Eye and Heart! and by this Means to be made <hi>meet</hi> for the Viſion of God, and for Bleſſedneſs
<pb n="45" facs="unknown:004001_0060_100375495E8CD4D0"/>in Him to all Eternity! And indeed there is <hi>no other</hi> Way to the true and proper perfect Happineſs of Man; for <hi>without Holineſs no Man can ſee God.</hi> Without <hi>Likeneſs</hi> there can be no <hi>Love;</hi> no Love in <hi>God</hi> to us, no Love in <hi>us</hi> to God, and <hi>both</hi> are neceſſary to the <hi>Felicity</hi> of Souls, whether in the Body or out of it.</p>
            <p>O the <hi>Miſery</hi> of Souls then, who by their Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Impenitency under the Goſpel do in Effect ſay to God, <hi>"Depart from us, we deſire not the Knowledge of Thee;</hi> the Recovery of <hi>Likeneſs</hi> to Thee or any <hi>Communion</hi> with Thee! O the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery</hi> of that Soul, which having <hi>loſt</hi> the Image of God and his Love, is <hi>content</hi> in the Want of it; ſeeks not the Recovery of it, nay refuſes the Means thereof! <hi>If our Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt, in whom the God of this World hath blinded the Minds of them that believe not, leſt the Light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the Image of God, ſhould ſhine into them.</hi> The ſame <hi>Serpent,</hi> the Devil, and <hi>Satan,</hi> who deceived our <hi>firſt Parents</hi> into the Loſs of <hi>God's Image,</hi> ſtill blinds and <hi>hardens</hi> Sinners, under the Light of the preached Goſpel, and they wilfully refuſe the <hi>Recovery</hi> of it in their own Souls. Sinners chuſe to periſh under <hi>Ignorance</hi> of God, <hi>Luſt, Servitude</hi> and <hi>Death;</hi> when <hi>Light, Holineſs, Liberty, Glory Honour and Immortality</hi> are ſet before them and tender'd to 'em. They periſh therefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Excuſe,</hi> and everlaſting <hi>Remorſe</hi> will be their Torment. The <hi>Sacrifice of Chriſt</hi> will be ſo far from ſaving them, that <hi>his Blood cries</hi> againſt them, and will inflame their Conſciences for Evermore. As it is written, <hi>Hebrews</hi> x. 26,—31.</p>
            <p>How <hi>earneſt</hi> therefore and <hi>inſtant</hi> ſhould we be in ſeeking the <hi>Recovery</hi> of the loſt <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of God, with our whole Soul? the <hi>Beginning</hi> of it in this Life, tho' here we can <hi>but know in part and propheſie in part, underſtand as a Child and ſpeak
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:004001_0061_100375536DEA74A0"/>as a Child;</hi> yet the <hi>Infant</hi> bears the Image of the Parent; the <hi>Perfection</hi> of it in the Life to come, where <hi>that which is perfect ſhall come, and that which is in part ſhall be done away;</hi> and we ſhall <hi>ſee Face to Face, and know even as we are known</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">1 Cor. xiii. 9, 10, 11, 12.</note>." <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my Soul from the Wicked,</hi> prays the <hi>Pſalmiſt, from Men of the World which have their Portion in this Life; As for me, I will behold thy Face in Righteouſneſs; I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake in thy Likeneſs</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Pſalm. xvii. 15.</note>. They are ſure to ſhine in the <hi>Divine Likeneſs</hi> for ever and ever, who here behold the Face of God <hi>in Righteouſneſs,</hi> How Divine and God-like there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, how full of Grace and Benignity to us, are the <hi>Exhortations</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Rom, xii. 2. 2 Cor iii. 18. Eph. iv. 24. Col. iii. 10. 2. Pet. 1 3, 4</note> 
               <hi>of the Goſpel,</hi> with reciting which I will <hi>conclude,</hi> as carrying in them a <hi>Light and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> a <hi>Majeſty and Goodneſs</hi> which no Words of Man can pretend to: <q>
                  <hi>And be ye transformed by the renewing of your Mind, that ye may prove what is that good, &amp; acceptable, and perfect Will of God: And be renewed in the Spirit of your Mind, and put on the new Man which after God is created in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs &amp; true Holineſs; and is renewed in Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge after the Image of Him that created him: According as his Divine Power hath given unto us all Things that pertain unto Life and Godlineſs, through the Knowledge of Him that hath called us to Glory and Vertue; whereby are given unto us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great and precious Promiſes, that by theſe you might be Partakers of the Divine Nature, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eſcaped the Corruption that is in the World thro' Luſt: Give all Diligence</hi> therefore <hi>to add unto your Faith Vertue, Knowledge, Temperance, Patience, God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, Brotherly-kindneſs, Charity; for if theſe Things be in you and abound, they make you that ye
<pb n="47" facs="unknown:004001_0062_1003755AA5668238"/>be neither barren nor unfruitful in the Knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. "Now the</hi> LORD <hi>is that Spirit, and where the Spirit of the</hi> LORD <hi>is there is Liberty: We all with open Face, beholding as in a Glaſs the Glory of the</hi> LORD, <hi>are changed into the</hi> SAME IMAGE, <hi>from Glory to Glory, even as by</hi> THE SPIRIT OF THE LORD.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="addenda">
            <head>Addenda.</head>
            <head type="sub">As a <hi>Marginal Note</hi> Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Eſſay</hi> on the ſeveral Diſpenſations of God to Mankind. p. 8.</note> THE <hi>Image of God</hi> in the <hi>Old and New Teſtament,</hi> generally, if not every where, ſignifies the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of God's <hi>Dominion.</hi> See <hi>Gen.</hi> ix. 6.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xi. 7. <hi>Col</hi> i. 15 See alſo to this purpoſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtic.</hi> xvii, 3, 4. And from hence it is likewiſe that <hi>Princes</hi> are figuratively called the <hi>Sons of Sons;</hi> eſpecially ſuch as exerciſe their Dominion with Juſtice and Mercy; (<hi>Pſalm</hi> lxxxii. 6, 7. <hi>John</hi> x. 33,—37.) tho' they are not poſſeſs'd of Bliſs Glory and Immortality.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
