<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Elisha lamenting after the God of Elijah. A funeral sermon preach'd at Boston, March 27. 1737. Occasion'd by the death of the Reverend Mr. Benjamin Wadsworth, late president of Harvard-College in Cambridge, and formerly Pastor of the Old Church in Boston. Who departed this life on March 16th. Having just enter'd the 68th year of his age. / By Thomas Foxcroft, sometimes Colleague-Pastor with him. ; [Four lines of Scripture texts]</title>
            <author>Foxcroft, Thomas, 1697-1769.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04">2009-04.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N03393</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N03393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 4140</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APY4713</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">4140</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99031865</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 4140.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N03393)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 4140)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 4140)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Elisha lamenting after the God of Elijah. A funeral sermon preach'd at Boston, March 27. 1737. Occasion'd by the death of the Reverend Mr. Benjamin Wadsworth, late president of Harvard-College in Cambridge, and formerly Pastor of the Old Church in Boston. Who departed this life on March 16th. Having just enter'd the 68th year of his age. / By Thomas Foxcroft, sometimes Colleague-Pastor with him. ; [Four lines of Scripture texts]</title>
                  <author>Foxcroft, Thomas, 1697-1769.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], vi, 69, [1] p. ;  21 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Fleet, for Samuel Eliot in Cornhill, and John Parker at the head of the town-dock.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston, New England, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1737.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Mr. Foxcroft's funeral sermon for the Reverend Mr. Wadsworth.</note>
                  <note>Running title: A funeral sermon for the Rev. Mr. Wadsworth.</note>
                  <note>Caption title: Survivors inquiring after the God of their pious predecessors.</note>
                  <note>Errata statement, p. 69.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wadsworth, Benjamin, 1670-1737.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  1737.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:004140_0000_1003DB3753518A98"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:004140_0001_1003DAE09BA06EF8"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Foxcroft</hi>'s <hi>Funeral Sermon</hi> FOR The Reverend Mr. <hi>Wadſworth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:004140_0002_1003DAE48E4467A0"/>
            <p>Eliſha <hi>lamenting after the GOD of</hi> Elijah.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Funeral Sermon</hi> Preach'd at <hi>Boſton,</hi> March 27. 1737. Occaſion'd by the DEATH of the Reverend <hi>Mr.</hi> BENJAMIN WADSWORTH, Late <hi>Preſident</hi> of Harvard-College in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and formerly <hi>Paſtor</hi> of the Old Church in <hi>Boſton. WHO departed this Life on</hi> March 16<hi>th.</hi> Having juſt enter'd the 68<hi>th</hi> Year of his Age.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Foxcroft,</hi> Sometimes Colleague-Paſtor with him.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Kin. 3.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Here is <hi>Eliſha,</hi> which poured Water on the Hands of <hi>Elijah.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thou haſt fully known my Doctrine, manner of Life, Purpoſe, Faith, Longſuffering, Charity, Patience.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON,</hi> New England, Printed by <hi>T. Fleet,</hi> for SAMUEL ELIOT in Cornhill, and JOHN PARKER at the Head of the Town-Dock. 1737.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="unknown:004140_0003_1003DAE987353AE8"/>
            <head>To the Old or Firſt Church in <hi>BOSTON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was a ſincere and high Reſpect for the Memory of my Reverend <hi>Father,</hi> your late excellent <hi>Paſtor,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a View to your Edification, which indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced me to entertain you, in my publick Diſcourſe on the Sabbath after his Funeral, with ſome Meditations ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the mournful Occaſion of his Death: and I doubt not, the ſame Principles had their Influence in putting You upon ſo unanimous a <hi>Vote,</hi> to aſk a Copy for the Preſs.</p>
            <p>I need not obſerve to You, with what Diſadvantages a Performance of this Nature from me (under my preſent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſitions) muſt appear; while the neceſſary Care of my broken Health forbids that Application of Thought and Care of Exactneſs, proper in preparing and publiſhing a Sermon on ſuch a Subject and Occaſion: which would have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently pleaded in my Excuſe, if I had declin'd the Preſs. However, in Deference to your Judgment and Requeſt, I have ſacrific'd my own Inclinations; and venture into the publick Light, hoping for the ſame Candour to an imperfect Diſcourſe from others in the reading, as it met with from You in the hearing. It muſt be allow'd, that an affected Niceneſs of Method and Ornaments of Language make but an odd Figure in a melancholy Funeral Sermon: and therefore I give you mine very much in its original inaccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Dreſs; tho' with ſome few Additions, which the ſcant Limits of a ſingle Hour obliged me to omit in the Pulpit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="ii" facs="unknown:004140_0004_1003DAEC670CB828"/>As to the <hi>Character</hi> of the Deceaſed, ſo far as I went into it, 'tis a Satisfaction to me, that I have your Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: for the World muſt think your printing the Sermon a loud Atteſtation to the Juſtice of my Obſervations on that head. I ſpake indeed with the greater Freedom, becauſe in <hi>your</hi> hearing, who could witneſs I ſpoke <hi>in the Words of Truth and Soberneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the known Principle and Practice of the deceaſed Servant of God to uſe a remarkable Caution and Modeſty of Speech an ſuch Occaſions; nor could he reliſh the flow'ry Pomp of <hi>Funeral Oratory,</hi> ſo common, and ſo often abus'd, in praiſing the Dead, to flatter the Living: Yet where any appear'd to him Perſons of diſtinguiſh'd Merits, and ſuch as by general Suffrage wou'd be allow'd to have ſomething due to their Memory, he wou'd ſet an Aſteriſm on their honourable Names, recommend their bright Example to Imitation, and ſpeak of their excellent Gifts, Graces, and Services, to the Honour of that God, who bleſs'd them, and made them Bleſſings to their Generation. Witneſs in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular his Funeral Sermon for the late Rev. Mr. <hi>Thomas Bridge,</hi> his worthy Colleague in the Paſtoral Relation, and my immediate Predeceſſor: The <hi>Text</hi> and the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> moſt ſitly applicable for the <hi>Author</hi>'s own Funeral Sermon. And accordingly I recommend it to your ſerious Review on this Occaſion.</p>
            <p>I take Leave now to remind You, with what a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Succeſſion of eminent Lights this golden Candleſtick has been diſtinguiſh'd. You have had your <hi>Wilſon, Cotton, Norton, Davenport, Oxenbridge, Allen, Bridge,</hi> and <hi>Wadſworth;</hi> precious Gifts to you from our aſcended Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, Paſtors and Teachers, who have fed You with Knowledge and Underſtanding: Beſides whom, You have enjoy'd the occaſional Labours of ſeveral worthy Aſſiſtants (<hi>Moodey</hi> and <hi>Bailey</hi> in particular) for many Months, or Years together. Your evangelical Advantages ſurely have
<pb n="iii" facs="unknown:004140_0005_1003DAF197125F40"/>
been great: and if your ſpiritual Improvements be not in ſome Proportion, your Account will be awful. And for my own part, <hi>when I conſider, I am afraid.</hi> It hath often been a ſolemn Thought with me, <hi>In whoſe Room</hi> I ſtood up; what aged, learned, laborious, wiſe, and venerable <hi>Men of God</hi> have ſucceſſively gone before me in this holy Miniſtry: and the Reflection has been very humbling to me, by a Senſe of my own comparative Inſufficiency, Inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, Unworthineſs, Nothingneſs. Sure I am, I've the greateſt Reaſon to ſtand aſtoniſh'd at the <hi>Divine Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> towards me: and to admire <hi>your Candour</hi> to me, your <hi>kind Acceptance</hi> of my Labours, and the <hi>generous Tokens</hi> of your Love in Reward of them, while I have been with many Imperfections miniſtring among You, now full <hi>20</hi> Years. And tho' according to the general Run of human Life, I may have ſtill many Days to ſerve You; yet the ſurprizing Blow of God's chaſtning Hand upon me, not many Months ſince (when all about my Bed conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me under a Sentence of Death) and my habitual In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities in Conſequence thereof, did awfully warn me, and do daily admoniſh me, not to expect a long Continuance in this preſent evil World. O join your Prayers with mine, that a Life ſo wonderfully reprieved from Deſtruction, may be employed more than ever for the Glory of God and the Service of your Souls, to which I hope it is ſincerely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted; and that when called from You (God only knows how ſoon or ſuddenly) I may be found with my Work done, and my Accounts ready, and may finiſh my Courſe with Joy. I wiſh you a <hi>durable,</hi> as well as great Bleſſing, in my dear <hi>Colleague,</hi> your other Paſtor! And this I pray, that your Love may abound yet more and more in Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and in all Judgment; that ye may approve Things that are excellent, and continue in the things which ye have learned, and be watchful to ſtrengthen the Things which remain that are ready to die.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="iv" facs="unknown:004140_0006_1003DAF4136DC140"/>Let us all concur in heartily lamenting the great and growing <hi>Degeneracies</hi> of the preſent Day: and let us unite our fervent Prayers, our ſolicitous Cares, and ſtrenuous Endeavours for the happy Reſurrection and Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing of Religion and Virtue among us, which is our Life, our trueſt proſperity, and brighteſt Crown. Surely <hi>it is Time to ſeek the Lord, till He come and rain Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And have we not Reaſon to lay to Heart the many ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful Inſtances of <hi>Mortality,</hi> we've ſeen in the Courſe of a very few Years, among our Pious and Uſeful, and our Aged and Honorable? <hi>For behold, the Lord, the Lord of Hoſts, doth take away from</hi> us <hi>the Stay and the Staff, the Judge, and the Prophet, and the Prudent, and the Ancient, the honourable Man, and the Counſellor, the cunning Artificer, and the eloquent Orator.</hi> Verily by repeated Loſſes of Men of Note in the Congregation, a holy ſovereign God has been not only leſſening our Number, but thinning our Glory, impoveriſhing our Treaſury, and weakning our Strength. Their hoary Heads were a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Ornament in our Aſſembly; their ſhining Characters reflected a ſuperior Luſtre upon it; and their ſeveral In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, Powers, and active Virtues abundantly ſtrengthen'd our Hands, and encourag'd our Hearts. But now a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Emptineſs is ſeen, where they us'd to appear and act. Alas, how ſadly do we miſs them! What lamentable Vacancies do we behold in one Seat and another; and few of the like excellent Spirit and Talents ſucceeding to fill up their Places! Have me not Reaſon to cry out, with the Prophet! <hi>O Lord God, ceaſe, I beſeech Thee; by whom ſhall</hi> Jacob <hi>ariſe? for he is ſmall. — Come and let us return to the Lord: for He hath torn, and He will heal us; He hath ſmitten, and He will bind us up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are bleeding particularly by a freſh and deep Wound <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Deceaſe of that good and merciful Man, one of our
<pb n="v" facs="unknown:004140_0007_1003DAF754AA9A88"/>
worthy and faithful Deacons, the late Mr. <hi>Jonathan Williams;</hi> over whoſe Grave I cannot refrain dropping a Tear of Condolence with You, and paying a ſmall Tribute to his Memory. May the God of all Grace ſanctify the Death of his Servant to the bereaved Children and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, to his mournful Brethren in Office, and to us all! We have loſt in him the amiable Example of a devout, juſt, peaceable, charitable, and humble Chriſtian, and the valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Help of a very active, prudent, and uſeful Servant of the Church. The main Qualifications of a <hi>Deacon,</hi> as they are laid down by the inſpir'd Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> were viſible in this our Brother; <hi>Gravity, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, Temperance, Generoſity, ſound Faith, and a pure Conſcience.</hi> We muſt bear him this Teſtimony, that he hath <hi>uſed his Office well;</hi> and having ſerved his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration according to the Will of God, he is <hi>(with</hi> Stephen) fallen aſleep. But <hi>if we believe that Jeſus died, and roſe again, even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus, will God bring with him:</hi> and for our further Conſolation, in the mean time, <hi>we ſee Jeſus who was made a little lower than the Angels, for the ſuffering of Death, crown'd with Glory and Honour; Head over all things to his Church, and the Saviour of the Body.</hi> Having aſcended up on high, he has received Gifts for Men: and of his Fulneſs may we ſtill look to receive, even Grace for Grace, Bleſſing upon Bleſſing. Ye that make Mention of the LORD, keep not Silence: and give Him no Reſt, till He eſtabliſh, and till He make our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a Praiſe in the Earth, as in former Years, and as in the Days of old; even until the Righteouſneſs thereof go forth as Brightneſs; and the Salvation thereof as a Lamp that burneth. Let it be your Prayer day and night, that a gracious God wou'd pardon our Sins, and heal our Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidings, whereby we have expoſ'd our ſelves to his fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Judgments; That he wou'd return and viſit his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, made weak by the Fall of ſo many of his righteous Ones; and that He wou'd cloſe the Breaches in our Walls,
<pb n="vi" facs="unknown:004140_0008_1003DAFE78A13910"/>
by raiſing up a Succeſſion of Perſons of a like excellent Spirit and exemplary uſeful Life, as thoſe that have left us, and who may be like Bleſſings to us, bright Pledges of his ſpiritual Preſence in the midſt of us. He has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed his gracious Preſence to his Church to the End of the World. Let us be Followers of them who through Faith and Patience inherit the Promiſes. So we may hope, He will be with us, as He was with our Fathers, and will never leave nor forſake us. Rejoyce in the Lord alway: and again I ſay, Rejoyce in Him, the inexhauſtible Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Life, who (whatever Streams are dried up) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains the ſame for ever. Be careful for nothing; but in every <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by Prayer and Supplication, with Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, let your Requeſts be made known to God: And the Peace of God, which paſſeth all Underſtanding, ſhall keep your Hearts through Chriſt Jeſus: To whom be Glory in the Churches, World without End. Amen.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the ſincere Sentiments, Advices and Wiſhes of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionate Paſtor, <hi>Thomas Foxcroft.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Boſton,</hi> 
                  <date>April <hi>2. 1737.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="unknown:004140_0009_1003DAFFFB4C7350"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Survivors inquiring after the GOD</hi> OF Their pious Predeceſſors.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>II. Kings, 2.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—Where is the LORD God of <hi>Elijah?</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS there's no Hiſtory in the World of like An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity with the <hi>Bible,</hi> ſo none of ſuch extenſive and happy Influence; none of equal Uſe and Service to Mankind. For in the ſacred Story we have ſuch Accounts of the <hi>Works of God,</hi> Creation, Providence, and Redemption, as preſent his amiable (but ſtill tremendous) Perfections to our View in the beſt and ſtrongeſt Light, far tranſcending the higheſt Diſcoveries of mere natural Reaſon; and conſequently have a powerful Tendency both to awaken in every conſidering Soul very awful Apprehenſions of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and Greatneſs, and to encourage our Hope and Confidence in his Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and Truth: And here too we have ſuch Narratives of innumerable <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Servants of God</hi> in former Ages of the World, their Character and Conduct, Experiences and Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, Lives and Deaths, as are eminently uſeful for the Direction of our Faith and Practice, afford very convincing Arguments for the Reality, Excellency and
<pb n="2" facs="unknown:004140_0010_1003DB01ED953080"/>
Advantage of Divine Revelation, and tend to acquaint us more fully with the glorious Principles of our holy Religion, to eſtabliſh our Belief of its important Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, and engage our Attention and Obedience to its incomparably wiſe and righteous Precepts. As an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Harmony runs thro' all the Revelations of God to the Sons of Men, ſo a beautiful Congruity every where appears in the Faith, Worſhip, and Morals of all Saints (tho' variouſly excelling in Proportion to the Divine Light and Grace diſpens'd to them) thro' all ſucceſſive Ages of the World. The inſpired Records of the <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> Age may have furniſh'd us with the plaineſt and faireſt, the moſt familiar and moſt inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective Copies for our Imitation: Yet <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>the Prophets</hi> are not to be thrown by as uſeleſs, nor the Examples of <hi>Old Teſtament-Saints</hi> to be neglected, as of no Importance to us under the Chriſtian Diſpenſation; but even theſe are applicable for the Regulation of our Belief, our Temper and Deportment, in the moſt eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Inſtances, with relation to the Things of God and Eternity, and for our Encouragement and Aſſiſtance upon many Occaſions in the Courſe of the Chriſtian Life.</p>
            <p>On the preſent Occaſion, when we are call'd to mourn the Death of an eminently pious and uſeful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God, I have ſingled out the Example of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Eliſha</hi> (who had <hi>his Maſter taken from his head</hi>) to teach us the moſt proper Conduct under ſuch a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation.</p>
            <p>My Text ſtands in Connection with the remarkable Story of <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Tranſlation to the Church triumphant above, and <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s Succeſſion into his Place in the Church militant below. We hear <hi>Eliſha</hi> pathetically mourning the Departure of the old illuſtrious Prophet: As he ſaw him aſcend in a Chariot of Fire, carry'd up by a Whirlwind into Heaven, he rent his Clothes, and with the Paſſion of a bereaved Son cried after him, <hi>My
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:004140_0011_1003DB06532D4D40"/>
Father, my Father, the Chariot of Iſrael and the Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thereof!</hi> — However, he did not long ſtand gazing up into Heaven: but preſently taking up the Mantle of <hi>Elijah,</hi> that had fallen from him at his ſudden Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and welcoming this deſirable Memorial of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared Father, the viſible Badge of his Office, and a happy Pledge of his inheriting the Bleſſing that had been promis'd him, he goes forth in the Spirit of <hi>Elias</hi> to enter into his Labours, and goes on his way crying after the GOD of his Maſter, and walking in the Steps of his Faith. That is now his ſolicitous Inquiry, <hi>Where is the Lord God of</hi> Elijah? Not ſatisfied with having <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Mantle, he muſt have <hi>Elijah</hi>'s GOD too, in the ſenſible Effects of his powerful and gracious <hi>Preſence</hi> with him (the ſame as had been with his holy Predeceſſor) which wou'd abundantly make Amends for the Loſs he was mourning under, be the moſt effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Relief to his ſorrowful Heart, the beſt Help to him in the important Work now devolv'd upon him, and an encouraging Preſage of his future Uſefulneſs.— He do's not employ himſelf in a fruitleſs Search for <hi>Elijah</hi>; like the Sons of the Prophets, who cou'd not believe his bodily Tranſlation to Heaven, but ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining that his <hi>dead</hi> Corpſe might be dropt upon ſome remote Mountain, or rather perhaps that he was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported <hi>alive</hi> to ſome diſtant obſcure Place, and (if ſo) ought ſtill to retain his Dignity and Station, as Head of the Prophets, would not be reſtrained from going in Queſt after him. Nor do's he lay out any Thought or Pains in curious Speculations upon the inviſible World and hidden Life, the Prophet was exalted to: nor in paſſionate Aggravations of his own and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Loſs, by the Departure of ſo eminent a Man of God. Neither do we hear any raſh Wiſhes for his Return; much leſs any idolatrous Application to him for his Favour and Help: No, tho' <hi>Elijah</hi> be in a State of Exaltation, a glorious and happy Saint, made like
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:004140_0012_1003DB0958E02230"/>
unto the Angels, yet <hi>Eliſha</hi> knows better than to pay him Divine Honours, or place him in God's ſtead. But well aware that his Help is in the Name of the Lord, and hoping to find him a very preſent Help, he looks off from the Creature, unto the Creator, who is bleſſed for ever, and who will cauſe the Bleſſing to reſt upon them, that wait for him. He aſks not for <hi>Elijah,</hi> but inquires after his GOD. <hi>Where is the LORD God of</hi> Elijah? Or, as it may be read, <hi>Where is Jehovah, the God of</hi> Elijah, <hi>even He</hi>! The Hebrew Words (APH HU) which our Verſion joyns to the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Clauſe, as ſpoken of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> ſtand in the Original connected with the Words foregoing, and are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by learned Criticks as adding an Emphaſis to <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s Queſtion, <hi>Where is the LORD, the God of</hi> Elijah, <hi>even He, Himſelf?</hi> 'Tis not the Language of Infidelity or Diffidence, the Expoſtulation of an unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving or doubting Soul, that queſtion'd the Being of <hi>Elijah</hi>'s God, diſputed his Omnipreſence, or ſuſpected his Power or Faithfulneſs to accompliſh the great and precious Promiſe <hi>Eliſha</hi> had lately received: But rather 'tis the humble and earneſt Expectation and Prayer of Faith, That <hi>Elijah</hi>'s God would be with his ſurviv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Son and Succeſſor, and now give an early Proof of <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Spirit being come upon him (according to his own former Wiſh, and the departed Prophet's Farewel-Benediction) in a double Portion of Gifts, Graces, and Bleſſings.</p>
            <p>Our Text may receive ſome Illuſtration by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring it with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.11,—17. (underſtanding <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be ſpeaking there) <hi>Then he remembred the Days of old,</hi> Moſes <hi>and his People</hi> (recollected and reaſon'd upon the Story) <hi>ſaying, WHERE IS HE that brought them up out of the Sea, with the Shepherd of his Flock? WHERE IS HE that put his holy Spirit within him? That led them by the right hand of</hi> Moſes, <hi>with his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Arm, dividing the Water before them, to make Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:004140_0013_1003DB1017BA4F70"/>
an everlaſting Name?— Look down from Heaven: — WHERE is thy Zeal and thy Strength, the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thy Bowels and of thy tender Mercies towards me? Are they reſtrained? Doubtleſs Thou art our Father, tho'</hi> Abraham <hi>be ignorant of us,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou Lord, art our Father, our Redeemer, thy Name is from Everlaſting. O Lord, return for thy Servants ſake, the Tribes of thine Inheritance.</hi> 'Tis the Church's Complaint of God's viſible Withdraw from his People, and a paſſionate Supplication for the Return of his favourable Preſence; back'd with a Plea from their Forefathers Experience of the Divine Power and Mercy in commanding glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Deliverances for them: the Remembrance of which they now improve to encourage their Faith and embolden their Hope in the preſent Day of Darkneſs and Diſtreſs. So <hi>Gideon,</hi> when the Angel of the Lord appeared to him, ſaying, <hi>The LORD is with thee, thou mighty Man of Valour</hi>; made that Reply, <hi>Oh my Lord,</hi> if the <hi>LORD be with us, why then is all this befallen us? and WHERE be all his Miracles, which our Fathers told us of?</hi> (Judg. 6.13.) As if he had ſaid, Where is the Lord God of our Fathers? Where are the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of his powerful and gracious Preſence? We ſee awful Signs of his Departure from us: but where are the happy Pledges of his Return to us! So the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.9, 10. <hi>Awake, awake, put on Strength, O Arm of the LORD: awake as in the ancient Days, in the Generations of old. Art thou not it that cut Rahab, and wounded the Dragon? Art thou not it which hath dried the Sea; that hath made the Depths of the Sea a Way for the Ranſomed to paſs over?</hi> — Thus in like manner <hi>Eliſha,</hi> under a deep Concern upon the awful Frown of Heaven in taking away <hi>Elijah</hi> (who had been a Prophet mighty in Word and Deed before all the People, a Father to him and to all the other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Religion and Sons of Learning, and an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Means of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Defence and Safety) and now
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:004140_0014_1003DB156658C9A8"/>
upon his Return to the Buſineſs of his Station, having the River <hi>Jordan</hi> in his Way, which he knew not how to get over, takes the Mantle of <hi>Elijah,</hi> and ſmites the Waters, crying out, <hi>Where is the Lord, the God of</hi> Elijah, <hi>even HE?</hi> — One notes upon it, "There are the <hi>Remains</hi> of great and good Men, which (like this Mantle) ought to be gather'd up and preſerv'd by Survivors; their Sayings, their Writings, their Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: that as <hi>their Works follow them</hi> in the Reward of 'em, they may ſtay behind with us in the Benefit of 'em. But what will it profit, what will it avail us, to have the <hi>Mantles</hi> of thoſe that are gone, their Places, their Books, their Patterns, if we have not their <hi>Spirit,</hi> and their <hi>God?"</hi> — We ſhould ſet our ſelves with a careful Hand to gather up whatever (in any kind) has fallen from our pious Predeceſſors, that may be of Uſe to us: but above all we ſhou'd make <hi>the Lord their God</hi> our Choice, and his gracious <hi>Preſence</hi> our Heart's Deſire, our ſpeedy and conſtant Purſuit. Thus <hi>Eliſha</hi> contented not himſelf with crying after <hi>Elijah,</hi> My Father, my Father! and taking up his Mantle: But proceeds to call upon his God, and cry after Him, <hi>Where is the LORD, the God of</hi> Elijah, <hi>even HE?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we may obſerve diſtinctly;</p>
            <p n="1">I. He inquires for JEHOVAH. — <hi>Where is the LORD?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being inſtructed by his Maſter <hi>concerning the Name of the LORD,</hi> and having often heard him call upon JEHOVAH, that <hi>great Name</hi> of his God; <hi>Eliſha</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows his Faith, adores the bleſſed God by the ſame exalted Name, aſks the ſpecial Tokens of his Preſence, and covets a more improv'd Acquaintance and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Him. He profeſſes his Belief in the One living and true God: implicitly renouncing <hi>Baal</hi> and every Idol; for he knew, that an Idol is Nothing in the World, and that there is none other God but One,
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:004140_0015_1003DB173348DC48"/>
               <hi>whoſe Name alone is</hi> JEHOVAH<note n="*" place="bottom">This ſingular Name JEHOVAH, which is in the Text, and throughout the Old Teſtament, tranſlated into our Language by the Word LORD (ever put in Capitals) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to GOD, and to GOD only. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.18. — Some obſerve, "The <hi>Heathen</hi> are thought to have us'd it for their ſupreme GOD with a little Variation from their <hi>Jo—ve,</hi> as they, in one <hi>Caſe,</hi> call their <hi>Jupiter,</hi> whom we call <hi>Jove</hi> in Engliſh, which is reckoned to be but a Contrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our <hi>Jehovah.</hi> And ought we not to let them know, Our <hi>Bible</hi> gives an Account of the <hi>Jehove,</hi> or <hi>Jehovah</hi> of whom the moſt famous of their Anceſtors had ſome dark Notices; imploying our beſt Intereſt and Influence that we may draw 'em to regard it"?—TRIN. of the Bible, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Leigh</hi>'s Crit. Sac.</note>. This is that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable Name, by which the moſt High has made Himſelf known, and ſtands diſtinguiſh'd from all other gods, who are very Vanity, and can neither give nor receive a Bleſſing. Whereas JEHOVAH (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Idea included in his Name) is an abſolute eternal unchangeable Eſſence, Self-exiſtent, and Self-ſufficient, and therefore All-ſufficient; having infinite Power, Perfection and Bleſſedneſs in Himſelf: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fountain of all created Nature, Exiſtence, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence, Operation and Enjoyment. It's of the ſame Import with his Name JAH (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.4.) and EHJEH (<hi>Exod.</hi> 3.14.) I AM. — For He alone properly <hi>IS:</hi> and in Compare with Him all Things, as well in Heaven above, as in Earth below, may be called Things that <hi>are not.</hi> He is the Being of Beings, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, inviſible, uncreated, everlaſting, immenſe, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable, incomprehenſible, independent, neceſſary; the firſt Cauſe and laſt End of all other Beings; the adequate and ſole Object of religious Worſhip and of Happineſs to the reaſonable Creature; and a God in Covenant with his People, true and ſtedfaſt for ever, willing and able and faithful to give Being to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and Birth to the Purpoſes of His Will. He that cometh unto God, muſt believe that <hi>He IS,</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:004140_0016_1003DB18F4353048"/>
that He is a <hi>Rewarder</hi> of them which <hi>diligently ſeek</hi> Him<note n="†" place="bottom">"As to the Import of the Name JEHOVAH, it conſiſts of <hi>Signs</hi> which attend the Paſt, the Preſent, and the Future Time in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> as has been remark'd by learned Men. <hi>JE</hi> in this Name is a Note of the Time <hi>to come; HO</hi> of the Time <hi>preſent; VAH</hi> of the Time <hi>paſt</hi>: And is as much as to ſay, <hi>He who is, and was, and is to come.</hi>—This Name is alſo taken Notice of, as made up of <hi>Letters</hi> all call'd <hi>Quieſcent</hi> or reſting ones in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Tongue: and as thereby pointing us to obſerve, That there is <hi>no Reſt ſhort of JEHOVAH</hi>; but all Reſt, Peace, Quiet and Satisfaction to be had richly, from Him, in and with Him.— This Name refers us, as is agreed on all hands, to One who has his Being from no other, and gives Being unto all Things; and among the reſt, to his Words of Promiſe and of Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, by bringing Things to paſs according to them"—<hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>NOTE, <hi>The Majeſty of Heaven is to be adored by his Name</hi> JEHOVAH, <hi>and by this Name we are to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after the true God: encouraging our Faith and Hope, while we ſeek Him, from the Conſideration of his immenſe Beings abſolute Perfection, and infinite Suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He challenges this Name as His appropriate Glory, and expects to be known and acknowledg'd by it. God ſpake to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſaid unto him, <hi>"I am the LORD:</hi> and I appeared unto <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> by the Name of <hi>God Almighty</hi>; and by <hi>my Name JEHOVAH was I</hi> (comparatively) <hi>not known to them.</hi> Wherefore ſay unto the Children of Iſrael, <hi>I am the LORD: and ye ſhall know that I am the LORD your God. THIS is my Name for ever, and this is my Memorial unto all Generations.</hi> See now that <hi>I, even I, am He; and there is no God with Me.</hi>— So he ſpeaks by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah; "I am the LORD</hi>; that is <hi>my Name:</hi> and <hi>my Glory</hi> will I not give to another. Ye are my Witneſſes, ſaith the LORD, and my Servant whom I have choſen; that ye may know and believe <hi>Me,</hi> and underſtand that I AM HE: <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="unknown:004140_0017_1003DB1D6045BBE8"/>
Me there was no God formed, neither ſhall there be <hi>after Me. I, even I, am the LORD.</hi> I am <hi>the Firſt,</hi> and I am <hi>the Laſt,</hi> and <hi>beſides Me</hi> there is no God; <hi>I know not any.</hi>— So He hath ſaid by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah:</hi> "The LORD is the <hi>true God,</hi> He is the <hi>living God,</hi> and an <hi>everlaſting King.</hi> The Gods that have not made the Heavens and the Earth, even they ſhall periſh. The Portion of <hi>Jacob</hi> is <hi>not like them:</hi> the LORD of hoſts is <hi>his Name.</hi> "Thus ſaith the LORD, let him that glorieth, glory in this, that he <hi>underſtandeth</hi> and <hi>knoweth ME,</hi> that <hi>I am the LORD,</hi> which exerciſe Lovingkindneſs, Judgment and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in the Earth: for in theſe Things I delight, ſaith the LORD.</p>
            <p>JEHOVAH is the tremendous Name, which ſtands at the Head of the <hi>Ten Commandments.</hi> "God ſpake all theſe Words, ſaying, <hi>I am the LORD.</hi> — This proclaims Him the only proper Object of Divine Homage and religious Service, enforces our Obedience to Him, awakens a holy Fear in us, invites our Faith and Love, and animates our Hope of a gracious Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Reward. It is written, "Thou ſhalt <hi>fear</hi> the LORD<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Him only ſhalt thou <hi>ſerve,</hi> and to Him ſhalt thou <hi>cleave,</hi> and <hi>ſwear</hi> by his Name,—"Hear, O Iſrael, The LORD our God is one LORD: and thou ſhalt <hi>love</hi> the LORD thy God with all thine Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Might. — <hi>"Know</hi> that the LORD thy God, He is <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>faithful</hi> God, which keepeth Covenant and Mercy with them that love Him and keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. — "Thou ſhalt remember the LORD thy God.— Thou ſhalt not go after <hi>other gods:</hi> for the LORD thy God is a jealous God. — <hi>Sanctify</hi> the LORD God in your Heart.— "If you do <hi>return unto the LORD</hi> with all your Heart, then <hi>put away ſtrange gods,</hi> and <hi>prepare your Heart</hi> unto the LORD, and ſerve Him <hi>only.</hi>— <hi>"Seek</hi> the LORD, while He
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:004140_0018_1003B88C513E5268"/>
may be found.—— "And when thou ſhalt ſeek the LORD thy God, thou ſhalt find Him, if thou <hi>ſeek Him with all thy Heart</hi> and <hi>with all thy Soul.</hi>— "Take Heed to thy ſelf that thou be not ſnared by following the Way of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and that thou <hi>inquire not after their gods.</hi>— "The Lord will be terrible unto them; for He will famiſh all the gods of the Earth: and Men ſhall <hi>worſhip</hi> HIM, every one from his place.— "I will ſtretch out mine Hand, ſaith the LORD, and will cut off the Remnant of <hi>Baal,</hi> and them that are turned back from the LORD, and thoſe that have <hi>not ſought the LORD, nor inquired for him.</hi>— "Thus ſaith the LORD to the Houſe of Iſrael, <hi>Seek ye ME,</hi> and ye ſhall live: But ſeek not <hi>Bethel.— Seek HIM</hi> that maketh the ſeven Stars and Orion: <hi>The LORD is His Name.</hi>— "Break up your fallow Ground: for it is Time to <hi>ſeek</hi> the LORD, till He come and rain Righteouſneſs upon You. Even the LORD God of Hoſts, the LORD <hi>is his Memorial:</hi> Therefore <hi>turn thou to thy God; keep Mercy and Judgment, and wait on thy God continually.</hi>— "Thus ſaith the LORD, <hi>Stand ye in the Ways and ſee, and aſk for the old Paths, where is the good Way, and walk therein, and ye ſhall find Reſt for your Souls.</hi> — "Thus ſaith the LORD, What Iniquity have your Fathers found in Me, that they are <hi>gone far from Me,</hi> and walked after Vanity? Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid they, <hi>WHERE is the LORD?</hi> The Prieſts ſaid not, <hi>WHERE is the LORD?</hi> and they that handle the Law, <hi>knew me not.</hi>— "But in the laſt Days it ſhall come to paſs, that many Nations ſhall come and ſay, Come and let us go up to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the LORD: for all People will walk every one in the Name of his god, and we will walk in <hi>the Name of the LORD</hi> our God for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>The Name of the LORD is <hi>the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> the <hi>Three that bear Record in Heaven, and theſe Three are One.</hi> We
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:004140_0019_1003DB2409DB73E8"/>
are baptiz'd into this Name, and in this Name of our God we are to walk: living a Life of Dependence upon Him, Devotedneſs to Him, and Communion with Him. We muſt be inquiring after and ſeeking the LORD in all his Ways, Ordinances and Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. That muſt continually be the Queſtion with us, <hi>WHERE is the LORD?</hi> His gracious Preſence muſt be our principal Aim and Deſire, as that in which lies all our Safety, Proſperity, Glory and Happineſs. <hi>"Bleſſed</hi> is the Man, O LORD, whom Thou chuſeſt and cauſeſt to <hi>approach unto Thee.</hi> "The LORD is my Shepherd; <hi>I ſhall not want:</hi> Yea, tho' I walk through the Valley of the Shadow of Death, <hi>I will fear no Evil</hi>; for <hi>Thou art with me.</hi> "The LORD is a <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Shield,</hi> He will give <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>no good Thing will He withold</hi> from them that walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly.— <hi>To whom ſhould we go but to HIM?</hi> Nor <hi>need</hi> we enquire after any other god: for He is able to do for us exceeding abundantly above all that we aſk or think. If JEHOVAH be his Name, what may we not expect from his favourable Preſence! Thus He ſaith, "Fear not, <hi>I am with thee.</hi> "Behold, I am the LORD: <hi>Is there any Thing too hard for Me?</hi> Verily, the Lovingkindneſs of the LORD is better than Life: and his Wrath worſe than Death. Who knoweth the Extent of his Goodneſs, or the Power of his Anger!— Let all the Inhabitants of the Earth venerate this great and terrible Name JEHOVAH, and tremble at his Preſence; for our God is a conſuming Fire, and who can ſtand before Him whence once He is angry! Cleanſe your Hands and Hearts, ye Sinners: Humble your ſelves in the Sight of the LORD: Stand in Awe, and ſin not: Draw nigh to Him, and He will draw nigh to You: Lift up your Souls to Him, and not to lying Vanities; Seek the LORD, and his Strength: Seek his Face evermore. And let the Heart of them that ſeek the LORD, be joyful. Ye <hi>Saints,</hi> glory in
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:004140_0020_1003B88FF027B688"/>
his holy Name: Extol Him that rideth upon the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens by his Name JAH, and rejoyce before Him. But ſerve the LORD with Fear, and rejoyce with Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling: for with Him is dreadful Majeſty, and He is terrible out of his holy Places.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Pharaoh</hi> may inſult and ſay, Who is the LORD, that I ſhou'd obey Him? But let <hi>Iſrael</hi> humbly ſubmit and ſay, Whatſoever the LORD commandeth, that will we do, and will be obedient. If <hi>Laban</hi> conſults his <hi>Teraphim,</hi> and bows down to graven Images; yet let <hi>Jacob</hi> ſeek JEHOVAH, and put away all ſtrange gods, pay his Vows to the LORD, and ſerve him only. Let the Prophets, which eat at <hi>Jezebel</hi>'s Table, follow <hi>Baal,</hi> and call on the Name of their Idol: But let <hi>Elijah</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the LORD, follow Him fully, and call on the Name of JEHOVAH. Let the Children of this World truſt in the Abundance of their Wealth, and make Gold their Confidence: But let the Children of Light truſt in the living God, make the LORD their Hope, and ſtay themſelves upon JEHOVAH, with whom is everlaſting Strength, and in whoſe Favour is Life. Acquaint now thy ſelf with Him, and be at Peace: thereby Good ſhall come unto thee. Under afflictive Loſſes, make it your Inquiry, <hi>Where is the LORD?</hi> Let none be heard ſaying, "They have taken away my gods, and what have I more! "Many there be that ſay, Who will ſhew us any Good? Their Inquiries are, "What ſhall we eat? and what ſhall we drink? and wherewith ſhall we be cloathed? Where is there a good Bargain to be got? Where is Mirth to be had? Which way ſhall we come to Honour? Thus they are full of the Cares and Cries of Nature and Paſſion. <hi>But none of them ſaith, WHERE is God my Maker</hi>? That's the Cry of Grace, "My Soul thirſteth for God, the living God: <hi>when ſhall I come and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before God"?</hi>— "O that I knew <hi>where I might find Him!</hi>— "Whom have I in <hi>Heaven but Thee?</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="unknown:004140_0021_1003DB281CA8C6D8"/>
and there is <hi>none</hi> upon <hi>Earth</hi> that <hi>I deſire beſides Thee.</hi> Lo, they that are <hi>far from Thee ſhall periſh:</hi> But it is <hi>good for me</hi> to <hi>draw near to God.</hi> — Such ſhould be the ardent Breathings of Faith, Love, and Deſire in our Souls toward JEHOVAH. We ſhould be daily ſeeking and aſking for Him; having our Eyes ever to the LORD, deprecating his Departure from us, and deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Preſence with us. We ſhou'd make it our Concern that our Fellowſhip may be with the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt, whoſe Name is JEHOVAH. We ſhou'd delight in approaching to Him: and Him we ſhou'd acknowledge in all our Ways. In the Day of Proſperity we ſhou'd bleſs the Lord as the Author of all our Mercies: and in the Day of Adverſity we ſhou'd conſider his Hand, and inquire wherefore He contendeth with us. Under all the Troubles of Life and Apprehenſions of Death, we ſhou'd be <hi>inquiring early after the LORD our God.</hi> When Religion is dying, we ſhou'd cry, <hi>Where is the LORD</hi>? and pray, <hi>Help LORD,</hi> when <hi>the godly Man ceaſeth.</hi> Under our moſt ſorrowful Bereavements we ſhou'd remember, <hi>The LORD liveth</hi>; and whoever dies and leaves us, ſtill JEHOVAH is nigh to them that ſeek Him, and is the ſame Yeſterday, to Day, and for ever. Tho' even an <hi>Elijah</hi> forſakes us; yet in this we may be confident, if the LORD his God and our God be with us, we ſhall have our Loſs abundantly compenſated. On ſuch an Occaſion then let Survivors be inquiring after the LORD God of <hi>Elijah.</hi>— Which brings me to obſerve, in the next place,</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Eliſha</hi> inquires for <hi>Jehovah,</hi> as the GOD of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah.— WHERE is the Lord GOD of</hi> Elijah, <hi>even He?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It mayn't be amiſs to premiſe here, that the Majeſty of Heaven is in our Text and many other Scriptures ſtiled JEHOVAH ELOHIM: upon which judicious Criticks have obſerv'd, that the <hi>ſingular</hi> Name <hi>Jehovah</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="unknown:004140_0022_1003DB30C6596978"/>
repreſents the Deity to us as <hi>One,</hi> while that of <hi>Elohim,</hi> being <hi>plural,</hi> repreſents Him as <hi>More</hi>; and <hi>Jehovah</hi> being join'd with <hi>Elohim,</hi> this perhaps is deſign'd to engage our Attention to what <hi>both</hi> ſuggeſt at one and the ſame time, The <hi>Unity of Eſſence</hi> and the <hi>Plurality of Perſons</hi> in the Godhead. We are not to take <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah Elohim</hi> in our Text as intending the <hi>Father</hi> only; however it may mean Him primarily, yet is not to be underſtood <hi>excluſively</hi> of the <hi>Son</hi> and the <hi>holy Ghoſt.</hi> Nor is <hi>Jehovah Elohim</hi> to be underſtood <hi>Jehovah</hi> ONE of the <hi>Elohim,</hi> but we fitly read it <hi>the LORD GOD,</hi> the ſacred <hi>THREE which are ONE. Eliſha</hi> cries out, <hi>Where is the LORD GOD of</hi> Elijah?</p>
            <p>Let it be more particularly remark'd:</p>
            <p n="1">1. He aſſerts, that <hi>Jehovah</hi> is GOD, <hi>the</hi> GOD. <hi>Eliſha</hi> might now have in his Thoughts what had happen'd in a late notable Controverſy between <hi>Elijah</hi> and his Adverſaries, upon that grand Queſtion, <hi>WHO is God? Elijah</hi> reprov'd all the People, ſaying, "How long halt ye between two Opinions? If JEHOVAH be <hi>God,</hi> follow Him: but if <hi>Baal,</hi> then follow him.— And finally he put the Diſpute upon this Iſſue, "Call ye on the name of <hi>your gods,</hi> and I will call on the Name of JEHOVAH; And He ſhall be the God that anſwereth by Fire; <hi>He</hi> [Hu, the ſame, Himſelf] <hi>the</hi> GOD!— And when all the People ſaw the Fire of the LORD fall upon <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Sacrifice, they humbled themſelves before the Prophet, and own'd their full Conviction, crying out, in that vehement and repeated Exclamation, JEHOVAH <hi>Himſelf the</hi> ELOHIM! <hi>The</hi> LORD, <hi>He</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">In the Original the Word is HU; which, ſome think, is one of the <hi>Names</hi> of God: But moſt Expoſitors judge it only a common Pronoun, and read it. <hi>He, Himſelf,</hi> or the ſame.—<hi>Dominus ipſe Deus.</hi> 1 Kin. 18.39.</note> is <hi>the</hi> God! It ſeems an <hi>Adoration</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:004140_0023_1003DB324A95E278"/>
like that of the Apoſtle <hi>Thomas,</hi> when in a Tranſport of Love and Joy, he broke out in that Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to the riſen Jeſus, <hi>My LORD and my GOD!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Import of <hi>Elohim</hi> or GOD, I take it not to be a mere <hi>relative</hi> Word, or a Term of <hi>Office</hi> only, ſignifying a kind Providence and Dominion, as ſome wou'd carry it, and properly applicable to created Rulers and Benefactors: But I look upon it to be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of an <hi>abſolute</hi> Signification (like the Word <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi>) and according to the Uſe of it in Scripture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and ſtrictly it denotes the ſupreme Being, under the Character of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> including the Idea of infinite Perfection, neceſſary Exiſtence, and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency. The original and genuine Meaning of the Word, I conclude, may be beſt learnt from the Uſe of it in ſuch Texts as thoſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.2. <hi>Say to the Prince of</hi> Tyrus, <hi>Thou art a</hi> MAN, <hi>and not</hi> GOD. So <hi>Num.</hi> 23.19. GOD <hi>is not a</hi> MAN, <hi>that He ſhould lie; neither the Son of Man, that He ſhould repent.</hi> And <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.9. <hi>I will not execute the Fierceneſs of mine Anger; for I am</hi> GOD, <hi>and not</hi> MAN. There's an obſervable and beautiful <hi>Antitheſis</hi> in theſe ſeveral Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which muſt be loſt, and the Texts unintelligible, if the word GOD be properly a mere Term of <hi>Office</hi> or <hi>Relation,</hi> and not of <hi>Eſſence</hi> or <hi>Nature,</hi> as well as the word MAN. Evident it is, tint the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Human</hi> NATURES are here put in Contradiſtinction, one to the other: and while the words [<hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Son of Man</hi>] ſignify a Being created, a Nature frail, imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and very mutable, the other and oppoſite word [<hi>God</hi>] is uſed to denote a Being uncauſed and eternal, a Nature abſolutely and immutably perfect, infinitely good and glorious and bleſſed in it ſelf, and for ever independent; which, upon a little Reflection, will be found Ideas eſſentially connected with, and inſeparable from the Character of <hi>Almighty.</hi> ELOHIM then, in the true, original, and complex Notion of the Word, is
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:004140_0024_1003DB33CF65FC70"/>
a Name appropriate to JEHOVAH. Indeed there is a conſequential, ſubordinate and ſecondary Notion, in which the Term may be us'd ſometimes, <hi>viz.</hi> that of a <hi>Ruler</hi> and <hi>Benefactor</hi>; for theſe Characters are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily included in the Idea of <hi>God Almighty:</hi> And by way of Analogy even Creatures, Angels and Men, are in that View of the Word ſometimes called <hi>Elohim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But however, it primarily imports the OMNIPOTENT, the Supreme and Firſt Cauſe: and is a Name not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable to any Creature, but in a <hi>lax, inferential,</hi> and <hi>metaphorical</hi> Uſe of the Word. JEHOVAH, even He alone is GOD, in the proper Application and ſtrict Senſe of the Term. None other are Gods <hi>by Nature</hi>; but are <hi>falſely ſo called,</hi> or figuratively, alluſively, and in the conſequential Notion of the Word: for none are really and properly Gods, if not ſo <hi>by Nature.</hi> Unto us there is but <hi>One God</hi>; but one Being that is eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and truly God: Yet this ONE is (ineffably) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>how THREE, variouſly denominated, <hi>the Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt.</hi> (1 Joh. 5.7.) Natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is capable of ſtrongly arguing the UNITY of the Godhead: but ſupernatural Revelation makes the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſcovery of a TRINITY <hi>in Unity.</hi> The holy Scripture makes thoſe <hi>Perſonal</hi> Attributions to the ſacred THREE, which manifeſtly infer their different Modes of Subſiſtence: and yet it aſcribes all Divine Perfections and Honours equally to them all, which as manifeſtly infers their being <hi>One</hi> in Eſſence. Not only the <hi>Father,</hi> but the <hi>Son</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> likewiſe, are called GOD in the genuine, abſolute, ſublime Senſe of the Word, without any ſpecial Limitation, without any Signatures of a figurative Uſe, or a diminutive and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Senſe deſign'd. All the eſſential Characters of GOD are attributed to the <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> in the ſame Heights of Language as to the <hi>Father,</hi> without any apparent Marks of Diſtinction; even thoſe peculiar Glories, which the ſupreme Being has ever challeng'd
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:004140_0025_1003DADE19CA14D0"/>
as his ſole Prerogatives, whereby He will be known and diſtinguiſh'd from <hi>all that is called God</hi> beſides, whether in Heaven or Earth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.8. <hi>I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the ending, ſaith the Lord, which is, and which was, and which is to come, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</hi> When therefore the Law of the LORD ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhall have no other gods before me,</hi> it is to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted as excluſive of Idols, and every mere Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but ſtill as incluſive of the <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> who together with the <hi>Father</hi> are the one Object of Faith, Devotion and Obedience. "Know ye, that the LORD, He is GOD. "This is the <hi>true God and eternal Life.</hi> "There is none <hi>good</hi> but <hi>One,</hi> that is GOD: and if thou will enter into Life, keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments. "Behold, the Lord GOD ſaith, I come quickly, and my Reward is with Me. "I am <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the Beginning and the End, the Firſt and the Laſt. "I <hi>Jeſus</hi> have ſent mine Angel to teſtify unto You theſe Things in the Churches.—And ſince we hear theſe Things, let it not be ſaid of us, as it is of ſome, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21. <hi>That when they knew GOD, they glorified Him not as GOD, neither were thankful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to obſerve,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Eliſha</hi> aſſerts <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Intereſt in JEHOVAH, and ſpecial Relation to Him, as the Lord <hi>his</hi> GOD.— <hi>Where is the Lord God of</hi> Elijah?</p>
            <p>For Explication of this it muſt be noted: Since the very Names <hi>JEHOVAH Elohim</hi> carry in them an Idea of abſolute Perfection, of eternal Power, and of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Goodneſs and Happineſs, hence when the ſupreme Being is ſaid to be <hi>Jehovah Elohim</hi> to a Perſon or Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it means his being That <hi>unto them,</hi> which He is <hi>in Himſelf,</hi> his ſhewing them his Glory, cauſing his Goodneſs to paſs before them, and giving them to ſee and enjoy Him <hi>as GOD.</hi>—They that make the Term <hi>God</hi> a mere Term of <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Relation,</hi> have contriv'd to fix their narrow and low Idea on the
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:004140_0026_1003DB39CAE51BB8"/>
Word with a View to the weakning and eluding an eminent Scripture-Argument for the true and proper Divinity of our <hi>Saviour</hi> and the <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> from one Place and another where they are expreſly called <hi>God.</hi> But now if we attend to the conſtant univerſal Uſe of the Word in Scripture, as apply'd to the <hi>Firſt Cauſe,</hi> we ſhall find it an <hi>eſſential</hi> Name, and carrying no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more of Relation or Office in it, than there is in the Name <hi>Jehovah.</hi> Words indeed of an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Signification may put on a relative Form, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing connected with Pronouns poſſeſſive, as <hi>My, Thy,</hi> &amp;c. But ſtill the primary Signification is retain'd, and is well conſiſtent with this Uſe of the Words. Thus, when God ſaith, "I will be <hi>thy God",</hi> it means <hi>(Ero tibi in Deum)</hi> I will expreſs the GOD <hi>to thee:</hi> which is but in other Words to ſay, I will be to thee <hi>the Almighty, the All-ſufficient</hi> (I will ſhew my ſelf JEHOVAH ELOHIM to thee) will act the Part of the <hi>Lord God Omnipotent</hi> towards thee, in performing my Promiſes to thee, and ſecuring to thee a perfect Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in the way of the Goſpel-Covenant. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, when the Lord is call'd <hi>the God</hi> of any, it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates his being their <hi>Covenant-God,</hi> in and through Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator, and his ſetting his Heart as the Heart of GOD upon them, his exhibiting the <hi>Divine Nature</hi> to them in agreable and bleſſed Effects, his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing the Character of GOD (an infinitely and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table perfect and mighty Being) in his tender Care of them, and wiſe and powerful Operations for their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and his own Glory from them, according to the Tenour of that gracious Covenant, into which He has taken them: and on their part, it implies their being under Covenant-Obligations to Him, owning Him in the Character of GOD, revering his Perfections, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing due Acknowledgements to Him, and ſeeking their Happineſs in Him, <hi>as</hi> GOD, who is above all, bleſſed for evermore.— Thus, the LORD GOD of <hi>Elijah</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="unknown:004140_0027_1003DB41B2D4BDB8"/>
(in our Text) means the ſupreme Being conſider'd as <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Covenant-God, his choſen Portion, his avouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sovereign, and the Object of his Worſhip, Faith and Hope, in Oppoſition to <hi>Baal,</hi> and the Creature, which others ſerv'd: or as having acted the GOD to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Elijah,</hi> taken him into Communion with Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, own'd and honour'd him as his Servant, reveal'd Himſelf to him, ſpoken by him, call'd and furniſh'd him to the Office of a Prophet, protected and ſucceeded him in it, and finally crown'd him with a glorious Reward. In theſe Regards the bleſſed God is call'd the GOD of <hi>Elijah.</hi> Not that He is ſo call'd in Excluſion of all others, as if this were <hi>Elijah</hi>'s peculiar Privilege: for the Scripture puts the ſame Honour on many beſides. Thus we hear God call'd the Lord God of <hi>Shem,</hi> the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp;c. importing the like near Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and endeared Affection between God and them, as in the preſent Caſe. But it is to be underſtood as ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in Excluſion of the Worſhippers of <hi>Baal,</hi> and of <hi>ungodly Sinners</hi> in general.</p>
            <p>Indeed in a very large Senſe <hi>Jehovah</hi> may be call'd <hi>the God of all Fleſh,</hi> the God of the <hi>whole Earth,</hi> as He is God <hi>unto</hi> all in ſome Regards; diſplaying the Powers and Perfections of the <hi>Deity</hi> in their Creation and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and doing thoſe Things for every one, in common, which none but GOD moſt high can accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh: and as He is the only rightful Object of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Worſhip, unto all, and their alone ſatisfying Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Happineſs. But there is a tranſcendent and very peculiar Senſe in which <hi>Jehovah</hi> is call'd the GOD of <hi>Elijah,</hi> with other the faithful Saints and Servants of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Here we may diſtinguiſh, and ſay briefly,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Conſider <hi>Elijah</hi> merely as an <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> knowing and owning the true Religion, JEHOVAH might be call'd <hi>his</hi> GOD; tho' but in Common with the reſt of the profeſſing <hi>Hebrews.</hi> Tho' there was a very gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:004140_0028_1003DB43C07562C8"/>
Apoſtaſy in this Prophet's Day, inſomuch that <hi>Elijah</hi> thought himſelf almoſt <hi>left alone</hi>; yet there was a Remnant of ſome Thouſands, in ſecret Corners of the Land, who had not bow'd the Knee to <hi>Baal.</hi> Theſe were together with him under the external Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Covenant of Grace, ſeparated for a peculiar People, under a ſpecial Care of Divine Providence; and ſtood viſibly intitled to the Lord as their God. He is frequently call'd the Lord God of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> in Common. And the Caſe is the ſame with every <hi>Chriſtian</hi> People under the preſent Diſpenſation. <hi>Is He the God of the</hi> Jews <hi>only? Is He not alſo the God of the</hi> Gentiles? which in times paſt have not believed God, yet have now obtained Mercy through their Unbelief. They that in former Ages were not a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, are now the People of God and Children of the Promiſe, to whom pertaineth the Adoption, and the Glory, equally as to <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old. And God is viſibly <hi>their</hi> GOD; He is in the midſt of every Chriſtian Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by the external Symbols of his gracious Preſence, and by his holy Spirit ſtriving with them: while other Nations that have not known the true Religion, and are <hi>without Chriſt,</hi> are repreſented as <hi>having no Hope,</hi> and being <hi>without GOD in the World.</hi>— O let us admire the Condeſcention of the bleſſed God in taking any of the fallen Children of Men into a Covenant of Grace, and affording them the Signs of his favourable Preſence and Means of Salvation. <hi>What is Man, O LORD, that thou art mindful of him! and what the Son of Man, that Thou viſiteſt him!</hi>— And let us adore His Sovereignty, in the viſible Diſtinctions of His Grace, while He diſcovers Himſelf in His Goſpel to one Perſon or People, and hides his Face from others.— Let us tremble at the Apprehenſions of our awful ſtanding in God's holy Covenant, mourn our Sins as peculiarly aggravated, and reſolve upon a future Care of keeping Covenant with God, at the ſame time em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:004140_0029_1003DB4842FD8C78"/>
the Promiſes by Faith. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.17, 18. <hi>Thus ſaith the LORD thy Redeemer, the holy One of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>I am the LORD thy God which teacheth thee to profit, which leadeth thee by the way that thou ſhouldſt go. O that thou hadſt hearkned to my Commandments! then had thy Peace been as a River, and thy Righteouſneſs as the Waves of the Sea.</hi> But I proceed to obſerve,</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Conſider <hi>Elijah</hi> as an Iſraelite <hi>indeed,</hi> a truly pious and good Man; ſo the LORD was <hi>his</hi> GOD in a <hi>more ſpecial</hi> and <hi>exalted</hi> Senſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elijah</hi> was one who cleaved to the Lord with Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of Heart, when all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſeem'd to be revolted from Him; but yet there was a Remnant according to the Election of Grace: and in common with theſe, <hi>Elijah</hi> had the LORD for <hi>his</hi> GOD. There is an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate Senſe, in which He is the Lord God of his <hi>Saints,</hi> or true Believers. Real Saints have the Lord for their reconcil'd God, manifeſting Himſelf to them ſo as He does not to the World, and doing thoſe Things for their Souls, which none other can do: His moſt terrible Attributes ſpeak Friendſhip to them, and ſtand engaged for their Safety and Happineſs: He is their actual, as well as choſen Patron here, and Portion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: As they follow Him with their whole Souls, ſo He loves them and ſeeks their Good with his whole Heart, and they are kept by the Power of God thro' Faith unto Salvation: They are his Favorites in this World, and Heirs of Life in the next. Hence the Pſalmiſt's devout and joyful Soul broke forth in thoſe exulting Words (Pſal. 48.14.) <hi>This GOD is OUR God for ever and ever, He will be our Guide even unto Death.</hi> To the ſame Purpoſe that triumphant Language of the Apoſtle (Rom. 8.38.39.) <hi>I am perſwaded, that neither Death nor Life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, nor Things preſent nor Things to come, nor Height nor Depth, nor any other Creature, ſhall be able to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate us from the Love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:004140_0030_1003DB4B567AAF38"/>
Lord.</hi> Even Death itſelf, which diſſolves all natural Unions and civil Relations, yet affects not the Saints Intereſt in God, but brings their ſeparate Souls into nearer Communion with Him. When He takes them out of the World, He gathers their <hi>Spirits</hi> to Himſelf, and ſtill remains <hi>their GOD,</hi> to the moſt happy Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes: and He will ſo in regard of their outward Man too; for the Reſurrection and Happineſs of the <hi>Body</hi> is imply'd in the Lord's being <hi>their GOD,</hi> according to our Saviour's Argument, <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.37, 38.— In a Word, To have the Lord for <hi>our GOD</hi> implies (in the ſtrict and full Meaning of the Phraſe) all the Joy, Glory and Bliſs, that human Nature is capable of. Nothing on this ſide the Perfection and Bleſſedneſs of Heaven will riſe up to the juſt Import of that great and precious Promiſe, That the Lord will be <hi>our GOD.</hi> All poſſible Excellencies concentre in Him, which are his own infinite Happineſs, and will be an all-ſufficient Happineſs to the Saints in Light. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16. <hi>But now they deſire a better Country, that is, an heavenly: wherefore God is not aſhamed to be called their God: for he hath prepared for them a City.</hi> And there he will eminently diſplay the GOD unto them in a beatific Senſe. Then ſhall the Apoſtle's Prayer for the Saints receive its compleat Anſwer, Eph. 3.19. <hi>That ye may be filled with all the Fulneſs of GOD.</hi> The communicable Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of GOD ſhall be theirs intirely. Then in a very exalted and now inconceivable Senſe, they will <hi>dwell in GOD, and GOD in them,</hi> thro'out a bleſſed Eternity.</p>
            <p>Allow me here to apply this Head, in a few REFLECTIONS.</p>
            <p n="1">1. See now the infinite <hi>Obligations</hi> we are under to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the bleſſed Mediator between GOD and Man, who ſuffered for us (the Juſt for the Unjuſt) that he might bring us unto GOD, and in whom GOD is reconciling the World unto Himſelf. In and through <hi>Chriſt</hi> only it is that JEHOVAH becomes our GOD and
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:004140_0031_1003DB53C6B21C80"/>
               <hi>Father,</hi> and takes us near to Himſelf. Behold, the <hi>Lamb</hi> of God, who was deliver'd for our Offences, and raiſed again for our Juſtification, and ever liveth to make Interceſſion for us! Ye know the Grace of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>: Sing forth the Honour of his Name, and make his Praiſe glorious. Sing to Him with thankful Souls in that adoring Language (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.18.) <hi>Thou haſt aſcended on high, thou haſt led Captivity Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: thou haſt received Gifts for Men; yea, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, that the LORD God might dwell among them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Learn too the vaſt <hi>Advantage</hi> and <hi>Excellence</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and how juſtly Believers place the higheſt Value upon <hi>reveal'd Religion,</hi> that opens to us the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, and preſents the bleſſed GOD in ſuch an amiable attractive Light to his People, as <hi>their GOD</hi> in Chriſt: which is a peculiar and exalted Reflection, the moſt fruitful of beneficial and glorious Effects in them, happily influential to enlarge, refine, and ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate their Minds, and draw out their Souls toward GOD, in fervent Deſires, in ſupreme Affection and Delight, firm Affiance and humble Submiſſion, vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Hopes and rais'd Expectations, the moſt ſincere and ſolemn Self-Dedications, intire Love of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with GOD, and conſtant Care of Obedience to Him; and by all tending to miniſter abundant Peace and Conſolation to them, under the various Troubles of Life, and the awful Proſpects of Death and Eternity: far above every Dictate of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> far above all <hi>moral</hi> Conſiderations, that the mere Light of <hi>Nature</hi> in its beſt Improvements was ever able to ſuggeſt. While the moſt enlighten'd <hi>Heathen</hi> can argue but darkly about an <hi>unknown GOD,</hi> and have no ſolid and rational Aſſurance that He is <hi>their GOD, We</hi> now through Comfort of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> have <hi>Hope,</hi> a Hope that ſhall <hi>never make us aſhamed.</hi> Well may the Saints (as all real ones do) account their <hi>Bible</hi> a Treaſure, prize the Oracles of God <hi>above Thouſands of Gold and
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:004140_0032_1003DB5643C7C600"/>
Silver,</hi> make his Statutes their <hi>Songs</hi> in the Houſe of their Pilgrimage, and take his Teſtimonies as their <hi>Heritage</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To have JEHOVAH for our GOD, what greater <hi>Privilege, Honour,</hi> or <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> than this! It ſpeaks the tranſcendent Happineſs and Dignity of the <hi>Saints</hi>: and it loudly calls upon 'em to admire and magnify the diſtinguiſhing and rich Grace of God toward them, in becoming <hi>their</hi> God, and taking them into Covenant and Communion with Himſelf, when Thouſands of their Fellow-Creatures round about them (originally not greater Sinners, nor by Nature any more the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Hell, than themſelves) are periſhing without Hope and without God in the World.</p>
            <p n="4">4. How ſhou'd we admire the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of the Saints, which God giveth them? It is ſeen in the <hi>Choice,</hi> they have made for themſelves, of JEHOVAH for their GOD, who is above all gods, the ſole worthy Object of Divine Service, and the only ſatisfactory Portion of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls, an almighty Friend, able to bleſs them and make them a Bleſſing in this Life, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete their Happineſs in the next.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And if the LORD be <hi>their GOD,</hi> what a conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous and ſignal <hi>Glory</hi> does it reflect on any <hi>Place,</hi> that abounds with <hi>Righteous</hi> Ones! Surely GOD is in the midſt of it, and He will appoint Salvation for Walls and Bulwarks round about it. What is the Name by which the City of Truth, the Land of Uprightneſs, ſhall be called? The God of Truth and Grace Himſelf hath pronounced it (Ezek. 48.35.) <hi>The Name of it ſhall be, JEHOVAH-SHAMMAH, The LORD is there.</hi>— This Inſcription, moſt lovely and beautiful, was it not once ſeen, engraven in faireſt Characters, on BOSTON &amp; NEW ENGLAND! When the People of this TOWN and Land, in the Days of our firſt Generations, were as <hi>a noble Vine and wholly a right Seed,</hi> then the GOD of <hi>Bethel</hi> was eminently the GOD of <hi>Boſton</hi>; the GOD of
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:004140_0033_1003B89F45388088"/>
               <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the GOD of <hi>New England</hi>: and how <hi>honorable</hi> a Place was it, a City of Renown, the Glory of all Lands! But alas, now that we have deeply corrupted our ſelves, and the Place is filled with <hi>degenerate Plants,</hi> how is our <hi>Glory departed</hi> in a very lamentable Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and <hi>turned into Shame</hi>! Are there not evidently but <hi>few</hi> (in Compariſon) that can truly call the GOD of our Fathers <hi>their GOD</hi>! Have not Multitudes, Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, forgotten the Rock of Iſrael, and practically de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and caſt off the LORD, even the LORD, the Hope of our Fathers! And what little Reaſon then have we to expect, that He will be a GOD to us, in like manner as He was to them! If, with <hi>Ephraim</hi> of old, we ſin yet more and more, and do not return to our Fathers GOD, may we not fear the Execution of that terrible Threatning (Hoſ. 13.7, 8.) <hi>Therefore I will be unto them as a Lion; as a Leopard by the way will I obſerve them; I will meet them as a Bear bereav'd of her Whelps.</hi>— I ſhall add the encouraging Words, which follow: O Iſrael, <hi>thou haſt deſtroyed thy ſelf, but in Me is thine Help.</hi>— O Iſrael, <hi>return unto the LORD thy God: for thou haſt fallen by thine Iniquity. Take with you Words, and turn to the LORD; So I will be as the Dew unto</hi> Iſrael, <hi>he ſhall grow as the Lily, ſhall caſt forth his Roots and ſpread his Branches, his Beauty ſhall be as the Olive-Tree, and his Smell as</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon.— Let us remember, that GOD is in the Generation of the <hi>Righteous,</hi> and He will exalt them: But Woe to the Generation of his Wrath. O that we were wiſe, that we underſtood this! May the bleſſed God pour out his Spirit from on high, and revive his Work among us; that it may come to paſs, which is written, "As yet they ſhall uſe this Speech in the Land of <hi>Judah,</hi> and in the Cities thereof, <hi>The LORD bleſs thee, O Habitation of Juſtice, and Mountain of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs!</hi>— Then will Salvation be nigh to us, and Glory dwell in our Land.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="26" facs="unknown:004140_0034_1003DB5A60843418"/>6. What has been ſaid, ſhou'd teach us to <hi>love</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi>; who have the Image of GOD upon them, and a Propriety in Him as <hi>their GOD</hi>: And this Reflection ſpeaks <hi>Encouragement</hi> to ſuch as are careful in all proper Ways to ſhew their Reſpect to the <hi>Godly</hi> Man, and put Honour upon the <hi>Faithful</hi> in the Land: But it may well ſtrike <hi>Terror</hi> on ſuch as envy, hate, injure, or ſlight them. The Righteous are a <hi>People near and dear to GOD,</hi> and He hears the Reproach of <hi>Moah</hi> and the Revilings of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Ammon,</hi> while in their Pride they magnify themſelves againſt the People of the LORD of Hoſts, and the LORD will be terrible to them: howbeit, our GOD will turn the Curſe into a Bleſſing, and He will bleſs them that bleſs his People. The Time is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when He will gloriouſly plead the Cauſe of his People, and when He will make his Saints an eternal Excellency, when they ſhall be as the Stones of a Crown, lifted up as an Enſign upon his Land, and the Sinners in the Earth ſhall <hi>take hold of the Skirt of him that is a</hi> Jew, <hi>ſaying, We will go with You, for we have heard that GOD is with You.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Here's a powerful Argument, which ſhou'd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade us all to be concern'd, that we may get into the <hi>Number</hi> of the <hi>Saints,</hi> and be able to claim a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in GOD, as <hi>our</hi> GOD. We ſhould examine what Evidences we have of a Covenant-Intereſt in GOD, and vital Relation to Him as <hi>our</hi> GOD in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> O let us all look to it, that we do not <hi>fail of the Grace of GOD</hi>; that we do not fail of ſecuring this great and moſt momentous Concern: for if the LORD be not <hi>our</hi> GOD, in the Senſe of the Goſpel-Covenant, He will be a <hi>Conſuming Fire</hi> to us. That's the Doom he has paſs'd on a hypocritical Nation, (<hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.9.) <hi>Ye are not my People, and I will not he your GOD.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever falſe Profeſſors may boaſt in the LORD, and ſay, <hi>He is our GOD</hi>; yet they ſhall find at laſt, that He
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:004140_0035_1003DB6064A8C7E8"/>
will reject their Confidences, and will be a GOD to them in no other than a dreadful <hi>vindictive</hi> Senſe, a God that judgeth Sinners: Verily <hi>their GOD</hi> will come with Vengeance, to puniſh them with everlaſting De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, who have not known Him, nor obey'd his Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally,</hi> in a Word, let ſuch as have ſincerely avouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the LORD for their GOD, ſee to it, that they <hi>walk worthy of the LORD unto all Pleaſing,</hi> that they adorn their high Profeſſion by a <hi>good Converſation in Chriſt,</hi> and continually be in Care to live and act up to their ſpiritual Dignity, Privileges and Hopes; making it appear to the World, that the LORD is indeed <hi>their GOD,</hi> by exhibiting the Image of GOD upon them, a viſible Reſemblance of his moral Perfections. Let your Light ſo ſhine before Men, that they ſeeing your good Works, may glorify GOD in You: and thus ſhall Chriſt be magnify'd in your Body, whether it be by Life or Death, and in nothing ſhall you be aſhamed, but you ſhall have Hope in Death, and Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Day of Judgment, that great Day of our GOD, when He ſhall come to be glorified in his Saints, and to be admired in all them that believe.</p>
            <p>I proceed now to the other and laſt Diſtinction I had in View.</p>
            <p n="3">[3.] Conſider <hi>Elijah</hi> as a faithful <hi>Prophet</hi> and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Miniſter of Religion, ſo the LORD was <hi>his GOD</hi> in a ſtill more emphatic Senſe. Being brought very nigh to GOD, ſeparated to ſpecial Service in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of GOD by a peculiar Covenant (like that we read of, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.8. <hi>the Covenant of</hi> Levi) being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with Miniſterial Gifts and Graces in a remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Eminency, as alſo admitted to a diſtinguiſhing Intimacy of Friendſhip and Communion with the GOD of Heaven, and at the ſame time there being ſo <hi>few other</hi> faithful Prophets in the Land, that <hi>Elijah,</hi> even he <hi>only</hi> had ſeem'd to <hi>remain a Prophet of the Lord,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="unknown:004140_0036_1003DB62188D9178"/>
at leaſt in Compare with <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prophets, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in mighty Crowds at the famous Conteſt he had with them before <hi>Ahab</hi> and all the People) upon theſe Conſiderations <hi>Elijah</hi> might well have this ſingular Honour put upon him, to have the LORD called <hi>his GOD,</hi> the Lord God of <hi>Elijah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, the Scriptures put the ſame Diſtinction on many others. Thus we hear Him call'd the Lord God of <hi>Shem,</hi> the God of <hi>Aaron,</hi> the God of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and other Prophets. And this Honour is extended to the faithful Prophets in general, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.6. <hi>The LORD GOD of the holy Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this, I think, is ſafely applicable (tho' in lower Reſpects) concerning <hi>ordinary,</hi> as well as extraordinary Prophets. The faithful Miniſters of Chriſt (tho' not furniſh'd with miraculous Gifts and Powers) may be call'd <hi>holy Prophets:</hi> and it's no Preſumption to claim <hi>Elijah</hi>'s GOD for <hi>the LORD their GOD.</hi> It is obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> tho' he did not the Miracles which <hi>Elijah</hi> is famous for, yet Chriſt pronounces him <hi>more than a Prophet,</hi> greater even than <hi>Elias,</hi> who was but a Type &amp; Figure of <hi>John:</hi> yet at the ſame time he adds, <hi>Notwithſtanding, he that is leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven, is greater than he</hi>; which Paſſage (tho' judiciouſly thought by ſome to have a confin'd Reſpect, as ſpoken by Chriſt of <hi>himſelf</hi>) is apply'd by many Expoſitors as ſpoken of the leaſt Saint or the leaſt Miniſter under the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Diſpenſation; and ſo apply'd, it is true, of the <hi>faithful Miniſter</hi> eſpecially, in ſome Regards. However, Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Miniſters in common being Divinely intitled <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> we need make no Scruple of applying to the Caſe of faithful Paſtors and Teachers, that remarkable Scripture, <hi>The Lord God of the holy Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I may ſay diſtinctly, tho' very briefly,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The LORD may be call'd the GOD of Miniſters in general, as they are by their ſpecial Character and Calling <hi>Men of God</hi>; in an eminent Manner ſeparated
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:004140_0037_1003DB69745D78C8"/>
from the World, and placed as Pillars in the Houſe of the living GOD; dedicated to a peculiar Miniſtry for the Intereſt and Honour of GOD in his Church; commiſſioned in the Word of GOD, and call'd in the Providence of GOD, and by the Spirit of GOD fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd and ſpirited to their ſacred Employment; which is to manage (in GOD's Name) a Treaty of Peace with Rebel-Mankind, ſhewing Sinners the Way of Salvation, and praying them in CHRIST's Stead (as tho' GOD did beſeech 'em by us) that they would be reconcil'd to GOD; to inſtruct in the Truths of GOD, and inculcate the Precepts of GOD; to warn, reprove, exhort, and comfort the People of GOD, according to their reſpective Caſes, and according to the Tenour of the Goſpel of GOD; to adminiſter the holy Seals of GOD's Covenant; to lead in the publick Devotions to GOD; to go before his People in an Example of all holy Converſation, and a lively Walk with GOD. And thus being by their <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>Office,</hi> eminent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Religion, and peculiarly the Servants of GOD, He may very properly be call'd the LORD GOD of Evangelical Miniſters in general now, in ſome ſort as He was of <hi>Elijah</hi> and the ancient Prophets. Indeed worldly and carnally-minded vicious Miniſters, it's confeſs'd, are ſome of the worſt of Mortals; and as having corrupted the Covenant of <hi>Levi,</hi> deſerve to be abandon'd of GOD and Man: Yet while Miniſters are in Behaviour as becometh Godlineſs, however their Hearts mayn't be right with God, they are ſtill to be held in Reputation by us as being by their Station and Character <hi>Men of God,</hi> and viſibly related to GOD as in a high Senſe <hi>their GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He is the LORD GOD of his <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>faithful</hi> Miniſters in a particular Manner and in a very ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Senſe.</p>
            <p>For (in the <hi>firſt</hi> place) Such do very eminently <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge</hi> and <hi>glorify GOD</hi> as the <hi>LORD their GOD.</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="unknown:004140_0038_1003B8A0D9F9BFF0"/>
They are true and upright Witneſſes <hi>for GOD,</hi> in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe Generation, as <hi>Elijah,</hi> who was very jealous for the LORD God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and boldly ſtood up for Him againſt the Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> an apoſtate People, and an ungodly Court.— So they are much <hi>with GOD</hi>; giving themſelves to Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as well as to the Miniſtry of the Word, and having their Converſation in Heaven.— They carry about with them much of the <hi>Image</hi> of GOD, and make it the Buſineſs of their Life to bring peculiar Revenues of Glory to His <hi>Name,</hi> by paying Him their own active Homages, and by perſuading all about them into due Acknowledgements of Him. — And in Proportion to the Vigour and Activity of Grace in them and the Supply of the Spirit of Chriſt, they are in Fact ſpecial <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of promoting the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of GOD.— In theſe Regards every faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſter may be ſaluted with the ſame exalted Title, as the Apoſtle gave to his own Son in the Faith (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.11.) <hi>O MAN of GOD!</hi> And indeed the ſame Apoſtle ſeems to apply this as the genuine Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of good Miniſters in Common (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17.) <hi>That the MAN of GOD may be perfect.</hi> Surely this is ſufficient to juſtify the Application of that other Text as concerning them, <hi>The LORD GOD of the holy Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But further (in the <hi>ſecond</hi> place) Such are in very ſignal Ways <hi>own'd</hi> and <hi>honour'd</hi> of GOD, as thoſe that are his peculiar Servants, and eſpecially related to Him as the LORD <hi>their</hi> GOD. As He has call'd them to ſpecial Work, and claims a ſpecial Propriety in them: So He extends a peculiar Favour to them, and beſtows peculiar Honours upon them, expreſſing Himſelf their GOD in an emphatical Senſe many Ways. He ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd the LORD GOD of <hi>Elijah</hi> and the inſpir'd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets by Inſtances of Favour and Honour done them, which were as extraordinary as their Commiſſion and
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:004140_0039_1003DB6AFA6BD750"/>
their Gifts: But ſtill his ordinary faithful Prophets are own'd and bleſs'd of GOD in Ways more common, yet uſually remarkable, and ſometimes very Singular. They have the Special Preſence of GOD with them, in their ſeveral Meaſures. They are the ſpecial Care of his Fatherly Providence, and have holy Angels inviſibly miniſtring to them. They have the Spirit of GOD and of Glory reſting upon them, and ſupplying 'em with Divine Light, Grace, and Comfort, in various Degrees, as it pleaſeth Him, and ſometimes very admirably, in their own Senſe and in the Apprehenſion of others. How have they at ſome Seaſons experienc'd very ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently the Communion of the Holy Ghoſt, in a high Degree! How has the Spirit of Supplication been pour'd out upon 'em, that (like <hi>Elias</hi>) they have pray'd earneſtly! And how has GOD honour'd them by ſignal Anſwers of Prayer! And in pleading his Cauſe, how has He ſometimes given them a Mouth and Wiſdom, a Courage and Zeal, that the Adverſary cou'd not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt! How have their Hearts flamed out in fervent Love to Chriſt, their whole Souls been fir'd with a holy Indignation againſt Error and Wickedneſs, and their melted Bowels guſh'd out in the tendered Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions to poor periſhing Sinners! They have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times appear'd full of GOD, in their Divine Temper and Conduct: and have had GOD manifeſtly <hi>with</hi> them in their Work, ſtanding by 'em in their ſpiritual En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters, ſtrengthning them to fulfil their ſacred Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and diſtinguiſhing them by making 'em the joyful Inſtruments of ſupporting and promoting the Profeſſion, Love, and Practice of Religion, and thereby the Intereſt and Honour of GOD in the World! What conſpicuous Teſtimonies from Heaven have ſome of GOD's faithful Miniſters receiv'd, in the extraordinary Succeſs viſibly attending their Labours for the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sinners, and the Edification of Saints! And when at laſt call'd off the Stage of Time, how glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:004140_0040_1003DB729B197448"/>
have the Scenes of a holy and uſeful Life ſhut up in a ſerene and peaceful, if not joyful and triumphant Death!— Shall we not own now, that JEHOVAH is <hi>the LORD GOD of the holy Prophets,</hi> in a bleſſed tranſcendent Senſe, very viſibly in the preſent World?</p>
            <p>Yet it muſt be remember'd, even all this do's not take in the complete Scope and Intention of thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive Words, <hi>The LORD GOD of</hi> Elijah: But the Expreſſion has a further View, and reaches to <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>better</hi> and <hi>eternal</hi> World. <hi>Eliſha</hi> (in our Text) looks beyond the preſent Life, and even after the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet's <hi>Departure</hi> out of this temporal State adores God as ſtill the LORD GOD of <hi>Elijah.</hi> In Truth, 'tis eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially with an Eye to a better Country, that is, an <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly,</hi> into which the Saints are tranſlated finally, that <hi>GOD is</hi> ſaid to be <hi>not aſhamed to be called their GOD:</hi> There it is that He beſtows <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 'em perfect Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Glory, according to the full Emphaſis of this big Expreſſion. And in that bleſſed upper World holy <hi>Prophets</hi> have <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> Rewards aſſign'd them. None indeed was ever (that we know of) tranſlated thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a Chariot of Fire, and without ſeeing Death, ſave <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Enoch,</hi> and perhaps few have a greater Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Heaven: Yet every <hi>Saint</hi> arrives as ſafe, under the Conduct of good Angels, in the World of happy Spirits, tho' by the common and inferior Road of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, and every faithful <hi>Prophet</hi> meets a glorious ſignal Reward in the Manſions above. In the City of God there are different Degrees of Happineſs, a Diverſity of Privileges and Honours. And the bleſſed God will decree a very advanced Glory and Felicity to his holy Prophets, diſcriminating them in their future Recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in Proportion to the varying Meaſures of their preſent Improvements in real Holineſs, and of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Services, if not their actual Uſefulneſs in this World. <hi>Peter,</hi> an inſpired Prophet and Apoſtle, not only hopes himſelf to be a Partaker of the future Glory,
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:004140_0041_1003B8A8B13D54D8"/>
but aſſures the faithful <hi>Elders</hi> and uninſpired Prophets, that when the CHIEF SHEPHERD ſhall appear, <hi>They</hi> alſo ſhall receive a <hi>Crown of Glory</hi> which fadeth not away: and it will, as to many, be a very rich and refulgent Crown, a <hi>far more exceeding</hi> (as well as <hi>eternal)</hi> Weight of Glory. As the aſpectable Heavens in their ſeveral Parts vary to our Eye in their Degrees of Light and Splendor: So likewiſe is it with the Saints in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate State, and in the Reſurrection-World. <hi>They</hi> (ſays the Prophet) <hi>that are wiſe</hi> (wiſe to Salvation of their own Souls) <hi>ſhall ſhine as the Brightneſs of the</hi> FIR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAMENT (which is a great, yet fainter Brightneſs) <hi>and they that have turned many to Righteouſneſs</hi> (ſo approving themſelves wiſe to win others Souls) <hi>ſhall ſhine forth as the STARS</hi> (with a ſuperiour and more remarkable Luſtre) <hi>for ever and ever.</hi> The SUN of Righteouſneſs will ſhine on ſuch with his ſuperlatively ſplendid and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nign Rays: and the SAVIOUR will expreſs the GOD to them in a moſt tranſcendent Manner, by poſſeſſing them of the ſublimeſt Happineſs, and transforming them into the Image of his own Glory, with a peculiar Perfection and Eminence that ſhall put a viſible eternal Diſtinction upon them.</p>
            <p>And now the happy Thought we have been dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon, might be improv'd to a great Variety of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent practical Purpoſes, in a large APPLICATION: But I ſhall ſuggeſt only the following important Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here's Matter of Encouragement and of Awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the <hi>Children</hi> of the <hi>Prophets</hi>; I mean their <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Off-ſpring. Such are eminently Children of the <hi>Covenant:</hi> and by their Fathers very high Profeſſion, and near Relation to GOD, are themſelves alſo viſibly brought nigh to Him. The <hi>Promiſe</hi> is to them, at leaſt in common with other the Children of religious Parents; for the Bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> is come upon the believing <hi>Gentiles, I will be a GOD to Thee and to thy
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:004140_0042_1003DB7431C5A748"/>
Seed:</hi> And while they wait on the LORD, they may encourage their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> by an Application of this great and precious Promiſe. But then at the ſame time it ſhou'd awaken a holy <hi>Fear</hi> in their Souls, to conſider the awful <hi>Vows</hi> of God which are upon them.</p>
            <p>Tho' the Children of Miniſters in Goſpel-Days are not <hi>holy to the LORD,</hi> in the ſame peculiar Senſe, as were the Sons of <hi>Levi</hi> under the <hi>Moſaic</hi> Diſpenſation: yet they are ſo in a Senſe, at leaſt in that common to all Children of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Parents; ſeparated from a World lying in Wickedneſs, externally call'd with an holy Vocation, devoted to GOD as his viſible Children, and engag'd to honour Him by all <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Duty and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Yea, the <hi>Miniſter</hi>'s Standing in the Church of God (as well as the Advantage of an Education in a Family well-order'd, as his ought to be) ſeems to raiſe and increaſe the ſolemn Obligations upon <hi>his</hi> Children to a very virtuous, holy and heavenly Life. It's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> (1 Tim. 3.4.) <hi>That he rule well his own Houſe, having his Children in Subjection with all Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity</hi>; and (Tit. 1.6.) <hi>Having faithful Children:</hi> which not only ſpeaks the Parent's Obligation, but hints alſo the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi>'s Duty. As it is expected of Miniſters, that they ſhew themſelves Patterns of good Works in general, and of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Duties in particular: ſo it's expected, that <hi>their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> (above all the Families in <hi>Iſrael)</hi> be Patterns of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, Order, Unity, Sobriety, Gravity. We would then command our Houſholds to keep the Way of the LORD. O our Children, in particular, we exhort you to be <hi>faithful Children,</hi> and to labour for <hi>all Gravity,</hi> in Thought and Temper, in Speech and Behaviour. We warn and beſeech you in the Name of Chriſt and by the Love of Chriſt, ſee to it, that you do in the firſt place ſincerely chuſe and avouch the GOD of your Fathers for <hi>your GOD,</hi> and then that you <hi>walk before Him and be perfect, walk worthy of Him,</hi> and as becometh your Baptiſmal Engagements, your religious Deſcent, and
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:004140_0043_1003DB7942876E30"/>
miniſterial Parentage. Verily the Glory of GOD, the Intereſt of CHRIST, the Honour of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> the Fame of <hi>New England,</hi> the Credit and Comfort of your anxious <hi>Parents,</hi> your <hi>own</hi> Reputation and Uſefulneſs, preſent Peace and future Happineſs, and the united Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations both of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> from you, are all very weighty and forcible Arguments, conſpiring with one Voice, to demand and urge your thoughtful Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, earneſt Prayer, and active Uſe of all proper Means, that you may be found <hi>early</hi> and <hi>faithful</hi> Keepers of GOD's holy <hi>Covenant.</hi> O let that be the upright, preſent and perſevering Profeſſion and Reſolution of your Souls (Exod. 15.2.) <hi>The LORD is my GOD, and I will prepare Him an Habitation; my Fathers GOD, and I will exalt Him.</hi> Read and apply the Royal Saint's dying Charge to his Son <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 CHRON. 28.9. Together with that very quickning Word from the Mouth of your bleſſed Saviour, PROV. 8.17.— Turn down the Leaves where you find the Places in your Bible, and make theſe Texts particularly familiar to you, often and cloſely meditating upon 'em, and praying over them. O that the bleſſed SPIRIT of Grace may ſet in with the Words, and give them a powerful and laſting Impreſſion on your Souls! — And for the Direction of your general Conduct, I recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to your frequent Peruſal (among other Parts of Scripture) that very copious, the' ſhort Chapter, the Second in the Epiſtle to <hi>Titus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[And now on this Occaſion I wou'd apply what has been ſaid more particularly to <hi>my own Children,</hi> and take the Opportunity in this publick manner to leave my moſt ſolemn Charges upon them. Hear, <hi>my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren!</hi> You will eaſily believe me when I tell you, <hi>GOD is my Record, how greatly I long after you all in the Bowels of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And now I command and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort You by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, I warn and charge You now before GOD and the World, that You <hi>obſerve
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:004140_0044_1003DB7E4B122310"/>
theſe Things,</hi> and have 'em always in Remembrance: that You make it your <hi>firſt</hi> Care to <hi>win Chriſt</hi> and ſecure an Intereſt in GOD as <hi>your GOD</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and then that You govern your whole Life and Practice in a juſt Conformity to the holy Religion You profeſs; deeply concern'd, and very vigilant, <hi>that the Name of GOD and his Doctrine may</hi> never <hi>be blaſphemed through YOU.</hi> Thus You may hope for the gracious Preſence of GOD with You, which is the only Source of all true Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity. That was the Sum of <hi>David</hi>'s paſſionate Wiſh for his beloved <hi>Solomon</hi> (1 Chron. 22.11.) <hi>Now, my Son, the LORD be with thee, and proſper thou!</hi> And in the believing proſpect of this, he cou'd chearfully die, and leave him: for that was his Hope, when going the Way of all the Earth, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.20. David <hi>ſaid to</hi> Solomon <hi>his Son, Be ſtrong, and of good Courage, and do it; for the LORD God, even MY God, will be with thee, He will not fail thee, nor forſake thee.</hi>]</p>
            <p>But to proceed in our Improvement of the Point;</p>
            <p n="2">2. This affords Direction and Incentive to <hi>Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates</hi> for the Miniſtry, in their preparing for and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into it. Undoubtedly, as the Apoſtle obſerves, This is a true Saying, <hi>If any Man deſire the Office of a Biſhop</hi> (or Goſpel-Miniſter) <hi>he deſireth a GOOD Work</hi>; a Work good in <hi>it ſelf,</hi> and good in its <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency,</hi> acceptable to GOD, and profitable to Men, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful in its Nature, and happy in its <hi>future</hi> Reward. We may well think, 'tis very pleaſing in the Eyes of GOD to ſee any <hi>deſiring</hi> this Office (ſo nearly relating to His own Kingdom and Intereſt) if their Thoughts be <hi>uprightly</hi> bent upon it, as well as their Genius and Talents ſuited to it; if they have indeed given their <hi>Hearts</hi> to the LORD, taken hold of his Covenant, and choſen Him for <hi>their GOD</hi> in Chriſt: Such unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably have juſt Grounds to look on themſelves Divinely call'd to the Work, and may humbly hope in GOD<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That He will beſtow a Bleſſing on their Studies, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:004140_0045_1003DB8049D4CCC8"/>
their Furniture of Knowledge, Prudence, and other a requiſite Accompliſhments for it; That He will open a Door for their regular Entrance into it; And that He will be with them in it, to direct, aſſiſt, and happily ſucceed them. Students in Divinity ſtanding for the Evangelical Miniſtry, are not unfitly intitled <hi>Sons of the Prophets:</hi> and ſhou'd improve this their honorary Character, as loudly monitory to 'em of their incumbent Duty, to know and ſeek <hi>the LORD GOD of the holy Prophets.</hi> And they that (together with a becoming Care of Proficiency in uſeful human Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) are ſolicitous, above all their Gettings, to get neceſſary <hi>Divine</hi> Knowledge, to get an Underſtanding enlighten'd and ſanctify'd, to <hi>diſcern ſpiritual Things,</hi> and to <hi>know the Myſteries of the Kingdom of GOD,</hi> to <hi>behold the Lamb of GOD,</hi> to <hi>behold Him that is inviſible,</hi> and to <hi>know Him that is True</hi>; they that <hi>begin</hi> here, and <hi>go on</hi> with this, do very hopefully bid fair to be <hi>good Miniſters</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, and Workmen that ſhall <hi>not need to be aſham'd</hi>; ſuch really make the beſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations for Goſpel-Service; they enter into it with the beſt Advantages; lay the beſt Foundation for Hope of Succeſs in it, and of Peace in Life and Death; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the beſt for a future Day of Accounts, and build ſtrong for a happy Eternity. The <hi>Man in CHRIST</hi> will be emphatically the <hi>Man of GOD:</hi> and ſuch an one the Apoſtle pronounces <hi>a Veſſel unto Honour</hi>; a Veſſel of Mercy prepared unto Glory, and in which GOD will make known the Riches of his Glory.</p>
            <p>But if any dare thruſt themſelves into the Miniſtry, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having firſt <hi>yielded themſelves to the LORD</hi>; without having firſt <hi>learned CHRIST,</hi> and <hi>acquainted themſelves with GOD</hi>; without having GOD enthron'd in their Hearts, and reigning over all the Powers of their Souls, over their whole internal Temper, Principles, Views and Thoughts, as well as external Life and Actions, having at beſt only the <hi>Form of Knowledge,</hi> without any
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:004140_0046_1003DB87BA52D4F8"/>
Vitality in it, and the <hi>Form of Godlineſs,</hi> without the Power of it; and conſequently without the neceſſary Evidences of a real and ſaving Union to Chriſt, Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the <hi>Communion of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and to an experimental Senſe of what it is to have the LORD for <hi>their GOD</hi>; ſurely ſuch (how excellent ſoever a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templative Genius, and whatever intellectual Acquire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or moral Ornaments they may have, as ſo many plauſible Marks of a Divine Miſſion, to recommend 'em in the Sight of <hi>Men)</hi> can never hope to <hi>ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves approved unto GOD,</hi> and muſt ſtand continually expos'd to the Reſentments of an accuſing Conſcience, which will very probably be often whiſpering in their Ears thoſe juſt and cutting Reproaches, <hi>Art thou a Maſter in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and knoweſt not theſe things! Thou which teacheſt others, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf!</hi>— Alas for the carnal graceleſs Miniſter, whoſe <hi>god</hi> is his <hi>Belly</hi> or the <hi>World,</hi> or whoſe Idol at beſt is <hi>Self,</hi> a falſe imaginary <hi>Phariſaical</hi> Self! how much more abundant Reaſon hath ſuch an one very evidently (under his ſtrong Symptoms, if not actual Senſe, of an unregenerate Mind) than the holy inſpir'd <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> to entertain the jealous Thought with a trembling Soul, which that humble Saint had his Heart ſo deeply affected with (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27.) <hi>Leſt that by any Means, when I have preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to others, I my ſelf ſhould be a CAST-AWAY!</hi>— This awful Text ſtands at the Pulpit-Door as <hi>a flaming Sword which turneth every way,</hi> to guard it from the rude Incroachments of every unhallow'd Foot. How little Account ſoever any may juſtly make of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Neceſſity of an uninterrupted Line of Succeſſion from the Apoſtles, and an authoritative human Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from Epiſcopal Hands in Virtue thereof, to the Being of holy Orders; yet certainly Perſons of any ſolid Reflection muſt allow, that the holy Nature and Ends of the Work of the Miniſtry, the holy Qualifications of the Scripture-Biſhop, and the holy Vows at his
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:004140_0047_1003DB8943DED458"/>
ſolemn Separation, the holy Eye of God upon the Preacher, and a holy future Reckoning, are Conſiderations which ſpeak the Pulpit a very ſacred Incloſure, not to be thrown open to all in Common, nor invaded by Perſons eſſentially deficient, in their intellectual, or moral and religious Character. We may pertinently apply here that of the wiſe Man, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Keep thy Foot when thou goeſt to the Houſe of God, and be more ready to hear, than to give the Sacrifice of Fools: for they conſider not that they do evil.</hi> And that of the Apoſtle to <hi>Timothy</hi> (1 Epiſt. 5.21, 22.) <hi>I charge thee before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the elect Angels,—Lay Hands SUDDENLY on no Man, neither be Partaker of other Men's Sins; keep thy ſelf pure:</hi> this (I ſay) is not only a ſolemn Caution to the <hi>Ordainer,</hi> but ſtrongly implies likewiſe a Divine Warning to the <hi>Probationer,</hi> not to ruſh upon the Miniſtry <hi>ſuddenly</hi> and unprepar'd, ignorant or in his <hi>Sins.</hi> 1 Tim. 3.6. <hi>Not a Novice, leſt being lifted up with Pride, he fall into the Condemnation of the Devil.</hi>— But now ſays the Apoſtle, (2 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.21.) <hi>If a Man purge himſelf from theſe, he ſhall be a Veſſel unto Honour, ſanctified and meet for the Maſter's Uſe, prepared unto every good Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How fitly then may thoſe Apoſtolical Exhortations be brought home to himſelf by every <hi>Candidate</hi> for the Miniſtry! <hi>"Thou therefore, My Son, flee theſe Things, flee youthful Luſts; but follow Righteouſneſs, Godlineſs, Faith, Love, Patience, Meekneſs, Peace, with them that call on the Lord out of a pure Heart: Be ſtrong in the Grace that is in JESUS CHRIST: Study to ſhew thy ſelf approved unto GOD: Lay hold on eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life".</hi>— And now he that obſerves and does theſe Things, will highly recommend himſelf to the tender Affection and Delight of his Fathers in the Miniſtry, as well as the People of God; and <hi>that</hi> will be their united earneſt Wiſh for ſuch an one, in the Language of the Apoſtle's comprehenſive Benediction
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:004140_0048_1003DB8FB481F0B8"/>
on his <hi>dearly beloved Son</hi> (2 Tim. 4.22.) <hi>The Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with thy Spirit! Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Point before us might be apply'd to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the <hi>Schools of the Prophets</hi>; Colleges or Academies for the training up meet Perſons to be employ'd in the Miniſtry. Such we read of as being in <hi>Iſrael</hi> of Old, under the Inſpection of the Prophets, <hi>Samuel, Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha:</hi> they are left on Record for an <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> to future Ages, and the <hi>Imitation</hi> thereof is doubtleſs very pleaſing to the <hi>LORD GOD of the holy Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A well-manag'd Education of Youth for the ſacred Purpoſe of Goſpel-Service muſt needs be highly <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto GOD</hi> (and therefore ought to be <hi>approv'd of Men</hi>) for as <hi>His</hi> Inſtitution has founded the <hi>Order</hi> of the Miniſtry, and that for a <hi>perpetual</hi> Continuance, ſo <hi>His</hi> Intereſt and Honour are not a little concern'd in the Introduction of <hi>ſuch</hi> into it as hopefully exhibit the Character of <hi>Men of GOD; Men in Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Men of Underſtanding,</hi> well ſtudy'd in the Theory of reveal'd Divinity, well ſtock'd with ſound Scripture-Principles, <hi>apt to teach, able rightly to divide the Word of Truth, able alſo to convince Gainſayers,</hi> and reſolv'd to <hi>fight the good Fight of Faith, rooted and grounded in the Love of Chriſt and in the Hope of the Goſpel,</hi> avouching the Lord for <hi>their GOD,</hi> and under the credible Marks of a ſincerely diſpos'd (together with a well-furniſh'd) Mind, devoting themſelves to the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>winning Souls</hi> to Chriſt, that <hi>others alſo</hi> may have the LORD for their Covenant-GOD. The Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent thus <hi>nouriſh'd up in the Words of Faith and of good Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>knowing how he ought to behave himſelf in the Houſe of God,</hi> may truly be ſaid to <hi>purchaſe to himſelf a good Degree,</hi> in the Church as well as the School: and how acceptable in the Sight of GOD, how happy the Nurſeries of Learning, that are wiſely go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd with a ſteady and prevailing View to this their principal Deſign, the qualifying of Youth with <hi>ſacred
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:004140_0049_1003DB9138C595A8"/>
Knowledge,</hi> and forming the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> as well as the Scholar! The Excellency and Advantage of ſuch an Education, and the important Duty of Tutors and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in the publick School (as well as of Parents and Children in the private Family) are pointed out in thoſe remarkable Paſſages of the Apoſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 Epiſt. 3.14,—17. which I will leave you to conſult your Bible for: and paſs to obſerve,</p>
            <p n="4">4. The preſent Doctrine ſuggeſts one apparent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Satan</hi>'s Malice and Rage againſt the <hi>Goſpel-Miniſtry.</hi> Againſt this his Heart burns with Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: againſt this he levels the whole Artillery of the Kingdom of Darkneſs. He abhors the Buſineſs, and hates the Deſign of the Miniſtry; he dreads the Succeſs of it; he envies and maligns the Perſons employ'd <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it, and in ſpecial the more faithful, active and zealous of the Order: he confronts them with all his helliſh Arts and Powers, has his Emiſſaries abroad continually, is ever laying unhappy Snares for them, and indefatigably carries on the moſt vigorous Oppoſition to them. Hence the Divine Apoſtle himſelf complains that <hi>Satan hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd him,</hi> and that ſuch as were the Devil's Tools <hi>did him much Evil,</hi> and <hi>greatly withſtood him.</hi> Now what muſt be the <hi>Principle</hi> lying at the bottom of this Spite at Miniſters, this accurſed Malignity againſt their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, their Office and Labours? It ariſes doubtleſs chiefly from his inveterate Hatred of GOD and the LAMB, <hi>whoſe they are and whom they ſerve.</hi> He's full of Rage at the <hi>Captain</hi> of our Salvation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can't but vent his Malice upon <hi>the good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. This Point affords abundant <hi>Conſolation</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> to the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This directs and calls them to ſee to it, that they make ſure of GOD for <hi>their GOD</hi> in Truth and Reality, and that they make it their Care to carry it in all Regards as becomes the Dignity and Sacredneſs
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:004140_0050_1003DB92C0FA4A38"/>
of the Relation they ſtand into GOD. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.11. <hi>But thou, O</hi> MAN <hi>of GOD, flee theſe Things, and follow after Righteouſneſs, Godlineſs,</hi> &amp;c. They ſhould ſtudy to exhibit the Character of <hi>Men of GOD</hi> in their whole Miniſtry and Life, in their public Work, and private Walk. How humble, lowly and ſelf-denying ſhou'd they be! how kindly affection'd and endear'd to one another! how compaſſionate to the Souls of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners! how delighted with the Image of GOD on his Saints! how ſpiritually minded, devout and prayerful! how thoughtful of GOD, zealous for his Honour, and fervent in Spirit, ſerving the LORD! how reſolv'd and how vigilant againſt the Powers of Darkneſs, the Enemies of GOD and Enemies of all Righteouſneſs! how bold in their GOD, to eſpouſe his Cauſe, and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate his Truths and Ways! how attach'd to their Divine Maſter's Inſtructions and Orders, careful to ſhew all good Fidelity in ſpeaking from the Mouth of the LORD, neither going beyond his Word, and ſo being wiſe above what is written, nor yet ſhunning to declare the whole Counſel of GOD! All this Duty their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion dictates, and their Relation to God invites to. Are they profeſſedly <hi>Men of GOD,</hi> and will He be a GOD to the faithful Prophets? What a powerful <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> is this to put them upon thus taking Heed to themſelves, that they fulfil their Miniſtry! and how abundantly improvable for their <hi>Direction</hi> in it!</p>
            <p>What <hi>refreſhing</hi> Proſpects and Reflections may this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford the faithful Servant of GOD! Is the LORD indeed <hi>his GOD?</hi> then how joyful may he be in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of his Intereſt in all the precious Promiſes of the Goſpel, and his Security againſt all the dreadful Menaces of the Law! How joyful in the Senſe of a gracious Pardon, of the Juſtification of Life, the Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sons, preſent perſevering Grace, and future everlaſting Glory! Is the LORD verily <hi>Elijah</hi>'s <hi>GOD?</hi> How little Reaſon has he to be diſcourag'd by any
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:004140_0051_1003DB9446EE5678"/>
Oppoſitions from Earth or Hell! W<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> tho' <hi>Ahab</hi> perſecute him as the Troubler of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and what tho' <hi>Jezebel</hi> be his ſworn Enemy? If GOD be for him and with him, what can Men or Devils do unto him! His GOD will certainly be his <hi>Shield</hi> in Danger, his <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> in Affliction, his <hi>Light</hi> in Darkneſs, his <hi>Defence</hi> againſt the Reproaches of the Enemy, his <hi>Guide</hi> and <hi>Help</hi> in the Courſe of his miniſterial Work and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Walk, the <hi>Strength</hi> of his Life, and his <hi>Hope</hi> in Death. The <hi>holy Prophets,</hi> in a believing View of GOD as <hi>their GOD,</hi> who is nigh to them at all times and who will never leave them, may have <hi>ſtrong Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation</hi> and <hi>good Hope through Grace:</hi> and while they ſhew themſelves <hi>approved unto GOD,</hi> they need not be aſham'd of the Goſpel, nor afraid of their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, nor even in Terror of Death, the laſt Enemy. For the <hi>God of their Life</hi> will preſerve them, that every one ſhall <hi>accompliſh as an Hireling his Day:</hi> and when they have finiſh'd their Work, their Reward above will be ſure and great; a Thought which muſt needs be ſufficient to reconcile them to Death, and make them eaſy under all Events of Life.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of the glorious and bleſſed Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, which that Miniſter, whoſe GOD is the Lord, has in the midſt of all his worldly Wants and ſpiritual Cares, Trials, and Exerciſes whatſoever, to refreſh his weary Soul. By them he may and ſhou'd encourage him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when (as <hi>Elijah,</hi> who was a Man ſubject to like Paſſions with us) he is ready to faint in his holy War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare. By them ſhou'd he animate his Faith, invigorate his Hopes, and fortify his Courage; and by them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame his Zeal, quicken his Alacrity, and prompt his Diligence in the Service of GOD: Yea, under the moſt melancholy Thought of a Miniſtry <hi>unſucceſsful,</hi> he may thus quiet his anxious Spirit, as the holy Prophet amidſt his Tears on the like ſad Ocaſion (Iſa. 49.4, 5.) <hi>Surely my Judgment is with the LORD, and
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:004140_0052_1003DB98C6127D38"/>
my Work with My GOD. Tho'</hi> Iſrael <hi>be not gathered, yet ſhall I be glorious in the Eyes of the LORD, and my GOD ſhall be my Strength.</hi>— So the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tells us his happy Experience and triumphant Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7,—18.) <hi>I have fought a good Fight,— henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown.— All Men forſook me; notwithſtanding, the LORD ſtood with me, and ſtrengthned me,— and the LORD will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve me to his heavenly Kingdom: Unto whom be Glory for ever and ever! Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Hence we may collect much of the <hi>Duty</hi> incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Goſpel-Miniſtry,</hi> and a powerful Argument to recommend this <hi>Order</hi> of Men to the Love and Eſteem of the <hi>World</hi> in general.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Is JEHOVAH the GOD of <hi>Elijah?</hi> Is He the <hi>LORD GOD of the holy Prophets?</hi> How then ſhou'd <hi>all Men</hi> every where, that have any Senſe of the Being of GOD, entertain his Miniſters with thankful chearful Hearts; whom He now ſends, not to the <hi>Jews</hi> only, but together with them unto the <hi>Gentiles!</hi> How incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent, how ſenſeleſs, abſurd and mad the common Prejudices of a blind and wicked World againſt this Order of Perſons! Behold, <hi>theſe Men are the Servants of the moſt high GOD, which ſhew unto us the Way of Salvation!</hi> A ſignificant and attractive Character, that juſtly invites Affection and Complacence, and ſhould make them welcome to all the periſhing Sons of <hi>Adam.</hi> As it is written (Iſa. 52.7.) <hi>How beautiful are the Feet of Them that preach the Goſpel of Peace, that publiſh Salvation, that ſay unto</hi> Zion, <hi>Thy GOD reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) This points out the Obligation upon <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Profeſſors, in chuſing the Place of their <hi>Habitation,</hi> to fix (if poſſible) where they may have the Advantage of a <hi>Goſpel-Miniſtry</hi>; at the ſame time it loudly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes them who for worldly Accommodations <hi>forſake
<pb n="45" facs="unknown:004140_0053_1003DBA24C839D00"/>
the Levite, and the Houſe of God:</hi> And this infers too the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of thoſe that prefer the Miniſtry of ſuch as have moſt of the <hi>Image</hi> of GOD ſhining upon 'em, and moſt of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of GOD viſibly breathing in them; But it detects the <hi>Folly</hi> of Thoſe who (meerly out of a fond Humour for ſome little differing For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities in Worſhip and Diſcipline, out of an angry Pique, or for ſome trifling Convenience, or other fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous Pretence) will eaſily forſake and caſt off a Miniſtry own'd of GOD, by the ſenſible Tokens of his ſpecial Preſence and Bleſſing, and perhaps come to give up all Regard for it, yea loſe even all Charity to it, as a regular and faithful Chriſtian Miniſtry; while yet they can glory in others, it may be, who have at leaſt as little of GOD appearing in their Character and Miniſtry, have as little of the Truth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel with them, as little of the true Genius of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity in their Preaching, and as little of the Power of Religion in their Devotion and Practice. Hear how the Apoſtle rebukes this unhappy Spirit of Schiſm and Envy (1 Cor. 3.4,—7.) <hi>For while one ſaith, I am of</hi> Paul; <hi>and another, I am of</hi> Apollos; <hi>are ye not carnal? Who is</hi> Paul, <hi>and who</hi> Apollos, <hi>but Miniſters, by whom ye believed, even as the LORD gave to every Man? So then neither is</hi> the one <hi>nor</hi> the other <hi>any Thing; but GOD, who giveth the Increaſe.</hi> And in ſome fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Words he thus exhorts them, <hi>Covet earneſtly the beſt Gifts: and yet ſhew I unto you a more excellent Way;— Follow after Charity, Let all your Things be done with Charity. And the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with you: My Love be with you all in Chriſt Jeſus. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) The preſent Doctrine ſerves for Direction to the <hi>Churches</hi> of Chriſt in their <hi>Election</hi> of Perſons into the Relation of Biſhops or Paſtors among them; which is undoubtedly their Right, by the Laws of Reaſon, and the Tenour of Scripture, and juſtify'd by ancient
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:004140_0054_1003B8B428F9B348"/>
Uſage: but if they wou'd employ this their Privilege and Power with Wiſdom and with Succeſs, they muſt in the firſt Place look and ſeek to <hi>the LORD GOD of the holy Prophets</hi> for his Guidance in the important Affair. As when a People have receiv'd the Bleſſing of a <hi>Man ſet over the Congregation, to go in and out before them,</hi> that is an able and faithful <hi>Miniſter for the Houſe of their GOD,</hi> they ſhou'd give GOD the <hi>Praiſe</hi>; (Ezra 8.18.) <hi>By the good Hand of our GOD upon us, they brought us a Man of Underſtanding:</hi> So likewiſe in the <hi>Want</hi> of ſuch a Bleſſing, GOD expects by <hi>Prayer</hi> to be ſought to for it. We have that primitive Example left on Record for our Imitation in <hi>this</hi> Regard; Act. 1.24. <hi>They prayed, and ſaid, Thou LORD, which knoweſt the Hearts of all Men, ſhew whether of theſe two THOU haſt choſen.</hi>— And then in forming their Judgment and Choice, they muſt be careful to conduct themſelves by <hi>Scripture-Rule,</hi> which ſtates the juſt <hi>Character</hi> of a chriſtian Biſhop or Elder very parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly: upon an Examination of which it will be obvious, that a Regard is to be had to his Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>moral,</hi> as well as intellectual, to his <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>divine</hi> Endowments, as well as rational Talents and human Virtues. Such an one ſtands <hi>firſt</hi> recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who hath choſen the LORD GOD of the Prophets for <hi>his GOD,</hi> and who hath moſt of the Spirit of the <hi>holy Prophets</hi> viſibly reſting upon him, the Spirit of <hi>Prayer,</hi> the Spirit of <hi>Love</hi> and of <hi>Power</hi> and of a <hi>ſound Mind</hi>; who hath obtained like <hi>precious Faith,</hi> and who adds to Faith <hi>Knowledge,</hi> eſpecially Knowledge <hi>Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical,</hi> both practical and experimental, as well as ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. And to ſuch an one ſurely the thinking ſerious Chriſtian will be ready to ſay, as the Woman to <hi>Elijah</hi> (1 Kin. 17.24.) <hi>Now know I by this, that thou art a MAN of GOD.</hi> Of ſuch an one it may moſt probably be hop'd, <hi>that the Word of the LORD in his Mouth is Truth:</hi> and ſuch an one is the moſt likely to have GOD <hi>with him</hi> in his whole Miniſtry.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="47" facs="unknown:004140_0055_1003DBA5D9EA3378"/>(4.) The Conſideration of GOD, <hi>before whom they ſtand,</hi> ſhould govern a People in their <hi>Conduct</hi> towards ſuch as <hi>are over them in the LORD</hi>; and it teaches them to <hi>eſteem 'em very highly in Love for their Work's ſake.</hi> Their very Work and Office, and the external Relation they bear to GOD and to his People, may well endear 'em to every conſiderate ſerious Soul: but eſpecially the <hi>faithful</hi> and <hi>good</hi> Miniſter, who is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally related to GOD as <hi>his GOD,</hi> as well as united with the People of God as <hi>his</hi> People by the common Bond of the Spirit, he who in his Labours and Life ſhews himſelf <hi>approv'd</hi> unto GOD, and commends him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to <hi>every Man's Conſcience</hi> in the Sight of GOD, ſuch an one is truly and eminently <hi>worthy of double Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi> He himſelf <hi>ſeeks</hi> the Honour that comes from GOD; yet <hi>deſerves</hi> Eſteem from <hi>Men:</hi> nor indeed can he but deſire an Intereſt in their Affections, with a View to their greater Satisfaction in his Miniſtry and better Edification by it. And this we know, that if we have but your <hi>Hearts</hi> engag'd to us upon right Principles, <hi>inward Love</hi> will (in proportion to its real Prevalence) dictate <hi>outward Reſpect,</hi> and forbid all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Slights, unkind Neglects and Diſcouragements. <hi>Obadiah</hi> ſhewed how <hi>greatly he feared GOD,</hi> when he expreſs'd the tender Care and Bowels of a <hi>Father</hi> to the <hi>Sons of the Prophets,</hi> and when to the <hi>Father</hi> of the Prophets he paid the Veneration and Duty of a <hi>Son</hi>: as you may read, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 18.7,—13.</p>
            <p>There's a <hi>Variety</hi> of Ways, in which People may exhibit their juſt and friendly Regards to the Miniſtry. They ſhou'd maintain worthy Thoughts of the <hi>Office,</hi> for its Relation to GOD, and Importance to Men; ſhou'd diligently attend on the public <hi>Adminſtration</hi> of it, and that in all the ſeveral Branches thereof, waiting upon GOD in all his Ordinances <hi>in Seaſon and out of Seaſon</hi>; ſhou'd joyn in Divine <hi>Worſhip</hi> with Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs and exemplary Devotion, and receive the
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:004140_0056_1003DBA75E43F878"/>
               <hi>Word</hi> with Meekneſs, a grave Attention, and faithful Self-Application; ſhou'd ſubject themſelves to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Acts of Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and carefully ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port all <hi>Goſpel-Order</hi>; cultivate <hi>Peace</hi> and a holy <hi>Unity</hi> among themſelves, that <hi>the Goſpel mayn't be hindred</hi>; and do all in their Power to <hi>encourage</hi> the Hearts, and <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> the Hands of their Miniſters, while <hi>watching for their Souls, as they that muſt give an Account</hi>: help 'em by a comfortable and decent <hi>Maintenance,</hi> by an amicable and open <hi>Correſpondence</hi> with them, by affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate and obliging <hi>Carriage</hi> towards them on all Occaſions, and by fervent daily <hi>Prayers</hi> in the Family and Cloſet for them: But above all, they are deſirous to ſee their People <hi>edify'd</hi> by their Miniſtry, <hi>profiting</hi> by their public Labours and private Viſits; ſo will they <hi>thank GOD, and take Courage,</hi> whatever Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Difficulties, Temptations, they may have to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict with in this preſent evil World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally,</hi> when the Man of God <hi>dies</hi> and leaves the World, he ſhould be follow'd to his Grave with all ſuitable Marks of publick Reſpect, and his Memory receive all proper Honours. The Conſideration of his ſpecial Relation to GOD, and of the ſpecial Preſence of the LORD his GOD with him, ſhou'd awaken very ſerious Thoughts in Survivors, and awe our Minds into a ſolemn Penſiveneſs, and holy Mourning: for not to reſent the Death of ſuch an one, wou'd be at once an Indignity to his Memory, and Ingratitude to GOD, the LORD his GOD, who diſplay'd his own Being and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to us in the Gifts and Graces of his Servant, and us'd and honour'd him to be an Inſtrument of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many Bleſſings to us, as well as keeping off Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from us.</p>
            <p>When a faithful Miniſter dies <hi>among</hi> his People, as their <hi>Loſs</hi> is great, their <hi>Sorrow</hi> ſhould be in Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. When an <hi>Elijah</hi> departs, well may they (with <hi>Eliſha</hi>) expreſs their Grief in all the Geſtures and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents
<pb n="49" facs="unknown:004140_0057_1003DBA8E6EF4518"/>
of a <hi>bitter Lamentation</hi>: Yet in the midſt of their diſquieting Thoughts they have this for their <hi>Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that as their faithful MINISTER is tranſlated to a <hi>better</hi> World (for whither elſe can the <hi>holy Prophet</hi> be taken?) ſo the LORD his GOD ſtill lives and remains among them, <hi>with whom is the Reſidue of the Spirit.</hi> While then they are <hi>weeping for themſelves and for their Children,</hi> and while they pay their mournful Reſpects to the Memory of the Dead, they may make the <hi>living God</hi> their Confidence, and truſt in Him to repair the Breach made upon them.</p>
            <p>And a People are call'd to take a ſolemn Notice of the Diſpenſation of Providence, when any Man of God is taken out of the World, who had <hi>formerly</hi> ſtood in a Paſtoral Relation to them. All Survivors ſhou'd lay to Heart the Death of any publickly uſeful and pious Perſon: and when ſuch an one has once been related to us ſo nearly in the Station of a <hi>Paſtor</hi> over us, it can't but be own'd the higheſt <hi>Condecency,</hi> that we <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh</hi> ourſelves among the <hi>Mourners</hi> at his Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and pay very ſingular Reſpects to his <hi>Memory</hi> in all proper Ways.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND here filial Duty commands me to make a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectful Mention of that</hi> Man of GOD, <hi>the Reverend Mr.</hi> BENJAMIN WADSWORTH, <hi>who for ſo many Years was</hi> a burning and ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Light <hi>in this Candleſtick of the LORD; tho' for ſome Years paſt at the Head of the</hi> School of the Prophets <hi>among us: but has lately received a Diſmiſſion from his Poſt below, to receive his Reward above.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Surely Death has in this Inſtance clos'd the Scenes of an active, uſeful, valuable Life, devoted to the Honour of GOD and Benefit of his People, and worn out with long Application to Divine Studies, fervent Prayers, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Services. For that was his</hi> proper Motto, <hi>SERVING THE LORD: and this muſt be the honorable
<pb n="50" facs="unknown:004140_0058_1003DBB0047F7D40"/>
Inſcription on his</hi> Tomb, HE HATH DONE GOOD IN ISRAEL, BOTH TOWARDS GOD, AND TOWARDS HIS HOUSE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I might go now into a very particular Account of the many</hi> good Things which were found in him towards the Lord his God, <hi>and might venture upon a large En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comium (even to</hi> the acknowledging of every good Thing, which was in him in Chriſt Jeſus) <hi>with as little Hazard of giving Offence to the moſt enviouſly cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, as perhaps in any Caſe that has fallen within my Notice: But as it has been my known Cuſtom of late Years (for ſome peculiar Reaſons) induſtriouſly to decline bringing</hi> Funeral-Characters <hi>into the Pulpit, I wou'd even now avoid a too</hi> pompous <hi>Appearance, and Affectation of</hi> Embelliſhment, <hi>tho' I cou'd not perſuade myſelf to be wholly ſilent on this</hi> uncommon <hi>Occaſion; when without Controverſy ſo much is due to the Memory of the</hi> Dead, <hi>and ſo much preſents it ſelf to be ſpoken for the Inſtruction of the</hi> Living, <hi>and to the Honour of that</hi> Divine Grace, by which he was what he was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If we ſhou'd here trace him back to his</hi> firſt <hi>Days, and look at him as a</hi> Student <hi>in the publick School, thoſe who were his Contemporaries, bear Witneſs to his early Piety, ſingular Gravity, Probity, Modeſty, and univerſal good Behaviour; to his exemplary Docility, his laudable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry in Academical Studies, and Proficiency in uſeful Literature: tho', his Favorite-Study was</hi> Divinity, <hi>the nobleſt Entertainment to every</hi> ſerious <hi>Mind, and a juſt</hi> Improvement <hi>in the theoretical and experimental Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it, certainly the beſt Preparative for that</hi> ſacred <hi>Work, on which his</hi> Eye <hi>was fix'd, yea his</hi> Heart <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd; nor indeed without</hi> that <hi>can it be expected, any ſhou'd be</hi> wiſe to win Souls, <hi>without which happy Skill the moſt accompliſh'd</hi> Maſter of Arts <hi>is like to prove but a</hi> blind Guide, <hi>an uncouth Miniſter, and muſt make a very aukward Figure both in his publick Performances, and his private Applications to Families and Perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Charge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="unknown:004140_0059_1003DBB18725D580"/>
               <hi>Or if we paſs over to his</hi> laſt <hi>Years, and view him as</hi> preſiding <hi>in the School, we ſhall behold a vigilant and compaſſionate</hi> Father <hi>to the Sons of Learning: continually</hi> ſtanding before his GOD, <hi>to ſpeak Good for them, and turn away Wrath from them: heartily</hi> mourning <hi>the Follies of ignorant and diſſolute Youths, and</hi> weeping over them <hi>day and night in his Prayers for their Converſion and Reformation, but</hi> rejoycing <hi>in the hopeful Proſpects from</hi> others <hi>of a ſober and religious Character: highly</hi> ſolicitous <hi>to carry on the beſt Education, and aſſiſt in forming</hi> Men <hi>and</hi> Chriſtians <hi>for future Service in the Church and Commonwealth; to propagate ſound Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and encourage the moſt profitable Studies; to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Flouriſhing of univerſal Virtue, Godlineſs and Honeſty; to eſtabliſh the wholſomeſt Laws and Orders, inculcate a due Obſervation of 'em, and enforce them by an impartial Execution; to ſecure the</hi> College <hi>its ſeveral Rights and Properties, and further the Proſperity of all its ſubſtantial Intereſts. — With what</hi> Diligence <hi>and</hi> Attention, <hi>with what</hi> Patience <hi>and</hi> Self-denial, <hi>with what</hi> Humility <hi>and</hi> Moderation, <hi>what</hi> Gravity <hi>and</hi> Conſtancy, <hi>what</hi> Caution <hi>and</hi> Circumſpection, <hi>and a Care of ſhewing all</hi> good Fidelity, <hi>he accquitted himſelf in the Conduct of that Society, thoſe (I doubt not) will readily teſtify, who were the more immediate Eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and to whoſe Province it more properly belongs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> my <hi>peculiar Situation rather ſeems to call me to the Conſideration of him in this</hi> Miniſterial <hi>Capacity, while ſo long and nearly related to this</hi> Church <hi>and unto</hi> Me. <hi>And here I might ſum up his amiable Character, in that deſcriptive Language of the Apoſtle</hi>; A beloved Brother in CHRIST, and a faithful Miniſter, and Fellow-Servant in the LORD, my Fellow-Worker unto the Kingdom of GOD, which hath been a Comfort unto Me, and a Helper of your Joy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I muſt confeſs, it was very much the ſuperiour Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reverence I bore to</hi> him, <hi>for his known general
<pb n="52" facs="unknown:004140_0060_1003DBB8E2B9C928"/>
Worth, and his Reputation for Candour and Kindneſs in particular, that determin'd me to accept the Call of this Church, and (contrary to my firſt Views and Purpoſes) to ſettle ſo early in the Miniſtry, where I might enjoy the Aſſiſtance of ſo pious, ſo prudent, ſo tender a Colleague, as</hi> the Guide of my Youth.—<hi>I've ever look'd on it indeed as a remarkable Inſtance of his Meekneſs and Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he ſo willingly conceded to the (perhaps too haſty) Deſires and Attempts of his People for the fixing one ſo young, unfurniſh'd, and unexperienc'd, a Partner with him, in the Charge of this ancient and then flouriſhing Congregation.— Sure I am, I've great Reaſon to be thankful for the Benefit of his fatherly Advices, as well as effectionate Prayers for me, and the excellent Example, in which he went before and led me, for ſo many of my Years in the leſs diſcreet Age of human Life: Nor was it (I truſt) without ſome Degree of a</hi> mutual <hi>Satisfaction, that I aim'd to</hi> walk in the ſame Spirit, <hi>and</hi> to ſerve with him, as a Son with a Father, <hi>in the Work of the Goſpel.—But</hi> do I begin to commend my ſelf? <hi>I am check'd by that Divine Caution,</hi> Let another Man praiſe thee, and not thine own Mouth. <hi>However, this Caveat againſt</hi> Self-Applauſe <hi>evidently implies in it a Permiſſion to give</hi> others <hi>their deſerved Praiſe,</hi> Honour to whom Honour <hi>is due. It's difficult indeed ſometimes to commend the</hi> Living <hi>without being ſuſpected of Flattery: but one wou'd think, that in praiſing the</hi> Dead <hi>we ſhou'd be very</hi> ſincere, <hi>when we have the awful Views of the</hi> Grave <hi>and</hi> Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity <hi>before us. The Apoſtle celebrated his living Partners, as</hi> the Glory of Chriſt, whoſe Praiſe is in the Goſpel throughout all the Churches: <hi>and he has drawn up a numerous Catalogue of</hi> deceaſed <hi>Prophets and Worthies, whoſe Memory be conſecrates to all Poſterity.</hi> By a Faith which wrought Righteouſneſs, the Elders obtained a good Report: <hi>and they are had</hi> in everlaſting Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="unknown:004140_0061_1003DBBA66E8A5C8"/>
               <hi>So concerning our deceaſed Elder and Father, may I not apply the Commendation given of</hi> Demetrius, <hi>and ſay,</hi> He hath good Report of all Men, and of the Truth it ſelf; yea, and we alſo bear Record, and ye know that our Record is true! <hi>I may appeal to You, as many of You as were of Years to obſerve and be acquainted with him while among us, concerning his Miniſtry and Practice,</hi> Ye know after what Manner he was with us: <hi>and</hi> your ſelves (<hi>ſome of You of more advanc'd Age</hi>) <hi>can remember and</hi> know what Manner of ENTRING in he had unto You, that it was not in Vain<note n="†" place="bottom">Mr. <hi>Wadſworth</hi> ſome time in the Year 1693 (when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menc'd Maſter of Arts) was call'd by a Vote of this Church to be aſſiſtant to their Teacher (the Rev. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>) as a Candidate: and continued preaching ſtatedly once or twice a Month (alternately with the Rev. Mr. <hi>Bailey</hi>) by repeated Deſires of the Church, until they proceeded to call him to the Paſtoral Office; unto which he was ordain'd on <hi>Sept.</hi> 8. 1696.— And he remain'd with us till the Cloſe of <hi>July</hi> 1725, when he went to reſide at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> having been ſome Weeks before inſtall'd the Preſident of <hi>Harvard-College.</hi>— So that this Church enjoy'd his Labours for about 30 Years.</note>. Ye are Witneſſes, and GOD alſo, how holily and juſtly and unblamably he behaved among us: as ye know, how he exhorted, and comforted, and charged every one of us, as a Father doth his Children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the</hi> Chriſtian Life <hi>he was an Example and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof to us all. An</hi> excellent Spirit <hi>was in him, which ſhed a viſible Influence on his external Life, Words and Actions. He was happy in being able uſually to preſerve a remarkable</hi> Tranquillity <hi>of Temper, by the Advantage of which he poſſeſs'd his own Soul, as by his mild Behaviour he ſpread a Glory over his whole Character, endear'd his Perſon, and recommended his holy Profeſſion and Miniſtry. He was not the Man of</hi> Contention, <hi>the</hi> wrangling <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putant, or the</hi> furious <hi>Bigot; but hated the deteſtable Name and Thing under every head, and was for letting his</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="unknown:004140_0062_1003DBBE78228B60"/>
Moderation <hi>be known to all Men: yet he cou'd occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally be</hi> warm, <hi>when he thought the Cauſe wou'd bear, and Duty requir'd it. And as he was govern'd by</hi> ſolid Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>he was</hi> much <hi>for</hi> walking by the ſame Rule, <hi>for</hi> minding the ſame Thing, <hi>and</hi> not meddling with them that are given to Change; <hi>tho' habitually as well</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>in Action, as</hi> deliberate <hi>in Judgment, yet when once reſolv'd and clear in his Thoughts (eſpecially if the Caſe was of Moment, and Conſcience ſenſibly intereſted) he wou'd be</hi> firm <hi>and</hi> ſteady <hi>to his Point: however, ſtill</hi> not ſelf-willed, <hi>not perverſely and criminally obſtinate, but ever profeſſing an Openneſs to Conviction, and able many times to give Way to the Inclinations of Others for Peace-ſake.— He ever expreſs'd a high Reverence for</hi> Authority <hi>and</hi> Order, <hi>and was for ſupporting them in the Societies where he was concern'd: exhibiting himſelf a Pattern of</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion <hi>to Rulers,</hi> Reſpectfulneſs <hi>to Superiors, and</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention <hi>to Men of lower Degree. Yet neither at any time uſed he</hi> flattering <hi>Words, or a</hi> Cloke <hi>of Covetouſneſs, nor of Men ſought he</hi> Glory.‐ <hi>He convers'd with much of an unaffected</hi> Compoſure, Simplicity <hi>and</hi> Truth: <hi>knowing how to ſhew Civility, without Complements; and to be affable and pleaſant, without Lightneſs or the uſual Airs of an unguarded Mind, as well as to be ſerious and reſerv'd, without the Humours of Preciſeneſs, or Auſterity: Eaſy of Acceſs, familiar in his Viſits, and his</hi> Speech ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd with Salt, <hi>peaceful, gracious, and ſuch as might</hi> mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Grace and Peace to the Hearers.— <hi>He knew how to bear the ſevere Trial of froward Cenſures, and injurious Treatment, with a diſpaſſionate Silence</hi>; not rendring Evil for Evil, or Railing for Railing, <hi>but</hi> patient, not a Braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, no Striker. <hi>Nevertheleſs, he was a faithful</hi> Reprover, <hi>and cou'd ſometimes even</hi> rebuke ſharply <hi>(where he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, the Fault deſerv'd, and the Caſe demanded it) as became a Hater of Sin and Lover of Holineſs, careful to</hi> keep himſelf pure, <hi>and</hi> not be a Partaker of other Men's Sins: <hi>But ſtill he would temper his Admonitions
<pb n="55" facs="unknown:004140_0063_1003DBC0FA847FD0"/>
with a juſt mixture of compaſſionate Tenderneſs; eſpecially if any Man that is called a</hi> Brother, <hi>were overtaken with a Fault, wou'd he</hi> reſtore ſuch an one <hi>in the Spirit of</hi> Meekneſs, <hi>as</hi> conſidering himſelf <hi>a Man ſubject to</hi> like Paſſions <hi>with others.— Tho' ever prudent in his Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy and Expences,</hi> ſober <hi>and</hi> temperate <hi>in all Things,</hi> not given to Wine, <hi>to Luxury and Extravagance: yet</hi> neither <hi>was he</hi> greedy of filthy Lucre, not covetous, but a Lover of Hoſpitality, a Lover of good Men, juſt, holy, blameleſs as the Steward of God; <hi>according to the Scripture-Character of the worthy</hi> Biſhop <hi>or</hi> Elder. <hi>Having his Converſation thus without Covetouſneſs, as he was himſelf</hi> content <hi>with ſuch Things as he had, ſo he</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat <hi>not to</hi> do Good <hi>unto others; knowing that with ſuch</hi> Sacrifices <hi>GOD is</hi> well pleaſed. <hi>But conſtantly with a religious Punctuality and Exactneſs laying by the</hi> Tenth <hi>of his Incomes, ſacred for ever to the Uſes of Charity and Benefaction, he had ſomething of a</hi> Fund <hi>to repair to, as Caſes preſented: and was</hi> ready <hi>to diſtribute,</hi> willing <hi>to communicate; ſending up very frequent</hi> Memorials before God, <hi>in giving</hi> much Alms <hi>to the</hi> People. <hi>He</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <hi>others</hi> to provoke them unto Love, and to good Works, <hi>both by Pattern and Propoſal.</hi> He went about (<hi>in Imitation of his Divine Maſter</hi>) doing Good: <hi>his</hi> Hands <hi>and his</hi> Lips <hi>together feeding many, refreſhing the Bowels of the</hi> poor <hi>Saints and cauſing the</hi> Widows <hi>Heart to ſing. When the</hi> Ear <hi>heard him, then it bleſſed him: and when the</hi> Eye <hi>ſaw him, it gave Witneſs to him. He was a</hi> Father <hi>to the Needy: and how often did the</hi> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>of them which were ready to periſh, come upon him!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He always bore the Reputation of a ſteady faithful</hi> Friend, <hi>and a kind obliging</hi> Neighbour: <hi>and many at all times found in him a</hi> Counſellor <hi>and a</hi> Comforter, <hi>ready to afford 'em his beſt Aſſiſtances under every Difficulty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He ſtudy'd Uſefulneſs in his own</hi> Family, <hi>both by his daily Inſtructions and Prayers, ſhewing a Deep Concern for the Souls of all under his Charge. And that he might be
<pb n="56" facs="unknown:004140_0064_1003DBC28D514D40"/>
found walking within his Houſe with a perfect Heart, he was greatly ſolicitous to have the</hi> Sabbath <hi>ſanctify'd in his Dwelling: and</hi> took Heed to himſelf, <hi>as well at home as abroad, that by an unblemiſh'd</hi> Example <hi>he might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce others to a ſtrict Obſervation of the</hi> Lord's Day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the</hi> Houſe of Prayer, <hi>he ſhew'd an exemplary</hi> Gravity <hi>in his whole Mein and Carriage, as one that</hi> reverenc'd God's Sanctuary: <hi>and when ſitting under the Adminiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trations of</hi> others, <hi>he was a very candid, as well as atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Hearer. <hi>GOD's Tabernacles were truly</hi> amiable <hi>to him, and hither he wou'd repair with a holy Pleaſure, not to be detain'd at any time by the little Impediments which many plead in Excuſe of their frequent Abſence. Nor was his</hi> Cloſet <hi>leſs his Delight in its Seaſon: But GOD alone was Witneſs to the</hi> Spirit <hi>and</hi> Manner <hi>of his ſecret Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.— He was one (we've Reaſon to think) that having choſen the LORD for</hi> his <hi>GOD, had his</hi> Fellowſhip with the Father and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and prayed alway in the holy Ghoſt. <hi>He</hi> feared <hi>GOD above many, and uſed his</hi> Name, <hi>which is Holy and Reverend, with a viſible</hi> Awe <hi>upon his Mind. He ſhewed a great Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the ſacred</hi> Scriptures; <hi>honoured the</hi> Works <hi>of GOD, and ador'd his wiſe and holy</hi> Providence. <hi>He</hi> exerciſed himſelf unto Godlineſs <hi>in all the various Branches of it: and was particularly remarkable for his</hi> Truſt <hi>in God, his</hi> Patience <hi>under Divine Corrections, and a humble</hi> Reſignation <hi>to the Will of Heaven, concerning him and his, as to all Events. He truly</hi> waited upon GOD: <hi>and</hi> waited for his SON from Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Sum, we beheld in him the rare Spectacle of an</hi> uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form <hi>Chriſtian, the</hi> perfect Man <hi>and</hi> the upright, <hi>conſiſtent in his Principles and Tempers, Profeſſion and Practice. Yet none ſurely will underſtand me now to aſſert his</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute <hi>Perfection. Even</hi> Aaron, <hi>the Saint of the Lord, was an Inſtance of the</hi> Law'<hi>s making Men</hi> Prieſts, <hi>which had</hi> Infirmity: <hi>and</hi> Peter, <hi>that mighty Apoſtle, was an Inſtance of the</hi> Goſpel<hi>'s making Man</hi> Miniſters, <hi>which
<pb n="57" facs="unknown:004140_0065_1003DBC7C1048368"/>
are ſometimes juſtly to be</hi> blamed. <hi>And perhaps ſeldom has any one liv'd more under the humbling Senſe of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Pravity and remaining Infirmity, than the deceaſed Servant of Chriſt. However, You all knew him to be one who very conſpicuouſly</hi> exerciſed himſelf always to have a Conſcience void of Offence, <hi>both</hi> towards God and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Man: <hi>and You can't but teſtify with what Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Conſtancy, Diligence and Patience he</hi> ran his chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Race <hi>among us. The Spirit of his Mind and Tenor of his Converſation were evidently ſuch as ſpake him an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament to his Profeſſion: and not many</hi> good Men, <hi>not many</hi> Miniſters, <hi>paſs through the World with a more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſully'd Reputation.</hi> Ye knew the Man and his Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication: <hi>and I'm ſure, his Memory as the</hi> devout <hi>and the</hi> juſt Man, <hi>the real and the improv'd Saint, is precious among You.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as the</hi> good MINISTER of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>I doubt not, Many are ready to</hi> riſe up and praiſe him. <hi>We have conſider'd him as an</hi> Example to the Believer: <hi>the ſolemn</hi> Care <hi>of which is made one ſpecial Duty of a</hi> Teacher, <hi>and the actual</hi> Being <hi>of which is of great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, to invite juſt Regards to his Perſon, to facilitate ſome of the more difficult Parts of his private Work, as well as give his publick Preaching a peculiar Force and Weight, and to procure his whole Miniſtry the Advantage of a ſpecial Endearment among his People. And will You not now bear your deceaſed Paſtor this additional Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, That while among You he was a</hi> faithful Steward <hi>of the Myſteries of God, feeding your Souls with the</hi> Bread of Life, <hi>and careful to give unto</hi> every one <hi>his Portion in</hi> due Seaſon! <hi>Ever mindful of the Honour and Intereſt of his LORD, and ever ſeeking the Welfare of his Charge.</hi> I thank CHRIST JESUS our LORD (who enabled <hi>him</hi>) for that He counted <hi>him</hi> faithful, putting <hi>him</hi> into the Miniſtry; <hi>and for that,</hi> having obtained Help of GOD, <hi>he was</hi> continued <hi>ſo long</hi> your Servant for JESUS ſake. <hi>In him you enjoy'd the</hi> nurſing Father, <hi>the vigilant Biſhop,
<pb n="58" facs="unknown:004140_0066_1003DBCEC24F56D0"/>
and the prudent Guide, a</hi> Seer in the Matters of GOD, <hi>who took You by the Hand and led You in the Paths of Righteouſneſs and Truth, with much of the</hi> Wiſdom that is from above, <hi>which is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſy to be intreated, full of Mercy and of good Fruits, without Partiality and without Hypocriſy.</hi> The Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Ephraim was with my GOD: <hi>and how did he</hi> watch for your Souls, as one that <hi>expected to</hi> give an Account!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He well knew</hi> how he ought to behave himſelf <hi>in the Houſe of GOD, which is the Church of the living GOD. In</hi> Prayer <hi>and</hi> Sacramental <hi>Adminiſtrations,</hi> the Man of God wept, <hi>while he poured out his Heart before the Lord. He approach'd the Throne of Grace with a filial Freedom, and yet with a godly Fear, as knowing he had to do with a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as well as a gracious, heavenly Father. His Pulpit-Prayers were uſually fill'd with</hi> Adorations <hi>of the Attributes and Providence of a faithful Creator, as well as the Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a merciful Redeemer: were large in the</hi> Confeſſions <hi>of Sin, particular in</hi> Supplications <hi>for the moſt needful Mercies, and often abounded with</hi> Thankſgiving. <hi>Nor was he unmindful to make</hi> Interceſſion; <hi>to pray for all Men, for Kings, and for all in Authority, for the Churches of the Saints at home, and for the whole Iſrael of God abroad. He bore the Publick much on his Heart: and never forgot the Poor and diſtreſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His</hi> Sermons (<hi>however appearing to others plain and eaſy) coſt him uſually not a little Pains, as well in the compoſing them, as in the committing them to Memory. He did not</hi> offer to his God of that which coſt him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <hi>nor put You off with extemporal Effuſions, or with haſty Productions. I have heard him, at the ſame time that he ſpake very</hi> humbly <hi>of his Performances in the Pulpit, yet ſay how his Brains have ſweat in the Study, and how the intenſe Thought of his Mind, together with the diligent uſe of his Pen, has been a</hi> Wearineſs to his Fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He labour'd for the moſt perſpicuous</hi> Method: <hi>and
<pb n="59" facs="unknown:004140_0067_1003DBD0703673F8"/>
ſearch'd the Scriptures, to collect the moſt pertinent and affecting</hi> Texts <hi>under every Head, which were commonly numerous, and judiciouſly choſen. Having clear'd his</hi> Doctrine, <hi>he wou'd follow it with</hi> Inferences, <hi>uſually practical; and enforce all with a closer Application to Conſcience, in ſome moving Words of</hi> Exhortation. <hi>He made it his Cuſtom to</hi> pen <hi>down his Diſcourſes at large, even to the writing out the Words of every Scripture-Quotation: finiſh'd his Preparations</hi> in Seaſon; <hi>and then with Care got 'em</hi> by Heart. <hi>I know not, that ever he was ſeen to uſe his Notes in the Pulpit: and being diſtinguiſh'd with the uncommon Talent of a very ſure and tenacious Memory, he deliver'd his Sermons</hi> memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riter <hi>with much</hi> Readineſs, <hi>and with a punctual</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs <hi>(as I have ſometimes had Occaſion to obſerve, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the niceſt Examination) according to the very</hi> Letter <hi>(not the Spirit and Scope only) of his Premeditations, as written in his</hi> Papers; <hi>which ſtill he was wont to bring with him to the publick Exerciſes, to prompt his Memory, if there ſhou'd be Occaſion. However, tho' he ſat ſo fair a Copy, he never took any Pains to draw me to follow it in this Inſtance: nor cou'd I ever obſerve him to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend very much this</hi> Memoriter-Delivery, <hi>when I've confer'd with him upon it: but he rather judg'd the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter's Care to</hi> impreſs his Sermons upon his own Heart and Conſcience, <hi>by a previous Review for practical Ends and perſonal Uſes, the</hi> wiſeſt <hi>Care, as apprehending this to be the</hi> beſt Way of getting Sermons by Heart. <hi>And this he wou'd inculcate: but as for the other, he was not for laying an unreaſonable Burden on any: as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> All Men cannot receive this Saying, ſave they to whom it is given; He that is able to receive it, let him receive it.—<hi>Now as to his Manner of</hi> Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>tho' in his</hi> young <hi>Days (as I have known him ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve) he was pleaſingly captivated with the Rhetorical Diction of many celebreted Writers (and in particular our famous and Rev.</hi> LEE, <hi>whoſe learned Labours he highly
<pb n="60" facs="unknown:004140_0068_1003DBD1F2B5A4C8"/>
valu'd) yet he ſoon grew leſs in Love with a florid Style, and addicted himſelf to the</hi> uſing great Plainneſs of Speech, <hi>as conceiving it beſt adjuſted to the Ends of Goſpel-Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, eſpecially in a common Audience, and "beſt becoming the Divinity and Riches of the Matter, which ſome while they think to adorn, do but adulterate it", and often raiſe a Cloud, inſtead of reflecting Light.</hi> Plainneſs <hi>of Phraſe he certainly affected: and if at any time he might be thought to carry this Point to a Degree beyond what an</hi> itching Ear <hi>wou'd rather be pleas'd with, we were not wont to impute it to a faulty Negligence, but aſſign'd a better Principle, that is, an humble Zeal to accommodate his Miniſtry to the loweſt Capacities, and feed the very</hi> Lambs <hi>of the Flock, the ignorant and young, whoſe Souls were equally precious to him as others, while he thought himſelf</hi> a Debtor both to the Wiſe and the Unwiſe <hi>alike.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As for the</hi> Subjects <hi>of his publick Diſcourſes, they were generally</hi> the weightier Matters of the Law, <hi>or the more important</hi> Myſteries of the Goſpel. <hi>He often went over the Perfections of</hi> GOD, <hi>the Offices of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>the Graces of the</hi> SPIRIT, <hi>the Duties of the</hi> Chriſtian Life, <hi>(in particular, Cloſet-Devotions, Family-Religion, Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-Sanctification, Covenant-keeping, Plain-dealing, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-mindedneſs,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>and the contrary</hi> Evils, <hi>the prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sins of</hi> the Times, <hi>the</hi> Folly <hi>of Wickedneſs, and</hi> Wiſdom <hi>of practical Godlineſs, the</hi> Vanity <hi>of this preſent World, the Happineſs of</hi> Heaven <hi>and Miſery of</hi> Hell, <hi>the Terrors of</hi> Death <hi>and</hi> Judgment <hi>to carnal</hi> Sinners, <hi>but the Joys of both to real</hi> Saints: <hi>ſuch were the Points he dwelt much upon, and frequently touch'd on the moſt of 'em, with ſolemn</hi> Memento<hi>'s, almoſt in every Sermon. He fed us with the moſt wholeſome Food, prepared with Care and Skill, tho' without much of artful Ornament; as aiming, not ſo much to gratify a delicate Fancy, as to nouriſh the hungry Soul. — As became a</hi> Watchman <hi>on the Wall, he ſeldom fail'd of</hi> accommodating <hi>the Tenor of his Diſcourſes to the various</hi> Emergencies <hi>of Providence;
<pb n="61" facs="unknown:004140_0069_1003DBD3CE2FED70"/>
that he might ſpeak</hi> Words in Seaſon, <hi>and take the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Men's preſent Thoughts and Tempers, to awaken Sinners and quicken Saints to a greater Mindfulneſs of that GOD, who governs all Events.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He performed all his Adminiſtrations with a holy</hi> Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>diſcovering the Power of Things divine and ſpiritual upon his own Heart, and a Thirſt to inſpire the like ſacred Warmth into the Hearts of others. Nor did he do the Work of the LORD negligently, but may be truly ſaid to have been</hi> abundant in Labours: <hi>ſerving GOD day and night with unceaſing Prayer, with diligent Study, with religious Conference, and many Labours, both ſeen and unſeen</hi>; willing to ſpend and be ſpent <hi>in the Service of his</hi> MASTER <hi>in Heaven, &amp; willing to have</hi> imparted unto Us, not the Goſpel of God only, but alſo his own Soul, becauſe we were dear to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Though he lov'd his Cloſet and Books; yet</hi> loving his Neighbour as himſelf, <hi>and remembring thoſe Words of our LORD,</hi> It is more bleſſed to give than to receive, <hi>he was much abroad, uſually every Day more or leſs, going a</hi> religious Circuit <hi>among his People: for which Purpoſe he wiſely</hi> redeem'd the Time <hi>at home by a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Uſe of his</hi> Morning-Hours. <hi>He judg'd</hi> Viſiting <hi>the Flock (ſick &amp; well) every One at his own Dwelling, too important an Inſtance of the Paſtoral Care to be unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily omitted, as affording peculiar Opportunities for</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the Seed <hi>ſown in his public Preaching, by private dealing with Souls, and more direct Applications to Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and Perſons. He</hi> neglected not <hi>therefore</hi> the Gift that was in him: <hi>but was</hi> inſtant, in Seaſon and out of Seaſon; <hi>no Man more abounding in Paſtoral Viſits: they were ſeldom long indeed, yet ſeldom too without Attemps to do Good, as he had Opportunity, at leaſt by dropping ſome weighty and ſavoury Sentence, ſome ſeaſonable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel or Reproof. And he has been much remark'd for his Impartiality, viſiting all his Charge,</hi> without prefer<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>g one before another; communicating the Goſpel pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately
<pb n="62" facs="unknown:004140_0070_1003DBD6A26FA0C8"/>
to them which were of Reputation, <hi>as well as unto others, and not overlooking any the meaneſt Cottages, while he paſs'd along to the richer Houſes. Yet He went not up and down as a</hi> Tale-bearer, <hi>or as a</hi> Buſy-body <hi>in other Men's Matters, nor was he carry'd about by an</hi> Athenian <hi>Temper,</hi> ſpending his Time in nothing elſe but either hearing or telling ſome new Thing: <hi>But he was like the</hi> good Shepherd <hi>that is</hi> diligent to know the State of his Flocks, and looketh well to his Herds. <hi>And very obſervant at the ſame time was he of that Apoſtolic Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi>; Rebuke not an Elder, but intreat him as a Father, and the younger Men as Brethren; the elder Women as Mothers, the younger as Siſters, with all Purity.— <hi>He walked</hi> circumſpectly, <hi>having no Fellowſhip with the unfruitful Works of Darkneſs, but rather reproving 'em by Word and Example. He watched in all Things, to</hi> give none Offence, <hi>that the Miniſtry might not be blamed: and to</hi> pleaſe all Men in all Things <hi>for their Good to Edification, as</hi> not ſeeking his own Profit, but the Profit of many, that they might be ſaved. <hi>And perhaps his private were no leſs uſeful than his public Labours: beſure his Viſits were of high Account among his People, and anſwer'd this valuable End, to enlarge your Hearts in Affection to his Perſon, which by a natural Efficacy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to make him unto You</hi> as a very lovely Song, <hi>and not</hi> Hatred in the Houſe of his GOD. <hi>How often have your Souls</hi> bleſſed <hi>him in your ſecret Thoughts, and your Ears hung upon his Lips, while You heard the</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Words <hi>which proceeded out of his Mouth!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And in (what I muſt not neglect to mention) that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Work of</hi> Catechizing <hi>the Youth, which he took a tender</hi> Father<hi>'s Pleaſure in, cannot many of You remember how upon ſuch Occaſions, while you were yet as feeble</hi> Lambs, <hi>he carry'd you often in the Arms of his Faith to the Throne of Grace for a Divine Bleſſing, always pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over you with a paternal Pity and Affection,</hi> that your Souls might be bound up in the Bundle of Life
<pb n="63" facs="unknown:004140_0071_1003DBDEC3111860"/>
with the LORD his GOD! <hi>At the ſame Time how did he feed your young Minds, according as they cou'd bear, with</hi> the ſincere Milk of the Word; gentle among you, even as a Nurſe cheriſheth her Children!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I may now appeal to you,</hi> Fathers, <hi>and ſay, in ſome ſelect Paſſages of bleſſed</hi> Paul<hi>'s Farewel-Speech to the</hi> Epheſians, <hi>juſtly applying them to the preſent Caſe:</hi> Ye know, from the firſt Day that he came among You, after what Manner he has been with You <hi>at all Seaſons,</hi> ſerving the LORD with all <hi>Humility</hi> of Mind, and with <hi>many Tears,</hi> and Temptations which befel him: and how he kept back nothing that was profitable unto You, but ſhewed You, and taught You Publickly, and <hi>from Houſe to Houſe,</hi> teſtifying unto you all Repentance towards GOD, and Faith towards our Lord JESUS CHRIST <hi>(which were the general Theme and conſtant Drift both of his publick Sermons and private Viſitations)</hi> nor ceaſed he to warn every one night and day with Tears. <hi>And I well remember, the happy Conſciouſneſs of his own Integrity and Faithfulneſs enabled him, often in the Courſe of his Miniſtry, to make that ſolemn Addreſs to You, in the Language of the ſame Apoſtle,</hi> I take You to Record this Day, that I am pure from the Blood of all Men: for I have not ſhunned to declare unto You all the Counſel of God. <hi>And ſuch was his Firmneſs of Mind and Reſolution in his Maſter's Work, that he cou'd ſay, ſtill in the Apoſtle's Words (which too he wou'd fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently bring into his Sermons</hi>) Bonds and Afflictions await me; but none of theſe Things move Me, neither count I my Life dear to my ſelf, ſo that I might finiſh my Courſe with Joy, and the Miniſtry which I have receiv'd of the Lord JESUS, to teſtify the Goſpel of the Grace of GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor was he without a deſirable</hi> Succeſs, <hi>and</hi> Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance <hi>in his Miniſtry. GOD hunoured him before us by viſibly owning his Labours, and crowning them in many Inſtances with an effectual Bleſſing. Both in his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="64" facs="unknown:004140_0072_1003DBE2417C3BD8"/>
and Viſits how did his</hi> Doctrine drop as the Rain, <hi>without Noiſe, but with good Effects; his</hi> Speech diſtil as the Dew, <hi>proſperouſly, tho' ſilently,</hi> as the ſmall Rain upon the tender Herb, and as the gentle Showers upon the Grafs, <hi>while</hi> he publiſhed the Name of the LORD <hi>and</hi> preached the acceptable Year of our GOD! <hi>He was truly a</hi> Barnabas <hi>among us,</hi> A good Man, and full of the holy Ghoſt and of Faith, and much People was added to the LORD, <hi>and we</hi> glorified GOD in him.— <hi>In the Eſteem, as well as the Succeſs he met with, GOD clothed him as with white Robes; and I doubt not, in that Day when GOD ſhall open his</hi> Book of Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance <hi>and</hi> bind up his Jewels, <hi>this his faithful Servant <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be dignify'd with a glorious Teſtimony from the Mouth of his bleſſed</hi> JUDGE. <hi>(Like that in</hi> Mal. 2.5, 6.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verily, not he that commendeth himſelf, is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but whom the LORD commendeth: and it's the</hi> good <hi>Man that obtaineth Favour of the LORD. Nor does He ſeldom give to</hi> ſuch <hi>that loving Favour from</hi> Men <hi>too, which is preferable to great Riches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The deceaſed Servant of GOD was in our Eyes a real</hi> Grace <hi>to his Order and</hi> Bleſſing <hi>to his Generation: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly</hi> held in much Reputation <hi>among us, juſtly valu'd by his</hi> Fellow-Servants <hi>in the Goſpel, and highly belov'd of his</hi> People. And others <hi>that ſaw him, as he went the Rounds among his Flock,</hi> to viſit the Fatherleſs and Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows in their Affliction, <hi>yea (like another</hi> Paul <hi>or</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas) <hi>to</hi> viſit all the Brethren in every Houſe, and ſee how they did, <hi>were ready to</hi> riſe up and call him Bleſſed, <hi>and to ſay to one another in the Words of the</hi> Shunamite <hi>to her Huſband concerning the Prophet,</hi> Behold now, I perceive that this is an holy Man of GOD, which paſſeth by us continually.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It will be aſk'd by ſome perhaps, How then came</hi> He <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to relinquiſh his Charge, or this</hi> Church <hi>to give up their Title to his Miniſtry? — I remember well</hi> my own <hi>Anxiety, and</hi> your <hi>Tears, as well as</hi> his, <hi>at our</hi> Parting <hi>(now
<pb n="65" facs="unknown:004140_0073_1003DBE3C545DA80"/>
nigh</hi> 12 <hi>Years ſince) when, tho' (I'm perſuaded)</hi> we were in his Heart to die and to live with us, <hi>yet a View to more extenſive Service, and therein to the Glory of GOD, a Care for the</hi> School of the Prophets, <hi>and therein for</hi> all the Churches, <hi>over-rul'd to carry him from us. No other Principles, I'm ſatisfied, cou'd have prevail'd to overcome</hi> his <hi>Reluctance to leave his</hi> dear Flock, <hi>nor any other Conſiderations have brought this</hi> Church <hi>into the</hi> Vote of Reſignation, <hi>concerning their</hi> beloved Paſtor, <hi>which not without many Thoughts of Heart they paſſed on that Occaſion: ſuch was the reciprocal Endearment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us. And I believe, that all wou'd have had the Springs of Grief more ſenſibly awaken'd in them, I'm ſure the aking Hearts of ſome had been almoſt diſconſolate, if we had imagin'd it a</hi> final Farewel (<hi>as in that remarkable Caſe not altogether unlike ours,</hi>—Act. 20.36,—38.) <hi>For tho' we had expected to have frequent Opportunities for</hi> ſeeing his Face <hi>and hearing his Voice in occaſional Labours among us, yet GOD was pleas'd very ſoon to extinguiſh our Hopes, by arreſting him with grievous Pains and great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, which he quickly fell into, and which much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd him, not ſuffering him for theſe many Years to be often or long from home. However, thro' the Favour of GOD to his Servant, ſtill he was wonderfully ſuſtain'd under his Burden, and carry'd on in the Duty of his Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſpirited to attend his daily Labours and Cares at the</hi> College (not regarding his Life, <hi>when cautious Friends wou'd ſometimes check his Zeal, ſaying,</hi> Maſter, ſpare thy ſelf) <hi>and to proſecute his Studies at Home, both with an aſſiduous unfainting Perſeverance, till call'd off by the Preſages of his</hi> End <hi>coming on; the LORD (in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence) ſaying in him, as to</hi> Moſes, Behold, thy Days approach that Thou muſt die! <hi>And while confin'd (for a few Weeks) to his Sick-Chamber, he ſtill found that</hi> Grace ſufficient for him, <hi>which had ever been his whole Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance in all Conditions. The</hi> LORD ſtood with him <hi>in his laſt Encounters, and</hi> ſtrengthned him on the Bed of
<pb n="66" facs="unknown:004140_0074_1003DBE9B5AC91F0"/>
Languiſhing, <hi>with Strength in his Soul. As his</hi> outward Man <hi>periſhed, the</hi> inward Man <hi>was renewed day by day; for which Cauſe he fainted not: But lay calm and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> ſtrong in Faith <hi>and full of humble Submiſſion</hi>; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to depart and be with CHRIST, <hi>and wiſhing the bleſſed Time might be haſtned, yet ſtill reſign'd to the Will of his heavenly Father. Favour'd with living Comforts in his expiring Moments, he cou'd and did with a lively Hope commit his Soul into the Hands of his dear</hi> REDEEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ER, <hi>in whom he had believ'd, and whom he had preach'd and ſerv'd; leaving his dying Teſtimony for</hi> CHRIST, <hi>his Truths and Ways</hi>; trembling for the Ark of GOD, and praying for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>; commending <hi>all about him</hi> to GOD, and to the Word of his Grace, <hi>and expreſſing the beſt Wiſhes in ſolemn manner for one and another that made their reſpectful Viſits to him.— May</hi> I <hi>never forget the</hi> Bleſſing wherewith the Man of GOD bleſſed Me before his Death! <hi>And may the LORD GOD of</hi> Elijah, <hi>who only can</hi> command <hi>the Bleſſing, cauſe it to reſt upon me, in my Service here on Earth, while the happy Spirit of my departed Father is enjoying his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Heaven, as his Fleſh, now laid in the Duſt, reſts in Hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SUCH WAS THE MAN, WHOM GOD HATH TAKEN!</p>
            <p>I pretend not indeed to have drawn his <hi>Character</hi> at full Length, and in all its lovely Proportions, tho' I've held you long upon it, beyond my firſt Intention. There may have happen'd ſome material <hi>Defects</hi>; but I am not conſcious of any faulty <hi>Exceſſes,</hi> nor yet of any artful <hi>Gloſſes,</hi> to ſet it in a falſe Light. The Reflection now is obvious, that we find, an uncommon Aſſemblage of very valuable uſeful Qualities form his amiable Character; ſuch as ſpeak him <hi>Great in the Sight of the LORD,</hi> and ſuch as may well make his Name precious with all that have a juſt Idea of <hi>real Greatneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It mayn't be amiſs to repeat here an Obſervation I've met with: "Tho' many had made a brighter and greater Figure in the Eye of the World, than <hi>John,</hi> yet CHRIST prefers <hi>him</hi> to them all; <hi>There hath not riſen a GREATER than</hi> John <hi>the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="unknown:004140_0075_1003DBED42A093B0"/>
Thoſe are the <hi>greateſt</hi> Men, that are the greateſt <hi>Saints,</hi> and the greateſt <hi>Bleſſings,</hi> under the vital Influence of the Spirit of God and of Glory.— I may therefore with a ſingular Propriety apply that well known Lamentation, in the preſent Caſe, <hi>Know ye not that a GREAT MAN is fallen this Day in</hi> Iſrael!</p>
            <p>And now ſhall we not all mingle our Tears over the Grave of the Man of GOD, <hi>mark the perfect Man,</hi> and mourn our own and the public Loſs in the Death of a Father in <hi>Iſrael</hi>!</p>
            <p>We heartily ſympathiſe with the bereaved <hi>Family</hi> and <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives:</hi> and pray GOD to comfort the many Mourners on this Occaſion. May the GOD of all Grace and Comfort, in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, ſupport his Handmaid, the deſolate <hi>Widow,</hi> under her heavieſt Sorrow! May her MAKER ſtill be her <hi>Husband,</hi> and remember her, the Kindneſs of her Youth, and Love of her Eſpouſals, and yet more ſenſibly eſpouſe her to Himſelf in Loving kindneſs, give her now the Oil of Joy for Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the Garment of Praiſe for the Spirit of Heavineſs!</p>
            <p>May the bereav'd <hi>College</hi> have this Stroke of the Divine Hand upon it ſanctify'd, both to <hi>the Maſter and the Scholar,</hi> even to all belonging or related to it! And may the GOD of the Spirits of all Fleſh chuſe out an <hi>Eliſha,</hi> to ſucceed in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Vacancy, on whom He will cauſe to reſt <hi>a double Portion of the good Spirit,</hi> ſo viſible on the <hi>Elijah</hi> taken from their Head!— May this Death be ſanctify'd alſo to <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and all of <hi>publick</hi> Character! May <hi>We,</hi> the Miniſters of <hi>this</hi> Church in particular, hear GOD's Voice, ſpeaking to us in louder Accents, and be excited to our Work, as by the Thought of <hi>Mortality</hi> and a future <hi>Account,</hi> ſo by wiſe Reflections on the <hi>Example</hi> left us by the deceaſed Servant of GOD!— <hi>Brethren, pray for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that this <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Congregation</hi> may have the Spirit of GOD ſpeaking powerfully to them on this Occaſion, awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a due <hi>Remembrance</hi> of the Man of God, and reviving the good <hi>Impreſſions</hi> of his Miniſtry! GOD expects, we remember and hear the Words, which He hath cried to us by his <hi>former Prophets</hi> (Zech. 7.7, 12.) and by his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> (Jude, <hi>ver.</hi> 17.) And that Exhortation ſeems to refer to the ordinary <hi>ſtanding Miniſtry</hi> (Heb. 13.7.) <hi>Remember them which have ſpoken to you the Word of God,</hi> &amp;c.— It's obſervable, Our Lord (as in <hi>Matth.</hi> 11) ſpake honorably of <hi>John,</hi> when he had finiſh'd his Teſtimony and was fallen into ſome Oblivion; intending by what he ſaid, to retrieve his declining Memory, and to reſtore his dying Work by reviving the People's Regard to his Preaching, which they had formerly <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> zealous to hear, and which therefore they ought now to think it worth ſome
<pb n="68" facs="unknown:004140_0076_1003DBF05A0489A8"/>
Care to recollect.— In Conformity to this great Example, I have been <hi>ſtirring you up, by Putting you in Remembrance:</hi> I've done it with a View to your Profit, as well as to the Praiſe of the Deceaſed, and in both to the Glory of GOD. Let us give GOD the Honour of all the Gifts, Graces and Uſefulneſs of his Servant; be thankful that we enjoy'd ſuch a Bleſſing in his Miniſtry; examine our Improvements under it, and purſue the Ends of it by a lively practical Remembrance.</p>
            <p>Reading his <hi>printed</hi> Works will ſerve to keep up his Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and (as it were) perpetuate his Miniſtry among us. I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to you in particular his valuable familiar <hi>Explanation of the Aſſembly's Catechiſm,</hi> his labour'd Treatiſe on <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and his judicious <hi>Guide to the Doubting.</hi> That was the Text which animated him in his many Publications, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12, 15.</p>
            <p>We ſhall do well to <hi>ſtir up</hi> one another <hi>by way of Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</hi>— We ſhall do well to review him as in the <hi>Pulpit</hi> and in his <hi>Viſits,</hi> and recollect in particular (as we are able) any remarkable Inſtructions, Advices, or Reproofs, we receiv'd from him: and let us be careful to maintain a <hi>good Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him always, even as it is meet, being mindful of his Tears, and following his Faith.</hi> I truſt, there are ſome among You, that were his <hi>Hope</hi> on Earth, and will be his <hi>Joy and Crown</hi> in Heaven: let ſuch ſtill live the Credit of his Miniſtry by a holy Perſeverance. But may we not fear, there are others, <hi>whom the Word preached</hi> by him <hi>did not profit?</hi> Yea, are not ſome of You conſcious, You were a Grief to <hi>his righteous Soul?</hi> Let ſuch tremble it the awful Proſpect of his ſtanding a <hi>Witneſs</hi> againſt you in the Day of Judgment. <hi>And</hi> (as it is written, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.33.) <hi>when it cometh to paſs (lo, it will come) then ſhall ye know that a PROPHET hath been among you.</hi> O fear, left you be put to <hi>mourn at the laſt,</hi> when there's no Remedy.</p>
            <p>Let us all hear GOD ſpeaking to us in thoſe Calls of his <hi>Providence</hi> and <hi>Word</hi> (2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.20.) <hi>Believe in the LORD your GOD, believe his Prophets.</hi> And (Jam. 5.10.) <hi>Take the Prophets, which have ſpoken in the Name of the Lord, for an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</hi>— Let us ſuppoſe the <hi>Man of God</hi> himſelf addreſſing us (as in <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.9.) <hi>Thoſe Things which ye have both learned and received, and heard and ſeen in ME, do; and the GOD of Peace ſhall be with You.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, Let us all now (as they, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.2.) <hi>lament after the LORD</hi>; and with <hi>Eliſah,</hi> inquire for the GOD of <hi>Elijah</hi>: making it our great Concern to ſecure the gracious Preſence of the <hi>ever-living GOD</hi> with us, which was the Sum of our departed Friend and Father's <hi>dying Wiſhes</hi> for us. Let our Inquiry be <hi>frequent</hi> and <hi>perſevering, fervent, penitent</hi> and <hi>believing, ſincere</hi> and <hi>practical.</hi> A juſt Reſpect to the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="69" facs="unknown:004140_0077_1003DBF798BE1B40"/>
of the Deceaſed, the Honour of God, and the Intereſt of Religion, our own Safety and Happineſs, are Conſiderations that unite to perſuade us into ſuch an Inquiry. This is one genuine Fruit of the Divine Nature in us, and a hopeful Sign of the Divine Preſence with us; and it bodes well to us for the coming World. If we have <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Grace, we ſhall attain his Glory too. Faith, Love, Hope and Deſire intenſe are as <hi>the fiery Chariot and Horſes</hi> to mount us up into <hi>heavenly</hi> Places <hi>now:</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> will conduct us thither when we <hi>die,</hi> gathering our Souls to the Aſſembly of glorify'd Spirits in <hi>Paradiſe</hi>: and in the <hi>Reſurrection-Day</hi> we ſhall ſee one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's <hi>Faces</hi> with Joy. GOD will raiſe the dead Bodies of the Saints, and <hi>ſhew them alive</hi> to us, as He did <hi>Elijah</hi> with <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Diſciples in the Mount of Transfiguration: but with this happy Circumſtance of Difference, that <hi>ours</hi> will be a <hi>final</hi> Meeting, and in <hi>greater Glory</hi>; for we ſhall dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the bliſsful <hi>Preſence</hi> of GOD through the Ages of <hi>eternal</hi> Futurity. Read 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13,—17. and <hi>comfort one another with theſe Words.</hi> Now the God of Peace be with us all! AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. <hi>8. lin. 13. read,</hi> But <hi>by my</hi>— P. <hi>14. l. 12. read,</hi> meaning <hi>the</hi>— P. <hi>42 l. 35. read,</hi> the Hope of <hi>future</hi>— P. <hi>61. l. 35. read</hi> or <hi>Reproof</hi>—.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N. B.</hi> Then are a few lighter Eſcapes of the Printer: but that of the <hi>Author</hi> in his <hi>Prefatory</hi> Epiſtle eſpecially asks Candour; the Hint (I mean) of <hi>ſome few Additions</hi> to the Sermon. For, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I really intended <hi>no other,</hi> when I ſent the <hi>Preface</hi> to the Printer, this having been diſpatch'd before I enter'd upon the <hi>Tranſcript</hi> of my Sermon, yet (thro' the Divine Favour my Hands being ſtrengthen'd beyond my Fears, as I was newly under a Return of great Indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) I found an Inclination to make ſome <hi>Additions</hi> not at firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd. Becauſe when I came to the ſeveral Heads of USE (moſt of which were barely hinted in the Pulpit) I cou'd not perſuade my ſelf to let them paſs the Preſs without ſomething of <hi>Inculcation;</hi> ſo I freely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg'd the Impreſſions upon me. And they are the Enlargements here, that have ſwell'd the Sheets to this <hi>enormous</hi> Size. However, I hope the Reader will find his <hi>Edification</hi> the better conſulted upon the whole: and if ſo, as I ſurely ſhall not repent my Paint, ſo others will the more eaſily <hi>forgive me this Wrong.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
