<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The favour of God the best security of a people and a concern to please him, urged; in a sermon delivered before the General Assembly of the colony of Connecticut, at Hartford, May the 8th, 1740. Being the day for electing the Honourable the governour, the deputy governour, and the worshipful assistants, there. / By Jacob Heminway, A.M. Pastor of the Church of Christ in East Haven. ; [Two lines from Psalms]</title>
            <author>Heminway, Jacob, 1683-1754.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N03694</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N03694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 4526</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW6044</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">4526</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99012177</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 4526.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N03694)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 4526)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 4526)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The favour of God the best security of a people and a concern to please him, urged; in a sermon delivered before the General Assembly of the colony of Connecticut, at Hartford, May the 8th, 1740. Being the day for electing the Honourable the governour, the deputy governour, and the worshipful assistants, there. / By Jacob Heminway, A.M. Pastor of the Church of Christ in East Haven. ; [Two lines from Psalms]</title>
                  <author>Heminway, Jacob, 1683-1754.</author>
                  <author>Connecticut. General Assembly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p. ;  15 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Green, printer to the governour and Company,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>N London [i.e., New London, Conn.]. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1740.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Mr. Heminway's sermon on Proverbs XVI. 7. When a mans ways please the Lord, he maketh even his enemies to be at peace with him.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Election sermons --  Connecticut --  1740.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>AEL Data (Chennai)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:004526_0000_100DA160C4407C58"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:004526_0001_100DA16310AC3BF8"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Heminway'</hi>s SERMON</p>
            <bibl>On Proverbs XVI. 7.</bibl>
            <q>When a mans Ways pleaſe the LORD, He maketh even his Enemies to be at Peace with him.</q>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:004526_0002_100DA166C33B5CB0"/>
            <p>THE Favour of GOD THE BEST SECURITY OF A PEOPLE AND A Concern to Pleaſe Him, Urged;</p>
            <p>In a <hi>SERMON</hi> delivered before the GENERAL ASSEMBLY of the Colony of <hi>Connecticut,</hi> at <hi>Hartford, May</hi> the 8<hi>th,</hi> 1740.</p>
            <p>Being the Day for Electing the Honourable the GOVERNOUR, the DEPUTY GOVERNOUR, and the Worſhipful ASSISTANTS, there.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Jacob Heminway,</hi> A. M. Paſtor of the Church of CHRIST in <hi>Eaſt Haven.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Pſal xci. 1.</bibl>
            <q>
               <hi>He that dwelleth in the ſecret place of the Moſt High, ſhall abide under the ſhadow of the Almighty.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>N LONDON.</hi> Printed and Sold by T. GREEN, Printer to the GOVERNOUR and COMPANY, 1740.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="unknown:004526_0003_100DA16854831170"/>
            <head>At a GENERAL ASSEMBLY holden at Hartford on the Second Thurſday of May, Anno Domini, 1740.</head>
            <opener>Ordered by this Aſſembly,</opener>
            <p>THAT <hi>Joſeph Whiting</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq;</abbr> and Capt. <hi>Iſaac Dickerman,</hi> Return the Thanks of this Aſſembly to the Reverend Mr <hi>Jacob Heminway,</hi> for his SERMON delivered before the Aſſembly on the Eighth Inſtant, and deſire a Copy thereof that it may be Printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Wyllys Secr.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="unknown:004526_0003_100DA16854831170"/>
            <head>The Favour of GOD the beſt Security of a People.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PROVERBS XVI. 7.</bibl>
               <q>When a mans Ways pleaſe the LORD, He maketh even his Enemies to be at Peace with him.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT being the pleaſure of the All-wiſe GOD to ſuffer War to happen in our Nation at this Day as in gives us all grounds to fear that our Ways have not been Pleaſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Him; ſo if we are ſenſible o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Danger, it can ſcarcely be imagined, but that we ſhould be thoughtful &amp; inquiſitive what we may beſt do to ſecure our ſelves from the invaſions of our Enemies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>And truly at this day, this has been the ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous tho't &amp; Enquiry of many in this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And in a time of Danger it is but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable that every one ſhould have a ſuitable Concern for his own &amp; others Safety. But here lies the difficulty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fully to determine what is the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d &amp; way that a Perſon or People can t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke for their own Defence and Security from their Enemies. And ſome are for one way and
<pb n="2" facs="unknown:004526_0004_100DA169F512F5B8"/>
ſome for another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And this being an Enquiry of ſuch Importance, that it is needful it ſhould be ſatisfyingly <hi>Anſwered,</hi> I have therefore tho't it beſt for us to ſeek for an Anſwer to this Enquiry from the Oracles of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For as <hi>God is wiſer than men,</hi> ſo his Counſels &amp; Directions <hi>are the ſafest for us to follow</hi> And therefore I have tho't it might be ſeaſon b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e &amp; ſuitable at this time, to Entertain you from this Portion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Writ, even this <hi>wiſe Proverb of Solomon;</hi> who as he was one of the Wiſeſt of meer men, ſo being a King he had the cleareſt inſight into the affairs of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and well knew what would moſt of all conduce to the Peace, Security &amp; Proſperity of a People. And whereas at ſome times and under ſome circumſtances, it might appear a difficult &amp; puzzling Queſtion to ſome how to make their Enemies to become their Friends &amp; to be at Peace with them, he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th in theſe words reſolved this Problem &amp; wiſely anſwer'd the Caſe in this ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng, <hi>When a many ways pleaſe the Lord, he maketh even his enemies to be at peace with him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> The words in themſelves are p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain &amp; obvious, and need little or no Exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ication. And by one <hi>who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ways pleaſe the Lord,</hi> we may underſtand <hi>a godly Perſon,</hi> one who <hi>orders his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght;</hi> One who is careful <hi>to obey God in all his ways,</hi> one that above all things is ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of <hi>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ning the friendſhip and favour of God.</hi> And when the caſe is ſo with any man or people,
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:004526_0004_100DA169F512F5B8"/>
God will <hi>make even their Enemies to be at Peace with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, He will not onl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> keep his Friends in peace with him but will alſo move and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline his very Enemies unto peace &amp; friendſhip, ſo that they ſhall not in any wiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As if he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſaid, <hi>When <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce a man has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the favour &amp; friendſhip of God, God will protect &amp; ſecure him, and not only make hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Friends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Friends; but will make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be either at Peace or become his Friends.</hi> God will make his worſt Enemies to be either ſo far at Peace with him as that they ſhall no ways hurt him, or be cordial Friends to him and do him good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And ſo in theſe few words, <hi>Solomon</hi> does very much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend Religion is the moſt likely way to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection &amp; Security from all Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>But here ſeems to be one <hi>Objection</hi> lying in the way of this Truth which may need a little <hi>Solution,</hi> and it is this;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How often in all Ages has it been obſerved, That th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe that have been godly &amp; whoſe ways did pleaſe the Lord, yet have had Enemies that were never at peace with them, but always endeavoured to do them miſchief?</hi> And Chriſt tells his faithful Followers, That <hi>they ſhould be hated of all men for his Name ſake.</hi> And we read of ſome of the Primitive Saints of the firſt Magnitude, <hi>of whom the world was not worthy,</hi> Heb. 11. 36,—Who had <hi>trials of cruel Mockings &amp; Scourgings; Yea, moreover of Bonds and Impriſonment. They were stoned, they were
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:004526_0005_100DA16D02024070"/>
ſawn aſunder, werr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emoted and ſlain by the Sword; They wandred about in Sheep-skins &amp; Goat-skins, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing destitute, afflicted, tormented: They wandred in Deſerts and Mountains, in Dens and Caves of the Earth.</hi> So that to a carnal Eye, one would be ready to think this Aphoriſm of <hi>Solomon</hi> to be but a Paradox, and that the Truth lay in the Reverſe; and that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe had the fewell Enemies and moſt Peace whoſe ways diſpleaſed God: As it hath been often found in Experience, That <hi>the tabernacles of Robbers proſper, and that thoſe that temp God are ſecure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How then muſt we underſtand this ſaying of <hi>Solomon,</hi> That <hi>when a mans ways pleaſe the Lord, he will make even his Enemies to be at peace with him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to this <hi>Objection,</hi> we muſt remember, That God makes a mans Enemies to be at Peace with him in a two-fold ſenſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>When he makes them become his Friends:</hi> When thoſe that were at Enmity with him and hated him, become Reconciled &amp; cordial Friends to him, to love him &amp; carry it friendly to him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>God makes a mans Enemies to be at Peace with him, when He protects &amp; ſecures him from all harm from them:</hi> So that tho' their Enmity remains and they would deſtroy him if they could, yet God curbs &amp; reſtrains their Power, ſo that <hi>their hands cannot perform their Enterpriſe:</hi> And ſo a man is as ſecure from all harm from his Enemies, as if they were at perfect Peace and Amity. In
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:004526_0005_100DA16D02024070"/>
this ſenſe we may underſtand that Text, Job 5. 23. <hi>Thou ſhalt be in league with the ſtones of the field, &amp; the beaſts of the field ſhall be at peace with thee.</hi> That is, You ſhall be ſecure from harm by them. Now tho' it be true. That when a mans ways pleaſe the Lord, he doth not always make his Enemies become his Friends, and ſo at peace with him in that ſenſe; yet He doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſecure him from all harm from his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, whether ſecret or open; and doth in his Providence ſo order the matter, That tho' the Enemies of the godly are ſomtimes permitted to make a ſpoil and a prey of their Eſtates, and to deſtroy their Children &amp; Friends, yea, and ſomtimes alſo to take them Captives &amp; keep them in Slavery, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and ſomtimes to deſtroy their Perſons; yet nothing they do or can do to them, ſhall be for their hurt: And God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits them to take nothing from them, but what they may better want than have: For this ſtands &amp; muſt ſtand as an everlaſting truth, Rom. 8. 28 <hi>All things ſhall work together for good, to them that love God.</hi> So that in this ſenſe, when a mans ways pleaſe the Lord, He doth always make his Enemies to be at peace with him: That is, So far as that they ſhall do him no hurt, but good, whatever their evil intentions may be.</p>
            <p>And we may farther take notice, That <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> here ſpeaks of man in particular, and not of man in general; becauſe it might then be
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:004526_0006_100DA16F2FFC2248"/>
juſtly Objected, That ſuch a thing never was, and probably never would be, that all men ſhould conſpire together to pleaſe God in their ways; And yet it is ſo ſpoken of man in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, that all men in general may be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to endeavour after it; and every one has reaſon to hope for the good of the Promiſe if his ways pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>And we may farther obſerve, That <hi>Solomon</hi> here ſpeaks of the Ways of a man pleaſing the Lord, rather than of his Heart, becauſe the <hi>ways</hi> of man are the beſt diſcovery of his <hi>heart;</hi> and it is but in vain for men to flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they pleaſe God in their <hi>hearts,</hi> when they diſpleaſe him in their <hi>lives</hi> &amp; <hi>ways.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the words thus conſidered may afford us this</p>
            <p>
               <label>DOCTRINE,</label>
               <hi>That the beſt way for men to be Secured from all their Enemies, is to Pleaſe GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much <hi>Solomon</hi> here teaches us in this Text, <hi>When a mans ways pleaſe the Lord, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth even his Enemies to be at Peace with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpeaking to this Doctrine, I ſhall offer theſe Two <hi>Propoſitions.</hi> [<hi>I.</hi>] That all men are more or leſs ſubject &amp; lye expoſed to Enemies. [<hi>II.</hi>] That the beſt way for them to be ſecured from all their Enemies is to pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>PROP. I. <hi>That all men are more or leſs ſubject and lye expoſed to Enemies,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="unknown:004526_0006_100DA16F2FFC2248"/>
There is no man on this ſide Heaven, can juſtly look upon himſelf as altogether free &amp; out of danger from his Enemies. Now, as men are made up of two main conſtituent parts, Namely, their Souls and their Bodies; ſo there are two ſorts of Enemies that all men are more or leſs expoſed to, Namely, the Enemies of their Souls &amp; the Enemies of their Bodies.</p>
            <p>And under the firſt ſort of Enemies may be compriſed <hi>the Devil &amp; his Angels;</hi> even all the powers of Hell &amp; Darkneſs, even all thoſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate Angels that kept not their firſt State, but left their own Habitation; who are reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in everlaſting chains under darkneſs to the <hi>Judgment of the great Day;</hi> who being filled with rage &amp; malice againſt God and all that belongs to Him. Theſe envious ſpirits being grieved that any of the Sons of men ſhou'd fill up thoſe empty Manſions in glory, which they by Sin have loſt, are therefore continually doing their utmoſt to hinder men from happineſs. And they are very ſubtil and cruel Enemies, and ſuch as all men have need to watch againſt &amp; beware of; as the Apoſtle exhorts us, 1 Pet, 5. 8 <hi>Be ſober, be vigilant, becauſe your adverſary the devil as a roaring lion walks about, ſeeking whom he may devour.</hi> And under this head, may alſo be comprehended <hi>the Luſts of the Fleſh,</hi> even all Sins which have a tendency to deſtroy the Souls of men, <hi>the wages of which is death.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:004526_0007_100DA171A10552C8"/>
the Apoſtle for this reaſon exhorts men <hi>to abſtain from fleſhly Luſts which war againſt the Soul,</hi> 1 Pet 2 11 Yea, and men themſelves, ſo far as they by their Temptations, Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions &amp; evil Examples, do draw us to Sin, are the Enemies of our Souls</p>
            <p>And under the ſecond ſort of Enemies, even the Enemies of our Bodies, may be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended <hi>whatever is Hurtful and Deſtructive to our Bodies and outward Eſtate;</hi> Even Men that are Enemies to us in a more ſecret or open way; and all things that tend to the hurt and deſtruction of our Bodies, even all Sickneſs &amp; Caſualties that we are expoſed to in this world, which have a tendency to ſhorten our days &amp; bring us to death. And truly, if there be ſo many things that may be counted Enemies, what man is there or can there be on Earth that is not ſubject to them? And truly, if we look upon ourſelves &amp; conſider, our ſtate, we ſhall ſee our ſelves more or leſs expoſed to Enemies. If we look both within &amp; without, before and behind, on the right hand and on the left, we ſhall ſee our ſelves lying open and expoſed to Enemies. And this brings us to our</p>
            <p>PROP. II. <hi>That the beſt way for men to be ſecured from all their Enemies, is to pleaſe God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to explain this Propoſition, we ſhall conſider two things.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="9" facs="unknown:004526_0007_100DA171A10552C8"/>
               <item>1. How men are to pleaſe God. And</item>
               <item>2. Evidence that this is the beſt way for men to be ſecured from all their Enemies.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. We ſhall conſider, <hi>How men are to pleaſe God</hi> And truly this is a Queſtion of very great importance. And it will be the Inquiry of every Soul truly ſenſible of Sin and of the dreadfulneſs of God's Wrath. Thus the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God of old, were very inquiſitive how to pleaſe God: And were ready to offer him any kind of Service, even that which was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, if they might but pleaſe him. Mic. 6. 6, 7 <hi>Wherewith ſhall I come before the Lord and how my ſelf before the high God? Shall I come before him with burnt-offerings, with calves of a year old? Will the Lord be pleaſed with thouſands of rams, or ten thouſands of rivers of oyl? Shall I give my firſt-born for my tranſgreſſion, the fruit of my body for the ſin of my ſoul?</hi> But however, men are naturally at a loſs about the way how to pleaſe God, yet He hath clearly Revealed it in his Word: As the Lord told his People, aforeſaid, Mic. 6. 8 <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good, and what doth the Lord thy God require of thee.</hi> And as <hi>Adam</hi> was to pleaſe God by keeping the Law of his Creation and performing the Covenant of Works, ſo now this power being loſt by the Fall, and man rendered unable to pleaſe God by the works of the Law, we muſt now only endeavour to pleaſe God by direction from the
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:004526_0008_100DA1736D6F87E0"/>
Goſpel. Therein the Lord hath ſhewed us what is good and what he doth require of us in order to pleaſe him. And particularly,</p>
            <p>(1) <hi>If we would pleaſe God we muſt believe in his Son.</hi> This is the great Command of God in the Goſpel, <hi>That we believe in the Name of his Only Begotten Son.</hi> And this is the ſummary Condition of the Goſpel Covenant. And as the Covenant of Works required us, <hi>To do and live,</hi> ſo the Covenant of Grace requires us, <hi>To believe &amp; be ſaved.</hi> And whoſoever now pleaſes God, muſt pleaſe him in his Son: For it is in <hi>Him only</hi> that he is well pleaſed with ſinners, <hi>Mat</hi> 3. 17. And all men out of Chriſt, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Anger of God; for <hi>He is angry with the wicked every day.</hi> Man being fallen and ſinful, and God being infinitely holy, of purer Eyes than to behold evil and that cannot look upon iniquity, it is impoſſible for men to obtain the Favour of God without Faith in his Son, So the Apoſtle tells us, Heb 116. That <hi>without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi> This therefore is the only way which God hath found out &amp; reveal'd in the Goſpel for men to pleaſe him, <hi>even to believe in Chriſt:</hi> By which we ſhall obtain the forgiveneſs of our Sins and an Inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all them that are ſanctified: And ſo ſoon as we are Juſtified by Faith, we have Peace with God thro' our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5 1.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="unknown:004526_0008_100DA1736D6F87E0"/>
(2) <hi>The way for men to pleaſe God, is to Repent &amp; turn from all their Sins.</hi> This is another great goſpel Command, Act<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 17. 30. <hi>He now commands all men every where to repent.</hi> This Repentance implies the work of God's grace in the thoro' Change of heart and life; which the Apoſtle calls. <hi>A turning from darkneſs unto light, &amp; from the power of ſatan unto God,</hi> Act. 26. 18 And this the Goſpel doth require of men, in order to the obtaining the Pardon of their Sins and the Favour of God, Act. 3. 19. <hi>Repent ye therefore and be converted, that your ſins may be blotted out.</hi> And in this way God does in his Word give men good aſſurance of their obtaining his Favour; See Iſa. 1. 16, 17 <hi>Waſh you, make you clean, put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes; ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Come now, let us reaſon together, ſaith the Lord; though your ſins are as ſcarlet, they ſhall be white as ſnow; though they be red like crimſon, they ſhall be as wool.</hi> So Iſa<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 557. <hi>Let the wicked forſake his way, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous man his thoughts, and let him return to the Lord and he will have mercy on him, and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon.</hi> So Jer. 3 12. <hi>Go and proclaim theſe words towards the north, and ſay, Return thou backſliding Iſrael, ſaith the Lord, and I will not cauſe mine anger to fall upon you for I am merciful, ſaith the Lord, and will not keep anger for ever.</hi> So Jer. 31. 20. Upon their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance God ſaith, <hi>Is Ephraim my dear ſon? is
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:004526_0009_100DA176055DFE30"/>
he a pleaſant child? for ſince I ſpake againſt him, I do earneſtly remember him ſtill; therefore my bowels are troubled for him, I will ſurely have mercy upon him, ſaith the Lord God.</hi> And ſo in the Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal's return to his Father, Luk 15 20. <hi>While he was yet a great way off, his Father ſaw him and had compaſſion, and ran &amp; fell on his neck &amp; kiſſed him.</hi> Chriſt ſhews us how well pleaſed God is in the Return of Sinners to him.</p>
            <p>(3) <hi>The way for men to pleaſe God, is to become Holy, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th in heart &amp; life.</hi> If we would be pleaſing unto God, we muſt be Converted, Renewed and Sanctified by the grace of God: For the Apoſtle tells us plainly Rom. 8 8 That <hi>they that are in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God.</hi> That is, Thoſe that are in a ſtate of Sin and Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. And as we muſt be Holy in heart, ſo alſo in life. If we would pleaſe God, we muſt lead a life of holineſs and conformity to the Will of God, indeavouring always to <hi>keep a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience void of offence both toward God and toward men.</hi> For altho' our beſt works being imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, cannot Juſtify us before God, yet when we are in Chriſt by Faith, God is well pleaſed with our good works &amp; does graciouſly accept them, &amp; will for Chriſt's ſake reward them. Thus we read, That <hi>God had a reſpect to Abel and to his offering,</hi> Gen. 4. 4. And ſo he hath to the Perſons and Services of his People. Thus the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us, Pſal 11. 7. That <hi>the righteous Lord loveth
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:004526_0009_100DA176055DFE30"/>
righteouſneſs, and his countenance doth behold the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right</hi> And God hath in all Ages of the world manifeſted his Favour &amp; Love to thoſe that have walked obediently before him. And the Lord promiſed his People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (and always made good his Promiſe to them) <hi>That he would be with them while they are with him.</hi> And ſo the Apoſtle ſaith indeed concerning all others, Act. 10 34, 35 <hi>Of a truth,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>God is no reſpecter of perſons; but in every nation he that feareth him and worketh righteouſneſs is accepted with him.</hi> And truly it is but vain for men to flatter themſelves that they pleaſe God, when they walk in a courſe of Sin &amp; Rebellion againſt him. For <hi>he hates all the workers of iniquity,</hi> and <hi>is angry with the wicked every day,</hi> Pſal 7 11. Theſe are the ways which the Goſpel directs us to in order to pleaſe God, and there is no poſſibility of pleaſing Him in any other way. And thus much for the firſt particular.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing for the clearing of this Propoſition, is, <hi>To ſhew that thus to pleaſe God is the beſt way to be Secured from all Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this appears,</p>
            <p>(1) <hi>Becauſe God is Almighty.</hi> And that he is ſo is fully declared in his Word and Works. Thus God was pleaſed to make himſelf known to the Fathers, to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> by the <hi>Name of God Almighty,</hi> Exod. 6 3. And his Eternal Power &amp; Godhead is ſeen in the things
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:004526_0010_100DA17869B54AB8"/>
that he hath made, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 20. And God is ſaid to be Almighty, becauſe he can do all things ſimply in their own nature poſſible to be done, which do not contradict the Nature of God nor the Creature And being Almighty he is able to ſecure &amp; defend us from all our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, both of Soul &amp; Body Be they never ſo Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, yet they are not Omnipotent. And if we pleaſe Him he will m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt certainly do it. Thus when <hi>Job</hi> by his holy &amp; upright walking pleaſed God, Satan ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of him, <hi>That God had made an hedge about him, and about all that he had on every ſide,</hi> Job 1. 10. Now it was the Power of God that made this Hedge, ſo that neither Men nor Devil could break over it to do <hi>Job</hi> any harm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> until God gave them leave. And therefore <hi>Eliphaz</hi> adviſed <hi>Job, To acquaint him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with God and be at Peace:</hi> And then tells him, <hi>That the Almighty would be his defence,</hi> Job 22. 25 And truly a better Defence it is not poſſible for a man to have And therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> mentions this as the great Privilege and Security of the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> That <hi>the Eternal God was their Refuge, and underneath were his everlaſting Arms:</hi> And that they were a People ſaved by the Lord, <hi>who was the ſhield <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f their help and the ſword of their excellency,</hi> Deut 33 27, 29.</p>
            <p>(2) <hi>For men to pleaſe God is the beſt way for them to be ſecured from all their Enemies, Becauſe he is the All-wiſe God, who is infinite in Wiſdom, and knows
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:004526_0010_100DA17869B54AB8"/>
all things which have been, are, or ever ſhall be. Known unto God are all his works from the foundation of the world.</hi> He ſees in the darkneſs, and the light dwells with him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And there is no darkneſs nor ſhadow of death where the workers of iniquity may hide themſelves: And all things are naked and opened unto the Eyes of him with whom we have to do: And he ſearcheth the hearts &amp; tries the reins of all the Children of men; and no thought can be withheld from him. And therefore he ſees all the ſecret Plots &amp; Deſigns of our Enemies againſt us, and can eaſily diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and diſappoint them, and turn their counſels into fooliſhneſs: And let them dig never ſo deep, they cannot hide their Counſels from the Lord, And therefore to pleaſe God &amp; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gage him on our ſide, is the beſt way to be ſecured from all our Enemies For he being infinite in Wiſdom, <hi>can take the wiſe in their own cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tineſs, ſo that their hands cannot perform their enterpriſe:</hi> And if we have the Almighty &amp; All-wiſe God on our ſide, we need not fear what Men or Devils can do againſt us.</p>
            <p>(3) <hi>For men to pleaſe God is the beſt way to be ſecured from all their Enemies, Becauſe he is Omni-preſent.</hi> He is of Infinite Preſence neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in any Place, nor excluded from any Place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but is every where Preſent. And God being preſent every where, if we can but pleaſe him &amp; get him on our ſide, He <hi>will be a preſent
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:004526_0011_100DA17B4DC7BD90"/>
help in time of trouble.</hi> Many perſons have been overcome by their Enemies, becauſe their help hath been at a diſtance from them: But God is with us always, where ever we are: And we can never go from his Spirit, nor fly from his Preſence. He is not only <hi>a God at hand,</hi> but <hi>a God afar off:</hi> And none can hide themſelves in ſecret places that he ſhould not ſee them. Go where we will, God is always with us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And ſo his Favour will be our beſt Security from all our Enemies.</p>
            <p>(4) <hi>To pleaſe God is the beſt way to be ſecured from all our Enemies, Becauſe he is the Everlaſting God.</hi> He is the ſame <hi>Yeſterday, to Day and for Ever.</hi> All other things that we can truſt to or depend upon for Protection from our Enemies, are but mortal, fading &amp; periſhing things: And tho' they might be able to deliver us if they could continue with us, yet by reaſon of their Frailty, they leave us to ſhift for our ſelves; and it may be, when we have moſt need of them. But God is the <hi>true God, the living God, and the everlaſting King.</hi> He is the Lord JEHOVAH, in whom is Everlaſting Strength. And is the ſame in all Generations. As able to Protect us now, as he was our Fathers in the days of old; and is <hi>a strong habitation, where unto we may continually reſort.</hi> And his Name is <hi>a ſtrong Tower, to which we may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and be ſafe.</hi> And therefore the beſt way for us to be ſecured from all our Enemies
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:004526_0011_100DA17B4DC7BD90"/>
is to pleaſe him; and ſo we ſhall get <hi>the Eternal God to be our Refuge, and his Everlaſting Arms underneath us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(5) <hi>To pleaſe God is the beſt way to be ſecured from all our Enemies, Becauſe he is the Lord of Hoſts, that hath the command &amp; diſpoſal o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all Creatures in Heaven &amp; Earth, and always doth his Pleaſure both in the Armies of Heaven &amp; amongſt the Inhabitants of the Earth; and none can ſtay his Hand:</hi> And even the worſt of Men, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, the Devils them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are ſubject to his Univerſal Kingdom and are under his Command., Now as we are apt to look upon our ſelves very ſecure when we have the Favour &amp; Friendſhip of ſome mighty King, that has many Subjects under his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo much more reaſon have we to look upon our ſelves very ſecure indeed, when the Lord of Hoſts is with us, who hath all Angels, Men and Things under his Command. Therefore the Church doth rejoice &amp; triumph in this, Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 46 7. That <hi>the Lord of hoſts was with her, and the God of Jacob was her refuge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(6) <hi>It will further appear to be the best way to be ſecured from all Enemies, even to pleaſe God, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we conſider that he is the Preſerver of all things</hi> As he made, ſo he upholds all things by the word of his Power: And every thing is dependant on him for their continuance in being. And God need not put forth any act of Power to deſtroy the World, but the very ſuſpenſion of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:004526_0012_100DA17FD99CA400"/>
Power would be ſufficient for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Hence he is called, <hi>The Preſerver of man and beaſt.</hi> And in his hand <hi>is the Soul of every living thing, and the Breath of all mankind:</hi> And it is in him <hi>we live, move and have our being;</hi> and his <hi>Viſitation preſerves our ſpirits:</hi> And therefore none of our Enemies can take away our Lives from us, without his leave &amp; permiſſion. And neither our Life nor our Enemies, is in their hand, but in God's. And therefore the beſt way for us to be ſecured from all our Enemies, both of Soul &amp; Body, is to pleaſe God and get him on our ſide. And we may then ſay with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, Rom. 8. 31. <hi>If God be for us, who can be againſt us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(7) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>It will further appear that to pleaſe God is the beſt way to be ſecured from all Enemies, if we compare God's Favour &amp; Protection, with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n do or poſſibly can put their Trust in for Safety, beſides God</hi> And truly we ſhall find that whatever we do or can put our Truſt in beſides God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is but vain. If we truſt to foreign Aids &amp; Helps, they will commonly prove but as <hi>Egypt</hi> did to the <hi>Jews,</hi> Even <hi>like a broken Reed, on which if a man lean it will go into his hand &amp; pierce him,</hi> Iſa 366 Or if we truſt to our own Numbers of men, the Pſalmiſt tells us, <hi>It is better to truſt in the Lord than to put confidence in man,</hi> Pſal. 118. 8. Or if we ſhould truſt to our Military Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as Horſes, Chariots, or the like, the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:004526_0012_100DA17FD99CA400"/>
tells us, <hi>That an horſe is a vain thing for ſafety, neither can he deliver any by his great ſtrength,</hi> Pſal 33. 17. And the Church renounces truſt in Chariots &amp; Horſes, and rather chuſes to truſt in God, Pſal 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7. <hi>Some truſt in chariots, and ſome in horſes; but we will remember the Name of the Lord our God.</hi> And if we ſhould make ſtrong Walls &amp; Bulwarks for our defence, they could not Protect us without God: For the Pſalmiſt tells us, That <hi>Except the Lord keep the city, the watchmen waketh but in vain.</hi> And if we put our truſt in Kings or Princes, however under God they may be a defence to us, <hi>Yet it is better to truſt in the Lord, than to put confidence in Princes,</hi> Pſal. 118. 9. And therefore the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> bids us <hi>not put our trust in princes, nor in the ſon of man in whom there is no help: His breath goeth forth, he returneth to his earth, in that very day his thoughts periſh.</hi> But ſaith he, <hi>Happy is he that hath the God of Jacob for his help, whoſe hope is in the Lord his God,</hi> Pſal. 146. 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>And thus I have finiſhed what I deſigned for the Proof of the Doctrine, and proceed to the <hi>Improvement</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>USE, I. OF INFORMATION.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>If it be then as we have heard, That it is the beſt way for a Perſon or People to be ſecured from their Enemies, even to pleaſe God; then hence we may ſee, on the other hand, That for a Perſon or People to Provoke and Diſpleaſe God, is the moſt ready way
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:004526_0013_100DA1827A5C1FE0"/>
to lay themſelves Open &amp; Expoſed to their Enemies.</hi> And as, when God is for us none can be againſt us; ſo when He is againſt us none can be for us. And as when a People pleaſe God, his Favour is as an hedge and wall of Security round about them, to keep off all Adverſaries &amp; evil Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: So when a People diſpleaſe God they break down this Hedge, and lay themſelves open to all their Enemies. And this we may obſerve in the Experience of the People of God in all Ages. And as the Lord by <hi>Moſes</hi> threatned them, Deut 32. 21,—25. That <hi>Becauſe they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked him to jealouſie, therefore he would let in their Enemies upon them</hi> As we may ſee he did in after ages And while they pleaſed him he gave them Peace, and ſecured them from their Enemies but when they provoked him by their Sins, be ſent the Sword upon them to avenge the quarrel of his Covenant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And the like we may expect, that God will ſtill do with his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in all after ages: For God is ſtill the ſame, and <hi>with him is no reſpect of Perſons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a very dangerous thing for men to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe God; and they take the moſt ready way to bring ruin and deſtruction upon themſelves. And truly, he knows not what the anger of God means, that cannot ſee all Woes, Plagues and Miſeries in the boſom of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>This Doctrine may inform ſuch as are concerned in the Electing of Perſons to any place of Civil Rule
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:004526_0013_100DA1827A5C1FE0"/>
and Government among a People, how to direct their Choice.</hi> If the pleaſing of God be the beſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and Security of a People, then make choice of ſuch Men who are moſt conſcientious in the pleaſing of God in their ways; ſuch as are true fearers of God and beſt friends to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. It is true indeed, That <hi>Godlineſs alone is not ſufficient to Qualifie men for places of Power and Truſt in the Common Wealth.</hi> Every good man is not fit for a Ruler<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> There are other Qualifications tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> eye muſt be had to in the Choice of Civil Rulers: For <hi>Wiſdom &amp; Knowlege</hi> are alſo neceſſary in a Ruler. The great God whom Rulers repreſent, and whom they ought to reſemble, is <hi>a God of Knowlege, by whom Actions are weighed.</hi> And truly, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent &amp; Imprudent men are as unfit to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at the Helm of Government, as an Unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Pilot at the Helm of a Ship. And that the happy Ends of Government may be obtained, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe that are intruſted with it ſhould be like the men of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> which were <hi>men that had underſtanding of the Times, to know what Iſrael ought to do,</hi> 1 Chron 12 32. It was therefore a needful direction that <hi>Moſes</hi> gave to <hi>Iſrael</hi> about the choice of Rulers, Deut. 1. 13 <hi>Take ye wiſe men and underſtanding and known among your tribes, &amp; I will make them rulers over you.</hi> And it was a needful requeſt of <hi>Solomon, Give me wiſdom and knowlege, to go in &amp; out before the people,</hi> 2 Chron.
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:004526_0014_100DA184495EA6B0"/>
1. 10. <hi>Juſtice and Faithfulneſs</hi> are alſo neceſſary Qualifications in a Ruler. This is plainly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, 2 Sam. 13. 3. <hi>The God of Iſrael ſaid, He that ruleth over men muſt be juſt.</hi> And if this be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Rulers, the Ruled will have cauſe to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it Prov. 29. 2. <hi>When the wicked bear rule the people mourn.</hi> And again, <hi>Courage &amp; Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is neceſſary. Rulers muſt be men of Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage becauſe of the many difficulties they will meet with in the faithful diſcharge of their Truſt. And they ſhould not fear the faces of men, <hi>Deut</hi> 1. 17 All ſuch Qualifications are very deſirable in Rulers: But <hi>Piety and the pleaſing of God,</hi> is the prime Qualification, and that which will put a Luſtre on all the reſt. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as a People deſire their own protection &amp; ſecurity, they ſhould chooſe ſuch to be Rulers as pleaſe God themſelves, and indeavour what they can to promote it in all thoſe under their Government.</p>
            <p>USE, II. OF EXHORTATION, Unto all, to indeavour in their reſpective places to promote the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing of God, ſeeing the Protection &amp; Security of a People doth ſo much depend upon it.</p>
            <p>And particularly,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>This Exhortation may be propoſed to</hi> RU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LERS, <hi>Indeavour to promote the pleaſing of God among this People</hi> And here, I hope I may take leave, in all humble ſubmiſſion, and in a deep
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:004526_0014_100DA184495EA6B0"/>
ſenſe of my own unworthineſs, to propoſe this Exhortation to the Honourable the GOVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOUR, the DEPUTY-GOVERNOUR, and the Worſhipful ASSISTANTS in Government, who are, or this Day may be Eſtabliſhed, or Re-eſtabliſhed Rulers over us, with the reſt of the Gentlemen of the GENERAL ASSEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLY here preſent. <hi>Honourable, Worſhipful and much Reſpected,</hi> You doubtleſs know that the Publick good is the end of Government, Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 4. <hi>He is the miniſter of God to thee for good.</hi> Rulers are to deſign and indeavour the Publick good of thoſe over whom Providence hath placed them. And this being the end of your Advancement, ſuffer me to remind you, <hi>That the moſt likely way to promote the Security &amp; Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of a People, is to promote the Pleaſing of God.</hi> And it cannot be reaſonably expected, that a People can do well &amp; be well, while they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe God and are a generation of his Wrath. Oh! Therefore do all that may be done by you to promote the pleaſing of God. And,</p>
            <p>(1) <hi>Be careful always to recommend the pleaſing of God, by your own Example to thoſe under your Rule, and be bright Examples in every good Work.</hi> And let all thoſe under your Rule ſee that you make it your main ſtudy, not to pleaſe men but God that tries your hearts. Good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are more influential than naked Precepts, and direct us better in the practiſe of Vertue,
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:004526_0015_100DA1870BDA4958"/>
and have an incouraging influence. And it is on many accounts neceſſary that you ſhine as Stars in your exalted Stations by the light of an holy Converſation; that you be Exemplary in every good work. Rulers being Leaders, had need to be always careful that they don't go wrong, for they will be apt to Lead many after them: and then the Event is like to be very ſad, Iſa 9 16 <hi>The leaders of this people cauſe them to err, &amp; thoſe that are led of them are deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(2) <hi>You may do much towards the promoting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion &amp; the pleaſing of God, by putting ſuch in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Power, as are truly Religious and have the fear of God in their hearts, &amp; are careful to pleaſe God.</hi> Tho' this Qualification be not of it ſelf ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, yet it may not be ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>look'd And truly if regard be not had to this, both our Civil and Sacred in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt will be much indangered. Men of looſe Principles and Practiſes, are not fit to fill up the Seats of Government. Thoſe that can't rule themſelves, are not fit to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> others. And truly, to advance ſuch to Place as are men of looſe Conver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, is the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dy way to bring in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rophaneneſs like a flood P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 12 8 <hi>The wicked</hi> will <hi>walk on every ſide, when the vileſt men are exalted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(3) <hi>You may alſo do much towards the pleaſing of God, by indeavouring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Prevent and Suppreſs every thing that is diſpleaſing to God, even all Vice &amp; Immorality.</hi> This muſt be done, or God cannot
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:004526_0015_100DA1870BDA4958"/>
be pleaſed: For <hi>he hates all the workers of iniquity and is angry with the wicked every day.</hi> Sin is that <hi>abominable thing that God hates;</hi> and his <hi>wrath is revealed from heaven againſt all ungodlineſs &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs of men</hi> And therefore, Sirs, as you would pleaſe God, do what you can to ſuppreſs Sin, and improve your Power againſt it to the uttermoſt: and be like <hi>Phinehas</hi> of old, <hi>who was zealous for God and againſt Sin;</hi> and <hi>bear not the Sword in vain,</hi> but <hi>whet &amp; brand ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it againſt Sin;</hi> and indeavour in the uſe of all proper means the Reformation of every thing that is amiſs among us. Let proper Laws be made againſt Sin, wherein they are wanted, and let the juſt and wholſome Laws already made, be faithfully Executed. And remember that you are God's Miniſters avengers to execute wrath on them that do evil <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 3 And if Sin be duly Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, it will be a good means to Suppreſs it. For this is the main deſign of humane puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to prevent Sin. Deut 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 11. <hi>All Iſrael ſhall hear &amp; fear, &amp; do no mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch wickedneſs.</hi> And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if Sin can be prevented &amp; ſuppreſs'd, we have reaſon to hope that God will be well pleaſed.</p>
            <p>Theſe, Sirs? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e things of Moment belonging to your Truſt which I would humbly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to you. And for your Encouragement, I might remind you, That this will gain you Honour &amp; Reſpect, both with God and men; and the remembrance hereof will be comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:004526_0016_100D82F7106718C0"/>
to you both in Life and Death; and then you will be able to ſay, as he did after great Services done for the Publick, Neh 5 19. <hi>Think upon me, O my God for good, according to all that I have done for this People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>This Exhortation may be propoſed to my Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers and Brethren in the</hi> MINISTRY. O Sirs, if the pleaſing of God, be as we have heard, the beſt way to protect &amp; ſecure a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from all their Enemies then ſuffer me, my Brethren, tho' leſs than the leaſt of all Saints, and the moſt unworthy of your Order, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind my ſelf and you, of the great Neceſſity lying upon us to indeavour the pleaſing of God.</p>
            <p>And particularly,</p>
            <p>(1) <hi>Let us ſee to it that me pleaſe God our ſelves.</hi> Let us ſtudy to ſhew our ſelves approved unto God; and let us indeavour to pleaſe him in all our ways. Let us be ſincere &amp; upright in our walking with God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and let us indeavour to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our whole Converſation aright before him. We that are ſet to teach others, ought in the firſt place to teach our ſelves; and ſhould learn &amp; practiſe thoſe leſſons which we teach others. And we muſt be le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Self-Condemned and Speechleſs in the Great Day, if we do it not. Surely, the love and regard of our own Souls ſhould quicken us hereunto And tho' we have been teachers of others, yet if we neglect our ſelves, Chriſt will refuſe us at the Laſt Day:
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:004526_0016_100D82F7106718C0"/>
as he hath told us, Mat. 7. 22, 23. <hi>Many will ſay unto me, Lord, Lord, have we not propheſied in thy Name? and in thy Name caſt out devils? and in thy Name done many wonderful works? And then I will profeſs unto them, I never knew you; depart from me ye that work iniquity.</hi> And, Oh! How ſad &amp; diſmal would our State be, if Chriſt ſhould ſo ſay to any of us in the Laſt Day? We muſt then, when it is too late, eternally Mourn over our wretched Souls, and ſay, as it is in, Cant. 1. 6. <hi>They made me the keeper of the Vineyard, but mine own Vineyard have I not kept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(2) <hi>As we ſhould indeavour to pleaſe God our ſelves, ſo let us indeavour to promote it in Others.</hi> Let us do our Utmoſt that every one of our People may pleaſe God and become Religious. Let us zealouſly indeavour the Reformation of growing Evils. Let us <hi>Cry aloud and not ſpare, and lift up our voice like a Trumpet to ſhew our People their tranſgreſſions and ſins.</hi> Let us faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Warn the wicked of his way to turn from it. Let us indeavour to do all the Duties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to our Miniſtry faithfully. Let us <hi>take heed to the Miniſtry which we have received of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> that we <hi>fulfil it.</hi> And let us be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon; Reprove, rebuke and Exhort with all long-ſuffering &amp; doctrine.</hi> Let us not only <hi>take heed unto our ſelves,</hi> but to all <hi>the Flock over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made us Overſeers, to feed the Church of God which he hath
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:004526_0017_100DA18C7783A798"/>
purchaſed with his own Blood.</hi> Let us teach tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors God's ways, that ſinners may be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted unto him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And to all our indeavours, let us add our fervent Prayers to the God of all grace, for the down-pouring of his Spirit: And let us make that our conſtant Requeſt, mention'd by the Prophet, Hab 3. 2. <hi>Revive thy work, O Lord, in the midſt of the years, in the midſt of the years make known; in wrath remember mercy.</hi> And to quicken us to all faithfulneſs in the diſcharge of our Truſt, let us remember the ſolemn Charge of God that is upon us, and the many Souls committed to our Care: Every one of which is of more Value than all the World; and for every one of which we muſt give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count unto God: And if any of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in through our neglect, God will ſeverely require their Blood at our hands.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>This Exhortation may be propoſed to</hi> PARENTS <hi>and</hi> HEADS <hi>of</hi> FAMILIES. Seeing the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God is the beſt way for the ſecurity of a People from all their Enemies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Exhorted to do your utmoſt to pleaſe God, both in your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons &amp; Families. Good Family Government and Inſtruction, hath a wonderful tendency to promote Religion, And the ſavour of what ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons our Youth commonly abides till old Age, Prov. 22. 6. <hi>Train up a child in the way he ſhould go, and when he is old he will not depart from it.</hi> And we may obſerve all the world over, how
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:004526_0017_100DA18C7783A798"/>
tenacious men are of what is delivered to them by their Parents, be it good or bad. And the neglect of good Family Government and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, is fatal &amp; ruinous to Religion and to the Souls of men. And too many Parents, &amp; ſome of thoſe that are otherwiſe Religious, yet are guilty of too many Neglects herein, either thro' Careleſneſs, worldly Incumbrance, or fond Indulgence. And by this means many of the Off-ſpring of godly Parents, turn into degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Plants and prove a generation that know not the God of their Fathers. And thus are many ſpoiled in the Bud, for want of good Family Care. And there are ſome other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents that are Rude &amp; Ignorant, who perhaps have been Bred themſelves much like the Beaſts they converſe with, and they breed up their Children without any thing of Religion in their Families. And there are others in the world, that breed up their Children as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanely, as the others do Sottiſhly; Teaching them, at leaſt by their Example, the neweſt Oaths that were laſt formed in Hell; and to Revile &amp; Scoff at all ſerious godlineſs and the Profeſſors of it: And perhaps ſomtime ſmiling to hear with what Emphaſis they can ſpeak in the dialect of Devils, and how wittily they can deride &amp; ſcoff at the godly. Such Families are but Nurſeries for Hell: And though God may ſomtimes ſnatch one or two of them by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion,
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:004526_0018_100DA18F55408958"/>
from among them, <hi>as Brands out of the Fire,</hi> yet generally they die as they live and go to the <hi>generation of their Fathers, where they ſhall never ſee light.</hi> Oh! Then of what vaſt Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is it for all Parents to ſee to it, that both they and their Houſes do ſerve &amp; pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>And to quicken them here unto,</p>
            <p>(1) <hi>Let all Parents Conſider what a fearful thing it will be, for them to be the Inſtruments of Ruining for ever, thoſe that received their Beings Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally from them; and to ſeek whoſe Welfare they ſtood obliged by all the Laws of God &amp; Nature.</hi> And in vain are all your Cares and Studies for their Bodies, whileſt their Souls Periſh for want of Knowlege. You, perhaps, Rejoiced at their Birth; but they will have cauſe to Curſe the day they were Born of you. You were careful of their Bodies, but careleſs of their Souls; Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to ſee them Rich, but indifferent whether they were Gracious. You neglected to teach them the way of Salvation, but the Devil did not neglect to teach them the way of Sin. You will one day wiſh, You had never been Parents, when the doleful Cries of your damned Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhall ring ſuch Notes as theſe in your ears, <hi>Oh! Curſed Father, Oh! Cruel and Mercileſs Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whoſe Example hath drawn me after you into all this Miſery. You had Time enough &amp; Motives enough, to have Warned me of this place of Miſery, while my heart was tender &amp; my affections pliable.
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:004526_0018_100DA18F55408958"/>
Had it not been as Eaſie for you to have Chaſtned me when I Sinned againſt God, as when I Provok'd you about a Trifle? One word ſpoken in ſeaſon might have ſaved my Soul.</hi> And, Oh! Who can think without horror &amp; amazement, of theſe &amp; ſuch like Cries &amp; Curſes of their Children, who have been caſt away and eternally loſt, by the very Inſtruments of their Being?</p>
            <p>(2) <hi>Let all Parents Conſider, That God hath In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted them with the Care of their Children; and doth require them to do, as</hi> Abraham <hi>did, even to command their Children &amp; Houſhold after them to keep the ways of the Lord: And will ſeverely Puniſh them (and probably in their Children) if they prove Negligent herein.</hi> Think and tremble at what God threatned againſt good <hi>Eli</hi> for this, 1 Sam. 3. 13 <hi>For I have told him, That I will judge his houſe for ever, for the iniquity which he knoweth, becauſe his ſons made themſelves vile and he reſtrained them not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly, <hi>This Exhortation may be propoſed to the</hi> BODY OF THIS PEOPLE. And, Sirs, it being a time of War and Rumors of War, and there is a probability that God will join our Enemies together. Every conſiderate Perſon will be ready to Enquire, <hi>What will be our beſt Security from the Invaſions of our Enemies?</hi> And, Sirs, in <hi>Anſwer</hi> to this <hi>Enquiry,</hi> I have this Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from God unto you, <hi>Oh! Endeavour to pleaſe God in all your ways, bec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me truly godly, and devote
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:004526_0019_100DA19180F773A8"/>
your ſelves to his Service; and endeavour always to have a Conſcience void of Offence toward God and toward men, and ſo get God to be your Friend, and then you need not fear what man can do unto you.</hi> And, dear Sirs, I have little reaſon to believe that I ſhall ever ſtand again in this Desk, upon ſuch a publick Occaſion; for I am now grown into Years, and am going the way of all the Earth: And I would therefore leave it with you as my dying Counſel and ſolemn Charge, <hi>That as you deſire to be ſafe here &amp; happy for ever, you would now and hence forward ſet your ſelves to pleaſe God in all your Ways.</hi> This, Oh! This, Sirs, will be greatly for your Comfort while you live; this will be your Rejoicing, <hi>even the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of your Conſcience, that in ſimplicity &amp; godly ſincerity, not in fleſhly wiſdom, but by the grace of God you have had your Converſation in the world.</hi> And this will alſo be for your unſpeakable Rejoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing when you come to leave the world, if you are able to ſay, as good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did upon his ſuppos'd Death-bed, <hi>Remember, O Lord, how I have walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and have done that which was right in thine eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this way you may with good grounds expect, That <hi>God will ſtill he with you, as he hath been with your Fathers,</hi> That <hi>He will not leave nor forſake you;</hi> but will ſtill be a <hi>Wall of Fire round about you, and the Glory in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he midſt of you;</hi> and that <hi>his Salvation ſhall ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for Walls &amp; Bulwarks.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
