<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The danger of spiritual pride represented. A sermon preach'd at Philadelphia, December the 30th, 1744. On Romans XII. 3. With some enlargements. / By Gilbert Tennent, A.M. Minister of the Gospel at Philadelphia. ; [Four lines from Proverbs]</title>
            <author>Tennent, Gilbert, 1703-1764.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N04585</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N04585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 5696</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APY3578</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">5696</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99030697</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 5696.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N04585)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 5696)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 5696)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The danger of spiritual pride represented. A sermon preach'd at Philadelphia, December the 30th, 1744. On Romans XII. 3. With some enlargements. / By Gilbert Tennent, A.M. Minister of the Gospel at Philadelphia. ; [Four lines from Proverbs]</title>
                  <author>Tennent, Gilbert, 1703-1764.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30, [2] p. ;  15 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Bradford, at the Sign of the Bible in Second-Street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1745]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Issued with Tennent's "The necessity of keeping the soul" (Evans 5699). The two sermons are signed continuously, and the "Corrigenda" (p. [31]) corrects errors in that work.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons --  1744.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:005696_0000_1026C1444F055258"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:005696_0001_1026C1460D29CFE0"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Danger of Spiritual</hi> PRIDE <hi>repreſented.</hi> A SERMON PREACH'D AT <hi>PHILADELPHIA, December</hi> the 30th, 1744. On ROMANS XII. 3. WITH SOME ENLARGEMENTS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GILBERT TENNENT,</hi> A. M. Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Philadelphia.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. xi. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When Pride cometh, then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Shame: But with the lowly is wiſdom.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. xiii. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Only by Pride cometh Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, but with the well adviſed is wiſdom.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>PHILADELPHIA:</hi> Printed by WILLIAM BRADFORD, at the Sign of the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Second-Street.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="unknown:005696_0002_1026C14A45F34CD8"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROMANS XII. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For I ſay, through the Grace given unto me, to every Man that is among you, not to think of himſelf more highly than he ought to think; but to think ſoberly according as God hath dealt to every Man the Meaſure of Faith.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Apoſtle having in the firſt Verſe of this Chapter, affectionately Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the believing <hi>Romans,</hi> to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs in general; does more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in the following Verſes, diſſwade them from two Evils which are great Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances thereof, <hi>viz. Conformity to the ſinful Cuſtoms of the World,</hi> and <hi>high Thoughts of their own Attainments.</hi> It is the laſt of theſe which the Apoſtle ſpeaks againſt in the Words of our Text, <hi>For I ſay through the Grace given unto me: i. e.</hi> I require and enjoyn you, by the Authority that God has graciouſly given me as an Apoſtle, <note n="*" place="bottom">1 Cor. iii. 10.</note> 
               <hi>to every Man that is among you: i. e.</hi> To one as well as another: As if the Apoſtle had ſaid; I addreſs you all, my
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:005696_0003_1026C14CB7DD3948"/>
Brethren, as if I particularly mentioned your Names; I except none of any Condition or Character, for you all need the Injunction, <hi>not to think of himſelf more highly than he ought to think: i. e.</hi> Not to be proud or puffed up with overweening extravagant Conceits of his Endowments and Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſuch as wiſdom, ability, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but to think ſoberly, <hi>i. e.</hi> modeſtly; <q>let him contain himſelf within Bounds, and not take upon him what doth not belong to him; let him not contemn others, and pretend to more than he hath. <note n="‡" place="bottom">See <hi>Pool</hi>'s Annotations</note>
               </q> 
               <hi>As God hath dealt to every Man the Meaſure of Faith.</hi> By Faith the Apoſtle doubtleſs intends, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Gifts, which are called Faith, becauſe they are given with it, and exercis'd by it. Theſe Gifts are given forth in various De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees or Meaſures to the Children of Men, a modeſt Notice of which, we may, and ought to take, that ſo we may be induc'd to give to God the Glory of them, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag'd to improve them for his Honour and Kingdom. But then we ſhould be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that we do not indulge an unreaſonable Conceit of the Extent of our Powers, or
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:005696_0004_1026C14E4199DDC8"/>
Meaſure of our Talents, imagining them to be much greater than they are; for tho' that may flatter our Arrogance, yet it betrays our Ignorance and Weakneſs; it is as inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to our Honour among the Intelligent, as it is prejudicial to our Uſefulneſs in the World. It is ſurely a great Inſtance of true Wiſdom, to think ſoberly of our ſelves; and hence the original Word <note n="†" place="bottom">Sophronein.</note> in our Text, ſignifies <hi>to be wiſe to ſobriety.</hi> Mr. <hi>Poole</hi> juſtly obſerves, That there is an elegant Paranomaſia, (or ſymphony of Sounds) in this Place of Scripture in the <hi>Greek,</hi> which our Language cannot reach. <note n="‡" place="bottom">Me uperphronein, par O Dei phronein alla phronein, eis to Sophronein.</note>
            </p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid I would obſerve, That even good Men are in great Danger of ſpiritual Pride, and of being puffed up for a Time with groundleſs and fooliſh Conceits of their Attainments. If this was not the Caſe, there wou'd have been no Need of the Injunction in our Text; nether wou'd their have been any Neceſſity of a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Satan ſent to buffet <hi>Paul,</hi> leaſt he ſhould be lifted up thro' the Abundance of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations that were given him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="unknown:005696_0005_1026C150F4E03588"/>In Diſcourſing upon this Subject, I ſhall ſpeak upon the <hi>Nature, Ingredients, Cauſes, Fruits</hi> and <hi>Cure of ſpiritual Pride.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Pride, as to its general Nature, may be thus deſcrib'd, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is a ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Conceit of our Attainments, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with an inordinate Deſire of our own Honour and Contempt of our Neighbour's Excellencies and Credit. To underſtand which, let the following <hi>Ingredients</hi> (or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars included in it) be conſider'd, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt: High-Mindedneſs,</hi> which is the Loftineſs or Swelling of the Mind with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Self-Conceit. When Perſons have too high Thoughts of their Powers and Talents, and are hereby diſpoſed to over-value themſelves and undervalue others; this is as natural to Mankind as it is unreaſonable in it ſelf, and fatal in its Conſequnces. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this pernicious Evil, the Text I am diſcourſing upon is expreſly Directed. This is indeed the bitter Root, the poyſonous Fountain from which the other ſinful Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents graſp'd in ſpiritual Pride (which I ſhall anon mention) do flow. Againſt this the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:005696_0006_1026C154BB3009E0"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> excellently cautions the Gentile Churches, in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Rom. xi. 20.</note> in the following Words: <hi>Well, becauſe of Unbelief they were broken off;</hi> (meaning the <hi>Jews) and thou ſtandeſt by Faith. Be not high minded but fear.</hi> Now altho' gracious Perſons may for a Time be carried away with High-Mindedneſs, thro' the Violence of Temptation; yet to be under the Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual or general Government of it, is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Evidence of a bad State towards God. This the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us of in his Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy</hi> 
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">2 Tim. iii. 3, 4.</note> in theſe Words: <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out natural Affection, truce Breakers, falſe Accuſers, incontinent, fierce, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, Traytors, Heady, high Minded, Lovers of Pleaſures more than Lovers of God.</hi> Upon theſe Words, <hi>viz. heady, high-minded,</hi> Mr. <hi>Poole</hi> thus gloſſeth: <note n="†" place="bottom">Vide Pool's <hi>Annotations</hi> in loc.</note> 
               <q>Raſh, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate, blown up as Bladders with an Opinion of their own Deſerts.</q> You may obſerve in the Verſes now quoted, that the Apoſtle puts high-minded Perſons in the ſame Catalogue with the groſſeſt Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, and declares that they love not
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:005696_0007_1026C15644C24AD0"/>
God tranſcendently. Surely thoſe that are renewed by the Holy Ghoſt, do <hi>learn of Jeſus to be meek and lowly</hi> in their habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Temper of Mind and outward Behaviour. <note n="†" place="bottom">Matt. xi. 29.</note> They are made to <hi>receive the Kingdom of Heaven as little Children,</hi> 
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Luke xviii. 17.</note> 
               <hi>are Fools</hi> in their own Eyes; <note n="‡‡" place="bottom">1 Cor. iii. 18.</note> and in compariſon of many others, they ſometimes ſee themſelves to be in reſpect of Knowledge, <hi>but as brute Beaſts.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Prov. xxx. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſians,</hi> 
               <note n="¶" place="bottom">Coloſſ. ii. 18.</note> juſtly Terms high-mindedneſs, to be the <hi>puffing up of a Perſon, vainly by his fleſhly Mind;</hi> probably alluding to Liquors ſwelling by the Yeſt into Spume and Froth, which has a Shew but no Solidity. For indeed, Pride is to the Mind of Man, in reſpect of Agitation and Tumor, as Yeſt is to Liquors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly:</hi> Another <hi>Ingredient</hi> in ſpiritual Pride is <hi>Ambition,</hi> which is an inordinate Seeking of Dignity, or high Places; proud Perſons have aſpiring Thoughts, and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine themſelves to be the fitteſt to manage the Helm of the State, or the Church; and if
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:005696_0008_1026C158B9631210"/>
others don't think ſo, they are not well pleas'd; they cannot bear to have others preferred before them, altho' the Preference be juſt and reaſonable. Something of this ſinful Temper appear'd in the Apoſtles Conduct, before the extraordinary Effuſion of the Holy Spirit at Pentecoſt; <hi>there was alſo a Strife among them which of them ſhould be accounted the Greateſt.</hi> This our Lord ſeaſonably oppoſed, <note n="†" place="bottom">Luke xxii. 24, 25, 26.</note> and for what we can learn, it ſoon evaniſh'd. But when a Love of Preheminence among the Brethren is habitual as well as inordinate, and attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a <hi>malicious pratting</hi> againſt the faithful Servants of Chriſt, on the Account of ſmall Differences in Sentiment or Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, which ſeems to have been the Caſe of <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> as the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> informs us, <note n="‡" place="bottom">3 Epiſt. 9, 10.</note> it is an awful Sign of a bad State! But to proceed,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly:</hi> Another <hi>Ingredient</hi> in ſpiritual Pride is <hi>Arrogance;</hi> which conſiſts in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to what we have not, and in deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that others ſhould think of us above what we are or have; this was the Practice
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:005696_0009_1026C15A43953C80"/>
of the falſe Teachers who troubled the Church of <hi>Corinth;</hi> they commended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by boaſting of Things beyond their Meaſure, hereby ſeeking to leſſen their Eſteem of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> and other ſound Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <note n="†" place="bottom">2 Cor. x. 10,—12, 13.</note> The very contrary whereof he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined ſhou'd be the Meaſure of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct: <note n="‡" place="bottom">2 Cor. x. 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>For we dare not,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>make our ſelves of the Number, or compare our ſelves with ſome that commend themſelves.— But we will not boaſt of Things without our Meaſure, but according to the Meaſure of the Rule which God hath diſtributed to us.</hi> This leads me</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly:</hi> To another particular included in ſpiritual Pride, which is <hi>boaſting</hi> of the <hi>Gifts</hi> or <hi>Graces</hi> which we really have: Proud Perſons and Boaſters are put together in the ſame Claſs by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Rom. i. 30.</note> thus, <hi>Backbiters, haters, of God, deſpiteful, Proud, Boaſters.</hi> Proud Perſons are full of Blaze and Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation about their Attainments; they take up much of their Time in trumpeting their own Praiſes, either more openly or covertly,
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:005696_0010_1026C15D9BD970B8"/>
and wou'd have all to admire them without Cauſe, as they do themſelves. But this low Artifice, procures not for them the Eſteem and Reſpect they deſire and Deſign from the Judicious, but the Contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly:</hi> Another <hi>Ingredient</hi> in ſpiritual Pride is, <hi>Contempt</hi> of, and <hi>Envy</hi> againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Excellencies,</hi> becauſe they ſtand in our Light and ſeem to diminiſh our Luſtre. This the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> confirms <note n="†" place="bottom">Jam. iv. 5, 6.</note> in the following Words: <hi>Do ye think that the Scripture ſayeth in vain, the Spirit that dwelleth in us luſteth to Envy.</hi>—Wherefore he ſayeth, <hi>God reſiſteth the Proud, but giveth Grace to the Humble.</hi> As much as we over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value our own Attainments, ſo much will we be enclined to undervalue others, that ſo we may Triumph in an imaginary Aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant over them. But this Diſpoſition of Mind is very Diſpleaſing to God and detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to us; and hence <hi>Solomon</hi> aſſures us, <hi>that the Almighty ſcorneth the Scorners, but giveth Grace unto the lowly.</hi> 
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Prov. iii. 34.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly:</hi> Another <hi>Ingredient</hi> is <hi>Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which appears in our attempting what
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:005696_0011_1026C16102526FC8"/>
exceeds our Strength, and medling with Things two high for us. Proud Perſons are full of vain Confidence, not knowing their Ignorance and Weakneſs, they ruſh into Snares and graſp at a Weight which their Shoulders are not equal to. Directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this was the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>'s Practice, and hence he was able to appeal to God in the following Language: <hi>Lord my Heart is not haughty nor mine Eyes lofty, neither do I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe my ſelf in great Matters, or in Things too high for me.</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Pſalm cxxxi. 1.</note> In theſe Words it is plainly intimated, that haughty or proud Perſons have lofty Looks, and are diſpoſed to meddle with Things above their Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which turns to their Diſgrace in the Iſſue.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of <hi>Pride</hi> are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Our <hi>Violation</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Works,</hi> by this we have loſt the Image of God, and contracted that of the Devil, of which <hi>Pride</hi> is a dreadful Lineament, <note n="‡‡" place="bottom">Rom. vii. 18. Rom. iii. 12.19.</note> and altho' the Governing Power of this evil be broken by Converſion, yet there are ſuch Remains of it, as will be a Grief
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:005696_0012_1026C162881F0E48"/>
and Exerciſe to us while we live. <note n="‡" place="bottom">Rom. vii. 24.</note> This Original Apoſtacy is therefore the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cauſe of Pride. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A more immediate Cauſe is the <hi>neglect of our own Hearts.</hi> If theſe were conſtantly watch'd, and frequently examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as they ſhould be, we would ſee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Reaſon for Humiliation, and have an Opportuniry of giving check to the firſt budings of Pride within us; But when our Hearts are neglected, our Wickedneſs is hid from us, the firſt Motions of Sin are not oppos'd, and thus we are <hi>puff'd up in our vain Imaginations,</hi> and look on our ſelves in a falſe Light.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Another <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Pride,</hi> is the <hi>Temptations of the Devil.</hi> He tries to blow the Coal of Corruptions in us to a Flame; he ſooths our Vanity, and flatters our Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance until we fall from the imaginary Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle into the Myre. Thus he treated <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah;</hi> the former he ſtirr'd up to Number the People, <note n="†" place="bottom">1 Chron. xxi. 17.</note> and the Latter to ſhew his Treaſures to the <hi>Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Ambaſſador, which brought Wrath upon the Nation.<note n="‡‡" place="bottom">Iſa. xxxix. 4—7</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="unknown:005696_0013_1026C1640EC84570"/>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The <hi>groundleſs Eſteem</hi> and <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe</hi> of <hi>ignorant People,</hi> and the <hi>Hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Panegyricks</hi> of <hi>deſigning Paraſites,</hi> are apt to ſtir up Pride, tho' they be equally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of our Notice; for the former know not our Weakneſs, and the latter are not ſo Honeſt as to acquaint us of it.</p>
            <p>It is true, Applauſe is apt, at firſt eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, to affect and pleaſe us; for as <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerves, <hi>as the fining Pot is for Silver, and the Furnace for Gold, ſo is a Man to his Praiſe.</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Proverbs xxvii. 21.</note> However it is a Sign of a weak Mind to be frequently overcome by ſuch a Temptation! Certainly the leſs Knowledge we have of God, our ſelves, or the Things of God, and the ſmaller Meaſure of Divine Grace we poſſeſs, the more apt we are to be puff'd up. Superficial Notions of Things give Occaſion for Pride, but a thorough Knowledge of them has a humbling Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency.</p>
            <p>But I proceed to ſpeak of the <hi>Fruits</hi> of <hi>Pride,</hi> and that both in Relation to <hi>God, our ſelves,</hi> and <hi>others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in <hi>Relation to God, Pride</hi> has the
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:005696_0014_1026C167B3F010F8"/>
following awful <hi>Fruits!</hi> It diſpoſes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn his <hi>Authority,</hi> to ſlight his <hi>Love,</hi> to murmur at his <hi>Providence,</hi> and refuſe a <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> to his <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pride</hi> diſpoſes to diſdain the Divine <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> and Government, like the wicked <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> of whom the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſpeaks. <note n="‡" place="bottom">Jer. ii. 31.</note> 
               <hi>They ſaid they were Lords and would come no more to the Almighty.</hi> Surely thoſe that wou'd hear the Commands of God to Purpoſe, muſt oppoſe Pride, and hence the Prophet intreated the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the following Manner, <note n="†" place="bottom">Jer. xiii. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Hear ye, be not proud for the Lord hath ſpoken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed <hi>Pride</hi> does equally diſpoſe to <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> againſt the Divine Love and Goodneſs. The Reaſon of which is this, ſuch Perſons have a high Opinion of their own Excellency's, and hence are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to look upon the Gifts of God, as leſs then their Merit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pride</hi> does likewiſe for the ſame Reaſon diſpoſe Men to <hi>murmur</hi> at God's <hi>providential Government,</hi> of the World in general, and of their Lot in Particular. They think that
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:005696_0015_1026C16940AE7428"/>
Things are not ſo well manag'd as they ſhould be, and eſpecially as to their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances: The Language of which is, that had they been of God's Council, they could have taught him Knowledge. O blaſphemous Arrogance!</p>
            <p>I may add, that another <hi>Fruit</hi> of <hi>Pride</hi> in Relation to God, is the Sinners <hi>Labour</hi> to <hi>eſtabliſh a Way of Juſtification by his own Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>his Refuſal of Submiſſion to the Righteouſneſs of God.</hi> 
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Rom. x. 3.</note> The Pride of Man's Heart is ſuch, that he diſlikes to be ſtrip'd of all Self-Dependance, and ſav'd in a Way of pure Grace! But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Fruits of Pride in Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to our ſelves, are theſe; viz. It tends to deceive us, as to our <hi>State of Soul, and Progreſs in Religion, as well as to corrupt us in Principle and Practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pride</hi> tends to <hi>deceive</hi> us as to the <hi>State</hi> of our <hi>Souls,</hi> by inclining us to think that we are ſomething when we are nothing. <note n="*" place="bottom">Gal. vi. 3.</note> Many are prompted by the Pride of their Hearts, to take Conviction for Converſion; legal, for evangelical Sorrow, and Preſumption for
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:005696_0016_1026C16C98B4F768"/>
that Faith which works by love, and changes the Life as well as the Heart. What avail ſuch Comforts as do not humble the Soul and reform the Practice?</p>
            <p>But if it does not entirely deceive us as to the State of our Souls, yet it tends to impoſe a cheat on us, as to our <hi>Progreſs</hi> in Religion, and to rob us of the <hi>Comforts</hi> of it; for by this we are inclined to think that we are better in Degree than we are, and for this God looks upon Sinners <hi>a-far off.</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Pſalm cxxxviii. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pride</hi> has likewiſe awful Tendency to <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt</hi> us in <hi>principle;</hi> and no wonder, becauſe it gives acceſs to the influence of that proud Spirit who is the Father of Lies, and great <hi>Hereſiarch;</hi> as well as creates an Averſion to Truth, which is of a humble Tendency, and ſo its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. It was a juſt Obſervation of <hi>Auſtin,</hi> "That Pride is the Mother of Hereticks." <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> who was the Hatcher of many Hereſies, was a very proud Man; he gave out that <hi>he was ſome great one.</hi> 
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Acts. viii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Pride makes Perſons raſh and poſitive in their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and that even about Things of a doubtful and circumſtantial Nature, and will not give them leave to weigh well what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="unknown:005696_0017_1026C16F282CE1B0"/>
objected againſt them. <q>Mark thoſe, ſaith one, who are turned any where from the Way of Truth, and ſee if they are not proud and conceited Perſons.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But this is not all, Pride alſo has a <hi>corrupt Influence</hi> upon the <hi>Practice;</hi> by this Men are diſpoſed to neglect the ſecret Duties of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legion, becauſe of the Diſtance from God occaſioned by it, and as to their publick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances; they are more for Show than Subſtance, regarding the Praiſes of Men more than of God. I may farther obſerve, That Pride inclines different Perſons, yea ſometimes the ſame Perſons at different Times to contrary Vices: <hi>e. g.</hi> To Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs and Prodigality. What is Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs but the Purveyor of Pride, that greedily ſeeks ſomething to ſupport its grandeur; and hence the Prophet <hi>Habakkuk</hi> aſſures us, <hi>That the proud Man enlargeth his Deſire as</hi> Hell, <hi>and is as Death and cannot be ſatisfied</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Hab. ii. 5.</note> And on the contrary, Men are prodigal from the ſame proud Principle, with deſign to appear great and to be talk'd of. But I haſten</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="unknown:005696_0018_1026928955B5E838"/>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To ſhew the bad <hi>Fruits</hi> of <hi>Pride</hi> in relation to <hi>others.</hi> And theſe are indeed many: ſuch as <hi>lying, raſh-judging, backbit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſinful Contention, hatred of Reproof</hi> and <hi>Schiſm!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proud Perſons</hi> are generally great <hi>Lyers;</hi> the inordinate Deſire they have to be admired and applauded, makes them tell lies in order to anſwer that End, they knowingly and repeatedly ſtretch Things beyond the Truth in Converſation, that they may affect thoſe they ſpeak to, and excite either their Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, Love, Admiration or Hatred, to a great Degree!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pride</hi> likewiſe cauſes <hi>raſh judging</hi> of others <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> for ſmall Matters. Too much of this unhappy Temper and Practiſe appear'd for a Time among both the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> Converts, in the Apoſtolick Day, they judg'd and cenſur'd one another ſeverely for their different Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Practice about Days and Meats; <hi>Bigots</hi> on both ſides of the Queſtion were very poſitive and Fire-hot, yea to ſuch a Degree of uncharitableneſs, did indiſcreet and diſproportion'd Zeal, carry thoſe Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant but well meaning Zealots; that they
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:005696_0019_1026C171B4F1ECB0"/>
not only condemned one anothers States, but were alſo diſpos'd to deſpiſe and reject one another out of Church Communion, on the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the aforeſaid circumſtantial Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. This temper and Practice the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> condemns.<note n="‡‡" place="bottom">Rom. xiv. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Let not him that eateth, (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he,) deſpiſe him that eateth not, and let not him which eateth not, judge him that eateth, for God hath received him. Who art thou that judgeſt another Man's Servant? To his own Maſter he ſtandeth or falleth.</hi> On the Contrary he recommends, <hi>Forbearance,</hi> 
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Rom. xiv. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Love,</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">1 Cor. x. 32, 33. 1 Cor. viii. 13. Acts xvi. 3. Act xxi. 20, 21, 24.</note> 
               <hi>Condeſcenſion,</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">Rom. xiii. 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>Peace,</hi> and a <hi>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual receiving each other into Church Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Rom. xiv. 1. Rom xv. 7.</note> But to proceed,</p>
            <p>Another <hi>Fruit</hi> of <hi>Pride</hi> is, <hi>Whiſperings</hi> and <hi>Backbitings;</hi> theſe the Apoſtle puts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 
               <note n="‡‡" place="bottom">2 Cor. xii. 20.</note> in theſe Words: <hi>Envyings, Wraths, Strifes, Bacbitings, Whiſperings, Swellings, Tumults.</hi> Where there are Swellings of Pride, there will be Whiſperings and Backbitings: Proud Perſons will not content themſelves, with
<note n="†" place="bottom">Rom. xiv. 9.</note>
               <pb n="21" facs="unknown:005696_0020_1026C17517258980"/>
raſh Judging of others in their Hearts, which is a great Evil; but they will reproach them with their Tongues alſo, that ſo they may raiſe their own Credit upon the Ruin of anothers Character!</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Pride</hi> cauſes by the Evils before mentioned, and many others, <hi>ſinful Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition,</hi> and makes Perſons <hi>hate Reproof;</hi> as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> obſerves, <hi>he that is of a proud Heart ſtireth up Strife:</hi> 
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Prov. xxviii. 25</note> And he elſewhere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us, <hi>that a Scorner loveth not one that reproveth him.</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Prov xv. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> impriſoned <hi>John</hi> for telling him of his Sin, <hi>tho' he before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced him.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Mark vi. 20, 27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed <hi>Pride</hi> makes Perſons <hi>Separatiſts</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> theſe are they ſaith <hi>Jude, with ſeparate themſelves, ſenſual, having not the Spirit.</hi> 
               <note n="¶" place="bottom">Jude xix.</note> Undoubtedly <hi>Pride</hi> is the great Source of all thoſe Diviſions and Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with which the Church of Chriſt has been rent and torn into ſo many Parts, from its early beginnings thro' the Succeſſive Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods of Time to this Day! <hi>Pride</hi> does not only prompt Men to rend themſelves from Churches, but alſo by unſound Doctrines
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:005696_0021_1026C1769DBAD700"/>
and other ſinful Methods, to cauſe Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in them. Of ſuch the Apoſtle ſpeaks in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Manner: <note n="†" place="bottom">Rom. xvi. 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Now I beſeech you Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, mark them that cauſe Diviſions and Offences, contrary to the Doctrines which we have learned, and avoid them. For they that are ſuch, ſerve not our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own Belly; and by good Words and fair Speeches, deceive the Hearts of the ſimple.</hi> But it is Time to proceed to the laſt Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Head of Diſcourſe, which was to ſpeak of the <hi>Cure</hi> of <hi>Pride;</hi> to which End I would obſerve,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt:</hi> That it is neceſſary to <hi>inſpect</hi> our own <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Lives,</hi> and labour to get a Senſe of our Guilt as to this Sin; and doubtleſs all of us are in a greater or leſſer Degree guilty of it; but ſuch as are generally under its governing Power are in the Gaul of Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs and Bond of Iniquity, <hi>and therefore ſhould repent of this their Wickedneſs, and pray to God, if perhaps, the Thoughts of their Hearts may be forgiven them</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Act viii. 21.—23.</note> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, all that are in any Degree guilty of
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:005696_0022_1026C1783405C3A8"/>
this malignant Evil, have great Cauſe for Grief and Shame!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly:</hi> We ſhould <hi>conſider</hi> ſeriouſly and frequently upon the <hi>Aggravations of this Sin;</hi> which are theſe following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1ſt: It is an <hi>antient Evil,</hi> the firſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that ever God had: By this the Angels and our firſt Parents fell from their original Integrity and Happineſs; the Angels want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be independent like God, became Devils; and we by the ſame Iniquity, have made our ſelves worſe than Beaſts.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, It is an <hi>unreaſonable Evil;</hi> we have <hi>nothing</hi> to be proud of, who are ſinful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Creatures, that derive all the Good we poſſeſs from God, and carry our Breath in our Noſtrils.</p>
            <p>Neither the Endowments of Nature, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements of Art, or Aids of Birth and Fortune, tho' they raiſe Men above the common Level, give them reaſon for Pride or a Contempt of their Fellow-Creatures; when it is conſidered, that theſe Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments were not their own originally, but the immerited Gifts of a ſoverign Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, which might have ordered us the Lot of Beggars or Ideots: Now ſeeing the
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:005696_0023_1026C17AB696B370"/>
difference between us and others is entirely owing to the divine Diſpoſal, and we have received all our Gifts from God, <hi>wherefore ſhould we glory as tho' we had not received them?</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">1 Cor. iv. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Continuance of thoſe Things is alſo ſo ſhort and uncertain, that it may juſtly give check to our aſpiring Thoughts about them; it is the vaineſt Vanity to be high-minded, and truſt in uncertain Riches, <hi>which often make to themſelves Wings and fly away, as the Eagle towards Heaven!</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Prov. xxiii. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But even tho' Wealth were permanent, yet its uſe is but narrow and limited, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſatisfy the Deſires of the Mind, or heal the Diſtreſſes of the Conſcience; all the Treaſures of the <hi>Indies</hi> cannot purchaſe a Balm for a wounded Spitit; and inſtead of curing the moral Diſorders of the Soul, it is frequently the occaſion of increaſing them; yea there are many Miſeries incident to human Life, wherein it can yield no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief: <hi>e. g.</hi> if a Man is afflicted with a Fit of the Gout or Stone, all the Banks of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe cannot purchaſe a Moments eaſe; and
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:005696_0024_1026C17F36DA4068"/>
if our Character is aſpers'd, whole Ingots of Gold cannot ſtop the Mouth of Fame! What has been ſaid of Wealth is juſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to other Gifts: <hi>and therefore let not the wiſe Man glory in his Wiſdom, nor the mighty Man in his Might, nor the rich Man in his Riches; but let him that glorieth, glory in this, that he underſtandeth and knoweth me,</hi> ſayeth the Almighty by the Prophet. <note n="‡" place="bottom">Jer. ix. 23, 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I may add, that it is very unreaſonable for us to be proud, conſidering the Meanneſs of our Original; ſurely we had our riſe from Nothing at firſt, and after we received a Being, it was, and is but a precarious One, and that conveyed with a criminal Taint, <hi>for we are ſhapen in Iniquity and conceiv'd in Sin.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Pſalm li. 5.</note> Now it is enough to take down the Spirit of the brighteſt Intelligence, to conſider that nothing was his Original, for this is a State more diſhonourable than the Chaos it ſelf; yet the Depravity with which we received our Nature, adds ſuch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Meanneſs and Diſhonour to our Original, as no Words are equal to!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, Pride</hi> is a <hi>pregnant Evil,</hi> moſt of the Sins of the World are either contain'd
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:005696_0025_10269287788FC450"/>
in it, or iſſue from it, as appears in ſome Meaſure from what hath been ſaid, to which let me add a few Particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pride</hi> ſtrikes at the <hi>Foundation</hi> of all thoſe <hi>Offices</hi> that we owe to our <hi>Neighbour;</hi> which take up the ſecond Table of the Law: For if we ſlight our Neighbour, how ſhall we perform any Duty we owe to him?</p>
            <p>And when we ſlight our Neighbour, do we not conſequently <hi>contemn God,</hi> who has by his Authority enjoyn'd us to honour him?</p>
            <p>Moreover by <hi>Pride</hi> we bring <hi>contempt</hi> upon <hi>ourſelves: For as thoſe that honour God, ſhall be honour'd by him; ſo thoſe that contemn him, ſhall be lightly eſteemed.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">1 Sam. ii. 30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Pride</hi> our Neighbour is wrong'd of that which is next to his Life, <hi>viz.</hi> His <hi>Character. Solomon</hi> juſtly obſerves, that <hi>a good Name is as precious Ointment.</hi> 
               <note n="**" place="bottom">Pro. vi. 16.17.</note> Our Uſefulneſs as well as Comfort do in ſome Meaſure depend upon our Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ion; both which are ſtruck at by <hi>Pride.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pride,</hi> in its Tendency, breaks the <hi>Bands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>iety,</hi> and ſaps the Foundations of all
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:005696_0026_1026C184297C21E8"/>
ſocial Juſtice, Comfort, and Benefit! It aims at the final Overthrow of all Society whether in Families, Churches, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealths. The Comfort and Uſe of which depend upon that <hi>Honour</hi> which is due from Inferiors to their Superiors; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which ſocial Offices cannot be with Reaſon expected.</p>
            <p>It was <hi>Pride,</hi> my Brethren, that brought <hi>Strife</hi> into <hi>Heaven</hi> it ſelf, and caſt down the Apoſtate Angels thence. It is <hi>Pride</hi> that robs God of the <hi>Honour</hi> due to his <hi>Providence,</hi> and makes Men guilty of the wildeſt <hi>Idolatry</hi> in burning Incenſe to their own Net!</p>
            <p>Surely it is <hi>Pride</hi> that makes men ſo <hi>maſterly</hi> and imperious in their Behaviour; ſo <hi>raſh</hi> in their Judgments and Cenſures; ſo <hi>peeviſh</hi> in their Tempers, and <hi>obſtinate</hi> in their Reſolutions. This makes Men, <hi>Argus</hi>-ey'd, in ſpying <hi>Motes in their Brothers Eye,</hi> but as blind as <hi>Moles</hi> in not diſcerning <hi>the Beam that is in their own!</hi> And thus it prevents Repentance, and puts a Bar to improvement. It makes Men ſtorm at re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, and deaf to Advice and Council: It magnifies the ſlender Shadow of Piety and Virtue in thoſe that are under its Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:005696_0027_1026C185AF47BE98"/>
and ſilences the Checks of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. And thus it paves the Way for Deluſion and Ruin! Which brings me to ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly:</hi> That Pride is a <hi>God-provoking Evil.</hi> It is one of the Six Things that God hates, yea of the Seven which is an Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to him. <note n="*" place="bottom">Prov. vi. 16.17.</note> And hence we are told that he reſiſts the Proud, <note n="†" place="bottom">James iv. 6.</note> and looks on them afar off: <note n="‡" place="bottom">Pſalm cxxxviii. 6.</note> As if they were not fit, as one expreſſeth it, to be touch'd with a pair of Tongs. And <hi>Jehovah</hi> likewiſe aſſures us, <hi>that Pride goes before Deſtruction, and a high Mind before a Fall.</hi> 
               <note n="‡‡" place="bottom">Prov. xvi. 18.</note> But,</p>
            <p n="3">3dly: We ſhould not only think often on the <hi>Aggravations of Pride,</hi> but likewiſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Imperfections</hi> of our <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> how weak are the former and corrupt the latter? How much Water is mingled with our Wine, and Droſs with our Silver?</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, We ſhould often <hi>meditate</hi> upon the <hi>Evils of our Hearts</hi> and <hi>Practice:</hi> Shall we be proud who have ſuch a Sink of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs within us? Who have done ſo little for God and ſo much againſt him?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="unknown:005696_0028_1026C18745136870"/>
               <hi>Fifthly:</hi> We ſhould alſo <hi>think</hi> frequently upon <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Judgment:</hi> Shall ſuch dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Worms as we be proud, who muſt be ſo ſoon reduced to rotteneſs, and brought to a ſtrict Account for all our Talents? As to civil Differences, they'll ſoon be levelled in undiſtinguiſh'd Duſt!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly:</hi> My dear Brethren! let us <hi>ſeek</hi> after more of the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>greater Nearneſs to him,</hi> both which have a noble Tendency to break the Pride of our Hearts, it was this that made <hi>Job abhor him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Job xlii. 6.</note> and <hi>Iſaiah</hi> complain, <hi>that he was a Man of unclean Lips!</hi> 
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Iſa. vi. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly: Think</hi> often on the <hi>Example</hi> of the <hi>Cloud</hi> of <hi>Witneſſes</hi> that have gone before you to Glory; particularly upon <hi>Abraham,</hi> who in his Supplication, expreſs'd the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Reverence of God's Majeſty; behold, ſaid he, <hi>I who am but Duſt and Aſhes, have taken upon me to ſpeak to the Lord, O let not the Lord be angry!</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Gen. xviii. 27.</note> Upon <hi>David</hi> who was abaſed by the Thoughts of the divine Goodneſs to him, ſaying, <hi>What am I, and what is my Father's Houſe, that thou has
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:005696_0029_1026C18AAF5F6160"/>
brought me hitherto?</hi> There are alſo many others that deſerve your Thoughts and Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, which time would fail to enumerate! and therefore I proceed to ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eightly: Think</hi> on the <hi>Example</hi> of <hi>Chriſt's Humility,</hi> who tho' he was <hi>in the Form of God, aſſumed the Form of a Servant:</hi> And ſhall not we for whoſe Sake this was done be <hi>cloathed with Humility,</hi> and ſeek to have <hi>the ſame Mind in us which was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus?</hi> Surely the aſtoniſhing Stoop of Divine Majeſty, to the humbleſt Circumſtances of Humanity, may make us aſham'd of ambitious Aſpirings!</p>
            <p>In fine, my dear Brethren! It ſhould be ſeriouſly conſidered that the ſubduing of our Pride, is the Deſign of God's providential Dealings towards us, both in its proſperous and adverſe Occurrences. The former ſhould make us aſham'd of it, and the latter imbitter it to us! O! therefore let us op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Stirrings of that malignant Diſorder in us, and invite the Aſſiſtance of Heaven by importunate Supplications; in the mean Time, <hi>thinking of our ſelves ſoberly as we ought to think.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="unknown:005696_0030_1026C18C4CE0F770"/>
            <head>CORRIGENDA.</head>
            <p>SERMON I Page 5, line 9, <hi>for</hi> they better, <hi>read</hi> the better; p. 7, l. 14, <hi>read</hi> there; p. 9, l. 1, <hi>dele</hi> from; in Do. l. 23, <hi>read</hi> Deſertion; p. 13, l. 8, <hi>read</hi> Crucifixion, p. 16. l. 17. <hi>read</hi> Appearance.</p>
            <pb facs="unknown:005696_0031_1026C18FC801C630"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
