<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Religion and government subsisting together in society, necessary to their compleat happiness and safety. A sermon delivered in the audience of the General Assembly of the colony of Connecticut, on their anniversary election at Hartford, May 9th, 1751. / By Benjamin Lord, A.M. Pastor of a church of Christ in Norwich. ; [Thirteen lines of Scripture texts]</title>
            <author>Lord, Benjamin, 1694-1784.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N05423</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N05423</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 6868</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX4957</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">6868</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99021737</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 6868.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N05423)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 6868)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 6868)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Religion and government subsisting together in society, necessary to their compleat happiness and safety. A sermon delivered in the audience of the General Assembly of the colony of Connecticut, on their anniversary election at Hartford, May 9th, 1751. / By Benjamin Lord, A.M. Pastor of a church of Christ in Norwich. ; [Thirteen lines of Scripture texts]</title>
                  <author>Lord, Benjamin, 1694-1784.</author>
                  <author>Connecticut. General Assembly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 63, [1] p. ;  17 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Timothy Green, printer to the gov. &amp; Company.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New-London [Conn.], :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1752.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Mr. Lord's election sermon, May 9. 1751.</note>
                  <note>Running title: Religion &amp; government both, in a community, necessary to their compleat happiness &amp; safety.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religion and state.</term>
               <term>Election sermons --  Connecticut --  1751.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:006868_0001_102A7F1C1FAB3550"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Lord</hi>'s Election Sermon, May <hi>9.</hi> 1751.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:006868_0002_102A7F1F355D6468"/>
            <p>Religion and Government ſubſiſting together in Society, Neceſſary to their Compleat Happineſs and Safety.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Delivered in the Audience of the General Aſſembly of the Colony of <hi>Connecticut,</hi> on their Anniverſary Election at <hi>Hartford,</hi> May 9<hi>th,</hi> 1751.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Benjamin Lord,</hi> A. M. Paſtor of a Church of CHRIST in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Gen. xx.11.</bibl>
And Abraham ſaid, becauſe I Thought, Surely the Fear of God is not in this Place; and they will ſlay me.—</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Neh. v.15.</bibl>
— But ſo did not I, becauſe of the Fear of God.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. xx.8.</bibl>
A King that ſitteth in the Throne of Judgment, Scattereth away all Evil with his Eyes.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. xxix.4.</bibl>
The King by Judgment Eſtabliſheth the Land.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rom. xiii.3.4.</bibl>
Rulers are not a Terror to Good Works, but to the Evil,—For he is the Miniſter of God to thee for Good.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>NEW-LONDON,</hi> Printed and Sold by TIMOTHY GREEN, Printer to the GOV.&amp;COMPANY, 1752.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="unknown:006868_0003_102A7F227AC0F848"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>At a GENERAL ASSEMBLY Holden at <hi>Hartford,</hi> 
                  <date>on the Second Thurſday of <hi>May, Anno Domini,</hi> 1751</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>ORDERED,</hi>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT</hi> HEZEKIAH HUNTINGTON <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
               <hi>and</hi> Mr. JOSEPH TRACEY JUN. <hi>Return the Thanks of this Aſſembly to the Reverend</hi> Mr. BENJAMIN LORD, <hi>for his Sermon Delivered on the 9th Day of</hi> May <hi>Inſtant, before the Aſſembly, and deſire a Copy thereof that it may be Printed.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>George Wyllys</hi> Secr.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="unknown:006868_0004_102A7F2538D18458"/>
            <head>An Election SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALM CXXII.4, 5.</bibl>
               <q>Whither the Tribes go up, tbe Tribes of the Lord, unto the Teſtimony of Iſrael, to give thanks unto the Name of the Lord. For there are ſet Thrones of Judgment: the Thrones of the Houſe of David.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE great Author of Nature, hath form'd and deſign'd his Creature Man for Society, both Civil and Religious; which, as it is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his very Make, and neceſſary to his preſent State; ſo, is adapted to his multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farious Advantage: Inſomuch, that any manner of Conduct, which expreſſeth a Man's mind to live by himſelf, abſtract from any Relation to Society; or to Worſhip only by himſelf and not with others; or that ſhews a thought, as if he could be ſafe and happy alone, Independant on Community; is a Contradiction to the deſign of the Creator in ranking him with the humane Species, &amp;
<pb n="2" facs="unknown:006868_0005_102A7F26DAB19A58"/>
to the Conſtitution &amp; Wants of ſuch a kind of Creature. For, the Foundation laid in our Nature for Society, together with the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Dependance we have on one another, eſpecially in the preſent fallen State, do all point out our Duty to dwell together as Brethren in Unity, as Members of Society, compacted and cemented by all the Bonds of Union, which fitly frame and build up Individuals into a Body politic for the Good of the whole.</p>
            <p>VERY evident then, it is; that <hi>Men</hi> were not deſign'd for an <hi>Unſocial Life,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially with their preſent depraved Powers, are by no means, to remain in <hi>a State of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>; each one to poſſeſs by himſelf, and uſe for himſelf his natural Rights &amp; Liberties, without any borrowed Strength and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage from others by Compact: i. e. without Incorporating into Society, or having any known eſtabliſhed Laws and Rules agreed upon, as a common Standard to govern the whole; or any ſupream Head or known acknowleged Rulers and Officers to keep the whole in a juſt Decorum; and that for the general Peace and Safety of them all.—</p>
            <p>BUT <hi>they</hi> are rather deſign'd by God to be, to Subſiſt, and Act in <hi>a State of Community,</hi> United and Strengthned by certain Bonds, for the Preſervation of the Lives &amp; Fortunes
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:006868_0006_102A7F2931ACF6F8"/>
of each Individual; and even from all Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Aſſaults by their Fellows. — And, as it is fitting; ſo, indeed neceſſary now, that Men's natural Rights be given up to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, whereby, thoſe may be exerciſed for the Good of every one; as they cannot be, while in the Hands of Individuals them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for, the Strength of each particular Perſon being giv'n up to Society and lodg'd with this collective Body, for common Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: Every Member may have the Strength of the whole employed for the Security of his own Life and Property. And alſo rejoyce in his Neighbours having the ſame Protection and Advantage with himſelf: So that, the Privileges of Society muſt be vaſtly greater than all the Rights of Nature ſeparately Conſider'd and Uſed. This, (it ſeems) is very plain.</p>
            <p>AND, as evident it is, that nothing Argues and Repreſents a People more truly great; or, Renders them more Safe and Happy; than their firm Union in theſe two Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Intereſts, Civil and Religious; (theſe always Implying the divine Preſence and Protection) theſe then, are the two grand things neceſſary to the well being of Society, (viz.) RELIGION AND GOVERNMENT; firmly Eſtabliſh'd, duly Exerciſed, and well United; as Subſiſting together in the ſame
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:006868_0007_102A7F2BDCC6CE58"/>
Community; rendring it, whether conſidered as <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State</hi>: An harmonious Polity. And happy, (I ſay) by virtue of this Union in what is their true and common Intereſt.—Which, was indeed the View here taken, of Jeruſalem of old; when ſaid to be <hi>Builded as a City, that is Compact together.</hi> For, however Populous that City, and Contiguous their Buildings; the main Excellence &amp; Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of this Union, and the chief Glory intended by it's being thus Compacted; lay in this, that <hi>there,</hi>was <hi>the Teſtimony of Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>there, the ſet Thrones of Judgment.</hi> Thus Situated near one to the other, that they might Befriend each other: And both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſerve the beſt Good of the Community, ſo Diſtinguiſhed and Dignified by them. which, was no ſmall Motive (it ſeems) to invite the People up to Jeruſalem, in a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective Body at certain Seaſons, that <hi>there</hi> they might'nt only join in Social Worſhip ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the divine Inſtitution; but alſo, <hi>there</hi> receive the ſignal Benefit of a civil Adminiſtration of God's Appointing like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe — As it is elegantly expreſſed in the Text, <hi>Whither the Tribes go up, the Tribes of the Lord, Unto the Teſtimony of Iſrael, to give Thanks unto the Name of the Lord, for there are ſet Thrones of Judgment, the Thrones of the Houſe of David.</hi> Which would be
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:006868_0008_102A7F2F6986BCC0"/>
an Advantage to them, not only when they were Together at Jeruſalem on public Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; but alſo when Diſperſed again to their ſeveral Diſtricts, and in their private Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: As, ſuch a Unity contributed to the common Safety &amp; Intereſt of the Whole at all Times.</p>
            <p>Now, this whole <hi>Pſalm,</hi> was Written by <hi>David,</hi> to promote the Peoples Unity in the Worſhip of God, and Subjection to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and ſo to Anſwer the Deſign of their common Good and Proſperity. And here. Obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ancient Practice of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by God's Appointment, (viz.) Their Aſſembling to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>at Jeruſalem,</hi> three times a Year to Worſhip God in the moſt public Manner, at theſe fixed Periods and appointed Solemn Feaſts, which the better part of the People greatly Rejoiced in; a delightful Token this! of their great and beneficial Unity. V. 1—3. <hi>I was glad, when they ſaid unto me, Let us go into the Houſe of the Lord. Our feet ſhall ſtand within thy Gates, O Jeruſalem. Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem is builded as a City that is Compact to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</hi> And Obſerve,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Recommendation of this Practice, and of the Excellence of Society, and of Unity therein, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Carrying therein, an Invitation to all the tribes of Iſrael to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:006868_0009_102A7F31005EFC68"/>
in their Aſſembling <hi>at Jeruſalem</hi> to Worſhip God together, and <hi>there,</hi> to receive the Benefit of the beſt civil Adminiſtration: for <hi>there,</hi> were the ſet Thrones of Judgment, <hi>the Thrones of the Houſe of David,</hi> as well as <hi>the Teſtimony of Iſrael:</hi> which, contains Arguments to preſs upon the People all that Conduct in a Community which becomes thoſe that would be Safe and Happy: As, their Agreeing well in <hi>their Religion</hi> and in their <hi>Regard to the Government</hi> which God had ſet over them: Let all the Tribes, (<hi>the Tribes of the Lord</hi> thus dignified with <hi>that Character</hi>) Agree to meet one another <hi>at Jeruſalem</hi>: For there's the <hi>Teſtimony of Iſrael</hi> and the ſet <hi>Thrones of Judgment:</hi> How grand the Expreſſions, full of Majeſty, anſwerable to the great Ideas and Richneſs of tho't Expreſs'd by them.—</p>
            <p>— <hi>The Teſtimony of Iſrael.</hi> i. e. God's Teſtimony delivered to Iſrael, honourably diſtinguiſhing them from all other People who had not his Word and his Statutes as Iſrael had. Becauſe of this, were the Tribes of Iſrael Directed and Encouraged to Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>at Jeruſalem</hi>: For <hi>there,</hi> was the <hi>Ark of God,</hi> wherein was his Teſtimony, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of his Mind and Will to his People. And another Argument (it ſeems) for their Aſſembling <hi>there,</hi> is that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was not
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:006868_0010_102A7F32926EDF40"/>
only the <hi>Holy,</hi> but the <hi>Royal City.</hi> For <hi>there,</hi> alſo, are <hi>ſet Thrones of Judgment.</hi> i e. an Eſtabliſhed civil Government by a divine Conſtitution, and Settled by God in <hi>the Houſe of David,</hi> a Man after God's own Heart. And add to all; this was <hi>the beautiful City,</hi> in that, it was ſo compacted and cemented in its public Intereſts; the Teſtimony of Iſrael and the ſet Thrones of Judgment ſo near together. i. e. their civil and religious Intereſts ſtrongly United for the benefit of the whole Community. For at that Time, <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> was not divided into two Cities or Towns, as when in the hands of the <hi>Jebuſites,</hi> but united (thô enlarged) as a City compact together: Eſpecially, United in its <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi>; which, (as <hi>Pool</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) were diſtinct and oppoſite before <hi>David</hi> took the <hi>Fort of Zion</hi> from the <hi>Jebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites</hi>; but now, happily United. <q>A good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sight this (ſays <hi>Henry</hi>) that the Teſtimony of Iſrael and the ſet Thrones of Judgment were ſuch near and good Neighbours. i. e. Mutually Serving one another. The Teſtimony of Iſrael direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Thrones of Judgment, and theſe protecting the Teſtimony of Iſrael.</q>—And thus may I obſerve, that the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Iſraels Aſſembling together, as one harmonious Body, finiſhes from the Advantage
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:006868_0011_102A7F35E75AA560"/>
of their having both Religion and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therein; both the means of the Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Salvation of their Souls; and of the Protection and Safety of their Perſons and Property. — And how indeed, can it go right well, with any people under Heaven where the bands of Society are burſt aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and thoſe two great and important In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts are Baniſhed; or are not well Eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and blended for the common Good of the whole, and the People well agreed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to make the beſt uſe of them both. Agreably, the deſign of all may be ſumm'd up in this general point of Doctrine to be diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of, on this moſt public Occaſion, (viz.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Religion &amp; Government, ſubſiſting together in a firm Union, are the Glory, Safety and Happineſs of a People Uniting, in their juſt Regard to Both.</hi> —</p>
            <p>Here I ſhall,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>I.</hi> Say ſomething, <hi>of the Religion and Government, which are ſo Eſſential to the Good of Community.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>II.</hi> Shew, <hi>the Importance of their Subſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together in Society to render it Happy, and alſo wherein the firm Union of theſe two great Intereſts doth Conſiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="9" facs="unknown:006868_0012_102A7F38601E9478"/>
               <hi>III.</hi> That <hi>it is equally Important and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that this Community it ſelf be United in their juſt Regard to both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>IV.</hi> Diſcourſe ſomewhat, <hi>of the Glory, Safety and Happineſs of a People ſo United in that Regard to both theſe,</hi> (viz) Religion and Government.</p>
            <p>And then Conclude with ſome <hi>Application</hi> agreeable to the great Occaſions of this Public Anniverſary. —</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>I.</hi> I ſhall ſay ſomething <hi>of the Religion, and Government, which are ſo Neceſſary to the Good of Community.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will obſerve, that theſe two Intereſts are what the ſacred Penman doth connect here, in the Idea, or general Notion of a happy People, comprized in the <hi>Teſtimony of Iſrael,</hi> and the <hi>ſet Thrones of Judgment</hi>: It ſeems, he did not ſpeak of Iſrael a Body Politic, as under any Advantage to be truly a Dignify'd and Happy People without <hi>Religion and Government</hi>; nor did he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to invite the Tribes of Iſrael up to Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, to take the great Privileges of ſuch a collective Body, but with the views of <hi>theſe</hi> being there, in an eminent Manner; and from thence, to ſpread their benign Influence, thro' all parts of that Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Community. Now then,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="10" facs="unknown:006868_0013_102A7F3B28F26818"/>1. As to <hi>the Religion,</hi> which is ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the Good of a Community. 'Tis certainly ſomething more than the <hi>Religion of Nature.</hi> 'Tis a Religion which has the Stamp of divine Revelation upon it; the Revealed Teſtimony of God. <hi>The Religion of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the great Head of the Church, and Governour of the Univerſe.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Religion of Nature,</hi> that is not Enough to make Individuals, nor a Community, Happy: When the Principles of it, are ſo much loſt from Man, by the Fall; and ſo conſtantly Corrupted by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved Reaſon and the Luſts of Men. I ſay then, the Religion taught by the <hi>Light of Nature</hi> and containing the Principles of moral Virtue, conſidered Abſtract from divine Revelation; is not ſufficient for fallen Man, nor for Society in this fallen State: Nor yet is <hi>the Religion of Moſes,</hi> i. e. the Religion taught by him however well A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted to the ſtate of the Jews of Old, ſufficient for us, or any Community now, in this Chriſtian State. But <hi>the Religion of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which explains both the Former, and Supplys what is wanting in them, is Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for us Chriſtians, in this State of Chriſtianity, which, is the beſt Friend to civil Government of any ſcheme of Religion at all. As it is beſt Calculated and Fitted to
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:006868_0014_102A7F3D91B45940"/>
Guide us into the way of Univerſal Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs: The Principles and Laws of it, being moſt perfectly Adapted to the good Regulation of Individuals and Communities in all things, that affect their Duty and Happineſs.</p>
            <p>IN a Word, <hi>the Religion,</hi> here Intended, as Eſſential to the Happineſs even of Society, is that which God has Revealed in his Word, in our Text, Expreſs'd by the <hi>Teſtimony of Iſrael</hi>: And now, the whole of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Religion, which the <hi>Goſpel Teſtimony</hi> opens, conſiſting in the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Laws of the Goſpel,</hi> and ſo, in that <hi>practical Regard</hi> to Jeſus Chriſt, which is there Taught and Recommended.</p>
            <p>To ſay then,</p>
            <p n="1">(1) The Religion ſo neceſſary in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State is what conſiſts in a <hi>right Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Faith,</hi> the Faith of the Goſpel, Including both the <hi>Doctrines</hi> which it Teacheth, and our <hi>Belief</hi> of them. — The very Syſtem of revealed Doctrines, which Comprehend and Perfect the Scheme of Principles, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to direct the Faith and govern the Life of Man, which are indeed the Principles Of Virtue and Godlineſs leading Men to Happineſs. Theſe are neceſſary for us, as Individuals and Members of Society.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="unknown:006868_0015_102A7F3FEEDE0C00"/>'TIS of great Conſequence how Men live, both on their own Account, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity's of which, they are Members; which is moſt likely to be according as their Principles are; whether good or bad; for, theſe are wont to have a great Influence on their Practice. And now, as the ſacred Scriptures are deſigned to form right Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in the minds of Men, to govern all their moral Conduct; ſo to inſpire them with right generous Principles of Behaviour, in Church and State: For, who are indeed <hi>bad Men,</hi> and yet <hi>good Members</hi> of either of them? If their Principles are form'd by their Ignorance and Luſts, rather than by the great Rule of Faith and Duty; they will of courſe be Irregular in Life, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, bad Members of Society. Their Conduct in <hi>the Church</hi> or <hi>common Wealth,</hi> will ſavour of their corrupt Principles, and be prejudicial to the Health and Peace of Both. So that with Regard to Society, 'tis needful that Men have a right Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Faith, true Principles <hi>of Virtue and Godlineſs</hi>; for, who knows not, that if Men have corrupt and looſe Notions of <hi>theſe,</hi> they will be Prophane and Vicious, Uncharitable &amp; Unpeaceable, &amp; ſome kind of Libertines, or other? which ſuits not with the good of Society. And can it be ſuppoſed, that Men
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:006868_0016_102A7F435E272590"/>
will be well Regulated in their Manners, if they are not ſo in their Belief? No. If they <hi>Err concerning the Faith,</hi> i. e. <hi>Err from the Truth</hi> in Principle, 'tis not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that they will <hi>do the Truth.</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">James 5.14 1 Joh. 1.6.</note>, But, as it is ſaid in another Caſe, <hi>They err in Viſion, they ſtumble in Judgment,</hi> and ſo in Conduct <note n="‖" place="bottom">Iſa. 28.7.</note> ſo that any Scheme of Principles, that are not well adapted to mens own moral good Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, is not well calculated for the good of Society.</p>
            <p>ARE the <hi>Errors of Popery,</hi> or <hi>the Wilds of Enthuſiaſm, &amp;c.</hi> friendly to Order &amp; Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Church or State? No, But forever inimical thereto. And indeed, in whatever proportion Mens Notions of Religion and Chriſtianity, are falſe, in the ſame they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves will likely tranſgreſs the Rules there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and ſo fail of that Virtue, Self-denial, Meekneſs, Conſtancy, public Spiritedneſs &amp; Benevolence which are repeatedly Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in the Goſpel: And ſo of courſe, diſturb the Peace &amp; Happineſs of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, they belong unto. And how evident is it, that if Numbers therein, have very looſe Notions of moral Virtue, they will fail of the practice of it, and tempt one another to tranſgreſs the Laws of it, in life;
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:006868_0017_102A7F44F537EAA8"/>
and be diſhoneſt, deceitful, &amp;c. and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Miſchievous to Society. It will be very natural to them to ſhew a diſlike of ſtrict Government; to be murmuring againſt good Laws, and faithful Rulers, who would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul their Luſts, and correct their Exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances: And ſo they will be always inclin'd to abuſe their Privileges, and ſacrifice them unto their own licentious Humours.</p>
            <p>HENCE it ſo often happens, that when men complain of the public ſtate of Things, as if this, and that, was wanting to compleat the Privilege of a free People; the bottom of it is their own want of virtuous Principles of Conduct to form them good Members of Society. Either they indulge ſloth or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſty, or ſome other evil deſtructive unto it; and ſo do not lay public Calamities to the right Cauſe. Indeed it is ſo, that if men have Unſcriptural, ill Principles; theſe. will affect the <hi>public State</hi>; as they naturally make men <hi>bad Members of it.</hi> But if they have the good Principles inculcated in the Bible; this, will tend to make them good Members thereof; diligent in their Buſineſs, true to their Truſt, righteous in their Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, faithful in their Places, &amp; ſome way bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial to Scciety, Yea, they will <hi>Study to be quiet, and to do their own Buſineſs,</hi> without giving Moleſtation unto others in theirs.
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:006868_0018_102A7F47C71F0F20"/>
They will <hi>fear God and keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; fear God,</hi> and <hi>honour the King,</hi> which is one of <hi>them</hi>; and <hi>for Conſcience ſake</hi> be ſubject to lawful Authority <note n="*" place="bottom">Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.</note>. Which all tendeth to the good of a Community.</p>
            <p>IT will then be granted that thoſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which beſt ſerve the deſign of mens <hi>perſonal</hi> Duty and Happineſs; do moſt of all contribute to the good Order, Peace and Happineſs of <hi>Society</hi>: Becauſe the Sounder men are really, in their Faith and ſettled Principles of Conduct, the more likely to live well; and the better they Live, the better Members of Society they always are. But now, to Talk of mens being good Members hereof, let their Principles with regard to Religion, be what they will; or let them have Religion, or no Religion, is to divide what God himſelf hath put together. And how can it be expected, that People will <hi>lead quiet and peaceable Lives,</hi> under the beſt model'd Government, and the wiſeſt Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations thereof, if they be not influenced by <hi>Godlineſs and Honeſty.</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">1 Tim 2.2.</note> Which clearly ſhews that right Sciptural Principles have great Influence upon the Obedience of the Subject. No Book in the World, is a better Friend to civil Government than the <hi>Holy Bible.</hi> No
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:006868_0019_102A7F4A8D76B760"/>
Scheme of Principles better Calculated to ſerve the civil State, than thoſe which are taught therein. And ſo there are no better Members of it, than the beſt of Chriſtians: to which purpoſe ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Put them in mind to be ſubject to Principalities &amp; Powers, to obey Magiſtrates; to be ready to every good Work; to ſpeak Evil of no Man; to be no Brawlers, but Gentle, ſhewing all Meekneſs unto all Men</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">Tit 3.1, 2.</note>. Hence,</p>
            <p n="2">(2) The Religion ſo neceſſary for us, and ever for the Health of Society, conſiſts in <hi>the Laws of God and Jeſus Christ,</hi> made known in the Holy Scriptures, and in <hi>our yielding Obedience unto them.</hi> Now there cannot be true &amp; effectual Religion without a Body of Sacred Laws to govern Mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and guide their Practice; Laws fitted to anſwer the Ends of our Obedience, or Living to God, which is practical Religion; but muſt needs fail, where men are either <hi>deſtitute</hi> of theſe Laws, or <hi>Diſobedient</hi> to them. For, good Principles and well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Doctrinally, would not be ſufficient to conſtitute Religion without rules of Practice. Yea, the beſt of Rules laid open to view are not Enough to make men happy, without Conformity to them, <hi>If ye know theſe things
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:006868_0020_102A7F4E43222B78"/>
happy are ye if ye do them.</hi> It is Obedience that crowns all.</p>
            <p>NOW the <hi>Religion of Chriſt,</hi> is moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly adapted to anſwer all the Purpoſes of our Duty &amp; Happineſs. <hi>Here,</hi> are the moſt perfect Laws ſuited to the Nature of Man, as a <hi>reaſonable Creature,</hi> and moſt proper to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect him as a <hi>Sinner: Here,</hi> is a ſufficiency of Direction for Man, in his preſent State, that there needs not any new Revelation from Heaven to direct him in one Branch of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Righteouſneſs, in any Capacity or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation that he ſuſtaineth. The Rules given in Chriſt's <hi>Written Law-Book,</hi> are compleat to form good Men, and good Members of Society. — So that, it argues a <hi>diſtempered Brain,</hi> if not a <hi>worſe Heart,</hi> to deſpiſe the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures and be fond of other Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, not given therein. If any do fancie to themſelves ſome new <hi>divine Directions</hi>; juſt, as they are forming to themſelves <hi>new Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Action,</hi> not contained in the Word of God; which they pretend to have immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from Heaven: Why! as they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and will Err in their perſonal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, (for a deceived heart hath turn'd them ſide) ſo, of Courſe they will prove bad Members of Church &amp; State. Their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Deluſion, Pride and Preſumption will hurry them into Practices deſtructive to
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:006868_0021_102A7F4FD3CF7110"/>
themſelves &amp; Society. Such <hi>Frieks of Fancy,</hi> and <hi>deluſive Dreams,</hi> which ſome have been govern'd by, muſt needs tend to diſturb the Community and pull down the Walls of its Defence, as faſt as ſuch Things can do it. And <hi>Centuries</hi> back, have produced ſad Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of their terrible Efforts; yea, very fatal Effects. Witneſs that famous Inſtance hereof in <hi>Saxony,</hi> A. D. 1522, and prevail'd more eſpecially in <hi>Munſter,</hi> where <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> made moſt dreadful Work, even in the <hi>State</hi>: Deſtroying firſt the public Peace, and then the Lives of Multitudes, as well as their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty. The like to which hath been threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>England</hi> above a Century paſt, when the like Diſeaſe had made conſiderable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs. And ſo it might be at any Time, here or there; when the ſame State-Diſtemper breaks forth, if God did not ſufficiently Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſk it, to reſtrain it before utter Ruin flooded in. But, from what it hath done in ſeveral Ages of the Church, and alſo from the Nature of it, it appears to be one of the moſt dangerous Things to Community; yea, one of the greateſt Engines in the hands of Satan to injure Church and State, that is at all. What Safety can there be with ſuch a Principle that violently hurries Men into a Conduct out of all Rule &amp; Reaſon, and yet under a Notion that it is all divine, and late
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:006868_0022_102A7F53113E71A8"/>
from Heaven? and muſt neither be reſiſted nor diſputed: For Enthuſiaſm always makes men ſo Confident of their being right in their Opinion &amp; Conduct, that no room muſt be given for ſober Examination. <q>It has, (ſays Mr. <hi>Locke</hi>) with ſome Men the ſame Authority, and is as confidently rely'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as either Faith or Reaſon, and wou'd ſet up Revelation without it: But in effect takes away both Reaſon &amp; Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Subſtitutes in the room of it, the ungrounded Fancies of a man's own Brain, and aſſumes them for a Foundation both of Opinion &amp; Conduct. Hence, we ſee that in all Ages, men, in whom Melancholy has mix'd with Devotion, or whoſe Conceit of themſelves, has raiſed them into an Opinion of greater Familiarity with God, and a nearer Admittance to his Favour, than is afforded to others; have often flattered themſelves with a perſwaſion of an immediate Intercourſe with the Deity, and frequent Communications from the divine Spirit. Their minds being thus prepared, whatever groundleſs Opinion comes to ſettle it ſelf ſtrongly upon their Fancies, is with them, an Illumination from the Spirit of God, and preſently of divine Authority. And whatſoever odd Action, they find in themſelves a ſtrong
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:006868_0023_102A7F57512BA140"/>
Inclination to do, that Impulſe is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to be a Call and Direction from Heaven, and muſt be Obeyed. 'Tis a Commiſſion from above and they can't Err in executing it. This I take (ſays he) to be properly Enthuſiaſm, which, tho' founded neither on Reaſon, nor divine Revelation; but riſing from the Conceits of a warmed, or over-weening Brain; works yet, where it once gets footing more Powerfully on the Perſwaſions and Actions of Men, than either of theſe two, or both together: For ſtrong Conceit, like a new Principle, carries all eaſily with it. When got above common Senſe, and freed from all reſtraint of Reaſon, or check of Reflection, it is heighten'd into a divine Authority in Concurrence with their own Temper and Inclination.</q> Thus Mr. Locke. And if this be a right Deſcription of <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> as fact has often prov'd it to be, then ſee what a dangerous thing it is in Church or State. What will ſtand before it; where it prevails, and is arm`d with Power to do it's own Pleaſure? what kind of Luſt or branch of Pride, will not the grand Enemy promote the Gratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of, by this Diſtemper? when once the way is ſo prepared, that Men think it is Religion, and what they have immediate
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:006868_0024_102A7F5A06531460"/>
Warrant for from God; why then, they will be Lawleſs, and diſobedient to lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, under colour of Obedience unto God. They will not ſtick at it, to be <hi>Unholy and Prophane, Murderers of Fathers &amp; Murderers of Mothers, and Man-ſlayers, and Whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> as the Scripture ſpeaketh <note n="†" place="bottom">I Tim 1. 9</note> 
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">
                  <p>I truſt, it will not appear any other than Duty and a proper Caution, that People be reminded of the tremendous Inſtances of this Nature which have lately happen'd within this Colony, (viz) at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> where it juſtly was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that ſeveral Perſons, were from ſuch vile Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples Poiſon'd to Death, the Circumſtances of which, all around, with the more direct proof in the caſe, would not ſuffer the Unprejudiced to think any thing more Favourably thereof.</p>
                  <p>And now, from this dreadful Example, as well as others of leſs Size, may we not juſtly be alarm'd with fear of the ill Conſequences of Enthuſiaſm &amp; Libertine Principles, which tend to carnal and all iniquitous Practices. And accordingly be timely and duly A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakn'd with a proper zeal againſt them.</p>
               </note>. And what not that is <hi>contrary to ſound Doctrine</hi> and the Rule of Duty? and all under a Notion of Acting by immediate Warrant from God. — Thus, they <hi>will walk after the Fleſh in the Luſt of Uncleanneſs, and deſpiſe Government, Preſumptuous are they, Self-willed, and not afraid to ſpeak Evil of Dignities,</hi> 
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">2 Pet. 2.10</note> And in another paſſage of Scripture the ſame ſort of
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:006868_0025_102A7F5B9C0D55E0"/>
Perſons are called <hi>filthy Dreamers,</hi> pretending to ſome divine Warrant, even for <hi>their defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Fleſh, deſpiſing Dominion and ſpeaking evil of Dignities.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Jude 8.</note>, They pretend God bids them condemn Magiſtrates and Miniſters and all religious or civil Eſtabliſhments, as a trick of State, and a ſcheme from beneath to abridge People of their Liberty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Here now, (as if ſuch kind of obſervations muſt be Suffered, to be verifi'd in Fact, to awaken our belief of the Truth of them) very Remarkable was it, that in the time of public Service, and juſt upon the delivery of this former part of the Sermon; there comes a man into <hi>Hartford</hi> riding furiouſly by the meeting Houſe, in a hoſtile manner and with a loud Outcry; who, by what he ſaid and did, appeared to be governed by ſome ſuch wild Principles and to deſign an inſult upon public Order &amp; Government. One man was ſorely Wounded by him, the Aſſembly greatly Diſturbed: divers of the Authority and others withdrawing in Sermon time to Suppreſs the diſorder and ſecure the diſorderly Perſon: this was a Specimen of what bad Principles would do, had they but power of their ſide.</note> And then, what ſhould hinder, if there be Power enough in their Hands, (and they are permitted ſo to do) to put down others, and ſet themſelves up, as was the caſe in the famous Inſtance before mentioned in <hi>Munſter</hi>? There is no degree of this Diſtemper, but what is Prejudicial to <hi>Men</hi> and to <hi>Society,</hi> For, when once Perſons get off, from the
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:006868_0026_102A7F5E09F62008"/>
only Infallible Standard of Faith &amp; Practice, and ſet up other Rules thereof, they wander, they know not where, and are expoſed to all the Deluſion &amp; Miſchief Imaginable. And as they injure themſelves, they always more, or leſs Injure the Community.</p>
            <p>Now, to receive and regard the <hi>Revelation of God,</hi> which he has made of Truth &amp; Duty, <hi>in his Word,</hi> is <hi>Religion</hi>; and tends to the Peace and Health of the <hi>State,</hi> becauſe it teacheth and directs Men to live Well, to follow Peace with all Men, and Holineſs; and Obey the Authority which God has ſet over them. And leſt any ſhould forget their Duty, after they are taught it, <hi>put them in Mind to be Subject,</hi> ſays the Scripture. But to pretend unto a Revelation <hi>Immediately from God,</hi> and to Obey that; this is <hi>not</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: And this is inimical and dangerous to the State, becauſe it gives out ſuch a Rule of Conduct, as Men fancie to have, yea ſuch as thoſe wou'd have it to be, who are govern'd by their own Pride and Ungodly Luſts, ſo that, with them, any thing, is from God, which they will pleaſe to have ſo; and this will Naturally lead them into a manner of Conduct very baneful to Society, and ſhew that they are worſe than unfriendly to the Health and Good thereof. — Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I have obſerved, that 'tis neceſſary, that
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:006868_0027_102A7F6082195E68"/>
both mens Moral and Civil Conduct be govern'd by certain Rules, known Laws, ſteddy Principles; all well Calculated to keep them in good Decorum; within the bounds of Truth and Equity; and ſuch are the Laws of God in his word, <hi>Holy, Juſt and Good,</hi> and ſitted to make Men ſo: They teach and urge all Truth and Honeſty, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Kindneſs and Beneficence. And what are the good &amp; wholſom Laws of a civil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, but ſuch as are taken out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or by way of juſt Conſequence derive thence? For, the more general Statutes of the Bible, requiring us, <hi>to do Juſtly, love Mercy &amp; walk Humbly with God,</hi> have a kind of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Explication in the good Laws of the civil State, with the Stamp of civil Authority upon them, which is from God: And with Minatory Penalties Annexed to give the more ſenſible Force to them, on ſuch, who, thro' their ſinful Paſſion, do need Coercive Methods and Reſtraints to make them Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient.</p>
            <p>AND, it is always the Duty of the civil Legiſlature to conform to the Word of God, (the great Standard of Truth, and Meaſure of Right and Wrong) in all their Laws, of however minute Conſequence: For, ſtill, all muſt be deſigned for, and therefore in their Nature directed to, the good of the whole
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:006868_0028_102A7F64FB0037B0"/>
Community. And therefore, have nothing unwiſe, unjuſt and Oppreſſive in them; even the Laws which order <hi>Labour,</hi> as well as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> for the common Good, ſhould diſtribute the ſame in ſuch a proportion as agrees well <hi>with Equity.</hi> And ſo all Precepts &amp; Orders with reſpect to Merchandize &amp; Trade, and the Medium thereof ſhould be in a ſtrict Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the fundamental Laws of Juſtice and Equity. This, being the Bottom, on which only the State can ſafely ſtand. Yea, in every Act of the Legiſlature, utmoſt Care muſt be had, that there be no Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Oppreſſion bor'n with, much leſs countenanced and encouraged by public Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
            <p>Hence I proceed,</p>
            <p n="2">2. To ſay ſomething of <hi>the Government,</hi> ſo neceſſary to the good of Community.</p>
            <p>IN the General, it is ſuch a <hi>civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as is founded in <hi>Reaſon and Scripture,</hi> and form'd for <hi>the good of the People,</hi> the great <hi>End</hi> of it. It muſt then be ſuch a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Adminiſtration as exiſts by the will of God; for, <hi>the Powers that be</hi> (which are lawfull &amp; good) <hi>are Ordained of God</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Rom. 13.1.</note> And therefore, ſuch as Secures and Defends
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:006868_0029_102A7F6690DA6460"/>
the Rights of the People; the <hi>civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi> being <hi>the Miniſter of God to them for Good</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Rom. 13. 4</note> for their Benefit. It was not the <hi>original</hi> Deſign, nor ever the <hi>true</hi> deſign of civil Government to Aggrandize particular men, at the expence of the public Good. But God Exalts ſome to places of public Authority that they may ſerve the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, and be Guardians to the peoples Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty — So then, an Abſolute unlimited <hi>Monarchy,</hi> or any Arbitrary Government which diſpoſes of mens Lives, Liberty, and Eſtate at pleaſure without Law, or Reaſon cannot be the Government here intended, for that in Nature is unſuitable to the main ends of Government. The great Deſign of mens coming <hi>into Society,</hi> and making up one ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Polity, is the preſervation of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, which in the <hi>ſtate of Nature,</hi> they could not Singly, and each one by himſelf Defend. Now, a meerly Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is contrary to this End, and tends di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to the deſtruction of the Body Politick, the very Reſult of Tyranny, that is an Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing of Power, beyond Authority, which cannot point at any thing ſhort of the Ruin of the Republic.</p>
            <p>NEITHER, can the Government here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:006868_0030_102A7F69313B7848"/>
be a levelling <hi>Anarchy,</hi> which throws the ſtate and all things therein, into Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: deſtroying the Diſtinction of Rulers, and Ruled, doth of courſe deſtroy the very foundation of the Peace &amp; Happineſs of civil Society; as it is Subverſive of it's very Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the great end of Government, the Preſervation of Property. For, if the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between ſome in the place of <hi>Power,</hi> and others in the place of <hi>Subjection,</hi> be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd and there be no acknowleg'd Rulers and Officers, how ſhall the Laws made by conſent of the Community for their common Good be executed for that End, or the good of any one individual Member? In the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of <hi>Anarchy,</hi> Men ſeem to be diſſolving Community it ſelf, and going back to the ſtate of Nature: to do every one what is Right in his own Eyes; which a greatly pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileg'd People are often, but too prone unto. As if a Government form'd for <hi>Liberty,</hi> to the Subjects, gave them a <hi>Licenſe,</hi> to act for themſelves abſtracted from Relation to Society and without concern for the common Good. Verily, 'tis a Principle near akin to Anarchy, that prompts men in a Community, to act, as Individuals with levelling Deſigns; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting how ſacred are the bonds of civil Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which they have taken upon them, and objecting againſt any ſettled form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:006868_0031_102A7A6185826298"/>
at all. For, tho' no particular Form of Government, or Mode of Adminiſtration, is preciſely determin'd by Reaſon or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for all particular Communities; but, this, left rather to be variouſly determined by the Prudence and Policy of different Kingdoms and civil Polities; according as beſt ſuits their particular Circumſtances and Intereſts: Yet, ſome Form or other is neceſſary; and in general, It ſeems, that all civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the right Stamp, muſt be agreeable to Scripture and Reaſon, and ſo to the Nature and Ends of a civil Community, the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Lives, Liberties &amp; Eſtates of all the Members thereof, againſt the force of Rapine, Injuſtice &amp; all manner of deſtructive Violence.</p>
            <p>So that, in a word, it may be obſerved, that in any well modell'd Government, and beneficial Adminiſtration of it; there muſt be known Eſtabliſh'd good Laws for the Regulation of mens Manners &amp; Security of their whole Property: as well as a wiſe and upright Legiſlature, that always hath theſe things at heart: Alſo, there muſt be known acknowleg'd faithful Judges and Officers to put theſe Laws in due Execution for the good of the Whole, that the People be kept in due Subjection to Rule and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for their own Benefit. This, is the
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:006868_0032_102A7F709EBFAC70"/>
Government ſo Eſſential to the good of Community. The like to which, is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of our own, in this Nation, and Land, and Colony eſpecially.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>II.</hi> I am to ſhew, <hi>the Importance of both, Religion and Government, ſubſiſting together in a Community, to render it Happy; as alſo, wherein, the firm Union of theſe two great Intereſts, doth conſiſt and appear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>NOW, it is true, there would be the leſs Need of civil Government, in a Community, in that proportion that Religion and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had its due Influence on the Members of it; becauſe in the ſame degree with that, wou'd be reſtrain'd all thoſe Luſts and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders of Men, which civil Government is Ordain'd to Curb: But, conſidering the Corruption of humane Nature, and the very great Prevalence thereof, (generally ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) as, breaking thro' all the reſtraints of Religion as it doth; civil Government alſo, is neceſſary, and muſt add, to all thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints, its own checking Reins, to keep mankind in any tolerable Decorum, for the common Good, Peace, and Safety of Society. And the infinitely Wiſe Supreme Governour of the World, foreſeeing what would be the out-breakings of the corrupt Paſſions of
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:006868_0033_102A7F72300EB818"/>
Men, not with ſtanding all the Force of the Religion that exiſts in this corrupt World, (while ſuch vaſt Numbers are ſo loſt to a due ſenſe of Virtue and Religion as they are) has out of Compaſſion to the world influence of civil Government to check and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the luſts of Men, by coercive Methods; that Pride, Envy, Malice, Unrighteouſneſs and Oppreſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> might not Ravage through the Earth, and deſtroy all before them. And as the Authority of civil Rulers is from God, for this very purpoſe, as ſaith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>by me Kings Reign and Princes decree Juſtice,</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">Jam. 4 1.</note> So the general Rules and Maxims of their Government in the whole Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration thereof, are to be taken from the Bible, to anſwer the ſame Ends, which the Laws of Religion are deſign'd to do (<hi>viz.</hi>) to make mankind as they ſhould be, Sober, Juſt and Good.</p>
            <p>But yet, were the whole of this great deſign to be effected by dint of humane Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, there muſt of neceſſity be ſo much of coercive Means (and conſtantly uſed) to keep the Community from being overrun with Diſorder, as would render it moſt Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy; for thoſe very diſorders ſuppoſed to be reſtrain'd by external Force &amp; Execution
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:006868_0034_102A7F746CE17C98"/>
of Penalties alone; would argue it ſo: Wherefore (it ſeems) that <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>civil Government both,</hi> muſt have their Exiſtence and Influence together; and both (in the beſt State that this World is ever found in) but little enough to render Society in any good meaſure Happy</p>
            <p>AND, let what will be ſaid of the difficulty attending civil Government, there is nothing makes more of this, than the Corruption of Men to be governed. <hi>Whence come Wars and Fightings,</hi> or Brawlings of all kinds of criminal Contentions, <hi>but from the Pride and Luſts of Men</hi>? <note n="‖" place="bottom">Jam 4.1.</note> Their unruly Paſſions of ſome kind or other, are a grand Source of all Miſchiefs in Community. As theſe prevail and break out, they neceſſarily give Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance unto it. So that from hence comes the great Difficulties, which attend the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Government: <hi>Wicked Men,</hi> the unjuſt, the contentious, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are <hi>they</hi> who diſturb <hi>the State,</hi> and make Rulers their <hi>great-Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, and the more of them the worſe.</hi> For, <hi>when the Wicked are multiply'd, Tranſgreſſion increaſeth,</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Prov. 29 16</note> and this always increaſeth miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief to Society. If <hi>one Sinner deſtroyeth much good,</hi> as ſaith the wiſe Man, <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 9 18.</note> many will deſtroy it, the more. Theſe are the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:006868_0035_102A7F770FD67D38"/>
chiefly, of ſo much more Buſineſs at Courts, than otherways, there could be any place for, and of ſo great a Number of civil Proſecutions &amp; immenſe Charges ariſing thence, ſo Impoveriſhing to the Country. For, <hi>the Law is not made for a righteous Man,</hi> to puniſh him; <hi>but for the Lawleſs and Diſobedient, for the Ungodly, and for Sinners,</hi> to puniſh them. <note n="‖" place="bottom">1 Tim. 1.9.</note> Theſe perplex Affairs, and Embarraſs Things of a public Nature; which cannot go on ſmoothly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their rough &amp; ungovern'd Humors, ſo that, it is neceſſary that a Community have <hi>Virtue and Religion</hi> prevailing in it as well as <hi>Government</hi> Adminiſtred therein, to render it Happy. Indeed, where the <hi>one</hi> of them exiſts, and is duly upheld, the <hi>other</hi> is the more likely to be alſo; for, they are friendly to one another, in their very Nature; as <hi>the Teſtimony of Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>the Thrones of Judgment</hi> uſed to be. — And, as the better Civil Government is, in its Conſtitution &amp; Adminiſtration, the more of Religion there is like to be: So, the more of this, the leſs Need of civil Laws to Reſtrain Men from Sin. Thus, as <hi>both</hi> are Neceſſary; <hi>both</hi> do contribute to the good of Community. They tend to make the Subject better, and ſo to
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:006868_0036_102A7F79E8E6C788"/>
mend the State: For, the Happineſs hereof, derives much from the Quality of its Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Thus, I have ſhewn the Importance of their ſubſiſting together in Society; that neither is like to do alone, in the preſent State of the World.</p>
            <p>THERE needs the Sword of the civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate <hi>to execute wrath upon him that doeth Evil</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">Rom. 13.4.</note> and will not be Reſtrained without ſuch <hi>a terror to evil Doers.</hi> And there needs a good degree of Virtue and Religion, to facilitate Government, and prevent ſo high a degree of coercive Methods as would keep the State in a perpetual Convulſion. <note n="†" place="bottom">Prov. 16.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>BUT wherein doth the firm Union of this beneficial Religion and Government in a Community conſiſt and appear?</p>
            <p n="1">(1)IN their being <hi>mutually Exerciſed for the Vindicating and Upholding of each other; that they may jointly Anſwer the general End of both, the good of the whole Community.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS now, is certainly according to their Nature, which renders them Friendly to <hi>one another</hi>; as well as to <hi>Society.</hi> They cannot juſtly be ſuppoſed Oppoſite the one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or in their Nature ſuch jarring Intereſts which Claſh, and tend to deſtroy the public good, and it is ſtrange that any ſhould in their
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:006868_0037_102A7F7C9C6E9468"/>
thought, ſeparate what God has Wiſely and Mercifully connected for ſo great and good a Deſign. Indeed, ſuch a kind of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Adminiſtration, as Militates againſt Religion; and breaths out ſlaughter againſt thoſe who practiſe it; as in the caſe of <hi>Darius's Decree,</hi> againſt <hi>Daniel</hi> in a matter, that concerned the Law of his God, <note n="‖" place="bottom">Dan 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>and <hi>Saul's ſpirit</hi> for the Diſciples of Chriſt at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> as far from anſwering the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral end of Government, the good of the People: And therefore is not of God. And ſo, if there ſhou'd be a Religion Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, which is inimical to civil Authority (as if that was all Uſurpation &amp; Impoſition) and that ſets People a praying againſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>laſpheming the Rulers: And that teacheth them to reſiſt the Powers that be Ordained of God; and ſo to refuſe rendring either <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, or Honour to whom,</hi> both are due. That cou'd not be a Religion beneficial to Society, any more than it is Right in its ſelf: For, the ſame Religion which requireth Men to <hi>render unto God the things that are God's,</hi> doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them alſo, <hi>to render unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>. Yea, <hi>let every Soul,</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>be ſubject unto the higher Powers: and that not only for Wrath,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="unknown:006868_0038_102A7F8027F1A988"/>
thro' fear of Puniſhment, <hi>but for Conſcience ſake</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Rom 13.1.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>AND, whatever Religion any have, that doth not teach men to love God and one another, to be peaceable Members of Society, and in their ſeveral Places to be beneficial thereto; that doth not make them obedient to the Laws of God, and to lawful Authority, which he hath ſet over them for their Good, it hath no Divine Stamp upon it, and is not of him. Certainly there is nothing in <hi>true Religion,</hi> to oppoſe civil Government. But, is the beſt Friend to it, of any thing at all, it puts men upon praying Earneſtly <hi>for Kings, and for all that are in Authority, <note n="‖" place="bottom">Tim. 2.2.</note> and to render Honour, to whom Honour, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to whom Tribute is due: Becauſe they are God's Miniſters, and attend continually on this very Thing.</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Rom. 63.65.</note>
            </p>
            <p>AND, Surely there ſhould be nothing in <hi>Government,</hi> to hurt Religion: That which God hath Ordained is moſt friendly unto it, to keep it in Reputation, to protect and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it. Well then, in a word, herein, doth conſiſt the Union between Religion and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſo beneficial to <hi>Society,</hi> that they give Countenance to one another, and ſo are the more ſerviceable to <hi>that,</hi> than either of
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:006868_0039_102A7F82E2DA2268"/>
them could be alone. <hi>Religion</hi> is directly helpful to Government, and ſo unto Society, as it makes men walk Orderly and ſubmit to Authority, as it prevents Jarrs and Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that are ſo troubleſome to the State, as well as to the Church; and <hi>Government</hi> is Inſtrumentally helpful to the Intereſt of Religion and ſo unto Society, when the ſame is exerciſed under the Awe ot the ſupreme Judge of Right and Wrong; under the influence of good Principles, with a direct Deſign to encourage Virtue and univerſal Righteouſneſs; guarding the Sacred Truths &amp; Precepts of God's Word, his Worſhip, his Sabbaths, his Inſtitutions, and Miniſtry, as well from the Criminal Neglect of the Careleſs, as from the Open Contempt of Wicked Men.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) It is alſo an Influence, and one way of diſcovery of this Union, <hi>When the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, and Miniſters of the Goſpel, are mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually Engaged to Encourage and Uphold each other, in the due Diſcharge of their diſtinct Offices, for the good of the whole Community.</hi> Their Example may go far, in giving both Religion and Government a Reputation with the People; as, when they are very Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary in their own perſonal Conduct, and faithful in their ſeveral Offices. And, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, are Friendly to one another, to Animate one, the other; to their duty as public Officers,
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:006868_0040_102A8E4CB62FD380"/>
for the common Benefit. It makes well for the People, when <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> go together in promoting God's Glory and their Good: And it makes well for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; they go the Stronger, &amp; their Work is the Eaſier, &amp; the more like to be Succeſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. And here let it be obſerv'd, that God hath ſo Ordained; that the Teſtimony of Iſrael, and the ſet Thrones of Judgment, be <hi>near Neighbours,</hi> and very Friendly to each other, for the public Good.</p>
            <p>THEN, let the <hi>Miniſters of Christ,</hi> whoſe buſineſs it is, <hi>to preach the Word,</hi> and give out the Contents of God's Teſtimony to Iſrael, preach it Faithfully to <hi>Rules,</hi> as well as others, and ſhew them their duty reveal'd therein. — Let them alſo very Expreſly and Earneſtly pray for the Rulers, and by their own example teach the People <hi>all obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to them, as well as <hi>Prayerfulneſs</hi> for them; yea, <hi>preſs</hi> it upon the People to pray for them, who would not then, be ſo ready to diſobey, and murmur againſt them, did they pray for them under a ſenſe of the Weight which is upon thoſe, Intruſted with the Affairs of civil Government. Alſo let them Labour to Inſtil into the People <hi>the very Principles</hi> of Loyalty and Obedience.</p>
            <p>AND, then let theſe <hi>Miniſters of State,</hi> whom God hath made Keepers and Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:006868_0041_102A8E1E52497520"/>
of both Tables of the Law, and hath ſet on the Thrones of Judgment, eſpecially for Good to the Church, be Friendly to the <hi>Miniſters of Religion,</hi> to Encourage their Heart and Strengthen their Hands in their Work, to Defend and Support them in their Character &amp; Office; and in all proper ways recommend it, to the People, to treat them as the Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, to Improve Reſpect and Maintain them as ſuch, and for this end, ſee that the People do give them the Recompence and Subſiſtance which the Goſpel Requireth. At leaſt that they make good their civil Contracts with them, and punctually fulfil their Obligations to them, which muſt needs be as Sacred, as their Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to be Juſt to one another, can be ſo. And ſurely the failure of Juſtice and Truth to them, cannot be leſs Offenſive to God, than not to be Juſt to one another, would be ſo. Well, the common and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Rule of Equity is, <hi>that which is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether juſt, thou ſhalt follow.</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Deut. 16. 20.</note> And with a ſpecial Application of it, in this Caſe, <hi>It is Written, they that preach the Goſpel ſhall live of the Goſpel,</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">1 Cor. 9 14.</note> and not be <hi>Unwritten,</hi> at our pleaſure. It cannot be a light Thing then, to Treat them, as the civil Law will not (and
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:006868_0042_102A8E2107DAAA78"/>
ought not) ſuffer Others to be dealt with. And may the civil Authority quietly &amp; juſtly quit their Hands of this Matter, without doing <hi>all</hi> that is properly in their Power to afford Relief in a cauſe that ſo much Affects the Intereſt of Religion among the People as this doth? For, can <hi>Miniſters</hi> apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moſt Faithfully and Studiouſly to their Work without <hi>a ſufficient Support</hi> from the People? if ſome can poſſibly do it, to the injury of their Children after them: Others cannot do it even ſo: But what ſaith the Scripture to this very purpoſe? <hi>Who goeth a Warfare at his own Charges</hi>? And doth not <hi>the Law of Nature and Nations,</hi> with the <hi>Expreſs Statute of Heaven,</hi>Declare that Men, orderly called to public Offices, are to be Supported in the Duties thereof, without Charge to themſelves. <note n="*" place="bottom">1 Cor. 9 7 — 14.</note> And have not <hi>the Rulers</hi> a concern in this Matter, to ſee that it is done, without Expoſing Miniſters to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their own Uſefulneſs to get their own Dues? Doubtleſs, as certainly ſo, as that, <hi>the ſet Thrones of Judgment</hi> were placed near <hi>the Teſtimony of Iſrael</hi> for the Protection thereof.</p>
            <p>AND, how Beautiful in all Ages of the Church, to ſee the Miniſters of State, and Religion mutual Helpers of one another, for
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:006868_0043_102A8E241DB95C18"/>
the general Good of Society? Without which, both may be the Weaker, and the leſs Succeſsful.</p>
            <p>But to proceed.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>III.</hi> It is <hi>equally Important, and Neceſſary for the Good of a Community, that the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it, be well United in their Regard both to Religion and Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'TIS true, if theſe Subſiſt together in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, the People will be proportionably United in their Regard to both, as the Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereof ſpreads among them: But yet theſe are diſtinct Conſiderations in this Reſpect, <hi>viz.</hi> that true Religion may be generally Profeſſed in, and by a Community; as well as a good civil Government Exiſt there, and both have ſome public Countenance and Eſtabliſhment: And, ſtill there be great Numbers of Individuals, who pay little, or no Regard to either of them; but are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly Rebelling againſt the Laws of God and the King. Now, where it is ſo, the <hi>State</hi> as well as the <hi>Church,</hi> muſt of Courſe, be in a very unhappy Condition. So many diſorderly Members to be cured, which una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably Wracks the whole Body. But, when the People are generally well United in a true practical Regard, both to the Teſtimony of Iſrael, and the Thrones of Judgment, the
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:006868_0044_102A8E26F7B6EC98"/>
prevailing Part being under the Influence of virtuous Principles, and in good Subjection to lawful Authority; why then, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity is very happy, and enjoys great Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Tranquility.</p>
            <p>So that I obſerve, Not only ſhould there be a Union of theſe Two great Intereſts, actually Subſiſting by public Countenance, in a Community; but the Members thereof ſhould be well United in their Regard to both; then it is indeed, <hi>as Jeruſalem, a City that is compact together</hi>: Cemented with Love, and other Social Virtues. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes vaſtly to the good of the Whole: For, now in this Caſe, thô there ſhould be ſome different Sentiments about the more circumſtantial Things in Religion, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment alſo; yet being United in the main eſſential Things, Love to God, and one another, in a benevolent and peaceable Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, they are happy. — But, on the contrary, how great the Difficulty in Church and Common Wealth, when the Members thereof, are ſo wide from one another, in what they ſhould be moſt of all United in; that they can't agree, ſo much as in mutual Love and Forbearance, and ſcarcely in the practice of common Juſtice and Equity, and ſpeaking Truth to, and every one, of his Neighbour, what Jarrs and Confuſions will
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:006868_0045_102A8E2A303F2688"/>
then enſue and ariſe, and ſpread into the public Affairs, wherein they, are obliged to be Concerned together? And their Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being Alienated from one another, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is in leſs Reputation among them, and Government of more difficult and ſucceſsleſs Adminiſtrations, becauſe their own Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, rather than Religion and good Order command their Attention and Employ both their Time and Powers. How often is it Obſerved that men are Prone to act in <hi>Civil,</hi> as they ſtand Affected in <hi>religious Matters</hi>: i. e. Contrarily (oppoſite to one another) which hurts the public Intereſt; but a firm United Regard to the Eſſentials, of both Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and good Order, would prevent this Miſchief.</p>
            <p>INDEED, where mens Intereſt doth ly by themſelves, as in many the affairs of Life; there, to have different Sentiments &amp; Modes of Acting don't affect the Public State, don't make any Jarr in, or break upon the Community. What if Huſbandmen have different Schemes and Ways of managing their Farms, and yet are profitable to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to the Public? Or Merchants have different Methods of keeping their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, and all bring out Truth? Why! the public Peace, and Good of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Wealth is not Diſturb'd or Injured hereby:
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:006868_0046_102A8E2DDF832F38"/>
But not ſo, in the public Affairs of Society, wherein the true Intereſt of the whole Body, doth ly together, and wherein the Members muſt be <hi>jointly</hi> Concerned, if they are <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly</hi> Concerned at all. Here, if they have very different Principles &amp; Schemes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct; and every one is ready to ſet up in Oppoſition to another; this, is very Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſive of the Foundations of Society and the Common Good thereof. Here now, a great Diviſion tendeth much to Deſtruction, <hi>If a Kingdom be divided againſt it ſelf, that Kingdom cannot ſtand.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Mark 3.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>SOME perhaps, are not ſufficiently aware of this, (viz.) of the ill, and moſt baneful Conſequences of a Diviſion in thoſe Things which are the Life of a Community; nor of the certain Duty of all the Members thereof. However they may differ one from the other in various Matters Prudential and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical; yet muſt lay utmoſt Weight upon it, to Agree in every Thing, neceſſary to the <hi>Being</hi> of Society! and as far as poſſible in all Things, conducive to the <hi>well Being</hi> of it. Wherefore, I have obſerved the great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of Peoples being well United in their regard to Religion &amp; Government, ſo neceſſary to the great Ends before mentioned. Hence,</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="44" facs="unknown:006868_0047_102A8E31114C2578"/>
               <hi>IV.</hi> I ſhall ſomewhat <hi>open the Glory, Safety &amp; Happineſs, of a People thus Uniting in their Regard to both theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THERE is nothing ſets a People ſo <hi>High</hi> as this doth: If they are Rich and Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous, and become Grand in outward Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance; it is nothing like Religion and good Order, to make them truly honourable: 'Tis <hi>Righteouſneſs that exalts a Nation</hi> that makes and argues them truly great. And all Power &amp; Policy, without Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Piety, will fail of doing it. If they are a Sinful Nation, a Wicked, Unrighteous, Prophane and Contentious People; that will Debaſe and Sink them into Contempt: For, <hi>Sin is a Reproach to any People.</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">I Tim. 2. 2.</note> There is no way that a community can be truly great and honourable without Righteouſneſs and good Order; and this muſt ſpread thro' the Whole Effectually to Anſwer the Purpoſe. The Rulers muſt be <hi>juſt</hi> Men, <hi>ruling in the Fear of God,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">2 Sam 23 3</note> Men of Eſtabliſhed Principles, of Virtue and Religion: And the ſame good Principles muſt govern the People, <note n="‡" place="bottom">Prov. 14.34 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Then, and then only are they Honourable indeed. This will be their Glory above every Thing elſe. For, what can ſo Ennoble a Perſon, or People, as their Conformity to God the
<pb n="45" facs="unknown:006868_0048_102A8E334E145308"/>
Foundation of Righteouſneſs, Goodneſs, and all Perfection, in Copying after Him; they have the Eſſentials of True Glory and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Oh! this true Virtue and Piety doth Brighten and Dignify the Powers of Man; this Inſpires him with ſuch Principles of Action, as carry him above the mean, ſelfiſh Principles, and Views that govern Earthly and Unſanctify'd Minds, which greatly hurt and diſhonour a People. But, theſe other Principles of true Goodneſs do make men public Spirited, ſet for the good of Society in all manner of Ways, not only by their own orderly Life &amp; diſcreet Management, but by their generous Temper which Commands their Subſtance, and all their Powers for the public Good, as there is Occaſion, &amp; Duty ſo Requires. Wherefore ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>look not every man on his own things, but every man alſo on the things of others, let this Mind be in you, which was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Phil. 2.4, 5.</note>. This is Chriſt-like to be Unſelfiſh, and full of generous Principles of Beneficence for the public Intereſt; ſuch Principles of true good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will diſpoſe Rulers to act above ſelf for God and the good of the People, the very end of Government. It has always been ſo,
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:006868_0049_102A8E34DB41FB48"/>
that Rulers, are the <hi>better Rulers</hi> for being <hi>good Men,</hi> &amp; the civil State always the better and more honourable, for the true Virtue and Piety diſplayed in <hi>their Lives,</hi> and blen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with <hi>their Adminiſtrations.</hi> How good were <hi>Iſraels Kings</hi> in their Government, when <hi>good Men?</hi> and how bad in <hi>their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> when <hi>bad men</hi>? and how low did Iſrael Sink then? it went well or ill with the People, according as their Kings and Rulers were. <hi>When the Righteous are in Authority, the people rejoyce, but when the Wicked bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Rule the people Mourn,</hi> and are bro't low <note n="‖" place="bottom">Prov. 29 2.</note>.</p>
            <p>AND, thus as to the <hi>Safety</hi> of a People and all the Branches of <hi>their Happineſs,</hi> it is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected with their Obedience. But forever expoſed to all manner of Judgments, is a Sinful and Diſobedient People; to Wars with their Enemies, unto Peſtilence and Scarcity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A Community is in Danger, or Safety, is Happy, or Miſerable, much ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Behaviour, as ſuch; if wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, very generally prevails among a People, and wink't at by their Rulers; Eſpecially if public Injuſtice and Wrong be done; this Expoſes the Public greatly. But, if all are United in their Regard to Truth, and Right; both Rulers and People, ſet to
<pb n="47" facs="unknown:006868_0050_102A8E367118D518"/>
pleaſe God and promote the Public Good by doing every one the Duty of his Place; then God will <hi>make their Enemies to be at peace with them,</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Prov. 16.7</note> Then he will <hi>take away</hi> and keep off, <hi>raging Sickneſs,</hi> 
               <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Deut. 7.12, 15</note> Afford them his ſaving Health, with <hi>all manner of Store,</hi> 
               <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Pſa. 144 12</note> Then he will be <hi>their Defence and Salvation,</hi> 
               <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Job 22 23, 25.</note> 
               <hi>Let Integrity preſerve me,</hi> 
               <note n="(e)" place="bottom">Pſal. 25.21.</note> (ſays David the King) And this preſerveth the <hi>Subjects,</hi> as well as the <hi>Prince:</hi> This preſerveth and upholdeth <hi>Society.</hi> God is <hi>a Refuge</hi> for his People, <note n="(f)" place="bottom">Deut. 35.27, 29 Pſa. 46. pertotum.</note> And who can reach them in ſuch <hi>an Hiding Place</hi>? He is their <hi>Rock of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> 
               <note n="(g)" place="bottom">Pſa. 62.2.</note> And to what Purpoſe for the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Batter againſt ſuch <hi>a ſtrong Rock, an Houſe of Defence to Save us?</hi> 
               <note n="(h)" place="bottom">Pſa. 31.2.</note> He is their <hi>High Tower,</hi> 
               <note n="(i)" place="bottom">Pſa. 18 2.</note> And what Enemy can Scale ſuch a Tower? <hi>If God be for us, who can be againſt us?</hi> 
               <note n="(k)" place="bottom">Rom. 8, 31.</note> 'Tis then the greateſt Policy of a People to be Honeſt with God and Man, and Secure the divine Preſence with them, which is their Glory, Safety, and Happineſs indeed. <hi>It is He that giveth Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation unto Kings.</hi> See Pſal. 144.10. And Proſperity to the <hi>Subjects</hi>; as it there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, in a Variety of Inſtances, both in our
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:006868_0051_102A8E3A21731C40"/>
               <hi>Children, &amp; in our <hi>Subſtance,</hi> &amp;c. Happy is that People that is in ſucb a Caſe, yea, happy is that People whoſe God is the Lord.</hi> Pſal. 144.15.</p>
            <p>The <hi>APPLICATION</hi> follows. And,</p>
            <p>FIRST, By way of <hi>Inference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hence,</hi> Learn that <hi>one great Bane</hi> of Society is mens Ignorance of the Nature of Society, or Unattention to the great Deſigns thereof.</p>
            <p>IF Perſons are Ignorant of the Diſtinction there is between the State of Men; as <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduals,</hi> and as <hi>Members</hi> of Community: If they are inſenſible of the Bonds of Society, and the ſacred Obligations ariſing thence, to act with unſelfiſh, ſteddy Views of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good: But are ready to ſeparate their own private Intereſt from that, and ſo practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally Renounce their Relation to the Body Politic; this hurts it greatly. If they Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, they may ſeek their own private Good, abſtracted from any Regard to the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity; or, as if their own particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt muſt be the Standard by which, to meaſure the public Good; and hence, frame their Schemes of Conduct to ſuit them, only, this is Miſchievous to Society. For now, when they come to act as Members of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,
<pb n="49" facs="unknown:006868_0052_102A8E3EA4F44038"/>
the <hi>great Queſtion</hi> with them is, What is good for <hi>me?</hi> and what will ſuit <hi>my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt?</hi> Not what is good for the <hi>Community,</hi> or proper for <hi>them</hi>? And this governs their Vote and Conduct; which is a Violation of the duty of Members, a betraying their Truſt, and breaking their ſolemn Bonds. For, at what Time, any particular Members are At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tach'd to their own Intereſt without Regard to and againſt the Intereſt of the whole; they practically break off from the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and go back to a ſtate of Nature; thus declaring for that, as Preferable to any other. And now, don't this Principle Naturally tend to Ill? For, each one acting ſo, (as every one might on the ſame Principle) would deſtroy the great ends of Society, and indeed the very Being of it. And this, I ſuppoſe upon a juſt Examination, will be found one great ſpring of the hurtful Diviſions in Church and State. This is what divides a Kingdom &amp; any Community againſt it ſelf and ſo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys it.</p>
            <p>BUT then further, we hence Learn <hi>another</hi> great Bane of Society is the want of Virtue and Religion therein. Not only do men hurt Society, when in public Affairs, they act as Individuals; but, and eſpecially when they act as open Tranſgreſſors of the divine Law, Indulge themſelves in Sin, in Deceit,
<pb n="50" facs="unknown:006868_0053_102A8E4044397F48"/>
Diſhoneſty, Intemperance, Litigiouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For, Sin is a great and moſt awful Diſorder in the Body Politick. And the more of it in particular Members, the more in the Body, which is weakn'd by the Prevalence of it in them.</p>
            <p>AND, from whatever Quarter do come bitter Complaints of the Times, and of the public State of Things; this is truly the grand Source of all our Miſchiefs, (<hi>viz.)</hi> our Sin, our low Regard to Virtue &amp; Religion, &amp; not making Conſcience of doing Juſtly, living So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, and Frugally, and walking Humbly with God, and Charitably with one another. 'Tis our caſting Contempt on the Goſpel and Inſtitutions of Jeſus Chriſt, on his Name, Sabbaths, Miniſtry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuing &amp; Abuſing our precious Privileges, Civil and Religious, with our Uncharitable Contentions, Diviſions, and Murmurings under the higheſt Liberties of any People upon the Face of the Earth; that ſo weaken, wound and deſtroy us: Verily, it is theſe Things that expoſe us to Ruin: Theſe are our <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> and Threaten our <hi>Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AGAIN, We Learn hence how much the <hi>Attention</hi> of a whole Community, ſhould be Awakened to their own Recovery; to ſeek it in all the Ways and Things ſo Eſſential to the good of Society, <hi>(viz.</hi>) In
<pb n="51" facs="unknown:006868_0054_102A8E431496C080"/>
acting from that unſelfiſh Love, and noble public Spiritedneſs, which ſhould for ever govern the Members of Society in their various Capacities, &amp; from Principles of ſolid Virtue in all their Conduct. For, where there is not practical Righteouſneſs among a People, they will be everlaſtingly Unhappy. And all the Politicks in the World cannot ſave them: This cannot be Contriv'd, and Righteouſneſs left out of the Scheme. But, vaſtly great is the Advantage hereof in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, eſpecially when People are United in their Regard thereunto. This, on the one Hand, will guard againſt <hi>Tyranny,</hi> &amp; arbitrary Power in the <hi>civil Magiſtrate</hi>; and on the other, againſt <hi>Sedition and Rebellion</hi> in the <hi>Subject,</hi> and ſo againſt all thoſe Impious and Unpeaceable Methods of Conduct, which are ſo prejudicial to the Public.</p>
            <p>IF thoſe on the Thrones of Judgment, take their Meaſures of Government from the Teſtimony of Iſrael, that will ſecure them from <hi>lawleſs Power:</hi> And if the People take their Meaſures of Conduct from the Word of God alſo, that will Guard them againſt Diſobedience to <hi>lawful Authority.</hi> And ſo both will keep their Place, and ſerve the common Good.</p>
            <p>AGAIN, We hence Learn, what a great <hi>Bleſſing</hi> to Society is <hi>a good Government.</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="unknown:006868_0055_102A8E46EB938868"/>
One of a happy Conſtitution, and wiſely and faithfully Adminiſtred. It has been tho't, that Government in ſome Reſpect bad, is better than none. Hence a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> not without <hi>ſome Tyranny,</hi> has been Choſen before <hi>Anarchy and Confuſion</hi>: But, a good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, founded in Scripture and Reaſon, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing to the Subjects all the Privilege which, of Right, &amp; in the Reaſon of Things, belongs to them: How great a Bleſſing this? For this is a great Incouragement to Virtue and Religion; the Soul and Life of a happy Society. And thus, it ſeems to be Expreſſed in our Text: <hi>For, there,</hi> are ſet Thrones of Judgment, the Thrones of the Houſe of David. As much as to ſay, the Tribes of Iſrael are juſtly incouraged to be Religious, to come up to Jeruſalem, to the Teſtimony of Iſrael, to the Ark of God there, and there to give Thanks to the Name of the Lord, and Worſhip him according to his Word; becauſe, <hi>there,</hi> is a good civil Government E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed &amp; Exerciſed for their Protection in the Worſhip &amp; Service of God. The <hi>ſet</hi> Thrones of Judgment, <hi>the Thrones of the houſe of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>: A Government in the Hands of one after God's own Heart, who Loves to Serve the <hi>God of Iſrael</hi> Himſelf, &amp; would have <hi>all Iſrael</hi> do ſo too. — Which Naturally leads me, to another Branch of the Improvement.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="unknown:006868_0056_102A8E489D9CAC58"/>SECONDLY, By way of <hi>Addreſs and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation:</hi> And firſt of all to the Honourable the <hi>Governour in Chief,</hi> and <hi>Deputy-Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi>; together with the Worſhipful <hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> Of this Colony.</p>
            <p>But, before I turn my Diſcourſe directly unto You. — The Vacancy ſo lately made in the chief Seat of Government, here, by Death; may juſtly call me, on this public Occaſion, to Lament the Loſs, we have ſuſtained in the Death of the late HONOURA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE GOVERNOR LAW; who, (as it hath been publickly and juſtly ſaid of Him) was, <q>a Gentleman of a critical Underſtanding in the Law; and thô not an <hi>Eloquent Orator,</hi> yet he was a <hi>wiſe Counſellour,</hi> and very Judicious, Wary, and Steddy in all his Conduct: As a Governour, he was a hearty Friend to the Rights &amp; Privileges of the Community, and always Steddily purſued that, which appeared to him, to be right in itſelf and moſt conducive to the public Good. — Little mov'd by popular Noiſe, or party Intereſts, keeping in his mind, a moſt clear, diſtinct, and ſteddy View of the public Affairs, without Involving himſelf or others into precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Meaſures. — He Moderated with his uſual Wiſdom and Steadineſs in the
<pb n="54" facs="unknown:006868_0057_102A7AAB5C1AD6E8"/>
laſt <hi>October</hi> Seſſion of the General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, which Ended but the day before he was Seiſed with the Illneſs that called him hence</q>.</p>
            <p>Thus, he finiſh'd his public Uſefulneſs and Life together: As it is Written, <hi>I have ſaid, Ye are Gods,— But ye ſhall die like Men,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Pſal. 82.6, 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>So, I leave the Dead of precious Memory, and ſpeak unto the Living,— You will then, HONOURED SIRS, ſuffer the Addreſs agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Importance of my <hi>Subject,</hi> and your <hi>Station.</hi> — You are here upon theſe Subordinate Thrones of Judgment, and the Government devolv'd on You, is of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Weighty enough, to Employ your beſt Attention, and Engage your utmoſt Fidelity to the right Adminiſtration thereof. — The <hi>Seats</hi> of civil Authority, are here called, <hi>ſet Thrones of Judgment</hi>: You are then to fill theſe Seats <hi>with Judgment,</hi> with the Diſplays of rightful Authority. Oh! how doth the very <hi>Epithet,</hi> ſpeak your Obligations to <hi>do Juſtice &amp; Judgment,</hi> and with the whole Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative Body, to uſe your utmoſt Wiſdom, to <hi>Eſtabliſh Judgment,</hi> Righteouſneſs &amp; Equity among us. — <hi>And who knoweth whether Ye are come</hi> to the Thrones of Judgment,<note n="†" place="bottom">Eſther 4.14.</note>
               <pb n="55" facs="unknown:006868_0058_102A8E506A0CADD0"/>
               <hi>for ſuch a Time as this</hi>? So Difficult and Critical as this; wherein there needs ſo much Penetration and Application to Contrive and Conduct our public Affairs for the beſt good of the Community. You, will ever think, that any Thing of the Nature of Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, which ſeems to have the Countenance of Public Authority will be very Evil in its ſelf, and Prejudicial unto us. And tho' no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this Nature, can be deſigned by ſuch a Government as this, that we are under; yet if it ſo happen that things do gradually come to run in a Channel, which unavoidably produceth it in the End; this will be a wrong to the Subject, that will be felt for a great while. For, it always wounds the State very deeply, when its Members Suffer by its own Acts, tho' originally deſign'd and directed quite another way. <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> indeed <hi>Exalteth a Nation,</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">Prov. 14.34.</note> and never <hi>more ſo,</hi> than when it proceeds <hi>from the Throne</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Prov. 20 8.</note> from the ſet Thrones of Judgment: But Injuſtice and Wrong, tho' but Obliquely coming from thence, has a very <hi>contrary Tendency.</hi> You, will therefore Conſider that a ſtrict Regard <hi>to Righteouſneſs,</hi> and a moſt ſteddy Conduct in Adminiſtration from <hi>that Princip1e,</hi> is a very Chief and Beneficial Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification
<pb n="56" facs="unknown:006868_0059_102A8E5359968980"/>
in the civil Ruler. <hi>The King by Judgment Eſtabliſheth the Land.</hi> 
               <note n="‡" place="bottom">Prov. 29.4.</note> And never perhaps did our Land need it more than now when People in various Reſpects, are got into ſuch an Unquiet and Unſettled Poſture.</p>
            <p>IN a word, You, will always remember that the Thrones of Judgment, which God hath <hi>Set,</hi> i.e. Eſtabliſhed, and Sets You on; are placed near the Teſtimony of Iſrael: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating, that from thence You are to form your <hi>Meaſures</hi> and fetch your <hi>Maxims</hi> of Government, and that the <hi>Teſtimony of Iſrael</hi> ſo nearly Situated to the <hi>Thrones of Judgment,</hi> (Eſpecially, under a Chriſtian Diſpenſation) is to be Defended and Protected by You in the great Intereſt thereof at all Times.</p>
            <p>IN the <hi>next place,</hi> ſhall I turn me to the Honourable Houſe of Repreſentatives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> who are now Choſen, into this Legiſlative Court. You have alſo, a kind of Seat on the Subordinate Thrones of Judgment, as, you are concern'd in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves, and Acts, which may go hence under the Stamp and Sanction of public Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. — And now to diſcharge your Truſts you are to look directly to the ends Of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="57" facs="unknown:006868_0060_102A8E566DBFF1D0"/>
the Honour of your great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployer, under whom; and the good of the People for whom, you Act; and Endeavour to the utmoſt of your Power that the way to this be prepared by <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi>; by which <hi>the Throne</hi> it ſelf is <hi>Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held and Eſtabliſhed.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Prov. 16 I2</note>. And which is ſo Eſſential to all good Government.</p>
            <p>IT lyeth very much with you, to diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance Injuſtice and all Immorality and Prophaneſs, Idleneſs and Sloth, and every way wherein, men are Injuring themſelves and the Public. — And in ſo critical a Day as this, which needs the wiſeſt Heads to deliver us from threatn'd Miſchiefs; let <hi>Integrity</hi> as well as Wiſdom <hi>guide you,</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Prov. 11.3.</note> I am far from Suggeſting any Schemes of your Conduct, in the management of public Affairs; but this, I may obſrve to You, that the Sacred Rules of Juſtice and Truth, muſt be ſtrictly Adhered to, in all You do; and no Policies to be admitted, which Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate againſt a Thing ſo Sacred as Equity.</p>
            <p>IF the Affair of our <hi>Paper Currency, &amp;c.</hi> come under Your Conſideration, let nothing be Tranſacted by You; but what the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Rules of Righteouſneſs and Goodneſs, will Vindicate You in.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="unknown:006868_0061_102A8E5991ABA2C8"/>Now then we have in the great divine Law-Book this Important Statute of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Enacted, Written, and Signed as follows,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye ſhall do no Unrighteouſneſs, in Judgment, in Mete-yard, in Weight, or in Meaſure. Juſt Balances, juſt Weights—ſhall ye have:</hi> I AM THE LORD YOUR GOD.</p>
            <p>DEUS REX.<note n="*" place="bottom">Lev. 19 35, 36.</note>
            </p>
            <p>THIS is one great and infallible Rule of Your Conduct: Fix your Eyes upon it, keep it in your View, and feel the weight of it upon your Hearts, and let the public Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves and Acts ſhew the Influence thereof. Thus Solemnly is it, Enacted, Exhibited, and Sign'd by GOD himſelf, <hi>the Lord our Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver and our King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND, ſee the Connection here, as if in one Breath the Lord Spake to the <hi>Judges,</hi> and the <hi>Merchants</hi> and every One, ye ſhall do no Unrighteouſneſs in <hi>Judgment,</hi> in <hi>Mete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,</hi> in <hi>Weight,</hi> nor any other Way. <hi>But Juſt Balances, and Weights; ſ) Juſt Laws, and Rules and a Juſt Medium</hi> ſhall ye have: The Lord hath decreed and ſaid it, and who then ſhall not take Notice of it? And again,
<pb n="59" facs="unknown:006868_0062_102A8E5BDDB1E208"/>
it is written, <hi>that which is altogether Juſt ſhalt thou follow, that thou mayeſt Live and Inherit the Land</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">Deut. 15.20.</note> 
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Thes. 4 5.</note>. Here you ſee, the <hi>very Life</hi> as well as <hi>the Subſtance</hi> of a People, as continued to them in Mercy, depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their being Juſt and Righteous; and this as Sacred as what is <hi>Moral</hi> and of <hi>Eternal Obligation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND, how can the civil Legiſlature be Clear, if the <hi>public Credit,</hi> a thing ſo Sacred as the <hi>Faith</hi> of a Community, be in the Courſe of Things moſt uncertain, which muſt expoſe People to Injure, &amp; be Injured? <hi>The Currant Money with the Merchant</hi> uſed to be a ſtable Thing, and has the Sanction of Scripture upon it as ſuch, <note n="*" place="bottom">Gen. 23.15, 16</note> that People knew what they had, and what to do with it, to anſwer their Occaſions without Injuſtice to others, or Wrong to themſelves. And ſhould not the <hi>Currant Money of a Colony</hi> be ſo too? If our <hi>Weights and Meaſures</hi> are leſſened by long uſe or worn away <hi>a little</hi> in Time, they ſhould be bro't to the Standard and made ſtrictly Juſt that People may not be Wrong'd nor do Unjuſtly in Buying and Selling. And why ſhould not our <hi>Paper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Medium</hi> that is ſunk away <hi>much,</hi> be ſome way bro't to Truth, that we may no lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nger
<pb n="60" facs="unknown:006868_0063_102A8E5E4B58FBC8"/>
be wrong'd by it? Or can there be found no Standard of Juſtice in this Matter, that poor <hi>Orphans</hi> and <hi>Others</hi> be not turn'd off, with one Half of their Righteous Dues? Verily the Cry of theſe and other the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed will be heard from on High. And, Oh! Let their Cauſe be heard below, and Conſider'd well on the Thrones, and Seats of Judgment <hi>here,</hi> before it is too late; to have all Right and Well, for a hearing at the Bar of Judgment <hi>hereafter.</hi> It will ſurely be the Honour and Safety of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in all Things, to do Juſtly and to love Mercy, that Superior Example, as from the Thrones of Judgment may in its happy Influence ſpread far &amp; wide; that <hi>Judgment</hi> every where <hi>may run down as Waters,</hi> as freely &amp; as plentifully, <hi>and Righteouſneſs as a mighty Stream</hi> that is not eaſily ſtopped. You will alſo be continued <hi>Patrons</hi> to the <hi>College</hi>; and laudably Ambitious to promote Learning ſo Uſeful in Church and State.</p>
            <p>IN the next Place, What ſhall I hint to my Fathers and Brethren in the Miniſtry? Surely, it becomes Us, in Regard to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Deſign of our Office eſpecially, to ſhew all juſt Concern for the Promotion of that Religion and good Order ſo Eſſential to the Good of Society.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="unknown:006868_0064_102A8E621BD6F018"/>A <hi>Religion</hi> which not only Teacheth, that there is A GOD whom <hi>as men,</hi> we are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Knowing and Enjoying; and whom we are Everlaſtingly Obliged to Love and Serve, — And <hi>as fallen Men</hi> we have bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken over the natural Obligations unto this: And that now, there are theſe Corruptions in our Nature as render us Unworthy of God, and Obnoxious to his Reſentments for Ever. — But, a <hi>Religion,</hi> that alſo Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that there is A SAVIOUR provided for us, that JESUS CHRIST the Son and Meſſenger of God is this Saviour, and the only Redeemer of Man. — A <hi>Religion</hi> that Inſtructs us in the Method of Salvation by Him, thro' his Perfect Obedience and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory Sacrifice; the only ſufficient Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs for us, and compleatly Effectual unto the Salvation of all that Believe.— A <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> that opens the Way of mens Obtaining this Faith which is Saving, by the Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony of God, concerning his Son, and the Influence of the Holy Spirit, which alone Applys the Word, Eſpecially, the Word Preached for this End. — A <hi>Religion,</hi> that Exhibits the Encouragement and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for Faith in Chriſt; not from any Thing in our ſelves, but from the Grace of the Goſpel, the Word of a God Inviting us to come to Chriſt not with ſtanding all our Sins
<pb n="62" facs="unknown:006868_0065_102A8E64062DE4D8"/>
and Unworthineſs, that we may be Saved from our Sins, the Guilt, the Filth, the Power and Fruits thereof. —</p>
            <p>MOREOVER, A <hi>Religion,</hi> that Enforceth all the Moral Obligations to Virtue and Holineſs with ſome New Sanctions, and Motives peculiar to a Goſpel State, which the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God hath Given, in the New Teſtament for that End.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And,</hi> now my Brethren, to promote ſuch a Religion, as Forms Men for God and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, is to ſerve both the Intereſt of the Church and the State alſo; for, the more Truly and Practically <hi>Religious,</hi> men are, the more <hi>Orderly</hi> in the State. This then let us do, and labour in, Spend and be Spent, in this Service, for the Good of <hi>Souls</hi> and of <hi>Society.</hi> — In the mean Time <hi>keeping</hi> well <hi>our own Vineyard,</hi> looking well to the State of our own Souls; ſeeing to it, that we are the Subjects of the Religion which we rightly Preach to others, and that we Live and Shine in all the Exerciſes of it; as Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples unto others, more and more bright and worthly of Imitation: That the latter part of our Day may be the Brighteſt, and our Sun Set, not in a Cloud, but in the Dawn of Eternal Day.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="unknown:006868_0066_102A8E660A90F0D8"/>TO CONCLUDE,</p>
            <p>Let all this Aſſembly <hi>Know Aſſuredly,</hi> that they muſt all be Subject unto the Laws of God, to the Religion of Jeſus Chriſt; unto whoſe Tribunal We are all Accountable, and muſt give Account. — And now to the Care of our own Souls, let us add all juſt Concern for the Proſperity of the Church and the State. And Earneſtly <hi>Pray for the Peace of Jeruſalem: For they ſhall proſper that Love thee.</hi> Say we then every one of us, <hi>Peace be within thy Walls, and Proſperity within thy Palaces.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>AMEN</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
