<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A general idea of the College of Mirania; with a sketch of the method of teaching science and religion, in the several classes: and some account of its rise, establishment and buildings. Address'd more immediately to the consideration of the trustees nominated, by the Legislature, to receive proposals, &amp;c. relating to the establishment of a college in the province of New-York. : [Three lines of quotations in Latin]</title>
            <author>Smith, William, 1727-1803.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N05612</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N05612</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 7121</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APV9051</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">7121</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99004650</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 7121.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N05612)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 7121)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 7121)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A general idea of the College of Mirania; with a sketch of the method of teaching science and religion, in the several classes: and some account of its rise, establishment and buildings. Address'd more immediately to the consideration of the trustees nominated, by the Legislature, to receive proposals, &amp;c. relating to the establishment of a college in the province of New-York. : [Three lines of quotations in Latin]</title>
                  <author>Smith, William, 1727-1803.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>86 p. ;  20 cm. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by J. Parker and W. Weyman, at the new printing-office in Beaver-Street,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New-York: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1753. (Price one shilling and six pence.)</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Outlining "a purely fictitious institution" to show the kind of college William Smith thought suitable for a new country. The concept informed the founding of the University of Pennsylvania. Cf. Wood, G.B.  Early hist. of the Univ. of Penn. (1896).</note>
                  <note>Signed on p. 81: W. Smith.</note>
                  <note>Parentheses substituted for square brackets in imprint transcription.</note>
                  <note>Errata statement, p. [3].</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Universities and colleges --  Planning.</term>
               <term>Universities and colleges --  Curricula.</term>
               <term>Education, Higher.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:007121_0000_102AF9EF68A78FF0"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:007121_0001_102AD6F2B29EA9F8"/>
            <p>A GENERAL IDEA OF THE COLLEGE OF <hi>MIRANIA;</hi> WITH A Sketch of the Method of teaching <hi>Science</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> in the ſeveral Claſſes: AND Some Account of its Riſe, Eſtabliſhment and Buildings.</p>
            <p>Addreſs'd more immediately to the Conſideration of the Truſtees nominated, by the Legiſlature, to receive Propoſals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> relating to the Eſtabliſhment of a COLLEGE in the Province of <hi>NEW-YORK.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Quid Leges ſine Moribus vanae proficiunt?</hi>
               <bibl>Hor.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Nullum Animal moroſius eſt; nullum majore Arte tractandum quam Home.</hi> Natura <hi>ſequitur melius quam ducitur.</hi>
               <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>NEW-YORK: <hi>Printed and Sold by</hi> J. PARKER <hi>and</hi> W. WEYMAN, <hi>at the New Printing-Office in Beaver-Street,</hi> 1753.</p>
            <p>[Price One Shilling and Six Pence.]</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="unknown:007121_0002_102AD6F5178149C8"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>VERSES ſpoken at the opening of the College of <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Introduction.</cell>
                     <cell>p. 7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Object of Education, and Deſign of our Creation,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 10, 11, 12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A grand Diviſion of Mankind into two Claſſes.</cell>
                     <cell>p. 13, 14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mechanic</hi>'s School,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 14, 15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Latin-School,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 16, 17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>College;</hi> or five learn'd Claſſes;</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1ſt, or Greek Claſs,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2d, or Mathematical Claſs,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3d, or Philoſophical Claſs,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>4th</hi> Claſs.—</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Rhetoric, 19, 20. Poetry,</cell>
                     <cell>p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Criticiſm, 16. Compoſition, 22. Taſte, 24, 25.</cell>
                     <cell>p. 16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5th Claſs.</cell>
                     <cell>p. 26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Animal Anatomy; Agriculture,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 16, 27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hiſtory, Politics, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 27, 28, 29</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Oeconomy of the Claſſes,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 31. 32. <hi>&amp;c</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Public Exerciſes,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 34, 35</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Declamation,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Dramatic Performances,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Engliſh Language,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid,</hi> p. 37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Modern Languages,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Maſters in athletic Exerciſes,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ib.</hi> p. 38</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Natural Religion and good Morals,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 38, 39</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>as enforc'd in the</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1ſt Claſs in the Study of <hi>Homer,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2d Claſs, eſpecially in the Study of Aſtronomy,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3d Claſs; chiefly in the Study of Micrography,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 42</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4th Claſs.</cell>
                     <cell>p. 46</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5th Claſs, In the Study of Agriculture, 47. By a Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skip,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi> p.48</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Taſte of true Greatneſs form'd, By Hiſtorical Facts,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 49, 50, 51, 52. 53</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Love of the Britiſh Conſtitution,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 55, 56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Good Effects of ſuch an Education,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 56, 57, 58, 59, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of the Edifice,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 61, 62, 63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Method of filling up the Claſſes, and carrying the whole into Execution in five Years.</cell>
                     <cell>p. 69</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Provincial annual Lottery,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 70</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>An Engliſh Lottery,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Commencement,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>An Engliſh School in each Townſhip,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 71</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And one Latin School in the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient Place in each County,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Concluſion,</hi> touching the Imitation of this Inſtitution of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rania,</hi> in the Province of <hi>New-York,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 75</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Poſtſcript, containing part of a Letter from the Weſt-Indies, with ſome Remarks upon it, and upon the Religion to be eſtabliſhed in our College.</cell>
                     <cell>p. 51, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>The Reader is deſired to correct with his P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the following ERRATA:</head>
            <p>PAGE 17, line 17, <hi>read</hi> Euclid's. p. 21, l. 12, <hi>r.</hi> Ariſtotle's Poetics. p. 24, l. 22, <hi>after</hi> Time <hi>place a Cemma,</hi> p. <hi>ibid,</hi> in the Note, l, 10, <hi>r.</hi> majeſtic, p. 29, l. 31, <hi>for</hi> third, <hi>r.</hi> ſaid. p. 32, l. 1. <hi>for</hi> two, <hi>r.</hi> too. p. 33, l. 1. <hi>r.</hi> videretur. p. 45, l. 21, <hi>r.</hi> God. p. 47, l. 1, <hi>r.</hi> to admire, p. 48; l. 4, <hi>r.</hi> odenterous.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="unknown:007121_0003_102AF93CA51B2D10"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THE following Sheets were plan'd at the ſame Time with the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet on the Situation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of our intended College, publiſh'd laſt <hi>October;</hi> and deſign'd to follow it whenever the Public, by a more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Attention to the Concerns of Education, ſhou'd ſeem prepar'd to receive it. For, however neceſſary and ſeaſonable an Enquiry, concerning the proper Situation and Advantages of a College in this Province, was in itſelf, as a firſt Step, to ſettle a Point that had been long diſputed, and to unite all Parties in a ſpeedy Execution; yet I was always convinced, that this is but the leaſt Part of what ought to be ſettled previous to our propos'd Eſtabliſhment, and Nothing more than a mere Trifle in Compariſon of the Conſtitution, Government, and Diſcipline of a College; with which indeed Nothing can be compared; and concerning which no Perſon, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, has more frequently employ'd his Thoughts than I have done. This will fully appear to thoſe who can form a juſt Idea of the Study and Labor it muſt have coſt to bring all the Parts of the following Work into their preſent Order in ſuch a ſmall Compaſs: A Labor, nothing cou'd have induc'd me, at preſent, to undergo, but an unfeign'd Zeal for the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of uſeful Literature in this uncultivated Corner of the Globe, and a fond Deſire to make ſome Amends to the Public, on the <hi>main Subject,</hi> for their kind and unmerited Reception of the former Eſſay.</p>
            <p>This Work is addreſs'd more immediately to the Conſideration of the Truſtees, tho' I am ſenſible that, by the Deſign of their Nomination, they are not empower'd to give any abſolute Deciſion on the Expediency of Propoſals of this Nature. However, as they are the only ſtanding Body, upon whom this great Work reſts, ſo far as it is yet advanc'd, it was proper to ſend theſe Papers abroad under their Protection. The Manuſcript wou'd have been preſented to them at their firſt public Meeting, had I not been advis'd by ſome of them, to whom I ſhew'd it, as private Friends, that ſuch a Scheme cou'd be beſt judg'd of in Print; when every Perſon might have the calm Peruſal of a Copy; and that the ſooner it appear'd, of the greater Service might it become.—As it was written with this very Intention, to give Men of Senſe and Learning an Opportunity of blaming, altering, or improving it, before the Meeting of the General Aſſembly, I immediately committed it to the Preſs, without conſulting Reputation, by adviſing, as uſual, with ſome of my very condeſcending and learn'd City Friends, by which Means it might have appear'd to greater Advantage. —But as I have ſtill a better Aim than any Reputation to be gain'd by the beſt executed Thing of this Nature, I ſhall not even envy my very Enemies the Pleaſure they may find in detecting ſome Imperfections which, on more Thought, I cou'd have remov'd; or others which, perhaps, I never intended to remove: Let them only ſhew they can do ſo with good Manners; then every Error they diſcover, or Improvement they propoſe, on the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Scheme, will be of ſome Service to the Public, and Matter of great Joy to the Author.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="5" facs="unknown:007121_0004_102AF940437C3E10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Verſes ſpoken at the Opening of The</hi> COLLEGE <hi>of MIRANIA.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>IT comes! at laſt, the <hi>promis'd</hi> AERA comes!</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Goſpel-Truth</hi> ſhall diſſipate the Glooms</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Pagan-Error;</hi> and, in copious Streams,</l>
               <l>O'er this dark <hi>Hemiſphere,</hi> ſhed <hi>ſaving Beams!</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="5">For, lo! her azure Wing bright SCIENCE ſpreads,</l>
               <l>And ſoft-approaches to theſe <hi>new-found-Shades;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Exultant, ſtretching forth her hallow'd Hands</l>
               <l>To plant her <hi>Laurels</hi> in ſerener Lands!</l>
               <l>Each <hi>Muſe</hi> around <hi>Her</hi> ſtrikes the warbling String;</l>
               <l n="10">And, mid <hi>Her</hi> Train, <hi>Peace, Juſtice, Freedom ſing—</hi>
               </l>
               <l>—A GODDESS comes!—they ſing and rend the Air—</l>
               <l>A GODDESS comes! to welcome <hi>Her</hi> prepare!</l>
               <l>Woods, Brooks, Gales, Fountains, long unknown to Fame,</l>
               <l>At length, as conſcious of your future Claim,</l>
               <l n="15">Prepare to nurſe the <hi>Philoſophic-Thought;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſwell the <hi>ſerious,</hi> or the <hi>ſportive</hi> Note!</l>
               <l>Prepare, ye <hi>Woods!</hi> to yield the <hi>Sage</hi> your Shade;</l>
               <l>And wave ambroſial Verdures o'er his Head!</l>
               <l>Ye <hi>Brooks!</hi> prepare to prompt the <hi>Poet</hi>'s Strains;</l>
               <l n="20">And ſoftly murmur back his amorous Pains!</l>
               <l>Haſte, O ye <hi>Gales!</hi> your ſpicy Sweets impart;</l>
               <l>In <hi>Muſic</hi> breathe Them to th' exulting Heart!</l>
               <l>Ye <hi>Fountains!</hi> haſte, th' <hi>inſpiring Wave</hi> to roll;</l>
               <l>And give <hi>Caſtalian Draughts</hi> to lave the Soul.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Tis done!—Woods, Brooks, Gales, Fountains, all, obey;</l>
               <l>And ſay with general Voice—or ſeem to ſay—</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="unknown:007121_0005_102AF9426E2C1D38"/>
—Hail, <hi>Heaven-deſcended!</hi> holy SCIENCE, hail!</l>
               <l>Thrice-welcome to theſe Climes; here ever dwell,</l>
               <l>With Shade and Silence, far from dire Alarms;</l>
               <l n="30">The Trumpet's horrid Clang, and Din of Arms!</l>
               <l>To Thee we offer every ſofter Seat;</l>
               <l>Each ſunny Lawn; or ſylvan ſweet Retreat;</l>
               <l>Each Flower-verg'd Stream; each
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Amber,</hi> in this Place, is a general Name for Gum. Reſins and all odorous vegetable Juice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, exſuding from Trees, Shrubs &amp; Herbs.</note> Amber-dropping Grove;</l>
               <l>Each Vale of <hi>Pleaſure;</hi> and each Bower o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Love:</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="35">Where <hi>youthful Nature,</hi> with ſtupendous Scenes,</l>
               <l>Lifts all the <hi>Powers;</hi> and all the <hi>Frame</hi> ſerenes.</l>
               <l>O then! here fix,—(<hi>Earth, Water, Air</hi> invite!)</l>
               <l>And bid a NEW-BRITANNIA ſpring to Light!—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Smit-deep, I antedate the <hi>Golden Days;</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="40">And ſtrive to paint them in ſublimer Lays!</l>
               <l>Behold! on Periods, Periods brightening riſe!</l>
               <l>On <hi>Worthies, Worthies</hi> croud before mine Eyes;</l>
               <l>See! other BACONS, NEWTONS, LOCKES appear;</l>
               <l>And to the Skies our Laureat-Honors rear.</l>
               <l n="45">See! mid undying <hi>Greens,</hi> they lie inſpir'd,</l>
               <l>On moſſy Beds, by heavenly Viſions fir'd;</l>
               <l>Aloft they ſoar, on <hi>Contemplation</hi>'s Wing,</l>
               <l>O'er Worlds and Worlds—and reach th' ETERNAL KING.</l>
               <l>Awak'd by other <hi>Suns,</hi> and kindling ſtrong</l>
               <l n="50">With pureſt Ardors for celeſtial <hi>Song,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Lo! other POPES and SPENCERS glad-reſound</l>
               <l>The <hi>rural Lay</hi> to Shepherds dancing round;</l>
               <l>Find other <hi>Twit'nams</hi> in each bowery Wood;</l>
               <l>And other <hi>Mullas</hi> in each ſylvan Flood.</l>
               <l n="55">Lo! the wild INDIAN, ſoften'd by their Song,</l>
               <l>Emerging from his <hi>Arbors,</hi> bounds along</l>
               <l>The green <hi>Savannah</hi> patient of the <hi>Lore</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of Dove-ey'd <hi>Wiſdom</hi>—and is <hi>rude</hi> no more.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="unknown:007121_0006_102AF943F96DE398"/>
Hark! even his <hi>Babes MESSIAH</hi>'s Praiſe proclaim;</l>
               <l n="60">Or fondly learn to liſp <hi>JEHOVAH</hi>'s Name!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O SCIENCE! onward thus thy Reign extend</l>
               <l>O'er Realms yet unexplor'd till Time ſhall end;</l>
               <l>Till Death-like <hi>Ignorance</hi> forſake the Ball,</l>
               <l>And Life-endearing <hi>Knowlege</hi> cover all;</l>
               <l>Till wounded <hi>Slavery</hi> ſeek her native Hell,</l>
               <l>In triple Bonds eternally to dwell!</l>
               <l>Not trackleſs Deſarts ſhall thy Progreſs ſtay;</l>
               <l>Rocks, Mountains, Floods, before Thee muſt give Way:</l>
               <l>Sequeſter'd Vales, at thy Approach, ſhall ſing;</l>
               <l n="70">And with the Voice of cheerful Labor ring.</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Wolves</hi> now howl, ſhall poliſh'd <hi>Villas</hi> riſe;</l>
               <l>And towery <hi>Cities</hi> grow into the Skies.—</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Pope's Wind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 399.</note> "<hi>Earth's diſtant Ends our Glory ſhall behold;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>"And the NEW-World launch forth to ſeek the OLD."</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <head>INTRODUCTION. <hi>To the</hi> TRUSTEES, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO every One that has the Intereſt and Reputation of this Province at Heart, particularly to You, it muſt give a very ſenſible Satisfaction to behold, at length, the general At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention drawn towards the Eſtabliſhing a public <hi>Seminary</hi> in it, under the Patronage of the Government, for the Inſtitution of Youth in the liberal <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences.</hi> The Spirit now ſeems to burn ſo much the ſtronger in Proportion to its Slowneſs in Catching; and gives ſure Preſage that we ſhall not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve our Honor, by rivaling the foremoſt of our Neighbors in this truly pious Work, but as far out-do them as they
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:007121_0007_102AF94589FD9248"/>have got the Start of Us, and as our ſuperior Abilities have put it in our Power.</p>
            <p>The Day, on which it is expected the <hi>General Aſſembly</hi> will meet, draws near; when, in Conſequence of a V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of laſt Seſſions, this important Affair will be the Subject of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberations. And, as the Plan or Idea of the whole Inſtitution ought, firſt of all, to be fix'd, that every Step they take may tend uniformly to the Execution of the ſame, it is the indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable Duty of every Perſon of Learning and Leiſure, to aſſiſt with his unbyaſs'd Thoughts on this Head. I, therefore, thought it incumbent on me to contribute my Mite for this good Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as well to exonerate myſelf of what I owe the State, as to ſatisfy the Expectations of ſome Gentlemen who have a Right at all Times to command me.</p>
            <p>While I was ruminating upon the Conſtitutions of the ſeveral Colleges, I had either perſonally viſited or read of, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to fix on any Thing, I durſt recommend as a Model worthy our Imitation, I chanc'd to fall into the Company of a valuable young Gentleman, named <hi>Evander,</hi> who is a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome Diſtinction of the Province of <hi>Mirania,</hi> After ſome Converſation on learn'd Topics, he was led to give me an Account of a Seminary eſtabliſh'd about twelve Years ago in that Province, in which I thought I perceiv'd all that ſeems excellent in the ancient and modern <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> reduc'd to the greateſt Method and Simplicity. This I have pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m'd to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to your Conſideration; which, as it may be further improv'd by you, and other learn'd Men among us, ſeems extremely well adapted to the Circumſtances of this Province of <hi>New-York,</hi> as we are now entirely ſuch as the <hi>Miranians</hi> were when they founded their College, with Regard to Riches, Trade and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Number of People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mirania,</hi> Gentlemen, is one of the Provinces of the <hi>New-World</hi> firſt ſettled by our Country-Men, the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> above a Century ago. In what Degrees of Lat. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it lies, is of no Importance; I am not to write its Hiſtory, but only to give a general Account of its College and the Method of Education practis'd in it; which, as nearly as I can remember, I ſhall do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ander</hi>'s own Words, as I am ſenſible that every Deviation from them would be a Blemiſh.—After a modeſt Apology, with which I ſhall not trouble You, he began as follows,—</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="unknown:007121_0008_102AF947E5D98B70"/>
            <head>
               <hi>EVANDER</hi>'s Account of the College of <hi>MIRANIA,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>"<seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T had been the peculiar Happineſs of my Countrymen, ever ſince their firſt Settlement, to enjoy an uninterrupted Tranquillity; at Peace with their Neighbours, unrival'd in their Trade, and bleſt in one Adminiſtration of a Succeſſion of mild and juſt Governors, who had the real Intereſt of the Province at Heart. Theſe favorable Circumſtances had, from time to time, beſides conſtant Supplies from the Mother-Country, invited over vaſt Numbers of Foreigners, who, quitting their native Land, ſought a calm Retreat in <hi>Mirania;</hi> where under the Protection of wiſe and equal Laws, and far beyond the Reach of Prieſtly Domination, and the rapacious Minions of ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred Robbers, they might dare to think for themſelves, dare to challenge and enjoy the Fruits of their own Induſtry.</p>
            <p>THUS, about twelve Years ago, the <hi>Miranians</hi> ſaw themſelves a mighty and floriſhing People, in Poſſeſſion of an extenſive Country, capable of producing all the Neceſſaries, and many of the Superfluities of Life. They reflected that the only Method of making theſe natural Advantages of laſting Uſe to themſelves and Poſterity,— the only infallible Source of Tranquillity, Happineſs and Glory,—was to contrive and execute a proper Scheme for forming a Succeſſion of ſober, virtuous, induſtrious Citizens, and checking the Courſe of growing Luxury. They were ſenſible, that tho' a Combination of lucky Circumſtances, almoſt wholly independent on them, had rais'd them ſo high, they ſhou'd be wanting to themſelves if they depended longer on blind Chance for any Thing which was now in their Power to command. They were convinced that, without a previous good Education, the beſt Laws are little better than <hi>Verba minantia,</hi> and, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd as ſuch, will be dup'd and broke thro' with Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:007121_0009_102AF94A8753FDE8"/>by illuſtrious Villains;—That the Magiſtrate can at beſt but fright Vice into a Corner, and that 'tis Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation alone can mend and rectify the Heart;—That no Government can ſubſiſt long on Violence and brute Force; and that Nature follows eaſily when treated rationally, but will not bear to be led, or driven. They ſaw alſo, that among the Foreigners, who were as numerous as the Engliſh, many Diſtinctions were forming upon their different Cuſtoms, Languages and Extractions, which, by creating ſeparate Intereſts, might in the Iſſue prove fatal to the Government. They wiſely judg'd, therefore, that Nothing cou'd ſo much contribute to make ſuch a Mixture of People coaleſce and unite in one common Intereſt, as the common Education of all the Youth at the ſame public Schools under the Eye of the civil Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Thus, ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y, indiſſoluble Connexions and Friendſhips will be form'd; Prejudices worn off; and the Youth will in Time either forget their very Extrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or from a more liberal Education, and manly Turn of Thought, learn to contemn thoſe little ridiculous Diſtinctions that ariſe among the Vulgar, becauſe their Fathers firſt ſpoke a different Language, or drew Air in a different Clime.</p>
            <p>With theſe Views the <hi>Miranians</hi> applied themſelves to project a Plan of Education; every Perſon of Genius, Learning and Experience offering their impartial Thoughts on this Subject, whether they were in a private or public Capacity; as ſenſible that an Undertaking of ſuch laſting Conſequences demanded the united Councils,—the Heads and Hearts of a whole country.</p>
            <p>The Object they kept always in Sight, was the eaſieſt, ſimpleſt and moſt natural Method of forming Youth to the Knowlege and Exerciſe of private and public Virtue; and therefore they did not ſcruple to reject ſome Things commonly taught at Colleges; to add others; and ſhorten or invert the Order of others, as beſt ſuited their Circumſtances. They often had this Sentence in their Mouth, which I think, in other Words, I have read in
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:007121_0010_102AF94C778EA030"/>TILLOTSON,—That the Knowledge of what tends neither directly nor indirectly to make better Men and better Citizens, is but a Knowlege of Trifles; it is not Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but a ſpecious and ingenious ſort of Idleneſs.—We muſt not then, ſaid they, wilder ourſelves in the Search of Truth, among the Rubbiſh contain'd in the vaſt Tomes of ancient Rabbies, Commentators and School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; nor in the more refin'd Speculations of modern Metaphyſicians concerning Spirit, Matter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor yet in the polemic Writings about Grace, Predeſtination, mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>l Agency, the Trinity, <hi>&amp;c. &amp;c.</hi> which ſo enflame the World at this Day, to the Diſgrace of Chriſtian Meekneſs and Charity. The Years of <hi>Methuſalem</hi> would be far too ſhort to attain any Proficiency in all the Diſputes and Reſearches of this Kind, which have ſo long puzzled the learn'd World, and are ſtill as much undecided as at firſt. Almighty God ſeems to have ſet the Knowledge of many Things beyond our preſent Ken, on purpoſe to confound our Pride, and whiſper to us continually the Degeneracy and Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of our Nature, and when we conſider ſuch Things in this Light, we make the only proper Uſe of them: For, ſuppoſe we could live long enough to become as well vers'd in all theſe Points, as the moſt ſubtle Doctor that ever breath'd, what would it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the main Point, the making better Men and Citizens? Why, juſt nothing at all! We ought then, continued they, rejecting Things ſuperfluous and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical, to mount directly up to fundamental Principles, and endeavour to aſcertain the Relations we ſtand in to <hi>GOD and univerſal Intelligence,</hi> that we may ſuſtain, with Dignity, the Rank aſſign'd us among intellectual Natures, and move in Concert, with the reſt of Creation in accompliſhing the great End of all Things.</p>
            <p>To ſatisfy ourſelves of this,—<hi>Quid ſumus, et quid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam victuri gignimur</hi>—requires no ſuch Depth of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, no ſuch ſubtle Reaſonings and tedious Reſearches, as ſome would perſuade us. For, beſides
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:007121_0011_102AF94F01DDF760"/>his reveal'd Will, God has given Intimations of his Will to us, by appealing to our Senſes in the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Nature, and the Conſtitution and Harmony of the material Univerſe. We have only to reaſon by Analogy, and chaſtiſe our Reaſonings by theſe holy Oracles. Then the leaſt Attention will convince us, that what God chiefly expects of us here, is to love Him, and all his Creatures, for his ſake;—to view thro' the Medium of Benevolence and Charity, thoſe inconſiderable Differences which, in a State of Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, muſt ſubſiſt among free Agents, and which God himſelf, perhaps, views with Pleaſure;—to do always the greateſt Good in our Power, whether to our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or Fellow Creatures, of whatever Country, Sect or Denomination they may be;—to act a juſt and honeſt Part in our ſocial Capacity;—and laſtly, as much as poſſible, to repair the Ruins of our Nature, by impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and enlarging our Faculties, and confirming our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Habits of Virtue, that thus we may in ſome ſort, be qualified to be replac'd in our original high Rank, to which, thro' the Redeemer's Merit, we may yet aſpire to riſe, and be advanc'd from Stage to Stage of Perfection and Bliſs, thro' all the endleſs Periods of our Being.—</p>
            <p>To ſay, or even think, our preſent Span is too ſhort for theſe Purpoſes, is Preſumption, is ſhocking Impiety; it is to arraign the Councils of the moſt HIGH, and charge him with Injuſtice. We have, in reality, not only Time enough to obey the Dictates of our ſerious Affections, by learning and diſcharging the Duties we owe to God and Man, but ſufficient left for Recreation, and innocent Amuſement; unleſs we will make Life too ſhort by creating Buſineſs for ourſelves which no Way concerns us, and turning our Attention to Subjects which, after all our Searches and Reſearches, will make us neither wiſer nor better than when we firſt ſet out.</p>
            <p>Hence it appears, continued they, of what laſting Importance it is, to accuſtom Youth early to diſtinguiſh
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:007121_0012_102AF951CE23CBF8"/>the True from the Falſe, by directing their Studies to ſuch Things as come more immediately home to their Buſineſs and Boſoms. Were Men as generally agreed what theſe Things are, as they ſoon would be, cou'd they lay Paſſion and Prejudice wholly aſide, then indeed the Buſineſs of Education wou'd be ſhort, eaſy and pleaſant; and the Government of <hi>Mirania</hi> would have found no Difficulty in fixing on a proper and unexcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable Plan for this Purpoſe. But they ſaw with Concern, that while there were Paſſion, Prejudice, Cuſtom, Malice, Pride, Ignorance and different Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in the Province to ſtruggle with, the beſt Scheme they could concert would not be alike acceptable to all, and would be liable to many Exceptions and Miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions.—No matter: That did not deter them from their Duty. They had the noble Reſolution to follow the unbiaſs'd Dictates of their own Good Senſe, conſcious that, tho' they could not project an inexceptionable, far leſs a perfect, Plan, they ſhould acquit themſelves to GOD, and the uncorrupted Judgment of Poſterity, by rendering it as perfect as they cou'd, and delivering it down in a Condition of being improved as often as Circumſtances might alter, and Experience diſcover De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in it.—But it would be needleſs to trouble you with all the Difficulties and Toils they encountered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they brought the Scheme to the Point of Perfection aim'd at:—I ſhall give an Account of the ſeveral Claſſes, and Method of Study, as they are at preſent: after that I ſhall give an Account of the Building, and conclude with taking Notice of the chief Steps taken by them in carrying the whole into Execution. This is what is moſt material for your Purpoſe. You muſt not, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever expect, I can be very particular in this Account: A full Detail of every Thing worth Notice in ſuch an Inſtitution, would furniſh Matter for a Volume; which would be an uſeful Book, if done by an able Pen.</p>
            <p>With Regard to Learning, the <hi>Miranians</hi> divide the whole Body of People into two grand Claſſes. The
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:007121_0013_102AF95356E22780"/>Firſt conſiſts of thoſe deſigned for the learn'd Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; by which they underſtand <hi>Divinity, Law, Phyſic, Agriculture,</hi> and the chief Offices of the State. The Second Claſs of thoſe deſign'd for Mechanic Profeſſions, and all the remaining People of the Country. Such a Diviſion is abſolutely neceſſary: For, if the ſhorteſt Way of forming Youth to act in their proper Spheres, as good Men and good Citizens ought always to be the Object of Education, theſe two Claſſes ſhould be edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated on a very different Plan. The Knowlege of the learned Languages, as the Means of acquiring other uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Knowlege, is indiſpenſibly neceſſary to the firſt Claſs. To the Second, the Time thus ſpent is entirely thrown away, as they never have any Occaſion to make uſe of thoſe Languages. A more general Tincture of the Sciences, except Arithmetic and Mathematics, will alſo ſerve their Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Any Scheme then, that either propoſes to teach both theſe grand Claſſes after the ſame Manner, or is wholly calculated for one of them, without regarding the other, muſt be very defective. And yet ſo it is, that Colleges are almoſt unverſally calculated for the Firſt Claſs; while a collegiate School for breeding Mechanics, is rarely to be met with. This Claſs of People, by far the moſt numerous, and alſo the Hands and Strength of every Government, are overlook'd, and have No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but this wretched Alternative left them; either to glean what Scraps of <hi>Science</hi> they can at private Schools, (often under no Regulations as to Morals or Method) or to go thro' a Courſe of Learning at Colleges, for which they have neither Time nor Uſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations gave Riſe to what is call'd the <hi>Mechanic's School</hi> in this Seminary. It might, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, as well have been call'd a diſtinct College; for it is no Way connected with what is call'd the College, (by Way of Diſtinction) than by being under the Inſpection of the ſame Truſtees, and the Government of the ſame Head, whom they call <hi>Provoſt</hi> or <hi>Principal.</hi> Moſt of
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:007121_0014_102AF95680FE70B8"/>the Branches of <hi>Science,</hi> taught in the College, are taught in this School; but then they are taught without Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, and in a more compendious Manner, as the Circumſtances and Buſineſs of the Mechanic require. This School is ſo much like the Engliſh School in <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphia,</hi> firſt ſketch'd out by the very ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us and worthy <hi>Mr. Franklin,</hi> that a particular Account of it here is needleſs. The <hi>Miranians</hi> only differ in this, that they teach every Thing neceſſary for the <hi>Mec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anic,</hi> in this School, without ſuffering the Youth of it to have Recourſe to the mathematical, or any other Profeſſor in the College, or learn'd Claſſes; which 'tis thought wou'd be inconvenient, as they muſt be taught at a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Hour, and by a different Method from what theſe Profeſſors teach the ſaid learn'd Claſſes.—They took Care at firſt to put a Maſter, and Uſhers, in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanics School, capable to teach all the Branches of Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence neceſſary for the Mechanic, in all the Perfection requiſite. The Expence
<note n="*" place="bottom">I can think of no ſolid Objection to ſuch an Inſtitution for Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanics. This Claſs of People muſt be educated as well as the other; and, were it neceſſary, it might be prov'd to a Demonſtration, that a leſs Number of Inſtructors, and conſequently a leſs Expence, can educate them in a Collection of Schools, in the Collegiate or Society Way, than when diſpers'd at ſeparate Schools. How much greater the Succeſs muſt be, and how much more conſiſtent with found Policy, in the former Caſe, will be evinc'd in the Courſe of this Narrative.—Should ſuch an Inſtitution for Mechanics, be included in the general one propoſed in this Province, as I hope it will, and ſhould not this Sketch, together with that of the Engliſh School of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> be ſatisfactory, I may afterwards give a more particular Idea of it.</note> is the ſame that it would be by the <hi>Pennſylvanian</hi> Method; becauſe the Number of Inſtructors in every School, can always be proportioned to the Number of Scholars.—In this School, nine Years compleat the Mechanic's Education; proportionable to which there are nine Forms or Claſſes. In the Three loweſt, <hi>Engliſh</hi> is taught grammatically, and as a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, with Writing. In the ſix higher Claſſes, <hi>Engliſh</hi> and Writing are continued, at the ſame Time that
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:007121_0015_102AF9580E1F9DA8"/>Accompts, Mathematics, Ethics, Oratory, Chronology, Hiſtory, the moſt plain and uſeful Parts of natural and mechanic Philoſophy, are taught; to which is added, ſomething of Huſbandry and Chymiſtry, which, as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd of late, they eſteem of great Uſe to every Mechanic. Thus, at about fifteen Years of Age, the Mechanic's Education is finiſh'd; and he comes out well qualified to make a good Figure in every Profeſſion wherein Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages are not required. All theſe Claſſes are taught at preſent by one Maſter and two Uſhers, but more muſt ſoon be wanted. The Maſter, whoſe Place is of very great Conſequence, and next in Truſt to the Head of the Seminary, is <hi>Vice-Principal,</hi> and governs the Whole in the Abſence, or during the Indiſpoſition of the <hi>Principal.</hi> The <hi>Miranians</hi> value themſelves highly on the Newneſs and Peculiarity of this School; and often tell Strangers that, as a trading People, it is of as great Importance to them, as the College for breeding Men for the learn'd Profeſſions. Indeed they ſpeak of erecting it ſoon into a ſeparate College, and calling it <hi>Barnard-College,</hi> in Honour of a famous Alderman of <hi>Mirania,</hi> who has left a very conſiderable Sum for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing it as a College. Then the two Colleges will be call'd the <hi>Univerſity of Mirania,</hi> a Name the Seminary is already intitled to. I proceed now to ſpeak of the five learned Claſſes, at preſent call'd the College, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory to which is</p>
            <div type="description_of_school">
               <head>The LATIN SCHOOL.</head>
               <p>This School is divided into five Claſſes, proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the five Years the Youth continue in it; which is long enough, as the Latin Tongue is here taught in the moſt ſamiliar and approved Method, without bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening the Memory too much with Rules. Such of the Youth as diſcover Genius, and are intended for the learn'd Profeſſions, are remov'd from the third Claſs of the Mechanic's School, to be entered into this, provided
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:007121_0016_102AF95AE3B6D668"/>they be nine Years of Age, can write tolerably, and read and articulate the Engliſh Tongue. The firſt four Years are wholly given to the Latin Tongue, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the Boys in Engliſh and Writing at leiſure Hours. The fifth Year, the higheſt Claſs divide the Day between Latin and Greek,; proceeding thro' the Declenſions, Conjugations, St. <hi>Luke</hi>'s Goſpel, <hi>Lucian</hi>'s Dialogues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus at 14 Years of Age, well vers'd in the Latin-Tongue, with ſome Tincture of the Greek, the Youth are enter'd into—</p>
               <div n="1" type="class">
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Greek Claſs,</hi> being the firſt, or loweſt of what is call'd the College.—In this, as in every other Claſs, the Youth remain one Year. In the Forenoon, they read <hi>Theocritus' Idyllia,</hi> with ſome ſelect Pieces of <hi>Heſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiod, Homer,</hi> and <hi>Xenophon:</hi> In the Afternon, they learn Arithmetic, vulgar and decimal; Merchants Accompts, ſome Parts of Algebra, and the firſt ſix Books of <hi>Eucild</hi>'s Elements.—The Maſter of this Claſs is ſtyled <hi>Profeſſor of Greek:</hi> His Place is of very great Importance, for giving the Youth an Opportunity of acquiring the Greek in all its Elegance and Purity, from a Maſter whoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Profeſſion that Language is. Without this Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of Greek, which is not to be acquir'd at Latin-Schools, eſpecially in the Country, (from which the Country Youth muſt, however, be immediately admitted into the learn'd Claſſes or College) it will appear, as we go along, impoſſible for them to bear their Part right in the remaining Studies; nothing being read but the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Authors.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="class">
                  <head>SECOND CLASS.</head>
                  <p>The next Year is ſpent in this Claſs; the Maſter of which is ſtyled <hi>Profeſſor of Mathematics.</hi> He carries the Youth forward in Algebra; teaches the eleventh and twelfth Books of <hi>Euclid,</hi> Geometry, Aſtronomy, Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology, Navigation, and the other moſt uſeful Branches of the Mathematics. So much of Logics and Metaphyſics as is uſeful, is join'd with Mathematics: But a ſmall Space of Time ſerves for theſe Studies; Logics, in particular,
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:007121_0017_102AF95D04CFB850"/>as commonly underſtood, being in great Diſrepute among them. They, therefore, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd their chief Attention this Year, to the more advantageous Study of Mathematics, which, by the Bye, they eſteem the beſt Syſtem of Logics that can be given to Youth. The Evolution of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical Truths, thro' a Chain of Propoſitions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes more, in one Year, ſay they, to expand the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the Mind, and accuſtom it, by a juſt Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to intricate Subjects, to reaſon cloſely, and in Train, than a Life ſpent in the ſophiſtical Diſtinctions and idle Jargon of School-Logic. At proper Seaſons, when the Weather permits, this Claſs is exercis'd in practical Geometry; in ſurveying Lands, Waters; and in plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ornamenting the Maps of ſuch Surveys. There is a weekly Exerciſe for their further Improvement in Greek and Latin.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="class">
                  <head>THIRD CLASS.</head>
                  <p>The Maſter of this Claſs is call'd <hi>Profeſſor of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy.</hi> The Day is divided between the Studies of Ethics and Phyſics: Under the latter, the <hi>Miranians</hi> compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend Natural Hiſtory; Mechanic, or corpuſcular Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and experimental Philoſophy; for the Illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which, they are provided with a complete Appara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. With Regard to Ethics, they ſeem to think that a full, yet compendious, Syſtem, calculated by ſome ſound Philoſopher, for Youth at Colleges, is a Book ſtill wanted. They own, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> excell in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tach'd Pieces on all moral Subjects; but theſe, ſay they, are only the—<hi>disjecta membra Ethices.</hi>—No one Author has handled the Subject of Ethics, in all its Ramifications, with a View to the Information of Youth: And 'tis dangerous as well as difficult, to learn Morals from dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Authors, moſt of whom claſh with one another; or had their peculiar Notions to propagate, and favorite Syſtems to erect.—In this Claſs, at preſent, they read the Philoſoph. Books of <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Cicero,</hi> in their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals, with <hi>Locke, Hutchinſon, &amp;c.</hi> the Profeſſor, taking Care to guard the Youth againſt every Thing in
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:007121_0018_102AF95F43C70E68"/>which theſe Authors ſtand ſingular.—But they have a Method peculiar almoſt to themſelves, of teaching Morals, upon which they lay the greateſt Streſs, and that is by hiſtorical Facts; of which I ſhall ſpeak by and by.—The private Reading of ſuch Books as <hi>Derham, Nettleton,</hi> on Virtue and Happineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for the greater Improvement of the Youth in the Studies of this Claſs; the Profeſſor, from Time to Time, ſatisfying himſelf, by proper Queſtions, what Advantage they reap from ſuch Books: I do not mention <hi>Keil, Graveſand, Newton</hi>'s Princip. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe claſſical Books; and ſuppos'd in the Study of natural Philoſophy.—</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="class">
                  <head>FOURTH CLASS.</head>
                  <p>The Maſter of this Claſs is ſtyled <hi>Profeſſor of Rhetoric and Poetry.</hi> As it is in this and the following Claſs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued <hi>Evander,</hi> that my Countrymen bring all that has been before taught, home to the Buſineſs of Life, and are more ſingular in their Method; I muſt beg to be ſomething more particular in the Account of them. A great Stock of Learning, without knowing how to make it uſeful in the Conduct of Life, is of little Significancy. You may obſerve, that what has chiefly been aim'd at, in the foregoing Claſſes, is to teach Youth to <hi>think well,</hi> that is, cloſely and juſtly. When this is attain'd, it is a noble Baſis; but wou'd, however, be uſeleſs without its Superſtructure, without teaching them to call forth, and avail themſelves of, their Thoughts, in <hi>writing, ſpeaking, acting</hi> and <hi>living well.</hi> To make Youth Maſters of the firſt two, <hi>viz.</hi> writing and ſpeaking well, which are the Buſineſs of this Claſs, nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes ſo much as being capable to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>h what has been well written or ſpoken by others: Hence the proper Studies of this Claſs, are Rhetoric and Poetry, from which ariſe Criticiſm and Compoſition.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall ſpeak firſt of Rhetoric, as it is the firſt Study. The Profeſſor begins with giving the Students a general Notion of the Precepts and different Kinds of <hi>Rhetoric,</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="unknown:007121_0019_102AF9619C147618"/>from <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Quintilian;</hi> then proceeds to make them read <hi>Tully</hi>'s Cration for <hi>Milo,</hi> leiſurely in its Original; applying, as they go along, the Precepts of Oratory; and making them apprehend its Plan, Series, Delicacy of Addreſs; the Strength and Diſpoſition of the Proofs; the Juſtneſs of the Tropes and Figures; the Beauty of the Imagery and Painting; the Harmony and Fullneſs of the Periods; the Pomp and Purity of the Diction; and, in fine, that Grandeur of Thought; that aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sublime; that Torrent of Eloquence, which, mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, warming, ſeizing the Soul, ſweeps all irreſiſtably down before it.—After this, <hi>Demoſthenes</hi>'s Harangue for <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſiphon,</hi> which <hi>Tully</hi> calls the Model of perfect Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, is read in its Original, and explain'd in the ſame Manner.</p>
                  <p>Theſe two celebrated Orations, thus explain'd and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, are judged ſufficient to give Youth a right Idea of Oratory, and fix its Precepts in their Mind, which is not to be done ſo much by reading many Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as by ſtudying a Few thoroughly: And therefore, only three more Orations, one in Greek, one in Latin, and one in Engliſh, are read in the School through the whole Year. Theſe are ſucceſſively handled thus: In the Evening the Profeſſor preſcribes a certain Portion of the Oration, and appoints the Students to write out their Obſervations upon its Conformity to the Laws of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toric; the Plan, Thoughts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by Way of Criticiſm; this they bring with them next Day to the Claſs or School, when the Part preſcrib'd is read over, and this Criticiſm of theirs examin'd and corrected. A new Portion, as before, is preſcrib'd againſt next Meeting, till in this Manner they have finiſh'd the whole three Orations.</p>
                  <p>In the ſame Manner is Poetry ſtudy'd, which is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, rather the ſame than a different Study; Poetry being nothing elſe but the eldeſt Daughter of Eloquence. The Arrangement of the Fable in the One correſponds to the Plan and Series of the Other. Tropes and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures they have in common: And where, in the Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:007121_0020_102AF963599C4A28"/>of her Dreſs, and the more frequent Uſe of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thets, <hi>&amp;c. Poetry</hi> affects to differ, the Youth are not unacquainted with it; as they have been made to obſerve it in reading the Claſſic-Poets. The Rules, Nature and Deſign of the ſeveral Kinds of Poetry, are, in the firſt Place explain'd; then, as in the Study of Rhetoric, they privately write a Piece of Criticiſm upon them, beginning with the leſſer Kinds, as the Ode, Elegy, Satyr, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> proceeding to the Drama, Paſtoral and Epopaea. All theſe Criticiſms are carefully revis'd and corrected by the Profeſſor, which is all the public Buſineſs of the Claſs. The Reading of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Poetry, and the beſt French and Engliſh Critics is allow'd, and even recommended, to aſſiſt and direct the Judgment of Youth in this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe.</p>
                  <p>Here I interrupted <hi>Evander,</hi> by telling him, that I thought this Study alone, might require half the Year. No, replied he; They don't ſpend above eight Weeks on the Study of all the Kinds of Poetry. This is owing chiefly to the placing the Study of Poetry after Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy and Rhetoric, which makes it extreme eaſy: And partly to the Age of the Youth, they being now, at leaſt, in their 18th Year, and capable of greater Application; partly to the Delight they take in the Study, and partly to their having read moſt of the different Kinds of Poems, when learning Languages, which renders the Review of them pleaſant, in order to apply the Rules of Criticiſm.—About a Fortnight is enough for all the leſſer Poems; the ſame Space of Time ſerves for the Drama and Paſtoral, (which all but the Engliſh Critics examine by the Laws of the Drama) and laſtly, about a Month ſerves for the Epopaea.—</p>
                  <p>The Remainder of the Year, which is about ſix Months, is ſpent in compoſing and delivering Orations; and 'tis no Wonder, that this Exerciſe is attended with great Succeſs, when defer'd to this its proper Seaſon. Philoſophy, Rhetoric and Poetry, being ſufficiently taſted and admir'd; the Youth muſt be animated, in
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:007121_0021_102AF966DD7ABCD8"/>their Compoſitions, to imitate thoſe bright Models that gave them ſo much Pleaſure in the Reading. The Study of Poetry, in particular, teaches them a certain Elevation of Thought; makes them give lively Deſcriptions, with Strength, Variety, Copiouſneſs and Harmony of Style; and diffuſe a Delicacy over every Thing they compoſe.—They begin firſt with ſmaller Eſſays on proper Subjects; thence proceed to frame Orations according to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and on the Models, of perfect Eloquence: Theſe the Profeſſor corrects, carefully pointing out where the Subject wou'd have requir'd more Conciſeneſs; where more Copiouſneſs; where the figurative Style, and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Speech; where the Plain and Simple; where they ought to have ris'n; where fallen; where they have given Conceit inſtead of Wit; the forc'd and far-fetch'd, inſtead of the eaſy and natural; Bombaſt and Swelling, inſtead of the Sublime and Florid. Thus to correct one Oration and hear another (that has been corrected before) deliver'd, with proper Grace and Action, is all the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Claſs at one Meeting or Diet. Of this the Youth have their Turns, ſo that when the Claſs conſiſts of twenty Students, each of them, in their Turns, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and deliver an Oration once in
<note n="†" place="bottom">When we allow but ten Days to compoſe an Oration, beſides attending the Duties of the Claſs: we muſt ſuppoſe their Pieces ſhort.</note> ten Days. And as they muſt all be preſent at the correcting and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two Orations each Day, they profit as much by the Faults or Beauties found in the Compoſitions of their School-Fellows, as by their own.—</p>
                  <p>In correcting the Compoſitions of Youth, however, the Profeſſor is ſenſible, that great Judgment and Art is requir'd: Always remembring that they are Youth, he is greatly careful not to diſcourage them by too much Severity. If ever he ſeems diſpleas'd at any Thing, it is when he diſcovers a Sort of Stiffneſs, Preciſion and Judgment in their Pieces above their Years, which he conſiders as a certain Sign of Coldneſs and Sterility;
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:007121_0022_102AF9695592BC50"/>while, on the other Hand, Redundancy of Thought, and ſprightly Sallies of Imagination, ſhare his diſtinguiſh'd Indulgence. Theſe he calls the blooming Shoots of Genius; and, tho' exuberant, thinks they are no more to be lopp'd off at an improper Seaſon, or in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilful Manner, than the luxuriant Growth of a thriving young Tree. It is dangerous for any Hand, but that of Time, to reduce theſe wholly within their proper Bounds.</p>
                  <p>I'm perſuaded, you will think it no Objection againſt the Study of Rhetoric, that it has often been proſtituted to the vileſt Purpoſes. What is there that may not be abus'd by <hi>bad Men?</hi> But in the Poſſeſſion of a <hi>good Man</hi> (and ſuch my Countrymen are careful to form all their Youth) Eloquence is the moſt glorious Gift of Nature. It makes Him the Sanctuary of the Unfortunate; the Protector of the Weak; the Support and Praiſe of the Good; and the eternal Terror and Controul of the Bad. We muſt often addreſs to the Paſſions wou'd we reach the Heart. And till we can lay Body aſide, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve ourſelves into pure Spirit, 'tis proud unmeaning Jargon, to ſay we can reliſh naked unornamented Truth; or be raviſh'd with the plain unaffected Beauties of Virtue.—The <hi>Miranians</hi> don't, however, propoſe to make Orators and Poets of their Youth, by theſe Studies. They are ſenſible both the Orator and Poet muſt be born, not made. But, ſay they, thoſe to whom Nature has given a Genius for Compoſition, either in Poetry or Proſe, will be thus put in the Method of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving that Genius to the greateſt Advantage; and thoſe who have no ſuch Genius, will, however, be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled, by theſe Studies to write elegantly, or at leaſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, in the epiſtolary Way, and on the common and moſt important Concerns in Life.</p>
                  <p>Unleſs the Taſte is thus form'd, and Youth taught to be ſound Critics, on the Beauties of thoſe celebrated Pieces that have challeng'd the Admiration of all Mankind, and ſtood the Teſt of Time; unleſs they can diſcover wherein thoſe Beauties conſiſt;—what is Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning?
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:007121_0023_102AF96AFAA02DC0"/>—Nay, without this
<note place="bottom">
                        <p>¶ In Support of <hi>Evander</hi>'s Sentiments in this Paragraph, ſuffer me to quote the following beautiful Verſes from Dr. <hi>Armſtrong</hi>'s Epiſtle on Benevolence.</p>
                        <l>
                           <hi>" 'Tis chiefly</hi> Taſte, <hi>or blunt, or groſs, or fine,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Makes Life inſipid, beſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>l or divine,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Better be born with Taſte to little Rent,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Than the</hi> dull <hi>Monarch of a Continent.</hi>—</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Without fine Nerves and Boſom juſtly warm'd,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>An Eye, an Ear, a Fancy to be charm'd;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In vain, majectic</hi> Wren <hi>expands the Dome;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Blank as pale</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>UCCO RUBENS <hi>lines the Room;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Loſt are the Raptures of bold</hi> Handel<hi>'s Strain;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Great</hi> Tully <hi>ſtorms, ſweet</hi> Virgil <hi>ſings in vain.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The beauteous Forms of Nature are effac'd;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Tempe'<hi>s ſoft Charms, the raging w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>try Waſt,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Each greatly-wild, each ſweet romantic Scene,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Unheeded riſes and almoſt unſeen.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Yet theſe are Joys with ſome of bett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To ſooth the Tolls of Life's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </note> Taſte, or Reliſh for the Pleaſures of Imagination; what is Life itſelf? Nature has given the Rudiments of it to every Man: But if we compare the Man who has perfectly cultivated it, with him who has not, they ſeem almoſt of a different Species. To the latter are entirely loſt, the <hi>Gay,</hi> the <hi>Tender,</hi> the <hi>Eaſy,</hi> the <hi>Natural,</hi> the <hi>Sublime,</hi> the <hi>Marvellous,</hi> and all the nameleſs <hi>Graces</hi> of a finiſh'd Piece!—Shou'd So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, ſhou'd Want of Buſineſs, ſhou'd Misfortunes of any Kind, force ſuch a Man to ſeek Relief from Books, alas! he finds them— "But formal Dullneſs, tedious Friends!"—He may read; but he will be as unconſcious of the maſterly and delicate Strokes of what he reads, as the Mountain is of the Ore lodg'd in its cavern'd Side. A ſtupid Sort of Admiration is the higheſt Pleaſure he is capable of receiving.—While, on the Contrary, the Man who has been taught to take the full Guſt of the generous Pleaſures ariſing from the Contemplation of <hi>Beauty, Order, Harmony, Deſign, Symmetry</hi> of <hi>Parts,</hi> and <hi>Conformity</hi> to <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> finds, within Himſelf, an unexhauſtable Fund of the moſt noble and rational Amuſement. No Moment of Time.—
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:007121_0024_102AF96D0C0E3A38"/>I ſpeak it feelingly, ſaid <hi>Evander,</hi>—No Moment of Time needs hang heavy on his Hands. No Situation, no Circumſtances,
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 paragraph">
                           <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> neither at home or abroad; neither in Youth nor old Age; neither in Proſperity nor Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; but can be render'd more agreeable, while he can taſte the intellectual Joys of his darling Studies. Suppoſe then Youth ſhou'd reap no other Advantage from the Studies in this Claſs, but the Power of filling up thoſe vacant Hours to Advantage, which thoſe, who want ſuch a Taſte, uſually ſpend in trifling Viſits, Cards, Hunting or Drinking-Matches, and other hurtful Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; we have Reaſon to think a few Months properly ſpent in forming this Taſte, a very eſſential Part of Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and the Maſter that neglects this in Education, may well expect to earn the bittereſt Curſes of thoſe he deprives of ſuch a ſolid Joy, in all Conditions of Life. But further, the <hi>Miranians</hi> ſay, that this Taſte for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite Letters, not only teaches us to write well, and renders Life comfortable to ourſelves, but alſo contributes highly to the Cement of Society, and the Tranquility of the State. They don't heſitate to affirm, that they think it almoſt impoſſible for a Man that has a Taſte for the imitative Arts, and can feel the noble Charms of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toric, Poetry, Painting, Muſic, Sculpture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—to be a boiſterous Subject, an undutiful Son, a rough Huſband, an unnatural Parent, a cruel Maſter, a treacherous Friend, or in any Shape a bad Man. Theſe Studies enlarge the Mind, refine and exalt the Underſtanding, improve the Temper, ſoften the Manners, ſerene the Paſſions, che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Reflection, and lead on that charming Langour of Soul, that philoſophic Melancholy, which, moſt of all, diſpoſes to Love, Friendſhip, and every tender Emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.—To conclude this Article, (which, as it treated my favorite Studies, I have, perhaps, tired you with)
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:007121_0025_102AF96FE148F348"/>it appears to me that the Studies, in this and the next Claſs, are thoſe we muſt chiefly cultivate, wou'd we be good Men and good Citizens.—<hi>Si Patri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>umus, ſi No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is vivere chari.</hi>—And all the Studies in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Claſſes ſeem of little other Value but as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for theſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="class">
                  <head>FIFTH or higheſt CLASS.</head>
                  <p>The Principal, whoſe Name is <hi>Aratus,</hi> inſtructs this Claſs in the Study of Agriculture and Hiſtory. The Knowlege of Nature acquir'd in the third Claſs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes greatly to make the Study of Agriculture eaſy at this Time. In ſome previous Lectures <hi>Aratus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes this Subject; and particularly gives the Youth a good Tincture of Phyſic and animal Anatomy, which is not only of great Uſe to teach them the proper Care of their own Health and Bodies; but highly neceſſary to explain the Oeconomy and Mechaniſm of Plants, the Structure of their Veſſels, their Generation, Manner of Life and Accretion, Perſpiration, Circulation of Sap, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of all which, the ſureſt Way of giving any Idea, is by obſerving and tracing the Analogy between Plants and Animals.—After this he examines, with the Youth, the mineral Strata of the Earth; enquires into the Nature of thoſe ſaline and aqueous Juices that conſtitute the nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Matter or Food of Vegetables; and of thoſe other Foſſils which, being either heterogeneous to the vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Subſtance, or too groſs and ſcabrous to enter into the Roots of Plants, ſerve however to ſoften and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the concreted Parts of the <hi>Earth,</hi> and prepare it for the Ends of <hi>Vegetation.</hi> The Whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> illuſtrated by a Courſe of chymical and ſtatical Experiments.</p>
                  <p>The Theory of Vegetation once explain'd, and toler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably underſtood; what remains in the Study of Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry is not very difficult. For after obtaining a good Inſight into the vegetable Oeconomy, the Quality of Soils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the Analyſis of Plants, Foſſils and Air, the Youth are enabled to judge what Effect every Manure will have on every Soil; what is the proper Manner of
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:007121_0026_102AF9724F96FB68"/>preparing the Ground for the Seed; and what Seed or Plant ſhou'd be aſſign'd each natural Earth. In this chiefly conſiſts the Huſbandman's Art. After this Foundation is laid, they proceed to read the beſt <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponic</hi> Writers, ſuch as <hi>Varro, Columella, Tull, Bradley, &amp;c.</hi> aſſigning, as they go along, the rationale, for the natural Phenomena and Rules of Tillage, recorded in theſe Authors, upon the Principles and Philoſophy of modern Naturaliſts.</p>
                  <p>One Part of the Day is given thro' the Year, to the Study of Agriculture, as laid down above: The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder to the Study of Hiſtory; by which, it is plain I do not mean the Reading of Hiſtory to ſatisfy the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity for a Moment, with the Knowlege of ſingle un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relative Facts; which, to their great Loſs is all that Youth generally profit by Hiſtory, at the Age, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Method, it is handled at Colleges.—In the Courſe of the above-mentioned Studies, and from their private Reading for Amuſement, the <hi>Miranian-Youth,</hi> I need not tell you, muſt by this Time have a pretty full Knowlege of the principal Events that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the World before they were born. The Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Claſs is of a far more noble and extenſive Nature. It is to review thoſe Events in the calm <hi>Light of Philoſophy,</hi> when related in their full Extent, attended with a Deduction of their immediate and remote Cauſes and Conſequences, in order to make them a Leſſon of <hi>Ethics</hi> and <hi>Politics,</hi>— an uſeful Rule of Conduct and Manners thro' Life. It is dangerous to ſend raw un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practis'd Virtue abroad into a World where Right and Wrong are too often confounded; and nothing can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e this Danger but the giving Youth a previous Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the World, and making them behold Virtue and Vice with all their Conſequences painted in genuine Colors by the Hiſtorian. Numerous are the Evils that ariſe in Society when Youth are ſent into it, eſpecially in any high Station without this Knowlege. In this Caſe neither Logics, Mathematics, Phyſics, Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toric,
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:007121_0027_102AF9742A6F4FD0"/>nor all the Branches of ſpeculative Knowlege they are capable of attaining can direct their Conduct, nor prevent their falling a Prey to deſigning Men. Theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ciences, however, if we do not ſtop at them, are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſeful, and render the Studies of this Claſs, pleaſant and profitable. As the Study of Agriculture was made eaſy by the previous Knowlege in natural Philoſophy; ſo is the previous Knowlege of the fundamental Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Ethics, a fine Introduction to the Philoſophical Study of Hiſtory. This Subject <hi>Aratus</hi> reſumes before entring upon Hiſtory. He conſiders Man in the ſolitary State of <hi>Nature,</hi> ſurrounded with Wants and Dangers, the whole Species at Enmity with one another, the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger lording it over the weaker, and nothing ſecure to any Man, but what he can either acquire or maintain by Violence: From thence he takes Occaſion to ſhew the Neceſſity Mankind lay under, of entering into Society, and voluntarily reſigning ſome Share of their natural Freedom and Property to ſecure the Reſt. Then he explains the different Forms of Government with the Advantages, and Inconveniencies in the Adminiſtration of each.</p>
                  <p>This being pren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s'd, the Youth enter upon the Study of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Hiſtory in this Manner, <hi>viz.</hi> the Principal preſcribes a Portion of it, which againſt next Day they muſt read in their Chambers, and abrige the Subſtance of it into Writing, about twice or thrice as large as a copious Argument of any Chapter. This fixes the Facts deeply in their Minds; teaches them moreover to expreſs themſelves in a ſhort laconic Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner when Occaſion requires it; and when the Hiſtory is finiſh'd, ſerves as a Recapitulation of the Whole, to which they may always have Recourſe thro' Life, and bring the Facts freſh into their Memory. Theſe Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maries are revis'd in the Claſs by the Principal, who is careful to make them apprehend the Blameable and Praiſe-worthy in the Conſtitution of the ſeveral <hi>Grecian</hi> States; and, in the familiar Way of Dialogue, to make
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:007121_0028_102AF97727002D38"/>them give their Opinion upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Facts mentioned, the Manners and Cuſtoms of the People, &amp;c. drawing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Morals from the Whole. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>his Manner a Portion is abrig'd, and deſcanted upon, every Day, till they have gone over the Hiſtory of the floriſhing Ages of <hi>Greece;</hi> which they perform in about the Space of a Month. The Hiſtory of <hi>Rome</hi> (Mr. <hi>Hooke's</hi> judicious Collection of it) is ſtudied in the next Place down to the Days of <hi>Auguſtus:</hi> This requires about two Months more,</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">See <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Letters on the Study of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> All between this Period and the Beginning of the 16th Century is paſt over, the Remainder of the Year being ſpent in the Study of modern Hiſtory; from <hi>Puffendorf's</hi> Introduction to which, they firſt take a general View of the principal States and Kingdoms in <hi>Europe,</hi> that now divide that Power among them, upon which depends the whole Syſtem of Police operating at preſent. After that they deſcend to ſtudy the Hiſtory of <hi>England,</hi> from the Beginning of the ſaid 16th Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, after the ſame Manner they before ſtudied the Hiſtory of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Rome;</hi> the Principal taking Care, as they go along, to note the Riſe, Intereſts, Dependen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Conſtitutions of the ſeveral Nations and States, whoſe Hiſtories are interwoven with that of <hi>England;</hi> and where a fuller Account than <hi>Puffendorf</hi>'s is neceſſary of theſe States, in order to underſtand their Reaſons and Motives of Action on any Occaſion, referring the Youth to that Period of their particular Hiſtories. From the Beginning of <hi>Henry</hi> VIIths Reign, to the End of Queen <hi>Ann</hi>'s, is what they ſtudy; and that Part of <hi>Rapin,</hi> with the Continuation to the End of the Third Queen <hi>Ann</hi> takes up about five Months. They conclude the whole with a View of our Colonies in this Hemiſphere; their State, Produce, Intereſts, Government,  taking ſome Notice as they go along, of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Settlements we are chiefly concern'd with in Trade. Every Sunday Night about an Hour is ſpent in the Study of the Bible Hiſtory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="30" facs="unknown:007121_0029_102AF978AF2C7638"/>
Tho' this is but a ſmall Part of the Hiſtory of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, yet it is as much as can conveniently be brought, and much more than generally is brought, into a Scheme of collegiate Education. The Youth are thus ſent into the World well acquainted with the Hiſtory of thoſe Nations they are likely to be moſt concerned with in Life; and alſo with the Hiſtory of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> which may be juſtly call'd the Hiſtory of <hi>Heroiſm, Virtue</hi> and <hi>Patriotiſm.</hi> This is enough to prepare them for Society, and put them in the Method of ſtudying the Hiſtory of any other Nations they think proper, in a philoſophical Manner, whenever their Inclination and Leiſure ſhall prompt them to it.</p>
                  <p>This, continued <hi>Evander,</hi> is a Sketch of the Studies of the ſeveral Claſſes; which I could with Pleaſure, in this Account, purſue thro' all their different Ramificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But as this is inconſiſtent with my deſign'd Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, I have only mention'd the general Heads of Science, wholly neglecting ſuch Branches as are either included in, or neceſſary to, the Knowledge of thoſe I have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd.—In the Second Claſs, you will obſerve I have not ſpoke a Word of plain Trigonometry, becauſe it is ſuppos'd in the Study of Geometry. Neither have I mention'd Perſpective, Painting, &amp;c. becauſe included in the beautiful Sciences of Optics; nor even Optics themſelves, nor ſpherical Trigonometry, as they are all ſuppos'd in the general Study of Aſtronomy. In like Manner, I have not mention'd Dialing, becauſe after being taught Aſtronomy, and the Uſe of the Globes, the whole Theory of Dialing is learn'd in a few Hours: And ſo of all the other Claſſes, which I take Notice of expreſsly, that you may not judge the Studies of any one Claſs unproportion'd to thoſe of another, without taking into the Account all their Branches, Praecognita, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—Here I told <hi>Evander,</hi> that I was well enough ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd the Studies of the Claſſes were very well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion'd, as they become ſtill more extenſive the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Youth advance in Years; but that I thought
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:007121_0030_102AF97BC6708F40"/>the Studies of every Claſs were more than Youth could probably become ſufficiently acquainted with in the Time allotted them.</p>
                  <p>He reply'd, that if the <hi>Miranian</hi> Youth did not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Duties of the College longer than the ordinary Terms, my Obſervation would be juſt. But, continued he, my Countrymen are entirely againſt long Vacancies, and interrupting the Studies of Youth for half the Year. They can't ſee any Advantage in ſuch a Practice; and are certain that it is attended with many Inconveniencies. Vacations and holy Days in this College, don't exceed two Months. Beſides, they don't propoſe any Thing more than to give the Youth a general Knowlege and Tincture of theſe Studies. This is all that can be done at College: For as Bent of Genius will not carry all the Youth of a Claſs the ſame Lengths in every Study; that Scheme of Education is humanly perfect, by which all the Students may become ordinary Proficients in all the Studies; and are put in a Method of excelling in thoſe particular Sciences to which Nature has bent their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius. The
<note n="*" place="bottom">They are and muſt be at leaſt in their 14th Year when entered into theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and in their 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th when they leave them, as may be gather'd from what is ſaid above.</note> Age of the Youth, contributes highly to aid the Execution of ſuch a Scheme; and I can aſſure you, from Experience, that by attending even eight or nine Months in the Year, all that is narrated above may be done by Youth of ordinary Genius; without making it any Burden to them.—You will, no doubt, take No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that the Number of Maſters are fewer than ordinary by this Scheme; and the Oeconomy different from the moſt Part of Colleges; which have a diſtinct Profeſſor for every Branch of Science; as a Profeſſor of <hi>Anatomy, Botany, Chymiſtry, Civil Law,</hi> &amp;c. while the Students attend a great many different Maſters and Studies at different Hours. But, tho' my Countrymen could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Salaries for ſuch a Number of Pofeſſors, they would never give into this Method; for they think it a great
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:007121_0031_102AF97E54C1A4F8"/>Diſadvantage to Youth, to be concern'd with two many Maſters and Studies at the ſame Time. They judge it a much better Method, that ſuch Branches of Science as are related to one another, ſhould be thoro'ly ſtudied under one and the ſame Maſter, before the Youth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed farther; and that the whole Studies or Branches of Science, ſhou'd be rang'd in their natural Order; that thoſe of each lower Claſs may be an Introduction to the Claſs above it, and the Youth thus rais'd by a Chain of eaſy Steps to the Summit of their Education. Hence a Profeſſor ſerves, by the above Scheme, for all the Branches of Knowlege that can be acquir'd in one Year; which reſolves the Claſſes and Maſters into a Number proportion'd to the Number of Years; and renders the whole Plan plain and regular.</p>
                  <p>That the Studies laid down for the five foregoing Claſſes, are rang'd in their natural Order, will beſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to thoſe who are beſt acquainted with the Nature and Object of them. I ſhall not trouble you, then, with any Defence of what may appear an Innovation of the Method of Study in theſe Claſſes; ſince you will allow, when you conſider the whole attentively, that to change this Order ever ſo little wou'd greatly confound and retard the Execution. With Regard to the three lower Claſſes, there can be no Objection; as Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics go before Philoſophy in every Seminary; and are ſo neceſſary to it, that Mr. <hi>Locke,</hi> I think, adviſes the Study of Mathematics ſuppoſe we ſhould propoſe no other Advantage by them than to ſtrengthen the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Faculty, and prepare the Mind for the Study of Philoſophy, by accuſtoming it to think cloſely, and call forth thoſe Thoughts in a ſyſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>matical Manner.</p>
                  <p>That Rhetoric, Poetry, Criticiſm and Compoſition, ſhould be learn'd after Philoſophy, ſeems decided by the Authority of the greateſt Orators and Poets.—Thus<hi>Horace—Scribendi recte, ſapere eſt &amp; Principium &amp; Fons.</hi>—Thus <hi>Tul'y</hi> blames the Orators of his Time for neglecting the Study of Philoſophy and polite Literature,
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:007121_0032_102AF9806B9F30C8"/>—<hi>Nemo vederetur exquiſitius quam Vulgus Hominium ſtuduiſſe Literis, quibus Fons perfec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Eloquentiae conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur; Nemo qui Philoſophiam complexus eſſet, Matrem O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ium bene Factorum, beneque Dictorum. Quintilian</hi> every Way is of the ſame Opinion. And <hi>Pliny</hi> adviſes it in expreſs Terms.—<hi>Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> primum, mox Eloquentiam diſcat, (Puer) quae male ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Moribus diſcitur.</hi> But without any Authorities, the Thing is ſelf-evident. Eloquence is generally the ſublimeſt Philoſophy; now it is abſurd to ſpeak of writing or compoſing philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally till we are Philoſophers; or of writing elegantly without a Taſte for polite Letters. In Reality, no Man but he who can diſtinguiſh philoſophically between Right and Wrong, (the <hi>Honestum &amp; Turpe</hi>) and who is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd of all the moral Virtues, can be a good Orator, for this Reaſon that no Man can move others, unleſs he himſelf is mov'd with what he ſpeaks. A bad Man may, to give his Words Force, ſeem mov'd when he reaſons of Virtue; but whenever his Character <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s fully detected, all his moſt artful Pretences this Way will only, ſo much the more, ſhock his Audience.</p>
                  <p>Here I aſk'd <hi>Evander,</hi> why foreign Univerſities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> plac'd Rhetoric before Philoſophy, if the latter was ſo neceſſary to it? He anſwer'd, that as far as he could learn, the Difference between the Method of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen, and that of the beſt model'd Colleges, was not material. 'Tis true, ſaid he, theſe Colleges begin the Study of Rhetoric in the lower Claſſes, but they continue it thro' the higher Ones. Thus the firſt Year perhaps the Youth learn no more than the Figures of Speech, and the Precepts; the Knowelege of Logic and Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar is enough for this Purpoſe. Compoſition, Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm, and that Part of Rhetoric to which Philoſophy and polite Letters are neceſſary, fall of Courſe after the Study of Philoſophy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is the ſame Thing upon the Whole; unleſs that it is inconſiſtent with this Maxim of my Countrymen, never to engage Youth in more than one or two Studies till they are fully Maſters
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:007121_0033_102AF9834D5AC708"/>of them; and to render their Plan as ſimple as poſſible, that they may ſtand in need of no more Profeſſors and Tutors than their Circumſtances enable them to employ; the ſole Conſideration that ever makes them depart from the Practice of Nations more learn'd than themſelves.</p>
                  <p>I preſume, I need offer no Reaſons for placing the Studies of Agriculture, Hiſtory and Politics in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Claſs. As theſe Studies ſeldom enter into the Scheme of Education, but are left for every Man's private read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after his Education at the Univerſity is finiſhed, it is plain they ſhould be laſt. They are indeed the Studies of Men, and require a ripe Judgment. But moreover all the former Studies, as I have obſerv'd already, are neceſſary and ſubſervient to them. Even Rhetoric her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is of great Uſe in reading a well-wrote Hiſtory, as the Beauties of the Diction and Speeches muſt otherwiſe be in ſome Degree loſt and untaſted. And if this was not the Caſe, yet ſtill, methinks, Hiſtory and Agriculture ſhould be plac'd laſt, in order to ſend Youth abroad into the World, warm (if I may ſo expreſs it) from thoſe Studies which their own Intereſts, and the Service of their Country will require them chiefly to cultivate till Death.</p>
                  <p>The next Thing to be ſpoken of is the public Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of theſe five Claſſes; for the <hi>Miranians</hi> are fully convinc'd of the great Advantages conſequent upon bringing Youth early to ſpeak in Public; and therefore have ſet all the Saturdays of the Year wholly apart for this Purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Upon theſe Days, the Maſters, Scholars, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Citizens as pleaſe to attend, being aſſembled in the Chapel after Morning Prayers; one of the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in the Firſt or <hi>Greek</hi> Claſs appears as Reſpondent with an Opponent or Interrogator from the Third Claſs; the latter pitches upon any <hi>Greek</hi> Author, the Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent has read during the Courſe of the Year in his Claſs, and preſcribes a Paſſage in it to be render'd into Engliſh <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>empore;</hi> this the Reſpondent does, pointing out the
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:007121_0034_102AF98590738088"/>Author's Beauties, Spirit and Sentiments; clearing up his Obſcurities and Difficulties; and giving an Account of the Caſe, Tenſe, Mood, Derivation, Conſtruction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of every Word. The Opponent takes Care to ſet him right where he errs; and gives him an Opportunity, by proper Interrogations, to diſplay his Skill and Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the beſt Advantage. The Maſter of that Claſs to which the Opponent belongs, ſuperintends theſe Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, and may interfere with his Aſſiſtance if there ſhou'd be Occaſion. But this ſeldom happens.—</p>
                  <p>After theſe, one of the 2d Claſs appears as Reſpondent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with an Opponent from the 4th, the Opponent endeavors to impugn a Theſis given out and defended by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent. Then he changes the Subject and interrogates him concerning his Skill in ſuch Branches of the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matics as he (the Reſpondent) has learn'd in his Claſs.</p>
                  <p>In the next Place, a Reſpondent appears from the 3d Claſs with an Opponent from the 5th. The Method of Exerciſe the ſame as above. The Subject Ethics and Phyſics.—</p>
                  <p>Beſides bearing a Part, as Interrogators, in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Exerciſes, the 4th and 5th Claſſes have an Exerciſe of Declamation peculiar to themſelves. Firſt one of the Youth in the Claſs of Rhetoric delivers a Speech with proper Grace and Action on any philoſophical Subject, or on the Nature, Rules and Advantages of Eloquence and Poetry, which are their preſent Studies.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, one of the 5th or higheſt Claſs delivers an Oration, fram'd according to the exact Rules of Rhetoric, upon any civil Topic that is, or may be, diſputed with Regard to the Intereſt of their Country. And ſuch Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangues I have often known to be of very public Service, not only when deliver'd, but when thought worthy of appearing in Print. Sometimes too their Subject is the Uſefulneſs of Hiſtory and Agriculture; the Pleaſures of Retirement, or any moral Subject. Thus when there are not above twenty Boys in each Claſs, every Boy in the three lower Claſſes appears in public twice a Year, and
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:007121_0035_102AF987191B17F0"/>thoſe of the two higher Claſſes four Times.—There are Exerciſes of the ſame Kind in the higher Claſſes of the Mechanic's School: And in the Latin School, inſtead of Exerciſes or public Acts, there are quarterly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations; and proper Rewards diſtributed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite Emulation.</p>
                  <p>Under this Article it may be proper to obſerve that the fourth, or Claſs of Rhetoric, on the King's Birth-Night, entertain the Town with ſome of our beſt dramatic Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances. And at their Commencement, the fifth Claſs do the ſame. On theſe Occaſions, they are honor'd with the Preſence of the Governor and all the Ladies and Gentlemen of Diſtinction. But the three lower Claſſes, as they have not been taught Rhetoric, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ed a Share in this; nor are theſe two higher Claſſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llow'd to exhibit any more, but this one Performance a-piece; as it wou'd interfere with the Duties of the Claſs to prepare themſelves for more: And this is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to teach Them this ſort of Exerciſe.</p>
                  <p>There is one Thing peculiar to the <hi>Miranians</hi> in theſe Exerciſes, which I had almoſt forgot to mention; and that is that all their public Acts, Declamations, <hi>&amp;c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the Engliſh Tongue. No People are more careful than they to teach Youth to tranſlate Latin readily, as may appear in the Courſe of the foremention'd Studies, where every Author is read in the Original: But, when this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ttain'd, they aim at nothing more. They are ſenſible, there is a great Difference between being able to explain a Claſſic Author extempore, and the Writing as good Language as that Author. Almoſt any Perſon may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the firſt:— But only an <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> a <hi>Caſimir,</hi> a <hi>Buchanan,</hi> and a few more, have wrote pure claſſic La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in, unmixt with Barbariſms and foreign Idioms, ſince it became a dead Language. They don't however, deny, but learned Men, to render their Works more univerſally uſeful, may write in the Latin-Tongue, tho' they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>annot write with claſſic Elegance and Purity. But they greatly condemn the Practice of neglecting the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Tongue,
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:007121_0036_102AF98947E11ED0"/>and embaraſſing a young Student, by obliging him to ſpeak or compoſe in a dead Language. While he is hunting after Words to explain Himſelf by, he muſt be continually on the Rack; one Half of his Sentiments, one Half of his ſprightly Sallies of Fancy, which wou'd otherwiſe ſhine thro' his Compoſitions, muſt eſcape his Memory ere he can find Words to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs them. The Conſciouſneſs of ſpeaking improperly, often barbarouſly, muſt damp his Ardor, and reſtrain him from delivering himſelf with that becoming Eaſe and Confidence, that Grace of Voice and Action, that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety and Harmony, which he cou'd not fail of, did he apply that Time and Pains to the Engliſh-Tongue, which is often without Succeſs given to the Latin.—Beſides, my Countrymen ſeem to think it below their Dignity, to declaim in a foreign Tongue, before an Engliſh Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. In particular, my Friend, continued <hi>Evander,</hi> very gaily; to ſpeak in Latin, we think, wou'd be an Inſult on our Ladies, who often honor us with their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence on thoſe Occaſions; and, by their brilliant Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, add new Grace to the Action, new Muſic to the Tongues, new Sprightlineſs to the Imagination, and new Fire to the Boſoms of the Youth.—</p>
                  <p>There are likewiſe Maſters in the College for teaching the French, Italian, Spaniſh and German Tongues, at private Hours; and a Fencing-Maſter, who, beſides the Uſe of the Sword, teaches the military Exerciſe. There is, laſtly, a Dancing-Maſter; whom I ſhou'd have mention'd firſt; as this Art is learn'd by the Boys when very young; <hi>viz.</hi> in the loweſt Claſſes of the Latin and Mechanic's School. None of the Youth, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, are oblig'd by the Statutes of the College to attend theſe Maſters; and if they do attend them, it muſt be before they are enter'd into the fourth or rhetorical Claſs, becauſe it wou'd interfere with the Duties of the two higher Claſſes, which, as you'll remember, conſiſts chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly in Reading and Writing in private. The Students in theſe two Claſſes are eſteem'd Men; and it is reckon'd
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:007121_0037_102AF98C2EE9C400"/>ſhameful for them to be ignorant of Dancing, Fencing and modern Languages till that Time.—None of theſe Maſters are included in the Inſtitution, in any other Thing, but that the Governors or Truſtees upon any Complaint that their Characters are bad and their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample dangerous, may deprive them of the Benefit of teaching the Youth; A Puniſhment great enough: For, tho' they have no Salaries from the Public, yet as each of them has generally thrice the Number of Boys that are in any of the Claſſes, their Income is nothing inferior to the Income of the Maſters that are upon the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And the College alſo gives each of them, that behave well, a handſom Gratuity yearly; as a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their being willing to encourage the Learning of all polite Arts and manly Exerciſes among the Youth.</p>
                  <p>Here <hi>Evander</hi> paus'd, as if in Expectation of ſome Remarks from me upon the Excellency of the Inſtitution he had given me an Account of. I told him that as far as he had yet proceeded I mightily approv'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> But that I thought the Study of Religion, without which no Scheme of Education cou'd be of Advantage to the State or private Perſons, did not ſufficiently enter into his Account; and that if the <hi>Miranians</hi> did nothing more this Way than he had ſpoken of, I judg'd their Scheme deficient in the moſt intereſting Article.</p>
                  <p>He reſum'd, that my Obſervation was juſt; and that it was for this very Reaſon he had left the Account of their Method of ſtudying Religion and Morals to a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate Article; as well, becauſe of their Importance, as becauſe they are the chief Object of the Studies of every Claſs, and conſequently cou'd not be brought into the Account of any particular Claſs.</p>
                  <p>My Countrymen, proceeded he, are fully perſuaded that thoſe who are entruſted with the Education of Youth can do more laſting Service to the <hi>Intereſts</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Virtue,</hi> at a Time when the Heart is ſuſceptible of every Impreſſion, than all the good Men, all the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, all the Magiſtrates, arm'd with all the Power, of
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:007121_0038_102AF98E0CF68AE0"/>a Country, can do, if, for Want of Education, the Heart is ſuffer'd to become callous, as it were, and obſtinate in the Habits of Vice. They were, therefore, extreme careful to look for ſomething ſtill better than Learning in all the Maſters they choſe into the Seminary; admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting none but Men of irreproachable Characters; MEN whoſe Lives ſhou'd be a daily Comment on their Precepts, and their genuine Goodneſs of Heart a conſtant Pledge for the Morals of the Youth committed to their Care; Men indefatigable in the Diſcharge of their Duty from a Conſciouſneſs of the weighty Truſt repos'd in them, and an unfeign'd Zeal for the preſent and future Intereſts of their Pupils; Men, in a Word form'd to command Love and Reverence; and from their Sweetneſs of Temper diſpos'd to ſtrew the Path to Science with Roſes. They prudently foreſaw, that upon their meeting with Men of this Character at firſt, not only depended the Reputation of the College, but in a great Meaſure, the <hi>Morals</hi> and <hi>Genius,</hi> of the Country to lateſt Generations.</p>
                  <p>Such Men they had the Happineſs to meet with: And it will, I hope, prove a pleaſing and uſeful Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, to take a more particular View of the Method of inculcating <hi>good Morals,</hi> or <hi>natural Religion,</hi> practis'd by Them; and which may be practis'd by every Good Maſter in the Courſe of theſe Studies. Some may be ready to imagine they beſtow a great deal of Time and Labor this Way; but, on the Contrary, tho' <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> is always in their Eye, it is but ſeldom in their Mouth. They know too much of human Nature, to propoſe teaching Morals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by formal Diſcourſes and tedious Lectures. At the very Thought of this, Youth take the Alarm and ſeem to put themſelves on their Guard againſt all that can be ſaid: While a Word dropt, as it were, caſually by a ſkillful Maſter in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Seaſon, ſhall ſtrike ſo much the deeper as it was now expected, and make an Impreſſion never to be eras'd. His great Buſineſs then, who wou'd train up Youth to Religion, conſiſts in the firſt Place, in getting the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:007121_0039_102AF990EF9390C0"/>Poſſeſſion of their Hearts; in keeping a jealous Eye over them; in preventing the Approach of every Thing that is of a noxious Quality; in making every Thing around them breathe <hi>Innocence, Purity</hi> and <hi>Truth;</hi> and laſtly, in watching the proper Opportunities of
<note n="†" place="bottom">It ſeems as unreaſonable to expect Leſſons of Morality can bring forth any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, unleſs the Heart is thus artfully prepar'd for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of them, as to expect any natural Seed will take Root and grow if ſown at a Venture without preparing the Ground for it.—</note> drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Seeds of Goodneſs into the Heart, while it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in this healthful State, which will not fail to bring forth
<note place="bottom" type="foot2">(2) <hi>Luke,</hi> viii. Chap.</note> an hundred Fold, provided he adds to the Whole his own Example, and ſeems fully perſuaded of the Truths he wou'd impreſs upon them; never men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning Religion and Virtue without the utmoſt Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Fervor of Soul.</p>
                  <p>Opportunities of this Kind will never be wanting to the Maſter who has himſelf a good Heart. I ſhall take Notice of a few of them; and tho' every claſſic Author furniſhes noble Leſſons of Morality, I ſhall confine my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the five learned Claſſes laſt-mention'd becauſe I wou'd be brief. I ſhall take Care to aſcribe Nothing more to the Scholar than I myſelf have felt; nor can I aſcribe half ſo much to the Maſter, as I have known the good <hi>Aratus</hi> to put in Practice: For under him I had the Happineſs to paſs thro' theſe five Claſſes; as I was one of the Youth with whom he open'd the College which cou'd not be open'd higher than the Greek Claſs, as will be ſhewn in the Sequel.—In this Claſs, under ſuch a Maſter, the Reading of <hi>Home<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> was like travelling thro' a delightful Country; richly variegated with all that is beautiful and grand in Nature; where every Thing conſpir'd— "To raiſe the <hi>Genius</hi> and to mend the <hi>Heart;</hi>"—conſpir'd to entice us forward thro' Meads of Pleaſure, in a flowry Path to <hi>Virtue!</hi>—How ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wou'd the good Man take Occaſion from the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments even of this Heathen-Author, to inculcate the
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:007121_0040_102AF99339869000"/>Belief of <hi>One Supreme GOD, Father and Diſpoſer of all Things;</hi> as alſo the Immortality of the <hi>Soul;</hi> future Rewards and Puniſhments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How zealouſly would he preſs Home upon us Reſpect for Kings, Magiſtrates, Parents and all Superiors? How beautifully wou'd he make us mark the <hi>Decorum</hi> and <hi>Honeſtum</hi> of Life painted in the Characters; and every Thing little and mean expos'd? In what affecting Language and noble Images would he ſhew us Hoſpitality, Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, Benevolence, Juſtice, Honor, Piety, Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, Prudence, Friendſhip, Fidelity, Sincerity, Intre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity, Patience and Reſignation recommended? In a Word there was no Virtue, no Duty of civil Life, but he would enforce from <hi>Homer;</hi> in ſo much that I was almoſt ready to ſubſcribe to the Opinion of thoſe who ſay (however hyperbolically) that was all that ever was written on Morals, nay were all the Arts and Sciences, loſt, the Stamina of the Whole might be gather'd again from <hi>Homer.</hi> And while <hi>Aratus</hi> taught us to gather the Roſes of ſuch an Author, he not only made us ſhun the Thorns; but, as Bees from poiſonous Herbs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract healing Liquids, he taught us even to reap Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages from thoſe very Abſurdities, thoſe monſtrous Fictions about the Nature of the Gods, their Jars, Thefts, Robberies, Rapes, Adulteries, Inceſts, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which were the Faults of the Age not of the Poet. From hence he took Occaſion to teach us the juſt Value of thoſe ſacred Volumes which have reſcu'd us from ſuch Superſtition and Blindneſs.</p>
                  <p>In the next Claſs what freſh Opportunities did he find of leading us from Worder to Wonder, and bringing the DEITY before our Eyes in the Study of His ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous Works? How were our Minds dilated and exalted when, in the Study of Aſtronomy, he led us to conſider the heavenly Bodies? And how little did every Thing we were wont to fancy great then appear to us? Even the terraqueous Globe on which we dwell, with all its Kingdoms and boaſted Grandeur ſeem'd in our Eye but
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:007121_0041_102AF99658719950"/>a ſmall Point in the Solar-Syſtem? The Solar-Syſtem itſelf dwindled into Naught when compar'd with the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Syſtems of thoſe Stars that in a clear Night ſtud the Cerulean! All theſe Syſtems again were loſt in the vaſt Expanſe when compared with that Infinity of Syſtems which Philoſophy's purer Eye can deſcry be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Reach of all Optics! And thus, while he taught us to riſe from Syſtem to Syſtem, beyond all definite Space, 'till we were loſt in the Imagination, and at the ſame Time convinc'd us, that ſo far from being nearer the Limits, we were ſtill but on the Frontiers of of the CREATOR's Kingdom;—how wou'd we ſtand aſtoniſh'd at our own Littleneſs, and the Grandeur of that
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <q>
                           <l>Whoſe Arm Almighty put theſe wheeling Globes</l>
                           <l>In Motion, and wound up the vaſt Machine!</l>
                           <l>Who rounded in his Palm thoſe ſpacious Orbs;</l>
                           <l>Who bowl'd them flaming thro' the vaſt Profound.</l>
                           <l>And ſet the Boſom of old Night on Fire!</l>
                           <bibl>Dr. YOUNG.</bibl>
                        </q>
                     </note> GOD whoſe Hand fram'd all thoſe Cluſters of Syſtems; kindled all their Suns; and feeds their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe <hi>Fires</hi> from Age to Age? How ridiculous and abſurd wou'd we then eſteem it for Man,—the Atom-Lord of this Atom-World,—ſwol'n with Pride, to ſtrut about and boaſt that all theſe were made for him; or to exalt himſelf againſt the great SOVEREIGN of ſuch an incomprehenſible Domain?—What a Thirſt of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege did the Contemplation of theſe Wonders kindle within us? And how did we ſeem to ſpurn this "evaneſcent Speck of Earth", and ardently affect that Period when, ſhaking off this cumbrous Vehicle of Fleſh, we ſhall perhaps ſcar thro' the wide Realms of Nature, ſee Things as they are, and be indulg'd in a free Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with all thoſe Syſtems and all their Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants?—While our Minds were in this State, then, then was the Time the good <hi>Aratus</hi> wou'd ſow, and ſow deep, the Seeds of Piety and Goodneſs. Then was the Time he wou'd preſs Home upon us the Worth and Immortality of our Souls. For, wou'd he ſay, if a God, that does nothing in vain, and that ſhews ſuch
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:007121_0042_102AF99912F731B0"/>Wiſdom and Deſign in all Things that come under our Comprehenſions, has endow'd you with Deſires and Paſſions ſo ſuperior to your preſent Objects, and with a Capacity of ſoaring ſo far beyond them; if he has given ſuch a reſtleſs Curioſity of prying farther and farther into the beautiful Scheme of <hi>Nature;</hi>—be aſſured this Curioſity will not be fruſtrated; you will not drop into Nought before this Scheme is unfolded to you! No: all thoſe noble Paſſions and Deſires will be fully ſatisfied! There are in Reſerve for you ſuperior Diſplays to be eternally open'd upon you, at proper Periods, as your Powers and Capacities are for ever enlarg'd! Mean Time, ſteddily practiſe what <hi>Right-Reaſon</hi> injoins; and wait patiently till your Change come.</p>
                  <p>Nor was it alone, by aſcending in the Scale of Nature that <hi>Aratus</hi> taught us to admire the Almighty Author's Greatneſs. We were forc'd to acknowlege Him ſtill greater, if poſſible, in the ſmalleſt than the greateſt Things; when in the third Claſs we deſcended in the Study of Nature to its other Limit (if Nature can be ſaid to have Limits).—To confine myſelf to that ſingle Branch of Phyſics call'd Micrography, how did it ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize us to diſcover living Creatures, Thouſands of which wou'd be imperceptible to the unaſſiſted Senſe, ſwarming by Legions in each Leaf and Grain; heaving and animating our choiceſt Cates; mantling our pureſt Liquors; and crouding even the tranſparent Atmoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phere. But when we were convinc'd that theſe Animal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules are ſo far from being the laſt Degree of Smallneſs, that there are others as much ſmaller than them, as they are ſmaller than us; then were we as much loſt in the Diviſibility of Matter, as we were formerly in its Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity. As in the one Caſe we cou'd conceive no End of the Magnitude and Addition of heavenly Bodies, ſo in the other, we cou'd conceive no End of Diviſibility and Smallneſs. On each Side of us the Gradation is endleſs. Aſtoniſh'd at ourſelves, we now ſaw Man in a different Light. He that but a little before ſeem'd
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:007121_0043_102AF99A9CC56AE0"/>only an Atom of an Atom-World almoſt imperceptible in the Boſom of the Univerſe, ſeem'd now diſtended into a World, even into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Univerſe, when compar'd but with the laſt Degree of perceptible Smallneſs. He now appear'd in his proper Place as—the <hi>Nexus utriuſque Mundi</hi>—the middle Link of Creation; not only as his Soul ſeems the mean Perfection between the higheſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of created Intelligence, and abſolute Inſenſibility; but as his Body ſeems the mean Bulk between the greateſt Aggregate of Matter, and the laſt Particle of poſſible Smallneſs.—But how was our Aſtoniſhment encreas'd, when we were convinc'd that every the Minuteſt of theſe Animals are form'd with as exact Proportion, Nicety, and Deſign, as Man himſelf;—
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <q>
                           <l>Each within this little Bulk contains</l>
                           <l>An Heart that drives the Torrent thro' its Veins:</l>
                           <l>Muſcles to move its Limbs aright: A Brain,</l>
                           <l>And Nerves diſpos'd for Pleaſure and for Pain:</l>
                           <l>Eyes, to diſtinguiſh; Senſe, whereby to know</l>
                           <l>What's Good or Bad, is, or is not, its Foe.</l>
                           <l>They too are pain'd with Love;—addreſs the <hi>Fair,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>And with their Rivals wage deſtructive War.</l>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Univer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                                    <desc>•••</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </hi>
                           </bibl>
                        </q>
                     </note>
that they have their diſtinct Joints, Limbs and Muſcles, all diſpos'd in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Weight and Meaſure; that they have their proper Veſſels, and Liquids circulating in thoſe Veſſels, cauſed alſo by the Syſtole and Diaſtole of a Heart, or ſomething analogous which expels the Blood or Liquids into thoſe Veſſels, and receives its refluent Stream; that they have not only all the Parts neceſſary to perform the animal Functions, but are ſenſible of Pain and Pleaſure; and know how to ſhun Danger and purſue their proper Happineſs: and laſtly, that tho' theſe are ſo extremely ſmall that Thouſands of them would not be ſo big as a Grain of Sand, yet they contain others within them form'd with the ſame Exactneſs as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves! Speculations of this Kind did not fail to impreſs us with juſt and noble Apprehenſions of the Deity: But oh! when our artful and pious Tutor reminded us, on theſe Occaſions, that GOD perform'd all theſe minute Operations, that he made the ſmall Heart, Arteries
<pb n="45" facs="unknown:007121_0044_102AF99CC4B14F28"/>Valves, and pour'd the vaſtly ſubtile Liquids into the Veſſels, of theſe diminutive Animals,—all with the very ſame Right Hand, with which he rounded thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe Orbs, and hung all thoſe Syſtems of Worlds, (whoſe inconceivable Numbers lately confounded us) at his Footſtool like a little ſparkling Signet of various Gems—Cou'd we, O cou'd we then, do you think, forbear to fall down in the deepeſt Abaſement and Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, crying out.—<hi>How wonderful, how incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, how Great, how Good is the</hi> LORD?</p>
                  <p>Forgive me, my Friend, proceeded <hi>Evander,</hi> if, in this Part of my Narrative, I ſhould be tedious, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover any unbeſeeming Raptures. The Time ſpent in theſe Studies was the happieſt Period of my Life, and which I have often wiſh'd I cou'd begin again: A Period, I can never reflect upon, without feeling my Boſom burn, and thinking I hear the good <hi>Aratus,</hi> with Hands outſtretched, and Eyes glowing Affection and Devotion pouring important Truths from his fervent Tongue, and leading us imperceptibly from the viſible to the inviſible Things of Gods. 'Tis impoſſible to expreſs what a Fund of Piety and natural Religion may be laid in, by a few Words dropt on theſe Occaſions, by a good and fervent Man, whoſe Perſon and Character we love, and whom we ſuſpect of no Deſign upon us but our own Welfare. I ſhould therefore have thought myſelf as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, had I neglected to take ſome Notice of theſe Opportunities of inſtilling Goodneſs, as the Maſter muſt be who, in the Study of Nature, can neglect to make the right Uſe of them. Such a One, indeed, neglects the moſt eſſential Part of Education; inaſmuch as a good Heart is infinitely preferable to all ſpeculative Knowledge:—He neglects to form a Reliſh for that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Contemplation of the Works of GOD, which is not only capable to give Joy and Satisfaction in all Times and Conditions of Life, but will no doubt conſtitute a great Part of our Pleaſure, and be the Subject of our Contemplation and Wonder for ever and ever!—On the other Hand, the Maſter who embraces theſe Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities,
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:007121_0045_102AF99F9D0FD990"/>with Judgment and Diſcretion, will have no Reaſon to join in the vulgar Complaint, that Youth will not learn Religion; and that Philoſophy rather tends to make them Freethinkers. 'Tis true, when a gloomy Temper and ſtarch Behaviour is put for Religion, Youth will ſpurn it; and when they get but a ſmall Tincture of Philoſophy they may be Free-thinkers in the modern Senſe. But, let them once taſte the manly, noble and generous Pleaſures, which true Philoſophy and true Religion impart;—never, never can they forſake them, for the mean Satisfactions of the narrow-ſoul'd Deiſt or Atheiſt, according to a fine Thought of the great <hi>Bacon:</hi> A ſuperficial Taſte of Philoſophy, ſays he, may perchance incline the Mind to Atheiſm; but a full Draught thereof brings it back again to Religion:—The weighty Senſe of which, <hi>Pope</hi> has happily transferr'd into the following beautiful Lines.—
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A little Learning is a dangerous Thing;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Drink deep, or taſte not the</hi> Piërian <hi>Spring:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>There ſhallow Draughts intoxicate the Brain;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And drinking largely ſobers us again.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <bibl>Eſſay on Crit.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have already hinted how much the Studies of the fourth Claſs, Rhetoric and Poetry, tend to better the Heart and improve the Temper. I ſhall therefore paſs to the Study of Agriculture, which <hi>Tully</hi>
                     <note n="‖" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Venio nunc ad Voluptates Agricolarum, quibus ego incredibiliter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap> quae nee ulla impediuntur Senectute, &amp; mihi ad Sapientis vit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m proxime a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>dere videntur.</hi>—De Senectute.—</note> and
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Res Ruſtica, ſine dubitotione, proxima &amp; quaſi Conſanguinea Sapientiae eſt.</hi>—De re ruſt.—</note> 
                     <hi>Colu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mella</hi> call the Study of Wiſdom, and the Life of a wiſe Man:—A Study, which has given that Happineſs to the moſt renown'd Names in Story which the World cou'd not give; and in their declining Age afforded them ſolid Pleaſures after being cloy'd with all that Mankind call Great.</p>
                  <p>It wou'd be needleſs and endleſs to enumerate all the Opportunities a Maſter of <hi>Aratus</hi>'s Character found to
<pb n="47" facs="unknown:007121_0046_102AF9A1D24F2240"/>lead us admire and adore the Deity in this Study. He cou'd not explain the Theory of Vegetation without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting whole Worlds of Wonders. He cou'd not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the Structure of the moſt indifferent Plant with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making us perceive in it the ſame Wiſdom and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign that appear in the Structure of the moſt perfect Animal. He cou'd not explore the mineral Kingdom without ſhewing us the ſame Agreement and Fitneſs in the Diſpoſition of Things, even amid the dark Receſſes and ſecret Bowels of the Earth, as on her beautiful Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face. Her beautiful Surface he cou'd not ſurvey with us, without ſwelling our Hearts with Wonder, Love and Gratitude.—In this Point, <hi>Aratus,</hi> ever zealous to teach us every Thing that can either improve or rationally amuſe, was ſingularly induſtrious.—It is a Diſgrace, he wou'd ſay, for <hi>Man</hi> to live like a Stranger in a <hi>World</hi> made chie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> for Himſelf; neither tracing the Wiſdom, nor adoring the Beneficence, of its Diſpoſition.—It is a Shame for a reaſonable <hi>Being</hi> to wander, as if deaf and blind, in the <hi>Midſt of Nature;</hi> neither attending her <hi>Voice.</hi> nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>iving any higher Emotions than the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcious <hi>Brute</hi> from gazing the awful lovely Spectacles ſhe preſents, with a Deſign to entertain and ennoble our beſt Faculties.—</p>
                  <p>To form the Taſte, therefore, aright in this Reſpect, our worthy <hi>Tutor</hi> (who us'd us in this higheſt Claſs more as Men and his boſom'd Friends, than his Pupils) wou'd, when the Seaſon and Study of Agriculture invited us to the <hi>Fields,</hi> entice us onward to ſome romantic Eminence, as if to ſhew us ſome curious Herb; and there, ſeating Himſelf, wou'd artfully turn our Attention and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation upon the wildly-beautiful Landſkips that every where ruſh upon the Sight in this new World, where Nature yet wantons in <hi>Virgin-Prime,</hi> freſh as it were from the Maker's Hand, and unprofan'd by little Works of Art.—Before us, we wou'd ſurvey mighty Rivers, whoſe diſtant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> among Nations and Regions yet unknown, rolling their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Floods in ſilent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:007121_0047_102AF9A371D46C88"/>towards the Main; bank'd with vaſt Woods and Foreſts, whoſe venerable Trees, planted by GOD himſelf, and almoſt coevel with the World, wave their gracef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l Verdure to every odoriferious Gale. Turning to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> other Side, we wou'd behold vaſt Lawns opening <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminable, between theſe Woods; enamel'd with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Colors, Wealth and Fragrance of Nature; and affording a finely diverſify'd Proſpect,—here gentle Brooks, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andring along their peebly Channels, to pour their tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Urns into theſe larger Rivers; there a wild Profu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of rich Hillocks tufted with various Trees, whoſe uncultivated Beauties, and embowering Shades, inviting Repoſe, ſeem'd form'd to be the gay Abodes of Peace and Love; and here again Groups of tame Animals feeding, in mingled Peace and Happineſs, with their wild Brothers of the Woods, yet unapprehenſive of the barbarous <hi>Huntſman</hi>'s Toils;—the whole rural Proſpect clos'd by vaſt Mountains pil'd into the Clouds, whoſe enormous Height even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake the diſtant Sight, and chill the Frame with delightful Horrors.—And while theſe beautiful Sights wou'd hold our Eyes and Hearts captive; <hi>Aratus,</hi> ever watching the Time to moralize, wou'd remind us how inſeparably <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Utility, Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence</hi> and <hi>Frugality,</hi> are always connected in the Works of GOD. Theſe Inequalities and Varieties on the Surface of the <hi>Earth,</hi> he wou'd ſuggeſt, not only ſerve to form enchanting Proſpects, but alſo to fructify the Soil. Theſe Hillocks and little Vallies form Rivulets, and drain off the ſupervacaneous Moiſture, theſe Rivulets form Rivers; theſe Rivers ſupply the Expence of Evaporations from the Ocean; theſe Evaporations form Magazines of Dews and Rains; and laſtly theſe Magazines of Dews and Rains are condens'd and call'd down upon the Earth by the Help of the high Mountains. Thus the Globe is ever ſupply'd with freſh Recruits of Moiſture, and ſaline Juices. And thus, tho' all T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gs di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ler, all agree to promote the ſame wiſe End<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Order walks Hand in Hand with Variety. The
<pb n="49" facs="unknown:007121_0048_102AF9A51DAC40A0"/>Mountains but ſtand the lofty Miniſters of the Vales. Unleſs they thus rear'd their gelid Creſts into the Skies to arreſt and condenſe the fluctuating Vapors, the hotter Countries wou'd be left deſtitute of Rain; and the whole Moiſture of the Globe, might by Degrees evagate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Poles, and be congeal'd round them. The Mountains alſo produce many curious Vegetables and Minerals of ſovereign Uſe, which are not to be found elſewhere.—But I ſhould never have done, ſhould I take Notice of all the Opportunities the good Man found in the Study of Nature, both to refine and exalt the Underſtanding.—I ſhall next paſs to the Study of Hiſtory, which as he manag'd it, is nothing elſe but Religion and Philoſophy taught by Examples. And indeed he was of the ſame Opinion with the great
<note n="*" place="bottom">Archbiſhop of <hi>Combray.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Fenelon,</hi> that the ſureſt and moſt ſucceſsful Method of teaching Religion is by hiſtorical Facts: a Truth, which from the Feelings of myſelf and School-Fellows in this Claſs, I am ſufficiently convinc'd of. For,</p>
                  <p>When the Mirror of Ages was held up to us, and all the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ebrated Names of Antiquity made to paſs in bright Review before us;—when we beheld the Train of private and public Miſeries, which has always been the Conſequence of Vice, with the glorious Effects of Virtue; —when we ſaw the public Villain branded with eternal Infamy, and deliver'd down as a Malefactor to all Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity, while the Patriot's Name is embalm'd and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd for ever illuſtrious by the concurring Shouts of Mankind;—cou'd we forbear, in our own Imaginations and Reſolutions, to enliſt ourſelves for Life under the Banner of Virtue? Cou'd we forbear to glow with a generous Emulation of earning the fair Eſteem of good Men, and ſharing ſome Part of the Fame of thoſe vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Worthies we read of? Or could we once think of committing a baſe and diſhoneſt Action, without ſhrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from it with Horror, at the Apprehenſions of the eternal Reproaches of the World?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="unknown:007121_0049_102AF9A8ECACD420"/>
The Study of Hiſtory, and the Knowlege of the Greatneſs, illuſtrious Atchievments, and Manners of other Nations, may ſupply the Place of travelling, and make Youth ſhake off that ridiculous Littleneſs of Thought, that contemptible Vanity, of making the Cuſtoms, Manners and Actions of the ſmall Spot where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were born, the Standard of Right and Wrong; —the Model of every Thing great and noble. This begets a more manly and generous Turn of Thought; extends their Views; and teaches them, as Citizens of the World, to do Juſtice to the Virtues of every Nation and People, unbiaſs'd by a weak Attachment to any particular Corner of the Earth. And indeed there is ſome Danger that Hiſtory, with all it's Advantages, ſhou'd have the ſame Effect that travelling too often has; I mean, to cure this Vanity too much, and make them too much in Love with the falſe Magnificence and Greatneſs of other Nations.—Youth are apt to be dazzled when they read of a mighty Thunderbolt of War, returning Victorious over vaſt Nations and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; his native City moving as it were from its Foundations to meet him and uſher him home, thron'd like a God on a triumphal Car; crown'd with Gold; buſkin'd with Pearl; clad in Purple ſtiff with Embroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dery; bearing Laurels in his Hand; famous Kings and Generals, loaden with Chains, led Captive before him; white-rob'd Senators following after him; ſolemn Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſic ſounding his Praiſes; ten thouſand Hands ſtrewing his Way with Flowers; and ten times ten thouſand Tongues ſwelling the loud, <hi>Iö Triumphe</hi> to the Skies! —On theſe Occaſions I have known the ſagacious <hi>Aratus</hi> ſtedfactly examine our Looks and Countenances; and if he had any Reaſon to judge, ſuch pompous Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were likely to pervert the Taſte of ſolid Glory, he would obſerve to us that all this Apparatus of the Triumph was only Externals, only the Trappings of the Conqueror, and no Part of the intrinſic Worth of the Man; nor of any V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lue, but as the Teſtimony of a
<pb n="51" facs="unknown:007121_0050_102AF9AB1FB91800"/>grateful People for ſome great and good Action. He wou'd remind us that there is ſomething ſtill greater than Victories and Triumphs, even in a good Cauſe, to which the chief Applauſe of Ages has been paid: That it is the Heart alone which denominates Men good and great; and that they who, obeying the Dictates of a good Heart, do all the good in their Power, are truly and equally great, whether their Lot be the private Shade, and the Command of a Family; or the public Theatre of the World, and the Command of Armies and Provinces.—</p>
                  <p>To illuſtrate this, he wou'd ask us, whether in our Senſe and the Senſe of all Ages and Men, <hi>Timeleon,</hi> when he declin'd all the Dignities offer'd him by the grateful <hi>Syracuſans,</hi> and retir'd to practiſe in Silence the Virtues of a private Life, only ſaving to himſelf the Pleaſure of ſeeing Millions happy by his Means, did not appear even as venerably great, as when he came at the Head of an Army, reſolv'd either to die or reſcue the ſame <hi>Syracuſans</hi> from Slavery and Oppreſſion? Whether <hi>Curius,</hi> when he refus'd the vaſt Sums offer'd him by the <hi>Samnite</hi> Ambaſſadors, tho' they found him ſo poor as to be cooking his own Supper in the Chimney-Corner, did not ſhew ſtill as much Magnanimity as when in the Front of dreadful War he conquer'd wherever he came? And whether he was not ſtill as great when ſerving up a Share of the ſame Supper to the ſame Ambaſſadors with that terrible Arm from which they ſo often had ſled trembling, as when twice carried in Triumph to the Capitol? Whether <hi>Fabricius</hi> and the ſame <hi>Curius,</hi> when they refus'd (notwithſtanding their private Eſtates were but a few Acres) to accept of any more than
<note n="*" place="bottom">Colume<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> de re <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uſt.</note> ſeven Acres of the Lands they had conquer'd (the Share of a common Soldier) did not acquire more Glory than in adding whole Kingdoms to the Commonwealth? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all Ages have not more applauded <hi>Fabius</hi> for
<pb n="52" facs="unknown:007121_0051_102AF9AD33D0F038"/>ſaving from certain Deſtruction, his Rival and Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary <hi>Minucius,</hi> who by the baſeſt Means had ſupplanted him in the Eſteem of the People, than for defeating the great <hi>Hannibal</hi> and ſaving the Republic? Whether <hi>Cincinnatus</hi> has not receiv'd more Renown for abdicating the Dictatorſhip on the ſixteenth Day, which he might have held ſix Months; and, when he cou'd be of no further public Uſe, ſtealing away from the Praiſes and Acclamations of his fellow Citizens, to manure his little Farm, and cheer his lovely-lonſom <hi>Racilia,</hi> to whom in his Abſence he had committed the Care of it;—whether I ſay, he has not receiv'd more Renown for this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Moderation, than even for deſerving thoſe Praiſes by ſaving the State from the <hi>Aequi?</hi> Whether he did not appear as illuſtrious at the Plough-Tail as on the triumphal Car? Whether he did not appear as great and venerable in the Sight of all Men, (perhaps more ſo in the Sight of God) when ſeated on a humble Turf he decided the Differences of his Neighbour-Peaſants, and reſtor'd Peace to a poor Family; than when ſeated on the high Tribunal of <hi>Rome,</hi> and veſted with uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulable Authority, he gave Law and Peace to half the World?—</p>
                  <p>Theſe renown'd Worthies, wou'd <hi>Aratus</hi> continue, when they conquer'd Nations; when they ſav'd their Country; when they triumph'd over its Enemies,— did what was great indeed; but that which many have done: But when they conquer'd themſelves; when they ſav'd their bittereſt Adverſaries; when they triumph'd over Poverty, and would not ſtoop to gather Gold, Diadems and Kingdoms for their own private Uſe, they did Deeds in which they ſtand ſingular;—
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Deeds far above Ambition's vulgar Flight,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That rais'd their Names to more than Mortal-Height!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Deeds that draw Wonder when but ſimply told;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That ſtill can charm us—as they charm'd of old,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And ſhall to lateſt Times their Luſtre hold.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="53" facs="unknown:007121_0052_102AF9B03A99F7E8"/>By Contraſts of this Kind I have known him labour, to preſerve and improve our Taſte of ſolid Glory; till unable to reſiſt their Impreſſion, we wou'd, like true Philoſophers, pronounce with our own Mouths, that if there are other Actions as great and heroic as Triumphs and Victories even in the Cauſe of Religion and Liberty; ſurely, one ſingle <hi>Deed of Love</hi> where we can, or one ſingle Sigh for <hi>Diſtreſs</hi> where we cannot relieve, as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponding more with the Scheme of Heaven, is ten thouſand Times more great and brave than, thro' the Luſt of Rule, to carry Violence and Conqueſt round the whole Globe. In this Senſe, the greateſt Conqueror is but the greateſt Brute, and the greateſt Coward.— Charm'd by ſuch illuſtrious Models of all human Virtue, who manag'd the Treaſures, and fill'd the moſt eminent Poſts, of their Country, without fouling their Fingers with a Bribe; who conquered the moſt opulent King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, without adding one Drachma to their private Fortune; and, whenever their Country's Service did not require their immediate Preſence, deſcended volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arily from the Command of Mankind to manure a few private Acres, and trace the Wonders of divine Power in the Works of Nature;—charm'd I ſay, at theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, we wou'd in theſe Moments receive a laſting Conviction,—That Nothing can be honorable but Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and the Plaudit of good Men; nothing ſhameful but Vice and Communion with the Bad; nothing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary but our Duty; nothing great and comfortable but the conſcientious Diſcharge of it: And that true Glory does not conſiſt in breathing the fiery Spirit of War, and thirſting eagerly after Dominion; but in delighting to ſee the World happy and unalarm'd; in fervently ſtriving to promote this Happineſs; in culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating the Arts of Peace; encouraging Agriculture and Manufactures; educating Children aright as the riſing Hopes of the State; and ſerving God in Tranquility of Mind and Purity of Heart.—Hiſtory will inform us that none, but thoſe who thus liv'd, have either been happy in their Life, or eſteem'd after their Death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="54" facs="unknown:007121_0053_102AF9B314071728"/>
I ſhall only mention one Advantage more in the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Study of Hiſtory; namely, that to behold the dreadful Effects of Tyranny and religious Impoſture in other Countries; and all the Scenes of great and real Diſtreſs to be met with, eſpecially in more modern Hiſtory; teaches Youth to ſet a juſt Value on our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Conſtitution, and tends more to ſoften the Breaſt, to purge and regulate the Paſſions, than all the <hi>imaginary Diſtreſs</hi> of the beſt conducted <hi>Drama.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How have I felt the Paſſions of <hi>Terror, Pity</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> to riſe alternately in my Breaſt, while <hi>Aratus</hi> has moralized on ſome hiſtorical Paſſages?—When animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting on the Conduct of inhuman Tyrants, he wou'd repreſent them, marking the Godlike Patriot's Body with inglorious Stripes; frowning the holy Sage to Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, Racks or Flames; ſpurning the Good and Brave to the moſt abandon'd Places of the Earth, or by Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands to the Gallies, Bonds and Gibbets;—and for what Crime? What Cauſe?—No Cauſe; no Crime, alledged! A Debauch; troubled Reſt; or ſome Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, had ſour'd the arbitrary Monſters' Tempers! or perhaps ſome contemptible Prieſt, Harlot or Minion was to be gratified thereby!—Again he wou'd repreſent them (when inſtigated by ſuch unrelenting Councillors, or by falſe Glory) brandiſhing the ruthleſs Sword of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion from Country to Country; tearing the tatter'd Weed from wintry Limbs; ſnatching the lean Morſel from the ſtarving Peaſant's Mouth, and (O more pierc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Thought!) from the Mouth of his weeping Spouſe and clamant Babes; rending—(O brutal! O cowardly!) rending the untaſted Virgin from her faithful Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom's longing Arms; razing Cities; ſpoiling Houſes and Fanes; dragging Prieſts from the Altar, with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's and Children, into Slavery; and forcing hoary Age in its laſt Period to become a <hi>Miniſter</hi> to the <hi>Vices</hi> of luxurious Youth:—In ſhort, wherever they come, Deſtruction reveling around them and turning the Earth into a human Shambles; Terror flying wildly-frantic
<pb n="55" facs="unknown:007121_0054_102AF9B4EA7EB150"/>before them; meagre Famine, ſhivering Nakedneſs, pale Deſpair, and every great Diſtreſs, in unfrequented Places, ſtalking horribly-ghaſtful behind them. Thus would the humane <hi>Aratus</hi> deſcribe, in the moſt moving Terms, the Woes attending civil and religious Tyranny, till he obſerv'd his Deſcriptions to have their full Effect upon us;—till he ſaw—
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Each tender Boſom heave the ſocial Sigh;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The ſocial Tear ſtart from each tender Eye.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then would he contraſt to theſe, more joyous Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects.—A Land of Liberty; Life and Property ſecure; hence, a People buſy to improve their unprecarious For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; Cities teeming with Wealth; Commerce extended as far as Winds blow and Waters roll; every Gale and Tide wafting Riches into Port, and bearing forth the Fruits of Induſtry in fair Exchange; Arts and Letters floriſhing; the loweſt Sons of Labor glad; luxuriant Harveſts nodding the heavy Head along the golden Plain; Paſtures green with copious Herbage; flowering Vales lowing Joy; conſenting Hills bleating it; the very
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <q>
                           <l>Oh <hi>Liberty!</hi> thou God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>eſs heavenly bright,—</l>
                           <l>Even Poverty looks che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rful in thy Sight;</l>
                           <l>Thou mak'ſt the gloomy Face of Nature gay,</l>
                           <l>Giv'ſt Beauty to the <hi>Sun,</hi> and Pleaſure to the Day.</l> 
                           <bibl>ADDIS.</bibl>
                        </q>
                     </note>
Sun himſelf ſeeming to dart his choiceſt Beams on the favor'd Land:—and above all, a KING who is the common Father of his People, and as ſuch reigning in their Hearts, watching over the happy Conſtitution of ſuch a Country, even with a Subject's Zeal; and uſing every generous Effort to reſcue the Wretched of other Climes from Slavery, and place them alſo in the Lap of Freedom, to taſte the ſame invaluable Bleſſings!—</p>
                  <p>While the good Man wou'd dwell on theſe pleaſing Themes, his Eyes wou'd ſparkle with Joy; and we, all Ear and Attention, wou'd hang upon his Tongue, loſt in a Train of mingled Paſſions hard to be deſcribed; till a conſcious Preference to the <hi>Britiſh Conſtitution,</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="unknown:007121_0055_102AF9B7066A8078"/>riſing gradually o'er the reſt, and ſwell'd at laſt to Tranſport too big to be reſtrain'd, wou'd force, from the cogenial Souls of Maſter and Scholars, this trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Exclamation—
<q>
                        <l>—<hi>O Nomen dulce</hi> Libertatis!</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O Jus eximium noſtrae</hi> Civitatis!</l>
                        <bibl>CIC.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And oh!—continued <hi>Evander,</hi> elevating his Voice; (as this was the concluding Study of our Education) O! with what an Extaſy of Joy, do you think, we reflected, that in a few Weeks we were going to be enroll'd active Members of that ſame happy <hi>Society</hi> we ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire; that ſame happy Society, in which, had it been left to our Choice, we would have choſen to live and die, above all thoſe we had read of in the Volumes of Hiſtory down to this preſent Day? What a mighty Influence muſt this ſingle Reflexion have on all our future Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct? And what may not be expected from young Men initiated into Society in this Diſpoſition of Mind; thus conſcious of the ineſtimable Privileges they are call'd to; thus prepar'd, thus reſolv'd to act a great and good Part?—Is it not reaſonable to hope, that Nothing will ever be able to deter or allure them from their Duty; but that they will continue firm, inexorably firm as Fate, to maintain and, if need be, to revenge ſuch a glorious Conſtitution, whenever, or howſoever infring'd; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſecret or open Villainy? May it not be expected that their genuine Goodneſs of Heart, impregn'd and fertiliz'd as it were by ſuch an Education, will be a living Spring of great and generous Actions;
<q>not ſpou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing forth a little frothy Water on ſome gaudy Day, and then remaining dry the reſt of the Year,</q>—but gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ever gently along with a pure and even Current, neither mudded with ſiniſter Views, nor o'erflowing its Banks with an ungovern'd and ill-judg'd Zeal even for what is Right? May it not be hop'd that whatever is their Lot they will ſuſtain it with Dignity? If Poverty; with that Magnanimity and Integrity which render'd
<pb n="57" facs="unknown:007121_0056_102AF9B9E135CCF0"/>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Epaminondas</hi> gloried in his Poverty, and in being able to reduce his Deſires and Wants within the Bounds of Nature, and the Smallneſs of his Eſtate; rather than to encreaſe his Eſtate to the Demands of Deſires and Wants, which, when this Boundary of Nature is once paſt, may be multiplied without End. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>pidas</hi> wou'd have ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>'d his plentiful Fortune with <hi>Epaminondas;</hi> but the latter always told him, that as Poverty brought no Diſgrace on him, he wou'd bring none on Poverty by quitting it.</p>
                        <p>There are ſome who, in Pity to themſelves, think all theſe Virtues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oned above, ſo ſuperior to human Weakneſs, that they wou'd either make them paſs for Fictions, or greatly exaggerated by Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians. I, for my Part, think them as certainly atteſted, as any hiſtorical Facts can be; and think moreover that, in the preſent Caſe, it is not worth while to enquire whether they are true or feign'd. If they are Deluſion, they are a plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ing Deluſion; and it is for the Intereſt of Mankind and Virtue to make Youth believe them true, tho' we knew them to be feign'd; that thus, they may be excited to as near an Imitation of them as poſſible.</p>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Epaminondas, Curius, Circi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> &amp;c. ſo venerable in their Sight, and that of all the World:—If Riches; (which is more hard, with that Moderation and Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of Heart, which render'd <hi>Cimon, Pelopidas, Atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> &amp;c. the Delight of all that knew them:—That they will not ſquander them away according to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Cuſtom, in pampering the Luxury of a Scoundrel-Train of Debauchees, who in return (deteſted Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) feed the Lord of the Table with the Oil of Flattery; but that they will bid the helpleſs Heart ſing for Joy, and cheer thoſe gloomy Retreats where, thro' an ingenuous Delicacy and miſtaken Shame, Poverty and modeſt Merit ſhroud themſelves from the faſtidious Scoff of giddy Pride and an undiſcerning World.—In ſhort may it not be hop'd they will entirely devote them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Service of their fellow Creatures, and their Country? And ſhould the prevailing Power of Calumny and Faction hinder them from doing the Good they meditate, or force them from the Scene of public Action, and perhaps into Exile; may it not be hop'd, that, even in theſe difficult Moments, the Love of their Country and Mankind will prevail over every other Conſideration;
<pb n="58" facs="unknown:007121_0057_102AF9BC308B3730"/>and that they will not with a headſtrong Oppoſition ſhock the Conſtitution, nor retire, like <hi>Camillus,</hi> uttering Curſes againſt their native Soil; nor, like <hi>Coriolanus,</hi> meditating great Revenge; but, like <hi>Milo,</hi> praying for the everlaſting Proſperity even of their ungrateful Citizens, in theſe moving and divine Words,—<hi>Valeant, valeant Cives mei; ſint incolumes, ſint florentes, ſint beati; ſtet h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c urbs pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>clara, mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ique Patria cariſſima, quoqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> modo de me merita erit: tranquilla Republica Cives mei, quoniam mihi cum illis non licei, ſine me ipſi, ſed per me tamen, perfruantur. Ego cedam atque abibo.</hi> Thus fore'd from the Service of their Country, then is the Time they will reap the choiceſt Fruits of ſuch an Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Their Minds now vacant from all worldly Cares, and honorably diſmiſs'd from Buſineſs and civil Duties, they can elevate themſelves ſo high, as to look down with calm Contempt on all they fell from. Inſtead of being the Citizens of one Kingdom, they will now ſee themſelves the Citizens of the World, and in the Society of univerſal Nature. Into whatever Clime they rove, there they will find themſelves at home; there they will be honor'd; there eſteem'd. If driven into the moſt abandon'd Parts of the Globe, yet even there they will not be alone; they will find themſelves in the Midſt of <hi>Nature,</hi> and in the Preſence of <hi>Nature's</hi> GOD; with whom ſuch an Education has taught them to hold high Converſe. Every the minuteſt Object around them will be capable of giving Amuſement and Inſtruction. So far from regre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ting the Loſs of Power and earthly Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eur, the whole Earth itſelf will appear, in their philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophic Eye, but a Speck of Dirt, no bigger than the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire appear'd to the younger <hi>Scipio</hi> in his Dream.—Shou'd, however, their relenting Country again demand their Service, ſacrificing all Reſentment to their Duty, they will return with no other Reluctance but that of exchanging the peaceful Amuſements o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eaſe for a Scene of Cares, Watchings and Toils.—In a Word, it may juſtly be expected that thoſe who are
<pb n="59" facs="unknown:007121_0058_102AF9BEA8243AD8"/>thus educated will, in all Circumſtances, and in all their Conduct and Dealings, do Honor to human Nature and wipe off that Reproach from the Chriſtian Religion, which many of its unworthy Profeſſors have brought upon it, in the Eyes of the Infidels around us. When an Education of this Kind has taught all Chriſtians that deal and converſe with theſe Nations of Infidels around us, to practiſe ſtrict Juſtice, Integrity, Honor, and all the other Precepts enjoin'd by our Religion, then theſe Nations will not fail to admire ſuch ſhining Vertues; and when once they admire, they will not be far from imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.—That glorious Aera, and thoſe happy Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, foretold and fondly anticipated, in the Verſes ſpoken at the firſt opening of this Seminary, will not then be far diſtant. But till ſuch an Education has made the idolatrous People around us in Love with our Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Actions; it is in vain to think all the pious Endeavours of ſingle Men, or the Tongue of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, or any Thing leſs than a Miracle can ſpread the Goſpel over theſe Parts among a ſagacious People that daily ſee us belye its Precepts.</p>
                  <p>Thus have I, as briefly as I could, given you a Sketch of the Method of teaching Science and natural Religion in theſe five higher Claſſes. The ſame is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the higher Claſſes in the Mechanics School, where the ſame Opportunities of inculcating natural Goodneſs offer in the Study of Phyſics and Hiſtory, tho' in a Method ſomewhat different. To this I have added a few of the Advantages my Country-Men have in Part reap'd, and muſt more and more reap from ſuch an Inſtitution. There is only one Thing wanting to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and perfect the whole; and that is the Study of <hi>ceveal'd Religion,</hi> by which I mean the general uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted Principles of Chriſtianity, which is all they teach at College. For this Purpoſe the Sunday Evenings are ſet apart; when about an Hour is ſpent, in all the Claſſes, in the Study of the Old and New Teſtament; the Law and hiſtorical Parts being chiefly left for the
<pb n="60" facs="unknown:007121_0059_102AF9C0EAF10EA8"/>higher Claſſes.—This is ſufficient, if any human Care can be ſo, to make Youth good Chriſtians. For when every proper Opportunity is embraced throughout the Week, to lay in ſuch a Fund of natural Religion and Goodneſs, as I have ſhewn above; the great Truths of Chriſtianity cannot fail of a favorable Reception on the Sundays, whether they come from the Maſters in the Evening Claſſes; or from the Pulpit in the Time of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service.—Eaſy and delightful muſt the Taſk of the Clergy be, when by the Conſtitution of a Country the whole Inſtructors of Youth go Hand in Hand with them in advancing the Intereſts of Vertue and Piety!— Happy, ſaid <hi>Evander</hi> (his Face brightening with a lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Exceſs of Fondneſs for his Country) Happy are the People that are in ſuch a Caſe!—Is it poſſible to figure aught more venerable and auguſt than the whole Wiſdom and Experience of a Community thus uſing every human Effort, to train up, and ſecure to the State, a Succeſſion of good Men and good Citizens to the lateſt Generations? Is it poſſible to conceive aught more lovely, than the Youth of a Country thus collected in <hi>one School of Vertue;</hi> and ſtriving, in the Preſence of the Public, with a noble Emulation, and divine He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roiſm, to excel each other in every Thing that does Honor to their Nature?—Can there be a Conſtitution more Praiſe-worthy than that which has contriv'd the Means of fanning and encouraging this
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Cives cum Civibus de Virtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e certantes.</hi>
                     </note> divine Conteſt concerning Vertue among Youth? Is there aught in the whole <hi>Sphere</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> which GOD himſelf ſurveys with greater Pleaſure, than a People thus employ'd? Nay, perhaps it is not too bold to think, that, if all the Ranks of <hi>Being,</hi> between <hi>Man</hi> and the <hi>Seraph</hi> that burns by the Throne of GOD, have ſtood firm in their Duty, and co-operated with HIM from the firſt of Time in accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing his <hi>eternal Scheme,</hi> yet he does not receive ſo much
<note n="†" place="bottom">Matt. xviii. 13.</note> Joy from beholding the Whole, as from ſeeing
<pb n="61" facs="unknown:007121_0060_102AF9C362A90818"/>a Society of fall'n <hi>Adam</hi>'s Race, thus aſſiduous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the Ruins of their Nature; thus ardently wreſtling to render themſelves acceptable in his Sight, that they may be reſtor'd to his Favor, and correſpond for ever with the <hi>general Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mony.</hi>—Can we then doubt but he will ſhower down his choiceſt Bleſſings on ſuch a People; and delight to make them long a diſtinguiſh'd Nation on the Earth? Conſider'd in this Light, well might <hi>Tully</hi> call Education a divine Work! well might <hi>Plato</hi> call it a God-like One!—</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="description_of_building">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> EDIFICE <hi>or</hi> BUILDINGS.</head>
               <p>I come next to give you a rude Sketch of the Edifice; for I am not Architect enough to deſcribe its whole Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donnance in Terms of art. It conſiſts of four Buildings which form an oblong Square, encloſing an Area of 120 Feet by 100 f. I ſhall ſpeak of each ſeparately.—</p>
               <p>Firſt, or <hi>North Building.</hi> The lower or Ground-Floor, the full Length of 120 f. is the <hi>public Chapel,</hi> where all the Scholars in the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inary, aſſemble every Morning to public Prayers. Here alſo all public Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, public Acts and Orations on the Saturdays; Commencements, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are held.—The Floor over this, of the ſame Length, is the <hi>public Hall,</hi> where the Youth eat in public; and where all public Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Balls, Plays, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are given. The Cielings of theſe two Floors being very high, this Building is of the ſame Height with the other Sides of the Square, where the Buildings conſiſt of three Floors or Stories each. This Chapel and public Hall are capable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving ſeveral Hundreds of People, beſides all the Youth of the Seminary. They are each of them well ſeated along the Walls, leaving a large Space in the Middle empty. The Chapel has a very beautiful Roſtrum.—</p>
               <p>Second, or <hi>Eaſt Building.</hi> Length 100 f. The Firſt or lower Floor is the <hi>Latin School,</hi> divided into five Claſſes, 18 f. ſquare each. But the Building being 26 f. wide, 8 f. is left towards the Area which conſtitutes a Piazza or Portico, 100 f. long, ſupported by a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb n="62" facs="unknown:007121_0061_102AF9C582A0BAC0"/>Row of Columns whoſe Members are in <hi>Ionic Proportion,</hi> and their Intercolumination of Conſequence 4 Modules or 2 Diam.—This Portico is of great Uſe as an Ambulatory for the Youth to exerciſe themſelves in, when thro' Rain, Snow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Area wou'd not be convenient. There is no Partition but a Curtain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe Claſſes; and each Claſs has a Door for itſelf from the Portico, with a Chimney and two Windows in the oppoſite Wall; but there are no Windows in the Wall towards the Portico, becauſe the Light wou'd not be good. This Method of making a Door for every Claſs, will be found of great Service to let the particular Claſſes go out and come in without diſturbing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when the Curtains are ſhut; and when the Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars become ſo numerous as to require a Maſter for every Claſs. The Curtains are far preferable to
<note n="†" place="bottom">There is only one Thing in which Partitions of Stone and Timber would have been better, and that is in ſtrengthening the Building; but as there is a Wall between the Portico and the Claſſes running the whole Length, a good Architect can render ſuch a Bail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſufficiently ſtrong without Partitions acroſs.</note> Partition Walls, becauſe when one Maſter is to teach two, three, or whatever Number of Claſſes, by removing the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, he brings them all as it were into one School.—</p>
               <p>The ſecond Floor of this Building is likewiſe divided, by Curtains, into the five learned Claſſes, of the ſame Dimenſions, with the five on the Floor below them. They have likewiſe a Door, Chimney and two Windows each. Before theſe Claſſes, and over the Portico is a Gallery, of the ſame Breadth of 8 f. and Length of 100. This Gallery, as their Circumſtances permit, is to be adorn'd with all curious Hiſtory-Painting for the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Taſte. The Pictures of the Benefactors of the College are hung in it, with the Statutes of the Seminary; and the Names of all the Youth that take the Degrees; and thoſe that win the yearly Prizes in the Latin School.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="unknown:007121_0062_102AF9C7A576CE18"/>
The higheſt or third Floor in this Building conſtitutes the public Library which is 60 f. long; and the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental-Room, where the Apparatus is kept and all Experiments perform'd: this takes up the remaining 30 f. of the Length of the Houſe. There is a ſtately Steeple to this Building, in which is a ſmall but handſom Obſervatory.—</p>
               <p>Third or <hi>South-Building.</hi> Length 120 f. The lower Floor conſiſts of the ſix lower Claſſes of Mechanics, which require the
<note n="*" place="bottom">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eet that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am in the Length of each Building, more than is taken up by the Claſſes, are for Stair Caſes. <hi>N. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Claſſes are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>gnt for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat Space of the Building ſet apart for every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> other Word to deſcribe it by, as School is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a Number of Claſſes.</note> full Length. The Dimenſions and Diſpoſition of theſe Claſſes the ſame as above; conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently there is another Portico before them, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates with that before the Latin School. The three higher Claſſes of Mechanics are on the 2d Floor of this Building, the Remainder of this Floor, and all the third Floor being Apartments for the Youth to lodge in.</p>
               <p>The fourth or <hi>Weſt-Building,</hi> is divided in the Centre by the public Entrance to the Area, which is an Arch 10 f. wide; and has a ſtrong Gate which is ſhut every Night. One half of this Building on that Side of the public-Gate next the mechanic Claſſes is laid out in more Apartments to accommodate the Youth. The other half, or lot of it, is ſet apart for the Principal and his Family. But the Entrance is on the Out<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ide of the College-Gate, that none of his Family may have any Communication with the College after the ſaid Gate is ſhut. The Principal has, however, a Door to the Area of the College from his Houſe, but he always keeps the Key of it himſelf.</p>
               <p>There is a very large Garden belonging to the College; fertil of every Thing fit for the Kitchen; and ſtor'd with all rare and curious Vegetables for the Advancement of natural Knowledge and Huſbandry. I ſhall ſay No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Government of the College, which differs
<pb n="64" facs="unknown:007121_0063_102AF9CA37715C00"/>little from any other good Inſtitution; nor cou'd I explain it to you without repeating the Statutes which would be tedious. In every Thing ſtrict Decorum and Oeconomy are obſerv'd. The <hi>Meals</hi> are plain, neat and plentiful. Every Scholar pays his Proportion of the monthly Bill. 'Tis the <hi>Principal</hi>'s Buſineſs to ſee that this Bill be juſt; and that the Victuals be well-dreſt, good and healthful according to the Statutes.— The College has the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege to ſend a Member to the General Aſſembly; and I, continued <hi>Evander,</hi> have the Honor at preſent to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them.</p>
               <p>This is a rude Sketch of the whole Inſtitution as it is at preſent: It remains to take Notice, according to my Promiſe, of the chief Steps taken in the Eſtabliſhment of it.—The foregoing Plans of Education and Building being ſketch'd out and agreed upon, a Charter was obtain'd incorporating a certain Number of Gentlemen by the Name of <hi>Truſtees,</hi> with Powers to carry the ſaid Plans into Execution, as far as they ſhould be enabled by public or private Contributions; and make ſuch Improvements of them as ſhou'd ſeem neceſſary, keeping always up to the original Intent of the Inſtitution. To enable Them to open the Seminary, a Law was made applying the Intereſt of a Sum that had formerly been rais'd, as Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for Inſtructors, in ſuch Proportions as they ſhou'd judge proper. But this Sum being inſufficient to employ any more Inſtructors than would be neceſſary for the firſt Year; about an hundred public-ſpirited Gentlemen ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to pay, for the Space of five Years, ſuch Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of any Sum not exceeding 600 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> per An.</hi> as the encreaſing Number of Inſtructors, ſhou'd render neceſſary; hoping before the Expiration of that Term a ſufficient Sum might be rais'd for Endowment.</p>
               <p>Thus authoris'd, and enabled, the Truſtees apply'd themſelves with all poſſible Diligence, Prudence and Unanimity to the Execution of their weighty Truſt; and in the firſt Place to engage three proper Perſons to open the Mechanic's and Latin School, and the Greek or
<pb n="65" facs="unknown:007121_0064_102AF9CBCADAAFC0"/>loweſt Claſs of what they call the College. This was the moſt difficult Part of their Work. Men duly qualified were not eaſily to be met with; and thoſe who were beſt quality'd were moſt backward to engage; as having an adequate Idea of the Importance and Difficulty of the Work they were invited to. They foreſaw that even the greateſt Prudence, with the moſt indefatigable Labor and Vigilance, cou'd not command Succeſs in the Beginning of ſuch a Work, unleſs they further laid their Account to bear patiently Reproaches, Slanders and the very Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom of their Characters from a Few.—(ſhall I diſgrace my Country by naming Them!)—a few lurking Traitors, who did not bluſh to throw Dirt at every Propoſal for eſtabliſhing ſuch an uſeful Inſtitution in <hi>Mirania;</hi> either becauſe they Themſelves cou'd not model it to their own Minds, or that they might favor the Intereſts of thoſe that were already ſo model'd in other Places. This and every other Obſtacle, however, the laudable Zeal of the Truſtees ſurmounted. They prevail'd upon the three Men, who are now, <hi>Principal, Vice-Principal,</hi> or <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of the <hi>Mechanic</hi>'s School, and <hi>Maſter</hi> of the Latin-School, to open their reſpective Parts of the Seminary in a Houſe of the City ſet aſide for this Uſe, till the Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice ſhou'd be finiſh'd; aſſuring theſe Men, that they, as Truſtees, wou'd not only ſupport them in the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their Office, but that they might depend on being alſo ſupported by the concurring Intereſt and Countenance of every Man of Worth in the Province. Happy was it for the Province, that Men of ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh'd Zeal were pitch'd upon as Truſtees; and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py was it for the Truſtees that Heaven directed them, in the firſt Inſtance, to the Choice of ſuch Maſters! To theſe concurring Circumſtances, under GOD, may be aſcrib'd all that Reputation, the Seminary has acquir'd. The Maſters as elſewhere obſerv'd, are truly affable, indefatigable and patient; which renders their Method of Communication familiar and ſecure. If at any Time the Youth ſhou'd not ſeem to comprehend their Meaning
<pb n="66" facs="unknown:007121_0065_102AF9CF63B0DB28"/>thoroughly, they vary their Method, and expoſe what they wou'd communicate in every poſſible Light, being apt, always, rather to ſuſpect their own Want of Method and Perſpicuity of Addreſs, than any Defect of Genius or Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention in the Youth. <hi>Learning</hi> in them, tho' univerſal, is but a ſecondary Qualification. Their amiable Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, mild Behaviour, Forbearance and Placability, have long ſince ſtruck Envy and Calumny dumb. Supported by the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the better Part of their Citizens, the Slanders of their Enemies had no other Effect upon them, but to quicken their Toils, make them redouble their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, in their Country's Service; and, with the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher of old, live and act ſo, that no Perſon ſhou'd believe any Thing to their Prejudice. On the Model of their Virtues, the other Maſters, admitted from Time to Time into the Seminary, thought it their Honor and Duty to form Themſelves, and ſecure general Eſteem. The <hi>Principal</hi> is a Clergyman of the eſtabliſh'd Religion of the Country, which was deem'd a reaſonable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliment, to the Conſtitution; but, by an expreſs Act of the Corporation, he forfeits his Place by accepting any paſtoral Cure, or following any other Profeſſion. The Government of ſuch a Seminary, and teaching the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Claſs, was deem'd ſufficient Buſineſs for one Man; and Buſineſs too of ſuch a Nature, as to entitle the Man, who diſcharges it conſcientiouſly, to handſome Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from his Country, without uniting inconſiſtent Offices to patch up a Living for Him.— There are, however, ſome of the other Profeſſors that are allow'd to encreaſe their Income, by ſerving as Clergymen, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the City. This was not thought incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent, as they have little other Care of the College up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, but attending their reſpective Claſſes duly at proper Hours; which Hours they muſt keep ſacred; and upon no Pretence whatever break in upon them.—</p>
               <p>The Seminary being thus opened, every private School, in or near the City, was ſuppreſt. For ſuch
<pb n="67" facs="unknown:007121_0066_102AF9D21C0C9290"/>Schools there was now no Uſe, the Province having, as it were, taken the Buſineſs of Education out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate into public Hands, and open'd one general School, calculated for training up all Ranks and Conditions of People, in the ſureſt and leaſt expenſive Method, to be good Men and good Citizens in their proper Spheres. Without this Step, the Claſſes cou'd never have been fill'd; and the whole Intention of the Inſtitutors wou'd have been defeated, had private Perſons been ſuffer'd to teach on a different Plan, and draw off the Youth by their Intereſt with particular Families, Sects and Parties; or, which is oftner the Caſe by a mean Attention to the Foibles and Weakneſs of Parents. In this Caſe, we ſhou'd never have beheld ſuch a divine Sight as all the <hi>Miranian</hi>-Youth aſſembled, as before ſaid, in <hi>One School of Virtue,</hi> fir'd with the noble Emulation of diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves by all that is Good, in the Eye of the Public. We ſhou'd never have ſeen that Mixture of People, of which <hi>Mirania</hi> conſiſts, coaleſc'd in the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Generation. As, therefore, it is the Buſineſs of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to ſee that Youth, who are the Property of the State, ſhou'd be educated according to the Intention of the State, they thought it incumbent on Them to take Care, that Nothing ſhou'd retard the Execution of that Plan for which they had toil'd ſo much, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to be at ſo much Expence. Thoſe, they thought, who cou'd be Enemies to ſuch a generous Undertaking, and wou'd not avail Themſelves of ſuch an Inſtitution, were certainly Enemies to the Well-Being of their Country; and, as ſuch, ought to be depriv'd of every other Means of public Inſtruction. Tho' this Precaution was commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, and ſeem'd abſolutely neceſſary to the Succeſs of the Underaking; yet the Conſequence and Diſpoſition of the People, render'd it needleſs.—In a ſhort Time, there was ſcarce a Perſon ſo blind, as not to ſee how far ſuch a public Inſtitution muſt be ſuperior to any other Education, and to prefer it accordingly. They ſaw, Nothing was propos'd but to train up their Children to
<pb n="68" facs="unknown:007121_0067_102AF9D3ACC84778"/>
                  <hi>Science</hi> and <hi>natural Goodneſs;</hi> and to keep them free of all Prejudices, with Relation to idle Diſputes, Diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Opinions, till a liberal Education and ripe Judgment, ſhou'd make them capable of thinking for themſelves.—Such an Education, ſay they, is what we owe to our Children; to educate them otherwiſe, is an unjuſt Impoſition on their reaſonable Faculties—What cou'd we wiſh more? On Sundays they go with our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to divine Service; and all the Week, we are ſatisfy'd, they are in the Hands of Men of Piety, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, Learning and Honor.—Nothing can be more catholic, nor more advantageous to Society, than ſuch an Inſtitution, as appears from this, that there is ſcarce an Inſtance of a religious Diſpute between thoſe educated in it. Men bleſt with ſuch an Education will, in all Probability, be good Men of any Proteſtant Church; nor will they think the different Modes of pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſing the ſame FAITH, and paying the ſame HOMAGE to the DEITY, of Conſequence enough to occaſion the leaſt Diſpute, or Breach of Charity, between Fellow-Citizens. There is ſcarce a Proteſtant Sect on Earth, that does not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in <hi>Mirania,</hi> and yet, I do not know a ſingle Perſon that, in Conſequence of ſuch a manly Education, has left the Sect or Community in which he was born. What, ſay they, ſuppoſe we communicate with our reſpective Congregations! let us all live quiet moral <hi>Lives,</hi> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably ſympathiſing with one another's Wants and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, then are we all of one Religion in the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental and moſt important Articles.—The only Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in Suppreſſing theſe Schools, wou'd have been againſt thoſe Schoolmaſters that had come to <hi>Mirania</hi> in Hopes of Subſiſtence, and had ſerv'd the Citizens when they cou'd not be ſerv'd otherwiſe. In Conſideration of this, the Truſtees prefer'd every one of them, that were found qualify'd, before any other Perſons even of equal Merit, that offer'd as Profeſſors, Uſhers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Schools of the Seminary.—</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="unknown:007121_0068_102AF9D5E74EED60"/>
I ſhall now ſhew you how the Claſſes were fill'd up, and Inſtance it in the five learned Claſſes; leaving you to apply it to the Claſſes in the Mechanic's School, as it wou'd be tedious to mention the Whole: You will be pleas'd only to remember, that the three Parts of the Seminary were open'd the ſame Day.</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt Year. <hi>Aratus</hi> open'd and taught the Greek or firſt Claſs, conſiſting of as many of the Youth of City and Country as had a good Knowlege of Latin and ſome Tincture of the Greek; there being no Youth fit to be advanced higher.</p>
               <p n="2">2d Year. With this ſame Set of Youth, he open'd the ſecond or mathematical Claſs. A Profeſſor of Greek was choſen in his ſtead to teach the Greek Claſs, which was fill'd up with the higheſt Claſs from the Latin-School; and ſome Youth from the Country.—This Year the Number of Scholars required one Uſher to aſſiſt the Maſter of the Latin-School; and two to aſſiſt the Maſter of the Mechanic's School. Thus four new Maſters were added, and the Gentlemen-Subſcribers aſſeſs'd propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably.</p>
               <p n="3">3d Year. <hi>Aratus</hi> advanc'd with his Scholars to the third Claſs. A Profeſſor of Mathematics was choſen to ſupply his Place in the ſecond Claſs, which was now fill'd up by thoſe that had been in the Greek Claſs the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Year; the higheſt Claſs in the Latin School being advanc'd into the Greek Claſs as before.</p>
               <p n="4">4th Year. He advanc'd with his Scholars into the fourth Claſs. A Profeſſor of Philoſophy was choſen to ſupply his Room in the third Claſs, which was fill'd up by advancing all the inferior Claſſes as before.</p>
               <p n="5">5th Year. <hi>Aratus</hi> open'd the Fifth, or higheſt Claſs. A Profeſſor of Rhetoric and Poetry was choſen for the fourth Claſs, which was fill'd up by the Youth that had made the third Claſs the former Year; all the inferior Claſſes being advanced one Claſs higher as uſual. Thus, the fifth Year, the Seminary was brought to that State in which I have above deſcribed it; all the Claſſes being full.—</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="unknown:007121_0069_102AF9D8DC02EDD0"/>
During theſe five Years, the Truſtees had been car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on the Edifice according to the Plan laid down; which they had been enabled to do by an yearly Lottery. But as they ſaw that a great Sum would be wanting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what might remain of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Lotteries, after the Erection of the Buildings; they empower'd certain Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen to ſollicit and manage a Scheme of a Lottery for them in <hi>London,</hi> in order to raiſe £. 8000 Sterling to be added to their own Funds for compleating the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the College. Theſe Gentlemen having previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly publiſhed the whole Plan of the <hi>Miranian</hi> Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the generous Deſign of it was ſo much approv'd and countenanc'd by the pious and learned of all Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations in that great City, that the Managers no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oner advertis'd the Scheme of a Lottery to enable the <hi>Miranians</hi> to carry their Project into Execution, than all the Tickets were ſold. And tho' it was propos'd to raiſe only eight Thouſand Pounds, yet as a great many of the ſmaller Prizes were generouſly given to the Managers for the Uſe of the College, about £. 12000 Ster. came clear to the <hi>Miranians.</hi> A famous Biſhop alſo gave a large Sum to be laid out in purchaſing a Library; and a Layman, a great Promoter of natural Knowlege, complimented them, at his Death, with his whole mathematical and philoſophical Apparatus. Thus at the Concluſion of the 5th Year, my Countrymen, by a Concurrence of happy Circumſtances, found their Edifice finiſh'd, and themſelves enabled to endow it in a Manner far ſuperior to their warmeſt Hopes.—Then it was that the fifth Claſs, of which I was one, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menc'd
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Maſters of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ts</hi> it the firſt Degree in this College, and all foreign Univer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ties, but <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>dge.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Maſters of Arts,</hi> in the Preſence of a vaſt Concourſe of People from all Parts. On this Occaſion the new Edifice was open'd with prodigious Eclat. The Orations and Ceremony of Commencement were held in the Chapel; after this a magnificent Entertainment was
<pb n="71" facs="unknown:007121_0070_102AF9DB4F61A710"/>ſerv'd up in the public Hall; and in the Evening, we who had commenc'd Maſters of Arts, entertain'd the Company with the Tragedy of <hi>Cato.</hi>—</p>
               <p>The Day following, all the Claſſes in the Seminary were publickly examined: That which was the 4th now becoming the 5th, in Lieu of thoſe who had proceeded Maſter of Arts; and all the lower Claſſes being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd one Claſs higher, to the loweſt in the Latin-School, which being thus left empty, was fill'd up from the Engliſh Claſſes in the Mechanic's School, by ſuch of the Youth as were deſign'd for the learn'd Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It was further appointed that this Cuſtom ſhould be obſerv'd yearly, on the Day after the Commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that for the more Regularity in the Claſſes of the Latin-School, upon which depends the Regularity of the Reſt, it was appointed that no Boys ſhould, for the future, be admitted into it but once each Year, and that always on the ſaid Day. There is no Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency in this Method; becauſe every Perſon, being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd of it, can take his Meaſures accordingly.—</p>
               <p>It was now at laſt, continued <hi>Evander,</hi> that the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranians,</hi> encourag'd by their Succeſs in this great Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, propos'd to render it ſtill more extenſive, by erecting Schools throughout the Province. You may be ready to imagine this ſhou'd have been the firſt Step, in order to ſupply the College with Students. But they conſider'd, that it would be impoſſible to find pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Maſters for theſe Country Schools, unleſs they firſt bred them at their own College; by which Means one uniform Scheme of Education might be carried on in every Part of the Province.—</p>
               <p>In every Townſhip, they erected an Engliſh School; and one Latin School in the moſt convenient Town of each County. As Maſters to the Engliſh Schools, they ſent young Men of Genius that had been educated gratis in the Mechanic's School. To the Latin-Schools, in the ſeveral Counties, they ſent fit Perſons, chiefly educated gratis in the Latin School and learned Claſſes
<pb n="72" facs="unknown:007121_0071_102AF9DD5521A718"/>of the College<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And theſe Maſters now ſend Youth from the Country, to be enter'd into the Greek Claſs, as well accompliſh'd as thoſe that are taught in the Latin School of the College. In the Generality of the Towns where theſe Schools are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> there was formerly a ſmall Sum paid to a Schoolma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er by the Society: This Sum is encreas'd by an Addition of ſomething more, paid by the reſpective Townſhips. In every County there are Gentlemen appointed Viſitors of theſe Schools.</p>
               <p>This is all that need be done in the Province for the Education of Youth at preſent. And it redounds greatly to the Glory of the Projectors, that little more need be done for many Generations. The College and the two Schools, if quite full, are capable of educating thirty Boys in each Claſs, (570 in the whole) and of ſending abroad yearly 30 well tutor'd Mechanics, and the ſame Number of Gentlemen for the learn'd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions and the Offices of the State. How many more are educated at the Country Schools I cannot aſcertain. The whole annual Expence of this Inſtitution, for Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to the Maſters, is but £. 1200 <hi>Miranian</hi> Currency: Cou'd it be poſſible to educate ſuch a Number of Youth with ſo little Expence by any other Method? Before the public Eſtabliſhment of it, the Education of Youth (if it then might be call'd Education) coſt the Province, and perhaps the City, a Sum equal to this: There was at leaſt as much more drawn out of the Province for the Want of ſuch an Inſtitution; and if we take into the Conſideration, that there is more than the Revenue of the College brought into the Province from other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries that prefer it to any other Seminary; and laſtly, that the Capital of this £. 1200 was for the moſt Part rais'd in <hi>England;</hi> it will appear how much we are Gainers by ſuch an Inſtitution even in Money Matters. What we have gain'd, and ſtill hope to gain, in other Reſpects, I have partly taken Notice of in the Courſe of this Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative; and ſhall only add that ſome of our Country-Men, who have return'd, after being abſent for the
<pb n="73" facs="unknown:007121_0072_102AF9E0AF818F60"/>Space of theſe laſt twelve Years can ſcarcely be perſuaded, that we are the ſame People;—our whole <hi>Genius;</hi>—the whole Face of the Country, ſeem ſo much chang'd and improv'd."—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
               <p>This is the Account, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> my Friend gave of the Seminary of <hi>Mirania.</hi> How far it may be ſtill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd, and imitated by us, is entirely ſubmitted to your Wiſdom. It is no romantic Scheme, but ſuch as I am certain may be eaſily put in Execution. Nothing that I can think of can be more ſimple, if the Extenſiveneſs of the Scheme is conſider'd. It is alſo well adapted, I conceive, to our Circumſtances: And as I have already ſaid that <hi>Mirania</hi> was ſuch as this Province is now, when its College was opened twelve Years ago; ſo it is not unreaſonable to add, that by following, and perhaps im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving, their Plan, we may, twelve Years hence, be all that <hi>Mirania</hi> is now repreſented to be. The Mechanic's School is an Inſtitution as neceſſary, in this trading Country, as in <hi>Mirania.</hi> To the Latin School, and the five learned Claſſes, there can be no Objection. Ten Years is the leaſt Time that can be allow'd for finiſhing the Studies laid down above for thoſe intended for the learned Profeſſions. A Claſs for each Year is the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard generally agreed upon, unleſs where the Numbers of Scholars render more neceſſary: But this is the greateſt Interval that can conveniently be between the Claſſes; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the Number of Claſſes, in the foregoing Scheme, cannot be reduc'd. But as theſe Claſſes may perhaps be
<note n="*" place="bottom">It is not probable however, that the Claſſes will be thin at firſt: For, even in the ſmall Part of the Province, I have had an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of knowing, there are above a Dozen young Gentlemen fit at preſent to be entered into the Greek Claſs, which is the higheſt that can be open'd in the College at firſt: Now ſuppoſe there were no more for this Claſs, and nearly the ſame Number for the lower Claſſes in the Latin School;—has there ever been a College open'd at firſt in this Part of the World under greater Advantages, or with ſuch a Number of Youth?</note> thin at firſt, we can do what is equivalent
<pb n="74" facs="unknown:007121_0073_102AF9E2E186AFF8"/>to a Diminution of their Number; I mean, to appoint but one Inſtructor for two or three Claſſes: And when the Numbers of Students ſhall render more Inſtructors neceſſary, our Abilities to employ more muſt be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably greater; for to me it ſeems inconſiſtent to ſay a thriving Country cannot always ſubſiſt a Number of Inſtructors proportion'd to the encreaſing Numbers of its Youth.</p>
               <p>In this Province one Maſter and two Aſſiſtants may for many Years be ſufficient for the Mechanic's School: A Maſter and one Aſſiſtant for the Latin-School: And the Head of the Seminary with two Aſſiſtants for the five learned Claſſes. But for the two or three firſt Years even one half of this Number may be enough. Now, as no other School will be wanted in the City, is the Expence of employing this Number of Inſtructors for the whole Youth of the City, and as many as ſhall be ſent from the Country, too much for this Province without any foreign Aſſiſtance? Let thoſe, who think it is, enquire whether the Education of Youth does not, at this very Day, coſt the Province more within and
<note n="*" place="bottom">How much this Province loſes at preſent, by ſending their Youth to be educated in other Places, ſeems but too little attended to. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of thoſe I have mention'd as fit for the Greek Claſs, among whom are the young Gentlemen at preſent under my Care, are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring to leave the Province in a few Weeks, for Want of ſome collegiate Institution. It ſeems ſtill leſs conſidered how much Money might be brought into the Country from the Weſt-Indies, if we had a College model'd in ſome ſuch manly Manner as that propoſed above. I am certainly inform'd by Gentlemen that have an Intereſt in the Weſt-Indies, that we might expect very great Aſſiſtance from theſe Iſlands, wou'd we only ſhew them that we have ſome good Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in View, and have made a Law for carrying it ſpeedily and properly into Execution. There are many Reaſons that induce the People of theſe Countries to give the Preference to this Province; particularly the Healthfulneſs of the Climate, our Situation, Simila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Manners, and ſome others I ſhall not mention; which wou'd alſo induce the Mother Country to patronize and encourage ſuch an Inſtitution among us. Happy for us, did we know as well as ſome of our Neighbours to make a right Improvement of the ſuperior Advantages, with which Nature and Fortune have favor'd us. This I do not mention to create mean Jealouſies between neighbouring Provinces, but to awaken and animate that generous Emulation, by which it will ever be the Intereſt of all of them to be actuated.</note> without itſelf, than it would coſt us by the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="75" facs="unknown:007121_0074_102AF9E4697E5C38"/>propos'd. But if we are really unable to carry ſuch a Scheme into Execution, yet ſtill let us begin it: There is no Danger ſuch a noble Undertaking ſhould fail of Succeſs. Why may we not expect the ſame good Fortune which the <hi>Miranians</hi> had in an Engliſh Lottery? If we ſhou'd be diſappointed in our Expectations from every Quarter; yet ſtill it will be glorious to have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted an extenſive and great Work. As we are about the Eſtabliſhment of a Seminary, we ſhou'd have an extenſive and univerſal Inſtitution, ſuch as is laid down above, always in our Eye. If we cannot do the Whole, in the foremention'd Space of Time, let us begin to do what is moſt neceſſary; and do it in ſuch a Manner, that our Poſterity ſhall have nothing to do but finiſh, in an uniform Manner, the Scheme at firſt projected.</p>
               <p>With Regard to the Edifice; what is call'd, in the foregoing Plan, the Second or <hi>Eaſt Building,</hi> might ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate all the Claſſes of a College in this Province for ſome Time. The Reſt of the Buildings of the Square may be added as Occaſion ſerves—</p>
               <p>A ſingle Province has a vaſt Advantage, in the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of a Scheme of this Nature, above an extenſive Monarchy. In large and populous Countries, Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot be immediately the Care of the Legiſlature; they can only enact good Laws for Education, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve the Execution of them upon fit Perſons, in every particular Seminary: But in a ſingle Province, where all the Youth may be collected into one general Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Legiſlature, or thoſe commiſſion'd by them, may, and ſhould, be the immediate Superintendants of Education; than which nothing can be more worthy their Care. The Practice of ancient States, in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, is truly ſurprizing and worthy our Regard. In their Infancy they did not buſy themſelves ſo much in
<pb n="76" facs="unknown:007121_0075_102AF9E5F87BBB68"/>making Laws for the Puniſhment of Criminals, as for hindering there being any Criminals among them, by ſtopping up the great Inlets of Vice, and training up Youth to be, as it were, conſtitutionally Good. Hence a mighty Republic ſubſiſted many Generations without a Law to puniſh <hi>Parricide;</hi> becauſe, as the firſt Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators wiſely foreſaw, no Perſon would be guilty of ſuch a Crime, while the Laws for educating Youth in the juſt Reverence of Magiſtrates, Parents and all Superiors remain'd in full Force. Hence it was that the Infancy of States generally exhibited all thoſe bright Models of Virtue mention'd above; whoſe happy Effects had taken ſuch deep Root as to ſupport them for ſome Time after all <hi>real Virtue</hi> was expired among them. We ſhould always keep thoſe Ages of Simplicity in our View, and form our Conduct upon the bright Patterns they preſent us with; remembring always, that as this is our Infant-Condition, we muſt follow thoſe Patterns, would we tranſmit to our Poſterity, a healthful and thriving State.</p>
               <p>Hence it appears how neceſſary it is to give <hi>Hiſtory, Agriculture</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> the chief Place in a Plan of Education calculated for an Infant-Country. It is Hiſtory that, by preſenting thoſe bright Patterns to the Eyes of Youth, awakens Emulation, and calls them forth ſteady Patriots to fill the Offices of the State. It is not by forming them mere Scholars the State can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come flouriſhing; but by forming them Patriots, and putting them in the Method of becoming Politicians and good Lawgivers. 'Tis but a few that have either Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or Genius to be benefited by the Labors of a mere learn'd Man; but a whole Country, may be made hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py by the ſucceſsful Toils of the Patriot; and happy not for one, but many Generations. Thoſe that are educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be true Patriots, are like ſo many <hi>Suns</hi> in Society. Poſſeſſing a larger Share of etherial Spirit, they infuſe Life, Spirit and Joy into all around them.</p>
               <p>'Tis ſhameful for any Man to be entirely ignorant of what happen'd in the World before he was born; but
<pb n="77" facs="unknown:007121_0076_102AF9E8E1080248"/>for a Man to be call'd to the Service of his Country, or to worm himſelf into high Offices, and even the Councils of his Prince, not only without knowing the Cauſes aſſigned for the Riſe, Glory and Fall of the chief Nations of the World, but even without knowing the Hiſtory and Conſtitution of his own Country, it is not only ſhameful, but the blackeſt Treachery; and worſe, methinks, than an open Conſpiracy againſt his Prince and Country.</p>
               <p>The Advantages of training up ſkilful Huſbandmen, are ſo manifeſtly great to us, as an Infant-Colony ſettled in the moſt fertil Soil, that it is needleſs to inſiſt on them. Did Gentlemen of Diſtinction underſtand the rational Part of Huſbandry, as they muſt by this Scheme, and ſet the Example to the Countrymen around them; were there ſome proper Laws made for encouraging an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Hands, and better ſettling this Province, it might be made the <hi>Granary</hi> of half the European Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements in <hi>America.</hi>—Who, that conſiders this, but muſt be ſurprized at the general Complaint, that this Country muſt be ruin'd unleſs a new War happens ſoon? Good Heaven! It is thoſe very Riches acquir'd in Time of War that impoveriſh us, and muſt in the Iſſue prove our Ruin if not prevented by proper Meaſures. In Time of War Riches pour in upon us all at once, and ſeem even to deluge our Streets: This turns our Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Improvement of our ſlower, but ſurer, natural Wealth; introduces Luxury; multiplies our Wants; and turns the Balance of Trade againſt us with the Mother-Country, which in a Moment drains us of all our Money, and leaves us dependent on the Chance of War for a freſh Recruit. What a precarious Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is this? Whereas, let us ſet our ourſelves to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove our Manufactures, and chiefly to call forth, from the teeming Womb of a grateful Soil of Earth, that luxuriant Wealth it is capable to produce, then have we in our Power an unprecarious Source of never-failing Plenty. In that Caſe the Balance of Trade can never be againſt us. In the longeſt Peace we cannot be poor;
<pb n="78" facs="unknown:007121_0077_102AF9EC0C1C0190"/>and in War, the Returns of our Bravery, in Defence of the true <hi>Britiſh Cauſe, Religion, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Commerce,</hi> muſt infallibly make us rich! We ſhall then no more, like the Waggoneer in the Fable, be ſeen idly praying <hi>Jupiter</hi> to do that for us, which, by applying our Shoulders to the Wheel, we may do for ourſelves.</p>
               <p>As for the Study of <hi>Religion,</hi> in the above Scheme, it is the Soul of the Whole. It teaches us not only to enjoy aright what Science, Hiſtory and Agriculture enable us to acquire in Life; but conſecrates us for Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and makes this Life, what it ſhould be, an Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to all the future Stages of the Conſummation of our Virtue and Happineſs!—</p>
               <p>All I have to add, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> is to beg your kind Acceptance, and candid Peruſal of this Work; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring always that it comes from a ſingle Perſon, of ſmall Experience, unaſſiſted with proper Books, and at a Diſtance from the Converſation of ſome of you, whoſe Sentiments I ſhould otherwiſe have often taken the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to enquire into, relating to many Parts of it. Conſcious of theſe Diſadvantages, I ſhou'd never have attempted ſuch a tedious and difficult Work, had I not ſeen it abſolutely neceſſary, and been apprehenſive that no other Perſon wou'd beſtow their Leiſure upon it. As to the Faults that may be found in it, I ſhall never be aſham'd of them, becauſe none but a Perſon that has an univerſal Knowledge of all the Branches of Science treated of, which I do not pretend to, cou'd avoid Faults. Whoever looks for a perfect Scheme, looks for what the Author never dream'd of, in a Work that might employ all the learn'd Men of the Province, and ſtill leave Room to find Faults and propoſe Improvements. —You, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> whoſe ſuperior Stations and Abilities have recommended you as the Firſt and more immediate Patrons of this great Work, will not, I hope, think the rudeſt Hints below your Notice; ſince even from theſe you are capable to reap Advantage. My very Errors may be render'd uſeful; ſince thoſe who can beſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="79" facs="unknown:007121_0078_102AF9EDC4D71708"/>will be leaſt liable to fall into, them. I ſhall not be ſorry to ſee the foregoing Scheme ſet wholly aſide, if Perſons of more Abilities can thereby be excited to plan a Better. Would every Perſon offer his Sentiments with the ſame Frankneſs that I have offer'd mine; a good Scheme might certainly be extracted from the Whole. Shou'd this Scheme of <hi>Mirania</hi> deſerve any Notice, no Perſon ſhall be more ready than I to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlege what is deficient in it; and aſſiſt in improving what is commendable, when I am enabled ſo to do by the Obſervations of thoſe who ſincerely wiſh Proſperity to this Undertaking. As for thoſe Writers who delight to give frequent Specimens of their Knack at Wrangling and Chicane; or who are determin'd to think Nothing right in this Affair, but what comes from themſelves, my Time is too precious to follow them thro' the Maze of Perplexity. They may, if they pleaſe, aſcribe every Thing I have done to a ſelfiſh Motive; I ſhall leave it to Time and the Iſſue of the Thing to convince them how much they have injur'd me. It will then be ſufficient Puniſhment for them to reflect on their Uſage of One who never offended them, but by a Zeal for the Happineſs of that Province, which they ought to love more, than one, who is a Stranger in it. There was no other Way I cou'd manifeſt that Zeal but on the Subject of Education, as all the Time I have liv'd in the World has been ſpent in my own Education and that of others. As this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject then happens to be very intereſting to this Province at preſent, I ſhou'd never have forgiven Myſelf, had I neglected the ſole Opportunity I can ever have of being in the leaſt Degree uſeful to it.—Sorry ſhou'd I be, however, if, after all my Partiality in treating this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I ſhou'd fall under the Diſpleaſure of any Sect or Party, who may claim an excluſive Right of modeling this Inſtitution to their Mind. Every Perſon is at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and I think ought, to offer his Sentiments. You, Gentlemen, and the Legiſlature are the only proper Judges of the Whole; and I make no Doubt you will,
<pb n="80" facs="unknown:007121_0079_102AD6EB4D1040E8"/>prefer that Scheme which you think beſt calculated to promote the Peace and Happineſs of the Province with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out regarding the Heats and Diſputes that may ariſe at firſt on this Head; or be ſtarted on purpoſe, to retard the Execution of a Work, far too long delay'd already.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I will not embaraſs You, nor my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, at the End of a Work of this Nature, by deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding farther into Particulars: Neither ſhall I once ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs You to exert yourſelves in this great Undertaking, for the ſame Reaſon that I did not once addreſs You, nor an honorable Branch of the Legiſlature on a former Occaſion. If You conſider my Deſign at that Time, ſuch an Addreſs as forc'd and foreign to it, wou'd have been Cenſure. My Buſineſs, then, was with thoſe who are the <hi>Maſters of the Purſe,</hi> and the chief Projectors of new Laws. This I ſhou'd never have mention'd in this Place, as being ſenſible that no Addreſs of mine can be of Importance enough to give or diminiſh Fame, had it not been made a Handle of, for want of a better, to create Jealouſies and Diſtruſts.—</p>
               <p>An Apology for the Method of conveying the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Propoſals wou'd, I hope, be needleſs to thoſe who conſider the Dryneſs of the Subject. When hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Article of Religion, I deſignedly ſcatter'd a few Flowers, that I might help to remove the vulgar Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; and ſhew that, by proper Conduct, this might be made the moſt agreeable and amuſing Part of Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. What I have ſaid on this Subject ſtands as it flow'd at firſt upon my Thoughts; which has made ſome of the Periods perhaps too long. But this I cou'd not help, unleſs I cou'd have ſpar'd Time to divide ſuch Periods, and add ſomething for Connexion; which wou'd, however, have made the particular Paragraphs much longer. The Verſes prefix'd, are part of an unfiniſh'd <hi>Paſtoral</hi> in Imitation of <hi>Virgil</hi>'s <hi>Silenus,</hi> entitled <hi>Science,</hi> and therefore a-kin to my Subject.—</p>
               <p>To conclude, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I have ſpar'd no Pains, and left none of the few Books, I have on Education,
<pb n="81" facs="unknown:007121_0080_102AF9F3AEB9E618"/>unconſulted: that I might render it uſeful, it being the laſt Service I am capable of offering to promote this great Undertaking. All I can do more, is to pray GOD that the Succeſs may be anſwerable.—Under GOD, it greatly depends on You to make it ſo: And no one can doubt, but you will zealouſly exert yourſelves for this Purpoſe, who reflects, that whatever Degree of Glory this Province ſhall acquire from ſuch an Inſtitution, your immediate Deſcendents will reap the chief Advantage of it, ſince the large Share of Property you will leave them poſſeſs'd of, muſt make them nearly concern'd in the Intereſt of the Province; and point them out for the chief Offices of the Government, which you now deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly fill.—</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>I am, Gentlemen, Your moſt obedient humble Servant,</hi> W. SMITH.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>itage</hi> on <hi>Long-Iſland,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>March</hi> 2, 1753.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>LAST Loſt, after moſt of the foregoing Sheets were printed off, I had the Honor to receive, by the Way of <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi> a Letter from a Gentleman of the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd for his Rank and Fortune, but more ſo, in the learn'd World, as a Patriot Writer. It came in Return to one ſent Him with my former Pamphlet, in <hi>November</hi> laſt; and as it contains ſome new Arguments for fixing the College in our Metropolis, which did not occur to me, and alſo confirms in the ſtrongeſt Manner what I have hinted in the
<note n="*" place="bottom">This Part of the Letter, had it come to Hand ſoon enough, ſhould more properly have been added after the ſaid Note. The Original has been ſhewn to ſome of the Truſtees.</note> Note, Page 74, of this preſent Work, <hi>viz.</hi> that the <hi>Weſt-Indian</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, wou'd certainly give this Province the Preference in the Education of their Children, I ſhall preſume upon the worthy
<pb n="82" facs="unknown:007121_0081_102AF9F5D7965480"/>Author's Forgiveneſs, and tranſcribe a Part of it; being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, that what he has ſaid in two Pages, muſt have more Weight than any Thing I cou'd ſay in twenty, to haſten ſuch an Eſtabliſhment here, as he, and all his Countrymen, ſeem more ardently to deſire, than many of our thoughtleſs Selves. Some, I am well aware, will miſconſtrue what I do into Vanity. Be it ſo; 'tis a Vanity the moſt commendable of all others; and ſuch as the Latin-Philoſopher has taught me not to diſown. <hi>Contemptu Famae, Virtus contemnitur.</hi>—But to return to the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, my learn'd Correſpondent writes thus;</p>
               <q>
                  <p>—Your Thoughts on Education are very juſt, and your Arguments in Favor of eſtabliſhing of a College rather in the City of <hi>New-York</hi> than elſewhere are convincing: But I wiſh you had been more copious on the latter Subject, and much more explicit and preciſe on the former. I wiſh you had fully deſcrib'd the Plan of <hi>Glaſgow-College,</hi> as improv'd by that great Philoſopher, Mr. <hi>Hutchinſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> together with your own, or other People's Improvements upon the proper Diſcipline of a College, which, perhaps, is the moſt material Part of ſuch a Plan; as it is the only ſtrong Barrier againſt the Admiſſion of Vice: For, I conceive, by proper Diſcipline, the Vices of a populous City, might be excluded from a College built in the very Suburbs; from whence the Youth might be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, twice a Week, at ſeaſonable Hours, to viſit Coffee-Houſes, the Exchange, and all the Reſorts of Buſineſs, except Taverns. Thus their Minds might be form'd to what the French call <hi>Police;</hi> as alſo to Comme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce, and to a ſtrict Obſervation of Mechanic Arts, which are the main Springs of Commerce. For want of Skill in thoſe Points of greateſt Importance to our Mother-Country it is, that Trade is ſo little underſtood by our Members of Parliament, and ſo much neglected at this very Time, when all other Nations are trying every Art to extend their Commerce. Is not this Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of our learn'd Men imputable chiefly to the Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Univerſities, ſo remote from every Theatre of Action, and of real and uſeful Life? And to what is the aukward Ruſticity of our Book-Worms to be aſcrib'd, but to an abſolute Receſs from all <hi>practical Politeneſs?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I wiſh alſo you had carry'd your Argument one Step farther, and hinted to the Legiſlature that a
<note n="*" place="bottom">It is thought the ſetting a part ſome <hi>Ferries,</hi> at preſent of little Value, might make a conſiderable Part of ſuch a Fund, always in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in Propertion to the Encreaſe of People, and the encreaſing Demands of the College.</note> Fund ſhou'd be eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd
<pb n="83" facs="unknown:007121_0082_102AF9F780748038"/>out of ſome public Tax, ſufficient not only to raiſe a convenient and elegant Structure, but to be an ample En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowment alſo, to encourage able Profeſſors in all the Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the beſt Maſters in <hi>athletic</hi> Exerciſes, to accept, nay to ſeek for a Station at the College of <hi>New-York;</hi> to which all our young Iſlanders wou'd then certainly go for Education, to the great Advantage of that City.—I am ſure, Sir, if you will but revolve theſe Points in your Thoughts for one Hour, you might offer ſuch a Syſtem, grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch clear Evidence, as would open the Eyes of Party, and Purblindneſs itſelf to a ſpeedy Eſtabliſhment of ſuch a College as you wiſh for; and ſuch as would gratify even the Wiſhes of Patriotiſm. But, I fear, if it reſts upon cold and ſlow Donations, the next, perhaps the tenth, Generation will not ſee the Completion of it. The Subject, I perceive, glows in your Boſom, and has exalted your Fancy to ſeveral ſublime Flights in the Poem at the End of your Treatiſe. I fear, your Apprehenſions of our Mother-Country's falling at laſt into the Way of other Nations, are but too well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. I hope I am too old to be a Spectator of that ſad Event: But when Corruption has taken hold of the main Roots, the beſt-grown <hi>Oak</hi> muſt ſoon—very ſoon—fall, even by the leaſt Breath of the <hi>moſt Chriſtian Tyrant!</hi> Where then can the People of a free State, fallen into Deſtruction, take Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary, but among their own Kindred, in a well-order'd and free Government, ſuch as thoſe of NORTH-AMERICA might be?—I had the Honor, to think as you do on this Subject, many Years ago; and have, therefore, advis'd all my Friends to ſecure a
<note n="*" place="bottom">What the Author here means is the Danger he, and all his Friends of the <hi>Carribbee-Iſlands,</hi> are expos'd to; as the French, in every late War, have form'd Deſigns to get the Poſſeſſion of theſe Iſlands; and as there is but too much Reaſon to fear, the vaſt naval Preparations, they are now making, will perhaps render them too ſucceſsful in their next Attempts.</note> Retreat there, as my Brother has wiſely done; and as I intend to do whenever he will point out an handſom Purchaſe to be made at a reaſonable Price; more eſpecially, if a proper <hi>Seminary</hi> for Learning is ſoon eſtabliſh'd among you! For it is owing ſolely to this Want of Education for our Children, that our Gentlemen here are not fond of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing in <hi>North-America.</hi>—But to return from this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, <hi>&amp;c. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Thus far this valuable Perſonage, whoſe Name, was I at Liberty to mention it, wou'd add new Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce to his important
<pb n="84" facs="unknown:007121_0083_102AF9F9110B6358"/>Obſervations: And how great a Satisfaction is it to me, that I am not only prepar'd to anſwer his Letter, by ſending him ſome Copies of ſuch a Plan of a College as he ſeems to deſire, and ſuch as I know muſt be agreeable to the manly Genius of thoſe Iſlanders, when diſpers'd among them; but that I can, moreover, on the beſt Foundation, aſſure them that every Thing good in the ſaid Plan, will, with all poſſible Speed, be carried into Execution in this Province? I have heard it ſaid, that we have no Reaſon to expect the <hi>Weſt-Indians</hi> wou'd ſend their Children here, as they have been long accuſtom'd to ſend them to <hi>England:</hi> But they who ſay ſo, know little what our Engliſh Univerſities are at preſent: For, to uſe the Words of the Authors of the <hi>Revie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> for <hi>November,</hi> 1750,—
<q>That even both our Univerſities (not forgetting that in the Metropo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is of a neighbouring Kingdom) are render'd of little Uſe to the Public, or to the Welfare of Religion, by the idle Doctrines and corrupt Manners which prevail in them, is a Truth equally notorious and melancholy: and any effectual Scheme for a thoro' Reformation, or (if this is impoſſible, thro' the Perverſeneſs of their Members) a <hi>total A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>lition</hi> of them, wou'd merit the Attention of every Lover of his Country, every Well-wiſher to true Chriſtianity, and to civil and religious Liberty.</q>—Beſides this, the Riſque and Expence of ſending Children from the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> to this Place, are not ſo great as to ſend them to <hi>England.</hi> It is not to be queſtion'd then, but theſe young Iſlanders, as my Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent hints, wou'd infallibly come for their Education to theſe Provinces, and that of <hi>New-York</hi> above all others, wou'd we go into ſome ſuch generous and liberal Inſtitution as that propos'd above. And what a noble Proſpect of Wealth and Glory does this open to <hi>Us,</hi> unleſs we will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar the Whole by ſome unprecedented religious Eſtabliſhment, that may be diſagreeable to the Perſuaſion of theſe Iſlanders? I always foreſaw the Diſputes that would ariſe on this Head, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in the foregoing Work ſteer'd quite clear of every Thing that might kindle them among a People that, till a few Months ago, ſeem'd remarkable for that Chriſtian Peace and Charity which reign'd among all religious Sects in the Province. But as theſe Diſputes have now taken their Riſe from another Quarter, I ſhould as freely give my Sentiments on them, as I have on every other Point relating to our intended Seminary, did not the <hi>Printer</hi> wait for this <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> to enable him to perform his Promiſe of publiſhing theſe Papers to-morrow.— Tho' I have every where given it as my Opinion that, in a
<pb n="85" facs="unknown:007121_0084_102AF9FA997522B8"/>well-conſtituted <hi>Seminary,</hi> all Proteſtant Youth ſhou'd be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted on a perfect Parity, and indulg'd in the free Exerciſe of the Religion of their Parents on Sundays <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—tho' I have call'd every Attempt to draw them off from this Religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can judge for themſelves, a manifeſt Impoſition on their <hi>tender Reaſon;</hi> and tho' I believe there is no Perſon among Us ſo bigotted, as to dream of refuſing that general Toleration to our young Students, which our wiſe Laws have granted to all other Perſons; yet certain it is, that to eſtabliſh a College, without eſtabliſhing ſome Form of public Prayer and Worſhip in it, would be a Thing wholly unheard of before; and would effectually defeat the Deſign of ſuch an Inſtitution. In this Eſtabliſhment then, the Preference muſt be given to ſome one of the Modes of Worſhip, or let me call them Churches, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſting at preſent; unleſs we delay the Founding a College for twenty, perhaps a hundred, Years more, till all Sides can agree to patch up ſome new ſort of religious Worſhip for it, out of all thoſe we have at preſent; which, however ſtrange it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, ſeems to be contended for. That ſuch a Preference will be productive of none of thoſe dreadful Conſequences denounc'd againſt it, might eaſily be made manifeſt. And it might as eaſily be made manifeſt, to which of our Churches (ſuppoſing them all equally orthodox, which is all that can be aſk'd) the Compliment of this
<note n="*" place="bottom">Tho' it is my ſincere and impartial Opinion, that we can never eſtabliſh any Religious Worſhip in a College, nor even a College itſelf in this Province, without ſuch a Preference; tho' I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> how much the Succeſs of the Undertaking depends upon ſuch an Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, and am perſuaded that our preſent Clergy, and chief Gentlemen, are of too Catholic a Spirit to dream of obtruding the Religion of any Church upon our Youth; and farther, tho' it might be proved from inconteſtable Experience, that uſing the Prayers of any Church upon public Occaſions, has no Tendency to bring the Students over to the Perſuaſion of that Church, when they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg'd in going to their reſpective Places of Worſhip on Sundays:— Yet as we are not ſure of a Succeſſion of ſuch Men, and as Things ſhould be made as eaſy as poſſible to all Parties; good Policy will direct the Legiſlature to temper this Preference with ſuch Limitations, as may for ever prevent our College from becoming a narrow One, or falling into the Hands of any Sect or Party.</note> Preference is due. Is there any one of them that has already a Preference by the Conſtitution of the Province? Is there any one of them that is known to have ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior Ability and Intention to beſtow large Donations on our Infant-College? Is there any Religion that wou'd in a ſuperior Degree, recommend our College to the Beneficence and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection
<pb n="86" facs="unknown:007121_0085_102AF9FF34B6E750"/>of the <hi>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Great,</hi> and perhaps the Legiſlature, in our Mother-Country? Or any Religion which, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtabliſh'd, wou'd draw the Youth of the <hi>American-Iſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> (I mean the <hi>Britiſh Antilles</hi>) rather to ours, than any of the neighbouring Colleges?—Thoſe who know the Anſwer to theſe Queſtions, will be at no Loſs to decide in this preſent Diſpute concerning the Religion to be eſtabliſhed in our future College.—I ſaid the <hi>American-Iſlands;</hi> it being chiefly from thence we are to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Students, as well as large Subſcriptions or Donations to aid us in this Work; and not from the neighbouring Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that have Colleges of their own. For let the Conſtitutions of thoſe Colleges be as narrow and partial as they are repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, can any one imagine that, when they are like to loſe the Advantage of educating their own Youth, on this Account, they will be ſo impolitic as not to alter and catholiciſe theſe Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions. At preſent they are under no Neceſſity of doing this, becauſe, all our American Colleges of Note being under the ſame narrow Government, Youth cannot better themſelves by leaving one to go to another. But, if ours is eſtabliſh'd in a proper Manner, they muſt new-model their Colleges to retain their Youth at Home; and what ſort of religious Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, among us, muſt be productive of ſo much Good, is very evident.—I cannot at preſent, and for the future, I fear, ſhall not, find Leiſure, to ſet theſe Points in the Light they deſerve. But what I have hinted may, I hope, excite ſome other Perſon, ſpeedily to do it.—</p>
               <p>All I ſhall add is, to intreat and obteſt the Legiſlature, by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of their <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> and the Glory of the <hi>Engliſh Name,</hi> to proceed, at their firſt Meeting, to take ſome reſolute and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſive Step in this whole Affair; without regarding the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>govern'd Heats of Sectaries, which, in that Caſe, will quickly die away. For to me it appears, that the longer this Work is delay'd, the more Difficulties will ariſe, or be rais'd, to retard it. Let them but begin;—Support, Aid and Succeſs will not — cannot—be wanting. This I have often ſaid before; and this (as the Matter is now become ſo intereſting) might as properly be ſaid, at the Concluſion of every public Paper, on whatever Subject, as <hi>Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> concluded his every public Speech with— <hi>Delenda eſt Carthago.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> 10th, 1753,</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
