<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian soldier. A sermon preached at Newbury, at the ordination of the Reverend Mr. Alexander Boyd; to the pastoral office at New-Castle, in the province of the Massachusetts-Bay, September 24th, 1754. / By the Reverend Mr. David MacGregore, of Londonderry. ; [Six lines of Scripture texts]</title>
            <author>McGregore, David, 1710-1777.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N05871</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N05871</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 7454</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX3264</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">7454</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99020032</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 7454.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N05871)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 7454)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 7454)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian soldier. A sermon preached at Newbury, at the ordination of the Reverend Mr. Alexander Boyd; to the pastoral office at New-Castle, in the province of the Massachusetts-Bay, September 24th, 1754. / By the Reverend Mr. David MacGregore, of Londonderry. ; [Six lines of Scripture texts]</title>
                  <author>McGregore, David, 1710-1777.</author>
                  <author>Congregational Church (New Castle, Me.).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p. ;  22 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Edes and J. Gill, at the new-printing-office in King-Street, for S. Kneeland in Queen-Street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1755.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Mr. MacGregore's sermon at the ordination of Mr. Alexander Boyd.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Boyd, Alexander.</term>
               <term>Ordination sermons --  1754.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:007454_0000_102D91D6C98FCCB8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:007454_0001_102D91D8CE86D770"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Mac Gregore</hi>'s SERMON At the ORDINATION OF Mr. <hi>Alexander Boyd.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:007454_0002_102D91DAD0C8BCD8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Chriſtian Soldier.</hi> A SERMON Preached at <hi>Newbury,</hi> AT THE ORDINATION of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Alexander Boyd;</hi> To the Paſtoral Office at <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> in the Province of the MASSACHUSETTS-BAY, <hi>September 24th,</hi> 1754.</p>
            <p>By the Reverend Mr. DAVID MAC GREGORE, Of <hi>Londonderry.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. ii. 10.</hi>
               </bibl> Fear none of theſe Things which thou ſhalt ſuffer.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. iv. 7, 8.</hi>
               </bibl> I have fought the good Fight, I have finiſhed my Courſe, I have kept the Faith.—Henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judge ſhall give me at that Day: And not to me only, but unto them alſo that love his appearing.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON:</hi> Printed by B. EDES and J. GILL, at the New-Printing-Office in <hi>King-Street,</hi> for S. KNEELAND in <hi>Queen-Street.</hi> 1755.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="unknown:007454_0003_102D91DD5B621220"/>
            <head>AN <hi>Ordination</hi> SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2 TIM. ii. 3.</bibl>
                  <p>Thou therefore endure Hardneſs, as a good Soldier of <hi>JESUS CHRIST.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>ONSIDERING the vaſt Importance of the Miniſterial Office, and what are like to be the happy or unhappy Conſequences of a faithful or unfaithful Diſcharge of it; there is great Need that every Argument be uſed, that may moſt powerfully excite to Miniſterial Faithfulneſs.</p>
            <p>And, as on the one Hand, a juſt View of the glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, conſequent upon a right Diſcharge of the Duties of that important Office, will, (its likely) prove an animating Motive to Miniſterial Faithfulneſs; So on the other, to conſider aright the many and great Difficulties which attend the faithful Exerciſe of this Office, may have the like Tendency.</p>
            <p>Such a View ſeaſonably taken at the Entry of the ſacred Office, may prevent Miniſters from repenting of their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, or from looking back after having put their Hands to the Plough.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="unknown:007454_0004_102D91DF4B327C50"/>
A right View of theſe Difficulties, and counting the Coſt before Hand, may prevent the unhappy Fate of the fooliſh Man, who began to build, but was not able to finiſh. This, by the divine Bleſſing, may quicken Miniſters to apply to their Work with Vigour and Reſolution; may excite them to put on the whole Armour of God, and to take all due Care to be well equiped for the important Service they are to be engaged in. With a View therefore to promote theſe good Effects, I propoſe by divine Help, to introduce the preſent Solemnity, by ſaying ſomewhat of the Difficulties that attend the fatihful Diſcharge of the Goſpel-Miniſtry; and to that End, have choſen the Words now read, as the Subject of Diſcourſe, where the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Thou therefore endure Hardneſs as a good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Text and Context, contain an Addreſs of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> to the Evangeliſt <hi>Timothy;</hi> in which, he gives him a Number and Variety of neceſſary and ſeaſonable Directions, with Reſpect to his fulfilling the ſeveral Parts of his important Office; particularly the firſt Verſe, he applies to him in theſe Words, <hi>Thou therefore my Son, be ſtrong in the Grace which is in Chriſt Jeſus, Be ſtrong:</hi> i. e. be ſtout and couragious, fear not any Enemy, or Oppoſition thou mayſt meet with in the faithful Execution of thine Office. <hi>In the Grace which is in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> q. d. don't depend upon thy own Strength, or natural Courage; but place thy whole Confidence in the gracious Influence and Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus. Remember that it is in him that thou haſt both Righteouſneſs and Strength; that all thy Springs are in this bleſſed Head of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence; and that without Him thou canſt do nothing. Then in the ſecond Verſe, he gives the Evangeliſt Direction con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the important Work of ſetting apart fit Perſons to the Office of the Goſpel-Miniſtry. <hi>The Things that thou haſt heard of me before many Witneſſes:</hi> i. e. The Doctrines of the Goſpel, and the Office of the Miniſtry, which have been by me committed to thy Truſt: the many Witneſſes before whom this was done, has Reſpect to the numerous Spectators who were preſent at the Evangeliſt's Ordination. The <hi>ſame commit thou to faithful Men:</hi> q. d. Take good Care, not only how thou fulfilleſt thy own Miniſtry, but alſo who thou intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceſt into the Miniſtry; that they into whoſe Hands the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Depoſitum is committed, be not only faithful, but able. Labour to have all the Evidence that the Nature of the Caſe will admit of, not only that they be Perſons who have an honeſt Intention, but alſo that they are in ſome good Meaſure
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:007454_0005_102D71EDADEE06B0"/>qualified to ſpeak as becomes the Oracles of God, and to perform the other Parts of that weighty Truſt.</p>
            <p>Then in the Text he proceeds to ſay, <hi>Thou therefore endure Hardneſs as a good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Here's a Duty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to, and the Manner in which it is to be done. The Duty we have in that Precept, <hi>endure Hardneſs,</hi> or as it might be literally rendered from the original <hi>Super-evil, viz.</hi> the Evil of Affliction: q. d. Expect a Number and Variety of Difficulties in the faithful Exerciſe of thy Miniſtry, and be ready to encounter them with Chriſtian Fortitude, and to bear them with Equanimity and Patience.</p>
            <p>The Manner in which the Duty is to be done, we have in theſe Words, <hi>As a good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> q. d. to excite thee to endure Hardneſs with the more Patience, Thou muſt remember that the Life of a Miniſter, is not a Life of Eaſe and Pleaſure; but on the contrary, a Life of Warfare, the Life of a Soldier; that Miniſters in the faithful Exerciſe of their Miniſtry, may rationally lay their Account with the Dangers, the Fatigues and Encounters of a long and hazardous Campaign.</p>
            <p>The Subject being thus introduced and explained, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing more largely upon it, I ſhall
<list>
                  <item>Iſt, Point to ſome of thoſe Things that Miniſters may rationally lay their Account to meet with, in the faithful Exerciſe of their Office; which will require their <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during Hardneſs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IIdly. I ſhall mention ſome of thoſe Qualitications which are mainly neceſſary, in Order to their <hi>enduring Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or encountring the Difficulties they may expect to meet. And then make Application.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And according to the propoſed Method,</p>
            <p n="1">I. I am to point to ſeveral of thoſe Things, that it is likely Miniſters will meet with, in the Exerciſe of their Miniſtry, which will require their <hi>enduring Hardneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I would obſerve in general, that they may in the whole of their Miniſterial Work, expect to meet with thoſe Things which will require their <hi>enduring Hardneſs.</hi> For
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:007454_0006_102D91E66264E6B0"/>conſider, that the preſent State of the viſible Church is mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; Chriſt's Diſciples while here in this World, are in a State of War, and need to put on the whole Armour of God, that they may fight the good Fight of Faith. The Church in the preſent State is like a Flock of Sheep among Wolves; ſhe has her Situation among Lions Dens, and the Mountains of Leopards. Believers, at preſent, are in a World that hates them, <hi>Job.</hi> 15.19. <hi>They have many Enemies, and theſe hate them with a cruel hatred, Pſal.</hi> 25.19. This Enmity began to break out very early in the Murder of righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> by his own Brother: <hi>and wherefore ſlew he him?</hi> The Apoſtle tells us, 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Becauſe his own Works were Evil, and his Brother's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</hi> And it has been manifeſting it ſelf in every Age ſince theſe Words of God were pronounced. Gen. 3.15. <hi>I will put Enmity between thee and the Woman, and between thy Seed and her Seed:</hi> in ſo much, that in every Age, there has been Occaſion for the Apoſtle's Obſervation, Gal. 4.29, <hi>But as then he that was born after the Fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the Spirit,</hi> even ſo it is now.</p>
            <p>Our Lord tells his Diſciples, that in the World they ſhall have Tribulation; <hi>and that through much Tribulation they may expect to enter into the Kingdom of God:</hi> And what he told them, they have found true. Hence it is obſervable, that the World has proven an unkind Step-Dame to our Lord himſelf, and to many of his deareſt Followers. The Pſalmiſt was not the only Saint who has had Reaſon to complain, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120.5. <hi>Wo is me that I am in Meſhech, and that I dwell in the Tents of Kedar;</hi> or to ſay as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.4. <hi>My Soul is among fierce Lions, and I dwell with them that are ſet on Fire.</hi> Believers in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State have not only Men, but Devils to oppoſe them; they have to encounter all the Legions of Hell, with Satan at their Head; <hi>they wreſtle not againſt Fleſh and Blood only, but alſo againſt Principalities and Powers, againſt the Rulers of the Darkneſs of this World, againſt ſpiritual Wickedneſs in high Places.</hi> Eph. 6.12.</p>
            <p>And as the preſent State of the Church is militant, ſo Miniſters are Officers in this War, under Chriſt the Captain of Salvation: It is their Buſineſs to animate and direct Chriſt's Soldiers to lead them out to Action; and while they are doing ſo, not to ſhrink back themſelves for fear of Danger; but to jeopard their Lives in the high Places of the Field, and if Need be, bravely to expoſe themſelves in the Fore-front of the hotteſt Battle, and to make a reſolute Stand againſt the united Powers of Earth and Hell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="unknown:007454_0007_102D91E856A7F510"/>
And as in the heat of a Battle, we ſee that the Enemy do endeavour principally to ſlay their Adverſary's Officers, ſo it is not to be doubted but that the Devil and his Party will bend their chief Force againſt the Officers in Chriſt's Army. What our Lord ſays to <hi>Peter,</hi> is applicable in a peculiar Senſe to every faithful Miniſter, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.31. <hi>Simon, Simon, behold Satan hath deſired to have you, that he may ſift you as Wheat.</hi> He who was bold enough to attack the Captain of our Salvation, in the Manner we read of, <hi>Matt.</hi> 4.1—11, will no doubt, as far as he is permitted, try every Method with Miniſters, that he may either over-power them by Force, or circumvent them by Fraud.</p>
            <p>From this general View of the Caſe, you may eaſily ſee that Miniſters in the Exerciſe of their Office, will need to <hi>endure Hardneſs.</hi> But I would be larger on this Head, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to point to ſeveral of the particular Things which will require their <hi>enduring Haadneſs.</hi> And,</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. The Oppoſition, and the bitter Scoffs they may expect to meet with, in their faithful laying down the Scheme of Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt, will call for their <hi>enduring Hardneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, there is nothing in this Scheme of Salvation which deſerves Oppoſition, or which is by any Means a fit Object of Ridicule: On the contrary, it is the moſt benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and withal the wiſeſt Deſign. It is full of <hi>Benevolence</hi> and breathes nothing but Love and Compaſſion to guilty pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted periſhing Creatures, in next Subordination to the Glory of God, according to <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.14; Peace and Pardon, and Holineſs, high Honours and ſpecial Favours, to the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Rebels. In a Word, conſidering the Benevolence of the Deſign<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it might reaſonably be expected that the Goſpel, inſtead of Oppoſition, would meet with a univerſal Welcome; that every Houſe, and every Heart would be open to receive the Saviour. <hi>It is certainly a faithful Saying, and worthy of all Accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave the chief of Sinners.</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. And as it is a benevolent, ſo it is a <hi>wiſe</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign: the Device of Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt, contains in it the brighteſt Diſplay of divine Wiſdom that ever the World was acquainted with; ſo far is it from having any Thing fooliſh or weak in it, any Thing that is a proper Object of Ridicule: Every Thing in the glorious Plan of the New-Covenant, is ſo well ordered, as to be worthy of a Being of infinite Perfection. Here's Wiſdom enough and enough, to
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:007454_0008_102D91EA4ADC7CB0"/>employ the richeſt ſpeculative human Mind. Nay, the Angels of Heaven, though not ſo nearly intereſted as Men are, yet they admire the manifold Wiſdom of God herein manifeſted, and love to pry into it. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. But then it is likewiſe true, that the Glory and Beauty of the New-Covenant. Way of Redemption, and the excellent Wiſdom therein diſplayed, are not diſcerned by carnal Eyes: With Reſpect to them, it is called <hi>hidden Wiſdom, the Wiſdom of God in a Myſtery, which none of the Princes of this World knew.</hi> 1 Cor. 2.7. Hence the Apoſtle had Occaſion to ſay as he does, 1 Cor. 1.23. <hi>We preach Chriſt crucified, to the Jews a ſtumbling Block, and to the Greeks Fooliſhneſs.</hi> He who ſaid ſo, altho' perhaps one of the beſt Preachers that ever opened a Mouth, was yet counted a Babbler, when he preached Jeſus, and the Reſurrection from the Dead.</p>
            <p>And as the Minds of Men are naturally the ſame now that they were ſeventeen Hundred Years ago, ſo the Goſpel is apt to meet with the ſame Treatment; and this not only from <hi>Jews, Mahometans</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> but alſo from profeſs'd Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians. Natural Men, however they may be born and brought up under a Chriſtian Diſpenſation, yet they cannot ſee into ſeveral of the important Doctrines of Chriſtianity. As for Inſtance, they can't ſee into the Doctrines of abſolute Decrees, or Original Sin: How an abſolute Predetermination is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with human Liberty: How it is juſt or poſſible that by the Diſobedience of one many ſhould be made Sinners: Or that by the Offence of one Judgment ſhould come on all to Condemnation. How it is conſiſtent either with infinite Wiſdom or Juſtice, that a Sinner ſhould be juſtified by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Righteouſneſs; or that the Juſt ſhould ſuffer for the Unjuſt, that he might bring Sinners to God. They can't ſee into the Doctrine of Regeneration, as importing the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Production and inſtantaneous Implantation of a new living Principle of Action in the Soul, operating ſo powerfully as to produce an immediate Change in all the Faculties.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and other the peculiar Doctrines of our holy Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, are Fooliſhneſs to them, and the Objects of their hearty Averſion. And therefore he who will preach them up, with faithful Boldneſs, and apply them with Cloſeneſs, may expect the Trial, at leaſt, of cruel Mockings; and very probably will meet with ſuch Oppoſition and Contradiction, as will demand all the Chriſtian Fortitude he is Maſter of, to bear up under them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="7" facs="unknown:007454_0009_102D91EC8BEF2918"/>
2. The cloſe and painful Application they ſhould give to their private Studies, will require their <hi>enduring Hardneſs.</hi> There is a Number and Variety of Acquirements, needful to qualify for the Work of the Goſpel-Miniſtry, which cannot be attained, without cloſe Application to Study. It were to be wiſhed, (if practicable) that Miniſters of the Goſpel were vers'd in all the various Parts of ſolid, uſeful Learning: That they were expert in the whole Compaſs of Science, and what is known by the Name of univerſal Scholars, But this, with Reſpect to Miniſters in general, is, (I own) rather to be wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, than expected; eſpecially in a young Country, where Things are yet, as it were, in <hi>Embrio,</hi> or in an infant State. But even in our preſent State, Miniſters ſhould have ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency of human Learning: as for Inſtance, It is at leaſt highly expedient, that the Goſpel-Miniſter underſtood ſo much of Grammar and Rhetorick, as to know ſomewhat of the Congruity and Elegancy of Language: That he have ſuch an Inſight into Logick and Metaphyſicks, as that he be capable of making proper Diſtinctions of knowing when an Argument is, or is not concluſive; of reaſoning with ſome Pertinency and Clearneſs of detecting Sophiſms, and of Abſtracting: That he did at leaſt know ſo much of Mathematicks, as to render him capable of reading Books of natural Philoſophy, with Underſtanding: That he be well acquainted with moral Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and with Hiſtory, ancient and modern, civil and ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtic; eſpecially, it is needful that he be acquainted with Divinity, Polemick and Syſtematick, as well as Practical.</p>
            <p>Now theſe Acquirements are not to be attained without Study, yea, much Study, which <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerves, is a Weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Fleſh. Many an one has endured that Hardneſs, by cloſe Application to Study, that has brought on Diſeaſe, and haſtned Death in the Meridian of Life.</p>
            <p>But this is not all: as the Study he proſecutes in order to attain miniſterial Qualifications, will require his <hi>enduring Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> ſo alſo will that, to which he behoves, to apply himſelf in the Exerciſe of his Office. A conſciencious Miniſter can't allow himſelf to put off People with a rude impremeditated extemporary Effuſion: On the contrary, he conſiders that the Intereſt of Souls is at Stake; one of which, is of more Value than a World beſides: That his Preaching is about Matters of infinite Moment; that he is like to be the Savour of Life unto Life, or of Death unto Death; the moſt glorious Life, or the moſt dreadful Death, to them that hear him. And
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:007454_0010_102D91EE6D3B1DE8"/>under the Influence of ſuch Conſiderations, he dare not offer to the Lord what coſt him Nothing; but though it ſhould be a Wearineſs to the Fleſh, he gives himſelf to cloſe Study, that by this Means he may bring beaten Oyl, to cauſe the Lamps to burn. The Foreſight that this may ſoon wear out animal Nature, and haſten temporal Death, don't at all deter him; he had much rather it ſhould be work'd out in ſuch Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than in any other; and hence he gives himſelf to Reading, to Meditation and to Doctrine; and deeply ſenſible that he can't prepare for the publick Service of the Sanctuary by his own Study, he's much in Cloſet Devotion, often plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Father of Lights, that he would enable him to find out acceptable Words, directing him to ſeaſonable Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and the moſt profitable Way of proſecuting them. In a Word, he who will make Conſcience of private Preparation for the publick Exerciſe of the Miniſtry, will find Need to <hi>endure Hardneſs</hi> in this Reſpect.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Faithful Reproof is another Part of his Work, in the Exerciſe of which the Goſpel Miniſter will need to <hi>endure Hardneſs,</hi> and has Occaſion for much holy Courage. Reproving and Rebuking are Parts of the Miniſterial Office, as well as Exhorting, 2 Tim. 4.2. <hi>He muſt cry aloud, and not ſpare, lifting up his Voice like a Trumpet in ſhewing God's People their Tranſgreſſions, and the Houſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>their Sins,</hi> Iſai. 58.1. Yea, if there be Occaſion for it, he muſt rebuke ſharply, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.13. Yea, he muſt not only reprove publickly from the Pulpit, but when there is Occaſion for it, he is to practice private perſonal Rebuke. The faithful Miniſter muſt not allow himſelf to reſpect Perſons, or to give flattering Titles to Men; but muſt faithfully reprove the Vices of the great, as well as of the ſmall. Though the Perſon that needs the Reproof be one in great Power; one who has the Eſtate, or even the Life of the Reprover at his Diſpoſal, yet this muſt not hinder him from a faithful Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his Duty. The Baptiſt is herein a ſhining Pattern; he was no Stranger to the tyrannical Diſpoſition of <hi>Herod.</hi> It is not unlike that he was ſenſible that he ran the Riſque of loſing his Head; and yet all this don't deter him from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the Tyrant, on Account of his abominable inceſtuous Marriage. Miniſters muſt follow ſuch an Example as this at their Peril; they muſt put their ſecular Intereſts, and even their Lives in their Hand, leaving the Conſequence to God. They muſt ſometimes miniſter thoſe Reproofs which perhaps will be galling to the Conſciences of wicked Men, though they ſhould like the Murderers of <hi>Stephen</hi> be cut to
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:007454_0011_102D91F35CC54BA0"/>the Heart, or angry even to Madneſs. It's true, the faithful Miniſter is to take Care that his Reproofs be wiſely diſpenſed, with Reſpect to Time, Place, Manner and other Circumſtances. He is alſo carefully to avoid Bitterneſs, to ſhun the Spirit even of a <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>Hear now ye Rebels, muſt we bring you Water out of this Rock.</hi> In a Word, he ſhould endeavour to apply theſe Cauſticks, with all that Tenderneſs, that the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Operation will admit of. But on the other Hand, he had Need to take Care, leaſt under the Colour of Prudence or Tenderneſs, he ſhould be unfaithful.</p>
            <p>This is another Branch of the ſacred Office, in which the Goſpel Miniſter will have much Need to <hi>endure Hardneſs.</hi> He will be apt ſometimes (it is likely) to have the Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of finding, that altho' the Reproof has been adminiſtred with all poſſible Wiſdom and Tenderneſs; yet by his Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, he has loſt the Good-will of the Reproved, who is become his Enemy for telling him the Truth, and ever after bears him a Grudge, and is ready to do him a Miſchief.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Goſpel Miniſter needs to <hi>endure Hardneſs,</hi> in oppoſing Errors and Erroriſts. The Apoſtle tells us, 1 Cor. 11.19, <hi>That there muſt be Hereſies, that they that are approved may be made manifeſt.</hi> Sometimes we ſee the ſovereign and all-wiſe God, whoſe Ways are paſt finding out, does for ſome End worthy of himſelf, ſee fit to permit falſe Teachers to enter into his Church; Perſons who make it their Buſineſs to corrupt the Word of God, and who are induſtrious to draw away Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples after them. It may be, the Errors they promote, though of a very dangerous Nature, eating like a Canker, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Vitals of Chriſtianity; yet are ſo ſpeciouſly guilded, that the Poiſon is not eaſily diſcerned; fair Pretences are made of Zeal for God; and ſuch guileful Methods uſed, that with good Words and fair Speeches, the Simple are in great Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being deceived.</p>
            <p>In ſuch a State of Things, that Miniſter who would expect to be owned <hi>as a good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> muſt exert him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; he muſt not ſee grievous Wolves entring in, not ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Flock, or the little Foxes ſpoiling the tender Vine: and in the mean Time ſtand by as an unconcern'd Spectator; but when he ſees Men ariſing, and hears them ſpeaking per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Things, to draw away Diſciples, he ſhould conſider him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as ſet for the Defence of the Goſpel, and not fly, leaving Chriſt's Sheep in the Power of Wolves; but to contend ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:007454_0012_102D91F5F9BDA978"/>for the Faith once delivered to the Saints, endeavouring with all Learning and ſound Doctrine, to convince the Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers; uſing his beſt Skill to eſtabliſh the Flock in the labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Truths of the Day, and to reduce any that are wavering, and begin to be drawn aſide from their Stedfaſtneſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Miniſters need to <hi>endure Hardneſs,</hi> in that careful Watch they are to keep over the Flock. Chriſt's Flock have much need of a careful Watch over them, conſidering what fooliſh Sheep they are, how apt to go aſtray, and what vigilant, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Enemies are engaged againſt them: And hence, although their chief Safety is owing to the omniſcient Eye of him that ſlumbers not, nor ſleeps, which is conſtantly exerciſed about them, without which, the Watchmen would watch in vain; yet it has pleaſed the great Keeper of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to appoint his Miniſters in the Station of Watchmen, Ezek. 3.17. <hi>Son of Man, I have made thee a Watchman to the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael. So likewiſe, Iſa. 62.6. <hi>I have ſet Watchmen on thy Walls, O</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>that ſhall never hold their Peace, Day nor Night;</hi> and in the Exerciſe of this Part of their Office, they are to guard againſt Drouſineſs. That's a ſad Character which we have of the Watchman of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Iſa. 56.10. viz. <hi>Sleeping, lying down, loving to Slumber.</hi> As the Miniſter of Chriſt would be owned by his divine Maſter at laſt, he ſhould take Care that this Character be not applicable to him. And in order hereto, he ſhould have his Eyes where <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us the wife Man's are, <hi>viz.</hi> in his Head; carefully obſerving the State of the Church, what are the Practices of her Enemies againſt her. In a Word, heedfully noticing what are the Phenomena of the natural, the moral, and the religious World; ſo as to be always qualified to give a right Anſwer to that Queſtion, <hi>Watchman, what of the Night?</hi> Now this is a Work which will require great Steadineſs and Application of Mind: And thoſe who will diſcharge it faithfully, will, (I believe) be often awake in a natural Senſe, when the Flock in that Senſe are aſleep.</p>
            <p n="6">6. There is a great Variety of Labours belonging to the Miniſterial Office, beſides what we have already touched upon, which will require their <hi>enduring Hardneſs.</hi> Preaching the Goſpel is a very laborious Work, as might be eaſily ſeen, had we Time to view the Nature of it. To hold forth the Love of God to Sinners in it's Origin and firſt Spring, <hi>viz.</hi> free ſovereign Grace; to open up the Nature of that Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion purchaſed by Chriſt; to ſhew what a wiſe, gracious, glorious Device the New-Covenant-Way of Salvation is;
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:007454_0013_102D91F80E711908"/>what a glorious Conſtellation of divine Perfections do ſhine forth in it; how well ordered it is in all Things; how wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in every Reſpect of it's divine Author: To diſplay aright the Manner of the Application of this precious Redemption: To preach the Terrors of the Law to awakened Sinners; repreſenting Hell naked before them, and Deſtruction without a Covering; ſhewing them what a fearful Thing it is to fall into the Hands of the living God: To direct awakened en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring Souls the right Way to Chriſt, ſteering them ſafe by thoſe fatal Rocks, upon which many Souls have been wrecked and finally loſt: To preach ſo as to ſuit a great Variety of Caſes among Believers, feeding Chriſt's Sheep, and feeding his Lambs; giving Milk to Babes, and ſtrong Meat to them who have their Senſes exerciſed: To make a judicious Choice of pertinent Subjects, well adapted to the Times, that may lead not only to Truth, but ſeaſonable Truth: To be inſtant in Seaſon, and out of Seaſon, not willingly loſing any Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity that preſents of ſerving Chriſt and Souls: To take due Care not only as to the Matter, but alſo as to the Style and Manner of delivering divine Truth; with the Preacher ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to find out acceptable Words, uſing all the Arts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuading and animating; and leaving no Mean uneſſay'd to convince the Judgments, and gain the Hearts of Men. This is Labour! this is Work! And he who will follow it faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, muſt <hi>endure Hardneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is not all: they who think the Whole of a Miniſter's Work is confined to the Pulpit, and his Preparations for it, do greatly miſtake the Nature of it: How ſhall he know what to preach, except he know the State of the Flock? And how can he know this ſufficiently, without taking Pains to know it? 'Tis needful therefore that he ſpend ſome convenient Part of his Time, not only in occaſional Viſits to the Sick, and upon other Emergencies; but alſo in ſtated Viſitation and Catechiſing, examining the Flock as to their Advances in Knowledge, and conferring freely with them about Soul-Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; ſtirring up the ignorant and careleſs, warning the unruly, comforting the feeble-minded, ſupporting the weak; teaching not only publickly, but alſo from Houſe to Houſe, <hi>Repentance towards God, and Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might alſo have mentioned the exerciſe of the Key of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> a Part of the miniſterial Office, which is often at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with great Difficulty, and which requires much holy Courage, Impartiality and Faithfulneſs, as well as Wiſdom:
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:007454_0014_102D91FA992B8AE0"/>as likewiſe, the adminiſtring the Seals of the Covenant, which ſuppoſes an Enquiry into the Qualifications of the Subjects of theſe Seals: A Work this, which ſome Miniſters I know find very weighty and difficult. In a Word, he who will faithfully apply himſelf to the various Labours of the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Office, will be apt to find it a Work of great and ſore Labour and Fatigue.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Goſpel-Miniſter will need to <hi>endure Hardneſs,</hi> in bearing up under ſinking Diſcouragements, which are apt to attend him in the Exerciſe of his Office. Some Miniſters have more of theſe than others; but I believe none are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely exempt from them, and ſome feel theſe to be many and great; Sometimes they feel the Weight of Souls lying on their Spirits, with an almoſt inſupportable Preſſure; they feel a Degree of the ſame catholic Concern, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. The general Intereſt of Chriſtianity lies near their Hearts; and it may be, they have the Affliction to ſee Religion low, corrupting Errors prevailing, practical Godlineſs much decay'd, and Matter daily tending from bad to worſe; ſo that the Things that remain, are even ready to die. Upon ſuch a melancholly View of Things, the faithful Miniſter cannot ſtand by as an unconcern'd Spectator: His ſeeing <hi>Zion</hi> in this Condition, will cauſe him to <hi>bang his Harp on the Willow;</hi> his Heart trembles for the Ark of God; he cannot prevent a good Deal of Dejection of Soul, and it may be, he feels ſcarce enough of Faith in Exerciſe, to breathe out faintly ſuch a Petition as that, Amos 7.2. <hi>O Lord God, forgive, I beſeech thee: By whom ſhall</hi> Jacob <hi>ariſe? for he is ſmall.</hi> Again, ſometimes his Heart is ready to die within him, to ſee ſo little Appearance of Fruit following his miniſterial Labours; to think that there is a ſad Probability that he ſhall prove the Savour of Death unto Death to ſome Perſons, that are very dear to him; that he muſt appear before Chriſt's Judgment-Seat, and bear Witneſs againſt them, that they deſpiſed the Grace of the Goſpel, and trampled under Foot the great Salvation. O! it is a cutting Thought. Sometimes he is ſorely exerciſed with the Fear that he hath already proved, or ſhall prove unfaithful, in the Execution of ſome important Branch of his Office; that he ſhall not be able to give any good Account of the weighty Truſt committed to him; that ſuch Souls ſhall periſh by his Neglect; and that he ſhall neither ſave himſelf, nor them that hear him. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he has unreaſonable and wicked Men, Men that have not Faith, Men of Beaſt-like Diſpoſitions, to deal with; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:007454_0015_102D91FC247C58E8"/>all Men ſeem to forſake him, and none to ſtand by him; and what is worſe ſtill, ſometimes his Maſter hides his Face. In a Word, his Diſcouragements are innumerable, both from without, and from within; ſo that on this Account alſo, he has Need to <hi>endure Hardneſs, as a good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And thus I have ſhewn (as I propoſed) ſome of the Difficulties attending the Exerciſe of the Miniſterial Office, which will require <hi>enduring Hardneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proceed next to the other General Head; which is,</p>
            <p>IIdly, To mention, and a little to inſiſt on ſome of thoſe Qualifications which are mainly neceſſary, in Order to the Goſpel-Miniſters <hi>enduring Hardneſs, as a good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 1ſt. It is needful in order to his <hi>enduring Hardneſs,</hi> that he be a Man of Faith. Without Faith it is hardly to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that he will <hi>fight the good Fight,</hi> and ſteadily adhere to his Maſter's Intereſt, in the midſt of Difficulties, ſo many and great: But if he have ſome good Meaſure of this divine Grace, it will have an happy Efficacy in enabling him to face and ſurmount Difficulties. Faith enables him to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance the Things of Time and Eternity, ſo as to give each its proper Weight; to put the Sufferings of the preſent Time in one Scale, and the Glory which is to be revealed in the other; and by this Means, evidently to diſcover that the light Afflictions of the preſent Time, are but as it were for a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo not worthy to be compared with the Glory that is to be revealed. Faith ſometimes enables him to ſee his divine Lord ſtanding by him, and to hear him adreſſing him in ſuch Words as once he did one of his faithful Miniſters, Act. 23.11. <hi>Be of good Cheer</hi> Paul. Faith ſometimes opens up the eternal World before him, and gives him ſuch a View as <hi>Stephen</hi> had, when he ſaid, <hi>I ſee the Heavens opened, and the Son of Man ſtanding at the right Hand of God,</hi> Act. 7.56. By Faith he hears the Captain of his Salvation ſaying, as Rev. 3.12. <hi>To him that overcometh, will I give to ſit down with me on my Throne; even as I alſo have overcome, and am ſet down with my Father on his Throne.</hi> In a Word, Faith ſo fortifies the Soul, that he is at Times carried in a Manner quite above Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement; ſo that on a Proſpect of the worſt that can happen, he is able to adopt the Language of the Apoſtle, Act. 20.22, 23, 24. <hi>And now I go bound in the Spirit to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Things that ſhall befal me there: Save that the Holy Ghoſt witneſſeth in every City, ſaying, That Bonds and Afflictions abide me.
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:007454_0016_102D91FE37E17350"/>But none of theſe Things move me, neither count I my Life dear unto my ſelf, ſo that I might finiſh my Courſe with Joy, and the Miniſtry which I have received of the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let thoſe Miniſters who would <hi>endure Hardneſs, as good Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> put on the whole Armour of God; above all, let them take the Shield of Faith; let them who have Faith, labour for an Increaſe of that divine Grace, let them often pray the Diſciples Prayer, <hi>Lord increaſe our Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is needful in order to his <hi>enduring Hardneſs,</hi> that he have a hearty Love to Chriſt and Souls. Where this Grace is wanting, the Perſon will be apt to do his Work grudgingly, and as of Neceſſity. Where Love is wanting, there will ſcarcely be any Motive ſtrong enough to engage him to adhere cloſely to his Maſter's Cauſe, when his doing ſo is attended with peculiar Danger and Difficulty. He'll hardly be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to expoſe his Life, or even his Eſtate, or his Name, for Chriſt and his Intereſt: On the contrary, his Behaviour will be apt to be like that, Joh. 10.12, 13. <hi>The Hireling fleeth, becauſe he is an Hireling, and careth not for the Sheep.</hi> But where this ſweet Grace of Love is, it has a conſtraining Influence on the Goſpel-Miniſter; it ties him by the Heart to the Service of his glorious Captain, ſo that he never thinks he can do too much, or enough in his Cauſe. Under the powerful Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of this Grace, he can cheerfully riſque his Life, when his Maſter's Intereſt requires it, with him who ſaid Act. 21.13. <hi>I am ready not only to be hound, but alſo to die for the Name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> We ſee what a powerful Principle natural Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is in Parents toward their Children, with what Pleaſure (under the Influence of it) they go through a World of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigue and Sufferings to provide for them; ſuch a Diſpoſition do thoſe Miniſters, who love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, feel to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Souls of their Flocks: So that the Expreſſion of <hi>Paul,</hi> with Reſpect to <hi>Timothy,</hi> is applicable to them, that they naturally care for their State, Phil. 2.20. <hi>Naturally, i. e.</hi> As a Parent under the Influence of natural Affection, cares for his Children. A faithful Miniſter, when Love is in Exerciſe, does really feel the Bowels of a Parent, and can ſay with Reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to the Flock of Chriſt, as the Apoſtle does, Gal. 4.19. <hi>My little Children, of whom I travel in Birth again, 'till Chriſt be formed in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. They ſhould be Perſons who have made ſome conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Advances in Mortification. This likewiſe is a very need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:007454_0017_102D934502CA0510"/>Qualification for <hi>a good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> If a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter have an inordinate Love to his carnal Eaſe, he'll hardly be willing to follow his Maſter in a thorny Path, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage with great Difficulties in the Cauſe of Chriſt: When Tribulation or Perſecution ariſes becauſe of the Word, by and by he'll be offended. If he love the World with a prevailing Love, it will be apt to take him off from the Cauſe of Chriſt: See a ſad Inſtance, 2 Tim. 4.10. <hi>Demas bath forſaken me, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loved this preſent World.</hi> Hence that of the Apoſtle, 2 Tim. 2.4. <hi>No Man that warreth, intangleth himſelf with the Affairs of this Life, that he may pleaſe him who hath choſen him to be a Soldier.</hi> If he be exceſſively fond of worldly Honour and Applauſe, he'll hardly be willing to be accounted a Fool, to have his Name caſt out as evil, and to have <hi>all Manner of Evil ſpoken againſt him for Chriſt's Sake.</hi> Hence that of our Saviour, Joh. 5.44. <hi>How can ye believe, which receive Honour from one another, and ſeek not the Honour that cometh from God only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He then who would behave himſelf <hi>as a good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſhould be one who has made ſome Progreſs in the difficult, but neceſſary Duty of Self-denial; one who has learned to make Poverty welcome, if it ſhould fall to his Lot; who knows how to be abaſed, as well as how to abound; one who can deny his Appetites and Paſſions, when they become importunate and over-eagar in their Cravings; or as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſays, who keeps under his Body, and brings it into Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; one who contrary to that Character, Joh. 12.43. <hi>Loves the Praiſe of God, more than the Praiſe of Men.</hi> In a Word, The <hi>good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is one who has learned to follow his Captain in Honour and Diſhonour, through good and evil Report; ſo that he thinks not ſtrange of the fiery Trial, but cloſely adheres to his divine Lord in Time of the greateſt Danger and Suffering.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Chriſtian Courage and Steadineſs of Mind, is a Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication much needed in Order to <hi>enduring Hardneſs.</hi> I join theſe two becauſe they are near a-kin, and often where the one is, the other will be found alſo. For want of the Grace of Chriſtian Courage, even faithful Miniſters are apt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the evil Day to give Way to ſinking Dejection of Spirit: They faint in the Day of Adverſity: when Things have a diſcouraging and threatning-like Appearance, they are ready to give all up for loſt; they can ſcarcely think of any Thing but of leaving their publick Station, and flying into ſome hiding Place, where they may have Shelter from the impending
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:007454_0018_102D720076583758"/>Storm. When Courage is wanting, every Difficulty is viewed on the darkeſt Side. For Inſtance, a Miniſter ſees little or no Appearance of Fruit following his Labours: On the contrary, it ſeems as tho' Sinners grew daily more ſecure and ſtupid; in this Caſe, he is apt to look on his dealing with Sinners as to no Purpoſe, and perhaps is juſt on the Point of reſolving that he will make no more mention of the Name of the Lord. Or it may be, he is ſituated as <hi>Lot</hi> was in <hi>Sodom,</hi> ſo that he ſees groſs Sins of almoſt every Kind abounding, and his righteous Soul is vexed from Day to Day with their unlawful Deeds: In this Caſe he is ready to ſay with Jer. 9.2. <hi>Oh that I had in the Wilderneſs a lodging Place of wayfaring Men, that I might leave my People and go from them, for they be all Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, an Aſſembly of treacherous Men,</hi> &amp;c. Or perhaps he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds evident Tokens of divine Anger; it ſeems as if the Lord were about to come forth againſt his People with a Sword inſtead of a Rod; that the Cloud gathers black and dreadful, and the Enemy is about to break in like a Flood: In ſuch a Caſe, through defect of Courage, he is ready to think of Nothing ſo much as of flying from the Storm. But when Chriſtian Courage is in Exerciſe, it will improve all theſe diſcouraging Appearances, as ſo many Arguments to diſſuade from an inglorious Retreat. Chriſtian Courage will by no Means admit of Flight in any of the Caſes above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named.</p>
            <p>Are Sinners very ſecure and ſtupid, ſo that nothing that can be ſaid appears to have any abiding Impreſſion on them? Says the good Soldier who has this Grace in Act, "I'll never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs continue in the Uſe of Means with theſe ſtupid Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, tho' at preſent they ſeem to be Hammer-hardned under the Word; he with whom is the Reſidue of the Spirit, can ſend a divine Influence, which will ſoon and effectually ſoften them; perhaps the Captain of Salvation, who is a King mighty in Battle, may lend me a choſen Shaft from his Quiver, which will reach the Joints and Marrow, ſo as to rouſe them that are at preſent ſleeping on the Sides of the Pit, with a dreadful Sound in their Ears: But whatever the Event may be, I'll (thro' Grace) do my Duty, whether theſe Sinners will hear, or whether they will forbear; I have Reaſon to think that the ſovereign Will of God concerning them will have Effect by my Miniſtry, and that I ſhall be a ſweet Savour of God in them that periſh, as well as in them that are ſaved." Or is it a Time when groſs Sins prevail to a high Degree? Though ſuch a ſad Scene ſhould open as that, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>When there
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:007454_0019_102D720239A4D600"/>is little or no Truth, nor Mercy, nor Knowledge of God in the Land; when by ſwearing and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and committing Adultery, they break out and Blood toucheth Blood.</hi> In this Caſe ſays the courageous Soldier, The more the Torrent of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs prevails, the more need I have to ſtand firm in my Station, endeavouring to ſtem the rapid Stream. Or is it a Time when Things appear with a threatning Aſpect; when the Lord ſeems to have forſaken his People, and there are ſad Tokens of his Anger; or when the Enemies of <hi>Zion</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be hatching ſome formidable Plot; yea, though he ſhould have Reaſon to think that their chief Aim is againſt his Perſon: In either of theſe Caſes ſays the good Soldier with Neh. 6.11. <hi>Should ſuch a Man as I fly?</hi> Nay, rather let me look on all theſe threatning Appearances as ſo many loud Calls to keep my Station; let me ſtand between the Living and the Dead, and do my utmoſt to appeaſe incenſed Heaven, and ſo avert impending Judgments: Shall I fly for fear of the Plots of Enemies, and leave Chriſt's Flock expoſed? how then ſhall I look my glorious Captain in the Face? how ſhall I clear my ſelf of that Character he has given of an Hireling, who fleeth becauſe he is an Hireling, and careth not for the Flock? rather let me put my Life in my Hand, and venture my all in the Service of my divine Lord; firmly believing that he will ſtand by me, while he has any Work for me to do, and then will receive me to himſelf: That he'll make me a fenced brazen Wall, againſt which, though mine Enemies fight, yet they ſhall never prevail.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The good Soldier is one who is acquainted with his Weapons. Being ſkilful in the Knowledge, and expert in the Uſe of the Chriſtian Armour, is a neceſſary Qualification of ſuch an one as would expect to <hi>endure Hardneſs.</hi> That a Soldier ſhould know his Weapons, every one will grant: Nor is it enough that he be a good Theoriſt in this Knowledge, but his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhould be practical: He ſhould be capable of handling his Weapons, eſpecially he ſhould be dexterous at the Uſe of his Sword. Even ſo every Chriſtian Soldier (but eſpecially the Officers in Chriſt's Camp) ſhould be acquainted with the Chriſtian Armour; particularly, they ſhould know the Uſe of the Sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God; they ſhould be able to adopt the Experience of him who ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.97. <hi>O how love I thy Law; it is my Study all the Day.</hi> They ſhould love not only to ſtudy it as a Science, but to feed upon it: And while they receive it in the Love of it, and derive Nouriſhment &amp; Delight from it, to ſay as Pſ. 119.103. <hi>How ſweet
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:007454_0020_102D7203F2999148"/>is thy Word unto my Taſte, I find it ſweeter than Honey to my Mouth.</hi> The <hi>good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſhould be ſo well acquainted with the Doctrines, the Precepts, the Promiſes and Theatnings of God's Word, as that he may have a ready Recourſe to it in every Time of Need; and know how to uſe this ſpiritual Sword, either to defend himſelf and his Flock, or offend the Enemy, as Need ſhall require: And if he has ſuch a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as this, of the Sword of the Spirit, he ſhall be enabled to ſtand in the evil Day, able to maſter every Difficulty, to overcome every Temptation: He ſhall be an over-match for all the Power of the Enemy; he ſhall both do great Things, and ſhall ſtill prevail.</p>
            <p>Having ſpoken to the two General Heads propoſed in the Doctrinal Part; I paſs on to the <hi>Improvement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Inference</hi> 1. May Goſpel Miniſters lay their Account to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Hardneſs,</hi> or to meet with great Difficulties in their Work? Then it may be inferred, that Perſons ſhould not be raſh or haſty in running into the Miniſtry; it would certainly be wiſe in them firſt to count the Coſt, and to weigh maturely the Difficulties, as well as the Encouragements which attend the ſacred Station; to make a cloſe Enquiry about what are their Views in engaging in this Office? Whether they have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Ground to conclude, that therein they have a ſingle Eye? Whether they have thoſe Qualifications, by which alone, they ſhall be enabled to acquit themſelves, as Workmen that need not to be aſhamed? To think of our Lord's Queſtion to <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> Matt. 20.22. <hi>Can ye drink of the Cup that I ſhall drink; and be baptized with the Baptiſm that I am baptized with?</hi> And to examine what Anſwer they are qualified to give.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Inf.</hi> 2. Are the Difficulties attending the Miniſterial Office ſo many and great? Then People ſhould take Heed that they do not by any Part of their Conduct, render them greater. It would be cruel to add a Load to a heavy Burden: People may do this many Ways; as when they appear diſpos'd to watch for Miniſters halting, to expoſe their human Frailties; repreſenting every leſſer Infirmity in the blackeſt Colour, as though it were the groſſeſt Crime; when they expect that a Miniſter ſhould perform the whole of his vocational Labours with the utmoſt Exactneſs, and yet do not afford him a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent temporal Support; like the cruel <hi>Egyptian</hi> Taſk-Maſters, who would allow no Straw, and yet demanded the full Tale of Brick; or when they won't endure ſound Doctrine and
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:007454_0021_102D7205EFA0A080"/>miniſterial Faithfulneſs, but count him an Enemy who tells them the Truth; but eſpecially, when they give a deaf Ear to the great Command of God in the Goſpel, to believe on the Name of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo leave Miniſters la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting their Want of Succeſs with heavy Hearts, ſaying, <hi>Who hath believed our Report? And to whom is the Arm of the Lord revealed?</hi> People would do well to conſider that faithful Miniſters are the Miniſters of Chriſt; and that he'll reſent the Neglect, and practical Contempt, or the ill Treatment of and Kind, that they meet with; that he who deſpiſeth them, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſeth not only Man but God. Beloved, Miniſters are engaged in difficult Poſts, and they much need your Sympathy and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and friendly Aſſiſtance: If you knew how hardly beſtead they often are, while without are Fighting, and within are Fears; you would ſurely pity them, and do all you could to lighten their Burden.</p>
            <p>Omitting other Uſes which the Subject might afford, I proceed to the laſt, <hi>viz.</hi> The Uſe of Exhortation: In which, I ſhall addreſs my ſelf (1.) to Miniſters. (2.) To Candidates for the Miniſtry. (3.) To the Candidate now to be ſet apart.</p>
            <p>And 1ſt. To You, <hi>My Reverend Fathers and Brethren in the Miniſtry;</hi> Permit me to ſay, That God who has choſen us from among our Brethren, to come near to him, and to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in Things Sacred, has in ſo doing, highly honour'd us. We are engaged in a Calling, which tho' mean and deſpicable in the Eye of a carnal World, yet would be no Diſgrace, but an Honour to Angels, to be employ'd in. To be workers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with God in that Building of Mercy, the Plan of which was projected in the Depth of infinite Wiſdom, from the Morning of Eternity: to be employed in the Quality of Ambaſſadors, to negociate between the King of Kings, and immortal Souls, about Matters of the greateſt Moment: What higher Honour! And as ours is a Station of high Honour, ſo of high Truſt and Importance; the great Head of the Church has intruſted us with Souls which are his choiceſt Jewels, and on whom he ſet ſo high a Value, as to ſhed his precious Blood for them: He puts ſuch Confidence in us, as to employ us in the Quality of Officers, to head his Soldiers in the War againſt Earth and Hell. Let us think of the Honour, and be humble; and let us think of the Truſt, and be faithful: Let us remember that all is Grace, that we have nothing but what we have received, that one main Reaſon why we are thus highly honour'd, is, that by our Meanneſs God might take Occaſion the more
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:007454_0022_102D724CC89D1BD0"/>illuſtriouſly to diſplay the Glory of his Grace; That he has put his Treaſure in earthen Veſſels, that it might the more evidently appear, that the Excellency of the Power is of God, and not of Man. Let us beware of any Action which looks like betraying our Truſt; on the contrary, let us be faithful to God and Souls; let us labour daily in the Uſe of Means, for an Increaſe of Faith, for more Love to God and Souls, more Mortification and Self-denial, more Chriſtian Courage and Steadineſs of Mind, more Skilfulneſs in the Knowledge and Expertneſs in the Uſe of our ſpiritual Weapons: In a Word, more of all thoſe Qualifications whereby we ſhall be fitted to <hi>endure Hardneſs, as good Soldiers of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And whatever miniſterial Qualifications it has pleaſed the Giver of every good Gift, and perfect, to beſtow on us, let us not bury them in the Earth, nor hide them in the unprofitable Napkin: On the contrary, let us ſtir up the Gifts that are in us; being inſtant in Seaſon, and out of Seaſon; not thinking much of our hard Study or Toil, or bodily Fatigue and Expence of Spirits, if ſo be, that thereby we may do any Service; not counting even our Lives dear, ſo that we may finiſh our Courſe with Joy, and the Miniſtry committed to us of the Lord Jeſus. Let us remember that there will be Time enough to reſt in Heaven, and hence, let us be willing now to labour; and let us not only be willing to work our ſelves, but let us do what we can to encourage others in their Work: Let all Chriſt's faithful Miniſters endeavour to ſtrengthen one another's Hands.</p>
            <p>If the Soldiers, but eſpecially the Officers in Chriſt's Army, begin to turn their Swords againſt one another, they are like to be an eaſy Prey to the common Enemy. O that this were duly laid to Heart! It would powerfully Influence us to cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate that ſtrict Unity, which (through the divine Bleſſing) would greatly ſtrengthen the common Cauſe, which would render us fair as the Moon, clear as the Sun, terrible as an Army with Banners.</p>
            <p>And to animate us to exert our ſelves to the utmoſt in our Maſter's Cauſe; let us conſider that our Charge is weighty; our Account will be ſolemn; and that the Time when we muſt make it up, is faſt approaching. Let us with the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> remember <hi>that we muſt ſhortly put off this our Tabernacle.</hi> Some of us, (it's likely) have almoſt done; a few Years, or it may be Months, and the preſent Scene with Reſpect to us, will for ever ſhut. O then, let us do ſpeedily and with our Might, whatever our Hands find to do: Let
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:007454_0023_102D72620BFC3108"/>us crowd in as much Service as we can, in the few remaining Days we have yet left. And to keep up our Spirits under the Coldneſs and Ingratitude of the World, the Contradiction and Oppoſition of unreaſonable Men, all our Unſucceſsfulneſs in our Work, all the Temptations that ariſe from Satan and our own Hearts; In a Word, all the Difficulties of the Campaign; let us look forward by Faith to that happy approaching Day, <hi>when Chriſt who is our Life ſhall appear, and we alſo ſhall appear with him in Glory; when they that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Firmament, and they that turn many to Righteouſneſs, as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To Candidates: I would ſay, <hi>My dear Brethren,</hi> we who have been acting our Part as Officers in Chriſt's Camp, muſt ſoon move off the Stage: Theſe Mouths that now ſpeak to you, muſt in a ſhort Time be ſtop'd with the Duſt of Death; and we have our Eyes on you to ſucceed us. 'Tis you, and ſuch as you, that muſt fill up our vacant Places, in the Camp of the Saints. Bleſſed be God, for ſome agreeable Proſpect of a Succeſſion! Be exhorted, <hi>Brethren,</hi> to labour for thoſe Qualifications by which you may be fitted to <hi>endure Hardneſs, as good Soldiers of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> and in order hereto, give your ſelves to Reading, to cloſe Study, and to Prayer; and let all your Endeavours be uſed in Subſerviency to the promiſed Aids of the divine Spirit. Beware of a proud, ſelf-ſufficient Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: Remember that a ſcriptural Biſhop muſt not be a Novice, leſt being lifted up with Pride, he fall into the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the Devil: Don't eſteem your ſelves to be already well enough qualified for the great Work of the Goſpel-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry; but on the contrary, endeavour to maintain a low Opinion of any Attainments you have already arrived at; and forgetting the Things that are behind, be preſſing forward. Let it be your daily Labour, to add to the Fund of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, either by getting ſome new Ideas, or thoſe you have, better digeſted: And let the governing Principle in all your Endeavours, be love to God, and Concern for his Glory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I'd addreſs my ſelf to the Candidate now to be ſolemnly ſet apart to the Work of the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>You are now, <hi>Sir,</hi> about to engage in a Station of great Importance, and great Difficulty: You are to have the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the everlaſting Goſpel, and the adminiſtring the Seal of the New-Covenant committed to your Truſt: You are to have the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven put into your Hand,
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:007454_0024_102D91FFF37C4088"/>with Authority miniſterially to open and ſhut, in the Name of him who openeth, and no man ſhutteth, and who ſhutteth, and no Man openeth: You are about to take the Charge of a Number of immortal Souls, each of which is of more Value than a World; on this Condition, that if any ſhould periſh by your Neglect, it is to be requir'd at your Hand. I truſt you have known theſe many Years, what it is to be a Soldier of Chriſt, which is a Character that belongs to every Chriſtian; and that you are not now to begin the War with the Devil, the Fleſh and the World: But that you are this Day, in ſomewhat of a peculiar Senſe, taking up Arms againſt Satan and his Kingdom, <hi>viz.</hi> as an Officer in Chriſt's Camp. And you may reaſonably expect to have the Power and Policy of Earth and Hell engaged againſt you. You are engaging in the miniſterial Work, in an evil Day, a Day of Trouble and of Rebuke, and of Blaſphemy; a Day when Religion appears to be low, and the Enemies of Chriſt and his Cauſe are apparently prevailing; when a Spirit of Conviction ſeems to be much withheld, and the Waters of the Sanctuary to have loſt (in a great Meaſure) their healing Virtue; ſo that the Ways of <hi>Zion</hi> mourn, and faithful Miniſters with heavy Hearts complain, that they have laboured in vain, and ſpent their Strength for nought: A Day, when many real Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans appear in a ſad Degree, to have loſt the lively affecting Views of divine Things; when a worldly Spirit prevails, ſo that there's too much Reaſon for the Apoſtle's Complaint, That all Men mind their own Things, and none the Things that are Chriſt's: when Inſtances of awful Impenitency and Hardneſs of Heart abound; when Sinners ſin with a high Hand, make light of their Danger, mocking at Fear, and laughing at the ſhaking of God's Spear. In a Word, the Charge is weighty, and the Days are evil; and to undertake ſuch a Charge, at ſuch a Time, is enough to make a frail Mortal tremble.</p>
            <p>And I make no doubt, <hi>My Brother,</hi> but your Spirits are weighted with it, and have been ſo before this Day; that you have been carefully counting the Coſt, and revolving the Difficulties in your Mind. I mention theſe Difficulties not to diſcourage you, but on the contrary, to animate you to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to your Work with the greater Vigour and Reſolution: And for your Encouragement, I ſhall propoſe a few animating Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="23" facs="unknown:007454_0025_102D92024B3867F0"/>
1. Conſider that though it is a very difficult, yet it is withal, a very honourable Work you are engaged in. In the Time of the flouriſhing of the <hi>Roman</hi> Common-Wealth, it was thought a high Honour to fight under their Banner: But you have the Honour of being enliſted this Day, and this, in a Place of ſome conſiderable Diſtinction too, under the Banner of him who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, who eſteems of the Monarchs of the Earth, as Graſshoppers. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> eſteem'd this Honour, an high Favour conferred on him, when he ſaid, Eph. 3.8. <hi>To me who am leſs then the leaſt of all Saints, is this Grace given; that I ſhould preach among the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>the unſearchable Riches of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider that you are to have your Maſter's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with you in the whole of your Miniſterial Work. It's true, the Work is great and difficult, and you may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend your ſelf weak and very unequal to it: But remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you have a ſtrong Lord to depend upon; and that as the Work you have to be employ'd in, is his Work, on him therefore you may with a humble Confidence depend, for all that Aſſiſtance you have need of; for who goeth a Warfare at any Time at his own Charges? He can give you the Wiſdom of the Serpent, as well as the Simplicity of the Dove; whereby you ſhall be able to countermine and baffle the moſt inſiduous Plots of the Devil and his Inſtruments, though they ſhould work like Moles under Ground, and dig deep as Hell to accompliſh their Deſigns. He can furniſh you with a brave, heroick, undaunted Spirit; whereby you ſhall be enabled to ſet your Face like a Flint, and with a calm intrepid Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, to face the moſt formidable Aſſaults of the Enemy. He can make you a fenced brazen Wall, againſt which, though your Enemies ſhould fight, yet they ſhall not be able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail. He can temper your Zeal and Courage with Humility and Prudence, and Self-denial: In a Word, he can give you the Chriſtian Temper in all its lovely Branches; ſo that you ſhall be able to contend for the Faith of Chriſt, with the Spirit of Chriſt. Did I ſay he can? I may add, he will, if you look on him by Faith, or depend aright upon him; for he has ſaid, <hi>My Grace is ſufficient for thee,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.9. This Promiſe belongs to every faithful Miniſter to the End, as well as to him to whom it was firſt made.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider that if you be faithful to your Colours, you are ſure of the Victory. What Soldier would not fight with
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:007454_0026_102D920521C93B20"/>Courage, who is ſure of a compleat Victory at laſt? But this is the Caſe of the <hi>good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It muſt be ſo, for he has Omnipotence on his Side; the Captain of his Salvation, is a King mighty in Battle, he will tread his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in his Anger, and trample them in his Fury; their Blood ſhall be on his Garments, and he will ſtain all his Raiment.</p>
            <p>The moſt formidable Party they can poſſibly make, is but as Briars and Thorns, before devouring Flames: If then he erect his Banner in the Name of Chriſt, he ſhall do valiantly; if he be ſtrong in the Grace which is in Chriſt Jeſus, he ſhall both do great Things, and ſhall ſtill prevail.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider that there is a glorious Reward conſequent upon miniſterial Faithfulneſs. It's true, I cannot propoſe any great earthly Reward for your Encouragement: on the contrary, many faithful Miniſters have been obliged to endure Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in this as well as in other Reſpects, to content themſelves with mean Fare, and ſome have been pinched for want of pure Neceſſaries. And altho' Miniſters ſhould have a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency, God having ordained, that they who preach the Goſpel ſhould live by the Goſpel; yet it would be unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable for them to expect to live in the Pomp and Splendor of temporal Princes, ſeeing their Lord has told them, <hi>That his Kingdom is not of this World.</hi> But conſider, that altho' you have no great ſecular Inducement, yet you have a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of a higher Nature than the Crowns of Princes, and the peculiar Treaſure of Kings and Provinces, <hi>viz. A Crown of Glory that fadeth not away.</hi> Think my Brother of that Day which is approaching, when the chief Shepherd ſhall appear, and you ſhall appear with him in Glory; when you ſhall have a Number of ſaved, glorified Souls, all ſhining in the Beauties of Holineſs, like ſo many radiant Gems to adorn your Crown of Glory. O think of that happy approaching Day! <hi>when they that are wiſe ſhall ſhine as the Brightneſs of the Firmament, and they that turn many to Righteouſneſs as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi> Or though it ſhould be your hard Lot to labour all your Days in vain, and ſpend your Strength for nought, and never to be inſtrumental of turning any to Righteouſneſs, (which I cannot think your Maſter will ſuffer to be the Caſe); Yet even in this Caſe, remember that your Judgment is with the Lord, and your Work with your God; and that your faithful Endeavours will be well accepted.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="25" facs="unknown:007454_0027_102D9206CC92B448"/>
5. Conſider that the more you do in your Station, and the more Hardneſs you are called to ſuffer in the Cauſe of your glorious Captain; it is likely the more you'll enjoy of his gracious ſpiritual Preſence. When the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was called before <hi>Nero,</hi> no Man ſtood with him, but all Men forſook him; yet he tell us, <hi>that then the Lord ſtood by him, and ſtrengthened him, ſo that he was delivered out of the Mouth of the Lion,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.16, 17. It was when the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> was baniſhed into the obſcure remote Iſle of <hi>Patmos,</hi> for the Word of God, and for the Teſtimony which he held, that he was favoured with thoſe glorious Viſions and Revelations, which you have on Record in the laſt Book of the New-Teſtament. If your Lord call you to great Trials, you ſhall have proportional Incomes of Grace; you ſhall be able to adopt the Experience of the Apoſtle, and his Fellow-Soldiers, 2 Cor. 1.5. <hi>As the Sufferings of Chriſt abound in us, ſo our Conſolation alſo aboundeth by Chriſt:</hi> So that you'll be qualified from what you feel, to unriddle theſe Paradoxes, 2 Cor. 6.9, 10. <hi>As dying, and behold we live; as chaſtned, and not killed; as ſorrowful, yet always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joicing; as having nothing, and yet poſſeſſing all Things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, <hi>Sir,</hi> are animating Conſiderations: under the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of them addreſs your ſelf to your Work, with a cheerful Courage and Vigour. Take Heed to your Miniſtry, that you fulfil it: Take Heed to your Self, and to your Doctrine; for in doing this, you will both ſave your ſelf, and them that hear you.</p>
            <p>I ſhould next addreſs my ſelf to the <hi>People,</hi> who are about to receive the Candidate for their Miniſter, were they preſent. They had appointed ſome of their Number to act in their Name, on the ſolemn Occaſion; but it pleaſed that wiſe Sovereign, who does every Thing for the beſt, to prevent their coming. However, altho' not perſonally preſent, we have their Concurrence in the Matter. Had they been here, I ſhould have ſaid to them; That after a ſufficient Time for Trial, they had proceeded to give a Call to this our Brother; and that ſaid Call had been proceeded in with as much Order as their Situation and other Circumſtances would admit of: that we rejoice with them, in that after a Series of Events, in which they have been liable to a Variety of Difficulties, and in which many Changes have paſſed over them; that a bountiful Lord is at Length about to beſtow on them a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, who we believe has obtained Help of God to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and who we truſt will be enabled to <hi>endure Hardneſs as</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="unknown:007454_0028_102D9208FA8BDE88"/>
               <hi>a good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> That as they had been hearing that he is engaging in a difficult Wurk, ſo we hope that they will not by any Part of their Conduct, wilfully add to his Difficulties: On the contrary, that they would yield him that limited Subjection and Obedience in the Lord, which they had ſolemnly promiſed in their Call; regarding and obeying him as having the Rule over them, and who watches for their Souls as one who muſt give an Account: That they would remember whoſe Name he comes in, and whoſe Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage he is charged with; and would eſteem him very highly in Love for his Maſter's Sake, and for his Work's Sake; eſpecially, that they would receive that Chriſt and Salvation he offers to them, as they would not oblige him to appear as a ſwift Witneſs againſt them at the great Day of Accompts: That they would be tender as to the expoſing any Frailties they may ſee in their Miniſter; eſpecially ſuch Things as they have Reaſon to think are no more then Indiſcretions, proceeding from meer Inadvertency, without any criminal Intention; that they would kindly draw the Veil of Charity over ſuch Things: That they would wreſtle with God in Prayer on his Behalf, that he may be in every Reſpect an able and ſucceſsful Miniſter of the New-Teſtament. And finally, that as he miniſters to them in Spirituals, that they would do to their utmoſt, cheerfully and liberally to miniſter to him in Temporals.</p>
            <p>May the Lord make Miniſters and People mutual Bleſſings to one another; that ſo the happy Day may come, when both he that ſoweth, and they that reap, may rejoice together.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
