<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Minutes of conferences, held at Easton, in October, 1758, with the chief sachems and warriors of the Mohawks, Oneidoes, Onondagoes, Cayugas, Senecas, Tuscaroras, Tuteloes, Skaniadaradigronos, consisting of the Nanitcokes and Conoys, who now make one nation; Chugnuts, Delawares, Unamies, Mahickanders, or Mohickons; Minisinks, and Wapingers, or Pumptons.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04">2009-04.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N06428</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N06428</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 8156</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APV6090</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">8156</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99001541</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 8156.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N06428)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 8156)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 8156)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Minutes of conferences, held at Easton, in October, 1758, with the chief sachems and warriors of the Mohawks, Oneidoes, Onondagoes, Cayugas, Senecas, Tuscaroras, Tuteloes, Skaniadaradigronos, consisting of the Nanitcokes and Conoys, who now make one nation; Chugnuts, Delawares, Unamies, Mahickanders, or Mohickons; Minisinks, and Wapingers, or Pumptons.</title>
                  <author>Pennsylvania. Treaties, etc. 1758.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32, [1] p. ;  (fol.) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by B. Franklin, and D. Hall, at the new-printing-office, near the market.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCCLVIII. [1758]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Minutes of the treaty proceedings between the province of Pennsylvania and neighbouring Indian tribes.</note>
                  <note>Title vignette: province seal.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Indians of North America --  Treaties.</term>
               <term>Treaties.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:008156_0000_102E3E40CDF26388"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="unknown:008156_0001_102E3E4257D68DE8"/>
            <p>MINUTES OF CONFERENCES, HELD AT <hi>EASTON,</hi> In <hi>OCTOBER,</hi> 1758,</p>
            <p>With the Chief SACHEMS and WARRIORS of the <hi>Mohawks, Oneidoes, Onondagoes, Cayugas, Senecas, Tuſcaroras, Tutcloes, Skaniada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radigronos,</hi> conſiſting of the <hi>Nanticokes</hi> and <hi>Conoys,</hi> who now make one Nation; <hi>Chugnuts, Delawares, Unamies, Mahickanders,</hi> or <hi>Mohickons; Miniſinks,</hi> and <hi>Wapingers,</hi> or <hi>Pumptons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>PHILADELPHIA:</hi> Printed and Sold by B. FRANKLIN, and D. HALL, at the <hi>New-Printing-Office,</hi> near the Market. MDCCLVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="conference_minutes">
            <pb n="2" facs="unknown:008156_0002_102E3E4525A32990"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="unknown:008156_0003_102E3E49F073CB18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Minutes of Conferences,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>At a</hi> MEETING <hi>held at</hi> Eaſton, <hi>on the Seventh of</hi> October, 1758.</head>
               <p>PRESENT,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Honourable</hi> WILLIAM DENNY, <hi>
                           <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Lieutenant-Governor of the Province of</hi> Pennſylvania,</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Eſquires.</head>
                           <item>LAWRENCE GROWDON,</item>
                           <item>RICHARD PETERS,</item>
                           <item>LYN-FORD LARDNER,</item>
                           <item>BENJAMIN CHEW,</item>
                           <item>JOHN MIFFLIN.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1758</label> THE Governor and Council coming to Town this Afternoon, <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with <hi>Moſes Tittamy, Daniel, Teepyuſcung,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac Stille,</hi> waited on his Honour, and made the uſual Salutations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brother,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am very glad to ſee you here again; you may remember that we have already made Peace, and you deſired me to halloo loud, and give Notice of it to all the <hi>Indians</hi> round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</p>
               <p>I have ſpoke loud, and raiſed my Voice, and all the <hi>Indians</hi> have heard me as far as the <hi>Twightwees,</hi> and have regarded it, and are now come to this Place.</p>
               <p>I bid you welcome, and join with me in caſting up our Eyes to Heaven, and praying the Bleſſing of the Supream Being on our Endeavours.</p>
               <p>According to our uſual Cuſtom, I, with this String, wipe the Duſt and Sweat off your Face, and clear your Eyes, and pick the Briars out of your Legs, and deſire you will pull the Briars out of the Legs of the <hi>Indians</hi> that are come here, and anoint one of them with your healing Oil, and I will anoint the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Governor returned him Thanks for the Viſit and his good Advice, which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to comply with, and appointed a Meeting in the Morning for that Purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>At a</hi> CONFERENCE <hi>held in the Town of</hi> Eaſton, <hi>on the</hi> 8<hi>th of</hi> October, 1758.</head>
               <p>PRESENT,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Honourable</hi> WILLIAM DENNY, <hi>
                           <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Lieutenant-Governor,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Eſquires, Members of the Governor's Council.</head>
                           <item>LAWRENCE GROWDON,</item>
                           <item>WILLIAM LOGAN,</item>
                           <item>RICHARD PETERS,</item>
                           <item>LYN-FORD LARDNER,</item>
                           <item>BENJAMIN CHEW,</item>
                           <item>JOHN MIFFLIN,</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Eſquires, Committee of the Houſe of Repreſentations.</head>
                           <item>ISAAC NORRIS,</item>
                           <item>JOSEPH FOX,</item>
                           <item>JOSEPH GALLOWAY,</item>
                           <item>JOHN HUGHES,</item>
                           <item>DANIEL ROBERDEAU,</item>
                           <item>AMOS STRICKLAND.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Eſquires, Commiſſioners for</hi> Indian <hi>Affairs in the Province of</hi> New-Jerſey.</head>
                           <item>CHARLES READ,</item>
                           <item>JACOB SPICER,</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="4" facs="unknown:008156_0004_102E3E4FDA4D42D8"/>
                        <hi>A Number of Magiſtrates and Freeholders, of this and the neighbouring Province, and of the Citizens of the City of</hi> Philadelphia, <hi>chiefly of the People called</hi> Quakers.</item>
                     <item>GEORGE CROGHAN, <hi>
                           <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Deputy Agent for</hi> Indian <hi>Affairs, under Sir</hi> WILLIAM JOHNSON.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>
                              <hi>INDIANS of ſeveral Nations,</hi> viz.</head>
                           <item>MOHAWKS. Nichas, <hi>or</hi> Karaghtadi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, <hi>with one Woman and two Boys,</hi> 4</item>
                           <item>ONEIDOES. Thomas King, Anagaraghiry, Aſſanyquou, <hi>with 3 Warrior Captains,</hi> 6 <hi>Warriors, and</hi> 33 <hi>Women and Children,</hi> 45</item>
                           <item>ONONDAGOES, Aſſaradonguas, <hi>with</hi> 9 <hi>Men, and</hi> 9 <hi>Women and Children,</hi> 19</item>
                           <item>CAYUGAS, Toka<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ion, <hi>with</hi> 8 <hi>Men, and</hi> 11 <hi>Women and Children,</hi> 20</item>
                           <item>SENECAS. Takeaghſado, Tagaſhata, <hi>or</hi> Segachſadon, <hi>chief Man, with 7 other Chiefs,</hi> 37 <hi>other Men,</hi> 28 <hi>Women, and ſeveral Children, in all,</hi> 83</item>
                           <item>TUSCARORAS, Unata, <hi>alias</hi> Jonathan, <hi>with</hi> 5 <hi>Men,</hi> 12 <hi>Women, and</hi> 2 <hi>Children,</hi> 20</item>
                           <item>NANTICOKES <hi>and</hi> CONOYS, <hi>now one Nation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                              </hi> Robert White, <hi>alias</hi> Wolahocumy, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaamokas, <hi>alias</hi> Charles, <hi>with</hi> 16 <hi>Men,</hi> 20 <hi>Women, and</hi> 18 <hi>Children,</hi> 56</item>
                           <item>Kandt, <hi>alias</hi> Laſt Night, <hi>with</hi> 9 <hi>Men,</hi> 10 <hi>Women, and</hi> 1 <hi>Child,</hi> 21</item>
                           <item>TU<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>LOES. Cakanonekoanos, <hi>alias</hi> Big Arm, Aſſwagarat, <hi>with</hi> 6 <hi>Men, and</hi> 3 <hi>Women,</hi> 11</item>
                           <item>CHUGNUTS. 10 <hi>Men, and</hi> 20 <hi>Women and Children,</hi> 30</item>
                           <item>CH<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>HOHOCKES, <hi>alias</hi> DELAWARES <hi>and</hi> UNAMIES. Teedynſcung, <hi>with ſundry Men, Women and Children,</hi> 60</item>
                           <item>MUNSIES, <hi>or</hi> MINISINKS. Egohohowen, <hi>with ſundry Men, Women and Children,</hi> 35</item>
                           <item>MOHICKONS. Abraham, <hi>or</hi> Mammatuckan, <hi>with ſeveral Men, Women and Children,</hi> 56</item>
                           <item>WAPIN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>, <hi>or</hi> PUMPTONS. Nimham, Aquaywochtu, <hi>with ſundry Men, Women and Children, in all,</hi>—47</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>In all,</hi> 507</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>CONRAD WEISER, <hi>
                           <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Provincial Interpreter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Captain</hi> HENRY MONTOUR, <hi>Interpreter in the</hi> Six Nation <hi>and</hi> Delaware <hi>Languages.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Delaware Indians, <hi>Interpreters in the</hi> Delaware <hi>Language.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <item>STEPHEN CALVIN,</item>
                           <item>ISAAC STILLE,</item>
                           <item>MOSES TITTAMY,</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Governor opened the Conferences with the following Ceremonies, addreſſing himſelf to all the</hi> Indians <hi>preſent, of every Nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IT gives me great Pleaſure to ſee ſo many of you, and of ſo many different Nations, at this Council Fire. I bid you heartily Welcome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With this String I wipe the Sweat and Duſt out of your Eyes, that you may ſee your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns Faces, and look chearful. With this String I take all Bitterneſs out of your Breaſt, as well as every Thing diſagreeable that may have gathered there, in order that you may ſpeak perfectly free and open to us. With this String I gather the Blood, and take it away from the Council Seats, that your Clothes may not be ſtained, nor your Minds any Ways diſturbed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three Strings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Weiſer</hi> interpreted the Subſtance of this Speech, and ſaying his Memory did not ſerve him to remember the ſeveral Ceremonies in Uſe on this Occaſion, he deſired <hi>Nichas,</hi> a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hawk</hi> Chief, to do it for him, which he did, and it was afterwards interpreted by Captain <hi>Henry Montour,</hi> in the <hi>Delaware</hi> Language, to <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> and the <hi>Delawares.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After a ſhort Pauſe, <hi>Tagaſhata,</hi> the <hi>Seneca</hi> Chief, roſe up, and repeating, as uſual, each Paragraph diſtincty as ſpoke by the Governor, he returned Thanks, and went through the ſame Ceremonies to the Governor, Council, and People of the Province, adding on the laſt String, that their Great Grandfathers had told them, that they had made a Road for them to travel to their Brethren the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and that whenever it ſhould be ſtopped, they would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a poor People. They were very glad to find the Road open to their Brethren, and ſhould take Care to preſerve it ſo on their Side.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three Strings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After Mr. <hi>Weiſer</hi> had delivered this in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and it was interpreted in the <hi>Delaware</hi> Language by <hi>Moſes Tittamy, Takeaghſado,</hi> or <hi>Tagaſhata,</hi> Proceeded;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brother</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="unknown:008156_0005_102E3E5164D8F7D8"/>
                  <hi>Brother</hi> Onas,</p>
               <p>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this Belt you ſent an Invitation to us to come to <hi>Pennſylvania,</hi> which reached our Towns about the Time that the Leaves put out laſt Spring, but we were then ſo much alarmed by the <hi>French,</hi> who were near us, that we could not then leave our Country. Some little Time ago we received another Belt from Sir <hi>William Johnſon,</hi> which he informed us was ſent to him by you, to be forwarded to us, to enquire into the Reaſons why we did not come to you, according to your firſt Invitation, and Sir <hi>William Johnſon</hi> deſired us to come here to meet you in Council; upon which we immediately aroſe, and came as ſoon as we could to your Council Fire, and now we are here, as you ſee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two Belts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brother,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is another Belt, by which we were invited lately to come to a Council Fire, that was kindled in an Iſland near the Sea: This ſurprized us, as we never heard of a Council Fire in an Iſland.
<note n="*" place="bottom">Meaning <hi>Burlington.</hi>
                  </note> We know of no Council Fires, but the old Council Fire at <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi> and the great Council Fire in <hi>Albany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here be laid the Belt on the Table.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then taking four other Strings of Wampum, he ſaid, Theſe were ſent to us by <hi>Nichas,</hi> the <hi>Mchawk</hi> Chief, with a Meſſage, that he was arrived in this Province, and deſired we would comply with the Invitation, and come down.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here be laid the four Strings on the Table</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nichas</hi> having acknowledged the Meſſage, and taken up the Strings, <hi>Tagaſhata</hi> concluded, ſaying, Theſe are your Belts, by which we were invited to this Council Fire; and as we are now come, we return them, and deſire to ſee the Belts that were ſent by us, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly one, on which were ſeveral Images of Men holding each other by the Hand.</p>
               <p>The Governor replied, that he would enquire for the Belts ſent by them, and they ſhould be returned.</p>
               <p>The Subſtance of theſe laſt Speeches of <hi>Tagaſhata</hi> was interpreted to <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> and the <hi>Delawares.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>October</hi> 9, 1758.</head>
               <p>THIS Morning his Excellency Governor <hi>Bernard</hi> arrived at <hi>Eaſton,</hi> and deſired a Meeting of the <hi>Indians,</hi> in order to make them the uſual Compliments; but was acquainted by Mr. <hi>Weiſer,</hi> that they were then in Council, deliberating on Matters neceſſary to be adjuſted before the Meeting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>October</hi> 10, 1758.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Indian</hi> Chiefs continued in Council the greateſt Part of this Day, and deſired the Governors would not be impatient.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>October</hi> 11, 1758.</head>
               <p>THIS Morning the <hi>Indian</hi> Chiefs communicated to the Governors, by Mr. <hi>Weiſer,</hi> the Buſineſs they had been conſulting upon, and ſaid they had concluded to ſpeak to us this Forenoon. The Governors waited till One o'Clock, expecting the <hi>Indians</hi> to meet them, being told that they were gathering together for that Purpoſe; but they not coming, after ſeveral Meſſages ſent to haſten them, it was agreed to meet punctually at Four o'Clock.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>At a</hi> CONFERENCE <hi>held at</hi> Eaſton <hi>with the</hi> Indians, October 11, 1758. P. M.</head>
                  <p>PRESENT,
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Governor</hi> DENNY, <hi>with his Council, and the ſeveral</hi> Pennſylvania <hi>Gentlemen, as before.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Governor</hi> BERNARD.</item>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <head>
                                 <hi>Eſquires,</hi> Indian <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for</hi> Jerſey.</head>
                              <item>ANDREW JOHNSON,</item>
                              <item>CHARLES READ,</item>
                              <item>JOHN STEVENS,</item>
                              <item>JACOB SPICER,</item>
                              <item>WILLIAM FOSTER,</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TAGASHATA,</hi> the <hi>Seneca</hi> Chief, intending to ſpeak firſt, on Behalf of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> had laid ſome Belts and Strings in Order on the Table.</p>
                  <p>As ſoon as the Company ſat down, <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> holding out a String, ſaid he had ſomething to deliver, and deſired he might be heard firſt of all. Mr. <hi>Croghan</hi> requeſted <pb n="6" facs="unknown:008156_0006_102E3E542A0F6908"/>to know, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> what he was going to ſay was the reſult of the <hi>Delaware</hi> Council, and if it was their Deſire it ſhould be ſpoke firſt; but no Anſwer was given him as to this.</p>
                  <p>Governor <hi>Bernard</hi> ſignifying his Deſire to bid the <hi>Indians</hi> welcome, and ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> mention to them the Buſineſs he came upon, it was agreed he ſhould ſpeak firſt, which he did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am glad to ſee ſo many of you met together, to cultivate Peace with your Brethren and old Friends the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> I heartily bid you welcome; and wiſh that the good Work for which you are now aſſembled, may proſper in your Hands, and have that Succeſs, which your wiſe Men, and all that wiſh you well, muſt deſire, as a Thing much to your Advantage.</p>
                  <p>The Situation of the Province over which I preſide, and the Diſpoſition of its People, have hitherto afforded very little Occaſion for Treaties with the neighbouring <hi>Indians</hi>; but having, ſome Months ago, ſent a Meſſage to the <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> I received a Meſſage from our Brethren the <hi>Senecas,</hi> and <hi>Cayugas,</hi> wherein they take upon them to anſwer my Meſſage to the <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> and deſire that I would meet them at the Council Fire burning at this Place.</p>
                  <p>It is not uſual for the King's Governors to go out of their Provinces to attend Treaties; but I am glad to have an Opportunity of ſhewing my good Diſpoſition to eſtabliſh Peace and Friendſhip with my Neighbours; and therefore I have waved all Forms, and am come here, according to the Invitation I received at <hi>Burlington.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To you therefore, our Brethren the <hi>Senecas</hi> and <hi>Cayugas,</hi> and your Nephews the <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> I now ſpeak, and deſire that you would take into your moſt ſerions Conſideration, my Meſ;<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to the <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> your Meſſage to me, and my Anſwer thereto, and let me know what we are to expect from you.</p>
                  <p>What is paſt, we are willing to forget; but I muſt remind you, that if you are diſpoſed to be our Friends for the future, you ſhould give us that Proof of your Sincerity which I have deſired in my Anſwer to your Meſſage, and return us the Captives that have been tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en out of our Province, and are now within your Power; this ſhould be one of the firſt Steps, and will be the beſt that can be taken, towards reſtoring and confirming that Brotherly Love and Friendſhip between us, which I am convinced will be for the mutual Benefit of all Parties.</p>
                  <p>This was interpreted in the <hi>Six Nation</hi> Language by Mr. <hi>Weiſer,</hi> and in the <hi>Delaware</hi> by Mr. <hi>Stephen Calvin,</hi> the <hi>Indian</hi> Schoolmaſter in <hi>Weſt-Jerſey.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then</hi> Teedyuſcung <hi>ſpoke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I deſire all of you who are preſent, will give Ear to me. As you, my Brethren, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired me to call all the Nations who live back, I have done ſo; I have given the Halloo, and ſuch as have heard me are preſent. Now, if you have any Thing to ſay to them, or they to you, you muſt ſit and talk together.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſit by, only to hear and ſee what you ſay to one another; for I have ſaid what I have to ſay to the Governor of <hi>Pennſylvania,</hi> who ſits here; he knows what has paſſed between us. I have made known to him the Reaſon why I ſtruck him. Now I and the Governor have made up theſe Differences between him and me, and I think we have done it, as far as we can, for our future Peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A String.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The above Speech was interpreted in the <hi>Six Nation</hi> Language.</p>
                  <p>Tagaſhata <hi>then roſe up and ſpoke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren the Governors, and your Councils,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It has pleaſed the moſt High that we meet together here with chearful Countenances, and a good deal of Satisfaction; and as publick Buſineſs requires grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Conſideration, and the Day is almoſt ſpent, I chuſe to ſpeak early To-morrow Morning.</p>
                  <p>The Governors anſwered, that they ſhould be glad to give all the Diſpatch poſſible to this good Work they were engaged in; and deſired the Chiefs would fix the Time of Meeting; but they declined it, ſaying, they were unacquainted with Hours, but would give Notice when they were ready.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <pb n="7" facs="unknown:008156_0007_102E3E55B0E21D48"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>At a</hi> CONFERENCE <hi>Held at</hi> Eaſton, <hi>on the 12th of</hi> October, 1758.</head>
               <p>PRESENT,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> GOVERNORS,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Gentlemen of their Councils,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>And others, as before.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>TAGASHATA,</hi> the <hi>Seneca</hi> Chief, taking the Strings and Belt of Wampum which Governor <hi>Bernard</hi> gave Yeſterday, repeated, according to the <hi>Indian</hi> Cuſtom, the Particulars of his Speech, and then added,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We approve of every Article mentioned to us Yeſterday by the Governor of <hi>Jerſey,</hi> all that be ſaid is very good; we look upon his Meſſage to us as a Commiſſion and Requeſt from him, that we ſhould bring Matters to a good Concluſion with our Couſins the <hi>Miniſinks.</hi> They themſelves ſent for us to do the ſame Thing, on their Behalf, and, at their Requeſt, we came here, have taken it in Hand, and will uſe our utmoſt Endeavours to bring about the good Work which Governor <hi>Bernard</hi> deſires, and do not doubt but it will be done to his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Satisfaction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I now ſpeak at the Requeſt of <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> and our Nephews the <hi>Delawares,</hi> living at <hi>Wyomink,</hi> and on the Waters of the River <hi>Saſquehannah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We now remove the Hatchet out of your Heads that was ſtruck into them by our Confine the <hi>Delawares,</hi> it was a <hi>French</hi> Hatchet that they unfortunately made uſe of, by the Inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>French</hi> we take it out of your Heads, and bury it under Ground, where it ſhall always, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and never be taken up again. Our Couſins the <hi>Delawares</hi> have aſſured us they will never think of War againſt their Brethren, the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> any more, but employ their Thought about Peace, and cultivating Friendſhip with them, and never ſuffer Enmity againſt them to enter into their Minds again.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Delawares</hi> deſired us to ſay this for them by this Belt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Nephews, the <hi>Miniſink Indians,</hi> and three other different Tribe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of that Nation, have, at laſt, liſtened to us, and taken our Advice, and laid down the Hatchet they had taken up againſt their Brethren the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> They told us they had received it from the <hi>French,</hi> but had already laid it down, and would return it to them again.</p>
               <p>They aſſured us, they would never uſe it any more againſt you, but would follow our Advice, and entreated us to uſe our utmoſt Endeavours to reconcile them to you their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, declaring they were ſorry for what they had done, and deſired it might be forgotten, and they would for ever cultivate a good Friendſhip with you. Theſe Declarations were made by the principal Warriors of Four Tribes of the <hi>Miniſink Indians</hi> at giving us this Belt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then, taking eight Strings of Black Wampum, he proceeded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We let you know that we have not only brought about this Union with our Nephews on the Waters of the River <hi>Saſquebannab,</hi> but alſo have ſent Meſſages to our Nephews the <hi>Dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares</hi> and <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> and to thoſe likewiſe of our own Nations, who are on the <hi>Ohio,</hi> under the Influence of the <hi>French.</hi> We have told all theſe that they muſt lay down the <hi>French</hi> Hatchet, and be reconciled to their Brethren the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and never more employ it againſt them, and we hope they will take our Advice. We the <hi>Mohawks, Senecas,</hi> and <hi>Onondagas,</hi> deliver this String of Wampum to remove the Hatchet out of your Heads, that has been ſtruck into them by the <hi>Ohio Indians,</hi> in order to lay a Foundation for Peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eight Strings of Black Wampum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tagaſhata</hi> ſat down, and then the <hi>Cayuga</hi> Chief, <hi>Tokanio,</hi> aroſe and ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſpeak in Behalf of the younger Nations, Part of, and confederated with, the <hi>Six Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, viz.</hi> The <hi>Cayugas, Oneidoes, Tuſcaroras, Tuteloes, Nanticokes,</hi> and <hi>Coneys.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="unknown:008156_0008_102E3E573760DD58"/>
A Road has been made from our Country to this Council Fire, that we might treat about Friendſhip; and as we came down the Road, we ſaw that (by ſome Misfortune or other) Blood has lately been ſpilt on it. By theſe Strings we make the Road wider and clearer;— we take the Blood away out of it, and likewiſe out of the Council Chamber, which may have been ſtained; we waſh it all away, and deſire it may not be ſeen any more, and we take the Hatchet out of your Heads.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gave three Strings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren, the Governors, and all the</hi> Engliſh,</p>
               <p>I now confine myſelf to the <hi>Cayugas,</hi> my own Nation.</p>
               <p>I will hide nothing from you, becauſe we have promiſed to ſpeak to each other from the Bottom of our Hearts.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French,</hi> like a Thief in the Night, have ſtolen away ſome of our young Men, and miſled them, and they have been concerned in doing Miſchief againſt our Brethren the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We did not know it when it happened, but we diſcovered it ſince. The Chiefs of our Nation held their young Men faſt, and would not ſuffer them to go out of their Sight, but the <hi>French</hi> came and ſtole them away from us, and corrupted them to do Miſchief. We are ſorry for it; we aſk Pardon for them, and hope you will forgive them; we promiſe they ſhall do ſo no more, and now, by this Belt, we take out of your Heads the Hatchet with which they ſtruck you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt of ten Rows.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He added, he had found out that ſome of their young People had been concerned in ſtriking us four Times.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>At a</hi> CONFERENCE <hi>with the</hi> Indians, <hi>held at</hi> Eaſton, October 13, 1758.</head>
               <p>PRESENT,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Governor</hi> DENNY,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Governor</hi> BERNARD,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The ſame Gentlemen,</hi> Indians, <hi>Interpreters,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as before.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>AS ſoon as the <hi>Indians</hi> had taken their Seats, Governor <hi>Denny</hi> made the following Speech.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren, Chiefs and Warriors of the</hi> United Nations, <hi>and others your Brethren and Nephews, now met here,</hi> Agreeable to your Requeſt, at our firſt Meeting, I now return you the Belt, which the young <hi>Seneca Indian</hi> brought me, with your Anſwer to the Invitation I gave you to come down to this Council Fire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here his Honour returned the Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I invited you to come down to the Council Fire kindled at this Place by me and your Nephew <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> with a Deſign to lay before you Matters of the greateſt Conſequence to you and us; I am now about to communicate them to you, and to anſwer all that has been ſaid by you to me, ſince our meeting together; I therefore, by this String, open your Ears, that you may hear clearly, and carefully attend to what I ſhall ſay to you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I muſt firſt put you in Mind, that perfect Peace and Friendſhip ſubſiſted between you and your Brethren, the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in this Province, from our firſt Settlement among you, and that whatever little Diſputes happened between your People and ours, they were amicably ſettled and adjuſted by our wiſe Men at our Council Fires, according to an Agreement made by our firſt Proprietary WILLIAM PENN, and your Fathers. Had this wiſe Agreement been care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſerved, as it always ought to have been, our late unhappy Differences had never aroſe. But what is paſſed cannot be recalled, and ſhall be forgotten. Let us both reſolve never to be guilty of the like Error for the future.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You gave us Yeſterday theſe two Belts, in Behalf of your Nephews the <hi>Delawares</hi> and <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> and joined with them in taking out of our Heads the Hatchets with which we had been ſtruck, acquainting us, <q>that theſe Hatchets were given to your Nephews by the <pb n="9" facs="unknown:008156_0009_102E3E59BAA7B388"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> they would not uſe them any more againſt us; but were heartily diſpoſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Friendſhip with us for the future.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> we thank you for the Pains you have taken in enquiring of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> true Cauſe why they ſtruck us.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hatchets are taken out of our Heads, and we are reconciled, we deſire that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wares</hi> and <hi>Miniſinks</hi> will conceal nothing from you and us, that ever did, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> heavy on their Minds, that the End of this Meeting may be anſwered, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Aſſiſtance, to put Matters that have at any Time diſturbed their Minds on ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> reaſonable Footing, that the Peace between us may never be interrupted, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the remoteſt Ages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two Belts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Strings of black Wampum, you the <hi>Mohawks, Senecas,</hi> and <hi>Onondagoes,</hi> told us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not only brought about an Union with the <hi>Delawares</hi> and <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the River <hi>Saſquehannah,</hi> but had alſo ſent Meſſages to the <hi>Indians</hi> now on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe of theſe two Nations, as thoſe of the <hi>Six Nations,</hi> under the <hi>French</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſiring them to lay down the Hatchet, and enter again into Friendſhip with their B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>n the <hi>Engliſh</hi>; and, on their Behalf, you have taken the Hatchets out of our Heads, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to lay a Foundation for a future Peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren, the</hi> Mohawks, Senecas, <hi>and</hi> Onondagoes,</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> was a very friendly Part, and we ſlatter ourſelves they will hearken to you, as there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> now here from thoſe <hi>Indians</hi> on the <hi>Ohio,</hi> with Meſſages to us, which will be de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vered in Publick.</p>
               <p>We accept your Strings, and approve your taking the Hatchet, on the Behalf of the <hi>Ohio Ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> out of our Heads, ſo far as to make it the Foundation of a future Peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nine Strings</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren, the</hi> Cayugas, Oneidoes, Tuſcaroras, Tuteloes, Nanticokes, <hi>or</hi> Conoys, <hi>the younger Nations, who are Parts of, and united with, the</hi> Six Nations,</p>
               <p>By theſe Strings you ſay, <q>That, as you came down the Road which has been opened <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> your Country to this Council Fire, you ſaw Blood lately ſpilt upon it, and have waſhed it away, not only out of the Road, but out of the Council Chamber, leſt that ſhould have been ſtained.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We join, by theſe Strings, with you, in removing the Blood. We bury it deep in the Earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three Strings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brothers the</hi> Cayugas,</p>
               <p>With this Belt <q>you juſtly lament the Folly of your young Men, who have ſuffered themſelves to be ſtolen away from you by the <hi>French,</hi> and then, at their Inſtigation, to ſtrike us. You take the Hatchet out of our Heads, you aſk Pardon for them, and deſire we will forgive the Miſchief they have done us, and both you and they promiſe never to hurt us more.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We accept the Belt in their Behalf, and give you this Belt in Token of our Friendſhip and Reconciliation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may remember, that the Day before Yeſterday, your Nephew <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> told me by this String, <q>that he had already ſaid to me, at our former Meetings, every Thing he had to ſay, and had made me acquainted with the Cauſe why he had ſtruck us, and that I knew what had paſſed between us.—That we had made up all Differences, and had done it, as far as we could, for our future Peace.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>That at my Requeſt he had given the Halloo, and brought down to this Place you who heard him, and are now preſent; and that he would ſit by, and hear what we ſaid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As there are a great many of you here, who were not preſent at our former Meetings, I think it proper, for your Information, to give you a ſhort Account of what has paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween your Nephews the <hi>Delawares</hi> and us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="unknown:008156_0010_102E3E5C4CCD30F0"/>About three Years ago your Brethren the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> living on the Borders of this Province, were ſtruck on a ſudden, at a Time when they were in profound Peace with you, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing their Buſineſs, ſuſpecting no Danger. Many were killed, and others carried away Captives.</p>
               <p>We were ſurprized, and did not know who ſtruck us, but ſent Meſſengers up the <hi>Saſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quehannah,</hi> as far as the <hi>Six Nation</hi> Country, to enquire whence the Blow came, and for what Reaſon</p>
               <p>On the Return of theſe Meſſengers, we were informed that the Hatchet had been ſtruck into our Heads by our Countrymen the <hi>Delawares</hi> and <hi>Shawaneſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some Time after this Diſcovery was made, a Ceſſation of Hoſtilities was brought about by the <hi>Six Nations,</hi> at our Requeſt, made to them for that Purpoſe by Sir <hi>William Johnſon</hi>; and, upon our Invitation, our Brother <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> came down, with a Number of <hi>Dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares</hi> and other <hi>Indians,</hi> to a Council Fire, kindled at this Place, where we have ſince had ſeveral Meetings.</p>
               <p>At one of theſe Meetings <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> told us, that the Cauſe of the War was, their fooliſh young Men had been perſuaded by the falſe-hearted <hi>French</hi> King to ſtrike their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the <hi>Engliſh</hi>; and one Reaſon why the Blow came harder was, that the Proprietaries of this Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> had taken from them by Fraud the Ground we now ſtand on, and all the Lands lying between <hi>Tohiccon-Creek</hi> and <hi>Wyomink,</hi> on the River <hi>Saſquehannah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At laſt all Blood was wiped away, and buried under Ground, and Peace Belts were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed between us and our Brother <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> who then told us he acted in Behalf of Ten Nations, and promiſed to bring in and reſtore to us all our Fellow-Subjects that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> been carried off Priſoners by them.</p>
               <p>For the Truth of this ſhort Relation I refer you to our Brother <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> who will confirm it to you more particularly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To continue our Friendſhip, it is abſolutely neceſſary to preſerve Faith, and keep the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes we make with each other.</p>
               <p>I will ſpeak plainly to you, and from the Bottom of my Heart, as one Friend ought to another, that nothing may lie heavy on my Mind to diſturb me hereafter; and I expect the ſame Openneſs and Freedom on your Parts.</p>
               <p>I deſire therefore to know the true Reaſon, why our Fleſh and Blood, who are in Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and in your Power, have not been delivered to us, according to the Promiſe made us by our Brother <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> in Behalf of all the <hi>Indians</hi> he repreſented; and what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thoſe Belts we gave him to confirm the Peace, and that Promiſe; for till that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is complied with, we can never ſleep in Quiet, or reſt ſatisfied in the Friendſhip of thoſe who detain our Children and Relations from us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the Governor had done ſpeaking, the <hi>United Nations</hi> gave the uſual Shouts of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, with great Solemnity, each according to Rank.</p>
               <p>Then Governor <hi>Bernard</hi> delivered the Belts requeſted by the <hi>Senecas, Cayugas,</hi> and <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinks,</hi> and ſpoke as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Governor of <hi>Pennſylvania</hi> has given a particular Anſwer to what has been ſaid to us both. So far as his Anſwer relates to the Province over which I preſide, I confirm what has been ſaid by this Belt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Previous to what follows, it is neceſſary to obſerve, that <hi>Piſquitomen,</hi> and another <hi>Ohio In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> having come to <hi>Philadelphia</hi> laſt Summer, acquainted the Governor, that the <hi>Indians</hi> in thoſe Parts had not received any Account of the late Tranſactions with this Government, not any Meſſage from it; and that they might be perſuaded to lay down the Hatchet, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor therefore took that Opportunity to ſend a friendly Meſſage to thoſe <hi>Indians</hi> by <hi>Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitomen,</hi> and appointed Mr. <hi>Frederick Poſt,</hi> a <hi>German,</hi> who underſtood the <hi>Delaware</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, to attend him, and acquaint the <hi>Indians</hi> at <hi>Ohio</hi> of the Peace made by the <hi>Saſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannah</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="unknown:008156_0011_102E3E5FED2649E0"/>
                  <hi>Delawares<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and other <hi>Indians,</hi> and the Diſpoſition of this Government to forgive what was paſt, if they would return to their antient Alliance. This Meſſage was accordingly delivered, and an Anſwer returned by <hi>Frederick Poſt, Piſquitomen,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Hickman,</hi> an <hi>Ohio Indian,</hi> who having come down together as far as <hi>Harris's</hi> Ferry, <hi>Frederick Poſt</hi> went to wait on General <hi>Forbes,</hi> and left the two <hi>Indians</hi> to proceed with the Meſſage, who being now arrived at <hi>Eaſton, Piſquitomen,</hi> who had the particular Charge of it, introduced it as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When I was at <hi>Allegheny,</hi> the chief Men ſat together as we do here now. I was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by the Governor, <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael Pemberton,</hi> theſe three Men, pointing to them and the chief Men told me, that when I ſhould come among the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Inhabitants, I muſt ſhake Hands for them with the Governor, <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael Pemberton</hi> (here he ſhook Hands with them) and that what they had to ſay, was written down in a Paper, which he then produced, and ſaid they deſired it might be read in Publick. Now you, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, who are Head Men, ſent <hi>Frederick Poſt</hi> with me, deſiring me to take and carry him in my Boſom there, and when I came there, to introduce him to the publick Council; I did this, and have brought him back ſafe again.</p>
               <p>Then taking a Belt, and three Strings of Wampum, which were delivered with the Paper, he ſaid he would interpret them; but as all that was ſaid was truly ſet down in the Writing, it was not neceſſary. Let it be read.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Piſquitomen</hi> delivered the Paper, with the Belt and three Strings of Wampum, who, on being aſked alterwards to whom they were ſent, anſwered, one was ſent to the Governor, another to <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> and another to <hi>Iſrael Pemberton.</hi> The Meſſage was read in theſe Words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Indians <hi>ſpeak now. Brethren, hear what I have to ſay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IT is a good many Days ſince we have ſeen and heard of you from all Sorts of Nations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the firſt Meſſage which we have ſeen and heard of you; we have not yet rightly heard you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have talked of that Peace and Friendſhip which we had formerly with you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We tell you to be ſtrong, and always remember that Friendſhip which we had formerly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We deſire you would be ſtrong, and let us once more hear of our good Friendſhip and Peace we had formerly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We deſire you to make Haſte, and let us ſoon hear of you again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gave a String.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hear what I have to ſay; look Brethren, ſince we have ſeen and heard of you of all Sorts of Nations, we ſee that you are ſorry that we have not that Friendſhip we formerly had.</p>
               <p>Look Brethren, we at <hi>Allegheny</hi> are likewiſe ſorry that we have not that Friendſhip with you we formerly had.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We long for that Peace and Friendſhip we had formerly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is good that you have held that Friendſhip which we had formerly amongſt our Fathers and Grandfathers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We muſt tell you we will not let that Friendſhip quite drop, which was formerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us. Now, Brethren, it is three Years ſince we dropped that Peace and Friendſhip which we formerly had with you. Now, Brethren, that Friendſhip is dropped, and lies buried in the Ground where you and I ſtand, in the Middle between us both. Now, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſince I ſee you have digged up and revived that Friendſhip, which was buried in the Ground, now you have it, hold it faſt. Do, be ſtrong, Brethren, and exert yourſelves, that that Friendſhip may be well eſtabliſhed and finiſhed between us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you will be ſtrong, it is in your Power to finiſh that Peace and Friendſhip well.</p>
               <p>Now, Brethren, we deſire you to be ſtrong, and eſtabliſh and make known to all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of this Peace and Friendſhip, that it, over all, may be well eſtabliſhed, as you are of one Nation, and one Colour, in all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Governments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When you have made this Peace, which you have begun, known every where amongſt 
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:008156_0012_102E3E6177F8B858"/>
your Brethren, and have finiſhed and agreed every where together on this Peace and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, then you will be pleaſed to ſend it to me at <hi>Allegheny.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When you have ſettled the Peace and Friendſhip, and finiſhed it well, and you ſend it to me, I will ſend it to all the Nations of my Colour; when I receive of you the Anſwer, and I have looked that every Thing is well done, ſo that I can ſend it to the Nations of my Colour, they all will join to it, and we all will hold it faſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When all the Nations join to this Friendſhip, then the Day will begin to ſhine clear over us. When we once hear more of you, and we join together, then the Day will be ſtill, and no Wind or Storm will come over us to diſturb us.</p>
               <p>Now, Brethren, you know our Hearts, and what we have to ſay, be ſtrong; if you do ſo, every Thing will be well; and what we have told you in this, all the Nations agree to join.</p>
               <p>Now, Brethren, let the King of <hi>England</hi> know what our Minds are, as ſoon as poſſible you can.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gives a Belt of eight Rows.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Received the above Speech from the under-written, who are all Captains and Counſellors, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Beaver King,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Shingas,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Delaware George,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Piſquitom,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Taſſacomin,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Owahanomin,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cockquacaukeheton,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cuhſhawmehwy,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Kekeknapalin,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Captain Peter,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Macomal,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Popauco,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Waſhaſcautaut,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Hickoman,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Kill Buck.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The above Names is of Captains and Counſellors.</p>
               <p>After this was interpreted in the <hi>Six Nation</hi> Language, and in the <hi>Delaware,</hi> the Three Strings were delivered to the Governor, <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael Pemberton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the Governor was going to cloſe the Conference, <hi>Nichas,</hi> the <hi>Mohawk</hi> Chief, ſpoke for ſome Time, with great Vehemence, pointing frequently to <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Weiſer</hi> was ordered to interpret it; but he deſired to be excuſed, as it was about Matters purely relating to the <hi>Indians</hi> themſelves, and deſired Mr. <hi>Montour</hi> might interpret it; after ſome Pauſe, he ſaid, perhaps it might be better if it was interpreted to the Governors, Councils, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, in a private Conference. Mr. <hi>Weiſer</hi> was deſired to mention this to the <hi>Indians,</hi> and know of them what they would chuſe ſhould be done, whether it ſhould be interpreted now, or at a private Conference, and they anſwered now; but ſoon after they ſaid, that, at the Requeſt of Mr. <hi>Weiſer,</hi> they conſented that it ſhould be interpreted in the Morning, at a private Conference.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <p>
                  <hi>October</hi> 14, 1758. The <hi>Indians</hi> declined meeting To-day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>At a private</hi> CONFERENCE <hi>with the</hi> Indians <hi>on the</hi> 15<hi>th of</hi> October, 1758.</head>
               <p>PRESENT,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Governor</hi> DENNY, <hi>His Council, and the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of Aſſembly.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Governor</hi> BERNARD, <hi>and the</hi> Jerſey <hi>Commiſſioners.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chiefs of the</hi> Mohawks, Senecas, <hi>and</hi> Onondagoes. <hi>Chiefs of the</hi> Oneidoes, Cayugas, Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caroras, Nanticokes, <hi>or</hi> Conoys, <hi>and</hi> Tuteloes.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Nichas, <hi>the</hi> Mohawk <hi>Chief, ſtood up, and, directing his Diſcourſe to both Governors, ſaid,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brothers,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WE thought proper to meet you here, to have ſome private Diſcourſe about our Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew <hi>Teedyuſcung.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You all know that he gives out, he is the great Man, and Chief of Ten Nations, this is his conſtant Diſcourſe. Now I, on Behalf of the <hi>Mohawks,</hi> ſay, we do not know he is ſuch a great Man. If he is ſuch a great Man, we deſire to know who has made him ſo. Perhaps you have, and if this be the Caſe, tell us ſo. It may be the <hi>French</hi> have made him ſo. We want to enquire and know whence his Greatneſs aroſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="unknown:008156_0013_102DD04B21E72F18"/>Tagaſhata, <hi>on the Behalf of the</hi> Senecas, <hi>ſpoke next.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I, for my Nation, ſay the ſame that <hi>Nichas</hi> has ſaid; I need not repeat it. I ſay we do not know who has made <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> this great Man over Ten Nations; and I want to know who made him ſo.</p>
               <p>Aſſarandonguas <hi>ſpoke next, on Behalf of the</hi> Onondagoes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am here to repreſent the <hi>Onondagoes,</hi> and I ſay, for them, that I never heard, before now, that <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> was ſuch a great Man, and much leſs can I tell who made him ſo. No ſuch Thing was ever ſaid in our Towns, as that <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> was ſuch a great Man.</p>
               <p>Thomas King <hi>ſpoke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren the Governors, and all preſent,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Notice that I ſpeak in Behalf of Five Nations, who have their Deputies here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Oneidoes, Cayugas, Tuſcaroras, Nanticokes,</hi> and <hi>Conoys,</hi> who have joined to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and now make one Nation, and <hi>Tuteloes.</hi> We Five are all connected together, and if any Thing is ſaid to one of us, it is communicated to all the reſt.</p>
               <p>On their Behalf I now tell you, we none of us know who has made <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> ſuch a great Man; perhaps the <hi>French</hi> have, or perhaps you have, or ſome among you, as you have different Governments, and are different People. We, for our Parts, entirely diſown that he has any Authority over us, and deſire to know from whence he derives his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tokaaio, <hi>the</hi> Cayuga <hi>Chief, ſpoke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſpeak now to you, on Behalf of the Nations juſt now mentioned to you. You may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that you ſaid the other Day, you could not be eaſy without your Priſoners were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned. We have conſidered this, and I now aſſure you that they ſhall be returned.</p>
               <p>We ſpeak from the Bottom of our Hearts; we will look carefully into all our Towns for them. You ſhall have them all. We will keep none. It there he any of them that have gone down our Throats, we will throw them up again. You told us, a tender Father, Huſband, Wife, Brother, or Siſter could not ſleep ſound, when they reflected that their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations were Priſoners. We know it is ſo with us, and we will therefore uſe our Endeavours to make your Hearts eaſy, and we give you this Belt as a Promiſe, that we will perform our Words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nichas <hi>ſpoke next, in Behalf of the</hi> Mohawks, Senecas, <hi>and</hi> Onondagoes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſpeak now on Behalf of my own Nation, and my two other Brethren, Deputies of the <hi>Senecas</hi> and <hi>Onondagoes.</hi> We remember you deſired us to leave nothing in our Hearts, but ſpeak open on every Matter, and you ſaid you would do the ſame to us.</p>
               <p>You told us, that you could not ſleep ſound whilſt your Priſoners were detained from you, nor could you have any Conſidence in the Friendſhip of thoſe who did detain them.</p>
               <p>We of theſe three Nations promiſe, that we will uſe our beſt Endeavours to make you ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy. When we return, we will enquire of every Town for the Priſoners. We will call our Councils, and lay what you have ſaid before them, and make diligent Enquiry for them through all our Towns, and all that we can find you ſhall ſee.</p>
               <p>If any of them are gone down our Throats, we will heave them up again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String of ſeven Rows.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>At a</hi> CONFERENCE <hi>with the</hi> Indians, <hi>on the</hi> 16<hi>th of</hi> October, 1758.</head>
               <p>PRESENT, <hi>The</hi> GOVERNORS, <hi>and the Gentlemen of their Councils,</hi> &amp;cc.</p>
               <p>THE Minutes of the preceding Conferences were read, and approved.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of Yeſterday's private Conference were read at the particular Deſire of the Chiefs of the <hi>Eight Nations,</hi> and interpreted to <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> and the <hi>Delawares,</hi> in the <hi>Delawares</hi> Language, by Mr. <hi>Stephen Calvin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="unknown:008156_0014_102E3E66489DF690"/>The Governors then ſpoke ſeparately; Governor <hi>Denny</hi> beginning as follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren, the</hi> Mohawks, Onondagoes, Senecas, Oneidoes, Cayugas, Tuſcaroras, Nanticokes <hi>and</hi> Tuteloes,</p>
               <p>In a Conference held with you Yeſterday, you told me, that we know your Nephew <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> gives out, that he is the great Man, and Chief of ten Nations, and that this was his conſtant Diſcourſe; by this Belt therefore you denied him to be ſo great a Man, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know of me who made him ſo, or gave him any Authority over you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will anſwer you truly, and tell you, in a few Words, all that I know of the Matter; I have already informed you, that after the <hi>Delawares</hi> had ſtruck us, you, our good Friends the <hi>United Nations,</hi> adviſed them to ſit ſtill, and do us no more Miſchief; and that ſoon after this, we invited the <hi>Delawares</hi> to meet us at a Council Fire kindled at this Place.</p>
               <p>We received an Anſwer to our Meſſage from <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> as a Chief among the <hi>Delawares.</hi> At the Time appointed he came, and told us, that he repreſented ten Nations, amongſt which the <hi>United Nations</hi> were included, that he acted as a chief Man for the <hi>Delawares,</hi> but only as a Meſſenger for the <hi>United Nations,</hi> who were his Uncles and Superiors; to whom he would faithfully carry every Thing that ſhould be tranſacted between us, that they might do as they ſaw Cauſe.</p>
               <p>We believed what your Nephew told us, and therefore made him a Counſellor and Agent for us, and deſired him to publiſh to all Nations of <hi>Indians</hi> what we did at our Council Fires, and to let them know we were ſincerely diſpoſed to be at Peace with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I can only ſpeak for myſelf, and do aſſure you, that I never made <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> this great Man, nor ever presented to give him any Authority over you; and I muſt do him the Juſtice to declare to you, that, at our former publick Treaties, <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> never aſſumed any ſuch Power, but, on many Occaſions, when he ſpoke of you, called you his Uncles and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors.</p>
               <p>I never ſhall attempt to nominate or impoſe a Chief on any <hi>Indian</hi> Tribe or Nation, but, on all Occaſions, will pay due Regard to thoſe who are choſen by their Countrymen.</p>
               <p>If any others have made <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> ſo great a Man, as to ſet himſelf above you, I am ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for it. It is more than I know, and they who have done it muſt anſwer for themſelves.</p>
               <p>I ſhould be greatly concerned, that any Uneaſineſs ſhould ariſe among you; and hope you will guard againſt it, and preſerve that Harmony which ought to ſubſiſt between Friends and Relations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this Belt and String, you premiſed me to make diligent Search in your Towns for our Fleſh and Blood, who are Priſoners among you, and return them to us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have always found you honeſt, and punctual in the Performance of your Promiſes; your Words therefore give me great Comfort, and fill all our Hearts with Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>We rely upon you that no Time may be loſt in fulfilling an Engagement, on which our Peace and Quiet ſo greatly depend.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt and String.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then Governor</hi> Bernard <hi>ſpoke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren of all the Confederated Nations,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As you propoſed your Queſtion, concerning <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> ſeparately, I think it proper to give you a ſeparate Anſwer thereto.</p>
               <p>I know not who made <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> ſo great a Man, nor do I know that he is any greater than a Chief of the <hi>Delaware Indians,</hi> ſettled at <hi>Wyomink.</hi> The Title of King could not be given him by any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Governor; for we know very well, that there is no ſuch Perſon among <hi>Indians,</hi> as what we call a King. And if we call him ſo, we mean no more than a Sachem or Chief. I obſerve, in his Treaties, which he has held with the Governors of <hi>Pennſylvania</hi> (which I have peruſed ſince our laſt Meeting) he ſays he was a Woman till you made him a Man, by putting a Tomahawk in his Hand; and through all of thoſe 
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:008156_0015_102E3E68C7FCE430"/>
Treaties, eſpecially in the laſt, held at this Town, he calls you his Uncles, and profeſſes that he is dependent on you; and I know not that any Thing has ſince happened to alter his Relation to you. I therefore conſider him to be ſtill your Nephew.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I heartily thank you for your kind Promiſes to return the Captives which have been taken from us. I hope you will not only do ſo, but will alſo engage ſuch of your Allies and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews, who have taken Captives from us, to do the ſame. That you may be mindful of this, I give you this Belt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the Governors had done ſpeaking, and their Anſwers were interpreted in the <hi>Six Nation</hi> and <hi>Delaware</hi> Languages, the <hi>Indian</hi> Chiefs were aſked if they had any Thing more to ſay; on which <hi>Tagaſkata</hi> aroſe, and made a Speech to his Couſins the <hi>Delawares</hi> and <hi>Miniſink Indians,</hi> directing his Diſcourſe to <hi>Teedyuſcung.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nephews,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may remember all that paſſed at this Council-Fire. The Governors who ſit there have put you in Mind of what was agreed upon laſt Year. You both promiſed to return the Priſoners. We, your Uncles, put you in Mind of this Promiſe, and deſire you will perform it. You have promiſed it, and you muſt perform it. We, your Uncles, have promiſed to return all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners among us, and therefore we expect that you, our Couſins and Nephews, will do the ſame. As ſoon as you come home, we deſire that you will ſearch carefully into your Towns for all the Priſoners among you, that have been taken out of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Province, and cauſe them to be delivered up to your Brethren. You know that this is an Article of the Peace that was made between you and your Brethren, in Confirmation of which you received a large Peace Belt; of which Belt we deſire you will give an Account, and let us know what is become of it, and how far you have proceeded in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this was interpreted in the <hi>Delaware</hi> Language, it was obſerved, that there were no <hi>Miniſink Indians</hi> preſent; the Governors therefore deſired Mr. <hi>Read</hi> and Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> would procure a Meeting of the Chiefs of the <hi>United Nations,</hi> with the <hi>Delawares</hi> and <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> and cauſe the Speech of <hi>Tagaſhata</hi> to be interpreted to the <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> in the Preſence of their Uncles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert White,</hi> the <hi>Nanticoke</hi> Chief, aroſe, and ſaid he was going to ſpeak in the Behalf of ſeven Nations, and, directing his Diſcourſe to the Governors, he delivered himſelf in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Language, as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is now more than two Years paſt, ſince we heard of our Couſins the <hi>Delawares</hi> taking up the Hatchet againſt the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> At the firſt, Sir <hi>William Johnſon</hi> ſent a Meſſage to the Head Nations, and when they received it, they ſent one to us at <hi>Otſaningo,</hi> telling us, that, as we lived cloſe by our Couſins, they deſired we would invite them to meet at our Town, and accordingly we invited them, and they came to a great Meeting at our Town of <hi>Otſaningo.</hi> We then gave our Couſins a Belt of a Fathom long, and Twenty-five Rows in Breadth, and deſired them to lay down the Hatchet that they had taken up againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and to be eaſy with them; and if they would follow this Advice, we told them, that they would live in Peace, until their Heads were white with Age, otherwiſe it might not be ſo with them.</p>
               <p>Not hearing from our Couſins of ſome Time, what they did in Conſequence of this Belt, we ſent to them two other Belts, one of Sixteen, and the other of Twelve Rows, deſiring them once more to be eaſy with their Brethren the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and not to ſtrike them any more; but ſtill we heard nothing from them: Indeed, ſome Time afterwards we underſtood the <hi>Dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares</hi> ſhould ſay, that the <hi>Indians</hi> at <hi>Otſaningo</hi> had grey Eyes, and were like the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſhould be ſerved as <hi>Engliſhmen</hi>; and we thought we ſhould have had the Hatchet ſtruck into our Heads. We now want to know what is became of theſe Belts; may be they may be under Ground, or they have ſwallowed them down their Throats.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As our Couſins have been loath to give any Anſwer to theſe Belts, we now deſire they may let us know, in a publick Conference, what they have done with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>October</hi> 17, 1758.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Indians</hi> were in Council all Day; and acquainted the Governors, that they could not be ready to meet before Morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <pb n="16" facs="unknown:008156_0016_102E3E6B54EB50F0"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>At a</hi> CONFERENCE <hi>held at</hi> Eaſton, <hi>on the 18th of</hi> October, 1758.</head>
               <p>PRESENT, <hi>The</hi> GOVERNORS, <hi>Council, Gentlemen, and</hi> Indiana, <hi>with the Interpreters as before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>MR. <hi>Read,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> acquainted the Governors, that, at a Meeting of the Chiefs of the Older and Younger Nations, with the ſeveral Tribes of the <hi>Delaware</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſink Indians</hi> on <hi>Monday</hi> Night, the Speech of <hi>Tagaſhata,</hi> delivered that Morning in the Publick Conference, reſpecting the giving up the Priſoners, was interpreted in the <hi>Delaware</hi> Language by <hi>Stephen Calvin</hi>; and another Belt, on the Part of the Governors, being joined to <hi>Tagaſhata</hi>'s Belt, they were both delivered to the <hi>Delaware</hi> and <hi>Miniſink</hi> Chiefs, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the Matter. When this was done <hi>Tagaſhata</hi> ſpoke to the <hi>Miniſink</hi> Chief, <hi>Egohohowen,</hi> ſaying, we were told by you that you had delivered up the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners, and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved you: But our Brethren have told us that they were not delivered up; and therefore we earneſtly deſire that they may be made eaſy on this Article. You know, Couſins, that their Hearts will always be in Grief till they ſee again their Fleſh and Blood. It is natural that they ſhould be ſo. It would be ſo with us, if it was our Caſe. We deſire you will be extremely careful to perform this Matter fully, and ſoon. Let there be perfect Peace, over all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Country. And let it now be publiſhed, that we may all live in Peace, and with Satisfaction, now, and for ever. I told you, <hi>Egohohowen,</hi> when you was in my Town, to bring with you the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners, and that our Brethren would expect it. I wiſh you had done it. But however do it now with all Speed, and it will be well.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Egohohowen</hi> anſwered, it is true, I was at my Uncle's Fire, and I believe he deſired me to bring the Priſoners down; but I ſuppoſe it was not interpreted to me, for I did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it clearly, but I now underſtand it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Miniſink</hi> and <hi>Delaware Indians</hi> were deſired to collect all their Warriors together, and give them theſe Belts, and receive from them their Anſwer, it being neceſſary they ſhould concur heartily in whatever ſhould be concluded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nichas,</hi> the <hi>Mohawk</hi> Chief, acquainted the Governors, that, as Counſellors, they had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, having nothing to propoſe at this preſent Meeting. The Warriors were to ſpeak now, and <hi>Thomas King</hi> was appointed to deliver their Words, who thereupon aroſe, and began with an Exhortation, as well to all concerned in publick Affairs, Governors and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, and <hi>Indian</hi> Chiefs and their Councils, as to Warriors of all Nations, White People and <hi>Indians,</hi> deſiring all preſent to attend carefully to what was going to be related, as Matters of great Conſequence, which would ſerve to regulate the Conduct of <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> to each other. He added, that the Relation going to be made, had taken a great deal of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to put it into Order, and it was made on Information given by the ſeveral <hi>Indians</hi> now preſent, who were acquainted with the Facts. Brethren, we the Warriors have waited ſome Time, in Hopes our Counſellors would have taken this Matter in hand, but as they have not done it, we have, at their Deſire, undertaken it, and they have approved of every Thing. I ſay, the Counſellors of the Five Younger Nations, as well as the Three Older Nations, have approved of what the Warriors are going to relate; and take Notice, that the Speech is not only the Speech of all the Warriors of the Elder and Younger Nations, but of our Couſins the <hi>Delawares</hi> and <hi>Miniſinks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was interpreted in the <hi>Delaware</hi> Language; and <hi>Thomas King</hi> then proceeded, direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Speech to the Governors, and all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> upon the Continent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have been inquiſitive to know the Cauſe of this War; you have often enquired among us, but perhaps you did not find out the true Cauſe of the Bitterneſs of our Hearts, and may charge us wrong, and think that you were ſtruck without a Cauſe by ſome of our own War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, and by our Couſins. But if you look a little about you, you will find that you gave the firſt Offence. For in Time of profound Peace, ſome of the <hi>Shawaneſe,</hi> paſſing through <hi>South-Carolina,</hi> to go to War with their Enemies, were taken up, and put in Priſon. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> knew they were going to War, and that they uſed to do it every Year; and yet, after they had perſuaded them in a friendly Way into their Houſes, they were taken up, and put into Priſon, and one, who was an Head Man of that Nation, loſt his Life, and the others were ſeverely uſed. This firſt raiſed Ill-will in the Minds of the <hi>Shawaneſe,</hi> and as the <hi>French</hi> came a little after this happened to ſettle on the <hi>Ohio,</hi> the <hi>Shawaneſe</hi> complained of it to them, and they made an artful Uſe of it, ſet them againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and gave them the 
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:008156_0017_102E3E6DD7590530"/>
Hatchet. Being reſolved on Revenge, they accepted it, and likewiſe ſpoke to their Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers the <hi>Delawares,</hi> ſaying, Grandfathers, Are not your Hearts fore at our being uſed ſo ill, and at the Loſs of one of our Chiefs? Will not you join us in revenging his Death? So by Degrees our young Men were brought over to act againſt you. On ſearching Matters to the Bottom, you will find that you, in this Manner, gave the firſt Offence. This we thought proper to let you know. It may be of Service for the future. You may be induced by this to take better Care in conducting your Council Buſineſs, ſo as to guard againſt theſe Breaches of Friendſhip; or, as ſoon as they happen, in correſponding immediately with one another, and with the <hi>Indian</hi> Nations, who are in any wiſe concerned, on ſuch Occaſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eight Strings of black Wampum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the Caſe of the <hi>Shawaneſe,</hi> that I have juſt now related. Another of the like Nature has ſince happened to the <hi>Senecas,</hi> who have ſuffered in the ſame Manner.</p>
               <p>About three Years ago, eight <hi>Seneca</hi> Warriors were returning from War, through <hi>Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> having ſeven Priſoners and Scalps with them; at a Place called <hi>Green Briar,</hi> they met with a Party of Soldiers, not leſs than One Hundred and Fifty, who kindly invited them to come to a certain Store, and ſaid, they would ſupply them with Proviſions; and accordingly they travelled two Days with them in a friendly Manner, and when they came to the Houſe, they took their Arms from the <hi>Senecas</hi>: The head Men cried out, here is Death; defend yourſelves as well as you can, which they did, and two of them were killed on the Spot, and one, a young Boy, was taken Priſoner. This gave great Offence, and the more ſo, as it was upon the Warriors Road, and we were in perfect Peace with our Brethren. It provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked us to ſuch a Degree, that we could not get over it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have juſtly demanded your Priſoners; it is right, and we have given you an Anſwer. And therefore, as we think this young Boy is alive, and ſomewhere among you, we deſire you will enquire for him. If he be alive, return him; if you have ſwallowed him down your Throats, which perhaps may be the Cafe, let us know it, and we will be content. His Name is <hi>Squiſſatego.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Six Strings of white Wampum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have one Word more to mention of the ſame Nature, and which was the very Cauſe why the <hi>Indians</hi> at <hi>Ohio</hi> left you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we firſt beard of the <hi>French</hi> coming to the <hi>Ohio,</hi> we immediately ſent Word to the Governors of <hi>Virginia</hi> and <hi>Pennſylvania</hi>; we deſired them to come, and likewiſe to ſupply us with ſuch Things as were proper for War, intending to defend our Lands, and hinder the <hi>French</hi> from taking the Poſſeſſion of them. But theſe Governors did not attend to our Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; perhaps they thought there was no Foundation for our Intelligence. The <hi>French,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, came, and became our Neighbours, and you neither coming yourſelves, nor aſſiſting us with warlike Stores, our People, of Neceſſity, were obliged to trade with them for what we wanted, as your Traders had left the Country. The Governor of <hi>Virginia</hi> took Care to ſettle on our Lands for his own Benefit; but when we wanted his Aſſiſtance againſt the <hi>French,</hi> he diſregarded us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this Treaty you juſtly demanded to ſee your Fleſh and Blood. We have preſſed this on our Couſins the <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> and they, by this String, deſired us to aſſure you, the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, that they would make ſtrict Search in their Towns, and ſincerely comply with your Requeſt, and return all the Priſoners in their Power.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two Strings of black and white Wampum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then directing his Diſcourſe to the Governor of the <hi>Jerſey,</hi> he proceeded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brother, the Governor of</hi> Jerſey,</p>
               <p>Our Couſins the <hi>Miniſinks</hi> tell us, they were wronged out of a great deal of Land, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſettling ſo faſt, they were puſhed back, and could not tell what Lands belonged to them. If we have been drunk, tell us ſo. We may have forgot what we ſold, but we truſt to you the Governor of <hi>Jerſey</hi> to take our Cauſe in Hand, and ſee that we have Juſtice done us. We ſay that we have here and there Tracts of Land, that have never been ſold. You deal hardly with us; you claim all the wild Creatures, and will not let us come on your Land to hunt after them. You will not ſo much as let us peel a ſingle Tree; this is hard, and has given us great Offence. The Cattle you raiſe are your own; but thoſe which are wild, are 
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:008156_0018_102E3E706285B138"/>
ſtill ours, and ſhould be common to both; for our Nephews, when they ſold the Land, did not propoſe to deprive themſelves of hunting the wild Deer, or uſing a Stick of Wood, when they ſhould have Occaſion. We deſire the Governor to take this Matter into his Care, and ſee Juſtice done in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two Strings of white Wampum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All that has been ſaid has been of one Nature, that is, of Matters that are Subjects of Diſpute; this that I am now going to ſpeak upon is of another Nature.</p>
               <p>Then, directing himſelf to the Governor of <hi>Pennſylvania,</hi> he ſaid,</p>
               <p>We muſt put you in Mind, that four Years ago, you bought at <hi>Albany</hi> a large Tract of Land over <hi>Saſquehannah,</hi> extending from the Mouth of <hi>John Penn's</hi> Creek to the <hi>Ohio.</hi> The Proprietaries Agents then paid <hi>One Thouſand Pieces of Eight</hi> for the Part which was ſettled by your People, that have been ſince driven off and killed. We acknowledge to have received Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for thoſe Parts that were ſettled, but for the other Part that we have not received Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for, that we reclaim. Our Warriors, or Hunters, when they heard that we had ſold ſuch a large Tract, diſapproved our Conduct in Council; ſo now we acquaint you, that we are determined not to confirm any more, than ſuch of the Lands as the Conſideration was paid for, and were ſettled; tho' included in the Deed, they are our hunting Grounds, and we deſire the Requeſt may be granted, and Notice taken, that it was made in open Confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three white Strings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then <hi>Thomas King</hi> ſat down.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Six Nation</hi> Chiefs being aſked if they had any Thing to ſay, anſwered, that they had done; and having eaſed their Minds of all that lay heavy upon them, they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home.</p>
               <p>The Governors promiſed attentively to conſider what was ſaid, and give them an Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Teedyuſcung <hi>then aroſe, and ſpoke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhould have ſaid ſomething at the Time our Uncles laid before you their Grievances, or Cauſes of Complaint, in Behalf of my Countrymen who lived near <hi>Goſhen.</hi> About three Years ago nine of their People were killed at <hi>Goſhen,</hi> when they were in Peace. I will not take upon me to ſay that the Land had never been ſold, but there was no Diſpute about this at that Time. I verily believe that they killed thoſe nine <hi>Indians,</hi> for no other Reaſon than becauſe they were hunting on that Land. I ſpeak to all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> when I mention this, as what was very wrong.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three white Strings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One of the <hi>Waping</hi> Tribes, or <hi>Geſhen Indians,</hi> tells me, that, as ſoon as thoſe nine Men were killed, he went with three Belts, and Tears in his Eyes, to <hi>George Freeland</hi>'s, in order to have the Matter made up; but he never received an Anſwer to this Day, tho' he told him that he would ſend the Belts to the Governor, and as ſoon as he ſhould receive his Anſwer, he would ſend for him, and let him know it; but he has never yet received any Anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I give you this String, to enquire what became of the three Belts, and what Anſwer was made to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three Strings of white Wampum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may remember we made Peace laſt Year, and a Peace Belt was made, a Fathom long, and of Fifteen Rows. Mr. <hi>Croghan</hi> was preſent, ſo were ſome of my Uncles, and the <hi>Miniſinks.</hi> They all ſaw it. You have aſked me what is become of that Belt, and how far it went. I will tell you; I ſent it up the <hi>Saſquehannah</hi> to <hi>Diahoga</hi>; from thence it went to <hi>Aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in</hi>; thence to <hi>Secaughkung.</hi> The chief Men there got together to conſider what was beſt to be done with it. They all concluded that it ſhould be ſent to our Uncle. He is a Man, and often told us he ought to ſee Things firſt, and conſider what is to be done. The <hi>Senecas</hi> had the Belt the firſt, and then all the <hi>United Nations</hi> afterwards; they had it almoſt a Year. Now it is come back, and in <hi>Lapachpeton</hi>'s Hands, who is one of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawares,</hi> and lives at <hi>Secaughkung.</hi> How far the Peace Belt went, I don't know; but I ſuppoſe it went thro' all my Uncles, and I aſſure you I will do as my Uncle does. He has promiſed you he will deliver up all your Captives, and I aſſure you I will do ſo, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I find them, in all my Towns. Four Tribes, now preſent, have agreed to this, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <pb n="19" facs="unknown:008156_0019_102E3E74569791C0"/>
                  <hi>Delawares, Unamies, Mohiccons,</hi> and <hi>Wapings,</hi> who are ſettled as far as <hi>Secaughkung.</hi> This Belt confirms my Words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I did let you know formerly what my Grievance was. I told you, that from <hi>Tohiccon</hi> as far as the <hi>Delawares</hi> owned, the Proprietaries had wronged me. Then you and I agreed that it ſhould be laid before the King of <hi>England</hi>; and likewiſe you told me you would let me know, as ſoon as ever he ſaw it. You would lay the Matter before the King, for you ſaid he was our Father, that he might ſee what were our Differences; for as you and I could not decide it, let him do it. Now let us not alter what you and I have agreed. Now let me know if King GEORGE has decided the Matter between you and me. I don't pretend to mention any of my Uncles Lands, I only mention what we the <hi>Delawares</hi> own, as far as the Heads of <hi>Delaware.</hi> All the Lands lying on the Waters that fall into the <hi>Saſquehan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah,</hi> belong to our Uncles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> then took up another Belt, deſigning to ſpeak to his Uncles the <hi>United Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>; but whilſt he was delivering the above, their Chiefs had one after another left the Council, ſeemingly much diſpleaſed, he therefore declined ſpeaking it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>October</hi> 19, 1758.</head>
               <p>THE Governors, having prepared their Anſwers, deſired the <hi>Indians</hi> to meet, but they continued holding private Councils among themſelves all that Day, till late in the Afternoon; and as the Governors were going to the Place of Conference, the <hi>Indians</hi> ſent Mr. <hi>Weiſer</hi> out of Council, to deſire they would defer meeting till the next Morning, their own private Buſineſs not being finiſhed.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>At a private</hi> CONFERENCE <hi>with the</hi> Indians, <hi>held at</hi> Eaſton, October 19, 1758. P.M.</head>
                  <p>PRESENT,
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>His Excellency Governor</hi> BERNARD,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Commiſſioners of</hi> New-Jerſey,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Chiefs of the</hi> United Nations, <hi>and of the</hi> Miniſinks <hi>and</hi> Wapings,</item>
                        <item>GEORGE CROOHAN, <hi>Deputy to Sir</hi> WILLIAM JOHNSON,</item>
                        <item>ANDREW MONTOUR, <hi>His Majeſty's Interpreter,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>STEPHEN CALVIN, <hi>Interpreter of the</hi> Miniſink <hi>and</hi> Waping <hi>Language.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>HIS Excellency reciting the Requeſt of the <hi>United Nations</hi> to him, to do Juſtice to their Nephews the <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> concerning their Claims to Lands in <hi>New-Jerſey,</hi> ſaid, he would make diligent Enquiry what Lands were remaining unſold by them; but as that would be a Work of Time and Expence, he wiſhed that ſome Means could be ſound to give them Satisfaction at this Meeting. The People of <hi>New-Jerſey</hi> ſaid, that they had bought all, or the greateſt Part of the <hi>Miniſink</hi> Lands; and the <hi>Miniſinks</hi> ſaid they had a great Deal of Land unſold.</p>
                  <p>He could not tell who was in the right; but would ſuppoſe there were ſome Lands un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, and upon that Suppoſition would give them ſome Money, by Way of Conſideration, for them, if they would propoſe a reaſonable Sum; and deſired they would adviſe about it, and give an Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>United Nations</hi> ſaid it was a very kind Propoſal, and recommended it to the Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the <hi>Miniſinks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame Day <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> waited on Governor <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> at his Houſe, bringing with him <hi>Iſaac Stille,</hi> for his Interpreter, and his Grandſon; and, in the Preſence of Governor <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Andrew Johnſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> acquainted the Governor, that the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> did not claim Lands high up on <hi>Delaware</hi> River; thoſe belonged to their Uncles; and be thought proper to let the Governor know this, that there might be no Miſunderſtanding of what he had ſaid in the publick Conference.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <pb n="20" facs="unknown:008156_0020_102E3E75DCDE9448"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>At a</hi> CONFERENCE <hi>with the</hi> Indians, <hi>held at</hi> Eaſton, October 20, 1758.</head>
               <p>PRESENT, <hi>The</hi> GOVERNORS, <hi>Council, Gentlemen and</hi> Indians, <hi>with the Interpreters, as before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>GOVERNOR <hi>Denny</hi> deſired to know of <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> if he propoſed to ſpeak, as the abrupt Departure of the <hi>Six Nation</hi> Chiefs from the Conference Yeſterday, had prevented him from finiſhing what he had to ſay.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> aroſe, and, addreſſing himſelf to the <hi>Six Nation Indians,</hi> ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uncles,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>According to our old Cuſtom, we uſed to ſpeak to one another at home; but we are now met here on Buſineſs, I muſt ſpeak to you in the Preſence of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Governors; and what I ſhall ſay, I deſire both you the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and my Uncles, who are here, will attend to.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uncles,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I take this Opportunity of ſpeaking to you in the Preſence of our Brethren the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and two of their Governors; pleaſe to take Notice what I am going to ſay.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uncles,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may remember that you have placed us at <hi>Wyomink,</hi> and <hi>Shamokin,</hi> Places where <hi>Indians</hi> have lived before. Now I hear ſince, that you have ſold that Land to our Brethren the <hi>Engliſh</hi>; let the Matter now be cleared up, in the Preſence of our Brethren the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſit there as a Bird on a Bow; I look about, and do not know where to go; let me therefore come down upon the Ground, and make that my own by a good Deed, and I ſhall then have a Home for ever; for if you, my Uncles, or I die, our Brethren the <hi>Engliſh</hi> will ſay, they have bought it from you, and ſo wrong my Poſterity out of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Governor</hi> Denny <hi>then requeſted the Attention of the</hi> Indians, <hi>and ſpoke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren, Chiefs and Warriors of the</hi> Six United Nations, <hi>and your Nephews, here aſſembled,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am much obliged to you for the Account you gave me the Day before Yeſterday, <hi>of</hi> the true Cauſe of the Bitterneſs of your Hearts towards us, and the Reaſons which induced ſome of your young Men firſt to ſtrike us, and others to ſide with the <hi>French</hi> on the <hi>Ohio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Advice you gave us, to take better Care and guard againſt any Breach of Friendſhip between us for the future, is very kind and wholſome; we will join with you, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prevent the like Evils for the Time to come.</p>
               <p>I promiſe you, that I will immediately ſend to the Governor of <hi>Virginia,</hi> to enquire after the <hi>Seneca</hi> Boy, <hi>Squiſſatego,</hi> who you ſay was left a Priſoner in his Country, and if he is alive, you may depend on his being returned to you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe Strings you put me in Mind, that the Proprietaries, four years ago, bought of you at <hi>Albany,</hi> a large Tract of Land over <hi>Saſquehannah,</hi> from the Mouth of a Creek called <hi>Kayarondinhagh,</hi> or <hi>John Penn's Creek,</hi> to the <hi>Ohio,</hi> and were paid by the Proprietaries Agents <hi>One Thouſand Pieces of Eight,</hi> as the Conſideration Money for ſuch Parts as were ſettled by our People; but that, as your Warriors diſapproved of your Conduct in Council for making that Sale, you now reclaimed ſuch of the Lands contained in that Grant, as you have not received a Conſideration for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Proprietaries of this Province have, on all Occaſions, manifeſted their particular Regard for you; they prefer your Friendſhip and the publick Good to their own private Intereſt. Their former Conduct gives you no Room to doubt the Truth of this; what I am about to tell you is a further Confirmation of it; therefore give me your Attention, and liſten to what I ſhall ſay. You may remember, that, at a Treaty you held with your good Friend Sir <hi>William Johnſon,</hi> three Years ago, ſome of your wiſe men told him, that there were ſome among them who were diſſatisfied with the Sale of the above Lands, made by them at <hi>Albany,</hi> and were deſirous 
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:008156_0021_102E3E77635E3EB8"/>
that Part of it ſhould be reſerved for them, though the Proprietaries had purchaſed it fairly of them, and paid <hi>One Thouſand Pieces of Eight,</hi> which was all they were to receive, till our People ſettled to the Weſtward of the <hi>Allegheny,</hi> or <hi>Appalaccian Hills.</hi> Sir <hi>William Johnſon</hi> repreſented this Matter to the Proprietaries, in your Behalf, whereupon they chearfully agreed to releaſe to you all that Part of the Purchaſe you have reclaimed, and, by a Letter of Attorney, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered <hi>Richard Peters,</hi> and <hi>Conrad Weiſer,</hi> to execute a Deed to you for thoſe Lands, on your confirming to them the Reſidue of that Purchaſe. On this Subject therefore you will pleaſe to confer with them, and ſettle the Boundaries between you, that they may releaſe the Lands to you accordingly, before you leave this Place, and ſet your Minds at Eaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thank you for the Pains you have taken with your Nephews, to prevail with them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn us ſuch of our Brethren as are Priſoners among them, and we depend on the ſpeedy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of their Promiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have ſomething to ſay to you which is of the utmoſt Importance to us all; it requires your particular Attention and Conſideration. Providence has brought you and your Nephews to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at this Meeting, Face to Face with us, that every Thing may be ſettled, and nothing remain, not ſo much as a Doubt, to create any Uneaſineſs in our Hearts hereafter. You know, Brethren, that there is an old Agreement between the Proprietaries and you, that you will not ſell any of the Lands lying within this Province to any one but them, and they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver take Poſſeſſion of Lands t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> they have bought them of the <hi>Indians.</hi> You know alſo, that the <hi>United Nations</hi> have ſold Lands to the Proprietaries, which your Nephews the <hi>Delawares</hi> now claim as their Right. This is the Caſe with Regard to ſome Part of the Lands lying between <hi>Toiccon</hi> Creek and the Head of <hi>Delaware</hi> River, which <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> in your Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Day before Yeſterday, ſaid, the Proprietaries had defrauded him of. The Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries are deſirous to do ſtrict Juſtice to all the <hi>Indians,</hi> but it cannot be ſuppoſed they can know in which of you the Right was veſted. It is a Matter that muſt be ſettled among your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; till this is done, there will probably remain ſome Jealouſy and Diſcontent among you, that may interrupt both your and our future Quiet, which we ſhould guard againſt by all Means in our Power.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I now acquaint you, that a Store of all Sorts of Goods for your Uſe is opened at <hi>Shamokin,</hi> where the <hi>Indians</hi> may be ſupplied, at the moſt reaſonable Rates, with any Goods they want, and the beſt Prices will be given to you for ſuch Skins, Furs and Peltry, as you ſhall bring them. Another Store is intended to be opened at <hi>Fort Allen,</hi> and you may depend upon it that ſuch Perſons will be placed there, who ſhall uſe you with the ſtricteſt Juſtice in all their Dealings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brother</hi> Teedyuſcung,</p>
               <p>As I underſtood at our laſt Meeting, that you were prevented at that Time, by the Abſence of ſome of the <hi>Six Nation</hi> Chiefs, from finiſhing what you then had to ſay, I defer an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, for the preſent, ſuch Parts of your Speech as relate to me. But I ſhall ſoon take an Opportunity of doing it.</p>
               <p>This was interpreted to the <hi>Delawares</hi> by <hi>Iſaac Stille.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the Governor had done ſpeaking, <hi>Tagaſhata</hi> and <hi>Nichas</hi> aroſe, and ſaid, they did not rightly underſtand that Paragraph relating to the Lands, and requiring them to ſettle Matters among themſelves; they ſaid the Governor had left Matters in the Dark; they did not know what Lands he meant. If he meant the Lands on the other Side of the Mountain, he knew the Proprietaries had their Deeds for them, which ought to be produced and ſhewn to them. Their Deeds had their Marks, and when they ſhould ſee them, they would know their Marks again.</p>
               <p>And then <hi>Conrad Weiſer</hi> being deſired to bring the Deed, Governor <hi>Bernard</hi> informed the <hi>Indians</hi> he was going to ſpeak to them; on which they acquainted him, that they choſe to be ſpoke to by one Governor only at a Conference; for that when they both ſpoke, their Belts were mixed, and they were thereby confuſed in their Councils. Whereupon he deferred his Speech to another Time.</p>
               <p>The Deed was then produced to the <hi>Indians,</hi> and <hi>Nichas</hi> ſaid, this Deed we well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; we know our Chiefs who ſigned it; ſome of them are preſent now; we ſold the Land, and were honeſtly paid for it; the Land was ours, and we will juſtify it. They were deſired 
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:008156_0022_102E3E79E8F6E870"/>
to take it with them into their Council Room, and confer on it, and ſettle the Matter among themſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Conference then broke up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> having Yeſterday requeſted of the Governor, that two Belts, which he then preſented to him, might be ſent as their joint Belts to the <hi>Ohio Indians:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Day the Chiefs of the <hi>United Nations,</hi> and <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> had a Meeting with two Members of Governor <hi>Denny</hi>'s Council, at which the following intended Anſwer from Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor <hi>Denny</hi> to the <hi>Ohio Indians,</hi> being firſt interpreted to the <hi>Indians,</hi> was conſidered, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled, and approved by all preſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Governor</hi> DENNY'<hi>s Anſwer to the Meſſage of the</hi> Ohio Indians, <hi>brought by</hi> Frederick Poſt, Piſquitomen, <hi>and</hi> Thomas Hickman.</p>
               <p>BY this String, my <hi>Indian</hi> Brethren of the <hi>United Nations</hi> and <hi>Delawares,</hi> join with me in requiring of the <hi>Indian</hi> Councils, to which theſe following Meſſages ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, to keep every Thing private from the Eyes and Ears of the <hi>French.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We received your Meſſage by <hi>Piſquitomen</hi> and <hi>Frederick Poſt,</hi> and thank you for the Care you have taken of our Meſſenger of Peace, and that you have put him in your Boſom, and protected him againſt our Enemy <hi>Onontio</hi> and his Children, and ſent him ſafe back to our Council Fire, by the ſame Man that received him from us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I only ſent <hi>Poſt</hi> to peep into your Cabbins, and to know the Sentiments of your old Men, and to look at your Faces, to ſee how you look. And I am glad to hear from him that you look friendly, and that there ſtill remains ſome Sparks of Love towards us. It is what we believed before-hand, and therefore we never let ſlip the Chain of Friendſhip, but held it faſt on our Side, and it has never dropped our of our Hands. By this Belt we deſire you will dig up your End of the Chain of Friendſhip, that you ſuffered, by the Subtilty of the <hi>French,</hi> to be buried.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It happened that the Governor of <hi>Jerſey</hi> was with me, and a great many <hi>Indian</hi> Brethren, ſitting in Council at <hi>Eaſton,</hi> when your Meſſengers arrived, and it gave Pleaſure to every one that heard it; and it will afford the ſame Satisfaction to our neighbouring Governors, and their People, when they come to hear it. I ſhall ſend Meſſengers to them, and acquaint them with what you have ſaid.</p>
               <p>Your requeſting us to let the King of <hi>England</hi> know your good Diſpoſitions, we took to Heart, and ſhall let him know it, and we will ſpeak in your Favour to His Majeſty, who has, for ſome Time paſt, looked upon you as his loſt Children. And we can aſſure you, that, as a tender Father over all his Children, he will forgive what is paſt, and receive you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into his Arms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Belt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you are in Earneſt to be reconciled to us, you will keep your young Men from attack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Country, and killing and carrying Captive, our Back Inhabitants. And will likewiſe give Orders that your People may be kept at a Diſtance from <hi>Fort Duqueſne,</hi> that they may not be hurt by our Warriors, who are ſent by our King to chaſtiſe the <hi>French,</hi> and not to hurt you. Conſider the commanding Officer of that Army treads heavy, and would be very ſorry to hurt any of his <hi>Indian</hi> Brethren.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A large Pelt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Chiefs of the <hi>United Nations,</hi> with their Couſins, our Brethren the <hi>Delawares,</hi> and others now here, jointly with me ſend this Belt, which has upon it two Figures that repreſent all the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and all the <hi>Indians</hi> now preſent, taking Hands, and delivering it to <hi>Piſquito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and we deſire it may be likewiſe ſent to the <hi>Indians,</hi> who are named at the End of theſe Meſſages
<note n="*" place="bottom">Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>agh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſy, Anigh Kalicko<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Atewateany, Towigh Towighr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>o, Geghdag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ghr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, Oyagh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, Siſaghroano, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iagg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ghro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o, Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>adyh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>go.</note>; as they have all been formerly our very good Friends and Allies; and we deſire they will all go from among the <hi>French</hi> to their own Towns, and no longer help the <hi>French.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren on the</hi> Ohio,</p>
               <p>If you take the Belts we juſt now gave you, in which all here join, <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Indians,</hi> as we don't doubt you will; then, by this Belt, I make a Road for you, and invite you to <pb n="23" facs="unknown:008156_0023_102E3E7B70679618"/>come to <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> to your firſt old Council Fire, which was kindled when we firſt ſaw one another; which Fire we will kindle up again, and remove all Diſputes, and renew the old and firſt Treaties of Friendſhip. This is a clear and open Road for you; fear therefore nothing, and come to us with as many as can be, of the <hi>Delawares, Shawaneſe,</hi> or of the <hi>Six Nation Indians.</hi> We will be glad to ſee you; we deſire all Tribes and Nations of <hi>Indians,</hi> who are in Alliance with you, may come. As ſoon as we hear of your coming, of which you will give us timely Notice, we will lay up Proviſions for you along the Road.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A large white Belt, with the Figure of a Man at each End, and Streaks of black, repreſenting the Road from the</hi> Ohio <hi>to</hi> Philadelphia.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Six Nation</hi> and <hi>Delaware</hi> Chiefs join with me in thoſe Belts, which are tied to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to ſignify our Union and Friendſhip for each other; with them we jointly take the Tomahawks out of your Heads, and bury them under Ground.</p>
               <p>We ſpeak loud, ſo as you may hear us; you ſee we all ſtand together, joined Hand in Hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two Belts tied together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Indian</hi> Chiefs being aſked, if it would not be proper to inſert in the Meſſage an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Situation of our Army to the Weſtward, and to deſire them to join General <hi>Forbes,</hi> againſt the <hi>French</hi>; they replied, that they would by no Means adviſe this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo ſoon to preſs them to take up the Hatchet, becauſe their Wounds were not yet heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor Peace made, which muſt firſt be done. They ſaid further, that as the <hi>French</hi> had many <hi>Indians</hi> fighting for them, and they by Intermarriages were related to the <hi>Indians</hi> who ſent the Meſſages, it could not be expected they would eaſily be perſuaded to join the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt they ſhould kill their own Fleſh and Blood, adding, that the only proper Meaſure that could now be taken, was to adviſe them to ſit ſtill, and keep out of the Way, and this Advice they believed would be hearkened to.</p>
               <p>They then deſired, that at leaſt two of our Inhabitants might accompany <hi>Piſquitomen</hi> and <hi>Thomas Hickman,</hi> the two Meſſengers, to the <hi>Ohio.</hi> The <hi>Six Nation</hi> Chiefs promiſed to ſend two of their own People with them; and <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> ſaid he would ſend one, it not two <hi>Delawares.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>At a private</hi> CONFERENCE <hi>with the</hi> Indians, <hi>held at</hi> Eaſton, October 21, 1758,</head>
               <p>PRESENT,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>His Excellency Governor</hi> BERNARD, <hi>and the</hi> Jerſey <hi>Commiſſioners</hi>;</item>
                     <item>THOMAS KING, <hi>Chief of the</hi> Oneidoes,</item>
                     <item>TAGASHATA, <hi>Chief of the</hi> Senecas,</item>
                     <item>TOKAAIO, <hi>Chief of the</hi> Cayugas,</item>
                     <item>EGOHOHOWEN, <hi>Chief of the</hi> Miniſinks,</item>
                     <item>NIMHAM, <hi>Chief of the</hi> Wapings, <hi>with other</hi> Indians <hi>of the ſeveral Nations</hi>;</item>
                     <item>GEORGE CROGHAN, <hi>Deputy to Sir</hi> WILLIAM JOHNSON,</item>
                     <item>ANDREW MONTOUR, <hi>His Majeſty's Interpreter to the</hi> United Nations,</item>
                     <item>STEPHEN CALVIN, <hi>Interpreter of the</hi> Delaware <hi>and</hi> Miniſink <hi>Languages.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>HIS Excellency informed them, that he met them to agree about the Price of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain Claims of the <hi>Miniſinks, Wapings,</hi> and other <hi>Indians,</hi> Claimants of Land in the Northern Parts of the Province of <hi>New-Jerſey,</hi> and deſired that it might be conſidered, that they knew not what they ſold, and he knew not what he bought; therefore the Price ought not to be large.</p>
               <p>That they might propoſe a Sum to him, or he would make an Offer to them; or it ſhould be left to their Uncles to confider of a Price, as would pleaſe them beſt.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Mingoes,</hi> or <hi>Six United Nations,</hi> by <hi>Thomas King,</hi> ſaid, that the <hi>United Nations</hi> had no Claim to the Lands of the <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> or others their Nephews, on the Eaſt Side of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laware,</hi> and ſhould therefore leave the fixing a Price to them.</p>
               <p>Then the <hi>Miniſinks</hi> and <hi>Wapings</hi> withdrew to conſult upon it; and being returned, <hi>Ego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hohowen,</hi> the <hi>Miniſink</hi> Chief, ſaid, they would chuſe the Governor ſhould make an Offer, as they might perhaps demand too much.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="unknown:008156_0024_102E3E804698D7C0"/>His Excellency, having conſulted the Commiſſioners, offered them <hi>Eight Hundred</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Dollars</hi> for their Claim in <hi>New-Jerſey,</hi> as an extraordinary Price.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Miniſinks</hi> ſaid, they ſhould be glad of the Opinion of their Uncles in the Matter.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Mingoes,</hi> or <hi>United Nations,</hi> by <hi>Thomas King,</hi> ſaid, that it was a fair and honourable Offer, and that if it were their own Caſe, they would chearfully accept of it; but as there were a great many Perſons to ſhare in the Purchaſe-money, they recommended it to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency to add <hi>Two Hundred Dollars</hi> more; and if that was complied with, the Report of it would be carried to all the Nations, and would be a great Proof of the Affection and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity of their Brethren the <hi>Engliſh</hi> on this Occaſion, and would be very agreeable to them.</p>
               <p>His Excellency deſired to know of the <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> and other Claimants, if they approved of the Propoſal of their Uncles, and they informed him that they did.</p>
               <p>The Governor, after conſulting the Commiſſioners, ſaid, it was more than he had intended to give; but as the <hi>United Nations</hi> had given themſelves the Trouble of being Med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, he could not refuſe their Recommendations, and was glad of the Opportunity he had of ſhewing his Regard to the <hi>United Nations,</hi> and his Benevolence to the <hi>Miniſink</hi> and other <hi>Indians,</hi> who had reſided in the Province where he preſided, and therefore complied with their Requeſt.</p>
               <p>His Excellency then deſired them to remember, that this Conſideration Money was to be in full for the Claims of all the <hi>Miniſink</hi> and <hi>Waping Indians,</hi> and all others who claim any Lands in a Map, which was laid before them at the ſame Time, which included all the Lands from the Line between the Provinces of <hi>New-York</hi> and <hi>New-Jerſey,</hi> and down <hi>Hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s River, to the Mouth of <hi>Rariton,</hi> up the ſame to <hi>Laometang</hi> Falls, on the North Branch of <hi>Rariton</hi> River; thence on a ſtrait Line to <hi>Paeoqualin</hi> Mountain, where it joins on <hi>Dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware</hi> River; and thence up the <hi>Delaware</hi> to <hi>Cuſhyhink</hi>; and recommended it to them to have reſpect to this in the Diviſion of the Conſideration Money.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Tagaſhata,</hi> the <hi>Seneca</hi> Chief, aroſe, and, addreſſing himſelf to the <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> and other <hi>Indian</hi> Claimants, ſpoke as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Nephews,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I deſire you will now give over all Thoughts of your Land, and that we may hear no more Complaints about it.</p>
               <p>Now you muſt remember the Friendſhip between you and your Brother, and tranſmit it to your Children; and make them acquainted with the Tranſactions of this Day. I recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this to you, not from my Lips only, but from the Bottom of my Heart. I hope it will alſo make a deep Impreſſion in your Hearts.</p>
               <p>It ſeems as if your Grandfathers had not told you of the Treaties they uſed to have with their Brethren, but carried them with them to the Grave. But we hope you will not do ſo, but carefully inform your Children of your Agreements. We have given you this Advice, and hope you will follow it. We alſo expect you will take Care of your young Men, that they do no more Violence to their Brethren the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Egohohowen</hi> then addreſſed himſelf to the Governor, and deſired to be heard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brother,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are now thoroughly ſatisfied, and we ſtill retain a Friendſhip for our Brethren the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> and we deſire, that if we ſhould come into your Province to ſee our old Friends, and ſhould have Occaſion for the Bark of a Tree to over a Cabbin, or a little Refreſhment, that we ſhould not be denied, but be treated as Brethren; and that your People may not look on the wild Beaſts of the Foreſt, or Fiſh of the Waters, as their ſole Property, but that we may be admitted to an equal Uſe of them.</p>
               <p>The Governor anſwered, that, as ſoon as he got home, he ſhould iſſue a Proclamation to notify to the People of his Province, that he had made a Peace with them; and to order, that, for the future, they ſhould be treated as Brethren, which he hoped would be done; but deſired that they would not go into thoſe Parts where they had lately committed Hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, till the Peoples Paſſions were cooled; for he could not be anſwerable for his Peoples Behaviour, whilſt their Loſſes were freſh upon their Minds.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="unknown:008156_0025_102E3E81D98D9C58"/>On the 21ſt of <hi>October</hi> the Members of the <hi>Pennſylvania</hi> Council received a Meſſage from Mr. <hi>Weiſer,</hi> that the Chiefs of the <hi>United Nations</hi> were met in Council, with their Nephews the <hi>Delawares,</hi> at the Houſe of <hi>Nicholas Scull,</hi> and that the <hi>Delawares</hi> had ſomething to ſay to their Uncles, which they deſired ſome of the Members of that Council, and Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſhould be Witneſſes of, and hear.</p>
               <p>Meſſieurs <hi>Growdon, Chew,</hi> and <hi>Miſſlin,</hi> attended accordingly, with Meſſieurs <hi>Galloway, Fox,</hi> and <hi>Hughes,</hi> Commiſſioners, and <hi>Iſrael Pemberton, Iſaac Zane,</hi> and ſome other <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> who were preſent at this particular Requeſt of the <hi>Delawares.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>PRESENT,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>All the</hi> Six Nation Chiefs,</item>
                     <item>TEEDYUSCUNG,</item>
                     <item>TAPISCAWEN, <hi>alias Samuel Davis,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>NOWALEKEEKA, <hi>or Four Steps,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>COMPASS,</item>
                     <item>AWEHELA, <hi>alias James Davis,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>LAPPINK,</item>
                     <item>NECCOCHOON, <hi>Munſey Chief,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>MOSES TITTAMY,</item>
                     <item>CONRAD WEISER, ANDREW MONTOUR, ISAAC SLILLE, <hi>Interpreters.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Teedyuſcung, <hi>on Behalf of the</hi> Delawares, <hi>aroſe, and ſpoke as follows.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uncles,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I DESIRE you will hear me. We have gone ſo far at this Treaty as to talk of Lands; I therefore thought proper to meet you here, to let you know that I have conſulted with all my Brethren, your Couſins, here preſent, about the Deed you, our Uncles, ſigned to the Proprietaries of <hi>Pennſylvania,</hi> ſhewn to us Yeſterday, for the Lands beyond the <hi>Kittochtinny</hi> Hills.</p>
               <p>We have ſeen the Deed, and know it well. <hi>Nutimus,</hi> one of our Chief Men, has ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, and here ſits one of our Men, named <hi>Philip Compaſs,</hi> who was preſent when the Sale was made; and remembers that <hi>Nutimus,</hi> our Chief, received <hi>Forty-four Dollars,</hi> as his Part or Share of the Conſideration Money. We agree to it, and acknowledge that the Land was fairly ſold. We give it up, and now confirm it. Let there be no Difference, nor any Thing more ſaid about it. This is not the Land I have diſputed with my Brethren the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</hi> That Land lies between <hi>Tohiccon</hi> Creek and the <hi>Kittochtinny</hi> Hills.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gave a String.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tokaaion,</hi> the <hi>Cayuga</hi> Chief, ſtood up and ſpoke as follows, addreſſing himſelf to <hi>Teedyuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cung.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Couſin,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thank you for your Openneſs and Honeſty on this Occaſion, freely to declare the Truth. We wiſh our Brethren the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> naming the Governors of <hi>Pennſylvania, Virginia, Caro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina</hi> and <hi>Jerſey,</hi> were ſo honeſt and preciſe.</p>
               <p>They have called us down to this Council Fire, which was kindled for Council Affairs, to renew Treaties of Friendſhip, and brighten the Chain of Friendſhip. But here we muſt hear a Diſpute about Land, and our Time is taken up, but they don't come to the chief Point.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> firſt began to do Miſchief; we told them ſo. They only thanked us for our Openneſs and Advice, and ſaid they would take Care for the future, but healed no Wounds. In ſhort, when they ſpeak to us, they do it with a ſhorter Beſt or String than that which we ſpoke to them with; tho' they can make Wampum, and we cannot.</p>
               <p>They ought not thus to treat with <hi>Indians</hi> on Council Affairs. Several of our ſtrong Belts are loſt in their Hands entirely. I fear they only ſpeak from their Mouth, and not from their Heart.</p>
               <p>On the ſame Day, <hi>P. M. Piſquitomen</hi> and <hi>Thomas Hickman</hi> came to take their Leave of the Governor, accompanied with Captain <hi>Bull, William Hayes,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac Stille,</hi> the Perſons appointed to attend them to the <hi>Ohio,</hi> who were particularly recommended to their Care and Protection by a String of Wampum.</p>
               <p>The Belts and Strings were numbered, as well in the written Paper containing the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, as on Labels tied to each of them, and delivered to <hi>Piſquitomen,</hi> and the written Meſſage was delivered, with the Paſſports, to Captain <hi>Bull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="unknown:008156_0026_102DD04980338380"/>The 22d of <hi>October,</hi> the <hi>Six Nation</hi> Chiefs held a private Council, and named two of their People to ſend to the <hi>Ohio,</hi> viz. <hi>Tojenontawoby,</hi> a <hi>Cayuga</hi> Chief, and the youngeſt <hi>Shick Calamy,</hi> who joined <hi>Piſquitemen,</hi> and ſet off this Afternoon. As they were ſetting out, Mr. <hi>Frederick Poſt</hi> arrived with News from General <hi>Forbes,</hi> that a large Body of <hi>French</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> having attacked his advanced Poſt at <hi>Loyal Hanning,</hi> were repulſed with great Loſs on their Side; which News he communicated to the <hi>Indians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At Noon the Governors, being prepared for a Conference, propoſed a Meeting of the <hi>Indians,</hi> which they deſired might be deferred till the Morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>October</hi> 23, 1758.</head>
               <p>This Morning one of the <hi>Seneca</hi> Chiefs died; Condolence Ceremonies, and Preſents being made as uſual, he was decently interred, a Number of the Inhabitants attending the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. This took up the Forenoon.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>At a</hi> CONFERENCE <hi>with the</hi> Indians, <hi>the ſame Day,</hi> P. M.</head>
                  <p>PRESENT, <hi>The</hi> GOVERNORS, <hi>and the Gentlemen of their Councils,</hi> &amp;cc. <hi>as before.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>THE Minutes were read, and approved, to the End of the publick Conference on <hi>Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> laſt; after which Governor <hi>Denny</hi> ſpoke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By this Belt, we heal your Wounds, we remove your Grief; we take the Hatchet out of your Heads; we make a deep Hole in the Earth, and bury the Hatchet ſo low, that no Body ſhall be able to dig it up again.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Belt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now we have healed your Wounds, we, by this Belt, renew all our Treaties; we bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the Chain of Friendſhip; we return to our firſt Affection; we confirm our ancient Union; we put freſh Earth to the Roots of the Tree of Peace, that it may bear up againſt every Storm that can blow, and live and flouriſh to the End of Time, whilſt the Sun ſhines, and the Rivers run. And we deſire you would publiſh it among your own, and all other <hi>Indian,</hi> Nations, who are your Friends and Allies, and engage them to join with you in a firm Peace with His Majeſty, and all His Subjects; in whoſe Behalf I give you this Belt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A large Peace Belt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We now open a Road to the old Council Fire, which was kindled by your and our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the City of <hi>Philadelphia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Be aſſured, that you will always find this Road open, eaſy and pleaſant to travel in, and, for the feature, whenever Occaſion calls, we ſhall be glad to ſee you there.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Belt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren of the</hi> United Nations, <hi>and all our other Brethren, your Couſins and Nephews,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We thank you for the Care and Diligence with which you have attended to the ſeveral Matters recommended to you in theſe Conferences, which has yielded us Abundance of Satisfaction.</p>
                  <p>This Treaty will convince all our Enemies, that we are now united in the firmeſt Band of Amity; and whilſt we join our Strength together, it will not be in their Power to hurt either you or us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Belt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As a Token of the Love we your Brethren of this Province bear to you, I ſhall make a Preſent of a Quantity of Goods, which we have prepared for you, and deſire your Accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of them; ſenſible of the approaching Seaſon, and of the many Difficulties you live under, from the preſent War. We give it with an hearty Good-will.</p>
                  <p>Here his Honour delivered a Liſt of the Goods, and deſired Mr. <hi>Weiſer,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Montour,</hi> would interpret it to them at a proper Time.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="27" facs="unknown:008156_0027_102E3E86E3C2E840"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>INVOICE of</hi> Indian <hi>GOODS brought to</hi> Eaſton.</head>
                     <item>3 Groce of narrow ſtarred Gartering.</item>
                     <item>4 Ditto of broad Star.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of middle Star.</item>
                     <item>4 Ditto of narrow <hi>Scotch.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of middle <hi>Turkey.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of broad <hi>Turkey.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 Ditto of beſt <hi>Scotch.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5 Ditto of mixt figured.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of narrow Calimancoe.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of broad Calimancoe.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of ſpotted.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of Leaf.</item>
                     <item>1 Ditto of <hi>London</hi> lettered.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of plad.</item>
                     <item>3 Ditto of middle Scarlet.</item>
                     <item>4 Ditto of broad Scarlet.</item>
                     <item>3 Ditto of ſuperfine.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of Boys, lettered.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of broad white lettered.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of coloured Pigeon.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of Camblet.</item>
                     <item>33 Painted Looking-glaſſes.</item>
                     <item>8 Pieces of red Stroud.</item>
                     <item>4 Ditto.</item>
                     <item>14 Ditto of Mazarine Blue.</item>
                     <item>1 Ditto.</item>
                     <item>1 Ditto black.</item>
                     <item>1 Ditto red, and one blue.</item>
                     <item>2 Pieces of 6-qr. blue Duffil.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of 7-8ths Ditto.</item>
                     <item>1 Ditto napped.</item>
                     <item>1 Piece of ſtamped Serge.</item>
                     <item>1 Piece of red Halfthicks.</item>
                     <item>1 Piece of brown Halfthicks.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of white Ditto.</item>
                     <item>1 Piece of blue Broadcloth.</item>
                     <item>5 Laced Coats.</item>
                     <item>8 Plain Ditto.</item>
                     <item>50 Pair of Shoes.</item>
                     <item>3 Dozen and one Pair of Womens Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted Stockings.</item>
                     <item>Ditto of Yarn Ditto.</item>
                     <item>4 Pieces and 2 Bandanoe Handkerchiefs.</item>
                     <item>1 Ditto Lungee Romals.</item>
                     <item>1 Ditto of Cotton Romals.</item>
                     <item>4 Ditto of Nonſopretties.</item>
                     <item>8 lb. Coloured Thread.</item>
                     <item>3 Dozen and ten Worſted Caps.</item>
                     <item>2 Ditto of Knives.</item>
                     <item>1 Ditto of Tobacco-boxes.</item>
                     <item>1 Ditto of coarſe Linen Handkerchiefs.</item>
                     <item>4 Pieces of figured Gartering.</item>
                     <item>4 Ditto of blue and white flowered Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchiefs.</item>
                     <item>3 Dozen and ten plain Hats.</item>
                     <item>2 Dozen of Taylors Shears.</item>
                     <item>6 Gun-Locks.</item>
                     <item>1 Bunch of black Beads.</item>
                     <item>3 Groce and an Half of Sleeve Link But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons.</item>
                     <item>4 Dozen of Ivory Combs.</item>
                     <item>1 Groce of Womens Thimbles.</item>
                     <item>100 Blankets.</item>
                     <item>160 Matchcoats.</item>
                     <item>246 Shirts, plain.</item>
                     <item>187 Ditto, ruffled.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brother</hi> Teedyuſcung,</p>
                  <p>By this Belt you put me in Mind, that we formerly referred our Diſpute about Lands to our Father King GEORGE, and you deſired to know if he has decided it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brother,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You ſhould conſider the Circumſtances of the Affairs of your Father King GEORGE; His Majeſty lives at a very great Diſtance from us, is now engaged in a War with the <hi>French,</hi> and the Buſineſs of War takes up a great deal of Time and Attention; beſides, in Time of War, we have but few Opportunities of hearing from him.</p>
                  <p>As yet I have had no Anſwer relative to your Affairs. You may depend upon it, as ſoon as I receive one, it ſhall be communicated to you. And I can aſſure you, the Proprietaries have preſſed Diſpatch, and will do every Thing they can to bring it to a ſpeedy Determination.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Belt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then Governor <hi>Bernard,</hi> requeſting the Attention of the <hi>Indians,</hi> addreſſed them as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren of the</hi> United Nations,</p>
                  <p>By this String you ſpoke on Behalf of our Brethren the <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> and ſaid that they were wronged in their Lands; that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſettled ſo faſt, that they were continually puſhing them back; and when they aſked for their Lands, they were told that they had ſold their Lands, and had got drunk, and forgot it. If they had ſwallowed their Lands, they muſt be content, but they did not believe that they had ſwallowed all, but that ſome was left. They deſired that I would enquire after their Lands that were left, and do them Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am glad I have an Opportunity, in the Preſence of ſo many Nations, to expreſs the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire I have of doing Juſtice to every one. The Throne of the Great King it founded on Juſtice, and I ſhould not be a faithful Servant to him, if I neglected to give Redreſs to all Perſons that have received Injuries from the People over whom the Great King has placed me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="unknown:008156_0028_102E3E8AAABF86F8"/>I have therefore had a Conference with the <hi>Miniſinks,</hi> in the Preſence of ſome of their Uncles, and have come to a full Agreement with them; the Proceedings of which are now ready to be read to you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have another Proof to give you of the Uprightneſs and Juſtice of our Province. We have come to an Agreement with the <hi>Delaware Indians,</hi> and other <hi>Indians,</hi> for the uncertain Claims they had on the Southern Parts of our Province; I hereby produce the Deeds that have been executed on this Occaſion, that the Subject of them may be explained to you, and be had in perpetual Remembrance by all the Nations preſent; and I deſire that you may all remember, that, by theſe two Agreements, the Province of <hi>New-Jerſey</hi> is entirely freed and diſcharged from all <hi>Indian</hi> Claims. In Confirmation of which I give you this Belt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Belt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brother</hi> Teedyuſcung,</p>
                  <p>By this String you tell me, that, after the killing the nine <hi>Indians</hi> near <hi>Eſopus,</hi> you carried three Belts to <hi>George Freeland,</hi> who undertook to give them to the Governor, and you aſk what is become of thoſe Belts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brother,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I can only ſay, that I never heard of thoſe Belts before; nor do I know what Governor <hi>George Freeland</hi> undertook to carry thoſe Belts to. The proper Governor was the Governor of <hi>New-York</hi>; for in his Province was this Miſchief committed. And probably the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>New-York</hi> had theſe Belts; for I have heard that he iſſued a Proclamation for appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the Perpretrators of this Fact. This Fact has been blamed by all good and wife Men; and I am glad it was not done by the People of my Province. I will acquaint the Governor of <hi>New-York</hi> with what you have ſaid upon this Occaſion, and I will enquire after thoſe Belts, and give you an Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A String.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Governor <hi>Denny,</hi> being obliged to return to <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> on urgent Buſineſs, took his Leave of the <hi>Indians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brethren,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It gives me great Pleaſure that the Buſineſs of this Treaty has been carried on with ſo much Satisfaction.</p>
                  <p>I am ſorry I am now to inform you, that I am obliged to leave you, having received laſt Night an Expreſs from General <hi>Forbes,</hi> who is now near the <hi>Ohio.</hi> My Buſineſs calls me to Town, I ſhall therefore leave Mr. <hi>Logan</hi> and Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> to tranſact the Remainder of the Buſineſs, and doubt not but they will act to your Satisfaction.</p>
                  <p>I aſſure you of my Affection for you, and wiſh you all Manner of Happineſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> aroſe, and deſired to be heard on Behalf of the <hi>Wapings,</hi> or <hi>Wapinger Indians,</hi> called the <hi>River Indians,</hi> living near <hi>Eſopus,</hi> and produced a ſhort broad Belt of white Wam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum, having in the Center two Hearts, of a reddiſh Colour, and in Figures 1745, wrote after the following Manner, 17♥♥45. The Belt had a round Circle Pendant, repreſenting the Sun; he then produced two Certificates, one from Governor <hi>Clinton,</hi> and the other from Governor <hi>Hardy,</hi> both which were much in Favour of the <hi>Wapinger</hi> Tribe of <hi>Indians.</hi> He ſaid the Belt was given them by the Government of <hi>New-York,</hi> and repreſented their Union, which was to laſt as long as the Sun ſhould continue in the Firmament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> addreſſed Governor <hi>Bernard,</hi> deſiring, by a String of Wampum, that he would extend his Protection to the Tribe of the <hi>Wapings</hi>; and as their Chief was old and infirm, he requeſted the Favour of a Horſe to carry him home, which was readily granted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Takeaghſado,</hi> or <hi>Tagaſhata,</hi> made the ſame Requeſt to Governor <hi>Denny,</hi> which was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe granted.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Six Nation</hi> Chiefs conſulted together, and, in a little Time, <hi>Nichas,</hi> in their Behalf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> an Anſwer to the Speeches of the Governors, laying the Belts and Strings upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Order they were delivered, and repeating diſtinctly what was ſaid on each of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> At the End of every Article he returned Thanks, and expreſſed the higheſt Satisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> particularly on the ratifying the Peace, and the large Belt given thereupon, which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> be ſent to all the diſtant Nations of <hi>Indians,</hi> to whom it would be very agreeable; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> likewiſe promiſed, that every Thing tranſacted in theſe Conferences, which, he again 
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:008156_0029_102E3E8D33D1B770"/>
ſaid, had afforded him great Pleaſure, ſhould be laid before the great Council at <hi>Onondago,</hi> whoſe Anſwer ſhould be carefully tranſmitted. He thanked Governor <hi>Bernard</hi> for making up all the Differences between the Government and the <hi>Miniſink Indians,</hi> ſo much to their Satisfaction. He made an Apology for the Want of Wampum, and the Exchange of other Belts, to give in Confirmation of their Performance of the ſeveral Things mentioned in the Governor's Speeches, agreeable to <hi>Indian</hi> Cuſtoms. Then wiſhed Governor <hi>Denny</hi> a good Journey.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>October</hi> 24, 1758.</head>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Weiſer,</hi> the Proprietary Agents, held a private Conference with the Chiefs of the <hi>United Nations,</hi> at the Houſe of <hi>Adam Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> in <hi>Eaſton</hi>; at which were preſent,
<list>
                     <item>WILLIAM LOGAN, <hi>
                           <abbr>Eſq</abbr> of the Council.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>GEORGE CROGHAN, <hi>
                           <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Deputy Agent to Sir</hi> WILLIAM JOHNSON,</item>
                     <item>CHARLES SWAINE, <hi>
                           <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Prothonotary, of</hi> Northampton <hi>County,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> HENRY MONTOUR, <hi>Interpreter, and</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> JOHN WATSON, <hi>Surveyor, in the County of</hi> Bucks.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>
                              <hi>And there were likewiſe preſent the following</hi> Indians.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Kurtahtaaty,</hi> Chief of the <hi>Mohawks,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Seguchſonyont,</hi> Chief of the <hi>Oneidoes,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Aſſaradungua,</hi> Chief of the <hi>Onondagoes,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Tagaſhata,</hi> Chief of the <hi>Senecas,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Tok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>io,</hi> Chief of the <hi>Cayugas,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nichaqua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>h,</hi> Chief of the <hi>Tuſcaroras,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Conmach,</hi> Chief of the <hi>Conoys,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Robert White,</hi> Chief of the <hi>Nanticokes,</hi> and Several other <hi>Indians.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>MR. <hi>Peters,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Weiſer,</hi> in Virtue of a Power of Attorney from the Proprietaries of <hi>Pennſylvania</hi> to them, under the Great Seal of the ſaid Province, having previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſettled with the <hi>Indian</hi> Chiefs the Limits of the Lands to be releaſed by the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietaries; and of the Lands to be confirmed by the <hi>United Nations</hi>; the Proprietary Releaſe, and the <hi>Indians</hi> Deed of Confirmation were read and interpreted, and the <hi>Indians</hi> expreſſing their Satisfaction at every Part thereof, and particularly with the Limits, as deſcribed in the Draught annexed to their Confirmation Deed, they were both executed in the Preſence of <hi>Williams Logan, George Croghan, Henry Montour, Charles Swaine,</hi> and <hi>John Watſon,</hi> who ſubſcribed their Names, as Witneſſes ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. A Belt was given to the <hi>Indians</hi> at the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and it was agreed, that both Deeds ſhould be produced at the next publick Conference, in order to be acknowledged.</p>
               <p>On the 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th of <hi>October</hi> the <hi>Indians</hi> were employed all Day in dividing the Preſents among their ſeveral Tribes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>
                  <hi>At a</hi> CONFERENCE <hi>held at</hi> Eaſton, <hi>with the</hi> Indians, October 26, 1758.</head>
               <p>PRESENT,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>His Excellency Governor</hi> BERNARD,</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Eſquires.</head>
                           <item>WILLIAM LOGAN,</item>
                           <item>RICHARD PETERS,</item>
                           <item>ANDREW JOHNSON,</item>
                           <item>CHARLES READ,</item>
                           <item>JOHN STEPHENS,</item>
                           <item>GEORGE CROGHAN,</item>
                           <item>CONRAD WEISER,</item>
                           <item>CHARLES SWAINE,</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Major</hi> ORNDT,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Sheriff and his Officers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> JOHN WATSON,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Chiefs of the</hi> United Nations, <hi>and of the other Nations of Indians,</hi> Moſes Tittamy, <hi>and</hi> James Davis, <hi>and ſeveral other</hi> Delawares.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>THE Secretary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aving obſerved to the <hi>Six Nation</hi> Chiefs, that the Governors were charged, by <hi>Tokaaio,</hi> with having omitted ſome Things in their Anſwers, and deſired to know what they were; <hi>Thomas King</hi> ſaid they were afterwards ſupplied, and recommended ſome Things to be more particularly mentioned than they had been; and agreeably to this Advice the following Speech was ſpoke by the Members of the <hi>Pennſylvania</hi> Council.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As we have now ſettled all Differences, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> confirmed the antient Leagues of Amity, and Brightened the Chain of Friendſhip; we now clean the Blood off your Council Seats, and 
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:008156_0030_102E3E8EBAFDDE20"/>
put them in Order, that when you hold Councils at Home, you may ſit as you formerly uſed to do in your Seats, with the ſame Peace and Tranquility.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String, conſiſting of One Thouſand Grains of Wampum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With this String of Wampum we condole with you for the Loſs of your wife Men, and for the Warriors that have been killed theſe troubleſome Times, and likewiſe for your Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Children; and we cover their Graves decently, agreeable to the Cuſtom of your Forefathers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String of One Thouſand Grains of Wampum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We diſperſe the dark Clouds that have hung over our Heads during theſe Troubles, that we may ſee the Sun clear, and look on each other with the Chearfulneſs our Forefathers did.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String of One Thouſand Grains of Wampum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> and Mr. <hi>Weiſer</hi> produced the Confirmation Deed, executed by the Chiefs of the <hi>United Nations,</hi> as before ſet forth, which the <hi>Indian</hi> Chiefs acknowledged to have been their voluntary Act and Deed, and that they clearly underſtood the Contents thereof, together with the Limits deſcribed in the Draught annexed to it; and the ſame being handed from <hi>Indian</hi> to <hi>Indian,</hi> it was re-delivered to the Proprietaries Agents.</p>
               <p>After which the <hi>Indian</hi> Chiefs produced the Proprietary Deed of Releaſe, executed by Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Weiſer,</hi> the Proprietary Agents, who acknowledged it to be their Act and Deed, in Behalf of their Conſtituents, and re-delivered it to the <hi>Indians,</hi> together with the Belt.</p>
               <p>His Excellency Governor <hi>Bernard</hi> produced the following Deeds; one executed by five <hi>Indian</hi> Attorneys, appointed by a Council of the <hi>Delaware</hi> Nation, for all the Lands lying in <hi>New-Jerſey,</hi> South of a Line from <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>qualin</hi> Mountain, at <hi>Delaware</hi> River, to the Falls of <hi>Laometung,</hi> on the North Branch of <hi>Rariton</hi> River, and down that River to <hi>Sandy-Hook</hi>; dated the 12th of <hi>September</hi> laſt, with Endorſements thereon, made by <hi>Teedyuſcung, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Tepaſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on,</hi> ſignifying their Agreement thereto, and Acknowledgment of their having received Satisfaction thereon, witneſſed by three Chiefs of the <hi>United Nations,</hi> who, in Behalf of the <hi>United Nations,</hi> approved the Sale; and alſo by ſeveral <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
               <p>Another Deed, dated the 23d of <hi>October</hi> Inſtant, at <hi>Eaſton,</hi> from the Chiefs of the <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Wapings,</hi> or <hi>Pumptons,</hi> Sixteen in Number, and included all the remaining Lands in <hi>New-Jerſey,</hi> beginning at <hi>Cuſhetung,</hi> and down the Diviſion Line between <hi>New-Jerſey</hi> and <hi>New-York,</hi> to the Mouth of <hi>Tappon-Creek,</hi> at the <hi>North</hi> or <hi>Hudſon's River,</hi> and down the ſame to <hi>Sandy-Hook</hi>; then to the Mouth of <hi>Rariton</hi>; then up that River to <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>metung Falls</hi>; then on a ſtrait Line to <hi>Pacqualin,</hi> where it joins on <hi>Delaware</hi> River; and up <hi>Dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware</hi> to <hi>Cuſhetung</hi>; endorſed by <hi>Nimbass,</hi> a Chief of the <hi>Pumptons,</hi> or <hi>Wapings,</hi> who was ſick at the Execution thereof, and approved by the <hi>United Nations,</hi> which was teſtified by three of their Chiefs, ſigning as Witneſſes. And Governor <hi>Bernard</hi> deſired all preſent might take Notice of the ſame, the <hi>Indian</hi> Title to all the Lands in the Province of <hi>New-Jerſey</hi> being conveyed thereby; which being interpreted in the <hi>Six Nation</hi> and <hi>Delaware</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, his Excellency addreſſed the <hi>Indians,</hi> as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am very glad this good Work has been ſo happily finiſhed. I came among you, wholly unacquainted with your Forms, and therefore if I have omitted any Ceremonial, you will readily excuſe me. But in whatever I have been deficient, I am ſure I have not wanted a good Heart towards you.</p>
               <p>The Circumſtances of our Province have hitherto rendered us unable to give you any great Proofs of our Regard for you; but I ſhall endeavour to perſuade my People to do you good Service for the future, by opening a Communication with you, which, if rightly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged, will be much to the Advantage of both People. And, for my own Part, I ſhall be always ready to do you Juſtice, and deſire that whenever you have Cauſe of Complaint a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my People, you will take Care to ſignify it to me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A String.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Five Nation</hi> Chiefs having laid all the Belts and Strings on the Table, that were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered at this and the laſt Conference, the <hi>Cayuga</hi> Chief, <hi>Tokaaio,</hi> deſired the Governors, and all preſent, would hearken to what <hi>Thomas King</hi> was going to ſay on Behalf of the <hi>United Nations</hi> (now Eight in Number) on which <hi>Thomas King</hi> aroſe, and taking up the firſt Belt, which was given by <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> when he requeſted a Deed for the <hi>Wyomink</hi> Lands, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed the <hi>Delawares, Teedyuſcung</hi> not being preſent, as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="unknown:008156_0031_102E3E913B02F2E8"/>
                  <hi>Couſins,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this Belt <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> deſired us to make you the Owners of the Lands at <hi>Wyomink, Shamokin,</hi> and other Places on the <hi>Sqſquehannah</hi> River; in Anſwer to which, we who are preſent ſay, that we have no Power to convey Lands to any one; but we will take your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to the great Council Fire, for their Sentiments, as we never convey or ſell any Lands, before it be agreed in the great Council of the <hi>United Nations.</hi> In the mean Time you may make uſe of thoſe Lands, in Conjunction with our People, and all the reſt of our Relations, the <hi>Indians</hi> of the different Nations in our Alliance, which being interpreted in <hi>Delaware,</hi> the String of Wampum was given to <hi>Moſes Tittamy,</hi> and <hi>James Davis,</hi> to be delivered to <hi>Teedyuſcung,</hi> as he was not preſent.</p>
               <p>Then taking up each Belt and String, in the Order it was delivered in this and the laſt Conference, he proceeded to repeat diſtinctly what had been ſaid under each Article, return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Thanks for all thoſe good Speeches, which he ſaid were extremely agreeable: He made particular Mention of the large Peace Belt, ſaying, the Nations were vaſtly pleaſed, that all the antient Treaties made here, at <hi>Albany,</hi> and elſewhere, were renewed, as well as that the old Council Fire at <hi>Philadelphia</hi> was kindled again, and a good Road made to it, that might be travelled without any Danger; theſe in particular, as well as every other Matter tranſacted at theſe Conferences, we will make known to our own Nations, and to every other in Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Alliance with us; and we are ſure they will be very well received.</p>
               <p>Then, addreſſing Governor <hi>Bernard,</hi> they thanked him for his Farewel Speech, ſaying, it was a very kind one, and that they were very glad at his having been preſent and given his Aſſiſtance at this Treaty, which had given them an Opportunity of gaining an Acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with him, which they would ever remember with Pleaſure. After a Pauſe, he deſired to be excuſed in mentioning ſomething that had been omitted by the Governors and their Councils. You have forgot to bring with you Ammunition, of which we always uſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a ſufficient Quantity, not only to ſerve us in our Journey, but ſupport us in our hunting Seaſon, that we might be enabled to make Proviſion for our Families. You have given us Gun-Locks without Guns, which are of no Manner of Uſe to us; and therefore this muſt ſurely have been forgot, as it is impoſſible for <hi>Indians</hi> to ſubſiſt without Guns, Powder and Lead, of which we have received none.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As many of us are old and infirm, we deſire our Brethren will be ſo good as to furniſh us with a Number of Waggons to carry ſuch of us as are not able to walk with the Goods you have been pleaſed to give us, as far as <hi>Wyomink,</hi> where we have left our Canoes, and then we will diſcharge the Waggons. We further deſire a Supply of Proviſions may be put into the Waggons, enough to ſerve us till we get to our reſpective Habitations.</p>
               <p>He then took up the Proprietary Releaſe, and returned Thanks for it. He ſaid that, when the <hi>United Nations</hi> firſt made the Requeſt to Sir <hi>William Johnſon,</hi> to be tranſmitted to <hi>Onas,</hi> they had no Doubt but <hi>Onas</hi> would comply with it, having always found him ready to grant all their Requeſts; with him we have never had any Difference, he has always ſettled our Affairs without giving us any Trouble, and to our Satisfaction. We heartily thank <hi>Onas.</hi> This Act confirms us in the good Opinion we have always had of him.</p>
               <p>Then, addreſſing himſelf to the <hi>Delawares,</hi> with a String of Wampum, he ſpoke as follows.</p>
               <p>This ſerves to put <hi>Teedyuſcung</hi> in Mind of his Promiſes to return the Priſoners. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Couſin, you have made this Promiſe in our Preſence; you did it indeed before, and you ought to have performed it; it is a Shame for one who calls himſelf a great Man to tell Lies; let us, as Counſellors, perform our Engagements and Promiſes; Couſin, you muſt not now fail to perform your Word; we are all one People, and we muſt all of us be punctual in the Performance of our Engagements. This was interpreted in the <hi>Delaware</hi> Language, and the String was given to <hi>Moſes Tittamy</hi> for <hi>Teedyuſcung.</hi> He then ſaid the <hi>United Nations</hi> had finiſhed what they had to ſay.</p>
               <p>Looking round the Room, he eſpied Mr. <hi>Vernon,</hi> the Perſon who had the Care of furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Indians</hi> with Proviſions, and he deſired, that, now Council Buſineſs was over, he might be ordered to take the Lock off the Rum, and let it run freely; that, as they were going away, their Hearts might me made glad, and we could very well ſpare it, as it was of no Uſe to us.</p>
               <p>Some Wine and Punch was then ordered in, and the Conferences were concluded with great Joy and mutual Satisfaction.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The END</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
