<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the fearful estate of Francis Spira, after he turned apostate from the Protestant church to popery. In the year, 1548. / Compiled by Nath. Bacon, Esq;</title>
            <author>Bacon, Nathaniel, 1593-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N07112</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N07112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 9059</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX4950</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">9059</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99021730</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 9059.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N07112)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 9059)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 9059)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the fearful estate of Francis Spira, after he turned apostate from the Protestant church to popery. In the year, 1548. / Compiled by Nath. Bacon, Esq;</title>
                  <author>Bacon, Nathaniel, 1593-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>vi, 7-36 p. ;  17 cm. (12mo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Fowle and Draper, at their office opposite the Founder's-Arms, Marlborough-Street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DCC.LXII. [1762] (Price 6 pence).</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Parentheses substituted for square brackets in imprint transcription.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spira, Francesco, d. 1548.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church.</term>
               <term>Catholic converts.</term>
               <term>Apostasy.</term>
               <term>Atheism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:009059_0000_10306B022E35AA88"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:009059_0001_10306B03EAA39A88"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF THE Fearful Eſtate OF Francis Spira, After he turned <hi>Apoſtate</hi> from the <hi>Proteſtant Church</hi> to <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</hi> In the YEAR, 1548.</p>
            <p>Compiled by NATH. BACON, <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON:</hi> Printed and Sold by FOWLE and DRAPER, at their <hi>Office</hi> oppoſite the <hi>Founder</hi>'s-Arms, <hi>Marlborough-ſtreet.</hi> M.DCC.LXII.</p>
            <p>[Price 6 Pence.]</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="iii" facs="unknown:009059_0002_10306B07C6044498"/>
            <head>An Introduction.</head>
            <p>FOR the Truth of this Hiſtory enſuing, beſides circumſtances of place, perſon, time, occaſion, ſo exactly obſerved; I refer myſelf to the Relation of thoſe godly men, who in ſeveral languages have manifeſted to the world the ſeveral paſſages thereof; and although I am not ignorant, that at the firſt they were not only not credited, but alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credited and ſlandered by ſuch as found them to be a blur to the <hi>Roman</hi> profeſſion, yet they loſt not their luſtre thereby; but being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted by many compurgators of ſeveral na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſome of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> religion, being all of them ſpectators of this tragedy; it oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned not only a further manifeſtation and confirmation of the truth, but alſo a large and more frequent confluence to ſee that which they had formerly only heard of. This partly appears out of the ſucceeding ſtory; but more fully out of an apology written by <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerius</hi> biſhop of <hi>Juſtinople,</hi> who was accuſed for diſperſing the fame of this example to the ſtain of <hi>Popery,</hi> in which apology to <hi>N. Rotan,</hi> ſuffragan of <hi>Padua,</hi> is ſhortly and plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, what was ſaid, what was done, and who were preſent. If it be demanded, what moved me to compile this treatiſe? <hi>Spira,</hi>
               <pb n="iv" facs="unknown:009059_0003_10306B0DF3DE3A90"/>
tell them, that it ſhould teach fear and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: and indeed among all thoſe that came to ſee him, few or none returned unſhaken. <hi>Vergerius</hi> in his firſt epiſtle ſaith; <q>I would fain go ſee him again, but I exceedingly fear and tremble:" and in his apology ſaith, It is ſuch a rare example, as I would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly go to the furtheſt parts of the world to hear or ſee the like.</q> The lady <hi>Jane</hi> to her father's chaplain (who had fallen into <hi>Spira</hi>'s ſin) ſaith, <q>Remember the lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtate of <hi>Spira.</hi>
               </q> I acknowledge that there hath been formerly a book publiſhed in our mother-tongue, concerning this ſubject, but as far as I can learn (for I could never yet obtain to ſee any one of them) it was nothing ſo large and various as this preſent treatiſe: and as I have heard, a tranſlation of only one of the tractates, from whence I have gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this preſent diſcourſe in part. Concerning my care and fidelity in this buſineſs, it is ſuch as I may truly ſay without changing of colour, that there is not one ſentence of all this work attributed unto the perſon of <hi>Spira,</hi> but it hath its warrant, either from the epiſtles of <hi>Verge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> and <hi>Geribaldus,</hi> profeſſors of the law in <hi>Padua,</hi> or from the diſcourſes of <hi>Henry Scrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, a Scotchman, Sigiſmund Gelons,</hi> a <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvanian,</hi> and <hi>Mart. Bocha</hi> a divine of <hi>Baſil:</hi>
               <pb n="v" facs="unknown:009059_0004_10306B109FA24440"/>
neither have I taken any other liberty than as a relation to wave the aforeſaid diſcourſes one within another, ſo as thoſe which under ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral writers, were before counted ſeveral, are now by my endeavours reduced into one en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire hiſtory, connexed by due ſucceſſion of time and occaſion, as punctually as could be aimed at, by the circumſtances noted in the writings of thoſe holy and learned men before named.</p>
            <p>N.B. EXtraordinary examples of divine juſtice God never intended for a nine days wonder, elſe would he, when he exemplified <hi>Lot</hi>'s wife have turned her into a ſtatue of melting ſnow, not of laſting ſalt; which ſtood, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells us, till his age, after the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and as ſome travellers report, till at this day, <q>Ut quoddam hominibus praeſtaret condimentum; quo ſapiant unde illud caveatur exemplum. Aug. de civit dei, lib. 6 cap. 30.</q> for a ſeaſon againſt corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a preſervative againſt apoſtacy. This tragedy, when freſh and new, was the converſion and confirmation of ſundry worthies: <hi>Vergerius,</hi> a daily ſpectator thereof, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking a rich biſhoprick of <hi>Juſtinopolis</hi> and tents of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; went to <hi>Baſil,</hi> and died a worthy Proteſtant: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny nations had eye-witneſſes of their own ſtudents <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the univerſity of <hi>Padua,</hi> who penned the ſtory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the copies whereof are frequently revived: our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ones were very defective, and now worn out of ſhops and hands ſundry manuſcrips of this abroad imperfect; which moved me to compare this labour of a worthy gentleman (who faithfully tranſlated it out of <hi>Italian, French,</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> letters) with the latin of <hi>Caelius Secundus Curi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Mattheus Gribauldus,</hi> profeſſors of the civil law in <hi>Padua; Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund
<pb n="vi" facs="unknown:009059_0005_10306B12B26EA500"/>
Gelons,</hi> a <hi>Tranſylvanian, Henricus Scotus,</hi> all daily viſitors of <hi>Spira,</hi> and find it accord with them. Touching <hi>Spira</hi>'s perſon, I find moſt learned writers do incline to the right and hopeful hand: moved by his ſweet, humble, and charitable ſpeeches: ſome few deſperate ones except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that fell from him in ſome little agonies, which kept him faſting and watching about ſix months ſpace, eating nothing but what was forced down his throat. The ſum of <hi>Calvin</hi>'s and <hi>Borthaus</hi>'s counſels (who write largely of the uſe of this pattern) is, that all learn to take heed of backſliding, which God's ſoul abhors, and not to dally with conſcience, an hell on earth if juſtly incenſed; more to be feared than the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> inquiſition, or all the ſtrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padoes and torments in the world; and take heed of <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi>'s principal errors; which were to diſpute with Satan over buſily in time of weakneſs: eſpecially to reaſon, and conclude from preſent ſenſe to God's paſt reprobation, and future damnation: both which is hard, if poſſible for any man to determine in his own, much more in others caſes. So commending thee to his grace who is able to eſtabliſh thee to the end, I bid thee farewell, and hope well, while the ſpace of grace laſteth, <hi>Dum ſpiras ſpera:</hi> ſo mayſt thou take good and no hurt by the reading of this terrible example.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Impriamatur Tho's. Wykes R. P. Epiſc. Lond. Cap. Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="unknown:009059_0006_10306B15CE5071A8"/>
            <head>A RELATION of the fearful Eſtate of <hi>Francis Spira.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the Year 1548, when the glorious Sun of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel was but newly riſen in <hi>Europe,</hi> in the days of the reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth of that name King of <hi>England:</hi> In the territory, and under the juriſdiction of the city of <hi>Venice,</hi> being the very border of <hi>Italy,</hi> in the town of <hi>Citadella,</hi> lived one <hi>Francis Spira,</hi> a civil lawyer, an advocate of great rank and eſteem, being of known learning, and eloquence; of great experience; of carriage circumſpect and ſevere; his ſpeech grave and compoſed, his countenance ſharp auſtere; every way befitting that authority whereunto he was advanced, endowed with outward bleſſings, of wife and eleven children, and wealth in abundance: what his worſt parts were, I have no other warrant, than his own words, which (if not tainted over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much with the bitterneſs of a deſperate mind, and bearing the countenance rather of paſſion, than of ſober confeſſion) may ſeem to add a period to all further commendations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I was</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>exceſſively covetous of money, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly I applyed my ſelf to get by injuſtice, corrupting juſtice by deceit, inventing tricks to elude juſtice: good cauſes I ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther defended deceitfully or ſold them to the adverſary perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly; ill cauſes I maintained with all my might; I witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſed the known truth; and the firſt committed unto me, I either betrayed or perverted.</hi> Thus having worn out forty four years, or there abouts, and the news of the new, or rather newly revived opinions of <hi>Luther</hi> coming unto thoſe parts, repreſented an object of novelty unto him; who being as deſirous to know as he was famous for knowledge; ſuffered not theſe wandering opinions to paſs unexamined,
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:009059_0007_10306B18893F9590"/>
but ſearching into the ſcriptures, and into all books of controverſy that he could get, both old and new, and finding more than fame or opinion, he began to taſte their nature ſo well as that he entertains, loves and owns them at length; and with ſuch zeal, as he became a profeſſor; yea a teacher of them, firſt to his wife, children, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and after to his friends, and familiar acquaintance; and in compariſon, ſeemed to neglect all other affairs; intending ever to preſs this main point, that <hi>We muſt wholly, and only depend on the free, and unchangeable love of God in the death of Chriſt, as the only ſure way to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> And this was the ſum of all his diſcourſe, and this continued for the ſpace of ſix years, or there-abouts; even ſo long that this fire could not keep itſelf within private walls, but at length it brake forth unto public meetings; ſo that the whole province of <hi>Padua</hi> dawned with the luſtre thereof. The clergy finding the trade of their pardons to decay; and their purgatory to wax cold, began to ſtir themſelves: gloſing their actions firſt with calumnious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſions upon the whole profeſſion, then more plainly ſtriking at <hi>Spira</hi> with grievous accuſations: And to effect their purpoſe, ſome promiſe labour, others favour, ſome advice, others maintenance; all join to divide, either his ſoul from his body, or both from God.</p>
            <p>Now as <hi>John Caſa</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi>'s legate reſident at <hi>Venice,</hi> by birth a <hi>Florentine;</hi> and one that wanted neither malice againſt thoſe of this way, nor craftines to effect his mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious purpoſes: To him theſe men repair with outcries againſt <hi>Spira;</hi> that he was the man that condemned the received rights of the Church, eluded the Eccleſiaſtical power, and ſcandalized the policy thereof; one of no mean rank; being a man of account and authority, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, learned in the ſcriptures, elegant in ſpeech; and in one word, a dangerous <hi>Lutheran;</hi> having alſo many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and therefore not to be deſpiſed.</p>
            <p>At this began the legate to caſt his eye on the terrible alteration that lately had happened in <hi>Germany;</hi> where,
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:009059_0008_10306B1B4472BBA0"/>
by the means of only one <hi>Luther,</hi> the <hi>Romiſh</hi> religion had ſuffered ſuch a blow, as that it could neither be cured by diſſimulation, nor defended by power; but the clergy muſt either mend their manners, or loſe their dignities: on the other ſide, when he ſaw how propenſe the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple inhabiting in the bordering countries of <hi>Italy</hi> were to entertain thoſe new opinions, he now thought it no time to diſpute, or perſwade, but with ſpeed repairs to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and procures authority from them to ſend for <hi>Spira.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spira</hi> by this time had conſidered with himſelf of the nature of his carriage, how evident and notorious it was and therefore ſubject to be envied by ſuch as neither liked his perſon nor religion, he perceived that his opinions were neither retired nor ſpeculative, but ſuch as aimed at the overthrow of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> fiction, and a change of policy, (wherein at the beſt he could expect but a bloody victory,) and that his enemies wanted neither power nor occaſion to call him to account in public, when he muſt either apoſtatize, and ſhamefully give his former life, yea his own conſcience the lye, or endure the utmoſt malice of his deadly enemies, or forſake his wife, children, friends, goods, authority, yea, his dear country, and betake him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to a foreign people, there to endure a thouſand miſeries, that do continually wait upon a voluntary exile. Being thus diſtracted, and toſſed in the reſtleſs waves of doubt without guide to truſt to, or haven to fly to for ſuccour; on a ſudden, God's Spirit aſſiſting, he felt a calm, and began to diſcourſe with himſelf in this manner:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why wondereſt thou thus in uncertainties, unhappy man; caſt away fear, put on thy ſhield, the ſhield of faith: Where is thy wonted courage, thy goodneſs, thy conſtancy? remember that Chriſt's glory lies at the ſtake, ſuffer thou without fear, and he will defend thee, he will tell thee what thou ſhalt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; he can beat down all danger, bring thee out of priſon, raiſe thee from the dead: conſider</hi> Peter <hi>in the dungeon, the martyrs in the fire, if thou makeſt a good confeſſion, thou mayſt indeed go to priſon, or death, but an eternal reward in
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:009059_0009_10306B1DF1B87848"/>
heaven remains for thee; what haſt thou in this world com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to eternal life, to everlaſting happineſs? if thou doſt otherwiſe think of the ſcandal; (common people live by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, thinking whatever is done, is well done) fear the loſs of peace and joy, fear hell, death, and eternal wrath; or if thy fleſh be ſo ſtrong, as to cauſe thee to doubt of the iſſue, fly thy country; get thee away, though never ſo far, rather than deny the Lord of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now was <hi>Spira</hi> in reaſonable quiet, being reſolved to yield to theſe weighty reaſons; yet holding it wiſdom to examine all things, he conſults alſo with fleſh and blood; thus the battle doth renew, and the fleſh begins in this manner:</p>
            <p>
               <q>Be well adviſed, fond man, conſider reaſons on both ſides, and then judge; how canſt thou thus overween thine own ſufficiency, as thou neither regardeſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of thy progenitors; nor the judgments of the whole Church; doſt thou not conſider what miſery this thy raſhneſs will bring thee unto? thou ſhall loſe all thy ſubſtance, gotten with ſo much care and travel, thou ſhalt undergo the moſt exquiſite torments that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice itſelf can deviſe, thou ſhalt be counted an heretick of all: and to cloſe up all thou ſhalt die ſhamefully. What thinkeſt thou of the loathſome ſtinking dungeon, of the bloody ax, the burning fagot, are they delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful? Be wiſe at length, and keep thy life and honour; thou mayſt live to do much good to good men, as God commands thee, thou mayſt be an ornament to thy country: and put the caſe thy country's loſs will be of ſmall eſteem with the, Wilt thou bring thy friends alſo into danger? thou haſt begotten children, will thou now cut their throats, and inhumanly butcher them, which may in time bring honour to their country, glory to God, help and furtherance to his Church? go to the legate, weak man, freely confeſs thy fault and help all theſe miſeries.</q> Thus did the cares of this world, and the deceitfulneſs of riches, choak the good ſeed that was
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:009059_0010_10306B20C272B580"/>
was formerly ſown; ſo as fearing, he faints, and yields to the allurements of this preſent world, and being thus blinded he goes to the legate at <hi>Venice,</hi> and ſalutes him with this news.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Having for theſe divers years entertained an opinion concerning ſome articles of faith, contrary to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox and received judgment of the church; and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered many things againſt the authority of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the univerſal Biſhop, I humbly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my fault, and error, and my folly in miſleading others: I therefore yield myſelf in all obedience to the ſupream biſhop, into the boſom of the church of <hi>Rome;</hi> never to depart again from the traditions and decrees of the holy See; I am heartily ſorry for what is paſt; and I humbly beg pardon for ſo great an offence.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The legate perceiving <hi>Spira</hi> to faint, he purſues him to the utmoſt; he cauſeth a recitation of all his errors to be drawn in writing, together with the confeſſion annexed to it, and commands <hi>Spira</hi> to ſubſcribe his name there, which accordingly he did; then the legate commands him to return to his own town; and there to declare this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his, and to acknowledge the whole doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be holy, and true; and to abjure the opinions of <hi>Luther,</hi> and other ſuch teachers, as falſe and heretical: <hi>Man knows the beginning of ſin, but who bounds the iſſues thereof? Spira</hi> having once loſt footing, goes down amain, he cannot ſtay, nor gain-ſay the legate; but promiſeth to accompliſh his whole will and pleaſure; he ſoon addreſſeth himſelf for his journey, and being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the way, bethinks himſelf of large ſpoils he had brought away from the conflict with the legate; what glorious teſtimony he had given of his great faith, and conſtancy in Chriſt's cauſe: and to be plain, how impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly he had denied Chriſt, and his goſpel at <hi>Venice;</hi> and what he promiſed to do further in his own country; and thus partly with fear, and partly with ſhame, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded; he thought he heard a voice ſpeaking unto him in this manner:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="unknown:009059_0011_10306B22845AB730"/>
               <q>
                  <hi>Spira,</hi> What doſt thou here? whither goeſt thou? haſt thou unhappy man, given thy hand-writing to the legate at <hi>Venice;</hi> yet ſee thou doſt not ſeal it in thine own country: doſt thou indeed think eternal life ſo mean, as that thou preferreſt this preſent life before it? doſt thou well in preferring wife and children before Chriſt? is the windy applauſe of the people, better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed than the glory of God: and the poſſeſſion of this world's good more dear to thee, than the ſalvation of thine own ſoul? is the ſmall uſe of a moment of time more deſirable, than eternal wrath is dreadful? Think with thyſelf what Chriſt endured for thy ſake; is it not equal that thou ſhouldeſt ſuffer ſomewhat for him? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, man, that the ſufferings of this preſent life, are not comparable to the glory that ſhall be revealed: if thou ſuffereſt with him, thou ſhalt alſo reign with him: thou canſt not anſwer for what thou haſt already done; nevertheleſs, the gate of mercy is not quite ſhut, take heed that thou heapeſt not ſin upon ſin, leaſt thou repent when it will be too late.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now was <hi>Spira</hi> in a wilderneſs of doubts, not knowing which way to turn him, nor what to do, yet being arrived in his own country, and amongſt his friends, with ſhame enough he relates what he had done, and what he had further promiſed to do; and now the terrors of God on the one ſide, and the terrors of this world on the other ſide, did continually rack him; and therefore he deſired of them advice in this ſo doubtful a caſe; his friends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſmall deliberation anſwered; that it was requiſite he ſhould take heed that he did not in any wiſe betray his wife and children, and all his friends into danger, ſeeing that by ſo ſmall a matter as the reciting of a little ſchedule, which might be done in leſs ſpace than half an hour, he might both free himſelf from preſent danger, and preſerve many that depended upon him; adding moreover, that he could get no credit in relenting from that which he had already in greateſt part performed before the legate at <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="unknown:009059_0012_10306B24427BFC80"/>
and that in the perfect accompliſhing thereof, little or no diſcredit could ariſe more than what by the former action already he had ſuſtained: on the other ſide, if he did not perform his promiſe made to the legate, he could neither diſcharge himſelf of the ſhame which he had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy incurred; nor avoid far more heavy and inſupportable injuries, than probably he ſhould have endured, if he had perſiſted obſtinately in his former opinions.</p>
            <p>This was the laſt blow of the battle, and <hi>Spira</hi> utterly overcome, goes to the <hi>Praetor,</hi> and proffers to perform his 'foreſaid promiſe made to the legate, who in the mean time had taken order to have all things ready, and had ſent the inſtrument of abjuration ſigned by <hi>Spira,</hi> to the <hi>Praetor,</hi> by the hands of a certain prieſt. All that night the miſerable man wears out with reſtleſs cares, without any minute of reſt; the next morning being come, he gets up, and being ready, he deſperately enters into the public congregation, where maſs being finiſhed, in the preſence of friends and enemies, and of the whole aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; being by eſtimation near two thouſand people; yea, and of heaven itſelf, he recites that infamous abjuration, word for word, as it was written: it being done, he was fined at thirty pieces of gold, which he preſently paid: five whereof were given to the prieſt that brought the abjuration, the other twenty-five were employed towards the making of a <hi>ſhrine</hi> to put the <hi>euchariſt</hi> in; then was he ſent home reſtored to his dignities; goods, wife and children: No ſooner was he departed, but he thought he heard a direful voice, ſaying to him; <hi>Thou wicked wretch, thou haſt denied me, thou haſt renounced the Covenant of thy Obedience, thou haſt broken thy vow; hence Apoſtate bear with thee the ſentence of thy eternal damnation:</hi> he trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and quaking in body and mind, fell down in a ſwoon; relief was at hand for the body, but from that time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:009059_0013_10306B274C1932D0"/>
he never found any peace or eaſe of his mind; but continuing in inceſſant torments, he profeſſed that he was captivated under the revenging hand of the great God: that he heard continually that fearful ſentence of Chriſt, that juſt Judge: that he knew he was utterly undone: that he could neither hope for grace, nor Chriſt's inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion with God the Father in his behalf, thus was his fault ever heavy in his heart, and ever his judgment before his eyes.</p>
            <p>Now began his friends ſome of them to repent too late of his raſh counſel; others not looking ſo high as the judgment of God, laid all the blame upon his melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic conſtitution; that overſhadowed his judgment, wrought in him a kind of madneſs: every one cenſured as his fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy led him, yet for remedy all agreed in this, to uſe both the wholeſome help of phyſicians, and the pious advice of divines, and therefore thought it meet to convey him to <hi>Padua,</hi> an univerſity of note, where plenty of all manner of means was to be had: this they accordingly did, both with his wife, children, and whole family; others alſo of his friends accompanied him: and being arrived at the houſe of one <hi>James Ardin,</hi> in St. <hi>Leonard</hi>'s pariſh, they ſent for three phyſicians of moſt note, who upon due ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the effects, and of other ſymptoms of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and ſome private conference one with another, among themſelves, returned their verdict in this manner, <hi>viz.</hi> That they could not diſcern that his body was afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any danger or diſtemper originally from itſelf, by reaſon of the over-ruling of any humour; but that this malady of his did ariſe from ſome grief, or paſſion of his mind, which being overburdened, did ſo oppreſs the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, as they wanting free paſſage, ſtirred up many ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours whereof the body of man is full; and theſe aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up into the brain, troubled the fancy, ſhadowed the
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:009059_0014_10306B2C101B17B8"/>
ſeat of the judgment, and ſo corrupted it: this was the ſtate of his diſeaſe, and that outward part that was viſible to the eye of nature, this they endeavoured to reform by purgation, either to conſume, or at leaſt to divert the courſe of theſe humours from the brain; but all their ſkill effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing, upon which <hi>Spira</hi> ſaid: <q>Alas poor men how far wide are you; do you think that this diſeaſe is to be cured by potions? believe me there muſt be another manner of medicine, it is neither potions, plaiſters, nor druggs, that can help a fainting ſoul caſt down with ſenſe of ſin and the wrath of God; it is only Chriſt that muſt be the phyſician, and the Goſpel the ſole antidote.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The phyſicians eaſily believed him after they had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the whole truth of the matter, and therefore they wiſhed him to ſeek ſome ſpiritual comfort. By this time the fame of this man was ſpread over all <hi>Padua,</hi> and the neighbouring country, partly for that he was a man of eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teem, partly becauſe as the diſeaſe, ſo the occaſion was eſpecially remarkable; for this was not done in a corner: ſo as daily there came multitudes of all ſorts to ſee him: ſome out of curioſity only to ſee and diſcourſe; ſome out of a pious deſire to try all means that might reduce him to comfort again; or at leaſt to benefit themſelves by ſuch a ſpectacle of miſery, and of the juſtice of God. Amongſt theſe <hi>Paulus Vergerius,</hi> biſhop of <hi>Juſtinopolis,</hi> and <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus Gribauldus</hi> deſerve eſpecially to be named as the moſt principal labourers for this man's comfort. They find him now about fifty years of age, neither affected with the dotage of old age, nor with the unconſtant head-ſtrong paſſion of youth, but in the ſtrength of his experience and judgment; in a burning heat, calling exceſſively for drink; yet his underſtanding active, quick of apprehenſion, witty in diſcourſe, above his ordinary manner, and judiciouſly
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:009059_0015_10306B2DC9C17B78"/>
oppoſite; his friends laboured him by all fair means to receive ſome nouriſhment, which he obſtinately gain-ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they forcibly infuſed ſome liquid ſuſtenance into his mouth, moſt of which he ſpit out again; exceedingly chaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing, and in this fretting mood of his; As it is true, <q>that all things work for the beſt to thoſe that love God,</q> ſo to the wicked all are contrary; <q>for whereas a plentiful off-ſpring is the bleſſing of God, and his reward being a ſtay to the weak eſtate of their aged parents, to me they are a cauſe of bitterneſs and vexation; they do ſtrive to make me tire out this miſery: I would fain be at an end, I deſerve not this dealing at their hands; Oh! that I were gone from hence, that ſome-body would let out this weary ſoul.</q>
            </p>
            <p>His friends ſaluted him, and asked him, what he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be the cauſe of his diſeaſe; forthwith he brake out into a lamentable diſcourſe of the paſſages formerly related, and that with ſuch paſſionate elocution, that he cauſed many to weep, and moſt to tremble. They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily to comfort him propounded many of God's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes recorded in the ſcripture, and many examples of God's mercy: <hi>My ſin</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>is greater than the mercy of God.</hi> Nay, anſwered they, the mercy of God is above all ſin: God would have all men to be ſaved: <q>It is true <hi>(quoth he)</hi> he would have all that he hath elected to be ſaved; he would not have damned reprobates to be ſaved: I am one of that number; I know it, for I willingly and againſt my knowledge denied Chriſt, and I feel that He hardens, and will not ſuffer me to hope.</q>
            </p>
            <p>After ſome ſilence, one aſked him whether he did not believe that doctrine to be true, for which he was accuſed before the legate? he anſwered; <q>I did believe it when I denied it, but now I neither believe that, nor the doctrine of the Romiſh Church; I believe nothing, I
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:009059_0016_10306B2F864B2520"/>
have no faith, no truſt, no hope: I am a reprobate like <hi>Cain</hi> or <hi>Judas</hi> who caſting away all hope of mercy fell into deſpair, and my friends do me great wrong, that they ſuffer me not to go to the place of unbelievers, as I juſtly deſerve.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here they began ſharply to rebuke him; requiring, and charging him that in any ways he did not violate the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, to which he anſwered; <q>The mercy of God is exceeding large, and extends to all the elect, but not to me, or any like to me, who are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed up to wrath, I tell you I deſerve it, my own conſcience condemns me: what needeth any other judge?</q> Chriſt came (ſaid they) to take away ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> ii. 14. and calling for a book, they read unto him the paſſion of Chriſt, and coming to his nailing to the Croſs, <hi>Spira</hi> ſaid, <q>This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is comfortable to ſuch as are elected, but as for me wretch, they are nothing but grief and torment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I contemned them.</q> Thus roaring for grief, and toſſing himſelf up and down upon the bed as he lay, he entreated them to read no more. As <hi>Gribauldus</hi> was coming to ſee him, <hi>Vergerius</hi> ſaid to <hi>Spira,</hi> dear Sir, here is doctor <hi>Gribauldus,</hi> a godly and faithful friend of yours, come to ſee you: <q>He is welcome, ſaid he, but he ſhall find me ill:</q> 
               <hi>Gribauldus</hi> replied, Sir, this is but an il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion of the devil, who doth what he can to vex you; but turn you to God with your whole heart and he is ready to ſhow you mercy: The Lord you know is full of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, it is he that hath ſaid, that <hi>as often as a ſinner repents of his ſin, He will remember his ſins no more.</hi> Conſider this in the example of <hi>Peter,</hi> that was Chriſt's familiar, and an apoſtle, and yet denied him thrice with an oath, and yet God was merciful unto him: Conſider the thief, that ſpent his whole life in wickedneſs, and for all that did not God graciouſly reſpect him in the laſt minute of his
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:009059_0017_10306B3550260C68"/>
life? Is the Lord's hand now ſhortened, that it cannot ſave? To this <hi>Spira</hi> anſwered: <q>If <hi>Peter</hi> grieved and repented, it was becauſe Chriſt beheld him with a merciful eye, and in that he was pardoned, it was not becauſe he wept, but becauſe God was gracious to him; but God reſpects not me, and therefore I am a reprobate: I feel no comfort can enter into my heart, there is no place there but only for torments and vexings of ſpirit: I tell you my caſe is properly my own, no man was ever in the like plight and therefore my eſtate is fearful.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then roaring out in the bitterneſs of his ſpirit, ſaid, <q>It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God:</q> the violence of his paſſion and action ſuitable, did amaze many of the beholders; inſomuch as ſome of them ſaid with a whiſpering voice, that he was poſſeſſed; he over-hearing it, ſaid, <q>Do ye doubt it? I have a whole legion of devils that take up their dwelling within me and poſſeſs me as their own, and juſtly too, for I have denied Chriſt.</q> We would aſk whether you did that willingly or not? (ſaid they) <q>That's nothing to the purpoſe (ſaid <hi>Spira</hi>) Chriſt ſaith, Whoſoever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies me before men, him will I deny before my Father which is in heaven. Chriſt will not be denied, no, not in a word, and therefore it is enough tho' in heart I never denied him.</q>
            </p>
            <p>They obſerving his diſtemper to ariſe from the ſenſe and horror of the pains of hell, aſked whether he thought there were worſe pain than what he endured for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, he ſaid, <q>that he knew there were far worſe pains than thoſe that he then ſuffered, for the wicked ſhall riſe to their judgment, but they ſhall not ſtand in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>Pſal.</hi> i. This I tremble to think of, yet do I deſire nothing more than that I might come to that peace where I may be ſure to feel the worſt, and to be freed from the fear of worſe to come.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="unknown:009059_0018_10306B3745201688"/>Aye, but you are to conſider (ſaid one) that thoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions for which you are accuſed before the legate, were impious, and therefore you are not to think you denied Chriſt, but rather that you confeſſed him, acknowledging the infallible truth of the Catholic Church. "Truly (ſaid he) when I did deny thoſe opinions, I did think them to be true, and yet I did deny them.</p>
            <p>Go to (ſaid others) now then, believe that they are true. <q>Now I cannot (ſaid he) God will not ſuffer me to believe them, nor truſt in his mercy. What would you have me do? I would fain attain to this power but cannot, though I ſhould preſently burn for it.</q> But why do you, (ſaid the other) eſteem this ſo grievous a ſin, when as the learned legate conſtrained you to it, which you ſurely would not have done if your former opinions had not been erroneous; no good <hi>Francis,</hi> the devil beſets thee, let not therefore the grievouſneſs of thy ſin (if any ſuch be) amaze thee. <q>You ſay right, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied he, the devil hath poſſeſt me, and God hath left me to his power, for I find I can neither believe the Goſpel nor truſt in God's mercy. I have ſinned againſt the holy Ghoſt, and God by his immutable decree hath bound me over to perpetual puniſhment, without any hope of pardon. It is true that the greatneſs of ſins, or the multitude of them, cannot bind God's mercy, all thoſe ſins that in the former part of my life I have committed, then did not ſo much trouble me, for I truſted God would not lay them to my charge. Now having ſinned againſt the holy Ghoſt, God hath taken away from me all power of repentance, and brings all my ſins to remembrance, and guilty of one, guilty of all. And therefore it is no matter whether my ſins be great or ſmall, few or many: They be ſuch as that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt's blood, nor God's mercy belongs to me.
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:009059_0019_10306B38F7FDA228"/>
God will have mercy on whom he will have mercy; and whom he will he hardeneth: This is it that gnaws my heart, he hath hardned me, and I find that he daily more and more doth harden me, and therefore I am out of hope: I feel it, therefore cannot but deſpair. I tell you there never was ſuch a monſter as I am, never was any man alive a ſpectacle of exceeding miſery. I knew that juſtification is to be expected by Chriſt, and I denied and abjured it, to the end I might keep this frail life from adverſity, and my children from poverty; and now behold how bitter this life is to me, and God only knows what ſhall become of this my family; but ſure no good is likely to betide it, but worſe and worſe: and ſuch a ruin at length as one ſtone ſhall not be left up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another.</q> But why ſhould you ſaid <hi>Gribauldus</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit ſo deeply of your ſin, ſeeing you cannot but know that many have denyed Chriſt, yet never fell into deſpair: <q>Well ſaid he, I can ſee no ground of comfort for ſuch, neither can I warrant them from Gods revenging hand in wrath; though it pleaſeth God yet to ſuffer ſuch to be in peace; and beſides, there will a time of danger come, and then they ſhall be throughly tryed, and if it were not ſo, yet God is juſt in making me an example to others: And I cannot juſtly complain, there is no puniſhment ſo great but I have deſerved it, for this ſo heinous offence: I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you it is no ſmall matter to deny Chriſt, and yet it is more ordinary then commonly men do conceive of; it is not a denial made before a Magiſtrate, as it is with me, for as often as a Chriſtian doth diſſemble the known truth; as often as he approves of falſe worſhip by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting himſelf at it, ſo often as he hath not things wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of his calling, or ſuch things as are unworthy of his calling, ſo often he denies Chriſt; thus did I, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am juſtly puniſhed for it.</q> Your eſtate (quoth
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:009059_0020_10306B3BA59713D0"/>
               <hi>Gribauldus</hi>) is not ſo ſtrange as you make it. <hi>Job</hi> was ſo far gone that he complained God hath ſet him as a mark againſt him, and <hi>David</hi> that was a man after Gods own heart, complained often that God had forſaken him, and was become his enemy, yet both received comfort again. Comfort yourſelf therefore, God will come at length tho' he now ſeem far off.</p>
            <p>
               <q>O Brother (anſwered <hi>Spira</hi> I believe all this; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils believe and tremble; but David was ever elected and dearly beloved of God; and though he fell, yet God took not utterly away his holy Spirit: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was heard when he prayed, <hi>Lord take not thy holy Spirit from me:</hi> but I am in another caſe, being ever accurſed from the preſence of God: neither can I pray as he did, becauſe his holy ſpirit is quite gone, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be recalled; and therefore I know I ſhall live in continual hardneſs ſo long as I live: O that I might feel but the leaſt ſenſe of the love of God to me though but for one ſmall moment, as I now feel his heavy wrath that burns like the torments of hell within me and afflicts my conſcience with pangs unutterable; verily deſperation is hell itſelf.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here <hi>Gribauldus</hi> ſaid, I do verily believe, <hi>Spira,</hi> that God having ſo ſeverely chaſtiſed you in this life, correcteth you in mercy here, that he may ſpare you there, after that he hath mercies ſealed up for you in time to come.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Nay (ſaid <hi>Spira</hi>) hence do I know that I am a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, becauſe he afflicteth me with hardneſs of heart Oh that my body had ſuffered all my life long, ſo that he would be pleaſed to releaſe my Soul, and eaſe my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, this burdened conſcience.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gribauldus</hi> being deſirous to eaſe his mind from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual meditation of his ſin; as alſo to ſound how for the preſent he ſtood affected to the Romiſh Church; asked him
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:009059_0021_10306B405E2C26D0"/>
what he thought become of the Souls of men ſo ſoon as they departed out of the body, to which he anſwered.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Although this be not ſo fully revealed in Scripture; yet I verily believe that the ſouls of the elect go preſently to the Kingdom of Glory; and not that they ſleep with the body as ſome do imagine.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Very well; ſaid one of the Spectators, why do the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures then ſay that God brings down to hell, and raiſeth up? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.6. ſeeing it cannot be meant of the eſtate of the Soul after death, which as thou ſayeſt, either goeth to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven without change or to hell without redemption: it muſt be underſtood of the eſtate of the ſoul in this life; like that wherein thou art at this preſent: and oftentimes we ſee that God ſuffers men to fall into the jaws of deſpair, and yet raiſeth them up again, and therefore deſpair not, but hope it ſhall be even thus with thee in his good time.</p>
            <p>This is the work (quoth <hi>Spira</hi>) this is the labour; for <q>I tell you when I at Venice did firſt abjure my profeſſion and ſo, as it were drew an indenture, the ſpirit of God often admoniſh'd me and when at <hi>Citadella,</hi> I did, as it were, ſet to my ſeal; the Spirit of God often ſuggeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to me, Do not write <hi>Spira,</hi> do not ſeal; yet I reſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the holy Ghoſt, and did both; and at that very preſent I did evidently feel a wound inflicted in my very will, ſo although I can ſay, I would believe; yet can I not ſay I will believe; God hath denyed me the power of will; and it befalls me in this my miſerable eſtate, as with one that is faſt in irons, and his friends coming to ſee him, do pity his eſtate, and do perſuade him to ſhake off his fetters, and to come out of his bonds which, God knows, he would fain do, but cannot: this is my very caſe, you perſuade me to believe, how fain would I do it but cannot.</q> Then violently graſping his hands together, and raiſing himſelf up, <q>Behold <hi>(ſaid he)</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="unknown:009059_0022_10306B426ABD5090"/>
I am ſtrong, yet by little and little I decay and conſume, and my ſervants would fain preſerve this weary life, but at length the will of God muſt be done, and I ſhall periſh miſerably, as I deſerve. Rejoice ye Righteous in the Lord; bleſſed are you whoſe hearts the Lord hath molified.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then after ſome pauſe; <q>It is wonderful, I earneſtly deſire to pray to God with my heart, yet I cannot; I ſee my damnation, and I know my remedy is only in Chriſt, yet I cannot ſet myſelf to hold on it; ſuch are the puniſhments of the damned; they confeſs what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, they repent of their loſs of Heaven; and cannot mend their ways.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As he was thus ſpeaking, he obſerved divers Flies that came about him, and ſome lighted on him: <q>Behold, ſaid he, now alſo <hi>Beelzebub</hi> comes to his banquet; you ſhall ſhortly ſee my end, and in me an example to many of the juſtice and judgment of God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>About this time came in two Biſhops, with divers Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the Univerſity, one of them being <hi>Paulus Vergerius,</hi> having obſerved <hi>Spira</hi> more than any other, being continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally converſant with him: told him his eſtate was ſuch as rather ſtood in need of prayer then advice, and therefore deſired him to pray with him in the Lords prayer: <hi>Spira</hi> conſented, and he began.</p>
            <p>(Our Father which art in Heaven) then breaking forth into tears he ſtooped, but they ſaid it is well, your grief is a good ſign. "I bewail (ſaid he) my miſery, for I perceive I am forſaken of God and cannot call to him from my heart as I was wont to do; yet let us go on, ſaid <hi>Vergerius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(Thy Kingdom come) O Lord (ſaid <hi>Spira</hi>) bring me alſo in this kingdom; I beſeech thee ſhut me not out. Then coming to thoſe words (Give us this day our daily bread) he added, <q>O Lord I have enough and abundance to feed
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:009059_0023_10306B44258A32F0"/>
this carcaſs of mine; but there is another bread I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg the bread of thy grace, without which I know I am but a dead man.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>(Lead us not into temptation) ſeeing Lord that I am brought into temptation, help me Lord that I may eſcape; the enemy hath overcome, help me I beſeech thee to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come this cruel tyrant.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things he ſpake with a mournful voice, the tears trickling down abundantly; and expreſſing ſuch affections and paſſion, as turned the bowels of thoſe there preſent, with grief and compunction: they then turning to <hi>Spira,</hi> ſaid, You know that none can call Chriſt Jeſus the Lord but by the holy Ghoſt: you muſt therefore think of your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, according to that ſoft affection which you expreſs in your prayers, inferring thereby that God hath not wholly caſt you off, or bereaved you of this Spirit utterly.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I perceive, ſaid <hi>Spira,</hi> that I call on him to my eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal damnation, for I tell you again, it is a new and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of example that you find in me:</q> If <hi>Judas</hi> (ſaid they) had but out-lived his days, which by nature he might have done, he might have repented, and Chriſt would have received him to mercy; and yet he ſinned moſt grievouſly againſt his Maſter which did ſo eſteem of him, as to honour him with the dignity of an Apoſtle, and did maintain and feed him: He anſwered, <q>Chriſt did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo feed and honour me, neither yet is my fault one jot leſs than that of his, becauſe it is no more honour to be perſonally preſent with Chriſt in the fleſh, then to be in his preſence now by illumination of his holy Spirit: And beſides, I deny that ever <hi>Judas</hi> could have repented, how long ſoever he had lived; for grace was quite taken from him, as it is taken from me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>O <hi>Spira</hi> (ſaid they) you know you are in a ſpiritual deſertion; you muſt therefore not believe what Satan ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts;
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:009059_0024_10306B49CE6FFBE0"/>
he was ever a lyar from the beginning, and a meer impoſture, and will caſt a thouſand lying fancies into your mind, to beguile you withal, you muſt rather believe thoſe whom you judge to be in a good eſtate and more able to diſcern of you than yourſelf; believe us, and we tell you, that God will be merciful unto you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O here is the knot</hi> (ſaid Spira) <hi>I would I could believe, but I cannot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then he began to reckon up what fearful dreams and viſions, he was continually troubled withal; that he ſaw the devils come flocking to his chamber and about his bed, terrifying him with ſtrange noiſes; that theſe were not fancies, but that he ſaw them as realy as the ſtanders by; and that beſides theſe outward terrors he felt continual butch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery of his conſcience, being the very proper pangs of the damn'd wights in hell.</p>
            <p>Caſt off theſe fancies (ſaid <hi>Gribauldus</hi>) theſe are but il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, humble yourſelf in the preſence of God and praiſe him. <q>The dead praiſe not the Lord (anſwered he) nor they that go down into the pit: we that are drowned in deſpair, are dead and are already gone down into the pit: what hell can there be worſe then deſperation; or what greater puniſhment? the gnawing worm, unquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fire, horror confuſion and (which is worſe than all) deſparation itſelf continually tortures me, and now I count my preſent eſtate worſe than if my ſoul (ſeparated from my body) were with <hi>Judas</hi> and the reſt of the damn'd. And therefore, I now deſire rather to be there than thus to live in the body.</q>
            </p>
            <p>One being preſent, repeated certain words out of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> 89.30. If thy children forſake my law and walk not in my judgments I will viſit their tranſgreſſions with rods, and their iniquity with ſtripes; nevertheleſs my lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſs will I not utterly take from them, nor ſuffer
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:009059_0025_10302D6A3A142230"/>
my faithfulneſs to fail: mark this, O <hi>Spira,</hi> my Covenant I will not break.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Theſe promiſes (ſaid <hi>Spira</hi>) belong only to the elect, which if tempted, may fall into ſin, but are again lifted up and recovered out: as the prophet ſaith, <hi>Though he fall, he ſhall not be utterly caſt down, for the Lord uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him:</hi> therefore <hi>Peter</hi> could riſe for he was elected; but the reprobates when they fall cannot riſe again, as appears in <hi>Cain, Saul,</hi> and <hi>Judas:</hi> God deals one way with the elect, and another with reprobates.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The next day he prayed with them in the Latin tongue, and that with excellent affection, as outwardly appeared. Bleſſed be God, ſaid <hi>Vergerius,</hi> theſe are no ſigns of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal reprobation; you muſt not, O <hi>Spira,</hi> ſeek out the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret counſels of Gods election and reprobation; for no man can know, ſo long as he lives, whether by his good or bad deeds, he be worthy of Gods love or anger: Do ye not know that the Prophet <hi>David</hi> complained, that God had caſt off his Soul?</p>
            <p>
               <q>I know all this, quoth <hi>Spira,</hi> I know the mercies of God are infinite, and do ſurpaſs the ſins of the whole world, and that they are effectual to all that believe, but this faith, and this hope, is the gift of God: O that he would give it me! But it is as impoſſible as to drink up the Sea at a draught. As for that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> if he had ever tryed that which I feel by woful experience, he would never have ſpoken as he did: But the truth is, never had mortal man ſuch an evident experience, of Gods anger and hatred againſt him as I have. You that are in a good eſtate, think repentance and faith to be a work of great facility: and therefore you think it an eaſy matter to perſwade a man to believe. The whole need not the Phyſician, and he that is well can ſoon give counſel to ſuch as are ill: But this is the hell to me,
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:009059_0026_10306B4B8CDE3080"/>
my heart is hardned, I cannot believe: Many are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but few are choſen.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Upon what ground, ſaid they, do ye conceive ſo ill an opinion of your ſelf</p>
            <p>
               <q>I once did know God to be my Father, not only by creation, but by regeneration; I knew him by his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son, the Author and finiſher of our ſalvation; I could pray to him and hope for pardon of ſins from him: I had a taſte of his ſweetneſs, peace and comfort; now contrarily, I know God not as a Father, but as an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: What more? my heart hates God, and ſeeks to get above him, I have nothing elſe to fly to but ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and deſpair.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It's like you think, ſaid they, that thoſe who have the earneſt and firſt fruits of God's Spirit may notwithſtanding fall away?</p>
            <p>
               <q>The judgments of God are a deep abyſs, (ſaid he,) we are ſoon drowned if we enter into them; he that thinks he ſtandeth, let him take heed leſt he fall: As for myſelf, I know I am fallen back, and that I once did know the truth, though it may not be ſo throughly: I know not what to ſay, but that I am one of that number which God hath threatned to tear in pieces.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Say not ſo, anſwered they, for God may come though at the laſt hour; keep hold therefore at the leaſt by hope.</p>
            <p>
               <q>This <hi>(quoth he)</hi> is my caſe. I tell you I cannot God hath deprived me of hope; this brings terror to my mind, and pines this body which is ſo weak, as it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not perform the ſeveral Offices thereof: for as the Elect have the Spirit teſtifying that they are the ſons of God, the reprobates even while they live, do often feel a worm in their conſcience, whereby they are condemned already: and therefore as ſoon as I perceived this wound inflicted on my mind and will, I knew that I wanted the gifts
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:009059_0027_10306B4D7A2E8418"/>
of ſaving grace, and that I was utterly undone; God chaſtneth his children with temperate afflictions, that they may come as gold out of the fire; but puniſheth the wicked with blindneſs in their underſtandings and hardneſs of heart, and woe be to ſuch, from whom God, takes his holy Spirit:</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here one rebuked him, and told him, he gave two much credit to ſenſe, that he was not to believe himſelf but rather him that was in a good eſtate, and I teſtify to you (ſaid he) that God will be merciful to you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nay</hi> (anſwered he) <hi>for becauſe I am in this ill eſtate; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can I believe nothing but what is contrary to my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and comfort; but you that are ſo confident of your good eſtate, look that it be true, for it is no ſuch ſmall matter to be aſſured of ſincerity: a man had need be exceeding ſtrongly grounded in the truth, before he can be able to affirm ſuch a matter as you now do; it is not the performance of a few out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward duties, but a mighty conſtant labour, with all intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of heart and affection with full deſire and endeavour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to ſet forth God's glory; there muſt be neither Fear of Legates, Inquiſitors, priſons nor any death whatſoever; many think themſelves happy that are not; it is not every one that ſaith, Lord, Lord, that ſhall go to heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They came another day and found him with his eyes ſhut, as if he had been drouzy, and very loath to diſcourſe; at which time there came in alſo a grave man from <hi>Cittadella;</hi> who demanded of <hi>Spira,</hi> if he knew him, or not; he lifting up his eye lids and not ſuddenly remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring him, the man ſaid to him; I am preſbyter <hi>Antonie Fontania;</hi> I was with you at <hi>Venice,</hi> about eight weeks ſince: 'O curſed day! (ſaid <hi>Spira</hi>) O curſed day! O that I had never gone thither! Would God I had then dyed!'</p>
            <p>Afterwards came in a Prieſt, called <hi>Bernardinus Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donius,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="unknown:009059_0028_10306B5030B613D8"/>
bringing with him a book of Exorciſms to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure this devil, whom when <hi>Spira</hi> ſaw, ſhaking his head, he ſaid, <q>I am verily perſwaded, indeed, that God hath left me to the power of the devil; but ſuch they are, as are not to be found in your Littany; neither will they be caſt out by ſpells.</q> The Prieſt proceeding in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended purpoſe, with a ſtrange uncouth geſture, and a loud voice, abjured the ſpirit to come into <hi>Spira</hi>'s tongue, and to anſwer: <hi>Spira</hi> deriding his fruitleſs labour, with a ſigh, turned from him. A Biſhop there preſent ſaid to <hi>Spira,</hi> Brother, God hath put virtue into the Word and Sacraments, and we have uſed the one means, and find not that effect which we deſire; ſhall we try the efficacy of the Sacraments, Surely, if you take it as a true Chriſtian ought to receive, the body and blood of Chriſt, it will prove a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign medicine for your ſick ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <q>This I cannot do, anſwered he, for they that have no right to the promiſes, have no right to the ſeals. The Euchariſt was appointed only for Believers, if we have not faith, we eat and drink judgment to ourſelves: I received it about a month ſince, but I did not well in ſo doing, for I took it by conſtraint, and ſo I took it to my deeper condemnation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here <hi>Vergerius</hi> began to importune him earneſtly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that he did not wilfully reſiſt grace, and put himſelf out of Heaven, charging him vehemently, by all the love that was between them, by the love which he bare to his Children; yea, to his own ſoul, that he would ſet himſelf ſeriouſly, to return to that faith and hope, which once he had in the death of Chriſt: With many ſuch like words, <hi>Spira</hi> having heard much of the like matter formerly, and being ſomewhat moved, ſaid, You do but repeat, <hi>Verge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> Why ſhould I hope? why ſhould I believe? God hath taken Faith from me; ſhew me then whither I ſhall
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:009059_0029_10306B52E7A81D68"/>
go, ſhew me a Haven whereto I ſhall retire. You tell me of Chriſts interceſſion, I have denyed him; you command me to believe, I ſay I cannot; you bring me no comfort; your command is as impoſſible for me to obey, as to keep the Moral Law. If you ſhould perſwade one to love God with all his heart, ſoul and ſtrength, and God gives him not power, can he perform your deſire? Do not the Church teach us to ſing, direct us, O Lord, to love thy command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Hypocrites ſay that they love God with all their heart, but they lie; for my part, I will not lie, but tell you plainly, ſuch is my caſe, that though you ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much importune me to hope or believe, though I deſire, yet I cannot, for God as a puniſhment of my wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs hath taken away from me all his ſaving graces, faith hope, and all; I am not the man therefore that you take me for; its like you think I delight in this eſtate, if I could conceive but the leaſt ſpark of hope of a better eſtate here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, I would not refuſe to endure the heavy weight of the wrath of that great God: yea, for twenty thouſand years, ſo that I might at length attain to the end of that miſery, which I now know will be eternal: But I tell you my will is wounded, who longs more to believe than I do? but all the ground-work of hope is gone, for if the teſtimonies of holy Scriptures be true (as they are certainly true) is not this true, <hi>Whoſoever denies me before men, him,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>will I deny before my Father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</hi> is not this juſtly my caſe as if it had been intended againſt this very perſon of mine? And I pray you, what ſhall become of ſuch as Chriſt denyeth, ſeeing there is no other Name under Heaven whereby you look to be ſaved; What ſaid St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews? It is impoſſible for thoſe who were once enlightned, and have taſted of the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gift, and were partakers of the holy Ghoſt, if they fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, to be renewed to repentance.</hi> What can be more plain
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:009059_0030_10306B55A11A2EA0"/>
againſt me? Is not that Scripture alſo: If we ſin wilfully after we have received the knowledge of the truth there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth no more ſacrifice for ſins, but a certain looking for of judgment? the Scriptures ſpeaks of me, St. <hi>Paul</hi> means me, St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells me, <hi>It had been better I had never known the way of righteouſneſs than after I have known, to return from the holy commandments, it had been better I had not known, and yet then my condemnation had been moſt certain.</hi> Do you not ſee evidently, that I have denyed the known truth; I may juſtly expect not only damnation, but worſe if worſe be imagined. God would have me undergo the juſt puniſhment of my ſin, and make me an example of his wrath for your ſake.</p>
            <p>The company preſent, admired his diſcourſe, ſo grievouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accuſing himſelf of his fore paſt life; ſo gravely and wiſely relating, concerning the judgments of God that they then were convinced, that it was not frenzy or madneſs, that had poſſeſſed him: and being as it were, in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his eſtate, <hi>Spira</hi> proceeded again in this manner. Take heed to yourſelves, it is no light or eaſy matter to be a Chriſtian; it is not Baptiſm, or reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or boaſting of faith in Chriſt (though even theſe are good) that can prove one to be an abſolute Chriſtian: you know what I ſaid before; there muſt be a conformity in life, a Chriſtian muſt be ſtrong unconquerable, not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying an obſcure profeſſion, but reſolutely expreſſing the Image of Chriſt and holding out againſt all oppoſitions to the laſt breath: he muſt give all diligence by righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and holineſs, to make his calling and election ſure: many there are that ſnatch at the promiſes in the Goſpel, as if they undoubtedly did belong to them, and yet they remain ſluggiſh, and fearleſs, and being flattered by the things of this preſent world, they paſs in their courſe with quietneſs and ſecurity, as if they were only happy men;
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:009059_0031_10306B5854C65C00"/>
whom nevertheleſs the Lord in his providence hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to eternal wrath; as you may ſee in S. <hi>Luke's</hi> rich man: thus it was with me, therefore take heed.</p>
            <p>Then came one of his nephews and offered him ſome ſuſtenance, which he diſdainfully refuſing, ſo moved the young man's choler, that he charged him with hypocriſy and diſſimulation, or frenzy; to whom <hi>Spira</hi> gravely anſwering ſaid, <q>You may interpret the matter as you will; but I am ſure, I am not only the actor, but the argument, and matter of the tragedy I would it was frenzy either fained or true, for if it were fained or true I could puff it off at pleaſure, if it were a real frenzy yet there was ſome hope left of God's mercy, whereas there is none, for I know that God hath pronounced me an enemy, and guilty of high treaſon againſt his majeſty; I am caſt away, a veſſel of wrath, yet dare you call it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling and frenzy; and can mock at the formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble example of the wrath of God that ſhould teach you fear and terror: but it is natural to the fleſh, either out of malice or ignorance, to ſpeak perverſely of the works of God. The natural man diſcerneth not of the things that are of God, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</q>
            </p>
            <p>How can this be, ſaid <hi>Gribauldus,</hi> that you can thus excellently diſcourſe of the judgments of God, and of the graces of his Holy Spirit, that you find the want of them, and earneſtly deſire them, and yet you think you are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly depriv'd of them.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Take this for certain, ſaith he, I want the main grace of all and that which is abſolutely neceſſary, and God doth many times extort moſt true and ſtrange teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timonies of his majeſty juſtice and mercy; yea, out of the mouths of very reprobates, for even <hi>Judas,</hi> after he had betrayed his maſter, was conſtrained to confeſs his ſin, and to juſtify the innocency of Chriſt; and therefore if I do the like, it is no new or ſtrange mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:009059_0032_10306B5B0AB9B270"/>
God hath taken faith from me, and left me other common gifts, for my deeper condemnation: by how much the more I remember what I had, and hear others diſcourſe of what they have, by ſo much the more is my torment, in that I know what I want, and that there is no way to be relieved.</q> Thus ſpake he, the tears all the while trickling down; profeſſing that his pangs were ſuch, as that the damned wights in hell endure not the like miſery: that his eſtate was worſe, than that of <hi>Cain</hi> or <hi>Judas,</hi> and therefore he deſired to die. <hi>Yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>the ſcriptures are accompliſhed in me, They ſhall deſire to die, and death ſhall fly from them.</hi> And verily, he ſeemed exceedingly to fear, leſt his life ſhould be drawn out to a longer thread; and finding no eaſe or relief, ever and anon cried out, <hi>O miſerable wretch, O miſerable wretch!</hi> then turning to the company, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought them in this manner. <q>O brethren! take a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent heed to your life, make more account of the gifts of God's Spirit than I have done; learn to beware by my miſery; think not you are aſſured Chriſtians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you underſtand ſomething of the Goſpel: take heed you grow not ſecure on that ground, be conſtant and immoveable in the maintenance of your profeſſion: Confeſs even until death, if you be called thereto: He that loveth father, mother, brother, ſiſter, ſons, daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, kindred, houſes, lands, more than Chriſt, is not worthy of him.</q> Theſe words, ſaid they, do not ſound like the words of a wicked reprobate. <q>I do but here imitate, ſaid <hi>Spira,</hi> the rich glutton in the Goſpel, who though in hell, yet was careful that his brethren ſhould not come to that place of torment: And I ſay to you brethren, take heed of this miſerable eſtate wherein I am.</q> Then turning himſelf to certain young men that were preſent, he deſired them to conceive him aright. <q>I
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:009059_0033_10306B5EAD578758"/>
do not ſpeak this to derogate from the certainty of ſaving faith and the promiſes of the Goſpel, for they are more ſure; but take heed of relying on that faith that works not a holy and unblameable life worthy of a believer: credit me, it will fail, I have tried it, I preſumed I had gotten the right faith, I preached it to others, I had all places of ſcripture in memory that might ſupport it: I thought myſelf ſure, and in the mean time lived impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and careleſly: behold now the judgments of God have overtaken me, not to correction, but to condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: And now you will have me to believe, but it will not be; for I feel too late that good things belongs only to ſuch as are good, whoſe ſins are cover'd with Chriſt's death and blood as with a veil, and guarded with his righteous merits from the flood of God's wrath, even as with a mighty wall, leſt miſerable mortals ſhould be ſwallowed up with the greatneſs of their ſin: but as for me, I have as it were, wilfully with my hands pulled down this Rampire, behind which I might have reſted in ſafety; and now are the ſwelling waters come even to my ſoul, and I am caſt away.</q> One of his familiar friends chanced to ſay, that certainly he was overcome with melancholly, which being overheard, <hi>Spira</hi> anſwered:</p>
            <p>
               <q>Well, be it ſo, ſeeing you will needs have it ſo; thus alſo is Gods wrath manifeſted againſt me, in that he hath taken from me the uſe of mine underſtanding and reaſon, ſo as I can neither rightly eſteem and judge of my diſtemper, nor hope of remedy. You ſee brethren what a dangerous thing it is, to ſtop or ſtay in things that concern Gods glory; eſpecially to diſſemble upon any terms. What a fearful thing is it to be near, and almoſt a Chriſtian? Never was the like example to this of mine; and therefore if you be wiſe, you will ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:009059_0034_10306B61A6867128"/>
conſider thereof. Oh that God would let looſe his hand for me, that it were with me now as in times paſt, I would ſcorn the threats of the moſt cruel tyrant, bear torments with invincible reſolution, and glory in the outward profeſſions of Chriſt till I were choaked in the flame, and my body conſumed to aſhes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay you are deſperate, O <hi>Spira,</hi> (ſaid they) why then do you not ſtrive with ſome weapon or other violently to make an end of your life, as deſperate men uſe to do? Let me have a ſword (ſaid <hi>Spira</hi>) why what would you do with it? (quoth they.) <q>I cannot tell you (ſaid he) what this mind would move me to upon occaſion; nor what I would do.</q>
            </p>
            <p>They perceiving ſmall effect of all this their labour; but rather that he grew worſe; for the avoiding of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of people (for every day ſeldom fewer than 20 con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued with him) and to ſtop the courſe of fame which was continually blown abroad of him, they conſult to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry him back again into his own country: and thoſe his friends that came to comfort him, began to take their leaves of him: <hi>Vergerius</hi> among the reſt required that at their parting they might pray together with him: <hi>Spira</hi> hardly conſented, and as unwillingly performed: for he ſaid, <q>My heart is eſtranged from God, I cannot call him Father, from my heart; all good motions are now quite gone, my heart is full of malediction, hatred, and blaſphemy againſt God; I find I grow more and more hardened in heart, and cannot ſtoop and help myſelf; your prayers for me ſhall turn to your own benefit, they can do me no good.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vergerius</hi> came to take his leave of him, whom <hi>Spira</hi> embracing, ſaid, <q>Although I know that nothing can bring any benefit to me a reprobate, but that every thing ſhall tend to my deeper condemnation; yet I give you
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:009059_0035_10306B6399844D88"/>
moſt hearty thanks for your kind office of love and good will; and the Lord return it to you with a plentiful increaſe to all good.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The next day being brought down to his intended jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, by the way looking round about him with a ghaſtly look, he ſaw a knife lying on a table, to which he running haſtily ſnatched hold of, as intending to miſchief himſelf, but his friends laying hold of him, ſtopped him in his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: whereupon with indignation he ſaid, <q>I would I were above God, for I know he will have no mercy on me!</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus went he homewards, often ſaying, that he envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the condition of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas.</hi> He lay about eight weeks in this caſe in a continual burning, neither deſiring nor receiving any thing but by force, and that without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, was ſo ſpent that he appear'd a perfect anatomy, expreſſing to view nothing but ſinews and bones; vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently raged for drink; ever pining, yet fearful to live long; dreaded hell, yet coveting death in a continual tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet his own tormentor: and thus conſuming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with grief and horror, impatience and deſpair, like a living man in hell; he repreſented an extraordinary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the juſtice and power of God: and thus (as far as appeareth) within a few days after his arrival at his own home, he departed this preſent life. Yet an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to make us remember that ſecret things belong unto the Lord our God; but charity to man, to teach him to hope all things.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
