<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Weathersfield, July 6, 1763. Being the day appointed by authority for a public thanksgiving, on account of the peace, concluded with France and Spain. / By James Lockwood, A.M. Pastor of the First Church in Weathersfield.</title>
            <author>Lockwood, James, 1714-1772.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N07381</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N07381</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 9417</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APV7687</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">9417</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99003217</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 9417.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N07381)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 9417)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 9417)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Weathersfield, July 6, 1763. Being the day appointed by authority for a public thanksgiving, on account of the peace, concluded with France and Spain. / By James Lockwood, A.M. Pastor of the First Church in Weathersfield.</title>
                  <author>Lockwood, James, 1714-1772.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35, [1] p. ;  19 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed ay [sic] James Parker and Company.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New-Haven: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1763]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: A thanksgiving sermon for the peace with France and Spain. 1763.</note>
                  <note>Caption title: A thanksgiving sermon.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>United States --  History --  French and Indian War, 1755-1763 --  Addresses, sermons, etc.</term>
               <term>Thanksgiving sermons --  1763 July 6.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>AEL Data (Chennai)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:009417_0000_0F743B160E0DBB88"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:009417_0001_0F743B166FCF1AF0"/>
            <p>A THANKSGIVING SERMON FOR THE PEACE, WITH FRANCE AND SPAIN. 1763.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:009417_0002_0F743B18A912C928"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT WEATHERSFIELD, JULY 6, 1763. Being the Day appointed by AUTHORITY FOR A PUBLIC THANKSGIVING, On Account of the PEACE, Concluded with FRANCE AND SPAIN.</p>
            <p>By JAMES LOCKWOOD, A. M. PASTOR OF THE FIRST CHURCH IN WEATHERSFIELD.</p>
            <p>NEW-HAVEN: PRINTED AY JAMES PARKER AND COMPANY.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="unknown:009417_0003_0F743B190F7EACC0"/>
            <head>A THANKSGIVING SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALM, L. 14, 15.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>Offer unto GOD Thankſgiving, and pay thy Vows unto the Moſt High. And call upon me in the Day of Trouble; I will deliver thee, and thou ſhalt glorify me.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ALL Nature is full of GOD: He not only inhabits Eternity, but he fills Immenſity: He is intimately preſent with all the Works of his Hands; upholding, ſuperintending, ordering and directing all Things, through the immenſe Univerſe: His all-ruling Providence extends to the vegetable and animal, as well as to the rational Creation; and ſo it does to all the dead Parts of Matter, thro' the whole created Syſtem; inſomuch that there is not a Motion in the natural, nor a Thought in the intellectual World, but what is ſubject to his Controul.</p>
            <p>As 'tis a Matter of great Importance, that a deep Senſe of this ſhould be fixed upon our Minds; the Holy Writings are admirably ſuited and adapted to this Purpoſe: There is a remarkable Difference in this Reſpect, between the holy Scriptures, and human Compoſitions; the latter are wont to relate Facts and Events as they are; pointing us to the immediate Cauſes or Occaſions of them; whereas the holy Scriptures are perpetually introducing
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:009417_0004_0F743B19DABE5BF8"/>
GOD in all the Scenes of Nature, and the Affairs and Tranſactions of Men; and repreſenting Him, as the ſupreme Cauſe and Agent, "Who worketh all things according to the Counſel of his own Will; without whom, not a Sparrow falls to the Ground; and by whom the Hairs of our Heads are all numbered." At the powerful Call of his Voice, the whole Univerſe of Things ſprang into Being, into Regularity, Order and Harmony; and his own al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Arm perpetually ſuſtains the univerſal Frame. The Laws of Nature as they are called, are no other, than certain Methods or Rules fix'd by Himſelf; agreeably to which He governs the natural World. If it rains, 'tis "God that ſendeth Rain on the Juſt and on the Unjuſt." If the ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Winds ariſe, in the Language of Inſpiration, "The Lord hath his Way in the Whirlwind and in the Storms and the Clouds are the Duſt of his Feet." Nahum 1. 3. If it thunders, "The GOD of Glory thundereth, He thundereth marvelouſly with the Voice of his Excellency." Pſalm xxix. 3. Job xxxvii. 4, 5. If there is an Earthquake, "GOD ſhaketh the Earth out of her Place, and the Pillars thereof tremble." Job ix. 6. And if we go on to conſider the Affairs of Men and Nations; the ſame Remark holds good. Does a Nation or Kingdom riſe, proſper and flouriſh; or, is it brought down to Ruin and Deſolation; ſtill the Hand of the ſupreme Ruler is to be acknowledged and adored. Is a Nation unſucceſsful in War; "It is GOD that poureth Contempt upon Princes, and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Strength of the Mighty." Or, does a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion prevail in Battle, and carry on a War to a
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:009417_0004_0F743B19DABE5BF8"/>
ſucceſsful Iſſue, a deſireable and happy Peace; "It is GOD that fighteth for his People; through him, they do valiantly; and he it is that treadeth down their Foes." Of every Deliverance and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation we receive; particular public and national Salvations; we are ſtill reminded to acknowledge and adore GOD, as the Author; and to render the Praiſe and Glory to Him. Theſe Sentiments of Piety and Religion the holy Writings unitedly tend to inſpire; particularly that Portion of them, I have now read to you; "Offer unto GOD Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, &amp;c.—" A careful Attention to the Works of Providence, and the Operations of GOD's Hand, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our Wiſdom and our Duty: And as we now have a particular Call to it; it is to be hoped, our Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be particularly careful, ſerious and devout.</p>
            <p>The Words may be accomodated to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Occaſion, of the preſent Solemnity; and be thus treated and illuſtrated.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. We have been in Trouble.</item>
               <item>II. We have called upon God, in the Day of Trouble.</item>
               <item>III. GOD hath delivered us. And now,</item>
               <item>IV. We are to offer unto GOD Thankſgiving.</item>
               <item>V. We are to pay our Vows unto the Moſt High.</item>
               <item>VI. And we are to glorify GOD. And then,</item>
               <item>VII. I would make ſome Improvement of the Subject.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I. <hi>We have been in Trouble;</hi> and who among Mankind have not? Into this apoſtate ſinful World, Men are born to Trouble and Sorrow as the Sparks fly upwards: All the Individuals of the human Race, more or leſs drink of this bitter Cup. Aches
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:009417_0005_0F743B1A393F9BF0"/>
and Pains and Maladies without Number, Croſſes and Diſappointments, and heart-felt Bereavements, are but ſome of the Sorrows and Troubles Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind are Subject to, in this Valley of Tears: And well would it be, very well, if theſe Sorrows were met and endur'd <hi>as</hi> from the Hand of GOD, the wiſe and good Governor of the World; with a calm and quiet Reſignation to his Pleaſure; and a firm and ſteady Reliance on his Providence and Grace.</p>
            <p>And as for Ourſelves, <hi>us</hi> in this Colony, and in this Land, including our Mother Kingdom; 'tis certain we have been in Trouble, great Trouble!—have been involv'd, for a long Time, in a bloody War with <hi>France</hi> and with the <hi>Savages</hi> of the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs; and for ſome Time, with <hi>Spain.</hi> War conſidered in itſelf, is a ſore and diſmal Calamity; and not to be entred upon, but with good Advice, and with a View to Peace: Nor does GOD wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly afflict his People, with ſo terrible a Scourge, but their Iniquities ſeperate between GOD and them, and draw down his Judgments upon them. Sin is the Cauſe, the hated Cauſe and Origin of all the Miſeries and Calamities that overſpread the Earth. 'Tis Sin that contracts the Brow of Heaven into Frowns; and ſtirs up the Indignation of an holy GOD. We are a ſinful, guilty and degenerate Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and the GOD of our Fathers has been angry with us, and has called for the Sword of our popiſh and pagan Adverſaries, to avange the Quarrel of his broken Covenant and violated Law; and to chaſtiſe and puniſh us, for our many Land-defiling Sins and Abominations.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="unknown:009417_0005_0F743B1A393F9BF0"/>
If we look back to the Commencement of the late War, how illy were we prepared for it? How low was the Nation ſunk into Indolence and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargy? How little of a martial Spirit, and the old <hi>Britiſh</hi> Bravery was to be found among them? How ſadly did this bode, and how diſcouraging and gloomy were our Proſpects? Accordingly, ſome of the Events of the firſt Year of the War were very calamitous and diſgraceful; ſuch as will ſtain the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Annals, and muſt be reſented with Shame and Grief by every ſenſible <hi>Engliſhman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The War opened in the Year ſeventeen hundred and fifty five, with the ill-conducted and unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful March of General <hi>Braddock,</hi> againſt Fort <hi>Du Queſne;</hi> a Fort erected by the <hi>French,</hi> on the Territory of his <hi>Britannic</hi> Majeſty: This Diſgrace and Overthrow was ſome what qualified by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of <hi>Nova-Scotia,</hi> by Colonel <hi>Monckton;</hi> and Sir <hi>William Johnſon'</hi>s Victory over a <hi>French</hi> Army, near Lake <hi>George.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Year fifty-ſix will not be thought honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Name or Hiſtory: The ſcandalous Behaviour of Admiral <hi>Byng</hi> in the <hi>Mediterranean;</hi> and in Conſequence of that, the Loſs of the Iſland of <hi>Minorca,</hi> cannot be recollected but with Shame and Regret. And not long after this, (for I mean not minutely to trace the ſeveral Steps of the War) what a melancholly and gloomy Period followed, to <hi>Great Britain</hi> and her Provinces. At Home, what Uncertainty, Darkneſs and Confuſion attended the public Counſels? And how were they embroil'd by Diviſions and Diſtractions? Whilſt Defeat, Fruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:009417_0006_0F743B1AF4D285A0"/>
and Shame attended the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Arms, in the ſeveral Quarters of the World.</p>
            <p>Let us fix our Attention for a Moment or two on <hi>America,</hi> the original Object of the Conteſt, in which we are moſt intimately concern'd, and to which therefore, I intend principally to confine theſe Remarks. How were our Fortreſſes and ſtrong Holds demoliſhed or burnt to Aſhes? Our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen and Friends captivated and butchered? Our Troops repulſed and turned back with Fruſtration and Shame? At that gloomy Period, what Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling took hold on us, and Confuſion covered us? How did every Countenance gather Paleneſs, and the Panic ſpread through whole Provinces?</p>
            <p>Did not the People of this Land tremble for the Ark of GOD, and all our dear Privileges? Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive, fearful, whether GOD would not permit an exaſperated Foe, elated with Succeſs and Victory, to carry the devouring Sword through the Land, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Deſolation and wide-ſpreading Ruin. This was a dark Day to the <hi>Britiſh American</hi> Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; a Day of Sorrow and Trouble; a Day, on which, we were loudly call'd upon, to look above an Arm of Fleſh—to look to the GOD of Armies, the Supreme Ruler of the World, and our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant God, for Protection, Deliverance and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And did we not take that Courſe? Which leads me to ſay,</p>
            <p>II. <hi>We have call'd upon God in a Day of Trouble.</hi> "Call upon me in the Day of Trouble." In the Seaſon of our Darkneſs and Diſtreſs, we poured out our Supplications before the Moſt High. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, daily Prayer to GOD, is a Duty incumbent on
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:009417_0006_0F743B1AF4D285A0"/>
every human Being, that underſtands what Prayer is: And for a Chriſtian, for one who names the Name of CHRIST to neglect Prayer, daily Prayer, is quite inexcuſable. In all our Ways we are to acknowledge GOD, and maintain an humble, holy Intercourſe with Him, through all the Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Affairs of our Lives. The Senſe and Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of our Hearts towards GOD, at all Times, ſhould agree &amp; harmonize with the various Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations and Aſpects of his Providence towards us: This is to maintain and enjoy Communion with GOD, in the Deſpenſations of his Providence. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Kindneſs and Smile of his Providence ſhould be met with correſpondent Gratitude, Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and Praiſe: So, for every Thing we ſtand in Need of for Time or Eternity, we are humbly to call upon God. In all the Sorrows and Troubles, Dangers and Diſtreſſes we are incident to, in this <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Sin and Changes, we are ſtill to make GOD our Refuge and Dependence; deeply ſenſible, that without GOD in vain is the Help of Man; that GOD is the exhauſtleſs Fountain of all Good, of all Help—the Father of Mercy and of Lights, from whom cometh down every good and perfect Gift: And in our Seaſons of ſpecial and imminent Diſtreſs and Danger, we have a particular Call, to be very fervent and importunate in our Addreſſes to GOD: And this, I hope, was, in ſome Meaſure, the Caſe during the Courſe of the late War; and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at that gloomy Period above-mentioned. Did not the Churches and Congregations of GOD's Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>New England</hi>—did not we in this Colony and in this Town, frequently and cheerfully meet
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:009417_0007_0F743B1BBA64D658"/>
in the Houſe of GOD, to offer up our Supplications, and pour out our Prayers before the Mercy-Seat, for Protection and Safety, for Deliverance and Salvation? How did you then ſeem to be ſtruck with a Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Senſe, that if GOD did not appear for us, and his own Arm did not bring us Salvation, we were a ruin'd and undone People? How forward did you then ſeem to be to look above all created Help, to Him that governs the whole World and orders all the Affairs of it as he pleaſes, and to ſeek and cry to him for Deliverance? With what Freedom and Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs did you croud the Sanctuary of GOD, eager to unite in pouring out your Supplications before his Throne, and to hear Inſtructions from his Word? You cannot have forgotten, how cheerfully you uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſetting apart Days for Faſting and Prayer; and Weekly Seaſons, for ſpecial and ſolemn Prayer, that GOD would mercifully appear for us and deliver us. And I hope a Conviction is left upon <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Hearts, that He is a Prayer-Hearing GOD, and that it is not a vain Thing to ſeek and pray to Him.</p>
            <p>And tho' we have Reaſon to ſuppoſe, that many Perſons did not pray, with ſuch a Senſe of their own Unworthineſs and evil Deſerts, and the Power and Wiſdom, Grace and Mercy and All-ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of GOD, and ſuch a Dependence on his Power and Grace through CHRIST, as they ought; yet, no Doubt, many Others were graciouſly ſincere and cordial in their Addreſſes to GOD. And I have thought and ſtill think, that a Spirit of Prayer and Supplication, in ſome thing of an uncommon De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, was poured out on GOD's People in the Land: And when GOD gives an Heart to pray, He is
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:009417_0007_0F743B1BBA64D658"/>
wont to find an Ear to hear. And did he not hear? Did he not hearken to the Voice of our Supplications, and ſend us an Anſwer of Peace? Did he not hearken to the Voice of Men, ſinful, guilty Men? And in Anſwer to the Supplications of his People, did he not make bare his own Arm, and work Deliverance and Salvation for us? Yes, He is a Prayer-hearing GOD, and has never ſaid to the Seed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſeek ye my Face in vain. And ſo I am led to ſay,</p>
            <p>III. <hi>God has delivered us.</hi> "Call upon me, in the Day of Trouble; I will deliver thee." Yes, GOD has delivered us, with a Salvation never to be forgotten.</p>
            <p>GOD might juſtly, provoked by our Sins, have given us up a Prey, into the Hands of thoſe that hated us; and doom'd us to a State of diſmal Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, under <hi>Gallic</hi> Chains and <hi>Popiſh</hi> Superſtition and Tyranny: But of his rich and abundant Grace he has delivered us. After a Period of Darkneſs and Perplexity; the Darkneſs vaniſhed, the Clouds ſcattered, and the Day dawn'd. "GOD'S right Hand, and his holy Arm, and the Light of his Countenance, have brought us Salvation, becauſe he had a Favour for us." Suddenly the Scene changed, and our Covenant GOD, who ſeemed in a Manner to have caſt us off, appeared for us, in our Diſtreſs.</p>
            <p>He was pleaſed to raiſe up thoſe, whom he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to honor, as the choſen Inſtruments of our Deliverance. In this Connection, the <hi>Patriot Pitt</hi> will not be forgotten. Unity and Harmony were reſtored to our public Counſels. The Britiſh Lion
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:009417_0008_0F743B1C817A5B60"/>
arouſed as from a Sleep. A martial Spirit and Fire was diffuſed and ſpread into our Fleets and Armies. Expeditions were form'd and plan'd with Wiſdom and Conſiſtency; and carried into Execution with Firmneſs and Steadineſs; and a Spirit and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that Nothing could daunt or reſiſt. The guilty, ambitious Schemes of <hi>France</hi> vaniſhed like a Dream of the Night: Our Enemies fled before us in every Climate: Our Fleets and Armies went on from conquering to conquer. The <hi>Britiſh</hi> Troops triumphed in every Quarter of the World: <hi>Europe, Aſia, Africa</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> beheld with Wonder our Succeſs and Victories.</p>
            <p>It would be beſide my preſent Purpoſe, to enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merate the great Things GOD has done in <hi>Africa,</hi> the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and <hi>Germany.</hi> Let me briefly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a few Inſtances nearer Home. <hi>Cape-Breton, Crown-Point, Quebec, Montreal,</hi> yea, the whole <hi>French</hi> Territory, almoſt, in <hi>North-America,</hi> wreſted from them, was given into our Hands: Beſides <hi>Guadaloupe, Martinic<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> &amp;c. in the <hi>Weſt-Indies;</hi> and the <hi>Havana</hi> from the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> The <hi>Spaniards!</hi> what a wretched, deſpicable Figure will they make, in the future Hiſtory of theſe Times! And what crowns all, the War is at Length terminated in a deſirable and happy Peace. The diſmal Calamities of War, which had overſpread the ſeveral Quarters of the Earth, are at an End. The Supreme Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, who ſays to the proud Waves of the Sea, "
"Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſhall ye go and no further," and who over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rules the Hearts of Men, has diffuſed a Spirit of Union and Harmony among the ſeveral contending Powers, and mercifully brought on a general Paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:009417_0008_0F743B1C817A5B60"/>
—a Peace, by which we have acquired a mighty Enlargement of Dominion and Territory, and many Advantages—a Peace peculiarly favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and advantageous to us, in <hi>America;</hi> even beyond our moſt ſanguine Expectations, when the War firſt opened. Theſe are the LORD'S Doings, and juſtly marvellous in our Eyes. Many and ſtrik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are the Demonſtrations of a divine Interpoſition, and of the Goodneſs and Power of GOD exerted in our Behalf.</p>
            <p>Who commanded the Winds and the Seas, and ordered the Seaſons, from Time to Time ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully? Who commanded the Earth to yield her Increaſe, and furniſhed Reſources ſufficient to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on ſo many Expeditions, in ſo many different Parts of the World, at the ſame Time? Who ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited the Soldiery to offer themſelves, and armed them with Patience, Reſolution and Courage? Who inſpired our worthy Commanders, by Sea and Land, with Wiſdom, Prudence and Magnanimity, ſo proportioned to their elevated and important Stations? Permit me to ſay, on this Occaſion; Who raiſed up the late intrepid, heroic Leader, the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant <hi>Wolf;</hi> and furniſhed him with Talents, to ſo uncommon a Degree, for the important Province he was called to? Who gave him an Head to Plan, and an Arm to execute the mighty Deſign, his Heart was ſo much ſet upon? To execute it in a Manner, that extorted the Admiration and Aſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment of his very Enemies? Who animated the Nation and it's public Councils with ſuch a Spirit of Union and Harmony, to proſecute the War with Vigor, according to the Meaſures ſo wiſely
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:009417_0009_0F743B1D35481748"/>
concerted? Finally, Who excited and animated ſo many of GOD's profeſſing People, in this Land, and we truſt alſo in our Mother Country, to pour out frequent and ſervent Prayers at the Mercy Seat, for the Smiles of Heaven on our military Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Doubtleſs, GOD is to be acknowledged and adored in all theſe Things. Yes, you may ſay; "The ſuperintending and directing Providence of the Moſt High extends to all Events, and without Him not a Sparrow falls to the Ground; for GOD governs the whole World." He does ſo: But then in ſome of GOD's Works, there ſeems to be more evident and ſtriking Marks of a divine Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency and Conduct; and the Footſteps of Deity are more plainly viſible: And here the Reſults of Battles, and the Events of War are to be ranked. Theſe depend on ſo many fickle Uncertainties as to us, and ſo many Things that are evidently beyond the Reach of human Power, as to render the Hand of GOD the more conſpicuous. When the Wind and the Weather, the various Elements and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>common Co-incidence of Circumſtances, have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired to favour our Enterprizes: When an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jarring Harmony has ſubſiſted among all Orders of Men concern'd: When they have all united in one View, in one grand Deſign: When a martial, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roic Ardor ſeem'd to glow in every Breaſt: When, though to a common Penetration, the Difficulties attending the moſt important and deciſive Conqueſt, that of <hi>Quebec,</hi> and which was a Key to the Reſt, ſeemed inſuparable; yet the diſtinguiſh'd Leader,<note n="*" place="bottom">WOLF.</note> by a Sagacity lent him from Above, diſcern'd the
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:009417_0009_0F743B1D35481748"/>
Method, perhaps the only Method, in which, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly ſpeaking, the Enemy could be overcome—diſcerned the Critical Moment, when it was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to wreſt a Victory—ſeized the happy Moment, and with a ſurprizing Preſence of Mind, Wiſdom and Courage that Nothing could diſconcert or daunt, ſurmounted all difficulties, and carried his Plan into Execution: I ſay, when this is the Caſe, who will not ſay, not only, that the Hand of GOD was there; but that it was a wonderful Work of his Power and Goodneſs? And when GOD has been pleaſed to vouchſafe a remarkable Series, an unbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Chain of numerous Victories; what pious Mind can contemplate the important Events, without owning and adoring the Hand of Heaven?—with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being ſtruck with a kind of Sacred Reverence of the Preſence of GOD; and his glorious Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his Power, Wiſdom, Goodneſs and Mercy ſo evidently conſpicuous therein.</p>
            <p>But that we may be the more ſenſible of the Goodneſs of GOD, and our Indebtedneſs to Him, for our late Succeſſes, and preſent happy Settlement; it may be proper to take Notice of one or two Things, which plainly determine it a great Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.</p>
            <p>Let us conſider, <hi>Firſt,</hi> the Evils, which were thereby obviated and prevented. How wretched had our Situation been, if <hi>French</hi> Plans had ſucceded, and their ambitious Schemes been carried into Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution? Had their Arms been ſucceded in <hi>Europe,</hi> according to their Deſign; what had been the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, with Regard to <hi>Great-Britain,</hi> but the overthrow of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Succeſſion, a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:009417_0010_0F743B1E26E7C338"/>
obtruded, and the Loſs both of civil and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Liberty, and the Kingdom being made a Scene of Deſolation and Blood? And as to their Intentions in <hi>America,</hi> how diſmal had been our Fate had they ſucceeded? By the Chain of Forts they had carried round us, and the Air, and Manner of their Operations, what leſs could they deſign, than our utter Ruin, and the wreſting from us this goodly Heritage GOD gave to our Fathers?. And can we imagine to ourſelves the execution of ſuch their Deſign without Amazement and Horror?—Their Popiſh and Pagan Armies marching into the Heart of our Country, practiſing their imhuman Cruelties without Pity?—Without Diſtinction, butchering Men, Women and Children, in their triumphant Progreſs; involving our Habitations, Churches and Towns in devouring Flames; and deluging the Land with Slaughter and Blood; whilſt the miſerable Remnant, ſtript of all their precious Privileges, Civil and Religious, would be reduced to a State of the moſt wretched Slavery. How diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal were ſuch a State of Things! But GOD in great Mercy has prevented it.</p>
            <p>The Pit they were digging for us, they are fallen into themſelves: And the Miſchief they were fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for us, GOD has brought down upon their own Heads: Their ambitious, towering Scheme, is daſhed to Pieces; and their whole <hi>American</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritory almoſt, is given up; and by the preſent Settlement annexed to the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Crown. So won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully has GOD delivered us.</p>
            <p>Let us conſider, <hi>nextly,</hi> the Worth and Value of theſe Acquiſitions, thus ſecur'd to us; and the Evils
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:009417_0010_0F743B1E26E7C338"/>
we are like to be ſecur'd againſt, for the Time to come. 'Tis not eaſy to aſcertain their Importance and value to the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Crown, and to theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces: They are, without Doubt, vaſtly valuable. The Conqueſt of all <hi>France,</hi> I imagine, would not have been equally ſo: For in that Caſe, it would be immenſely chargeable to keep it; and in the End, perhaps <hi>Britain</hi> would become a Province of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſundry Views, the Reduction of <hi>Canada,</hi> is juſtly accounted a very important Acquiſition. It directly conduces to the future Security and Peace of theſe Colonies. What a bloody Scourge have the <hi>French</hi> Settlements in <hi>Canada</hi> been to theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, from Generation to Generation? What horrid and inhuman Butcheries have been perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated? How much <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Blood has been ſhed upon our Frontiers, by the blood-thirſty <hi>Savages,</hi> ſpirited and ſet on by the faithleſs <hi>French?</hi> But theſe horrid Butcheries are, we hope, likely to be forever over and at an End.<note n="*" place="bottom">The preſent in human and cruel Out-breakings of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages, we truſt, will be of no long Continuance—that proper Meaſures will be concerted, for their being ſpeedily and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually ſuppreſs'd.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, what an immenſe Source of Wealth may this Acquiſition prove; as it opens a moſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable Trade with the Natives, for a vaſt Extent of Territory round.—But to wave this, and paſs to take in another Point of View, a very intereſting and glorious one to a Chriſtian. May we not hope, that theſe Events will ſerve to give the Savages ſome Impreſſions in Favour of the Goſpel, the pure
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:009417_0011_0F743B20B1AB4948"/>
Goſpel, unadulterated with <hi>popiſh</hi> Mixtures. Will not the Natives, after having conſidered and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe Things, be naturally led to ſay, as the <hi>Heathen</hi> did, with Regard to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in Pſalm cxxvi. 2. "Then ſaid they among the Heathen, the Lord hath done great Things for them." "The GOD of <hi>Britons</hi> and of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> has done great Things for them: He is a great GOD, and a mighty King." And may we not hope, that their Minds may thence receive ſome powerful Touch in Favour of the Bleſſed Goſpel: And that a Way may be opened for the ſpreading the glorious Goſpel among them; and their being brought to a profeſſed and cordial Subjection to the Prince of Peace: That ſo, in theſe dark Corners of the Earth, where Satan's Seat from Time immemorial has been, the Churches of CHRIST may be erected, and his Goſpel and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion taught; and Multitudes of Souls train'd up for the Kingdom of Heaven. What a bleſſed, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Event would this be, if CHRIST the King of <hi>Zion</hi> ſhould then take to himſelf his great Power and Reign! But I need ſay Nothing further, to give you an Impreſſion of the Greatneſs of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance and Salvation mercifully granted us of GOD. "The LORD is our Strength, and he is become our Salvation." Our Covenant GOD, and the GOD of our Fathers has done this; the GOD that brought our Fathers into this Land, and planted them here; who watched over them in the Days of their ſmall Things; who planted his Church here, and ſtill defends and cheriſhes that Vine which his own right Hand had planted. 'Tis He that has fought our Battles for us, and
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:009417_0011_0F743B20B1AB4948"/>
triumphed gloriouſly. 'Tis He that has carried us on from Victory to Victory, to the preſent hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Settlement. Let a Senſe of this ever be found warm at our Hearts, and let us feel the Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we are under of Love and Homage, of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, Thankſgiving and Praiſe to the GOD of all our Salvations. Wherefore,</p>
            <p>IV. <hi>Let us offer unto God Thankſgiving, and praiſe his Name.</hi> This is the Duty we are now call'd to: Let us ſee to it, it be done aright. Our Hearts ſhould be impreſs'd with a deep Senſe of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſalvation of GOD; and they ſhould act and flow out in the warmeſt and moſt cordial Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to the Supreme Ruler, and our Celeſtial Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor. To engage us to the acceptable Diſcharge of this Duty, let us conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>This is a moſt fit and reaſonable Thing.</hi> 'Tis our treating GOD and acting towards Him, as being what he is; infinitely the beſt of Beings, and the glorious Source and Spring of all our Salvations. When we ſincerely aſcribe our public Succeſſes, our Victories and Triumphs, and in Conſequence of theſe, our preſent Settlement, to GOD; we aſcribe them to their true Source and Original. And this, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with correſpondent Gratitude and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving to the Moſt High, is moſt reaſonable, fit and right; for unto GOD the Honor and Praiſe do belong.</p>
            <p>Men can claim no other Honor from ſuch E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, than what belongs to moral Inſtruments, the Honor of having faithfully employed their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed Talents for the Good of Mankind. In this View, our wiſe Counſellors and Politicians,
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:009417_0012_0F743B217667FE68"/>
our heroic Chiefs and Commanders, and our brave Soldiers too, juſtly come in for their Share of Praiſe. A Tribute of Honor and Praiſe is due to them from a preſerved and grateful Country. But as they were raiſed up by GOD, and furniſhed with their various Talents, and ſpirited and call'd forth to the Exertion of them, for the Welfare and Salvation of their Country, by GOD; ſo the Praiſe and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry are ultimately due to him. Bleſs the LORD, O our Souls, and all that is within us, praiſe his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Name: This is reaſonable, fit and right.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>This is delightful to ſerious and pious Minds.</hi> True Devotion is the moſt noble and delightful Exerciſe of a reaſonable Creature. A fixed and governing Habit of Devotion, is the trueſt Ornament and Glory of a Man: And ſincere Gratitude and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving is the moſt animating Part of Devotion: It warms and exalts the Soul, with noble and affecting Conceptions of the Atributes of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity, diſplay'd for the Good of Mankind. And when whole Countries and Kingdoms are relieved and made happy, the more elevated and delightful muſt be the Views of the pious and devout, of the Goodneſs and Mercy, the Wiſdom and Power of GOD; whence all their public Salvations reſult. I might add here, this Branch of Devotion is no leſs honorable to GOD, than it is delightful to good Men. GOD himſelf takes Pleaſure in ſeeing his reaſonable Creatures rejoicing in his Goodneſs, and in Himſelf the Author of all their Salvation: Yes, it is honorable and pleaſing to the moſt high GOD, to ſee whole Provinces and Kingdoms kneeling before him, and ſincerely aſcribing the Praiſe and
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:009417_0012_0F743B217667FE68"/>
Glory of all their public Salvations and Bleſſings to Him. Permit me then to ſay, as the <hi>Levites</hi> did to the Congregation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> on another Occaſion, "Stand up and bleſs the LORD your GOD forever and ever, and bleſſed be thy glorious Name, which is exalted above all Bleſſing and Praiſe." Nehem. ix. 5.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Sincere and Heart-felt Gratitude, on this Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, has a Tendency to make us, as a People, more vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and religious.</hi> It tends to meliorate the Heart, and make the Life better. True Devotion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces to improve and ſtrengthen, in the Heart, every Principle of Virtue and Holineſs. A reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and grateful Senſe of GOD and his Goodneſs, prevailing in the Heart, naturally diſcovers itſelf in a Care and Endeavour to pleaſe and honor Him. A due Senſe of the Loving kindneſs and Mercy of the LORD, tends to melt and fill the Heart with a Senſe of our own Unworthineſs, and to prompt us, from a Principle of Gratitude, to pleaſe and ſerve the GOD of all our Salvations: So that our public Solemnities of Thankſgiving and Praiſe, if rightly attended, tend to diffuſe and ſpread a Spirit of Devotion and Piety through the Land, and to animate and ſtir up People to lead Lives of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Obedience—to make us a better People, more virtuous, holy and religious, more careful to maintain good Works, and to do whatſoever GOD has commanded us. Let us then, with all our Hearts, offer unto GOD Thankſgiving and bleſs his holy Name. And ſo I am prepared to ſay,</p>
            <p>V. <hi>We are to pay our Vows to the Moſt High.</hi> "Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer unto GOD Thankſgiving, and pay thy Vows
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:009417_0013_0F743B21C8790970"/>
unto the Moſt High." We are, in ſundry Views, under ſtrongeſt Obligations to make ſuitable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to GOD, for all his Goodneſs and Mercy.</p>
            <p>Shall I call to your Remembrance, this Day, our ſolemn Tranſactions with GOD, in that gloomy Seaſon, preſently after Fort <hi>William-Henry</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and deſtroyed by the <hi>French;</hi> and the Aſpects of Providence ſeemed ſo very dark and threatning; when we thought it our Duty, to ſet apart a Day for ſolemn Humiliation and Prayer before GOD: You may perhaps remember, the Words treated on, on that Occaſion, were thoſe in <hi>Judges</hi> x. 15. "We have ſinned, do thou unto us whatſoever ſeemeth good unto thee, deliver us only, we pray thee this Day." Were you not ready, in that Seaſon of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs, to fall down before GOD; and in the Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Souls to confeſs your Sin, your Guilt and evil Deſerts; and to implore Protection and Deliverance, on what Terms GOD pleaſed? "De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us only this Day from our Enemies, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us in what other Way thou wilt for our Sins: Send Sickneſs, ſend Peſtilence, ſend Blaſting and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine if thou wilt; let us fall into the Hands of the living GOD, and not into the Hands of unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Men; not into the Hands of our cruel and bloody Enemies." Were you not ready to proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate yourſelves before the Mercy-Seat, and ſeriouſly to promiſe and vow to the Moſt High, and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with Him, that if He would deliver and ſave you, you would be his faithful Servants forever; would devote yourſelves wholly to Him, to walk before Him and to keep his Commandments all the Days of your Lives: And if you did not
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:009417_0013_0F743B21C8790970"/>
do ſo, were ready to own, you ſhould be the moſt guilty and inexcuſable Creatures imaginable. Well, GOD did appear for us and deliver us: He has ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us with a mighty Salvation; carried us with Succeſs and Victory, thro' the War, and brought us to this happy Period of it: Now then we muſt pay our Vows to the Moſt High—our Vows of Gratitude and Love, of Homage and ſincere Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. The devout <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſays in Pſalm lxvi. 13, 14. "I will go into thy Houſe with Burnt Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: And will pay thee my Vows, which my Lips have uttered, and my Mouth hath ſpoken, when I was in Trouble."</p>
            <p>We are not to forget our ſolemn Tranſactions with GOD in Years paſt; but muſt ſtill hold them in Remembrance; and render unto GOD according to all the Benefits we have receiv'd. But, whether we formally and explicitly made Vows and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to GOD, in the Seaſon of our Diſtreſs, or not; was not ſomething like this implied, in the Solemn Prayers and Supplications we pour'd out in GOD's Houſe, from Time to Time?—And I may add, I hope, in our Families and in our Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets too? What was the Import and Meaning of thoſe Prayers? Was it not plainly implied, in all that Variety of Phraſe and Expreſſion, that might be made Uſe of from Time to Time?—That we humbly beg'd Deliverance, Succeſs in the War, and a final happy Settlement and Peace, at the Hand of GOD; ſenſible that GOD only could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow theſe Bleſſings; that if He ſhould be pleaſed to beſtow them, it would be all Mercy, rich un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merited Mercy and Grace; and that it ſhould be
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:009417_0014_0F743B2272DB39E0"/>
regarded, reſented and improved by us as ſuch; and we ſhould hold ourſelves bound and obliged to make all proper Returns to the GOD of all our Salvations? Theſe then are the Returns we are now bound to make, to bleſs and praiſe the Name of GOD; and to expreſs our Gratitude by Lives of Holineſs and New Obedience.</p>
            <p>Beſides, we may by no Means forget, that as we are the profeſſing People of GOD, we are under Covenant Obligations, to walk with GOD according to his Word; and to make a right Uſe and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement not only of his Word and Ordinances, but likewiſe of all the Diſpenſations of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. Yes, we are under ſolemn covenant Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to improve the Salvation and Mercy we now celebrate, ſo as to be induced thence to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate ourſelves, all our Powers and Faculties, our Time and Talents to GOD, to his Service and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. O let us not fail, on this Occaſion, to anſwer the Obligations, we are under to GOD; and with glad and devout Hearts, to pay our Vows to the Moſt High. I muſt add in the</p>
            <p>VI. Place, <hi>We muſt now glorify GOD.</hi> "I will deliver thee, and thou ſhalt glorify me." No Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can glorify GOD, by making any Addition to his eſſential Glory; or by making GOD any more glorious than he really is. It is beyond the Reach or Capacity of Men or Angels, to make GOD any more really Glorious than he always was, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways will be; for he is infinitely perfect, infinitely glorious, independently of all Creatures: But we glorify GOD, declaratively or manifeſtively, when we manifeſt or ſhew forth his Glory: When we
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:009417_0014_0F743B2272DB39E0"/>
think, ſpeak, act and live ſo as ſpeaks and declares GOD to be glorious: Particularly,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>We are to glorify GOD, by entertaining high and honorable Tho'ts of Him.</hi> We muſt remove from our Apprehenſions of GOD, every Thing that implies Imperfection; and conceive of Him, as a Being of infinite Perfection and Glory. All poſſible, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Perfections and Excellencies muſt meet in our Idea of GOD: And we muſt conceive of Him, as the firſt and infinitely the greateſt and beſt of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. We think honorably of GOD, when we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally think and conceive of Him to be, what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally is, infinitely glorious. Particularly, we muſt entertain very high and admiring Thoughts of thoſe Perfections of the Deity, his Wiſdom, Power, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant Faithfulneſs, his Pity and Compaſſion, his Goodneſs, Grace and Mercy, that have been emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently diſplayed in working Salvation for us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>We are to glorify GOD by proper and ſuitable Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Actings of Soul towards Him.</hi> By heartily believing the Revelations He has made of Himſelf in his Word; by reverencing the Operations of his Hand, in his Works of Providence; by truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Him, through the Mediator, for all the Bleſſings of Time and Eternity; by loving GOD, the beſt of Beings, with all our Hearts and with all our Souls; and by being effectually induc'd by all that Goodneſs and Mercy, in which he has paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before us, to take up our complacential ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Reſt in GOD, to delight ourſelves in Him, as our Portion, and the Object of our Supreme Felicity. In a Word, every grateful and devout Temper of Mind, ſuitable and adapted to the great
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:009417_0015_0F743B23429A5220"/>
Things GOD has done for us, ſhould be call'd forth into flouriſhing Exerciſe, to the Honor and Glory of GOD.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>We muſt glorify GOD, by ſpeaking reverently and honorably of Him and to Him.</hi> It is infinite Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the great GOD, to let Himſelf down to us: And it becomes us to take his Sacred Name into our Lips, with greateſt Humility and Reverence: Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially on this Occaſion does it become us, to pour out through our Lips, the warmeſt Gratitude of our Hearts to the Father of Mercy, and our great Deliverer and Benefactor, and by offering Praiſe and Thankſgiving to glorify Him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>We are to glorify GOD, by Lives devoted to Him.</hi> "By adorning the Doctrine of GOD our Saviour in all Things; and making our Light ſhine be-Men that ſeeing our good Works, they may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify our Father which is in Heaven." By worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſerving GOD according to his Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: By practiſing Juſtice, Love and Charity to our Fellow-Men; and by Humility, Meekneſs and Purity in all our Behaviour. We are to glorify GOD, by improving our Time and Talents well; and by bringing forth Fruit, in Proportion to the Means and Advantages we enjoy. In a Word, we are to glorify GOD, by living and conducting our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſuch a Manner, that the natural and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Language of the whole Tenor of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and Deportment may be, that GOD is ſuch an infinitely glorious Being, as he has revealed Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be in His Word. Let us now make ſome IMPROVEMENT of this Subject. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Let us ſeriouſly enquire, how we have been affected
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:009417_0015_0F743B23429A5220"/>
and influenced, in Heart and Life, by all God's various Dealings with us, in the Courſe of his Providence, from the Time when the late War opened to the preſent Day? And be perſuaded, in Obedience to the preſent Call of divine Goodneſs and Mercy, ſpeedily to reform and amend what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is ſtill to be found amiſs in us, or among us.</hi> GOD has been paſſing before us of late Years, by terrible Things in Righteouſneſs: He has likewiſe cauſed his Goodneſs and Mercy, in remarkable, wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Inſtances of it, to paſs before us: And by all, He has been calling upon us, loudly and long cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon us; to conſider, to repent, to reform and turn to GOD and our Duty. And what Influence have all GOD's Calls, and all the Means He has been uſing with us, had to effect and bring about a Reformation? Are we, in Conſequence of all, become a reformed, and truly religious People? Are we in any Meaſure—in any conſiderable Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure reformed? Some particular Perſons, I doubt not, have repented and turned to GOD; it would be ſad indeed if none had: But has there been any Thing like a general Reformation effected, by all GOD has been doing with us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Is there not as much—is there not more Sin in the Land, than when the War began? What one Sin is generally bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off and forſaken? Truly, I fear, not ſo much as one. Are we more pious, godly and devout than we uſed to be? Do we prize God's Word, Day and Ordinances more? Are we more ſtrict and exemplary in all the Branches of Piety, than formerly? Are we more juſt, kind, charatable, peaceful and forgiving, with Regard to Men? Has a Reformation been carried on in our Families? Is
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:009417_0016_0F743B23F8EC24C0"/>
Family Religion reviv'd among us? In a Word, Do we live and conduct ourſelves more, as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Diſciples and Followers of the bleſſed JESUS, than we uſed to do? I much fear, but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of this can be anſwered in the Affirmative: 'Tis too plain we are yet a ſinful People; and there are many dark and threatning Symptoms upon us. Let us, without Delay, take our Caſe into ſerious Conſideration, and receive Conviction of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity we are under, of a thorough Reformation. If GOD'S awful Rod has not driven you; let his great Goodneſs and Mercy lead you to Repentance: And do not, after your Hardneſs and impenitent Hearts, treaſure up to yourſelves Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath, and the Revelation of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judgments of GOD. It is a dreadful Thing to remain hardened and impenitent under all GOD'S various Dealings with you, for your Reformation. O be perſuaded to break off every known Sin, and to turn, with all your Hearts, to GOD in CHRIST; and enter, without Delay upon a Life of ſtrict Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and real Godlineſs. Let a grateful Senſe of the unmerited Goodneſs of God, effectually engage you, to make all proper and ſuitable Returns to Him, and to live to the Praiſe and Glory of the GOD of all your Salvations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Let us be perſuaded to the ſteady Practice of thoſe Virtues and Rules of Prudence, that are conducive to the public Welfare, Strength and Tranquility.</hi> As for the preſent Peace, may it be laſting as it is welcome, and may Generations yet unborn, rejoice in the happy Conſequences of it. And in this Seaſon of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility and Repoſe, it concerns us to turn our At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:009417_0016_0F743B23F8EC24C0"/>
to ſuch Things, as tend to render us a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and flouriſhing People. The political Precauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that may be proper at this Juncture, being out of my Province, I leave to thoſe, who have the Conduct and Management of our public Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs: But the improvement and Cultivation of moral Diſpoſitions and ſocial Virtues, muſt always be proper to be recommended from this Place. If we conſider, how much we are exhauſted, by the Length and Expenſiveneſs of the War;—how bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with Debts, and how many Individuals in the Colony are ſunk, or ſinking apace under the Burden: It ſeems proper to call to Mind, the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of checking and diſcouraging, a Spirit of Prodigality and Expenſive Vanity; which in the natural Train of Things tend to ſink us into Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and Diſgrace: And of promoting and culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating Tranquility, Prudence and Induſtry, and a Method of living according to our Station and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility: This would have a happy Tendency to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us a flouriſhing People. 'Tis like wiſe of high Importance, that we apply ourſelves to the diligent Practice of all ſocial Virtues and Duties:—That we ſtudiouſly ſhun and avoid all injurious Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Mankind—all Strife and Contention; and every Thing that has a Tendency to breed mutual Alienation, Diſguſt and Ill-will; and that we practiſe Equity and Moderation, Kindneſs, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Beneficence, and every proper Art of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Indearment; and that we live together in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruffled Peace, Friendſhip, Love and Harmony: This would be our Strength, our Beauty and our Glory. 'Tis proper to obſerve further, that hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:009417_0017_0F743B24B3C4E630"/>
any Thing more directly and effectually conduces to the Strength, Firmneſs and Proſperity of a State or People, than a Public Spirit, and a generous Regard to the Good of the Whole; and a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinating our private Views and Intereſt to the Welfare of the Public: A Senſe of this ſhould be fixed deep in our Hearts. Permit me alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind you, on this Occaſion, of how great Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance it is to the Welfare of the Community, that a wiſe and diligent Care be taken of the Education of Youth; that they be trained up in the Way, in which they ought to go; that ſo they may become Worthy Members, not only of the Churches of CHRIST, but of the Civil State. They ſhould be form'd betimes to a Veneration and Reverence for Laws, both Human and Divine; and for all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority in Family, in Church and State—to Induſtry, Diligence and Frugality; to every ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and amiable Virtue; and to every Temper and Practice that tend to render them Bleſſings in the World: That ſo, when their Fathers fall aſleep, a Generation may ariſe, who ſhall ſhine as Lights in the World, and mark their Way through Life with worthy and laudable Actions, to another and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter World.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Let us be perſuaded, from the Occaſion of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Solemnity, to look forward with Hope and Joy and Truſt in God, to that State of Purity and Peace, the Church of Chriſt expects in the latter Day; and to the complete and endleſs Purity and Peace of the Heavenly World.</hi> 'Tis painful to a pious and benevolent Mind to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Miſeries and Calamities Mankind have groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under, from Generation to Generation, ever ſince
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:009417_0017_0F743B24B3C4E630"/>
the Entrance of Sin into the World. Bloody Wars and Devaſtations, and Mankind purſuing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring one another like Beaſts of Prey; make up a great Part of the Hiſtory of paſt Ages: And whence come Wars and Fightings upon the Earth? They come from the Ambition and Luſts of Men: And will the Ambition and Luſts of Men always prevail to ſuch a Degree, as to drive Peace in a Manner, from the Earth; and render this lower World a Stage of Calamity and Miſery, an Acel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dama, a Field of Blood? Will Satan, the god of this World, always prevail, to lead ignorant, ſtupid Mankind captive to their Ruin; and, as it were, go off the Stage victorious? This can hardly be thought: No, the Prince of Peace, is the Lion of the Tribe of Judah: He has bruiſed the Serpent's Head; and led Captivity captive: And He will aſſert the Conqueſt He has gained over the Powers of Darkneſs: He muſt reign and triumph; and His Cauſe will finally prevail: His Kingdom of Truth and Righteouſneſs and Peace, will be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſet up, on the Ruins of Satan's Kingdom. A Period, a long and happy Period of a Thouſand Years, is juſtly expected; when Satan ſhall be bound, and the Goſpel of CHRIST ſhall be univerſally ſpread over all the Nations of the Earth; and the Earth ſhall be full of the Knowledge of the LORD, as the Waters cover the Sea; and Mankind in general through the Earth, in ſome good Degree, ſhall be conform'd in Heart and Life, to the Goſpel and Temper of JESUS: The glorious Goſpel will pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully prevail, to the diſarming their fierce Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; regulating their exorbitant Deſires, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:009417_0018_0F743B278D9DFA28"/>
the moſt kindly and benevolent Sentiments: Hence, once for all, they will beat their Swords into Plow Shares, and their Spears into Pruning Hooks; and they will learn War no more: But Mankind, being united in the Sacred Bands of the Goſpel Charity, will dwell together in Love, in Peace and undiſturb'd Tranquility. This bleſſed Period, 'tis probable, will not come on, till we are dead and forgotten in the Earth: Yet ought we not, by Faith in the Word of GOD, to look forward to that Day, with Pleaſure and Joy; and earneſtly breathe after that Purity and Holineſs, that Peace and Joy, which will then bleſs the Earth. But eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially does it concern us, to look forward with Faith and Hope and Joy, to the complete and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Peace and Purity of the Heavenly World: Where there will be no Sin, nor Trouble, no War nor Uneaſineſs; but all will be Purity, Peace and Happineſs. This bleſſed State, if we are the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants of CHRIST, we may juſtly expect; and it cannot be far off; for Death is haſtening upon us. This is that glorious Reſt, which GOD, of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded Goodneſs and Grace, has prepared for all good Men. The Holineſs, the Joy and Glory of that World, far exceed our preſent Thoughts: "Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, nor have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the Heart of Man, the Things GOD has prepared for them that love Him." 'Tis of much greater Importance to us, that we diligently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for that World; than that we attempt to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe it. Let us ſee to it, that the Goſpel has it's ſanctifying and ſaving Influence upon our Hearts and Lives; that we are accepted in the Beloved;
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:009417_0018_0F743B278D9DFA28"/>
and intitled to the Heavenly Felicity; and that we act and live, as it becomes the Candidates for ſuch a Kingdom and World; and the Diſciples and Followers of the bleſſed JESUS: That we enjoy the ſolid Evidences of the ſpecial Love and Favour of GOD, and that Peace of GOD poſſeſs our Hearts, which paſſeth Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Let it be our Care, to live in Peace; in our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, in our Neighbourhood, and with Mankind around us: And that we improve and flouriſh, more and more in the divine Life; and grow up by happy and ſwift Advances to a Me<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>neſs for a better World; ardently aſpiring and breathing after the complete Purity, Reſt and Happineſs of that State: So when we ſhall be call'd off from theſe Regions of Guilt and Miſery, of War and Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; we ſhall aſcend to thoſe peaceful, bliſsful Realms on High; where no Sin will ever pollute; no Enemy will ever moleſt; but all will be Peace and Joy and endleſs Tranquility.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
