<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the King's Most Excellent Majesty in Council, the representation and petition of Your Majesty's dutiful and loyal subjects, freeholders and inhabitants of the province of Pennsylvania.</title>
            <author>Dickinson, John, 1732-1808.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N07666</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N07666</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 9786</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APY4129</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">9786</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99031262</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 9786.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N07666)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 9786)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 9786)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the King's Most Excellent Majesty in Council, the representation and petition of Your Majesty's dutiful and loyal subjects, freeholders and inhabitants of the province of Pennsylvania.</title>
                  <author>Dickinson, John, 1732-1808.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2, [2] p. ;  34 cm. (fol.) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Miller?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Philadelphia :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1764]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An unsigned petition, drawn up by John Dickinson in July 1764, protesting the General Assembly's proposal for a change from proprietary to royal government.</note>
                  <note>Imprint supplied by Evans.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pennsylvania --  Politics and government --  To 1775.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="unknown:009786_0000_0F7A553BFB77E850"/>
            <pb n="1"
                facs="unknown:009786_0001_0F7A553C43405620"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE KING's Moſt Excellent MAJESTY in COUNCIL, The REPRESENTATION and PETITION of Your Majeſty's dutiful and loyal Subjects, FREEHOLDERS and INHABITANTS of the Province of <hi>Pennſylvania.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Moſt humbly ſheweth,</opener>
            <p>THAT having received certain information that the Aſſembly of this Province, during their laſt ſitting, had drawn up a PETITION to your Majeſty, ſetting forth among other things, "That miſchievious diſagreements ſubſiſt in this govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which proceed, as they conceive, from the very Nature of it; and that a Spirit of Violence, Riot and Confuſion prevails among us, which cannot be controuled by the preſent Powers of Government and renders a Change of the ſame neceſſary":—Sundry Magiſtrates and reputable Freeholders, alarmed at the Nature of this Petition, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the whole Province as deeply affected by it, did (in Behalf of themſelves and others) apply to the Speaker of Aſſembly for Copy of the ſame, and to know whether the Houſe intended to tranſmit it to England, without communicating its Contents to their Conſtituents, and obtaining their fulleſt and moſt explicit Content therein.</p>
            <p>THAT they were informed by the Speaker, that the Petition had already been tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be laid before your Majeſty, and no Copy of it could be given without the Leave of the Houſe, at their Meeting in September next; when we apprehend it might be too late for us to ſubmit our Senſe of this Matter to your Majeſty; and therefore we beg Leave in all humble Duty, to <hi>repreſent</hi>—</p>
            <p>THAT as there is no civil Happineſs on Earth which we ſhould eſteem equal to that of being under your Majeſty's immediate perſonal Government, if our remote Situation could permit ſuch a Bleſſing; yet as we and all your American Subjects muſt be governed by Perſons authorized and approved by your Majeſty, on the beſt Recommendation that can be obtained of them, we cannot perceive our Condition in this Reſpect to be different from our Fellow Subjects around us, or that we are thereby leſs under your Majeſty's par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Care and Protection than they are; ſince there can be no Governor of this Province, without your Majeſty's immediate Approbation and Authority.</p>
            <p>THAT the particular Mode or Frame of Government which we enjoy under your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in this Province (as derived to us by the Charter of your Royal Anceſtor KING CHARLES the Second, and delivered to us by our wiſe Founder WILLIAM PENN <abbr>Eſq</abbr>) is held in the higheſt Eſtimation by good Men of all Denominations among us, and hath brought Multitudes of induſtrious People from various Parts of the World, who truſting in the perpetual Enjoyment of the ineſtimable Privileges it gives them, have, at their own Expence, ſettled this Colony, and raiſed it, in a few Years, to be one of the moſt flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in your Majeſty's American Dominions chearfully embracing every Opportunity of manifeſting their Loyalty and Affection to your Majeſty's Royal Perſon and Family.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2"
                   facs="unknown:009786_0002_0F7A553CF97CA8D8"
                   rendition="simple:additions"/>THAT ſuch Diſagreements as have ariſen in this Province we have beheld with Sorrow, but as others around us are not exempted from the like Misfortunes, We can by no Means conceive them incident to the Nature of our Government, which hath often been adminiſtred with remarkable Harmony; and your Majeſty, before whom our late Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes have been laid, can be at no Loſs, in your great Wiſdom, to diſcover whether they proceed from the above Cauſe, or ſhould be aſcribed to ſome other.</p>
            <p>THAT this Province (except from the Indian Ravages) enjoys the moſt perfect inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Tranquility; and a Spirit of Riot and Violence is ſo foreign to the general Temper of its Inhabitants, that there are as few inſtances of any Diſturbance of this kind to be met with among them ſince the firſt Settlement of the Colony, as perhaps among the like num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of People in any part of the World: That where ſuch diſturbances have happened, they have been ſpeedily quieted; the civil Powers have been ſupported; and tho' there are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps Caſes in all Governments, where it may not be poſſible ſpeedily to diſcover Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, yet we know of no inſtance among us where Perſons legally accuſed or convicted, have been ſcreen'd from public Juſtice; and if the executive Part of our Government ſhould ſeem in any caſe too weak, we conceive it is the Duty of the Aſſembly, and in their Power, to ſtrengthen it, without repreſenting us in a Light that might undeſervedly ſubject us to your Majeſty's Royal Diſpleaſure, which we ſhould deem the greateſt of all Misfortunes.</p>
            <p>WE therefore moſt humbly PRAY—That your Majeſty would be graciouſly pleaſed, wholly to diſregard the ſaid Petition of the Aſſembly, as exceeding grievous in its Nature; as by no means containing a proper Repreſentation of the State of this Province; and as repugnant to the general Senſe of your numerous and loyal Subjects in it; there being but few of them (comparatively ſpeaking) who could by any means be prevail'd on to give the leaſt Countenance to this Meaſure.</p>
            <p>AND your Petitioners, as in duty bound, ſhall ever pray <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
