<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Serious address, to such of the inhabitants of Pennsylvania, as have cannived [sic] at, or do approve of, the late massacre of the Indians at Lancaster; or the design of killing those who are now in the barracks at Philadelphia.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N07702</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N07702</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 9834</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APV9219</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">9834</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99004839</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 9834.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N07702)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 9834)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 9834)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Serious address, to such of the inhabitants of Pennsylvania, as have cannived [sic] at, or do approve of, the late massacre of the Indians at Lancaster; or the design of killing those who are now in the barracks at Philadelphia.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Anthony Armbruster] for the author,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1764.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 12: A Pensylvanian.</note>
                  <note>Ascribed to the press of Anthony Armbruster by Evans. Cf. the edition printed by Andrew Steuart (Evans 9836), which names "Mr. Armbluster" as printer of the first edition.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Massacres --  Pennsylvania.</term>
               <term>Paxton Boys.</term>
               <term>Conestoga Indians.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:009834_0000_0F7A500E2EABF3C8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:009834_0001_0F7A500EF3EBFE00"/>
            <p>A SERIOUS ADDRESS, To <hi>Such of the Inhabitants of PENNSYLANIA,</hi> As have cannived at, or do approve of, the late Maſſacre of the Indians at <hi>Lancaſter;</hi> or the Deſign of killing thoſe who are now in the Barracks at PHILADELPHIA.</p>
            <p>PILADELPHIA: <hi>Printed for the AUTHOR,</hi> 1764.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="unknown:009834_0002_0F7A500FE2C8ADA8"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>My</hi> BRETHREN <hi>and</hi> COUNTRYMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MADNESS in any Society of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is generally a Fore-Runner of their Deſtruction. For, before <hi>the Almighty</hi> deſtroys a Nation or People, he permits them firſt to be ſo infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated as to run into Extravagancies, which by natural Conſequences, bring Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon them. The Maſſacre of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians at <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and the too general Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation it has met with, are Evidences of very great Madneſs: And that Calamities, by Occaſion thereof, are impending over us, will appear from the following Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To put any Man to Death (tho' in open War) when he may be made a Priſoner, is contrary to the Laws of Nations.</p>
            <p>UNDER the <hi>Moſaic Diſpenſation,</hi> we find the Jews, who were under the immediate Direction of GOD himſelf, obſerving and performing their Treaties with great Punc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuality.—Thus the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> were ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe of the Publick Faith of the
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:009834_0003_0F7A50106CCAD3D0"/>
               <hi>Iſralites</hi> plighted to them, tho' the ſame was obtained by Fraud and Falſhood. And we find the good old Patriarch <hi>Jacob,</hi> by divine Inſpiration, on his Death-Bed; bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly curſing two of his Sons; becauſe of the Murder of <hi>Schechem</hi> and his Family, in cool Blood, after Peace had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded; tho' before he had committed a Crime worthy of Death.</p>
            <p>IT is a fundamental Law of all <hi>civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments,</hi> that no Perſon ſhall put another to death by his own Authority, let him have committed what Crime he may, if he can, with Safety be apprehended, ſo as to be brought to Tryal by the Laws of the Community.</p>
            <p>To make War on one Nation for the Offences of another Nation; or to ſlay one Man for the Crime of another, ſeems con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>natural Juſtice.</hi> But to butcher Infants at the Breaſt, in capable of diſtingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhing between Right and Wrong, for the Crimes of their Parents, or of the Nation to which they belong, or perhaps only for the Crimes of <hi>other</hi> Nations of the ſame Colour, is ſhocking to every Perſon who has the common Feelings of Humanity. The
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:009834_0004_0F7A5012AD9D6228"/>Viſiting the Iniquities of the Fathers upon the Children can only be underſtood of ſuch Children, who, from the Examples of their Fathers (which is too commonly the Caſe) purſue the ſame vicious Courſes. For to underſtand it otherwiſe, would be incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the moral Government of the <hi>Divine Being;</hi> who, by the Prophet has forbid to uſe this Proverb; "the Fathers have eaten ſower Grapes, and the Childrens Teeth are ſet on Edge: Becauſe the Soul that ſinneth, ſhall die, and the Son ſhall not bear the Iniquity of the Father."</p>
            <p>To apply theſe Doctrines to the preſent Caſe of the Indians, let us conſider;</p>
            <p>THAT the Indians conſiſt of different Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Tribes independent of one another, and make War or Peace ſeparately without each others Conſent,—Some indeed for their mutual Protections have joined in Aſſociations, like thoſe of the Swiſs Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, or the united Provinces. The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtogoe Tribe in the Year 1701. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed a Grant of their Land to <hi>W. Penn;</hi> and, by a ſolemn Treaty with this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, agreed to live together with us as
<pb n="6"
                   facs="unknown:009834_0005_0F7A5012C80CDE08"
                   rendition="simple:additions"/>one People. A ſmall Spot of Land was aſſigned to them to live upon: And, tho we did not make them Hewers of Wood and Drawers of Water, they have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there ever ſince, in no better Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than that of poor Basket-Makers and Broom-Makers. If ſome of them have, now and then, been guilty of Offences, they were always ready to be apprehended and brought to Tryal: And indeed, from the prevailing odium againſt Indians in general, if a Jury could be preſumed to be byaſſed, 'tis moſt likely they would be ſo, in Favour of the Proſecutors.</p>
            <p>DURING all the Time of our late Troubles they lived quietly and peaceably amongſt us, and ſome of them have been employed by the Government.</p>
            <p>BUT, notwitſtanding all this, an enraged Body of People, irritated by the Murders of ſome of their Relatives, <hi>by Indians of other Nations,</hi> on the Frontiers, came to the Indian Town and killed and ſcalped ſix of them, in cool Blood. The Reſidue of the whole Tribe, being fourteen in Number, in Purſuance of Promiſes made at ſolemn Treaties, immediately upon this,
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:009834_0006_0F7A5013B948B028"/>put themſelves under the Protection of the Magiſtrates, and were lodged in the Work-Houſe; which is Part of the Publick Goal in <hi>Lancaſter.</hi> But this was in vain. For a Party of fifty Men came to the Goal in broad Day-light; broke it open, and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly murdered thoſe Indians, not ſparing a Woman Seventy-ſeven Years of Age, nor a Child ſucking it's Mother's Breaſt. Now I appeal to every Man, who will give himſelf Leave to conſider, if ſuch an Act be not contrary to the Laws both divine and human, which I mentioned before.</p>
            <p>BUT the immediate apparent Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of this tumultuous Riot, and atroci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous Murder, is an additional Proof of the Infatuation of theſe People and their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betors.</p>
            <p>IT appears, from the publick Papers, that Negotiations for a general Peace with the Indians were in great Forwardneſs, which theſe unlucky Affairs muſt greatly retard, if not altogether prevent. For, how can Indians, who have been <hi>at War</hi> with us, confide in the Promiſes of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, when they find that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:009834_0007_0F7A5014388A9C00"/>unable to protect the friendly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, who have always been <hi>at Peace</hi> and have claimed it's Protection, from the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages of our own bad People! To extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the Indians is impracticable: It has been ſaid (and I believe with a great deal of Reaſon) that all the Forces in <hi>Europe</hi> could not totally deſtroy them. The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites will ſtill be in the Land. And while we continue at Enmity with them, they will be Thorns in our Sides, and Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars in our Eyes.—We have a long extended Frontier; to defend, all of which, from the Attacks and Incurſions of Savages, is impoſſible.—And theſe unhappy People who have committed this Outrage, if they had not been demented, ought, from their expoſed Situation, to have been the moſt cautious of doing any Act which might prevent ſuch a Peace. On the contrary their Friendſhip might be of very great Benefit to us.—The Skins and Furrs are great Weights in the Ballance of Trade between <hi>Great-Britain</hi> and us. Exchange is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by lowered, and conſequently the Prices of Goods which we import.</p>
            <p>ANOTHER apparent bad Conſequence is,
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:009834_0008_0F7A5014EF46FB48"/>unleſs the Indians have more Humanity than ſome of us, who profeſs, to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Light of the Goſpel, and to be Followers of the Prince of Peace; We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect but that the Priſoners, of our own Blood, who are now amongſt them, will ſhare the ſame Fate with the unhappy Wretches in <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Goal.</p>
            <p>THIS Province has been a Land of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; and Juſtice has hitherto been <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually</hi> adminiſtred, without Aſſiſtance of a Military Force. It has alſo been an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylum for People of tender Conſciences, who removed hither for the Liberty of worſhipping the <hi>Supream Being,</hi> in the Manner they believed moſt agreeable to Him. Theſe ineſtimable Privileges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced our Anceſtors to leave their Native Land, to encounter the Dangers of the Deep, and ſettle in this Howling Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; which is now become a fertile Field, a Land of Plenty. But alas! is it likely we ſhall long enjoy theſe Privileges? Can you imagine that <hi>Great-Britain</hi> will ſuffer the Adminiſtrations of Juſtice in ſo valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a Province as <hi>Pennſylvania</hi> to be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted; the Goals broke open; the Civil
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:009834_0009_0F7A5015B06DCBF0"/>Officers inſulted; Trade rendered pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious; and every Thing put into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, by a <hi>Mob?</hi> No certainly!</p>
            <p>INSURRECTIONS which had but ſmall Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings have often aroſe to great Heights; Becauſe, when once a Mob have broke through the Limits preſcribed by the Laws, 'tis uncertain, how far they will wander in the Fields of Anarchy and Confuſion; and what Extravagancies they will run into which at firſt they did not Deſign. If theſe People ſhould take it into their Heads, not to pay Taxes, or not to pay the Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries for their Lands, or the Merchants for their Goods; what would be the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence? Is it not highly probable, that, to prevent the like, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will oblige us to maintain a Military Force to ſupport the Civil Authority; and <hi>dragoon</hi> us into our Duty, <hi>at our own Expence!</hi> The Iron Rod of Military Power muſt correct thoſe who are deaf to the Voice of Reaſon and ſuperior to the Fear of the Laws.—Great is the Law, it muſt, and it will prevail. Whoever thinks himſelf exempted from the civil Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction only gnaws a File, which will
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:009834_0010_0F7A5017320BC098"/>break his Teeth.—Beſides, as 'tis currently reported, that theſe Outrages, Tumults and Inſurrections have been excited ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, and abetted, principally and chiefly, if not altogether, by Perſons diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting from the Church eſtabliſhed in <hi>England;</hi> it is too likely, if they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated and encouraged, that every Perſon who would bear an Office muſt conform to the Rites of that Church, in the ſame Manner as in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>FROM all theſe Hints, which I have thrown together, without Order or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, I hope you will be convinced, that it is your Duty to Uſe your Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with theſe deluded People, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt from their intended Enterprize; and that you will endeavour to convince them of their Error in what they have already done. Why ſhould they be rendered deſperate by having a Price ſet upon their Heads, like Wolves? Why ſhould they have a Mark ſet upon them; and wander like Fugitives and Vagabonds in continual Fear? Or why ſhould we be put to the Expence of maintaining an Army in Time of Peace, which we
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:009834_0011_0F7A5017EDAD63D0"/>might have done without? Or pay Tithes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to Clergy, whom many of us do not chooſe to hear preach? Or why ſhould you deprive yourſelves of filling the Poſts you are otherwiſe qualified for, by vindicating a wrongheaded Mob?</p>
            <p>THE lower Sort of People are very imitative of their Superiors.—They watch their Motions, Looks and Eyes:—If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more ſenſible Part of you would openly avow your Diſapprobation of theſe Meaſures, you will find this Rage and Clamour will ſoon ſubſide; Theſe People will diſperſe; they will crumble like the Duſt, and diſappear [at leaſt in a hoſtile Manner] like the Snow that melted yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>yours &amp;c. A <hi>PENSYLVANIAN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
