<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The devotions of God's people adjusted to the dispensations of his providence. A sermon preached in the First Parish of Hingham, December 6, 1770. The day observed throughout the province as a day of public thanksgiving and prayer. / By Ebenezer Gay, A.M. Pastor of the First Church in Hingham. ; [Four lines of Scripture texts]</title>
            <author>Gay, Ebenezer, 1696-1787.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N09464</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N09464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 12054</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX3361</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">12054</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99020129</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 12054.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N09464)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 12054)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 12054)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The devotions of God's people adjusted to the dispensations of his providence. A sermon preached in the First Parish of Hingham, December 6, 1770. The day observed throughout the province as a day of public thanksgiving and prayer. / By Ebenezer Gay, A.M. Pastor of the First Church in Hingham. ; [Four lines of Scripture texts]</title>
                  <author>Gay, Ebenezer, 1696-1787.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23, [1] p. ;  21 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Draper,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MCCLXXI. [i.e., 1771]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Mr. Gay's sermon preached in the First Parish of Hingham, December 6. 1770. A day of thanksgiving and prayer.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thanksgiving sermons --  1770 Dec. 6.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:012054_0000_0F896FCA361DF930"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:012054_0001_0F896FCAF568E1D0"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>GAY</hi>'s SERMON Preached in the Firſt Pariſh of HINGHAM, <hi>December</hi> 6. 1770. A Day of Thankſgiving and Prayer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:012054_0002_0F896FCBB75CED88"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Devotions of God's People adjuſted to the Diſpenſations of his Providence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN THE FIRST PARISH OF <hi>HINGHAM, December</hi> 6, 1770.</p>
            <p>THE Day obſerved throughout the Province as a Day of public THANKSGIVING and PRAYER.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>EBENEZER GAY,</hi> A.M. Paſtor of the firſt Church in HINGHAM.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Offer a Sacrifice of Thankſgiving with Leaven.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Amos, 4.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Offer unto God Thankſgiving, and pay thy Vows unto the moſt High. And call upon me in the Day of Trouble: I will deliver thee, and thou ſhalt glorify me.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm, 50. 14.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON:</hi> Printed by RICHARD DRAPER, MCCLXXI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="unknown:012054_0003_0F896FCC769FE6E8"/>
            <head>THE Devotions of GOD's People adjuſted to the Diſpenſations of his Providence.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JEREMIAH XXXI. 7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>FOR thus ſaith the Lord, Sing with Gladneſs for Jacob, and ſhout among the Chief of the Nations: Publiſh ye, praiſe ye, and ſay, O Lord, ſave thy People, and the Remnant of Iſrael.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN this Chapter, as in the foregoing, the Prophet foretells the Reſtoration of the Jews from the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> ſeventy Years Captivity:—that they ſhould return into their own Land, rebuild their Cities and Houſes; plant their Vineyards, and eat the Fruits thereof, and be happily reſettled in their former State of Freedom and Plenty; in which they ſhould be adorned with ſignal Marks of the divine Favour, and all the Signs of religious and civil Joy— <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord, Sing with Gladneſs for Jacob,
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:012054_0004_0F896FCD37322468"/>and ſhout among the Chief of the Nations:</hi> &amp;c. when you ſee the Dawning of thoſe bleſſed Times, expreſs your Joy for the Reſtoration of Jacob's Poſterity, in the moſt public Manner that can be, in the Sight of the Chiefeſt of thoſe potent Nations, from whence you are to be delivered. <hi>Publiſh ye, Praiſe ye—</hi> Publiſh thoſe good Tidings with the higheſt Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Praiſe and Glory to God,—<hi>and ſay, O Lord, ſave thy People, the Remnant of Iſrael,</hi>—likewiſe pray earneſtly that God, who hath begun ſo glorious a Work, would go on to complete and perfect it.</p>
            <p>THE Words afford us this ſeaſonable Inſtruction; <hi>That the joyful Praiſes of a People for Mercies recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſhould be accompanied with fervent Prayers unto God to ſave them from Judgments which are ſtill felt, or feared, by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEN the Jews Deliverance from the Miſeries of a long Captivity in Babylon was begun, in the firſt Steps of their Return from among the Nations which oppreſſed them, they were to <hi>ſing for Gladneſs, and ſhout</hi> for Joy, to <hi>publiſh</hi> with the Voice of Praiſe and Thankſgivings the great Favour of God towards them: And at the ſame Time to pray with all Earneſtneſs that God would ſtill deliver his People from the Calamities they were yet under, or might expect to meet with in their Journey to, and after their Arrival in their own Land. And what the Lord ſaid unto them in the Words of the Text, he ſpeaketh unto us, and all the People of this Province; teaching us to obſerve this Day of public Thankſgiving as a Day of ſolemn Prayer alſo:—That while we ſing for Gladneſs, and ſhout forth the Honour of God's Name, publiſhing with the Voice of Thankſgiving the Salvation, he hath
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:012054_0005_0F896FCDF747F270"/>ſhewed our Nation and the People of this Land, in the Courſe of the Year paſt, and praiſe him therefor, we likewiſe make this fervent Prayer unto him, <hi>O Lord, ſave thy People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>GOD's Diſpenſations towards his People, and Mankind in general, to which we ſhould accommodate our Devotions, are mixed of Mercies, and Judgments. In the Adminiſtrations of his moral Government He diſpenſeth both, in ſuch Meaſure and Manner, as his Wiſdom directeth his Juſtice and Goodneſs. The Condition of a People in this World is not at any Time altogether proſperous, nor quite deſperate. Their State is uſually ſuch as is elegantly deſcribed by the Prophet, Zech. 14.6.7. <hi>It ſhall come to paſs in that Day, that the Light ſhall not be clear nor dark. But it ſhall be one Day, which ſhall be known to the Lord, not Day nor Night: But it ſhall come to paſs, that at Evening-time it ſhall be Light.</hi> Throughout the Day of Man's Life on Earth, the Light is neither clear nor dark—it is neither Day nor Night with him:—underſtanding by Light and Darkneſs, by Day and Night, Good and Evil. This is true of a People, during their continuance as ſuch. Their Condition here is never perfectly and purely good, nor ſo throughly bad, as to be void of all Comfort. In Heaven the Light is clear, without any Darkneſs at all: In Hell there is the blackneſs of Darkneſs for ever. In Heaven it is all Day, <hi>there is no Night there;</hi> but nothing elſe in the Dungeon of Hell. But Light and Darkneſs, Good and Evil, Peace and Trouble, which are perfect and ſeparate in the other World, are, in a leſſer Degree of them blended in this. In this World there is a Day of Proſperity, and a Night of Adverſity; and yet neither Day, nor Night:
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:012054_0006_0F896FCEB7692288"/>—Not a Day without <hi>the Evil of it,</hi> nor a Night of unallayed Affliction. Sometimes the Light may prevail above the Darkneſs, but does not wholly diſpel it; ſometimes the Darkneſs prevails above the Light, but doth not wholly exclude it. The brighteſt Day of Proſperity is not without Clouds, nor the darkeſt Night of Adverſity without Gleams of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. Good and Evil, as to the Degrees of them, ſucceed each other; and they are curiouſly interwoven into one Web, by the Art of divine Providence. So God tempereth his Diſpenſations, intermingles Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and Croſſes, and the Work of his Providence is chequered.</p>
            <p>To convince all, that <hi>verily he is a God that judgeth in the Earth,</hi> and engage our dutiful Regards to him, as the great, the wiſe, the juſt, and good Governor of the World, the Lord uſeth a Variety and Mixture of Diſpenſations towards Men in their preſent probationary State. In no other imaginable Way of dealing with ſuch Creatures as we are, could there have been ſo ſuitable a Diſplay of his glorious Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to excite our due Acknowledgment of him in this high Relation he ſuſtaineth to us. If there were only Afflictions to be met with in this World, Sinners would have no Knowledge of the Goodneſs of God from his Providence, nor Invitations therefrom to Repentance. But he is <hi>the Lord that exerciſeth Loving kindneſs in the Earth,</hi> and ſheweth his Bounty to his offending Creatures, that they might be induced to remember and return to him He maketh his Sun to riſe on the Evil and on the Good, and ſendeth Rain on the Juſt and on the Unjuſt. He leaveth not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf without Witneſs to any, in that he giveth Rain from Heaven, and fruitful Seaſons, filling their Hearts
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:012054_0007_0F896FCF74E52340"/>with Food and Gladneſs. All the Gifts of God's common Bounty, which are promiſcuouſly ſcattered abroad on every ſide, are ſo many Witneſſes ſent to atteſt the divine Care and Goodneſs, which leadeth Men to Repentance. And were it not for the <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments God executeth in the Earth,</hi> the Righteouſneſs of his moral Government would not appear, and no ill Conſequence of perſiſting impenitent in Wickedneſs would be dreaded by Men. Pſ. 55.19. <hi>God ſhall both hear and afflict them, even he that abideth of old: Becauſe they have no Changes, therefore they fear not God.</hi> Uninterrupted Proſperity would baniſh all fear of God out of the World. God maketh himſelf known, as infinitely worthy of our higheſt Regards, by the Mercies and Judgments he diſpenſeth, according to his own Declaration, in Iſai. 45.6.7. <hi>That they may know from the riſing of the Sun, and from the Weſt, that there is none beſides me, I am the Lord, and there is none elſe: I form the Light, and create Darkneſs: I make Peace, and create Evil: I the Lord do all theſe Things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To prevent the Exceſſes which People are apt to run into in both States, proſperous and adverſe, the Diſpenſations of Providence are mixed of Mercies and Judgments: That we might not ſurfeit on Proſperity, nor deſpond in Adverſity,—wax wanton, nor become deſperate. Did Men always enjoy a flouriſhing Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, would they not be corrupted, and deſtroyed thereby? <hi>Jeſurun</hi> waxed fat, and kicked:—then he forſook God which made him, and lightly eſteemed the Rock of his Salvation.<note n="*" place="bottom">Deut. 32.15.</note> Did they meet with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Diſappointment and Trouble, would they not be ſwallowed up of Sorrow? <hi>I had fainted,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>unleſs I had believed to ſee the Goodneſs
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:012054_0008_0F896FD0FB58D348"/>of the Lord in the Land of the living.</hi> A Mixture therefore of providential Diſpenſations is neceſſary to prevent Mens being ruin'd by uninterrupted Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or overwhelm'd with perpetual Adverſty: And to teach them Moderation in all things; <hi>to weep, as tho' they wept not; and to rejoice, as tho' they rejoiced not; and to uſe this World, as not abuſing it, ſince the Faſhion of it paſſeth away.</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Cor. 7.30, 31.</note> God wiſely diſpenſeth Good and Evil to Men, that they might not in their Proſperity ſay, their Mountain ſtandeth ſtrong, and they ſhall never be moved, but rejoice with trembling: Nor in their Adverſity ſay, they ſhall never be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, but hope ſtill in God. The moſt proſperous Condition here is deficient in ſome Conveniences, and blended with ſome Troubles, that Men might not be exceſſive in their Rejoicings: And the moſt adverſe Condition hath ſomewhat of Good in it, to compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſate for its Evils, and Hope lieth at the bottom of it, that they ſhould not be immoderate in their Griefs. Some Evil there always is in our State on Earth, to ſhew that we are not paſt Danger: and ſome Good, to ſhew that we are not ſhut out from all Hope. As a wiſe Pilot taketh in ſo much Burthen, as will ballaſt the Ship, and not ſink it: So in the midſt of the Favours with which we are encompaſſed in this World, God layeth ſuch a Burthen of Affliction upon us, as might ſerve to keep us ſteady, when the Wind of Temptation filleth the Sails. The Scales of Providence are even, and God weigheth out Good and Evil in due Proportion; puts that into one Condition, which may reduce it to ſome Ballance with another. He ſo allayeth the Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Proſperity, and the Bitterneſs of Adverſity, that we might preſerve an equal Temper of Mind in both, and not be puffed up with one, nor caſt down by the other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="unknown:012054_0009_0F896FD1F4E92698"/>
THE Diſpenſations of Providence being for wiſe and good Reaſons mixed of Mercies and Judgments, our thankful Praiſes ſhould be accompained with our fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant Prayers. When we <hi>ſing for Gladneſs,</hi> and ſhout for Joy, publiſhing God's Mercies and praiſing him for them, we ſhould ſay, <hi>O Lord, we beſeech thee, ſave thy People.</hi> Our devotional Addreſſes to God ſhould be conformable to his Diſpenſations towards us. We have this Direction given us for them in Scripture, Phil 4.6. <hi>In every Thing by Prayer and Supplication, with Thankſgiving, let your Requeſts be made known unto God.</hi>—In every Thing that occurs, in every Condition, and on every proper Occaſion, let Prayer be mingled with Thankſgiving,—offer your Petitions with your Thanks to Almighty God. So in 1. Theſ. 5.16. <hi>Rejoice evermore, pray without ceaſing. In every thing give Thanks: For this is the Will of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning you in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> It is his Will declared in the Goſpel, that Chriſtians ſhould be always rejoicing, praying, and giving of Thanks, whatever their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances may be—never to ceaſe praying, nor in any thing to omit Thankſgiving. Theſe Duties may be well performed together without Interference, or juſtling one another: There is always room and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for both.</p>
            <p n="1">1. THERE is always Room and Occaſion for Praiſe and Thankſgiving, even in Circumſtances of greateſt Affliction and Diſtreſs. We are never incompaſſed with ſuch Troubles and Sorrows in this Life, as not to have greater Cauſe of Thankfulneſs, than Complaint. We ſhould conſider what Proportion there is between the Mercies and Judgments diſpenſed to us in the Adminiſtrations of Providence, and not be diſcompoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and put out of tune by the latter for ſinging with
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:012054_0010_0F896FD2757E1B68"/>Gladneſs, and praiſing God for the former. We are too apt to pore only on the Afflictions we ſuffer, and to overlook the Bleſſings we enjoy. It is our Weakneſs, and Sin, that a ſmall Inconvenience attending us, hindereth us from rejoicing in, and praiſing God for many and great Comforts. <hi>One dead Fly cauſeth all our Ointment to ſtink.</hi> One diſagreeable Circumſtance of our worldly State, marreth the grateful Reliſh of the whole. So long as there was one Man at Court, who would not cringe to him, all <hi>Haman</hi>'s Honors, Riches, royal Feaſts, and the like Accommodations, <hi>availed Him nothing.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.13.</note> The Poſſeſſion of a Kingdom would not keep <hi>Ahab</hi> from being <hi>heavy and diſpleaſed,</hi> when he could not get a ſmall Vineyard he coveted.<note n="†" place="bottom">1. King's 21.4.</note> The imaginary want of that pinched him in all his Affluence of Wealth, and took away his Stomach, ſo that he might have ſtarved in the midſt of his royal Dainties. Had we a due Conſideration of the innumerable and ineſtimable Benefits God hath done unto us, we ſhould in any Afflictions we ſuffer be diſpoſed to ſay as <hi>Job</hi> did in his, <hi>ſhall we receive Good at the Hand of the Lord? and ſhall we not receive Evil alſo?</hi> Do we not receive more good than evil Things in this Life? The leaſt of the former is more; the greateſt of the latter is leſs than we deſerve. Are our Afflictions worthy to be compared with our Mercies? <hi>Wherefore doth a liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Man complain, a Man for the Puniſhment of his Sins?</hi> A Man ſtill among the living, and conſcious that his Lot might juſtly be among the dead, ſhould praiſe the God of his Life. He enjoys the moſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thing in this World, and for the ſake of which, had he every other, he would part therewith. He ſhould therefore reſolve as <hi>David, While I live, will I praiſe the Lord: I will ſing Praiſes unto my God while I have any being.</hi> Whatever our Loſſes, Croſſes,
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:012054_0011_0F896FD3382DA338"/>and Afflictions be, we are, in Compariſon of what is due to us, very favourably dealt with. Should a Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor exact but a ſmall part of our Debt to him, ſhould we not be much pleaſed, and ready to thank him? And why ſhould we not be ſo with reſpect to God, dealing thus graciouſly with us? He might juſtly deprive us of all good Things: Strip us of all our Comforts, and ſeparate us to all evil, and only evil: It is plainly therefore our Duty to be thankful in any Condition on this ſide the Grave and Hell. We muſt acknowledge with the afflicted Church, <hi>It is of the Lord's Mercies that we are not conſumed,—they are new every Morning: Great is thy faithfulneſs</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Lam. 3.22, 23.</note> Even in Judgment inflicted on us, who might have it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Mercy, there may be more Mercy in it than Judgment: In which Senſe that is true which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Mercy rejoiceth againſt Judgment,</hi>—<note n="†" place="bottom">Jam. 2.13.</note> boaſts itſelf—triumphs over it. God, as the Sun (ſaith one) when he ſeemeth moſt to infeſt and ſcorch us, doth even then diſpenſe uſeful and ſalutary Influences upon us. There is not indeed any thing in Nature ſo venemous, but that from it by Art and Induſtry may be extracted ſome what medicinal and of ſalutary uſe, when duly applied. In moſt apparent Evils lieth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed much Good, which if we carefully ſeparate, we may find Benefit and taſte Comfort from. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo thoroughly bad, as being well ordered and improved, will not yield us more good. <hi>It is good for me,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, that I have been afflicted.</hi> There is nothing commonly more neceſſary, more whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and beneficial to Men than Adverſity. Afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the School of Wiſdom, in which we learn God's Statutes. It is the Furnace of the Soul, in which it is tried and refined. It is the Means of reclaiming them from Sin, and improving them in Grace, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:012054_0012_0F896FD3F680B2A0"/>them unto Glory. Why then ſhould they be dumb to God's Praiſes in it, bear it with ſullen Silence, or break forth into Words of Impatience under it? They have reaſon to ſing of the Wiſdom, the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Faithfulneſs of God, in his chaſtiſing them: Not only to be contented with, but thankful for the Troubles, Diſaſters, and Diſappointments they meet with in an evil World, as they prove on many Accounts advantageous to them. We ſhould return Thanks to God, not for our Food only, but alſo for our Phyſic, which, tho' diſtaſteful to our Palate, is profitable to our Health. Whatever proceeds from good Intention, and tendeth to a happy End,—is deſigned, and effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually conduceth to our good, is a fit Subject of Thankſgiving. If we conſult Experience, we ſhall find, that, as many have cauſe to mourn that they have enjoyed ſo much Proſperity, and received their Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation here; ſo many have cauſe to rejoice that they have ſuffered Adverſity, and taſted ſo deep of the bitter Cup.<note n="*" place="bottom">Periiſſem, riſi Periiſſem.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. THERE is likewiſe Room and Occaſion for Prayer and Supplication even in Circumſtances of greateſt Proſperity and Peace. In ſuch the Lord's People ſhould <hi>beſeech</hi> him to <hi>ſave</hi> them—to deliver them from the Evil ſtill incumbent, or to which they are expoſed—to lengthen out their Tranquility—to complete and perfect their Salvation. With their thankful Acknowledgments of Mercies received, they are to make their humble Addreſſes to the Throne of Grace for all which they farther need. If we ſincerely praiſe God for any Tokens of his Favour which he ſheweth us, we ſhall be ſo affected with the Tokens of his Anger which there ſtill may be, as earneſtly to deſire the removal of them. And if we are truly thankful for his Bleſſings, we cannot but be deſirous
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:012054_0013_0F896FD4B7373D18"/>of their Continuance and Increaſe. We may ſeem highly gratified with ſome Inſtances of God's Bounty to us, greatly pleaſed with the Smiles of his Providence in ſome Reſpects, and yet our rejoicing in them, and praiſing God for them may ariſe from carnal Self-love; or becauſe Proviſion, we may vainly imagine, is made for our Luſts, and we are Heaven's Favourites, who are ſo bountifully dealt with; if we, at the ſame Time, take no Notice of the Marks of God's Diſpleaſure upon us in other Reſpects, cauſing us to rejoice with trembling, and in our praiſing God to pray unto him for his Salvation.</p>
            <p>THE Memory of paſt Benefits, and Senſe of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, which there is in Thankſgiving, confirms our Faith, and nouriſhes our Hope of future. The Mercies of God are to be thankfully received and entertain'd by us, as Pledges of his Love, and ſo Encouragements to truſt in him, and ſeek unto him for all we farther need. And a truly grateful Senſe of Benefits done unto us, is the beſt Preparation of the Heart to aſk for more. It is the Diſpoſition to which our divine Benefactor hath ſpecial Regard, in the Beſtowment of them. He is ready to give, wherever he ſeeth a Diſpoſition worthily to entertain his Bleſſings: So that the moſt thankful Receiver of them, is the moſt ſucceſsful Petitioner for them. When therefore we are moſt ſenſible of our great Benefactor's Goodneſs in thoſe Effects of it which we with Hearts glowing with Gratitude acknowledge; our ardent Petitions breathed out to him with our thankful Praiſes will (we may hope) be accepted and granted by him. Fervent Prayer, mingled with Thankſgiving, availeth much. If we thus make known our Requeſts to God, he will be ſo far from ſtinting his Hand to us, that he
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:012054_0014_0F896FD575962B90"/>will <hi>rejoice over us to do us good,</hi> and be as ready and as highly pleaſed to multiply his Benefits upon us, as we can be to aſk and receive them.</p>
            <p>IN every thing that we give Thanks, there is need of Prayer alſo, that it may be to us Matter of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving:—that it may prove advantageous unto us, that our Bleſſings may not be curſed, nor our Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be unſanctified to us; but that all Things of different Qualities mixed and diſpenſed by the ſkilful Hand of Providence, may, either in their preſent and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate, or in their future and more remote Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>work together for our good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THERE being always Room and Occaſion in all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Circumſtances for Thankſgiving and Prayer, theſe are Duties which ſhould always accompany one another.</p>
            <p>MY BRETHREN,</p>
            <p>WE ſee the Expedience and Propriety of appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this Day to be obſerved as a Day of <hi>public Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving</hi> throughout this Province: and that the Purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of a <hi>public Faſt,</hi> (which ſome may think would have been more ſeaſonable) may be anſwered thereby, if the People, as they are exhorted, <q>accompany their devout Praiſes for the many great and undeſerved public Mercies, which amidſt the various Tokens of his Diſpleaſure, God hath beſtowed on us, with their fervent Prayers to him, that thoſe Judgments which we labour under may be removed—that thoſe we have reaſon to fear may be averted—and that we may be prepared ſuitably to receive every Token of Divine Favour which it may pleaſe a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful God to beſtow upon us.</q> The religious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:012054_0015_0F896FD63724F180"/>of the Day being in the Magiſtrates Order for it ſo clearly pointed out to us, the Miniſter ſhould direct and urge the ſincere Performance of it.—Suffer we therefore this Word of Exhortation, <hi>ſing for gladneſs,—publiſh ye, praiſe ye, and ſay, O Lord, ſave thy People.</hi> Let us offer our united Praiſes for the Favours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon us in the Courſe of the Year paſt, which hath not indeed been withouts it's Troubles, and ſuch as have been complained of as the greateſt ever met with in the Country. We have yet Cauſe to celebrate our annual <hi>ſolemn Feaſt,</hi> and rejoice before the Lord. An Expreſſion in the Prophets occurs to my Thoughts; <hi>Offer a Sacrifice of Thankſgiving with Leaven.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Am. 4.5.</note> Leaven was forbidden in other Sacrifices,<note n="†" place="bottom">Lev. 2.11.</note> but requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in this of Thankſgiving,<note n="‖" place="bottom">C. 7. V. 13.</note> to teach us (ſaith <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi>) to temper our Joy with Sorrow and Affliction in this Life. Our Joy on this Day of the Gladneſs of our Hearts, ſhould be tempered, but not ſtifled, with a ſorrowful Senſe of the Affliction which the Province is in. Notwithſtanding which, there are many and great public Mercies, which call for our thankful Acknowledgments. Particularly, the Peace which we have in the Peace of our Nation with foreign Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, by His Majeſty's Care preſerved to all his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions. It is for a Lamentation, that we have been no more at peace among ourſelves. Pray we for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>—The general Health we have been and ſtill are favoured with, demands our public Thanks; and we ſhall heartily render the ſame to God, unleſs the Commonneſs and Continuance of ſo great a Bleſſing hath abated and enervated our Gratitude. We have not been viſited this Year with infectious, or any epedemical Diſeaſes, which have ſometimes carried People away as with a Flood: Though ſome (alaſs!) have been <hi>driven from Light
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:012054_0016_0F896FD6F9DFCFA8"/>into Darkneſs, and chaſed out of the World,</hi> by the Violence of ſtormy Winds, and of human Hands. While our Souls bleſs the Lord, who healeth our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, and redeemeth our Lives from Deſtruction, who ſtilleth the Noiſe of the Seas, the Noiſe of their Waves, and the Tumult of the People; let us pray, that the People may be forgiven all their Iniquity, and ſo the Inhabitants of this Land may not ſay, <hi>we are ſick:</hi> nor have Occaſion, or Colour, of Complaint, that their <hi>Blood is ſhed like Water</hi>—poured forth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Pity or Remorſe—too often the ſad Conſequence of inteſtine Jars and Quarrels. Let us beſeech the Lord, who ruleth the raging of the Sea, to reſtrain the Wrath of Men, which is cruel when it breaketh out in mobbiſh Fury, or military Reſentment.</p>
            <p>THERE is the Joy of a plentiful Harveſt, in which we are to ſing with Gladneſs, and ſhout forth the Praiſes of Him that hath given us fruitful Seaſons, and crowned the Year with his Goodneſs ſo that we have all Things neceſſary and convenient for Life and Godlineſs ſtill given us richly to enjoy, tho' ſo much of the worldly Subſtance of many, eſpecially in this and other maritime Towns, hath been deſtroyed by the raging Tempeſt, and ſwelling Tide. By whatever Means our Eſtates have been dimiſhed, or our thriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them obſtructed,—whether by impoveriſhing Events of divine Providence, or oppreſſive Meaſures of human Government, or our own Imprudence, yet the good Encreaſe of our Land (free from Parliamentary Taxation) certainly calls for the Obſervation of this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſary Solemnity. In which, while we with Hearts full of Food and Gladneſs give Thanks to the Author of our Plenty, let us take heed, and pray, that our Table may not become a Snare before us, and what is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:012054_0017_0F896FD7B4E16250"/>for our Welfare be a Trap—that we may not abuſe the good Things our great Benefactor with ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral a Hand beſtowed on us, to Intemperance and Senſuality, Irreligion and Forgetfulneſs of God. Let not <hi>the Feaſt of In-gathering</hi> be made by any of us the Seaſon, nor prove to any the Occaſion of riotous Exceſs, and ſinful Extravagance. May the Lord ſave his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this Land from ſuch Gluttony and Drunkenneſs, and voluptuous Living, as he charged his People Iſrael with in their affluent Circumſtances, and, which was an Aggravation of their Sins, they moſt indulg'd themſelves in on the ſolemn Feaſt-days appointed and ſet apart on purpoſe religiouſly to commemorate the Bleſſings and Benefits they had received from God, and to return him due Thanks therefor. "Wo unto them that riſe up early in the Morning, that they may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſtrong Drink, that continue until Night, till Wine inflame them. And the Harp and the Viol, the Tabret and Pipe, and Wine are in their Feaſts, but they regard not the Works of the Lord, nor conſider the Operation of his Hands,"<note n="*" place="bottom">Iſa. 5.11, 12.</note>—i. e. the Works of God in Memory of which thoſe Feaſts were kept. Their only Care and Thought was to feed and pamper their Luſts with the Produce of a fruitful Land, and not to bleſs God who gave it them for an Inheritance, and therefore he cut them ſhort as he threaten'd, —<hi>Yea, ten Acres of Vineyard ſhall yield one Bath, and the Seed of an Omer ſhall yield an Ephah,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">V. 10.</note>—the Harveſt ſhould produce but the tenth part of the Seed.</p>
            <p>OF the enumerated public Mercies which we are called upon this Day thankfully to acknowledge, there is none, perhaps, to which People find their Hearts ſo indiſpoſed, as that of the Adminiſtration of civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; which hath been loudly complained of in
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:012054_0018_0F896FD93A9C68E8"/>our Mother-Country, and in this. And it might only increaſe the Clamours of ſome at it, to exhort them to ſing with Gladneſs for it, and to bleſs God with thoſe Tongues that have been uſed to curſe Men, made after his Image. I don't ſuſpect there are any ſuch among my Hearers; and may therefore ſafely put them in Mind of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Exhortation to Chriſtians, under greater Oppreſſion from bad Rulers, than we ſuffer at this Day; that <hi>Thankſgivings,</hi> as well as <hi>Prayers, be made for Kings, and for all that are in Authority.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">1 Tim. 1.1, 2</note> Magiſtrates are the Miniſters of God to us for good, and when they faithfully diſcharge their Office, and anſwer the End of their Inſtitution, they are to be reckon'd among the greateſt Bleſſings of God to the World. With all their ſuperior Abilities and Advantages to promote the common Wealth, they have the natural Infirmities of other Men, and far beyond other Men are ſubject to Temptations, which too often miſlead them into pernicious Courſes of Adminiſtration, and they do the People much hurt. And when the <hi>Wicked bear Rule, the People mourn.</hi>—And if it ſhould admit of a doubt, whether Mankind receive Good from civil Government, ſufficient to make amends for the Evil they ſuffer, through the Miſtakes, Follies, and Tyrannies of thoſe who manage it; yet they muſt be worſe Rulers than are known in <hi>Old England,</hi> or <hi>New,</hi> from whoſe Adminiſtration People do not receive more Benefits, than they ſuffer Miſchiefs: And they ſhould accept the former with Thankfulneſs to God, while they groan under, and in lawful Ways ſeek Deliverance from the latter. What the Proportion between theſe hath been in the late difficult Times, among us, I'm not about to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute: Would only obſerve to you, that the religious Privileges, for the Sake of which principally, our pious
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:012054_0019_0F896F0216A19FF8"/>Anceſtors came into this Land, are hitherto enjoyed by us: and 'tis not pretended to be more than the Beginning of Encroachment on our civil Rights, that hath ſo juſtly alarmed our Fears of loſing them all. By the Bleſſing of God on the Government over us, we continue as yet poſſeſſed of the moſt valuable Liberties and Privileges belonging to Engliſhmen, and Chriſtians, and do lead our Lives ſo comfortably as we do. We have ſtill Rulers that will not oppreſs us themſelves, nor, if they can prevent it, ſuffer others to oppreſs us.—Thoſe exerciſing Authority over us, whom we may juſtly call Benefactors; and for whom we owe our Thanks to him whoſe Miniſters they are to us for Good.</p>
            <p>IF the late Diſturbance of the public Peace, is to be imputed wholly to oppreſſive Acts of Government, (which are apt to make a <hi>wiſe</hi> People <hi>mad,</hi>) yet this with all it's bad Conſequences is to be regarded as a ſore Judgment of God upon us; and the Joy of this Day be mixed with Sorrow on account of it. By leaving us to fall into ruinous Contention among our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves—into a moſt unquiet State, in which Men's Minds have been extremely diſcompoſed, and exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated; their Mouths filled with evil Speeches, bitter Invectives, and horrid Execrations; and their Hands ſtretched out in baſe injurious Deeds of Violence—the public Counſels have been divided—friendly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Commerce interrupted,—Tumults raiſed—Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages commited—Blood ſhed, a righteous God hath puniſhed us for our Iniquities. His holy Anger hath been teſtified againſt us in all our Troubles, whoever were the moſt active, faulty Inſtruments of them. Let us therefore, in the exerciſe of godly Sorrow, which is conſiſtent with ſpiritual Rejoicing, beſeech the
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:012054_0020_0F896FDA4366D980"/>Lord to ſave his People out of ſo ſinful and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous a State. Let us hope continually in God, pray to him without ceaſing, and praiſe him more and more. If we are truly thankful for any Tokens of the divine Favour towards us in the Adminiſtrations of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, our fervent Prayers accompanying our devout Praiſes to the great Governor of the World, who hath the Hearts of all Kings and Rulers in his Hand, may avail to procure his Bleſſing on the public Counſels, ſo as that they ſhall be directed to ſuch Meaſures as ſhall promote our laſting Welfare and Tranquility. We muſt not expect the Perfection of Happineſs under the beſt human Management of our public Affairs, and that all things will proceed according to our Minds. Nor muſt we faint, and be diſcouraged, tho' our Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances be not all at once redreſſed. For the Exerciſe of our Faith and Patience Things may remain ſtill in doubtful uncertainty, and we not be able to ſay whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they tend to Ruin, or Eſtabliſhment. The late Time of Trouble and Diſtreſs in the Land, hath been ſpoken of as the darkeſt Day that ever paſſed over us. Be it ſo, yet who knows but that the preſent is the <hi>Evening Time</hi> of ſuch a Day, when God hath ſaid <hi>it ſhall be light?</hi> Let us rejoice in Hope, and pray in Faith, that we, and our Children to the lateſt Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, may enjoy ſuch Peace, Freedom, and Felicity in the Land which our Fathers have left us for an Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, as God promiſed to give his oppreſſed People, the Remnant of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in their Reſtoration to their former happy State, for which they were to <hi>ſing with Gladneſs, and ſhout among the Nations, to publiſh, praiſe, and pray,</hi> as in the Text. Jer. 30.18.—<hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, I will bring again the Captivity of Jacob's Tents, and have Mercy on his Dwelling Places, and the City ſhall be built on her own Heap, and the
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:012054_0021_0F896FDAB561D908"/>Palace ſhall remain after the Manner thereof. And out of them ſhall proceed Thankſgiving, and the Voice of them that make merry: And I will multiply them, and they ſhall not be few; I will alſo glorify them, and they ſhall not be ſmall. Their Children alſo ſhall be as aforetime, and their Congregation ſhall be eſtabliſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, and I will puniſh all that oppreſs them. And their Nobles ſhall be of themſelves, and their</hi> GOVERNOR <hi>ſhall proceed from the midſt of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
