<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Essay on education; delivered at the public commencement, at Yale-College, in New-Haven, September 9th, 1772.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N09732</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N09732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 12384</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX7313</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">12384</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99024166</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 12384.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N09732)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 12384)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 12384)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Essay on education; delivered at the public commencement, at Yale-College, in New-Haven, September 9th, 1772.</title>
                  <author>Dwight, Timothy, 1752-1817.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p. ;  21 cm. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas and Samuel Green,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New-Haven: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCCLXXII. [1772]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Trumbull suggests Timothy Dwight as author.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Education.</term>
               <term>Baccalaureate addresses --  1772.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:012384_0000_0F894505A8A35DB8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:012384_0001_0F894505E7DE0A18"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY ON EDUCATION; DELIVERED AT THE PUBLIC COMMENCEMENT, At YALE-COLLEGE, in NEW-HAVEN, September 9th, 1772.</p>
            <p>NEW-HAVEN: PRINTED BY THOMAS AND SAMUEL GREEN, MDCCLXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="unknown:012384_0002_0F894506A8E14178"/>
            <head>An ESSAY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is an obſervation no leſs true than common, that the HUMAN MIND bears a ſtrong reſemblance to the wild and unmanured garden of nature, which (tho' amidſt an infinite profuſion of weeds and briers) by diligence and culture becomes fertile, fair and flouriſhing. Our minds being furniſhed with latent powers, it is the buſineſs of EDUCATION to unfold and bring them to light. EDUCATION is a kind of ſecond creation; it gives form and comelineſs to thoſe rude and unwrought materials, which, like the natural World, in its chaotic ſtate, are "without order and void." NATURE gives us talents; it is EDUCATION which applies them right or wrong; the firſt beſtows propenſities and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections which may be directed to good, either public or private; the latter improves or perverts them. The infant mind is pliant and ductile, like wax, you may mould it to any form; you may ſtamp a fair or deformed impreſſion upon it; error or knowledge, indolence or induſtry, virtue or vice.</p>
            <q>
               <l>"'Tis EDUCATION forms the youthful mind,</l>
               <l>Juſt as the twig is bent, the tree's inclin'd."</l>
            </q>
            <p>In youth the faculties are vigorous and alert, the concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on quick, and the memory retentive. We are endued with a general appetite for glory; EDUCATION determines it to this, or that particular object. Different virtues and vices are expoſed to view, to captivate the attentive ſpectator, without always diſplaying their different concomitants or effects. As youth is unbiaſſed by prejudice; ſo it is ſuſceptible of any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and withal credulous; curious, yet eaſily impoſed on.
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:012384_0003_0F894507682F2BA0"/>Poſſeſſed of an innate and almoſt inſuperable propenſity to imitation, we imbibe opinions, as eaſily as we do manners. To nothing ſhort of this can it be imputed, that many more are influenced by the idle reveries of the humorous, and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick notions of the capricious, than by the moſt excellent ſentiments of the wiſe and counſels of the worthy. We muſt diveſt things of their falſe garniſh, leſt emerging from the ſhade of obſurity, we be dazzled with artificial ſplendor and rendered incapable of ſeeing objects in their real forms.</p>
            <p>Allured by the deluſive charms of a tempting World, the YOUTH as he advances in years, makes excurſions, extends his acquaintance, and fixes upon ſome object as the darling or his purſuit. He proportions the worth of every thing around him, accordingly as it firſt ſtrikes his imagination. All the gaieties of the world aſſault him at once—Pleaſure allures him, riches ſollicit, and honours court him—If he withſtands the firſt attack, it is ten to one, but the ſecond proves too powerful; he ſoon forms different ideas of virtue and merit, yields him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a captive and becomes a ſlave. Has he been taught to deſpiſe Pleaſure, the grand Miſtreſs of the world? the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, thrilling ſenſation, ſtrengthened by natural fire, will ſoon enervate his reſolution and unſinew the moſt confirmed purpoſes of reaſon and philoſophy; unleſs CULTURE has diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed the deceitful charms. Has he heard avarice contemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the narrow views of ſelf-intereſt ridiculed? Has he been told that the fawning courtier of popular applauſe juſtly ſinks into contempt? Till EDUCATION has taught him the d'ſhonour and infamy to which they lead, he will be liable to fall into the ſame beaten track, and in the end fail of that praiſe, which is the fair attendant of virtue.</p>
            <p>Life is a maſquerade, where a fictitious character is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently aſſumed. Being fond of indolence, we content our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a ſuperficial ſurvey of men and things, without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them behind the ſcenes, as well as in the open theatre. The world is variegated with objects, which make a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> appearance without diſcovering their intrinſic worth; and theſe have a powerful influence to captivate the youthful ſpectator, whoſe education has been ill and partial; who has
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:012384_0003_0F894507682F2BA0"/>never been taught to look beyond the confines of his own narrow experience. EDUCATION draws the curtain which conceals their true character, gives us right ideas of honour and merit, and ſerves as a clue to direct us to right objects of choice.</p>
            <p>While the paſſions are opening, curioſity is awake, and the young mind is ready to take its ply from the ſeducements of faſhion and creditable examples. What makes the little MISS, ſo imperious and haughty; who ſwells with rage at every imaginary affront, and never thinks that She is treated with proper reſpect; what, but the early incenſe offered to her vanity? Why is almoſt every aſſembly crowded with flaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing COQUETS, but becauſe they have been accuſtomed from their cradles, to admire their own <hi>ſweet</hi> figure? No ſooner does ſhe perceive reſpect paid to dreſs, beauty and external mien; but ſhe uſes every little artifice to catch the attention of beholders. This done, ſhe grows important, in her own eyes, and imagines innumerable graces included in her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; while every little formality of the inſinuating GALLANT, contributes to the unguarded charmer's deluſion. Why does the <hi>Youth</hi> when freed from the reſtraints to which younger years are ſubject, prove a ſpend-thrift, an abandoned rake, but from the over-fondneſs of doating parents, and the bad company with which he is converſant? Why does the World ſwarm with ſhallow-pated BEAUS, but becauſe intrigue has been the height of their ambition, and to make good their point, they have referred to dreſs and conqueſt all their views and intentions? If we hold the airy <hi>Nothing</hi> up to view, we ſhall find all its qualifications, the moſt general concomitants of a narrow, contracted education. View the empty <hi>bubble:</hi> a fickle, capricious mind with little or no genius; proud and oſtentatious, yet for the moſt part of mean extraction; profuſe, yet not generous; having much raillery with little wit; falſely delicate; unacquainted with virtue and truth; well verſed in all the little arts of diſguiſe and diſſimulation; averſe to induſtry; fond of noiſe and confuſion; ſtrongly tinctured with pedantry; in low intrigues no novice: and I wiſh it were a <hi>rara avis,</hi> to whom this character might juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:012384_0004_0F89450826DDDC10"/>be applied. What forms the quack, the ſupple courtier and the ſham patriot; but that train of grovelling arts and low dealing, which hath led them the way to fraud and chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane? Whence ſuch a ſpawn of wild enthuſiaſts, of blind bigots, but from their narrow education? Why, in a word, are mankind ſo ignorant, and withal ſo conceited; ſo ill founded, yet ſo obſtinate, in their opinions; ſo prone to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and eaſe, and ſo impatient of induſtry and frugality; but becauſe they have been hoodwinked before they had time to open their eyes, and nouriſhed from their infancy in popular prepoſſeſſion, in vanity and indolence? Nor is this the only miſ-conduct we meet with, in an age where the views of edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation are directed more to manners than to morals; where prudence is but artifice; where graces caſt a ſpecious gloſs upon vice, and the paſſions are allowed to give colouring to the objects of purſuit.</p>
            <p>The grand affair of launching into the world, takes place in a period of life the moſt eventful that we ever experience. The wiſdom of the ſerpent is as neceſſary as the innocence of the dove; and unleſs our minds are rightly attempered with both, we ſhall ſplit upon the dangerous ſhoals before we ſpy them. It is a foible to which human nature is extremely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, to be content with preſent attainments, and guard the ſafe ſide, while the weak one is left to defend itſelf. An Education (which deſerves the <hi>name</hi>) inculcates maxims of honour and probity, inſpires the nobleſt ſentiments of moral duty, and impreſſes an equal deteſtation of all the vices of depraved humanity. A Youth elated with ſuch ſublime ideas, which his parents, his tutors, his books, or even his own ingenuous heart has rendered familiar to him, (little miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſting that vice can put on more than one garb) opens forth into the World; not <hi>that</hi> which he has ſo long dreamed of; but a World new, ſtrange and inconſiſtent with all his former expectations. The moſt faſhionable vices he beholds pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troniſed, proſperous and triumphant, virtue diſcountenanced, unſucceſsful and degraded.—He finds the edge of ridicule turned on ſome of thoſe qualities, he has hither to been moſt fond of.—If he quits the clamorous crowd, where impiety is
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:012384_0004_0F89450826DDDC10"/>made a point of honour, and profaneneſs eſteemed a good recommendation; he will ſoon unite himſelf to the more ſpecious and atractive party. At firſt, his ſimplicity in what they term <hi>Good breeding,</hi> makes him the dupe of this plauſible ſociety: but ſoon, their occaſional hints, their negligent ſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſms, their ſallies of wit and polite raillery, on what he has been accuſtomed to hold ſacred, debauch his mind, and create a fondneſs for thoſe ſcenes, which were once his greateſt aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The truth is, the Youth ſhould be fortified with a <hi>gradual</hi> intelligence of the World, that he may be prepared to ſee it without ſurpriſe, and live in it without danger. His firſt ſteps ſhould be ſhort and ſecure; his aſſociates few, and of the beſt. The veil muſt be taken off from ſome parts, and left ſtill upon others; while he has, painted out before him, what he does not ſee, and even more hinted at, than can be painted.</p>
            <p>If his mind is at firſt contracted within a narrow circle, this gradual acquaintance with the things around him, will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large his views, and teach him to regard himſelf as a CITIZEN OF THE WORLD, aſſert his native liberty, and deſpiſe a SLAVE of <hi>any</hi> ſect or party. This will learn him to act with cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in points where it is not impoſſible that he may be deceived; and on the other hand, it will as effectually guard him againſt every wrong bias, hung upon the mind by a favourite paſſion, or particular education.</p>
            <p>An opinionative zeal for our own tenets, is the grand inlet, the unguarded avenue of the mind, by which a thouſand er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors find admiſſion, unnoticed. We muſt ſearch the inmoſt receſſes of our thoughts, ſift our own ſentiments, and ſubject them to frequent reviews, that we may enable the mind to detect its own ſophiſms, and guard againſt the fallacies, upon which it practiſes. It is admirable to obſerve, how many artifices muſt be uſed, to procure admiſſion for the moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent truths, into minds, frightened by novelty, or rendered inſenſible by accidental prejudice. Nay, ſome are ſo very fond &amp; tenacious of their <hi>own unerring</hi> principles, that when one of their darling poſitions is attacked, they uſe no other wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:012384_0005_0F894508E7602F58"/>but ſtupidity, to elude the force of argument. To have the mind warmed with a love for truth, and willing to diveſt itſelf of all prepoſſeſſion and prejudice, it muſt be tempered with candour. This will prove no leſs an incentive to vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, than a barrier againſt vice. REASON, the ſupreme law of our nature, will then be the ſtandard by which we may correct our falſe notions of honour and pleaſure.—Vice will appear as it is; a violation of our nature, and a fall from its true dignity: virtue its higheſt ornament and perfection.</p>
            <p>Animated with ſuch principles, the youth will dare to take a higher aim in life, than the purſuits of the idle rabble; will reverence his nature, and be aſhamed of thoſe ſtains which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade it. He will keep his head and heart equally poiſed for action; enter the buſy ſcenes of life; ſuffer his paſſions to grow warm, without diſturbing the coolneſs of reaſon; while every grateful emotion which he feels, reſulting from a manly, generous conduct, fires him with a love for virtue and every noble principle.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
