<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter from an eminent minister of the Church of Scotland; written to a minister of his acquaintance, at some distance, in the same kingdom. Giving an account of his conversion and wonderful change in his preaching, after he had been of some years standing in the ministry. : [Three lines of Scripture texts]</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04">2009-04.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N10102</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N10102</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 12832</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW7281</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">12832</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99013435</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 12832.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N10102)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 12832)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 12832)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter from an eminent minister of the Church of Scotland; written to a minister of his acquaintance, at some distance, in the same kingdom. Giving an account of his conversion and wonderful change in his preaching, after he had been of some years standing in the ministry. : [Three lines of Scripture texts]</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p. ;  21 cm. (8vo and 4to) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by William McAlpine, about mid-way betwixt the governor's and Dr. Gardiner's, Marlborough-Street,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1773.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Two states noted, differing in type face and set-up of the title page. In one, the fifth line of the title ends with the word "of" and the sixth line ends with "in". In the other, the fifth line ends with "his", the sixth with "the".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conversion --  Christianity</term>
               <term>Preaching.</term>
               <term>Pastoral theology.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:012832_0000_0F8B404A2052AC68"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:012832_0001_0F8B404AF9A969E0"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM An Eminent Miniſter of the Church of SCOTLAND; written to a Miniſter of his Acquaintance, at ſome Diſtance, in the ſame KINGDOM.</p>
            <p>GIVING AN ACCOUNT Of his CONVERSION and WONDERFUL Change in his PREACHING, after he had been of ſome Years ſtanding in the Miniſtry.</p>
            <q>
               <p>—For if I yet pleaſed Men I ſhould not be the ſervant of Chriſt.</p>
               <bibl>Gal. i 10.</bibl>
               <p>Let every one of us pleaſe his neighbour for his good to edification.</p>
               <bibl>Rom iv. 2.</bibl>
               <p>—To have a conſcience void of offence towards God and towards men.</p>
               <bibl>Acts xxiv. 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>BOSTON: Printed and Sold by WILLIAM McALPINE, about Mid-way betwixt the <hi>Governor</hi>'s and Dr. <hi>Gardiner</hi>'s, Marlborough-<hi>Street,</hi> 1773.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="unknown:012832_0002_0F8B404BD2E2BF50"/>
            <head>A LETTER From an Eminent Miniſter in the Church of Scotland: written to a Miniſter of his Acquaintance at ſome diſtance in the ſame Kingdom.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY deſire and intenſion in this Letter is to inform you what the Lord has lately done for my ſoul: In order to this, it may be needful to give you a little previous information of my manner of life from my youth up, to the preſent time.</p>
            <p>When I was about the age of fourteen, God was pleaſed to ſhew me that I was a ſinner, and that I muſt be born again before I could enter into his kingdom. Accordingly, I betook myſelf to reading, praying and watching; and was enabled hereby to make ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in ſanctification. In this manner I went on, tho' not always with the ſame diligence till about half a year ago. I thought myſelf in the right way to heaven, though as yet I was wholly out of the way; and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined I was travelling towards Sion, though I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet ſet my face thitherwards. Indeed God would have ſhewn me that I was wrong, by not owning my miniſtry, but I had no regard to this for a long time, imputing my want of ſucceſs to the haughty hearts of my hearers, and not to my naughty doctrine.</p>
            <p>You may aſk, perhaps, What was my doctrine?
<pb n="2" facs="unknown:012832_0003_0F8B404C611A3A58"/>
Why, dear Sir, it was the doctrine that every man will naturally hold whilſt he continues in an unregenerate <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, viz. that we are to be juſtified partly by our faith, <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by our works. This doctrine I preached for eight years, and though I took ſome extraordinary pains, and <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſanctification upon the people very <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yet they continued as <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſanctified in their hearts, and unholy in their lives, as before. There was indeed a little more of the form of religion in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh but not a <hi>whit</hi> more of the <hi>power</hi> Juſt after I had preached eight years in this manner, I began to be diſcouraged; and now ſome ſecret miſgivings aroſe in my mind that I was not right myſelf. This happened about ſix months ago. Thoſe miſgivings grew ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and at laſt, very painful. Being then under great doubts, I cried unto the Lord very earneſtly. The conſtant language of my heart was this—"Lord, if I am right, keep me ſo; if I am not right make me ſo Lead me to the knowledge of the truth as it is in Jeſus."</p>
            <p>After about ten days crying unto the Lord, he was pleaſed to return an anſwer to my prayer, and in the following wonderful manner. As I was ſitting in my houſe one morning, and muſing upon a text of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the following words were darted into my mind with great power, and ſeemed, indeed, like a voice from heaven, (viz.) <hi>Ceaſe from thy own works,</hi> before I heard theſe words, my mind was in a very unuſual calm; but as ſoon as I heard them, my ſoul was in a tempeſt directly, and the tears flowed from my eyes like a torrent. The ſcales fell from the eyes of my underſtanding immediately, and I now clearly ſaw the rock I had been ſplitting on for near thirty years.</p>
            <p>Do you aſk what this rock was? Why, it was ſome
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:012832_0003_0F8B404C611A3A58"/>
ſecret reliance on my <hi>own works</hi> for ſalvation. I had hoped to be ſaved, partly in my <hi>own</hi> name, and partly in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s name; though I am told there is ſalvation in no other name except in the name of Jeſus Chriſt, Acts iv. 12. I had hoped to be ſaved partly through my own works, and partly through Chriſt's mercies; though I am told we are ſaved by grace through faith, and not of works, Eph. ii. 7, 8. I had hoped to make myſelf acceptable to God, partly <hi>through my own good works,</hi> though we are told that we are accepted thro' the beloved, Eph. i. 6. I had hoped to make my peace with God, partly through my own obedience to his laws, though I am told that <hi>peace</hi> is only to be had by faith, Rom. v.i. I had hoped to make myſelf a child of God by [legal] ſanctification, though we are told, that we are made children of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus, Gal. iii. 26. I had thought that Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the new Birth, or the new Creature conſiſted in this legal ſanctification, but now I know it conſiſts in faith, 1 John v. 1.—Compare alſo theſe two paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages together, Gal. vi. 15.—and Gal. vi. 5.—where you will find that the new creature is <hi>faith working by love</hi>; the apoſtle adds theſe words, <hi>working by love</hi>; in order to diſtinguiſh a <hi>living</hi> faith from a <hi>dead</hi> one. I had thought that ſanctification was the way to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, but now I am aſſured that ſanctification fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows after juſtification; or in other words, that we muſt firſt be juſtified by faith before we can have any true ſanctification by the Spirit. When we are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied it is done <hi>freely,</hi> that is, graciouſly without any the leaſt merits of ours, and ſolely by the grace of God through Jeſus Chriſt, Rom. iii. 24—28.</p>
            <p>All that is previouſly needful to juſtification, is this, that we are convinced by the Spirit of God of our own
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:012832_0004_0F8B404D8D24D670"/>
utter ſinfulneſs, Iſa. lxiv. 6.—Convinced that we are the children of wrath by nature, on account of our Birth-ſin, Eph. ii. 3.—And that we are under the curſe of God on account of actual ſin, Gal. iii. 10.—And under theſe convictions come to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, renouncing all righteouſneſs of our own, and relying ſolely on him, who is appointed to be "the Lord our righteouſneſs," Jer. xxiii. 6. Again, Chriſt ſays, "Come unto me all ye that labour and are heavy laden, (with the burden of ſin) and I will give you reſt," i. e. I will take the burden away, I will releaſe you from the guilt of ſin. Where you may obſerve, that the only thing required of us when we come to Chriſt, is to come burdened and ſenſible that none can remove this burden but Chriſt. Again, Chriſt did not come to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance. See alſo Luke iv. 1<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Hear how he cries out in Iſa. lv. 1. "Ho e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that thirſteth, come ye to the waters and drink, come buy wine and milk (i. e.) the bleſſings of the Goſpel) without money and without price." Where we are ordered to bring no money, i. e. no merits of our own, we muſt not think to make a purchaſe of theſe bleſſings by any deſerts of ours. They are offered freely, i. e. graciouſly, and muſt be received freely. Nothing more is required of us than to thirſt after them. Why was the Phariſee rejected? [Luke xviii. 10.] Becauſe he came pleading his own works before God He was devout, juſt, chaſte and abſtemious; and thanked God for enabling him to be ſo. Very well; ſo far all was right. But then he had ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance on theſe works, and therefore pleads the merits of them before God; which ſhewed that he did not know what a ſinner he was, and that he could only be ſaved by grace through faith. He opens his mouth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:012832_0004_0F8B404D8D24D670"/>
God, and pleads his own cauſe; though God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares that every mouth ſhall be ſtopped before him, and the whole world brought in guilty before God, Rom. iii. 19. And why was the Publican juſtified? Not on account of his own good works, but becauſe he was ſenſible of his evil ones; and accordingly came ſelf-accuſed, ſelf-condemned, and crying out for mercy.</p>
            <p>And now dear Sir, hear what is the riſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of true religion in the ſoul of man. When the Spirit of God has convinced any perſon that he is a child of wrath, and under the curſe of God, [in which ſtate every one continues to be, till he has received Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt into his heart by faith,] then the heart of ſuch a one becomes broken for ſin; then, too, he feels what he never knew before, that he has no faith: and accordingly laments his evil heart of unbelief. In this ſtate men continue ſome a longer, ſome a leſs time, till God is pleaſed to work faith in them. Then they are juſtified, and are at peace with God, Rom. v. 1. i. e. have their ſins forgiven them, for that is the meaning of the word, <hi>peace.</hi> See Luke vii. 48,—50. —When we have received faith from God, [for it is his gift, Eph. ii. 8.] to juſtify our perſons, then we afterwards receive the Spirit to ſanctify our natures, Eph i 13.—Gal. iii. 14. And now the work of [goſpel] ſanctification goes forwards; now his fruit is more and more unto holineſs; now the love of God is ſhed abroad in his heart by the holy Spirit, Rom. v. 5. Now he walks in the comforts of the holy Ghoſt, Acts ix. 13. Now he is filled with joy and peace in believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Rom. xv. 13. Now he rejoices with joy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable and full of glory, 1 Pet. i. 8. And now he has the Spirit of God bearing witneſs with his own ſpirit, that he is a child of God, Rom. viii. 16. 1 John
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:012832_0005_0F8B404DE3A726C8"/>
v. 10.—Theſe are things which I was an utter ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to before, notwithſtanding all my reading, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and praying; and theſe are things that every one muſt be a ſtranger to, till he is made a child of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>But to proceed; though a believer is continually more and more ſanctified, "in body, ſoul and ſpirit," yet his hopes of heaven are not built on his ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but on Chriſt; he knows he is only complete in Chriſt, Col. ii. 10. And that the moment he ſeeks to be juſtified by his own obedience to God's law, that moment he falls from Chriſt and ceaſes to have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in him, Gal. v. 4. Accordingly, though he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to abound in all the fruits of righteouſneſs, yet, like St. Paul, he deſires to be found only in Chriſt, not having [i. e. not relying on] his own righteouſneſs, but on the righteouſneſs of God by faith, Phil. iii. 8, 9.</p>
            <p>And now let me point out to you the grand deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which had like to have ruined my ſoul. I ſaw ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry early ſomething of the unbelief of my nature, and the neceſſity of being born again. Accordingly I watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, prayed and faſted too, thinking to purity my heart by theſe means, whereas it can only be purifyed by faith, Acts xv 9. Watching, praying and faſting are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary duties, but I, like many others, placed ſome ſecret reliances on them, thinking they were to do that for me, in part at leaſt, which Chriſt only could. The truth is, though I ſaw myſelf to be a ſinner, and a great ſinner, yet I did not ſee myſelf an utter loſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and therefore I could not come to Jeſus Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to ſave me; deſpiſed the doctrine of juſtification by faith alone, looking on it as a fooliſh and a danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous doctrine; I was not yet ſtript of all my righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, could not conſider it as "filthy rags," and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:012832_0005_0F8B404DE3A726C8"/>
I went about to eſtabliſh a righteouſneſs of my own; and did not ſubmit to the righteouſneſs of God by faith, Rom. x. 3 —I did not ſeek after righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs through faith, but, as it were, by the works of the law. Thus I ſtumbled and fell, Rom. ix. 31, 32. In ſhort, to uſe a homely ſimilitude, I put the juſtice of God in one ſcale, and as many good works of my own as I could in the other, and when I found, as I always did, my own good works not to be a ballance to the divine juſtice, I then threw in Chriſt as a make-weight. And this every one really does, who hopes for ſalvation partly by doing what he can for himſelf, and then relying on Chriſt for the reſt.</p>
            <p>But, dear Sir, Chriſt will be either a whole Saviour, or none at all. And if you think you have any good ſervice of your own to recommend you unto God, you are certainly without any intereſt in Chriſt. Be you ever ſo ſober, ſerious, juſt and devout; you are ſtill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the curſe of God as I was, and know it not, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided you have any allowed reliance on your own works, and think they are to do ſomething for you, and Chriſt to do the reſt.</p>
            <p>I now proceed to acquaint you with the ſucceſs I have lately had in my miniſtry. As ſoon as God had opened my eyes, and ſhewed me the true way to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, I began immediately to preach it And now I dealt with my hearers in a very different manner from what I uſed to do. I told them very plainly, that they were children of wrath and under the curſe of God, though they knew it not, and that none but Jeſus Chriſt could deliver them from that Curſe. I aſked them if they had ever broke the law of God once, in thought, word or deed? If they had, they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the curſe: For it is written, "Curſed is every one
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:012832_0006_0F8B404F740667B8"/>
that continueth not in all the things that are written in the book of the law to do them." And again, "he that keepeth the whole law, and yet offendeth in one point, is guilty of all." If, indeed, we could keep the whole law, without offending in one point; if we had done, and could continue to do all things in God's law, then we might lay claim to eternal life on the ſcore of our own works. "But who is ſufficient for theſe things?" If we break God's law, we immediately fall under the curſe of it, and none can deliver us from this curſe but Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. There is an end for ever after, of any juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification from our own works. No future good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour can make any atonement for paſt miſcarriages. If I keep all God's law to day, this is no amends for breaking them yeſterday. If therefore I am once un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the curſe of God, for having broken God's law, I can never after do any thing of myſelf to deliver me from this curſe. I may then <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, "O! wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from this body of ſin?" And find none able to deliver, but Jeſus Chriſt, Rom. vii. 24, 25. So that if I am once a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, nothing but the blood of Jeſus Chriſt can cleanſe me from ſin. All my hopes are then in him, and I muſt fly to him as the only "refuge ſet before me."</p>
            <p>In this manner, dear Sir, I preached, and do preach to my people, labouring to bring them off from ſelf-righteouſneſs to a dependance on Chriſt's righteouſneſs only for juſtification, in the ſight of God: labouring to ſhew them that they were all in a loſt and periſhing ſtate, and that nothing could recover them out of this ſtate, and make them children of God, but faith in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And now ſee the conſequence. This was ſtrange doctrine to my hearers. They were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, all armed and vexed. The old man, the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:012832_0006_0F8B404F740667B8"/>
nature was ſtirred up, and railed and oppoſed the truth. However, the minds of moſt were ſeized with ſome convictions, and the hearts of ſome were truly broken for ſin, ſo that they came to me, as thoſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Acts, 'pricked to the heart,' and crying out, "What muſt I do to be ſaved?" I then laid the promiſes before them, and told them, if they found themſelves under the curſe, Chriſt was ready to deliver them from it; if they were really weary and heavy laden, Chriſt would give them reſt; if their hearts were broken for their ſins, and they would look up unto Chriſt he would heal them. I exhorted them alſo to thank God for theſe convictions, aſſuring them it was a token of good to their ſouls. For God muſt firſt ſmite the heart before he can heal it, Iſa. xix. 22. I generally found that they received comfort from the promiſes of God in his word; and though they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained much of the burden of ſin, and of an evil heart of unbelief, yet they always went away refreſhed and comforted. The good fruits begin now to appear, not a few rejoice in Chriſt and love him; they love his word, and meditate in it; they exerciſe themſelves in prayer, and adorn their profeſſion by a ſuitable life and converſation.</p>
            <p>And now let me make one reflection. I preached up ſanctification very earneſtly as (as above mentioned) for eight years, and never brought one ſoul to Chriſt, never had ſucceſs at all; but as ſoon as ever I preached Jeſus Chriſt, and faith in his blood, then conviction of ſin took place in the hearers hearts, yea, and believers were, every now and then, added to the church And now let me aſk, what is the reaſon why my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry was not bleſſed, when I preached up ſalvation partly by faith, and partly by works? It is becauſe
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:012832_0007_0F8B4051775AAB68"/>
this doctrine is not of God; and he will proſper not miniſters but ſuch as preach ſalvation in his own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed way, [viz] by faith in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Let me now apply myſelf to your own heart, and may God diſpoſe you to receive my words in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of meekneſs. Indeed, Sir, I love and reſpect you, elſe I could not have wrote to you ſo freely. Are you then in the ſame error that I was in for near forty years, [viz] that you muſt be ſaved partly by faith, and partly by works? And have you conſtantly preached this doctrine? Then you may be certainly aſſured of theſe two things; firſt, that you never yet brought one ſoul to Chriſt, by your miniſtry. And ſecondly, that you are not yet in the way of ſalvation yourſelf. Oh! be not diſpleaſed with me for telling you the truth.—But you will ſay perhaps, that you have not only been ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, but ever zealous in preaching the word of God. So was I; but there is a zeal which is not according to knowledge, and that zeal I had, though I knew it not. You may ſay farther, that you have read and prayed much, ſo have I, but ſtill 'I knew nothing as I ought to know,' till God was pleaſed to ſhew me that I was blind, and then I cried heartily to him for light and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and he opened mine eyes, John ix. 39.</p>
            <p>Dear Sir, will you attend to the following advice? it is very ſafe advice, be the ſtate of your ſoul what it will. Pray to God to lead you into the knowledge of the truth as it is in Jeſus. Beſeech God to keep you in the truth, if you have received it; or if you are in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, to reveal it unto you If you will do this heartily and conſtantly, God will not ſuffer you to abide in darkneſs, if, indeed, you are in darkneſs, Jam i. 5.</p>
            <p>I now proceed to give you ſome account of myſelf, and of the impediments which kept me from the truth.
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:012832_0007_0F8B4051775AAB68"/>
When I firſt went to the College, I applied myſelf di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to my ſtudies, thinking human learning to be the chief, if not the only neceſſary qualification for a divine. Accordingly I ſtudied the Claſſics, Mathematicks, Ethics, Logics, Metaphyſics, and read the works of our moſt eminent Divines; and this I did for twenty years; and all the while was departing more and more from 'the truth as it is in Jeſus;' vainly hoping to receive light and inſtruction from human wiſdom, which could on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be had from the word and Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>During this time, I was thought one of the true mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt by ſome people, only becauſe I was a little more grave, and took a little more pains in my miniſtry than ſome others of my brethren; but, in truth, I was not, I was an utter ſtranger to the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of their maſter, which they preached as well as to Chriſt himſelf in my heart and could not abide the doctrine of juſtification by faith, in particular. But when God was pleaſed to open mine eyes about half a year ago, he ſhewed and taught me other things. Now I ſaw that nothing had kept me ſo much from the truth, as a deſire of human wiſdom. Now I perceived that it was as difficult for a wiſe or learned man to be ſaved, as it was for a rich man; or nobleman: 1 Cor. i. 26. Now I ſaw that God even ſtill choſe the fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh things of this world to confound the wiſe, and the weak things to confound the mighty, for two plain reaſons, 1ſt, that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence, ver. 29. and 2d. to ſhew that faith did not ſtand in or was not produced by the wiſdom of man, but by the power of God, 1 Cor. ii. 5. Now I diſcerned, that no one could underſtand the word of God, but by the Spirit of God, 1 Cor. ii. 12. Now I ſaw that every be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever in Chriſt was anointed by the holy Spirit of God,
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:012832_0008_0F8B40521ED3B558"/>
and thereby led to the knowledge of all needful truths, 1 John ii. 20. Now I ſaw that Juſtification by faith alone was a fundamental doctrine of chriſtianity; and did no longer wonder at the want of ſucceſs in thoſe miniſters who did not preach this in particular, and the other fundamental doctrines of goſpel. They preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not Chriſt's doctrine, and Chriſt owned it not. I once neither believed nor preached Juſtification by faith only, yea, what was more dreadful, I was undermining this fundamental doctrine, and yet dreadful as this is, I fear it is the caſe of too many of the clergy in this kingdom. Scarce any thing is preached but juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by faith and works, at beſt. And what is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence? Why there is ſcarce any true religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, the goſpel of Chriſt is not truly preached by us, and Chriſt will not own our miniſtry. Look around the Pariſhes which are near you, and ſee whether you can find any thing beſides the form of religion, and not much of that. Nay, amongſt thoſe who are thought religious people; who are ſober, ſerious, juſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout; who read and pray, and give alms, and even faſt; amongſt theſe you will ſcarce find one who knows any thing of the power of religion, and has experimental knowledge of it. For if you aſk ſuch people in the very words of ſcripture, "whether they know that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is in them, otherwiſe they are reprobates," 2 Cor. xiii. 5. Whether Chriſt dwells in their hearts by faith, Eph. iii. 17. Whether their ſins are forgiven for Chriſt's ſake, John ii. 12. Whether they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived an unction from the holy One, 1 John ii. 20. Whether the love of God has been ſhed abroad in their hearts by the holy Ghoſt, Rom. v. <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Whether they are filled with joy and peace in believing, Rom. xv. 13. Whether they walk in the comfort of the holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:012832_0008_0F8B40521ED3B558"/>
and do ever rejoice with joy unſpeakable and full of glory, Acts ix. 31. 1 Pet. i. 8. And laſtly, whether the Holy Spirit bears witneſs with their own ſpirit that they are the children of God, Rom. viii. <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4. &amp;c. If, I ſay, you aſk the better ſort among us, whether they have any experience of theſe matters. they would ſtare at you with the utmoſt amazement, and would think you an Enthuſiaſt, if they did not call you ſo. Or, at moſt, they would have expected to be enquired at ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about the orthodoxy of the head, than about theſe experiences which reſide in the heart alone, as being fuller of that than the other. Now ſuch people who are only orthodox, and ſuch who have all the form, but none of the power of religion, who are outwardly reformed but not inwardly renewed by the Holy Ghoſt. Theſe laſt are what our Saviour calls "whited ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres," beautiful without, but full of rottenneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; theſe are "ſtriving to enter into the kingdom of heaven, but are not able," becauſe they do not "ſtrive lawfully:" for they do not ſeek to enter in through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, but partly through Chriſt, and partly thro' themſelves, partly by faith, and partly (if not wholly) by works, and they firſt make a Chriſt of their ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxy, make it to be 'all in all,' to ſupply the place of heart-Religion and holineſs of life. And even when theſe two<note n="*" place="bottom">Orthodoxy and outſide Religion.</note> are found joined in any, it makes them but almoſt chriſtians. And if at any time it happens, that ſome are ſeized with deep convictions, and are made ſenſible of their utter need of Chriſt, and that they can only be juſtified by faith in his blood; theſe not find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proper food for their ſouls from one miniſter, are obliged with thoſe people who have from time to time been brought into the ſame ſtate of ſoul, to go and hear another that preaches the true goſpel, where they can
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:012832_0009_0F8B405261206090"/>
find him. This is often the caſe, ſo ſcarce are goſpel miniſters nowadays. It is no wonder therefore that there are ſo few real chriſtians. If you read the fathers of the church, if you read the works of our good old reformers, and works that were publiſhed a hundred years ago, you will there find the goſpel of Chriſt preached, and the true doctrines of Proteſtants. But ſince that time, I mean in the laſt Century, the clergy, eſpecially of the church of England, have been gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally departing more and more from this goſpel and thoſe doctrines; ſo that at length there were few clergymen to be found in England but who preached contrary to them. And almoſt all the ſermons that have been publiſhed in the laſt century,<note n="*" place="bottom">Meaning the ſame as referred to in the laſt note.</note> are full of that ſoul-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying doctrine, that we are to be juſtified either partly by our own works, and partly by Chriſt's merits, or by the former only.</p>
            <p>Do you aſk how the clergy came to fall into this pernicious doctrine? I anſwer very eaſily. Every man, whilſt he continues under the power of the carnal mind and is not awakened to ſee his utter loſt condition, is naturally diſpoſed to embrace this doctrine. For not being yet convinced by the Spirit of God, that all his righteouſneſs is as filthy rags, Iſa. lxiv. 6. And that he is without help and ſtrength in himſelf, Rom. v. 6. I ſay, not being convinced of this, he naturally goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to eſtabliſh ſome righteouſneſs of his own, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubmit to the righteouſneſs of God by faith. Not being yet ſenſible of his utter loſt and helpleſs ſtate, he muſt have ſome reliance on himſelf. And thus inſtead of looking wholly to Jeſus Chriſt for ſalvation, he looks partly to Chriſt and partly to himſelf: inſtead of ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for righteouſneſs and ſtrength from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, he ſeeks for it partly from Chriſt and partly
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:012832_0009_0F8B405261206090"/>
from himſelf: inſtead of ſeeking to be juſtified in the Lord, he ſeeks after juſtification partly thro' the Lord, and partly through himſelf. But ſee what Chriſt ſaith of this matter, Iſa. xlv. 23, 23, 24, 25, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And now let me aſk, how the whole church of Rome happened to depart from the ſimplicity of the goſpel, and to fall into this doctrine of works, which we [the clergy of the church of England and Scotland] now preach. It was owing to the depraved nature of man, which makes him think himſelf to be ſomething and can do ſomething, though he is nothing and can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to juſtify himſelf in God's ſight. At the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation thoſe churches returned again to Jeſus Chriſt, and pleaded juſtification on the goſpel-footing of faith only. And ſo it continues: but though their Articles [and our confeſſion of Faith] continue ſound and evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical in this doctrie, [and are in every other doctrine, at leaſt, that is eſſential to ſalvation, agreeable to the word of God;] yet their and our clergy have departed once more from them, and are advancing to Rome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in this particular, with haſty ſtrides; preaching in ſpite of Articles or Confeſſions and ſubſcriptions, that moſt pernicious, Papiſtical, and damnable doctrine of Juſtification by faith and works. Which doctrine, I am verily aſſured no one can hold, and be in a ſtate of ſalvation. Oh, that God would once more viſit in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy theſe poor diſtreſſed Churches!</p>
            <p>When I ſat down to write, I did not intend to have filled more than half a ſheet, but when I took my Pen in hand, I knew not how to lay it aſide, I have wrote my ſentiments with great freedom, and I hope without offence.</p>
            <p>May God give a bleſſing to what I have wrote. May he enlighten your eyes, as he has done mine; adored
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:012832_0010_0F8B40531EF76610"/>
be his mercy: may he lead you by his Spirit to "the knowledge of the truth as it is in Jeſus;" and make you inſtrumental in bringing ſouls "from darkneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to light," and "tranſlating them out of the kingdom of Satan, into the glorious kingdom of his dear Son." AMEN.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
