<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The watchman's alarm to Lord N---H; or, The British Parliamentary Boston port-bill unwraped [sic]. Being an oration on the meridian of liberty; not to inflame but to cheer the mind: or as an apple of gold in the pictures of silver for the mourning captives in America. : With some observations on the liberties of the Africans. / By the British Bostonian. ; [Sixteen lines of quotations]</title>
            <author>Allen, John, fl. 1741-1774.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N10865</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N10865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 13757</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APV5850</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">13757</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99001282</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 13757.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N10865)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 13757)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 13757)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The watchman's alarm to Lord N---H; or, The British Parliamentary Boston port-bill unwraped [sic]. Being an oration on the meridian of liberty; not to inflame but to cheer the mind: or as an apple of gold in the pictures of silver for the mourning captives in America. : With some observations on the liberties of the Africans. / By the British Bostonian. ; [Sixteen lines of quotations]</title>
                  <author>Allen, John, fl. 1741-1774.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p., [1] leaf of plates : ill. ; (4to) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Russell, in Rucks-Street, (over Mr. J. Badger's auction and broker's-store) near the State-House, leading to Marblehead.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Salem [Mass.]: N.E. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M,DCC,LXXIV. [1774]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Allen by Adams.</note>
                  <note>The frontispiece, a cartoon, is entitled: The able doctor, or America swallowing the bitter draught.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Boston Port Bill, 1774.</term>
               <term>Slavery --  United States.</term>
               <term>Liberty.</term>
               <term>United States --  History --  Revolution, 1775-1783 --  Causes.</term>
               <term>United States --  History --  Revolution, 1775-1783 --  Addresses, sermons, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="unknown:013757_0000_0F91EBEF0D4B9080"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:013757_0001_0F91EBEFCCD2DA28"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> America Swallowing the Bitter Draught.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:013757_0002_0F91EBF08E6CBFC0"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE WATCHMAN'<hi rend="sup">s</hi> ALARM TO LORD <hi>N—H</hi>; OR, THE <hi>Britiſh</hi> Parliamentary <hi>Boſton</hi> Port-Bill unwraped BEING AN ORATION ON THE MERIDIAN OF LIBERTY; Not to inflame but to cheer the Mind: Or as an APPLE of GOLD in the PICTURES of SILVER for the mourning CAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIVES in AMERICA. With ſome OBSERVATIONS on the LIBERTIES of the AFRICANS.</p>
            <p>By the BRITISH BOSTONIAN.</p>
            <q>
               <p>And he ſaid unto me, Watchman what ſeeſt thou? And I ſaid, I ſee a flying Roll, and the Length is Twenty Cubits, and the Breadth is Ten Cubits, and in it was written, <hi>MOURNING, LAMENTATION,</hi> and <hi>WOE.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EZEKIEL.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And he ſaid unto me, this is the curſe that goeth forth upon the Face of the Earth.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ZECHARIAH.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And it came to paſs when <hi>Jehudi</hi> had read Three or Four Leaves, he cut it with a Penknife and burnt it in the Fire that was on the Hearth until it was all conſumed.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JEREMIAH.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>O Liberty! O Virtue! O my Country!</l>
               <l>It is a noble Act to ſtem Taxation's Rage.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>CATO.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>As it is required of Watchmen to be open, free, and faithful to every Enquiry made, it is therefore hoped that no one will be angry at the free Anſwers returned by the Watchman in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to the Enquiries made. Watchman what of the Night, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The whole being intended as a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſerious, ſuitable, and cheerful Satyr.</p>
            <p>SALEM: N. E. Printed by E. RUSSELL, in Rucks-ſtreet, (over Mr. J. BADGER's Auction and Broker's-Store) near the State-houſe, leading to <hi>Marblehead.</hi> M,DCC,LXXIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="explanation_of_plate">
            <pb facs="unknown:013757_0003_0F91EBF14D757EE0"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN EXPLANATION Of the Plate in the Firſt Page.</head>
            <p n="1">I. AMERICA, as a woman cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a mourning Mantle.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Lord N—H with the <hi>Boſton</hi> Port-Bill ſeen from his pocket, forcing the taxed tea down the throat of <hi>America,</hi> which ſhe furiouſly pukes up again in his face.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Britannia</hi> in a diſconſolate Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with prayers and tears, mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the diſtreſſes of her daughter <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. S—r. G—l <hi>W—n,</hi> that falſe, ficle, defaming, treacherous
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:013757_0004_0F91EBF2155C1038"/>
court ſycophant, binding <hi>America</hi> with the iron hand of tyranny.</p>
            <p n="5">V. A late <hi>America</hi> Repreſentative holding the feet of <hi>America</hi> that ſhe might not kick againſt the iron power of the preſent A—n.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Lord B— in an Highland dreſs, with fury in his eyes, and a broad ſword in his hand, on which is wrote his heart, and what he would wiſh to enforce— military law.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. and VIII. The <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſadors, pointing to Lord N—H with his Port-Bill, and ſmiling at the mad conduct of the <hi>B.....h</hi> A............n in forcing Taxes from the <hi>Americans</hi> without their conſent.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. <hi>Boſton</hi> cannonaded.</p>
            <p n="10">X. <hi>Boſton</hi> petition under feet.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="oration">
            <pb facs="unknown:013757_0005_0F91EBF2DF1B45A8"/>
            <head>THE WATCHMAN'<hi rend="sup">s</hi> ALARM, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Men, Brethren, and Fathers, and ye that fear <hi>GOD,</hi> give audience.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE peculiar ſolemnities of this day are more immediately adapted, by the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic conſent of the churches, to paint forth the life and MEREDIAN of LIBERTY. The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs you are in, and the danger there is of your loſing your rights, call aloud to ſupplicate the throne of GOD for deliverance; to pray for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration of your juſt rights, and a final ſettlement of the ſure enjoyment of them.</p>
            <p>By liberty, is meant political liberty; and, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the true etimology of the word, in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>'s dictionary, it is a power of acting agreable <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the laws which are made and enacted by <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conſent of the PEOPLE, and no ways incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the natural rights of a ſingle perſon, or the good of ſociety. This is the liberty which is oppoſed to ſlavery.</p>
            <p>Liberty of the mind is the free thought that expands, ruminates from ſea to ſea, and from ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to the end of the earth, and none can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul it. The chariot of a thought, of a wiſh, of a deſire, is like the wings of the morning, which flies to the <hi>uttemoſt parts of the earth</hi>; and is like the ſun which rejoices to run its race; it is like the fountains which riſe ſpontaneouſly free; it is like the emitting life of the vine to all its bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; like the flowing rivers, the fertile fields in their pleaſant growth, or like the gentle zephyrs which diffuſes its fragrant life through the globe.
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:013757_0006_0F91EBF3987BB728"/>
This is freedom which is above the controul of man, or beyond the ſuppreſſion of any parliament or miniſterial tyrant. This is that kingdom of liberty which no man can deſtroy, and therefore not the liberty we are this day to treat of and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnize. That which calls upon every heart and commands every ſoul, is that of a civil and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred nature, which is ſo much in danger.</p>
            <p>Civil liberty is the people's inherent right to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy; namely, all the privileges of their laws ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their compact with their King; this right is ever inherent in the people, and cannot be given to kings, nor taken away by any parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whatſoever; the enjoyment may, but the right cannot; its creation is natural and riſes with every generation. This is the power of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which <hi>binds kings in fetters and nobles in irons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sacred liberty is a ſatisfaction of ſoul in the choice of worſhip and adoration of GOD: This is JEHOVAH's law for the ſouls of men, and <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but devils and prieſtly tyrants have ever <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to invade this right.</p>
            <p>But as your civil rights are deſtroyed, your ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol town beſieged, your harbor blockaded, your port ſhut, trade, which is the ſinews of life and liberty is ſtopped by power and force of arms, what have we not to fear reſpecting our divine liberty? This makes it a night of diſtreſs and ſorrow, of great darkneſs and many fears: This makes me mourn for the affliction of <hi>Joſeph</hi>; to mourn with them that mourn, to hang my harp with the reſt of the captives and weep; yet not as thoſe who are without hope, <hi>for he that hath delivered doth deliver, in whom we truſt he will yet deliver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this night of ſorrow naturally leads me to
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:013757_0007_0F91EBF4699CDCD0"/>
the words of the Prophet, for the preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Watchman what of the night? Watchman what of the night?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What indeed! a very proper, a very important queſtion at this time. The moſt remarkable tranſactions of the GOD of heaven for the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of his people are made manifeſt as a key to unlock, or as a door to open the divine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns by interrogations. Thus when man had ſinned and marred the beauty of his creation; when that light, life, love, adoration, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of his GOD had forſaken his ſoul, the GOD of heaven ſaid unto him, Adam, <hi>Where art thou?</hi> Thus when a cloud of ſorrows covered the camp of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and GOD ſeemed to forſake his people, <hi>Joſhua,</hi> whoſe name denotes the LORD's ſalvation, ſaid, <hi>If</hi> Iſrael <hi>turn their backs upon their enemies, what wilt thou do unto thy great name?</hi> Thus <hi>Elihu,</hi> when he taught <hi>Job</hi> the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of his heart and nature, and how unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming it was in him in calling himſelf righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and juſtifying himſelf under his affliction before GOD, ſeeing his heart was corrupt, that it was not his thoughts, words, or actions that could acquit him before GOD, and therefore he ſays, <hi>How ſhall a man be juſt with</hi> GOD? How indeed! But this queſtion I leave for the Prieſts to anſwer, who are very buſy about it, but in general know nothing of the matter.</p>
            <p>Another ſolemn queſtion we have, which is, Who ſhall go to heaven? I hope you would be glad to know this, my hearers; you will find it, Pſ. xxix.3. <hi>Who ſhall aſcend unto the hill of the</hi> LORD? <hi>and who ſhall ſtand in his holy place? He that hath clean hand and a pure heart.</hi> Is it him?
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:013757_0008_0F91EBF529D60D70"/>
Then it is plain, my friends, that it is not you nor me, for our hearts are <hi>impure.</hi> Who can it be? A very proper queſtion. Were they the Prophets and Patriarchs? No! no! for they were like you and me, they had often unclean hands, and always a corrupt heart. Who can it be? That is the point. Are they our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, then? O no, my friends, no, no, that is a ſettled point; certain, both in heaven and in earth, for the ſcripture ſays, <hi>We have all ſinned, and are verily men, ſubject to like paſſions,</hi> and therefore not pure in heart. Who can they be? I think I will leave it for the Prieſts to tell you, whom I believe, if <hi>Paul</hi> was alive, would ſoon tell them they know but very little of this matter; this I know they will not let me go, becauſe, they ſay, I have eat with unwaſhen hands: What then? Have not they or have not I waſhed them ſince? Will not that do? If it will I think I have as good a right to go to heaven as they have. May not one crowd in with them? No, no, they will not give you elbow room. Well, they need not be afraid, for I will not go with them, nor truſt my ſoul among them. You may, if you pleaſe, brethren, for I have no dominion over your faith, but would fain be a helper of your joy.</p>
            <p>Again, when ſin and ſatan, when death and hell had invaded the rights of the whole creation and made it groan; when ſinners were to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, GOD glorified, ſalvation finiſhed, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs revealed, life, liberty, and glory to be made manifeſt to the ſons of men; an inquiry, according to ſcripture ideas, ſeems to ariſe from the ſacred throne, <hi>Who is this that engageth his heart to approach unto me, ſaith the</hi> LORD? Who, indeed? The anſwer you have from CHRIST's
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:013757_0009_0F91EBF5E2A621E8"/>
own own lips, Iſa. lxiii.5. <hi>And I looked and there was none to help, and I wondered that there was none to uphold; therefore mine own arm brought ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Once more, when the church ſaw, prophetically ſaw, the great work finiſhed, namely, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhining like the light of the morning, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation ſealed as the finiſhed work of the GOD of heaven, ſin ſuffered for, the law fulfilled, GOD glorified, death, hell, and the grave triumphed over. She ſays, <hi>Who is this?</hi> Who is this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that has done all this? Few know among the Prieſts, and fewer deſire to know among the people: But it is <hi>I,</hi> ſaith the Redeemer, <hi>that ſpeak in righteouſneſs, mighty to ſave.</hi> This ſhews what divine deſigns and grand diſplays of mercy are made manifeſt by ſcripture interrogations.</p>
            <p>Which leads me to the contemplation words, or firſt inquiry,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Watchman what of the night? Watchman what of the night?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will tell you as well as I can, but be patient, for I am not eloquent, and my talent is ſmall, and I am but a poor man and little eſteemed in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> I have read of a poor wiſe man who by his wiſdom delivered the city, yet no man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membered the ſame poor man: But never you mind that, for there is nothing new under the ſun.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What of the night?</hi> you aſk. I will tell you, it is a <hi>very good night</hi>; I mean for honeſt men to be out in, the ſtars are clear, the ſky is ſerene, the wind is calm: It is to be ſure a <hi>bad night</hi> for thieves and robbers, who intend to catch our perſons, ſteal our properties, and rob us of our rights, it is a very bad night for them. The ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſays, <hi>If a thief comes, he comes in the night</hi>;
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:013757_0010_0F91EBF691EF6A58"/>
but he loves a dark night. But be not afraid, for the <hi>morning cometh</hi>; remember from a <hi>night</hi> aroſe all the bleſſings of creation, the beauties of paradiſe, and all the happineſs of the life that now is, and the hope of that which is to come. As it is written, <hi>And darkneſs covered the face of the deep, and he ſaid let there be light, and there was light</hi>; therefore fear not the night, <hi>though weeping may endure for a night, yet joy cometh in the morning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet ſometimes by <hi>night</hi> I own we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>deep troubles,</hi> national diſtreſs, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal ſorrows, as was the caſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> of <hi>Job,</hi> of the prophets, and the nations of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and of <hi>Judah</hi>; and it is worthy our attention for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; did I ſay, nay but for eternity, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ponderous ſorrows of CHRIST's ſoul, when he poured out his ſoul to death, when he made his ſoul an offering for ſin, when his ſoul was troubled, when being in an agony, and his ſweat was as the drops of blood, when his ſoul <hi>was ſore amazed,</hi> when dying the juſt for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, to bring us nigh unto GOD. All theſe ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows in their ponderous weight and preſſing feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are ſet forth by the figure of a <hi>dark night</hi>; this, ſays CHRIST, <hi>is your hour and power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: And there was darkneſs over the whole land until the ninth hour.</hi> Hence he ſays, <hi>My head is wet with dew, and my locks with the drops of the night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it appears that the word <hi>night</hi> denotes ſorrows perſonally and nationally, and this is your caſe, as well as that of the united colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, ſo far as they feel for and ſympathize with you.</p>
            <p>Not long ſince your Forefathers, who were the Patriarchs and Apoſtles of <hi>America,</hi> though
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:013757_0011_0F91EBF758837B70"/>
diſtreſſed by the ſavage tribes, yet they enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their political charter liberties ſettled by compact with their king.</p>
            <p>Not long ſince the capital of <hi>America,</hi> the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian harbor of the continent was open, your caſtle commanded, your colors flying, your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce ſpreading, your importance growing, your laws ruling, peace and plenty flowing, your war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſpirit ſhining, your ſtandards renowned: But alaſs! be aſtoniſhed, O heavens at this, how has your loyalty almoſt proved your ruin; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your power, beholding your importance; jealous, jealous of a growing empire, the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Miniſtry take the rein of government, break the compact of their King, aſſume the right of making your laws, and uſurp the authority of taxing your property, tyrannically and oppreſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the whole globe, continue to block up your harbor, cruelly cutting through the ſilver veins of trade, ſtained your ſtreets with the bloody dews of death; they have ſeized your caſtle, beſieged your town with all the majeſtic horrors of war! But lo! they look to a peaceful, ſerene people in the light of a few powerleſs, harmleſs doves, trembling upon the ground they tread; and only to unneceſſary fearful minds terrible as an army with banners; this is their hour and power of darkneſs, but fear not, the <hi>morning cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Watchman what</hi> do you hear <hi>of the night?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will tell you, as I <hi>ſtand continually upon my watch tower in the day time, and ſit whole nights in my watchward.</hi> I ſaw a brother watchman coming near my watch-ward, he is an old faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful watchman, his name is <hi>Micah,</hi> to whom I ſaid, having had a familiar acquaintance with him, <hi>Watchman what of the night?</hi> He did not
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:013757_0012_0F91EBF8192CB3C0"/>
ſay, as <hi>New-England</hi> people generally do, I do not know, Sir, and immediately begin to tell you; but he ſays, like an honeſt whig, I will tell you, if your heart be as my heart; you will find it in my journal,Sir, <hi>Micah</hi> vii.3. <hi>That they may do evil with both hands earneſtly, the Prince aſketh and the Judge aſketh for a reward; and the great Man uttereth his miſchievous deſire:</hi> SO THEY WRAP IT UP. Have they not done wrapping up yet? What will they wrap up next? The ſeas, the morning light, the ſun, theſe they have wrapped up long ago in <hi>England</hi>; nay the beaſts of the forreſt and the fowls of the air, and the felicity of the fields and the bleſſings of the earth, <note n="*" place="bottom">Alluding to the land tax, window tax, beer tax, tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> the rain from heaven; nay, the earth, air, and ſea is wrapped up by them; ſo that there is nothing, O happy! but heaven left for us to make our eſcape from them. In ſhort they are like death and the grave, which cries, GIVE, GIVE, but we have nothing to give them. Have they not wrapped up our harbor, our common, our caſtle, our trade, our wharves, our ſhips that we cannot launch them? What would they have? Have they not wrapped up a great part of the lands of <hi>America,</hi> called the <hi>King's lands and tall pines</hi>? Have they not wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up our charter rights, liberties, and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutional privileges? Have they not wrapped ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven millions annually from <hi>America?</hi> What more would they have? Brother Watchman I I will tell you: They want to wrap up <hi>America</hi> into the <hi>Britiſh</hi> kingdom; they want to make three biſhopricks in <hi>America,</hi> a Biſhop for <hi>Boſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, &amp;c.</hi> a Biſhop for <hi>New-York, &amp;c.</hi> a Biſhop for the <hi>Carolinas, &amp;c.</hi> all officers and offices to
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:013757_0013_0F91EBF8DBF549A0"/>
be held in the power of the Crown, and at the diſpoſe of the King, and ſixty more lordſhips by degrees, then peradventure (for they do ſuch things in <hi>England</hi>) the next will be to wrap up our wives and our daughters. Stop, we will not have them wrapped up by them however; but I believe it is beſt to unwrap it all and ſee what is in this political bill of parcels.</p>
            <p>Pray brother Watchman can you tell me who ſent for this parliamentary bill of parcels? O yes: Mr. <hi>T— H—n,</hi> Mr. <hi>P—n,</hi> Mr. <hi>O—r,</hi> and others, by private and confidential letters. Well then, let them pay the bill and defrey the expences of it; What have we to do with it? It is hard they ſhould ſend to parliament for a bill of parcels and then charge it upon innocent people, and leave it to children yet unborn to ſuffer for it. And is it not unjuſt for thoſe who wrapped this bill to ſend it to, and charge upon thoſe people who never ordered it? I think it can never ſtand in equity.</p>
            <p>But Watchman, as you are free and open, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your commiſſion, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> xxi.6. <hi>For thus hath the</hi> LORD <hi>ſaid unto me, go and ſet a Watchman, let him declare what he ſeeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will; what ſaw you? Being upon my watch tower ſome time ago, I ſaw in a grand aſſembly a large parliamentary bill of parcels put together. Another brother Watchman (his name is <hi>Zecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah</hi>) coming by, I ſaid to him, well brother <hi>Watchman, what of the night?</hi> What ſeeſt thou? And he anſwered, <hi>I ſee a flying roll, and the length thereof is twenty cubits, and the breadth is ten cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits:</hi> And he ſaid to me, <hi>this is the curſe that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth upon the face of the earth.</hi> Upon which another Watchman came up who is uſed to be
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:013757_0014_0F91EBF9956EF428"/>
among captives, to whom I ſaid, Watchman what have you to ſay of the night? I will tell you; <hi>I looked,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>and behold a hand was ſent unto me, and lo! a roll of a book was therein, and he ſpread it before me, and in it was written within and without,</hi> LAMENTATION, MOURNING, <hi>and</hi> WOE, with this motto or inſcription upon it, <hi>And ſo they wrap it up.</hi> Colonel <hi>Barre</hi> coming in, and looking at it and ſeeing the inſcription, ſays, <hi>So they wrap it up</hi>; let us unwrap it and ſee what they have wrapped up before it goes, and upon unwrapping the firſt parcel out tumbled the d—l, upon which he ſays, Why, my Lord, did you wrap the d—l to ſend him away: Do not you know you cannot do without him? nor the M—y or P—t at preſent. I ſuppoſe he had a hand in the matter, as he came out upon opening the firſt paper. Indeed Colonel I would have no hand in the matter, I did always deſpiſe it; it was brought to me to get ſigners, but I could not get one of all my peers in the lower regions to conſent: For my part I leave other kings to make acts to ſhake their kingdoms, but I know better than to do it myſelf, for if I take away the rights of my people, I ſhall not get a new ſubject theſe thouſand years; therefore I think you might have let me alone, as I was wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up in a <hi>ſleep</hi> to go to <hi>America,</hi> paſſage free, under a royal commiſſion, to command fleets and troops in <hi>America</hi> to kill muſquetoes, for as to the people they do not deſerve it: Take care of him, my Lord, ſays the Colonel, poor d—l he muſt not be loſt; upon which his Lordſhip ſaid, <hi>Come Tom, come,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">A free ſpeech to an old friend.</note> and he took him under his cloak, upon which the Colonel miſſing him,
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:013757_0015_0F91EBFA60700BF0"/>
he ſays, what is become of the poor d—l? To which Mr. <hi>P</hi>— ſaid, his Lordſhip has taken him under his cloak, and put him in his cloſet. I fear, ſays the Colonel, in his boſom where he uſed to dwell, or otherwiſe he never could have framed ſuch an act as this: <note n="*" place="bottom">Let not the Reader think the Author is any way given to a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of levity, it is what he always deſpiſed from his youth; but only introduced ſome lively turns of thought to cheer the captives who weep and hang their harps upon the willows becauſe of the night. <hi>There is a time to rejoice,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon.</hi> Neither think it ſtrange, that the Author ſpeaks ſo familiar about the d—l, when he ſpeaks no harm of him, though he has been at parliament, in the cloſet chamber, and privy council, when he has read of the d—l's being in a much better place, and among better company than moſt of theſe, even among the <hi>ſons of</hi> GOD, Job i.6. <hi>And ſatan came alſo.</hi> And as to his entering the heart of his Lordſhip, it is nothing ſtrange when we read of his entering the heart of a much better man, even of a diſciple of JESUS. And <hi>ſatan entered into the heart of</hi> Judas Iſcariot.</note> To block up <hi>Boſton</hi> harbor, cut off all trade, ſecure their wharves, appoint ſuch as they pleaſe, under what direction they pleaſe, the Governor to chuſe the Council, the Sheriff to chuſe the juries, until the people of <hi>Boſton</hi> ſhall make ſuch ſatisfaction, ſuch conceſſions, and enter into ſuch obligation of better obedience, as the <hi>B—ſh</hi> M—y ſhall think proper. This will never do; it muſt be all unwrapped and thrown away for waſte paper. Why could not your Lordſhip have wrapped up the olive-branch and not the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheathed ſword. Is this the way to gain their treaſure, to win their affection, or procure their happineſs; ſuch an act ſuppoſing the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to have a right to make laws for the <hi>Americans</hi>; ſuch an act as this can never do, becauſe it does at once deſtroy that near union between <hi>America</hi> and the Mother Country, alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate their affections from their Sovereign, ſtop the bleſſings of commerce, and ſpread death, want
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:013757_0016_0F91EBFB18669500"/>
and poverty through the <hi>Britiſh</hi> nation, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will occaſion a revolution of the ſtate; beſides, the grand queſtion is, who are the rebellious and diſobedient? If there are any, it muſt be the <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricans</hi> or the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Parliament. If the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Parliament have a right to tax the <hi>Americans,</hi> then the <hi>Americans</hi> are diſobedient to their laws. But if they have no right to tax them, (which it is clear they have not, nor do they barely attempt to prove it) then it is plain who are the firſt ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, and cauſe of all the diſtreſſes at Home, and confuſion in <hi>America,</hi> for where there is no power or liberty of repreſentation, there are not according to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> laws, any right of taxation.</p>
            <p>Some ſay that the tea was not ſubject to any taxation, but an impoſt duty. What is the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, if it muſt be paid by an advance price by the people, without their conſent to a duty or taxation? They ſay it was the deſtruction of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate property. What difference does this make between its being private property or parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary property? The grand queſtion is, whether any people under heaven have not, by the law of ſelf preſervation, a right to deſtroy any perſons power or property who deſtroy their ſettled rights as a people? Beſides, is it juſt or uſual for one nation to tax the private properties of another nation and province, and oblige them under pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties of death to pay the tax? Is not this a breach upon the law of nations? And do not ſuch law-breakers deſerve to be puniſhed by the loſs of their property? Can mankind think it ſtrange that the juſtly angry populace ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy what their Governor would not ſtoop to ſave? Let the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company aſk par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:013757_0017_0F91EBFBDFB6D9C8"/>
of the Public whom they have offended.</p>
            <p>Colonel <hi>Barre,</hi> General <hi>Conway,</hi> Governor <hi>Pownall,</hi> Meſſieurs <hi>Burkes, Dowdeſwell,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, very many more who are the moſt honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Members of the Houſe of Commons, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrapped it much in the ſame manner, and laid it aſide as waſte paper. Nay, the Peers of the land, the Houſe of Lords, many of them united therein: Lord <hi>Chatham</hi> has much contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it; Lord <hi>Cambden</hi> has boldly declared againſt it: Likewiſe the following Peers, in a paper, intitled, the Lord's Proteſt, diſtinguiſhed themſelves in the cauſe of <hi>American</hi> freedom, namely, <hi>Richmond, Portland, Abingdon, King, Eſſingham, Rockingham, Abergavenny, Leſter, Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Fitzwilliam, &amp;c.</hi> who all unwrapped and diſapproved of the bill, the charge, and the demands. [May thoſe illuſtrious Peers and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners, who have ſo nobly diſtinguiſhed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the cauſe of <hi>America,</hi> in oppoſition to thoſe who were for taxing them, be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully remembered, and handed down to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. May their names be held in eternal ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, ſo long as one ſpark of the noble ſenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of gratitude ſhall remain in the breaſt of an <hi>American!</hi>] But his Lordſhip ſaid,
<q>We will let the <hi>Americans</hi> know that we will ſit quiet no longer under their inſults, whatever may be the conſequence; we muſt riſque ſomething or ALL is OVER.</q>
Upon which taking the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of a thin houſe in great haſte they in a hurry wrapped it up again, got a royal ſignet upon it, and ſent it <hi>all over.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A remark. Now my Lord all <hi>is over</hi>; all the bill is <hi>over,</hi> the ſhips are over, and the army is
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:013757_0018_0F91EBFCA0B3C3E0"/>
over, we hope, my Lord, it is all over: For we do not want no more, and your Lordſhip may take theſe back as ſoon as you pleaſe, for we have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for them to do. It puts me in mind of a ſoldier who ſerved in the laſt war, who being ordered by his General, namely, <hi>S—x,</hi> to feed his horſes with peas, rice, and corn, when the ſoldiers and many others had not bread to eat; the ſoldier therefore went to the Surgeon and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him to draw all his teeth; why, ſaid the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, do they ake? He ſaid no, but his General had robbed him of his bread, and given it to his horſes, and thereby he had nothing for his teeth to do, therefore he would not keep them. Thus it is, my Lord, we have nothing for his Majeſty's ſhips and armed force to do, unleſs it be to kill Muſketoes, and therefore we do not chuſe to keep them.</p>
            <p>It puts me in mind of what my brother Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſaid, (his name is <hi>Jeremiah</hi>) when I aſked him what they did with the roll? And he ſaid, <hi>It came to paſs when</hi> Jehudi <hi>had read three or four leaves, he cut it with a penknife, and burnt it in the fire that was upon the hearth until it all was conſumed.</hi> And it came to paſs; that is enough, it is not needful to know how it came to paſs, that the Watchman does not tell us, but if it comes to paſs that is all we wiſh for peace ſake.</p>
            <p>But to be more cloſe and ſerious; to hear the widows mourn for fear, labor fail, children cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, trade ceaſing, children begging daily bread, the ſtreets unoccupied, the ſea uncloathed, the harbors undreſſed; to hear the noiſy cannons roar, to ſee the blazing ſpear diſplayed, the bloody banner ſpread, and all this by brethren, by our
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:013757_0019_0F91EBFD6BD0CC00"/>
own mother's ſons, by fleſh of our fleſh and bone of our bone; for what they know not on the other ſide of the atlantic, nor do we on this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinental ſhore: Something is ſurmiſed, we are wickedly repreſented to his Majeſty, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>we</hi> muſt, ſays his Lordſhip, riſque <hi>ſomething, or all is over.</hi> What muſt they ſet <hi>Iſrael</hi> to fight againſt <hi>Judah.</hi> There is the ſame mad miſtaken paralleled caſe at large in <hi>Joſhua</hi> xxii. However my Lord, you have riſqued ſomething indeed, namely, the crown and peace of the ſtate; his Majeſty's ſhips, army, and ammunition, and we judge all is over, they are come ſafe; we mean to uſe them well as brethren; and I wiſh the tea was paid for, if that may anſwer all the end they came for, and make way for union and peace, which has been whiſpered.</p>
            <p>But it is yet a night ſeaſon; methinks I hear you ſay, <hi>Watchman what of the night?</hi> What ſhall we do to night? I will tell you; firſt, praiſe GOD for the mercies of the day, humbly truſt his promiſe for ſafety through the night, then do as regular people do, eat your ſupper, go to bed and ſleep quietly until morning, then ariſe and pay your morning ſacrifice of praiſe to GOD and go to your daily labor, and whatſoever thine hands findeth to do, do it with all thy might. Fear not the night, for the morning cometh, for the LORD our GOD is with us; fear them not, for there be more for us than they that be with them; fear them not.</p>
            <p>Secondly, love your King, feelingly, firmly, and affectionately: But remember that allegiance and obedience is only due to a King, as his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and coronation oath is fulfilled to you; it
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:013757_0020_0F91EBFE2922BB30"/>
is the law not the man that ought to rule. The King is by conſent of the people made their royal <hi>Truſtee,</hi> or grand <hi>Truſt</hi> for the preſervation of their rights; if he fails here he is no longer King according to the laws of <hi>England</hi>; therefore pray that the Almighty may give him judgment as a royal diadem to his crown, for the peace of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> and her union happineſs with <hi>America</hi>; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor your Governor with reverence and duty to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry branch of legal authority; be kind to the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery; be genteel to the officers; pray for Lord <hi>N.</hi> that the GOD of heaven may bleſs and we hope forgive him, as he did <hi>Abitophel,</hi> and ſend him to his own place as he did <hi>Judas.</hi> I have heard that his Lordſhip is a man of fine ſenſation, quick underſtanding, a great ſenator, and a faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to the Crown. But how a perſon can be a man of honor, honeſty, fine ſenſations, a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſenator, who can propoſe, aim, and proceed to diſtreſs thouſands of thouſands of innocent peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by deſtroying their eſſential liberties and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural rights, by the arbitrary arm of <hi>iron power,</hi> and thereby bid defiance to the law of nature and nations, which <hi>binds kings in fetters and nobles in irons.</hi> The man who dares this is the greateſt tyrant beneath the ſun. Was his Lordſhip a man of fine ſenſations, of quick underſtanding, poſſeſſed of the feelings of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity for the happineſs of mankind, he would ſurely have felt the piercing pleas, the nervous reaſonings, the cutting arguments, not only of Lord <hi>Chatham,</hi> Lord <hi>Cambden,</hi> and others, but of thoſe (if I may expreſs it) angelic arguments of Colonel <hi>Barre</hi> to his Lordſhip, for the peace of <hi>Britain</hi> and the happineſs of <hi>America</hi>; but
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:013757_0021_0F91EBFEE7349B18"/>
lo! nothing will do but the iron rod, and not the olive-branch, and therefore I think if the Almighty will forgive him, mankind can very well ſpare him. But if there ſhould a ſingle ſon of <hi>Iſſachar</hi> upon the earth, who is <hi>born like a ſtrong aſs to couch between two burdens,</hi> who can approve of this act, an act that deprives GOD of the grand deſigns of creation, man of his inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent rights, and the bleſſings of Providence; an act that takes away his labor, his bread, his all, his eſtate, his exiſtence; an act that makes the widow mourn, the fatherleſs to cry for bread; an act that forbids the merchant to trade; his ſtores to be open, his wharves to be uſed; an act that ſets land and water, winds and waves, blood and banners all in array againſt a loyal people, to make them love their King, whom they always adored. If there ſhould be ſuch a being upon the earth who can plead for this act, he muſt be happy; for ſurely the <hi>Almighty has made him without a ſoul, and conſequently he can have no ſins to anſwer for.</hi> What ſhall I ſay to ſuch a one? He lives indeed, but he muſt die; <hi>Duſt thou art,</hi> (that is all) <hi>and unto duſt thou muſt return.</hi> Shall I ſay in the Prophet's lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, <hi>Hell from beneath moves to meet thee at thy coming.</hi> No; heaven forbid! indeed there is no danger, for it is ſo full already of more ſenſible beings, that there is no room, in charity we hope for ſuch there. Thus you ſee that we are more mild and charitable for thoſe Perſons who vainly call themſelves Friends to Government: They ſay that we, yea and thoſe honeſt <hi>Britiſh</hi> Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament who plead for the rights of injured <hi>America</hi> are a ſet of damned—&amp;c.
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:013757_0022_0F91EBFF9E0A0870"/>
and ought to be damned. Now we are not for having theſe friends to government, as they falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtile themſelves, damned: No; but for their being ſaved even from the power of damning others. But I would ſay as <hi>Samuel</hi> did unto <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi>; GOD <hi>forbid that I ſhould ſin in ceaſing to pray for you, for I bare you record that you have zeal for your</hi> King and Country, <hi>but not according to</hi> the <hi>knowledge</hi> of the eſſential and charter rights of the <hi>Americans</hi>; therefore it it is that ſuch multiply words without knowledge, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Watchman you have told us what of the night: But Watchman what of the <hi>morning?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will tell you; the morning cometh, the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of hope, the morning of help, the morning of mercies. The morning cometh; that is hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, it cometh. How? without the aid of man, of its own accord, by infinite power. Thus our deliverance comes from the GOD of Heaven. Who among you would dare in a dark <hi>night</hi> to attempt to help omnipotence to ſpread the wings of the <hi>morning</hi>? Would not the attempt in thought be blaſphemous; wait with patience, the morning cometh freely as the gift of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and thus comes your deliverance, not only temporal but ſpiritual and eternal, as the fruit of omnipotent love and power. Hence CHRIST is ſaid to be as the light of the <hi>morning, as the light of the morning without clouds.</hi> And this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is believed by all mankind, but the Prieſts and the people. The Prieſt ſays, GOD will give ſalvation as the light of the morning; he offers it to you, but you muſt aſſiſt the Almighty, and help him on your part, or you cannot have it, by fulfilling the conditions of the covenant;
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:013757_0023_0F91EC0056E89BD8"/>
by coming up to the terms of the goſpel, by getting faith, by laying down your arms of <hi>hoſtility, &amp;c.</hi> O! if they will but do theſe good things, in plain Engliſh help the Almighty a little, win him over by a few dead promiſes and prayers, and then he will give them the light of the morning, I mean his favor: Hence it is they tell the dead they muſt live or they will be damned, <hi>that is all</hi>; the deaf they muſt hear or they will periſh; the blind they muſt ſee or they will be loſt. But ſays the dead in ſin, I cannot give myſelf life, and the deaf, I cannot hear, and the blind I cannot ſee: But ſays the Preacher you will be damned if you do not; putting all the firſt, living, and moving power upon thoſe who have neither life nor power, yet according to them they muſt be damned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have it not: And this they call the light of the goſpel; poor Ignoramus's: I do not mean as Gentlemen or as Scholars, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the goſpel of CHRIST, my ſoul of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten melts for them with holy compaſſion, at other times, like <hi>Elijah,</hi> in order to awaken them, I cannot but mock them with a holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, <hi>Why halt they between two opinions?</hi> I do not mean all; there are ſome whom I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to hear. But O when will the Prieſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim, <hi>When ſhall the people know the joyful ſound?</hi> namely, that ſalvation from the GOD of Heaven is as free, as unconditionally free and powerful to the ſouls of men as the light of the morning is unto mankind.</p>
            <p>Further, let it be remembered what natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts ſay, that it is darkeſt juſt before the <hi>morning light</hi>; this ſcripture experience and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:013757_0024_0F91EC0118B85E80"/>
delivering mercies have made manifeſt to the ſons of men; then why ſhould we fear; remember what the Prophet ſays, <hi>In the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſhall be light,</hi> add as <hi>David</hi> ſays, <hi>Though weeping may endure for a night, yet joy cometh in the morning.</hi> You never knew a night but the morning followed it, nor a dark affliction ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſoul or body, but what a ſure mercy followed it, juſt as the morning followeth the night; as it is written, <hi>The evening and the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were the firſt day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the night is the womb of the morning, ſo is the night of affliction the womb of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times ten thouſand mercies to mankind; by this very idea, the glory of heaven, the joy of ſaints, and the ſalvation of ſinners is declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Pſalm</hi> cx.3. ſpeaking to the MESSIAH, JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH ſays, <hi>From the womb of the morning thou haſt the dew of thy youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover by the light of the morning we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the beauties and bleſſings of the day.— Thus it is by the light of the morning of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, to ſpeak in ſcripture language <hi>When</hi> JEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH <hi>ſcatters the princes in</hi> Salmon, <hi>rebukes kings, and binds princes in fetters, and nobles in irons, to make known deliverance to</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ſalvation to</hi> Iſrael. This makes the mountains to rejoice, and the trees of the field to clap their hands, and the people to ſay amen. <hi>This is the</hi> LORD's <hi>and it is marvelous in our eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Once more: The morning cometh, the light of the morning is ſure to ſcatter the darkneſs of the night, it is omnipotent, and uncontroulable. Who can ſtop the expanding wings of the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? It is a beam of omnipotence; the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:013757_0025_0F91EC01D9C99000"/>
rays are the rays of the Deity. Wait on the LORD then and be of good courage for the <hi>morning cometh.</hi> Nor is it in the power of kings, princes, potentates, parliaments, or any arbitrary arm to ſtop theſe morning mercies; for as the morning ſurely chaſes away the darkneſs of the night, ſo the LORD JESUS, who is the light of the morning, ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chaſe away every night of ſorrow from them that fear him: <hi>Unto you that fear my name,</hi> ſays GOD, <hi>ſhall the ſun of righteouſneſs ariſe with healings in his wings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One more inquiry: <hi>Watchman what of the night?</hi> Do you think we deſerve it? I know we deſerve it from GOD, but not from man; and I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that you deſerve it from GOD? I am glad you are ſo humbly ſenſible: But what if I ſay you deſerve it from GOD, and will tell you for what; it is for your iniquitous and diſgraceful practice of keeping <hi>African</hi> ſlaves, a cuſtom ſo evidently contradictory to the laws of GOD, and in direct violation of the <hi>charter</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">The liberty of the <hi>Africans</hi> is as much their right, nay their char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter right, according to the <hi>charter</hi> of this province, ſettled by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament, as it is the right of the Governor, the greateſt Gentleman, or <hi>Engliſhman</hi> in <hi>America</hi> to be free, as the charter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares.
<q>Our will and pleaſure is, and we do hereby for us, our heirs, and ſucceſſors, grant, eſtabliſh, and ordain, that all and every of the ſubjects of us, our heirs, and ſucceſſors, which ſhall go to and inhabit within our ſaid province and territory, and every of their children which ſhall happen to be born there, or on the ſeas in going thither, or returning form thence, ſhall have and enjoy all liberties and immunities of <hi>free</hi> and natural ſubjects within any of the dominions of us, our heirs, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, to all intents, conſtructions, and purpoſes whatſoever, as if they and every of them were born within this our realm of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </q>
               </note> of this province, and the natural and unalienable rights of mankind; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any among you, <hi>profeſſing</hi> chriſtianity, although at the ſame time are guilty of ſo glaring a treſpaſs on the laws of ſociety and humanity, may incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtently
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:013757_0026_0F91EC029CE7B438"/>
gloſs over their deteſtable uſage with the idle <hi>pretence</hi> of chriſtianizing them, when it is well known more than one half thoſe who are owners of theſe black people do not care what becomes of the ſouls of them, if they can reap the profits ariſing from the labor of their bodies, at leaſt until they arrive at the age of fifty, a period which is far beyond the meridian of man's natural life. I only judge from their conduct towards theſe miſerable creatures, more eſpecially with regard to their education, and this aſſertion is notoriouſly verified in reſpect of thoſe who hold ſlaves in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> as well as in moſt parts of <hi>America,</hi> even where the chriſtian religion is profeſſed, they are not learned to read one word of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or ſay their catechize: Nay, ſome venture to ſay, were they to have learning, and to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the principles of religion, they would be of no ſervice to any one: However, admitting their motives of importing theſe <hi>Africans</hi> to make chriſtians of them, if they can, to be ſincere, is it likely any man will be willing to bind himſelf for life, in order to obtain your chance ſalvation, by means of your prayers, feelings, movings of the ſpirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which perhaps moſt of you may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count works of righteouſneſs?</p>
            <p>This truly benevolent and public-ſpirited way of freeing black men when they are old, reminds me of a ſtory I heard of one who was held in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage until he was near ſixty years of age, when his maſter very generouſly offered him his freedom, after telling him he had been a faithful, honeſt ſlave, and thanked him for his paſt good ſervices. But hear the honeſt reply of the aged, decripid, and untutored <hi>African,</hi> arrived at ſuch a period
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:013757_0027_0F91EC0358BA9100"/>
of life as to occaſion grey hairs, by age and hard labor; <hi>I tank you, Maſer, I tink you hab all de marrow, hes way you take care de bone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bluſh ye pretended votaries for freedom! ye tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling patriots! who are making a vain parade of being the advocates for the liberties of mankind, who are thus making a mockery of your profeſſion, by trampling on the ſacred natural rights and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges of the <hi>Africans</hi>; for while you are faſting, praying, non-importing, non-exporting, remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating, reſolving, and pleading for a reſtoration of your charter rights, you at the ſame time are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing this lawleſs, cruel, inhuman, and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble practice of enſlaving your fellow-creatures, which is ſo diſgraceful to human nature; a practice which muſt redound to the eternal diſhonor of any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple much more to thoſe who <hi>wear</hi> the chriſtian name, and muſt ſurely make the heart of every feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſon ſhudder at the thought of being held in perpetual ſlavery, but ſhocking to relate, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alized by millions of unhappy mortals in the world, a greater part of which I am ſorry to ſay are dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in this <hi>American</hi> land of freedom!</p>
            <p>But if ye fail of aboliſhing this vile cuſtom of ſlave-making, either by a law of the province, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law, (which I am told has happily ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in many inſtances of late) or by a voluntary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſement, the oppreſſed ſons of <hi>Africa</hi> may very juſtly retort this ſtubborn paſſage of ſacred writ up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> lviii.6. <hi>Looſe the bands of wickedneſs, undo the heavy burdens, let the oppreſſed go free, that ye break every yoke</hi>: And may truly ſay with the ſame Prophet, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> i.13, 19. <hi>Bring no more vain oblation: The calling of aſſemblies I cannot away with; it is iniquity even the ſolemn-meeting. If ye
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:013757_0028_0F91EC041E1971C0"/>
be willing and obedient ye ſhall eat the good of the land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let me aſk you, I mean thoſe who are guilty in this reſpect, with what face can you look up to the ALMIGHTY, that juſt and righteous Being, and beg of him his aid and aſſiſtance in our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical affairs, while we are oppreſſing our <hi>African</hi> brethren ten thouſand times as much by keeping them in ſlavery for life? And what is a trifling three penny duty on tea in compariſon to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable bleſſing of liberty to one captive? But O ſhocking the very imagination! yet more amaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reality! to know we have millions among us who are ſlaves to all generations, at leaſt we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign them as ſuch, unleſs ſome kind arm ſhould interpoſe in the behalf of theſe miſerable people to put an end to their bondage. O how it makes me rejoice, yea it makes me leap for joy, when I mention the much honored names <note n="*" place="bottom">The word of GOD commands us to give honor to whom honor is due, and ſurely it is not due to any more than to thoſe who relieve the <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,</hi> and give <hi>liberty</hi> to them who are in <hi>bondage</hi>: We deſire there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to mention five honorable Gentlemen, who have, from chriſtian principles and from a ſincere love of <hi>liberty,</hi> given <hi>freedom</hi> to their ſlaves, namely, JOSEPH BOWDITCH, <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Capt. SAMUEL BARTON, and Mr. JONATHAN PHELPS, ſer. of <hi>Salem.</hi> Major FULLER, of <hi>Newtown,</hi> Mr. ROBERT PIERPONT, of <hi>Boſton,</hi> and the REFER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REES, on a caſe brought on at the inferior court of common pleas for the county of <hi>Eſſex</hi> for July term, between Mr. CALEB DODGE, of <hi>Beverly</hi> and his negro ſervant, who gave a verdict in favor of the negro, by which he obtained his freedom, there being no law of the province to hold a man to ſerve for life.</note> of thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy patriots for liberty, thoſe ſincere friends to the rights and liberties of mankind, who, emulated with a ſpirit of liberty, have ſo nobly let public virtue triumph over ſordid ſelf-intereſt, and have releaſed a number of valuable black ſervants who were held in bondage. May they and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be bleſſed for this truly god-like act; and may their public-ſpirited example be followed by
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:013757_0029_0F91EBDE8CA06C00"/>
many, very many Gentlemen who are owners of ſlaves. Let it never be told in the ſtreets of <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> that nurſery of freedom, that there is one bond-ſlave dwells therein.</p>
            <p>To conclude this ſolemn and much diſcuſſed ſubject, however little regard may have been paid to it by thoſe whoſe intereſt it may juſtly be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be to ſlight every thing that ſhall be advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in favor of the <hi>Africans.</hi> However the time is coming, I hope, when inſtead of theſe ſorely diſtreſſed and much oppreſſed <hi>Africans</hi> retorting paſſages of ſcripture on you ſlave-makers, our Savior's words may come with full power and have their deſired effect, namely, <hi>Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, do ye even ſo to them.</hi> Though little account may be made of them in the religious as well as political world, they ought to be the eternal rule of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to mankind.</p>
            <p>Some of you may remember what your late Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor <hi>Pownall</hi> ſaid to his ſervant <hi>Frank,</hi> on his confining a number of birds in a cage: Says his Excellency, Whoſe birds are thoſe in that cage? Mine, Sir, replied his ſervant. What did they coſt? Two dollars, Sir. Says his Excellency, there are your two dollars for them, let them be free, for I will have no being that GOD has made, in bondage in my houſe. Soon after the Governor purchaſed a number of flying-ſquirrels to ſend to <hi>England,</hi> which he confined in a cage: His man <hi>Frank</hi> ſeeing them, enquired of his fellow-ſervants whoſe ſquirrels they were? They informed him they belonged to his Excellency; on which <hi>Frank</hi> immediately let them all free: And on his carrying the tidings to his Excellency, enquired of him, what the ſquirrels coſt? The Governor was a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:013757_0030_0F91EBDF4DAF43F0"/>
angry at firſt for his freedom in aſking what they coſt? but on telling him he had ſet them at liberty, and offering to pay for them, his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency was much pleaſed with the familiar, ſoft ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition in favor of liberty.</p>
            <p>Sir, One word if you pleaſe as Watchman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Watchman what of the night?</hi> I mean of the night of miniſterial darkneſs of the goſpel; what of the night, Watchman?</p>
            <p>Who is he that makes this inquiry? Thou art ſure a ſenſible ſoul, for I have not had ſuch an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry ever ſince I have been upon my watch tower in <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This enquiry, my hearers, will naturally lead me for a few minutes to ſpeak of religious liberty, and you that do not love religion or ſacred liberty may go out, there will no body take any notice of it but GOD, and you know and others will know that you do not mind him much; but I chuſe to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to the enquirer, becauſe among ſenſible people it is known that the Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſters, in general, by their arbitrary au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the churches and deſpotic power by councils have as much deſtroyed the charter rights of the church of CHRIST, as the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Miniſtry have the rights of the <hi>American</hi> ſubjects.</p>
            <p>However I will tell the enquirer it is a dark night indeed, inſomuch that the people in a ſacred ſenſe <hi>ſeem to</hi> me <hi>to dwell in the land of darkneſs and of the ſhades of death,</hi> but it is a very good night for blind <hi>folk,</hi> for blind Prieſts and blind people, for <hi>the blind lead the blind,</hi> the night and the day are both alike to them; they group at noon-day and ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon the dark mountains; for if the light that is in them be darkneſs, how great is that darkneſs; nor will they come to the light leſt their miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:013757_0031_0F91EBE00D1AF330"/>
deeds ſhould be reproved, and if any dawn of light appears to any, the Prieſts with the inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly fine thread of prejudice ſews their eyes, as man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind ſew up the eyes of <hi>flutterers</hi> to blind them, that by them they may catch more pigeons, and thereby make them ſeven fold more the children of condemnation. The Prieſt goes his old, cold, deathly and phariſaical round (like a horſe in a mill) of long prayers, tears, conditions, terms; do your part, lay down your arms, ſubmit and GOD will change his <hi>anger,</hi> will love you and have mercy upon you. Such phariſaical <hi>rubbiſh</hi> we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually from the pulpit: If you aſk bread they give you a ſtone; if you talk to them in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of <hi>Canaan,</hi> they anſwer you in the language of <hi>Aſhdod</hi>; this makes it a dark night, a dark night to the church indeed. When do we ever ſee the miniſtration of glory made manifeſt by the Prieſt, by preaching CHRIST as the light of the <hi>morning,</hi> or ever proclaim the light of a DIVINE RIGHTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUSNESS, of a finiſhed ſalvation, of pardon alone by CHRIST's death, atonement by his blood, of vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory by his reſurrection, of peace only by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the finiſhed righteouſneſs and atonement. When do we hear of the power of the HOLY GHOST in regeneration, giving freely like the light of the morning, life, light, peace, joy, and conſolation by the miniſtration of the goſpel, and thereby engaging their ſouls by the bonds of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty grace, to <hi>new obedience</hi> day by day. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we have a little of theſe things mentioned, but depend upon it, in general, there is <hi>death in the pot,</hi> when ever the ſons of the Prophet ſeeth it: They are always ſetting forth GOD and the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at a diſtance from each other, like two <hi>angry parties,</hi> and then they perſuade the creature not to
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:013757_0032_0F91EBE0CD461DF8"/>
be angry any longer, and then GOD will not be angry with him, ſo the people the beſt of them in general ſo eſteemed, they think right to get a robe of ſelf-righteouſneſs, being ignorant of GOD's righteouſneſs, and then judge all is well with them, and are pleaſed, like children, with themſelves, vainly thinking that GOD is pleaſed with them, becauſe the Prieſt tells them ſo: <hi>And ſo they wrap it up</hi>: And if any one attempts to unwrap it and ſays as CHRIST did, <hi>How can ye eſcape the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hell?</hi> they are like the ſcribes and phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, exceeding angry to be ſure, and ſay why <hi>he is a troubler in</hi> Iſrael, he is beſide himſelf, he has not the approbation of the Standing Miniſtry. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I am of Mr. <hi>C—ſ—ll</hi>'s mind who, was deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to procure the <hi>approbation</hi> of the Standing Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, that he might be more extenſively uſeful in the world. He replied, by no means, for he had had their <hi>reprobation</hi> for twenty years, which he thought far more preferrable.</p>
            <p>But though your ſorrows may yet continue, your harps hang upon the willows, and things may yet grow darker and darker, and your ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows be like the ſwellings of <hi>Jordan,</hi> yet fear not, the morning cometh. <hi>Though the fig-tree ſhould not bloſſom, nor there ſhould be no fruit on the vine; the labor of the olive fail, and the field yield no meat, and the flocks be cut from the field, and there ſhall be no herd in the ſtalls; yet wait on the</hi> LORD <hi>and be of good courage, the</hi> morning cometh. Support your congreſs, maintain your union, ſtrengthen your affection, relieve the poor, perſevere in piety, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and prudence as a band of brethren united in one COMMON CAUSE, be fearleſs, be harmleſs, and may GOD ALMIGHTY bleſs you.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
