<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some necessary remarks on the education of the youth in the country-parts of this, and the neighbouring governments.</title>
            <author>Benezet, Anthony, 1713-1784.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N12459</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N12459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 15739</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APV5894</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">15739</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99001328</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 15739.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N12459)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 15739)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 15739)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some necessary remarks on the education of the youth in the country-parts of this, and the neighbouring governments.</title>
                  <author>Benezet, Anthony, 1713-1784.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p. ;  (12mo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Philadelphia :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1778?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Anthony Benezet by Evans.</note>
                  <note>Imprint supplied by Evans.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious education of young people.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="unknown:015739_0000_0F9A234570BFACE0"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:015739_0001_0F9A23462E35ECF0"/>
            <head>SOME NECESSARY REMARKS ON THE EDUCATION OF THE YOUTH <hi>in the</hi> COUNTRY-PARTS <hi>of this, and the neighbouring</hi> GOVERNMENTS.</head>
            <p>THAT the religious and civil education of our young people is an affair of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt importance, as it not only concerns the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of individuals, but the welfare and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of Society, all are ready to acknowledge; but when we caſt our eyes over the country and conſider the little attention and pains employed therein, we muſt allow that people either do
<pb n="2" facs="unknown:015739_0002_0F9A2346EF5B3AE0"/>
not ſpeak as they think, or that what they mean by education, is ſomething elſe than to qualify their children to be uſeful and ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in life; and to fit them for eternal happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. If the boy be deſigned for any of the learned profeſſions, inquiry is made for a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to teach him Latin; but if he be only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for the common offices of life, it is thought ſufficient that he be taught to read and write, with a little arithmetick, and that often but very imperfectly; no matter by whom, but the cheaper the better. Thus it happens that perſons, every way, unqualified, both in learning and morals, are, for the ſake of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it done cheaper, entruſted with the educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of children; by which means, the youth are deprived of learning, and inſtead of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving in virtue, which ought to be the main deſign of inſtruction, rather become proficients in vice. For, it is an undoubted truth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by fatal experience, that children catch the vices of thoſe with whom they converſe, and that impreſſions made on their tender minds are deep and laſting. The love we owe to God our great and good Creator, good will to men, a ſtrict regard to truth; a government of their appetites and paſſions, ſhould be, as much as poſſible, enforced on the youth <note n="*" place="bottom">The chief aim of inſtruction pointed out by the Goſpel and enforced by the wiſe men of every age and nation was the amendment of the heart: The Lacedemonians and Perſians accounted ingratitude a crime, whoever was ever capable of forgetting a benefit was looked upon as the enemy of mankind.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="unknown:015739_0003_0F9A2347AD78ABB8"/>If we really wiſh to ſee our children grow up in virtue and knowledge, and qualified to be uſeful members of Society, the means muſt be procured, to which it is to be hoped, that thoſe who have not, as well as thoſe who have children, would cheerfully contribute, without regard to any immediate advantage, they are to reap; virtuous perſons qualified for ſo weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty an employment muſt be ſought for: And in order that this may be done upon a laſting bottom, where the eſtabliſhment of a School is neceſſary, a fund ſhould be raiſed, which thro' the divine bleſſing, by donations, legacies, &amp;c. may become a laſting ſettlement; a lot of ground ſhould be provided, ſufficient for a garden, orch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, graſs for a cow, &amp;c. a houſe, ſtables, &amp;c. erected thereon: There are few neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, but may, in money from the rich, and materials and labour from others, contribute ſo much as will anſwer this charge; ſuch a ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with a reaſonable Salary, will be an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to a ſober perſon, with a family, who will be likely to ſpend his life in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; ſuch an one, from the experience he will gain, will be much more likely to anſwer the good end propoſed, than ſuch tranſient perſons as are often employed. Indeed the illjudged cuſtom which has generally prevailed with the country people, of hiring a ſingle perſon, on account of cheapneſs, and for the ſake of board<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, amongſt themſelves, is attended with many inconveniences. Theſe are frequently perſons of no ſtability, and little principle, who engage in that ſervice, for a preſent mainten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:015739_0004_0F9A23486EDF7B30"/>
which they are ready to quit, when ever ſomething more agreeable to their intereſt or humour offers; ſo that, they have as little deſire as opportunity, of gaining that neceſſary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, which, nothing will ſo effectually give, as a ſerious and ſteady practice.</p>
            <p>It is a moſt abſurd piece of thrift, for the ſake of adding 40, or 50 pounds to a child's fortune, to deprive him of the benefit of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per education, for only to conſider it in the light of prudence, the child, if well inſtructed, will readily ſave or gain that much more; and, if taught wherein true happineſs conſiſts, he will never repine at the want of that ſmall ſum; but to a perſon unprincipled in virtue, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with evil habits, what is 40 or 50 pounds more or leſs? Nay, does not daily experience ſhew us that the greateſt wealth often anſwers little or no other purpoſe, than to adminſter to folly, luxury, and debauchery; to inflame the paſſions of the youth, and give a wider range to their licentiouſneſs.</p>
            <p>And, in order that this neceſſary ſervice ſhould be managed to the beſt advantage, a number of perſons the beſt qualified, and able to attend the ſervice, ſhould be choſen, to take upon them the care and overſight of the School; to adviſe and aſſiſt the maſter; and to be eſpecially careful, that the children of the poor be encouraged to attend, and be admitted, free of coſt. And the maſters and overſeers are exhorted, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, not to repine or grudge any labour they may beſtow in this good ſervice, beyond what has been uſual; but remember, they are promoting the purpoſes of our good Creator, whoſe will is the happineſs of his creatures, who is able and willing to repay even a cup of cold water given in his name; and the comfort it will
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:015739_0005_0F9A23492FCD3690"/>
in future afford them to reflect, that they have in ſome meaſure, been the happy inſtruments in laying the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for making the youth ſerviceable and happy here, and of promoting their eternal happineſs hereafter.</p>
            <p>The following advices are ſubmitted to the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe overſeers and Tutors who may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to the care of ſuch Schools.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. That in teaching Engliſh, particular care ſhould be taken to make children ſpell correctly, by exerciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, frequently, in that neceſſary branch of their learning.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. That endeavours be uſed to make the Scholars read with proper emphaſis and punctuation, to which purpoſe it will be alſo neceſſary, beſides the Bible to make uſe of Hiſtorical and Religious Authors, of which the School ought to be furniſhed with proper ſetts.</p>
            <p n="3">3d. That ſuch parts of Grammer as are applicable to the Engliſh tongue, be taught thoſe boys who are fit for it, in order to make them write properly, but that they be as little as poſſible, perplexed with ſuch nice diſtinctions, as have no foundation in the nature of our language.</p>
            <p n="4">4th. That the Maſter as often as is convenient make a practice of dictating, to ſuch Scholars who write tolerably well, ſome ſentence out of ſome good Author which they are to write after him; then the Maſter carefully correct it, making ſuch Grammatick and Orthographic remarks as are neceſſary: This the Scholar muſt write over in his Book, which being again reviewed by the Maſter and the remaining omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions noted, may be copied in the neateſt manner on the oppoſite page. Some modern Grammarians alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that the Tutors give their ſcholars ſome portion of Hiſtory, &amp;c. expreſſed in falſe Orthography, Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, &amp;c. which they with the help of a Dictionary and ſome general Grammatic Rules muſt make out as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect as they can, which after being ſubmitted to the Tutor's Remarks and Correction, ſhould be neatly copied over in their writing Books. Theſe methods if carefully purſued will much help their diction; improve
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:015739_0006_0F9A2349EDAC0C10"/>
their ſpelling; teach them to copy correctly; and in ſome meaſure ſupply the want of Claſſical Learning</p>
            <p n="5">5th. That in writing care be taken to promote a ſtrong free hand, which will be of moſt common uſe, and from which all other hands may be eaſily formed. And that the Maſter be particularly careful to make the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pils ſit in right poſitions at their writing and that they hold their pen properly, on this their perfection in writing very much depends.</p>
            <p n="6">6th. That in teaching Arithmetick it be recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the maſter to give in the firſt place the moſt plain and practical rules; leaving thoſe that are abſtruce and not generally neceſſary, to boys of the brighteſt genius, or leiſure.</p>
            <p n="7">7th. That a ſmall, but very plain ſet of Merchants Accompt Books, <hi>viz.</hi> a Day Book, or Journal and Ledger be provided, juſt ſufficient to make the Scholars acquainted with the nature of the moſt plain entries of Debtor and Creditor; that they not only be made to copy theſe, in a neat and correct manner, but that the maſter uſe his beſt endeavours that they be made to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the reaſon of what they are doing.</p>
            <p n="8">8th. That no latin be attempted to be taught, unleſs a School ſhould be erected ſolety for that purpoſe: The teaching that language, in an Engliſh School, infallibly conſuming more of the maſters time, than can be ſpared from his other buſineſs; and the few Latin-Scholars muſt be very indifferently attended</p>
            <p n="9">9th. That ſome method be thought of for limiting the number of ſcholars, ſo that the maſter be not over-preſt, in ſome ſeaſons of the year; and that the poor be properly conſidered.</p>
            <p>That ſuch Rules, or Orders as may be thought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, be provided and ſet up in ſome public place in the School; and that the maſter be enjoined to require ſtrict obedience to every one of them.</p>
            <p>The following Rules of conduct to ſcholars extracted, from thoſe uſed in ſome of the ſchools in Philadelphia, are propoſed to the conſideration of overſeers, and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, to be improved and added to, as their experience and ſituation may make neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="7" facs="unknown:015739_0007_0F9A234C07198910"/>1ſt. Fail not to be at ſchool preciſely at the time appointed; unleſs good reaſon can be aſſigned to the maſter.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. Be always ſilent at your ſtudies, ſo that your voices be not heard, unleſs when ſaying your leſſons, or ſpeaking to your maſter: Hold no diſcourſe with your ſchool-fellows, during the time of ſtudy, unleſs to aſk ſomething relating to your learning and then in a low voice.</p>
            <p n="3">3d. Make all your ſpeeches to your maſter with due reſpect; obſerving cheerfully his directions, according to your abilities.</p>
            <p n="4">4th. Behave yourſelves always in a gentle, obliging manner, to your ſchool-fellows; tenderly affectionate, never provoking one another; contending nor complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about frivolous matters; but courteouſly uſe kind expreſſions one towards the other; obſerving to make ſome grateful return for any little kindneſs received.</p>
            <p n="5">5th. Be not forward to divulge any thing paſſed in ſchool, nor to mock, or jeer your ſchool fellows for being corrected; it is unkind, and may happen to be your own caſe.</p>
            <p n="6">6th. Never tell a lie, or uſe artful evaſions, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud any perſon, by word or deed: Swear not at all; nor uſe the name of God irreverently, or in vain: Mock not the aged, the lame, deformed or inſane. Throw no ſticks, ſtones, dirt, ſnowballs, or any other thing at any perſon, or creature: Revile no perſon; nor utter any indecent expreſſions: Never return any injury or affront; but forgive, agreeable to the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive injunction given us in the Lord's prayer, To for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give as we deſire to be forgiven, and the Apoſtle's ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. <hi>That we forgive one another, even as God, for Chriſt's ſake, has forgiven us;</hi> but in all things to the beſt of your power, behave in a modeſt, civil, and complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant manner to all.</p>
            <p>At Home. Before you riſe from your beds, obſerve to look up to your Creator, offering a mental petition to Him for help and protection, during the courſe of the day.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="unknown:015739_0008_0F9A234C2DC47228"/>Obſerve, cheerfully, and readily, to comply with your parent's commands; always addreſſing them with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reſpect, remembering the bleſſing annexed, in the third commandment, to the duty of honouring your Parents.</p>
            <p>Treat your Brothers and Siſters with affection and good manners; and, in like manner, behave to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Servant; with kindneſs uſing the word <hi>pleaſe,</hi> &amp;c. where proper; that your good example may induce them ſo to behave to you: Join not in their idle talk or jeſting; but chooſe the company of perſons, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is moſt improving in the beſt things.</p>
            <p>Be not forward to ſit down at table before your elders; when ſeated be not eager to fall to your victuals, like the brute beaſt; but firſt make a ſolemn pauſe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to retire in your minds, in thankfulneſs to the ſupreme giver of them. Dont offer to carve or aſk for yourſelves, but wait till you are ſerved; find no fault with your food; but having eaten moderately, riſe from table, without noiſe, unleſs deſired to ſtay.</p>
            <p>At places of Worſhip, Obſerve to be preſent at the times appointed, entering the place ſoberly, ſo as not to diſturb the meditations of thoſe that are met: Sit in a decent compoſure of body and mind, putting up your petitions to your heavenly Father, with an humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend diſpoſition; requeſting to be enabled to offer him ſpiritual and acceptable worſhip. When worſhip is over riſe not up in a hurry, nor be impatient to be gone, but reſpectfully paſs along without preſſing, and return decently home.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
