<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some brief hints of a religious scheme, taught and propagated by a number of Europeans, living in a place called Nisqueunia, in the state of New-York. / Written by Valentine Rathbun, Minister of the Gospel. ; [Two lines from Proverbs]</title>
            <author>Rathbun, Valentine, b. 1724.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N13973</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N13973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 17682</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APV4987</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">17682</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99000317</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 17682.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N13973)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 17682)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 17682)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some brief hints of a religious scheme, taught and propagated by a number of Europeans, living in a place called Nisqueunia, in the state of New-York. / Written by Valentine Rathbun, Minister of the Gospel. ; [Two lines from Proverbs]</title>
                  <author>Rathbun, Valentine, b. 1724.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p. ;  18 cm. (12mo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re printed and sold by Benjamin Edes and Sons, in State-Street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M,DCC,LXXXII. [1782]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shakers.</term>
               <term>Watervliet (N.Y.) --  Church history.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:017682_0000_0FA21E4E83660E60"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:017682_0001_0FA21E4F333B0168"/>
            <p>SOME BRIEF HINTS OF A RELIGIOUS SCHEME, Taught and propagated by a Number of EUROPEANS, living in a Place called <hi>Niſqueunia,</hi> in the State of NEW-YORK.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN BY Valentine Rathbun, MINISTER OF THE GOSPEL.</p>
            <q>
               <p>He that is firſt in his own cauſe ſeemeth juſt: but his neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Proverbs of Solomon.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON:</hi> Reprinted and ſold by BENJAMIN EDES and SONS, in <hi>State-Street.</hi> MDCC, LXXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="unknown:017682_0002_0FA21E52EA1D5388"/>
            <head>Some brief Hints, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>AT the earneſt requeſt of many enquiring minds, I have undertaken to preſent to the public the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ter, form, and manner of a new and ſtrange religion, that has lately taken place among many people in the Commonwealth of Maſſachuſet's, and of New York: and in purſuing my purpoſe, I ſhall take the following method:—</p>
            <p>IN the firſt place—I will preſent to view, the leaders and teachers of this new and ſtrange religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I will ſhew their manner of addreſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I will ſhew their doctrine, with the ſcripture evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence they bring to prove it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I will ſhew their manner of worſhip.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I ſhall ſhew the directions which they give to thoſe that come to them to be inſtructed.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I will ſhew the power and effect of their inſtructions on their adherents.</p>
            <p n="7">7. I ſhall ſhew what this new religion is, as pointed out by ſcripture teſtimony.</p>
            <p n="8">8. I ſhall give ſome reaſons for my knowledge in this new religion, not by mere ſpeculation, but by ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful experience.</p>
            <p n="9">9. I ſhall cloſe the whole, by a word of advice to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and people.</p>
            <p>To return therefore according to my promiſe, in the firſt place, to preſent to public view, the leaders and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of this new and ſtrange religion.</p>
            <p>The whole number conſiſts of five males and ſeven fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males; three of the males and two females profeſs to be perfect, or to have attained a ſtate of perfection; the other ſeven not perfect yet, but very far advanced. This peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are Europeans, a part of which came from England to
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:017682_0003_0FA21E52F7D07F78"/>New York in the year 1774, and lived at New York and Albany, and places adjacent, two years—and in the year 1776, the reſt came to Philadelphia, and travelled through Pennſylvania, to New-York, where the whole twelve came together and directly went and made a purchaſe of land in a place called Niſqueunia, about nine or ten miles northweſt from Albany, where they immediately ſettled, and went to clearing their land, and following their ſeveral occupations of blackſmithing, weaving and ſhoe making, and were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known and unnoticed, unleſs by a few of their neighbours, until the 17th day of April 1780; at which time, one Talmage Biſhop brought tidings into New Lebanon, of a number of ſtrange and wonderful Chriſtians; the people, like the Athenians of old, were filled with deſire to ſee new things, and run to ſee them. This brings me to ſhew,</p>
            <p n="2">2d. Their manner of addreſs —</p>
            <p>When any perſon goes to ſee them, they all meet him with many ſmiles, and ſeeming great gladneſs; they bid him welcome, and directly tell him they knew of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yeſterday. This ſets the perſon a wondering at their knowledge, and preſently they get the perſon ſome victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als; then they ſit down and have a ſpell of ſinging; they ſing odd tunes, and Britiſh marches, ſometimes without words, and ſometimes with a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ure of words known and unknown. After ſinging they fall to ſhaking their heads in a very extraordinary manner with their eyes ſhut and face up; then a woman about forty years old ſits &amp; makes a fare of prayer, chiefly in an unknown tongue, (if I may ſo call it) then one of the men comes to the perſon and pretends to interpret the woman's prayer; after which they tell the perſon he has come to the light place to be inſtructed; they inquire the perſon's name, and ever after call him by his Chriſtian name; they uſe no compliments, but their language is, <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>nay.</hi> If the perſon have long hair, or a club, they bring the bible, and read to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cor. xith chap and 14th verſe, then telling him if he intends to be inſtructed, he muſt firſt have his hair cut ſhort; telling of him that he wears the mark of the beaſt. If he conſents to have his hair cut, after it is done, they
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:017682_0004_0FA21E540B80A420"/>come round him and touch him with their fingers here and there and give him a ſly croſs, and in a very loving way put their hands on his head and then begin to preach their doctrine to him. But this leads me to enter on the third thing propoſed viz.</p>
            <p n="3">3 To ſhew their doctrine, with the ſcripture evidence they bring to prove it.</p>
            <p>They introduce their doctrine with a multitude of good words; ſaying, we muſt hate ſin, love GOD, take up our croſs &amp;c. Then proceed to ſay, in the firſt place, that there is a new diſpenſation taking place, in which the ſaints ſhall reign a thouſand years with Chriſt, and that in that ſtate the ſains ſhall be perfect, and that they have entered into it and that they are the only church in the world; telling the perſon or hearer, that they have all the apoſtolic gifts that were ever given; then they tell the perſon that he has come to the right place for inſtruction, for they only are able to teach; then they pauſe a while to ſee how the perſon receives it, if they find he liſtens, and ſeems to be coming, they proceed and ſay, all the churches now in the world are antichriſt, and falſe churches, and that there is not one perſon born again among them all, and that there has not one gone to heaven for theſe twelve hundred years, no, not ſince the apoſtolic age. If the perſon makes any objections, they tell him he muſt not diſpute, his buſineſs is to hear and receive inſtruction, and all hands will fall to confirming the truth of what is declared: This puts the perſon to ſilence, &amp; then they proceed, with a great laugh, and tell him they have many things to ſay to him, which he is not yet able to bear; this is to engage the perſon to hear. Then, ſecondly, they proceed to ſay, that all exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ordinances, eſpecially baptiſm and the Lord's ſupper, ceaſed in the apoſtolic age; and that GOD has never ſent one man to preach, ſince the apoſtles days, until they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the new diſpenſation, and were ſent by GOD from Great Britain, to call in GOD's elect; and to confirm the truth of what the teacher has ſaid, he (the teacher) falls a trembling, and will ſay he feels the blood of Chriſt, now running down his thigh and leg. Then they tell the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:017682_0005_0FA21E549AC42858"/>he can't bear any more now, but he muſt come again very ſoon and they will tell him more; and thus they with many fawning embraces, part with him for that time.</p>
            <p n="3">3 When he comes again then meet him with great joy, claſp him in their arms, and tell him they have the great love of Gon; and after things are a little ſettled, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with him again, telling him that he muſt confeſs his fins to them, from his childhood, that they may take his caſe, and travail for him, that he may be born again. If he be a profeſſor of godlineſs, and pleads that he hopes his fins are forgiven, and waſh'd away by the blood of Chriſt; they tell him nay, they are not forgiven. They tell him whatſoever is done in ſecret, muſt be revealed on the houſe top: And that they being the church, are the houſe top. Then one takes him alone, and if he confeſſes his fin to him, then he tells it to the reſt: But if it be ſuſpected that he keeps back part of his fin, he muſt confeſs the whole, all being preſent.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They tell him that they ſee angels, and converſe with them, and hear them ſing, and ſing with them; and the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, they alſo freely converſe with. They further tell him, the ſong that they ſing, is the ſong of the hundred and forty and four thouſand, which no man can learn, but only thoſe that are redeemed from the earth. Then tell him, they have got a mother; pointing to a woman, one of their company: And that ſhe ſpeaks ſeventy two tongues, and that when ſhe ſpeaks in unknown tongues, the living people cannot underſtand her; yet the dead underſtand her, for ſhe talks to them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They proceed and ſay, the judgment is ſet, the books are opened, and the dead are now riſing, and coming to judgment, and they are ſet to judge the world: Quoting 1 Cor. vi. chap. 2 verſe. They tell the perſon, that the great tribunal is that church, and that the dead are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming before them every day to be judged. They go on to ſay all that have died in an imperfect ſtate, have gone to hell, or to a priſon ſtate; and there to pay the debt to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine juſtice, by ſuffering; and that there are degrees of puniſhment, which they are to paſs through; great fins, a
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:017682_0006_0FA21E5596BEDC58"/>great degree of hell, ſmall fins, a ſmall hell; And after paſſing through the ſeveral degrees of puniſhment, &amp; pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole debt, out they come, and ſtand before us, (ſay they) and are acquitted, and go home to heaven; they quote for proof, Pſal. xvi. 10. Pſal. lxviii. 18. Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel xvi. 44—61. 1 Peter, iii 18, 19, 20. 1 Peter, iv. 6.</p>
            <p>They comment on thoſe texts thus: Did Chriſt go to hell? Yes. When? Why when he was crucified. What did he go there for? Why, to preach to the ſpirits in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. What did he preach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them? Why the goſpel. Why did he preach the goſpel to the old world, or to the dead? Why that they might be judged as unconverted ſinners, but finally live, according to GOD in the ſpirit, after they have paid the debt in ſuffering.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They ſay, that the forecited woman, about forty years of age, is the woman ſpoken of in the xiith chapter of the Revelations of John, who was clothed with the ſun, having the moon under her feet, and on her head a crown of twelve ſtars; and that ſhe has travail'd and bro't forth the man child. Further, that ſhe is the mother of all the elect; and that ſhe travails for the whole world; and that no bleſſing can come to any perſon, but only by and through her; and that in the way of her being poſſeſſed of their ſins, by their confeſſing of them, and repenting of the fame, one by one, according to her direction.</p>
            <p n="7">7. They hold themſelves ſo far immortal, that they ſhall never die, but ſhall be changed in the twinkling of an eye, and go from this to the upper regions; and that now, they are above all temptations and ſufferings, and can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be lifted up or caſt down; only as they ſuffer in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail for the elect. I might ſtill proceed much further on this head; but as it will neceſſarily fall into their inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to their adherents, I paſs by it for the preſent, and ſhall proceed,</p>
            <p n="4">4. To ſhew their manner of worſhip (if it may be ſo called)</p>
            <p>The manner and form of their worſhip is entirely new, and different from all others: It differs but little on the Sabbath from any other day: They begin by sitting down
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:017682_0007_0FA21E55F7D75190"/>and ſhocking their heads in a violent manner, turning their heads half round, ſo that their face looks over each ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, their eyes being ſhut; while they are thus ſhaking, one will begin to ſing ſome odd tune, without words or rule; after a while another will ſtrike in; and then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and after a while they all fall in and make a ſtrange charm:—Some ſinging without words, and ſome with an unknown tongue, or mutter, and ſome with a mixture of Engliſh: The mother, ſo called, minds to ſtrike ſuch notes as makes a concord, and ſo form the charm. When they leave off ſinging, they drop off, one by one, as oddly as they come on; in the beſt part of their worſhip, every one acts for himſelf, and almoſt every one different from the other; one will ſtand with his arms extended acting over odd poſtures, which they call ſigns; another will be danc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſometimes hopping on one leg about the floor; another will fall to turning round ſo ſwift, that if it be a woman, her clothes will be ſo filled with the wind, as tho' they ware kept out by a hoop; another will be proſtrate on the floor; another will be talking with ſomebody; and ſome fitting by ſmoaking their pipes; ſome groaning moſt diſmally; ſome trembling extremely; others acting as tho' all their nerves were convuls'd; others ſwinging their arms with all vigour, as though they were turning a wheel, &amp;c. Then all break off and have a ſpell of ſmoaking, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times great fits of laughter.—They have ſeveral ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes in a day eſpecially on the Sabbath. When they go to eat, they fit down, and have a ſpell of ſinging and ſhaking the head at the table, before they eat; ſometimes they kneel down, ſhake their heads and groan, ſay nothing, and then fall to eating, and will be very merry and airy. If one has done eating before the reſt, he kneels down, ſhakes his head a ſpell, and off he goes and leaves the reſt eating; ſo each one diſmiſſes the table for himſelf: But it is impoſſible to point out any exact form; for they vary and differ, and ſeldom act the ſome form exactly over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. They chuſe ſo to do, to be ſingular, leſt, as they ſay, they ſhould be connected with Babylon. Every day their worſhip is ſimilar to what has been obſerved. They
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:017682_0008_0FA21E56E2ED0A40"/>have no public prayer, no preaching, and but little read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Their actions in worſhip is according to the dictates of the ſpirit that governs them; then they profeſs, faying, they are in a ſpiritual diſpenſation.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wn as far as may be, their manner of worſhip, I proceed 5thly, to ſhow the directions which they give to thoſe that come to them to be inſtructed.</p>
            <p>When any perſon goes to them to be inſtructed, they enquire of him, whether he has given his vote and money for the defence of the country, and preſently tell him it is contrary to the goſpel to bear arms, ſaying Chriſt's kingdom has not of this world; they labor to convince him that it is a great error to have any thing to do with war and fighting: they directly tell him, he is not born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and that he muſt obſerve their inſtructions in order that he may attain to the new birth — Then they tell him, he muſt confeſs his ſin to them; for if he hides his ſin, they can do nothing for him: They further tell him, if he refuſes, they can tell him all his ſin that he ever committed; and pretend that he can keep nothing hid from them; and when they have frightened him to a confeſſion then they further tell him, he muſt renounce and abſtain from all the works of the fleſh; telling him, that the firſt fall of our firſt parents, was carnal copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that this ruined the world; and that every one that has any thing to do with man or women in the work of generation, is acting Adam and Eve's ſin over again: They tell the man to abſtain from his wife, the woman from her huſband, and that if the wife doth not agree to it, the huſband muſt put her away; and if the huſband will not agree to it, the wife muſt leave her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; and for an example, the mother, ſo cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, did tell how ſhe left her huſband, in New York and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the men, how he left his wife in England. They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> young men and young women if they marry, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve any thing to do with the works or lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts of the fleſh they can never be born again: They ſhew the neceſſity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving this inſtruction, by quoting Rev. iii. 3. 4. 5. They dwell more on this part of their inſtructions than
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:017682_0009_0FA21E5786D78E70"/>all the reſt. They tell their adherents, if they conform to their inſtructions in this point, there is no ſear of their being born again; but if they diſobey they certainly will be damned. While they are thus inſtructing their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, they ſometimes uſe great ſeverity, and ſometimes, great flattery, to frighten on the one hand and allure on the other; and while they are thus at work with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they come round him, touch him with their ſingers in different places, creſs him here and there, get their hand on his head, and prophecy, that great bleſſings are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid up for him: They preſently make him believe them, and as ſoon as they ſee the ſpirit begin to operate on him, then they tell him, that now he has received the Holy Ghoſt, and now if he diſobeys, it is a gone caſe with him: They tell him, if he had never come to ſee them, and had died in his ignorance without receiving the Holy Ghoſt, he would have gone to hell or a priſon ſtate, and ſuffered a while, and then come out and gone to heaven; but now, if he turns back, there is no forgiveneſs, neither in this world, nor that which is to come; They quote for proof. Matt. xii .32. This is to terrify the perſon, and bring him into an abſolute dependence on them: Then they tell him, he muſt come often to them to be inſtructed, or he will be in danger of being taken by evil ſpirits and bed wrong; and that he muſt not think he can underſtand the bible, or know in any reſpect how to act, but only as he receives inſtruction from them: They tell him they have many things for him, which he is not yet able to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but as faſt as he is able to receive it, they ſhall inſtruct him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Thus the perſon is kept in conſtant expectation of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing new. If the perſon ſeems to be ſober, then one takes him by the hand, and round the floor with him, and make him run and ſkip about, and laugh heartily at him, and will tell him he muſt not be melancholy; and when they get him merry with them, then let him go: Then they tell the perſon, for his admiration, that ſince he has been preſent they have had many of the dead come before them to be judged; and make him believe they know his that's, and know ſuture events, and nothing can be hid from them; telling how people are together, and talking about
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:017682_0010_0FA21E5A01197A98"/>them, and what they ſay, &amp;c. Then they tell the perſon that they ſhall never die, and alſo all thoſe that obey them, and get to be perfect, ſhall never die, but be changed in a moment, and go home body and ſoul: But all the bodies of more than are in their ſins, ſhall never riſe.—They fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tell him, that the hundred and forty and four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, which were ſealed; twelve thouſand out of each tribe, is a work yet to be done; and that they are of the tribe of Benjamin, though the youngeſt tribe, and laſt in the account, yet firſt in the order of being ſealed; and that they are the firſt fruits of that tribe; and that all that are to be brought in in America, will belong to that tribe: And thus, the laſt is to be firſt, and the firſt laſt.</p>
            <p>I might ſtill proceed, on this head; but it would be endleſs to repeat all their inſtructions to their adherents, as they are ever ſtudying new things to keep up the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence and admiration of their diſciples. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore paſs on:</p>
            <p n="6">6thly, To ſhew the power and effect of their inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on their adherents.</p>
            <p>There is a very extraordinary and uncommon power attends their inſtructions; in the firſt place, a total blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as to all their former views, of religion and the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, on the inſtructed, takes place; and then a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuation of the mind, to believe all their teachers ſay.—Preſently, a ſtrange power begins to come on, and takes place in the body, or human frame, which ſets the perſon a gaping and ſtretching; and ſoon ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him a twitching, as though his nerves were all in a convulſion. I can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it to nothing nearer in its feelings than the operation of an clecteriſing machine; the perſon believes it is the power of GOD, and therefore dare not reſiſt, but wholly gives way to it.—Thus the power comes on, more and more; and as the power increaſes, ſo their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> increaſes, in their teachers. If any body oppoſes them it brings on the power quick, ſtrong and violent; and they cry out, on the oppoſer, that he will be damn'd for oppoſing the power of GOD; and fall to twitching and trembling as though they had an extreme fit of the ague. This power as it increaſes, brings on, many times, extreme weakneſs
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:017682_0011_0FA21E5B0EF7F478"/>of body, ſo that their limbs fail them, and they fall to the floor, or on the ground, and lie helpleſs: At other times, it brings on great ſhakings—and ſhrugging of the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders—and tramping about with the feet—diſmal groans and out cries—and perhaps may iſſue, for that time, in great laughter and lightneſs. And in the time of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals, they grow very dum, and ſay but little; and as the power has its fits on them ſo it grows more powerful, till it leads on to what they call ſigns. The power will take their hand, ſtretch it up, pull the other down, they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it—the hand up, it a ſign of mercy, the hand down, of judgment: Sometimes their hand is ſtretched out for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, then away they run after it; if it leads to ſome perſon, they lay their hand on his head,—then croſs their arms, one acroſs the other,—then ſay he muſt take up his croſs, and renounce the works of the fleſh,—then they ſtretch both hands behind them, and ſay he muſt leave the world behind him: Sometimes their hands will be cramp'd up, one finger ſtretched out ſtrait, another down into their hand, and their hand all out of common ſhape: Sometimes their hand will ſtretch out, and after it they run—through woods—croſs lots—over ſences—ſwamps—or whatever, till they come to a houſe; perhaps they will be ſtopt ſeveral times in their courſe, and their head turn them round, as though they had loſt their way; then take a new ſet off and run again; perhaps, when they get to the houſe, they will lie down on the ground—make a round ring with their finger, among the dirt—puther about in it—then ſtart up—double their fiſt at it—run away from it—come at it again—ſhow the looks of vengeance at it—threaten it with poſtures—then run and jump into it, and ſtamp it all to pieces—This ſign they interpret to be the old heavens, which are to paſs away with a great noiſe—When he goes into the houſe, he flatters round with his hands flying, and hiſſing as if he intended to drive all the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s out of the room—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut this, he ſays, is to hunt all the evil ſpirits out, which the houſe is full of.</p>
            <p>After he has done his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, he follows his hand off, without aſking how they do, or bidding them farewell.—Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a they meet together for their worſhip, they fall a
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:017682_0012_0FA21E5BB24BABE0"/>groaning and trembling, and every one acts alone for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; one will fall proſtrate on the floor, another on his knees and his head in his hands, on the floor; another will be muttering over articulate ſounds, which neither they or any body elſe underſtand. Some will be ſinging, each one his own tune; ſome without words in an Indian tone, ſome ſing jig tunes, ſome tunes of their own making in an unknown mutter, which they call new tongues; ſome will be dancing and others ſtand laughing heartily and loudly; others will be a drumming on the floor with their feet, as though a pair of drum ſticks were beating a ruff on a drum head; others will be agonizing, as though they were in great pain; others jumping up and down; others fluttering over ſomebody, and talking to them; others will be ſhooing and hiſſing evil ſpirits out of the houſe, till the different tunes, groaning jumping, dancing, drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, laughing, talking and fluttering, ſhooing and hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing makes a perfect bedlam; this they call the worſhip of GOD. They ſpeak highly of their teachers, and ſay thoſe men at Niſqueunia are the angels of GOD, ſent forth to gather in GOD's elect. Some of them ſay, that the woman called the mother, has the fulneſs of the God-Head bodily dwelling in her, and that ſhe is the Queen of Heaven, Chriſt's wife; and that all GOD's elect muſt be born through her; yea, that Chriſt through her is born the ſecond time. They ſay that that church (as they call it) has power to ſhut the Heaven that it rain not, and to bring on all manner of plagues, as often as they will — They prophecy that this goſpel (as they call it) muſt be preached to all the world, and all thoſe that do not fall in with it will be damn'd. If any body oppoſes them, they get round him, threaten him with damnation, ſtorm and ſtamp at him, ſtare open their eyes, pucker up their mouths and cry oh! oh! oh! at him, and act all the poſtures of vengeance, which is enough to frighten a Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules out of his wits.</p>
            <p>Every one as ſoon as they fall in with this new religion, immediately throw down their arms, and cry out againſt the means of defence made uſe of againſt the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and appear the moſt obſtinate againſt all the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:017682_0013_0FA21E5C6DB06940"/>of the country. I have heard ſome of them ſay, that all our authority, civil and military, is from Hell, and would go there again. The effect of this ſcheme is ſuch, that men and their wives have parted, children ran away from their parents, and ſociety entirely broke up in neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhoods; it makes children deny and diſown their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and ſay they are full of devils. They are continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally throwing out their curſes on all that do not fall in with them; prophecying the deſtruction of the country; declaring they belong to the kingdom of GOD, and at the ſame time, if they were aſked whether they are born again, they will ſay nay. If any perſon goes to reaſon with them, they immediately put their fingers in their ears, or run off out of hearing, or elſe drown <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with clamour, noiſe and curſes: And as their teachers adviſe and order children to run away from their parents, and men to ſhut thin doors againſt their own brethren, by blood, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them any admiſſion into their houſes; all their order are punctually obeyed.</p>
            <p>They make great dependance on their fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, and ſay it is the power of GOD, and GOD has taken that way to preach by them: One of them had a ſign, that a certain man had committed murder, and charged him with it, which the man denied; he again had a ſign, that a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain man intended to kill two children and their mother, on a certain night; then he had a ſign for two of his aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates to go and lay all night behind the houſe, and watch for him, and when they heard the children cry, to ruſh in, take the man and bind him, and bring the man to him; the two men obeyed his orders, believing in his ſign: about break of day he had a ſign, that they catched the man and bound him; however, in the morning, the two men returned, having not ſeen the man. Thus their ſigns in general prove falſe; however they got out this way, that the ſign is true, but they made a falſe interpretation. I knew another, who under the operation of the ſpirit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied, that at the end of two weeks, New London would be deſtroyed, and at the end of four weeks, Albany would be burnt a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the next day the world would be at an end; all which proved falſe. Another had a ſign, that a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:017682_0014_0FA21E5CC36AADF8"/>man, on ſuch a day, would kill him, and on the third day be ſhould riſe again into line and action; which like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe proved falſe. One of their poſtures which increaſe among them is, turning round very ſwift for an hour, and ſometimes for two hours at a time, till they are all wet with ſweat; this they ſay, is to ſhew the great power of GOD.</p>
            <p>They meet together in the night, and have been heard two miles by the people, in the dead of the night; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a company of them will run away to ſome houſe, get into it, raiſe a bedlam, wake up all in the houſe, and the neighbours round about for a mile: They run about in the woods and elſewhere, hooting and tooting like owls; ſome of them have ſtripped naked in the woods, and tho't they were angels, and inviſible and could go about among men and not be ſeen, and have loſt their cloaths, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found them again. Sometimes while eating at the table, they ſay their dead parents and brethren come on the table and ſet on a pye, and they ſee them, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>At one of their meetings, they hung a woman by the neck, but took her down before ſhe was dead, to ſhew as a ſign, how they were to be perſecuted: and now while I am writing, I am informed by good authority, that two men in the ſcheme have murdered themſelves, one cut his throat, the other ſtabbed himſelf, after he had tried twice to kill his wife, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I might proceed much further, but it is as impoſſible to fully ſet forth the power and effects of this new religion, as to trace the airy road of the meteor: I therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, 7thly, to ſhew what this new religion is, as pointed out by ſcripture teſtimony.</p>
            <p>In opening this propoſition it will be neceſſary to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, on the great purpoſes of GOD, which will termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in two grand events; find, the deliverance of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and fulfilling his promiſes to them; Secondly, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the man of ſin. Theſe events will conclude and finiſh the reign of Antichriſt: And the work of GOD in general, has a ſpecial reſpect both in his providence and grace, to the grand concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="unknown:017682_0015_0FA21E5DD1704B60"/>
Every age of the church have had their trials and combats, with the great enemy of GOD and his people; and as GOD's work and deſigns have advanced forward to the power of the enemy has increaſed; and it is very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the laſt ſtruggles of the enemy will be the moſt powerful and dangerous; this GOD ſaw, and in his great goodneſs has advertiſed his people of the deluſions a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors that would take place in the laſt days; knowing that the crafty ſerpent would act over again his ſubtle wiles, in the higheſt pretentions of the greateſt good. We are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by our Lord in Matt. xxiv 24. that falſe Chriſts and falſe prophets ſhall ariſe, and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſhew great ſigns and wonders, inſomuch that if it were poſſible, they ſhould deceive the very elect</p>
            <p>This matter is more fully opened and illuſtrated by the great apoſtle Paul, in his epiſtle to the Theſſalonians, ii. 3-12, he gives advice not to be deceived; for the day of Chriſt ſhall not come before there come firſt a falling away; and that the man of ſin be revealed, whom he calls the ſon of perdition, who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped: So that he as God ſitteth in the temple of God ſhewing that he is God;—he ſhews in the 7th verſe, that it is the great myſtery of iniquity, whoſe coming ſhall be after the working of Satan, with all power, and ſigns and lying wonders, with all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, &amp;c. As this great deluſion is to take place in the laſt days before the coming of Chriſt, we are charged by our Lord to watch, we are therefore to watch the ſigns of his coming, and to watch the motions of the myſtery of iniquity, which if well attended to, it will appear moſt evident, that this is the day in which we may expect to ſee Satan in the highteſt and moſt deluſive machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, having great wrath, knowing that he hath but a ſhort time. Rev xii 12. And while men are looking for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at revolution, or change of times to take place, when Chriſt ſhall reign in and with his church a thouſand years;—Satan finds in the moſt fit ſeaſon to preſent a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, dreſt in the higheſt colours of ſanctity and holineſs; and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> many expect to ſee new things take place in the mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m ſtate; ſo Satan improves his advantage on ſuch, by
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:017682_0016_0FA21E5E4D9C0A10"/>preſenting new religion, new laws, new modes and forms, new churches, new preaching, new doctrine, new views, new diſcoveries, new ſpirit, new bibles, or ſeen in a new light, new heaven and new glory.—And that all old things are to paſs away, no more old religion, no more old modes and forms, old churches, old preaching, and doctrine are to ceaſe; old views, old experiences, and old converſion to be rejected; old friendſhip, old relations, and old love to be known no more. And while the pleaſing picture by the arch enemy is preſented to view, it finds many admirers.</p>
            <p>It is very evident, that this is the very day in which this work of Satan is on the wheel: And notwithſtanding, it may appear unaccountable to every rational mind, that any of the human ſpecie ſhould fall in with ſo diabolical a ſcheme; yet when we conſider i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s fine dreſs of perfection, and the ſpirit of infatuation, and witchcraſt, that attends it, it may form our minds into a belief, that it can be and really is ſo.</p>
            <p>It is further evident, that Antichriſt cannot appear in any other light or path, but only that which Chriſt and his Apoſtles have marked out for it.—I will therefore compare the works and character of Antichriſt with this new and ſtrange religion, as it is delineated and ſet forth.</p>
            <p>The apoſtle Paul, in his ſecond epiſtle to Timothy, iii. 1-9 points out this very people, in this new religion, and ſhew they were to appear in the laſt day, bearing the character of GOD's enemies. Again, in 1 Tim. iv. 1, 2, 3. The Holy Ghoſt points out the doctrines of this new reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and calls them the doctrines of devils, which are taught them by ſeducing ſpirits. Again, 2 Pet. ii 1, 2, 3. Their hereſies are ſpoken of, and of their denying the Lord that bought them. Nothing is more evident then, that the apoſtle points out this very people, for they throw away their converſion and begin to repent of their ſin which they committed in their childhood; and thus to atone and make ſatisfaction, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> own works into a ſtate of perfection; but if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h ſhould overtake them before they get to be perfect, then down to hell they muſt go, to pay the remainder in ſuffering and when they have paid the debt and are born again in hell,
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:017682_0017_0FA21E5F26F9E3D8"/>then to come out and go to heaven; will they thank Chriſt, as the great mediator, and adore him, for his atoning blood and righteouſneſs? No, not at all; Oh, dreadful ſcheme, that ſtands oppoſed to the glorious plan of redemption by Chriſt! Well might Peter and Jude ſay of them, wells without water clouds without rain, twice dead pluck'd up by the roots, wondering ſtars; for whom is reſerved the blackneſs of darkneſs for ever. Again,</p>
            <p>I find goſpel religion ſays, being juſtified by faith, Rom. v. i. but this new religion ſays by works—To decide this matter, I ſhall attend to the apoſtle, in Rom. iv. 4 5. where he ſays, "To him that worketh, is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of debt; but to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteouſneſs" The true chriſtian ſees by faith, lives by faith, walks by faith, fights the good fight of faith, and gets the victory by faith: But the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this new religion, do not ſo much as talk about faith in Chriſt; but they place their whole knowledge in their religion, on their pretended viſions, propheſies and ſigns. Another thing which proves this new religion to be falſe, is what follows—The apoſtle James, in his epiſtle i. 5. ſays. "If any of you lack wiſdom, let him aſk of GOD, who giveth liberally." But this people go to Niſqueunia, to aſk of a number of Europeans, what they ſhall do?—who tell them, agreeable to what I find 2d Peter, ii. 18 19. They ſpeak great ſwelling words of vanity, and allure thro' their much wantonneſs, thoſe that were clean eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from them who live in error; and while they promiſed them liberty, they themſelves are the ſervants of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.—And further, inſtead of attending to the worthy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of our Godly teachers, they are burning all the books of divinity and learning, they come at.—In this new religion, is the whole magazine of error, treaſured up in the great myſtery of iniquity, in which is found all the power of deluſive witchcraft, to blindfold ſouls and lead them to hell. I might cite a multitude of ſcripture i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proof of this point, but ſhall only ſay, the whole cannon of
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:017682_0018_0FA21E5FD7820548"/>GOD's word is levelled againſt this new religion, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth and will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>arnally condemn it, and all its propagators ſhall not be able to ſtand the trial; with which I cloſe this head and proceed,</p>
            <p n="8">8thly, To give ſome reaſons for my knowledge in this new religion, not by mere ſpeculation, but ſorrowful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</p>
            <p>On the 13th day of May laſt, I received a requeſt from a church at Stillwater, above Albany to attend on a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrence, the 25th day of the ſame month; and being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to go, two of my brethren offered to bear me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, provided I would return back by the way of Niſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unia with them to ſee a new &amp; ſtrange people living there. I conſented to their propoſition, in conſequence of their company in my journey, and on the 26th of ſaid May we arrived at Niſqueunia: The Europeans though ſtrangers, received us very kindly, and preſently told us they knew of our coming the day before: this ſet me a wondering at their knowledge. After they had got us ſome victuals, one of them came and ſit down by me and begun to ſpeak many good words, ſaying, I muſt hate ſin have GOD and take up my croſs &amp;c. then went on to tell about a new diſpenſation, and that they had got into it; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is words ſeemed to be ſo well placed, that I heard them with atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Mean while a man, out of their company, ſtands up before me, and began to ſtretch and bend and extend his arms up and down, and to act all manner of poſtures, and turn his eyes almoſt inſide out; I had never ſeen or heard of ſuch actions before, and it ſet me a wondering what he meant. By this time my mind was much engaged, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to one that ſpoke good words and to the other that acted ſo oddly Mean while, he that ſpoke drew near to me and very little while would touch me with his finger; but I thought it was that I might mind well what he ſaid; he likewiſe would give me ſspanſ and put his hand on my head or about me, which took not much notice of. The mother, ſo called, looked very ſmiling came and ſat down, and began to ſing a ſtrange <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with a myſtical voice, in a mixture of words known and unknown, which ſeemed to be a perfect charm.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="unknown:017682_0019_0FA21E608CF4ECD0"/>
After they had been the object of attention for ſome time, I turned my thoughts on my former views of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and found, to my admiration, my mind was turned wholly upſide down; and began to think I had been all my life in a dream about religion—After a further diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of their worſhip, I felt greatly ſhocked and confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yet a ſecret belief kept prevailing, that they were the people of GOD. I tarried all night, but ſat up, hearing and ſeeing thoſe ſtrange things 'till the break of day, in which time they gave me a hint of their purgatory ſcheme, which greatly ſhocked my mind: In this tumult of tho't I left them in the morning, about eight o'clock, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home.</p>
            <p>In a very ſhort time I found a power come on me, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from what ever I had felt before, and made me feel very weak and maugre, and in a little time it ſo affected my nerves, that they gave a twitch, as ſudden as a flaſh of lightning; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt I thought, what can that be? But immediately the anſwer was ready; it is the power of GOD: This made me give way to it, during not to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> it, and immediately it gave me another twitch; it had this effect on me to make me attend to the power, and in ſo doing I tho't I attended on GOD: It never bro't me to what they call ſigns &amp; to ſo great a ſhaking as ſome have; however, I fully believed it was the work of GOD, and yet I found great difficulties to get along; to give up my old experience, appeared a great thing, and to hold them was contrary to the ſcheme. However, I reconciled my difficulties as well as I could, by concluding, that in the new diſpenſation, new things would appear, and greater light would ſhine, and whatever was wanting in my old experience would now appear; yet ſo far as they were they might be good; yet many told me. I would ever be weak in the new, 'till I threw away all the old.</p>
            <p>I went again to Niſqueunia and received further inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Europeans, and ſeemed to be more confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Having given them a relation of my life, they made me many large promiſes of very great bleſſings, and ſtill I remained under the operation of the ſpirit.—But in a little time the effect of this new work in many, appeared ſo
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:017682_0020_0FA21E61553BA370"/>wild, that it troubled me much, and I thought it my duty to ſever between the precious and the vile; which when I began to do, they rose upon me with a diſmal hiſs, and had a ſign to ſtop me; however, I went through againſt their ſigns; and as the work went on, more incoſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhoods appeared which made me repeat a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of ſuch things, and made mention of ſome imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections I had ſeen in their teachers; this made them riſe in ſuch a clamour, hiſs and uproar, as though the infernal den had broke looſe: This gave me ſuch a ſhock, that I could go no further, till I had examined the ſchemo over again. For this purpoſe I attended to my Bible more carefully, and my eyes began to be opened, and the power on me began to decreaſe; but had great threatnings ſent to me from the teachers and others; telling me if I turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back, domnation was my portion — Their propheſies and their ſigns appeared more and more falſe, which ſtill opened my eyes, and gave me great jealouſy, that this new religion was led by a falſe ſpirit, and in a little time the operation wholly left me; my eyes were wide open, and I was as though I had come out of a dark cellar, into the brighten beams of the noon day ſun.</p>
            <p>I am very ſenſible, that the ſpirit which leads on this new ſcheme, is the ſpirit of witchcraft, and is the moſt powerful of any deluſion I ever heard or read of except what I find in Acts viii. 9, 10, 11. If I have been in any meaſure a means of leading any perſon into this wicked and dreadful deluſion, I am very ſorry, and as I heartily rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of my folly, I aſk the forgiveneſs of all, eſpecially thoſe, that like myſelf, have been attending to creatures, inſtead of looking to GOD.</p>
            <p>Having thus given a ſhort, but true relation of this new religion in it, ſeveral parts together with my real and abſolute knowledge of the ſame, by ſorrowful experience, I paſs on to the 9th and laſt propoſition, viz. To cloſe the whole by a word of advice to miniſters and people.</p>
            <div type="address">
               <head>To the MINISTERS of the GOSPEL.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend SIRS,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AS God has called you to the great and arduous work
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:017682_0021_0FA21E62654AF770"/>of the miniſtry, to teach the way of life, and watch over ſouls; it becomes my duty to advertiſe you of the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evils and dangerous errors that are prevailing in our land, that by a timely information you may be able to guard againſt thoſe damnable hereſies, abominable impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and horrible blaſphemies, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ted out in this piece.</p>
               <p>When I conſider the diſtreſſes of my bleeding country, the burthen of war, and want of religion, it may juſtly ſerve, as a ſtrong motive, to engage every true lover of God and his country, to uſe his utmoſt endeavours to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the union, peace and tranquility of the people in the civil ſtate, and to quicken all into action, in the great and momentous concerns of eternity — While the infernal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of an unwearied enemy are ripening into action, in leading ſouls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſtruction, by deluſive charms, it becomes your duty to uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ur utmoſt exertions to prevent their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitous ſhipwreck, by the overflowing deluge of an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite brood of evils.</p>
               <p>The great and glorious doctrines of the goſpel are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended as a ſacred barrier againſt bewitching error: O then endeavour to inculcate in the minds of your hearers, the great mediatorſhip of Chriſt—the neceſſity of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating grace, and a divine faith in God, through the blood and righteouſneſs of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain practical Godlineſs, by carefully and cloſely attending and adhering to every divine requirement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dear Sirs,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THERE never was a day that more loudly called for faithful watchmen, than the preſent time; while we ſee Satan transforming himſelf into an angel of light, and bringing forward his deep laid ſcheme, to undermine the glorious plan of Redemption by Chriſt: And as he at firſt deceived the woman, and made uſe of her to delude the man, ſo he is playing his old prank over again, ſending one woman from the State of New York, and another from the State of Rhode Iſland, who vie with each other, and are as dangerous to the heedleſs paſſenger as Scylla and Charybdes are to the unſkilful mariner. O then! what need is there of ſkilful pilots and experienced helmſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to ſteer the ſhip of Zion, and keep her in the true channel of faith and love to GOD.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="unknown:017682_0022_0FA21E62B8366950"/>
The battle is now begun, Michael and his angels, and the dragon and his angels, are now formed one againſt the other, for the grand deciſion. Now we may expect the whole artillery of the infernal den, charged with error, deluſion and blaſphemy, attended with all the power of helliſh fury, in the laſt ſtruggle of the enemy.</p>
               <p>Now, therefore, you are to fight againſt all the powers of darkneſs, and withſtand Satan, not only in his malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant rage and envy, but alſo in his deceitful flatteries and counterfeit friendſhip. For the old enemy of GOD and his people, like a grand politician, will try every method, by power, fraud &amp; lies, to carry his diabolical deſigns into execution. You need therefore the whole armour of GOD, that you may be able to withſtand and having done all to ſtand; but there is no fear to them that put their truſt in Chriſt, who will again come up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the fields of Edom, glorious in his apparel, travelling in the greatneſs of his ſtrength, and will trample his enemies in his fury, and ſprinkle his garments with the blood of his enemies. You know your leader and where your ſtrength lies; it is your duty to attend cloſely to his directions that you may be powerful in your warfare, to pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> down the ſtrong holds of ſin and Satan, and in ſo doing ſave yourſelves and them that hear you, and at laſt receive a crown of righteouſneſs which the Lord, the righteous judge, will give at that day.</p>
               <p>Dear Fathers in Chriſt, I cloſe my addreſs to you, by wiſhing you the bleſſings of GOD in your pious labours to promote religion and virtue, and the advancement of the Redermer's kingdom. I commend you to GOD, and the power of his grace, who is able to make you ſucceſsful in building up your churches in the moſt holy faith, and at laſt to give you all an inheritance among them that are ſanctified.</p>
               <p>I now turn myſelf to the people in general. My dear countrymen, I am deeply affected at the fearful omens of impending deſtruction that ſo loudly threaten our bleeding land. Surely GOD is angry, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>okens of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure are plainly diſcovered. It is a day that calls for lamentation and mourning, repentance and reformation; it is for our ſin that GOD has permitted the ſword to be
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:017682_0023_0FA21E64430BE840"/>unſheathed upon us; and tyranny to clank its chains and threaten us with ſlavery. Notwithſtanding it was our duty to look to GOD for help, and in an humble dependance on him, to ſtand forth in our defence, againſt a cruel ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; yet how has our armies degenerated into nurſeries of impiety, and the contagious diſtemper that we have been oppoſing, ſpread itſelf in our land? Vice and immorality abounds; ſtupidity and prophaneſs prevails; ambition and diſcord has been a growing evil; and how many of our countrymen, loſt to the tender feelings of the human heart, been found more cruel than the Oſtrich. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny traiterous plans have been formed for our blood and treaſure, by a banditti of infernal miſcreants? And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding GOD has prevented, and his good providence blaſted the deſigns of thoſe Cain's and Judas's, that have combin'd againſt us, yet how have we forgot the danger, without being found in ſuitable returns to GOD.</p>
               <p>The great enemy of GOD that has filled the world with uproar, war and death, has ever envied the recovery of man by a glorious Mediator; and has ever been trying to circumvent the merciful deſigns of GOD, through Chriſt, for the ſalvation of ſouls. And in addition to all his ſubtil wiles he takes the advantage of the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y of religion and virtue, and makes it his opportunity to play his magic games attended with the doctrine of purgatory, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the creature inſtead of the Creator, and an earthly and creature tribunal, to bring the whole creation of men to trial. The ſcheme is ſo naked and ball'd, with all its ſplendid ſhew of perfection, that every rational mind would recoil at the thought of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lling in with ſuch a dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical plan, was it not for a bewitching power that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it, which turns every thing upſide down, and puts darkneſs for light, error for truth, bitter for ſweet, and hell for heaven.</p>
               <p>Multitudes have fallen in with this dreadful ſcheme, and are ſo infatuated in their ſenſes that they are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of their reaſon, and paſt recovery unleſs GOD inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for them. While the leaders of this dreadful cataſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trophe, like the bowels of Aetna, are ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ing up their ſulphur; like wild-fire it flies, and catches at a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:017682_0024_0FA21E64F8A995B0"/>and ſpreads like a plague. For ſuch a deluſion to take place in the land, loudly proclaims the judgment of GOD. For a people to be carried away with the power of error, beſpeaks their great darkneſs and ignorance of the truth.</p>
               <p>Men, Brethren and Fathers, ſuffer me to addreſs you with a word of advice. One great end and deſign of this piece is to timely advertiſe you of the growing evils that are prevailing in our land, eſpecially the fatal deluſion ſet forth in this narrative. Conſider the great and noble end of your creation. You were not made to be the meer play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things of time, nor to furniſh Satan with materials to carry on his dark deſigns and horrid intreagnes againſt the Moſt High, but to honor and glorify GOD. Therefore, for this great end and purpoſe, break off from ſin of every kind, encourage religion and virtue in each other; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully attend to the dectrine and advice of your godly teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; liſt up your hearts in your deſires to GOD, for his holy ſpirit to enlighten and lead you into the truth; cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attend to the word of GOD, make it the man of your counſel. Let all your conduct ſpeak forth your belief of the Deity, and judgment to come; and by becoming holy we ſhall be a happy people, and ſhall ſee the return of GOD's bleſſings, Satan diſappointed and blaſted, and the glorious kingdom of Chriſt advancing. I cloſe my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to you, by heartily recommending to your ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration the great duty of guarding againſt thoſe dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous errors, and deſtructive deluſions, which lead the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided ſoul into the endleſs mazes and winding labyrinths of trouble and ſorrow.</p>
               <p>And may GOD preſerve you and lead you to himſelf, through faith in Jeſus Chriſt, with which I cloſe, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe myſelf the public's real friend and humble ſervant,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Valentine Rathbun, (Miniſter of the Goſpel.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>PITTSFIELD,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Dec.</hi> 5, 1780.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
