<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon, delivered at the First Church in Boston, March 13th, 1785: occasioned by the return of the society to their house of worship, after long absence, to make way for the repairs that were necessary. / By Chales [sic] Chauncy, D.C. and Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, established in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts.</title>
            <author>Chauncy, Charles, 1705-1787.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04">2009-04.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N14942</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N14942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 18953</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APY2064</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">18953</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99029139</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 18953.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N14942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 18953)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 18953)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon, delivered at the First Church in Boston, March 13th, 1785: occasioned by the return of the society to their house of worship, after long absence, to make way for the repairs that were necessary. / By Chales [sic] Chauncy, D.C. and Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, established in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts.</title>
                  <author>Chauncy, Charles, 1705-1787.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23, [1] p. ;  22 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Greenleaf and Freeman, north side the market,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M,DCC,LXXXV. [1785]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Dr. Chauncy's sermon, delivered at the First Church in Boston, March 13th, 1785.</note>
                  <note>Two states of the title page noted. In one, "Boston" in the title is misspelled "Boson"; in the other it is spelled correctly.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>First Church (Boston, Mass.).</term>
               <term>Sermons --  1785.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:018953_0000_0FA9063F41FE25A8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:018953_0001_0FA90640054E6DD0"/>
            <p>Dr. CHAUNCY's SERMON, DELIVERED at the FIRST CHURCH IN BOSTON, MARCH 13th, 1785.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:018953_0002_0FA90640EAD49598"/>
            <p>A SERMON, DELIVERED at the FIRST CHURCH IN BOSTON, MARCH 13<hi>th,</hi> 1785: OCCASIONED BY THE RETURN OF THE SOCIETY TO THEIR HOUSE of WORSHIP, AFTER LONG ABSENCE, TO MAKE WAY FOR THE REPAIRS THAT WERE NECESSARY.</p>
            <p>BY CHALES CHAUNCY, D. D. And FELLOW of the AMERICAN ACADEMY of ARTS and SCIENCES, eſtabliſhed in the COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONWEALTH of MASSACHUSETTS.</p>
            <p>BOSTON, Printed by GREENLEAF and FREEMAN, North ſide the MARKET, M,DCC,LXXXV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="unknown:018953_0003_0FA90645E5290408"/>
            <head>A SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>I. KINGS, viii, 27.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But will God in very deed dwell on earth? Behold the heaven, and heaven of heavens, cannot contain thee, how much leſs this houſe that I have built?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Jewiſh nation were now aſſembled at Jeruſalem, to devote the Temple they had built there to an obſervance of the public ſervices of piety; and king Solomon, in their name, and as their mouth, adores that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious being, whom the heaven of heavens cannot contain, humbly ſupplicating that he would graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly condeſcend to hearken to the cry of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple when they ſhould pray to him in this houſe: in imitation of ſo pious an example, let us, upon our return to our houſe of worſhip, after long abſence, to make way for its being ſo repaired as to be comfortable and convenient; let us, I ſay, make it our prayer, that the God who dwelleth on high would hearken to our ſupplications when we pray
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:018953_0004_0FA9064777CB6E98"/>
in this place, and that his ears may be open, both night and day, to hear in heaven, and do for us according to the greatneſs of his mercy in Chriſt. And, as we are now aſſembled to pay a religious regard to the public offices of piety, may it pleaſe God to enable you, with an engaged ſeriouſneſs, to attend to what may now be offered to lead you, ſo far as I am able, into an intelligible, though inadequate idea of the truth meant, when it is ſaid of God, in my text, that <hi>the heaven of heavens can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not contain him, much leſs any houſe built with hands</hi>; and to ſhew you that this is a real truth. I ſhall be as brief as poſſible upon theſe points, that I may have time and ſtrength to enlarge upon ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections as are important in themſelves, and may be ſeaſonable for us to conſider and improve under preſent circumſtances.</p>
            <p>ACCORDING to this method I would begin with ſaying, that, when God is repreſented as not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the heaven of heavens, much leſs in any houſe built with hands, his OMNIPRESENCE is the truth intended to be conveyed. It would be a wrong ſentiment of God, ſhould we conceive of him as confined to heaven, or earth, or any particular place in theſe worlds; for he is, if I may ſo ſpeak, diffuſed all over heaven and earth, yea, all parts of the univerſe; inſomuch, that he is no where excluded, but as truly preſent in every place, as in any place at all. It may ſeem to us, as though the ſpace that is occupied by created bodies and ſpirits would exclude the preſence of God, at leaſt from theſe parts of ſpace. But this is owing to our ignorance of God, our incapacity of conceiving juſtly of the MANNER in which
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:018953_0005_0FA9064788E1DD60"/>
he exiſts. He exiſts in all other exiſtencies. His preſence pervades their very ESSENCE. There is no ſuch thing as poſſeſſing exiſtence where God is not preſent; there is no going where he is not. To this purpoſe is that beautifully ſtriking language of the inſpired David, in the 139th Pſalm, <hi>Whither ſhall I go from thy ſpirit? or whither ſhall I flee from thy preſence? If I aſcend up into heaven, thou art there: if I make my bed in hell, behold thou art there: if I take the wings of the morning and dwell in the uttermoſt parts of the ſea, even there ſhall thy hand lead me, and thy right hand ſhall hold me. If I ſay, ſurely the darkneſs ſhall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me, even the night ſhall be light about me; yea, the darkneſs bideth not from thee, but the night ſhineth as the day: the darkneſs and the light are both alike to thee.</hi>" The preſence of God knows no bounds. It is not limited to this or any of the other worlds that conſtitute the univerſe. Thoſe, we have abundant reaſon to believe, are vaſtly nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, as well as large, taking up an inconceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble extent of ſpace. But we may not think, that they are the boundaries or limits of the Deity's preſence. He not only fills theſe worlds, and every place in them, but that whole extra mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dane ſpace in which almighty power might ſtill be diſplayed in making new worlds beyond the utmoſt ſtretch of the imagination of men or angels.</p>
            <p>THE ſcriptures, it is true, ſpeak of God as <hi>dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in heaven,</hi> and <hi>coming down from heaven to earth.</hi> It repreſents him as having had his <hi>reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the tabernacle</hi> erected by Moſes; and as leaving that, and taking up his <hi>abode</hi> in the <hi>temple</hi> that was built by Solomon. But theſe are figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:018953_0006_0FA90648A5792F78"/>
modes of expreſſion, not intended to lead us into an apprehenſion, as though God was not at all times equally preſent, in regard of his exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in all places whatſoever; but to give us to underſtand that <hi>heaven</hi> is the place where he moſt conſtantly and gloriouſly makes it appear that he is preſent; and that the <hi>tabernacle</hi> of Moſes, and the <hi>temple</hi> of Solomon, were for a while, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the pleaſure of God, the places from whence he ſaw fit to make manifeſt his preſence by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications of mercy or judgement. He was as truly preſent in all other places of the earth, as in this tabernacle and temple; though not to the ſame purpoſes of manifeſtation. And he is now, and has all along been, as really preſent on earth, and in every part of it, as in heaven itſelf; though heaven is the place where he makes it apparent, in the higheſt and nobleſt ſenſe, that he is preſent: and he is accordingly ſaid, after the manner of ſpeaking among men, to <hi>be</hi> there, to have <hi>his throne</hi> there, and to <hi>live and dwell</hi> there. The plain truth is, notwithſtanding the modes of ſpeech which have been mentioned, which, though figurative, and borrowed from comparatively low ſimilitudes, are well adapted to human weakneſs; I ſay, that notwithſtanding theſe modes of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we muſt conceive of God as abſolutely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confined in the extent of his exiſtence, as being at once preſent throughout the univerſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it, in all places, and in all ſpace, without bounds and limits. And reaſon concurs with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation in leading us into this idea of God.</p>
            <p>WE are aſſured, from the regular exerciſe of our reaſonable powers, that the God we believe
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:018953_0007_0FA9064903F48ED8"/>
in, and worſhip, is an infinitely perfect being; and if he is infinitely perfect, he muſt be unlimited in the extent of his exiſtence. Theſe ideas are inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably connected with each other. We find, by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that we, who are the higheſt order of beings in this lower world, are confined in our exiſtence within a narrow ſphere, not being able to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent but in one place at the ſame time, and being equally unable to move from this place to that but within certain limits, and in certain periods of time: and from hence we certainly know, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we feel it to be true, that we poſſeſs exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in an imperfect degree only, as it is thus bounded in its extent: and from hence alſo we can readily perceive, that, by enlarging the extent of exiſtence in our imaginations, we ſhall have an idea of it as ſtill more perfect; and by enlarging it to the utmoſt of our capacity, and then, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it ſtill capable of enlargement beyond all bounds, we come as near as our intellectual pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers will permit, to exiſtence that is infinitely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. And ſuch exiſtence muſt be attributed to God. He muſt be ſuppoſed to fill heaven and earth, all worlds, all things, all place, all ſpace with his boundleſs and unlimited preſence; or his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence will be leſs perfect than it might be, that is, he will not be an abſolutely perfect being, or, in other words, he will not be God. The argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, from natural reaſon, is equally ſtrong in proof of all the perfections of God. As he is a ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtent Being, without beginning to be, or deriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he is from any other, there is the ſame reaſon to aſcribe to him one perfection as another, and every perfection without limitation in degree. There is therefore, upon the foot of reaſon, as
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:018953_0008_0FA90649EB5F93A0"/>
good grounds to think, that he poſſeſſes abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extenſive exiſtence, as that he poſſeſſes it at all. For what is there that ſhould limit his exiſtence, confining it within theſe or thoſe bounds? We know of nothing, we can conceive of nothing; but are unavoidably led to think, from his having exiſtence at all, that he is not confined within any ſuppoſable bounds, but is univerſally diffuſed, filling all worlds, all things, and all ſpace.</p>
            <p>BUT the omnipreſence of God is the doctrine of revelation, as well as of reaſon. The ſacred books that contain the revelations of God, it is true, do not enter upon a philoſophical conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of any of the divine attributes; but treat of them principally in a way that is adapted to anſwer the ends of piety. And thus it ſpeaks of the "preſence" of God; not concerning itſelf ſo much about its ſtrict philoſophic notion, as to lead us into ſuch ſentiments with reference to its extent, as may be of moſt uſe to the purpoſes of religion. And it ſufficiently gives us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that it is amazingly extenſive, not being confined to heaven, but diffuſing itſelf ſo as to fill both heaven and earth. The language of the bible is emphatically ſtrong to this purpoſe. Says the prophet Jeremiah, perſonating the great God himſelf by commiſſion from him, <hi>Do not I fill heaven, and earth?</hi> The inſpired David, in the 139th Pſalm, very ſtrongly, as well as beautifully deſcribes the bleſſed God, as "preſent every where, in heaven, in hell, in the uttermoſt parts of the ſea;" yea, as "poſſeſſing our very reins." And the great apoſtle of the Gentiles, in making known the one true and living God, to the ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:018953_0009_0FA9064A8078D1B0"/>
people at Athens, deſcribes him to them, Acts xvii. 27, 28. <hi>Not as far from every one of us; for in him we live, and move, and have our being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IT may not be unworthy of notice here, that the omniſcience and omnipreſence of God involve each other; at leaſt, they are ſo nearly and cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly connected, that we cannot eaſily, if at all, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of the one without the other. Perhaps, they are inſeparable It may be, God could not be omniſcient, if he was not omnipreſent. Now, the ſcripture is full and expreſs in declaring the omniſcience of God, which is a conſtructive proof of his omnipreſence alſo. He is repreſented as <hi>knowing all things,</hi> whether paſt, preſent or to come. He is ſaid to be well acquainted with even <hi>the hearts of all the children of men,</hi> the devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, imaginations, purpoſes, and moſt ſecret work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yea, we are aſſured, that "<hi>nothing is hid from his allſeeing eye,</hi>" and that he has a moſt clear, perfect, and certain knowledge of all things, not excepting the volitions, and determinations, of free intelligent agents, however, they may be ſecreted from all other beings whatever. The inſpired David, with equal propriety and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, expreſſes himſelf upon this matter, in the 139th Pſalm, <hi>O Lord, thou haſt ſearched me, and known me, thou knoweſt my down ſitting, and mine up riſing, thou underſtandeſt my thoughts afar off. Thou compaſſeſt my path, and my lying down, and art acquainted with all my ways. For there is not a word in my tongue, but lo! O Lord, thou knoweſt it altogether. Thou haſt beſet me behind and before, and laid thine hand upon me.</hi> It is obvious to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that, in theſe words of the holy prophet,
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:018953_0010_0FA9064E1C320098"/>
there is a connection between the knowledge and preſence of God. This is obſervably conſpicuous in the 3d verſe, <hi>Thou compaſſeſt my path, and my lying down, and art acquainted with all my ways.</hi> And it ſhould ſeem as though he had it in direct view to ground the omniſcience of God, of which he had been ſpeaking, upon his omnipreſence, for he goes on, in the following verſe to tell us, there was no <hi>going from his preſence</hi>; for he exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in heaven, in hell, on earth, and even in the hearts of men. A moſt marvellous truth this; but yet, a moſt certain one, as we have ſeen both from reaſon and revelation.</p>
            <p>I NOW proceed to what I had principally in view in the choice of this ſubject, to make the proper reflections which are deducible from it. And,</p>
            <p n="1">I. IF God is preſent every where, then he is equally the object of adoration and worſhip in all parts of the earth, and may reaſonably be prayed to in this, or that, or the other place, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the ſea, or the dry land. For, being omnipreſent, we can be in no place where his ear will not be open to our cry: and he can as well hear, and anſwer our requeſts in one place as another.</p>
            <p>IT is true, ſhould God be pleaſed to ſpecify any one place in diſtinction from another, as the place where he would be applied to, and from whence he would make the manifeſtations of his preſence in the beſtowment of favours; it would now be fit and reaſonable he ſhould be worſhiped in this place in preference to, and diſtinction from, every
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:018953_0011_0FA9064F0ACF8C30"/>
other. And thus it was, reſpecting the Jews of old. The tabernacle, in the days of Moſes, and for ſeveral ages, was the ſpecial place, where God had declared he would be preſent to the purpoſes of manifeſting himſelf in bleſſings to his people. In this place therefore, rather than any other, and in diſtinction from every other, it was their duty, as a nation, to pay their religious homage to him. The Divine preſence, as to its mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation, was removed, in the days of Solomon from the tabernacle to the temple at Jeruſalem. This became now the habitation of God, the place from whence he commanded the bleſſing: and to this place it was that the tribes of Iſrael were obliged to come, from all parts of Canaan, to offer ſacrifice, and pay religious honour to the Deity. But the goſpel of Chriſt makes no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between one place and another. The time has long ſince come, when the command to worſhip him at Jeruſalem, or in any one place in diſtinction from another, is no more in force; but we may pay homage to our Maker in any place whatever. It is of no importance where this is done: only, we muſt "worſhip God in ſpirit, and in truth." Men may, under the influence of ſuperſtition, or to ſerve their worldly ends, conſecrate certain ſpots of ground, and the buildings erected on them; calling them holy, as being, after their conſecration, the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of God, the places where he is more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly preſent than in other places: but it ought to be ſeriouſly realized, that no prieſt, biſhop, pope, or any power on earth, can confine the preſence of the immenſe Being, as to any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious purpoſe, to any houſe built with hands;
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:018953_0012_0FA9064FDA2EE568"/>
nor are there any offices of divine worſhip, but may be as truly acceptable to God in any place, as in the beſt conſecrated temple, provided they are performed "with clean hands and a pure heart."</p>
            <p>IT is obſervable, we read, in the ſacred books, that our Saviour ſometimes preached from the ſide of a fiſhing veſſel, to thoſe who ſtood on the ſhore; ſometimes from the declining part of a mountain; ſometimes in the wilderneſs; ſometimes in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate houſe; and ſometimes in the open field: and he much oftener carried on the worſhip of God, with his diſciples and followers, in ſuch places as theſe, than in the Jewiſh ſynagogues, or even the temple itſelf; which ſurely he never would have done, if his goſpel had not taken away all diſtinction between one place and another; inſomuch, that where ever any meet together in his name, and to worſhip the father through his mediation, they may be ſure of being accepted, if they <hi>lift up holy hands with a pure heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>NOT but that it is highly fit houſes ſhould be erected for public worſhip; for worſhipping God, in a public manner, is both a <hi>moral</hi> and <hi>inſtituted</hi> duty; and being ſo, houſes muſt be built for this purpoſe; otherwiſe people could not come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, at ſtated times, to join as one in paying homage to their Maker.</p>
            <p>IT was under the influence of theſe ſentiments, that the fathers of this church, in ancient times, built the firſt church for public worſhip in this town. It ſtood at a ſmall diſtance from the ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:018953_0013_0FA90650C396C708"/>
corner of the preſent State Houſe. Here they met for public worſhip about nine or ten years. A larger and more commodious houſe was then built in the place where we now worſhip. The firſt ſermon preached in it was on Auguſt the 23d, 1640. If we reckon from this date, that houſe was made uſe of for the public ſervices of religion <hi>ſeventy one years,</hi> when it was reduced to aſhes by the moſt extenſively deſolating fire that was ever known in Boſton. By the beſt accounts I have been able to get, about one <hi>hundred and ten families</hi> were forced out of their dwelling places, ſome of which ſuffered much in their worldly intereſt, others were deprived of all they had. A number of perſons alſo loſt their lives, either by blowing up of houſes, or by venturing too far to quench the flames, or reſcue endangered goods from deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Awfully diſtreſſing indeed was this night, as alſo was the face of our deſolate places the next day. I was myſelf, when a little boy, a ſpectator of the devouring flames, and the deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation occaſioned by them. God grant we may never ſee again ſuch an awful fire. It was not judged convenient to rebuild with wood; and the winter coming on, when brick work could not be well engaged in, it was defered till the ſpring, to which it was owing that <hi>about one year and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven months</hi> were completed before we could meet together in an houſe of our own to worſhip our maker. The firſt ſermon preached in this then new houſe was on May the 3d. 1713. Through the kind providence of him who is <hi>head over all for the good of the church,</hi> no bad accidents, no evil occurrences, have wholly hindered our worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping God in this houſe, till, by the decays <hi>naturally</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="unknown:018953_0014_0FA90651443BFFE8"/>
ariſing from a courſe of years, it became neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it ſhould be repaired. This has been done, thanks be to God, with remarkable harmony among yourſelves, and ſafety to thoſe who have been your workmen. Permit me to rejoice with you on this account, as alſo, that, while your houſe was repairing, brotherly love ſo pleaſingly and conſpicuouſly ſubſiſted between you, and the Siſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Church with whom you united in your atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on goſpel inſtitutions, and that we parted, not with divided hearts, but in the exerciſe of that mutual love which becometh the diſciples of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
            <p>I CONGRATULATE you, my brethren in Chriſt, not in a way of ceremonial compliment, but with that ſincerity which is always proper, when a Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Miniſter is ſpeaking from the ſacred deſk; I congratulate you upon your having repaired this houſe, adapting it with decency and convenience to the purpoſe of your meeting together to pay homage to the ſupreme Governour of the world. I doubt not you entered into <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>courts</hi> this morning with praiſe, making your ſupplications to the father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in ſome ſuch language as that of the 24th Pſalm, uttered upon the Ark's being fixed in the temple of old, built by the ſpecial direction of heaven, <hi>Lift up your heads, O ye gates, and be lifted up ye everlaſting doors, that the King of glory may come in.</hi> You will not imagine, that the God of glory will come down to dwell in this houſe, as he dwelt in the tabernacle built by Moſes, or in the temple built afterwards by Solomon: But he may, and will, if it be not your own fault, dwell in it in a far higher and
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:018953_0015_0FA906522A088F20"/>
better manner, in the ſpiritual ſenſe; that is, to the purpoſes of ſuch graces as ſhall prepare you for admiſſion into his temple, in the Jeruſalem that is above, where you ſhall give glory to God, and the Lamb in all perfection, and ſo as that you ſhall be uninterruptably happy forever.</p>
            <p>THE houſe you have repaired, and in which you begin this morning to pay homage to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity, is, as to external appearance, more convenient and beautiful, than in its former ſtate. May the <hi>ſpiritual glory</hi> of this latter houſe be greater than that of the former. The firſt houſe, I have reaſon to believe, had often the glory of the grace of God through Jeſus Chriſt, manifeſted in it, by the converſion of ſinners, and edification of ſaints in faith, comfort and holineſs, until they were crowned with eternal life. May this glory of the Lord be more univerſally and conſpicuouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played in this latter houſe, under the miniſtrations of your preſent paſtors, and all ſucceeding ones, that it may be ſaid of multitudes that they were born here, in the ſpiritual ſenſe, that they were nurtured here, and carried on from babes in Chriſt, until they attained to the ſtature of men, and were formed to a meteneſs for heavenly glory.</p>
            <p>NEARLY ſixty years, are now compleated, my beloved brethren, ſince I have been with you in the ſervice of the Goſpel; and my labours, I truſt; have not been wholly in vain, notwithſtanding my manifold infirmities and imperfections. Need I an epiſtle of commendation from you? Ye are yourſelves, ſome of you, I have abundant reaſon to believe, my epiſtle, yea rather the epiſtle
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:018953_0016_0FA9065587A882A0"/>
of Chriſt, through a divine influence, accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my miniſtrations, however unworthy, written not with ink, but with the ſpirit of the living God; not in tables of ſtone, but in fleſhy tables of the heart. Such truſt have I through Chriſt, God-ward. And it is my joy now, and may it be my crown of rejoicing in the preſence of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt at his coming!</p>
            <p>I AM now grown old, and unable, through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold infirmities, to go on with the work of the ſacred miniſtry. Thanks be to God you have my ſon in the goſpel to ſupply my place, and he will do it much to your advantage, as he is now in the prime of life, and ſingularly qualified to ſerve the intereſt of Chriſt among you. I am decreaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſhall decreaſe ſtill more and more, but he will increaſe: God grant it may be in all ſpiritual wiſdom and underſtanding, that he may be more and more furniſhed for a maſter-workman in the kingdom of Chriſt. God Almighty bleſs him, and make him, and long continue him, a rich bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to you and yours; and may he be improved by heaven, as an inſtrument of turning many to righteouſneſs, that he may ſhine as a ſtar of the firſt magnitude, in the firmament of heaven, forever and ever.</p>
            <p>I SHALL now conclude with a few words of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, which you may look upon as the laſt and dying words of your aged paſtor from this deſk, as he does not expect to be much longer with you; and my beloved ſon in Chriſt, will I doubt not, join with me in recommending them to you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="unknown:018953_0017_0FA9065666EF50D0"/>IN the firſt place: As that day, which, from the Apoſtle John, and in his ſtile, we call the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>day,</hi> is eminently <hi>the day</hi> on which it is your duty to appear in the courts of the Lord's houſe, be adviſed to make it your delight to rejoice at its approach, and not to ſuffer it to be a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs to you. Be glad at every return of this appointed ſeaſon to glorify God in the houſe of his glory. This was the temper of holy David, and muſt, in a good degree, be your's, or you will not carry in your breaſts, one of the ſtrongeſt proofs, that you are poſſeſſed of that real piety, without which you cannot, upon a ſolid foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hope for the ſalvation of God. Diſtinguiſh yourſelves from thoſe multitudes, in this degena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate age, who are made uneaſy upon ſeeing the light of this day of God, and feel impatient until it is paſſed and gone; and ſet before their view ſuch an example of pious regard to the Lord's day, as may happily tend to excite in them a care of imitation.</p>
            <p>BE adviſed alſo to be ſteady and conſtant in waiting upon God in <hi>the place where his honour dwells.</hi> It is amazing condeſcention in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of heaven, that he will permit ſuch worms of the duſt as we are, to appear in any houſe we may build to meet in to worſhip him. He hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles himſelf to take notice of the adoration of angels: and yet he readily bows the heavens, and comes down, that he may fill his houſes for worſhip with his glory. Will you not then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice at opportunities of appearing in this houſe, where you may hope he will manifeſt his glory? You cannot, in any way, do greater honour to
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:018953_0018_0FA9065684E14C50"/>
yourſelves, or put yourſelves under greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages in order to your obtaining the bleſſing, even live forever more. Do not ſuffer yourſelves to be needleſsly abſent from the houſe of God, but attend there in a ſteady, uniform courſe, on the inſtitutions of divine worſhip. Content not yourſelves with joining in prayer, and in hearing the preached word; but pay all due honour to the ordinance of the ſupper. In obedience to the command of God's King in Zion, neglect not to eat bread, and drink wine, in remembrance of him who died for your ſins, that, by making atonement for them, he might open a way for the diſplay of God's mercy in their pardon. Breaking bread at the table of Chriſt, is a plain, expreſs part of goſpel worſhip, and as proper and ſuitable an one as any that has been appointed to be attended on in his houſe, and as neceſſary an one, in point of obligation, to be regarded by all who call themſelves the diſciples of Chriſt. Let thoſe among you who have hitherto been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindful of their duty, in this ſpecial inſtance, be humbled in a ſenſe of their paſt neglect, and at length be perſuaded to come into the ſteady con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued practice of it, that the attendants at the goſpel ſupper may be numerous, more ſo in the latter houſe than in the former.</p>
            <p>BE adviſed again to come ſeaſonably to this houſe of worſhip, from ſabbath to ſabbath, ſo as that no part of the publick devotion of the ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary may be carried on without your joining in it. You are ſo ſituated, in common with the other chriſtian ſocieties in this town, that you may, with caſe, if it be not your own fault,
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:018953_0019_0FA90657466D2828"/>
aſſemble together ſo nearly at the ſame time, as that you may all unite as one in every exerciſe of publick piety towards God. And it is pity, that any, through careleſſneſs, or any worſe cauſe, ſhould come ſo late to God's houſe, as to loſe the opportunity of bearing their part in beginning the worſhip of God, whether by prayer, reading his holy word, or ſinging to his praiſe. Too common a fault this, in all our churches, and it were to be wiſhed it might be generally amended.</p>
            <p>BE adviſed yet further to take all due care, that the ſervices of God's houſe be performed in a becoming manner. In order whereto, your out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward behaviour ſhould be grave, ſerious, and not, in any meaſure, expreſſive of levity, careleſſneſs, and indifferency, with reſpect to thoſe exerciſes of piety, you meet together to unite in. I am not going to point out to you any particular geſtures of body, whether kneeling, or ſtanding, or ſitting, as moſt decent; nor to ſpeak of any one geſture as ſuited to one part of worſhip, and another as better to another. I ſhall leave this to thoſe who are fond of ceremonial nicety, and imagine God is ſo too. All I aim at ſaying is only this in general, that you ſhould maintain a care of appearing outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decent and reverent in the time of worſhip; reſtraining yourſelves from any thing, either in look, geſture, or behaviour that is light, or vain, or in any reſpect unbecoming the preſence you are in, or the ſolemn duties you are to perform.</p>
            <p>BUT it is not enough that you behave in God's houſe with external decency; but there muſt be alſo the inward reverence of your hearts, in all the
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:018953_0020_0FA906580C83ACA0"/>
acts of divine worſhip you engage in. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, there may be the former where there is not the latter. Your deportment in the houſe of the Lord may be viſibly ſerious and devout, while yet your thoughts may he vainly wandering to the ends of the earth. You may come, and ſit before God in his houſe, and all the while your hearts may be going after coveteouſneſs, pride, ſenſuality, or ſome luſt or other. It is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore enough, that you are externally decent in the time of worſhip, but you ſhould revere and honour the God you adore, in your hearts; bearing it in mind, that he is a ſpirit, and will be pleaſed with no worſhip but that which is performed in ſpirit, and in truth. Whenever, therefore, you come to God's houſe to attend on the inſtitutions of piety, look well to your inward frame of mind, and be above all things careful, that you yield to God the love of your hearts, and ſerve him with true goſpel ſincerity. For God looketh not at the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance, but the heart; and will not therefore eſteem himſelf <hi>ſanctified by thoſe who come nigh him,</hi> unleſs they ſerve him with reverence and godly fear. The upright in their worſhip are thoſe only his <hi>countenance will behold with delight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>FINALLY, be adviſed to exhibit and maintain a conſiſtent character; not imagining that your <hi>whole duty</hi> lies in <hi>ſanctuary devotion,</hi> or that this will atone for the ſins of your lives. It is a ſure truth, and you ſhould impreſs it on your minds as ſuch, that you will only trifle with God in the ſervices of his houſe, if, when you go from it, you behave as <hi>men of the world, whoſe only portion is here.</hi> The whole tenor of your converſation ſhould correſpond
<pb n="23"
                   facs="unknown:018953_0021_0FA90658C93F7650"
                   rendition="simple:additions"/>
to the ſacred exerciſes of <hi>the place where his honour dwells.</hi> You ſhould make it appear to all you converſe with, that the love of God reigns in your hearts. And from love to him, and a principle of unfeigned faith in Jeſus Chriſt, a vein of true chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian piety and goodneſs ſhould run through your whole conduct in life. Holineſs to the Lord ſhould be inſcribed on all your employments and enjoyments. Whether you eat or drink, whether you buy or ſell, or whatever you do, you ſhould do all to the glory of God, and in the name of Chriſt: ſo may you hope, and upon juſt and ſolid grounds, that your ſacrifices of prayer and praiſe, and all your acts of devotion, whether they are offered to God from your cloſet, families, or his houſe of worſhip, will be acceptable to him; and that, from worſhipping and ſerving him here on earth, you ſhall, in proper ſeaſon, have entrance granted to you into the temple of God above, where you ſhall join, with that innumerable company which have been ſelected from the reſt of mankind, in all ages, in ſinging— HALLALUJAHS, TO HIM THAT SITTETH ON THE THRONE, AND TO THE LAMB, FOR EVER AND EVER. AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
