<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter, from Daniel Rathbun, of Richmond, in the County of Berkshire, to James Whittacor, chief elder of the church, called Shakers.</title>
            <author>Rathbun, Daniel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 128 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N15134</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N15134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 19212</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW7285</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">19212</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99013439</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 19212.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N15134)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 19212)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 19212)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter, from Daniel Rathbun, of Richmond, in the County of Berkshire, to James Whittacor, chief elder of the church, called Shakers.</title>
                  <author>Rathbun, Daniel.</author>
                  <author>Rathbun, Valentine, b. 1724.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xi, [2], 14-128 p. ;  18 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the printing-office, near the great ferry.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Springfield, (Massachusetts) :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCCLXXXV. [1785]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An attack on the Shaker community at Nisquennia, N.Y., by an apostate Shaker.</note>
                  <note>Preface signed: V.R. [i.e., Valenite Rathbun?].</note>
                  <note>Parentheses substituted for square brackets in imprint.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whittaker, James, 1751-1787.</term>
               <term>Shakers --  New York (State).</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:019212_0000_0FAA674628C52240"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:019212_0001_0FAA6746775BA568"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM DANIEL RATHBUN, Of RICHMOND, in the County of <hi>Berkſhire.</hi> TO JAMES WHITTACOR, Chief Elder of the Church, called SHAKERS.</p>
            <p>SPRINGFIELD, [MASSACHUSETTS] PRINTED <hi>at the</hi> PRINTING-OFFICE, <hi>near the</hi> GREAT FERRY. MDCCLXXXV.</p>
            <p>1785</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="unknown:019212_0002_0FAA67472EAFD3F8"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>COURTEOUS READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE following ſheets by the author will inform you, that in theſe laſt ages of the world, the myſtery of iniquity has advanced near to its perfection. It may be a queſtion with ſome, whether the following piece is a true relation of thoſe facts declared, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may looſe its weight and authority in ſuch minds. Under this view of the matter, I think it my duty to endeavour to enforce the truth of ſaid piece, by ſhewing firſt my acquaintance with the ſeveral matters inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 2dly. By acquainting the reader with the character of the author through the general courſe of his life. 3dly. By ſhewing the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives that induced the author to write the following piece, letterwiſe to <hi>James Whittacor.</hi> 4thly. To alarm, awaken, and quicken all to watchfulneſs in this day of dangers.</p>
            <p>Firſt then—Reſpecting my knowledge and acquaintance with the ſeveral matters inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the author's piece. Ever ſince the firſt appearance of the European ſcheme, I have had a careful and watchful eye on it; and conclude I have kept pace with it in my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations,
<pb n="iv" facs="unknown:019212_0003_0FAA6747ED30C578"/>and am fully ſenſible of the truth of ſaid piece in a general view; tho' there may be ſome particular things in ſaid piece which I have not ſeen with my eyes and heard with my ears; yet I have no doubt of the truth of them, if I may judge of the product from the principle. I fully know their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines in general—particularly as to their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of perfection; the doctrine of one ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme earthly head; the doctrine of an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tribunal, to judge the whole world; the doctrine of the reſurrection day being now come; the doctrine of the dead daily riſing by thouſands; the doctrine of making ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for ſin committed by ſuffering here or in hell, and after payment is made, then to receive redemption and go to heaven; the doctrine of celibacy; the doctrine of a new diſpenſation, in which they are beyond the bible; the doctrine of miracles done among them, and many other doctrines, too tedious to mention in a preface. I am fully ſenſible, that their doctrines in general exactly agree with the doctrines of the church of Rome, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not only been acquainted with the Romiſh religion by hiſtory; but having been in the Romiſh dominions, and ſeen and heard for myſelf; but I really think that in the church of Rome, the miſtery of iniquity never aroſe to ſo high a key as it has in theſe people call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="v" facs="unknown:019212_0004_0FAA6748B8131270"/>Shakers; and if it be poſſible in thoſe Shakers, the devil has outdone himſelf. As to the practice and conduct of thoſe people called Shakers, I really think the author of the following piece inſtead of exaggerating, and carrying things beyond the truth, has fell almoſt infinitely ſhort of what might be ſaid with truth. I think it not neceſſary in this ſhort information to enter the liſt of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars in their conduct; for it would be as impoſſible to preſent the whole to view, as to found the ocean where there is no bottom, or to count all the ſtars in the heavens.</p>
            <p>2dly. I come to acquaint the reader with the character of the author to the following piece. As to his general character through the world, I am under peculiar advantages to know it—he being brought up with me, and for a ſeries of about fifty years, my connection and acquaintance has been continued, and I muſt own; acknowledge and declare, that I never knew of any blot, blemiſh, or ſcandal ever cleaving to him, or his character, any more than what is common in the beſt of men, who are all ſubject to the common infirmities of human nature. I ever found him a ſtrictly honeſt man in all his dealings; and for many years he has been a profeſſor of religion, and a member of a church. And as I was conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with him often, while he was writing the
<pb n="vi" facs="unknown:019212_0005_0FAA67496D0D7280"/>following piece, I ever found him exceeding careful in his writing not to go beyond his knowledge in things, and to uſe as ſoft terms as poſſibly would do, to give any idea of the matter. And I have ever found him remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably free from prejudice againſt the Shakers, which is a thing rarely to be found among thoſe that have ſuffered leſs than he has by them. It is therefore my opinion, that the publick may freely receive his piece as the real truth. There is one thing that may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſtumble ſome minds, which is, that ſuch a man ſhould be taken in by ſo diabolical a ſcheme; but in anſwer to this, it may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membered what we read in the prophet Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iel, 11 chap.—35 verſe, and ſome of them of underſtanding ſhall fall to try them, and to purge, and to make them white, even to the time of the end; and again, when we conſider the power of Anti-Chriſt, that if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the elect ſhould be deceived by it, while it appears in the deceivable dreſs of high ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity and holineſs in this day of declenſion, in which many errors abound. The conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which may remove thoſe doubts and open the way for charity to be exerciſed. But if any are ſtill diſpoſed to wonder, then there is a greater wonder, then why the author of the following piece was taken in by the Shak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which is, how our father Adam came to
<pb n="vii" facs="unknown:019212_0006_0FAA674A38536348"/>fall into ſin, who was perfect, and without any ſinful propenſities in his nature, as he came out of the hands of God? When this queſtion is anſwered, the other may be reſolved more eaſily. The author's hope was of greater good in which he fell, and ſo was Adam's, for which he fell.</p>
            <p>I now proceed to the third thing propoſed, by ſhewing the motives that induced the author to write letterwiſe to <hi>James Whittacor.</hi> Firſt. As James Whittacor is the chief Elder, and has the whole controul of his church and all its diſciples, the author has therefore wrote to him, and laid in his objections againſt him and his ſcheme, in order thereby to convince him if poſſible of his ill policy and wicked craft in his grand deception impoſed on man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind—and that it might check his wild career for the future.—2dly. Another motive that induced the author to write letterwiſe was, that the diſciples of ſaid Whittacor might be convicted by it, eſpecially reſpecting them, as well as their leaders, that ſo they might be recovered from the ſnares of death before it be too late, and brought to the knowledge of the truth as it is in Jeſus Chriſt. 3dly. A third motive that induced the author to write letterwiſe was, that as his greateſt difficulty was with ſaid Whittacor, and not being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to ſtate his objections, and tell him his
<pb n="viii" facs="unknown:019212_0007_0FAA674AEB70FCA8"/>faults face to face, the author therefore tho't it his duty to keep as near the rule of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel as might be in writing to him in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, that ſaid Whittacor might take it to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and have fair opportunity to make anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in his own vindication; or to confeſs his faults and make ſatisfaction. Or finally at laſt, to be left without excuſe in the day of trial. 4thly. A fourth motive that induced the author to write letterwiſe was this, The author was not inſenſible that in every ſubject that belongs to the ſyſtem of truth, the moſt eligible method would be to divide the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject into as many propoſitions as naturally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, and conſider each one in its ſeveral parts—all which will coincide one with another.</p>
            <p>But in the ſubject he has undertaken to preſent to publick view there is nothing but confuſion, inconſiſtency, and oppoſition, even to itſelf. He has therefore choſen ſuch a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod as would give him the largeſt latitude to follow it in all its cramp corners—ſkulking holes, and winding paths, where it hides itſelf from the vulgar eye—for in the way of letter writing there is full liberty to catch the ſeveral parts where they may be found; to reach forward to that which is before, and bring up that which is behind—make refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and inferences at every turn. Theſe are ſome of the reaſons no doubt which moved the author to write letterwiſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="ix" facs="unknown:019212_0008_0FAA674BAE7DFE28"/>
I now proceed 4thly to the alarming con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of what we find contained in the following piece; together with other frauds that lead to deſtruction, that it might awaken and quicken all to a careful watchfulneſs, in this day of dangers.</p>
            <p>When I conſider the privileges both civil &amp; ſacred that we as a people are indulged with, and what might juſtly be expected by God from us as a people in general in humble thankfulneſs, and a wiſe improvement of all his mercies—I ſay the bleſſings of God, both in his providence and grace, lays us under the ſtrongeſt obligations to be a reformed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, holy people; ever being found in ſuitable returns to GOD for all his benefits. But inſtead of this, or ſuch a line of conduct, how ſad is the ſtate of religion, and how much more deplorable is the ſtate of the world in general. A great part of the people irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and profane. Many others that do not ſo much as make a profeſſion of religion, and ſtill many others that make a profeſſion are under the power and dominion of Anti-Chriſt, and counterfeit religion—paſſing for true coin, and none or very few laying of it to heart. Now many, lo here, and lo there, are ſounding in our world, and many powerful inſtruments ſent out by the arch enemy,to ſeduce and lead mankind aſtray, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural product is errour, hereſy, idolatry,
<pb n="x" facs="unknown:019212_0009_0FAA674C86AACD68"/>novelty, and abominable impieties, which are introduced for religion. But a few out of the great whole of the people in our land that are true fearers of God, and ſtand cloathed with his word. The deceivers and deceived have formed and maintained a perfect religious bedlam in our world, while deiſm and atheiſm in conſequence prevail. This indeed is a day of dangers, if I now advert to the corrupt ſcheme diſcovered by the following piece.—There we may find many hundreds of poor deluded people carried captive, who are made perfect ſlaves to their leaders. Many have gone down to the grave thro' labour and hard fatigue, under the orders of their teachers. Many others have broke and deſtroyed their conſtitutions. Many in a decaying and dying ſtate, and yet drove on with ſeverity and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour by their hard hearted Pharoah-like maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, while their leaders live on the ſpoils of their diſciples, and wallow in wealth and caſe, and regale themſelves in rioting and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in chambering and wantonneſs. Theſe things are truly alarming, and ought to wake us up to attention and watchfulneſs; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly while we conſider, that while we are eſcap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one ſnare, another is ready to take us. It is evidently the laſt days of the world, in which every method is taken by the arch ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to ſeduce mankind and deſtroy their ſouls. Every thing is drawing to a cloſe, and ripen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="xi" facs="unknown:019212_0010_0FAA674E9346B140"/>for the final event. The ſtate of mankind by the fall is ſuch, they are oppoſed to noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much as to their own ſalvation, in the way God has propoſed, by his Son in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; and therefore every falſe ſyſtem of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is more readily embraced by a blind and ignorant world. What an awful ſurpriſe will all falſe profeſſors meet with in the final con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, when it is too late to recover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Under this view of the matter, let us all watch and pray, leſt we enter into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: and let him that thinketh he ſtandeth take heed leſt he fall.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>From the publick's humble ſervant, <hi>V. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="unknown:019212_0011_0FAA674EC2C601B8"/>
            <head>Contents of the following LETTER.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi>—Objections againſt intemperance.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi>—Againſt a new diſpenſation and miniſtry.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi>—A compariſon with the Papiſts and French Prophets in England, in <hi>1707—8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi>—Of the forbidden fruit and Adam's fall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi>—Of the doctrines of devils, and forbiding to marry.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi>—Of the man of ſin and myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi>—Of the trial of ſpirits by the word and teſtimony of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi>—And laſtly, an Addreſs to chriſtian friends, ſhewing the manner in which the author was led in with and out from among the people called SHAKERS.</item>
            </list>
            <byline>By DANIEL RATHBUN.</byline>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="unknown:019212_0012_0FAA674F90003CB8"/>
            <head>A LETTER, &amp;c. TO ELDER JAMES WHITTACOR,</head>
            <p>AFTER ſo long a connection with you, it appears to me but juſt and reaſonable, that I ſhould let you know the cauſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of my declenſion from you—ſome of which I have made known to you in the courſe of our travels together; but never having my mind anſwered, and that you might have no juſt cauſe of offence, I have now undertook to ſtate my objections in writing, and ſupport them by the beſt authority I can, or lay my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf open to be refuted.</p>
            <p>It is true I ſet out with you in the ſimplicity of my ſoul, not knowing who you was or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bound; but you ſaid Mount Zion—and I was for that; and ſo we went on, and the firſt thing that ever really ſtumbled me was, what I ſaw in the mother at Elijah Wile's, ſhe
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:019212_0013_0FAA675035D23A90"/>look'd very red, and acted to my acceptation, as tho' ſhe had drink'd too hard. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed bro't great diſtreſs and trouble upon me, and how could it be otherwiſe, when I had put myſelf into her hands as an infallible guide, truſting ſhe was perfect; and if ſo, I thought ſhe could not have any licentious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites. This gave me ſome confuſion, but after much trouble and reaſoning about it, I endeavoured to put it out of my mind, and hope the beſt; but 'ere long I was troubled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with ſeeing the ſame thing in her, and in others of the lead; and about the ſame time, many of the brethren being troubled on the ſame account, were chaſtiſed by the church for falſe judging; and reports of this ſort were current about in the world. This indeed gave me ſome doubt of your infallibility; and eſpecially as I knew theſe things were not meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accidental, but common, or at leaſt in time grew very common. Yet I did not mean to ſeperate from you without ſufficient light and ſtrength in my own ſoul, to come off without danger and loſs. It was therefore that I did not, but endured with great trouble and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of ſoul what I cannot expreſs, for above two years ſince I firſt began to complain and open my troubles to you on this account as I had opportunity; but not being convinced that my complaints were cauſeleſs, nor you that the things I complained off were warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:019212_0014_0FAA6750EE00E2D0"/>and ſeeing no reformation; but rather an increaſe, I felt a gradual decline from you, and it could not be otherwiſe, except I could be made ſenſible that vice was no ſin; and if ſo in one thing, why not in all? And though to the pure all things are pure, as you often would plead; yet it is in the temperate uſe of them; for temperance is one of the fruits of the ſpirit, ſee Gal. 5 chap. 23 verſe; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whoſoever goes into exceſſive drinking, is not pure; for nothing more incapacitates or renders them more incapable to ſerve ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God or man. And if all things were pure to you, why ſhould ſuch liberties be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in ſome things even to exceſs and ſome abſtinence in others even to diſtreſs. I think God has given me ſome underſtanding of what is right and what is wrong; therefore if I ſhould ſee any perſon that you or I could name intoxicated with liquor repeatedly and from time to time, ſo that they would ſtumble in their walk and fumble in their ſpeech with an inflamed countenance, and irregular be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, and you ſhould tell me that ſuch an one was the only lead of God ſet up in the world, to whom all ſouls muſt come, and by whom all muſt be ſaved that are ſaved, or made perfect of Adam's race, firſt and laſt, I could not believe it. I ſay I could not believe it; it would be violence upon myſelf to attempt to believe it; nor do I think any can believe
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:019212_0015_0FAA6751A7D03708"/>it but only ſuch as muſt conſequently believe that the commands of God are annulled, the bible out of date, and a new miniſtration ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before heard of taking place; where all things is inſerted, vice is become virtue, and virtue vice. But more particularly at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time I went with the church from Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood to Wooburn and when we arrived at Nathan Kindale's in that place, the mother and elder William took a private chamber and I ſuppoſe lay down to ſleep, for they were there I believe ſome hours before I could ſee them; and at length I went into the chamber and elder William was got up, but he appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me as if he had been drinking very hard, both by his words and actions. I think the Mother was not got up. But the whole ſcene was ſuch as gave me great trouble, and I had afterwards to confeſs my jealouſy. I know that my troubles were very great on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count at that time. At another time I ſaw you ſo much amiſs with liquor at William Mories in the town of Norton, you fumbled in your ſpeech and acted very oddly, ſo that I was exceedingly afraid it would be obſerved by the ſpectators that were preſent. Afterward when the church came to Aſhfield, I think you cannot but remember how many crying ſpells I had about their hard drinking; and how many times I have been chaſtiſed on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for my falſe-juding the church as they
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:019212_0016_0FAA67529A0A4668"/>called it. At another time I having heard that the mother was drunk at landlord Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cox's in New-Windſor, on their way from Enfield to New-Providence, my troubles were ſo hard upon me that I roar'd and cry'd great part of one whole day together, that I was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt down ſick; but afterwards, when the church came through the town of Richmond, on their way to Niſqueunia, they made ſome ſtay among us, at which time I ſaw more of it, and that very apparently at Sam. Fitch's, and the widow Goodrich's; but more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly after they went over into New-Leban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: eſpecially on the day that the mother was carried by authority before <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Grant, there I ſaw ſuch a flagrant proof of what I had in part ſeen and ſo long ſuſpected, that I was now ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied as to this matter. But ſtill ſome how or other I did not leave you till I had ſeen much more of it. At Niſqueunia one time for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral days together I believe the mother was the moſt of the time amiſs with liquor; that ſhe would act I thought ridiculouſly odd, and one time when I was there at Niſqueunia the mother went over to John Partington's, and ſhe was well for what I knew when ſhe went off; but I heard directly that ſhe was under great ſufferings there; and when ſhe return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed I thought ſhe was quite drunk, and I had a fair obſervation of her. Now elder James, I appeal to your own conſcience—deny it
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:019212_0017_0FAA67535AC82BB0"/>if you can, and face God in it. And now to cloſe this point, I refer you to certain paſſages of ſcripture, I. Cor. 5—11, but now I have written to you not to keep company if any man that is called a brother be a fornicator, an idolater, a railer, or a drunkard, &amp;c, with ſuch an one no not to eat. Again, I. Cor. 6—10, nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, &amp;c, ſhall inherit the kingdom of God. And again, Romans 13—13 let us walk honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as in the day time; not in rioting and drunkenneſs, in chambering and wantonneſs, &amp;c. and after this the command of God to me by the Apoſtle Paul, II. Theſſ. 3 chap. and 6 verſe, now we command you brethren in the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that you withdraw yourſelves from every brother that walketh diſorderly, and not after the tradition which ye received of us, verſe 7, for yourſelves know how ye ought to follow us, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus having made my firſt objection againſt your intemperance, which practice is inconſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent with both reaſon and ſcripture, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently with the happineſs of man both here and hereafter, which is one great and grand cauſe of my ſeparating from you.</p>
            <p>I come now to make my ſecond objection, which is againſt your new diſpenſation and new miniſtration, at the head of which the mother is exalted, and prefered above Chriſt, and her apoſtles above the apoſtles of Chriſt;
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:019212_0018_0FAA6753EABAA110"/>in which you go contrary to the miniſtration of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; and in effect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the bible, if I can ſee the conſiſtency of things. For I believe you will not deny but that the mother did go by her immediate gifts of viſions, revelations, and propheſy, as you call them, without any regard to the bible, which I think does produce a miniſtration quite different from either that of Moſes or Chriſt, as appears by ſome ſhocking inſtances, particularly children that were of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, curſing their parents that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, calling them wolves and devils, &amp;c. Again children chaſtiſing their parents in very opprobious language that were believers. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain men and women, parents and children, dancing ſtark naked together; as alſo, men and women, parents and children going into the creek and ſwimming together; and again the mother's pounding and beating the private parts of both men and women in her diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline—theſe things have I ſeen and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that will come in, in their proper places. Now were theſe and ſuch like things are mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, and are eſſential and neceſſary parts of the miniſtration, I and every body elſe that ſees and hears ſuch things, muſt agree that it is ſure enough a new miniſtration, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you would own it or not, it is ſo, becauſe I find no ſuch things miniſtred or commanded in the bible. And now I ſhall inſtance a few
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:019212_0019_0FAA6755D7C290B8"/>of your doctrinal points which you make uſe of in ſupport of your new diſpenſation, new apoſtles and miniſtry. Firſt—It has been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten urged among you that the preſent day is ſeven times greater than that of Chriſt's firſt appearance, and conſequently the preſent miniſtration is ſeven times greater than that of the apoſtles. It was in this view, as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that Samuel Fitch ſaid in my hearing, if I underſtood him right, that the mother was ſeven times greater than Chriſt. And again, he ſaid if I remember right, that Chriſt had been and gather'd his company, and now mother was gathering her company; and that when Chriſt ſhould hereafter appear with his company, mother would alſo appear with her company, making the mother the head of this diſpenſation, as Chriſt was of that, with the addition of ſeven times greater. Elder Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ington alſo ſaid in my hearing at the time when the people returned from the mother's funer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to the houſe that either the mother was, or he believed ſhe was gone to prepare a place for them, and that he believed ſhe was then preſent and heard every word that was ſaid. I will alſo tranſcribe a certain clauſe in Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Scale's letter to me in his own words, wherein he ſays, "two of the leading perſons have ſealed their teſtimony with their blood, whereby it is of force." Theſe are his own words. Now elder James was ever any thing
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:019212_0020_0FAA675696DF9740"/>more abſurd. At another time Joſeph Meech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em told me in anſwer to my queſtion, that you (viz.) mother and elders were got beyond all that was written; if he denies this article as he ſeemed to do when I was at church laſt, it would deſtroy all my charity for him. I think the ſame has apparently tranſpired in your general doctrine in ſuch like expreſſions as theſe, the ſcriptures were good in their day, but nothing to us in this new diſpenſation; and would often chaſtiſe me for believing and holding to what was written in the bible—calling it letter, and old heavens, and a back diſpenſation. Now to ſpeak plain, I think for you who preach ſuch doctrine and yet often read and expound, and apply ſcripture, is an inconſiſtent impoſition upon yourſelves and others; for what have you to do with letter and old heavens, and a back diſpenſation, who are in the new? Now obſerve, where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you are inconſiſtent you muſt be alſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and ought to be willing to be taught; for where there is ignorance and inconſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy there is no ſafety. If you make any uſe of the ſcripture, and they are any thing to your purpoſe, how have you got beyond them? And if you are included by them, how is it a new miniſtration? For the very gifts you pretend to, as viſions, revelations, tongues and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, you quote from ſcripture to prove your miſſion and miniſtry by. Pray how then are
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:019212_0021_0FAA6756F92A2BA8"/>you in a new one beyond it? Why will you be here and there both, or ſomebody no where? Either own the bible and go according to it, or prove its invaldity, and have nothing to do with it; for how can you be in a new ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold greater day with the ſame old apoſtolick gifts in a ſeven fold leſſer degree. Elder James pray look, for I muſt think that if you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent, I am not a rational creature. But to return, I ſhall firſt prove by ſcripture, whether it be any thing to you or not, that there is two, and but two days of diſpenſation, which is that of Moſes and Chriſt, the law and the goſpel which include the two ſtates of man, (viz.) law and grace, the firſt Adam and the ſecond Adam ſtates, and that theſe are to be continued to the end of the world, and all mankind are and will be included in the old covenant and the new to the end of time, which two covenants were in the two teſtimonies or miniſtrations of Moſes and Chriſt; and there is no other, nor ever will be, as I will ſhew you by ſcripture, if that proves any thing,—Firſt with reſpect to the perpetuity, if not the eternity of the law, ſee Mal. 4—4, remember ye the law of Moſes my ſervant which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him in Horeb for all Iſrael, with the ſtatutes and judgments—and Chriſt in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to this ſame law ſays, Matt. 5—18, for verily I ſay unto you, till heaven and earth paſs one jot or one tittle, ſhall in no wiſe paſs
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:019212_0022_0FAA6757B1B41348"/>from the law till all be fulfilled. And St. Paul having treated particularly of juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by faith without the deeds of the law, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally concludes, Rom. 3.31, do we then make void the law by faith? God forbid, yea we eſtabliſh the law. By what I have already quoted it appears that the prophet Malachi, confirms the law, at leaſt throughout the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh oeconomy, and Paul confirms it through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the apoſtolick day; and Chriſt confirms it till the heavens and earth be no more. And now with reſpect to the goſpel, according to the teſtimony already given by Chriſt and his apoſtles: as to its duration and continuance, Chriſt ſays, Matt. 24—14 and this (not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) goſpel of the kingdom ſhall be preached for a witneſs unto all nations, and then ſhall the end come. Again, Matt. 28—20 teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you (mark I have command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you) and lo I am with you always, even unto the end of the world, Amen. And Paul I think allows of no other miniſtration but the law and goſpel to the end of time. See Rom. 2—16, in the day when God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt, according to my goſpel. Read a few verſes foregoing in this paſſage laſt quoted, wherein you may ſee that the law as well as goſpel is that by which men will be judged in the great day. And alſo with reſpect to the continuance of
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:019212_0023_0FAA67586FA284E0"/>the apoſtolick miniſtration, you may ſee I: Peter 1—25, but the word of the Lord endur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forever; and this is the word which by the goſpel is preached unto you. And that you may alſo ſee that there is no allowance for any other miniſtration but that of the apoſtolick according to their teſtimony in that day, ſee Gal. 1—8, but though we or an angel from heaven preach any other goſpel unto you than that which we have preached unto you let him be accurs'd. And in the 9th verſe he ſays, if any man preach any other goſpel, &amp;c. I think what I have already laid down is ſufficient to prove that there is but two teſtimonies, and two miniſtrations, that of Moſes and Chriſt, which are the two witneſſes, or the two teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, who have dedicated their teſtimony with blood, as you may find in the 9th of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews, and indeed in that whole epiſtle at large. What then could William Scales mean when he ſaid that two of the leading perſons had ſealed their teſtimony with their blood, whereby it is of force? which if it be ſo, yours muſt be a third teſtament and miniſtration, and conſequently a third covenant, which annuls the ſecond or new covenant ſpoken of in 8th of Hebrew. Now elder James, dare you or any of you ſay, that there is or ever will be more than theſe two covenants? But if you have got a teſtament or a miniſtration that is not contained in that new covenant miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:019212_0024_0FAA67592F2C1C60"/>ſpoken of in the 8th chap. of Hebrews, it muſt be another, whatever it be, then what will you call it, and where will you place it? and it is evident that you do think you are in a new day and diſpensation; becauſe you call all that is written a back diſpenſation and old heavens; and even if it were as you ſuppoſe that you were in the new heavens, that alſo is contained in what you call a back diſpenſation, ſee Iſaiah 65—17 and on, compared with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations 21ſt chap. &amp;c, wherein the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſtate and circumſtance of the new heavens and earth, with thoſe that dwell in them is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred and given by the prophet Iſaiah and John the revelator both, for it is what they teſtified and yet is contained in what you call a back diſpenſation and old heavens; but if you ſhould ſay that you have entered into what they ſaid ſhould take place, it would at once deſtroy the very idea of your new diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and miniſtry, where the mother is the head gathering her company according to Samuel Fitch's doctrine, as recited above and you the apoſtles; and on the other hand, if it be as elder Partington ſaid, that the mother was gone to prepare a place for them, that alſo as effectually deſtroys the very idea of Chriſt's miſſion and miniſtry for that end according to what is written in the bible; eſpecially with reſpect to us in this day, then ſurely we have done with the bible, and muſt depend wholly
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:019212_0025_0FAA675A2565AB60"/>upon the mother, whoſe miniſtration does produce what is not contained in the bible. Now I deſire you to obſerve that if it be as you ſay, that this is a new day and diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of which the mother is the firſt born, and conſequently the head or lead; then ſhe ſtands in this day and diſpenſation to us, juſt as Chriſt did in that day and diſpenſation of the goſpel, according to what is written, where Chriſt was the firſt born, among many brethren, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the head and lead to them; and as he was Chriſt and a Saviour to them, ſo is the Mother Chriſt, and a Saviour to us, for Sam. Fitch told me that he had no Chriſt to look to but the mother, and as Chriſt had a new teſtament and died for them in that day, ſo the mother has a new teſtament, and died for us in this day—for this is what you pretend, and as Chriſt ſealed his teſtimony with his blood whereby it is of force, ſo has the mother ſealed her teſtimony with her blood, whereby it is of force, according to William Scale's. And as Chriſt's death and ſufferings was mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious for their ſalvation in that day, ſo is the mother's death and ſufferings merritorious for our ſalvation in this day; and as they in that day were to obey Chriſt's miniſtry, ſo we muſt obey the mother's miniſtry in this day; and as it is ſaid in Zachariah 12th chap. they ſhall look upon Chriſt whom they have pierced and mourn, and be in bitterneſs, &amp;c.
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:019212_0026_0FAA675C19F79928"/>even ſo we in this day ſhall look upon the mother whom we have pierced and mourn, and be in bitterneſs; as I once heard Samuel Fitch hold forth in his doctrine; and as it was expedient for Chriſt to go away—and he was gone to prepare a place for his followers, even ſo it was expedient for the mother to go away, and ſhe was gone to prepare a place for her followers, according to what elder Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ington ſaid; and as Chriſt was preſent with his followers by his ſpirit in that day, ſo is the mother preſent with her followers by her ſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it in this day, miniſtring gifts to them. Now elder James is not this another Chriſt in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of that we read of; and is not what ſhe miniſters quite another goſpel—if you call it goſpel? and does not this entirely ſet aſide the bible as a thing out of date? and put your teſtimony in its place? and does not this ſet Chriſt aſide, and put the mother in his place, with the appellation of ſeven fold greater? and do you not take great pains to eraſe every idea of God and Chriſt out of the minds of your people, but only what dwells in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the elders? and to deface and eraſe the very remembrance of that old letter, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſcripture, ſaying you have got the ſpirit. And are you not therefore inconſiſtent to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle at all with the bible, except you could prove by it, its own invalidity and diſſolution? for elder James you muſt know, it would be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:019212_0027_0FAA675C3B807BA0"/>to ſuppoſe, that a new day and diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could take place but at the end and expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the former; therefore if you do really believe that you are entered into a new day and diſpenſation, as you ſay you have, you muſt know of conſequence that whatever im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements you have made from the bible was a grand impoſition; and if you make any uſe of ſcripture you bring it into force, and will overthrow the mother, eſpecially if her miniſtry and that of her apoſtles differ from that of Chriſt's and his apoſtles—which is the next thing to be attended to.</p>
            <p>Firſt the teſtimony of Chriſt's goſpel ſays, I. Timothy, 2—12, but I ſuffer not a woman to teach nor to uſurp authority over the man; but to be in ſilence: but the mother's teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony ſays the contrary, and takes unlimited authority upon herſelf; even to ordering, dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating, ſtripping and whipping both men and women. Now can any creature ſuppoſe that God will be with and own any one in the breach of his commands? What have you elder James to vindicate this point but the diſannuling of the commandment? and that cannot be done without breaking with the whole book, and the author of it too. This proves your new diſpenſation: but if the commands of God ſtand, it will overthrow your whole ſyſtem, and you with it. I think it is entirely needleſs to undertake to prove, that the woman
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:019212_0028_0FAA675D4ED27AB8"/>ſpoken of in the 12th chap. of Rev. and alſo that in Jeremiah 31—22, and that again in the 45th Pſalm, from the 10th verſe and on. May none of them be applied to the mother, as you pretend, becauſe ſhe is at the head of the great and laſt diſpenſation, far enough be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all them, they being in the former, and this pretence ſaves me the labour, and proves ſhe is not. And beſides that in the Rev. and in the Pſalms was undoubtedly a figurative deſcription of the church, and that in Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, a propheſy of Chriſt's nativity, with a hint at the manner of it. But to proceed to another particular, Chriſt's Goſpel ſays, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew 15—4, for God commanded ſaying, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor thy father and mother; and he that curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth father or mother, let him die the death—theſe are Chriſt's own words, and every awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened and enlightened conſcience muſt know and feel that there is a moral rectitude in them and his obligations to obey them as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, both in his law and goſpel too; but it is certain that under the mother's mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry I have heard children curſe their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents—and it was appointed in the church, and I take it to be a criterion in your ſyſtem to cut off all natural affection by the higheſt provocation; and alſo under the mother's miniſtry, children do diſhonor their parents I know, for I ſaw a young man of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany order his father to ſtrip in the midſt of
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:019212_0029_0FAA675E272F43E8"/>a large room full of people both men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, then ſeizing him by his private mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, hauling him this way and that by them, chaſtizing him aloud for his old heavens and luſt, and then taking him up and ſetting him upon his head and ſhoulders, heels upwards, then by force wrenching his naked thighs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and taking him again by his members, and handling them in the view of all preſent, every way expoſing his father to the utmoſt ſhame. Was not this diſhonoring his parent, elder James, and breaking the command of God? the mother being preſent and the mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it: when Chriſt expreſsly ſays, Matt. 5—19, whoſoever therefore ſhall break one of theſe leaſt commands, and teach men ſo, ſhall be called leaſt in the kingdom of heaven. But whoſoever ſhall do, and teach them, ſhall be called great in the kingdom of heaven. Is not here a material difference in the two mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations, and the one tending directly to the deſtruction of the other? but you will ſay that Chriſt is come in the mother, and it is he that does it; but will Chriſt contradict or counteract his own word? or will he tell the mother to do what he forbids? for when God commanded children to honour their father and mother, would Chriſt in the mother ſet this young man to diſhonor his father, as relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above? Does not ſuch a doctrine tend to the aboliſhing of the ſcriptures, and opening
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:019212_0030_0FAA675E6F487248"/>an uninterrupted way to the mother's mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry? but here obſerve, that although Chriſt ſays, Matt. 10—35, for I am come to ſet a man at variance againſt his father, and the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againſt her mother, and the daughter-in law againſt her mother-in-law, &amp;c. and this being the neceſſary conſequence or effect of the goſpel, to ſet at variance and ſeparate them that believe from them that believe not; yet ſo far is the believer from curſing his father or mother, or any body elſe, that he will bleſs and curſe not: yea he will bleſs them that curſe him, and do good to them that hate him, and perſecute him according to the commands of Chriſt, ſee Matt. —44; and ſo far is he from diſhonouring his parents by any abuſive language or behaviour, that he honours and obeys them, according to goſpel command. In Col. 3—20, children obey your parents in all things, for this is well pleaſing to the Lord; but wherever the ſon diſhonours the father the character is bad, as you may ſee, Micah 7—6 and wherever children diſobey their parents, their character is bad, as you may ſee, Rom. 1—30, and II. Tim. 3—2, this is what we read in the ſcriptures; but under the mother's miniſtry I have ſeen and known the greateſt of what men would call abuſive treatment of children to their parents, I think that ever I heard of, and all under a pretence of religion
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:019212_0031_0FAA675F2BA9F2B0"/>and freeing their ſouls. Diſhonouring and diſobeying parents is a plain and open breach of the commands of God, according to what is written; and if your miniſtry leads into theſe things it muſt be ANTE, or againſt, let the pretence be what it will; except it be as you ſay a new diſpenſation, where there is no God, nor Chriſt, nor bible, but what is in the mother, that can do us any good; then I ſay you have no buſineſs with the bible, and ought not to impoſe upon people with it, nor do I think you would if they were able to bear it; but where as I am in full belief of the ſcriptures—thanks to God for it. I mean to contend earneſtly for the faith which was once delivered to the ſaints. Again we read I. Cor. 6—10, nor revilers ſhall inherit the kingdom of God. Again I. Cor. 5—11, nor a railer with ſuch an one no not to eat. And again James 4—11 ſpeak not evil one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brethren, for he that ſpeaketh evil of his brother, and judgeth his brother, ſpeaketh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil of the law, and judgeth the law, &amp;c. I could quote many texts of ſcripture, from the old and new teſtament to the ſame effect, whereby it appears that railing, reviling, and evil ſpeaking is contrary to the nature and ſpirit of the goſpel of Chriſt, which teſtifies that ſuch ſhall not inherit the kingdom of God. Therefore, whoever allows themſelves in theſe things, pretend what they will, they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:019212_0032_0FAA675FE779E948"/>of God; and what can tend more to deſtroy people's morals; and is it not the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of a meek and quiet ſpirit; and does it not belong to another kingdom? For Chriſt when he was reviled, he reviled not again; when he was perſecuted, he threatened not, but committed himſelf to him that judgeth right. And Paul ſays, being reviled we bleſs; being defamed we entreat; being perſecuted we ſuffer it: but it is not to be marvelled at if another miniſtration produces other things for ſuch as is the tree, ſuch the fruit will be. And James ſays, out of the ſame mouth proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth bleſſing and curſing, (and ſo it is with you) my brethren theſe things ought not to be ſo. Again, Paul to Timothy ſays, the ſervant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle towards all men? apt to teach, patient, in meekneſs inſtructing them that oppoſe themſelves &amp;c. but you do ſtrive. Again, Paul to the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians ſays, let all bitterneſs, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evil ſpeaking be put away from you, with all malice, and be kind one to another—tender hearted, forgiving one another even as God for Chriſt's ſake hath forgiven you. Now Elder James this ſeems to be the nature and ſpirit of the goſpel;—therefore I am bold to ſay, that there can be no drunkard, no curſer of parents, no diſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orer of parents, no diſobedient to parents, and ſuch like can be found in Chriſt's goſpel; and
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:019212_0033_0FAA67619E419718"/>if you have any ſuch in yours, then it muſt be another. Elder James I honeſtly tell you, that I have ſpared you in relation to railing, fearing you was not able to bear a true decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of facts without offence: I have kept back the words and ſuppreſſed the ideas that offered themſelves to give it its own complec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and leaſt I ſhould be a railer too. But if an honeſt recital of facts ſhould offend you, I ſhould think that you was not good; or that the things acted were not good, and you were aſhamed of them, and ought to confeſs and ſuppreſs them; for if you knew how ſome of your people treats my character, if you had any ſenſe of humanity, you would be aſhamed of them, and if you had any ſenſe of chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianity you would be ſorry for them, and take unwearied pains to teach them better; which I think you muſt do, except you as well as they are ſo loſt from God as to act that out, that may in time convince every body, and prove the abſurdity of your new miniſtry. I ſpeak this not that it annoys me; but that by plain facts and fair reaſon and ſcripture, you might be convicted; and beſides this, to my own maſter I ſtand or fall: or even allowing that I was in fault, I think you ought to have taken the goſpel rule, Gal. 6—1, brethren if a man be overtaken in a fault, ye which are ſpiritual, reſtore ſuch an one in the ſpirit of meekneſs, conſidering yourſelf leſt you alſo
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:019212_0034_0FAA67626A080E38"/>be tempted. But your people ſeem to have a different mode of diſcipline. I am ſenſible, that it is a received opinion among you, that to come out with great wrath and anger in teſtimony againſt what you call ſin is right; but is not wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evil ſpeaking ſin itſelf? elſe why is it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden? ſee Eph. 4—31—again, Titus 3—2 to ſpeak evil of no man; to be no brawlers, but gentle, ſhewing all meekneſs unto all men: then to rail and exclaim, and falſely accuſe &amp; that in anger too, is againſt the commands of God and therefore ſin; from which I ſee no eſcape but by repentance and faith in Chriſt, except by taking refuge in a new diſpenſation would do. I know that part of Paul's charge to Timothy and Titus, was to reprove and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke; but that was by preaching the word, which carries reproof and rebuke in it to thoſe that ſin; but I am far from believing that either of them, in obeying Paul's charge, ever conducted as many of you do, for it muſt be done in meekneſs, without bitterneſs, anger, wrath, clamour, or evil ſpeaking, &amp;c. Is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into ſin the way out of it?</p>
            <p>Another point to be examined is, whether your mother's character agrees with that giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en by St. Paul, Titus 1ſt chap. wherein he ſays, if any man be blameleſs, the huſband of one wiſe, having faithful children, not accuſed of riot, or unruly. For a biſhop muſt be
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:019212_0035_0FAA6762ECD7E390"/>blameleſs as the ſteward of God, not ſelf-will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not ſoon angry, not given to wine, no ſtriker, not given to filthy lucre, &amp;c. Mark, he ſays, if any be blameleſs, which he could not be if he were found in the breach of any one rule given in this character—the huſband of one wife; but your mother was no huſband nor did ſhe allow of any huſband, or wife at all, and them that were ſuch ſhe would part them forever, if they would be of her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity; and certainly they were accuſed of riot, and of being very unruly, for they will many of them drink hard, ſing and dance all night, ſtrip naked and ſpank one anothers arſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and make as much noiſe as they can among themſelves, and to thoſe that are oppoſed to them, they will judge and condemn, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to hell with the moſt dreadful oaths &amp; curſes; calling them boogers, devils and Sod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omites; beſides puſhing, hunching, pulling hair, ſtriking, biting, and ſpitting in their faces—ſee the widow Goodrich in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and the others almoſt as bad, in the moſt angry, venemous manner I think that ever I ſee any where in any caſe. Mark I don't mean that this is the caſe at all times; for there is at ſometimes the greateſt appearance of love and meekneſs. And as to the mother's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſelf-willed, I would mention one inſtance and let that ſuffice for the preſent: as you will likely remember when the church as you
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:019212_0036_0FAA6763C9BA3048"/>call them was at Elijah Sloſon's, a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of people being gathered, you began your doctrine and the people being inquiſitive and deſirous to aſk ſome queſtions, you would not allow of it, but ſaid to them that when you &amp; your brethren, viz. the ſpeakers had done, they ſhould have their opportunity and be fairly heard and anſwered; at which they gave audience and kept good order 'till you had all got through. Then your mother ſlipped into the houſe (for this was out of doors) and ſent a meſſenger immediately to call you in, but you lingering a little, ſhe ſent another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs for you and the reſt of the elders, at which you went in; then ſhe took you up ſtairs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a chamber and chaſtiſed you for diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence—I being preſent and an eye and ear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the whole. The people were offended at their diſappointment, and William Baker, a young man partly believing in that way fell off for this thing. In this ſhe would have her way, and force you to break your agreement. Again, ſhe was very often very angry, and much given to wine and ſtrong drink, and certainly ſhe was a ſtriker, both of me and many others. And as to her being given to, or greedy of filthy lucre, let her pretence be what it would, this is certain, ſhe did require that we ſhould reſign up all we had to her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal. Now elder James I leave to you judge, whether your mother's character agrees with
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:019212_0037_0FAA676468DFAB38"/>that given by St. Paul. But perhaps you will ſay, that your mother was not a biſhop, but the firſt and great apoſtle of a new diſpenſation, and you the biſhop. Well, will that help the matter as to character. Will a drunkard, a railer, a ſelf-willed angry ſtriker, and one that demands all I have, and will ever prepare war againſt us, if their be any heſitation about it? I ſay, will ſuch an one do, being a woman too, for the great apoſtle or biſhop, or the Chriſt of your new diſpenſation? for you do ſay, or at leaſt you have ſaid, that there is no God, nor Chriſt but what was in your mother, and you her elders; nor no ſalvation but by her; and this pretence of a new day and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation is a handſome covering for all, and well accounts for the many unaccountable things produced by her miniſtry, and for the mother's appearing in ſo different a character from that given by St. Paul. Now elder James if you would but rationally attend to what has been already ſaid, you muſt be convinced that you have not the characters of chriſtians ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to any thing we find in ſcripture.—Therefore, if you make a pretence of being the people of God, you had better tell every one honeſtly, as you do the ſtrong believers among you, that you are got clear beyond all that is written in the bible, and let people know who and what you be before you take them and put out their eyes, and ſet them a
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:019212_0038_0FAA67652C07D5D8"/>grinding in your mill, for then the poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do not know how to get away, nor were to go; for though you have renounced the ſcripture, or rather have got beyond it; yet you will craſtily make uſe of it, to catch and hold as many as you can, ſaying in the words of Chriſt, that he came, that they that ſee not, might ſee, and that they that ſee, might be made blind—endeavouring to make them as blind as poſſible to all they ever did ſee, and to believe that all the religion ſince the apoſtle's time was only anti-chriſtian; and that all that they ever thought to be good was only bad; and great part of what they uſed to think was bad, to be good, ſaying to the pure, all things are pure, and that what goeth into a man, does not defile him; and in ſuch crafty ways in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing the greateſt vices and ſuppreſſing the virtues of all your followers; and thus put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out their eyes to that which is good, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in belief of what is bad; calling e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil good and good evil; not ſuffering them to read the ſcriptures, nor receive any thing but what you teach them; and the more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and rage they could manifeſt or feel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt every thing that was not in your line, the more they were careſs'd and applauded by you; and they are made to believe it to be one of the greateſt virtues, and an eſſential point of obedience upon which their doctrine depends, to feel the greateſt hatred and anger
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:019212_0039_0FAA6766099ED848"/>againſt their oppoſers: calling it the anger of God; you craſtily leading on in it, by quot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch ſcriptures as theſe, viz. Chriſt look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about upon them with anger, &amp;c. Again, he took a ſcourge of ſmall cords, and drove out the buyers and ſellers. And again, he ſays, ye ſerpents, ye generation of vipers, &amp;c. And Paul to Elimos, O ſull of ſubtilty and miſchief, thou enemy of all righteouſneſs; thou child of the devil, &amp;c. forgetting that theſe words were and are yet ſpoken to thoſe that oppoſe and go contrary to Chriſt and his apoſtle's doctrine and miniſtry, which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you have no right to make uſe of, except you will own them and ſubject to their goſpel, and not make it a cloak of maliciouſneſs; for the wrath of man worketh not the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God, ſee James 1ſt chap. 20 verſe. Elder James I ſpeak what I know of your crafty ways to drive the people into thoſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages, even to that degree that I hear that one of your pupils ſtruck at one of her op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers with an axe, and threatened his life. To be ſure ſhe does much at ſtriking with ſticks, and biting, and ſpitting in the face I believe, for I have ſeen the wounds that was ſaid ſhe gave: and is ſhe not therefore according to your own doctrine the ſeed of Cain that killed his brother with a ſtick? Beſides many others I could name, that by the accounts are not much if any thing behind her in acts of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:019212_0040_0FAA6766AB4CEE30"/>and violence; and yet I have no doubt but the poor creatures verily think they do God ſervice. O! how much blood has been ſhed by this religious anger ſince the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world; and this is certainly the effect of your new miniſtration; and beſides all this Elder James, I have been many times burdened at your hypocriſy and deceit, deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at one time what you ſaid at another: par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly once at Elias Brown's, in Preſton, when we left Stonington on our way to Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lsam, they queſtioned you of things that I knew was among you, and you would not own it. I thought then if I remember right, they would likely ſoon be certified of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and report, that you had lied about it. I have many times obſerved ſuch things in you that has given me great trouble. Alſo, your mother ſaid one time in my hearing, that Ames Rathbun had never brought any thing and given to the church, when I knew the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. At another time when ſome of thoſe you call the world ſeemed to ſuſpect and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse her of taking money of her people, ſhe plumply denied it, when I abſolutely knew that ſhe had taken of me both ſilver and gold, and I knew that ſhe knew it, for ſhe would ſpeak of it at other times in commendation of me, I ſuppoſed for an example to others. At another time at Aſhfield, in the caſe between Iſaac Chancy and Talmage Biſhop, and ſome
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:019212_0041_0FAA67676C495760"/>others that were entangled in the ſame affair, it came before her for deciſion, and after ſhe had been ſome time upon the matter, ſhe came out with reproofs againſt them, and then made an appeal to me, meaning as I ſuppoſed, that I ſhould join with her, and come out ſharp againſt them alſo; I knowing her mind and my own ignorance of the matter, was ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened in myſelf what to do, at length come out in ſuch terms as I thought I might with a good conſcience; but it not anſwering her mind ſhe came right upon me with chaſtiſement, I thought becauſe I would not tell a lie. And many times in her appeals to me—in her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline upon others, I have been ſo afraid, I think I may ſay, that I ſhould bring her upon me like a lion, if Ii did not even wrong my conſcience in joining with her, as would bring me to great ſtreights in my mind; and this I ſuppoſe from my obſervation of others, that they think it to be perfectly agreeable to God's will to ſay as you do at a venture, you being their God or guide, if they can pleaſe you they feel well enough; but I ws afraid to truſt it, for I did believe, and do ſtill, that there was another God beyond you that I was anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werable to. One time elder John Partington chaſtiſed me, thumping upon me becauſe when the world, as you call them, told me of your mother's getting drunk, I did not deny it, and came out againſt them with a ſharp ſword for
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:019212_0042_0FAA67692F30D368"/>falſely accuſing the people of God. Elder William has alſo chaſtiſed me for the ſame thing, ſaying I loſt my faith and confidence for not being more bold and zealous to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the people of God, when indeed I knew that what they ſaid, and much more was true, and I could not deny it without lying againſt my own conſcience. Elder William has of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten forced me, and others to ſay I will or I will not do this and that, when I fear'd to do it leſt I ſhould not be able to perform. Now elder James was not this making us liars; and great pains has been taken alſo, to make us railers. Children often called up to tell the worſt things they could about their parents and friends in open aſſemblies, and to berate them to the laſt degree, rendering them as ridiculous and odious as devils, even calling them ſuch; and thoſe that ſignalized them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moſt in this manner, were higheſt eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the church. I myſelf have been reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and I thought deſpiſed for not doing more in this line than my conſcience would allow of. Many have gone ſo far in raillery as falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to accuſe, and when convicted of their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, they would twiſt out, ſaying, it was in a ſinful nature to do all theſe things, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore guilty of the nature if not the actions. I have alſo ſeen ſuch a lead given to exceſſive drinking, that I could not go with it without ſacrificing or violating my conſcience; and
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:019212_0043_0FAA6769F3970FD0"/>therefore it was that I complained to you ſo much about it. I think it is very evident that your people in general are become great drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers—and that from your examples; for if you did not do it yourſelves, they would not dare to do it. I have certainly ſeen and, heard com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints from others, of your often-being, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide yourſelves; eſpecially when you rode a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. One time you and elder William, and George Darrow, came in to John Spires, I being there, and George ſmelt and acted as if he was full of rum up to his gullet, and the reſt of you not much behind him. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this ſame George was chaſtiſed ſharply at Aſhfield for covetouſneſs by the church when they were there; but afterwards becoming very liberal and free with liquor to your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the elders, and partaking of it with you himſelf, he ſoon became a great favorite of the church, while I ſunk into contempt for my uneaſineſs and complaints againſt ſuch practiſes. You may likely remember a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time when you and elder William came to my houſe from Barrington, in Court time, elder William fumbled in his ſpeech and tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about, and ſpewed on the floor, and was hurried away to bed under a pretence of great ſufferings. I did not ſee this at this time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from home; but was informed of it by my wife, who ſays ſhe ſaw it. I ſaw Knap's wife come to the church in a ſleigh, I being
<pb n="45" facs="unknown:019212_0044_0FAA676A6B03B418"/>there, that ſhe could ſcarce get into the houſe, being apparently to my exception almoſt drunk; and elder William received her with great joy, comforting and ſtrengthening her, without the leaſt reproof that I know of, either then or afterwards for it. She appeared to me to be then as full of what you call the power of God, as ever, and would keep for ſome time hallowing out aloud, as her uſual manner was, and elder Williams laughing and rejoicing, as it ſeem'd, to ſee her keep ſo alive in religion, as I ſuppoſed, he would have us all think, when I knew and could not but think that every one that ſaw her muſt know that ſhe had more rum religion than any other at that time, except ſuch as had a great ſhare of the ſame themſelves. Now elder James theſe and ſuch like things were certainly the cauſe and reaſon of my ſeparating from you, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the command of God in II. Cor. 6—17, wherefore, come out from among them, and be ye ſeperate faith the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing, and I will receive you. And it is evident to me that your lead was unclean, and out from all bible rules and commands, into ſuch a diverſity of enormities which I have ſeen and heard, and know to be among you; and I ſolemnly declare that I do believe accoding to my obſervations of things amongſt you, that thoſe that are the deepeſt in thoſe what I call vices and abominations as
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:019212_0045_0FAA676B2FBA71E0"/>related above are the higheſt in the eſteem and favour of you and your church. I have more to ſay, but ſhall cloſe theſe objections by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrence to the 28th of Iſaiah, at the beginning, wo to the crown of pride, to the drunkards of Ephraim, whoſe glorious beauty is a fading flower, which are on the head of the fat val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of them that are overcome with wine. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Lord hath a mighty and ſtrong one, which as a tempeſt of hail and a deſtroying ſtorns, as a flood of mighty waters overflowing ſhall caſt down to the earth with the hand, the crown of pride, the drunkards of Ephraim ſhall be troden under feet. Wherefore I adviſe you to tell your poor infatuated company, that you have been deceiving them; and while you have been promiſing them liberty, you yourſelf have been a ſervant of corruption leaſt this woe be upon you, all which incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtencies and abſurdities ſeems to be the real and neceſſary production of your new diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation and miniſtry.</p>
            <p>Now elder James, omiting many things that might juſtly come under conſideration for a further demonſtration of the falſehood of your pretences, I proceed to make a compariſon, between you and the Papiſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they hold that the Pope is the ſupreme head of the church, and you hold that the mother was, while living, and now you are ſupreme head of your church, for you ſay
<pb n="47" facs="unknown:019212_0046_0FAA676BEBA62220"/>Chriſt came in you, and Chriſt and his people are one; and this is the idea you give us, that when you ſpeak to us Chriſt ſpeaks to us, for their is no other Chriſt. Again, you are as abſolute and deſpotick as the Pope, and are as arbitrary in your diſcipline, and hold your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as infallible as he. Herein you agree only being two different communions; one or both is miſtaken in aſſerting, that no body can be ſaved out of your communion. He ſays this of his, and you of yours. However I think this to be very ridiculous for either, except your characters were better. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts hold to Purgatory, and ſo do you, and in the ſame manner, both with reſpect to their going in and coming out; and for what end? they worſhip their dead ſaint, and ſo do you, and pray to them, ſing verſes, ſerenade, and celebrate your mother and father William as you call them. This I have ſeen and heard, among ſuch as were of your communion, and you yourſelf bid me confeſs to your mother, after ſhe was dead, the laſt time I viſited you at Niſqueuniah. Now is not praying and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing to the dead an unſcriptural as well as an irrational thing? and what warrant have we for it but your hold aſſertions? except it be that ſcripture in the 8th of Iſaiah, 19th verſe, and when they ſhall ſay unto you, ſeek unto them that have familiar ſpirits, and unto wizards that peep and that mutter, ſhould not
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:019212_0047_0FAA676CAEF98EF8"/>a people ſeek unto their God? for the living to the dead; to which I ſhall ſpeak more particularly in its proper place. Now the Papiſts pretend to prove the doctrine of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory by their apoaritions and revelations, ſo do you. The Papiſts make confeſſion of their ſins to the Pope and a great number of father confeſſors under him, and ſo do you in your order; and the Pope and father confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors pretend a power to abſolve or forgive ſins, and ſo do you; they make the penitents kneel in confeſſion before the fathers, and ſo do you; they adminiſter corporal puniſhment in their diſcipline, and enjoy repentance, and ſo do you; the penitent after confeſſion, kiſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es the fathers hand, or ſleeve if there is favor, and ſo it is among you. They have their convents and nunneries for men and women, who are exempted from marriage, and ſo it is among you, only not in ſo popular a manner for want of ability. They have their inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo have you in every idea of it, I think ſo far as you can go, without the civil authority; and againſt thoſe that diſſent from them, their excommunications, curſes, invec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and imprecations are the ſame of yours, for what I can ſee, and their hatred and aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt all but their own ſect, is the ſame of yours; they pretend to the gifts of healing and caſting out devils: of apparitions, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations and propheſy—if the accounts be
<pb n="49" facs="unknown:019212_0048_0FAA676D6A371548"/>true, in a greater degree perhaps than ever yet you pretended. The Papiſt will ſend a father confeſſor into a family to take the lead and government of it, who becomes abſolute maſter of the houſe, and has the controul of the whole family, both parents and children and ſhe ordering and diſpoſition of them, as we are informed by the author of the book entiled the maſter key to Popery, and I think the ſame is in practice among you. See Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron Williams at Nathan Kindal's, in Woobon, Rufus Cogſwell at Joſhua Burtch's in Ston<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ington, Benjamin Ellis at Joſeph Bennets at New-Providence, &amp;c. Beſides the many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confeſſors that make it their buſineſs to travel about from houſe to houſe to take the confeſſions and give their inſtructions and orders to families: Such as Ebenezer Cooley, Iſrael Chancey, Joſeph Meechem, Joſhua Cogſwell, and many others, for all which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices the Papiſts make great demands upon their people; but I think you go clear beyond them, for you require all that they have, even their whole eſtates, and their perſons and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies too, to be entirely at your diſpoſal, tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them that ſhort of this, they will leave their ſouls and ſoterrifying the poor infatuates to a compliance rather than go to holl. The Papiſts and you too as I underſtand hold, that every ſoul has to ſuffer either here or hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for all their ſin, and yet you have power
<pb n="50" facs="unknown:019212_0049_0FAA676E2B0F50C0"/>to remit them. How inconſiſtent that is: but of this more hereafter. It is ſaid that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Papiſts many of the prieſts of pure lives aſſert, that they have ſeen the little boy Jeſus in the conſecrated hoſt, juſt as I have heard Amos Rathbun aſſert, that he has ſeen Jeſus Chriſt like a little boy in James Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacor. I underſtand by viſion or apparition, both they and you pretend to the power of miracles; but very few if any are manifeſt, or believed; but among yourſelves, which if it were true, is no more than what we read of the beaſt and falſe prophet in three paſſages of ſcripture in the Revelations. I read of one among the Papiſts that aſſerted ſhe had ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al times ſeen Jeſus Chriſt, and that he had talked with her. At another time ſhe ſaw the Holy Trinity. And Joſeph Meechem among you told me that John Partington, one of your elders, had often ſeen Jeſus Chriſt, and alſo the prophet Daniel, and I think talked with them. Another article is, that the Papiſts have their ſecondary mediators, ſuch as the virgin Mary, St. Peter, St. Paul, and a great number of their eminent ſaints beſides, who are dead, whom they worſhip and pray to, deſiring them to pray and intercede with Chriſt for them; and this is a known profeſſed principle among you. Even Joſeph Meechem told me, and I have often heard it talkt among you, that God would not hear us but by ſecondary mediators
<pb n="51" facs="unknown:019212_0050_0FAA676EF45EC0E8"/>under Chriſt; and that we could not be ſaved, but by the mother's interceſſion. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I have heard her pray'd to many times ſince ſhe was dead: this is therefore another Popiſh tenet. Again both their and your puniſhing the particular part that ſin'd in your diſcipline, &amp;c. Again, the Pope and Prieſts among the Papiſts do not allow the common people the liberty of reading the bible; and hold forth that the people ought to obey them blindly in every thing without heſitation; and I know this to be the caſe among you, for great efforts have been made to beat me and others off from reading the bible. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Samuel Fitch one time came forth with this doctrine, that we ought to believe and obey whatever came from the mother, if we did not ſee the reaſon and propriety of it; and that we had no right to queſtion or doubt of the truth of what the mother ſaid or did—this is as nearly his words as I can repeat them, and exactly the ſenſe as I receive it: to which I then took an exception, and ventured to ſay to Joſeph Meechem, that Fitch's doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine deprived me of ſeeing and knowing for myſelf. The news of my objection was ſoon carried, and ſoon followed with chaſtiſement for my gainſaying Samuel Fitch. Now elder James from this compariſon of things, I think you have no reaſon to blame me or any others for believing and calling you Papiſts, which I
<pb n="52" facs="unknown:019212_0051_0FAA676FB26C37E8"/>really do, and as ſuch enounce you, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare myſelf a Proteſtant. Proteſting againſt your Romiſh idolatry and ſuperſtition, as Luther did in his time, expecting the Popiſh bull full of invectives, which, however, I have as little faith in, as I have in your unſcriptural doctrine and diſcipline. But once more by way of compariſon: it is evident from ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teſtimony, that the man of ſin, or myſtery of iniquity before its deſtruction, ſhall ariſe, full in the character given of it by St. Paul, II. Theſſ. 2 chap. and it has been gradually increaſing ever ſince the firſt degeneracy of the chriſtian religion and the riſe of Popery; and the many accounts that have been given by the writers of almoſt every age ſince, even down to this day, ſhew us, that according to Chriſt's words, Matt. 24—24, for there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſigns and wonders, inſomuch that if it were poſſible, they ſhall deceive the very elect, has been abundantly verified by the impoſtures of theſe times, whoſe pretenſions to perfection and the power of miracles, ſuch as caſting out devils, unknown tongues vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, revelations and propheſy; and even to be Chriſt himſelf, have turned out to be a meer cheat, and themſelves perſons of the moſt immoral and debauched lives, of all whom it would be endleſs to write particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; yet I think, it neceſſary to quote a few
<pb n="53" facs="unknown:019212_0052_0FAA6770683B6870"/>paſſages from a book called the French pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, written in the year 1707—8. Firſt, John Lacy, <abbr>Eſq</abbr> in his preface to that book, gives this account of his operations in that day like yours in this, page 4th. They began by a preternatural courſe of breathing, then my head come to be ſhaken violently and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly, and with a very quick motion horizon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, or from ſide to ſide; then my ſtomach had twitches, not much unlike an hyccup; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward my hands and arms were violently ſhaken, and ſometimes a catching or twitches all over my body. After which he ſays, he had the gift of tongues and propheſy, and to denounce the judgments of God immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly coming down on the city of London, and kingdom of England. And to make it as pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick as poſſible that men might have timely warning, concerning which, as I underſtand, Sir Edmund Calamy, in his remark upon it ſays, page 34: "'Tis well known to many that it was prophetically declared by one of them, and afterward reported by many, that a diſmal judgment would fall on this city, in three weeks time; but bleſſed be God, tho' many weeks have ſince paſſed or elapſed, this noble city, the ruin of which would be the greateſt joy to hell and Rome that could be, continues ſafe." This John Lacy goes on propheſying for ſeveral days together, now and then making a ſtop or pauſe and whiſtling
<pb n="54" facs="unknown:019212_0053_0FAA677270967A00"/>a ſpell, ſee page 71 and 72; "he whiſtles, he whiſtles, he whiſtles." In his prophetical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration he ſays, page 78, "with many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues will I ſtrike them," he ſtriking on his knee at the ſame time, giving the ſign, page 80, "hear he rolled about on his ſeat, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his body, and moving his head and hands like a man ſick at heart, page 95, he ſhakes much his hand, and ſeems to threaten; here he ſtrikes ſeveral times, pointing his fingers ends to his heart, crying out, O! rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſs, rottenneſs, I ſee it, I ſee it." Goes on to ſay, "have you not read, out of his belly ſhall flow a ſpring of living water: what was the meaning of that to him, who believe in Chriſt? and if you do not believe in my Chriſt, now, now, taking poſſeſſion of his throne, your ciſtern ſhall be empty of that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle knowledge you have ſoon." Now elder James here is the ſame craft that you have uſed with us to terrify us along, pretending that Chriſt was come in you, and that if we did not believe Chriſt in you, viz. believe you, we ſhould ſoon be left deſtitute of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God. See your picture in theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers and read the fact. The following words were written by one who believed in the French Prophets, in a letter to his friend, wherein he ſays, page 9, "but that which fully determined me in this point was their predicting things miraculous to be wrought
<pb n="55" facs="unknown:019212_0054_0FAA67734F7C4390"/>within a determined time by them, and that time very ſhort, and declaring to the world, that if the power of God does not before the 29th of April next atteſt to the work, they will own themſelves deluded." Here I would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that this man was gain'd to the belief of them by their bold aſſertions, who was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly convinced after the 29th of April; except they could make as good a ſhift, as I quoted by Edmund Calamy, in one of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks, page 34: "in a warning which is ſaid to have been dictated by the ſpirit, on the 26th of July laſt, are theſe words: the tower guns will roar in a few days, by this day ſen night; but a week and a fortnight paſſed, and no man could hear the ſound of them; by that time it ſhould ſeem their ſpirit was convinced it might be charged with a falſity: upon Aug. 12th, therefore, that is 17 days after the predic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out came a ſalvo; and 'tis declared that the tower guns were the guns from the tower of heaven, with which this city was to be bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and that the key of time was not yet given, by which to explain the ſeven night expreſſed; but that a few months ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the key. Is not this a meer bantering the world, under a pretence of revelation." Now elder James is not this juſt like ſome of your ſhifts among you: firſt to declare that the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and elders would never die, and ſome would ſay not a natural death; and when they
<pb n="56" facs="unknown:019212_0055_0FAA6773703DCAE0"/>did die, they either denied that they ever ſaid ſo, of they would ſay that they were not dead. I have been credibly informed, that the mother delivered it as propheſy, that ſhe herſelf, and elder William and you, and John Partington and ſeveral more of the elders would die by perſecution; and when Thaddius Noble, ſince the mother and elder William's death, told this prediction to John Partington, he ſaid "why I will tell thee brother William ſuffered to death, he bleed out of every hole in his body—I think theſe were the very words. Now why was he not honeſt enough to own the miſtake; but becauſe that would be to give up your perfection and infallibility, and convince the people. I could mention many other things that are now on my mind; but would only aſk you whether you think that the cauſe of God is upheld by falſehood and fraud? But to return, in page 24 we have an account that the French Prophets of that time declared, that a new diſpenſation had taken place; and the millennium was juſt then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencing, and that the new diſpenſation ſhall be publiſhed in all parts, in three years time; and the great work which ſhould be effected was compleat reſtoration; the whole creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on appear in its primitive beauty, and man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the perfections of Adam, and his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate communion with God: and the wicked cut off by the judgments of God from the
<pb n="57" facs="unknown:019212_0056_0FAA67742FB0FFE8"/>earth, and ſo ſay you within your time limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This was what they ſo confidently aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, and yet an abſolute falſehood in every part of it, altho' attended with what they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and likely thouſands of others, verily thought was a miraculous power, or the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God—ſee Sir Richard Buckley's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, page 35th, "among much more than a thouſand extacies that I have ſeen, I have ſeen many ſo very much agitated and moved, that no part of their body could be ſaid to be in repoſe, as if they had been ſtomach ſick, heart ſick, fainting, rack'd with cholicks, ſtone and gout;" and I have ſeen the ſame among you, even to ſpilling blood. See another paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage quoted from this ſame author, page 89, "and thoſe evidences do ariſe from the oper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations and effects wrought by it, which are either of the graces of the holy ſpirit wrought powerfully in the hearts of thoſe whom he has called into this diſpenſation, or of his gifts, to wit. thoſe that follow the gift of prayer and ſupplication—the gift of exhortation—of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction—of languages—of diſcerning the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of the heart—the gift of miniſtration—of the ſame ſpirit to others, by laying on of hands, and the gift of healing, of every one of which I ſhall give clear and manifeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances." All theſe I know you pretend to. Much more I could quote from this author in favor of thoſe pretenders (he being one of
<pb n="58" facs="unknown:019212_0057_0FAA6774E9604900"/>their proſelytes) to the new diſpenſation, Chriſt's ſecond coming—the millennium be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, and the gifts attending, and the great work of reſtitution of all things to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in three years time. This is exactly what you pretend, only yours is to be eleven years; of which they are ſo bold and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that Sir Edmund Calamy ſays in trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe page 38, "they talk much of their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, but do but queſtion their being inſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and you will ſee diſdain in their looks: this is certainly true concerning you. Again he ſays, they openly and ſcurrilouſly traduce the office of the miniſtry, and villify all that are in it without diſtinction, in moſt opprobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous language: I believe there is hundreds, if not thouſands that can ſay they have heard the ſame from you. Again, he ſays page 39, "they that ſet up for prophets, freely pour out their curſes on all that oppoſe them, and ſeem to delight in nothing more than in threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning viols of wrath and fire from heaven on all ſuch as refuſe to own them the peculiar heritage of the Lord, and his ſpecial meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; and ſo do you it is well known, and for which you have had ſome trouble. Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on oppoſers is their common theme, on which they are warmeſt and freeſt, and they are required not to pity thoſe that fall under thoſe judgments: nay, upon the ſuppoſition of their near approach, they often ſcornfully
<pb n="59" facs="unknown:019212_0058_0FAA6775AEA75C00"/>inſult," and ſo again I ſay do you. Now elder James this is a picture to the life in every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and was I a Shaker I ſhould know it to be mine. Firſt, they then ſaid Chriſt was come, and the millennium begun, and in three years time the great and grand revolution was to be accompliſhed, &amp;c. and they had all the gifts and operations by the accounts that you pretend to, to evince the truth of their decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and they were as bold and confident as you, and after all they got defeated in Bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilfieds, at the grave of Doctor Ames, and thence became a blot in the annals of England, and will remain ſo to all future poſterity no doubt. Notwithſtanding all which, a little number of you, a woman at the head, who I have no doubt were Papiſts, have rallied again with a raft of Popiſh tenets, and have made another ſally, declaring that Chriſt is come in you, for the ſame end and purpoſe that the others pretended, fixing the time at eleven years from the beginning of your miniſtry at Niſqueuniah for the accompliſhment of the conſummation of all things, at which time alſo your millennium began, or in other words uſurpation began—five of which years are already paſſed. But again, ſee F. C's remark, page 38, "and ſo when they whiſtle and hiſs, and drum, and trumpet in their extacies, and take theſe things with many other childiſh and fantaſtick motions for evident marks of
<pb n="60" facs="unknown:019212_0059_0FAA677668A48698"/>a gracious viſitation, and when the ſpirit em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys them to beat and thump, and cuff, and trample upon one another, and to play tricks like merry Andrews upon a ſtage. Can this be the ſpirit of God,"—theſe are exactly his words of what was among them, and certainly the ſame is among you; except the words drum and trumpet. Again this author ſays con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the church of Rome, page 42, "the hiſtories of the lives of their ſaints are full of viſions, extraordinary revelations and exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies." And again he ſays, page 43, "the Romiſh church has he-ſains and ſhe-ſaints, famous for viſions and revelations, from one age to another." Here I would obſerve, that the church of Rome, that mother of harlots, and abominations of the earth, have had thoſe what you call gifts of viſions, revelations, and propheſy for many ages; the French prophets the ſame, and you the ſame—all pretending perfection, and yet are known to have lived at the ſame time in the moſt ſcandalous vices, both they and you. I have read of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious zeal of the Papiſts, beſides the bloody inquiſition, that thought it a virtue, and have committed many murders upon thoſe of a different perſuaſion; and alſo among the French prophets and their adherents in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, of whom I have been treating. We have this account page 51, "another of them that has been charged with killing ſeveral
<pb n="61" facs="unknown:019212_0060_0FAA67782D231978"/>perſons in cold blood, from which charge he has never yet cleared himſelf as I can hear of, has declared in the hearing of many, that he would murder his own father if he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to do it by inſpiration," And from what I have ſeen of the violences committed among you, I have many times feared that murder would be done, even among your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in your diſcipline; beſides the rage and threatnings of ſome of your people againſt their oppoſers, and all as they pretend in the gifts of God. But once more, with which I ſhall conclude this head: ſee Edmund Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my's treatiſe, page 47, "the late ſtory of Mr. Maſon, in Buckinghamſhire, ought not to be forgotten, he firmly expected the appearance of Chriſt in a little village in that county, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Water-Stratford, to conduct his people from thence to Jeruſalem, and begin the mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iennium. But about the very time that was fixed for Chriſt's appearance, Mr. Maſon died and left a company of poor deluded people behind him, who continued together praying and dancing and ſinging night and day in hopes of Chriſt's ſudden appearance among them. But after long waiting to no purpoſe they at laſt deſpaired." Now elder James it is evident by the events that all theſe referred to, and many others that might be mentioned were deceived, and their poor deluded follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſadly diſappointed, whoſe credentials I
<pb n="62" facs="unknown:019212_0061_0FAA67790A4ADB70"/>think were exactly the ſame of yours; and what greater likelihood is there of your ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding than they. Perhaps you will ſay that you have taken up a greater croſs than they, in refraining or forbidding marriage, and that you mortify the fleſh with more bodily exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe than any of them ever did. Well that is true, which yet gives me but greater doubt of your ſucceſs</p>
            <p>In the next place I ſhall proceed to conſider ſome paſſages of ſcripture in relation to ſome of your doctrines and character.</p>
            <p>Firſt then: You ſay, as I underſtand, that the firſt ſin, that our firſt parents committed in the garden of Eden, was the act of copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that being the forbidden fruit, which I desire you to reconcile with the command of God to them: to be fruitful and multiply, and repleniſh the earth, Gen. 1—28. You ſay, If I underſtand you, that Eve was the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den tree, that Adam was forbid to touch on pain of death, which however agrees not with ſcripture, for the tree of knowledge of good and evil was in the garden before the woman exiſted, and Adam forbid to cat of it, ſee Gen. 2—9 and 17 verſe. Now obſerve, the act of copulation could not be the forbidden fruit, becauſe that could not be pertaken but toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and at once; but Eve pertook of it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately from her huſband, as you may ſee Gen. 3—6, as alſo I. Tim. 2—14, therefore
<pb n="63" facs="unknown:019212_0062_0FAA677981C42DD0"/>what ever elſe it might be, the woman was not the tree, nor the act of copulation the fruit here ſpoken of; conſequently theſe paſſages of ſcripture muſt be wrong, if you be right.—Obſerve again, Adam was ſorbid to touch the forbidden tree, Gen. 3—3; but concerning his wife it is ſaid, Gen. 2—24, therefore ſhall a man leave his father and mother and ſhall cleave unto his wife, and they ſhall be one fleſh, which could not be but by a touch of copulation, which was it that made them one fleſh. This deſtroys the idea of the woman's being the tree that Adam was forbid to touch. This therefore proves your hypotheſis to be falſe, which is the grand fundamental pillar of your whole ſyſtem, which muſt go head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long for want of a better foundation. Again, you ſay, that all marriages were and are of the devil, firſt and laſt. Here again you are too faſt, for marriage was inſtituted and performed in the garden before the fall, as appears Gen. 2d chap. 22d 23d 24th verſes, and the rib which the Lord God had taken from man made he a woman, and brought her unto the man, and Adam ſaid, this is now bone of my bone and fleſh of my fleſh: ſhe ſhall be called woman becauſe ſhe was taken out of man: therefore ſhall a man leave his father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſhall cleave unto his wife, and they ſhall be one fleſh. This is marriage in every ſenſe of it: for its proper definition is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="64" facs="unknown:019212_0063_0FAA677A29170718"/>and joining together. Is it not therefore preſumptuous to contradict ſcripture? And call this of the devil? Again Gen. 24th chap. wherein you may ſee the godlineſs, the ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and inſpiration of Iſaac and Rebeckah's marriage, of the angels attending, verſe 7, the bleſſing and prediction of Rebecka's being the mother of thouſands and millions, and that her ſeed ſhould poſſeſs the gate of thoſe that hate them, as in verſe 60, and preceeding this in the 50th verſe, then Laban and Bethuel anſwered and ſaid, the thing proceedeth from Lord—but you ſay from the devil. Therefore I deſire you to conſider whether you be able to diſpute this point with God. Again, ſee Matt. 19—4—5—6, and he anſwered and ſaid unto them, have ye not read that he which made them at the beginning made them male and female, and ſaid for this cauſe ſhall a man leave father and mother and ſhall cleave to his wife, and they twain ſhall be one fleſh. And what follows in the 6th verſe is the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Chriſt's own words: wherefore they are no more twain, but one fleſh: what there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God has joined together let no man put aſunder. Here obſerve, Chriſt acknowledges that God joined them together, and forbids man to put them aſunder; but you ſay the devil joined them together, and go about to put them aſunder, in which you both contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict Chriſt and break his command. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
<pb n="65" facs="unknown:019212_0064_0FAA677B07B943B0"/>Paul in his goſpel ſays, Eph. 5—22 wives ſubmit yourſelves unto your own huſbands as unto the Lord: verſe 23, for the huſband is the head of the wife, even as Chriſt is the head of the church, &amp;c. therefore as the church is ſubject unto Chriſt, ſo let the wives be to their own huſbands in every thing; verſe 25, huſbands love your wives, even as Chriſt alſo loved the church, &amp;c. verſe 28, ſo ought men to love their wives as their own bodies: he that loveth his wife loveth himſelf: verſe 29, for no man ever yet hated his own fleſh, but nouriſheth and cheriſheth it, even as the Lord the church. Then in reference to the ſacred inſtitution of marriage, in the ſame words before quoted ſays, verſe 31, for this cauſe ſhall a man leave his father and mother, and ſhall be joined unto his wife, and they two ſhall be one fleſh. Mark, ſeveral things may be noted from this paſſage of ſcripture: firſt, that the Apoſtle makes uſe of the marriage ſtate and union between the huſband &amp; wife to repreſent the marriage ſtate and union between Chriſt and the church; by which he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth the marriages that you diſown, and gives ſpecial rules for them to go by. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that theſe rules and commands were given to huſbands and wives as ſuch, who were at the ſame time alſo married to Chriſt, ſee Rom. 7, hence learn, that being married to a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth not hinder us from being married
<pb n="66" facs="unknown:019212_0065_0FAA677BB514F570"/>to Chriſt, which you deny. Thirdly, the very terms of huſband and wife, ſuppoſes marriage.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, if marriages were all of the devil, I wonder the Apoſtle ſhould make uſe of that for a compariſon of the ſpiritual ſtate and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion between Chriſt and his church. Again, St. Paul ſays, Heb. 13—4, marriage is honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in all, and the bed undefiled; but whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers and adulterers God will judge—which being given out in poſitive terms, in the new covenant miniſtration, I think is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to decide all controverſies, and ſtill the clamours that may ariſe on this head. But to return, with reference to the forbidden fruit, you ſay as I ſaid before that it was the act of copulation between Adam and Eve, and is ſtill forbidden fruit to every man and his wife, therefore it is incumbent on you to ſhew where it is forbidden and by whom, that I &amp; others may believe it upon better authority than your bare aſſertion. I deſire you would anſwer this queſtion if you are able, or own that I was right in ſaying you had renounced or at leaſt did not go by the bible, for if you cannot prove that act to be forbidden by God, then certainly you are miſtaken in calling that the forbidden fruit, which was not nor is not forbidden. I know that for me o copulate with another man's wife, or to ſteal another man's goods would be forbidden fruit, becauſe God hath commanded ſaying, thou ſhalt not
<pb n="67" facs="unknown:019212_0066_0FAA677C72825410"/>commit adultery—thou ſhalt not ſteal; but I am far from believing that Adam's copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating with his wife, when he was implicitly bid to do it, was the occaſion of his fall, for it was certainly and inſeparably connected with multiplying, and his ſin conſiſted only in breaking the command of God: for where no law is, there is no tranſgreſſion, Rom. 4, 15. Again, ſin is not imputed when there is no law, Rom. 5—13. And again, nay I had not known ſin, but by the law, for I had not known laſt, except the law had ſaid, thou ſhalt not covet, Rom. 7—7, therefore except you can produce the law of God that forbids copulation between man and wife, you cannot make it a ſin, and conſequently that could not be the cauſe of Adam's fall. And again, except you can produce the law of God that forbids marriage, you cannot make it a ſin, and therefore not of the devil, as you pretend. And St. Paul ſays, I. Cor. 7—28, but and if thou marry, thou haſt not ſinned, and if a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin marry ſhe hath not ſinned. Now elder James by what has been ſaid it is evident, that you deny and contradict the ſcripture, both of the old and new teſtament, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by have departed from the faith of thoſe holy men, that wrote the ſcriptures, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muſt fall into that character given by St. Paul, I. Tim. 4th chap. which I ſhall attend to in the next place.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="unknown:019212_0067_0FAA677D2C33B068"/>
I. Tim. 4—1, Now the ſpirit ſpeaketh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, that in the latter times ſome ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the faith, giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits and doctrines of devils, verſe 2 ſpeaking lies in hypocriſy, having their conſcience ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a hot iron, verſe 3, forbidding to marry, &amp;c. Here elder James is one of the blackeſt characters I think what we can find in the bible, which is given of a people that ſhould ariſe in the latter times, which particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly belongs to thoſe that are found in this character, let them be who or where they will.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Apoſtle ſays, that in the latter times ſome ſhall depart from the faith, viz. the Apoſtle's faith and goſpel, then certainly thoſe that renounce it, calling all that is written in the bible letter, old heavens, and a back diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, and that Chriſt therein teſtified of that we believe in, and depend on for ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to be anti-chriſt, the devil, old belzebub, high king of hell, which are Samuel Fitch's words and terms for it, and to which you alſo agree. I ſay I think ſuch have to all intents departed from the faith, in the ſenſe of the text, giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits and doctrines of devils, as if he ſhould ſay, giving heed to them ſpirits that deceive, miſlead, and debauch people: ſee the definition agreeable with that Rev. 2—20, notwithſtanding I have a few things againſt thee, becauſe thou ſuffereſt that woman Jezebel, which calleth herſelf a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheteſs,
<pb n="69" facs="unknown:019212_0068_0FAA677DF56F8120"/>to teach and ſeduce, to wit, deceive, miſlead, and debauch my ſervants, tho' God has expreſsly ſaid, I. Tim. 2—12, but I ſuffer not a woman to teach, nor to uſurp authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over the man; but to be in ſilence; as in I. Cor. 14—34, let your women keep ſilence in the churches, for it is not permitted unto them to ſpeak, but they are commanded to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der obedience, as alſo ſaith the law; but Jez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebel never would obey God, but will be ſeduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, viz. deceiving, miſleading, and debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the people. Here obſerve, there was Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebel in the days of Elijah the prophet, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer and a Jezebel in the days of John the revelater, a ſeducer and a Jezebel ſtill; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the mother or any other woman call herſelf a propheteſs and ſet up for a teacher and leader, uſurping authority over men, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, miſlead, and debauch people, ſhe comes full into the character of Jezebel, and is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer. Tho' all fraud it is true originates from the devil, firſt and laſt, he being the old ſeducer, that deceived the deceivers, and ſet themſelves to deceive others, as you and the mother deceived me, for it is certain that you deceived me when I came firſt among you, by inſinuating and pretending that you was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and had attained to compleat redemption from ſin, and that if we would obey your doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, we ſhould be ſoon there too, which I found to be nothing but a cheat, for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="70" facs="unknown:019212_0069_0FAA677EC41FC940"/>I went with you, the further I had to go, and the more I did the more I had to do, and inſtead of freedom and millennium glory, as I expected, I found the greateſt bondage and ſlavery, and to give thee all we had beſides, &amp; at laſt go to purgatory for what I could ſee. Thus was I deceived by you, and ſo I believe are all thereſt; and as to your perfection, that may be ſeen by the accounts in this letter: and again, as to our being miſled by you, I think it was wholly a forſaking God and Chriſt, and depending upon you for ſalvation, which will fail every one that truſts to it, if the bible be true; for that ſays curſed is man, that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arm; and again, it is certain your people are debauched, by having their civility, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and I think their morality alſo deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and becoming the moſt profane, deſulto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, foul-mouth'd people, I believe that ever made any pretenſions to Goodneſs; and not only in words but alſo in behaviour, as may be ſeen in the former part of this letter. All which proves you to be ſeducers; having been yourſelves ſeduced, whoſe doctrine as ſuch, muſt be doctrines of devils. Verſe 2d. Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lies in hypocriſy, having their conſcience ſear'd with a hot iron. I have already ſpoken ſomething in particular, in relation to this; and therefore I ſhall only add, that from my general obſervations, I do really think, that I
<pb n="71" facs="unknown:019212_0070_0FAA677F68CE9438"/>never ſaw ſuch a falſe people as you. I think none but ſuch whoſe conſcience is ſear'd with a hot iron, could ſo wholly give themſelves up to falſe propheſy, falſe accuſations, and falſe reports as you do; I mean you all as a ſect, and for the truth of this, I appeal to all that are well acquainted with you. Verſe 3d. for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding to marry, and commanding to abſtain from meats, which God hath created to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with thankſgiving, of them which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and know the truth. Verſe 4th. For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very creature of God is good, and nothing to be refuſed, if it be received with thankſgiving: verſe 5th. For it is ſanctified by the word of God and prayer. Here it is plain, the Apoſtle ſpeaks of forbidding to marry, as a grand ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial article in the doctrines of devils, which is given as a diſtinguiſhing mark of thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers here ſpoken of. And now that you might ſee, that you have departed from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles goſpel, and conſequently from the faith; I refer you to 1 Tim. 3d chap. where the ſame Apoſtle gives the character of Biſhops and Deacons, each having a wife and children, and yet chief officers in the church of Chriſt: that it might be ſeen and known, in thoſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times ſpoken of by the ſpirit, that there was no ſuch thing, as forbidding to marry, in the church of Chriſt: and that thereby thoſe deceivers ſpoken of in the latter times, that ſhould ariſe, forbidding to marry, might be
<pb n="72" facs="unknown:019212_0071_0FAA6781571F1CF8"/>more eaſily known and detected. Now elder James, by this you ought to be convinced of your error, in forbidding to marry: and that you do forbid to marry, is certainly true, I have often heard you deny it, and as often heard you forbid it, at leaſt implicitly, I can inſtance particulars, wherein you have forbid, and even prevented marriages, to wit. Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah Kindale has often told in publick that ſhe was juſt going to be married to the man ſhe loved before ſhe fell in with you. Jonathan Shoſſon was going to be married to Hannah Goodrich; Job Biſhop was going to have Deſier Sanford; William Miles and Mary Clerk as I have heard—many more I could mention that are now on my mind, that were likely agreed to marry, but were broken off and terrified out of it by you: nor do you allow any in your community, but ſuch as wholly renounce marriages: and thoſe that were married before, you part them forever or diſown them; and for a further conformation of this I can ſay I was preſent with the mother one time at Aſhfield, when ſhe undertook to break the marriage of Pitman Cook and his wife, and I aſſiſted therein, and dar'd not do otherwiſe, for fear of falling under her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. The manner was this, ſhe having prepoſſeſſed the minds of her people, that ſhe herſelf was that battle-ax and weapon of war, ſpoken of in Jeremiah 51—20 that was to
<pb n="73" facs="unknown:019212_0072_0FAA6781CE591498"/>break in pieces the nations and deſtroy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms: ſhe was to break in pieces the horſe and his rider: the chariot and his rider: ſhe was to break in pieces man and woman, old and young: the young man and the maid, &amp;c. She ſaid it was their luſt brought them together, and that he that married them was not a man of God, and therefore what he did was not of God, but of the devil, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore void, not regarding what is ſpoken by Malachi, 2d chap. 14—15—16 verſe, the whole paragraph to which I refer you, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to read: and I ſuppoſe they hold their marriage to be void, and themſelves acquit from each other ever ſince, for they call their marriage covenant a covenant of death and hell, and ſo do many if not all the reſt. At another time at Harwood, I being preſent, Samuel Fitch, I ſuppoſe by the mother's di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection brought in his wife and ſon, and I think daughter too, that being all his family, ordered them to kneel down, then kneeled down with them himſelf, in the midſt of an aſſembly of their own sort of people, then in the audience of the whole, in a ſolemn man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, renounced his wife and children, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his wife and children ever any more, and forbid his wife ever eſteeming him her huſband again, declaring ſhe was no more his wife, nor he her huſband—this I ſaw and heard, which was deſigned as I ſuppoſed to give a lead to
<pb n="74" facs="unknown:019212_0073_0FAA6782681012B0"/>others. Beſides the ſevere chaſtiſements and many methods taken by you to ſet men and women, huſbands and wives at the greateſt diſtance in affection from each other. now elder James are not theſe things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to marry in the higheſt ſenſe? and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not this with what elſe has been ſaid, which I defy you to deny, bring you full into the character here given by St. Paul, of thoſe that depart from the faith, giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits and doctrines of devils, ſpeaking lies in hypocrify having their conſcience ſeared with a hot iron, forbidding to marry &amp;c. what follows in the 4th and 5th verſe being a declaration, of Gods approbation to the marriage rights; I ſhall paſs to another obſervation in the ſame chap. Verſe 7th. But refuſe prophane and old wife's fables; and exerciſe thyſelf rather unto Godlineſs: verſe 8th, for bodily exerciſe profiteth little, &amp;c. verſe 9th, this is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation. Here obſerve, it is evident to me at leaſt, that the mother was a very profane old wife, and that her doctrines were meer fables, being I think altogether unſcriptural, and her religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted much in bodily exerciſe, and therefore of little profit: this is another characteriſtick given by the Apoſtle in the ſame chapter with the above, and then concludes emphatically in the following words, this is a faithful ſaying and worthy of all acceptation, which is a clear
<pb n="75" facs="unknown:019212_0074_0FAA6784EC668038"/>manifeſtation of the Apoſtle's diſapprobation of what you make ſo much account of you laying the whole ſtreſs of our ſalyation upon our faith in and obedience to an old wife's ſables and great bodily exerciſes, which the Apoſtle ſets nothing at all by. Herein there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore appears a great difference between you and the Apoſtles, which you account for by the introduction of a new diſpenſation, which however I think brings you into a moſt dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful character according to ſcripture predic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now elder James by what has been ſaid it is evident, that however wrong all others may be, you cannot be right, if the ſcriptures be true: and tho' you may pretend to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond them, and hence take liberty to go con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to them, I deſire you to read this adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement of a runaway, departed from the faith: take warning and return, left you be taken up by it and puniſhed according to the rule which the ſcriptures gives in ſuch caſes. Again, II. Theſſ. 2—4, who oppoſeth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhiped, ſo that he as God ſitteth in the temple of God ſhewing himſelf that he is God. This is a deſcription of the man of ſin, the ſon of perdition, that ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed before the coming of Chriſt, as appears in the preceeding verſes, and in the 19th verſe ſays, for the myſtery of iniquity doth already work, only he who now letteth will let, until
<pb n="76" facs="unknown:019212_0075_0FAA6785CAD5F0E8"/>he be taken out of the way; as if he ſhould ſay, that which is myſterious and out of ſight, and yet iniquitous doth already work, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting Chriſt and the true religion, and that by a miſt of darkneſs and the power of decep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it would let or hinder the man of ſin as ſuch being diſcovered or revealed, even until the time of Chriſt's coming, at which time the myſtery of iniquity, which is a deception, a cheat and fraud ſhall be taken out of the way; verſe 8th, and then ſhall that wicked be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the ſpirit of his mouth, and ſhall deſtroy with the brightneſs of his coming, viz. then the man of ſin which is it that oppoſeth every thing both good and had that ſtand, in the way of its own exaltation and honour, wanting the pre-eminence and exalting itſelf above God, ſhould be deſtroyed, to wit, Anti-Chriſt, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Chriſt, and counterfeit religion, mixed with pride, ſelf and vain glory; and this is that abomination of deſolation, ſpoken of by Daniel the prophet, ſtanding in the holy place, and referred to by our faviour, Matt. 24—15, which when we ſee we ſhould flee from it, and which the coming of Chriſt will be the deſtruction of not only in a political and general ſenſe, at his final and laſt coming, but alſo in every individual elect ſoul, in whom he comes by his ſpirit through all ages down to that day, and it cannot be otherwiſe, for where ever and
<pb n="77" facs="unknown:019212_0076_0FAA67874BC5CB40"/>whenever Chriſt comes, the man of ſin is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown; therefore where the man of ſin is, Chriſt is not come, either in a general or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual ſenſe—but more eſpecially in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter days, according to the ſenſe of the apoſtle, when the myſtery of iniquity ſhall riſe to the heighth, and the man of ſin exalt himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all that is called God in the religious ſyſtem: the appearing of Chriſt ſhall conſume and deſtroy with the brightneſs of his come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; verſe 9, even him whoſe coming is after the working of Satan, with all power and ſigns and lying wonders, by which it is evident, that juſt before the coming of Chriſt there ſhould a people ariſe, in whom Satan would work with all power of deluſion, deception, and ſigns and lying wonders, which undoubtedly are the ſame that Chriſt ſpeaks of Matt. 24—24, for there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſigns and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, inſomuch, that if it were poſſible, they ſhall deceive the very elect; and bids us nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther believe nor follow them. Again. Rev. 13—13, and he doeth great wonders, ſo that he maketh fire come down from heaven on the earth in the ſight of men; verſe 14, and deceiveth them that dwell on the earth, by means of theſe miracles which he had power to do in the ſight of the beaſt. And again, Rev. 16—13, and I ſaw three unclean ſpirits like frogs come out of the mouth of the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,
<pb n="78" facs="unknown:019212_0077_0FAA6787B08F59C8"/>and out of the mouth of the beaſt, and out of the mouth of the falſe prophet; verſe 14th, for they are the ſpirits of devils working miracles, &amp;c. then in the 15th verſe, Chriſt ſays, behold I come as a thief. Here obſerve, in this paſſage in the Rev. Chriſt comes as a thief, after the going forth of theſe miraculous deceivers, which juſt agrees with what St. Paul has juſt been ſaying, that Chriſt's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is after, or not until after the working of Satan, with all power, and ſigns, and lying wonders; from whence we learn, that in theſe latter days, there ſhould ariſe falſe Chriſt's, falſe prophets and deceivers, with all power, even the power of miracles, and ſigns, and lying wonders.</p>
            <p>And indeed herein lies the power of decep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; all which great and wonderful things, is yet no evidence of their being the people of God; But the contrary; eſpecially if they oppoſe and exalt themſelves, pretending to be Chriſt, and at the ſame time, having baſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rale; working as in verſe 10th with all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs &amp;c. which juſt completes the character of thoſe deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers here ſpoken of, verſe 11th, and for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhould believe a lie; verſe 12, that they all might be demned who believed not the truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs. Now elder James I having made ſome obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations
<pb n="79" facs="unknown:019212_0078_0FAA67887583DFF8"/>in referrence to a few paſſages of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture under this head: ſhall in the next place proceed to make a compariſon of what I have found among you, with what is here written.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, It is certain that you oppoſe ev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery thing that does not acknowledge your miſſion and miniſtry, which being contrary to the bible, you oppoſe that, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the divine author of it too and even ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to go contrary to his commands, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what is written, as a thing invalid and out of date; and it is as certain, that you do oppoſe all mankind, of all ranks and degrees ſects and denominations of men under hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, condemning them altogether, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring they will all go to hell, that do not acknowledge you to be the only lead of God in the world, and ſubject themſelves to your miniſtry; you oppoſe every argument that can be raiſed, and every text of ſcripture, that can be produced in ſupport of any other reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion but your own. This I think is oppoſing and at the ſame time exalting yourſelf, for juſt as much as you run down others, you exalt yourſelf; and not only ſo, but you plainly ſay, there is no God that can ſave ſouls, but what is in you, the elders and the mother, and there has been great pains taken to bring me and others into this belief, for indeed I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver could believe it: and I hear that ſome of your people begin to declare openly, that James
<pb n="80" facs="unknown:019212_0079_0FAA6675CE32B848"/>Whittacor is the faviour of the world, and you ſuffer and even order your people to kneel down to you: when the angel would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer John the Revelator to fall down to him; nor would the apoſtle Peter ſuffer Cornelius to do the like to him; and God has alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded ſaying, thou ſhalt have no other Gods before me: thou ſhalt not bow down thyſelf to them, nor ſerve them, Exod. 20—5; but you preſume upon it, and require that ack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledgment paid to you. Is not this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing and exalting yourſelf above all that is called God? according to the character given of ſuch; and is not this implicitly calling yourſelf God, and robbing him of his glory; bending the people's whole attention to you as God, and you terrifying them to it, taking the whole government and controul of them, and their intereſt too, wholly depriving them of the liberty of ſeeing and believing for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or knowing any thing but what you tell them concerning their ſouls—and this juſt comes to what Samuel Fitch ſaid, as I told you before, that he had no other Chriſt to look to but the mother; and ſince ſhe was dead, you take the throne and are become ſupreme judge of quick and dead—this you pretend abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if I underſtand you. I ſay is not this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting yourſelf above all that is called God? it aſtoniſhes me to think, that any mortal ſhould have their conſcience ſo ſeared, as to
<pb n="81" facs="unknown:019212_0080_0FAA6675F8DD4040"/>make ſuch pretenſions; you certainly know that you are not God: then how dare you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your people, to deify and make a God of you, who are but a poor frail mortal, as the mother and elder William was, who pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame things, and are dead. I wonder you are not afraid of being ſmitten of God, and eaten of worms as Herod was for the ſame thing. But the ſcriptures muſt be fulfilled: there muſt be ſome that oppoſe and exalt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above all that is called God, or that is worſhiped—ſo that they as God ſet in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, or the church, or the religious ſyſtem, there ſhewing themſelves to be God, which is the man of ſin, the ſon of perdition. But ſecondly, with reſpect to the myſtery of iniquity among you, I can ſay that I have been confounded many times, not knowing how to account for ſuch inconſiſtencies, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile ſuch high appearances of religion and ſincerity, with ſuch wickedneſs and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions at the ſame time, in the ſame perſons; nothing was more common among you, than to uſe the moſt prophane language, eſpecially when chaſtizing others—yet in the higheſt zeal of religion; and to uſe equivocations and deceit under a pretence of defending the cauſe of God, and even when in liquor much more reſolute for God againſt ſin than at other times. Your perſuading of us that liquor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated right the contrary in you that were
<pb n="82" facs="unknown:019212_0081_0FAA6676AE28A680"/>perfect to what it did in them that were not: that whereas it influenced them to ſerve the devil; it animated you to ſerve God: and even in the times of your intoxications, there would be an appearance of the mighty power and gifts of God in you, as you call it: I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo have took notice that by the greateſt fits of anger, rage and execrations againſt ſomebody or other, you would find the greateſt releaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as if your ſouls were ſolaced in heaven. One thing a man told me that he ſaw of a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel between the mother and elder William, that was very ſharp and bloody, with many hard blows, and dreadful curſing and outrage, till they were both maul'd and bruiſed by each other, and directly after the people were chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized for falſe judging, and this ſalvo put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, that Paul and Barnabas contended and parted: and Paul withſtood Peter to the face, keeping up a ſhew of religion in it; and when any of you come out againſt others, in the greateſt railleries and accuſations, many of which I have no doubt were falſe, you would turn it into a pretence of love and faithfulneſs to them; and ſo you find ways to turn every vice into a virtue, giving way to your paſſions, foul language, equivocations to ſay no worſe of it, and hard drinking, which are all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the ſcriptures, and yet all in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon practice among you in the higheſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions of religion, and attended with the
<pb n="83" facs="unknown:019212_0082_0FAA66776D54A510"/>mighty power and gifts of God to all appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. This looks I think like a myſtery of iniquity, where the greateſt abominations are committed: children abuſing their parents in the moſt ſhocking manner that ever was heard of, being ſet on by the mother and you, and ruling over their parents: and wives rul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over their huſbands, all which is againſt the laws of God and nature: yet all under the higheſt appearance of divine approbation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing attended at the ſame time with an increaſe of thoſe ſupernatural gifts. This I ſay looks like the myſtery of iniquity ſpoken of, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with that Rev. 17—5, and upon her fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head was a name written myſtery—Babylon the great—the mother of harlots—and abom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inations of the earth. But again, thirdly, it is ſaid that the coming of Chriſt is after the working of Satan, with all power and ſigns &amp; lying wonders: and this is the caſe with you, for you aſſume the prerogative of all power under heaven, and without diſtinction or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, villify and condemn it, as what muſt ſall before you, and acknowledge your mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration firſt and laſt: and beſides you pretend to the power of miracles, which if it were ſo, is no more than what the falſe prophet and unclean ſpirits could do, as before quoted: to be ſure you have power to ſcare and terrify your own people eſpecially, and make them believe juſt what you pleaſe: and indeed ſo
<pb n="84" facs="unknown:019212_0083_0FAA66782B81B9D0"/>far as I myſelf believe you to be thoſe deceivers here ſpoken of, I believe you to have the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of falſe miracles, for I have ſeen one that was of you, cauſe fire to come down from heaven, as I then thought, he being in a great rage, gave a violent ſcreech and ſtamp with his foot, at which inſtant I ſaw a flaſh of fire or lightning all at one and the ſame inſtant. Another perſon told me that he ſaw the ſame thing at another time. One time when I was at the church, as elder William came out of his room, he ſaid he heard a clap of thunder among the dead, and ſaw the lightning. Here obſerve, we read that theſe things ſhall be done by the beaſt, which includes the falſe prophet and unclean ſpirits; but not a word of any ſuch thing is ever ſaid ſhall be ſeen or done among the people of God. I would juſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay, you have the power of deception, to ſhift and turn yourſelves into every ſhape to deceive. 4thly, Signs and lying wonders every body that knows you, knows that you are full of ſigns: ſigns with the hand, polling, point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, reaching, ſwinging, touching, ſtroking, ſtriking, ſhaking, and the like: as alſo on the floor falling down, rolling, tumbling, wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, kicking, thumping, pitching over, roaring, crying, ſcreaming, hollowing <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing led about by ſigns, following the band this way and that: moreover hiſſing, mouthing, lolling out the tongue, grinning, biting, glar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="85" facs="unknown:019212_0084_0FAA6679098A7D58"/>with many ſtrange poſtures of the body and limbs: beſides great trembling, ſhaking, turning, twitching, ſtamping with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> voice, now and then hollowing out ſharp and ſudden. Now whether you call theſe ſigns good or bad, they are among you, and exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agree with this prediction, and where do you ſee it elſe? 5thly, Lying wonders and ſigns without meaning or ſignification, are the ſame thing: yet there are other things that may more properly be conſidered as what is meant by lying wonders, to wit. viſions, which are very frequent and wonderful, yet little or no truth in them, and nothing to be known by them as I can ſee.</p>
            <p>Even the mother's viſions were no better, for I have often heard of a viſion that ſhe had of you, in which ſhe ſaw you in the very act of copulation with a woman; which you muſt own was a lying wonder, or betray your guilt; either of which dethrones you. Again Eleazer Goodrich's revelation at Amos Rath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bun's, where he charged a man with mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering a perſon in times paſt, and of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a deſign then of murdering a woman, and her two children, and to prevent which, ſent two men privately to watch the houſe the night it was to be done, which turned out to be a lying wonder. I did not ſee this myſelf; but often heard the ſtory and believed it, even altho' I was then in that faith;
<pb n="86" facs="unknown:019212_0085_0FAA6679B2C2B0A0"/>but I ſaw him a day or two after at Ezekiel Goodrich's, where as though he was Chriſt, took the judgment ſeat, cut off anumber of ſouls, and ſentenced them to hell; baptized ſeveral perſons in the name of the Trinity; and ſaying he that betrayed him was at hand: then putting one hand to his forehead, puſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it back and with the other hand, with his forefinger, would ſaw acroſs his throat, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating the ſign ſeveral times over, and ſaying again, that he that betrayed him was at hand; and that in three days, he ſhould be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; at which I, and I believe all the reſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, thought that the man, whom he had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of murder at Amos Rathbun's, had a deſign againſt his life; for I found by his expreſſions, that it was he that ſhould betray him; I tarried till late at night before I went home, and afterward enquired, and found that nobody came neither then, nor afterward to give him any diſturbance; which though attended with ſuch a mighty power, and ſigns, as would ſcare people into the belief of it; yet was but a lying wonder. I could menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the names of a conſiderable number of perſons that have been cut off, and received the ſentence of damnation from thoſe that have aſſumed the judgment ſeat, one of which was confirmed by the mother; who has ſince been reſtored, and is now in good ſtanding among you: and I was knowing that his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="87" facs="unknown:019212_0086_0FAA667C2FE91B30"/>was everlaſting woe; and never to find repentance: I have been often ſcared and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified almoſt out of my wits by ſuch things, till I found that great part if not all, was but lying wonders: I have had to run to the relief of your people in Tyringham, with all ſpeed while I was in that way, who were in the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt confuſion, almoſt in diſtraction and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, by the havock which William Allen and his wife, and ſome others made in that place, by their lying wonders; yea one of them that was a believer in your way told me, that in one of his wives high religious turns, he never ſaw any creature ſo full of lying won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as ſhe was. I ſaw the mother one time, in a great rage with one of Elijah Wiles's ſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for ſomething ſhe had ſaid about the church, ſhe cut her off, and gave her wholly to the devil as I took it, and ſaid, that within a fortnight ſhe would hang herſelf, as there was a God. Theſe I think were exactly her words, which terrified me very much, believing then as I had been taught, that not one of her words could fail; but no ſuch thing happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for I have long ſince ſeen the girl alive and well. At another time, I heard the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tell a viſion to Nathan Goodrich, how ſhe ſaw the great angel of God going forth, blowing his trumpet, and his brother Ezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el that was dead was with him, and that ſhe had a particular command from them, or
<pb n="88" facs="unknown:019212_0087_0FAA667D5951AC98"/>from God, to come to his houſe, and warn him of approaching death; and admoniſh him to ſet his houſe in order. This is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a year and half age, and the man is yet alive and well I believe, for I live not far from him. There was alſo a propheſy, uttered by one of the brethren, that Albany ſhould be deſtroyed within one year from that time, which is I think about three years ago; but I heard but lately it ſtands ſafe yet; and all with the greateſt aſſurances, and yet abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lying wonders; and what makes them ſuch, is becauſe they are not true, for the events prove it; and yet you have the confidence to threaten people with the judgments of God, damnation and the bottomleſs pit, if they do not believe, and ſubject to your lead and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; by which many are terrified into it; others being won by flatteries are taken in and lod away byit. But 6thly, deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, making uſe of ſcripture, ſuch as ſuits your turn, to catch and entangle them that hear you, when at the ſame time it is a declared principle among thoſe of you that are ſtrong, that you are in a new day and diſpenſation, beyond the bible and do not mean to go by it, nor make any rule of it; at the ſame time you will hold forth certain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect rules in ſcripture, to convict people of their imperfection and ſhort coming, and thereby deſtroy all the faith, in what they had
<pb n="89" facs="unknown:019212_0088_0FAA667E425843F8"/>received, and by telling them that you are perfect draw them away after you: is not this deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, firſt to make uſe of ſcripture to decoy and catch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which you will not own nor go by your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? ſecondly, to deſtroy all their former faith by the ſcripture, and build them up in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother without the ſcripture, often quoting your viſions, revelations, unknown tongues and propheſy, as the infallible evidence of your being the only people of God in the world: which however I think, upon a proper diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of matters, is no more nor leſs, then what is given in this and the like character, as the diſtinguiſhing marks, of the greateſt deceivers ſpoken of in the whole bible. I have been much burdened latterly, with almoſt all your expoſitions of ſcripture; believing that you corrupted the word, and perverted the people; whether ignorantly or deſignedly I leave; but you would certainly read wrong, and put a wrong conſtruction upon it; which whether it were ignorance or craft in you, it certainly diſqualifies you for the high ſtation you aſſume, and proves there is no ſuch thing as perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and infallibillity in you, as you pretend. I ſhall give but only one inſtance, Rom. 11, 22. Behold therefore the goodneſs and ſeverity of God, on them which fell, ſeverity; which was ſpeaking of the fall of the Jews through unbelief. But you would read it thus, on
<pb n="90" facs="unknown:019212_0089_0FAA667EF1DCB5A0"/>them which feel ſeverity, perſuading the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the words, that it was the goodneſs of God to them for to feel ſeverity, and take the liberty to be more ſevere, and cruel to them as I thought. This you would often menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and whether you know better yet, or not, I cannot tell; for I was ſo kept under I dared not tell you of it. Now elder James, upon the whole, if you ſhould deny this character here given by St. Paul to be yours, I beg you would tell me whoſe it is, and make out the compariſon to demonſtration as I have done, in reference to you, by comparing what I have found amongſt you in fact; with thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular paſſages of ſcripture herein referred to. For nothing is certainly known to be right or wrong, but by the ſacred record of truth, which is given as a rule to try the ſpirits by; which is the next thing to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>I John 4, 1, Beloved, believe not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits whether they are of God: Becauſe many falſe prophets are gone out into the world. As if he had ſaid prove them, compare and try them, by the rules that I give you, and by the written word of God, But elder James, you will not allow of it; But you ſay, we muſt believe and obey what you ſay at a venture, or go to hell: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in therefore is a trial of the ſpirits at once, verſe 2; hereby know ye the ſpirit of God; every ſpirit that confeſſeth that Jeſus Chriſt is
<pb n="91" facs="unknown:019212_0090_0FAA667FE73D16F8"/>come in the fleſh is of God: here is an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible rule given, to try the ſpirits by; and no man can ſay, that Jeſus is the Lord; but by the Holy Ghoſt; neither can any man confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, but they that have received him; viz. his ſpirit, his words and goſpel; neither can any man confeſs Chriſt, that does not know Chriſt; and he that ſaith he knows him, and keepeth not his commands is a liar, and the truth is not in him. I John 2, 4, But again, it was a thing well underſtood in the days of the Apoſtles, that Chriſt was come in the fleſh, for the deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction of the fleſh; therefore to confeſs Chriſt come in the fleſh, is to confeſs the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of ſin deſtroyed, to wit; the carnal mind which is a fleſhly mind, vicious habits, appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites and inclinations of the fleſh deſtroyed; as appears Coloſ. 2, 11, in whom alſo you are circumciſed with the circumciſion made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hands, in putting off the body of the ſins of the fleſh, by the circumciſion of Chriſt; as if he ſhould ſay, in whom alſo ye are cut off, with the cutting off made without hands, in the putting of the body of the ſins of the fleſh, by the cutting off of Chriſt; mark, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion under the law, was a figure of the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off of Chriſt, or the body of the ſins of the fleſh, which body of ſins, Chriſt takes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf, in behalf of all his elect, in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner, and was cut off for them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="92" facs="unknown:019212_0091_0FAA6680696DB298"/>as it is ſaid, that Chriſt our paſſover was ſlain for us, even ſo Chriſt our body of ſins was cut off for us; in whom we have redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through his blood; even the forgiveneſs of ſins: again, I Peter 4, 1, foraſmuch then, as Chriſt hath ſuffered for us in the fleſh, arm yourſelves with the ſame mind; for he that hath ſuffered in the fleſh, hath ceaſed from ſin. Rom. 6, 6, knowing this, that our old man is crucified with him, that the body of ſin might be deſtroyed, that henceforth we ſhould not ſerve ſin; verſe 7th for he that is dead, is freed from ſin, as if he had ſaid, by Chriſt's dying for us, we are dead to ſin:verſe 8th now if we be dead with Chriſt, we believe that we ſhall alſo live with him; which death to ſin, and life in Chriſt Jeſus, we obtain or come into poſſeſſion of, through faith in him; and not for any thing that we have done, or can do. Therefore whoſoever confeſſeth, that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſ Chriſt is come in the fleſh in a goſpel ſenſe, is of God, and feels his ſoul delivered from the fleſh, by Chriſt's coming in the fleſh, and if he cannot expreſs it experimentally for himſelf, it is no confeſſion at all; he is antichriſt or of antichriſt. Now elder James, I do not remember of ever hearing any ſuch things as theſe among you, the whole four years and half that I was with you, nor have I the leaſt idea, that you have any expectation of ſalvation by him that died on calvary, according to the
<pb n="93" facs="unknown:019212_0092_0FAA66813116F0B8"/>miniſtration given by him and his apoſtles in that day. But it was mothers miniſtry, and mothers ſufferings while ſhe lived, and now it is yours.</p>
            <p>But I deſire your further attention, Rom. 8—8, ſo then they that are in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God, to wit, they that are not delivered from the body of the ſins of the fleſh through faith in Chriſt, cannot pleaſe God, for ſuch are in the fleſh in the ſenſe of the text, and may be known by their fruit, as we find Gal. 5—19, now the works of the fleſh are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, which are theſe, adultery, fornication, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, laſciviouſneſs: verſe 20, idolatry, witchcraft, hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, ſtrifes, ſeditions, hereſies: verſe 21, envying, murders, drukenneſs, reveling, and ſuch like, of the which I tell you before, as I have alſo told you in time paſt, that they that do ſuch things ſhall not inherit the kingdom of God. Now elder James, firſt, I cannot ſay that you in particular are guilty of adultery or forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in a natural ſenſe, tho' you may be in the higheſt degree, in a ſcriptural ſenſe; but it is evident there is many that are of you, who are guilty in the natural way. 2dly, I ſuppoſe that filthy dreams defiles the fleſh, and is uncleanneſs, Jude 8 verſe, of which there is more among you I believe, than any where elſe, as I am greatly knowing, having been a father confeſſion among you. 3dly, And I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="94" facs="unknown:019212_0093_0FAA6681E9207910"/>that for you to order men and women to ſtrip naked and dance, and go ſwim together, is laciviouſneſs. 4thly, And I ſuppoſe there was never more abominable idolatry commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than there is among you, by their making a God of you, and you of yourſelf. 5thly, And I ſuppoſe that all ſeducers are witches and wizzards, and all falſe doctrines hereſies, and deluſions are witchcraft. The Galatians were bewitched in that way, which is no doubt the apoſtles meaning here. 6thly, And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred here ſpoken of evidently abounds among you, eſpecially againſt thoſe that are in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. It is a common thing to hear one and another of you expreſs your hatred againſt ſuch and ſuch ones when you are commanded to hate no man, and to love your enemies. 7thly, Again, variance, I have ſeen and heard much of even among you that call yourſelves the church, and elſewhere among you. 8thly, Emulation is envy and diſdain, ſtriving to go beyond others. And do you not ſet your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up above all others, and even envy and diſdain them; but more eſpecially thoſe that are not of you. I have heard elder John Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ington tell a man that was a believer among you, that he felt as if his ſoul diſdained the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man's ſoul. 9thly, Again, wrath is ſo apparent, their needs no particular inferences given: you call it the wrath of God, which I doubt of; but if it were ſo, where is any goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb n="95" facs="unknown:019212_0094_0FAA668445F187B8"/>rule for you to act it out in the manner you do? It is put into this catalogue as the works of the fleſh. 10thly, And again, ſtrife is among you in a high degree, far beyond what I ever ſaw it in any other people, profeſſor or prophane I think. 11th, Alſo ſedition, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up families, ſetting ſome againſt the others and bringing the greateſt confuſion, trouble and diſtreſs upon them, if they would not all come into your way. It would be too tedious to mention the number of families that are broken by what I ſuppoſe to be ſedition, one ſet againſt another: and where there is any of your ſort of people in a family, they muſt have the rules, if it be but a child, or quit the family, tho' againſt the parents will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. 12th, Again, Hereſies, I ſuppoſe, that all that is held to or preached up contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the bible, is hereſy; at leaſt I take that to be the apoſtle's ſenſe of it: and I do not ſee wherein you go by it, or according to it at all. 13th, And again envyings, I leave it to you elder James whether you do not envy me, if not, ſee if there is none elſe of you that do, for I ſuſpect them. 14th, Again, murders. I do not think that you have deſignedly mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered any body; but I believe you have been the cauſe of many deaths by driving people beyond their ſtrength: I would only give my opinion in this and leave it to God. 15th, Again, drunkenneſs, this is alſo among you,
<pb n="96" facs="unknown:019212_0095_0FAA6685F4DABF18"/>and is what I ſo often complained of, as you will likely remember, and what firſt began to open my eyes to ſee other miſdemeanours. Laſtly, revelings, are high carouſing dances, this or ſomething very much like it I think is alſo among you in the higheſt degree, all which the apoſtle ſays are the works of the fleſh: and as he had told them before, he tells them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that they that do ſuch things ſhall not inherit the kingdom of God. Now then I would make this inference, that whoever does theſe works of the fleſh, has not the body of ſin deſtroyed in him, and therefore Chriſt is not come in him, pretend what he will: nor does he, nor can he confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, and therefore not of God: he is anti-chriſt, as ſaith the apoſtle. But once more verſe 6th, we are of God: he that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God heareth us: he that is not of God, heareth not us, hereby know we the ſpirit of truth, and the ſpirit of error. Here the apoſtle peremptorily declares, that they in that day were of God, and they that know God would hear them; But you ſay you know God, and yet will not hear them, nor go by them. Here you contradict the apoſtle, and fleeing again to the horns of your old alter for refuge, by pretending that you are in a new diſpenſation beyond them, which is a covering for every variation from them. What right then have you to take this paſſage of ſcripture from them
<pb n="97" facs="unknown:019212_0096_0FAA668674AC2180"/>as you do, and apply it to yourſelves? and now call upon others in their words to come to your terms, ſaying, they that know God hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you, and they that are not of God heareth not you. Is not this impoſing upon people with craft and deception? But the apoſtle has determined it, that if you or any other will not hear them, you are not of God: and tells us that hereby we ſhall know the ſpirit of truth, and the ſpirit of error. But now having tried the ſpirit by the help of God thus far, I ſhall cloſe this head in the words of St. Paul, Eph. 4—14, that we henceforth be no more children, toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine, by the ſlight of men and cunning craftineſs whereby they lie in weight to deceive. But again for a further trial of the ſpirits by the word, in a more general ſenſe, in which I pray God give me animpartial mind, and underſtanding; Iſaiah 8, 19. And when they ſhall ſay unto you, ſeek unto them that have familiar ſpirits, and unto wiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards that peep, and that mutter; ſhould not a people ſeek unto their God? For the living to the dead? It is certain elder James, that you have a number of perſons out abroad in the world, great part of the time, if not all, who are perſuading people to ſeek unto you, and it is as certain, that ſpirits do attend you, and ſpeak to you and you to them: I do not ſay you are wizards; but I think I may ſay that
<pb n="98" facs="unknown:019212_0097_0FAA6687392ADB70"/>you are conſtantly peeping in every dark hole and corner, to ſpy out ſomething amiſs in peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And the definition of muttering, is ſpeaking confuſedly; and it appears to me, that you did all make a God of the mother; and though ſhe is dead, you ſeek to her for the living that is, them that are alive. I do now really think, I have not ſtrained any one point; but have given a ſhort and true account of things as they be. Here the prophet as much as ſays, when any ſhall ſay unto you, to ſeek to ſuch a people as this, then he ſay verſe 20th, To the law and to the teſtimony; if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them: which he refers to, as a rule to try them by; which appears to me, as an infallible proof againſt you; ſeeing you have renounced the law and teſtimony. And where, or whenever, we find a people whoſe marks and character exactly agree with this prediction, let it be in what day or age of the world it will, they are the people intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and it may be expected, that when men leave the ſcriptures, and follow their own feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and conceptions, they are not only in danger of being impoſed upon; but often run into the higheſt enthuſiaſm therefore to the law and teſtimony. Now I leave you to make what reflections you pleaſe upon it: while I proceed to another paſſage of ſcriptue. Jude 3d verſe. Beloved, when I gave all diligence
<pb n="99" facs="unknown:019212_0098_0FAA6687F21A1878"/>to write unto you, of the common ſalvation, it was needful for me to write unto you, and exhort you, that you ſhould earneſtly contend for the faith, that was once delivered to the Saints, to wit, the ſame faith that the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles had in the atoning blood and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt, according to their doctrine and teſtimony, which agrees with the prophet Iſaiah, as recited above; to the law and to the teſtimony &amp;c. And therefore there is no other law nor teſtimony, nor faith, nor ever will be that God will own; till the final, and laſt appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; as you may ſee, II Thes. 1, 10, When he ſhall come, to be glorified in his Saints, and to be admired in all them that believe; Becauſe our teſtimony among you, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in that day. Again, Jude 4th verſe, But there are certain men crept in unawares, who were before of old ordained unto this condemnation, ungodly men, turning the grace of God into laſciviouſneſs, and denying the only Lord God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. This agrees with II Peter 2, 1, Wherein they are called falſe teachers, who ſhould privily bring in damnable heriſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſwift deſtruction. I believe, that turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the grace of God into laſciviouſneſs, is turning religion into baudy and balderdaſh language and behaviour, which I have ſeen
<pb n="100" facs="unknown:019212_0099_0FAA6688AAB9BA98"/>and heard to an exceſſive degree among you, enough to abaſh and daſh the countenances, of all modeſt people. Here obſerve, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſays, it was thoſe falſe teachers, that turned the grace of God into laſciviouſneſs; and you ſet up for teachers, and are found in theſe things. He ſays thoſe ungodly men crept in unawares, and it is true we were not aware of ſuch things among you, when we firſt join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you, nor had we then any idea, of ſuch doctrines as you now hold forth, nor of ſuch diſcipline, nor of ſuch practices and behaviour ſo inconſiſtent with reaſon and ſcripture. And Peter ſays, thoſe falſe teachers. ſhould privily bring in damnable hereſies, to wit, doctrines contrary to ſcripture, even denying the Lord that bought them. And I think, I have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly ſhewn already, wherein you deny both God and Chriſt; but what is in you, as head or chief ſince the mother's death; why now elder James, I cannot ſee, but that you fall into this character, which if it be ſo, you are in danger of ſwift deſtruction. For he that is able to characteriſe from ancient times, was able to tell the fate. Jude 8 verſe, Likewiſe alſo theſe filthy dreamers defile the fleſh, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe dominion, and ſpeak evil of dignities; now whoever does theſe things, are the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or people intended: and by your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding to marry, your people are become fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy dreamers, I certainly know, by my own
<pb n="101" facs="unknown:019212_0100_0FAA6689917AA3D0"/>experience, and by the frequent confeſſions of others, for when nature is every other way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, it takes its courſe that way, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes habitual.</p>
            <p>And again, it is natural for thoſe that ſet themſelves up above all others, in power and dignity, to deſpiſe and ſpeak evil of them: which is beyond what Michael the Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, dared to do to the devil; verſe 10. But theſe ſpeak evil of thoſe things which they know not; but what they know naturally as brute beaſts; in thoſe things they corrupt themſelves. Peter ſays, and ſhall utterly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in their own corruption; verſe 11th. He pronounces a woe againſt them, and compares them with Cain, and Balaam and Core. Now elder James, I deſire not to magnify, nor to miſapply things, but certainly, Cain was a murderer, Balaam was after a reward, and Core was a gainſayer: here the apoſtle Jude was pointing out a people, that are like them; but firſt I would obſerve, that love and hatred, are the greateſt marks of diſtinction between the children of God, and the children of the devil, as you may ſee I. John 3—15, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever hateth his brother is a murderer, and ye know that no murderer hath eternal life abiding in him; but on the other hand I. John, 4—7, beloved let us love one another, for love is of God: and every one that loveth, is born of God, and knoweth God. Now to
<pb n="102" facs="unknown:019212_0101_0FAA668A682BC870"/>take you as a people you are full of violent expreſſions of hatred againſt all others, but your own ſect; and all ſuch I think are of Cain's denomination; for their is no ſuch thing as hating a brother or fellow creature in the kingdom of Chriſt: and he that hates feels like a murderer, and is ſuch, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of Cain. But again, when you firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to call upon us to give up our eſtates to you, it was with this pretence, that the poor and the rich ſhould all fare alike; but inſtead of that, the poor are neglected and much poorer than they were before, and you are living away upon what the rich bring in, and building a large veſſel with it, and likely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to carry off what you can get, and leave the poor to ſhurk for themſelves. This I take to be running greedily after the error of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam for reward—concerning whom we read, II. Peter, 2—14, an heart they have, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed with covetous practices, curſed children, verſe 15, which have forſaken the right way, and are gone aſtray, following the way of Balaam, the ſon of Boſer, who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſs. But again, with reſpect to the gainſaying of Core, he roſe up with his company, and ſaid the congregation of the Lord was all holy; and it ſeems did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to obey Moſes and Aaron, but gainſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them. And now you are riſen up with a company, ſaying the congregation of the Lord
<pb n="103" facs="unknown:019212_0102_0FAA668AF2D67720"/>are all holy—meaning your own company, and are gainſaying Moſes and Aaron, yea Chriſt and his apoſtles too, and will not obey them, nor follow their lead; but are ſet out for your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves another way. Again, verſe 17, theſe are wells without water—clouds that are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with a tempeſt, to whom the miſt of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is reſerved forever: compared with Jude 13th verſe, raging waves of the ſea foaming out their own ſhame: wandering ſtars, to whom is reſerved the blackneſs of darkneſs forever. I think theſe wells without water, may be apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applied to teachers without knowledge: and clouds carried with a tempeſt, to people driven on with the rapid ſpirit of enthuſiaſm: and raging waves of the ſea foaming out their own ſhame, to thoſe whoſe religion conſiſts much in anger and violence, and ſhameful indecenſies: and wandering ſtars to thoſe who have departed from the law and teſtimony of God—all which ſo exactly reſembles what may abundantly be ſeen among you, that I can make no diſtinction: verſe 14th, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch alſo, the ſeventh from Adam, propheſied of theſe, &amp;c. Again verſe 16th, theſe are murmurers, complainers, walking after their own luſts, and their mouth ſpeaketh great ſwelling words, having mens perſons in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration becauſe of advantage. Firſt then, I ſuppoſe that finding a great deal of fault and being often diſpleaſed, is to murmur and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain:
<pb n="104" facs="unknown:019212_0103_0FAA668D655933F8"/>and to eat and drink to exceſs, if that were all, is walking after their own luſt: and great ſwelling words are bold, confident, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous expreſſions: and to ſhew more reſpect to the rich and honorable than to the poor and deſpiſed, is an evidence of having their perſons in admiration for ſome advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage thereby. Now elder James, I leave it to you, whether you do not ſhow more reſpect and take more pains to keep <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Joſeph Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, David Meechem, Joſeph Merkum, Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah Williard, David Hammon, and ſuch like perſons, than you have done to David Mudge, Thadius Hoburt, Ebenezer Davis, and Moſes Crane—but you have loſt theſe people, and they are gone off—this is as you ſay, beyond the bible, II. Tim. 3—1, this know alſo, that in the laſt days perilous times ſhall come, that is, times of great danger—of people's being led away by deſigning men, under a pretence of religion, into what is expreſt, verſe 2d, for men ſhall be lovers of their ownſelves, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, boaſters, proud blaſphemers, diſobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy. Now elder James, there is indeed a great appearance of love among yourſelves, and of as much hatred to all others: and as to covetouſneſs God will be your judge, but this is certain, that you do take away men's eſtates, and do not give to the poor neither; but conſume it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong yourſelves. And as to your being
<pb n="105" facs="unknown:019212_0104_0FAA668EDB3C03F0"/>proud, I really think there is the greateſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of pride, haughtineſs, ſcornfulneſs, and diſdain, both in words and behaviour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, that I ever ſaw in any profeſſing people: and I think you are great boaſters of your extraordinary gifts, of your pure and ſenſeleſs lives, of your denial and croſs, in all which you go not beyond others, as I can ſee, except it be in refraining women, which is but an error: in all other things, I think you take more liberty than people generally do, and in this view of yourſelves, you look down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others with anger and diſdain, becauſe they do not do as you do, and be as good as you be. He next mentions blaſphemers, and I think for you to ſet up the mother above Chriſt, as you really did, and ſince ſhe is dead, for you and your people, to ſet yourſelf up above Chriſt, as I take it you do, is blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: and I think for you or any of you, to call every other God, and Chriſt, but what is in you the devil, old Belzebub, which you do, is alſo blaſphemy: and I think for you to curſe the God that I worſhipped, in plain and bold terms, as you have done, was alſo blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy. Then he ſays, diſobedient to parents: in your order the children of believing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, muſt obey their parents ſo long as they can keep before them; but if the child out travels his parents, in your Judgment of the matter, the child takes the lead and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="106" facs="unknown:019212_0105_0FAA668F6A0E0D60"/>of his parents, and that with great ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; But the children of unbelieving parents, muſt win them over to the faith, or quit them, though they be under age, and againſt their parents will and commands, and ever after, treat them very villainouſly in words eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally: and it may be obſerved and known, that ſuch children, are very unthankful to their parents, for any thing they ever received from them, and ſuch I believe to be unholy as is ſaid above. But again, verſe 3d: Without natural affection, truce brakers, falſe accuſers, Inconſiſtent, fierce, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good. Firſt, it is an eſſential article in your ſyſtem of religion, to wholly deſtroy and root out all natural affection: nor are they proper members of your community, till they are without natural affection; and then they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come implacable, unmerciful, as you may ſee in the ſame words: Rom. 1, 31. Secondly, truce breakers, this is called Rom. 1, 21, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant breakers, and it is true you do break the moſt ſolemn covenants, between huſbands and wives, which is apparent: and without doubt many between young men and maids, that lies hid, and it is a wonder, if many co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants have not been broken by you, that Souls has made to ſerve God, in a different way from this: and I think you do all in your power, to break the covenant of grace, and ſet people to work, a one ſide of both law and
<pb n="107" facs="unknown:019212_0106_0FAA66902D5EF5B0"/>goſpel: and to depend upon you for ſalvation. Thirdly, falſe accuſers, this is a general com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt you, and what has ſo univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incencſed people againſt you, and when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you would get buffeted for it, you would call it perſecution; when perhaps it was only for your faults. 4thly, Inconſiſtent, this is luſting, and take you as a people, I believe there is a conſtant raging, of luſt among you, being prohibited all acceſs to women. And 5thly, fierce deſpiſers, of thoſe that are good, now I think you cannot deny, but that you effect to be fierce, and if you diſcover any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, that are languid and low, you fall upon them and bounce them about, till you wake them up, and make them as fierce, as ſo many red hot heaters; till you habituate them to it, and in this frame they become ſuch fierce deſpiſers of all others that are not of them, and like them; nor will you ſuffer them to come ſhort of this: and this you call your teſtimony againſt the wicked and ſin. But again 4th verſe, Traitors, heady, high mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, lovers of pleaſure, more than lovers of God. Firſt then I remember, that when we come firſt among you, ſome were ſcrupulous of confeſſing their ſins, for fear it would be known, you told them they need not fear for that, for you kept all cloſe, and never let the world know any thing of ſuch matters; but ſince that you betray all thoſe ſecrets in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,
<pb n="108" facs="unknown:019212_0107_0FAA6690F56EB218"/>if not the particular perſons: and it is very common for one brother or ſiſter to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray another to the church, and get them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely chaſtiſed, and they are encouraged in it, yea children are ſcrutinized by the church, and made to betray every thing they know a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their parents, which I have ſeen, and it looks to me like treachery. Again, 2dly, heady, high minded, viz. will have your way, being above, and knowing better than all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and this is true: for if you found out at any time, that any of us only thought by way of queſtion, in our own minds, whether you was right or not, in ſuch or ſuch a caſe, you would be upon us like ſo many lions, with chaſtiſement: and this looks to me like being heady, and high minded. And again 3dly. Lovers of pleaſure more than lovers of God: agree all with this is that, Rom 1, 32, Who knowing the judgments of God, that they that commit ſuch things, are worthy of death, not only do the ſame, but have pleaſure in them that do them. From which it appears, that they took pleaſure in thoſe things, and in them that did them; and loved that more than they did God.</p>
            <p>Therefore, whoever does theſe things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that are here ſpoken of by the apoſtle, and takes pleaſure in others that do the ſame, they are the perſons intended, verſe 5, having a form of godlineſs, but denying the power
<pb n="109" facs="unknown:019212_0108_0FAA6691AE4D16A0"/>thereof—from ſuch alſo turn away, as if he ſhould ſay, having an appearance of godlineſs transformed into the miniſters of Chriſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending godlineſs, and at the ſame time deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the power and efficacy of Chriſt's goſpel for our ſalvation: or that there is any power that can ſave ſouls, but what is in themſelves, from ſuch turn away: verſe 6th, for of this fort are they that creep into houſes and lead captive ſilly women, laden with ſins, and led away with divers luſts. Such women as theſe are eaſily convicted of their dangerous ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and are liable to be taken captive, and led away by thoſe that pretend to be perfect, able to bare their burdens and unlaid them of their ſins; and this is the craft of deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to creep into houſes, working firſt with the women, to get the man, and then the whole houſe or family: as the Philiſtines firſt wrought with Delilah to get Sampſon: and ſo Titus 1—11, ſubvert whole houſes, teaching things which they ought not for filthy lucres ſake, or for their eſtates: verſe 7th, ever learning and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth. This is the caſe with your poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, continually going for inſtruction, and growing more ignorant, which differs entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from what St. Paul tells us ſhall be in the new covenant ſtate: Hebrews 8—11, and they ſhall not teach every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, ſaying, know the
<pb n="110" facs="unknown:019212_0109_0FAA669269276A68"/>Lord, for all ſhall know me, from the leaſt to the greateſt. Again, I. John, 2—27, but the anointing which ye have received of him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the fame anointing teacheth you of all things and is truth, and is no lie, and even as it (mind as it) hath taught you, ye ſhall abide in him. Again, Chriſt ſays, John 16—13, how be it, when the ſpirit of truth is come, he will guide you into all truth—not you elder James. But to proceed, verſe 8th, now as Jannes and Jambres withſtood Moſes, ſo do theſe alſo reſiſt the truth, men of corrupt minds, reprobate concerning the faith. Obſerve here, the apoſtle ſays, that as they withſtood Moſes, ſo does theſe reſiſt the truth, which truth is what the prophets and apoſtles have wrote, and when the ſpirit of truth comes in any one, it leads into all truth, that is into the volume of the ſcriptures, and gives him to ſee and feel the truth and reality of them, for when Chriſt comes, he comes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſcriptures, not to deſtroy the law and prophets, and when he comes again, either by his ſpirit to gather his elect, or perſonally to judgment, he will not deſtroy his own goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel or miniſtration already given—and this you ſay is what we cannot be ſaved by it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet by Chriſt, in a once crucified Chriſt; but you ſay we muſt be ſaved by faith in a Chriſt that is come in the mother. Hereby
<pb n="111" facs="unknown:019212_0110_0FAA6693714AF908"/>I ſuppoſe you reſiſt the truth, for why could we not be ſaved by a Chriſt come in any body elſe as well? theſe, the apoſtle ſays are men of corrupt minds, reprobate concerning the faith, which faith is that the apoſtle had, in a once crucified Chriſt. But to conclude:—with reſpect to Chriſt being come in you, there is nothing appears to make it evident; but to the contrary: and indeed there is no ſuch thing as Chriſt's coming in the manner you pretend, ſo long as there is any exalting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above God in his temple, for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will be their deſtruction, as the riſing ſun diſpels darkneſs. Another reaſon I would offer, and that is what the apoſtle Peter ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt ſays, Acts 3—21, whom the heavens muſt receive, until the times of reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titution of all things. Again, I. Cor. 15—28, and when all things ſhall be ſubdued unto him, then ſhall the Son alſo himſelf be ſubject unto him that put all things under him, that God may be all in all. Firſt, we ſee not yet the reſtitution of all things to their primitive rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, until which time the heaven is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him. Again 2dly, all things are not yet ſubdued unto him, ſeeing there are ſo many uſurpers yet extant.</p>
            <p>CHRISTIAN FRIENDS,</p>
            <p>AFTER having concluded my letter to JAMES WHITTACOR, I think myſelf under
<pb n="112" facs="unknown:019212_0111_0FAA6695D61624F0"/>obligations to tell you how I came to fall in with the people called Shakers, and how I was led out from them.</p>
            <p>Firſt. I having been a profeſſor in the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt order, for a number of years: at length, hearing of a ſtrange people at Niſqueuniah, about nine miles north weſt from Albany, and being previouſly poſſeſſed of an opinion from certain paſſages of ſcripture, that about this time, Chriſt was to make his ſecond appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ſome where or other, and hoping it might be among them, I went to ſee them, and found a very ſenſible, religious people to appearance. They received and treated me very kindly, and after a while began ſome converſation, intimating they had attained the great and wonderful things, even the apoſtolic gifts. They ſang together after ſhaking awhile, and then the mother ſpake in her unknown tongue: afterward came together and began to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, whether I thought I was born again or not? I ſaid that I had a hope: they aſked me if I did not commit ſin—I did not deny it, then they took the bible and turned to that in John, he that is born of God, doth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin: he that ſinneth is of the devil: he that ſineth hath not ſeen him, neither knows him, &amp;c. and all with ſuch a grace and ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and I being ignorant, brought me to a pauſe: they pretended they were perfect, and ſtood with Chriſt in full redemption: and that
<pb n="113" facs="unknown:019212_0112_0FAA66970442CE18"/>Chriſt had made his ſecond appearance in them: and that they had the word of God, for all ſuch as would believe in his ſecond ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing: had much talk this evening: the next day I took a kind leave of them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home full of thoughts, and wondering at the ſtrange things that I had heard and ſeen. Soon after I made them another viſit, when they taught me the neceſſity of confeſſion of ſins, ſhewing ſcripture warrant for it, and ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it upon me, as what they had all come into, in order to obtain repentance and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from ſin—inſinuating that if I would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the word of God through them, I might ſoon attain to the ſame great and glorious things. This being for what I knew what I was looking for, I complied, thinking it would do me no hurt if it did me no good, at the ſame time many others ran to ſee as I did, &amp; fell in, they pretended as I ſaid, to have the ſame apoſtolic gifts, and there was ſo much of a reſemblance, I knew not but that it might be ſo, and there was the moſt extraordinary appearance of love and union among them, that I ever ſaw. I began to think I had found the people I was looking for, and the millen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium was begun. We had now ſet out for perfection, and began to forget our old reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and attend to the new lead: we had confeſſed our ſins, and began to think ourſelves better then others: felt very joyfull, inviting
<pb n="114" facs="unknown:019212_0113_0FAA66972EB3BBF8"/>everybody to come and go with us to Mount Zion. They ſtrictly enjoined it upon us to ſearch our hearts, and make full confeſſion of all former ſins, and to practice confeſſions to them of all future ſins, of thought, word, and deed: and after a while, they began to teach us the neceſſity of forſaking all for Chriſt, and to refrain from our wives, ſaying, if ye live after the fleſh, ye ſhall die; but if ye through the ſpirit do mortify the deeds of the body, ye ſhall live. They ſaid moreover, that the act of copulation was the forbidden fruit in the garden, which being taken, procured our fall and loſs: this we alſo complied with, ſtill thinking that as we did more we grew better. All was yet calm and mild. After a while a-again, they taught us the neceſſity of laying all at the apoſtle's feet—ſhewing ſcripture for it, and give up all to their diſpoſal for the relief of the poor, ſaying, let the brother of low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree rejoice in that he is exalted; and let the brother of high degree rejoice in that he is made low, refering to ſcripture, which we could more eaſily do, having given up our wives, we cared not much what became of all the reſt. By and by they began to dance: this ſhocked me very much; but they read Jeremiah 31—13, then ſhall the virgin rejoice in the dance, both young men and old toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſaying, this was that day. In a little time they carried thoſe dances into great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigue
<pb n="115" facs="unknown:019212_0114_0FAA669862C72ED8"/>and labour, for the mortification of the fleſh. I began now to think I muſtobey every command of God, in order to obtain perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but they taught me to look wholly to them, who were the only lead of God for my ſoul, as Moſes was to the children of Iſrael: they were for a time for what I could ſee, ſtrict in their morals, ſevere in their diſcipline, and conſtant in their devotions. This looked to me to be right: I began to think we were the only people of God, and that the whole world lay in wickedneſs: we thought we obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God, and therefore could not fail of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acceptance with him: and that all others that did not do as we did, would certainly be loſt. We were taught to believe in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and be obedient to our inſtruction, and thereby we ſhould believe in Chriſt, and obey him in his ſecond appearing; they often quot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe words, that Chriſt was the author of eternal ſalvation to all them that obey him, which was to obey the Mother, Chriſt being come in her, and by whom he ſpeaks to us, as the children of Iſrael obeyed God in obeying Moſes, by whom God ſpeaks to them, and her miniſtration being attended with viſions, revelations, unknown tongues, and propheſy to all appearance as we accepted, we dared not but believe what they ſaid, and that they were what they pretended to be: they often threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nining or us with damnation, and the loſs of
<pb n="116" facs="unknown:019212_0115_0FAA66988ACF6CF0"/>our ſouls, if we diſbelieved and diſobeyed them. This drew our attention to them in neglect of the bible, or any other God or Chriſt but what was in them, which was what they often ſaid, and would inſiſt upon it, that there was no ſaviour but what was in them: thus was I caught and carried away, believing it muſt be right, and yet ſome how or other at length found it all gendered to bondage, and knew not how, for I had done my utmoſt, and meant to do it ſtill in obeying God; yet ſuch trouble and diſtreſs would often come upon me, I knew not how, nor for what; but it felt like the bands of death: it would firſt ſet me a groaning, and as my diſtreſs increaſed to hollowing, like a man void of reaſon; and after long enduring ſuch things, I have gone to the church and told the mother how it was with me. She would ſpeak comfortably to me, and ſend me into the dance, and hurry us round, and make us as jovial as poſſible, and labour it off, and then reſume great cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs again—and this became a general prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to get rid of our burdens. I might not follow any teachings of God in my own ſoul a one ſide of the mother's inſtructions, and I was taught by the elders, that God would not hear me no more than he would a devil: I muſt go to the mother and elders, and they muſt pray for me, and teach me; this had a tendency to cut me off from ſeeking any where
<pb n="117" facs="unknown:019212_0116_0FAA66992D3C4E98"/>elſe but to them. I began now to be in great trouble at times, fearing all was not right; but I had got in, and could not get out: felt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate and loſt, and all I had now to build any hopes of ſalvation upon, was my obedience to their inſtructions and orders; and the further I went the more I felt involved. Oh! what a bondman I have been in Egypt, and ſhut up in Babylon, and could not get out: I began now to ſuſpect I had miſſed my way to mount Zion, and come to Sinai, for I could hear lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle elſe but thunder and tempeſt: the ſound of a trumpet in the nature of it, and the voice of words: a fiery law and dreadful curſes: old Pharoah ſaying ye are idle, ye are idle, or in their own words, ye are ſlothful, ye are ſlothful, and if you are not a thouſand times more faithful then ever you have been, you will looſe your ſouls: the whole tale of brick required, and no ſtraw given: perfection re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired without grace: and we were beaten by ſevere chaſtiſement, and my ſoul groaned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der cruel bondage, and theſe dreadful thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings from the church, and chaſtiſements within it they ſaid was God's roaring out of Zion, and I think uttering his voice from Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem; and I did not know but that it was ſo, till about two years after I firſt joined them, when things that had lain hid began to riſe and come to view, which I knew could not be good, and that gave me great doubts and
<pb n="118" facs="unknown:019212_0117_0FAA6699F9820FA8"/>fears concerning the whole of that religion, and then my troubles increaſed: I was afraid to go forward or backward, for I had loſt poſſeſſion of every thing I dared truſt to, yea I was afraid to read the bible, or believe any thing of it. To follow a corrupt lead would be fatal, and to join with any ſect, looked to me like going back into Sodom. Here I ſtopped, like Iſrael at the red ſea, and cried to God, nor could I help it then: yea my ſoul cried to God day and night: many times in the utmoſt confuſion, almoſt in diſtraction &amp; deſpair, and dared not ſtir one ſtep, this way or that, by any detriment of mind, tho' I went ſeveral times after this to the church, which would but increaſe my trouble, for ſeeing and hearing ſuch things as I could not join with; I had been in great honour and reſpect among them, but was now fallen into contempt, my children ruled over me, and was ſet on by the mother to chaſtiſe me: one eſpecially was made uſe of to reprove and chaſtiſe me open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and publickly for my coveteouſneſs, in not giving up all I had to the church, and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing myſelf to their diſpoſition. Elder John Partington was ſo hard upon me once in this matter, in a publick aſſembly, that he really ſcared and terrified me, with ſuch great and terrible words and threatnings; and ſeveral others I ſuppoſed were ſet on by the mother to keep ſlouting and galling of me, if poſſible,
<pb n="119" facs="unknown:019212_0118_0FAA669AB3FE2288"/>to force me to a compliance. This indeed brought great trials upon me: I dared not go and ſell what I had and give it to them, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept what came in victuals and cloathing, in which I ſuppoſe I was not behind any. They were alſo as hard upon me to make me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all other religion but theirs, and every idea of any God or Chriſt, but what was in them; and alſo to renounce all that ever I experienced, as ſomething in the old heavens. They diſapproved of my reading the bible, driving things to a great extremity with great words and dreadful threatnings, which would make me like Job, almoſt, if not quite long for death. After ſuch trials I have gone out into the woods and fell on my knees, and on my face, roaring and crying and telling God they were trying to force me to renounce him and deny Chriſt, which I dared not do, tho' I ſhould die for it. They told me abundantly, that God would not hear my cries and prayers no more than he would a devil: to their terms I muſt come, or go to hell.</p>
            <p>Here I was held a long time in Babylon at the red ſea, and under Sinai's dreadful thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, in the myſtery all at once, and felt my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf under Job's affliction: my friends that came to ſee me and labour with me being of this profeſſion, who no doubt felt friendly to me, would read me off and condemn me, as Job's friends did him, and try to terrify and
<pb n="120" facs="unknown:019212_0119_0FAA669B6A07C7E8"/>perſuade me to renounce my old religion, ideas and notions of any other God or Chriſt than what was in the church; but my ſoul held its integrity, and often cried out in the language of Job, though he ſlay me yet will I truſt in him. My breath, to wit, my words was ſtrange to my wife; my children were all as it were dead to me, being all in that religion and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me: my worldly ſubſtance all gone from me as to any ſatisfaction in it, or enjoyment of it as heretofore, &amp; tho' I had ſeen many things erroneous and abſurd among them, yet I da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not leave them in a profligate manner, nor reſent any of their conduct; for I knew, be it as it might with others, it was God's hand upon me, every deſpiteful word, and all the hard treatment I received from any, was God's hand upon me, and correction from God by them, he ſuffering them ſo to do, and all this was juſt upon me: for I like the Galatians had left the faith of the goſpel, and was ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſtification by the works of the law. But this I did not then yet ſee, but was determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to wait upon God, and die in Babylon or at the red ſea, in the ſituation I was then in, for I could go no further till God delivered me, which I had a meaſure of faith to believe he would, in his own time and way: but after having through fear refrained reading the bible ſome time, and my troubles increaſing, one day being in my houſe, and looking towards
<pb n="121" facs="unknown:019212_0120_0FAA669C2A0003A0"/>the bible, thought with myſelf, O! how I uſed to love that book; but now I am afraid of it, and afraid of every thing, all is loſt, and I am loſt, and know not where to go; but thought again, I will go and take the bible and read, let come of it what will: and as God would have it, when I come to open the book and read, I found it ſpake to me, and into me, deſcribing the ſtate of my ſoul, and ſpeaking the language of my heart, my ſoul had fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with it, and I knew that I was in the ſame travel that they had been in that wrote; I ſenſibly felt virtue and life from their words: now I again knew the bible was true; and my ſoul felt ſuch a deliverance, that I could not read for crying, with love and joy and thankfulneſs to God, for his mercy to ſuch a poor loſt ſoul. I could ſcarce read any where, but it ſeemed to be new to me, and life in it; and I could ſcarce read a ſentence, before I ſhould burſt out a crying again, with joy and thankfulneſs and love to God: it would ſpeak ſo right into my ſoul, and my ſoul in the word, becoming one with it as Chriſt ſays, I in you, and you in me, that is his word abid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in us, and we abiding in his word, having fellowſhip with him, in and by his word. Here I found joy and peace in believing: I began now to try to recover my family again, to an adherance to the bible, which at length ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded—who all came off with me, except my eldeſt daughter, who was ſent away at a great
<pb n="122" facs="unknown:019212_0121_0FAA669EA08875F0"/>diſtance from the church, perhaps to keep her out of the way. Now I ſaw the neceſſity and importance of believing and obeying the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: particularly the words of Chriſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning falſe Chriſts, and falſe prophets, that ſhould ariſe and ſhew great ſigns and wonders, and if it were poſſible, deceive the very elect: and alſo of thoſe that ſhould cry lo here is Chriſt, and lo there: he ſays believe them not: go not after them; but thro' inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and diſobedience to the command of Chriſt, I went after them, and believed them, that Chriſt was come in them, and that the kingdom of God was come in them, when I ought to have looked for it, and found it in my own heart. Here I believe God gave me ſorrow and repentance for departing from God, and putting confidence in creatures that could neither ſave themſelves, nor them that truſted in them. Here God was pleaſed to divide the red ſea of Chriſt's blood, and open a way of redemption for my ſoul through faith in his blood, giving me to ſee the line of grace in diſtinction from the line of works, that I had been led along in under the old covenant and a broken law, where there was no poſſible ſalvation, till we were ſlain by it: Rom. 7—11, and become dead to it: Gal. 2—19, and wholly divorced from it: Rom. 7—3, and made alive through faith, in that all atoning blood and righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt, who became the end of the law for righteouſneſs to all them that believe: nor is the beſt doings
<pb n="123" facs="unknown:019212_0122_0FAA669FCC8D45A8"/>that ever man did or can do, ſince the goſpel day, in order thereby to attain life and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication before God, any better, than if he had cut off a dog's neck, or offered ſwines blood: Iſaiah 66—3, and it is an infallible evidence, that he that is at work for life, has not got it, nor can he obtain it in that way, for this wholly ſets Chriſt aſide, and invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates the goſpel: and this was the caſe: Rom. 9—31, but Iſrael which followed after the law of righteouſneſs hath not attained to the law of righteouſneſs. Verſe 32d. Wherefore? becauſe they ſought it not by faith, but as it were by the works of the law, for they ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at that ſtumbling ſtone. Again, Rom. 10—3, for they being ignorant of God's righteouſneſs, and going about to eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs, have not ſubmitted themſelves to the righteouſneſs of God, which righteouſneſs of God is Chriſt's righteouſneſs, which is become ours by imputation, through our faith in him, and this is certainly the caſe of theſe people called Shakers: they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to eſtabliſh their own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by their own works, and yet come ſo ſhort of it, as to fall into great abominations. Their whole dependance is upon their own doings for ſalvation: not ſo much as one word ſaid about what Chriſt has done and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for us, among them; but it is what they themſelves do, and the mother and elders ſuffer for them: and ſince her death, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="124" facs="unknown:019212_0123_0FAA669FF141FC40"/>to ſuffer for their own ſins, till they have paid the laſt nite: and the more they ſuffer here, the leſs they ſhall ſuffer in hell or purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, before they come out again: and if any attain to perfection here in this life, it muſt be by ſo much greater degrees of ſufferings, and in this belief, they put themſelves to all the hardſhips, fatigues and ſufferings, they are poſſibly able to endure—and all this in order to obtain ſalvation, not expecting of it in any other way: and this is their new heaven's ſtate, which is wholly under the law of works, and entirely excludes Chriſt and the goſpel, ſee Gal. 5—4, Chriſt is become of no effect unto you, whoſoever of you are juſtified by the law, ye are fallen from grace. Again, Gal. 2—16, knowing that a man is not juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the works of the law, but by the faith of Jeſus Chriſt: even we have believed in Jeſus Chriſt, that we may be juſtified by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the works of the law, for by the works of the law ſhall no fleſh be juſtified. Again, for as many as are of the works of the law, are under the curſe. Here I ſay God ſhewed me the legal line, where there was no ſalvation; for the law made nothing perfect, Heb. 7, 19. Again, Gal. 3, 21, for if there had been a law given, that could have given life, verily righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhould have been by the law. Again, Gal, 2, 21, for if righteouſneſs came by the law, then Chriſt is dead in vain. By all which
<pb n="125" facs="unknown:019212_0124_0FAA66A0AFFB0908"/>it is evident, that all they that are at work, in what way or manner ſoever, expecting ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by it, are under the law, and under the curſe. Here I ſaw therefore there was no righteouſneſs or perfection to be attained by the law, or by our own works; and all that I had done ſince I joined theſe people, or could poſſibly do, was no better then droſs and dung, and that if ever any ſoul was ſav'd, it would be by free grace, and not for works of right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſs that we have done; but of his own mercy he ſaved us, by the waſhing of regener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and renewing of the Holy Ghoſt—be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The old covenant was a covenant of works, which all mankind are under by nature, and condemned to death; but the new covenant was a covenant of grace—grace is the joyful ſound to every new condemned criminal, and bleſſed are the people that know it. Grace is the eſſence of the goſpel, its nature is to ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and redeem, breaks every yoke and ſets the priſoners free—it beſtows freely wine and milk, without money and without price—&amp; it is by grace we are ſaved through faith, and that not of ourſelves, it is gift of God—not of works, leaſt any man ſhould boaſt, Eph. 2—8—9. Grace is free mercy and love of God to a loſt world, in giving his only begotten ſon, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life. Grace pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures
<pb n="126" facs="unknown:019212_0125_0FAA66A1804DF508"/>a perfect and compleat righteouſneſs, wrought out by Jeſus Chriſt, in offering up himſelf a ſacrifice to God for us, adequate, and that is every way anſwerable to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the law, for all them that believe, and one diſcovery of this by faith, does more towards breaking my heart in godly ſorrow and repentance, and exalting the Lord alone, and filling my ſoul with humiliation and love, and giving me more freedom of ſoul, than all that the leolal ſyſtem can afford. Grace makes us feel our dependence, and to value Chriſts blood; grace is the whole theme of them that are ſaved; by grace, in all their thank offerings and praiſes, they bring forth Chriſt the head ſtone with ſhouting, crying grace, grace unto it, Zach. 4, 7, not that the new covenant doctrines of grace and faith, deſtroys the neceſſity of obedience to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, for Chriſt ſays, I come not to deſtroy the law and the prophets, but to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill; and St. Paul ſays, do we then make void the law through faith, God forbid, ye we eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the law; but here is the defect among all the unregenerate, they do not love God, and therefore do not obey him, all that they do in the outward form of obedience, is from ſelf and to ſelf, and not to God, and what he he does is that he might find favour and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of God by it; and to obtain life; but the renewed ſoul obeys from the heart, becauſe he loves God, and loves his commands;
<pb n="127" facs="unknown:019212_0126_0FAA66A22A67C238"/>for no more does any one love God, then he loves his commands; hence David ſays, O! how love I thy law; and St. Paul ſays, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the law of God after the inward man; and this they do, becauſe they have obtained life; and from life, and the nature of God in them; which only is obedience, in the ſenſe of the commands; again, here is another blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der men make, they think becauſe God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, they muſt obey; and ſo they muſt or be loſt, except Chriſt obeys for them, and when they think they have obeyed, they think they ſhall be excepted; But alas! they have broke the law already, and the ſentence is paſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and die they muſt do what they can now, except through faith in Chriſt's dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them, they be acquitted: for this is true, he died for all, and has fulfilled and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the demands of the law, both in it's preceptive, and penal part, by his active and paſſive obedience, for all his elect: and they are thereby acquitted; nor has the law any demands upon them for they are dead to it; agreeable to Rom. 7, 4, Therefore my brethren ye are become dead to the law by the body of Chriſt. This was a wonderful deliverance to my ſoul, when God was pleaſed to open it unto me, and make it mine; I ſaw and felt too, that I was become dead to the law, by that crucified bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt; that it had its whole demand of him for me, that he had kept it for me, and ſuffered the penalty due to me, and I had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do, but to believe and truſt in him,
<pb n="128" facs="unknown:019212_0127_0FAA66A314451258"/>and love and obey him forever. Again, Rom. 5, 10, for if when we were enemies, we were reconciled to God, by the death of his ſon, much more being reconciled, we ſhall be ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his life; here I ſaw, that it was the death of Chriſt, that reconciled us to God, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of our own doings; and that our whole ſalvation depends upon the life of Chriſt; and becauſe he lives we ſhall live alſo; John 4, 19, here I can ſay bleſſed be God, I knew what it was to cat the fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his blood by faith, as really and ſenſibly, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my body fed on temporal food, and ſound strength and nouriſhment thereby: his fleſh was meat indeed, and his blood was drink indeed, which my ſoul fed on by faith: for this fleſh and blood of Chriſt was the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that made peace, and reconciled God and man again, and is the bread of life to the ſoul of the believer, as appears John 6—51, I am the living bread which came down from heaven: if any man eat of this bread, he ſhall live forever: and the bread that I will give is my fleſh, which I will give for the life of the world. Here is therefore full and free redemption, and whoſoever does really believe theſe things does feel his ſoul ſaved. As Chriſt ſays, he that believes ſhall be ſaved. Thus when God was pleaſed to recover me again to the faith of the goſpel, I felt my ſoul enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to reſt, and ceaſed from its own works, as we read Heb. 4, 3, For we which have believed, do enter into reſts as he ſaid &amp;c. Again, verſe 10th. For he that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into his reſt, he alſo hath ceaſed from his own works, as God did from his. And this was the coming of Chriſt the kingdom of God, and the millennium be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in my ſoul, which I had been trying to find; but could not by obſervation, or the works of the law. And now to conclude, in the words of King Jeſus, Rev. 2, 2, I know thy works and thy labour, and thy patience, and how thou canſt not bear them which are evil, and thou haſt tried them, which ſay they are Apoſtles and are not, and haſt found them liars.—</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
