<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true interest of the United States, and particularly of Pennsylvania, considered, with respect to the advantages resulting from a state paper-money: with some observations on the subject of a bank, and on agriculture, manufactures and commerce. / By an American.</title>
            <author>Barton, William, 1754-1817.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N15361</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N15361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 19498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 19497</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APV6174</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">19498</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99001632</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 19498.</title>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 19497.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N15361)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 19498)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 19498; 19497)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true interest of the United States, and particularly of Pennsylvania, considered, with respect to the advantages resulting from a state paper-money: with some observations on the subject of a bank, and on agriculture, manufactures and commerce. / By an American.</title>
                  <author>Barton, William, 1754-1817.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 31, [1] p. ;  (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Charles Cist, at the corner of Fourth and Arch-Streets.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M,DCC,LXXXVI. [1786]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Barton by Evans.</note>
                  <note>Evans entry 19497 is, according to Shipton &amp; Mooney, "Evans' reconstruction of the JCB defective copy of 19498."</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paper money --  Pennsylvania.</term>
               <term>Currency question --  Pennsylvania.</term>
               <term>Pennsylvania --  Commerce.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:019498_0000_0FABADE61C999438"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:019498_0001_0FABADE6E62B54F0"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRUE INTEREST OF THE UNITED STATES, AND PARTICULARLY OF PENNSYLVANIA, CONSIDERED; WITH RESPECT TO THE ADVANTAGES RESULTING FROM A STATE PAPER-MONEY: WITH SOME OBSERVATIONS ON THE SUBJECT OF A BANK, AND ON <hi>Agriculture, Manufactures and Commerce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY AN AMERICAN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PHILADELPHIA:</hi> Printed by CHARLES CIST, at the Corner of <hi>Fourth</hi> and <hi>Arch-ſtreets.</hi> M,DCC,LXXXVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="unknown:019498_0002_0FABADED442821F8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:019498_0003_0FABADEDC382F0E8"/>
            <head>THE TRUE INTEREST OF THE UNITED STATES, AND PARTICULARLY OF PENNSYLVANIA, CONSIDERED, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE ſovereignty and independence of the United States of America being eſtabliſhed, it becomes an object of the utmoſt importance to them to adopt, and ſteadily to purſue, ſuch a ſyſtem of national policy, as may moſt effectually promote the proſperity, ſtrength and duration of that eſtabliſhment. Nature has done her part for this riſing empire:—The wiſdom and virtue of its citizens muſt accompliſh the reſt.</p>
            <p>THE objects which conduce to the well-being of a people are ſo numerous and extended, as to render the conſideration of them all, a taſk too great and too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex for an individual. A rational ſcheme of civil polity, executed in a faithful adminiſtration of government, is, doubtleſs, one of the moſt momentous and eſſential of theſe objects: but even this comprehends a great variety of intereſting concerns. We ſhall, therefore, confine our obſervations, in the courſe of this Eſſay, to ſome of thoſe points which appear more peculiarly connected with the circumſtances of this country, and our national happineſs.</p>
            <p>A CIVILIZED nation, without commerce, is a ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm in politics. It is in the rudeſt ſtate of mankind
<pb n="2" facs="unknown:019498_0004_0FABADEE5F8FBE10"/>
only, that a people can exiſt, without any communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with other ſocieties, or commercial intercourſe among themſelves, every one ſupporting himſelf by his own labour. Indeed ſo abſolute a ſtate of nature can only be conceived, but has ſcarcely exiſted in reality. The wants, the fears, the weakneſs, nay the very nature of man, neceſſarily conſtitute him a ſocial animal: And, in the very origin of ſociety, their mutual neceſſities, with the various talents, means and opportunities of indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duals for ſupplying them, muſt have produced a recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of ſervices, and an occaſional interchange with one another of that property, which each had acquired by his own exertions.</p>
            <p>COMMERCE may then be conſidered as coeval with man himſelf, and <hi>barter</hi> as its firſt ſtage.</p>
            <p>IT is obvious, however, that the exchange of one kind of commodity for another muſt have proved too imperfect a ſpecies of traffic to anſwer the purpoſes of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, after civilization had multiplied their wants, and extended the objects of them beyond their mere <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN order, then, to remedy the inconvenience of barter, certain ſubſtances have been adopted, amongſt the various nations of the earth, as the ſcale or ſtandard for meaſuring the value of every ſpecies of property; thereby to aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the relative worth of every commodity, compared with others, and with this common ſtandard.</p>
            <p>THE ſubſtances, moſt univerſally employed for this purpoſe, are <hi>ſilver</hi> and <hi>gold,</hi> though the former is eſteemed the ſtandard. Theſe metals poſſeſs an <note n="*" place="bottom">The value of the precious metals is, however, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanced, by their peculiar aptitude to perform the office of an <hi>univerſal money</hi> far beyond any real, <hi>inherent</hi> value they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs. This <hi>extrinſic</hi> value of gold and ſilver, which belongs to them when under the modification of <hi>coin</hi> or in bullion, is totally diſtinct from their <hi>inherent</hi> value, as a <hi>commodity.</hi> For, as Dr. Franklin has juſtly remarked, "gold and ſilver are not <hi>intrinſically</hi> of equal value with iron, a metal in itſelf capable of many more beneficial uſes to mankind. Their value reſts chiefly in the <hi>eſtimation</hi> they happen to be in among the generality of nations, and the credit given to the opinion, that that eſtimation will continue: Otherwiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a pound of gold would not be a real equivalent for even a buſhel of wheat." (See the Doctor's Remarks on a Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation from the Board of Trade to the King of Great-Britain, dated 9th February 1764.) We are apt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the <hi>inherent</hi> value of the <hi>commodity</hi> with its <hi>extrinſic</hi> value as a <hi>money</hi>; and to unite the two, in eſtimating the <hi>intrinſic</hi> value of the <hi>ſubſtance.</hi> Whereas Bank-notes, or any other ſpecies of <hi>ſymbolical</hi> money, may, under certain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulations, acquire that "eſtimation" among a people, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to conſtitute <hi>money,</hi> and to anſwer all the uſes of a <hi>circulating medium of alienation</hi> in a State.</note> 
               <hi>intrinſic</hi> value,
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:019498_0005_0FABADEF23197170"/>
by reaſon of their extraordinary purity and ſcarceneſs;— and certain other qualities render them ſuitable materials for receiving ſuch criteria, as that they may be readily diſtinguiſhed, in the tranſactions of men, for <hi>that ſtandard,</hi> whereby the relative worth of all commodities is aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. The diſtinguiſhing marks given, by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and ſanction of a State, to certain portions of metal, denominate them <hi>coin.</hi> Theſe, which we call <hi>actual-money,</hi> are graduated (if we may uſe the expreſſion) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the proportion and quality of metal they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, by an arbitrary ſcale, termed <hi>money of account</hi>; which, in every country reſpectively, <q>repreſents an invariable ſcale for meaſuring value.</q>
            </p>
            <p>BUT it is to be obſerved, that gold and ſilver coin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives not its intrinſic value from performing the office <note n="†" place="bottom">"By money" (ſays ſir James Steuart) <q>I underſtand <hi>any</hi> commodity, which, purely in itſelf, is of no mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial uſe to man, but which acquires ſuch an <hi>eſtimation</hi> from his opinion of it, as to become the univerſal mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of what is called value, and an adequate equivalent for any thing alienable.</q> Political Oeconomy, Book I. ch. 6.</note> of <hi>money</hi>; but poſſeſſes it as a <hi>commodity.</hi> For, as <note n="‡" place="bottom">Vide his Obſervations on National Induſtry.</note> Mr. Anderſon expreſſes it, <q>
                  <hi>Money,</hi> conſidered in itſelf, is of no value.—But among civilized nations, who have found how convenient it is for facilitating the barter or exchange of one commodity for another, it has received an artificial value.—So that, although uſeleſs in itſelf, it has come to be accepted among all civilized nations, <hi>as a token proving that the perſon who is poſſeſſed of it had given ſomething of real value in exchange for it</hi>;
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:019498_0006_0FABADF0DC873130"/>
and is, on that account, accepted of by another in exchange for ſomething that is of real utility and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſic worth.</q>—In ſtrictneſs, therefore, the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of gold and ſilver-coin, in alienation, is no more than bartering one commodity for another of equal value, or rather price. The intrinſic value of ſuch coin, does, in fact, render it in ſome degree an imperfect me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium of alienation; for, being itſelf a commodity, it is liable to riſe and fall in value, like every other article of commerce:— And, accordingly, we find that the price of ſilver is continually varying in the London market; and the Engliſh Eaſt-India Company ſend ſilver to China, in order to purchaſe gold.</p>
            <p>THUS money, formed of the precious metals, may be conſidered in a two-fold point of view—as a merchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able commodity, and as a medium of alienation. In the former capacity, it adds to the riches of a country, merely in proportion to its intrinſic value: But, <hi>as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> it can no otherwiſe produce this effect, than paper or leather-money, or any other <hi>ſign</hi> of property.</p>
            <p>IF we recur to the original uſe of <hi>money,</hi>—as an <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> by the intervention of which alienation might be effected, and the neceſſity of barter ſuperſeded,—it muſt appear evident, that we judge very erroneouſly, when we ſuppoſe <hi>intrinſic value</hi> to be inſeparably connected with it. At the ſame time it muſt be acknowledged, that ſpecies of money, which poſſeſſes <hi>intrinſic value,</hi> has one ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage that does not appertain to <hi>ſymbolical</hi> money; namely, that being itſelf a merchantable commodity, it may be <hi>bartered,</hi> at a <hi>foreign</hi> market, for other commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities. This advantage, however, as ſhall be ſhewn in the ſequel, is not more than equivalent to thoſe that are deducible from a well founded <hi>ſymbolical</hi> money, which is capable of anſwering all the <hi>domeſtic</hi> and <hi>internal</hi> purpoſes of a <hi>circulating medium</hi> in a nation.</p>
            <p>FROM what has been premiſed we may infer, that <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> in its <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <p>
                     <hi>"Money</hi> is an univerſal medium, or common ſtandard, by a compariſon with which the value of all merchanciſe may be aſcertained; or it is a <hi>ſign</hi> which repreſents the real value of all commodities." Black. Comm. I. 279.</p>
                  <p>Lord Shelburne, ſpeaking in the Houſe of Lords, called <hi>"money</hi> one <hi>type</hi> of property: <hi>Paper</hi> (he adds) is another." Vide Anderſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>in Nota.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>proper</hi> ſignification, is not wealth, but the
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:019498_0007_0FABADF1AD7E9F28"/>
               <hi>ſign, token,</hi> or <hi>repreſentative</hi> of it. The abſolute riches of a country conſiſt in the abundance of thoſe productions of nature, that miniſter directly to the ſupport, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency, and the enjoyment of mankind. Where na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has beſtowed theſe gifts with a liberal hand, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, collectively, may juſtly be termed rich, though deſtitute of money: On the other hand, where theſe bleſſings appear to have been dealt out to a people in a more ſparing manner, they are comparatively poor, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their country may abound with gold and ſilver-mines. For if we conſider the former country as totally unconnected with any other; it is evident that the wants of all its inhabitants may be ſupplied by the means of bartering; but if we place the other in the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connected ſtate, it is equally plain, that their gold and ſilver can be of little uſe to them;—the <hi>real, inherent</hi> worth of thoſe metals being very ſmall, and the country deficient in thoſe things which conſtitute <hi>true</hi> and <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial riches.</hi>—In the one caſe, the neceſſity of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering among themſelves is attended with inconvenience. In the other, the ſcarcity or want of the neceſſary articles themſelves, excludes, in a great degree, the poſſibility of barter and the uſe of money, and occaſions proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able diſtreſs.</p>
            <p>LET us now view each of theſe countries as opening a commercial intercourſe with the other and with foreign nations.—The wealthier country, by exporting the ſuperfluous quantity of its produce, would be enabled to procure in return, either gold and ſilver, or ſuch other commodities as they might require to ſupply thoſe <hi>arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial</hi> wants, which refinement of manners may have created. Thus the wealthy State might increaſe its riches.</p>
            <p>BUT the poorer country would be obliged to ſend abroad their gold and ſilver, to purchaſe a ſufficiency of thoſe articles which their more immediate neceſſities might require. Should the quantity of theſe metals, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by ſuch a country, be only adequate for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, its inhabitants would certainly continue poor; or, if the quantity ſhould be ſo great as to introduce amongſt
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:019498_0008_0FABADF22E969AF0"/>
them, from other countries, not only the neceſſities and conveniencies, but luxuries and the ſuperfluities of life; the effect would be a prevalence of ignorance and <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <p>"There may be too much money in a nation. And there is certainly too much, if it renders the great body of the people idle, and enables them to purchaſe what they want from foreigners, without any labor or induſtry of their own." Characteriſtics of the preſent Political State of Great-Britain.</p>
                  <p>"When money can be obtained in great quantities by little labor, the ſlower and better means of obtaining it by manufactures and induſtry will always be neglected. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, with all its dreadful train of ills, immediately follows; the bulk of the people become ſunk in indolence and miſery, and a few riot in all the exceſs of diſſipation and extravagance." Anderſon's Obſervations on National Induſtry.</p>
               </note> ſloth, the parents of wretchedneſs.</p>
            <p>HENCE we ſee that the <hi>real</hi> riches of a nation do not conſiſt in money; but that they may ſubſiſt without it.</p>
            <p>COMMERCE and money are ſo intimately connected, that, to form a juſt idea of either, we ſhould conſider both. The former, as we have already obſerved, origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from the neceſſities of mankind; the latter was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented as an expedient, for conducting the operations of the other with the greater facility, by removing the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties and inconveniencies of barter. <hi>Commerce,</hi> conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the continual exchange and mutual transfer of thoſe things amongſt men, which their reſpective wants, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther natural or artificial, have rendered deſirable; and the uſe of <hi>money</hi> being introduced, as the medium or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument by which this was to be effected; it follows, that theſe two objects ſhould bear a due proportion to each other. The more extenſive the alienation of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty is in any country, the greater will be the quantity of money, <hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> requiſite for carrying it on.</p>
            <p>HENCE we may trace the fallacy of that opinion, maintained by ſome, that it is immaterial, whether the quantity of money in a nation be great or ſmall, as the value of all the labour and commodities within it, taken together, muſt be equal to the whole ſum of its money. —Were ſuch a nation cut off from all communication with every other, there might be ſome truth in the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:019498_0009_0FABADF2E7952208"/>
But as money is a medium, not only of the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal commerce of every nation, ſeparately conſidered; but of their commercial intercourſe, one with another; it is plain that the quantity of this <hi>univerſal</hi> medium in each country muſt not only bear a certain proportion to the alienation within that country, but the entire quantity therein muſt alſo be in a relative ratio to the quantities in all the other trading countries of the world between whom there is an intercourſe, collectively, compared with the amount of the alienation in them all.</p>
            <p>A COMMERCIAL intercourſe between nations would have a tendency to give to each a quantity of this univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal medium, proportionate to its ſhare in ſuch negociations. But either the natural advantages, or thoſe reſulting from political inſtitutions, which one country poſſeſſes above another, deſtroy this kind of equilibrium in the commerce of nations, and create that difference which conſtitutes one rich and another <hi>relatively</hi> poor: — The manner in which this effect may be produced, has been briefly pointed out.</p>
            <p>AS the riches of a country do not <hi>abſolutely</hi> depend on the quantity of money it poſſeſſes; but on the extent and productiveneſs of its lands, the number and induſtry of its inhabitants, and the plenty and intrinſic value of its natural produce—the abundance or ſcarcity of theſe denominate it <hi>really</hi> rich or poor. And as the ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enation and interchanging of theſe <hi>real</hi> riches of a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try conſtitute its trade; the utility and indeed neceſſity of employing ſome ſubſtance which may <hi>repreſent</hi> theſe riches, as the <hi>medium</hi> of transfer, demonſtrate likewiſe the neceſſity of <note n="*" place="bottom">"If a nation has a quantity of money equal to its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, the lands, commodities and labor of the people ſhall bear a middle price. This ſtate is the beſt, and tends moſt to enrich the people, and make their happineſs laſting." Conſiderations on a Paper Currency, written by the late Tench Francis, Eſq. Attorney-General of Penn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvania.</note> proportioning that medium to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of alienation, according to the great commercial ſcale of price and value.</p>
            <p>NOW as, in the commerce of nations, certain natural and political cauſes, either ſeparate or conjunct, deſtroy
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:019498_0010_0FABADF3C9C6AF80"/>
that equilibrium before ſpoken of; and make the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance ſo preponderate on one ſide or the other, as that ſome enjoy the <hi>balance of trade</hi> in their favour, while others have it againſt them, the uſe of COIN, as an <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal medium,</hi> is evident—anſwering as an <hi>equivalent</hi> to make up thoſe deficiencies that ariſe from a wrong ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance in the foreign commerce of countries.</p>
            <p>THIS, indeed, is the chief preeminence which gold and ſilver poſſeſs, as a circulating medium of trade, over ſymbolical money. In many reſpects they are inferior to it. The immenſe quantities of theſe <note n="‡" place="bottom">Sir William Blackſtone tells us, that above a thouſand millions of bullion are calculated to have been imported in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Europe from America, within leſs than three centuries; and the quantity is daily increaſing.</note> metals which are continually procured from the bowels of the earth, and introduced into the dealings of men, under the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification of <hi>coin,</hi> render them, in ſome degree, impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per subſtances to be the<note n="*" place="bottom">"No material money, let it be contrived as it will, is exempted from viciſſitudes in its value as a metal. This is proved by the univerſal riſings and ſinkings in the price of commodities, in conſequence of circumſtances peculiar to the <hi>coin.</hi> Theſe riſings and ſinkings of prices, I ſay, are properly riſings and ſinkings <hi>of the value of the coin,</hi> and that again is a lengthening and contracting of the equal parts of the ſcale of value which is attached to it." Steu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>art's Political Oeconomy, vide note 13.</note>
               <hi>invariable meaſure</hi> of value. They have ſuffered a progreſſive depreciation in the eſtimation of nations, in conſequence of their great increaſe: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides which, they are liable to perpetual fluctuation of price, owing to their being a commodity; and being, as ſuch, in demand among trading nations, may be drawn away from that country where it was employed as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of facilitating its commerce.</p>
            <p>IF we take a retroſpective view of our ſubject, this inference may be deduced—that the principal uſe of <hi>coin,</hi> is the enabling a nation the more eaſily to pay an unfavorable balance on its foreign trade. This, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſhould it not proceed from any <hi>natural</hi> deficiencies on the loſing ſide, a wiſe State will take care to rectify: if the contrary, ſuch adverſe trade ſhould be entirely diſcontinued.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="unknown:019498_0011_0FABADF597561730"/>IT being evident, that a <note n="*" place="bottom">"Pennſylvania, before they made any <hi>Paper-money,</hi> was wholly ſtript of its gold and ſilver, though they had from time to time, like the neighbouring colonies, agreed to take gold and ſilver coins at higher and higher nominal va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues, in hopes of drawing money into, and retaining it for the internal uſe of, the province. During this weak prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, ſilver got up by degrees to 8/9 an ounce, and Engliſh crowns were 6, 7, and 8/ pieces, long before Paper-money was made. But this practice of increaſing the denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was found not to anſwer the end. The BALANCE OF TRADE <hi>carried out the gold and ſilver</hi> as faſt as it was brought in, the merchants raiſing the price of their goods, in proportion to the increaſed denomination of the money. The difficulties for the want of caſh were accordingly very great, the chief part of the trade being carried on by the extremely inconvenient method of barter; when, in 1723, Paper-money was firſt made there, which gave new life to buſineſs, <hi>promoted greatly the ſettlement of new lands,</hi> by lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſmall ſums to beginners on eaſy intereſt, to be repaid by inſtalments; whereby the province has ſo greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in inhabitants, that the export from hence" (Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, where this was written) "thither is now more than tenfold what it then was; and by their trade with foreign colonies they have been able to obtain great quantities of gold and ſilver to remit hither, in return for the manufac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of this country.—New-York and New-Jerſey have alſo increaſed and improved greatly, during the ſame peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od, with the uſe of Paper-money."—Vide Dr. Franklin's Remarks on a Repreſentation from the Engliſh Board of Trade to the King of Great-Britain, dated 9th February 1764.</note> 
               <hi>ſymbolical</hi> money is capable of anſwering all the purpoſes of a circulating medium within a State; we ſhall proceed to examine, how far this country may be benefited by ſuch a currency; and on what principles it had beſt be inſtituted, to advance the true intereſt of the whole community.</p>
            <p>THAT exceſs of the <hi>real</hi> riches of any country which belong to its inhabitants, beyond what their own uſe and conſumption may need, is as unprofitable to the proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, without the means of alienation; as treaſure, in the poſſeſſion of the miſer, is uſeleſs to his neighbour: In both caſes, it is the <hi>alienation</hi> of the property that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes to its value. Thus, although the American
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:019498_0012_0FABADF5DF9B2020"/>
States comprehend a great and fertile territory, capable of yielding an almoſt infinite variety of valuable produc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and inhabited by a very large number of enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing, induſtrious people, who poſſeſs the products of their labor; yet, if deſtitute of a <hi>circulating medium</hi> which ſhould <hi>repreſent</hi> theſe <hi>real</hi> riches, the country might with propriety be called <hi>poor.</hi> But how is this <hi>repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative</hi> value of the real riches of a nation to be obtained, by the people, in the firſt inſtance?</p>
            <p>THIS queſtion opens to us the nature and uſe of CREDIT. Money being the <hi>repreſentative</hi> of <hi>real value,</hi> the poſſeſſion of it denotes, that the owner had given ſome equivalent for it. Therefore, as the acquiſition of <hi>money</hi> muſt neceſſarily be ſubſequent to the means of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring it, thoſe <hi>means</hi> (which muſt have conſiſted of ſome of the conſtituents of real riches, equivalent to the money) muſt have been obtained by the aid of a <hi>credit.</hi> As <hi>coin,</hi> or real money, as it is ſometimes ſtiled, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as the repreſentative of <hi>actual, coexiſtent</hi> value; ſo <hi>credit</hi> may be ſaid to repreſent <hi>anticipated</hi> value;—and <hi>ſymbolical</hi> or <hi>paper-money</hi> may be termed the <hi>evidence</hi> or <hi>token</hi> of credit:—Hence this kind of currency is deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated paper-credit or bills of credit.—The obvious uſe of credit is to ſupply the place of actual money. It fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes a mode of conducting the operations of alienation or commerce, without the immediate intervention of money or occaſion of barter. But being uſed merely as a ſubſtitute for actual money, it ſhould be regulated by the ſame ſcale: and this evinces the propriety of a State not iſſuing a greater ſum in a <hi>paper-money</hi> (which is the <hi>evidence of credit)</hi> than is wanted to ſupply the deficiency of its actual money; ſo that the amount of its coin and paper-credit might form a ſum ſufficient for its aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If, therefore, thoſe things that conſtitute real riches, abound in a country where there is little coin, that country will need a large ſupply of paper-credit to repreſent that proportion of its riches which the diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate quantity of its coin could not effect, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to enable it to carry on an alienation adequate to its riches.</p>
            <p>AS too extenſive a credit muſt needs operate in a manner ſimilar to the circulation of too much money, the great end to be obtained, with reſpect to this point, is, to determine on the beſt poſſible <hi>ſtandard</hi> for aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:019498_0013_0FABADF6A03160F8"/>
the requiſite proportion. This may vary in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent countries, according to the nature of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and other circumſtances peculiar to each. For this reaſon, we ſhall apply the principle to theſe States; to which our enquiries more immediately relate.</p>
            <p>MONEY, and conſequently credit, being inſtrumental to commerce, it ſhould be ſubſervient to its intereſt. The extenſiveneſs and fertility of the <hi>lands</hi> in this country render <note n="†" place="bottom">"It has always appeared to me." ſays Mr. Anderſon, "a little ſurpriſing, that mankind ſhould have in general entertained ſuch juſt ideas with regard to the means of mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing manufactures flouriſh, and ſuch defective notions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning improvements in agriculture. For there is no man ſo ignorant as not to know at once, that the only poſſible way to make a manufacture thrive, is to procure a ready vent for the goods; as without this every other encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, however liberal, muſt be ineffectual. And is it not ſufficiently obvious, that agriculture, although it has been diſtinguiſhed by another name, is, to every intent and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, a <hi>manufacture</hi> in as ſtrict a ſenſe of the word as the forming a yard of broad-cloth; and differs not in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect from other manufactures, as to the means of making it flouriſh?" Obſervations on National Induſtry.</note> 
               <hi>agriculture</hi> the main ſource of its wealth. But, as this fund can only be productive, in proportion to the degree of labor employed in drawing forth its riches; and as that labor muſt alſo be antecedent to even that ſhare of its products which is neceſſary to afford the agent the means of exertion, and to ſubſiſt him in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termediate time; the anticipation required is produced, by the inſtrumentality of credit.</p>
            <p>THE productions of the earth being eſſential to the exiſtence of man, makes the poſſeſſion of lands the moſt valuable ſpecies of property; and they are eſteemed the beſt ſecurity for any credit given. The lands of this country may be conſidered as our great ſtaple, and the culture of them as our principal <note n="*" place="bottom">See the foregoing note.</note> manufacture. In this point of view, <hi>they</hi> may be juſtly deemed the beſt ſtandard for determining what amount of a circulating medium the exigencies of the State may demand, and its abilities ſupport:—For the ſame reaſon, they are the fund on which <hi>that ſpecies</hi> of credit ought to be eſtabliſhed, which
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:019498_0014_0FABADF75CFB0588"/>
applies in a manner peculiarly beneficial to the intereſt of this country, and ſuitable to its circumſtances.</p>
            <p>IT will be readily underſtood, that we here allude to that <hi>credit</hi> which is furniſhed by a State to the culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators (or, what is, in America, much the ſame, the proprietors) of landed eſtates; to enable them, by anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipating the products of ſeveral years labor, ſo to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment induſtry and multiply the means of carrying it on, as to accelerate improvements; and thereby enrich both individuals and the State. <hi>Such</hi> a credit is that created by means of a State LOAN-OFFICE. This is an <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <p>Governor Pownall, a gentleman of extenſive political talents, and well acquainted with the intereſts of this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſpeaks of this inſtitution in theſe remarkable words— "I will venture to ſay, that there never was a wiſer or a better meaſure, never one better calculated to ſerve the uſes of an increaſing country, that there never was a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure more ſteadily purſued, or more faithfully executed, for forty years together, than the <hi>Loan-Office</hi> in Pennſylva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, formed and adminiſtered by the Aſſembly of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince."—This writer gives a ſketch of the Loan-Office Act of Pennſylvania, paſſed in the year 1739, which he ſtiles, "the completeſt of the kind, containing all the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which experience had from time to time ſuggeſted, in the execution of preceding Acts."—Vide his "Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Colonies."—By this act, the truſtees of the Loan-Office were to lend out the bills on real ſecurity of at leaſt double the value, for a term of ſixteen years, to be repaid in yearly quotas or inſtalments, with intereſt: Thus one ſixteenth part of the principal was yearly paid back in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the office, which made the payment eaſy to the borrower: <hi>The intereſt was applied to public ſervices</hi>; the principal, during the firſt ten years, let out again to freſh borrowers.</p>
                  <p>The new borrowers, from year to year, were to have the money only for the remaining part of the term of ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years, repaying by fewer, and of courſe proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly larger inſtalments; and during the laſt ſix years of the ſixteen, the ſums paid in were not to be remitted, but the note burnt and deſtroyed; ſo that at the end of the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years the whole might be called in and burnt, and the accounts completely ſettled.</p>
                  <p>The truſtees were taken from all the different counties in the (then) province, their reſidence in different parts giving them better opportunities of being acquainted with the value and circumſtances of eſtates offered in mortgage. They were to continue but four years in office; were to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count annually to committees of Aſſembly; and at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration of that term, they were to deliver up all monies and ſecurities in their hands, to their ſucceſſors, before their bonds and ſecurities could be diſcharged, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
               </note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:019498_0015_0FABADF99AD22660"/>
ſo admirably adapted to the circumſtances of this country, ſo well calculated to relieve its neceſſities, founded on ſuch ſound principles of national policy, and the proſperous effects of which have been ſo fully experienced, that it is indeed much to be wondered, how the people of America remain ſo inattentive to the moſt important intereſt of their country, as not to have it eſtabliſhed in every State in the Union! We are well aware of the prejudices that have been entertained againſt a paper-currency; and, indeed, the manner in which it was iſſued, during the late war, afforded too much grounds for ſuch prejudices. But arguments drawn from the abuſe of a thing, do not militate againſt the excellence of the thing itſelf or its uſe: And this obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation will ſtrongly apply to the ſubject before us.</p>
            <p>ACCORDING to the principles before laid down, our circulating medium ought to keep pace with the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing improvement of the country: Yet we know that the balance of our trade with foreign nations is adverſe; and, conſequently, that the gold and ſilver-monies of the country muſt diminiſh in the ſame degree. Here, then, is the great and direct ſource of that diſtreſs and embarraſsment, which pervade the United States, ariſing from the inſufficiency of a medium of alienation. While the cauſe continues, it is in vain to look for a ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the effects; and it is greatly to be feared, that unleſs a timely ſtop be put to the evil, the country will be involved in a general calamity. The remedy is in our own power. Should we neglect to apply it, or ſuffer ourſelves to be ſo far either influenced or deceived, by falſe repreſentations and partial intereſts, as to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice the general good to private views, we would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſerve nor enjoy thoſe means of national happineſs that now lie within our reach.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="unknown:019498_0016_0FABADF9A696F3B8"/>LET us then (to uſe the expreſſion of an <note n="§" place="bottom">The author of the characteriſtics of the preſent politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſtate of Great-Britain.—The ſame writer obſerves that "the more the lands of any country are <hi>locked up,</hi> the leſs muſt the country be improved: And the more eaſily lands can be transferred and exchanged in commerce; induſtry, trade and manufactures, will be more ſpeedily and ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully promoted."</note> anony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous writer) <hi>coin our lands,</hi> and thereby obtain from thoſe moſt valuable of all mines, a ſufficient circulating medium of commerce. for this purpoſe let LOAN-OF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FICES be inſtituted in the ſeveral States, on principles ſimilar to thoſe whereon the loan-office of Pennſylvania was eſtabliſhed for many years. The <hi>medium</hi> furniſhed by means of this inſtitution, is founded on the baſis of <hi>credit</hi>; and, as it is expreſsly calculated to promote, in the firſt inſtance, the extenſion of <hi>agriculture,</hi> that great <hi>ſtaple manufacture</hi> of this country, which of courſe forms the greateſt part of its commerce.—at leaſt that branch which tends moſt to its intereſt,—it is the beſt medium we can employ to advance the national welfare. It is, beſides the only ſpecies of money partaking of the nature of <hi>credit,</hi> that is not liable to abuſe.</p>
            <p>FOR, being eſtabliſhed on that kind of it denominated <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>"Private credit</hi> is eſtabliſhed upon a <hi>ſecurity,</hi> real or perſonal, of value ſufficient to make good the obligation of repayment both of capital and intereſt: <hi>This is the moſt ſolid of all."</hi> Sir James Steuart on Political Oeconomy.</note> 
               <hi>private</hi> credit, it cannot exceed, in quantity or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal value, the actual and real worth of the ſecurity which it repreſents. The <hi>demand</hi> for money muſt ever be proportionate to its <hi>uſes</hi>; and thus the neceſſary <hi>quantity</hi> may be eaſily accommodated to the demand. Nor can there be any doubt of this being a proper ſtandard of regulation with reſpect to a loan-office mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; becauſe, the <hi>uſes</hi> originating from, and being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to, funds of the moſt valuable and ſubſtantial nature, namely lands, the borrower would not be willing to pay intereſt for a greater ſum than he could reaſonably ſuppoſe might be employed to his advantage. Added to this, that the ſum lent would not exceed one half the eſtimated value of ſuch fund, pledged as a ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for its repayment or redemption.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="unknown:019498_0017_0FABADFA75D207C8"/>THE value of lands is uſually computed at the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of a certain term of years; that is, being them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a <hi>fund,</hi> the profits accruing from its employment within a given portion of time, will determine the value of the <hi>ſtock</hi> producing thoſe profits, compared with the profits ariſing from the uſe of money, the meaſure of that value, in the ſame country. So that, if the circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating medium of a country be duly proportioned to its commerce, and if that medium or money will yield an average profit of <hi>ſix per centum per annum,</hi> to thoſe who make uſe of it, the value of lands in that country may be eſtimated at about ſixteen years purchaſe: On the ſame principle the intereſt of money is regulated, by a compariſon with the productive value of labor and lands. This ſuggeſts the uſe of a well-regulated <hi>credit</hi>; which, by operating as ſtock, augments the profit on the actual capital employed in conjunction with it.</p>
            <p>HERE we trace the beneficial effect of the credit ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the agriculturiſt from a loan-office, in a ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical money. The lands, in an improved country only, can be valued at any certain number of years pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe. But in this new country, the progreſſive im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the lands from year to year, is continually increaſing the capital of the landholder. And this effect,—this immenſe ſource of national wealth and fund of credit,—will not ceaſe, until the cultivation of our lands ſhall have arrived at ſuch a height and become ſo general, as that the annual profits of farming will not ſurpaſs the intereſt of money. The very low <hi>price</hi> which improvable lands bear in this country, is no criterion of their <hi>value</hi>; but ariſes ſolely from the inſufficiency of the <hi>means</hi> neceſſary for acquiring and improving them; for an uncultivated ſoil is of as little uſe, as a diamond in the boſom of the mine.</p>
            <p>As money derives its value from its <hi>uſes,</hi> it is evident, that, when the quantity does not exceed thoſe uſes, its value will not be impaired. The difficulty, with reſpect to a ſymbolical money in general, is to aſcertain the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductiveneſs</hi> and to ſecure the <hi>certainty</hi> of the <hi>fund,</hi> which creates the uſes. <hi>Taxes</hi> are a ſufficient fund for ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the credit of a paper-money, provided due regard be had to theſe eſſential points. The credit of paper iſſued by <hi>Banks</hi> founded entirely on mercantile credit, in thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercial countries which enjoy a favorable balance of trade,
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:019498_0018_0FABADFC4AE3C3F8"/>
may alſo be rendered ſufficiently ſtable, by prudence and circumſpection in the managers. But in both inſtances, neither can the productiveneſs of the fund be aſcertained, nor its certainty be ſecured, by any real ſtandard. The operations of a merely mercantile Bank are, in a peculiar manner, liable to extend credit beyond its proper bounds, in countries which carry on a diſadvantageous foreign trade: becauſe the intereſt of the proprietors will lead them to circulate a fictitious money, in their paper-cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, to as large an amount as they may ſuppoſe conſiſtent with their own ſafety; and this very credit adds to the means of accelerating that trade, already prejudicial to the nation. The notes of ſuch a Bank are iſſued on <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantile</hi> credit. "This," ſays Sir James Steuart, "is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed upon the <hi>confidence</hi> the lender has, that the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower, from his integrity and knowledge in trade, may be able to replace the capital advanced, and the intereſt due during the advance, in terms of the agreement." It is this kind of credit that the ſame author ſtiles, <q>the moſt precarious of all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>THE great temptations that lie in the way of Banks on mercantile credit, on the one hand, and of States on the other, to iſſue their paper on their reſpective funds of <hi>mere confidence,</hi> in too great quantities; by over-rating the productiveneſs of thoſe <hi>anticipated funds</hi> on which that <hi>confidence</hi> is grounded (and which are, neceſſarily, ſubject to ſome uncertainty, from the nature of them)—thoſe very circumſtances tend to render the <hi>credit</hi> of <hi>ſuch</hi> paper very delicate.</p>
            <p>BUT that ſpecies of <hi>paper-money,</hi> that is iſſued on the ſecurity of <hi>lands,</hi> which are made an actual equivalent <hi>depoſit</hi> for its redemption, from the moment of its going into circulation, is not liable to any objections on this ſcore. The <hi>fund itſelf,</hi> that is, the land, is actually exiſting; and the credit, eſtabliſhed on it, repreſents the value of <hi>this</hi> fund, and not of the <hi>anticipated profits</hi> to be derived from the employment of it. The more firmly to eſtabliſh the credit of a <hi>loan-office</hi> money, no perſon can borrow from the State more than one half the eſtimated value of his land: And in order to diſſeminate the advantages of this credit the more extenſively, and to enhance its uſefulneſs, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate ſums only (not exceeding, perhaps, two hundred pounds) are loaned to individuals, let the value of their
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:019498_0019_0FABADFCF69DD3A8"/>
lands be what they may;—by which means, this inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutition is peculiarly adapted to benefit the new ſettlers and leſſer proprietors of lands, a claſs of people who moſt ſtand in need of encouragement in this country.</p>
            <p>THIS kind of money, being eſtabliſhed on permanent and certain funds, is extremely well calculated not only for a circulating medium within the particular State which iſſues it, but alſo as a medium of trade between the ſeveral States; for, as Sir James Stuart obſerves, <q>it is the intereſt of every trading State to have a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity of paper, <hi>well-ſecured,</hi> to circulate through it, ſo as to facilitate payments every where, and to cut off inland exchanges, which are a great clog upon trade, and are attended with the riſque of receiving the paper of people, whoſe credit is but doubtful.</q>
            </p>
            <p>IT is a trite objection to paper-money, that it ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes gold and ſilver from the country where it ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains. This has been often invalidated. Dr. Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin (in his remarks on the report, &amp;c.) has ſhewn, that it is an <hi>unfavorable balance of trade</hi> that draws the gold and ſilver out of the country, and that the "neceſſity of ſubſtituting ſome medium in their ſtead has induced the making of paper-money which could not be drawn away." So far is the paper-money the cauſe of this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that, by increaſing alienation and the means of exciting induſtry, it has a direct tendency to increaſe the ſtock of coin ih the country. And, as the quantity of paper-money in a country will not ſuffer any dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of its value while it does not exceed its <hi>uſes,</hi> this currency can have no effect in raiſing the price of labor and commodities, while kept within thoſe bounds.</p>
            <p>A LOAN-OFFICE money being employed in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of lands becomes <hi>realiſed</hi> in a ſpecies of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty which, in theſe ſtates, is productive of much greater emoluments, both to the public and to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors, than can be derived from the uſe of ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied capitals, in any manner of trade, honorable to an individual, or conſiſtent with the common weal.</p>
            <p>AT the ſame time that the cultivator of the ſoil is, by this means, enriching himſelf, and increaſing the <hi>real</hi> wealth of his country in a direct point of view, other ſalutary conſequences reſult from a <hi>loan-office</hi> credit. Its circulating paper, by filling up the chaſm in the medium
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:019498_0020_0FABADFECBE6A180"/>
of alienation, occaſioned by the ſcarcity of coin, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages induſtry and genius, promotes arts and manufac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; enlivens commerce, gives the means of comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſubſiſtence to the poor, and enables all claſſes of people to contribute to the ſupport of Government and eſtabliſhment of public credit, by a regular and liberal payment of taxes. Indeed the revenue that might be obtained from the intereſt on a loan-office money, would, of itſelf, form a very conſiderable fund, applicable to public uſes.</p>
            <p>THE numerous and important advantages, accruing from this kind of inſtitution, are by no means exaggerated. On the contrary, a little reflection will ſuggeſt, to any perſon acquainted with this country, many other inſtances wherein its operations muſt be extremely ſerviceable: But the nature of the inſtitution need to be only under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to demonſtrate its utility.—Neither is it a ſcheme founded on mere theoretical principles, as the experience of <note n="*" place="bottom">See note page 9.</note> Pennſylvania can teſtify: She, as well as ſome of her ſiſter States, has heretofore felt the invigorating influence of this cheering political ſun.—May it ſpeedily ariſe to re-enlighten this weſtern world; and, by dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing its benign rays throughout our infant empire, quicken the feeds of induſtry, art, manufactures, and commerce!</p>
            <p>IF we compare the nature and effects of this <hi>loan-office</hi> money with the paper circulated by a mercantile Bank, how great is the contraſt!—We have ſhewn in what manner the circumſtances of this country require an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing currency; while, at the ſame time, the unfavor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able balance of its foreign trade is continually draining away its coin.<note n="§" place="bottom">"The only occaſion where <hi>coin</hi> is neceſſary in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidation of <hi>paper,</hi> is for payment of the balance of trade with foreign nations.—But ſurely nothing is ſo ill judged as to erect an imaginary balance within the ſame ſtate; or, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to permit money-jobbers to erect it, at the expence of raiſing intereſt, and hurting trade, in the very places where it ſtands in the greateſt need of encouragement." Steuart's Pol. Oec.</note> From thence we inferred the neceſſity of
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:019498_0021_0FABADFEDB9C5048"/>
calling in the aid of <hi>credit,</hi> as a ſubſtitute for money, and plainly pointed out <hi>lands</hi> as the proper fund for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting that credit.</p>
            <p>WHEN we conſider for what purpoſes a credit is uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and neceſſary, in this country, we muſt be convinced that <hi>that</hi> ſpecies of it which is furniſhed by a mercantile Bank, is ſo far from anſwering the end, that it has a direct tendency to defeat it. The uſe of credit being to ſupply the place of real funds, it is obvious that it can only prove beneficial to a nation, when thoſe funds are employed in promoting and extending ſuch branches of its commerce as tend to enrich it, by increaſing its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and diminiſhing its imports. This is the effect produced by the paper-credit, created by Government, by means of a loan-office.</p>
            <p>BUT a mercantile Bank cannot lend on any other ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity than mere confidence, grounded on opinion only. The farmer, who is deſirous of borrowing a little pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniary capital towards enabling him to improve or cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate his eſtate, cannot obtain a farthing from the Bank, on the ſecurity of his lands, be their value what they may: Whilſt the merchant, whoſe property is of the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious and deluſive nature, may readily procure a ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious capital to facilitate his importation of foreign mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe. Thus, the farmer being excluded from this credit, with which the importer is ſo eaſily accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated, the balance of trade againſt the country will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe by the very means which ought to operate in its favor.</p>
            <p>WHO, then, are to be benefited by this Bank?— We have ſeen that the farmer is not; neither are the people at large. The State might, indeed, be occaſionally obliged and indulged with favors from the directors: But, we would aſk, would it be conſiſtent with the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, the intereſt, nay the <hi>ſafety</hi> of Government, to lay themſelves under obligations to, and render themſelves dependent on a private trading company?—Every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent man will anſwer—No. The State has funds of credit of a much ſuperior kind; and is not under the neceſſity of ſubmitting to ſuch an indignity. The only claſs of people who could derive any advantage from a mercantile Bank among us, would be thoſe connected with the inſtitution itſelf; except, perhaps, in ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively few inſtances. The wrong balance of our
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:019498_0022_0FABAE00618E2A08"/>
trade, by increaſing the demand for money, would raiſe the price above its value as a circulating medium and common ſtandard. And, by this means, the ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders might draw an intereſt on their Bank property, far beyond its juſt level. We have already ſeen the Bank in Philadelphia making a dividend to the proprietors of its funds, of more than double the legal intereſt of money. It is not, therefore, to be wondered, that ſome of theſe proprietors, eſpecially thoſe moſt intimately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected with the inſtitution, ſhould be extremely anxious to ſupport what is ſo very ſubſervient to their private intereſts.</p>
            <p>BUT let us turn our attention to the tendency of this Bank, in ſome other reſpects.—The farmer can bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row nothing from thence.—When he applies to a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied man for a loan from his private fortune, on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of his lands, he cannot ſucceed; becauſe no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will lend his money even on landed ſecurity, at ſix per cent per annum, while he can inveſt it in a fund which will yield him twice that intereſt. What then muſt be the conſequence? The farmer, finding himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, with all his toil, to cultivate his lands to any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, without the aſſiſtance of ſome credit; being debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the acquiſition of it; and obſerving the ſuperior emoluments derived from banking, without any labour; ſells his lands, and becomes a Bank-ſtockholder. This inducement will have a general operation, and the ſame cauſe which leads the farmer to ſell, produces a disincli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the monied man to purchaſe, landed eſtates: Conſequently, the value of lands muſt ſink; and agricul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the great ſupport of our country, muſt decline.</p>
            <p>NOT only the cultivation of lands is obſtructed by theſe means, but alſo the improvement and extenſion of our ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and towns. Many who poſſeſs unimproved town-lots would erect houſes on them, if, by mortgaging their ground, they could obtain money for the purpoſe; but the Bank renders this impracticable. Even monied men, who own property of this kind, will not employ it in build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when bank-ſtock will afford them greater profits than the rents of houſes, on the ſame amount of fund. In this manner, the Bank has a direct tendency to keep houſe-rent high; and to prevent the employment of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, carpenters, ſmiths, and all that numerous and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful body of mechanics, who derive their ſubſiſtence, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:019498_0023_0FABAE0234DDB8D0"/>
wholly, from the conſtruction of houſes. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors of houſes in Philadelphia were formerly very well ſatisfied to receive the legal intereſt of their money in rents; but, while twelve per cent per annum can be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by banking, the landlord may exact double rent for his houſe. Yet were he to ſell it, he would probably not procure more than the capital of the legal intereſt. So that the Bank may be juſtly conſidered as an auxiliary cauſe of our exorbitant rents; a circumſtance ſo grievous to the tenants, ſo neceſſarily productive of the high price of labor among our artiſans and mechanics, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to the whole community.—In ſhort, ſuch a train of evils reſult from the <hi>high intereſt of money,</hi> alone, that its baneful effects may be traced every where, and every claſs of our citizens muſt ultimately experience them. A few monied men and private individuals derive, indeed, an immediate benefit from this ſource; but the cultivator of the ſoil, the induſtrious manufacture and mechanic, in fact the State itſelf, become inevitably ſufferers.</p>
            <p>It is eaſy to conceive, why perſons, who have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barked their funds in the Bank, are ſo averſe to a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency iſſued by Government. In proportion to the ſcarcity of money, will be the demand for credit; and while the Bank can monopolize this credit, it may alſo monopolize the emoluments accruing from it. Any competition with the proprietors of the Bank would leſſen their profits; and, for that reaſon, will be oppoſed. This oppoſition to a State paper-money was exhibited in a ſtriking manner by the friends and ſupporters of the Bank, when the Legiſlature were about iſſuing the bills of credit now in circulation; but, notwithſtanding the fears that were ſuggeſted of its depreciation, the ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of the funds appropriated for their redemption have fully ſupported their credit.</p>
            <p>IF it be the intereſt of the State to iſſue a paper-cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, which, we preſume, is incontrovertible; and if the primary object of the Bank, namely its own immediate profit, be incompatible with the intereſt of the State, in that particular, is it not reaſonable to ſuppoſe, that every ſpecies of <hi>influence</hi> which the Bank poſſeſſes, will be exerted againſt ſo advantageous and neceſſary a meaſure of Government?—Apprehenſions of an undue exerciſe of influence from ſo powerful and uncontroul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:019498_0024_0FABAE02DFE79E28"/>
a combination of property in private hands cannot, therefore, be ill-grounded, in the infant ſtate of our public credit. Such apprehenſions have exiſted in old, trading nations, where the conſequences could not prove ſo dangerous to the State.—When the Britiſh Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment extended the term, for which the Bank of England held its charter, only ten years beyond its ordinary dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of twenty-one years, Mr. David Hartley ſounded the alarm; and, in his letter of the 22d of June, 1781, to the Lord Mayor of London, on that occaſion, (pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in Almon's Remembrancer for that year) has pointed out the injurious tendency, with reſpect to Government, of the additional influence given to the Bank, by that meaſure.</p>
            <p>IN the year 1721, an attempt was wade to inſtitute a Bank in Ireland. Upon that occaſion, the Houſe of Commons, by a majority of 150 to 80, "reſolved, that the erecting or eſtabliſhing of a public Bank in that kingdom would be of the moſt dangerous and fatal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences to his Majeſty's ſervice, and the trade and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the nation." Addreſſing the King on this ſubject, they ſay, "As this was a matter of univerſal and national concern, your dutiful Commons took the ſame into their moſt ſerious conſideration, and not find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any ſolid or good foundation for eſtabliſhing a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Bank, ſo as to be beneficial to the nation, or even conſiſtent with the welfare or liberties of it, think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obliged in duty to your Majeſty, and juſtice to themſelves and thoſe whom they repreſent, to offer their humble opinion to your Majeſty, that the eſtabliſhing of any public Bank in this Kingdom, will be greatly prejudicial to your Majeſty's ſervice, and of moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and pernicious conſequence to the welfare and liberty of this nation. Your faithful Commons do therefore moſt humbly beſeech your Majeſty, out of your tender concern for the good of all your ſubjects, to deliver them from the <hi>apprehenſions they lie under, of the</hi> POWER <hi>and</hi> INFLUENCE <hi>of a public Bank, if once erected,</hi> by giving ſuch directions as your Majeſty ſhall think proper, to prevent the eſtabliſhment of the ſame in this Kingdom."</p>
            <p>HENCE it is plain, that the Legiſlature of Pennſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania have not been ſingular, in their dread of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of a Bank.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="unknown:019498_0025_0FABAE035A115AE8"/>UPON the whole, if we trace the <note n="*" place="bottom">"No method has hitherto been found to eſtabliſh a medium of trade, in lieu of money, equal in all its advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to <hi>bills of credit,</hi> funded on ſufficient taxes for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging it; <hi>or on land ſecurity of double the value for repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, at the end of the term:</hi> The experience of near half a century in the middle colonies has convinced them of it, among themſelves, by the great increaſe of their ſettlements, numbers, buildings, improvements, agriculture, ſhipping and commerce." Vide Doctor Franklin's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks, &amp;c.</note> effects of a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blic Loan-office money, through its various operations, it will be found in every reſpect highly beneficial, and in no inſtance detrimental, to the State: Whereas, thoſe of a great mercantile Bank, in the preſent circumſtances of our commerce, are totally oppoſite.</p>
            <p>COMMERCE is ſo intimately connected with money, that the importance of a well regulated commercial ſyſtem is to obvious to need any comment. It is a ſubject highly intereſting to this country, eſpecially under its preſent circumſtances, and claims the ſerious attention of every good citizen. Our internal proſperity,—our ſtrength and reſpectability among nations,—depend ſo much on the right management of this great concern, that there is no duty more incumbent on thoſe who have the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our public affairs, than to watch over its operations with an eagle-eye.</p>
            <p>WHEN the circulating medium bears a due proportion to the alienation, or, in other words, the commerce, of a nation, the <hi>courſe of exchange,</hi> may juſtly be deemed the criterion of the ſtate of its <hi>foreign</hi> trade. If the balance be adverſe, exchange will be high; and if it be favorable, bills will be low. For ſhould the commodities imported into a country exceed in value thoſe exported from it, in any given time, the demand for bills would raiſe their price above the par of exchange; and the exports ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the imports would produce a contrary effect. But if the exceſs of the latter were ſo far to overbalance the former, as to render the remittance of bills more unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable than that of gold and ſilver; <hi>coin</hi> and bullion would then be exported to pay the balance due to the foreign country.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="unknown:019498_0026_0FABAE05048BAA70"/>THIS, as we have before obſerved, is the uſe of <hi>coin,</hi> and the cauſe of the ſuperior worth attributed to it in the capacity of a money. The ſubſtance of which it is made being in univerſal eſtimation among mankind, it is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity conveniently tranſportable from one country to another to make up thoſe deficiencies in its <hi>foreign</hi> trade, which the country exporting it cannot otherwiſe ſupply. When, therefore, coin is in demand for this purpoſe, a premium will be offered for it; and its price will riſe, like that of any other commodity in ſimilar circumſtances, according to the demand. Now, as the ſum of a circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating medium, neceſſary for the purpoſes of alienation within a <hi>proſperous</hi> country, muſt be greatly beyond that of the coin any occaſions can require for its negotiations with foreign nations; any cauſe which might contribute to <note n="†" place="bottom">"In England, as bullion has been wanted or not wanted for exportation, its price has varied from 5/2 to 5/8 per ounce. This is near 10 per cent. but was it ever ſaid or thought, on ſuch an occaſion, that all the bank-bills, and all the coined ſilver, and all the gold in the kingdom were <hi>depreciated</hi> 10 per cent?—Coined ſilver is often wanted in England for change, and one per cent. is given for it by ſome bankers; are gold and bank-notes, therefore, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preciated</hi> one per cent?"—See Dr. Franklin's Remarks, &amp;c.</note> advance the price of coin, above the rate of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral currency of that country, (ſuppoſe a paper-money) ought to be conſidered as raiſing the price of the coin, in its quality of a <hi>commodity,</hi> and not as a depreciation of the currency, in its office of a <hi>money.</hi> Becauſe, in ſuch a caſe, the high intereſt or premium that coin would command, would occaſion a diminution of the <hi>price</hi> of even <note n="*" place="bottom">"If a nation's commerce, on uſes of money, exceed the quantity of it, their lands, labor, and commodities, ſhall <hi>fink beneath their worth</hi> in other countries. Few purchaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of land will be found, in regard to the ſuperior profit that muſt attend the uſe of money in trade; <hi>the wealthy merchant ſhall be at the head of affairs:</hi> With few competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he ſhall be able to grind down the farmer in the ſale of his commodities; and, when thoſe fail to ſupport him, in the purchaſe of his lands. The artiſan's labor ſhall be depreciated by the merchant who exports it, or the needy farmer who uſes it. The wealthy only ſhall accumulate riches, the Commonwealth ſhall decline, and in time far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers and artiſans muſt deſert the place for another, where their labor ſhall be better rewarded.—<hi>Here,</hi> the uſe of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-money</hi> will ſhake off the fetters and clogs of the poor. Merchants will multiply; they will raiſe the price of labor, and of the fruits of the earth, and thereby the value of land. An equal diſtribution of gain and profit ſhall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, and deſtroy the partial accumulations of wealth."— Francis's Conſiderations on a Paper Currency.</note> landed property, the trueſt riches of a people, and
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:019498_0027_0FABAE06F34A8228"/>
one of thoſe ſpecies of property of which money is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned only to <hi>repreſent</hi> the value: Yet the <hi>intrinſic value</hi> of the lands would continue unaltered; nor could they, with any propriety, be ſaid to have depreciated.</p>
            <p>BUT this is merely a ſuppoſable caſe; as that favor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able balance which conſtitutes the commercial proſperity of a country, excludes the poſſibility of that compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, which advances the price of coin above its value as a money.</p>
            <p>THE foregoing conſiderations ſufficiently ſhew, that the grand <hi>deſideratum</hi> in the commerce of a nation, is to maintain a favorable balance in its foreign trade; which is evidenced by a general courſe of low <note n="*" place="bottom">When exchange riſes ſo high as to occaſion a demand for <hi>coin,</hi> to ſubſtitute as a remittance in lieu of bills, a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium above its ordinary value as a <hi>money</hi> will be given for it; and thus the <hi>intereſt of money</hi> will riſe in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try above its juſt level: For Dr. Franklin has obſerved (in his Remarks on the Report, &amp;c.) that whenever bills of exchange have advanced in price in this country, the purchaſer has invariably been obliged to give more in ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as well as in paper for them, the ſilver having gone hand in hand with the paper.—"Low intereſt," ſays Sir James Steuart, "is principally advantageous for carrying on to keep circulation full, by facilitating the melting down of property."</note> exchange.</p>
            <p>THOSE meaſures, therefore, that tend to increaſe the exports and diminiſh the imports of a nation are the eſſential means of obtaining that end.</p>
            <p>FOR this purpoſe, the <hi>internal</hi> commerce of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:019498_0028_0FABAE079C529C40"/>
muſt be promoted, by increaſing its <hi>real riches.</hi>— <note n="*" place="bottom">"Thoſe who wiſh to make agriculture flouriſh in any country, can have no hope of ſucceeding in the attempt, but by bringing commerce and manufactures to her aid; which, by taking from the farmer his ſuperfluous produce, gives ſpirit to his operations, and life and activity to his mind." Anderſon on National Induſtry.</note> Agriculture muſt be extended, population encouraged, the acquiſition of raw materials facilitated, and domeſtic manufactures, eſpecially of the natural productions of the country, eſtabliſhed:— The commercial proſperity, and conſequently the real independence, of the Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can States, will be accelerated or retarded, according to the progreſs of theſe.</p>
            <p>WE have already endeavoured to enforce the neceſſity of eſtabliſhing a circulating medium, on the fund of our lands, as a primary ſtep to advance the intereſt of the whole community, by putting in the hands of the landholder the means of improving his eſtate. But im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements in agriculture will avail but little, unleſs a demand be kept up for the products of landed eſtates. The demand for the ſupply of foreign countries, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on a combination of various circumſtances, muſt prove extremely fluctuating. For this reaſon, the more it can be rendered independent of ſuch extraneous cauſes, the more regular will be the demand. And, therefore, the nearer the number of tradeſmen, mechanics, artiſts, and all that deſcription of people who uſually inhabit towns, approaches that of the agriculturiſts, by ſo much the leſs will the intereſt of the latter be affected by the precarious operations of foreign trade. Alſo, the fuller the population of the nation is,—provided a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient proportion of the inhabitants be employed in uſeful handicraft trades, mechanic arts, and as merchants in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducting the buſineſs of alienation,—the more beneficial will be the nature of its commerce, conſidered in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional point of view. In ſuch circumſtances, the export-trade of the country will be enlarged, while its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portations of foreign manufactures will be leſſened in the ſame rates; and thus the intereſt of the <note n="§" place="bottom">"It would be of much importance to the State," ſays Mr. Anderſon, "if country gentlemen, and the Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at large, would learn to diſtinguiſh with preciſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thoſe kinds of commerce and manufactures that tend only to enrich the merchant, and thoſe that at the ſame time tend to enrich the country and augment its internal proſperity; for theſe are often disjoined; ſo often, indeed, that thoſe kinds of traffic which are in general moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the merchant, are leaſt beneficial to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try."—Obſervations on National Induſtry.</note> merchant
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:019498_0029_0FABAE07DD4D6B48"/>
will be made to coincide with that of his country:— Otherwiſe, however patriotic principles a merchant may poſſeſs, he will find them aſſailed by his private intereſt. A few individuals in a nation may be actuated by ſuch exalted ſentiments of public virtue, as to ſacrifice their own intereſts to the general welfare; but theſe inſtances muſt be rare; and profeſſional men of every deſcription are neceſſarily, as ſuch, obliged to purſue their imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate advantage.</p>
            <p>UNTIL the country becomes pretty fully populated, the price of labor will continue high; and, although this would be no diſadvantage to a wealthy country, if cut off from foreign trade, yet it would be a conſiderable obſtruction to the eſtabliſhment of domeſtic manufac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; which, we have ſhewn, are <note n="§" place="bottom">"There are ſome inſtances of nations peculiarly ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated which have flouriſhed by means of commerce, without agriculture; there are alſo a very few examples of manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures flouriſhing among a people who could have little dependence on the produce of the ſoil: But there is not among all the records of paſt ages a ſingle proof of a people who have enjoyed, for any length of time, a ſpirited agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culture, without the aid of commerce, or manufactures, or both." Anderſon's Obſervations on National Induſtry.</note> eſſential to a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing ſtate of agriculture.</p>
            <p>IN order, therefore, to create a demand for domeſtic manufactures among us, the introduction of thoſe foreign ones, which interfere with them, muſt be laid under cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain reſtrictions; and theſe muſt be continued, until the competition, occaſioned by the diſparity of prices in the foreign and domeſtic articles of the ſame kind, ſhall be deſtroyed, by a gradual reduction of the price of labor at home.—Theſe reſtrictions may conſiſt in <hi>duties</hi> on the
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:019498_0030_0FABAE08A20C81C8"/>
imported <note n="*" place="bottom">"Dr. Price, ſpeaking of the foreign trade of the American States, has this ſentiment.—"Indeed, I tremble when I think of that rage for trade which is likely to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail among them. It may do them infinite miſchief. All nations are ſpreading ſnares for them, and courting to a dangerous intercourſe. Their beſt intereſt requires them to guard themſelves by all proper means; and, <hi>particularly,</hi> BY LAYING HEAVY DUTIES ON IMPORTATIONS." Obſervations on the American Revolution.</note> commodity, <hi>bounties</hi> on the domeſtic manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture, and, in ſome caſes, both co-operating, with rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ſame article.—Sir James Steuart has ſo well expreſſed our ſentiments on this head, that we will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey them in his words. Treating of the means of inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting manufactures in a State, he ſays—"The ruling principle which ought to direct a ſtateſman is to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the manufacturing of every branch of natural pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions, by extending the home conſumption of them; by excluding all competition of ſtrangers; by permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the riſe of profits, ſo far as to promote dexterity and emulation in invention and improvement; by relieving the induſtrious of their work, ſo often as demand for it falls ſhort. And, until it can be exported to advantage, it may be exported with loſs, at the expenſe of the public. To ſpare no expenſe in procuring the ableſt maſters in every branch of induſtry, nor any coſt in making the firſt eſtabliſhments; providing machines, and every other thing neceſſary or uſeful to make the undertaking ſucceed."</p>
            <p>THE carrying trade of the United-States is alſo an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of great national importance. The country abounds with naval ſtores; and ſhip-building is, or may be, one of our moſt beneficial employments.</p>
            <p>THIS ſpecies of manufacture is of ſuch a magnitude as to demand the attention of Governments in a particular manner. The ſame principles on which thoſe meaſures are founded, which have been mentioned as neceſſary to promote domeſtic manufactures, generally, may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the encouragement of this.—Sir Joſiah Child (in his diſcourſe on trade) declares himſelf of opinion, that, in relation to trade, ſhipping, profit and power, the
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:019498_0031_0FABAE0A28A70350"/>
               <note n="§" place="bottom">The Act of navigation was paſſed in the 12th Car. II. A. D. 1660.—Sir Joſiah Child wrote about eighteen years afterwards.</note> Engliſh Navigation-Act is one of the beſt and moſt politic laws that ever was made in England; and without which, that country would not have had one half the number of ſhipping, or trade, nor have employed half the number of ſeamen, which it did at the time he wrote. Our policy undoubtedly dictates the propriety of impoſing <hi>extraordinary</hi> duties on dutiable commodities impo<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> from foreign countries into theſe States, in veſſels <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> abroad or owned by foreigners; eſpecially on articles of mere luxury: Although ſome conſiderations may render particular exemptions and diſcriminations indiſpenſable and proper. In <note n="*" place="bottom">We will not attempt to ſpecify thoſe caſes to which the firſt part of this propoſition may be applicable: A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination of circumſtances muſt deſignate theſe.—But our infant <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> trade ſeems to come under the latter head. It is true, that the importations from the Eaſt conſiſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally in thoſe things, which are uſually denominated ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of luxury. But, as many of theſe have, by long ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, acquired among us the character of <hi>neceſſaries,</hi> and are therefore conſtantly imported from Europe, at ſecond hand; policy dictates the expediency, of giving every poſſible en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to the American merchant, in carrying on a trade <hi>directly</hi> to the Eaſt-Indies. Thus will the profits on that trade, now enjoyed by ſtrangers, center with our own citizens; while this new channel of commerce will employ an additional number of American ſhipping and ſeamen, and furniſh a vent for an article, the natural pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of this country, much eſteemed in the Eaſt.</note> ſome inſtances, certain kinds of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe ought, perhaps, to be exonerated from all duties, whether imported in American or foreign bottoms: But in other caſes, ſuch exemption might properly be reſtricted to goods imported in American veſſels only.</p>
            <p>BUT a very obvious and important reflection ariſes here:—And that is, that every effort which can be made by individual States, for placing our foreign trade on an advantageous footing for this country, is liable to be fruſtrated, by other States counteracting them, or not coinciding in ſimilar meaſures. The want of that <hi>uniformity,</hi> which is neceſſary to give efficiency and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manency
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:019498_0032_0FABAE0BE20D4CE8"/>
to the commercial ſyſtem of a nation, will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in a great degree, ineffectual, all partial regulations for the advancement of our trade. A power muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be lodged <hi>ſomewhere,</hi> for adjuſting the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercial, as well as the political, intereſts of the ſeveral States in the Union, to <hi>one general ſcale</hi>; and, according to the principles on which our foederal Conſtitution is framed, this power ought to be veſted in the SUPREME HEAD OF THE UNION, in order to eſtabliſh the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of the United States on the ſolid baſis of <hi>national</hi> ſyſtem.</p>
            <p>IN the mean time, the unſettled ſtate of our foreign trade lays us under a double obligation aſſiduouſly to promote our <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <p>By raiſing large flocks of ſheep, ſufficient quantities of wool may be ſupplied for the manufacturing of coarſe wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len cloths, ſtockings, common hats, &amp;c.—Hemp furniſhes us with the valuable article of cordage; and flax-ſeed, which is a conſiderable export from this country, yields an oil that is applied to various uſeful purpoſes: A large ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of coarſe and middling linen cloths may alſo be drawn from hemp and flax, ſuch as ſail-duck, ſacking, oznabrigs, ſheeting, and the like.—Virginia and North-Carolina grow cotton of a very good quality, which may be manufactured into various kinds of clothing, &amp;c. Thread and cotton ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, of an excellent fabric, have long been made àmong us. The ſine hats of this country are much ſuperior to any imported.—All manufactures of leather may be carried on to the greateſt advantage.—Iron (beſides excellent caſtings and the manufacture of ſteel) may likewiſe be wrought into all kinds of heavy work, and into nails and ſundry other arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, much to the benefit of the country.—Paper is already made here, of an excellent quality and in large quantities. Glaſs-houſes have heretofore been erected in divers parts of the continent, and good glaſs has been made at them. Gun-powder, a very important article, has been brought to great perfection here.—Pot-aſhes are likewiſe a very ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able manufacture for this country.—Beſides, ſeveral articles of manufacture are produced from wheat, barley, rye, hops, tobacco, &amp;c.—The culture of ſilk might alſo prove a mine of wealth to the middle and ſouthern States.—The cultiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vine, madder, rhubarb, and ſundry kinds of fruits, would likewiſe be productive of real emolument to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
                  <p>Theſe, and a multitude of other materials, that are and might be ſupplied by the United-States, would, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per encouragement, employ great numbers of our citizens in trades and manufactures, from which they would derive profit, and the public a national benefit.</p>
               </note> inland commerce and home-conſumption. The United-States occupy a vaſt extent of fertile coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, lying in various climates, yielding the neceſſaries of life in the utmoſt abundance, and furniſhing a great diverſity of commodities, and raw materials for manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facturing.</p>
            <p>THE commercial intercourſe carried on between the ſeveral States, by ſea, ſhould be reſtricted to American veſſels; and the communication from one part of the country to another, inland, ought to be rendered as eaſy and convenient as poſſible, by improving the roads, opening canals, and removing all obſtructions to the navigation of the rivers, where practicable,—in order to facilitate and promote the interior commerce of the United-States.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="unknown:019498_0033_0FABAE0C91F605C0"/>THE influence of example, manners and faſhion, may alſo greatly contribute to our ſucceſs, in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of theſe great objects of national proſperity. Here the real patriot is enabled to teſtify his love to his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and this he may evidence in a variety of ways,— according to his talents, his opportunity, or his ſtation.</p>
            <p>WE have endeavoured, in the courſe of theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, to fix the public attention on ſome of thoſe momentous concerns, on which the proſperity of this country ſo much depends. The circumſcribed limits of an Eſſay would not ſuffer us, even had other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances permitted, to enter into ſo full a diſcuſſion of the ſubject, as its importance merits. But the reaſoning, ſo far as it goes, will, we apprehend, be fully ſatisfactory to every diſintereſted and unprejudiced reader.—</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
