<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doctrine of "laying on of hands," examined and vindicated. By the Rev. David Jones, A.M. ; [Three lines from II Timothy]</title>
            <author>Jones, David, 1736-1820.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N15492</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N15492</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 19738</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW3382</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">19738</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99009299</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 19738.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N15492)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 19738)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 19738)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doctrine of "laying on of hands," examined and vindicated. By the Rev. David Jones, A.M. ; [Three lines from II Timothy]</title>
                  <author>Jones, David, 1736-1820.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Francis Bailey, at Yorick's-Head, in Market-Street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M,DCC,LXXXVI. [1786]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Philadelphia Baptist Association.</term>
               <term>Imposition of hands.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Doctrinal and controversial works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:019738_0000_0FACA6F225720388"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:019738_0001_0FACA6F2E37A1F70"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DOCTRINE OF <hi>"Laying on of Hands,"</hi> EXAMINED <hi>and</hi> VINDICATED.</p>
            <p>BY THE REV. DAVID JONES, <hi>A. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>In meekneſs inſtructing theſe that oppoſe themſelves; if God peradventure will give them repentance to the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of the truth,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim ii. 25.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>PHILADELPHIA:</hi> PRINTED by FRANCIS BAILEY, at YORICK'S-HEAD, in <hi>Market-Street.</hi> M.DCC.LXXXVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="unknown:019738_0002_0FACA6F3A29AD748"/>
            <head>THE DOCTRINE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE ſubject to be conſidered is the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Laying on of Hands, as exhi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bited in the xxxi chapter of our Confeſſion of Faith; part of which we will tranſcribe, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>We believe that Laying on of Hands, with prayer, upon baptized believers, as ſuch, is an ordinance of Chriſt, and ought to be ſubmitted unto by all ſuch perſons, that are admitted to partake of the Lord's Supper; and that the end of this ordinance is not for the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit, but for a farther reception of the Holy Spirit of promiſe; or for the addition of the graces of the Spirit and the influences thereof, to confirm, ſtrengthen, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them in Chriſt Jeſus; it being ratified and eſtabliſhed by the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit in the primitive times,</q> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is granted, that an article of faith em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced by a church doth not make it truth in itſelf; but we muſt conceive that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the meaning in which the church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Scripture on that ſubject. It muſt therefore argue a degree of precipitance in aſſociated members belonging to indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:019738_0003_0FACA6F463797390"/>churches, to reſolve that to be a matter of <hi>indifference,</hi> which, at the ſame time, ſtands exhibited to the world, as an anticle of their faith. By this example, a future aſſociation might reſolve another article away as no bar of communion, till, at laſt, it would be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to know what is the faith and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of a regular Baptiſt church.</p>
            <p>It is with great reluctance we appear in vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of one of our articles of faith; but the perſevering imprudence of ſome of our young miniſtring brethren, renders it neceſſary to inveſtigate the ſubject, and either explode it, or maintain it with that zeal which becomes the diſciples of Chriſt. If it cannot be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by ſcripture, let us drop it; if it can, let us unanimouſly practiſe it: for all other expedients will be only healing the hurt of the daughter of Zion ſlightly, crying <hi>Peace, peace, when there is</hi> none.</p>
            <p>The article under conſideration contains the following propoſitions, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. That the regular Baptiſt churches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Philadelphian Aſſociation believe that laying on of hands on bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized believers, as ſuch, is an ordinance inſtituted by Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
               <item>II. That none ought to be admitted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Lord's Supper, without ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the ſame.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="4" facs="unknown:019738_0004_0FACA6F5222C6DA8"/>
III. That it was not inſtituted, nor ever uſed to confer the extraordinary gifts of the Holy Spirit.</item>
               <item>IV. That the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit, which did ſometimes attend it, afford an argument to prove it an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
               <item>V. That one end of this holy inſtitution was to comfort, confirm, and ſtrengthen true believers, by additional meaſures and gifts of the Holy Spirit.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe five propoſitions contain the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal points to be inveſtigated on this ſubject, and if theſe appear, by fair ſcriptural argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, we hope to ſee once more unity of faith in our churches. It is wiſhed that the reader would endeavour to remove prejudices for or againſt the inſtitution, that the point may be examined impartially, comparing ſpiritual things with ſpiritual.</p>
            <p>After our bleſſed Lord roſe from the dead, he was ſeen by the apoſtles ſorty days, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with them, and inſtructing them in the <hi>things pertaining to the kingdom of God,</hi> Acts i. 3. What he taught them, we muſt learn from their doctrine and practice. We know it was his poſitive command, to <hi>teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever he had command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="unknown:019738_0005_0FACA6F5E1BBF4B0"/>
If we find the apoſtles, by their example, teaching the Laying on of Hands on bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized believers, as ſuch, then we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that our redeemer taught them ſo to do; conſequently, we need not be ſurpriſed to find the inſtitution called the Doctrine of Chriſt, becauſe he taught it to the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles himſelf.</p>
            <p>We are now naturally led to read the Acts of the Apoſtles, where we find exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to bear witneſs to the ordinance. The firſt is recorded in Acts viii. 14—17. As we ſhall have occaſion frequently to refer to this paſſage, we will now tranſcribe it, <hi>viz. Now when the apoſtles which were at Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, beard that Samaria bad received the word of God, they ſent unto them Peter and John. Who when they were come down, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them that they might receive the Holy Ghoſt. (For as yet he was fallen upon none of them: only they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jeſus.) Then laid they their bands on them, and they received the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reader will pleaſe to obſerve, who the perſons were, on whom the apoſtles laid their hands; and the plain reading will ſhew that they were the men and women, who believed and were baptized by Philip.</p>
            <p>A man muſt be ſtrangely infatuated with his own fancy, who would preſume to aſſert that the apoſtles laid hands only on ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:019738_0006_0FACA6F6A18106C0"/>at Samaria, who were thereby ordained as officers, when the word <hi>them</hi> plainly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to the men and women, who believed and were baptized.</p>
            <p>We proceed to conſider the example of the apoſtle Paul, Acts xix. 1,—6. To aſſiſt the reader's memory, we will tranſcribe the verſes, <hi>viz. Paul having paſſed through the upper coaſts, came to Epheſus: and finding certain diſciples, he ſaid unto them, have ye received the Holy Ghoſt ſince ye believed? And they ſaid unto him, we have not ſo much as heard whether there be any Holy Ghoſt. And he ſaid unto them, unto what then were ye baptized? and they ſaid, unto John's baptiſm. Then ſaid Paul, John verily baptized with the baptiſm of repentance, ſaying unto the people, that they ſhould believe on him, who ſhould come after him, that is, on Chriſt Jeſus. When they heard this, they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jeſus. And when Paul had laid his hands upon them, the Holy Ghoſt came on them; and they ſpake with tongues, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied, and all the men were about twelve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we have a plain hiſtory of facts, <hi>viz.</hi> Paul met ſome diſciples at Epheſus—he aſk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them whether they had received the Holy Spirit.—They appeared ſtrangers to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. —Paul knowing that the Holy Ghoſt, in the <hi>capacity of a comforter,</hi> was promiſed to all goſpel believers, and that they were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:019738_0007_0FACA6F772C7D508"/>in the name of the Holy Ghoſt, as well as in the name of the Father and Son; aſks them unto what were they baptized? they told him, unto John's baptiſm.—Paul ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains that, and points out what John taught reſpecting him, who was to come after him, that is, Chriſt.—When theſe diſciples heard the matter explained, they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jeſus. Then Paul proceeds, and Laid his Hands on them, as the next ordinance following baptiſm; and, no doubt, he then conſtituted them into a church.—Laſtly, the Holy Ghoſt came on them, not only in the gifts and graces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to goſpel believers; but alſo the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary gifts attended this holy inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at this time, tho' it was not the apoſtles deſign in Laying his Hands upon them, which we hope to prove, when we come to conſider that head. Neither can we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that he ordained them all officers, for their circumſtances could not require it.— We know what our opponents ſay on this paſſage, but we beg the reader to ſuſpend his judgment till he hears what may be ſaid.</p>
            <p>We will now follow the apoſtle to his Epiſtle to the Hebrews, chap. vi. 1, 2. <hi>Therefore leaving the principles of the doctrine of Chriſt, let us go on unto perfection; not laying again the foundation of repentance from dead works, and of faith towards God, of the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:019738_0008_0FACA6F837E5A1A0"/>of baptiſms, and of Laying on of Hands, and of reſurrection of the dead, and of eternal judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the old fathers and divines, which I have ſeen, agree that this text proves the Laying on of Hands on believers, as ſuch, to be inſtituted by Chriſt himſelf; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is mentioned with the important chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doctrines, or doctrine of Chriſt, who is the head of the church, and lawgiver of his people.</p>
            <p>Such evidence of this truth appeared at the reformation, that the church of England retained the ordinance, under the name of confirmation; but a very learned divine in England, would perſuade us that the paſſage refers to the old diſpenſation, and therefore the Laying on of Hands refers to the prieſts laying on their hands on the ſacrifices. As we are forbid to call any man father or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in religion, we muſt beg leave to ſee with our own eyes, and diſſent from him, and believe great and good men are but men, and what is hid ſometimes from the wiſe and prudent, is revealed to babes. Tho' we would pay the greateſt regard to the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor's judgment, yet it is ſo ordered that no one man ſhould excel in all things.</p>
            <p>Finding ſome of my brethren reaſoning on the ſubject agreeable to the doctor's expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; it induced me to read the Epiſtle
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:019738_0009_0FACA6F8E24E64F8"/>twice over; but inſtead of being convinced of my miſtake, it eſtabliſhed me in the firm belief that the ſentiment was a groundleſs fancy, probably generated by Rabinical no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of which he only too much abounds.</p>
            <p>We will give our reaſons why we believe the paſſage doth not refer to the Moſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal diſpenſation. (1.) There is no mention made in all the epiſtle, concerning the prieſts laying their hands on the ſacrifice; nor any thing plainly referring to that practice.— (2.) The Moſaical rites are in no part of ſcripture called the doctrines of Chriſt; but goſpel truths are called ſo; therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring ſpiritual things with ſpiritual, we muſt conclude the apoſtle means the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of the New-Teſtament, by the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of Chriſt. Let us attend to what the apoſtle John ſays, in his ſecond epiſtle and 9th verſe. <hi>Whoſoever tranſgreſſeth, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth not in the doctrines of Chriſt, hath not God: he that abideth in the</hi> doctrine <hi>of Chriſt, hath both the Father and the Son.</hi> Other texts might be quoted to the ſame purpoſe; but we diſmiſs the paſſage for the preſent, tho' we ſhall have occaſion to conſider it again. And we come to the Second pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Which was, That none ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to receive the Lord's Supper without ſubmiſſion to this ordinance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="unknown:019738_0010_0FACA6F9A1F45E18"/>
Before we inveſtigate the ſubject, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to premiſe a few particulars relative to the Lord's ſupper, and a goſpel church.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We conceive the Lord's ſupper to be a church ordinance. Preaching the goſpel and baptiſm cannot be properly called church or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, becauſe they neceſſarily precede the very exiſtence of a church. The Lord's ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per was firſt celebrated by our Redeemer among his apoſtles, and where no church ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts, it cannot be properly adminiſtered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there can be no diſcipline without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federation; it follows, therefore, if a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand believers met together, they could not orderly adminiſter the Lord's ſupper, before they entered into confederation, or a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary compact, by which they take on them the laws of Chriſt, and engage ſubmiſſion to his authority on earth. I am not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that they ſhould always meet in the ſame place; no, this is left to their diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they may break bread from houſe to houſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though we read not in what manner the apoſtles conſtituted a church of Chriſt, yet we read of many churches, and ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality or voluntary act, muſt have made them ſuch.</p>
            <p>We proceed now to inveſtigate the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; and from every circumſtance, it ſeems very probable, that Peter and John
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:019738_0011_0FACA6FA62D45DD8"/>were ſent to Samaria for the very purpoſe of conſtituting them into a goſpel church. We find Barnabas ſent to Antioch on a ſimilar oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and immediately we read of a church there, with whom he and Paul aſſembled.</p>
            <p>One end of Laying on of Hands might be to devote them to God as an houſe to dwell in, and as the Lord's building, they prayed for them that they might receive the Holy Ghoſt as a <hi>comforter,</hi> and be filled with his precious gifts and graces, to enable them to bear witneſs for Chriſt, to confirm and ſtrengthen them to grow up to the fulneſs of the ſtature of a man in Chriſt Jeſus. The ſame may be ſaid of the twelve men, whom Paul baptized at Epheſus, Acts xix. for we conclude the holy apoſtle taught them to obſerve all things commanded by Chriſt; he therefore devotes them to the Lord by Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Hands on them; but with no view, that they ſhould thereby receive the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, for this would be taking the office of the Spirit on himſelf, for it is the Spirit that diſtributes the gifts ſeverally as he will. We will illuſtrate this point, when we come to ſpeak on that head.</p>
            <p>If we grant there was a church conſtituted at Samaria, and another at Epheſus, in which the Lord's-ſupper was adminiſtered, then we muſt conclude, Laying on of Hands pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded the reception of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="unknown:019738_0012_0FACA6FB22D1ECD8"/>
Before we proceed further on the ſubject, we would give ſome reaſons, why we believe that Laying on of Hands was uſed, as an external act in devoting a perſon or perſons to God and his ſervice. The ſcriptures ſhew it was an antient cuſtom, under the legal diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation; and tho' now it is a goſpel ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, we may learn ſome things relative to it, by obſerving on what occaſions it was formerly uſed. It was the external act, by which the Levites were devoted to God and his ſervice. Numbers viii. 10. <hi>And thou ſhalt bring the Levites before the Lord, and the children of Iſrael ſhall put their hands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Levites.</hi> Verſe 14. <hi>Thus ſhalt thou ſeparate the Levites from among the children of Iſrael: and the Levites ſhall be mine.</hi> The third and fourth chap. of Leviticus prove that it was a fixed ſtatute in offering all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices for ſin: whoever brought an animal to a prieſt to be offered a ſacrifice, he laid his hands on it, thereby, not only transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his ſin figuratively, but alſo devoting it to God; and this ſetting of the creature apart for a holy uſe, is called ſanctifying it, as it was wholly given to God. It was uſed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly on ſome other occaſions, not neceſſary to mention at preſent. We are now conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering it as a New-Teſtament inſtitution, and ſee, by a parity of reaſoning, one thing taught by it is, when hands are laid on bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:019738_0013_0FACA6FBE219B898"/>believers, as ſuch, that the perſon, like the Levites, is devoted to God and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; he is a living ſacrifice, ſeparated from the ſervices of ſin, as the temple of the Holy Ghoſt to dwell in, to offer up ſpiritual ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, holy and acceptable to God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>Much has been ſaid about the ordination of officers in the church; but taking the Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of Hands in this point of view, we ſee it means no more than an external act, by which the perſon is publicly devoted to God in that office, and as this precedes his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to adminiſter other holy ordinances, ſo on baptized believers, as ſuch, it precedes their admittance to the Lord's ſupper. It would be as regular, to allow a perſon to baptize, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> before ordination, as to admit any to the Lord's ſupper before ſubmiſſion to Laying on of Hands.</p>
            <p>The objections, which ariſe againſt the one, will certainly militate againſt the other, equally ſtrong, if impartially examined. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we paſs from this propoſition, we will make ſome further remarks on Heb. vi. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>Here you ſee ſix articles mentioned of the chriſtian faith, and they are called the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the doctrine of Chriſt, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies they mean ſomething embraced, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and performed in the beginning of a chriſtian life. 2. They are called foundation
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:019738_0014_0FACA6FCA1B7B2D8"/>principles, "not laying again the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion." Some reaſons have been already aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, why we cannot believe this paſſage refers to the prieſts Laying their Hands on the ſacrifices; but the groundleſſneſs of the conjecture, will more fully appear, by mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome remarks on theſe principles. Let us conſider them as they ſtand—</p>
            <p>The words ſeem to be figurative, referring to a mechanic, who firſt lays a foundation, and proceeds to finiſh the building; or in other words, brings it to perfection, "Not laying again the foundation." Whatever may be the true meaning of theſe ſix princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, we ſee, they are called a foundation.</p>
            <p>We cannot ſuppoſe them to be the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our ſalvation, for Chriſt is that, and other foundation, in that point of view, can on man lay; we ſhall therefore conclude them to be the foundation or beginning of the chriſtian life. In this ſenſe, let us conſider them diſtinctly. 1. Repentance from dead works, is a phraſe agreeing to New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment language; here we are repreſented to be dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, and our works, in that ſtate, bring forth fruit unto death. No man truly ſets out in a new or chriſtian life, while he willingly retains one ſin. A right eye muſt be plucked out, for we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſerve God and mammon. The love of ſin in the heart, muſt be removed; and it is
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:019738_0015_0FACA6FD61FC1A90"/>truly ſo, when that precious word is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, <hi>viz. A new heart will I give you, and a new ſpirit will I put within you,</hi> Ezek. xxxvi. 26. Moreover, repentance from dead works is never repeated, becauſe the ſoul that is made alive in Chriſt, never falls into a ſtate of death. Repentance, as a backſlider or ſinful child, may be often repeated, but repentance from dead works remains as a foundation, or beginning to live in newneſs of life.</p>
            <p n="2">2. "Faith towards God," tho' on ſome accounts it might be applied to the legal diſpenſation, yet it is much plainer to the mind of God revealed in the goſpel, where we are ſo often called upon to believe the teſtimony or record given of his ſon. It is repreſented by our Lord as the principal work pleaſing to God. <hi>This is the work of God, that ye believe on him whom he hath ſent,</hi> John vi. 29. and the apoſtle John ſays, <hi>This is his commandment, that ye ſhould believe on the name of his ſon Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 John iii. 23. The ſame apoſtle repreſents all who have not this faith towards God, as practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally making him a liar, 1 John v. 10. Faith towards God includes in it, a firm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the whole revelation, which he hath made; and, in particular, credit of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord which he hath given of his Son. This faith is the beginning of a goſpel life, in
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:019738_0016_0FACA6FE216A7D38"/>which we live a life of faith on the Son of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The doctrine of baptiſms ſtands agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the goſpel order, in which repentance and faith precede it. Baptiſm is a beginning, foundation principle of newneſs of life, and therefore is never repeated, becauſe we are once dead with Chriſt—once buried with him in baptiſm—once raiſed up to walk in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life.</p>
            <p>Baptiſm is here in the plural number, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe more things than one is meant by it. Not only immerſion in water and the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary effuſions of the Spirit; but perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſufferings for Chriſt's ſake. Our bleſſed Lord taught us, that if any man would come after him, he muſt deny himſelf and take up his croſs and follow him. And in another place, he ſays, <hi>In the world, ye ſhall have tribulation.</hi> The apoſtle Paul taught the ſame doctrine, when he ſaid, <hi>That we muſt through much tribulation enter into the kingdom of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 4th principle is Laying on of Hands. This is performed at our firſt embracing chriſtianity, and, as it is never repeated, it is therefore a beginning of a new life. We are once made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt as a comforter, and once devoted to God as his temple to dwell in. If a perſon is ordained to an office in the church, it is repeated as
<pb n="17"
                   facs="unknown:019738_0017_0FACA6FEE56040A8"
                   rendition="simple:additions"/>an external act devoting the perſon to God in that office; hence we read of Timothy firſt having the hands of Paul laid on him, as a believer, and afterwards, the hands of the preſbytery were laid on him, when he was ordained an officer in the church.</p>
            <p>In reſpect to the two remaining principles, it is ſcarcely neceſſary to obſerve, that they ſtand in the very language of the New-Teſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament; and it requires a wiſdom, which is not from above, to apply the words to the Old Teſtament; tho' it is acknowledged the doctrine is contained therein, but the apoſtle in this epiſtle has not treated of ſuch paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in the Old Teſtament as refer to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Whoever reads the New-Teſtament, muſt be convinced, that the reſurrection of the dead, and eternal judgment, are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects frequently inſiſted on in a very peculiar manner. We ſhall juſt obſerve, that we are baptized in hopes of the reſurrection from the dead, and we wait for the coming of Chriſt to judge the world, when he will change our vile body, that it may be faſhioned like unto his glorious body.</p>
            <p>From what was been ſaid, we hope it doth appear, that this paſſage in the Hebrews re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to the New-Teſtament diſpenſation; and if ſo, it follows, that when the Hebrews were conſtituted into a church, they ſubmitted to this holy ordinance, as the external miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:019738_0018_0FACA6FFA39A5D58"/>of the Spirit; and by which, they were devoted as an habitation for God to dwell in. And if, at the firſt conſtitution of the church, it was uſed, it follows, that when any join the church, they ought to follow the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſet before them.</p>
            <p n="3">III. We come now to conſider the Third propoſition, which was, That Laying on of Hands was not inſtituted, nor ever uſed, to confer the extraordinary gifts of the holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>Why any perſon ſhould conclude that the extraodinary gifts of the Spirit, was the end of the inſtitution, we know not, except they argue that as theſe gifts attended the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, they were therefore the end. The abſurdity of this way of reaſoning will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, before we diſmiſs the ſubject. Had this been the end, we might reaſonably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, that the apoſtles would have given ſome intimation of the ſame; but as there is none on record, we infer, it was not the deſign.</p>
            <p>We will examine the paſſages, where it is ſuppoſed the apoſtles uſed it to confer the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit; and if it appears, that it was not their deſign in the adminiſtration of this ordinance, then we hope, the point will be given up, and we ſhall truly unite in the apoſtles practice.</p>
            <p>We will review the verſes already tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, <hi>viz.</hi> Acts viii. 14—17. and we find
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:019738_0019_0FACA70063662240"/>the matters of fact are the following, 1. Peter and John were ſent from Jeruſalem to Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria. 2. When they came, they prayed for them that they might receive the Holy Ghoſt. 3. They laid their hands on them, and they received the Holy Ghoſt. Not one word of the extraordinary gifts, <hi>"They received the Holy Ghoſt."</hi> The ſcripture doth not ſay, that the apoſtles even prayed for any particular gift, ordinary, or extraordinary; but that they might receive the Holy Ghoſt HIMSELF. Obſerve that, verſe 15. If it is thought, by receiving the Holy Ghoſt, the extraordinary gifts are meant, and none have them gifts now, it follows, that none have the Spirit now, which is poſitively contrary to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Chriſt, who ſays, the comforter ſhall abide with us ever, John xiv. 16. Now, if we are not obliged to believe that by receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Holy Ghoſt, the extraordinary gifts are meant, then nothing is proved againſt us from this paſſage.</p>
            <p>Not one word is ſaid about ſpeaking with tongues, or working miracles; and if theſe effects had followed, it would not prove it was the deſign of the act, but an attendant of it, for the ratification of the ſame, as will appear hereafter. We will not diſpute but the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit attended the adminiſtration of the ordinance; but theſe gifts were diſtributed, when, where, and in
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:019738_0020_0FACA70122560DE8"/>what manner, the Holy Ghoſt himſelf willed. Theſe gifts are in his hands, and not in the hands of man, or ſubject to his will. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, if hands were laid on perſons to confer the extraordinary gifts, then we would aſk, was this always the end? If it is anſwered in the affirmative, then it follows, that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance ſhould not be uſed now, at the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of miniſters, becauſe formerly a gift attended it, 1 Tim. iv. 14.</p>
            <p>We have no reaſon to believe that the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gifts always attended, this ordinance in the apoſtles days, becauſe, had this been the caſe, there could have been no room for this queſtion. <hi>Do all ſpeak with tongues?</hi> 1 Cor. xii. 30. We would recommend to our reader to open his Bible, and read to the 12th verſe of this chapter, and he will plainly ſee that all the gifts were in the hands of the Spirit, and diſtributed according to his own will.</p>
            <p>The proceedings of Peter and John at Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria agree to this doctrine, when they pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them that they might receive the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And here an important queſtion ariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether the apoſtles meant the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary gifts of the Holy Ghoſt? or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they meant the receiving the Holy Ghoſt, in his office <hi>as the comforter</hi> and ſpirit of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation? In the latter ſenſe, he is promiſed to dwell in his people, to the end of the
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:019738_0021_0FACA701E2783030"/>world, and this meaning we prefer; becauſe the extraordinary gifts are not promiſed to all true believers in Chriſt, conſequently, the the apoſtles could not pray for them in faith; but the Holy Spirit, as a <hi>comforter,</hi> is a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy promiſed to all that truly believe, to the end of the world; therefore in this capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city they prayed for him. <hi>And I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, that he may abide with you forever; even the Spirit of truth,</hi> John xiv. 16, 17. Moreover, the apoſtles were ſent to Samaria for the comfort of true believers, but the extraordinary gifts were for a ſign to them that believe not, conſequently not prayed for in this place. This way of reaſoning agrees with peter's conduct, when his hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers aſked what ſhall we do? His anſwer was, <hi>Repent, and be baptized every one of you, in the name of Jeſus Chriſt, for the remiſſion of ſins, and ye ſhall receive the gift of the Holy Ghoſt. For the promiſe is unto you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many as the Lord our God ſhall call,</hi> Acts ii. 37—39. This promiſe muſt be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled to all, whom the Lord our God ſhall call; but the extraordinary gifts are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on any, in our days, and never were conferred on all in the apoſtles days, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, the Holy Ghoſt in his office as a comforter, muſt be meant.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="unknown:019738_0022_0FACA702A352EC48"/>
It is granted that the extraordinary gifts did attend the adminiſtration of this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Acts xix. 6. But this doth not prove that Paul laid his hands on them for that end. And this will appear by making ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks on the paſſage. 1. Paul finds diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples at Epheſus, and aſks them, <hi>Have ye received the Holy Ghoſt, ſince ye believed?</hi> where note, the very queſtion implies that the Holy Ghoſt is the common privilege of all the children of God, and is enjoyed, in a greater or leſſer meaſure, by every true believer; but the extraordinary gifts were never either promiſed or enjoyed by every ſaint, therefore could not be meant by the apoſtle. 2. The queſtion ſhews, that agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the apoſtle's meaning, every believer receives the Spirit <hi>after believing,</hi> and not before, which muſt mean receiving him in his office as a comforter. Hence we read, <hi>After ye believed, ye were ſealed with that holy Spirit of promiſe.</hi> 3. If the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gifts had been meant, it would have been as natural for the apoſtle to have aſked, "Do ye ſpeak with tongues, or work mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles?" Nay, the extraordinary gifts were ſo viſible, that he might have ſeen them without aſking. 4. He ſpeaks of the Holy Ghoſt as that which all might expect, who truly believed and were baptized in the name of the trinity, <hi>Unto what then were ye bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized?</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="unknown:019738_0023_0FACA7036174E548"/>They told him, it was unto John's baptiſm. Paul explains the nature of that, and of baptiſm after Chriſt's aſcenſion, which would lead him to ſpeak of the Spirit as a promiſed comforter. When they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, he baptized them in the name of the Lord Jeſus; and then proceeds accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to goſpel order, and Lays his Hands on them, and the Holy Ghoſt came on them; and they ſpake with tongues and propheſied. From no circumſtance can we infer, that Paul laid his hands on them, to confer the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>It is true, that here the extraordinary gifts <hi>attended</hi> and followed the Laying on of Hands, and ſo did they attend and follow preaching, praying and meeting; will any one ſay, this was the end of theſe divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions? By no means, the gifts of God are beſtowed when and where he pleaſeth. We are in hopes, that we have proved to a demonſtration, and full ſatisfaction of all, who wiſh to know the mind of the Lord, that hands were laid on none with any view of conferring the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit; but, on the other hand, the apoſtles uſed this holy inſtitution as the external act, by which the Holy Ghoſt was given to true believers, in the character and capacity of a comforter, or a ſpirit of conſolation. And although God hath not confined himſelf to
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:019738_0024_0FACA70427BE58D0"/>any means, yet he hath confined us in our waiting on him; and this is called inſtituted worſhip. This point might be further illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, but we come to the Fourth propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That the extraordinary gifts of the Holy Spirit, which at firſt attended the Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of Hands, afford an argument to prove the continuance of the ordinance.</p>
            <p>The glorious goſpel contained myſteries ſo far tranſcending the human underſtanding, that God was graciouſly pleaſed to attend its firſt promulgation, with ſuch marks of his majeſty and power, that every objection might be ſilenced, and the opponents remain without excuſe. It could never be ſuppoſed, that the ſupreme would impoſe on his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, by ſuch exertions of his divinity as were diſplayed, by raiſing the dead, reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſight to the blind, caſting out devils, curing complaints of body without medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, ſpeaking with tougues never learned, foretelling exactly future events. When theſe things attended the goſpel, they were certain proofs that it was of God; hence the apoſtle tells us, that God confirmed the goſpel, <hi>with ſigns and wonders, and divers miracles, and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, according to his own will,</hi> Heb. ii. 4.</p>
            <p>By reading the ſcriptures, we ſee, in what manner God confirmed his own inſtitutions,
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:019738_0025_0FACA704E2739480"/>by the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit; yet this is never uſed as an argument againſt the continuance of other ordinances; and why it is advanced againſt the Laying on of Hands, we know not, excepting it is the caſe, that we are only too great ſtrangers to the Spirit, in the capacity of a comforter. To illuſtrate the propoſition a little more, we will conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a few paſſages of ſcripture; and the firſt we would preſent is Acts ii. 1—4.</p>
            <p>Here we read of no other duty performed only aſſembling together in one place, when the extraordinary gifts were diſtributed.— Shall we reaſon from hence, becauſe theſe gifts do not attend our aſſembling together now, therefore, it is no duty? or ſhall we not ſay, it was thereby confirmed as a duty? 2. When Peter and John prayed, the place where they were aſſembled was ſhaken; and they were all filled with the Holy Ghoſt, Acts iv. 31. But ſuch power and gifts of the Spirit do not now attend praying, ſhall we therefore pray no more? hath it ceaſed to be a duty? 3. When Peter preached at the houſe of Cornelius, the Holy Ghoſt fell on all his hearers, and they ſpake with tongues, Acts x. 44—46. But no ſuch gifts now at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend preaching, muſt it therefore ceaſe? If our brethren reaſon conſiſtently and are right, aſſembling, preaching, and praying are no longer to be performed, becauſe the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gifts do not attend them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="unknown:019738_0026_0FACA705A1C8C208"/>
Perhaps ſome will object, that this was not the end propoſed in the examples pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. We grant it is the truth; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly affirm, that the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit was not the end of Laying on of Hands in the inſtances produced; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the extraordinary gifts are an equally forcible argument for the continuance of it. Why do our brethren lay hands on mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters at their ordination? There was a gift attended Timothy's ordination, 1 Tim. iv. 14. but none attends it now, muſt it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be performed no more? By no means, becauſe, almoſt all the divine inſtitutions were at firſt confirmed by ſigns and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and divers gifts of the Holy Ghoſt. Therefore, while meeting, preaching, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ordination continue in the church, we muſt conclude, from ſimilar reaſoning, that Laying on of Hands ſhould likewiſe continue, being confirmed by the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gifts of the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="5">V. We come now to the laſt propoſition, which was, That one end of this holy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was to comfort, confirm and ſtrengthen true believers, by additional meaſures and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>From what has been already ſaid, the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er will ſee, that we conſider the Holy Spirit in different points of view, bearing different appellations according to his work and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:019738_0027_0FACA706626E4520"/>to us. The Spirit of God doth regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate us, and therefore we are ſaid to be born of the Spirit, John iii. 6. In this ſpiritual birth, he doth not act in the capacity of a comforter; but as a ſpirit of ſanctification and holineſs. This neceſſarily precedes his operations as a comforter. Perhaps, one reaſon of difficulties in the mind of ſome, may be for want of this diſtinction, reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spirit of God; yet it is neceſſary to be preſerved, or we cannot underſtand what is meant by the Spirit's coming after the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion of Chriſt, and not before.</p>
            <p>We are not to think, that God hath bound himſelf to any ordinance or duty, in ſuch a manner, that when one is performed by us, the other muſt be performed by him; he ſtill remains a ſovereign, and may work, when, where, and in what manner he pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, yet he hath ordained in what manner we are to wait on him. And we are encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, by his gracious promiſe, that they who wait on him, <hi>ſhall renew their ſtrength,</hi> Iſaiah xl. 31. Our attendance on all the divine inſtitutions, is waiting on the Lord, and tho' we do not feel our ſtrength renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet it is our duty to wait on him in his own appointments.</p>
            <p>The Holy Ghoſt, as a teacher and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, is promiſed by Chriſt, to all true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers under the goſpel diſpenſation, John
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:019738_0028_0FACA707221C3168"/>xiv. 15, 16, 26. In this capacity, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him. In this capacity, we may expect him in Laying on of Hands. In this capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, we believe, he ſhall remain with his people to the end of the world; for in this capacity they need him, ſeeing that no man can call Jeſus Lord, but by the Holy Ghoſt. The apoſtles were born of God long before Chriſt's aſcenſion, yet they received not the Spirit, in his work and office as a comforter, till the day of Pentecoſt.</p>
            <p>We preſume no conſiderate chriſtian will ſay, that they received <hi>only</hi> the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit, when the promiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained what is incomparably more excellent, even the Spirit of God himſelf in his office as a comforter. In this capacity, he increaſes every grace implanted in us as a Spirit of holineſs, till we grow up to the fulneſs of the ſtature of a man in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid of the Epheſians, after that they believed, they were <hi>ſealed with that holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of promiſe,</hi> Eph. i. 13. mark the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, "after you believed," <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not before. The Holy Ghoſt as a Spirit of ſanctification works faith in us, and implants every grace in our hearts: theſe graces are increaſed in us afterwards, by the power of the Holy Ghoſt, hence we are ſaid to grow in grace. Where he begins a good work, he carries it on to perfection, in the uſe of all the means ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:019738_0029_0FACA707E263AE30"/>by the head of the church; hence it is, that we wait on the Lord in the ordinance of Laying on of Hands, as well as others, for our growth of grace and joy in the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Perhaps ſome may think, they have as much of the Spirit as thoſe, who ſubmit to the Laying on of Hands, and therefore it is not neceſſary. Whoever reaſons after this manner, ſpeaks not like a ſervant of the Lord, but rather aſſumes to be his maſter, who would dictate unto him. If any would chooſe to ſhew their faith by diſobedience, we think it beſt to ſhew our faith by obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Peter's hearers received the baptiſm of the Holy Ghoſt, nevertheleſs they were baptized in the name of the Lord, and by the expreſs command of Peter.</p>
            <p>Some people deſpiſe baptiſm and the Lord's ſupper, under pretence that they have all that is meant by thoſe outward things; ſhall we conclude, that they ſpeak as chriſtians? or muſt we not conclude that their language and conduct is unbecoming the goſpel of Chriſt? becauſe he hath appointed all his ordinances for our growth in grace. The apoſtle enumerates the graces implanted in the ſoul, when it is born of God, which are theſe, <hi>viz. Love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſs, goodneſs, faith, meekneſs, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance,</hi> Gal. v. 22, 23. Now the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:019738_0030_0FACA708A28ADD70"/>as our comforter increaſes theſe graces, till we come to the fulneſs of the ſtature of a man in Chriſt Jeſus. Verily, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more wanted in all our churches, than greater meaſures of the holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>Here is cauſe of lamentation, that any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbance hath been made, by the imprudent conduct of ſome of our brethren in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. We are afraid they have not conſidered the conſequences of their conduct, for we are thereby in great danger of confuſion in our churches, which will ſoon end in a ſeparation. The blame muſt lie at their door, who admit members into the church without Laying on of Hands, for we are bound in conſcence to keep the ordinances as we received them; and are obliged to withdraw from every brother, who walketh diſorderly. I ſhall conclude with a ſhort addreſs to the churches.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dearly beloved in the Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>"YE have now conſidered the arguments for the continuance of this holy ordinance. Whether they appear of force to you or not, they have confirmed me abundantly. By in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtigating the ſubject, the objections againſt the inſtitution appear groundleſs, and have had their riſe chiefly from not conſidering the holy Spirit in his office as a comforter. The apoſtle exhorts us to content earneſtly for the faith once delivered to the ſaints, and to be
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:019738_0031_0FACA70962DD00C8"/>perfectly joined together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment, keeping the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. Beware of innovations.—Mark them who cauſe divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned. Study diſcipline. No article of faith ſhould be left to vote either in a church, or an aſſociation, for by following this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample every truth may be voted away. Some diſpute the doctrine of predeſtination and election; was it left to vote, it would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from our Confeſſion of Faith, <hi>provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> the majority were <hi>Arminians.</hi> Let the word of Chriſt dwell richly in you, and pray for greater meaſures of the holy Spirit; for it is the Spirit that can lead you into all truth, and ſeal you to the day of redemption.</p>
                  <p>"We hope the ſubject has been ſo explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that ye ſee plainly the apoſtles uſed the Laying on of Hands, on believers, as ſuch, and that it never was performed with any view of conferring the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit; theſe were diſtributed, when and where it pleaſed the holy Spirit, but no ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was inſtituted for that purpoſe. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, they attended meeting, preaching, and praying, and ſometimes, they did not, even in the apoſtles days. No argument, worthy of notice, can be advanced from ſuch diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions of the Spirit. One thing is certain, which is this, that once it was in practice,
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:019738_0032_0FACA70A229B3120"/>and none can be ſure, it ſhould ceaſe. Why ſhould the peace of Zion be diſturbed for an uncertainty? If it ceaſes to be adminiftered on believers, as ſuch, you ſee, by ſimilar rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, it ſhould not be uſed in the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of miniſters; therefore if any practiſe the one, and refuſe the other, we muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them of inconſiſtency and partiality. Finally, beloved brethren, ye ſee your ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, ye are the temple of the Holy Ghoſt. Grieve not the holy Spirit, whereby ye are ſealed to the day of redemption. Defile not the temple of the holy Spirit. Pray that your miniſters may be filled with the Spirit, to ſpeak the word with clearneſs and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that ye yourſelves may hear in the Spirit. The grace of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the love of God, and the communion of the Holy Ghoſt, be with you all. <hi>Amen.</hi>"</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
