<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon, delivered in presence of His Excellency Samuel Huntington, Esq. L.L.D. governor, and the Honorable the General Assembly of the state of Connecticut, convened at Hartford, on the day of the anniversary election. May 13th, 1790. By Nathan Strong, A.M. Pastor of the First Church in Hartford.</title>
            <author>Strong, Nathan, 1748-1816.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N17691</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N17691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 22913</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APV7550</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">22913</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99003079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 22913.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N17691)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 22913)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 22913)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon, delivered in presence of His Excellency Samuel Huntington, Esq. L.L.D. governor, and the Honorable the General Assembly of the state of Connecticut, convened at Hartford, on the day of the anniversary election. May 13th, 1790. By Nathan Strong, A.M. Pastor of the First Church in Hartford.</title>
                  <author>Strong, Nathan, 1748-1816.</author>
                  <author>Connecticut. General Assembly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p. ;  21 cm. (4to) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Hudson and Goodwin.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Hartford: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DCC.XC. [1790]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Mr. Strong's election sermon.</note>
                  <note>Printers' monogram device on title page.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Election sermons --  Connecticut --  1790.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:022913_0001_0FBAB81080F116C0"/>
            <p>Mr. Strong's Election Sermon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:022913_0002_0FBAB8140C0C59C0"/>
            <p>A SERMON, DELIVERED IN PRESENCE OF HIS EXCELLENCY SAMUEL HUNTINGTON, ESQ. L.L.D. GOVERNOR, And the Honorable the GENERAL ASSEMBLY of the STATE of CONNECTICUT, Convened at HARTFORD, on the Day of the ANNIVERSARY ELECTION. MAY 13th, 1790.</p>
            <p>BY NATHAN STRONG, A. M. PASTOR OF THE FIRST CHURCH IN HARTFORD.</p>
            <p>HARTFORD: PRINTED BY HUDSON AND GOODWIN. M.DCC.XC.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="unknown:022913_0003_0FBAB81692CAD638"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>At a General Aſsembly of the State of Connecticut, in America, holden at Hartford, <date>on the ſecond Thurs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day of May, A.D. 1790.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ORDERED, That Colonel Thomas Seymour and Captain Jonathan Buli, return the Thanks of this Aſsembly to the Reverend Nathan Strong, of Hartford, for his Sermon delivered at the General Election, on the 13th Day of May 1790, and requeſt a Copy thereof that it may be printed.</p>
            <closer>A true Copy of Record, Examined, by <signed>George Wyllys, Sec.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="unknown:022913_0004_0FBAB817FAE09220"/>
            <head>ELECTION SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ROMANS, xiii. 7, 8, 9.</bibl>
               <q>Render therefore to all their dues: tribute, to whom tribute is due; cuſtom, to whom cuſtom; fear, to whom fear; honor to whom honor. Owe no man any thing, but to love one another: for he that loveth another hath fulfilled the law. For this, Thou ſhalt not commit adultery, Thou ſhalt not kill, Thou ſhalt not ſteal, Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs, Thou ſhalt not covet; and if there be any other commandment, it is briefly comprehended in this ſaying, namely, Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thyſelf.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS paſſage, which is a ſummary of the laws of Religion, may alſo be conſidered as a ſummary of thoſe political and ſocial du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by which a nation is made happy. The chapter in connection is the beſt political diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertation that was ever penned. Without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering into a compariſon of the ſeveral kinds
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:022913_0005_0FBAB81B16554130"/>
of government, which men have erected, the writer confines himſelf to general truths and duties, which are neceſſary in all of them, are founded in the nature of ſociety, and approved by reaſon and experience.</p>
            <p>HE begins the chapter with aſſerting the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine origin of civil government. <hi>The powers that be are ordained of God, whoever reſiſteth the power reſiſteth the ordinance of God.</hi> Infinite wiſdom ſuffers us to chuſe our own form of government, and deſignate the inſtruments by whom it ſhall be executed; but the ordinance is ſtill the LORD'S, and to refuſe obedience is ſinning againſt heaven.—Nor hath any man a right to complain, as the inſtitution was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for human good, and there is an eaſy way of reconciling our own intereſt with all the powers of a well regulated government. <hi>For rulers are not a terror to good works but to the evil. Wilt thou then not be afraid of the power?</hi> doſt thou deſire it to be a bleſſing and not an evil to thee? <hi>do that which is good and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame. For he is the miniſter of God to thee for good. Wherefore ye muſt needs be ſubject, not only for wrath but conſcience ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AFTER aſſerting the divine origin and the neceſſity of civil government, in ſome of the kinds practiſed by men; the Apoſtle recapitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, in our text, the principal duties by which ſociety is united, protected and made happy, and ſums up his deſcription in theſe words, <hi>And if there be any other commandment, it is briefly comprehended in this ſaying thou ſhalt love thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:022913_0006_0FBAB81D62A8B9F8"/>
as thyſelf.</hi>—If there be any political duty, not otherwiſe expreſsly commanded, we may find it in the great law of chriſtian love; this law directs rulers and ſubjects in every poſſible connection, and will make them faithful in their reſpective places. On reviewing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nection of the chapter, it appears that the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle deſigned our text, as a collection of political maxims, by which ſociety may be preſerved, and the great end of government be promoted under whatever form or conſtitution it ſubſiſts: and on further attending to the ſame maxims, we find they are the eſſential laws of religion, which were early given to men as a rule of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and their preſent and future well being. I think this is a clear proof, that religion and a well regulated civil government are ſubjects which cannot be ſeperated. A good ruler or a good ſubject will not ſuffer theſe laws to go out of his view. Happineſs is the great end deſigned by all ſocial inſtitutions; for this, the laws and duties of religion are enjoined on crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures by the wiſdom of their maker; for the ſame end men have organized government, and defined its powers and duties; both have rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ſocial capacities and enjoyments of connected minds, and aiming at the ſame end, muſt in a conſiderable degree procure it by the ſame means. So far as religion and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deviate from each other, one or the other of them deviates from the nature of men, and the effects of their ſocial relation.</p>
            <p>HAPPINESS cannot ſubſiſt without love and juſtice, between thoſe who are brought into
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:022913_0007_0FBAB820AD327328"/>
connection by the ſupreme providence. The bleſſedneſs of a perfect world, and the perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of divine government, are repreſented to us by the abundance of theſe virtues. We have no reaſon to ſuppoſe that ſyſtems of virtue or law, eſſentially different, are neceſſary for the good government of the heavenly and earthly ſocieties; as they both aim at the ſame thing, the happineſs of rational minds in union with each other. There is not an idea, in the world, more dangerous to ſociety, or more debaſing to civil government, than this, that it ſtands on a baſis of human wiſdom and will, apart from thoſe great religious obligations, which direct the manner and duties of intercourſe in all worlds.</p>
            <p>RELIGION, or love, holineſs and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the names by which it is commonly called in the ſacred oracles, is the conſtitution and law of the ſupreme government, by which the Almighty is glorified, and his creatures connec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in bleſſedneſs; and the nature of intelligent beings admits not a ſafe introduction of other principles; depart from theſe and we act no longer like reaſonable men or like chriſtians.</p>
            <p>OUR apprehenſions of a perfect and glorious ſociety muſt be defective, as we have not the aid of experience; but in accounting to our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the bleſſedneſs and ſtability of its or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, we always conceive the perfect exerciſe of religion, as a cauſe ſufficient for the effect. If the laws of religion are ſufficient to render the divine government moſt glorious and happy;
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:022913_0008_0FBAB821B8432AF0"/>
and if the practice of religion will give a future perfection to the heavenly life, why are not the ſame principles and practice, the ſtrength and ſafety of men's government in this world. The LORD our GOD governs according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things, and his adminiſtration always ends well; and are not men, when they act for him in the temporary authorities of the world, moſt like to ſucceed, to ſupport their own dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and be a bleſſing to others, when they adopt in their adminiſtration and act from the ſame principle.</p>
            <p>A RULER needs religion much more than his unofficered brethren, to ſupport his mind under trials, and to guard him againſt temptations. When the reſpectable citizen riſes from private into public life, he muſt expect to exchange quietneſs for trouble; honor, though alluring, has its bitterneſs and its dangers; enemies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unknown, will riſe up; the jealous will ſift all his actions, and what man can be ſo guarded as to have all his behaviour eſcape cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? The ambitious, thinking him in the way of their own progreſs, will be his enemies. To ſupport the mind under theſe evils, and lead it into the exerciſe of prudence and patience, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is neceſſary.</p>
            <p>To hold great power and places of confiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial truſt is a ſtate of temptation, which every man cannot reſiſt, and thoſe who are wiſe will not accept a call to public ſervice, until by examination, they find in their hearts fixed principles of fidelity. A bad man may ſeek elevation, but it is only a good man who can
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:022913_0009_0FBAB823C7A1CBE0"/>
bear it; many ſhine in adverſity, which cools the appetites and unſocial paſſions; but to ſhine in proſperity; to be humane and juſt in the circle of a court; to be true and honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the treatment of all mankind; to be righteous and honeſt when power gives oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for oppreſſing, the aſſiſtance of fixed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious principles are certainly neceſſary. If religion be neceſſary to aſſiſt us in the common duties of life, it is more neceſſary where duties are multiplied and enlarge.</p>
            <p>POLITICAL elevation is generally eſteemed honorable, but it is not always attended with honor, for this depends not on the elevation itſelf, but on the principles and conduct of the perſon who is raiſed. What is true honor but the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teem and love of mankind on virtuous reaſons? He who renders to all their dues—who preſerves himſelf from a tranſgreſſion of GOD' laws, by injuring the purity, intereſt or reputation of others, and performs the political and brotherly duties enjoined in the command—thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thyſelf; he hath an hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or which enemies cannot long ſtain, nor time wipe away. But a profuſion of knowledge, and the glare of great abilities, without fixed princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of love to GOD and men, are like a ſong, the ſounds die away and the pleaſing ſurprize of the mind departs.</p>
            <p>HAVING made theſe general remarks on the uſefulneſs of religion in civil ſociety, and in the character of one who rules men; that we may ſee its efficacy in the cleareſt manner, let us more accurately trace its nature and effects in the mind.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="unknown:022913_0010_0FBAB824EED77480"/>WE are now to conſider the formation of a character, which will be uniformly ſupported thro life, and where a ſteady practice evidences ſome habitual diſpoſitions, that cannot be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by every ſlight temptation.</p>
            <p>THE great end of political aſſociations is beſt anſwered where there is the moſt perfect union, and thoſe principles are moſt eſſential to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which have the greateſt tendency to produce union. The intereſts of individuals, are by the emergencies of time thrown into many ſituations. We live with many others whoſe paſſions are complicated, various and pointed to their own perſonal ends. Every leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer diſtrict, every family, and individual in the family, hath intereſts of its own. If theſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſts have a ſupreme influence the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt evils will enſue. It is the buſineſs of government to hold the balance between them, to check the overbearing and point them to a common good, and for this it needs the aſſiſtance of ſome pervading ſocial bond, and this bond can be no other than religion.</p>
            <p>BUT few minds are ſo enlightened in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of nature and the ſupreme wiſdom which formed it, as to ſee that a purſuit of the general good will be an eventual advancement of each man's private good; and where there is this enlarged underſtanding if the heart be corrupt, the paſſions will rebel.</p>
            <p>IN all rational ſociety there needs ſome cementing principle of the heart, by which
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:022913_0011_0FBAB8263832F680"/>
the minds who compoſe it may be united, have one intereſt, one common good, and one happineſs.</p>
            <p>MANY philoſophers, and politicians of renown in their times, have enquired for this bond of union without ſucceſs, and ſeduced by their own reaſoning, have ſubſtituted art, corruption or power.</p>
            <p>CHRISTIAN love in its comprehenſion of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, is the ſupreme tie of ſocial connexion. This is the ſame as the Apoſtle means, when he ſays—<hi>owe no man any thing, but to love one another—and if there be any other command, it is briefly comprehended in this ſaying, thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thyſelf.</hi>—He that loveth his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour hath fulfilled the law; he will exerciſe all the varieties of love as they are modified in the actions of juſtice, truth, integrity and benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; he will render to all their dues, tribute to whom tribute is due, cuſtom to whom cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, fear to whom fear, and honor to whom honor; he will reverence the property, peace and reputation of all mankind; and by his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine love he will be made happy in doing good to others.—Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy ſtrength and with all thy mind, and thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thyſelf, are the two greateſt laws of an enlightened policy, in every community of reaſonable creatures; this is religion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> heart, and the viſible practice of it is that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in life, by which a man becomes a good ruler, or a good ſubject, according as GOD is pleaſed to place him. Theſe firſt laws of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:022913_0012_0FBAB82935F35B08"/>
are as excellent for earth as for Heaven; and as good a directory in civil adminiſtration, as in chriſtian living.</p>
            <p>I WOULD not be underſtood that the holy ſcriptures are a code of civil law, nor that they ſuperceed its neceſſity, nor that the religion of CHRIST determines the moſt proper conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of nations. The divine law and goſpel have in view a more comprehenſive object, the gov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ernment, the glory and happineſs of the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſtill they embrace thoſe moral and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous principles, in all their varieties, on which the happineſs and ſtability of leſſer ſocieties muſt depend.—Public peace is the fruit of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on—union is the reſult of chriſtian love and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. When every man regards the welfare of his brother and of the whole, the political bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is ſtrong, full of energy and happineſs.</p>
            <p>THESE are the moſt permanent and ſafe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples on which ſociety can be organized, and all others are liable to an eaſy diſſolution. Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conſtrain a kind of order in the ſtate, but its very appearance is gloomy, and it is deſtitute of happineſs. Fear which awes cannot ſweeten the heart and feelings of mankind; the ſubject compelled to quietneſs by a dread of ſeverity, at the ſame moment wiſhes revolt, and the pleaſant amities of living are all denied.—The ſelfiſh paſſions may be variouſly addreſſed, and a ſyſtem of human art conſtructed; But to how many caſualties it is ſubject and how often annihilated in a moment, the hiſtory of empires is full of witneſs. Juſtice, truth, righteouſneſs and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy are the ſolid baſis of empire, and theſe are
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:022913_0013_0FBAB82B15BF6DB8"/>
but branches of religion or chriſtian love. To theſe permanent principles of ſociety nothing may be oppoſed, and the neceſſity which men ſometimes urge is but a deluſion. All the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of a pious and good life, ought to be the object of national encouragement. Theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile the heart of the ſubject to the welfare of the whole and of his brethren. They make a ruler the friend and father of his country; and might the heart of every citizen be inſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with theſe principles, the art and exerciſe of government would become extremely ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and each one would be influenced by his feelings, to act in the ſphere of his duty. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercion or an artful addreſs to the paſſions of different orders of men would fall into diſuſe, for it is only thro human degeneracy, that theſe ſubſidiary aids can produce any benefit.</p>
            <p>I AM ſenſible that human nature muſt be taken by the civil governor as he finds it, and that there is not in the world a ſufficiency of true religion to effect ſo happy a ſtate as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed; but ſtill he ought not to let theſe great principles of ſociety go out of view, and if he doth, will certainly injure the public.</p>
            <p>IT is not uncommon for ſome, on obſerving men's corruption, to embrace dangerous opin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions on this ſubject. Aiming at a wiſe and deep policy, they ſubſtitute colluſion, intrigue, and an artful addreſs to the paſſions and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſts of parties, in the place of love, juſtice and truth. They inſinuate that religion and its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions have nothing to do with government and civil policy, and that the moral obligations
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:022913_0014_0FBAB82E40DA8950"/>
which may be a fit ſubject for the exhortation of a clergyman, cannot be very ſtricly conſulted by thoſe who manage the civil intereſts of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. When any collection of people are ſo corrupt, that they will not bear reproof and the corrective reſtraint of government, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ought, to be diſbanded and feel the correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their own vices; and that which ought to be done the natural operation of things will ſpeedily effect. Such repreſentations as I juſt mentioned, may ſometimes proceed wholly from corruption of heart; an ambitious man, who knows himſelf deſtitute of religious prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, muſt be unwilling to have their uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in ſociety generally acknowledged; but very often I believe they proceed from an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of human nature, and the nature of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety. Tho the arts of corruption may ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed with a man for a few times, a loſs of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic confidence will put it out of his power to repeat them often. Let him that ruleth over men be juſt; ruling in the fear of the LORD, is a law of perpetual uſefulneſs, and derives its fitneſs from the nature of ſociety indeed reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is the beſt bond of ſociety, and being ſuch is the beſt ſupport of government.</p>
            <p>THO a diſtinction is made in the ſtate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the civil and Eccleſiaſtical departments, neither of them is independent of the other. Civility and the good order of political regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations are a great advantage to religion; reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and its inſtitutions are the beſt aid of government, by ſtrengthening the ruler's hand, and making the ſubject faithful in his place, and obedient to the general laws.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="unknown:022913_0015_0FBAB82F38C4F968"/>THO the author of our holy religion aſſumed no temporal authority, and gave no opinion on the ſeveral kinds of government, or the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral juriſdictions of men; yet he eſtabliſhed as firſt principles in his church, thoſe laws which are eſſential to the peace of every ſtate; on which every kind of authority muſt ſtand, which can be a bleſſing to the people; or which nerve the hand of government and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the liberties of mankind. Hence we find that wherever a juſt underſtanding of chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity hath obtained, and its duties been prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, they have had a benign influence on the liberty of nations: And where a contrary ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect hath been aided by what men called reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as was the caſe in the Papal Hierarchy, it was owing to a ſubverſion of the true prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of chriſtianity. A ſpurious ſuperſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was raiſed by the corruption of men, falſely called by the name of religion, and not calculated to refine either the affections or prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the people, but to aid a ſecular power by terrifying men, while thoſe who were firſt in church and ſtate ſhared their ſpoils.</p>
            <p>THE religion of JESUS, with no weapons in its hand but thoſe of truth and love, ſilently ſubverts oppreſſion; makes the people regular in diſcharging their duties, and rulers upright and humane in their adminiſtration; and there needs no other means to ſubvert the tyrannies of the world, than the univerſal ſpread and practice of this religion.</p>
            <p>WHEN as ſubjects, we find that religion aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, us in doing all enjoined duties, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciles
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:022913_0016_0FBAB830CC07C5E0"/>
us to the intereſt of the public and our neighbours, we muſt ſuppoſe, that it will give equal aſſiſtance to thoſe whom GOD appointeth to be in authority over us; and that their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ought to be adorned by obedience to the divine law. We feel ſure that religion will guard them againſt temptations—lead them to a ſound policy—to liberal feelings—to a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal regard of the people, and an unduanted ſupport of juſtice.</p>
            <p>IF there be not a miſtake in theſe leading propoſitions, the following important conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion muſt be received; that without religion no ſociety whatever can long ſubſiſt in peace, or thoſe who are members of it have reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in the connexion.</p>
            <p>THE ſupreme will commands religion, for its uſefulneſs to his connected creatures. He ſaw that by this, the minds he created would become happy, and be joined in a communion, that makes the advantage of each one, matter of joy to the whole, and the dignity and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the whole, an object of delight to each individual. He ſaw that thus the intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent kingdom would have one ſpirit, one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and one happineſs. On what other foundation can rational and uſeful union ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in this world? In both caſes the ſubjects are the ſame and have the ſame powers, faculties and capacities. Do not thoſe perſons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore act unnaturally, and againſt the laws of exiſtence, who attempt the eſtabliſhment of any ſociety on other principles beſide thoſe of religion? are not their expectations of its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manency
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:022913_0017_0FBAB832B84DE508"/>
without reaſon? Have we not always found the ſpirit of religion our beſt aſſiſtance in the duties and connexions of life? Have we not found our families happy, in the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, as its ſpirit and orders reigned in them? Or looking back on the civil ſtate, can we recollect a ſingle inſtance of public injuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, or the ſemblance of it, or the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary prevalence of any immorality, which was not followed with great evils? The law of GOD and nature can never be repealed.</p>
            <p>THE concluſion extends itſelf ſtill further; Firſt, that it is the right; and Secondly, that it is the duty of civil rulers to protect religion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is their right. It is a plain maxim of reaſon, that the civil ſtate is veſted with all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary powers of ſelf-preſervation. If it be lawful for mankind to combine in a political union, they have right to perpetuate the eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhment; and as the paſſions of men are, there can be no comfortable living without ſuch eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabliſhments. To deny civil government the right of protecting religion, and ſuppreſſing ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religion, is denying it the moſt eſſential means of ſelf-preſervation. All kinds of vice militate againſt the ſtate, and religion in the modifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of its virtues are its ſafe-guard. To or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganize the civil ſtate, and appoint a number of the people to be rulers; to commit the public to their charge and make them reſponſible for its well-being; and then to deny them the means and power of protecting and encouraging reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is a ſevere requirement. If any man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts the charge, under this reſtriction he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes beyond human performance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="unknown:022913_0018_0FBAB835EC280808"/>Secondly, IT is the duty of rulers to protect and encourage religion, and of the people to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them in doing it. The public weal is the moſt ſacred of all earthly betruſtments. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man when called to office, hath an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to refuſe this care, if he thinks himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable, or finds that his heart is not honeſt enough to do it with fidelity; but when the truſt is accepted, the obligations to a faithful performance are moſt ſacred. No light cauſes will execuſe either the civil, or religious miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the public, for unfaithfulneſs in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his office. The happineſs of an indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual is dear, and the forfeit of it more bitter than can be deſcribed; how much more dear the aggregate happineſs of the public body? Entering into ſociety, we depoſit our property lives, friends and happineſs, in the hand of the public; the public recommit this truſt to the care of rulers, and give them a right and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſee it inviolably preſerved. If religion and its inſtitutions be the moſt certain means to preſerve, is it not their duty to protect and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage virtue and piety? Or can any man be called faithful in his appointment, who hath neglected to give this encouragement, both offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially and in the private example of his life? He hath had the viſible dignity, but with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciouſneſs of unfaithfulneſs, can he feel honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to himſelf, or be ſo vain as to ſuppoſe that he is reſpected in the hearts of the people? Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a conviction of the truth I have urged, can he look back upon himſelf with a peaceful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? The parent who hath been a fearer of the Lord, and a faithful ſubject and citizen, when he ſees his family corrupted by ſuch irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:022913_0019_0FBAB836ED0859D0"/>
as the ſtate ought to ſuppreſs, hath reaſon to complain, that his expence and allegiance have not been repayed by that guardian care, which he had a right to expect from the civil power, which alone can ſtop the ſources and puniſh the inſtruments of corruption.</p>
            <p>MAY I be ſuffered to ſuggeſt another ſerious truth. The government is the LORDS; men are the inſtruments of providence in arranging its powers and duties, and appointing proper per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to execute them; the government is ſtill the LORD'S. He commits his creatures to ſuch of their brethren, as are ſuppoſed to have moſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and diſcreetneſs. The whole earthly ſtate, is deſigned as a ſchool of inſtruction, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to mature ſuch virtues, as will make men perfectly happy in another life. This is one end of government, for we cannot diſconnect time and eternity. This great people are placed in the hands of their rulers, by Almighty GOD their tender Father and Saviour. He ſits ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme King and expects fidelity from all; every care and exertion that ſuch religion be encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as will ſecure preſent and eternal happineſs. Could we keep alive a ſenſe of divine things, and the connexion between this and another world, theſe truths would make a deep impreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion on all our hearts.</p>
            <p>By commending religion to the protection of the ſtate, and the practice of its leading charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I do not mean to urge an intolerant and perſecuting ſpirit, which is very different from a tender care of piety. Many differences of opinion in a land of Chriſtian light, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:022913_0020_0FBAB8388F78E060"/>
the non-eſſentials and the ritual of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Several of theſe matters, the great head of the Church when he was on earth, did not think proper to determine. Their propriety often depends on local or temporary circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, or on the particular conſtruction and feelings of different minds. Such differences when conſcientiouſly maintained, have not a dangerous effect either on the eſſentials of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or good order of the ſtate; and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may tolerate them with ſafety. If we look thro the chriſtian ſectaries, who differ in ceremonies and words, candor will perceive, that the greateſt number of them unite, in the weighty matters of faith, piety, religion and juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, towards GOD and towards men. A diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of knowledge is now advancing a liberal ſpirit. May the Great Head of the Church haſten the period, when thoſe who think alike, concerning a divine love, juſtice, faith and truth, may join their hands and hail a future meeting in Heaven, where ceremonies and modes of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion will not ſeparate, brethren. Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath taught, that tolerancy in theſe things is the moſt powerful means of union; and a conſcientious government will find little diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in determining when to encourage and coerce.</p>
            <p>BUT while we ſpeak of a liberal ſpirit, let not immorality and irreligion think they have a right to our tenderneſs. Liberality is a divine affection of the heart, a love of the truth and of men, and cannot be pleaſed with vice. True liberality is chriſtian love, and delights in GOD and in all the virtues he commandeth, and is
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:022913_0021_0FBAB83C23D92B78"/>
moſt miſtaken by ſuch perſons, as triumph in vice over the ſocial obligations: If there be who ſpeak with lightneſs of a moſt perfect and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious providence; if there be, who think they may treat the religion of their brethren with lightneſs; if there be a few, either ſo odd or weak in their way of thinking, as not to ſee in our ſacred books, truths moſt favorable to ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and a moſt glorious deſcription of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, his juſtice and goodneſs; if there be, who live wicked and immoral lives, they ought not to think it conſiſtent either with the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or ſafety of the ſtate to protect their ſins. A delirious man is to be pitied, but for his ſake a nation cannot change its inſtitutions: An im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moral man is a ſubject of our forgiveneſs and prayer as chriſtians, and of our neighbourly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices as citizens; but muſt not expect, that the venerable public, with ſuffer him to ſport with the principles of their exiſtence.</p>
            <p>OUR ſubject admits a variety of practical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, on which I may not enlarge. It in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs us all how to be good citizens: Every man is a member in the political body; and every member hath a place in which it may be uſeful. If any are not uſeful, it is their fault; for divine wiſdom hath ſo organized the body, there is a place, a buſineſs and a duty for all. The man who doth his duty, be his ſervice what it may, deſerves well of the ſtate. No order, profeſſion or employment, may ſay to another, there is no need of thee. All will do well if they reſpect the great principles of religion, if their hearts poſſeſs divine love, and their prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice be in obedience to the law of GOD; and
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:022913_0022_0FBAB83E2A2542C8"/>
without theſe a man's character will be defect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive, whether he move in a high ſphere, or hath a humble place in the ſtate. Religion will make us contented with ſuch place and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment as providence appointeth, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize us to think of ourſelves we are not uſeleſs. The want of religion, if it doth not make a perſon entirely uſeleſs, yet in a great meaſure deſtroys him to mankind; and our riſing admiration of his uſeful accompliſhments, diſſolves in tears of ſorrow for degenerate human nature.</p>
            <p>OUR ſubject reproves all thoſe vices injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to ſociety, and none is more ſo than a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſpirit. Partial affection for local diſtricts and their intereſts, muſt breed oppoſition, and the general good will be forgotten in intereſted altercation. But of all party intrigue, that is the moſt open inſult on the dignity of a free ſtate, and moſt threatening to its happineſs, when offices are bartered for emolument, and dignities divided by private influence. Such things religion forbids, and decency with a ſigh turns her face from the ſcene.</p>
            <p>RELIGION forbids, and when it prevails a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a people will prevent, the cruel practice of privately ſlandering the reputation of eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted characters. To wound in the dark is an eaſy thing, and a ſmall capacity influenced by a bad heart can do it effectually. Unfounded jealouſies, are as dangerous to the public as to thoſe who ſuffer them, and by being often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, ſhake the foundation of government, and place the worthy and unworthy, on the ſame level of confidence in the minds of the people.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="unknown:022913_0023_0FBAB83F63F1D3F8"/>RELIGION is the beſt friend of men's liberties and properties. Undert his influence, govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will be juſt to all its engagements, and the intereſt of every citizen ſtand ſecure, on the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis of equity and juſtice. Where the ſpirit and practice of religion reigns, the ſigh of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion will ceaſe, and men no longer groan under the power of their brethren. A great part of the happineſs of the world, muſt be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the humane influence of the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of JESUS, and the remainder of oppreſſion is a witneſs how imperfectly his doctrines are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and how little there is of his ſpirit, even in the countries which are called chriſtian. On the ground of prophetic aſſurance we expect a day, in which this religion ſhall fill the earth, and when it happens, there will be no traffick in the bodies and ſouls of men; oppreſſion and ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very will ceaſe and the image of the Creator in reaſon and underſtanding, will be allowed as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of a right to the privileges of his family.</p>
            <p>OUR ſubject recommends to the rulers of the ſtate, an encouragement of all thoſe inſtitutions, by which religion and ſcience are diffuſed among the people. It is the manner of divine wiſdom, to work by means regularly eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. When the inſtitutions of religion fall into diſrepute, we have no right to expect, that the ſpirit of piety will prevail among the people. The viſible orders of religion are an incloſure, which holds its friends together; and under an idea of tolerancy many have run into an oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite extreme of opinion, that in all caſes where men pretend conſcience, they ought to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the direction of law. To argue
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:022913_0024_0FBAB841501AA670"/>
much on theſe matters may not be ſalutary, but I think a little attention will determine the point; for when we look on thoſe diſtricts within the United States, in which all legal protection hath been denied to the inſtitutions of religion, we can eaſily trace the political evils, jealouſies and confuſion which have enſued.</p>
            <p>SCIENCE is friendly to religion and good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and on this ground claims protection from government. The expences of education are the moſt economical depoſit which can be made for the liberties of our offspring. Men of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation will neither forfeit, nor quietly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the loſs of their civil rights; but the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant are enſnared by their brethren. Much therefore is due to the minds of our youth, who will fill the firſt offices in the ſtate and in the church and be the only pillars of order, when a few years have laid this honorable and pious Aſſembly in the duſt.</p>
            <p>IF religion and ſcience are the ſtrength of the ſtate, and the preſervation of public liberty, we ought to reflect with gratitude on the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of GOD, in furniſhing ſo many characters eminent in both. When we look on this col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, it calls to our remembrance many of our fathers, who, by their piety and wiſdom, were pillars in our Iſrael; and who now receive a more permanent reward than men can give. It is but a ſmall return, which even a grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful people can make to the fidelity of their rulers; but tho we cannot reward, an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the obligation is beautiful, and muſt encourage their hearts in doing us good.
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:022913_0025_0FBAB842B7C01458"/>
The chief officers of the ſtate, who are gathered before the LORD on this occaſion, to bleſs his name and aſk his preſence, have a right to our dutiful addreſs.</p>
            <p>MAY IT PLEASE YOUR EXCELLENCY,</p>
            <p>THE GOD of our fathers who hath all power and dominion, hath been pleaſed to put an important truſt into your hands, and ſelect you as the inſtrument of exerciſing his government, and diſpenſing his favor to this people. Tho an elevated ſtation among men, cannot diveſt you of the weakneſſes of humanity; tho we make no doubt, but in the preſence of a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ruler you feel in yourſelf all the imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a creature; yet you will indulge us in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning our thanks, for many benefits you have rendered to the ſtate, and eſpecially for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deviating teſtimony you have borne in favor of religion, both by your precept and example. Much is in the power of your excellency; tho the Gods of the people muſt die like men, and be ſoon reduced to a level with their brethren, yet they have a weighty influence on public opinion and practice, and the happineſs of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, perhaps even for another world, ſtands or falls with them. Impreſſed with this truth, we look to our firſt Magiſtrate to do more than any other man can do. You ſtand in the place of the LORD to this people—they conſider you cloathed with an authority from Heaven—they have confidence in your ſingular art of preſid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with united firmneſs and moderation—through a good opinion of your judgment, as well as an inclination men have to imitate the
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:022913_0026_0FBAB84697A905A8"/>
great, they will be ſtrongly impelled by your example. While ſubordinate orders of men in the ſtate have their ſphere of duty and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, we look to you, Sir, to be the moſt decid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and powerful friend of that religion and righteouſneſs, which is the true wiſdom of gov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ernment, and will eſtabliſh our proſperity on a permanent baſis. To our rulers, and chiefly to your care, we have committed every thing that is dear to us on earth; our lives, properties, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and happineſs, hoping that by a mild adminiſtration, you may be able to preſerve the betruſtment; but if ſeverity be at any time ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, to reſtrain the invaſions of vice, we ſhall pray without ceaſing, that the GOD of Heaven will give you wiſdom to uſe the ſword he hath put into your hand. The honor of being firſt among many is great; but much greater is the honor of being faithful to GOD who hath giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en this appointment, and of exerciſing it like a good man; and while we gratefully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the dignity of your ſtation, we beſeech the moſt high to make you a chriſtian indeed, and fill your heart with the comforts of unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed religion. The reward which we cannot give, your Excellency will find in living near to GOD, in feeling your dependence on his grace thro the Redeemer, and in adoring his holineſs. When wearied with the cares of State, in the retirement of devotion you will feel and ſay, it is good to be here. And when Almighty GOD takes you from this people and the honorable truſts he hath give you on earth, may you dwell forever in his love.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="unknown:022913_0027_0FBAB8480983BEC8"/>MAY I likewiſe be permitted to expreſs the public regard and expectations, to the Honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Lieutenant-Governor, the Council, and Houſe of Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>HONORABLE GENTLEMEN,</p>
            <p>THIS annual preſentment before GOD, of the Rulers and chief Eſtates of the land, is an event which muſt intereſt the feelings of a pious mind. It cannot fail to enkindle in us a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent devotion, when we behold the princes, the heads of families and repreſentatives of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, addreſſing our heavenly King for his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and direction. This anniverſary of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is a ſolemn engagement before GOD, that the government ſhall be according to his will; that a reſpect for his inſtitutions ſhall be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and religion encouraged. If you, who are the honorables of the land, countenance virtue and juſtice; if piety is conſpicuous in your lives; if induſtry, temperance, juſtice and a fear of GOD, are patronized by the laws you enact; if you appoint perſons of wiſdom and diſcreet goodneſs to execute the laws of the State; good order will prevail and vice be aſhamed: But without this aid from you, Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orable Gentlemen, there is reaſon to expect that licentiouſneſs will break over every bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier, diſhonor GOD who hath ſo often protected this people and their fathers, and induce a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eral wretchedneſs. The experience of all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple witneſſes the ſacred truth, that righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs exalteth a nation; and it is alſo a truth as certainly known, that the manners of a people, do in a great meaſure take their complexion
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:022913_0028_0FBAB849769A39C8"/>
from public meaſures. When we conſider how much your reſpectable body can do for GOD, and the eternal intereſt of men, we muſt earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly ſolicit your care, to preſerve the purity of the people, to encourage good living, and reward by your confidence in them, ſuch men as fear the LORD and obey his law.</p>
            <p>THE local ſituation of your honorable body, in every part of the State; your opportunity for perſonal obſervation of the manners in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſtrict;—the force of your example, unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with legiſlative authority, will eſſentially aid you in doing what is requeſted. The harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the people and peace of the land follows the harmony and union of their Rulers; and when the citizens ſee that every kind of vice is diſcountenanced by thoſe in dignified ſtations, it will be a powerful guard of their principles and manners. To ſtand the guardians of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic happineſs is a ſolemn ſituation, and one in which every man needs to be divinely aſſiſted.—Honorable Gentlemen, may the GOD of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom make you ſkilful to govern and wiſe unto eternal peace.</p>
            <p>THE ſons of Aaron are alſo before the LORD. The ſanctity of their profeſſion, and its near connection with my ſubject, naturally calls my addreſs to them:</p>
            <p>REVEREND FATHERS AND BRETHREN,</p>
            <p>THE duty incumbent on all chriſtian citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, piety towards GOD, and righteouſneſs and love to men, is doubly incumbent on us. We
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:022913_0029_0FBAB84CFA704038"/>
are conſecrated to the ſervice of religion, and under the moſt ſolemn vows. There is every reaſon, that we uſe a greater diligence than oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er men, in promoting a divine knowledge of GOD and his Son, love, faith, vital piety, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimental religion and a good practice. If thoſe who act in the civil department, are judged guilty for ſpiritual negligence; how much greater is the criminality of a goſpel miniſter, who is expreſsly ſet apart as a watchman for the ſouls of men. From the advantage to be deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in this life, we have the ſame inducement as other men, to urge the power and practice of godlineſs; national proſperity is a motive which will animate the heart of every good man. Tho not cloathed with civil power, we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected with the ſtate. Wiſe men of every pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, know the ſalutary influence of an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened and pious clergy, on the civil ſyſtem, and therefore much is expected from us; and much may be done to advance juſtice and peace, encourage obedience to the laws, and ſtength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the hand of government. But more weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſiderations are drawn from another world. The ſouls of this people are to be happy or wretched forever, and of this happineſs or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery we are the meſſengers. To deſcribe the perfections and will of GOD; to aſſert his gov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ernment, and declare his wrath againſt ſin; to publiſh the Goſpel of JESUS CHRIST, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain its peculiar doctrines, which are full of holineſs and love; to urge a chriſtian faith and practice; to encourage men by the glory pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to godlineſs, and awaken them by the terrors of the LORD prepared to avenge ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; to be an example to the church in
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:022913_0030_0FBAB84EC16E2278"/>
humility, ſobriety and every grace, are our pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar duties; and we cannot excel in them without much labour and prayer. For the right performance of theſe duties, there is a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar neceſſity that we take much care of our own hearts, and be perſonally warmed with love to GOD and men. Whatever aſſiſts us to love religion, will furniſh us with miniſterial accompliſhments, eſpecially to abound in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, will comfort, enlighten and aſſiſt us in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry duty, and give us a happy preparation, thro divine mercy, for that immortality which we preach to others. Let us be united in a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent charity, and in ſupplication for an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering of the ſpirit, on us and on our church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and when our LORD cometh he will make us perfect unto eternal peace.</p>
            <p>MY Brethren of every character, let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve here before the LORD that we will ſerve him. Bleſſed are the righteous; but one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner deſtroyeth much good, and diſturbeth his land. This honorable legiſlature are the anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ones of the LORD; it is our duty to pray that they may be endowed with wiſdom, to give them reverence, and to honor all the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and miniſters of juſtice in the land. Our political happineſs in a great degree depends on our own conduct, for a vicious people can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a happy one.</p>
            <p>ESPECIALLY let us endeavour by faith and patience, by charity and good works, to obtain the promiſes, and ſecure to ourſelves a habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not made with hands, eternal in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens. How precious are theſe moments of
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:022913_0031_0FBAB850357FD4D0"/>
time, and who can deſcribe how much depends on a right improvement of them? The ſoul which remains in ſin ſhall die; but for the pure in heart, there is reſerved an inheritance, incorruptible, undefiled, and that ſadeth not away.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>PRINTED BY HUDSON AND GOODWIN.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
