<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Amendments proposed to be added to the Federal Constitution, by the Congress of the United States of America, begun and held at the city of New-York, on Wednesday, the fourth day of March, in the year M,DCC,LXXXIX.</title>
            <author>United States. Congress (1st, 1st session : 1789).</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-03">2005-03.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N17725</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N17725</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 22953</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW8622</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">22953</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99014843</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 22953.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N17725)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 22953)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 22953)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Amendments proposed to be added to the Federal Constitution, by the Congress of the United States of America, begun and held at the city of New-York, on Wednesday, the fourth day of March, in the year M,DCC,LXXXIX.</title>
                  <author>United States. Congress (1st, 1st session : 1789).</author>
                  <author>United States. Constitution.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p. ;  18 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Thomas Adams, printer to the Honourable the General Court.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Boston, Massachusetts, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M,DCC,XC. [1790]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Constitutional amendments --  United States</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:022953_0000_0FBAC393ED3BA2B8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:022953_0001_0FBAC397CAB4EFB0"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AMENDMENTS PROPOSED TO BE ADDED TO THE FEDERAL CONSTITUTION, BY THE CONGRESS OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA, Begun and held at the CITY of NEW-YORK, on WEDNESDAY, the fourth Day of MARCH, in the YEAR M, DCC, LXXXIX.</p>
            <p>PRINTED at <hi>BOSTON,</hi> MASSACHUSETTS, BY THOMAS ADAMS, PRINTER to the HONOURABLE the GENERAL COURT M, DCC, XC.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="unknown:022953_0002_0FBAC399902043F0"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>UNITED STATES,
<date>OCTOBER 2d, 1789.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN pursuance of the inclosed Resolution, I have the honor to transmit to your Excellency, a copy of the Amendments proposed to be added to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of the United States.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I have the honor to be, with due consideration, your Excellency's most obedient Servant G. WASHINGTON.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>His Excellency</hi> JOHN HANCOCK.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="resolution">
            <head>CONGRESS of the UNITED STATES. In the <hi>HOUSE</hi> of <hi>REPRESENTATIVES,</hi> THURSDAY, 24th of SEPTEMBER, 1789.</head>
            <p>RESOLVED, by the Senate and House of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentatives of the United States of <hi>America</hi> in Congress assembled, That the PRESIDENT of the United States be requested to transmit to the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the several States which have ratified the Constitution, copies of the Amendments, proposed by Congress, to be added thereto; and like copies to the Executives of the States of <hi>Rhode-Island</hi> and <hi>North-Carolina.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Attest— JOHN BECKLEY, Clerk.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="resolution">
            <head>UNITED STATES OF <hi>AMERICA.</hi> In <hi>SENATE, SEPTEMBER, 26th, 1789.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>RESOLVED, That the Senate do concur in this Resolution.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Attest— SAMUEL A. OTIS, Secretary.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="amendments">
            <pb facs="unknown:022953_0003_0FBAC39B6F551890"/>
            <head>Congress of the United States, Begun and held at the city of NEW-YORK, on Wednesday the fourth of MARCH, one thousand seven hundred and eighty-nine.</head>
            <p>The Conventions of a number of the States having at the time of their adopting the Constitution, expressed a desire, in order to prevent misconstruction or abuse of its powers, that further declaratory and restrictive clauses should be added: And as extending the ground of public confidence in the government, will best insure the beneficent ends of its institution:</p>
            <p>RESOLVED, by the Senate and House of Representatives of the United States of AMERICA, in Congress assembled, two thirds of both Houses concurring, That the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Articles be proposed to the Legisla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the several States, as Amendments to the Constitution of the United States, all or any of which Articles, when ratified by three fourths of the said Legislatures, to be valid to all intents and purposes, as part of the said Constitution, viz.</p>
            <div type="articles">
               <pb n="4" facs="unknown:022953_0004_0FBAC39CEE9F8FE8"/>
               <head>ARTICLES in Addition to, and Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of, the CONSTITUTION of the UNITED STATES of AMERICA, proposed by Congress, and ratified by the Legisla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the several States, pursuant to the fifth Article of the original Constitution.</head>
               <div n="1" type="article">
                  <head>Article the First.</head>
                  <p>AFTER the first enumeration required by the first Article of the Constitution, there shall be one Representative for every thirty thousand, until the number shall amount to one hundred, after which the proportion shall be so regulated by Congress, that there shall be not less than one hundred Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives, nor less than one Representative for every forty thousand persons, until the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Representatives shall amount to two hundred; after which the proportion shall be so regulated by Congress, that there shall not be less than two hundred Representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, nor more than one Representative for every fifty thousand persons.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="article">
                  <head>Article the Second.</head>
                  <p>NO law varying the compensation for the services of the Senators and Representatives, shall take effect, until an election of Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentatives shall have intervened.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="article">
                  <pb n="5" facs="unknown:022953_0005_0FBAC3A1A502BF28"/>
                  <head>Article the Third.</head>
                  <p>CONGRESS shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion, or prohibiting the free exercise thereof, or abridging the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of speech, or of the press; or the right of the people peaceably to assemble, and to petition the government for a redress of grievances.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="article">
                  <head>Article the Fourth.</head>
                  <p>A WELL regulated militia being necessary to the security of a free State, the right of the people to keep and bear arms shall not be infringed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="article">
                  <head>Article the Fifth.</head>
                  <p>NO soldier shall in time of peace be quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in any house without the consent of the owner; nor in time of war, but in a manner to be prescribed by law.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="article">
                  <head>Article the Sixth.</head>
                  <p>THE right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses, papers, and effects, against unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be violated; and no warrants shall issue, but upon probable cause, supported by
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:022953_0006_0FBAC3A2F8751830"/>
oath or affirmation, and particularly describ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place to be searched, and the persons or things to be seized.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="article">
                  <head>Article the Seventh.</head>
                  <p>NO person shall be held to answer for a capital, or otherwise infamous crime, unless on a presentment or indictment of a Grand-Jury, except in cases arising in the land or naval forces, or in the militia when in actual service in time of war or public danger; nor shall any person be subject for the same offence to be twice put in jeopardy of life or limb; nor shall be compelled in any cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal case, to be a witness against himself, nor be deprived of life, liberty or property, without due process of law; nor shall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate property be taken for public use, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out just compensation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="article">
                  <head>Article the Eighth.</head>
                  <p>IN all criminal prosecutions, the accused shall enjoy the right to a speedy and public trial, by an impartial jury of the State and District wherein the crime shall have been committed, which District shall have been previously ascertained by law, and to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the nature and cause of the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation;
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:022953_0007_0FBAC3A4DB292BB8"/>
to be confronted with the witnesses against him; to have compulsory process for obtaining witnesses in his favor, and to have the assistance of counsel for his defence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="article">
                  <head>Article the Ninth.</head>
                  <p>IN suits at common law, where the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversy shall exceed twenty dollars, the right of trial by Jury, shall be preserved, and no fact, tried by a Jury, shall be otherwise re-examined in any Court of the United States, than according to the rules of the common law.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="article">
                  <head>Article the Tenth.</head>
                  <p>EXCESSIVE bail shall not be required, nor excessive fines imposed, nor cruel and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usual imprisonments inflicted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="article">
                  <head>Article the Eleventh</head>
                  <p>THE enumeration in the Constitution, of certain rights, shall not be construed to deny or disparage others retained by the people.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="article">
                  <pb n="8" facs="unknown:022953_0008_0FBAC3A5EE93D7E8"/>
                  <head>Article the Twelfth.</head>
                  <p>THE powers not delegated to the United States, by the Constitution, nor prohibited by it to the States, are reserved to the States respectively, or to the people.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>FREDERICK A. MUHLENBERG, <hi>Speaker of the House of Representatives.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <signed>JOHN ADAMS, <hi>Vice-President of the United States, and President of the Senate.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <signed>Attest. JOHN BECKLEY, <hi>Clerk of the House of Representatives.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <signed>SAMUEL A. OTIS, <hi>Secretary of the Senate.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
