<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The importance of parental fidelity in the education of children illustrated, in a discourse, addressed to the congregation in the North Society of Preston, the Lord's-Day following the 28th of Feb. 1792. / By Levi Hart, A.M. Pastor of a church in Preston. ; Being the thirtieth anniversary of his first sermon to that people. ; [Four lines of Scripture texts]</title>
            <author>Hart, Levi, 1738-1808.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N18759</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N18759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 24381</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APY4225</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">24381</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99031361</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 24381.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N18759)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 24381)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 24381)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The importance of parental fidelity in the education of children illustrated, in a discourse, addressed to the congregation in the North Society of Preston, the Lord's-Day following the 28th of Feb. 1792. / By Levi Hart, A.M. Pastor of a church in Preston. ; Being the thirtieth anniversary of his first sermon to that people. ; [Four lines of Scripture texts]</title>
                  <author>Hart, Levi, 1738-1808.</author>
                  <author>First Congregational Church (Griswold, Conn.).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38, [2] p. ;  22 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bushnell &amp; Hubbard,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Norwich [Conn.]: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M,DCC,XCII. [1792]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Mr. Hart's anniversary sermon for February 28th, 1792.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious education of children.</term>
               <term>Anniversary sermons --  1792.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:024381_0000_0FC6395F0BDA1E60"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:024381_0001_0FC63963E089B258"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. HART's</hi> ANNIVERSARY SERMON FOR FEBRUARY 28th, 1792.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:024381_0002_0FC639650DC07260"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IMPORTANCE OF PARENTAL FIDELITY IN THE EDUCATION OF CHILDREN ILLUSTRATED, IN A DISCOURSE, <hi>Addreſsed to the Congregation</hi> IN THE NORTH SOCIETY OF PRESTON, the Lord's-day following the 28th of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1792.</p>
            <p>By LEVI HART, A. M. <hi>Paſtor of a Church in Preſton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING THE THIRTIETH ANNIVERSARY OF HIS FIRST SERMON TO THAT PEOPLE.</p>
            <q>"I have no greater joy than to hear that my children walk in the truth." <bibl>
                  <hi>John III: 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>"Moreover I will endeavor that ye may be able, after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, to have theſe things, always in remembrance." <bibl>
                  <hi>2. Peter I: 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>NORWICH: PRINTED BY BUSHNELL &amp; HUBBARD, M,DCC,XCII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="unknown:024381_0003_0FC6396684B1A130"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM LXXVIII. 5, 6, 7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He eſtabliſhed a teſtimony in Jacob, and appointed a law in Iſrael, which he commanded our fathers, that they ſhould make them known to their children. That the generation to come might know them, even the children which ſhould be born, who ſhould ariſe and declare them to their children. That they might ſet their hope in God, and not forget the works of God, but keep his commandments.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE importance of the riſing generation, has engaged the attention of the wiſe and good, in all ages. Experienced old men have ardently deſired the beſt good of poſterity. Patriarchs, prophets, and apoſtles have laboured to promote it. The inſpired writer of this Pſalm, impreſſed deeply with the ſubject, calls on us to attend to the words of his mouth, even the words which had been received from the fathers which, ſaid he, we will not hide from their children, "ſhewing to the generations to come the praiſes of the Lord, and his ſtrength and his wonderful works."</p>
            <p>THE words of our text contain a ſummary of God's law and teſtimony which he appointed for his people, to be tranſmitted to ſucceeding generations; that the knowledge and practice of true religion might be preſerved to the end of the world. It will not be doubted that this ſubject claims our moſt ſerious attention, on the preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="unknown:024381_0004_0FC63968120AED50"/>WE ſhall attempt an illuſtration of it by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the law and teſtimony which God hath eſtabliſhed in his church. And</p>
            <p>THE great importance of tranſmitting them to poſterity.</p>
            <p n="1">I. WE are to conſider the law and teſtimony which God hath eſtabliſhed in his church.</p>
            <p>WERE we to confine our views to the time of the Pſalmiſt, nothing more would be compriſed than thoſe ſacred books of the old teſtament<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which were compleat in his day. The words of our text have a manifeſt reference to the writings of Moſes, but they may be more extenſively ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied. God's law and teſtimony was a progreſſive revelation, through the ſeveral periods, from the firſt age of the world, till the completion of the ſacred canon. Before the deluge, and in the days of the patriarchs, Noah and Abraham, only a few revelations were given to the church.—Large additions were made in the time of Moſes. In ſucceeding ages, the will of God was further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to man, by his prophets and other inſpired meſſengers, till the ſcriptures of the old teſtament were compleated. And, at the appointed time, the Divine Redeemer appeared, in our world, and having finiſhed his labours and ſufferings on earth, and aſcended to glory, he ſhed down the Holy Ghoſt on his apoſtles and others, to commit to writing the whole New Teſtament for the benefit of his church, to the end of the world.—Thus, "Holy men of God, ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt<note n="§" place="bottom">1 Peter i. 21.</note>," And, "God, who at ſundry times and in divers manners, ſpake to the fathers,
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:024381_0005_0FC6396C3A2C1318"/>
by the prophets, hath in theſe laſt days ſpoken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us by his Son<note n="§" place="bottom">Heb. i. 1, 2.</note>."</p>
            <p>HENCE, we are to underſtand, the law and teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony of God, in the days of the Pſalmiſt, to compriſe all parts of divine revelation then given to the church. To us they imply the whole canon of holy ſcripture. Theſe ſacred writings are "given by inſpiration of God, and are profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in righteouſneſs. That the man of God may be perfect, thoroughly furniſhed unto all good works<note n="‖" place="bottom">2 Tim. iii. 16, 17.</note>." But they, "principally, teach, what man is to believe, concerning God, and what duty God requires of man." Proofs, of the being and perfections of God, ſurround us in his works. "The heavens declare his glory, and the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſheweth his handy work. Day unto day ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth ſpeech, and night unto night ſheweth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge<note n="¶" place="bottom">Pſalm xix. 1, 2.</note>." And "the inviſible things of him, from the creation of the world are clearly ſeen, being underſtood by the things which are made, even his eternal power and Godhead<note n="⁋" place="bottom">Pſalm xix. 7.</note>." But "the law of the Lord is perfect, converting the ſoul. The teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, making wiſe the ſimple<note n="‖‖" place="bottom">Rom. i. 20.</note>." It is from the written word that we are to learn in the fulleſt manner, the divine perfections and will, and without which we are utterly in the dark as to the door of hope for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and the way in which ſalvation is attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>THE law and teſtimony of God inſtruct us in all needful truth. In theſe, we are taught in the
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:024381_0006_0FC63972EA49B6D0"/>
cleareſt manner, the natural and moral perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God.—The creation of all things, by the word of his power.—The relations of man to his Creator, and to his fellow creatures.—The origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſtate of innocence and felicity, and the nature and extent of God's moral government.—Thoſe divine writings, teach us the ſad and inexcuſable apoſtacy of the firſt man, and the conſequent ſtate of ſin and condemnation, to him and his poſterity. Here we learn that myſterious glory of the divine exiſtence.—<hi>A Trinity in Unity.</hi>—From this we are led, in the progreſſive revelation, to a view of the ſecond perſon in the adorable Trinity, as the Redeemer of man.—The holy ſcriptures inform us of "the counſel of peace," or the plan of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption fixed in the purpoſe of God, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in the perſon of, THE WORD. The great myſtery of godlineſs is here diſplayed. "God was manifeſt in the fleſh, juſtified in the ſpirit, ſeen of angels, preached to the Gentiles, believed on in the world, received up into glory." The work of redemption, is evidently, the greateſt of God's works revealed to man. To this all his other works tend, and in this they centre. For this reaſon a principal part of the ſacred ſcriptures are employed in treating on this ſubject.</p>
            <p>"OF this ſalvation, the prophets enquired and ſearched diligently, who propheſied of the grace which ſhould come unto us; ſearching what, or what manner of time, the ſpirit of Chriſt which was in them did ſignify, when it teſtified before hand, the ſufferings of Chriſt, and the glory which ſhould follow."</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="unknown:024381_0007_0FC6397528A430A8"/>THE apoſtles were "witneſſes of the ſufferings of Chriſt," and they "determined to know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing among their hearers, ſave Jeſus Chriſt and him crucified."</p>
            <p>IN connexion with the perſon and work of Chriſt, and redemption by his blood; the law and teſtimony reveal to us the work of the holy ſpirit, in the application of redemption, and the way in which ſinners become united to Chriſt, and partakers in the ſaving benefits of his death. Here we are taught the neceſſity of "repentance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and faith towards our Lord Jeſus Chriſt." That without faith, it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,"—That "he who believeth ſhall be ſaved, but he who believeth not, ſhall be damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed." That men are "juſtified by faith without the deeds of the law"—"Juſtified freely by the grace of God, through the redemption which is in Jeſus Chriſt." From theſe oracles, we alſo learn, that the faith of God's elect, is connected with a life of chriſtian holineſs, or obedience to all divine commands,—that "thoſe, only who do God's commandments, are bleſſed, have right to the tree of life, and ſhall enter in through the gates into the city."</p>
            <p>ALL goſpel inſtitutions and ordinances belong to the divine teſtimony, and are enjoined in the holy ſcriptures.—The religious and devout obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them is an important part of chriſtian holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and thoſe who fear God, count them among their greateſt bleſſings.—Private and ſocial prayer to God, and other branches of his worſhip—The obſervation of the Lord's day.—Of the chriſtian ſacraments.—Baptiſm, and the Lord's Supper, are
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:024381_0008_0FC63977369FA480"/>
not only enjoined as duties, but granted as privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges.—In connexion with thoſe is the inſtitution of the chriſtian church and evangelical miniſtry.—The office and work of the miniſtry, and the order, unity and diſcipline of the church, are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God, "for the perfecting the ſaints, for the edifying the body of Chriſt, till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt."</p>
            <p>THE holy ſcriptures enjoin the duties of ſenſible dependence on God.—Submiſſion in adverſity, and of humility and thankfulneſs in proſperity. They teach us in whatever ſtate we are, "therewith to be content," and furniſh rules by which if duly applied, we ſhall "know how to be abaſed and how to abound—to be full and to be hungry."—They inſtruct us to be as ſtrangers and pilgrims on earth, to lay up treaſure in heaven, and endure as ſeeing him who is inviſible. In all conditions, and through all changes, living or dying; the word of God furniſhes a rich ſupply of needful truth: that the good man may ſay with thankful praiſe, "thy teſtimonies, O Lord, are wonderful, therefore doth my ſoul keep them." "The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of thy word giveth life, it giveth under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the ſimple."</p>
            <p>IT muſt be remembered that God's law and teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony contain all neceſſary rules of duty in our various relations to each other. There we may learn our duty and happineſs, as huſbands and wives, parents and children, and in all other do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtic relations.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="unknown:024381_0009_0FC6397979F65548"/>THE word of God alſo, inculcates the love of our neighbor, and teaches us to reſpect all men as ſuch. It requires us to "love our enemies, and do good to thoſe who hate us, to pray for thoſe who deſpitefully uſe us, and perſecute us."—To "bear one another's burdens, relieve the diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, viſit the fatherleſs and widows in their afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions," and be "ready to every good work."</p>
            <p>THIS ſacred book not only teaches men the love of their country, but inſpires them with that true patriotiſm which ſeeks its beſt intereſt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces all becoming exertions to promote it.—And that in ſuch a manner as to advance the good of deſerving individuals, and to coincide with the true intereſt of other countries, and of mankind.—We muſt not omit to obſerve, that the love of our country, required in the holy ſcriptures, is ſuch as is ſubſervient to the glory of God. To this, all its exertions tend, and in it they are ultimately abſorbed.</p>
            <p>THE divine word teaches us to ſpend life in preparation for death and heaven.—It aſſures us of the conſcious exiſtence of thoſe, who are abſent from the body—Of the reſurrection, both of the juſt and unjuſt—Of the final judgment, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verending bleſſedneſs of the righteous, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the wicked, and it preſents the moſt awful and endearing motives to perſuade us to live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the governing influence of thoſe great and everlaſting realities; and it offers ſuch divine ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, in afflictions and death, as if duly applied, will enable us to walk through the valley of the ſhadow of death, and fear no evil, and in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of thankful exultation to cry, "O death,
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:024381_0010_0FC6397AC440B6F0"/>
where is thy ſting. O grave, where is thy vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory!</p>
            <p n="2">II. THE great importance of tranſmitting to poſterity, the divine law and teſtimony will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from the following conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. THE worth of poſterity.</p>
            <p>THE importance of man will deeply impreſs the mind which attentively conſiders it. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and future exiſtence are, both of them, high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intereſting, but eſpecially the latter. The va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious endowments of the mind of man, in connex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion with his immortality, render his exiſtence im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, in the higheſt degree.—Such is the worth of the human ſoul, that in the eſtimate of unerring wiſdom, it is not to be exchanged for the whole world<note n="‖" place="bottom">Math. xvi. 26.</note>. This worth is ſummarily compriſed in the capacity for poſſeſſing and diffuſing happineſs, or which iſſues in the ſame, for union to God and his kingdom. Each individual of the preſent and future ages will fill a place in the ſcale of beings, through never-ending duration: important in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry period of his exiſtence; how important then in the whole of it! The preſent infant of a day, is a being of immortality, and will act a part which will materially effect the felicity, not of himſelf only, but of the whole moral ſyſtem, and that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>SUCH conſiderations ſhow the importance of man, and the worth of poſterity; but it is ſtill more ſtrongly marked in the agency of God with reſpect to our race. This world is evidently cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated to be an habitation for man, the various or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of inferior creatures, were made and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:024381_0011_0FC6397C4BD678C8"/>
for his ſervice; and the whole courſe of events from the firſt creation, is directed with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to him. But what ſwallows up all other conſiderations on this ſubject, is, <hi>the work of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption!</hi> to this, nothing can be added to evince the importance of man, and the worth of poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: the whole is expreſſed in ſaying that "<hi>in due time, Chriſt died for the ungodly</hi>
               <note n="§" place="bottom">Romans v. 6.</note>." and that, "<hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">John iii, 16.</note>."</p>
            <p n="2">2d. THE felicity and uſefulneſs of poſterity de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on a becoming regulation of their principles and manners. This conſiſts in their receiving God's teſtimonies, and reducing them to practice. Theſe teſtimonies enjoin the ſeveral branches of that religion which is ſummarily contained in the love of God and man. Without which they can be neither happy nor uſeful<note n="¶" place="bottom">This aſſertion reſpects only the nature and tendency of moral diſpoſitions, and is by no means to be underſtood in oppoſition to the important truth, that God by his wiſe and holy agency, ſo over-rules the wickedneſs of his enemies, and counteracts its nature and tendency as to render it ſubſervient to the purpoſe of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite wiſdom and holineſs, and thus, by "educing good from ill," he cauſes the wrath of man to praiſe him, and the remainder of wrath, he graciouſly reſtrains.</note>.</p>
            <p>THAT each of theſe depend on ſuch diſpoſitions will appear to be true, to whatever particular we apply the obſervation.</p>
            <p>WHAT but mutual affection conſtitutes that har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of minds which is termed friendſhip?—Such union of hearts is the ſource and band of domeſtic felicity: if this be wanting, how deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably miſerable is the neareſt of human connex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:024381_0012_0FC63983B18BDA68"/>
even in the midſt of all other earthly good. But where this is found it not only gives worth to all other enjoyments, but ſupplies their abſence, and gives truly ſublime ſatisfaction in the midſt of calamity. All family relations, and other ſocial connexions are found to be happy in proportion to this, and the reverſe if it be wanting.</p>
            <p>THE intereſts of ſociety at large are proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably effected, and depend on the union of its mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and where this in any good meaſure exiſts, the benevolent ſpectator will behold it with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and exultingly cry out, "Behold how good and how pleaſant it is for brethren to dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in unity."—But as man is a being of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, and a member of that vaſt ſociety, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing all intelligent beings, his felicity and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs are principally to be meaſured in relation to that.—When viewed in this connexion, how intereſting is the preſent ſubject!—Thoſe whoſe principles and manners are formed to the buſineſs and enjoyments of God's kingdom, are prepared for the nobleſt exiſtence. It is by the love of God and man they are thus formed. Without this their noble endowments will be employed in a manner ſtrongly tending to the injury of others, and with regret to themſelves. This tendency will be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual and everlaſting.</p>
            <p>THE only poſſible method of eſcape from this evil is in receiving God's teſtimonies and reducing them to practice.—And in this way only will they live in the moſt uſeful manner to others on earth, and be actively uſeful in heaven.</p>
            <p n="3">3d. THAT poſterity may be thus uſeful and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, they muſt be inſtructed in God's teſtimonies.
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:024381_0013_0FC639868521A110"/>
It belongs indeed to God only, to form the heart to the love of divine truth. Paul may plant, and Apollos water, the beſt means may be applied in vain, unleſs attended with the bleſſing of God. However, it is his good pleaſure to bleſs his own inſtitutions. We are as totally dependent on him for the health and ſupport of the body. Our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread is the gift of his bounty, no leſs than the food for the ſoul. But who will infer from thence, that we are not to apply the appointed means, to obtain food for ourſelves and our families? The duty is not leſs evident, and is much more impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in regard to the ſoul. A proper ſenſe of our dependence on God, that our poſterity may be formed to be uſeful and happy, will lead to a faithful application of the appointed means.</p>
            <p>AN acquaintance with the word of God is the great appointed medium of that felicity and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs which is to be ſought for poſterity; this is to be obtained by inſtruction. For many reaſons it is important that this inſtruction ſhould be given in youth: the mind is then moſt ſuſceptible of laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impreſſions; habits of ignorance and obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy are not formed, at moſt they have not attained the firmneſs of long indulgence; bad example has not exerted its baneful influence to ſtrengthen them in the way of death; inveterate cuſtom has not fixed them in the walks of vice, and rendered them callous to the truths of religion, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances of conſcience.</p>
            <p>SAD experience evinces, that few who have ſpent their youth in vice and folly, are brought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and reformation in advanced age. Of theſe few were the caſes examined, it would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:024381_0014_0FC6398AB4011858"/>
be found that in moſt of them, the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was laid by early inſtruction. Innumerable have been the inſtances of its ſucceſs. How many of God's people have bleſſed him for the inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their youth, and that from their childhood they have "known the holy ſcriptures, which are able to make them wiſe to ſalvation, through faith in Chriſt Jeſus."—Admitting that a few have been made wiſe to ſalvation who never enjoyed this ineſtimable privilege, (for we rejoice in the unlimited ſovereignty of God, and that he hath mercy on whom he will have mercy:) yet how diſproportioned are their means to be uſeful and happy, and how deeply muſt they lament the want of that early and pious inſtruction recommended in our text! and how ſuperior the advantages of thoſe who have enjoyed it!</p>
            <p>BUT alas! how vaſt are the numbers of thoſe, who live and die in extreme ignorance of God and religion; not only in the regions of unenlighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed paganiſm, but even in the midſt of thoſe who enjoy the goſpel! Their untaught childhood and youth have prepared them to deſpiſe religious knowledge in riper years. Habits of vice have induced them to add contempt to ignorance, till they have increaſed the number of thoſe "fools who deſpiſe wiſdom and inſtruction, make a mock at ſin, and die for want of wiſdom."</p>
            <p n="4">4th. THE inſtruction of children and youth in God's teſtimonies, ſhould be the great concern of parents.</p>
            <p>IF poſterity are inſtructed at all in theſe things, it muſt be principally by their care.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="unknown:024381_0015_0FC6398C09421248"/>THIS inſtruction cannot be ſuppoſed to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by themſelves, or their own unaſſiſted ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertions. If it be not the duty of parents, to whom doth it belong? and how ſhall it be obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? The God of nature has eſtabliſhed the courſe of ſociety,—the relations of parent and child are his appointment; he hath conſtituted that ſingleneſs of affection, that identity of inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts and enjoyments between the two parents, which directs their joint exertions, in nurſing and educating their offspring, and which nothing but the height of obſtinacy in wickedneſs can prevent.—As children in general muſt probably be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taught in God's teſtimonies, and devoted to ruin if they are neglected by their parents, ſo the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt benefits may be hoped for in a compliance with this duty.—The advantages in the hand of parents for ſucceſs are diſtinguiſhingly great: they are much in the company of their children, and have abundant opportunity to impreſs the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of religion on their minds.—The earlieſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of their offspring are highly favorable to ſuch views. Beſide the foundation in nature for the moſt tender reciprocal affections between pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and children—the early dependence in one, and exertions of kindneſs in the other, greatly increaſe the nearneſs; the parents are ſtrongly prompted to inſtruct, and the children to learn; prepoſſeſſed as they are, in favor of their parents, and inclined to adopt their ſentiments and manners, will they not hang on their lips, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the inſtructions of wiſdom!—Allowing that the ſtate of ſin which is common to man, and in which our children are partakers, is oppoſed to
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:024381_0016_0FC6398D8D57F460"/>
the admiſſion of ſaving knowledge, is this an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection againſt <hi>parental inſtruction</hi>? doth it not even ſhew its ſuperior importance?—Or, are all means to be neglected, becauſe the fallen race are dull of hearing? Should we not infer juſt the reverſe, and in imitation of the divine example, "give them line upon line, and precept upon precept<note n="‖" place="bottom">Iſaiah <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>."</p>
            <p>MOREOVER this important duty is committed to parents, by the wiſdom of God—under the ancient diſpenſation ſuch are the divine directions.</p>
            <p>"THESE words, which I command thee this day, ſhall be in thine heart, and thou ſhalt teach them diligently unto thy children, and ſhalt talk of them when thou ſitteſt in thine houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou lieſt down, and when thou riſeſt up. And thou ſhalt bind them for a ſign upon thine hand, and they ſhall be as frontlets between thine eyes, and thou ſhalt write them upon the poſts of thy houſe, and on thy gates<note n="§" place="bottom">Deut. vi. 6, 7, 8, 9.</note>. That your days may be multiplied, and the days of your children, in the land which the LORD ſware unto your fathers to give them, as the days of heaven upon the earth<note n="¶" place="bottom">Deut. xi. 21.</note>."</p>
            <p>AMONG the many paſſages in the ſacred writings inculcating this important duty, we add only this ſummary direction.—"Fathers provoke not your children to wrath, but bring them up in the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and admonition of the Lord<note n="⁋" place="bottom">Epheſians vi. 4.</note>."</p>
            <p n="5">5th. WE muſt not omit to obſerve, that paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal education is the great inſtituted mean for the good of poſterity: this might be ſhewn from the experience of all ages, and the word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="unknown:024381_0017_0FC6399527A41A10"/>IT appears from particulars already mentioned, that childhood and youth are the ſeaſons for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting thoſe practical ſentiments in the human mind, which are to influence through life, and moſt eſſentially affect the condition of man through the whole of his exiſtence. Experience confirms this truth, both in the happy fruits of a well di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected education, and in the ſad conſequences where it has been neglected.—Admitting that a good education has not always been attended with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired ſucceſs, and that ſome men have become wiſe and good who never enjoyed it; in the former caſe it only proves the ſad degeneracy of human nature, and the great danger of youth; and in the latter, it diſplays the ſovereign freedom of devine grace: but in neither, counteracts the dictates of reaſon and common experience, found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the ſtated courſe of events in the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, and the hiſtory of man.—Becauſe the beſt medicines are not always ſucceſsful to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the ſick, and in ſome inſtances they recover with none or with bad ones; ſhall we, herefore not apply this ſtated mean of recovery, or ſhall we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the advice of Quacks and Empiries to that of the moſt approved practitioners?</p>
            <p>BUT a truth of this importance reſts not meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or chiefly on the concluſions of fallible man.—The word of God abundantly confirms it.</p>
            <p>TO ſet this matter in the ſtrongeſt light would require long quotations from many parts of the ſacred writings, and would draw out the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to an unreaſonable length, and indeed, would be needleſs, as few or none have ever appeared to deny the preſent truth. And writers
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:024381_0018_0FC6399A0BCF7000"/>
who have differed widely as to the ſtanding of the children of faithful parents, with reſpect to the gracious covenant of God, and their title to its bleſſings, have nevertheleſs agreed in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine appointment of parental education, as the great mean for the good of poſterity <note n="§" place="bottom">
                  <p>A particular diſcuſſion of the ſtanding of baptized children, as diſtinguiſhed from others who are educated under the goſpel, and the obligations and encouragements which are peculiar to them, would not have been adapted to the particular deſign of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; and would rather have diverted the attention of the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from its main object; which was to impreſs the minds of <hi>all</hi> parents with a practical ſenſe of the duty and importance of the religious education of their children: and <hi>all</hi> children and youth with a ſenſe of their great obligations to improve whatever degree of religious education they have enjoyed, in a life of practical religion.</p>
                  <p>The additional privileges and duties of thoſe who are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of faithful parents, devoted to God by chriſtian baptiſm in their infancy, are exceedingly important; and worthy a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and ſeparate coſideration: but could not ſo properly be illuſtrated in this diſcourſe.</p>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>UNDER the general term of <hi>parental education</hi> we mean to compriſe the whole of the duty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined on parents in training up their children; their dedication to God in their infancy, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his inſtitution, perpetuated by a courſe of daily prayer, unreſervedly devoting them to him for his bleſſing.—A courſe of <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and well directed inſtructions, from the firſt opening of their underſtandings, ſuitable to their age, capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and other circumſtances, ultimately adapted to their laſt improvement in the knowledge of God and true religion, and to excite them to a life of practical holineſs.—Add to this, the ſteady and well directed exertions of parental authority and love; enforcing their inſtructions: and above
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:024381_0019_0FC6399B09923DB8"/>
all, the efficacious influence of wiſe and pious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; without which, there can be little hope from inſtruction and the exerciſe of authority. From the combined influence of theſe, we are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to hope for ſucceſs in parental educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and not merely or cheifly from its natural tendency, however well adapted, but from divine inſtitution and that gracious influence which God is pleaſed often to beſtow, in connection with the means of his own appointment.—That means are divinely inſtituted for the beſt good of young children, and even <hi>infants</hi> cannot be queſtioned, after the expreſs deciſion of our bleſſed Redeemer.</p>
            <p>ON a certain occaſion, when ſuch were brought to him, (undoubtedly by their parents,) for his bleſſing, ſome of his diſciples were ſo remarkably blind, as to object to it; but he ſweetly reproved them.—The hiſtory of this event deſerves our at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. It runs thus. "And they brought young children or infants to him, that he ſhould touch them, and lay his hands on them, and pray: and when his diſciples ſaw it, they rebuked thoſe who brought them. But when Jeſus ſaw it, he was much diſpleaſed; and ſaid, ſuffer the little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to come unto me, and forbid them not: for of ſuch is the kingdom of God.</p>
            <p>VERILY I ſay unto you, whoſoever ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the kingdom of God as a little child, he ſhall, in no wiſe, enter therein. And he called them unto him, and took them up in his arms, and put his hands on them and bleſſed them<note n="‖" place="bottom">Math. xix, 13—15. Mark x, 13—16. Luke xviii, 15—17.</note>."</p>
            <p>FROM paſſages, adduced in this diſcourſe, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nection
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:024381_0020_0FC6399D90005FE0"/>
with our text; we have ſufficient evidences of the divine appointment of parental education, as the great mean of the good of poſterity. Would any attend more fully to the extent of the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, they may conſult the hiſtory of Gods co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with Abraham—the hiſtory of Job's at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to the beſt good of his children—the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired writings of David and Solomon—and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the whole bible.</p>
            <p>THE reflections and conduct of our divine teacher, in the caſe juſt quoted, are full of the moſt uſeful inſtruction. Happy parents, who brought thoſe children to Chriſt for his bleſſing, and happy children who received it from him. For we know that thoſe whom HE bleſſeth, are indeed bleſſed.</p>
            <p>How much muſt thoſe parents have been edified and comforted, by ſuch condeſcending love of the bleſſed Jeſus—what laſting impreſſions muſt have been made by it on the minds of the children,—and what animating encouragement is, hereby, preſented to parents and children, in all ages, to go and do likewiſe<note n="§" place="bottom">Hiſtory informs us that the celebrated Ignatius, afterwards Biſhop of Antioch, was one of theſe infants. See Dodredges in loc.</note>!</p>
            <p>FROM ſuch views, we may reaſonably hope for the bleſſing of God in common with the faithful and well directed performance of parental duty; that our children may be uſeful and happy on earth, and bleſſed forever in the kingdom of God. We proceed to obſerve,</p>
            <p n="6">6th. THE education of the preſent generation, may be juſtly expected to have a happy influence on many ſucceeding ages.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="unknown:024381_0021_0FC6399EC60E1C20"/>THIS is a leading ſentiment in the text.—It was verified in the Pſalmiſt, who had received the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant truths, which it contains, in this manner through ſucceſſive generations, from Moſes to his own time; agreeably to the divine injunction to which he refers, which required ſuch inſtructions to their children, "<hi>that the generation to come might know them. Even the children which ſhould be born, who ſhould ariſe and declare them to their children,</hi> that they might ſet their hope in God, and not forget the works of God, but keep his commandments."</p>
            <p>SCRIPTURE hiſtory abounds with facts in confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the preſent truth. We may reaſonably conclude, it was in this way, that the knowledge and practice of true religion were preſerved in the family of <hi>Seth,</hi> to the time of the deluge; while the pious race were diſtinguiſhed by the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of "<hi>the Sons of God</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">Geneſis, vi. 2.</note>." The intercourſe of theſe, with the wicked deſcendants of Cain, broke the chain of religious education, and a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral apoſtacy brought on the deſtruction of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <p>NOAH was found righteous before God in that evil generation, and was ſaved with his family from the common ruin. His ſon <hi>Ham</hi> very ſoon forſook the true religion, and was the father of a degenerate and accurſed race; moſt probably in conſequence of alliance with the family of Cain<note n="§" place="bottom">Geneſis, iv. 22. <hi>Naamah</hi> is the only fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male deſcendant of Adam, mentioned by name in the hiſtory of the old world, as ſome Expoſitors ſuppoſe, becauſe ſhe was the wiſe of Ham, and the mother of a degenerate race after the flood.</note>. But the true religion was preſerved for many
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:024381_0022_0FC639A052D4C918"/>
years in the family of Shem. No doubt by means of the pious education which he received from his father Noah, and tranſmitted to his children.</p>
            <p>WHEN idolatry was faſt ſpreading among his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendents, moſt probably <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the fruit of affinity with the wicked poſterity of Ham, and the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent neglect of good parental education, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to call Abram, one of his poſterity, and the ninth in deſcent from him, and inſtruct him in the religion of his pious progenitors, and alſo to favor him with ſeveral new and important reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. How he improved theſe, in the education of his children, we learn from the divine decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in the following words: "I know him, that he will command his children and his houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord, to do juſtice and judgment<note n="§" place="bottom">Geneſis xviii. 19.</note>." We may have the fruits of his pious exertions in the character of his deſcendents, Iſaac and Jacob, "the heirs with him of the ſame promiſe."</p>
            <p>As the choſen family increaſed, and their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with their idolatrous neighbors was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, there was a decline of religious education, and the nation became ſadly degenerated. This was uniformly the caſe, when they married ſtrange wives of the idolatrous nations round them, which effectually obſtructed a religious education. But the good effects of it in theſe inſtances, where it did exiſt, are conſpicuous in the hiſtory of that people from beginning to end. It is obſervable alſo, in ſome who were not of the choſen family—the inſtance of the Rachabites is inſtructive and memorable. The injunctions of Jonadab, their
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:024381_0023_0FC639A4EA91D3C0"/>
father or progenitor, were religiouſly obſerved by them for many ages<note n="‖" place="bottom">Compare, 2d Kings x. 15, with Jeremiah xxxv. 1—11.</note>. The pious Timothy was the happy ſubject of that "unfeigned ſaith which dwelt firſt in his mother Lois, and his grand mother Eunice<note n="§" place="bottom">2d Timothy i. 5.</note>; and from a child, no doubt by the pious education of his mother, he had known the Holy Scriptures, which were able to make him wiſe to ſalvation through faith in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus<note n="¶" place="bottom">Chapter iii. 15.</note>."</p>
            <p>SUCH is the readineſs of the human mind to be influenced by parental education, that, when this is oppoſed to the dictates of the Holy Scriptures, and the cleareſt reaſon, it often eſtabliſhes youth in oppoſition to the truth, and fixes prejudices, which the labours of their beſt and wiſeſt friends, are never after able to remove. What happy influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then may we expect from it, when wiſely conducted on the principles of reaſon and revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            <p>THE influence of parental education is evident in the hiſtory of all nations.—Principles and manners have deſcended from father to ſon, through ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive generations—in domeſtic and more exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded life—in laws, politics and religion. We ſhall be eſtabliſhed in this truth, by attending to the paſt and preſent habits of our own country. In how many reſpects are thoſe of the preſent gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in buſineſs, policy and religion, to be tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced back to our anceſtors through ſeveral ages? And this notwithſtanding our ſingular convulſions and important revolution in government, ſo ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tending to a ſimilar revolution in our habits and cuſtoms.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="unknown:024381_0024_0FC639A702A34B00"/>THE truth will receive confirmation, even, from ourſelves and the place in which we live; as in all other things, ſo in particular in regard to the promotion of order, and the intereſts of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Who are the men, of the preſent age, among us, whoſe labours and example, maintain the peace and good order of ſociety, the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord's day, and the public inſtitutions of religion? Are they not the deſcendents of thoſe venerable anceſtors who taught theſe things diligently to their children, and who added the pious efficacy of their examples and their prayers? and who are the people among us, that are a dead weight on ſociety?—oppoſers of order, and who openly trample on the inſtitutions of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? and who are rarely to be ſeen in this houſe of prayer? Are they not generally, the deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents of progenitors like themſelves, whoſe fatal examples have fixed their poſterity in the path of ruin? For though inſtances might be named of apoſtates, from the good principles and examples of their anceſtors, they are comparatively few, and in moſt caſes may be accounted for, from dangerous connections, in childhood, youth, or ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per years. And how few, whoſe unhappy lot hath been the reverſe of a wiſe and virtuous education, have ever emerged from that degraded condition of the mind, and become uſeful in ſociety; the ſupporters of good order and religion?</p>
            <p>REFLECTIONS like theſe, muſt have often occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to obſervers of human nature, either in the hiſtory of other ages and countries, or in attention to their own. And they muſt have made deep im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the great importance of a virtuous and well directed education.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="unknown:024381_0025_0FC639AC11685068"/>SUCH views, we are led to ſuppoſe, have influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced the wiſe and good in all ages, in the educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their children. Was it not the belief of truths like theſe, which induced Abraham to "com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his children and houſhold after him, that they might keep the way of the Lord<note n="§" place="bottom">Gen. xviii. 19.</note>?—and Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua to reſolve that "as for him and his houſe they would ſerve the Lord<note n="‖" place="bottom">Joſhua xxiv, 15.</note>?—What brought the aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful judgments of God on Eli and his houſe, but the neglect of this important duty? when "his ſons made themſelves vile, and he reſtrained them not<note n="¶" place="bottom">1ſt Samuel ii. iii. &amp; iv. chapters.</note>."</p>
            <p>DAVID, the man after God's heart, cloſed his life with an addreſs, of this import, to the princes of Iſrael, and to his ſon.—"Now keep and ſeek ye all the commandments of the Lord your God, that ye may poſſeſs this good land, and leave it for an inheritance for your children after you, forever."—"And thou Solomon my ſon, know thou the God of thy father, and ſerve him with a perfect heart, and with a willing mind. For the Lord ſearcheth all hearts, and underſtandeth all the imaginations of the thoughts. If thou ſeek him, he will be found of thee, but if thou forſake him, he will caſt thee off forever<note n="⁋" place="bottom">1ſt Chron. xviii. 1, 9. See alſo 1ſt Kings, ii. 1—4.</note>."—Job, whoſe ſingular piety is much celebrated in holy ſcripture, has the honorable teſtimony, that he "ſanctified his ſons, and continually offered burnt offerings ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the number of them all<note n="§§" place="bottom">Job i. 5.</note>."</p>
            <p>THUS in the remoteſt ages, as well as in later times, good men have eſteemed the religious edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:024381_0026_0FC639ADC3D6BA20"/>
of their children and poſterity, as an object of the firſt importance; and they have poſſeſſed "no greater joy, than to learn that their children walk in the truth." In this they have ever been agreed, from ſuch views as have been mentioned, of which it is not the leaſt that the education of the preſent generation, may be juſtly expected to have a happy influence on many which ſhall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
            <p>WITH the utmoſt propriety, did the pious pſalm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt remind us of the divine inſtitution by Moſes on this ſubject. "That the generation to come might know his ſtatutes; even the children which ſhould be born, who ſhould ariſe and declare them to their children; that they might ſet their hope in God, and not forget the works of God, but keep his commandments."</p>
            <div type="improvement">
               <head>Improvement.</head>
               <p>MANY are the ſerious and weighty reflections furniſhed by this ſubject, and they will readily oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to the conſiderate mind. But "the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the riſing generation," and the awful and endearing motives to fidelity in parents and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, are among the firſt.—To theſe we ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend in the following addreſſes.</p>
               <p n="1">I. To the parents of the congregation. Thoſe of you who are advanced in life, will remember that thirty years have now paſſed away ſince our firſt interview in this place of worſhip! Thirty years are uſually accounted the life of a miniſter. I am not inſenſible that my life and miniſtry have been attended with many imperfections, for which I have cauſe for deep humiliation. But I am not
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:024381_0027_0FC639B023E82B50"/>
conſcious of deſignedly ſhunning to declare all the counſel of God, or of keeping back any thing which was profitable to you.—"I have not ſought yours but you."—Senſible that the beſt part of my days is already paſt, and that the time of my departure is at hand, I would wiſh to be pure from the blood of all men, and eſpecially of the people of my charge, and to be ready to give up the account of my ſtewardſhip. I am not only concerned for an admiſſion to the joys of the redeemed for myſelf; but, am earneſtly deſirous, that you, and your children, may alſo be partakers. This has been a leading object, of my labours among you, from the firſt of my miniſtry. Many of you who are now advanced in life, were the youth of the congregation, at the time of my ſettlement. "The fathers, where are they?" The venerable anceſtors of t<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> people, are no more on earth. The paſtor with his flock, who founded this ſociety are long ſince, removed to the world of ſpirits.<note n="§" place="bottom">
                     <p>The church of Chriſt in the north ſociety in Preſton, was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on the thirtieth of November, 1720, at which time the Rev'd Hezekiah Lord, was ordained to the paſtoral office there, by prayer and the impoſition of the hands of
<list>
                           <item>The Rev'd Meſſieurs,
<list>
                                 <item>SAMUEL WHITING.</item>
                                 <item>SALMON TREAT.</item>
                                 <item>JOSEPH COIT.</item>
                                 <item>SAMUEL EASTABROOK.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>He ſerved in the goſpel miniſtry with great faithfulneſs and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teem, and with happy ſucceſs, till June twenty-third 1761 when he was removed by death, in the ſixty-fourth year of his age and forty-firſt of his miniſtry. At the time of his ſettlement the church conſiſted of forty-two members; two hundred and thirty-three were added during the courſe of his miniſtry; eighty of which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained at his death.</p>
                     <p>On the fourth of November, 1762 he was ſucceeded by the Rev'd Levi Hart, who was ſet apart to the goſpel miniſtry and paſtoral office in like manner by
<list>
                           <item>The Rev'd Meſſieurs,
<list>
                                 <item>BENJAMIN LORD.</item>
                                 <item>JABEZ WIGHT.</item>
                                 <item>NATHANIEL EELLS.</item>
                                 <item>JOSEPH FISH.</item>
                                 <item>JONATHAN BARBER.</item>
                                 <item>ASHER ROSSETER.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>At Mr. Hart's ſettlement, the church conſiſted of eighty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular members: from that time eighty-ſeven have been added, fifty-ſeven have been removed by death, thirty-four have remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and joined other regular churches—three have joined the Anabaptiſts, and one has been excommunicated.</p>
                     <p>A better wiſh cannot be uttered for the preſent paſtor and church, than that they may follow their predeceſſors wherein they followed Chriſt; and ſee their children walking by the ſame rule, minding the ſame thing.</p>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="30" facs="unknown:024381_0028_0FC639B18DB41650"/>
Thoſe, who were the principal actors in my ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, are either ſilent in death, or ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling with the lateſt calamities of declining life. Many of them acted their part well, and their ever dear and honoured names are "like preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ointment" to poſterity. Much is the debt of gratitude from their children. You have now ſucceeded to their place—to diſcharge that debt, you muſt fill it up uſefully. On this condition, they will not be aſhamed to own you, as their children, hereafter. That you may thus do, and be bleſſed, ſuffer the word of exhortation from him who "lives if ye ſtand faſt in the Lord."</p>
               <p>YOU will ſeriouſly conſider, that the intereſts of this people and of future generations are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved on you, and that you are to give account to God for the important betruſtment. That you may do it with joy, be pleaſed to remember and practiſe the following particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="unknown:024381_0029_0FC639B302DE3CD8"/>
                  <hi>Firſt of all,</hi> "Acquaint yourſelves with God and be at peace with him." To this you are invited, not only by all the motives which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect yourſelves, but alſo on account of your children and poſterity: for what reaſonable hope can be indulged of fidelity, in the education of your children, if you are not faithful to your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves?</p>
               <p>LET it be your firſt care then, to have juſt views of the religion of the bible, and reduce it to practice. True religion as exhibited in the ſcriptures, and exiſting in good men, is a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and conſiſtent whole; conſiſting of various parts, harmoniouſly uniting, and mutually illuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating each other. It is doctrinal, experiment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and practical, and in each of theſe, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nection and dependence, of the parts, on each other, add ſtrength, conſiſtence and beauty to the whole, and prove it to be every way wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of God, and ſuitable to man. Let this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine religion be exemplified in your profeſſion and your lives.</p>
               <p>NEXT to your duty, as individuals, I would intreat you to do honour to chriſtianity, as huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and wives. This will be effected, by living in that conjugal harmony, for which there is every inducement, from perſonal and domeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ic felicity—from the intereſts of poſterity—from this world and the world to come. Then you will "dwell together according to knowledge, and as fellow heirs of the grace of life, and your prayers will not be hindered."<note n="‖" place="bottom">1 Peter iii. 7.</note> In this way, you may be like that excellent pair, of whom
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:024381_0030_0FC639BA74425F48"/>
we have this honourable teſtimony, "that they were both righteous before God, walking in all the commandments and ordinances of the Lord blameleſs."<note n="¶" place="bottom">Luke i. 6.</note> Many are the branches of genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine chriſtianity, or ways of exemplifying its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent nature—they are correſpondent to all our relations to God, and to our fellow-creatures, to ſociety on earth, to this world and the world to come. A right apprehenſion, of its leading principles, will be abundantly uſeful in directing your judgment, and influencing your practice at all times, and in all conditions.</p>
               <p>OUR particular attention is now called to that only, which is the ſubject of this diſcourſe; The education of poſterity.</p>
               <p>MAY I not ſay, in your behalf and my own, that "we have no greater joy than to hear that our children walk in the truth." To parents, as members of ſociety, and as chriſtians; their edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is a leading object. We have received God's teſtimonies from our parents, let us com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to our children. We are eſpecially called to this, on account of their dangerous ſtate, from the circumſtances of the age in which they live. For though we ſhould not "inquire wiſely in aſking why the former days were better than theſe,"<note n="§" place="bottom">Eccleſiaſtes vii. 10.</note> as human nature and the world, are ſubſtantially, the ſame in all ages; there are, however, occaſional differences, important to be regarded in the education of youth. You are not inſenſible, that the preſent age has the marks of degeneracy in ſeveral particulars, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence the manners of the people, the order of
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:024381_0031_0FC639BFA8F3F688"/>
ſociety, and the intereſts of religion. The wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, in families, and in public, and the religious obſervation of the Lord's Day, were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally practiſed by our fathers, and with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency. But what a ſad reverſe has taken place in our day! Numbers, it is to be feared, are not well grounded in the firſt principles of chriſtianity, and are in a condition to become an early prey to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, who would betray them into falſe religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or even to none.</p>
               <p>THIS may, no doubt be traced to ſeveral influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encing cauſes.—But may we not conclude, that one of the greateſt, is the criminal neglect of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parents in the education of their children, and their own bad examples? The children of ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies have an unhappy influence on thoſe who are better taught, and the contagion of vice and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is widely extended; for "man is born like the wild aſſes colt<note n="§" place="bottom">Job xi. 12.</note>," and human nature tends to evil.</p>
               <p>THIS calamitous event of our day, adds a new and important motive to all that have been named, for parental fidelity in the education of children. Their danger is uncommonly great, and we are at leaſt, in part accountable for it.—How highly doth it concern us, to improve the remainder of our life, faithfully, for the good of our children. We wiſh they may grow up to be uſeful and happy in family connections, to be good members of ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to ſerve their generation, to honor their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and Redeemer, tranſmit to their children the principles of virtue and piety, and be prepared for heaven.—That none of theſe important objects
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:024381_0032_0FC639C21CCC1DB8"/>
may be loſt through our neglect, we ſhould "bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord;" that they may know and practice God's teſtimonies, "and ariſe and declare them to their children; that they may ſet their hope in God, and not forget his works, but keep his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Let theſe things be in our hearts, that we may teach them diligently to our children; and talk of them when we ſet in our houſes, and when we walk by the way, and when we lie down, and when we riſe up." Our inſtructions muſt be adapted to their age, capacities, and other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. They muſt be ſupported by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertions of parental authority and love; but above all <hi>by our examples and prayers.</hi> We muſt devote them to God from their earlieſt infancy, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate the dedication by prayer, as long as we live, that the God of our pious progenitors may be their God; and we muſt be in all reſpects, as far as poſſible, what we would wiſh them to be. We muſt walk before them in the path of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which leads to uſefulneſs and felicity on earth, and to glory in Heaven.—Among the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inducements to this, it will be uſeful to recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the inſtructions and example of our pious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; theſe muſt, in ſome inſtances at leaſt, be freſh in our minds. Such recollections muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly ſoften the heart, and the impreſſions of theſe truths will be proportionably deep. What child or parent ever read the following addreſs of the wiſe man to his children, without the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt emotions? "Hear ye children the inſtruction of a father, and attend to know underſtanding. <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> give you good doctrines, forſake you not
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:024381_0033_0FC639C3830EEDB0"/>
my law. <hi>For I was my father's ſon, tender and only beloved in the ſight of my mother. He taught me alſo and ſaid unto me—Let thine heart retain my words, keep my commandments, and live.</hi>"</p>
               <p>THE happy influence of ſuch parental education, was early diſplayed in his choice of wiſdom, in preference to riches and long life<note n="§" place="bottom">1 Kings, iii. 1—14.</note>. And he faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tranſmitted it to poſterity, in the book of proverbs, addreſſed to his children. It remains, that, in our reſpective conditions, we go and do likewiſe.—The remainder of our time, for paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal exertions, is ſhort; many of you like me, are in the advance of life—we ſhall ſoon be ſilent in death.—What we do for our children and poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, muſt be ſpeedily accompliſhed.—The leading motives to fidelity and vigor, in this honorable ſervice have been already conſidered.—You will recollect them.—Let me hope they will ever be preſent to your thoughts, and influence your practice; that if our ſeparation ſhould be near, and I ſhould never more addreſs you on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, I may die, with the joyful proſpect of your fidelity and ſucceſs;—that he who ſowed, and they who reap, may rejoice together.</p>
               <p n="2">II. To the children and youth.</p>
               <p>A FEW words will compriſe the ſubſtance of what I would wiſh to be impreſſed on your hearts. I have little to offer which can be called new; but it is not leſs weighty and intereſting for being old. The text and ſubject are not more impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant to your parents, than to you. If their obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations and motives, reſpecting your education, are ſuch as have been named, yours are propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:024381_0034_0FC639C5C38FB670"/>
to receive their inſtructions, and reduce them to practice. It is for your ſakes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your intereſt is ſo deeply involved, that they are thus obliged. On this depends your felicity and uſefulneſs in this and the future life.</p>
               <p>THE price in your hand to get wiſdom is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly precious; but its continuance is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and at beſt it is ſhort.—If you follow the dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates of a virtuous and truly good education, you will be uſeful and happy on earth, and bleſſed in heaven—God will be your friend and protector here, and your portion forever. But if you deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe the inſtructions of parental piety, it is at your peril; you will be marked for wretchedneſs and reproach on earth, and for aggravated mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery in hell. And you will "mourn at the laſt, and ſay, how have we hated inſtruction, and our hearts deſpiſed reproof? And have not obeyed the voice of our teachers, nor inclined our ear to them that inſtructed us<note n="‖" place="bottom">Proverbs v. 11, 12, 13.</note>."—That this may not be your awful doom, <hi>Remember</hi> that you are the creatures of God—born for immortality—ruined by ſin, and muſt partake of the goſpel ſalvation, or be ruined forever.—Your continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on earth at moſt will be ſhort, much ſhorter than you can, now, readily conceive. The flight of time, is exceedingly rapid. How ſoon have the laſt thirty years paſſed away? and are forever gone!—what changes have theſe thirty years produced?—thoſe who were then the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of the congregation are generally gone—we have ſucceeded in their place, and you in ours.—More than five hundred, of all ages, have
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:024381_0035_0FC639C837EDDF00"/>
died in the ſociety; nearly an equal number of children, at preſent conſtitute our ſchools; as appears from the late viſitation<note n="‖" place="bottom">Thirteen ſchools are annually maintained in the ſociety, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the winter; which are viſited at the cloſe of the ſeaſon, by the paſtor, in company with the civil authority and ſelect-men, to inſpect their manners and inprovement in learning; and their knowledge in the aſſemblies' catechiſm; and to give them inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions adapted to their age and capacity, on the nature and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of early virtue and piety.</note> They will ſoon fill your place—you ours, and we ſhall be gathered to our fathers. The following thirty years will probably be marked with changes as numerous and affecting as thoſe which are paſt. Should you live during thoſe thirty future years, which is much to be doubted, they will be but "a vapour which appears for a little ſeaſon, and then vaniſheth away."</p>
               <p>I GIVE you my beſt wiſhes for time and eternity, with the following ſhort directions: "Remember now your creator in the days of your youth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the evil days come, and the years draw nigh, when you ſhall ſay you have no pleaſure in them." "Fear God, and keep his commandments, for this is the whole duty of man: For God ſhall bring e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very work into judgment, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil<note n="§" place="bottom">Eccleſiaſtes xii. 1, and 13, 14.</note>."—Give ear to good inſtruction from your parents and others—pray for a bleſſing—ſtudy your bibles, eſpecially the book of Proverbs, particularly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted for the benefit of youth—watch and pray againſt temptations, and the deſtructive influence of bad example—ſtrive to be wiſe and good—a bleſſing to your parents, connections and ſociety—to be uſeful to yourſelves and others, and in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs for death and heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="unknown:024381_0036_0FC639CA97280250"/>LET me recommend to your imitation the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of young Joſeph, who rejected the allurements of guilt, with this excellent reflection, "How can I do this great wickedneſs, and ſin againſt God<note n="§" place="bottom">Gen. xxxix. 9.</note>?"—and that of the pious Timothy, who attended to the religious inſtructions of a faithful parent, and, "from childhood knew the holy ſcriptures, which were able to make him wiſe to ſalvation through faith in Chriſt Jeſus<note n="¶" place="bottom">2 Timothy i. v. &amp; iii. 15.</note>;" and whoſe future charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter marks the value of a virtuous education wiſely improved.</p>
               <p>FINALLY, and above all, remember and imitate the example of the bleſſed Jeſus, who at the age of twelve years, engaged the attention, and exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the aſtoniſhment of his moſt learned inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, at his underſtanding and anſwers, "and ſtill was ſubject to his parents; and as he advanced in age and ſtature, increaſed in wiſdom, and in favor with God and with man<note n="‖" place="bottom">Luke ii. 46—52.</note>."</p>
               <p>MAY you live, and be wiſe, uſeful and happy, to a good old age—many years after your parents and miniſter ſhall be gone to their fathers—May you faithfully tranſmit to the children of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing age, the pure religion of the bleſſed Jeſus—May it be perpetuated in this place, through all generations till his ſecond coming—May we meet in heaven, with each other, with our pious anceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors—the children of future ages, and with all the redeemed, and be to the praiſe of divine grace forever. AMEN.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
