<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An oration delivered at Lenox, the 4th July, 1793, the anniversary of American independence. By Elisha Lee, Esq.</title>
            <author>Lee, Elisha, 1757-1835.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-03">2005-03.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N19690</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N19690</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 25713</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX4665</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">25713</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99021444</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 25713.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N19690)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 25713)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 25713)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An oration delivered at Lenox, the 4th July, 1793, the anniversary of American independence. By Elisha Lee, Esq.</title>
                  <author>Lee, Elisha, 1757-1835.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p. ;  20 cm. (4to) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Loring Andrews.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Stockbridge [Mass.]: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M,D,CCXCIII. [1793]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Mr. Lee's oration.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fourth of July orations --  1793.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:025713_0000_0FCF016255770690"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:025713_0001_0FCF0166F84B3588"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ORATION Delivered at LENOX, the 4th July, 1793, the Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary of American Independence.</p>
            <p>By ELISHA LEE, Esq.</p>
            <p>STOCKBRIDGE: Printed by LORING ANDREWS. M, D, CCXCIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="apology">
            <pb facs="unknown:025713_0002_0FCF016939176310"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>—APOLOGY—</head>
            <p>IT was not the intention of the Author to submit the follow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing pages to the publick, through the medium of the Press. A very shor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time intervened, from the notice given him by the Committee appointed to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> arrangements for the celebration of the Anniversary of American Independ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence, of their choice of the person to deliver a publick Address on the occasion to the day on which he was to meet his fellow citizens, for that purpose — The critic will make allowance for ideas thus has<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y arrang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, while the ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ercise of the candour of a very respectable list of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, at whose <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> request the work has been committed to the Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ss, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> doubted.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="unknown:025713_0003_0FCF016AAE726950"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>RESPECTED FRIENDS AND FELLOW CITIZENS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AGREEABLY to arrangements made on the last anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary, by a committee of patriotic gentlemen, we are now c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nvened to celebrate the auspicious day that gave b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rth to the liberty of Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ca. Seventeen years have this day elapsed since the declaration of her INDEPENDENCE.</p>
            <p>From the multiplicity of objects, which, upon this interesting occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, force themselves upon the imagination, what choice for your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rtainment shall be made by the speaker? Shall he trace the more hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and remote, or point out the immediate causes of the event, which we celebrate? Shall he pronounce a panegyric upon the ardent and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roic spirit of our countrymen, who were the immediate actors? Shall he recapitulate the consequences which have resulted from the revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on, or, with a prophetic enthusiasm, anticipate those which yet may ensue in the future happiness of our country?</p>
            <p>When I look around upon an audience so numerous and respectable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> when I consider the novelty of my own situation, and the arduous task assigned me, I feel a diffidence, which I cannot conceal. When I re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>flect that the INDEPENDENCE of America has annually been th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eme of the learned orator, and experienced Statesman, shall I not de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ir of furnishing any thing, either new or entertaining? But I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eved from this embarrassment, by a reliance on the candor of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tory, who will reflect that the performance is designed for their grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cation: I am encouraged by a belief that the emancipation of our country, and the freedom of man, will never be too often the subjects of popular applause, nor ever bec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e uninteresting to the PATRIOT and PHILANTHROPHIST.</p>
            <p>If we consider the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to the establishment of American INDEPEND<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not overlook the character of our ancestors, or the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> their emigration from Europe. The rage for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the reign of the first JAMES, resulting from his bigotted att<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hment to the <hi>hierarchy,</hi> and the penal laws made against non-conformists, were the immediate causes of the
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:025713_0004_0FCF016C1597E4A0"/>
first settlements in America. Men, whose minds had but just been libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rated from the shackles of the Papal tyranny, and whose hearts wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> impressed with the awful dignity and sublime simplicity of the sacre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> writings, (not long before committed to their hands,) were fired wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> indignation at such severe restraints. Unable to escape the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sh of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> penal laws, and ardently desirous of establishing a <hi>pure church,</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> formed the adventurous project of withdrawing from their native coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>try, and of settling in the wilds of America.</p>
            <p>Perhaps there is no passion, which rouses the human mind to such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> height of <hi>magnanimity</hi> and <hi>heroism,</hi> as the indignation, which religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> enthusiasm feels, under the scourge of oppression.</p>
            <p>The love of religious and civil LIBERTY is intimately, and necessaril<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> allied: Our ancestors, who first settled in America, keenly felt thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> united force; and, during the progress of their arduous undertaking<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> stood in need of all their inspiration.</p>
            <p>The very great equality in the circumstances of the first emigrant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and the natural independence inspired by a situation at the distance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> three thousand miles from the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent country, were favourable to civi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> liberty. The same period, too, which, during half a century, saw a vio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lent contest between the <hi>rights</hi> of the people and the <hi>prerogatives</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Crown, furnished new emigrations to America. These consisted o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men, who were universally the partizans of LIBERTY.</p>
            <p>The forms of government which were established by the colonists were in a high degree democratical. A division of the legislative pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, in imita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of the British Constitution, was very generally and judi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ciously retained. At the same time an <hi>hereditary order</hi> of nobility, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>unequal, unnatural,</hi> and <hi>absurd</hi> arrangements for the election of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> members of the British House of Commons were, from obvious causes with equal propriety discarded.</p>
            <p>In addition to the circumstances already mentioned, calculated, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may observe, to inspire our ancestors with rational ideas of Liberty, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preparing the way to INDEPENDENCE, some of their civil institutions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> covered the highest wisdom, and conduced directly to the same illustriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> event. As a proof of the justice of this remark, need I mention th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>parceling</hi> the country into small <hi>towns</hi> and <hi>districts; giving</hi> to the inh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>bitants of each <hi>corporate powers</hi> and <hi>privileges; obliging</hi> them to <hi>est<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>blish</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="unknown:025713_0005_0FCF0171E6D5F888"/>
and <hi>support</hi> SCHOOLS for the education of youth, and to <hi>settle</hi> and <hi>maintain</hi> teachers of morality and religion? These institutions, which obtained more especially in New-England, diffused among the whole body of the people, a greater degree of <hi>useful, moral</hi> and <hi>political</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege than, perhaps, ever before existed among the people of any other coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry.</p>
            <p>The war, which broke out in the year 1755, and which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>promised by the treaty of Paris hastened on this gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rious EVENT. Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t war, the principal seat of which was in America, the number and ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtions of the colonial troops gave the parent country an exalted opinion of our wealth, population and resources. The conduct of that war, under the auspices of the immortal CHATHAM, was the most glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the British annals; but its conclusion left the nation emcumbered with an immense addition to her debt. Hence originated the <hi>system</hi> of American taxation—To carry this <hi>system</hi> into execution, there ensued a <hi>black</hi> catalogue of oppressive measures, taken up injudiciously and upon slight consideration, la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d aside upon the appearance of opposition, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priciously reassumed, and eventually, with a fatal blindness and obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, pursued, from the <hi>era</hi> of the <hi>Stamp Act</hi> to the final di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of the empire.</p>
            <p>Upon this occasion, and before the gentlemen who are now present, a ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ification of the opposi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of America to that iniquitous <hi>system,</hi> would be unn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cessary, pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>haps impert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nent—The claim on the part of Great Britain of a parliamentary power to levy taxes without the consent of the Colonies, and to bind them in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ases whatever, was a palpable devia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from every principle of reason and justice, and a pointed violation of the <hi>chartered</hi> rights of the Colonists, and of the spirit of the British consti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. To have made such claim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> required the <hi>unprincipled wantonness</hi> of power, to have acquiesced in it, the <hi>baseness</hi> and <hi>timidity</hi> of slaves. These belonged not to Americans. They opposed every appearance of the exercise of that claim, with a <hi>firmness</hi> and <hi>unanimity,</hi> which n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thing but the most enlightened attention to their rights, and a sacred regard for their prese<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vation, could have ensured.</p>
            <p>More than eighteen years have now circled through the heavens, since the blood of brethren was first spilt in the guilty contest that ensued; since <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate withdrew the gilded curtain from the <hi>villain</hi> despotism, and
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:025713_0006_0FCF017443B8DD98"/>
pointed the indignation of astonished man against the <hi>author</hi> of his poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical misery! —Upon thy clouded b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow, O LEXINGTON, on that event<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful day, hovered the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>NIUS of EMPIRE, and the DESTINY of MAN! The remembrance of that day, when thy green bosom was sprinkled with the blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of thy sons, is like the shock of the lightning, like the inspiration of a divinity!</p>
            <p>The commencement of hostilities animated the freemen of America, with one soul. Whilst <hi>imagination</hi> fails in the attempt to paint that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r of enthusiasm, which from Saint-Croix to St. Mary, agitated the bosom of America; PHILOSOPHY will forever, with exultation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect the dignifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d proceedings of the American CON<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ESS, and with a sacred pride, hold them up, for the imitation of future ages—So great fortitude in the midst of dangers, such cool and temperate fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mness in the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st alarming and tumultuous periods, such candor and sob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iety triumphing over the phrenzy of passion, in no <hi>deliberative bodies,</hi> of other ages or countries, were before ever exhibited!</p>
            <p>The situation of America, from the commencement of hostilities to the public declaration of INDEPENDENCE, was a <hi>solecism</hi> in the history of political revolutions. The whole continent rung with the din of arms hostile to the invading troops; but the people had not yet contemplated the idea of a separation from Great Britain. The Congress pursued the most spirited measures for the prosecution of a defensive war; and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t they presented to his British Majesty a humble and loyal petition for the redress of grievances.</p>
            <p>This petition, to the perpetual disgrace of British politics and huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, was treated with indignity. Contracts were entered into for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hire of <hi>German mercenaries.</hi> Measures the most <hi>irritating</hi> and <hi>alarming</hi> were adopted by the British administration. The consequence was such as might reasonably have been expected; the eyes of America were opened to see the natural issue of such a contest, and the dream of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nciliation was dispelled. The idea of petitioning with one hand, whilst the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er brandished the sword of defiance, was finally di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>carded. The propriety also of streng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hening the cause of America, with foreign alliances, early occurred To negocia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e these with any probability of success, required a renunciation on the part of America of all political connection with Great Britain.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="unknown:025713_0007_0FCF01751FB30D20"/>The ERA had now arrived, for the establishment of the EMPIRE of LIBERTY, in the NEW WORLD.</p>
            <p>The GENERAL CONGRESS, on the ever memorable fourth of July, in the year 1776,
"appealing to the SUPREME JUDGE of the world for the rectitude of their intentions, solemnly published and declared that the United Colonies were, and of right ought to be, <hi>free</hi> and INDEPEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DENT STATES; and that they were absolved from all allegiance to the <hi>British Crown.</hi> And for the support of this declaration, with a firm re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance upon the protection of Divine Providence, they mutually pledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to each other their lives, their fortunes, and their sacred honor."</p>
            <p>The remembrance of that august transaction we now celebrate. This day, this glorious day, by the united voice of the millions of America, is dedicated to the exultations of PATRIOTISM, the triumphs of LIBERTY, and to <hi>gratitude</hi> to HEAVEN!</p>
            <p>The sacred "<hi>pledge</hi>" of American "<hi>honor</hi>" was not forfeited; her
"reliance upon the protection of Divine Providence,"
was not in vain; and the Supreme Judge of the world, to whom she had appealed, justifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d
"the rectitude of her intentions,"
by accomplishing, after an eight years war, the object for which she had fought!</p>
            <p>The most illustrious actors on that theatre of honor, have survived the storm of war; they enjoy the rewards of patriotism, in the highest offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the government; they still continue to bless their country.— Whilst the names of WASHINGTON, ADAMS, and HAMILTON, give a lustre and dignity to virtue; dear to America, and forever sacred be the memory of THOSE, who fought and bled in so righteous a cause.</p>
            <p>Are not the spirits of MERCER, MONTGOMERY, and WARREN, from the regions of immortality, looking down, with the sublimest transport, on the present felicities of their country? Do I not hear a celestial choir chanting that consolatary Ode
"Tis delightful, tis honorable, to die for our country."
<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Horace.</hi>
               </note> Others, who lived to see the cause of Liberty crowned with glorious success, have since taken the highest stand in the TEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLE of FAME. There a splendid wreath of military honor encircles the brow of GREEN; and SCIENCE, rejoicing in the acquisitions of her em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and HUMANITY, brightening with new irradiations of benevolence, minister to the immortal spirit of FRANKLIN.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="unknown:025713_0008_0FCF0176DAB5DC30"/>The magnitude of the American revolution, and the consequent hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness of our country, deserve our attention—America, from a state of undefined dependence on Great Britain, has assumed an illustrious rank among the nations of the Earth. Her trade, no longer the monopoly of a single foreign nation, has extended itself to every quarter of the globe. Mercantile enterprize, no longer restricted, has penetrated the remotest regions. The Baltic and the Mediterranean, the Brazils and the Bay o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hudson, China and the Indies, the immense Eastern and Pacific Oceans, are witnesses of our commerce.</p>
            <p>Whilst our citizens have enriched themselves, by their commercial industry, the means have been furnished, by the most imperceptible spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of taxation, to establish funds adequate to all the objects of national justice and policy. The permanent resources of our country, constitut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the common stock of the happiness and enjoyments of our citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, in their hands rema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n untouched: These await her call, if any great occasion should render them necessary.</p>
            <p>America, from her fortunate situation, and from the mild spirit of the government, is a stranger to that system of <hi>war</hi> and <hi>taxes,</hi> of <hi>ambition</hi> and <hi>misery,</hi> which is the scourge of Europe, and which subjects to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremest wretchedness nine tenths of her inhabitants:</p>
            <l>Where "one man,</l>
            <l>Compounded and made up like other men</l>
            <l>Of elements tumultuous, in whom lust</l>
            <l>And folly, in as ample measures meet,</l>
            <l>As in the bosoms of the slaves he rules,</l>
            <l>Becomes a despot absolute, and boasts</l>
            <l>Himself the only freeman of his land;</l>
            <l>And when he pleases, and on whom he wills,</l>
            <l>Makes war, with any, or with no pretence</l>
            <l>Of provocation given, or wrong sustained;</l>
            <l>Forces the beggarly last doit, by means</l>
            <l>That his own humour dictates, from the clutch</l>
            <l>Of poverty, that thus he may procure</l>
            <l>His thousands, weary of penurious life,</l>
            <l>A <hi>splendid</hi> opportunity to <hi>die!</hi>" <note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Cooper's Poems.</hi>
               </note>
            </l>
            <pb n="11" facs="unknown:025713_0009_0FCF017E8F4178C8"/>
            <p>To a system so replete with <hi>debasement</hi> and <hi>misery,</hi> may America for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever continue a stranger!</p>
            <p>The encrease of our population, and the extension of our settlements, have been still more considerable than the growth of our commerce. The circumstances relative to this subject, which will not fail to astonish posterity, can neither pass unnoticed, or unadmired by the present ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eration. History furnishes us with nothing similar to the amazing oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urrences which in this regard are taking place in America. That a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ountry of such extent as the United States, should, in a period little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onger than a century and an half, be converted from a <hi>wilderness</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ered with forests, into the <hi>busy haunts</hi> of men, is a spectacle never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore presented to human observation. The enquirers into the ancient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opulation of <hi>Europe,</hi> have doubted whether the number of her inhabit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts have greatly increased within the last two thousand years. The <hi>small <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epublics</hi> of Greece were founded many ages before the time of Solon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Lycurgus; <hi>Italy</hi> also saw a long period intervene between the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of Rome and the establishment of the consular power: And yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any cen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uries elapsed after the times last mentioned, before those <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ute regions</hi> became generally occupied by the genuine Greeks and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans. In <hi>America,</hi> since the commencement of the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, a million souls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave been added to our population; within the same period a country <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s extensive as the Island of Great Britain has been covered with people! The eastern counties of our own Commonwealth, the northern counties of New-Hampshire, Pennsylvania, and Vermont, the western districts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f New-York, and the back country of the Southern States, will amply <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rove the truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f this remark.</p>
            <p>Within the last eighteen years the GENIUS of CULTIVATION <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as explored his way over the <hi>appallachian hills,</hi> descended into the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le regions on the <hi>Ohio</hi> and <hi>Mississipi,</hi> and conducted to the bosom of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat <hi>delightful wilderness</hi> more than SEVENTY THOUSAND inhabit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants—In consequence of the American Revolution, political knowledge has emerged from her state of pupilage, and directed her attention to its most deserving object, the equal happiness of all men.</p>
            <p>The doctrine of an equality of rights, as founded in nature and the reason of things, has been vindicated. The system of representative <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>overnments, ground<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d on the choice of the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ple, as the legitimate
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:025713_0010_0FCF01781EBA60F8"/>
source of authority, has extended itself, and been more firmly establish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed. The right of a people to alter the forms of their governments, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to establish new ones, whenever it becomes necessary to their politic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> happiness, has received the fortunate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anction of American experience.</p>
            <p>The animating principles of civil Liberty have not been confined <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> America. The FIRE that was kindled here, and which spread its <hi>sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tary light</hi> over the NEW-WORLD, has beamed its rays on the EAST<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ERN HEMISPHERE, and <hi>burns</hi> in Europe. During the last ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a spark was struck out by the collision of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> France: This had not become extinct at the period of the America<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> war. The French troops, who fought in America, returned to Europ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>advocates</hi> of freedom. PHILOSOPHY too raised her piercin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> voice, and <hi>despotism</hi> trembled for his fate. A new order of things com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>menced in France, and we have seen the immense fabricks of <hi>religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> superstition</hi> and <hi>civil tyranny,</hi> swept away with the besom of destruction.</p>
            <p>Whilst the enlightened sons of FREEDOM, and the children <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> BENEVOLENCE have compassionated the groans of their oppresse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brethren, whilst with transport they have seen the <hi>debasing corruptions</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the old world shirink at the <hi>regenerating touch</hi> of LIBERTY, and a ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vista opening into future times, for the happiness of men; Ah! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve their souls been sickened with the <hi>sad reverse!</hi> How weeps HU<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>MANITY the outrages she endures!</p>
            <p>O, LOUIS! thou mildest monarch of a race of Kings, the SWOR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which thou heldest out for the defence of American Liberty, hath <hi>pier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed</hi> thy generous heart! LIBERTY is wounded by the atrocity of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>unworthy</hi> fate—INDIGNANT JUSTICE has flown from the <hi>unha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed</hi> scene—and <hi>anarchy</hi> and <hi>assassination</hi> are prowling o'er thy tomb!</p>
            <p>The flame of Liberty, which in America was mild and benign, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> France has become a Volcano of fire, that threatens to bury in one pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>miscuous ruin the monuments of <hi>despotism,</hi> and all the works of <hi>civiliz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In America, justice, moderation, order and religion disdained not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> follow in the train of Liberty: in France—But perhaps I am entering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dangerous ground: Perhaps a revolution from the ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emes of <hi>Arbitra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Power,</hi> to the fair mid-way region of temperate LIBERTY, without vibration towards <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Licentiousness</hi> is imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ssible. Whilst <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="unknown:025713_0011_0FCF01812773EA20"/>
our speculations are confounded amidst the contradictory variety of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropean information, there is perhaps but one point at which it is safe to rest. If the renovation of France be the design of heaven, it will not <hi>ultimately</hi> be defeated, neither by the crimes of the daemoniacs of Paris, nor by the efforts of a <hi>confederacy,</hi> the most extensive and formidable, that ever astonished mankind.</p>
            <p>Whilst Europe is involved in the horrors and devastations of war, AMERICA is reposing in the calm <hi>sunshine</hi> of PEACE; her <hi>prosperity,</hi> the <hi>envy,</hi> and her GOVERNMENT the <hi>ambition,</hi> of the eastern world. To trace the vestiges of so unparralleled a progress in the career of glory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd happiness, is beyond the scope of the present address. A single <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ketch is all that can be expected.</p>
            <p>The dissolution of the Colonial governments, at the time of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Independence, was followed by the establishment of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions chosen by the citizens of the respective Colonies—Each Colony became an independent republic—To combine these in one general union, articles of <hi>confederation</hi> were adopted—By virtue of these arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, the federal representatives were invested with little more than a mere nominal power, or the authority of recommendation—The <hi>pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure</hi> of the war, and the <hi>enthusiasm</hi> of Liberty, produced a patriotism and unanimity which superseded the necessity of energetic laws, and conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the weakness of the Federal Government. Upon the conclusion of the war, the debility of this system became palpable.</p>
            <p>America was threatened with a universal disorganization. The <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentions</hi> and <hi>jealousies,</hi> the <hi>interested politics,</hi> and <hi>wild anarchy</hi> of the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Republics, were about to be repeated on the great theatre of Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica. In this gloomy eclipse of the hopes of our country, a light sprung up from the midst of darkness. The CONSTITUTION of the Unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed States was formed by a Convention of the most illustrious characters, and adopted by the citizens of the respective states. To this <hi>source,</hi> we trace the present happiness of America. This <hi>event</hi> forms another glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ERA, in the history of our country. The leading speculations of gloomy politicians, on this subject, have been convicted of sophistry, by the irresistable light of truth and experience—Under the AUSPICI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUS ADMINISTRATION of this CONSTITUTION, have we not seen the accomplishment of all the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, for which it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed?
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:025713_0012_0FCF017A34D5BDD8"/>
Have we not seen a <hi>more perfect union formed, justice established, domestic tranquility ensured, and the general welfare</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>YES! all America, in the particulars I have men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ioned, realizes the most important blessings—<hi>Disorder</hi> and <hi>confusion</hi> have fled beyond the Atlantic Ocean—The <hi>daemon insurrection,</hi> divested of his savage nature, has assumed the mild virtues of humanity, and become a pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of ORDER—PUBLIC CREDIT has obtained a glorious resurrection; and the hearts of the war-worn soldier, and of the destitute widow and orphan, have been made to sing for joy.</p>
            <p>An Eulogy upon the FISCAL ARRANGEMENTS, and other great and wise measures of the Congress, since the adoption of the CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STITUTION, is superfluous;—Their highest praise is written in the most SPLENDID CHARACTERS, on the WHOLE FACE of our country; it is painted in the most <hi>amiable colours,</hi> on the HAPPINESS and PROSPERITY of all our citizens!</p>
            <p>Yes, my respected auditors, amidst the convulsions and miseries of Europe, every true friend of America finds new motives of attachment to his country—Where shall we find a region blest with so great natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral advantages? Where shall we discover so much <hi>useful knowledge</hi> and <hi>information</hi> so <hi>equally,</hi> so universally diffused, amongst all classes of the people? look thro' every quarter of the globe, examine the history of all past ages, where shall we find an example of equal happiness and prosperity enjoyed by any other people on the earth?</p>
            <p>Whilst the face of our country, under the improving hand of agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culture, brightens with smiles, and the wilderness blossoms like the rose; whilst industry is sure of the reward of opulence, and enterprise opens a thousand avenues to wealth; whilst the hearts of all our citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens are filled with food and gladness, and the cherub health, with that rosy bloom which
"Nature's fair and cunning hand laid on" <note n="¶" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Shakespear.</hi>
               </note>
Gives the highest relish to every enjoyment; have we not reason to love our country?</p>
            <p>Whilst the fabric of our government unites with the bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ssings of LI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERTY, the dignity of ORDER, and the energy of POWER; whilst
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:025713_0013_0FCF018359985288"/>
impartial justice administers the laws, in protecting innocence, and guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the acquisitions of industry; whilst the rights of nature are secured from the ravages of <hi>anarchy</hi> and the grasp of <hi>oppression</hi>; have we not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to venerate that government?</p>
            <p>YES, my fellow citizens, we LOVE our COUNTRY; we GLORY in her CONSTITUTION; and we HONOUR her illustrious AD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MINISTRATORS!</p>
            <p>Let <hi>haggard envy</hi> calumniate those virtues which she cannot imitate: Let <hi>anarchy,</hi> under the semblance of PATRIOTISM, bellow his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions of the dangers of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>BERTY, whilst he conceals a <hi>poignard</hi> to stab her to the heart: We know their <hi>false</hi> and <hi>hollow</hi> voice; their malice shall not disturb our tranquility: We respect those VIRTUES which have dignified our COUNTRY<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Whilst, on this occasion, we celebrate the commencement of AME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RICAN LIBERTY, to secure the perpetuity of HER reign, let us rally around the standards of order, stability, and obedience to the laws. Let PEACE and GOOD WILL towards men be the scope of HER <hi>ambition,</hi> and the badge of HER <hi>distinction,</hi> and we may hope that her EMPIRE will be IMMORTAL<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
