<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Columbia: An ode.</title>
            <author>Dwight, Timothy, 1752-1817.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N20523</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N20523</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 26923</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX6432</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">26923</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99023244</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 26923.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N20523)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 26923)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 26923)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Columbia: An ode.</title>
                  <author>Dwight, Timothy, 1752-1817.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : music ; 21 x 20 cm. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John M'Culloch?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Philadelphia? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1794?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Song in six stanzas; first verse, printed with music, begins: Columbia! Columbia! to glory arise.</note>
                  <note>"Columbia was written and set to music by [Timothy] Dwight in 1777, while he was serving as chaplain in General Parsons brigade of Connecticut Volunteers."--Wolfe, R.J. Secular music, 2641.</note>
                  <note>The ode was sung during commencement exercises at the Young Ladies' Academy of Philadelphia on Dec. 18, 1794. Cf. Neal, James Armstrong. An essay on the education and genius of the female sex. To which is added, an account of the commencement ... Philadelphia, 1795, p. 24-26. Evans suggests that the ode was printed by John M'Culloch of Philadelphia, a noted printer of music at this time.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>National songs.</term>
               <term>Broadsides.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="music">
            <pb facs="unknown:026923_0000_10137398FA911A60"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:026923_0001_10136B5DDE7758D0"/>
            <head>
               <hi>COLUMBIA:</hi> An <hi>Ode.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>COLUMBIA! COLUMBIA! to glory ariſe, The queen of the world and the child of the ſkies: Thy genius commands thee, with raptures behold, <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>While ages on ages thy ſplendor unfold. Thy reign is the laſt &amp; the nobleſt of time; Moſt fruitful thy ſoil, moſt inviting thy clime: Let the crimes of the eaſt ne'er in- <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>crimſon <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſcience, and virtue thy fame; and virtue thy fame; and virtue thy fame. Be freed<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>To conqueſt and ſlaughter let Europe aſpire,</l>
               <l>Whelm nations in blood and wrap cities in fire;</l>
               <l>Thy heroes the rights of mankind ſhall defend,</l>
               <l>And triumph purſue them, and glory attend.</l>
               <l>A world is thy realm, for a world be thy laws</l>
               <l>Enlarg'd as thy empire, and juſt as thy cauſe:</l>
               <l>On Freedom's broad baſis thy empire ſhall riſe—</l>
               <l>Extend with the main, and diſſolve with the ſkies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fair Science her gates to thy ſons ſhall unbar,</l>
               <l>The eaſt ſee thy morn hide the beams of her ſtar;</l>
               <l>New bards and new ſages, unrivall'd, ſhall ſoar</l>
               <l>To fame, unextinguiſh'd when time is no more.</l>
               <l>To thee, the laſt refuge for virtue deſign'd,</l>
               <l>Shall fly, from all nations, the beſt of mankind;</l>
               <l>Here, grateful to Heav'n, with tranſport ſhall bring</l>
               <l>Their incenſe, more fragrant than odours of ſpring.—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor leſs ſhall thy FAIR ONES to glory aſcend,</l>
               <l>And genius and beauty in harmony blend;</l>
               <l>The graces of form ſhall awake pure deſire,</l>
               <l>And the charms of the ſoul ſtill enliven the fire:</l>
               <l>Their ſweetneſs unmingled, their manners refin'd,</l>
               <l>And virtue's bright image impreſt on their mind,</l>
               <l>With peace and ſoft rapture ſhall teach life to glow,</l>
               <l>And light up a ſmile in the aſpect of woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy fleets to all regions thy pow'r ſhall diſplay—</l>
               <l>The nations admire, and the ocean obey;</l>
               <l>Each ſhore to thy glory its tribute unfold—</l>
               <l>And the eaſt and the ſouth yield their ſpices and gold.</l>
               <l>As the day-ſpring, unbounded, thy ſplendor ſhall <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ow,</l>
               <l>And earth's mighty kingdoms before thee ſhall bow;</l>
               <l>While the enſigns of union, in triumph unfurl'd,</l>
               <l>Huſh tumults of war, and give peace to the world.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus as down a lone valley, with cedars o'er-ſpread,</l>
               <l>From war's dread confuſion, I penſively ſtray'd,</l>
               <l>The gloom from the face of fair heav'n retir'd;</l>
               <l>The winds ceas'd to murmur, the thunders expir'd.</l>
               <l>Perfumes, as of Eden, flow'd ſweetly along,</l>
               <l>And a voice, as of angels, enchantingly ſung—</l>
               <l>COLUMBIA! COLUMBIA! to glory ariſe,</l>
               <l>The queen of the world, and the child of the ſkies.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
