<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The political progress of Britain; or, An impartial history of abuses in the government of the British Empire, in Europe, Asia, and America, from the Revolution in 1688, to the present time. The whole tending to prove the ruinous consequences of the popular system of taxation, war, and conquest. : [One line of quotation]</title>
            <title>Political progress of Britain</title>
            <author>Callender, James Thomson, 1758-1803.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N21591</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N21591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 28380</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APY1854</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">28380</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99028929</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 28380.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N21591)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 28380)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 28380)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The political progress of Britain; or, An impartial history of abuses in the government of the British Empire, in Europe, Asia, and America, from the Revolution in 1688, to the present time. The whole tending to prove the ruinous consequences of the popular system of taxation, war, and conquest. : [One line of quotation]</title>
                  <title>Political progress of Britain</title>
                  <author>Callender, James Thomson, 1758-1803.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4, [1], 4-71, [1] p. ;  21 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.T. Callender.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1795]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 4, 1st count: James Thomson Callender, an exile for writing this pamphlet, Philadelphia, March 31, 1795.</note>
                  <note>"The matter of this edition does not correspond with Folwell's edition (Evans 28379) except in places here and there."--Evans.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  18th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Colonies --  Administration.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:028380_0000_0FD8DEF31702F9D8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:028380_0001_0FDA797520045D88"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE POLITICAL PROGRESS OF BRITAIN; OR, AN IMPARTIAL HISTORY OF <hi>ABUSES in the GOVERNMENT</hi> OF THE <hi>Britiſh Empire,</hi> IN EUROPE, ASIA, AND AMERICA, FROM THE REVOLUTION IN 1688, TO THE PRESENT TIME.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The whole tending to prove the ruinous Conſequences of the popular Syſtem</hi> Or TAXATION, WAR, AND CONQUEST.</p>
            <p>"THE WORLD'S MAD BUSINESS."</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PHILADELPHIA:</hi> PRINTED FOR J. T. CALLENDER.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="unknown:028380_0002_0FD8BE735868F278"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE Firſt Edition of <hi>The Political Progreſs of Britain</hi> was publiſhed at Edinburgh and London, in Autumn, 1792. The ſale was lively, and the proſpect of future ſucceſs flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The plan was, to give an impartial hiſtory of the abuſes in government, in a ſeries of pamphlets. But while the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor was preparing for the preſs, a ſecond number, along with a new edition of the firſt, he was, on the 2d of January, 1793, apprehended, and with ſome difficulty made his eſcape. Two bookſellers, who acted as his editors, were proſecuted; and after a very arbitrary trial, they were condemned, the one to three months, and the other to ſix months of impriſonment. A revolution will take place in Scotland before the lapſe of ten years at fartheſt, and moſt likely much ſooner. The Scots nation will then certainly think itſelf bound, by every tie of wiſdom, of gratitude, and of juſtice, to make reparation to theſe two honeſt men, for the tyranny which they have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered in the cauſe of truth. In Britain, authors and editors of pamphlets have long conducted the van of every revolution. They compoſe a kind of forlorn hope on the ſkirts of battle: and though they may often want experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or influence, to marſhal the main body, they yet enjoy the honour and the danger of the firſt rank, in ſtorming the ramparts of oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>A copy of the firſt edition was handed to Mr. Jefferſon, late American Secretary of State. He ſpoke of it, on diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent occaſions, in reſpectful terms. <q>He ſaid that it contained the moſt aſtoniſhing concentration of abuſes that he had ever heard of in any government.</q> He inquired, why it was not printed in America? and ſaid, that he, for one, would gladly become a purchaſer. Other gentlemen have delivered their opinions to the ſame effect; and their encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement was one cauſe for the appearance of this Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can edition.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="unknown:028380_0003_0FD8BE750EFE2A50"/>The work is intended for that claſs of people who has not much time to ſpend in reading, and who wants a plain but ſubſtantial meal of political information. The facts are, therefore, crowded together as cloſely as poſſible. All the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetry of authorſhip has been avoided. The ambition of the writer was to be candid, unaffected, and intelligible; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe truth is the baſis of ſound argument, ſimplicity the ſoul of elegance, and perſpicuity the ſupreme touch-ſtone of accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate compoſition.</p>
            <p>A report was circulated, and believed, in Scotland, that this production came, in reality, from the pen of one of the judges of the court of ſeſſion. The charge was unjuſt. His lordſhip did not write a ſingle page of it; but he ſaid openly, that its contents were authentic, and unanſwerable; and that the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic were welcome to call it his.</p>
            <p>For the extreme raſhneſs of his plan, the writer can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not offer an apology that prudence will accept. A ſhort ſtory may, perhaps, convey the motives of his conduct. In 1758, the Duke of Marlborough, with eighteen thouſand men landed on the coaſt of France. The troops, when diſembarking, were oppoſed by a French battery, which was immediately ſilenced, for it conſiſted only of an old man, armed with two muſkets; he was ſlightly wounded in the leg, and made priſoner. The Engliſh aſked him, whether he expected that his two muſkets were to ſilence the fire of their fleet? "Gentlemen," he replied, <q>I have done only my duty, and if all my countrymen here had acted like me, you would not this day have landed a Concale.</q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JAMES THOMSON CALLENDER, <hi>An Exile for writing this Pamphlet.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 31, 1795.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="unknown:028380_0004_0FD8DE475DB15180"/>
            <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>WITHIN the laſt hundred years of our hiſtory, Britain has been five times at war with France, and ſix times at war with Spain. During the ſame period, ſhe has been engaged in two rebellions at home, beſides an endleſs catalogue of maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres in Aſia and America. In Europe, the common price which we advance for a war, has extended from one to three hundred thouſand lives, and from ſixty to an hundred and fifty millions ſterling. From Africa, we import annually between thirty and forty thouſand ſlaves, which riſes in the courſe of a century to at leaſt three millions of murthers. In Bengal only, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed or expelled, within the ſhort period of ſix years, no leſs than five millions of induſtrious and harmleſs people <note n="*" place="bottom">Infra, chap. 1.</note>; and as we have been ſovereigns in that country, for above thirty-five years, it may be reaſonably computed that we have ſtrewed the plains of Indoſtan with fifteen or twenty millions of carcaſes. If we combine the diverſified ravages of famine, peſtilence, and the ſword, it can hardly be ſuppoſed, that in theſe tranſactions leſs than fifteen hundred thouſand of our countrymen have pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed; a number equal to that of the whole inhabitants of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain who are at preſent able to bear arms. In Europe, the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock of our antagoniſts has been at leaſt not inferior to our own, ſo that this quarter of the world alone has loſt by our quarrels, three millions of men in the flower of life; whoſe deſcendants, in the progreſs of domeſtic ſociety, would have ſwelled into multitudes beyond calculation. The perſons poſitively deſtroyed muſt, in the whole, have exceeded twenty millions, or two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand acts of homicide <hi>per annum.</hi> Theſe victims have been ſacrificed to the balance of power, and the balance of trade, the honour of the Britiſh flag, the univerſal ſupremacy of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:028380_0005_0FD8DE48DFC5B290"/>
and the ſecurity of the Proteſtant ſucceſſion. If we are to proceed at this rate for another century, we may, which is natural to mankind, admire ourſelves, and our atchievements, but every other nation in the world muſt have a right to wiſh that an earthquake or a volcano may firſt bury both iſlands to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the centre of the globe; that a ſingle, but deciſive ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ortion of Almighty vengeance may terminate the progreſs and the remembrance of our crimes.</p>
            <p>In the ſcale of juſt calculation, the moſt valuable commodity, next to human blood, is money. Having made a groſs eſtimate of the deſtruction of the former, let us endeavour to compute the conſumption of the latter. The war of 1689 coſt ſixty mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of public money, and at the end of it, the public debts amounted to twenty millions, or by another account<note n="*" place="bottom">Memoirs of Britain and Ireland, vol. ii.</note>, to be ſeventeen millions and a half; ſo that not more than one third part of the expences were <hi>borrowed.</hi> In Queen Anne's war, forty or fifty millions ſterling were alſo ſunk in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, beſides about thirty millions, which were added to the former public debt. Very large ſums have ſince been abſorbed in other wars, over and above thoſe which were placed to the national credit. In 1783, by the report of the commiſſioners of public accounts, the total debts of Britain extended to two hundred and ſeventy-nine millions, ſix hundred and ninety-eight thouſand pounds, though many millions have been paid off in time of peace, by what is called the ſinking fund. Hence we ſee, that this ſum of <hi>two hundred and ſeventy-nine millions</hi> is much inferior to the actual charges of theſe wars. The total amount may be fixed ſomewhere perhaps between four and ſix hundred millions. To this we muſt ſubjoin the value of ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen or twenty thouſand merchant ſhips taken by the enemy. This diminutive article of ſixty or an hundred millions would have been ſufficient for tranſporting and ſettling eight or twelve hundred thouſand farmers, with their families, on the banks of the Potowmack or the Miſſiſſipi. By the report above quoted, we learn, that in 1789, the intereſt of our public debts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:028380_0006_0FD8DE4A9ABD0050"/>
to nine millions, and five hundred thouſand pounds, which is equivalent to an annual tax of twenty ſhillings <hi>per</hi> head, on every inhabitant of Britain. The friends of our intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and reſpectable miniſter, Mr. Pitt, make an infinite buſtle about the nine millions of debt which his ingenuity has diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged. They ought to arrange, in an oppoſite column, a liſt of the additional taxes which have been impoſed, and of the myriads of families, whom ſuch taxes have ruined. At beſt, we are but as a perſon transferring his money from the right pocket to the left. Perhaps a Chancellor of the Exchequer might as well propoſe to empty the Baltick with a tobacco-pipe. Had the war with America laſted for two years longer, Britain would not at this day have owed a ſhilling; and if we ſhall perſiſt in ruſhing into carnage, with our former contempt of all feeling and reflection, it may ſtill be expected that, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the practice of other nations, a ſponge or a bonfire will finiſh the game of funding.</p>
            <p>What advantage has reſulted to Britain from ſuch inceſſant ſcenes of prodigality and of bloodſhed? In the wars of 1689, and 1702, this country was neither more nor leſs than an hobby horſe for the Emperor and the Dutch. The rebellion in 1715 was excited by the deſpotic inſolence of the Whigs. The pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of Bremen and Verden produced the Spaniſh war of 1718, and a ſquadron diſpatched for ſix different years to the Baltick. Such exertions coſt us an hundred times more than thoſe quag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire Dutchies are worth, even to the Elector of Hanover; a diſtinction which on this buſineſs becomes neceſſary, for as to Britain, it was never pretended, that we could gain a farthing by ſuch an acquiſition. In 1727, the nation forced George the Firſt into a war with Spain, which ended as uſual with much miſchief on both ſides. The Spaniſh war of the people in 1739, and the Auſtrian ſubſidy war of the crown, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced in 1741, were abſurd in their principles, and ruinous in their conſequences. At ſea, we met with nothing but hard blows. On the continent, we began by hiring the Queen of Hungary to fight her own battles againſt the King of Pruſſia; and ten years after the war ended, we hired the King of Pruſſia
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:028380_0007_0FD8DE4EDF171758"/>
with ſix hundred and ſeventy-one thouſand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> to fight his own battles againſt her. If this be not folly, what are we to call it? As to the quarrel of 1754, <q>It was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marked by all Europe, ſays Frederick, that in her diſpute with France, <hi>every wrong ſtep was on the ſide of England.</hi>
               </q> By nine years of butchery, and an additional debt of ſeventy millions ſterling, we ſecured Canada; but had Wolfe and his army been driven from the heights of Abraham, our grandſons might have come too early to hear of an American revolution. As to this event, the circumſtances are too ſhocking for reflec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. At that time an Engliſh woman had diſcovered a remedy for the canine madneſs, and Frederick adviſes a French cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent <hi>to recommend this medicine to the uſe of the Parliament of England, as they muſt certainly have been bitten by a mad dog.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the quarrels of the Continent we ſhould concern ourſelves but little; for in a defenſive war, we may ſafely defy all the nations of Europe. When the whole civilized world was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied under the banners of Rome, her Dictator, at the head of thirty thouſand veterans, diſembarked for a ſecond time on the coaſt of Britain. The face of the country was covered with a foreſt, and the ſolitary tribes were divided upon the old queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Who ſhall be king?</hi> The iſland could hardly have attained to a twentieth part of its preſent population, yet by his own account, the invader found a retreat prudent, or perhaps neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. South Britain was afterwards ſubjected, but this acquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was the taſk of centuries. Every village was bought with the blood of the legions. We may confide in the moderation of a Roman Hiſtorian, when he is to deſcribe the diſaſters of his countrymen. In a ſingle revolt, eighty thouſand of the uſurpers were extirpated; and fifty, or, as others affirm, ſeventy thouſand ſoldiers periſhed in the courſe of a Caledonian cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign. Do the maſters of modern Europe underſtand the art of war better than Severus, and Agricola, and Julius Caeſar? Is any combination of human power to be compared with the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents and reſources of the Roman empire? If our naked an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors reſiſted and vanquiſhed the conquerors of the ſpecies, what have we to fear from any antagoniſt of this day? On ſix
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:028380_0008_0FD8DE5129D211E8"/>
months warning we could muſter ten or twelve hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand militia. Yet, while the deſpots of Germany were fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about a ſuburb, the nation has condeſcended to tremble for its exiſtence, and the bloſſoms of domeſtic happineſs have been blaſted by ſubſidies, and tide-waiters, and preſs-gangs, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſemen. Our political and commercial ſyſtems are evidently nonſenſe. We poſſeſs within this ſingle iſland, every produc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both of art and nature, which is neceſſary for the moſt comfortable enjoyment of life; yet for the ſake of tea, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and tobacco, and a few other deſpicable luxuries, we have ruſhed into an abyſs of blood and taxes. The boaſted extent of our trade, and the quarrels and public debts which attend it, have raiſed the price of bread, and even of graſs, at leaſt three hundred <hi>per cent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This pamphlet conſiſts not of fluent declamation, but of curious authenticated and important facts, with a few ſhort obſervations interſperſed, which ſeemed neceſſary to explain them. The reader will meet with no mournful periods to the memory of <hi>annual</hi> or <hi>triennial</hi> parliaments; for while the members are men ſuch as their predeceſſors have almoſt always been, it is but of ſmall concern whether they hold their places for life, or but for a ſingle day. Some of our projectors are of opinion, that to ſhorten the duration of parliament would be an ample remedy for all our grievances. The advantages of a popular election have likewiſe been much extolled. Yet an acquaintance with Thucydides, or Plutarch, or Guicciardini, or Machiavel, may tend to calm the raptures of a republican apoſtle. The plan of univerſal ſuffrages has been loudly recommended by the Duke of Richmond; and, on the 16th of May 1782, that nobleman, ſeconded by Mr. Horne Tooke, and Mr. Pitt, was ſitting in a tavern, compoſing advertiſements of reformation for the newſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>papers. MUTANTUR TEMPORA. But had his plan been adopted, it is poſſible that we ſhould at this day, have looked back with regret, on the humiliating yet tranquil deſpotiſm of a Scots, or a Corniſh borough.</p>
            <p>The ſtyle of this work is conciſe and plain; and it is hoped that it will be found ſufficiently reſpectful to all parties. The
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:028380_0009_0FD8DE529C990F68"/>
queſtion to be decided is, are we to proceed with the war ſyſtem? Are we, in the progreſs of the nineteenth century, to embrace five thouſand freſh taxes, to ſquander a ſecond five hundred millions ſterling, and to extirpate twenty millions of people?</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="unknown:028380_0010_0FD8DE541CEF3618"/>
            <head>THE POLITICAL PROGRESS OF BRITAIN.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Dutch proweſs, Daniſh wit, and Britiſh policy,</l>
                     <l>Great NOTHING! mainly tend to thee.</l>
                     <bibl>ROCHESTER.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE people of Scotland are, on all occaſions, fooliſh enough to intereſt themſelves in the good or bad fortune of an Engliſh miniſter; though it does not appear that we have more influence with ſuch a miniſter, than with the cabinet of Japan. To England we were for many centuries a hoſtile, and we are ſtill conſidered by them as a foreign, and in effect a conquered nation. It is true, that we elect very near a twel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> part of the Britiſh Houſe of Commons; but our repreſentatives have no title to vote, or act in a ſeparate body. Every ſtatute proceeds upon the majority of the voices of the whole compound aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: What, therefore, can forty-five perſons accompliſh, when oppoſed to five hundred and thirteen? They feel the total in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignificance of their ſituation, and behave accordingly. An equal number of elbow chairs, placed once for all on the miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial benches, would be leſs expenſive to government, and juſt about as manageable. I call theſe, and every miniſterial tool of the ſame kind, expenſive, becauſe thoſe who are obliged to
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:028380_0011_0FD8DE572B63C5D8"/>
                  <hi>buy,</hi> muſt be underſtood to <hi>ſell</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <q>Damn you and your inſtructions too, I have BOUGHT you, and I will SELL you,</q> ſaid a <hi>worthy</hi> repreſentative to his conſtituents, when they requeſted him to attend to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in parliament. <hi>Political Diſquiſitions,</hi> vol. i. p. 280.</note>; and thoſe who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the banners of oppoſition, can only be conſidered, as having rated their voices too high for a purchaſer in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary auction <note n="†" place="bottom">To this general cenſure we can produce a few exceptions, but the individuals are ſo well known, that it would be needleſs to name them.</note>.</p>
               <p>There is a faſhionable phraſe, <hi>the politics of the county,</hi> which I can never hear pronounced without a glow of indignation; compared with ſuch <hi>politics,</hi> even pimping is reſpectable. Our ſupreme court have, indeed, with infinite propriety, interpoſed to extirpate what are called in Scotland, <hi>parchment barons,</hi> and have thus prevented a crowd of unhappy wretches from plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into an abyſs of perjury. But, in other reſpects, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion is of no conſequence, ſince it moſt certainly cannot be of the ſmalleſt concern to this country, who are our electors, and repreſentatives; or, indeed, whether we are repreſented at all. Our members are, moſt of them, the mere ſatellites of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the day; and forward to ſerve his moſt oppreſſive and criminal purpoſes.</p>
               <p>It ſeems to have been long a maxim of the monopolizing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectors of our ſouthern maſters, to extirpate, as quickly as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, every manufacture in this country, that interferes with their own. Has any body forgotten the ſcandalous breach of national faith, by which the Scottiſh diſtilleries have been brought to deſtruction? Has not the manufacture of ſtarch alſo been driven, by every engine of judicial torture, to the laſt pang of its exiſtence? Have not the manufacturers of paper, printed callicoes, malt liquors and glaſs, been harraſſed by the moſt vexatious methods of exacting the revenue? methods equivalent to an addition of ten, or ſometimes an hundred <hi>per cent.</hi> of the duty payable. Let us look around this inſulted country, and ſay, on what manufacture, except the linen, government has not faſtened its bloody fangs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="unknown:028380_0012_0FD8DE58A8EC0748"/>In the Exciſe annals of Scotland, that year which expired on the 5th of July 1790, produced for the duties on ſoap, <hi>ſixty-five thouſand pounds.</hi> On the 5th of July 1791, the annual amount of theſe duties was only <hi>forty-five thouſand pounds;</hi> and by the ſame hopeful progreſs in three years more at fartheſt, our miniſters will enjoy the pleaſure of extirpating a branch of trade, once flouriſhing and extenſive. Two men were ſome years ago executed at Edinburgh for robbing the Exciſe Office of twenty-ſeven pounds, but offenders may be named, who ten thouſand times better deſerve the gibbet. We have ſeen that oppreſſive ſtatutes, and a method of enforcing them, the moſt tyrannical, have, in a ſingle year, deprived the revenue of twenty thouſand pounds, in one line only, and have driven a crowd of induſtrious families out of the country; and then our legiſlators, to borrow the honeſt language of George Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> "have the inſolence to call this GOVERNMENT."</p>
               <p>By an oriental monopoly, we have obtained the <hi>unexampled privilege</hi> of buying a pound of the ſame tea, for ſix or eight ſhillings, with which other nations would eagerly ſupply us for twenty-pence; nay, we have to thank our <hi>preſent</hi> illuſtrious miniſter, that this trifling vegetable has been reduced from a price ſtill more extravagant. His popularity began by the commutation act. Wonders were promiſed, wonders were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and wonders have happened! A nation, conſiſting of men who call themſelves <hi>enlightened,</hi> have conſented to build up their windows, that they might enjoy the permiſſion of ſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in the dark a cup of tea, ten <hi>per cent.</hi> cheaper than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; though not leſs than three hundred <hi>per cent.</hi> dearer than its intrinſic price.</p>
               <p>Such are the glorious conſequences of our ſtupid veneration for a miniſter, and our abſurd ſubmiſſion to his capricious dictates!</p>
               <p>At home Engliſhmen admire liberty; but abroad, they have always been harſh maſters. Edward the Firſt conquered Wales and Scotland; and at the diſtance of five hundred years, his name is yet remembered in both countries with traditionary horror. His actions are ſhaded by a degree of infamy uncommon even in the ruffian catalogue of Engliſh kings.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="unknown:028380_0013_0FD8DE5A1BCF04C0"/>The rapacity of the BLACK Prince, as he has been emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally termed, drove him out of France. At this day, there are Engliſh writers who pretend to be proud of the unprovoked maſſacres committed by his father and himſelf in that country; but on the other hand, Philip de Comines aſcribes the civil wars of York and Lancaſter, which followed the death of Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Fifth, to the indignation of divine juſtice.</p>
               <p>Ireland, for many centuries, groaned under the moſt oppreſſive and abſurd deſpotiſm; till, in defiance of all conſequences, the immortal Swift, like another Ajax,
<q>"Broke the dark phalanx, and let in the light."</q>
He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ght his country to underſtand her importance. At laſt ſhe reſolved to aſſert it, and, as a neceſſary circumſtance, ſhe aroſe in arms. England ſaw the hazard of contending with a brave, an injured, and an indignant nation. The fabric of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny fell without a blow; and a ſhort time will extinguiſh the laſt veſtige of a ſupremacy, diſhonourable and pernicious to both kingdoms.</p>
               <p>In the Eaſt and Weſt Indies, the conduct of Britain may be fairly contraſted with the murder of Atabaliba, and will prove equally ruinous to the deteſted conquerors <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <p>
                        <q>The civil wars to which our violent deſire of creating <hi>Nabobs</hi> gave riſe, were attended with tragical events. Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal was depopulated by every ſpecies of public diſtreſs. In the ſpace of <hi>ſix</hi> years, half the great cities of this opulent kingdom were rendered deſolate; the moſt fertile fields in the world lay waſte; and FIVE MILLIONS of harmleſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious people were either expelled or deſtroyed. Want of foreſight became more fatal than innate barbariſm; and men found themſelves wading through <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>ruin,</hi> when their only object was <hi>ſpoil.</hi>
                        </q> 
                        <hi>Dow's Hiſtory of Indoſtan,</hi> vol. iii. p. 70. This book was publiſhed in 1772, and the preſent quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation refers to our conduct at that period.</p>
                     <p>In this dreadful ſcene, the moſt diſtinguiſhed actor was Lord Clive. But neither four millions ſterling, nor even immenſe quantities of opium could ſtifle in his boſom the agonies of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection. In 1774, he cut his own throat.</p>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>When our ſublime politicians exult in the victory of Seringa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, and the butchery of the ſubjects of a prince, at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:028380_0014_0FD8DE5EC2C83FF0"/>
of ſix thouſand leagues, I am convinced from the bottom of my heart, and ſo will the majority of my countrymen be, long before this century has elapſed, that it would be an event, the moſt auſpicious both for Bengal and for Britain, if Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wallis and all his myrmidons could be at once driven out of India.</p>
               <p>But what quarter of the globe has not been convulſed by our ambition, our avarice, and our baſeneſs? The tribes of the Pacific ocean are polluted by the moſt loathſome of diſeaſes; our brandy has brutalized or extirpated the Indians of the weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern continent; and we have hired by thouſands the wretched ſurvivors to the taſk of bloodſhed. On the ſhores of Africa, we bribe whole nations by drunkenneſs, to robbery and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; while in the face of earth and heaven, our ſenators aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſanctify the practice.</p>
               <p>Our North American colonies were eſtabliſhed, defended, and loſt, by a ſucceſſion of long and bloody wars, and at a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded expence of at leaſt two or three hundred millions ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <note n="*" place="bottom">In the war of 1775, Britiſh officers pilfered books from a public library, which had been founded at Philadelphia by an individual more truly eſtimable than many of the whole profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion put together; I need hardly ſubjoin the name of Franklin.</note>. We ſtill retain Canada, at an annual charge of ſix or ſeven hundred thouſand pounds. This ſum is wreſted from us by an exciſe, which revels in the deſtruction of manufactures, and the beggary of ten thouſand honeſt families <note n="†" place="bottom">Look into Ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſely's or Robertſon's tax-tables: What conciſe! what tremenduous volumes! When our political writers boaſt of Britiſh liberty, they remind us of Smollet's cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in Bedlam bombarding Conſtantinople. If the victims who groan under our yoke, were acquainted with the confuſion and ſlavery which our avarice or mad ambition have inflicted on ourſelves, a very conſiderable ſhare of their abhorrence would be converted into contempt or pity.</note>. From the province itſelf we never raiſed, nor hope to raiſe, a ſhilling of revenue; and the ſole reaſon why its inhabitants endure our dominion for a month longer is, to ſecure the money we ſpend among them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="unknown:028380_0015_0FD8DE63E81B9018"/>
               <head>CHAP II.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>'Tis time to take enormity by the forehead and brand it.</p>
                     <bibl>BEN JOHNSON.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <q>DURING the reigns of Charles and James the Second, above ſixty thouſand Nonconformiſts ſuffered, of whom <hi>five thouſand</hi> DIED IN PRISON. On a moderate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, theſe perſons were pillaged of FOURTEEN MILLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS of property. Such was the tolerating, liberal, candid ſpirit of the Church of England <note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Vide</hi> Flower on the French Conſtitution, p. 437, and his Authorities.</note>.</q> This eſtimate cannot be intended to include Scotland, for it is likely that here alone, Epiſcopacy ſacrificed ſixty thouſand victims. Of all ſorts of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, the records of the Church from the moſt outrageous bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſque on the human underſtanding. As to Charles the Second, it is full time that we ſhould be ſpared from the hereditary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of a holiday, for what Lord Gardenſtone has juſtly termed "his BANEFUL RESTORATION."</p>
               <p>It is vulgarly underſtood that our political millenium com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced with "the <hi>glorious</hi> Revolution." Let the reader judge from what follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Two hundred thouſand pounds a year <hi>beſtowed upon the parliament,</hi> have already (1693) drawn out of the pockets of the ſubjects MORE MONEY than <hi>all our kings ſince the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt have had from the nation!</hi>—The King (William) has about ſix ſcore members, whom I can reckon, who are in places, and are thereby ſo entirely at his devotion, that though they have mortal feuds, <hi>when out of the Houſe,</hi> and though they are violently of oppoſite parties, in their notions of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, yet they vote as lumpingly as <hi>the lawn ſleeves.</hi> The Houſe is ſo <hi>officered</hi> by thoſe who have places and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:028380_0016_0FD8DE66A0BFE558"/>
that the King can baffle any bill, quaſh all grievances, and ſtifle all accompts <note n="*" place="bottom">Burgh's Political Diſquiſitions, vol. 1, p. 405.</note>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>A pawnbroker deſcending from the pillory would not be ſuffered to reſume his profeſſion. A porter convicted of theft, would be deprived of his ticket. We might be tempted to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that a ſolicitude to embrace pollution, can hardly exiſt even in the meaneſt and moſt worthleſs rank of mankind. It ſeems incredible, that an aſſembly conſiſting of <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> ſhall firſt by a ſolemn vote diſcharge one of their members as <hi>a raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> and in a ſhort time after, <hi>place him at their head.</hi> That ſuch a caſe has actually happened, appears upon record.</p>
               <p>In the year 1711, the Houſe of Commons reſolved, <q>That <hi>Robert Walpole, Eſquire,</hi> having been this ſeſſion of parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament committed a priſoner to the Tower, and expelled this Houſe for <hi>a breach of truſt</hi> in the execution of his office, and NOTORIOUS CORRUPTION, when Secretary at War, was, and is incapable of being elected a member to ſerve in this preſent parliament.</q> Such an expulſion would for ever have bolted him out of any ſociety but a Britiſh ſenate. In 1715, when a new parliament was called, he reſumed his ſeat. He roſe ſuperior to competition; and the end of his career was worthy of his outſet. Yet his character can loſe nothing by a compariſon with that of his conſtituents, the burgeſſes of Lynn, who attempted inſtantly upon his expulſion, to return him a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time as their repreſentative, but their choice was rejected. Nor was it becauſe Walpole had pilfered five hundred guineas that he was expelled and ſent to the Tower. He was a <hi>Whig,</hi> and at that time the majority in the Houſe of Commons were <hi>Tories.</hi> This was regarded as the true cauſe of his ſentence <note n="†" place="bottom">George the Second, on his acceſſion, had reſolved to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs Walpole. The miniſter offered on condition of keeping his place, to obtain an addition of an hundred thouſand pounds <hi>per annum</hi> to the civil liſt, and a jointure of an hundred thouſand pounds to Queen Caroline. His terms were accepted. It is impoſſible for the human mind to conceive a more ſordid tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action. Edmund Burke, in what he calls an appeal to the old whigs, has gravely aſſured us, that <q>Walpole was an <hi>honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> man, and a <hi>ſound</hi> WHIG. He was not a prodigal and <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt</hi> miniſter. He was far from governing by <hi>corruption.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="unknown:028380_0017_0FD8DE679AED3810"/>The Earl of Wharton, <hi>another</hi> WHIG, was fined in a thouſand pounds for an outrage too groſs to be repeated. This did not deprive him of his ſeat in the Houſe of Peers, nor impede his progreſs to the government of Ireland, where his conduct rivalled that of Rumbold in Bengal, or Verres in Sicily.—About the year 1770, General Burgoyne was fined in a thouſand pounds for bribery at an election for Preſton. He enjoys a ſeat in the preſent parliament.</p>
               <p>On the ſubject of parliamentary corruption, no writer has ſpoken with more frankneſs and perſpicuity, than Mr. Dodding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, in his celebrated Diary. In a converſation with the Duke of Newcaſtle, in 1753, about an election for Bridgewater, there is the following curious paſſage: <q>I recommended my two parſons, Burroughs and Franklin. The Duke entered into it very cordially, and anſwered me, that they ſhould have the firſt crown livings that ſhould be vacant in their parts, if we would look out and ſend him the firſt intelligence.</q> And again, <q>Mr. Pelham declared, that I had a good deal of <hi>marketable ware,</hi> PARLIAMENTARY INTEREST, and that if I would empower him to offer it all to the King, <hi>without conditions,</hi> he would be anſwerable to bring the affair to a good account.—The Duke of Newcaſtle ſaid, that what I did was <hi>very great,</hi> that he often thought with ſurpriſe, at the eaſe and <hi>cheapneſs</hi> of the election at Weymouth, <hi>that they had</hi> NOTHING <hi>like it.</hi> I ſaid, I believed there were few who could give his Majeſty SIX members for <hi>nothing.</hi>—The elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion coſt me three thouſand four hundred pounds. I was fairly choſen, nor would the returning officer have dared not to return me, had he not been encouraged by the ſervants of adminiſtration. The borough was loſt, and loſt ſolely by a Lord of the Bed-chamber, and the Cuſtom-houſe Officers.</q> 
                  <hi>(Par nobile fratrum!)</hi> 
                  <q>Lord Bute had told Anſon, that room muſt be made for Lord Parker; who replied, that all was engaged. Bute ſaid, <hi>What, my Lord, the King's Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally boroughs full, and the King not acquainted with it!</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſeemed quite diſconcerted, and knew not what to ſay <note n="*" place="bottom">Doddington's Diary, 3d ed. p. 256, 283, 293, 309, <hi>et ſeq.</hi>
                     </note>.</q>
                  <pb n="17" facs="unknown:028380_0018_0FD8DE6977D2C580"/>
This agrees exactly with the account given by Mr. Courtney, in a late debate in the Houſe of Commons, where he obſerved, that members came into parliament with a label at their mouths, inſcribed, <hi>Yes,</hi> or <hi>No.</hi> The ſtate of Britiſh repreſentation has been often examined and cenſured. A few particulars may ſerve as a ſpecimen of the reſt.</p>
               <p>England is ſaid to contain eight millions of inhabitants, who ſend to the Houſe of Commons five hundred and thirteen mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. At this rate, every million ought, upon an average, to chuſe ſixty-four repreſentatives. The cities of London and Weſtminſter contain between them, about a million of people, who elect not <hi>ſixty-four,</hi> but <hi>ſix</hi> members for parliament. The borough of Old Sarum, which contains only <hi>one</hi> inhabitant, ſends <hi>two</hi> members.</p>
               <p>On this topick, a ſhort extract from Mr. Burgh's Political Diſquiſitions, may entertain the reader.—<q>Two hundred and fifty-four members are elected by five thouſand ſeven hundred and twenty-three votes; now, the moſt numerous meeting of the Commons ever known, was on occaſion of the debate about Walpole, A. D. 1741. There were then five hundred and two in the Houſe. Therefore, two hundred and fifty-four comes very near a majority of the Houſe, or the <hi>whole acting</hi> and <hi>efficient</hi> number. And the greateſt part of theſe illuſtrious five thouſand ſeven hundred and twenty-three, who have the power of conſtituting lawgivers over the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of the nation, are themſelves perſons of no property <note n="*" place="bottom">Political Diſquiſitions, vol. 1, p. 45.</note>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The writer has here committed a ſlight inaccuracy; for, in the debate about Walpole, theſe two hundred and fifty-four members, who are not, in fact, elected by a two hundredth part of the nation, would have ſeemed an actual majority of ſix votes againſt the whole other repreſentatives in the Houſe. In the year 1770, the Engliſh nation became jealous that their liberties were in danger, becauſe Government had interfered in the election of Mr. Wilkes, as a member for the county of Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex. The letters of Junius are chiefly employed upon this
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:028380_0019_0FD8DE6A9C73BCB8"/>
topic. Junius, with all his merit, reſembled a barber, who plucks out a ſingle hair, when he ought to be ſhaving your beard. It could not be of the leaſt conſequence to the county of Middleſex, nor is it of any concern to any other county in England, who are their repreſentatives, ſince the two hundred and fifty-four members who are elected by A TWO HUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DREDTH PART of the nation, and the forty-five make-weight Scotch members, are alone ſufficient to inſure a majority. The ſubject is too abſurd to admit of an argument, and too deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for declamation. If Government were candidly to ſend two hundred and fifty-four exciſemen, or clerks from the Bank of England, into parliament, in place of theſe two hundred and fifty-four members, it would ſave the expence of election, and a great part of the neceſſary expence of corruption. It is true, that the maſters of rotten boroughs are often inrolled in the ranks of oppoſition; and among others, the Earl of Chatham began his progreſs as a member for Old Sarum. But an oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition always conſiſts, in part, of adventures, who, as Dr. John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon obſerves, <q>having eſtimated themſelves at two high a price, are only angry that they are not <hi>bought</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Vide</hi> Falſe Alarm.</note>.</q> There is a cant expreſſion in this country, that our Government is deſervedly <hi>the wonder and envy of the world.</hi> With better reaſon it may be ſaid, that Parliament is a mere outwork of the court, a pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanx of mercenaries embattled againſt the reaſon, the happineſs, and the liberty of mankind. The game laws, the dog act, the ſhop tax, the window tax, the pedlars tax, the attorney tax, and a thouſand others, give us a right to wiſh that their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors had been hanged.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="unknown:028380_0020_0FD8DE6DF5177DE0"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Felicior eſſem</l>
                     <l>Anguſtis opibus: mallem tolerare Sabinos,</l>
                     <l>Et Vejos: brevior duxi ſecurius aevum.</l>
                     <l>Ipſa nocet moles.</l>
                     <bibl>CLAUDIAN.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IT is now eighty-eight years ſince <note n="*" place="bottom">In 1704.</note> we ſurpriſed Gibraltar. We have retained this barren, uſeleſs rock, under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of protecting our trade in the Mediterranean; and it is even a ſorry conceit in Britain that we are thus maſters of a kind of toll-bar to the entrance of that ſea. Had the paſſage been only five hundred yards wide, this fancy would have had ſome foundation. But, unfortunately, the <hi>Strait,</hi> as we call it, is <hi>twenty miles</hi> in breadth; ſo that all the ſhips in the world may paſs it every day, in contempt of all our batteries. As to the protection of our merchants, it is equally ſuperfluous, for our commerce to that part of Europe was far more extenſive, long before we poſſeſſed Gibraltar, than it is at this moment <note n="†" place="bottom">This circumſtance has been fully explained by Dr. Adam Smith, in his Inquiry, book 4, chap. 7.</note>; and this unqueſtionable fact proves the abſolute impertinence of the whole ſcheme. A plain compariſon from domeſtic life will il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate what I ſay. Let us put the caſe, that a private gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is like Britain, overwhelmed with debt. He builds and furniſhes a handſome inn on the road to his country ſeat, and he gives the premiſes to his butler, with a penſion of five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds, on condition, that in dirty weather, he ſhall be ſuffered to pull off his boots in the kitchen. But were even the port of Gibraltar ſunk to the centre of the earth, we can have no want of ſhelter at the ſhorteſt diſtance. There are three ports on the oppoſite ſide of the Strait. Beſides, we cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this fortreſs, unleſs we preſerve a ſuperiority at ſea, and as
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:028380_0021_0FD8DE6F1B1194A8"/>
long as we preſerve that ſuperiority, Gibraltar is of no conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. For the memorable progreſs of Admiral Blake on the coaſt of Barbary proves, that while we can launch a victorious navy, manned as it is by a race of veterans beyond all praiſe, we can always command a free navigation in every harbour of the globe. So much for the importance of this boaſted acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. Let us now conſider its expence; and on this head the reader may, if he thinks proper, prepare himſelf for aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The fortreſs, for a long period paſt, has coſt us five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand pounds a year, beſides the extraordinary advances in time of war, and the ſums which the garriſon, by ſober in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, might have earned at home in time of peace. For the ſake of moderation, let us compute that Gibraltar, during the whole ſpace of our poſſeſſion, has required, upon an average, only two hundred thouſand pounds <hi>per annum;</hi> on multiplying this ſum by eighty-eight, we are preſented with an amount of ſeventeen millions and ſix hundred thouſand pounds ſterling. Could the premiſes be diſputed, the total expence would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed credibility; for at the rate of five <hi>per cent.</hi> of compound intereſt, a ſum doubles itſelf in fourteen years; and, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, in the courſe of eighty-four years, from 1704, to 1788, the firſt payment of two hundred thouſand pounds will increaſe to twelve millions and eight hundred thouſand. The ſimple intereſt of this ſum, for the four additional years, from 1788 to 1792 incluſive, amounts to two millions five hundred and ſixty thouſand pounds, and the whole ariſes to <hi>fifteen millions three hundred and ſixty thouſand pounds.</hi> This, however, concerns only <hi>one</hi> year of our conqueſt. The firſt four years extend in the whole to <hi>fifty-ſeven millions and ſix hundred thouſand pounds ſterling.</hi> Another loſs alſo muſt be taken into this unfathom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able accompt. The garriſon of this fortreſs conſiſts always of at leaſt four thouſand men, and ſometimes of more than twice that number. An ordinary workman can earn ten ſhillings a week, and the labour of four thouſand ſuch workmen is worth to the public above an hundred thouſand pounds <hi>per annum.</hi> This adds one third part more of additional loſs. The total expence therefore, which this acquiſition exhauſted in the firſt
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:028380_0022_0FD8DE71ED0ADA70"/>
four years only, including the legal intereſt of our money down to this day, cannot have been leſs than <hi>eighty-ſix millions four hundred thouſand pounds.</hi> We are likewiſe entitled to compute not only what we have poſitively loſt, but what we might with equal certainty have gained. Britain and Ireland contain about an hundred and four thouſand ſquare miles, and if this ſum of eighty-ſix millions four hundred thouſand pounds had been expended on the purpoſes of agriculture, it would have ſupplied a fund of eight hundred and thirty pounds ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for every ſquare mile. Hence, inſtead of an intereſt of <hi>five</hi> per cent. the funds thus employed would have returned a profit of <hi>ten</hi> or <hi>twenty,</hi> or perhaps of <hi>fifty</hi> per cent.</p>
               <p>The reader may proſecute, and contemplate the ſequel of this calculation. All the current caſh in Europe, or in the world, would come infinitely ſhort of diſcharging ſuch a reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning. Britain may be ſuppoſed at this time to contain about fifteen hundred thouſand families, beſides thoſe who are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported upon charity. Now, dividing the preſent annual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of five hundred thouſand pounds equally among them, it amounts to a ſhare of ſix ſhillings and eight pence <hi>per</hi> family. The money ought to be raiſed under a diſtinct title, ſuch as the Gibraltar <hi>additional ſhilling of land tax,</hi> the Gibraltar <hi>malt tax,</hi> the Gibraltar <hi>exciſe on tobacco,</hi> the Gibraltar <hi>game licence,</hi> the Gibraltar <hi>horſe licence,</hi> the Gibraltar <hi>attorney licence,</hi> or the Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltar <hi>ſtamp duty on legacies.</hi> In that caſe, the nation would inſtantly conſider what they are about, and caſt off ſuch a prepoſterous burden. The payment of ſix ſhillings and eight pence is frequently the ſmalleſt part of the grievance. By the expence of exciſemen, of proſecutions, and of penalties, five ſhillings of revenue may often coſt a Britiſh <hi>freeman</hi> ten times as many pounds ſterling <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <p>I ſhall mention an example in point, which occurs while I am now writing. An old woman had been in the practice of ſupplying her neighbours with halfpennyworths of ſnuff. She was ordered, under a penalty of <hi>fifty pounds,</hi> to pay <hi>five ſhillings</hi> for a licence, and ſhe did ſo. Had ſhe been able to buy from the manufacturer four pounds of ſnuff at a time, the buſineſs might have reſted there; but as this was beyond her power, it was required by the terriers of taxation, that ſhe ſhould make oath, once a year, to the quantity ſhe ſold. Her memory failed, and ſhe is now, with a crowd of other victims, in an exciſe court, which will very poſſibly bring her to beggary. This is like a drop in the ocean of exciſe. The very ſound of the word announces utter deſtruction; for it is derived from a Latin verb, which ſignifies <hi>to cut up by the roots.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>What "our moſt excellent conſtitution" may be in theory, I neither know nor care. In practice, it is altogether a CONSPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RACY OF THE RICH AGAINST THE POOR.</p>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="unknown:028380_0023_0FD8DE72DD42CC88"/>Before the acquiſition of Gibraltar, England, in the whole courſe of her hiſtory, had only three wars with Spain. The firſt in 1588, was produced by the piracies of Drake and others, and by the aſſiſtance which Elizabeth afforded to the Dutch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volters. The ſecond war was likewiſe unprovoked on the part of Spain. Cromwell found it neceſſary to vent the turbulence of his ſubjects in a foreign quarrel, and Jamaica was invaded and ſeized without even a pretence of juſtice. On this conqueſt chiefly has England founded that hopeful branch of her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, the Slave-Trade, while the climate has annually extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated, by thouſands, the vagrants from Europe. The third Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh war had an origin worthy of its predeceſſors. The King of Spain, by his will, transferred his dominions to a Prince of the houſe of Bourbon. His ſubjects conſented or ſubmitted to the choice, and England, with a degree of inſolence unmatched in hiſtory, interfered in favour of an Auſtrian candidate. The conteſt ended with our acquiſition of Minorca, and Gibraltar; an injury to Spain of the moſt offenſive nature. Since that period her court has always been forward to contend with us; and five wars <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Viz.</hi> in 1718, in 1727, in 1739, in 1762, and in 1779.</note>, begun and terminated in the ſhort ſpace of ſixty-five years, aſſures us of their indelible indignation. Nor can we be ſurpriſed at their animoſity; for what would an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhman ſay or feel, were Plymouth and Dover fortified by a French garriſon? Happily for the ſpecies, our countrymen at Gibraltar have been but ſeldom attacked. Hence, in a time of war, they have commonly inflicted and ſuffered far leſs miſchief than muſt have been committed on both ſides in a piratical ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:028380_0024_0FD8DE7456B2BEC8"/>
to the coaſt of Peru, in deſolating the plains of Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſtan, in burning the ſhipping at St. Maloes, or in ſtorming the peſtilential ramparts of the Havannah <note n="*" place="bottom">The Major of a Britiſh regiment who ſerved at that ſiege, had in his company, on his arrival at Cuba, an hundred and nine healthy men. Of theſe, as he himſelf told me, <hi>five</hi> only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to Europe.</note>.</p>
               <p>In 1708, we captured Minorca, and after what has been ſaid as to Gibraltar, it is unneceſſary to expatiate on the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous expences which it muſt have coſt us during half a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, till it was in 1756 ſurrendered to the French. On this event the whole Engliſh nation ſeemed to have run out of their ſenſes. Yet to the loſs of this fortreſs, we may in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure attribute our <hi>ſucceſs,</hi> as it was called, in that war; for the charge of ſupporting Minorca muſt have been felt as a dead weight upon our other operations. It was reſtored in 1763, and in 1781, it was a ſecond time, and I hope for ever, ſeparated from the Britiſh dominions. By the loſs of this fortreſs we ſave an inceſſant and extravagant expence. With me it is an object of regret, that the brave Elliot and his garriſon had not been forced to capitulate by the firſt bomb diſcharged againſt them. The individuals, acting as they did, from the moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous and honourable principles, have acquired and deſerved our warmeſt gratitude; and, as it may be expected that ſuch events will hereafter become leſs frequent, their glory will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend with increaſing luſtre to the laſt generations of mankind. But their efforts were fatal to this country; for it is ſelf-evident that we had much better have wanted this mock appendage of empire. The ſiege itſelf produced ſcenes of ſuch ſtupenduous deſtruction, that they cannot be peruſed without horror. Nine years of peace have ſince elapſed, and, in that time, including the endleſs expence of fortifications, it is probable that Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltar has coſt us at leaſt five millions ſterling; beſides, we have been again on the verge of a war with Spain, which has added a comfortable <hi>item</hi> of four millions to the debts of the nation. If the annual expence of Gibraltar amounts to five hundred thouſand pounds, this is about one thirty-ſecond part of our
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:028380_0025_0FD8DE7CAACD88E8"/>
public revenue. Nothing but the power of its diſpoſal can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain for a Britiſh miniſter a majority in the Houſe of Commons. Three hundred and twenty members are about the uſual num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>under his influence</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">When the whole ſtrength of each party is called forth, a minority are commonly within an hundred voices of the miniſter, which correſponds with tolerable accuracy to the computation in the text. In the regency queſtion, Mr. Pitt, with the whole nation at his back, muſtered only two hundred and ſixty-nine members.</note>; and therefore the patronage of Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltar may be conjectured to purchaſe ten votes in the market of St. Stephen's chapel <note n="†" place="bottom">In the Spaniſh negociation in 1757, the Earl of Chatham (then Mr. Pitt) propoſed to cede Gibraltar to Spain, and again, in 1761, he offered it as <hi>the price of the Family Compact.</hi> Vide <hi>His Life,</hi> in two large volumes juſt publiſhed. This propoſal evinces, that the fortreſs was not, in Mr. Pitt's opinion, of much importance to Britain.</note>.</p>
               <p>Though writers have preſumed to ſpecify the annual charge of Gibraltar, an exact eſtimate cannot poſſibly be obtained. The public accounts are preſented to parliament in a ſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extricable confuſion. Indeed, their immenſe bulk would alone be ſufficient to place them far beyond the reach of any human comprehenſion. A ſingle circumſtance may ſerve to ſhow the way in which parliamentary buſineſs is commonly performed. A ſtatute was paſſed and printed ſome years ago, containing three ſucceſſive references to the <hi>thirty</hi>-FIRST day of November.</p>
               <p>For a foreign conteſt, our government is moſt wretchedly adapted. In the war of 1756, Frederick, that Shakeſpeare of kings, fought and conquered five different nations. In the courſe of his miraculous campaigns, he neither added a ſingle impoſt, nor attempted to borrow a ſingle ſhilling. At the ſame time our boaſted Earl of Chatham was overwhelming this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try with taxes, and contracting an annual debt of fifteen or twenty millions ſterling. With a more deſtructive miniſter no nation was ever curſed. Yet this man we prefer to Sir Robert Walpole, a ſtateſman, whoſe maxim it was to keep us, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, at peace with all the world.</p>
               <p>In 1662, Dunkirk, then poſſeſſed by England, coſt an annual
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:028380_0026_0FD8DE7CAEA3C9F0"/>
expence of an hundred and twenty thouſand pounds. At the ſame period the whole revenues of the nation did not amount to eleven hundred thouſand pounds. The retention of the town muſt have proved a hot-bed of future wars with France. Charles the Second, at this time ſold it to Lewis the Fourteenth, for the ſum of four hundred thouſand pounds. This was, I believe, the only wiſe, laudable, or even innocent action of his reign. It had almoſt produced a rebellion; and, as Mr. Hume obſerves, <q>has not had the good fortune, to be juſtified by any party.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Domeſtic improvement is, in all caſes, more advantageous than military acquiſition. Yet in the great outlines of our hiſtory, we have inceſſantly forſaken the former, to purſue the latter. James the Firſt, though in private, and even in public life, univerſally deſpiſed, was one of the beſt ſovereigns that ever ſat on the Britiſh throne. Without a ſingle quality which could recommend him to our eſteem, he preſerved the Engliſh nation, though much againſt their will, in peace, during his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire reign of twenty-two years. Hence both iſlands made ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid advances in wealth and proſperity. "Never," ſays Stowe, <q>was there any people, leſs conſiderate, and leſs thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful than at this time, <hi>being not willing to endure the memory of their preſent happineſs.</hi>
                  </q> On the ſame principles of rapine, which dictated the retention of Dunkirk, James has been ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely blamed for delivering back to the Dutch three of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified towns, which had been put into the poſſeſſion of Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth. Mr. Hume has, with much propriety, vindicated his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. Had it been poſſible that the life of ſuch a prince, and the tranquillity of this country, could have been prolonged to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day, it is beyond the power of Britiſh vanity to conceive the accumulated progreſs of Britiſh opulence. Both iſlands would, long before this time, have advanced to a ſtate of cultivation, not inferior to that of China. The productions of the ſoil, and the number of inhabitants, might have exceeded, by tenfold, their preſent amount. Public roads, canals, bridges, and buildings of every deſcription, muſt have multiplied far beyond what our moſt ſanguine wiſhes are capable of conceiving. A ſhort review of the deſtruction committed by foreign wars within the laſt hundred
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:028380_0027_0FD8DE7E2D1D0AB0"/>
years of our hiſtory, can hardly fail to amuſe, and may perhaps inſtruct the reader.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Facilis eſt deſcenſus Averni.</hi>
                        <bibl>VIRG.</bibl>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis eaſy into hell to fall;</l>
                     <l>But to get out again is all.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <q>THE ground of the firſt war, ſays Dr. Swift, after the Revolution, as to the part we had in it, was to make France acknowledge the late king, and to recover <hi>Hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's Bay.</hi> But during that whole war the ſea was almoſt entirely neglected, and the greateſt part of ſix millions <hi>annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi> employed <hi>to enlarge the frontier of the Dutch.</hi> For the king was a general, but not an admiral; and although king of England, was a native of Holland.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>After ten years of fighting, to little purpoſe, after the loſs of above <hi>an hundred thouſand men,</hi> and a debt remaining of <hi>twenty millions,</hi> we at length hearkened to the terms of Peace, which was concluded with great advantages to the Empire and Holland, but <hi>none at all to us</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">The Conduct of the Allies.</note>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This account does not give us much encouragement to ſend for a ſecond ſovereign from Holland. Dutch generoſity ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to have proved a very miſerable bargain. It is hardly poſſible that James, with all his prieſts and dragoons, could have committed one hundredth part of this havock. So much for a Proteſtant hero, and a glorious Revolution.</p>
               <p>William aſcended and ſupported his throne by a ſeries of the meaneſt and moſt diſgraceful expedients. He excited Argyle and Monmouth to rebellion. He bribed the ſervants of James to betray to himſelf the ſecrets of their maſter. He inſtructed
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:028380_0028_0FD8DE83A20941C0"/>
theſe miniſters to drive the King of England into thoſe very meaſures which forced a Revolution. He was baſe enough to deny the ligitimacy of the Prince of Wales; he taught two thankleſs daughters to forſake, and ruin, and inſult their father. When embarking for this country, <q>he took Heaven to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that he had not the leaſt intention to invade or ſubdue the kingdom of England, much leſs to make himſelf maſter thereof, or to invert or prejudice the lawful ſucceſſion <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon's Hiſtory of Britain, vol. 1, chap. 3.</note>.</q> James had quarrelled with the Church of England, and this was one of the chief cauſes of his deſtruction. Yet all the biſhops, except eight, as well as many temporal peers, refuſed to take the oaths to the new government; and Sancroft, Archbiſhop of Canterbury, who had been at the head of the oppoſition to James, was, along with five other biſhops, depoſed for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal. The convention parliament who made William King of England, were <hi>elected by himſelf,</hi> and contained, beſides other extraordinary materials, <hi>fifty members of the Common Council of London.</hi> With this very parliament he was immediately on the worſt terms; and Sutherland, Marlborough, and Admiral Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, with many other chiefs of his party, entered into a conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy for his expulſion. The Iriſh rebels had forfeited lands to the value of three millions three hundred and twenty thouſand pounds. This immenſe property William divided almoſt alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether among his Dutch favourites, and the Counteſs of Ork<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, an Engliſh concubine, whoſe ſervices were rewarded with an eſtate of twenty-ſix thouſand pounds a year; while, at the ſame time, with the moſt ſordid ingratitude, he turned his back on the family of Monmouth, who had been his tool and his vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim. Theſe acts of robbery were reverſed by parliament. I paſs over the tragedies of Glencoe and Darien, for on ſuch a character, they reflect no peculiar reproach. William was the father of our public debt, which he multiplied as much as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that beſides other mean purpoſes, he might attach to his perſonal ſafety the creditors of the nation. As to parliament, in 1690, the Speaker <q>
                     <hi>promiſed to the king to manage his
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:028380_0029_0FD8DE8844EDCF70"/>
own party,</hi> provided he might be furniſhed with money to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe votes <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon's Hiſtory of Great Britain, vol. 1, chap. 10.</note>.</q> His majeſty conſented. In the progreſs of this conſpiracy, his agent was expelled from the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, for accepting from the City of London a bribe of a thouſand guineas. A bribe of ten thouſand pounds, from the Eaſt-India Company, "was traced to the king <note n="†" place="bottom">Ibid. vol. 2, chap. 2.</note>;" a magiſtrate, whoſe office it was to ſign the warrant for executing a pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocket. William extinguiſhed this inquiry by a prorogation. <q>Thus ended, ſays the hiſtorian, <hi>a wretched force,</hi> in which the feeble efforts for obtaining juſtice were ſcarce leſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graceful than venality itſelf.</q> On the 20th December 1697, the Commons granted William ſeven hundred thouſand pounds a year for the ſupport of the civil liſt. This comprehended fifty thouſand pounds a year, which he promiſed to pay to King James's queen as her jointure, and fifty thouſand pounds a year, which he demanded as neceſſary to eſtabliſh the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of the Duke of Glouceſter. To the queen he never paid a farthing, and to the Duke only fifteen thouſand pounds a year. This prince died on the 24th of July 1700, and in 1701 the Commons, after a violent debate with the adherents of the court, compelled William to refund the fifty thouſand pounds, which he had engaged to pay to the exiled queen; and above twenty thouſand pounds, which the Duke of Glouceſter had left behind him <note n="‡" place="bottom">
                     <p>Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 3 and 4. The hiſtorian has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated this anecdote in ſuch a manner, that we cannot learn what ſums the exiled queen ought to have received. When her join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is twice mentioned in chapter 3, he calls it fifty thouſand pounds a year. But after four years, in chapter 4, he contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts this ſtatement, by informing us, that William had retained <hi>the</hi> fifty thouſand pounds due to her, which, with the reverſion by the death of the Duke of Glouceſter, amounted to <q>
                           <hi>near</hi> an hundred thouſand pounds.</q> By the account in chapter 3, the whole ſums, including intereſt, ſhould have been about two hundred and fifty thouſand pounds.</p>
                     <p>This miſtake is hardly worth notice here, but is mentioned merely to ſhew that one may ſometimes be forced to ſeek a way through very diſcordant materials.</p>
                  </note>. Mr. Pitt complains of authors who publiſh
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:028380_0030_0FD8DE895D24B180"/>
libels on the Revolution. To forbid a perſon from publiſhing his ſentiments on a hiſtorical event which happened above an hundred years ago, is in itſelf an example of the utmoſt inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of deſpotiſm. To depoſe one tyrant was highly proper; but it was not leſs fooliſh to exalt another <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <p>Smoliet's character of William is a curious jumble.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>He was religious, temperate, <hi>generally juſt</hi> and <hi>ſincere.</hi>—He involved theſe kingdoms in foreign connections, which, in all probability, will be <hi>productive of their ruin.</hi> He ſcrupled not to employ <hi>all the engines of corruption.</hi> He entailed upon the nation a growing debt, and a ſyſtem of politics big with miſery, deſpair, and deſtruction.</q> The reſt of this paſſage is too long for inſertion; but the author's inference appears to be, that William was the moſt ruinous ſovereign who ever ſat on the throne of England.</p>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>More coſt more honour,</hi> ſays the proverb; and by this rule the Revolution was certainly a more ſplendid tranſaction than the nation had ever ſeen. <q>The expences of England, from the landing of the Prince of Orange on the 5th of November 1688, to the 29th of September 1691, had amounted to near EIGHTEEN MILLIONS. Beſides, great arrears were owing to the army in Ireland, the navy was <hi>deſtitute of ſtores,</hi> and <hi>the ſhips were out of repair</hi> 
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 1. All our continental wars and ſubſidies, from 1688, to this day, muſt be aſcribed to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution.</note>.</q> In 1693, a bill paſſed both Houſes, providing for annual ſeſſions of parliament, and a new election once in three years. To this bill, the FOUNDER OF ENGLISH FREEDOM refuſed his aſſent, which in 1694 was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by compulſion. After having told all the world for ten years, that James had impoſed a ſpurious prince upon the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he engaged in 1697, to obtain that prince to be declared his ſucceſſor <note n="‡" place="bottom">Ibid. vol. ii. chap. 3. The author adds, <q>The ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors provided by the act of ſettlement, he either <hi>deſpiſed</hi> or <hi>abhorred.</hi>
                     </q> Theſe were the illuſtrious Houſe of Brunſwick.</note>. A man of common ſpirit would rather have been a chimney ſweeper than ſuch a ſovereign.</p>
               <p>As for the inferior actors in the Revolution, we may inquire <hi>what have they done?</hi> They did not transfer the load of taxes from the poor to the rich. They did not extirpate entails, and
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:028380_0031_0FD8DE8AD9BAE618"/>
rotten boroughs. They did not eſtabliſh an univerſal right of conſcience, and an univerſal right of citizenſhip. They did not advance even a ſingle ſtep towards exalting the motely parliament of England into the actual repreſentatives of a free people. They did not avoid a moſt deſtructive and endleſs quarrel on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent. They did not reduce the civil liſt even to the prodigal eſtabliſhment of Charles the Second <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Viz.</hi> Four hundred and ſixty thouſand pounds. The ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of ſeven hundred thouſand pounds is no doubt one of thoſe <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>wholeſome</hi> PROVISIONS ſo gratefully referred to in Mr. Pitt's late proclamation. There can be no queſtion, that in the courſe of an hundred years, the civil liſt has reduced many hundred thouſands of his Majeſty's <q>
                           <hi>faithful</hi> and <hi>loving</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</q> to beggary. That <hi>the weakeſt come always to the worſt,</hi> is a trite obſervation. The principal hardſhips of every tax muſt in the laſt reſort fall upon the poor. At this day the <hi>civil liſt,</hi> with all its abyſs of appendages, abſorbes above eleven hundred thouſand pounds <hi>per annum</hi> of Engliſh money. This expence would, at leaſt in Scotland, be more than ſufficient to maintain two hundred and fifty thouſand paupers, for thoſe in the poor's houſe of the pariſh of St. Cuthbert's, near Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, coſt but about four pounds each <hi>per annum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hence it follows, that the royal eſtabliſhment is in fact equal to an eſtabliſhment of many myriads of beggars. As to the ELECTORAL HOARD, we have curious and authentic informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but this ſubject deſerves a chapter by itſelf.</p>
                  </note>. They did not extirpate the moſt abſurd and extravagant prerogatives of the ſovereign, to adjourn or diſſolve a parliament at pleaſure, to baſtardize a peerage with the puppers of deſpotiſm, to interpoſe a refuſal to the moſt neceſſary laws, and to plunge at his will three na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions into blood and bankruptcy. <hi>What then did they do?</hi> They obtained for their countrymen a right <hi>to petition</hi> THE CROWN <note n="†" place="bottom">They might as well have ſpoke about the right of blowing one's noſe. Yet this miſerable ſtipulation, extracted from the very dregs of ſlavery, has been thought of infinite conſequence.</note>. They ſettled the ſucceſſion on a family whom their hero, for what reaſon he beſt knew, <hi>deſpiſed</hi> and <hi>abhorred.</hi> The whole work was a change, not of meaſures, but of maſters. Where then ſtands the difference between the trimmer Halifax, and the trimmer Thurlow; between Sutherland the traitor to all parties, and our Hibernian panegyriſt of the Baſtile? The Duke of
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:028380_0032_0FD8DE8C57BB7080"/>
Marlborough gave a juſt account both of the Whigs and Tories. <q>I do not believe, ſaid he, that either party is ſwayed by any true principles of conſcience or honeſty. Their profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are always different; their views preciſely the ſame. They both graſp at the poſſeſſion of power; and the Prince who gives them the moſt is their greateſt favourite <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 8.</note>.</q> Were farther evidence wanting, Burnet, himſelf both a whig and a courtier, tells us that the whigs <hi>ſet every thing to ſale.</hi> He complained of the practice of bribing parliament to the king, and William aſſured him, <hi>that it was not poſſible to help it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As a partial defence of our anceſtors it may be urged, that in the end of the laſt century, the nation was unripe for a rational conſtitution. But ſince we know this to be true, why are we diſturbed with rhapſodies on one of the moſt queſtionable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binations that ever deformed hiſtory? Does any body compare the packed convention parliaments of the two kingdoms, in 1689, with the democratical members of the firſt national aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of France? As well might we parallel Charles Jenkinſon with the Duke of Sully, or the aſſaſſin of Culloden with the conqueror at Bannockburn. Did the philoſophical and conciſe decrees of the French patriots grovel in the feudal jargon of ſubjecting a people and their poſterity forever to the aſſignees of a Dutchman who was univerſally deteſted? As well might we fancy a reſemblance between the daubing of a ſign-poſt, and the pencil of Reynolds, or the exerciſe of a ſchool-boy and the ſtanzas of Buchanan.</p>
               <p>Upon the whole, as William betrayed James into ſeveral of thoſe crimes by which a revolution became neceſſary, his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory is an object not of reſpect but abhorrence. His conduct was like that of an incendiary who firſt ſets fire to your houſe, and then claims ten times the worth of the whole building for his ſervice in quenching it. To praiſe him and his revolution, diſcovers an ignorance of hiſtory, or a contempt of common honeſty. It is as much a burleſque upon reaſon, as when a King of England calls himſelf King of France; or as when a
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:028380_0033_0FD8DE8DDE3C2878"/>
perſon, like Henry the Eighth, whoſe word is truſted by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body, aſſumes for his title <hi>Defender of the Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſince the authors of the revolution did not ſurpaſs the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minutive ſtandard of Court integrity, why has our temple of venality <note n="*" place="bottom">In the Anecdotes of Lord Chatham, we are told that Mr. Pelham was intruſted with <hi>what is uſally called</hi> THE POCKET LIST OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS; and Mr. Pitt ſometimes ſaid to his friends, "I was obliged to BORROW the Duke of Newcaſtle's "<hi>majority,</hi> to carry on the public buſineſs."</note> for ſo long a time reſounded with the wretched laram of whig families and whig virtues? Why ſhould common men wander from their natural and juſt progreſs to obſcurity, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ck the attention of future ages? Had Archimedes been only the beſt archer at the ſiege of Syracuſe, had Columbus lived and died but the moſt expert pilot in the port of Genoa, had the eloquence of Shakeſpeare ſhrunk to a level with the drama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick muſhrooms of this day, theſe memorable benefactors of mankind had vaniſhed into inſtant oblivion. Had Thomas Paine been nothing ſuperior to a vagabond ſeamen, a bankrupt ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, a diſcarded exciſeman, a porter in the ſtreets of Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphi, or whatever elſe the inſanity of Grub-ſtreet chuſes to call him, an hundred thouſand copies of his writings had never announced his name in every village on the globe, where the Engliſh language is ſpoken, nor would the rays of royal indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation have illuminated that character which they cannot ſcorch.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Nulla unquam de morte hominis cunctatio longa eſt.</l>
                     <l>No delay as to the death of a man is ever too long.</l>
                     <bibl>JUVENAL.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IN the war which ended by the peace of Ryſwick, ſeven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred millions ſterling were ſpent, and eight hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men periſhed, yet none of the parties gained one penny of
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:028380_0034_0FD8DE94A3FD2E38"/>
money, of almoſt one foot of territory. In 1693, Lewis made very ample offers for peace which William refuſed. Had Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam accepted theſe offers of Lewis, <q>the war of the firſt grand alliance would have ended <hi>four years ſooner than it did,</hi> and the war of the ſecond grand alliance <hi>might have been prevented</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Memoirs of Great Britain and Ireland, part iii. book 10.</note>. During ſome years previous to the peace of Ryſwick, the price of corn in England was <hi>double,</hi> and in Scotland <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>druple</hi> its ordinary rate; and in one of thoſe years, it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that in Scotland <hi>eighty thouſand people died of want</hi> 
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Ibid. part iii. book 5.</note>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The war which followed the Revolution coſt England <hi>ſixty millions ſterling</hi> 
                  <note n="‡" place="bottom">Ibid. Part iv. book 1.</note>. Let us ſuppoſe that an equal ſhare of this ſum was ſpent in each of the nine years, during which it laſted, and at ſix <hi>per cent.</hi> the compound intereſt of the ſums advanced annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally up to the peace of Ryſwick in 1697, amounts to <hi>fifteen millions ſterling.</hi> Four thouſand merchantmen were taken by the enemy <note n="§" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 7.</note>; and De-Foe, in one of his pamplets, tells us, that the damage in this way had been computed at twenty millions. The intereſt of this ſum, eſtimated in the ſame manner with that of the public expences up to the peace, will produce five mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions. But that our calculations may be perfectly ſafe, let us bring down both principal and intereſt to <hi>fifteen millions,</hi> and we ſhall paſs over the expence of at leaſt four thouſand bankruptcies, and ten times that number of lawſuits. The different ſums above ſpecified extend to ninety millions ſterling. Let us next put the caſe that this money had been placed at a compound in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of five <hi>per cent.</hi> 
                  <note n="‖" place="bottom">The legal intereſt of money was not reduced from ſix <hi>per cent.</hi> to five, till the twelfth year of Queen Anne. The writer of the Memoirs of Great Britain obſerves, that in thoſe days, parliament found more difficulty in borrowing at <hi>eight</hi> per cent. than we do now in getting money at <hi>four.</hi> Lord North paid, and we have ſtill the ſatisfaction of paying <hi>ſix</hi> or <hi>ſeven</hi> per cent. for the money that ſupported his American war; and this is known to all mankind, with it ſeems a ſingle exception. At <hi>four</hi> per cent. we could not raiſe a ſingle ſhilling.</note> At the end of ninety-eight years from
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:028380_0035_0FD8DE94A6401188"/>
the peace of Ryſwick, that is to ſay in 1795, theſe ninety millions would have doubled themſelves exactly ſeven times, and the final produce would have been ELEVEN THOUSAND FIVE HUNDRED AND TWENTY MILLIONS STERLING, or a dividend of <hi>eleven hundred and fifty-two pounds</hi> to every indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual inhabitant of Britain. This ſum is equal to the diſcharge of our national debts forty-eight times over, and is five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſeventy-five times greater than the whole gold and ſilver coin at preſent in the three kingdoms. Such has been the price of <hi>a Dutch frontier,</hi> and of <hi>Hudſon's Bay.</hi> As Britain and Ireland are ſaid to contain an hundred and four thouſand ſquare miles, if the money had been employed in the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of agriculture, it would have ſupplied a fund of <hi>an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and one thouſand one hundred and fifty-three pounds fifteen ſhillings and eleven pence, and ſeven thirteenth parts of a penny</hi> for each ſquare mile. This ſum is much more than upon an average the whole landed property of both iſlands is worth <note n="*" place="bottom">In the Memoirs of Great Britian and Ireland, the author eſtimates the mere <hi>loſs of labour</hi> to the contending nations during the nine years of war, at ninety millions Sterling, excluſive of the additional loſs of labour <hi>for life,</hi> by the mutual ſlaughter.</note>.</p>
               <p>An objection may be advanced to this ſtatement, that a great part of the ſixty millions thus expended by government was <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezzled among ourſelves,</hi> and that as it never actually went out of the country, <hi>we are not at this day a farthing poorer than if the money had never been raiſed.</hi> If we might oppoſe the language of common ſenſe to the jargon of political ſophiſtry, I would anſwer, that when a grazier in Yorkſhire has been knocked down and robbed, he cares but little whether his guineas are to be ſtaked at the gaming tables of Paris or of London. But we ſhall admit that the Dutch adminiſtration like all thoſe which have come after it, was a ſcene of inexpreſſible infamy; that <hi>thirty millions</hi> out of the <hi>ſixty</hi> were pilfered in their road to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the public; and that the peers and others who ſtole this money applied their plunder to ends as honeſt as could have been deviſed by the farmers and tradeſmen who were ſtripped of it. This is not very feaſible, for what is won in a bad way is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:028380_0036_0FD8DE965BCD85F0"/>
ſpent in a worſe one; but let us proceed. In eſtimating the expences of the war, there was <hi>omitted</hi> an article of loſs at leaſt equivalent to theſe thirty millions. It has been obſerved, that a workman can, upon an average, earn about ten ſhillings a-week, which in London is at preſent about half the common wages of a journeyman taylor. Reduce this to twenty-five pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> and his life may be eſtimated at twelve years purchaſe, or three hundred pounds in value to the public. In the war in queſtion, we loſt an hundred thouſand men, and by this moderate and ſimple computation, the price of their blood to Britain was not worth leſs than thirty millions Sterling. Even this number of an hundred thouſand lives is moſt likely far leſs than the actual deſtruction. Four thouſand merchant ſhips were taken by the French privateers, and theſe alone muſt have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, one with another, twelve or thirteen mariners, which gives us an amount of fifty thouſand priſoners; of whom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the numbers killed, at leaſt ten or fifteen thouſand would periſh of jail diſtempers, of their wounds, of cold or hunger, and above all, of a broken heart.</p>
               <p>As the pillage of public money is one of the worſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of war, I ſhall here ſay ſomething farther on that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. In 1695, Knight and Duncombe, two members of the Houſe of Commons, were expelled for having forged indorſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on Exchequer bills. Duncombe confeſſed the charge, and his ſhare of the booty had extended to <hi>four hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds.</hi> I am not informed what was the amount of Knight's plunder; or that of ſeveral others who were concerned. The Commons, in a fit of purity, paſſed a bill to fine Duncombe in half his eſtate. By the ſtatute laws of England, he ſhould have ſuffered death. The bill for his fine was rejected in the houſe of Lords <note n="*" place="bottom">Memoirs of Great Britain and Ireland, part iii. book 4.</note>, by the caſting vote of the Duke of Leeds, who was himſelf a ſwindler of the firſt diſtinction. The Earl of Cheſterfield had ſome reaſon for terming that houſe an hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital of <hi>Incurables.</hi> Salmon tells us, that the miniſtry gave whatever intereſt and premiums were demanded for the loan of
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:028380_0037_0FD8DE979EAA9600"/>
money, and that proviſions and naval ſtores were taken up at an advance of thirty, forty, and ſometimes fifty <hi>per cent.</hi> above their proper price. But, indeed, after the dimiſſion of Mr. Duncombe, <hi>with his four hundred thouſand pounds in his pocket,</hi> every charge of this kind becomes perfectly credible.</p>
               <p>Whether in the preſent age, matters have been much mended, there was nobody better able to inform us than the late Earl of Chatham. <q>There is a ſet of men, ſays he, in the city of London, who are known to live in riot and luxury, upon the plunder of the ignorant, the innocent, and the helpleſs, upon that part of the community, which ſtands moſt in need of, and beſt deſerves the care and protection of the legiſlature. To me, my Lords, whether they be miſerable jobbers of Change Alley, or the lofty Aſiatic plunderers of Leadenhall Street, they are all equally deteſtable. I care but little whether a man walks on foot, or is drawn by eight horſes, or by ſix horſes; if his luxury be ſupported by the plunder of his country, I deſpiſe and abhor him. My Lords, while I had the honour of ſerving his Majeſty, <hi>I never ventured to look at</hi> THE TREASURY, <hi>but from a diſtance;</hi> it is a buſineſs I am unfit for, and to which I never could have ſubmitted. The little I know of it, has not ſerved to raiſe my opinion of what is vulgarly called the <hi>monied intereſt;</hi> I mean that BLOODSUCKER, that MUCKWORM, which calls itſelf the friend of Government, which pretends to ſerve this or that adminiſtration, and may be purchaſed on the ſame terms <hi>by any adminiſtration.</hi> Under this deſcription I include the whole race of commiſſioners, jobbers, contractors, clothiers, and remitters <note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Vide</hi> his ſpeech in the debate on Falkland's Iſlands, which has been re-printed in the Anecdotes.</p>
                        <p>This quarrel ended like others, in our diſappointment, and perhaps diſgrace. Beſides much expence and trouble to indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduals, the nation ſquandered between three and four millions ſterling. <hi>Quid vis inſane?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </note>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The war of 1689 is at this day almoſt forgotten, in the blaze of more recent and ſtupendous follies. Yet the preſent ſhort ſketch of thoſe calamities which it produced, cannot fail of
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:028380_0038_0FD8DE991D24A1E0"/>
leading us into ſome melancholy reflections on the general ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of the military ſyſtem. War may produce advantage to a race of barbarians, who have nothing to do, and nothing to loſe; but for a commercial nation, it can be no better than an alderman deſerting his ledger, to bet in a cock-pit. Of this ſyſtem there is no part more injurious than that which enjoins the capture of merchant ſhips. An honeſt mariner has by the labour of half his life earned a thouſand pounds, and embarks his whole property in a veſſel freighted from Leith or Dunkirk. He is boarded by an enemy's privateer; his effects are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited; and he himſelf is to rot for ſix, or twelve, or eighteen months in a French or Engliſh jail; while his wife, his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or perhaps his father—but this part of the picture becomes too ſhocking for the contemplation of humanity. Of theſe matters, kings or courtiers almoſt never think. At a certain elevation, the human heart ſeems to contract a <hi>froſt</hi> more impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrable than the ſummit of the Alps or the Andes. It would be an auſpicous event for mankind, if all the ſhips of war in the world could be reduced to aſhes in one day.</p>
               <p>We have adopted a fancy, that frequent hoſtilities are una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable. Yet the Swiſs, a nation of ſoldiers, and placed in the midſt of contending tyrants, have hardly been thrice at war in the courſe of three centuries. The reaſon is, that their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments are founded on wiſdom, benevolence, and integrity; while ours breathe only maxims of a leſs amiable nature <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <q>The republics of Europe are all, and we may ſay always in peace. Holland and Switzerland are without wars, foreign or domeſtic; monarchial governments, it is true, are never long at reſt; the crown itſelf is a temptation to enterpriſing <hi>ruffians</hi> at <hi>home;</hi> and that degree of pride and inſolence, ever attendant on regal authority, ſwells into a rupture with foreign powers, in inſtances where a republican government, by being formed on more natural principles, would negociate the miſtake.</q> 
                     <hi>Common Senſe.</hi>
                  </note>. Other inſtances from the hiſtory of our own iſland may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the ſame purpoſe. <q>For <hi>more than a century</hi> after the memorable year 1189, there was no national quarrel, nor na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional war between the two kingdoms <note n="†" place="bottom">Annals of Scotland, by Lord Hailes, vol. i. p. 133.</note>.</q> This circumſtance
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:028380_0039_0FD8DE9AA39CD628"/>
becomes the more remarkable, becauſe, at that time our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors were fit for almoſt nothing elſe but fighting. The fatal conteſt that began in the end of the thirteenth century, ſprung from the ambition of Edward the Firſt. The reſpective na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions lived in a profound peace, and were alike ſolicitous to preſerve it.</p>
               <p>From the year 1403, to the battle of Flodden, in 1513, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſpace of <hi>an hundred and ten years,</hi> peace was maintained between the two kingdoms, with very little interruption; though ſometimes there was a war which hardly laſted above a ſingle campaign. During the long and bloody ſtruggle between the houſes of York and Lancaſter, the Scots interfered only once or twice at moſt, and that was at the earneſt deſire of the Engliſh exiles; but they formed no ungenerous and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable plans of conqueſt. Even to Flodden they were driven by the temerity of their ſovereign; and his fortunate death put an inſtant end to hoſtilities. Our anceſtors, whom we conſider as barbarians, were unacquainted with the deliberate ſyſtematic thirſt of blood which marks a modern politician; and what quarrels they had, aroſe from the folly of their ſeveral monarchs. We have not enjoyed ten years of peace together ſince the Revolution. Even when we ceaſe to fight in Europe, a war muſt immediately commence in Aſia, or Africa, or Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica, and in the face of all this work, we call ourſelves the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt people in the world.</p>
               <p>Peace may be conſidered as the univerſal parent of human happineſs. Induſtry cannot long thrive without it, and to this we are indebted for a great part of our comforts, our enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and our reſources. Spain has long been envied for her gold and ſilver mines, which, by Dr. Robertſon's account, have in two centuries and a half, produced above two thouſand mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions ſterling. But ſober induſtry is vaſtly more valuable than all the mines in the world. If we can forbear butchery, we need not deſpair of diſcharging every penny of our public debt, with eaſe, in leſs than a century; or if we ſhould not, ſtill the property of the nation would increaſe with ſuch rapidity, that the debt itſelf muſt be hardly felt. To make this truth evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:028380_0040_0FD8DEBAE31D70E0"/>
let us attend to what follows. As a counterpart to the bubble of Falkland's Iſlands, four millions ſterling have lately been expended on a Spaniſh convention. Had they been placed out at five <hi>per cent.</hi> of compound intereſt, they would in ninety-eight years have produced five hundred and twelve millions ſterling, and at preſent one half of this latter ſum would be more than ſufficient to diſcharge all our incumbrances, and make us as free of debts as our grandfathers were when the Prince of Orange landed. It is true, that the job government of Britain cannot, like that of a Swiſs canton, place money at intereſt, but from calculations of this ſort, we may form a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, as to what we are capable of ſaving, by conſidering what we have ſpent. The American war alone added about one hundred and fifty millions to our public debt, and yet we are in reality a richer nation than when that war began <note n="*" place="bottom">On the ſubject of national improvement, the reader may conſult with advantage Dr. Campbell's Political Survey of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; an Eſtimate of the Comparative Strength of Britain, dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the preſent and two preceding reigns, by George Chalmers, <abbr>Eſq.</abbr> and a continuation of this latter work, by the ſame ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant and profound writer, publiſhed about ſix months ago. Our preſſes are groaning under controverſial divinity, heraldy, blank verſe, commentaries on Shakeſpeare, and every other imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſpecies of nonſenſe, while the books here referred to, have not in this country been honoured, as I am informed, with even a ſecond edition.</note>. Our funds, as we call them, have not hitherto recovered the ſhock, but that is, in ſpite of common prejudice, a happy circumſtance. Had THE YOUNG MAN been able to borrow money with equal facility as his father, we ſhould certainly have been ſcourged into a Spaniſh war. Now, though the country has recovered, and though our commerce is greatly ſuperior to what it had ever before been, it is evident, that if we had not poſſeſſed an almoſt inexhauſtible vital principle of reproduction and accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, ſo great a havock of property as an hundred and fifty, or even an hundred millions ſterling, muſt have reduced whole provinces of this iſland to a deſart. Such a complete recovery from the loſs of more than an hundred millions in leſs than ten years, preſents us with a regular annual overplus of at leaſt ſix
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:028380_0041_0FD8DEA0F36F6390"/>
or eight millions. But that we may not overſhoot the mark, let us rate the clear annual profits of Britiſh commerce and agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culture at only five millions. We ſhall find that this yearly accumulation of ſtocks with the legal compound intereſt only, amounts, in twenty-eight years, to three hundred millions. So that by a peace of twenty-eight years, we ſhall become a more opulent nation, than we would be at this moment were all our debts paid off to the laſt farthing.</p>
               <p>Before we call this proſpect extravagant, let us conſider what has actually happened. The moſt ſanguine projector, thirty years ago, would not have preſumed to believe that four mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions ſterling were by this time to be employed in extending and adorning a ſingle city in Scotland. Yet this progreſs of elegance continues to riſe upon us like enchantment. Who in the laſt century would have ſuſpected that by this time our North American colonies were to contain four millions of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants? It muſt be owned, that beſides other evils, Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltar, Canada, Nova Scotia, Botany Bay, the Eaſt India Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and the civil liſt, are a ſort of political millſtones hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the neck of Britiſh proſperity. Yet ſuch are our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſources, that if we chuſe to deſiſt from the war ſyſtem, our wealth muſt in the courſe of fifty years extend beyond all cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation. Mr. Fox, if providence ſhall continue to bleſs us with his abilities till that period, will not then have the ſmalleſt difficulty in obtaining a penſion of forty thouſand pounds a year for every deſcendant of the royal family. Three ungrateful nations will then ceaſe to affirm, that for his conduct in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain debate <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vide</hi> his ſpeeches in parliament on the ſettlement of the Duke of York. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the clerk of a counting-houſe were to loſe at the gaming-table a thouſand pounds of his maſter's money, or even of his own, he would be diſcharged as unworthy of truſt. There is a man, who is ſaid to have loſt five hundred thouſand pounds in that way, and when he had thus reduced himſelf to bankruptcy, we have ſeen him preſerved to the management of an annual revenue of ſixteen millions ſterling. It is difficult to conceive a more gigantic inſtance of ſtupidity and depravity than ſuch a choice. That a Houſe of Commons ſhould adopt a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of this ſort, is quite <hi>in character;</hi> but that individuals, who have the happineſs of their country at heart, ſhould applaud ſuch a ſelection, muſt fill every ſober man with aſtoniſhment. To ſweep off large ſums at the gaming-table, is a diſhonourable dirty practice. Mr. Fox, in the boundleſs diverſity of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures, muſt have ruined many a family, and ſent many a helpleſs woman with ſorrow to the grave.</p>
                     <p>In the manuſcript of a tour in Switzerland, which I have ſeen, the following paſſage deſerves peculiar attention. <q>At Bern, a heavy penalty is impoſed upon any perſon, who in one day ſhall loſe more than two pounds five ſhillings ſterling by gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and every member of government, and officer in public ſervice, is obliged to take an oath, not only that he ſhall faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and honourably obſerve this law, but that he ſhall zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly maintain it, and that he ſhall freely and impartially give information againſt all perſons who to his knowledge ſhall offend againſt it. The preſence of ſome of thoſe diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons in all good companies, proves in fact an invincible bar to immoderate play.</q> With what contemptuous pity would a Swiſs hear us prattling, that our government is the <hi>envy</hi> of the world!</p>
                  </note>, any other man would have deſerved a flogging at
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:028380_0042_0FD8DEA5D6938E68"/>
every whipping-poſt in England. At that happy period, we ſhall ſupport, without winching, an hundred Lords of the Bed-chamber, and as many Lords of the Neceſſary Houſe. With theſe crumbs of comfort, I proceed to the war of the Spaniſh ſucceſſion, a legacy from our Dutch benefactor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>England has been the prey of jobs ever ſince the Revolution.</p>
                     <bibl>PAINE.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>CHARLES the Second King of Spain had no children; he was of declining years, and a feeble conſtitution. There were three candidates for the inheritance of his dominions, the Emperor, the Dauphin of France, and the Electoral Prince of Bavaria. The Emperor claimed right as male repreſentative
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:028380_0043_0FD8DEA88F09F1F0"/>
to the family of Auſtria. Philip the Fourth, predeceſſor and father to Charles, had left behind him two daughters by dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent marriages. The eldeſt was mother to the Dauphin; the youngeſt had eſpouſed the Emperor, and their daughter, an only ſurviving child, had been married to the Elector of Bavaria, to whom ſhe had born that Prince who was at preſent a candidate. It ſeems that the Dauphin of France, as deſcending from the eldeſt daughter of Phillip the Fourth, had the neareſt right; but as the other nations of Europe were extremly jealous of France, it was early foreſeen that the Dauphin's claim would meet with a dangerous oppoſition. On the 1ſt of October 1698, the King of France, the King of England, and the Republic of Holland, engaged in a contract as to this ſucceſſion. Their bargain was, that the Dauphin ſhould ſucceed to the kingdoms of Naples and Sicilly, and a certain portion of the provinces of Spain itſelf. The other two candidates were to ſhare the reſt of the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and this agreement hath ſince been called the <hi>firſt</hi> treaty of partition. So vaſt an acceſſion of territory would have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered France a moſt formidable neighbour to the Dutch, and on their part the treaty ſeems to have been an act of imprudence. The ſecret of this combination having come to light, Charles in a rage inſtantly made a teſtament, by which he transferred the whole dominions of Spain, to the young Prince of Bavaria. But as the latter died ſoon after, he made a ſecond will, by which he bequeathed the ſucceſſion, alſo entire, to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke Charles, the Emperor's ſecond ſon, by a marriage which he had entered into after the death of his Spaniſh empreſs. The former parties, on the 14th March 1700, engaged in a <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> treaty of partition, by which the Dauphin was to receive a large addition to his ſhare, and the remainder was reſerved for the Emperor. This tranſaction alſo reached Charles, before it was cloſed; and in Auguſt 1699, his ambaſſador at London de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Engliſh miniſtry an intereſting appeal on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of William. He remarked, that if ſuch proceedings were allowed, no people, no dominion could be ſafe againſt the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of the ſtrongeſt, and the deceits of the moſt malicious; that ſhould ſtrangers be ſuffered to put their hands into the lines
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:028380_0044_0FD8DEA999CCD7D8"/>
of ſucceſſion of kings, no ſtatutes, no municipal laws would be obſerved; that no crown could be free from the attempts of aliens; and the crown of England leſs than any crown; and that were men to lie watching for the ſickneſs of ſovereigns, no health could be conſtant, and no life ſecure. He alſo reminded them, that the expences of a war, and the deſtruction of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, muſt be the certain conſequence of ſuch adventures.</p>
               <p>For this honeſt production, the ambaſſador was forced to leave England. On the 2d of October 1700, the King of Spain, by the advice of the Pope, made a third teſtament. To put an end to all projects of a partition, he left the whole em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, undivided, to the Duke of Anjou, the ſecond ſon of the Dauphin of France, and grandſon to Lewis the Fourteenth. By this choice, he attempted to avert the calamities of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted ſucceſſion. For as the Duke of Anjou was not heir to the crown of France, that circumſtance removed the objection of making a hazardous augmentation to the French domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. This meaſure was more ſimble, juſt, and practicable, than that adopted by William and the Dutch. On the 25th No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember 1700, Charles died; and though he bequeathed ſuch a ſplendid legacy to the houſe of Bourbon, he had been one of William's allies in his laſt long and bloody war againſt France; a fact which evinces the mutability of the political world.</p>
               <p>On the death of their ſovereign, the Spaniſh nation deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined that a conſpiracy of foreigners ſhould not be ſuffered to partition their provinces. They diſpatched a courier to the court of France with the teſtament of their late ſovereign, and if Lewis ſhould refuſe to accept the monarchy for his grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they gave him orders to proceed to Vienna, and make an offer of the univerſal ſucceſſion to the Archduke. Thus Lewis had his choice of two meaſures. If he accepted the teſtament of Charles, his grandſon was at once, and without oppoſition, put into poſſeſſion of the Spaniſh dominions, at the hazard of a quarrel with the Dutch and England. If he refuſed this offer, the Auſtrian Archduke was with equal certainty to aſcend the throne, and Lewis was to depend on the very doubtful friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his old enemies, the Dutch and England, for their aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:028380_0045_0FD8DEAB75DCCD98"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> conquer a ſhare of Spain, in oppoſition to the Emperor and that nation. But as Lewis himſelf was feared and hated both in Holland and England, there is not the leaſt probability, that he would have obtained any ſerious aid in his pretenſions, from theſe two countries. We cannot therefore with reaſon condemn him, when he accepted for the Duke of Anjou the offer of the Spaniſh crown. The reader is requeſted to pay par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular attention to this conciſe and candid ſtate of the caſe; for even at preſent, it is the vulgar opinion that Lewis acted upon this occaſion with treachery. It would be more proper to ſay, that William engaged in an enterpriſe far above his power, and that he ſhewed an utter indifference to the intereſt of his kingdoms. The preference which the Spaniſh nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon the Duke of Anjou, was in the moral ſenſe an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vindication of the acceptance of Lewis. If there be ſuch a thing as equity upon earth, it muſt begin with this maxim, that a people are at all times entitled to their choice of a maſter.</p>
               <p>On the 17th of April 1701, William acknowledged the Duke of Anjou, as the lawful ſovereign of Spain, by a letter under his own hand. The Dutch alſo recognized his right. On the 7th of September thereafter, William, with his wonted conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, entered into an alliance with the Emperor and Holland to attack the young monarch. The deſign avowed in the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles was, to obtain the Dutchy of Milan from the crown of Spain, as a compenſation to the Emperor; and Flanders, or part of it, as a barrier for Holland. What England was to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, we are not informed. On the 6th of September 1701, James the Second expired, and Lewis, on his death, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged his ſon as King of England. Though this was but an empty form, William employed it as a pretence to ſeduce the nation into a ſecond war. His project was embraced with exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation by all parties.</p>
               <p>Yet though Lewis was to blame, we ourſelves had behaved but little better. Our aſſumed title as <hi>King of France,</hi> is not only a diſhonourable untruth, but a wanton inſult to a reſpectable people. William prepared for a campaign, but happily both
<pb n="45" facs="unknown:028380_0046_0FD8DEB4388FE778"/>
for others and himſelf, a fall from his horſe put an end to his battles and his treaties, on the 8th of March 1702 <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <p>In drawing up this ſtatement, Mr. Macpherſon has been chiefly followed, with ſome additions from the Memoirs of Great Britain and Ireland, printed in 1788. In this laſt work, William is every where repreſented as a virtuous and ſublime character. The ſtory of the Counteſs of Orkney, and the trite cataſtrophe of Darien, with many others of the ſame ſort, are completely explained away. The partition treaties are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, as pregnant with future bleſſings to England; for the hiſtorian ſeems to fancy that the Allies could have divided the provinces of Spain, with the exactneſs and tranquillity of a grocer cutting a pound of cheeſe. The ſequel ſufficiently proved the abſurdity of ſuch a ſuppoſition,</p>
                     <p>This writer has aſſigned a remarkable reaſon for ſending into the world his ſecond volume. <q>But ſeeing England lately, as I thought, on the brink of ruin, becauſe ſhe was on the brink of a <hi>continental war,</hi> I thought that the pictures of miſery, even amid ſucceſs, which the continental wars of the two grand alliances preſent, might make the public attend to <hi>the proſpect before them.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is impoſſible to publiſh from more honourable motives, or to atteſt a more important truth.</p>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>Before we enter into the events of this war, it may not be improper to illuſtrate, by an exact and intereſting parallel, what Dr. Swift calls "our <hi>infamous</hi> treaty of partition." Let us ſuppoſe, that for ſome years before the death of Queen Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, all Europe had foreſeen that ſhe was to die childleſs, that James the Sixth of Scotland was to be her ſucceſſor, and that by ſuch an increaſe of dominion, England was to enſure a deciſive addition of power and importance. "No," exclaimed the Dutch, the French, and the Auſtrians, <q>WE cannot, Elizabeth, permit you and your people to chuſe a ſovereign for Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. We all know that <hi>Maſter</hi> 
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Henry the Fourth of France uſed to call him ſo.</note> James is a fool. He has married a daughter of the King of Denmark; and hence the Britiſh Empire would become but a province to the court of Copenhagen. We have formed a much better plan, and you muſt adopt it. Jerſey, Guernſey, and Plymouth, Dover caſtle, and the county of Kent, are to compoſe a frontier in the hands of his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty. The
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:028380_0047_0FD8DEB59E78A8C0"/>
iſles of Wight, Angleſea, and Man, muſt be delivered up to their High Mightineſſes for the convenience of importing gin; and you muſt likewiſe permit them to catch and cure pilchards on the coaſt of Cornwall. To Ireland you never had any title but that of a robber, and as you are deteſted by the whole nation, to the very laſt man, it is neceſſary, for preſerving <hi>the balance of power,</hi> to declare them independent. As for the reſt of your dominions, we have brought you a GERMAN maſter, born at the diſtance of a thouſand miles, a ſtranger to your country, your laws, your manners, and your language. In defence of <hi>his</hi> RIGHT, we have diſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barked on the coaſt of Yorkſhire two hundred thouſand armed ruſſians; and unleſs you inſtantly acknowledge him as ſucceſſor, we ſhall ſpread deſolation from Caithneſs to the land's end. If his Daniſh majeſty declines to aſſiſt us in overwhelming his ſon-in-law, our admirals have orders to beat Copenhagen about his ears. We are perfectly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined; and before we give up the point, we ſhall ſpend the laſt drop of our blood, and the laſt farthing of our money; beſides diving into more debt than our poſterity can pay off in an hundred generations.</q>
               </p>
               <p>On the 4th of May 1702, hoſtilities were declared againſt Spain. "We haſtily engaged in a war," ſays Swift, <q>which hath coſt us SIXTY MILLIONS, and after repeated, as well as <hi>unexpected</hi> ſucceſs in arms, hath put us and our poſterity in a worſe condition, not only than any of our allies, but than even <hi>our conquered enemies themſelves</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">The Conduct of the Allies. This is the caſe at the end of almoſt every war, and reminds me of a remark made by Lord Monboddo. Somebody once aſked him, Whether Europe or America had profited moſt by the diſcoveries of Columbus? "The balance," replied his Lordſhip, <q>is pretty equal. We gave them <hi>brandy</hi> and <hi>the ſmall-pox;</hi> and they gave us <hi>rum</hi> and <hi>the great pox.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </note>.</q> The two firſt cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigns eſcaped without any deciſive event. On the 25th of November 1702, the Commons, in conſequence of a mendicant meſſage from the Court, aſſigned the yearly ſum of an hundred thouſand pounds to the Prince of Denmark, her Majeſty's
<pb n="47" facs="unknown:028380_0048_0FD8DEB71C0533D8"/>
huſband, in caſe he ſhould ſurvive her. So extravagant a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion confirms the remark of Milton, that <hi>the trappings of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy would ſet up an ordinary commonwealth.</hi> On the 28th of October 1708, the Prince died, and as he was a perſon of the moſt innocent character, it ſounds harſhly to ſay, that his exit was deſirable. Yet had he outlived Anne, twenty thouſand neceſſitous families muſt each have paid five pounds a year of their pittance to ſupport him. And this ſingle impoſition would, while it laſted, have comprehended more ſubſtantial injuſtice and oppreſſion than all the other thefts and robberies in the country.</p>
               <p>In September 1703, Charles, the ſecond ſon of the Emperor Leopold, was declared King of Spain, and as ſuch, was acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by all the Allies, including the Dutch and England, who had both formerly recognized the title of the French Prince. It is needleſs to expatiate on the juſtice or decency of ſuch a meaſure. In Auguſt 1704, Marlborough won the battle of Blenheim. In October 1706 Lewis offered better terms of pacification <hi>than were afterwards excepted.</hi> With what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety then are we to blame <hi>his</hi> ambition? "The Whigs," ſays Mr. Macpherſon, <q>who were now poſſeſſed of the whole power of government in England, <hi>inſulted common ſenſe,</hi> in the reaſon which they gave for rejecting the propoſed peace. They ſaid, that the terms offered by France were TOO GOOD, to be the foundation for a laſting tranquillity, and therefore they ought not be admitted.</q>—Had Lewis engaged to reſtore Normandy to England, that, upon <hi>Whig</hi> principles, would have been a ſtill better reaſon for refuſing an agreement. Such were the political heroes whoſe <hi>virtues</hi> we vaunt of adopt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and by whom Europe was condemned to remain for ſix years and five months longer, a ſcene of confuſion, diſtreſs, and carnage! This inſolence very ſoon met with its reward. On the 25th of April 1707, an entire <hi>Whig</hi> army was diſperſed, taken, or extirpated, at Almanza, by the Duke of Berwick. Sixteen thouſand of the vanquiſhed were killed or made pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners. In this campaign, the Duke of Marlborough atchieved nothing worthy of his former fame. Prince Eugene, with forty
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:028380_0049_0FD8DE9C23304918"/>
thouſand men, invaded Provence, and inveſted Toulon. His forces were in danger of being ſurrounded, and his eſcape or flight was marked with the uſual and heroic circumſtances of ſlaughter and devaſtation. Four Engliſh men of war, with Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral Shovel, a perſon whoſe abilities had raiſed him from the rank of a common ſailor, foundered on the rocks of Scilly. In ſhort, the diſaſters of the Allies were ſo numerous and ſevere, that Lewis might at this time have turned the chaſe, if his counſels had not been governed by an old woman. The Scots, by a bargain ſufficiently queſtionable had been <hi>united</hi> with England. The whole nation were inflamed into a degree of madneſs. The Pretender's birth day was publicly celebrated at Edinburgh; and a memorial was tranſmitted to France by a number of nobility and gentry, who promiſed to embody in his favour five thouſand horſe and twenty-five thouſand foot. The propoſal was rejected. In 1708, the Allies were more ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and among other bleſſed events, they gained Liſle, with the loſs of eighteen or twenty thouſand men. For what no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table purpoſes have we dragged the ſmith from his anvil, and the farmer from his plow! In 1709, the Government bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the Bank of England four hundred thouſand pounds, at ſix <hi>per cent.</hi> beſides granting them ſeveral advantages, which may have raiſed the real intereſt to ten or twelve <hi>per cent.</hi> and all this for the pleaſure of making a German King of Spain. The practice of advancing money to the public was at that time, and has been ever ſince, a very profitable traffick to thoſe gentlemen of whom Lord Chatham has made ſuch honourable mention. Lewis, in the beginning of this year, had renewed his offers of peace. He attempted, as Torcy relates, to bribe the Duke of Marlborough, by a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional preſent of four millions of livres; but his Grace, after due conſideration, declined the propoſal. The aged and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate King promiſed <hi>to yield the whole Spaniſh monarchy to the Houſe of Auſtria without any equivalent</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 7.</note>. He conſented to a ſeries of the moſt degrading demands which his enemies could
<pb n="49" facs="unknown:028380_0050_0FD8DEBD1CBAC068"/>
invent, but they left him no choice between reſiſtance and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. France was in the mean time ravaged by a terrible fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, which ſerved to fill up the meaſure of univerſal wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs. Whatever we may think of Lewis himſelf, and even a deſpot may deſerve our pity, one muſt have the nerves of a Dutchman or a <hi>Whig,</hi> if he does not feel for the miſeries of twenty millions of people. On the 10th of September 1709, theſe conferences were ſucceeded by the victory of Malplaquet, which Marlborough purchaſed with the lives of twenty thouſand men, while the French, though <hi>defeated;</hi> left but eight thouſand dead on the field.</p>
               <p>In 1710, Lewis made freſh offers of ſubmiſſion. <q>He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed even a ſubſidy of a million of livres monthly to the Allies, till King Philip <hi>ſhould be driven out of Spain</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 7.</note>.</q> But mark what follows:—They required that Lewis ſhould aſſiſt them <hi>with all his forces,</hi> to expel his grandſon from the throne of that kingdom. We need not enlarge upon the baſeneſs of trampling a fallen adverſary, ſince our illuſtrious anceſtors might have improved their morality from a boxing ſtage. A ring of chairmen would be aſhamed of ſuch conſummate barbarity. Whether Lewis would have ſubmitted to this laſt act of degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is doubtful, for Eugene and Marlborough obſtructed the progreſs of explanation, and commenced the campaign.— <q>They gained three places of importance, and conquered twelve leagues of a fine country. But they loſt twenty-ſix thouſand men by the ſword. <hi>Half their infantry was ruined</hi> by wounds, diſeaſes, and fatigue <note n="†" place="bottom">Ibid.</note>.</q> In Spain, we obtained during this year two victories. Stanhope, the Engliſh general, entered Madrid. <q>The army lived at large upon the people, without order, without moderation, and without diſcipline. They raiſed contributions on private perſons. <hi>They pillaged the churches, and ſold publicly the utenſils of the altar</hi> 
                     <note n="‡" place="bottom">Ibid.</note>.</q> Nobody can be ſorry to hear that on the 8th of December 1710, theſe ruſſians were defeated. Stanhope himſelf was taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, with five thouſand Britiſh troops.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="unknown:028380_0051_0FD8DEBE96F8CC60"/>By this time the nation were almoſt tired with the expence of this war, and had begun to ſuſpect the abſurdity of its firſt principles. But as the Cabinet was comletely garriſoned by the partiſans of Marlborough, to reverſe the ſyſtem, required both a ſtrong and dexterous hand. A circumſtance in itſelf trifling contributed to this event; and the friends of mankind muſt acknowledge, that for once at leaſt, public happineſs has been promoted by public ſuperſtition. On the 3d of November 1709, Henry Sacheverell, a Tory parſon, preached at St. Paul's a ſermon, in which he enforced, with much virulence, the nonſenſe about paſſive obedience and non-reſiſtance. In this performance, the Earl of Godolphin. Lord High Treaſurer of England, and one of the chief leaders of the Whigs, was perſonally attacked, and the whole party were eager to puniſh the man who had thus conteſted their darling doctrines. They brought him to a trial before the Houſe of Peers; and this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure gave the Tories an opportunity for aſſerting <hi>that the Church was in danger.</hi> The great body of the people broke into a tranſport of rage. <q>The current, which had been long chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ran down with a force, that levelled every thing before it <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 8.</note>.</q> During the trial, the pews of five diſſenting meeting-houſes were burnt in the ſtreets. The outrages of the rabble were directed by perſons of higher rank, who attended at their heels in hackney coaches; the watch word was—<hi>The Church and Sacheverell.</hi> Thoſe who joined not in the ſhout were inſulted and knocked down; and Burnet tells us, that at his door one man got his ſkull cleft with a ſpade, for his refuſal. The ſermon was ordered to be burnt by the hangman, but the public flame was kept up with much addreſs by the Tories. Sacheverell made a journey into Wales, and was every where received with raptures of admiration. The Queen, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, embraced this opportunity to free herſelf from the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of an inſolent faction. On the 8th of Auguſt 1710, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphin was diſmiſſed. A new parliament was ſummoned to meet on the 25th of November thereafter. The frenzy of the
<pb n="51" facs="unknown:028380_0052_0FD8DEC6A1C468C0"/>
mob was ſupported by the ſubſtantial logic of the Treaſury; and a majority was returned of Tory members. Harley, the new miniſter, and his aſſociates, had too much ſenſe to diſcover abruptly their deſigns to the people. The ſum of fourteen mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions five hundred and ſeventy-three thouſand, three hundred and nineteen pounds, nineteen ſhillings and eight pence half-penny, was voted to diſcharge the arrears in the navy and other offices, and the ſervices of the current year. At this critical moment, a ſecond ſtroke of fortune advanced the pacific views of the Tories. On the 1ſt of May 1705, the Emperor Leopold had d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>: and on the 6th of April 1711, his eldeſt ſon and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, Joſeph, died alſo; and without regarding his own two daughters, left his brother Charles, <hi>our intended, King of Spain,</hi> his univerſal heir. <q>His death <hi>ſuddenly changed the whole ſtate of affairs.</hi> The war undertaken by the grand alliance for preſerving the balance of Europe, was now <hi>likely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it for ever;</hi> and men who judged of the future by the paſt, began to dread the irreſiſtible power of the Emperor Charles the Fifth, in the perſon of a prince of his family <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 8.</note>.</q> Hence, <hi>even upon our own mad principles,</hi> it became juſt as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to oppoſe the ſucceſſion of our candidate Charles, as that of the Duke of Anjou. Yet with the moſt aſtoniſhing impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, the Whigs and our Allies, Charles and the Dutch, were anxious to continue the war. The German princes, and among others, the Elector of Hanover <note n="†" place="bottom">In a Memorial printed by his envoy, and a letter from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Harley, dated November 7, 1711.</note>, expreſſed their higheſt diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the projected peace. The arguments of George, if ſuch they may be called, are too frivolous for confutation or inſertion here. Portugal and Savoy ſeconded the German chorus. <q>The emoluments derived from war were greater than their expectations from peace.—The money of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritime powers, and chiefly that of England, more than the territories of the Houſe of Bourbon, was the grand object of thoſe petty tyrants, who <hi>fed on the blood of ſubjects whom they
<pb n="52" facs="unknown:028380_0053_0FD8DEC797905170"/>
let out for ſlaughter</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 8. Seventeen thouſand of theſe miſerable victims were at one time furniſhed by the Court of Hanover. <hi>Macpherſon's State Papers,</hi> vol. ii. p. 497.</note>.</q> Compared with merchants of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, an ordinary offender is a paragon of innocence. When a nation ſends for ſovereigns from ſuch a ſchool, there appears but a melancholy preſage of the proſpect before it.</p>
               <p>The campaign of 1711, elapſed without effort on either ſide. The ſurrender of Bouchain on the 13th of September, cloſed the military exploits of the Duke of Marlborough. The new miniſter of England had been engaged in attempting to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile the demands of the contending powers. But the States of Holland were ſo much exaſperated by the conduct of Queen Anne, that they were at no pains in concealing their deſign to treat her as they had treated her father. They propoſed <q>to fit out a fleet to aſſiſt the Elector of Hanover to ſtrike the ſceptre from her hand <note n="†" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 8.</note>.</q> On the 7th of December, parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment met. Harley had ſecured a Tory majority in the Houſe of Commons; but his party was ſomewhat inferior in the Houſe of Peers. Affairs had now come to a criſis. The leaders of the Whigs were ſuſpected of intending an immediate appeal to arms. It became therefore neceſſary to diſmiſs the Duke of Marlborough from his military command; and on the laſt day of December, Harley produced what is now called <hi>a batch of peers.</hi> Twelve gentlemen devoted to the court were created members of the Upper Houſe. Anne had the very ſame right to have created twelve thouſand. The conſtitution of Britain, like the ſword of Dionyſius, hangs by a ſingle hair.</p>
               <p>On the 17th of January 1712, Mr. Walpole was committed to the Tower. He had received five hundred guineas, and a note for five hundred more, for two contracts when ſecretary at war, for ſupplying the forces in Scotland with forage. <q>A member, ſays Burnet, who was a Whig, was expelled the Houſe; and a proſecution was ordered againſt him:—but <hi>the abuſe goes on ſtill, as avowedly as ever.</hi>
                  </q> The Duke of Marlborough's conduct underwent a ſevere cenſure, and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donnel,
<pb n="53" facs="unknown:028380_0054_0FD8DEC91CE4D1F0"/>
his ſecretary, was expelled by the Commons. The campaign of 1712 was unfortunate on the part of the Allies. The Britiſh forces under the command of the Duke of Ormond remained inactive; and even the abſence of the abilities of Marl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough ſeems to have been ſeverely felt. The peace was not finally ſettled till March 1713. The Whig faction, to their eternal infamy, ſtrained every nerve to prevent it. By this peace, beſides the iſlands of Minorca and St. Chriſtopher's, and the fortreſs of Gibraltar, for ourſelves, we obtained the iſland of Sicily for the Duke of Savoy, which produced the Spaniſh war in 1718, a partial right for our merchants of trading to South America, which began the Spaniſh war of 1739, and Nova Scotia, which gave riſe to the French war in 1756. This war was more deſtructive than that of 1689, as it laſted for eleven campaigns. Dr. Swift computes that each of them coſt us ſix or ſeven millions ſterling. The loſs of lives and of ſhipping could be hardly, if at all inferior to that of the former war, as our battles were numerous, and as the protection of our commerce was altogether neglected. In a word, the nation ſquandered ſeventy or eighty millions, that Marlborough might pilfer <hi>one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To Dr. Swift we are much indebted for the termination of this war. His pamphlet on <hi>The Conduct of the Allies,</hi> excited a ſort of political earthquake, and more than all his admirable verſes muſt endear him to diſtant poſterity. A few paſſages may ſerve as a ſpecimen of the reſt. "It will appear," ſays he, <q>by plain matters of fact, that no nation was ever ſo long, or ſo ſcandalouſly abuſed, by the folly, the temerity, the corruption, and the ambition of its domeſtic enemies; or treated with ſo much inſolence, injuſtice, and ingratitude, by its foreign friends.—We are deſtroying many thouſand lives, and exhauſting our ſubſtance, not for our own intereſt, which would be but common prudence; not for a thing indifferent, which would be ſufficient folly; but perhaps to our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, which is perfect madneſs.—The common queſtion is, if we muſt now ſurrender Spain, what have we been fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for all this while? The anſwer is ready. We have been fighting for the ruin of the public intereſt, and the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="54" facs="unknown:028380_0055_0FD8DECFBA192B40"/>
of a private. We have been fighting to raiſe the wealth and grandeur of a particular family;</q> (that of Marl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,) <q>to enrich uſurers and ſtockjobbers, and to culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the pernicious deſigns of a faction, by deſtroying the landed intereſt.—Since the monied men are ſo fond of war, I ſhould be glad if they would furniſh out one campaign <hi>at their own charge.</hi> It is not above ſix or ſeven millions; and I dare engage to make it out, that, <hi>when they have done this,</hi> inſtead of contributing equal to the landed men, they will have their full principal and intereſt at ſix <hi>per cent.</hi> remaining of all the money they ever lent to the government.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Even at this day, we are deafened about the glorious victories of the Duke of Marlborough, and though by the death of the Emperor Joſeph, the object of diſpute was utterly extinguiſhed, a crowd of authors perſiſt in lamenting that our commander was checked in the career of pillage and butchery. Happy might it have been for this country, had Marlborough, with all his forces, periſhed on the field of Blenheim; ſince it may be ſuppoſed, that ſuch a ſtroke would at once have blaſted our cruſades upon the continent. As if his Grace had not enjoyed ſufficient opportunities of plundering the treaſury of the nation, as if the manor of Woodſtock, the palace of Blenheim <note n="*" place="bottom">Dr. Swift eſtimates Woodſtock at forty thouſand pounds, and adds, that Blenheim Houſe had coſt two hundred thouſand pounds, and was at the time of his writing <hi>unfiniſhed.</hi> There can be no wonder, that we muſt now pay nine-pence per pound of importation duty for Peruvian bark, and three guineas for leave to ſhoot a partriage worth two-pence.</note>, and an hundred thouſand pounds a year <note n="†" place="bottom">The ſum has been ſtated higher, but ſuch computations are always in part random.</note>, had not been adequate to the ſervices of himſelf and his Ducheſs, we are ſaddled with as annual payment of five thouſand pounds to his family for ever. When a conſtitution, deſerving that name, ſhall ſucceed our preſent political anarchy, it is not difficult to foreſee ſome of the firſt objects of reformation. The Earl of Chatham en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys four thouſand pounds a year, becauſe his father added ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty millions to the national debt. The Duke of Richmond raiſes from the city of London an annual revenue, ſaid to be
<pb n="55" facs="unknown:028380_0056_0FD8DED0A1950BC0"/>
twenty thouſand pounds, becauſe he is deſcended from the ſon of a criminal <note n="*" place="bottom">Charles II.</note>, who deſerved an hundred times over to have been ſtogged out of human ſociety.</p>
               <p>As a commentary on the preceding narrative, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult a quotation from Dr. Johnſon's pamphlet on Falkland's iſlands. The reflections which it contains have more than once extorted, in my hearing, the admiration of the late Dr. Adam Smith, who was far from being a general advocate for this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>It is wonderful, with what coolneſs and indifference the greater part of mankind ſee war commenced. Thoſe who hear of it at a diſtance, or read of it in books, but have never preſented its evils to their minds, conſider it as little more than a ſplendid gaine, a proclamation, an army, a battle, and a triumph. Some indeed muſt periſh in the moſt ſucceſsful field, but they die upon the bed of honour, <hi>reſign their lives amidſt the joys of conqueſt, and, filled with England's glory, ſmile in death.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The life of a modern ſoldier is ill repreſented by heroic fiction. War has means of deſtruction more formidable than the cannon and the ſword. Of the thouſands and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands who periſhed in our late conteſts with France and Spain, a very ſmall part ever felt the ſtroke of an enemy; the reſt languiſhed in tents and ſhips, amidſt damps and putrefaction; pale, torpid, ſpiritleſs, and helpleſs; gaſping and groaning, unpitied among men, made obdurate by a long continuance of hopeleſs miſery; and were at laſt whelmed in pits, or heaved into the ocean, without notice, and without remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. By incommodious encampments, and unwholeſome ſtations, where courage is uſeleſs, and enterpriſe impractica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, fleets are ſilently diſpeopled <note n="†" place="bottom">
                        <p>The manning of a fleet has often produced almoſt as much miſchief as its <hi>depopulation.</hi> On this ſubject there is here ſubjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a ſhort but ſhocking ſtory, which happened about the time when Dr. Johnſon's pamphlet was firſt printed, and which can harbly be regarded as a digreſſion, ſince it reflects additional hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror on the war ſyſtem.</p>
                        <p>A workman, in London, was apprehended by a preſs gang. His wife and child were turned to the door by their landlord. Within a few days after ſhe was delivered of a ſecond child in a garret. On her recovery, ſhe was driven to the ſtreets as a common beggar. She went into a ſhop, and attempted to carry off a ſmall piece of linen. She was ſeized, tried, and condemned to be hanged. In her defence ſhe ſaid, that ſhe had lived creditably and happy, till a preſs gang robbed her of her huſband, and in him, of all means to ſupport herſelf and her family; and that in attempting to clothe her new born infant, ſhe perhaps did wrong, as ſhe did not, at that time, know what ſhe did. The pariſh officers, and other witneſſes, bore teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the truth of her averment, but all to no purpoſe. ſhe was ordered for Tyburn. <hi>The hangman dragged her ſucking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant from her breaſt, when he ſtrained the cord about her neck.</hi> On the 13th May 1777, Sir William Meredith mentioned this aſſaſſination in the Houſe of Commons. <q>Never, ſaid he, was there a fouler murder committed againſt the law, than that of this woman by the law.</q>—Such were the fruits of what Engliſhmen call <hi>their ineſtimable privilege of a trial by jury.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It would not be difficult to fill a large volume with deciſions of this ſtamp, though there is not perhaps any ſingle caſe, which is in all its circumſtances ſo abſolutely infernal. The reader may compare the <hi>guilt,</hi> as it was termed, of Mary Jones, with the progreſs of thoſe <hi>noble patriots,</hi> whoſe hiſtory is recorded in the next chapter, and who are at this day held up as the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours of Britain, and then ſay which of the two parties beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a halter.</p>
                        <p>General Gunning, a man who is not worth a ſhilling, was lately fined in five thouſand pounds for ſeducing a doxy who was as forward as himſelf; and Mr. Tatterſal, the editor of a London newſpaper his juſt now been fined in four thouſand pounds for a paragraph which aſſerted, that a lady had an amour with her footman. It was proved that Mr. Tatterſal was at a great diſtance from London, when this ſtory was print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and conſequently, that had it been even a forgery on the Bank of England, the law could not have touched a hair of his head. There can be no doubt that the lady will accept the laſt farthing aſſigned by this verdict, and ſuch an acceptance can leave no ſtriking impreſſion of female generoſity. Another ſplendid ſpecimen of an Engliſh jury ſhall conclude this long note.</p>
                        <p>Some years ago, Mr. Cooper, of London, was accuſed of being the printer and publiſher of a performance deemed a libel. Upon ſtrict inquiry, it was found, that it had been printed at his office; but it was proved, that at the time when this was done, he was in ſo dangerous a ſtate of health, as to be given up by the phyſician who attended him, and that for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral months before the publication, as well as at that period, he had been entirely diſabled by ſickneſs from either attending his office, or knowing what was doing in it. Notwithſtanding theſe circumſtances, a Middleſex jury found him guilty; and, as ſoon as he had recovered from his ſickneſs, he was placed on the pillory, and, no doubt, would have been pelted by miniſterial hirlings, had not a number of reſpectable gentlemen prevented it by their perſonal attendance.—So much for the liberty of the preſs, when protected by a Middleſex jury.</p>
                     </note>, and armies ſluggiſhly melted away.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="unknown:028380_0057_0FD8DED40FB04BE0"/>
                  <q>Thus is a people gradually exhauſted, for the moſt part with little effect. The wars of civilized nations make very
<pb n="57" facs="unknown:028380_0058_0FD8DED52261BA30"/>
ſlow changes in the ſyſtem of empire. The public perceives ſcarcely any alteration but an increaſe of debt; and the few individuals who are benefited, are not ſuppoſed to have the cleareſt right to their advantages. If he who ſhared the danger enjoyed the profit, and after bleeding in the battle grew rich by the victory, he might ſhew his gains without envy. But at the concluſion of a ten year's war, how are we recompenſed for the death of multitudes, and the expence of millions, but by contemplating the ſudden glories of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters and agents, contractors and commiſſaries, whoſe equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pages ſhine like meteors, and whoſe palaces riſe like exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The are the men who, without virtue, labour, or hazard, are growing rich as their country is impoveriſhed; they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice when obſtinacy or ambition adds another year to ſlaughter and devaſtation; and laugh from their deſks at bravery and ſcience, while they are adding figure to figure, and cipher to cipher, hoping for a new contract from a new armament, and computing the profits of a ſiege or a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="unknown:028380_0059_0FD8DED89632BD40"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Where I have treated high life with freedom, I hope I ſhall not be underſtood to propagate the doctrine of levellers.—I have no ſuch intention.—I mean to give a juſt picture of human life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> according to my own knowledge of it, and according to my ſenſe of truth, without ceremony or diſguiſe.—I do not wiſh, in any degree, to diminiſh the reſpect which is juſtly due to perſons and families of diſtinction.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Letter to the People of Laurencekirk.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THERE is not in hiſtory a more ſignal example of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, than the conduct of the Emperor, the Dutch, and Marlborough, to the Queen of England. She had fought for ten years the battles of her Allies. She had advanced her ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to be the firſt ſubject in Europe. When ſhe refuſed to complete the ruin of her country for the caprice of the former, when the inſolence of the latter compelled her to diſmiſs him, loaded with the plunder of nations, from her preſence, theſe worthy aſſociates conſpired for the deſtruction of their bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factreſs. It is not certain that William himſelf had ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded into ſuch a climax of baſeneſs. Though his partition treaties were abſurd in a Britiſh ſovereign, we may forgive, in his hoſtilities with Lewis, the reſentment of a Dutchman. When we peruſe the plan of Eugene for ſetting fire to the ſtreets of London, and the palace of St. James's <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. 2, chap. 9.</note>, even his tranſcendant behaviour at the Revolution almoſt fades before it.</p>
               <p>By the prudence and firmneſs of Harley, the plots of Eugene were diſcovered and diſappointed; and on the 17th of March 1712, he was obliged to embark with ſome precipitation for the Continent. The neutrality of the Engliſh forces in the next campaign, with the final termination of the war, has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready been mentioned. It does not appear that the Elector of Hanover was engaged in the ſcheme of dethroning Anne. His
<pb n="59" facs="unknown:028380_0060_0FD8DEDB18CA67B0"/>
beggarly condition may have contributed to the moderation of his ſentiments. In 1713, he ſolicited from the Engliſh Crown a penſion for his mother the Princeſs Sophia. <q>In the preſent ſituation of his affairs, a freſh ſupply of revenue was much wanted. His agents every where complained of their too ſcanty allowance. The Whigs, with all their patriotiſm, <hi>were ſoliciting for penſions.</hi> Some <hi>Lords,</hi> who were zealous for the Proteſtant ſucceſſion, were, it ſeems, <hi>too poor to follow their conſciences. They had ſold their votes to the Miniſtry.</hi> But—<hi>they would take ſmaller ſums from</hi> HIS ELECTORAL HIGHNESS. The Earl of Sunderland, in his attachment to the family of Brunſwick, had advanced three hundred pounds to one of theſe poor <hi>conſcientious</hi> Lords. The Earl wiſhed <hi>to ſee this ſum repaid.</hi> Though the Elector might be willing to gratify ſuch faithful friends, he had reaſon to expect that <hi>they would help to ſerve themſelves.</hi> They were, therefore deſired to promote, with all their influence, the penſion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded for the Princeſs. His Highneſs was no ſtranger, upon the preſent occaſion, either to the abilities or poverty of the Duke of Argyle. The whole world knew his love of money, He deſired that nobleman, and his brother the Earl of Ilay, to promote the allowance to the Electreſs, as <hi>they might expect good penſions to themſelves from that fund</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 9. and Hanover Papers, Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary 27, 1713.</note>.</q> This penſion was never obtained; and the Electreſs herſelf died about ſixteen months after, on the 28th of May 1714. <q>The Elector himſelf ſeems to have become indifferent concerning the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of his family to the throne. Teazed by the unmean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing profeſſions of the Tories, and haraſſed by the demands of the Whigs, he dropped all correſpondence with both parties. He ſuffered his ſervants to continue their intrigues in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. He liſtened to their intelligence. But to the requiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Whiggiſh friends for money, <hi>he turned a deaf ear.</hi> He was however perſuaded at length, to order ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds to the Lord Fitzwalter, to enable that NEEDY
<pb n="60" facs="unknown:028380_0061_0FD8DEDD154772E0"/>
PEER to pay a debt of three hundred pounds to Sunderland. <hi>He allowed forty pounds to the author of a newſpaper, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying to the public, paragraphs favourable to</hi> THE PROTES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TANT SUCCESSION. He added ten pounds to that <hi>(immenſe)</hi> ſum, <hi>after various repreſentations from his council and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 9.</note>."—"The excluded party in Britain haraſſed, at the ſame time, the Elector, with propoſals <hi>for his invading the kingdom with a body of troops.</hi> They ſuggeſted, that ſhould the Dutch refuſe a ſquadron of men of war, ſome ſhips of force might be obtained from Denmark. But the Elector rejected the ſcheme, as utterly improper and impracticable <note n="†" place="bottom">Ibid. This was about the 21ſt of March 1713, a full year after the departure of Prince Eugene. Their objects were to prevent the peace, which was ſigned about this time, to recover their places, and ruin the Miniſtry.</note>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>On the 9th of April 1713, the Queen opened a ſeſſion of parliament. The ſtream of popularity had now turned againſt the Whigs. <q>In this diſtreſsful ſituation, they implored Kreyenbeg to lay their humble ſolicitations <hi>at the feet</hi> of the Elector. They entreated his Highneſs, for the ſake of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to ſend over the Electoral Prince. Without the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of one of the family, they ſolemnly averred, that the ſucceſſion muſt inevitably be defeated <note n="‡" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 10.</note>.</q> All this canting had very little foundation in fact. The bulk of the nation were determined in favour of the Proteſtant ſucceſſion. But theſe ſycophants wiſhed to make themſelves of importance with George the Firſt. The following paſſage will ſet the nature and motives of their conduct in a proper light.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Whigs had, in the beginning of the year (1713) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſed the Elector with demands of <hi>penſions for</hi> POOR LORDS. They had perpetually teazed his Highneſs for money to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical writers, and for ſpies planted round the Pretender. Though their ſolicitations on theſe ſubjects had been at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with little ſucceſs, they continued to make applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſame diſagreeable kind. When the ſeſſion was
<pb n="61" facs="unknown:028380_0062_0FD8DEDE1D927EE0"/>
drawing to a concluſion, and a diſſolution was foreſeen, they demanded <hi>one hundred thouſand pounds</hi> from the Elector, <hi>to corrupt boroughs, to influence elections, and to return men of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutional and</hi> WHIGGISH <hi>principles</hi> to the enſuing parliament. The magnitude of the ſum left no room for heſitation in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting their requeſt. One repulſe, however, was not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent either to intimidate or diſcourage a party ſo eager in the purſuit of their deſigns. They diminiſhed their demand to <hi>fifty thouſand pounds.</hi> The Elector plainly told them, that he could not ſpare the money. That he had done the greateſt ſervice conſiſtent with his own particular ſituation, and the ſtate of Europe in general, to the well affected in Britain. That he had engaged the Emperor and Empire <hi>to continue the war againſt France.</hi> That he had employed <hi>ſeventeen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> of his troops againſt that kingdom. That this circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance had deprived the French King of the power of ſending an army into Britain with the Pretender. That could he even advance the money, which was far from being the caſe, the ſecret could never be kept; and that a diſcovery might be dangerous, from the offence that the meaſure was likely to give to the Britiſh nations<note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 10.</note>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Within a few pages, we meet with freſh applications of the ſame kind. <q>The Whigs again urged the Elector <hi>to invade the kingdom.</hi> They promiſed to furniſh him with ſums, upon his credit, <hi>to ſave their country,</hi> and to execute his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; but with an inconſiſtence repugnant to theſe large promiſes, they reverted to their former demands of money from his Highneſs. They aſked penſions <hi>for poor conſcientious Lords who were in want of ſubſiſtence.</hi> They demanded, with the moſt vehement entreaties, <hi>two thouſand pounds,</hi> to carry the elections for <hi>the Common Council of London.</hi> They repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, that, with that ſum, they could chuſe their own crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and terrify the Queen and parliament with remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances and addreſſes throughout the winter <note n="†" place="bottom">Ibid.</note>.</q> It is not ſurpriſing that Mr. Macpherſon is a moſt unpopular hiſtorian.
<pb n="62" facs="unknown:028380_0063_0FD8DEE35A962700"/>
But the facts which he has advanced are unqueſtionably true. The original correſpondence of the parties is ſtill extant in their own hand writing. Let us proceed, therefore, with a few far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extracts from this authentic and inſtructive author. <q>A propoſal made by the Baron de Bernſtorff, Preſident of the Elector's Council, was received by Marlborough and Cado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan with eagerneſs and joy. He inſinuated, that his Electoral Highneſs might be induced to borrow to the extent of <hi>twenty thouſand pounds</hi> from his friends in Britain. This ſum was to be laid out on the <hi>poor Lords,</hi> and <hi>the Common Council of London,</hi> during the three years the parliament was to ſit. The firſt would be thus enabled to vote according to their <hi>principles;</hi> the latter might ply the Government, and haraſs the Queen and her miniſters with remonſtrances in favour of civil liberty and <hi>the Proteſtant ſucceſſion.</hi> Marlborough and Cadogan undertook to furniſh the money on the obligation of his Electoral Highneſs, provided the intereſt of five <hi>per cent. ſhould be regularly paid.</hi> But his Highneſs would give no obligation either for the principal or intereſt. He how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſignified to his agents, that his friends ſhould advance the money, as they might be certain of being reimburſed as ſoon as his Highneſs, or the Electreſs his mother, ſhould come to the throne <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 10.</note>." It does not appear that his friends choſe to advance their money on this promiſe.</q> On the 20th of March 1714, George made anſwer to ſome freſh demands <q>of money for poor Lords, Common Councils, bribery of members, and private penſions, that <hi>he would hear</hi> NO MORE OF THAT AFFAIR. That, from the narrowneſs of his own income, he could not enter upon theſe heads, into any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with his antagoniſt, the Lord Treaſurer. But that, <hi>except in the article of expences,</hi> he was willing to ſupport, to the utmoſt, their party <note n="†" place="bottom">Ibid.</note>.</q> It would be idle to ſuppoſe that one part of the iſland was leſs corrupted than another. In July 1713, <q>the Duke of Argyle told Halifax, that <hi>with twenty thouſand pounds,</hi> he would anſwer for all the elections in
<pb n="63" facs="unknown:028380_0064_0FD8DEE864B5BC50"/>
Scotland <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon's State Papers, vol. ii. p. 498.</note>.</q> The reaſon aſſigned for refuſing theſe applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, was clear and ſatisfactory. A letter from the Court of Hanover contains theſe words:—<q>The Elector cannot give the money demanded for the elections. Beſides, he ſhould fail infallibly, as the Court <hi>would always have the heavieſt purſe</hi> 
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Ibid. p. 497.</note>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Nothing is more ſurpriſing, than the inaccuracy which abounds in many, even of our beſt hiſtorians. There cannot be ſtronger proofs imagined of the corruption of both Houſes of Parliament, than what have been juſt now produced. Yet, with this blaze of evidence before his eyes, the writer of the Memoirs of Britain has advanced a very ſtrange aſſertion.— When ſpeaking of Mr. Duncombe's acquittal in the Houſe of Peers, in 1695, he adds, <q>For the honour of the Houſe of Lords, <hi>this is the only inſtance in Engliſh hiſtory,</hi> in which the diſtribution of private money was ſuſpected to have had influence with a number of Peers <note n="‡" place="bottom">Memoirs of Britain, vol. ii. part 3d, Book iv.</note>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>After ſuch a ſpecimen of the honeſty of the Whigs it would be unneceſſary to enumerate all the other methods which they fell upon to embaraſs their unfortunate Queen. One of their ſchemes was, to bring over the Elector Prince, under the title of the Duke of Cambridge, as a head to their party. But un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckily this project was equally diſagreeable to the Elector of Hanover and to the Queen. In a letter to George, dated 30th May 1714, <q>I am determined," ſays Anne, "to oppoſe a project ſo contrary to my royal authority, however fatal the conſequences may be <note n="§" place="bottom">State Papers, vol. ii. p. 621.</note>.</q> And George himſelf abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed every propoſal of this kind. <q>His refuſal was ſo peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, that the Whigs, and even his ſervants, made no ſcruple of aſcribing his conduct to <hi>a jealouſy of his own ſon</hi> 
                     <note n="‖" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 10.</note>.</q> It has been ſaid, a thouſand times over, that George the Firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained the moſt violent ſuſpicion as to the legitimacy of his
<pb n="64" facs="unknown:028380_0065_0FD8DEE95E93FCD8"/>
ſon; and that his jealouſy was fatal to the life of a Swediſh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleman. His wife, the Princeſs of Zell, was at this very time in confinement for her amours; and in this ſituation the unhappy woman died, after a melancholy captivity of thirty-ſix years.</p>
               <p>Another modeſt contrivance to haraſs the Queen, deſerves peculiar notice. On the 8th of April 1714, <q>it was propoſed to requeſt her Majeſty to iſſue a proclamation, ſetting a price <hi>on her brother's head.</hi> The Tory Lords repreſented, that the motion was as inconſiſtent with common humanity, as it was repugnant to the Chriſtian religion; that to ſet a price on any man's head, was to encourage aſſaſſination by public au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; and that ſhould ever the caſe come before them, as peers and judges, they would think themſelves bound, in juſtice, honour, and conſcience, to condemn ſuch an action as murther. The Whigs <hi>argued upon the ground of</hi> EXPEDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENCY <note n="*" place="bottom">Macpherſon, vol. ii. chap. 10.</note>.</q> The motion was rejected.</p>
               <p>The Whigs did not always confine their operations to bribery. We may comprehend from what follows, the genuine character of ſome of their principal leaders. In 1694, William planned an expedition againſt Breſt. The particulars were betrayed to James the Second, in a letter from Marlborough, where he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains that Admiral Ruſſel was not ſufficiently hearty in the cauſe of the exiled. In conſequence of this act of treachery, the Engliſh forces were repulſed on their landing at Breſt. Six hundred were ſlain, and many wounded; one Dutch frigate was ſunk after loſing almoſt her whole crew. Another example may ſerve to ſhow the character of there leaders in a proper light. In 1695, Sir John Fenwick, a Major-General, had been engaged with Penn, the founder of Philadelphia, and others, in a project for a rebellion in England, and had, on its diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, fled. Some time after he returned, was found out, and arreſted. To ſave his life, he tranſmitted to the King an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the treaſonable correſpondence of Godolphin, Marl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough, Ruſſel, and many other <hi>Whigs of diſtinction</hi> with James. His accuſation <q>is now known to have been in all
<pb n="65" facs="unknown:028380_0066_0FD8DEEADBA54540"/>
points true;</q> and as there was only one evidence againſt him, <q>he could not be convicted in <hi>a court of law,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired two." But the perſons whom he had accuſed, "be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that they could not be ſafe <hi>as long as he lived.</hi>
                  </q> A bill of attainder was therefore brought in againſt him, and Ruſſel appeared at the head of the proſecution. The ſequel produced a crowd of proceedings <q>which exceeded the injuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the worſt precedents in the worſt times of Charles the Second and his ſucceſſor;</q> and the whole were vindicated by Burnet, in a long ſpeech. The bill paſſed both houſes by a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row majority; and on the 28th of January 1696, Fenwick was beheaded on Tower-hill, <hi>"without evidence or law."</hi> Lady Fenwick attempted to bribe a perſon whoſe teſtimony ſhe dreaded, to fly the kingdom. The accuſers prevailed on this wretch to place people behind a curtain to overhear the offer; <q>and this attempt of a wife to ſave her huſband's life from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <hi>was turned into an evidence of his guilt</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Memoirs of Britain, vol. ii. part 3. book 7.</note>.</q> Theſe are the words of a hiſtorian, who is himſelf a profeſſed Whig, who has been a lawer, and is now a Judge. It is difficult to ſay, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the conduct of the parliament, who paſſed ſuch a ſentence, or of his Majeſty who ſigned it, was moſt completely inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſencible.</p>
               <p>On the 1ſt of Auguſt 1714, Queen Anne died; and as much has been ſaid in praiſe of her virtues, a ſhort account of a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action conducted by her Tory parliament is here inſerted, which in part is abridged from the Anecdotes of the Earl of Chatham.</p>
               <p>It has been told by many hiſtorians, that for four years, Queen Anne gave an hundred thouſand pounds <hi>per annum</hi> out of her civil liſt, to ſupport the war againſt France; and hence they deduce an argument of the oeconomy and patriotiſm of that Princeſs.—But, on the 25th of june 1713, her Majeſty ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the Commons that ſhe had contracted a very large debt upon the revenues of the civil liſt; and ſhe ſpecified that this deficiency amounted in Auguſt 1710, to four hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds.—Mr. Smith, one of the tellers in the Exchequer,
<pb n="66" facs="unknown:028380_0067_0FD8DEEF31907230"/>
who ſeems to have been too honeſt a man for his office, aroſe and informed the Houſe, that the eſtimate of this debt was to him aſtoniſhing; as at the time pointed out, he could affirm, that the debt amounted to little more than an hundred thouſand pounds. Other members undertook to prove, that the funds aſſigned to her Majeſty for ſeven hundred thouſand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> had produced <hi>eight</hi> hundred thouſand pounds, ſo that in the courſe of eleven years, her Majeſty had received eleven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand pounds of an <hi>overplus,</hi> and after deducing the pretended <hi>gift</hi> of four hundred thouſand pounds, ſhe had ſtill <hi>ſeven hundred thouſand pounds ſterling</hi> of the public money in her pocket. Though this was the ſame virtuous aſſembly which had expelled Walpole from bribery, theſe obſervations could not obtain attention; ſince the very next day the Houſe voted five hundred and ten thouſand pounds for payment of this debt. <q>This, adds the hiſtorian, is the truth, and the whole truth of that generous exploit of the daughter of James the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. It was a mean trick, by which the nation was cheated of four hundred thouſand pounds <note n="*" place="bottom">Anecdotes of the Earl of Chatham, vol. ii. p. 50.</note>.</q> He ſhould have ſaid, five hundred and ten thouſand pounds, for that was the exact ſum granted.</p>
               <p>It is entertaining to remark the ſtyle in which a courtier ſometimes talks of his ſovereign. When William, in a fit of deſpondency, had once threatened to reſign the crown of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <q>Does he ſo?" ſaid Sunderland, "there is Tom of Pembroke, (meaning Lord Pembroke) who is as good a block of wood <hi>as a king can be cut out of.</hi> We will ſend for him, and make <hi>him</hi> our KING <note n="†" place="bottom">Memoire of Great Britain, vol. ii. part 3. book 7.</note>.</q> To the ſame purpoſe the Princeſs of Wales, in 1753, expreſſed herſelf as to George the Second, in a converſation with Mr. Dodington. <q>She ſaid, with great warmth, that when they talked to her of the King, ſhe loſt all patience, for ſhe knew <hi>it was nothing:</hi> that in theſe great points ſhe reckoned the King no more <hi>than one of the trees we walked by,</hi> or ſomething more inconſiderable which ſhe named, but that it was their puſillanimity <hi>which
<pb n="67" facs="unknown:028380_0068_0FD8DEF197D66AC0"/>
would make an end of them.</hi>"—"She ſaid, that if they talked of the King, ſhe was out of patience; it was as if they ſhould tell her, that her little Harry below would not do what was proper for him; that juſt ſo the King would <hi>ſputter</hi> and <hi>make a buſtle,</hi> but when they told him that it <hi>muſt</hi> be done from the neceſſity of his ſervice, he muſt do it, <hi>as little Harry muſt,</hi> when ſhe came down <note n="*" place="bottom">Dodington's Diary, p. 205, and 213.</note>.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>I am no orator as Brutus is,</l>
                     <l>To ſtir men's blood; I only ſpeak right on.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I tell you that which you yourſelves do know.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <bibl>SHAKESPEARE.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE hiſtory of England has been continued in the laſt chapter, to the beginning of the diſaſtrous but memorable reign of George the Firſt. We ſhall cloſe this part of the work with ſome general obſervations on the civil liſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>There we find places piled on places, to the height of the tower of Babel. There we find a maſter of the houſehold, treaſurer of the houſehold, comptroller of the houſehold, cofferer of the houſehold, deputy-cofferer of the houſehold, clerks of the houſehold, clerks comptrollers of the houſehold, clerks comptrollers deputy-clerks of the houſehold, office keepers, chamber-keepers, neceſſary-houſe-keepers, purvey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors of bread, purveyors of wine, purveyors of fiſh, purvey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors of butter and eggs, purveyors of confectionary, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verers of greens, coffee-women, ſpicery-men, ſpicery men's aſſiſtant-clerks, ewry-men, ewry-men's aſſiſtant-clerks, kitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en-clerks-comptrollers, kitchen-clerk-comptroller's firſt clerks, kitchen clerk-comptroller's junior clerks, yeomen
<pb n="68" facs="unknown:028380_0069_0FD8BE6EA727C9D8"/>
of the mouth, under yeomen of the mouth, grooms, grooms children, paſtry-yeomen, harbingers, harbingers yeomen, keepers of ice houſes, cart-takers, cart-takers grooms, bell-ringers, cock and cryer, table-deckers, water engine turners, ciſtern cleaners, keeper of fire buckets, and a thouſand or two more of the ſame kind, which if I were to ſet down, I know not who would take the trouble of reading them over. Will any man ſay, and keep his countenance, that one in one hundred of theſe hangers on is of any real uſe?—Cannot our King have a poached egg for his ſupper, unleſs he keeps a purveyer of eggs, and his clerks, and his clerk's deputy-clerks, at an expence of 500<abbr>l.</abbr> a year? while the nation is ſinking in a bottomleſs ocean of debt? Again, who are they, the yeomen of the mouth? and who are the under-yeomen of the mouth? What is their buſineſs? What is it to yeoman a King's mouth? What is the neceſſity for a cofferer, where there is a treaſurer? And, where there is a cofferer, what occaſion for a deputy-cofferer? Why a neceſſary-houſe keeper? cannot a King have a water-cloſet, <hi>and keep the key of it in his own pocket?</hi> And my little cock and cryer, what can be his poſt? Does he come under the King's chamber window, and call the hour, mimicking the crowing of the cock! This might be of uſe before clocks and watches, eſpecially repeaters, were invented; but ſeems as ſuperfluous now, as the deliverer of greens, the coffee-women, ſpicery men's aſſiſtant-clerks, the kitchen-comptrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler's firſt clerks and junior clerks, the groom's children, the harbinger's yeomen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Does the maintaining ſuch a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of idlers ſuit the preſent ſtate of our finances? When will frugality be neceſſary, if not now? Queen Anne gave an hundred thouſand pounds a year to the public ſervice <note n="*" place="bottom">The reader is already acquainted with the progreſs and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of this act of royal munificence.</note>. We pay debts on the civil liſt of ſix hundred thouſand pounds in one article, <hi>without aſking how there comes to be a defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency</hi> 
                     <note n="†" place="bottom">Political Diſquiſitions, vol. ii. p. 128.</note>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="unknown:028380_0070_0FD8DEF534BF72D0"/>The following converſations on the ſame ſubject, between the late Princeſs of Wales and Mr. Dodington, cannot fail to excite the attention and ſurpriſe of every reader. "She," the Princeſs, <q>ſaid, that notwithſtanding what I had mentioned of the King's kindneſs to the children and civility to her, <hi>thoſe things did not impoſe upon her</hi>—that there were other things which ſhe could not get over, ſhe wiſhed the King was leſs civil, and that he put leſs of <hi>their</hi> money into his own pocket: that he got full thirty thouſand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> by the poor Prince's death.—If he would but have given them the Dutchy of Cornwall to have paid his debts, it would have been ſomething. Sould reſentments be carried beyond the grave? Should the innocent ſuffer? Was it becoming ſo great a King <hi>to leave his ſons debts unpaid?</hi> and ſuch incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable debts? I aſked her, what ſhe thought they might amount to? She anſwered, ſhe had endeavoured to know as near as a perſon could properly inquire, who, not having it in her power, could not pretend to pay them, She thought, that to the tradeſmen and ſervants they did not amount to ninety thouſand pounds; that there was ſome money owing to the Earl of Scarborough, and that there was, abroad, a debt of about ſeventy thouſand pounds. That this hurt her exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, though ſhe did not ſhew it. I ſaid that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to new-make people; the King could not, now, be altered—.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>We talked of the King's accumulation of treaſure, which ſhe reckoned at four millions. I told her, that what was become of it, how employed, where and what was left, I did not pretend to gueſs; but that I computed the accumulation to be from twelve to fifteen millions. That theſe things, within a moderate degree, perhaps leſs than a fourth part could be proved <hi>beyond all poſſibility of a denial;</hi> and, when the caſe ſhould exiſt, would be publiſhed in controverſial pamphlets <note n="*" place="bottom">Dodington's Memoirs, p. 167 and 290. Theſe debts of the Prince of Wales are ſtill unpaid.</note>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="unknown:028380_0071_0FD8DEF616577B80"/>In 1755, Mr. Pitt had a conference with the Duke of New-caſtle, which has been recorded by Mr. Dodington. A ſhort ſpecimen may ſerve to ſhow how the Britiſh nation has been bubbled by Government. <q>The Duke <hi>mumbled</hi> that the Saxon and Bavarian ſubſidies were offered and <hi>preſſed,</hi> but there was nothing done in them: that the Heſſian was perfected, but the Ruſſian was not concluded.—Whether the Duke meant unſigned, or unratified, we cannot tell, but we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it is ſigned. When his Grace dwelt ſo much upon the King's <hi>honour,</hi> Mr. Pitt aſked him—what, if out of the FIF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEEN MILLIONS <hi>which the King had ſaved,</hi> he ſhould give his kinſman of Heſſe one hundred thouſand pounds, and the Czarina one hundred and fifty thouſand pounds to be off from theſe bad bargains, and not ſuffer the ſuggeſtions, ſo dangerous to his own quiet and ſafety of his family, to be thrown out, which would, and muſt be, inſiſted upon in a debate of this nature? Where would be the harm of it? The Duke had nothing to ſay, but deſired they might talk it over again with the Chancellor. Mr. Pitt replied, he was at their command, though <hi>nothing could alter his opinion</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Dodington's Memoirs, p. 373.</note>.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The reader will here obſerve, that thirty-ſeven years have elapſed ſince George the Second had ſaved FIFTEEN MIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIONS from the civil liſt. It has been ſaid above, that a ſum at five <hi>per cent.</hi> of compound intereſt doubles itſelf in fourteen years. This is not perfectly exact, but as my former calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations did not require ſtrict minuteneſs, the concluſions remain unſhaken. Where a topick ſo delicate as the civil liſt is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, the utmoſt accuracy may be expected, and therefore it muſt here be premiſed, that in fourteen years, an hundred pounds produce about a fiftieth part leſs than a ſecond hundred pounds, that is to ſay, <hi>ninety-ſeven pounds nineteen ſhillings and eight pence,</hi> or in decimal fractions .9799316 parts of an integer. Now, at this rate, theſe fifteen millions would, in thirty-ſeven years, have multiplied to more than ninety-one millions and an half. It is indeed true, as Mr. Dodington, ſays, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="71" facs="unknown:028380_0072_0FD8DEF9EA54C6D8"/>
tell <hi>what has become of it,</hi> or <hi>how it has been employed,</hi> but we know that no part of it has been applied to the ſervice of the nation. We have ſince paid ſeveral large arrears into which the civil liſt had fallen, and an hundred thouſand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> have been added to the royal ſalary. At the ſame time, the nation has been borrowing money to pay that ſalary, the expences of Gibraltar and Canada, for the ſupport of the war-ſyſtem, and other matters, nominally at three and a half, or four <hi>per cent.</hi> but in reality, as ſhall be explained hereafter, at ſix or eight <hi>per cent.</hi> Hence, by the way, the calculations as to Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltar are one third part lower in point of compound intereſt <hi>than they ſhould have been,</hi> and the fifteen millions of George the Second, inſtead of increaſing to ninety-one millions and a half, would, at ſeven and an half <hi>per cent.</hi> have extended to about <hi>an hundred and thirty millions, ſeven hundred and fifty thouſand pounds;</hi> which would a preſent buy out more than one half of our national debt, and ſave the country from an annual burden of perhaps <hi>four millions and an half ſterling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt miſerable part of the ſtory ſtill remains to be told; but the particulars muſt be deferred to ſome future opportunity. The civil liſt is a gulf yawing to abſorb the whole property of the Britiſh empire. We look back without ſatisfaction, and forward without hope.</p>
               <p>Lord Cheſterfield informs us, that George the Firſt was exceedingly hurt even by the weak oppoſition which he met in parliament, on account of ſubſidies; and could not help com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining to his moſt intimate friends, that he had come over to England to be <hi>a begging King.</hi> His vexation was, that he could not command money without the farce of aſking it; for in his reign, as at preſent, the debates of parliament were but a farce. Such were the liberal ſentiments of the firſt ſovereign of the Proteſtant ſucceſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
