<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon, preached on Monday, the fourteenth of July, one thousand seven hundred and ninety-four, being the anniversary of the French Revolution. : In the original and first incorporated Presbyterian Church of Williamsburgh, South-Carolina. / By the Rev. James Malcomson, Minister of said church. ; [Six lines of quotations]</title>
            <author>Malcomson, James, 1768?-1804.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N22014</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N22014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 29019</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX6191</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">29019</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99022992</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 29019.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N22014)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 29019)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 29019)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon, preached on Monday, the fourteenth of July, one thousand seven hundred and ninety-four, being the anniversary of the French Revolution. : In the original and first incorporated Presbyterian Church of Williamsburgh, South-Carolina. / By the Rev. James Malcomson, Minister of said church. ; [Six lines of quotations]</title>
                  <author>Malcomson, James, 1768?-1804.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>42 p. ;  19 cm. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Harrison and Bowen.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Charleston [S.C.]: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M,DCC,XCV. [1795]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' monogram device on title page.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bastille Day.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Revolution, 1789-1799.</term>
               <term>Anniversary sermons --  1794.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:029019_0000_0FDE96ABD8671DB8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:029019_0001_0FDE971AEBF46548"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON, PREACHED ON MONDAY, THE FOUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEENTH OF JULY, ONE THOUSAND SEVEN HUNDRED AND NINETY-FOUR, <hi>BEING THE ANNIVERSARY OF THE</hi> FRENCH REVOLUTION. IN THE ORIGINAL AND FIRST INCORPORATED PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH OF WILLIAMSBURGH, <hi>SOUTH-CAROLINA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY THE REV. JAMES MALCOMSON, MINISTER OF SAID CHURCH.</p>
            <q>It is not the wiſdom of men, that attracts our wonder, or engages our gratitude; but the hand of God we are led to admire and adore. <bibl>
                  <hi>Page</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>—And underſtood not that a grateful mind by owing owes not, but ſtill pays, at once indebted and diſcharged; what burden then? <bibl>MILTON.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>CHARLESTON: PRINTED BY HARRISON AND BOWEN. MDCC,XCV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="unknown:029019_0002_0FDE96AE9446FAA0"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALMS, 78. VERSE 42.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>They remembered not his hand, nor the day when he delivered them from the enemy.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>OF all other crimes, <hi>ingratitude</hi> is the baſeſt, moſt mean, and contemptible. It is degrading to the human character. It is unworthy of connection with the exalted diſpoſitions of rational beings. It argues a want of feeling—a want of goodneſs, of honeſty, and juſtice. The common opinion of mankind reprobates the principle;—but although univerſally deſpiſed, it is too <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="unknown:029019_0003_0FDE96B3C4B5FA78"/>IT will be readily allowed that all men are not equally involved in the cenſure, all men are not alike guilty of the charge. Let it be mentioned to the honor of human nature, that there are many inſtances of GRATITUDE, and even diſintereſted bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence, that have, and ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded. It would be painful to read every page of hiſtory filled with inſtances of <hi>ingratitude,</hi> if we could not place againſt them many inſtances of humanity, charity, and gratitude. Hiſtory is replete with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of characters of extraordinary worth—the names of perſons of the moſt amiable and reſpectable characters. The ſacred, volumes—the treaſures of divine truth were written for our inſtruction. REUEL <note n="*" place="bottom">EXOD. 2d. 20th. 21ſt.</note> the prieſt of Midian, was grateful to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, for preſerving his daughters, from the violence of the ſhepherds, and gave him his daughter Zipporah to be his wife. SAUL <note n="†" place="bottom">1ſt. SAM. 15th &amp; 6th verſe.</note> was kind and grateful to the Kenites, and
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:029019_0004_0FDE96B60CEA07C0"/>
would not deſtroy them, with the Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites, becauſe they were kind to the Iſrael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, when they came out of Egypt—And the character of DAVID will ever be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, for remarkable inſtances of grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude;—his kindneſs to Hanun <note n="‡" place="bottom">IId. SAM. 10th. &amp; 2d. verſe.</note>, although badly received, will ever be admired;—His conduct to Jonathan's <note n="§" place="bottom">IId. SAM. 9th. &amp; 7th. verſe.</note> family, and to Barzillai <note n="‖" place="bottom">IId. SAM. 19th. 32d. to 38th. &amp; 1ſt. KINGS 2d. &amp; 7th.</note>, will ever be ſpoken of, with approbation and eſteem.</p>
            <p>HAPPY would it have been for mankind, had ſuch characters been more univerſal, and ſuch diſpoſitions more predominant in the world: Had this been the caſe always, unſuſpecting innocence would never have been deceived by thoſe, from whom grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and friendſhip was due, and in whom confidence was repoſed;—Ingratitude, treachery, and deceit, would have been words without meaning.—Joſeph would not
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:029019_0005_0FDE96B795B68090"/>
have been neglected in the priſon, by the chief butler;—Such a character as Judas would have been entirely unknown.</p>
            <p>HOWEVER great the crime of ingratitude is, when man is guilty of it, towards man, it is more reprehenſible, and of greater magnitude, when men are guilty of it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God: And this the Iſraelites are charged with in the text,—"THEY RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MEMBERED NOT HIS HAND, NOR THE DAY WHEN HE DELIVERED THEM FROM THE ENEMY."</p>
            <p>THE general conduct of the Iſraelites is a continued hiſtory of repeated inſtances of ingratitude towards their God—their preſerver—deliverer and friend. They were choſen by God as a favorite people—diſtinct from all other nations, and enjoying the bleſſings of heaven in a remarkable manner. They experienced the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary interpoſition of God—in his proviſion for them, and in his deliverance of them,
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:029019_0006_0FDE96BA1D0B7878"/>
from ſlavery and bondage. "I am the Lord thy God which brought thee out of the land of Egypt and out of the houſe of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,"—was conſidered as a principal mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to obedience. A recognition of their deliverance, would have called forth their gratitude, but they did not, they would not <hi>remember.</hi> Their oppreſſion in the land of Egypt was ſo grievous and intolerable, that when Moſes announced unto them the meſſage of God, concerning their intended deliverance, "they hearkened not, for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of ſpirit, and for cruel bondage." Slavery has a tendency to dull the mind, and ſtupify the ſenſes—and ſo it was with the Iſraelites, that a few days after their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from their place of bondage—they remonſtrated with Moſes, "wherefore haſt thou dealt thus with us, to carry us out of Egypt. Would to God we had died by the hand of the Lord, in the land of Egypt, when we ſat by the fleſh-pots, and when we did eat bread to the full—for ye have brought us forth into this wilderneſs to kill
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:029019_0007_0FDE96C06CC4EC18"/>
this whole aſſembly with hunger." Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they beheld the power of god in the deſtruction of their "taſk-maſters" in the Red Sea—yet they murmured for want of bread. Although they were fed in a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous manner with manna from heaven, yet they murmured for water—although they were ſupplied by water from a flinty rock, yet they tempted the Lord with words of contempt "Is the Lord among us or not."</p>
            <p>IN order to give a further diſplay of his power, the Almighty delivers to the Iſrael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites the law, from Mount Sinai, with thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings, lightning, and the noiſe of the trumpet—and after he had enjoined ſome ceremonial obſervances, for the regulation of their conduct, he ſays, "and I will dwell among the children of Iſrael, and will be their God, and they ſhall know, that I am the Lord their God, that brought them forth out of the land of Egypt, that I may dwell amongſt them; I am the Lord their God."</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="unknown:029019_0008_0FDE96C1F61542B8"/>IT might have been expected from theſe inſtances of divine favour, that the Iſrael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites would not readily forget their God, their deliverer, and lawgiver; yet God's attention to, and care of them, is not more remarkable than their <hi>ingratitude.</hi> In the abſence of Moſes they made a molten calf, and ſaid "Theſe be thy Gods O Iſrael which brought thee up out of the land of Egypt!" They went a whoring after other Gods—yet their God did not forſake them, but continued to conduct them through the wilderneſs, by a mighty hand and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched arm—when they were brought to the borders of the promiſed land—they murmured againſt Moſes and Aaron, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, "Would God we had died in the land of Egypt, or would God we had died in this wilderneſs; and they ſaid one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let us make a captain, and let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into Egypt." They were ſo full of <hi>ingratitude,</hi> and ſo obſtinately wicked, that they would rather ſerve the Egyptians and be <hi>ſlaves,</hi> as ſerve the Lord and be <hi>free.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="unknown:029019_0009_0FDE96C4038569B8"/>
Thus we ſee, and mankind in all ages have learned, by miſerable experience, that a diſpoſition to ſubmit to, or abet in, the promoting of ſlavery, is founded on, and derived from the groſſeſt perverſion and corruption of human nature—to ſubmit to <hi>tyranny</hi> is to encourage idolatry, and to promote <hi>ſlavery</hi> is to promote <hi>ſpiritual wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs in high places.</hi> There is ſomething remarkable in preferring ſlavery, and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, to rational liberty, and freedom, which is the natural wiſh, and deſire of the human mind; this diſpoſition to ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cannot eaſily be accounted for, unleſs we conſider it as proceeding from <hi>a deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined oppoſition to the will of God:</hi> This we may ſuppoſe from the conduct of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, they frequently felt the ſeverity of God's judgments, yet they did not fear him—they were frequently delivered by him from their enemies yet they did not love him—they preſerred the ſervice of idols to the ſervice of God—their language was "who is the Lord that he ſhould reign
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:029019_0010_0FDE96C5898CFDF8"/>
over us." They ſacrificed unto idols and not unto God—they provoked the Lord to jealouſy with ſtrange Gods. After they had obtained poſſeſſion of the <hi>promiſed land,</hi> and reſted from a ſtate of warfare with the neighbouring nations, their <hi>ingratitude</hi> to God, is no leſs apparent; their neglect of God brought them in ſubjection to the king of Hazor, by whom they were mightily oppreſſed for twenty years, afterwards by Midian for ſeven years. They were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the generalſhip of Gideon—who was an inſtrument in the hand of God for that purpoſe. But inſtead of being thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to God for their deliverance, they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe all to Gideon and offer to reward him with what they had no right to beſtow, their propoſal was to make him king. "Rule thou over us, thou, and thy ſon, and thy ſon's ſon."<note n="*" place="bottom">JUDGES 8th. and 22d.</note> His anſwer to their propoſal was ſufficient to have convinced them of their ingratitude to God. "I will not rule over you, neither ſhall my ſon
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:029019_0011_0FDE96CD346A7CD0"/>
rule over you, THE LORD SHALL RULE OVER YOU." Theſe words require no comment, they are plain, and ſufficiently explicit.</p>
            <p>IN the days of Samuel although they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the bleſſings of peace, having obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a decided victory over the Philiſtines under the hand of God who deſtroyed them with thunder—yet they neglected the true God and remembered not his deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of them. They murmured againſt Samuel's ſons for which there might have been ſome reaſons as they were neither ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt nor impartial in the diſtributing of judgment.—But they did not reſt here—they aſked for a king that they might be like all the nations—this requeſt was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing both to Samuel and God. "And the Lord ſaid unto Samuel they have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me, that I ſhould not reign over them," from which we ſee that <hi>all thoſe who wiſh for an earthly ſovereign, abjure the ſovereignty of
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:029019_0012_0FDE96CEDB76BF18"/>
God.</hi> Samuel endeavored to diſſuade them from perſiſting in their fooliſh wiſhes—he informed them that a king would enſlave, and oppreſs them, but they refuſed to obey his voice and ſaid, "nay, but we will have a king to reign over us," that we may alſo be like all the nations, that our king may judge us, and go out before us and fight our battles."<note n="*" place="bottom">Read the 8th. Chap. of the 1ſt. Book of SAMUEL</note> I ſhall only remark, that however natural it was for the Iſraelites to wiſh to have their battles fought for them, eſpecially as they were fatigued with fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet we do not find that kings have come up to their expectations herein, for inſtead of fighting the battles of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, we find by bloody experience that the people have been <hi>obliged</hi> to fight <hi>the battles of kings!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The hiſtory of kings can ſhew too well the fulfilling of Samuel's prophecy "And ye ſhall cry out in that day becauſe of your king which ye ſhall have choſen you—and
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:029019_0013_0FDE96D08B40E7B8"/>
the Lord will not hear you in that day." This affords ground for an obſervation which may be extended to all men, that the greateſt puniſhment God inflicted on the Iſraelites, was in ſatisfying all their wiſhes.</p>
            <p>WHEN we read in ſacred ſcripture an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the general conduct of the kings of Iſrael of many of their bloody diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and <hi>wicked reigns,</hi> and compare their conduct with thoſe who have aſpired to as great, if not greater power, in every ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent period of the hiſtory of the world—we cannot avoid lamenting the folly and wickedneſs of men, who allow them to rule and oppreſs them. It was in God's wrath the firſt king was given—and it is for the puniſhment of men, they have been conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued. But as the effect ceaſes when the cauſe ceaſes to operate—ſo, it is reaſonable to ſuppoſe that the puniſhment would ceaſe when the crime which puniſhes itſelf would ceaſe and determine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="unknown:029019_0014_0FDE96D210E827D0"/>WE have thus far taken a general view of the conduct of the Iſraelites, from their departure from the land of bondage, until they entered into the promiſed land—un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefully rejected the authority of the king of Heaven, and obtained an earthly king to reign over them. The words of the text lead us to enquire into the particular charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es which the pſalmiſt here makes againſt them—AND FIRST—"They remember<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not his hand." In the government of the univerſe God's agency is viſibly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played. It is not ſufficient to ſay that every event is brought about by <hi>general</hi> cauſes—and that the world is governed by <hi>general</hi> laws. God exerciſes a <hi>particular</hi> govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This is evident from particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of effects brought about contrary to the <hi>general</hi> laws of nature and providence; a wiſe obſerver of human nature and of the ways of God hath informed us—that the race is not to the ſwift, nor the battle to the ſtrong neither yet bread to the wiſe, nor
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:029019_0015_0FDE96DA3AB54430"/>
yet riches to men of underſtanding, nor yet favour to men of ſkill."<note n="†" place="bottom">ECCLESIASTES 9th. Chap. 11th verſe.</note> And we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by an authority which cannot be diſputed—'are not five ſparrows ſold for two ſhillings? And not one of them is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten before God. But even the very hairs of your head are all numbered <note n="‡" place="bottom">LUKES GOSPEL, 12th Chap. 6th &amp; 7th verſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>. Gods preſence is boundleſs—the whole univerſe is open to his view—governed by his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom—and under his powerful control.—The laws of nature confeſs his wiſdom and his ſkill—and their operations, MAN is formed to contemplate, admire and adore!—For God's glory and our good, for his honor and our inſtruction—God frequently interpoſes in a miraculous manner—gives a new arrangement to the courſe of his laws, and aſtoniſhes our minds no leſs by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors than his wonders.—Thus we find that the Old Teſtament gives a copious detail of his miracles and his wonders. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:029019_0016_0FDE96DD01B16538"/>
and the earth ceaſed to perform its diurnal revolution for ſeveral hours; or in the emphatical language of Scripture, "the Sun ſtood ſtill;"<note n="*" place="bottom">JOSHUA 10th, 12th.</note> "And the Moon was ſtayed."</p>
            <p>Although ſuch extraordinary miracles are not now performed, nor perhaps ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary,—we can ſtill trace God's over-ruling Providence, and the wonders of his hand.—The revolutions which take place in the Political, as well as in the Natural World, are all the effect of God's wiſdom and power. To forget God and deny his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,—to aſcribe ſucceſs to human wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom—to the arm of fleſh and not to the mighty <hi>hand</hi> of God, is the baſeſt <hi>ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</hi> Alas! What is man when compar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with God? Or what avails the power of man, when compared with the power of God? If events were the reſult of man's wiſdom and contrivance how diſordered would the affairs of the univerſe appear?
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:029019_0017_0FDE96DE8D31BB38"/>
If God who opens the eyes of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and imparts of his wiſdom—would withdraw his influence, the affairs of men would wear an appearance ſtill more diſordered. If God who reſtrains the wrath of man was to allow it unreſtrained exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe—what would the conſequence be? The hiſtory of the world, is at beſt, but a black catalogue of the enormities and vices of men! It ſerves to ſhew what men are, even under the government of the Wiſe Ruler of the univerſe.</p>
            <p>In the conduct of divine Providence there are many things myſterious, many things beyond our comprehenſion. Theſe things can be but partially underſtood here, part will remain to be underſtood hereafter,—Although we are imperfect yet we muſt diſcern the operations of God's Providence—If we aſcribe ordinary effects to him as the cauſe—we have much more reaſon to conſider him as the cauſe of extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry actions. If David who was but a ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:029019_0018_0FDE96E0145F60B8"/>
—a youth unaccuſtomed to war—ſlew Goliath who was a man of extraordinary, ſize, who was accuſtomed to fight and well prepared for it—ſurely this victory muſt be aſcribed to the <hi>hand</hi> of God. If the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites were preſerved from the Egyptians by a pillar of cloud by day, and a pillar of fire by night, it was the effect of ſupernatural power.—If the ſea divided its waters to give them a ſafe paſſage on dry land—and cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again and overwhelmed the Egyptians—this cannot be accounted for according to the regular laws of nature, but muſt be aſcribed to God's extraordinary power—If the Iſraelites who were but a ſmall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion when compared with their enemies, were enabled to eſcape from the oppreſſion of the Egyptians and to conquer all nations before them, ſo that they obtained undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbed poſſeſſion of the land of Canaan, it certainly was very ungrateful in them to aſcribe that deliverance and conqueſt to themſelves, yet "they remembered not
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:029019_0019_0FDE96E96AEDC6D0"/>
his hand" nor SECONDLY "the day when he delivered them from the enemy."</p>
            <p>What particular inſtance of their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance the Pſalmiſt here alludes to we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not determine. It is more than probable it was their deliverance from Egyptian tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; the context ſeems to favor this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture. The Pſalmiſt is lamenting their diſobedience and <hi>ingratitude.</hi> "How oft did they provoke him in the wilderneſs, and grieve him in the deſert, yea they turned back and tempted God, and limited the holy one of Iſrael. They remembered not his hand nor the day when he delivered them from the enemy; how he had wrought his wonders in Egypt, and his ſigns in the land of Zoan."</p>
            <p>The Paſſover which is probably here al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded to, was appointed as a feſtival for the Iſraelites, on which anniverſary they were to commemorate their miraculous delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of Egypt, when the deſtroying
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:029019_0020_0FDE96EAF2ABD510"/>
Angel <hi>paſſed over</hi> the houſes of the children of Iſrael, but ſmote all the firſt born of the Egyptians with death. This was a wonderful deliverance, ſo great, that it might have been reaſonably preſumed, there would have been no danger of its being ever forgotten by them. There is nothing more apt to leave a laſting impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on our minds than works which are believed to be ſupernatural. Hence we find that credulity and ignorance have been the prolific parents of a blind and nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous offspring. Superſtition and all her votaries, can trace their deſcent from this ſource. This has given riſe to deiſm, and even ſcepticiſm. Becauſe ſome are too credulous, founding their opinions on the ſuggeſtions of an extravagant fancy, and deluded imagination—therefore others will ſcarcely believe any thing—Becauſe ſacred ſcripture informs us of ſeveral miracles, therefore ſome deny its authenticity. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they <hi>cannot</hi> underſtand, therefore they <hi>will not</hi> believe. The Iſraelites however,
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:029019_0021_0FDE96EC7B67B7C8"/>
are not charged with unbelief, but with ingratitude. The pſalmiſt doth not ſay <hi>they believed not,</hi> but <hi>they remembered not:</hi> Notwithſtanding the impreſſion which the miracles were calculated to make on their minds, yet they became as a dream of the night, or as <hi>a tale that hath been told, and is ſoon forgotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is natural for us to be elated with grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to the author of a favour <hi>recently</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; we eſteem a benefactor when a ſenſe of his favors are freſh on the mind; but time with ſilent influence, is too apt to wipe off the impreſſion; In order to counteract this, we find that God appointed ſeveral days to be held in religious memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial by the Iſraelites, they had certain days appointed for ritual obſervances, and for commemorating ſome remarkable events; for this purpoſe was the paſſover appointed by an expreſs command. "And this day ſhall be unto you for a memorial and you ſhall keep it a feaſt unto the Lord through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:029019_0022_0FDE96EE06BE1300"/>
your generations; you ſhall keep it a feaſt by an ordinance for ever.—And Moſes ſaid to the people—remember <hi>this day</hi> in which ye came out from Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage, for by ſtrength of <hi>hand</hi> the Lord brought you out from this place." Thus it appears that it is not only peculiar to human nature to remember with grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude favours <hi>lately</hi> received, but the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of days for that purpoſe, ſhews, that it is ſanctioned by the high authority of divine inſtitution, and founded in uner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring wiſdom. Thus we find that the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt favour ever conferred on the human race—the ſalvation of penitent ſinners by Jeſus Chriſt is to be commemorated by all his followers, until his ſecond coming at the final conſummation of all things. "This do in <hi>remembrance</hi> of me" is an authority of the higheſt origin, and moſt incontro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertible obligation. This is a commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a great deliverance from oppreſſion and bondage—the bondage of ſin and death. What perſon is ſo far loſt to ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:029019_0023_0FDE96F495F7C780"/>
of gratitude, as not to <hi>remember</hi> it? So natural is the deſire of commemorating important events that we find in the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of all nations, either barbarous or civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized, certain days have been attended to, with a ſtrictneſs bordering on enthuſiaſm. To this natural deſire, divine authority is added, to perpetuate the remembrance of ſpiritual and temporal bleſſings. In order that our gratitude may have free exerciſe, it is highly becoming in us to imitate the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine conduct, by ſetting apart certain days, for religious joy and gratitude, on which we may call to our remembrance, <hi>the mighty hand of God.</hi> The anniverſary of the birth of a patriot or hero, an illuſtrious ſtateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or commander, is celebrated with the warmeſt effuſions of joy, how much more grateful ought we to be, on the anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary of the birth of a <hi>cauſe,</hi> which brings freedom and deliverance, to milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who were groaning under the ſhackles of tyranny, deſpotiſm, and the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme indigence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Need I call up to your
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:029019_0024_0FDE96F7CEBE1028"/>
minds, thoſe patriots who have ſtruggled, and thoſe heroes who have bled in the cauſe of liberty and mankind? Need I mention the names of illuſtrious reformers, who, in every age of the world, have outbraved the ſtorms of perſecution and with manly fortitude, have oppoſed the claims of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny both in civil and eccleſiaſtical af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs?—Their actions are recorded, their memories are bleſſed, their names will be perpetuated. They will be ſpoken of with veneration, and gratitude, whilſt the ſun, moon, and ſtars endure,—even to the lateſt generation: whilſt their names are recorded on the page of hiſtory, let the memory of the <hi>cauſe</hi> which they laboured to ſupport be imprinted on our hearts. The lateſt inſtance of this kind is the REVOLUTION IN FRANCE, which has been joyful to upwards of 25,000,000 pleaſing to every friend of liberty, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity—and aſtoniſhing to all the world. THIS DAY being the 14th of July, calls up to our minds the deſtruction of the
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:029019_0025_0FDE96F95E5E5290"/>
Baſtile that place devoted for the innocent victims of tyrannic fury. Five years are now elapſed, ſince that happy and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing event took place; and as friends of the human race we rejoice at the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance. In this happy revolution we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the <hi>hand</hi> of God, and <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the day</hi> on which our fellow-men <hi>were delivered from the enemy.</hi> As men we feel the ſacred influence of ſympathy, and chriſtianity teacheth us to "<hi>rejoice with thoſe who do rejoice,</hi> as well as to weep with thoſe who weep." We look forward to that happy period, when the demon of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny will ceaſe to oppreſs, and afflict mankind; and we truſt in God, that the French revolution is one link, in the great chain of cauſes, which will bring about that happy time. But whilſt we rejoice in the cauſe of liberty, we muſt lament the numerous ſacrifices, which the complete eſtabliſhment of it, renders unavoidable. The enemies of the Revolution have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavored to tarniſh and render it abortive,
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:029019_0026_0FDE96FB9CF1A330"/>
by encouraging treachery, civil inſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and bloodſhed; but he who ſits in heaven will laugh at their proceedings and put them all to ſcorn—"The wrath of man will praiſe him, the remainder there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he can reſtrain." He will render the counſels of the wicked of none effect, <hi>that the man of the earth may no more oppreſs.</hi>
               <note place="bottom">PSALMS 10th and 18th.</note> We do not undertake to juſtify the conduct of every <hi>pretended</hi> friend to the French revolution; ſome have attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to diſgrace it by their intemperate zeal, and ſanguinary meaſures;—but even this has ſerved the cauſe of the revolution, and in the end it will appear that God can bring good out of evil.—It is not the violence of men, nor the intemperance of meaſures, but the <hi>greatneſs of the cauſe,</hi> we ought to praiſe, and rejoice in;—It is not the wiſdom of men that attracts our wonder, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages our gratitude;—but <hi>the hand of God,</hi> we are led to admire and adore.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="unknown:029019_0027_0FDE970299D9A530"/>How diſtreſſing was the former ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the people of France, under an abſolute monarchy;—almoſt conſtantly embroiled in wars at the caprice of their monarch, inſecure in their perſons,—forced from their families, and all that was dear to them, harraſſed by their <hi>nobleſſe,</hi> an ariſtocracy which ate the fruit of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, and a body of dignified clergy, who preyed on their vitals. They were kept in ignorance by thoſe, whoſe office it was to enlighten and inſtruct them. They planted vineyards, without knowing who ſhould eat the fruit thereof. They carried ſeed into the field without knowing who ſhould gather in the Harveſt. Their wives and their children, as well as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, were frequently a prey to relentleſs inſult, and cruelty. They were expoſed to all the miſeries of ſlavery, poverty, and diſtreſs.</p>
            <p>Let their former ſituation be compared with their preſent;—how wonderful the
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:029019_0028_0FDE9704D27F7D28"/>
contraſt! If they are obliged to fight, it is in their own defence, and not as ſlaviſh mercenaries. Their laws are of their own making—their perſons and properties invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable. Every one can now ſit down "un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own vine, and his own fig-tree and none maketh him afraid." In ſome other countries, not only the bodies but the minds of men are enſlaved—they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to ſubmit to the deciſions of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſted though ignorant pretenders to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual authority. But in France prieſt craft as well as king-craft is done away,—every denomination enjoys the bleſſings of free and candid enquiry. Is it not ſurpriſing that ſuch a change could take place in the courſe of five years—although oppoſed by all the formidable artillery of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined deſpots of Europe? Who would not rejoice at the happy proſpect which it affords? Who would not ſacrifice every thing that is dear to him, nay, even life itſelf, rather than be deprived of ſuch inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable privileges?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="unknown:029019_0029_0FDE97065AC731B0"/>Whilſt we rejoice this day in the eman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of a great and powerful nation, let us not be forgetful of the revolution of this country, which may be conſidered as introductory to the revolution in France. You had been long oppreſſed and inſulted, and new chains were forging for you—Your forefathers had fled from perſecution and you made a noble ſtand againſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of perſecution, which purſued you, and was about to ſettle here.—Your deliverance was brought about by the interpoſition of heaven. At the commencement of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution, "Your hands had not been taught to war, nor your fingers to fight." Courage and reſolution ſupplied the place of ignorance and inexperience. The juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of your cauſe ſupplied the place of a numerous army.—Your cauſe was the cauſe of heaven.—Your enemies under the artful profeſſion of being foſter-fathers, and foſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mothers, carried fire and ſword, havock and deſtruction, through your land.—They were experienced in all the art of
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:029019_0030_0FDE9707E10041E8"/>
war and had other bloody hirelings in their pay and ſervice.—They oppoſed the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful principles of truth and juſtice, courted the vengeance of heaven, and ſet God at defiance.—You had to combat a king whoſe paſſions were paramount to reaſon and juſtice—A wicked miniſtry who had neither wiſdom nor honeſty, a government with the name but ſcarcely the ſhadow of liberty and repreſentation, a people deluded, bribed, and corrupted, by thoſe who rob, and plunder them; an army of worthleſs mercenaries, partly engaged through views of plunder, and partly for the ſake of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolence.—Theſe were your enemies from abroad, and theſe are at preſent the moſt inveterate enemies of the French.—Their conduct has for many years diſcovered the greateſt pride, inſolence, and low cunning.—They carry on their wars, not by bravery but by bribery, by encouraging treachery and diſſenſions, by circulating calumnies, and promoting maſſacres.—Their favourite maxim is "divide and conquer." Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:029019_0031_0FDE970E96E753B8"/>
the pride of Roman Glory they aim at no leſs than the dominion of the ſeas, and the empire of the world. To none can the adage be better applied, than to them. QUEM DEUS VULT PERDERE, PRIUS DIMENTAT."</p>
            <p>But you had others to combat with—your enemies from abroad by corruption and fair promiſes cauſed you to have ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies at home; and "a man's greateſt enemies are thoſe of his own houſehold." Your domeſtics were armed againſt you and you were armed againſt each other. It was owing to the mighty hand of God that you were delivered from internal ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and from the tyranny of a foreign le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlation. This was among the many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances when tyranny begat liberty, and yet endeavored to deſtroy its offspring—when Providence ſaved the innocent child and deſtroyed the wicked and unnatural parent.—When the Almighty ſupported the oppreſſed, and cut off the oppreſſor;
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:029019_0032_0FDE9710D4EB7418"/>
juſtly may we ſay. "Lord who is like unto thee which delivereſt the poor from him that is too ſtrong for him, and from him that ſpoileth him." In the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hova is everlaſting ſtrength.</p>
            <p>After a long, unnatural, and bloody conteſt, you have now the quiet and undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbed poſſeſſion of your liberty, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties. You have no haughty tyrant to exact obedience from you, at his caprice, and pleaſure. You have no imperious Lords, to inſult and oppreſs you. You have ho dignified clergy, nor mitred bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, to impoſe penalties on you, on ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your private opinions; or to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act from you the tenth of your labour and induſtry. If you have rulers, you appoint them, and they muſt be reſponſible. They are your ſervants and not your maſters: Every official character is choſen by, and from among yourſelves, and their duty and intereſt are inſeparable from yours. As Chriſtians you enjoy religious liberty, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicans
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:029019_0033_0FDE97125C77C3F8"/>
you enjoy civil liberty; the one is your prerogative as Chriſtians, the other your birth-right as men; they are inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in themſelves, it remains with you to preſerve them inviolable, as an inheritance for poſterity.</p>
            <p>It is our duty as miniſters of the goſpel, to warn you againſt corruption, to exhort you to beware of moral, and political cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. We warn you to ſuppreſs <hi>ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to beware of <hi>faction,</hi> and to "live peaceably with all men." Beware of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſting too much power to any, either in church or ſtate. This has been the cauſe of eclipſing the purity of religion, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volving the world in bloodſhed. The trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of revolutions ought to be a leſſon to mankind to prevent the neceſſity of them. Tho people ſeldom murmur or revolt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe; but they are juſtly puniſhed when they give cauſe for their own com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, and this is the caſe, when through indolence or inattention, they ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:029019_0034_0FDE9713E9788BF0"/>
to be brought under the rod of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. The drunkard and debauchee may complain of ſicknneſs, poverty, and a ruined conſtitution, but he is too well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the cauſe.</p>
            <p>Whilſt you continue <hi>firm and determined</hi> republicans, <hi>plain</hi> in your manners, <hi>correct</hi> in your morals, <hi>frugal</hi> in your oeconomy, <hi>united</hi> in your conduct; it may be ſaid of you "one ſhall chaſe a thouſand and two put to flight ten thouſand." By this rule of conduct you will be ſtrongly fortified againſt all your enemies you will have God for your leader and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; but if ever you give power, worſhip, and reverence to <hi>any human creature,</hi> you ſerve an idol, and forfeit the favour of God!</p>
            <p>You have given to the world the beſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of human government that ever was known, ſince the time that the Iſraelites were ſo fooliſh as to aſk for a king. All
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:029019_0035_0FDD609984119870"/>
other governments that have been called re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publics, commonwealths, or democracies, did not ſecure the rights and liberties of the people; a majority were overlooked and miſrepreſented; the nearer that any go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment has approached to a republic by equal repreſentation, the more proſperity the people enjoy, the ſtronger they are, and the better enabled to oppoſe all their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. We do not undertake to vindicate your government from all errors, or to ſay that it is perfect: but this much we ſay that if there are any diſeaſes in your conſtitution, they admit of a cure, and if incurable, you are well taught not to ſhrink from amputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, "If thy right hand offend thee, cut it off, and caſt it from thee."<note n="*" place="bottom">MATTHEW 5th. and 30th<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> It is better that a diſeaſed member ſhould be cut off, than that the whole body ſhould be infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and rendered incurable.</p>
            <p>The enemies of the liberty and happineſs of men have aſſerted, that civil wars are
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:029019_0036_0FDE971D2F9D1258"/>
unavoidable in republics. This we deny, <note n="*" place="bottom">MATTHEW <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and facts prove the contrary. The hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of the Iſraelites under a common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and under their kings, will ſhew the falſehood of the aſſertion. Under a commonwealth the tribes were united—But in the reign of their firſt king their civil wars began. The conteſt between the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of Saul and David; between Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah and Iſrael, and their kings, ſhews what monarchy is. Let there be no pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of extraordinary honor, or profit, and there will be no bloody contentious about filling them.</p>
            <p>IF the profits ariſing from the crown of England, and its prerogative, had not been ſo great, there would have been leſs blood ſhed in the quarrels betwixt the houſes of York and Lancaſter. If the loaves and fiſhes were out of the queſtion thoſe delud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed people would not have been involved in the preſent war. They have waged war
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:029019_0037_0FDE971EB6B45560"/>
againſt principles—they have declared for the ſuppreſſion of reaſon and philoſophy, they have reſolved to ſtifle the principles of truth—to ſtop the progreſs of liberty—and they have appealed to the ſword to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabliſh their cauſe. They have declared <hi>they will never treat with the French as a people, until they have choſen a king.</hi> By this declaration they are enemies to every friend of liberty; WE accept the challenge and let it be our prayer to the Almighty Ruler of all events to diſappoint their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed deſigns, and to fortify us againſt their intrigues.</p>
            <p>THE eyes of the world are directed to the preſent bloody conteſt in Europe—The tongues of the oppreſſed, and of every friend to liberty are ſaying "we wiſh you ſucceſs" This ſhould recall to your minds, a recollection of your own virtuous ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, for the cauſe of liberty, and indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. By the hand of <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od you were led on to victory and glory. It ought to be
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:029019_0038_0FDE9720F3208BF8"/>
your deſire, and prayer to God for thoſe who are engaged in the ſame honorable cauſe, that their conteſt may ſoon have the ſame glorious iſſue. The cauſe of the French concerns all men, but more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately the liberty and happineſs of theſe free and independent ſtates.</p>
            <p>WHAT the iſſue of the preſent conteſt may be, is beyond <hi>the reach of human calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> to determine; infinite wiſdom is alone competent to decide. But this much we may ſafely aſſert that if the French are unſucceſsful, they are either unworthy of the bleſſings of liberty—or God hath thought proper to delay the ſuppreſſion of tyranny, which is ANTICHRIST until a more proper time. But why ſhould we ſuppoſe that this time is not God's time, for putting an end to civil and religious ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny. In a certain ſenſe it may ſaid to be the deſire, the wiſh and expectation of all nations. The voice of the oppreſſed is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for freedom, the blood of the innocent
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:029019_0039_0FDE972773639420"/>
victims of tyranny is calling for vengeance.</p>
            <p>THE proſpect of American affairs was frequently more gloomy than the ſituation of the French has yet been—and why ſhould we diſtruſt the ſame powerful <hi>hand,</hi> by which the Americans were ſaved and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered? Can we ſuppoſe that the wiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of all events—would lead them on thus far, through a number of intrigues and conſpiracies—through the <hi>Red Sea</hi> of blood, through a <hi>wilderneſs</hi> of troubles, and leave them at laſt to the ſavage rage of mercileſs enemies, to be carried back to their former ſtate of oppreſſion, and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage—and thereby blaſt the hopes, and diſappoint the expectations, of all the friends of liberty in the world? Such a thought derogates from the perfections of God, and is an inſult to the ruler of the Univerſe.</p>
            <p>BUT it is ſaid the French are deiſtical, nay atheiſtical; for they have aboliſhed all
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:029019_0040_0FDE9728FAD81640"/>
religion. Was this the caſe, we might an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that God frequently makes uſe of wicked men, to accompliſh a good cauſe.—But why ſhould we ſuppoſe that they are void of religion? Is it a proof of their want of religion, becauſe they have abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed <hi>human</hi> eſtabliſhments of it? Are they void of religion becauſe they have changed their calendar—Are they void of religion becauſe they have given free enquiry, and liberty of worſhip to all? Such charges are made againſt them, either by thoſe who are careleſs of religion themſelves, or by thoſe who make it an engine of ſtate poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. To conclude.</p>
            <p>A CONSTANT remembrance of God's protection and deliverance of us, is the beſt preſervative againſt dangers.—If we retain a ſenſe of God's power on our minds, we will be in leſs danger of ingratitude, or forgetfulneſs of his mercies. And ſurely it is neither unwiſe, nor unbecoming, in thoſe who reap all the benefits of civil and
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:029019_0041_0FDE972A8643A340"/>
religious liberty, to wiſh for ſucceſs to others, who are gloriouſly contending for the ſame happineſs. It is the cauſe of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, the cauſe of religion, the cauſe of God. Liberty, like the light of heaven, whilſt it chears the hearts of numbers, is not diminiſhed in its luſtre. It is intended for, and ought to comprehend in its influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>all</hi> the rational creatures of God.—Let us rejoice in the proſpect which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſituation of Europe and the world af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords! Let us pray that the rays of liberty as the path of the juſt, may ſhine more and more, to the perfect day—that <hi>God who executeth judgment for the oppreſſed, would break every yoke, and let the oppreſſed go free.</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
