<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Important state papers: containing the treaties existing between the United States and foreign powers.</title>
            <title>Treaties, etc.</title>
            <author>United States.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 92 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N22533</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N22533</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 29760</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW8543</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">29760</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99014753</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 29760.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N22533)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 29760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 29760)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Important state papers: containing the treaties existing between the United States and foreign powers.</title>
                  <title>Treaties, etc.</title>
                  <author>United States.</author>
                  <author>France. Treaties, etc. United States.</author>
                  <author>Great Britain. Treaties, etc. United States.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>92 p. ;  (12mo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Samuel Loudon, Jun.?] at the office of the Diary, no. 82, Water Street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New-York, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1795.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Diary was published by Samuel Loudon, Jun. until his death in Sept. 1795.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>United States --  Foreign relations --  Treaties.</term>
               <term>Treaties.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Re-keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:029760_0000_0FE259DF90AC3BF8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:029760_0001_0FE24BF35DFBA0F0"/>
            <p>IMPORTANT <hi>STATE PAPERS:</hi> CONTAINING THE TREATIES EXISTING BETWEEN THE <hi>UNITED STATES</hi> AND FOREIGN POWERS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>NEW-YORK,</hi> PRINTED AT THE OFFICE OF THE <hi>DIARY, No. 81, Water Street.</hi> 1795.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="unknown:029760_0002_0FE2589A52ADE028"/>Important State-Papers.</head>
         <div type="treaty">
            <head>Treaty of Commerce between France and the United States of America.</head>
            <p>THE Moſt Chriſtian King and the Thirteen United States of North America, to wit, New-Hampſhire, Maſſachuſſetts-Bay, Rhode-I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland, Connecticut, New-York, New-Jerſey, Penn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvania, Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, North Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolina, South Carolina, and Georgia, willing to fix in an equitable and permanent manner, the rules which ought to be followed relative to the correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence and commerce which the two parties de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to eſtabliſh between their reſpective countries, ſtates &amp; ſubjects; His Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty and the ſaid United States have judged that the ſaid end could not be better obtained, than by taking for the baſis of their agreement, the moſt perfect equality and reciprocity, and by carefully avoiding all thoſe burthenſome preferences which are uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſources of debate, embarraſſment and diſcontent; by leaving alſo each party at liberty to make reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting navigation and commerce, thoſe interior regulations which it ſhall find moſt convenient to it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and by founding the advantage of commerce ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon reprocal utility, and the juſt rules of free intercourſe; reſerving withal to each party the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of admitting, at its pleaſure, other nations to a participation of the ſame advantages. It is in the ſpirit of this intention, and to fulfil theſe views, that his ſaid majeſty having named and appointed for his plenipotentiary, Conrad Alexander Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:029760_0003_0FE2589BE13E3930"/>
royal ſyndic of the city of Straſbourg, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of his majeſty's council of ſtate; and the united ſtates on their part, having fully empower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Bejamin Franklin, deputy from the ſtate of Pennſylvania to the general congreſs, and preſident to the Convention of the ſaid ſtate; Silas Deane, late deputy from the ſtate of Connecticut to the ſaid Congreſs, and Arthur Lee, counſellor at law: The ſaid reſpective Plenipotentiaries, after exchanging their powers, and after mature deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, have concluded and agreed upon the following articles.</p>
            <p n="1">Article 1. THERE ſhall be a firm, invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable and univerſal peace, and a true and ſincere friendſhip between the moſt chriſtian king, his heirs and ſucceſſors, and the United States of America, and the ſubjects of the moſt chriſtian king and of the ſaid ſtates, and between the countries, iſlands, cities and towns ſituate under the juriſdiction of the moſt chriſtian king and of the ſaid United States, and the people and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of every degree, without exception of perſons or places, and the terms herein aftermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, ſhall be perpetual between the moſt chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian king, his heirs and ſucceſſors, and the ſaid United States.</p>
            <p n="2">Art. 2. The moſt chriſtian king and the United States engage mutual not to grant any particular favor to other nations, in reſpect of commerce and navigation, which ſhall not immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come common to the other party, who ſhall enjoy the ſame favor freely if the conceſſion was freely made, or on allowing the ſame compenſation, if the conceſſion was conditional.</p>
            <p n="3">Art. 3. The ſubjects of the moſt chriſtian king ſhall pay in the ports, havens, roads, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, iſlands, cities or towns of the United States,
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:029760_0004_0FE258A1E08082C8"/>
or any of them, no other, or greater duties or impoſts, of what nature ſoever they may be, or by what name ſoever called, than thoſe which the nations moſt favored are or ſhall be obliged to pay; and they ſhall enjoy all the rights, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, privileges, immunities, and exemptions in trade, navigation and commerce, whether in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from one port in the ſaid ſtates to another, or in going to and from the ſame, from and to any part of the world, which the ſaid nations do or ſhall enjoy.</p>
            <p n="4">Art. 4. The ſubjects, people and inhabitants of the ſaid United States, and each of them ſhall not pay in the ports, havens, roads, iſlands, cities, and places under the denomination of his moſt chriſtian majeſty, in Europe, any other or greater duties or impoſts, of what nature ſoever they may be, or by what name ſoever called, than thoſe which the moſt favored nations are or ſhall be obliged to pay: and they ſhall enjoy all the rights, liberties, privileges, immunities, and exemptions in trade, navigation and commerce, whether in paſſing from one port in the ſaid dominions in Europe, to another or in going to and from the ſame, from and to any part of the world, which the ſaid nations do or ſhall enjoy.</p>
            <p n="5">Art. 5. In the above exemption is particularly compriſed, the impoſition of one hundred ſous p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ton, eſtabliſhed in France on foreign ſhips, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs when the ſhips of the United States ſhall load with the merchandize of France, for another port of the ſame dominion; in which caſe the ſaid ſhips ſhall pay the duty above mentioned, ſo long as other nations the moſt favored ſhall be obliged to pay it; but it is underſtood, that the ſaid United States, or any of them are at liberty, when they ſhall judge it proper, to eſtabliſh a duty equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in the ſame caſe.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="6" facs="unknown:029760_0005_0FE258A4F0201950"/>Art. 6. The moſt chriſtian king ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, by all means in his power to protect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all veſſels and the effects belonging to the ſubjects, people or inhabitants of the ſaid United States, or any of them being in his ports, havens, or roads, or on the ſeas near his countries, iſlands cities or towns; and to recover and reſtore to the right owners, their agents or attornies, all ſuch veſſels and effects which ſhall be taken within his juriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion—and the ſhips of war of his moſt chriſtian ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, or any convoy ſailing under his authority, ſhall upon all occaſions, take under their protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all veſſels belonging to the ſubjects, people, or inhabitants of the ſaid United States, or any of them, and holding the ſame courſe, or going the ſame way, and ſhall defend ſuch veſſels as long as they hold the ſame courſe, or go the ſame way, againſt all attacks, force or violence, in the ſame manner as they ought to protect and defend the veſſels belonging to the ſubjects of the moſt chriſtian king.</p>
            <p n="7">Art. 7. In like manner the ſaid United States and their ſhips of war ſailing under their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſhall protect and defend, conformably to the preceding article, all the veſſels and effects belonging to the ſubjects of the moſt chriſtian king, and uſe all their endeavors to recover, and cauſe to be reſtored, the ſaid veſſels and effects that ſhall have been taken within the juriſdiction of the ſaid United States or any of them.</p>
            <p n="8">Art. 8. The moſt chriſtian king will employ his good offices and interpoſition with the king or emperor of Morocco or Fez; and the regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Algiers, Tunis, and Tripoly, or with any of them; and alſo with every other prince State or power of the coaſt of Barbary in Africa; and the ſubjects of the ſaid king, emperor, ſtates and
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:029760_0006_0FE258A680BDBE38"/>
powers, and each of them, in order to provide as fully and efficaciouſly as poſſible for the benefit conveniency and ſafety of the ſaid United-States, and each of them, their ſubjects, people and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, and their veſſels and effects, againſt all violence, inſults, attacks or depredations on the part of the ſaid princes, and ſtates of Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or their ſubjects.</p>
            <p n="9">Art. 9. The ſubjects, inhabitants, merchants, commanders of ſhips, maſters, and mariners of the ſtates, provinces and dominions of each party reſpectively, ſhall abſtain and forbear to fiſh in all places poſſeſſed, or which ſhall be poſſeſſed, by the other party, the moſt chriſtian king's ſubjects ſhall not fiſh in the havens, bays, creeks, roads, coaſts or places which the ſaid United States hold, or ſhall hereafter hold; and in like manner the ſubjects, people and inhabitants of the United States, ſhall not fiſh in the havens, bays, creeks roads, coaſts or places, which the moſt chriſtian king poſſeſſes or ſhall hereafter poſſeſs; and if any ſhip or veſſel ſhall be found fiſhing contrary to the tenor of this treaty, the ſaid ſhip or veſſel with its lading (proof being made thereof) ſhall be confiſcated; it is however underſtood that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion ſtipulated in the preſent article, ſhall take place only ſo long and ſo far, as the moſt chriſtian king or the United States ſhall not in this reſpect have granted an exemption to ſome other nation.</p>
            <p n="10">Art. 10. The United States their citizens and inhabitants, ſhall never diſturb the ſubjects of the moſt chriſtain king in the enjoyment and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the right of fiſhing on the banks of New-foundland, nor in the indefinite and excluſive right which belongs to them on that part of the coaſt of that iſland which is deſigned by the treaty of Utrecht, nor in the right relative to all and
<pb facs="unknown:029760_0007_0FE258A93581B548"/>
each of the iſles which belong to his moſt chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian majeſty, the whole conformable to the true ſenſe of the treaties of Utrecht and Paris.</p>
            <p n="11">Art. 11. The ſubjects and inhabitants of the ſaid United States, or any one of them, ſhall not be reputed <hi>Aubains</hi> in France, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſhall be exempted from the <hi>Droit d' Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baine,</hi> or other ſimilar duty, under what name ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; they may by teſtiment, donation or otherwiſe, diſpoſe of their goods, moveable and immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, in favour of ſuch perſons as to them ſhall ſeem good, and their heirs, ſubjects of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States, reſiding in France or elſewhere, may ſucceed them <hi>ab inteſtat,</hi> without being obliged to obtain letters of naturalization, and without hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the effect of this conceſſion conteſted or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peded, under pretext of any rights or preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of provinces, cities, or private perſons; and the ſaid heirs, whether by ſuch particular title, or <hi>ab inteſtat,</hi> ſhall be exempt from all duty called <hi>Droit de detraction,</hi> or other duty of the ſame kind; ſaving nevertheleſs the local rights or du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as much and as long as ſimilar ones are not eſtabliſhed by the United States, or any of them. The ſubjects of the moſt chriſtian king ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy on their part, in all the dominions of the ſaid States, an entire and perfect reciprocity, relative to the ſtipulations contained in the preſent article: But it is at the ſame time agreed, that its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents ſhall not affect the laws made, or that may be made hereafter in France, againſt emigrations, which ſhll remain in all their force and vigour; and the United Sates, on their part, or any of them, ſhall be at liberty to enact ſuch laws, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to that matter, as to them ſhall ſeem proper.</p>
            <p n="12">Art. 12. The merchant ſhips of either of the parties, which ſhall be making into a port be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:029760_0008_0FE258B21A704F80"/>
to the enemy of the other ally, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whoſe voyage and the ſpecies of goods on board her, there ſhall be juſt grounds of ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, ſhall be obliged to exhibit, as well upon the high ſeas, as in the ports and havens, not only her paſſports, but likewiſe certificates, expreſsly ſhewing that her goods are not of the number of thoſe which have been prohibited as contraband.</p>
            <p n="13">Art. 13. If by exhibiting of the aboveſaid cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates, the other party diſcover there are any of thoſe ſorts of goods which are prohibited and declared contraband, and conſigned for a port under the obedience of his enemy, it ſhall not be lawful to break up the hatches of ſuch ſhip, or to open any cheſt, co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fers, packs, caſks, or any other veſſels found therein, or to remove the ſmalleſt parcels of her goods, whether ſuch ſhip belong to the ſubjects of France, or the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the ſaid United States, unleſs the lading be brought on ſhore, in the preſence of the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the court of admiralty, and an inventory thereof made; but there ſhall be no allowance to ſell, exchange, or alieniate the ſame in any manner, until that after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and lawful proceſs ſhall have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad againſt ſuch prohibited goods, and the court of admiralty ſhall, by a ſentence pronounced, having confiſcated the ſame, ſaving always as well the ſhip itſelf, as any other goods found therein, which by this treaty are to be eſteemed free; neither may they be detained on pretence of their being as it were infected by the prohibited goods, much leſs ſhall they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated as lawful prize; but if not the whole car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go but only part thereof ſhall conſiſt of prohibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or contraband goods, and the commander of the ſhip ſhall be ready and willing to deliver
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:029760_0009_0FE258B3B860C128"/>
them to the captor who has diſcovered them, in ſuch caſe the captor having received thoſe goods, ſhall forthwith diſcharge the ſhip, and not hinder her by any means freely to proſecute the voyage on which ſhe was bound. But in caſe the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band merchandizes cannot be all received on board the veſſel of the captor, then the captor may, notwithſtanding the offer of delivering him the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traband goods, carry the veſſel into the neareſt port, agreeable to what is above directed.</p>
            <p n="14">Art. 14. On the contrary it is agreed, that whatever ſhall be found to be laden by the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and inhabitants of either party on any ſhip belonging to the enemies of the other, or to their ſubjects, the whole, although it be not of the ſort of prohibited goods, may be confiſcated in the ſame manner as if it belonged to the enemy, except ſuch goods and merchandize as were put on board ſuch ſhip before the declaration of war or even after ſuch declaration, if ſo be it were done without knowledge of ſuch declaration; ſo that the goods of the ſubjects of either party, whether they be of the nature of ſuch as are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited or otherwiſe, which, as is aforeſaid, were put on board any ſhip belonging to an enemy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the war, or after the declaration of the ſame, without the knowledge of it, ſhall no ways be liable to confiſcation, but ſhall well and truly be reſtored without delay to the proprietors demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame; but ſo as that if the ſaid merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes be contraband, it ſhall not be any ways lawful to carry them afterwards to any port belonging to the enemy. The two contracting parties agree, that the terms of two months being paſſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the declaration of war, their reſpective ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from whatever part of the world they come, ſhall not plead the ignorance mentioned in this article.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <pb n="11" facs="unknown:029760_0010_0FE258B5498D2120"/>Art. 15. And that more effectual care may be taken for the ſecurity of the ſubjects and inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of both parties, that they ſuffer no injury by the men of war or privateers of the other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, all the commanders of the ſhips of his moſt chriſtian majeſty and of the ſaid United States, and all their ſubjects and inhabitants, ſhall be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid doing any injury or damage to the other ſide; and if they act to the contrary they ſhall be pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed, and ſhall moreover be bound to make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for all matter of damage, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt thereof by reparation, under the pain and obligation of their perſons and goods.</p>
            <p n="16">Art. 16. All ſhips and merchandize of what nature ſoever, which ſhall be reſcued out of the hands of any pirates or robbers on the high ſeas, ſhall be brought into ſome port of either State, and ſhall be delivered to the cuſtody of the officers of that port, in order to be reſtored entire to the true proprietor, as ſoon as due and ſufficient proof ſhall be made concerning the property thereof.</p>
            <p n="17">Art. 17. It ſhall be lawful for the ſhips of war of either party, and privateers, freely to carry whitherſoever they pleaſe, the ſhips and goods ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from their enemies, without being obliged to pay any duty to the officers of the admiralty, or any other judges; nor ſhall ſuch prizes be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted or ſeized when they come to and enter the port of either party; nor ſhall the ſearchers or other officers of thoſe places ſearch the ſame, or make examination concerning the lawfulneſs of ſuch prizes; but they may hoiſt ſail at any time, and depart and carry their prizes to the places expreſſed in their commiſſions, which the commanders of ſuch ſhips of war ſhall be obliged to ſhew: On the contrary, no ſhelter or refuge
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:029760_0011_0FE258B6D65306E0"/>
ſhall be given in their ports to ſuch as ſhall have made prize of the ſubjects, people, or property of either of the parties, but if ſuch ſhall come in, being forced by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>reſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> weather, or the danger of the ſea, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> proper means ſhall be vigorouſly uſed, that they go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t and retire from thence as ſoon as poſſible.</p>
            <p n="18">Art. 18. If any ſhip belonging to either of the parties, their people or ſubjects, ſhall within the coaſts or dominions of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther, ſtick upon the ſands, or be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>cked or ſuffer any other da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, all friendly aſſiſtance and relief ſhall be given to the perſons ſhipwrecked, or ſuch as ſhall be in danger thereof. And letters of ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct ſhall likewiſe be given to them for their free and quiet paſſage from thence, and the return of every one to his own country.</p>
            <p n="19">Art. 19. In caſe the ſubjects and inhabitants of either party, with their ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ping, whether public and of war, or private and of merchants, be forced through ſtreſs of weather, purſuit of pirates, or enemies, or any other urgent neceſſity, for ſeeking of ſhelter, and harbour, to retreat, and enter into any of the rivers, bays, roads or ports belonging to the other party, they ſhall be received and treated with all humanity and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and enjoy all friendly protection and help; and they ſhall be permitted to refreſh and provide themſelves at reaſonable rates with victuals, and all things needful for the ſuſtenance of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or reparation of their ſhips and conveniency of their voyage, and they ſhall no way be detained or hindered from returning out of the ſaid ports or roads, but may remove and depart when and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they pleaſe, without any let or hindrance.</p>
            <p n="20">Art. 20. For the better promoting of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce on both ſides, it is agreed, that if a war
<pb facs="unknown:029760_0012_0FE258C12A2A1528"/>
ſhould break out between the ſaid two nations, ſix months after the proclamation of war ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to the merchants in the cities and town<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s where they live, for ſelling and tranſporting their goods and merchandizes; and if any thing be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them, or any injury be done them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that term, by either party, or the people or ſubjects of either, full ſatisfaction ſhall be made for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="21">Art. 21. No ſubject of the moſt chriſtian king ſhall apply or take any commiſſion or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etters of marque for arming any ſhip or ſhips to act as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateers againſt the ſaid United States or any of them, or againſt the ſubjects, people, or inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the ſaid United States, or any of them or againſt the property of any of the inhabitants of any of them from any prince of ſtate with which the United States ſhall be at war; nor ſhall any citizen, ſubject, or inhabitant of the ſaid United States or any of them, apply for or take any commiſſion or letters of marque for arming any ſhip or ſhips to act as privateers againſt the ſubjects of the moſt chriſtian king, or any of them, or the property of any of them, from any prince or ſtate with which the ſaid king ſhall be at war; and if any perſon of either nation ſhall take ſuch commiſſion or letters of marque, he ſhall be puniſhed as a pirate.</p>
            <p n="22">Art. 22. It ſhall not be lawful for any fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign privateer net belonging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſubjects of the moſt chriſtian king, nor citizens of the ſaid United States, who have commiſſions from any other prince or ſtate at enmity with either nation to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their ſhips in the ports of either of the one or the other of the aforeſaid parties, to ſell what they have taken, or in any other manner whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to exchange their ſhips, merchandizes or
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:029760_0013_0FE258C3E7AF6898"/>
any other lading: neither ſhall they be allowed even to purchaſe victuals, except ſuch as ſhall be neceſſary for going to the next port of that prince or ſtate from which they have commiſſions.</p>
            <p n="23">Art. 23. It ſhall be lawful for all and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar the ſubjects of the moſt chriſtian king, and the citizens, people and inhabitants of the ſaid United States, to ſail with their ſhips with all manner of liberty and ſecurity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diſtinction being made who are the proprietors of the merchandize laden there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; from any port to the places of thoſe who now are or hereafter ſhall be at enmity with the moſt chriſtian king or the United States. It ſhall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be lawful for the ſubjects and inhabitants aforeſaid, to ſail with the ſhips and merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes aforementioned, and to trade with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> liberty and ſecurity from the places, ports and havens of thoſe who are enemies of both or either party, without any oppoſition or diſturbance whatſoever, not only directly from the places of the enemy aforementioned to neutral places, but alſo from one place belonging to an enemy, to another place belonging to an enemy, whether they be under the juriſdiction of the ſame prince or under ſeveral. And it is hereby ſtipulated, that free ſhips ſhall alſo give a freedom to goods and that every thing ſhall be deemed free and exempt which ſhall be found on board the ſhips belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſubjects of either of the confederates, although, the who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e lading or any part thereof ſhould appertain to the enemies of either, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traband goods being always excepted. It is alſo agreed in like manner, that the ſame liberty be extended to perſons who are on board a free ſhip, with this effect, that although they be enemies to both or either party, they are not to be taken out of that free ſhip, unleſs they are ſoldiers and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ual ſervice of the enemies.</p>
            <p n="24">
               <pb n="15" facs="unknown:029760_0014_0FE258C575FEC8D0"/>Art. 24. This liberty of navigation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce ſhall extend to all kinds of merchandizes except thoſe only which are diſtinguiſhed by the name of contraband, and under this name of contraband or prohibited goods ſhall be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended arms, great guns, bombs with their fuſes and other things belonging to them, cannon-ball, gun-powder, match, pikes, ſwords, lances, ſpears, halberts, mortars, pedarts, grenadoes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, muſkets, muſket-balls, helmets, bucklers, breſt-plates, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ts of mail, and the like kinds of arms proper for arming ſoldiers, muſket-reſts, belts horſes with their furniture, and all other warlike inſtruments whatever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Theſe merchandizes, which follow ſhall not be reckoned among contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band or prohibited goods; that is to ſay, all ſorts any wool, flax, and all other manufactures woven of of cloaths, ſilk, cotton, or any other materials whatever, all kinds of wearing apparel, together with the ſpecies whereof they are u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d to be made, gold and ſilver, as well coined as uncoined, tin, iron, latten, copper, braſs, coals, as alſo wheat and barley, any other kind of corn or pulſe, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, and likewiſe all manner of ſpices, ſalted and ſmoked fleſh, ſalted fiſh, cheeſe and butter, beer, oil, wines, ſugars, and all ſorts of ſalts, and in general all proviſions which ſerve for the nouriſhment of mankind and the ſuſtenance of life; furthermore, all kinds of cotton, hemp, flax, tar, pitch, ropes, cables, ſails, ſail-cloth, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chors and any parts of anchors, alſo ſhip-maſts, planks, boards and beams of what trees ſoever, and all other things either proper for building, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing ſhips, and all other goods whatever, which have not been worked into the form of any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument or thing prepared for war by land or ſea, ſhall not be reputed contraband, much leſs
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:029760_0015_0FE258C70A49D5B8"/>
ſuch as have been already wrought up for any other uſe; all which ſhall be wholly reckoned among free goods as likewiſe all other merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes and things, which are not comprehended and particularly mentioned in the foregoing enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration of contraband goods, ſo that they may be tranſported and carried in the freeſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by the ſubjects of both confederates, even to places belonging to an enemy, ſuch towns or places being only excepted, as are at that time beſieged, blocked up or inveſted.</p>
            <p n="25">Art. 25. To the end that all manner of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions and quarrels may be avoided and prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, on one ſide and the other, it is agreed, that in caſe either of the parties hereto, ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in war, the ſhips and veſſels belonging to the ſubjects or people of the other ally muſt be furniſhed with ſea-letters or paſſports, expreſſing the name property and bulk of the ſhip, as alſo the name and place of habitation of the maſter or commander of the ſaid ſhip, that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear thereby that the ſhip really and truly belongs to the ſubjects of one of the parties, which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port ſhall be made out and granted according to the form annexed to this treaty; they ſhall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be recalled every year, that is, if the ſhip happens to return home in the ſpace of a year; it is likewiſe agreed, that ſuch ſhips being laden are to be provided not only with paſſports as above mentioned, but alſo with certificates, containing the ſeveral particulars of the cargo, the place whence the ſhip ſailed, and whither ſhe is bound, that ſo it may be known whether any forbidden or contraband goods be on board of the ſame, which certificates ſhall be made out by the officers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> place whence the ſhip ſet ſail, in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed form; and if any one ſhall think it fit or
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:029760_0016_0FE258D0D2F9CDA8"/>
adviſeable to expreſs in the ſaid certificates, the perſon to whom the goods on board belong, he may freely do ſo.</p>
            <p n="26">Art. 26. The ſhips of the ſubjects and inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of either of the parties coming upon any coaſt belonging to either of the ſaid allies; but not willing to enter into port, or being entered into port and not willing to unload their cargoes or break bulk, they ſhall be treated according to the general rules preſcribed or to be preſcribed relative to the object in queſtion.</p>
            <p n="27">Art. 27. If the ſhips of the ſaid ſubjects people or inhabitants of either of the parties ſhall be met with, either ſailing along the coaſts or on the high ſeas, by any ſhips of war of the other, or by any privateers, the ſaid ſhips of war or privateers, for the avoiding of any diſorder, ſhall remain out of cannon ſhot, and may ſend their boats on board the merchant ſhip which they ſhall ſo meet with, and may enter her to the number of two or three men only, to whom the maſter or commander of ſuch ſhip or veſſel ſhall exhibit his paſſport concerning the property of the ſhip, made out according to the form inſerted in this preſent treaty, and the ſhip, when ſhe ſhall have ſhewed ſuch paſſport, ſhall be free and at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to purſue her voyage, ſo as it ſhall not be lawful to moleſt or ſearch in any manner or to give her chaſe or to force her to quit her intended courſe.</p>
            <p n="28">Art. 28. It is alſo agreed, that all goods when once put on board the ſhips or veſſels of either of the two contracting parties, ſhall be ſubject to no further viſitation, but all viſitation or ſearch ſhall be made before hand, and all prohibited goods ſhall be ſtopped on the ſpot before the ſame be put on board, unleſs there are manifeſt tokens or
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:029760_0017_0FE258D3E386E8E0"/>
proofs of fraudulent practice; nor ſhall either the perſons or goods of the ſubjects of his moſt chriſtian majeſty or the United States, be put under any arreſt or moleſted by any other kind of embargo for that cauſe, and only the ſubject of that ſtate to whom the ſaid goods have been or ſhall be prohibited, and who ſhall preſume to ſell or alienate ſuch ſort of goods, ſhall be duly pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed for the offence.</p>
            <p n="29">Art. 29. The two contracting parties grant mutually the liberty of having each in the ports of the other, conſuls, vice-conſuls, agents, and commiſſaries, whoſe functions ſhall be regulated by a particular agreement.</p>
            <p n="30">Art. 30. And the more to favor and facilitate the commerce which the ſubjects of the United States may have with France, the moſt chriſtian king will grant them in Europe one or more free ports, where they may bring and diſpoſe of all the produce and merchandize of the thirteen united ſtates; and his majeſty will alſo continue to the ſubjects of the ſaid ſtates, the free ports which have been and are open in the French iſlands of America, of all which free ports the ſaid ſubjects of the united ſtates ſhall enjoy the uſe agreeable to the regulations which relate to them.</p>
            <p n="31">Art. 31. The preſent treaty ſhall be ratified on both ſides, and the ratifications ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed in the ſpace of ſix months, or ſooner if poſſible.</p>
            <p>IN FAITH WHEREOF the reſpective Pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potentiaries have ſigned the above articles both in the French and Engliſh languages; declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nevertheleſs, that the preſent treaty was originally propoſed and concluded in the French language and they have there to affixed their ſeals.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="unknown:029760_0018_0FE258D572B984F8"/>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>DONE at Paris,</hi> 
                  <date>this <hi>ſixth day of February, one thouſand ſeven hundred and ſeventy-eight.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>(L. S.) C. A. GERARD.</item>
                     <item>(L. S.) B. FRANKLIN.</item>
                     <item>(L. S.) SILAS DEANE.</item>
                     <item>(L. S.) ARTHUR LEE.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treaty">
            <head>TREATY OF ALLIANCE EVENTFUL <hi>AND</hi> DEFENSIVE. BETWEEN FRANCE <hi>&amp;</hi> AMERICA.</head>
            <p>THE Moſt Chriſtian King and the thirteen united ſtates of North America, to wit, New-Hampſhire, Maſſachuſetts Bay, Rhode-Iſl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and, Connecticut, New-York, New-Jerſey, Penn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvania, Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, North-Carolina, South-Carolina, and Georgia, having this day concluded a Treaty of Amity and Commerce, for the reciprocal advantage of their ſubjects and citizens, have thought it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to take into conſideration the means of ſtrengthening thoſe engagements, and of ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering them uſeful to the ſafety and tranquility of the two parties; particularly in caſe Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, in reſentment of that connection, and of the good correſpondence, which is the object of the ſaid treaty, ſhould break the peace with France, either by direct hoſtilities, or by hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her commerce and navigation in a manner contrary to the rights of nations, and the peace ſubſiſting between the two crowns. And his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and the ſaid united ſtates having reſolved in that caſe, to join their councils and efforts againſt tht enterprizes of their common enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="unknown:029760_0019_0FE258D705848960"/>The reſpective plenipotentiaries empowered to concert the clauſes and conditions proper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil the ſaid intentions, have, after the moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation, concluded and determined on the following articles.</p>
            <p>ARTICLE 1.</p>
            <p>IF war ſhould break out between France and Great Britain, during the continuance of the preſent war between the united ſtates and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, his majeſty and the ſaid united ſtates ſhall make it a common cauſe, and aid each other mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually with their good offices, their counſels and their forces according to the exigencies of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctures, as becomes good and faithful allies.</p>
            <p n="2">Art. 2. The eſſential and direct end of the preſent defenſive alliance is, to maintain effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, the liberty, ſovereignty and independence abſolute and unlimited of the ſaid united ſtates, as well in matters of government as of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce.</p>
            <p n="3">Art. 3. The two contracting parties, ſhall each on his own part, and in the manner it may judge moſt proper, make all the efforts in its power againſt their common enemy, in order to attain the end propoſed.</p>
            <p n="4">Art. 4. The contracting parties agree, that if either of them ſhould form any particular enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize in which the concurrence of the other may be deſired, the party whoſe concurrence is deſired, ſhall readily and with good faith join to act in concert for that purpoſe, as far as circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and its own particular ſituation will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and in that caſe, they ſhall regulate by a particular convention, the quantity and kind of ſuccour to be furniſhed, and the time and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:029760_0020_0FE258E36E303BE8"/>
of its being brought into action, as well as the advantages which are to be its compenſation.</p>
            <p n="5">Art. 5. If the united ſtates ſhould think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it to attempt the reduction of the Britiſh power, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in the northern parts of America, or the iſlands of Bermudas, thoſe countries or iſlands in caſe of ſucceſs, ſhall be confederated with, or dependent upon the ſaid United States.</p>
            <p n="6">Art, 6. The moſt chriſtian king renounces forever the poſſeſſion of the iſlands of Bermudas, as well as of any part of the continent of north America, which before the treaty of Paris, in 1763, or in virtue of that treaty were acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to belong to the crown of Great Britain, or to the United States, heretofore called Britiſh colonies, or which are at this time, or have lately been under the power of the King and Crown of Great Britain.</p>
            <p n="7">Art. 7. If his moſt chriſtian majeſty ſhall think proper to attack any of the iſlands ſituated in the Gulph of Mexico, or near that Gulph which are at preſent under the power of Great Britain all the ſaid iſles in caſe of ſucceſs, ſhall appertain to the crown of France.</p>
            <p n="8">Art. 8. Neither of the two parties ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude either truce or peace with Great Britain, without the formal conſent of the other firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; and they mutually engage not to lay down their arms, until the independence of the United States ſhall have been formally or tacitly aſſured, by the treaty or treaties that ſhall terminate the war.</p>
            <p n="9">Art. 9. The contracting parties declare, that being reſolved to fulfil each on its own part, the clauſes and conditions of the preſent treaty of alliance, according to its own power and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, there ſhall be no after claim of compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:029760_0021_0FE258E54E605BE0"/>
on one ſide, or the other, whatever may be the event of the war.</p>
            <p n="10">Art. 10. The moſt chriſtian king and the United States, agree, to invite or admit other powers, who may have received injuries from England to make common cauſe with them, and to accede to the preſent alliance under ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions as ſhall be freely agreed to, and ſettled between all the parties.</p>
            <p n="11">Art. 11. The two parties guarantee mutually from the preſent time and forever, againſt all other powers, to wit, the United States to his Moſt chriſtian majeſty, the preſent poſſeſſions of the crown of France in America, as well as thoſe which it may acquire by the future treaty of peace; and his moſt chriſtian majeſty guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antees on his part to the United States, their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty ſovereignty and independence, abſolute and unlimited, as well in matters of government as commerce, and all their poſſeſſions, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, or conqueſts, that their confederation may obtain during the war, from any of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions now or heretofore poſſeſſed by Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in North America; conformable to the fifth and hath articles above written, the whole as their poſſeſſion ſhall be fixed and aſſured to the ſaid ſtates, at the moment of the ceſſation of their preſent war with England.</p>
            <p n="12">Art. 12. In order to fix more preciſely the ſenſe and application of the preceding article, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting parties declare, that in caſe of a rupture between France and England, the reciprocal gua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantee declared in the ſaid article, ſhall have its full force and effect, the moment ſuch war ſhall break out; and if ſuch rupture ſhall not take place, the natural obligations of the ſaid guaran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, ſhall not commence until the moment of the
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:029760_0022_0FE258E6DD8F69D0"/>
ceſſation of the preſent war, between the United States and England, ſhall have aſcertained their poſſeſſions.</p>
            <p n="13">Art. 13. The preſent treaty ſhall be ratified on both ſides, and the ratifications ſhall be exchanged in the ſpace of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> months, or ſooner, if poſſible.</p>
            <p>IN FAITH WHEREOF the reſpective Plenipotentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to wit, on the part of the moſt chriſtian king, Conrad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>nder Gerard, Royal Syndic of the city of Straſbourg, and ſecretary of his Majeſty's cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of ſtate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and on the part of the United States, Benjamin Franklin deputy to the general Congreſs from the ſtate of Penn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvania, and preſident to the convention of ſaid ſtate; Silas Deane, heretofore deputy from the ſtate of Connecticut; and Arthur Lee, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor at law, have ſigned the above articles both in the French and Engliſh languages; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring nevertheleſs, that the preſent treaty was originally compoſed and concluded in the French language, and they have hereunto af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed their ſeals.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>DONE at PARIS, <date>
                     <hi>this ſixth day of February, one thouſand ſeven hundred and ſeventy-eight.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>(L. S.) C. A. GERARD.</item>
                     <item>(L. S.) B. FRANKLIN.</item>
                     <item>(L. S.) SILAS DEANE.</item>
                     <item>(L. S.) ARTHUR LEE.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="passport">
            <pb n="24" facs="unknown:029760_0023_0FE258E86AA66560"/>
            <head>Form of the Paſſports and Letters which are to be given to the ſhips and barques according to the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-fifth article of the Treaty of Amity and Commerce.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>To all who ſhall ſee theſe preſents, Greeting,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It is hereby made known, that leave and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion has been given to  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  maſter and commander of the ſhip called  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  of the town of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  burthen  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  tons or thereabouts, lying at preſent in the port and haven of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  and bound for  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  and laden with  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  After this ſhip has been viſited, and before ſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he ſhall make an oath before the officers who have the juriſdiction of maritime affairs, that the ſaid ſhip belongs to one or more of the ſubjects of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  the act whereof ſhall be put at the end of theſe preſents; as likewiſe that he will keep and cauſe to be kept by his crew on board, the marine ordinances and regulations, and enter in the proper office a liſt, ſigned and witneſſed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the names and ſirnames, the places of birth and abode of the crew of his ſhip, and of ll who ſhall embark on boord her, whom he ſhall not take on board without the knowledge and permiſſion of the officers of the marine, and in every part or haven where he ſhall enter with with his ſhip, he ſhall ſhew his preſent leave to his officers and judges of the marine, and ſhall give a faithful acount to them of what paſſed and was done during his voyage, and he ſhall carry the colours, arms, and enſign of the king or united ſtates during his voyage, in witneſs whereof we have ſigned theſe preſents, and put the ſeals of our arms thereunto, and cauſed the ſame to be cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſigned by  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  at  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  day of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  anno Domini.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="decree">
            <pb facs="unknown:029760_0024_0FE258F1830A8C98"/>
            <head>Authentic copy of the <hi>DECREE</hi> of the Queen of Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, for opening a Commercial Intercourſe between her Subjects, and thoſe of the United States.</head>
            <head type="sub">PORTUGAL.</head>
            <p>Her Majeſty has been pleaſed to order the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing decree to be tranſmitted to her Royal Court of Exchequer, that publication may be made of the ſame.</p>
            <p>WHEREAS by the Declaration of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence of the United States of North America, the object intended by the Royal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the 4th of July, 1776, and the publication thereof, by our Court of Exchequer, on the 5th of the ſame month, have ceaſed to operate. We are therefore pleaſed to aboliſh and annul the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree and publication aforeſaid; and do hereby or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that free entrance be granted in all the ports of our dominions, unto all ſhips and veſſels coming from North-America, in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as was formerly had in the admiſſion of thoſe which arrived from the ſaid colonies in the ports aforeſaid, and that all hoſpitality and favour be ſhewn them, which is uſually done to other friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nations.</p>
            <p>Our court of Exchequer will ſee this performed accordingly; and are ordered to cauſe this decree to be printed and ſet up in all public places of our city of Liſbon, and of other ports of this kingdom and Algarve, that all perſons may have due notice thereof, and none plead ignorance of the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>GIVEN at Salv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>terta de Magos, <date>the 13th of February 1783,</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>(Signed) With her Majeſty's Cypher</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <pb n="26" facs="unknown:029760_0025_0FE258F42E895868"/>
               <p>And in order that all perſons may have notice of this royal reſolution of our Lady aforeſaid, we have cauſed theſe preſents to be printed, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed at all public places of this city and other parts of this kingdom, agreeable to the tenor of the Decree above mentioned.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Liſbon, <date>this 17th of February, 1783.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>(Signed Gonſola Joſe da Silveira Preto.</item>
                        <item>Joſe da Conſta Ribeiro.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="treaty">
            <head>A Treaty of <hi>AMITY</hi> and <hi>COMMERCE,</hi> between their High Mightineſſes the States-General of the United Netherlands, and the United States of America.</head>
            <p>THEIR High Mightineſſes the States-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the United Netherlands, and the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States of America, to wit, New-Hampſhire, Maſſachuſetts, Rhode-Iſland and Providence plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, Connecticut, New-York, New-Jerſey, Pennſylvania, Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, North-Carolina, South-Carolina, and Georgia, deſiring to aſcertain, in a permanent and equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner, the rules to be obſerved, relative to the commerce and correſpondence which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to eſtabliſh between their reſpctive ſtates, countries and inhabitants, have judged that the ſaid end cannot be better obtained, than by eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing the moſt perfect equality and reciprocity for the baſis of their agreement, and by avoiding all thoſe burthenſome preferences which are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the ſources of debate, embarraſſment and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content; by leaving alſo each party at liberty to make, reſpecting commerce and navigation, ſuch ulterior regulations as it ſhall find moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:029760_0026_0FE258F5C2525858"/>
to itſelf, and by founding the advantages of commerce ſolely upon reciprocal utility, and the juſt rules of free intercourſe, reſerving withal, to each party, the liberty of admitting at its plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, other nations to a participation of the ſame advantages.</p>
            <p>On theſe principles their High Mightineſſes the States General of the United Netherlands, have named for their Plenipotentiaries, from the midſt of their aſſembly, Meſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urs their deputies for the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign affairs; and the ſaid United States of Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica, on their part, have furniſhed with full pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Mr. John Adams, late Commiſſioner of the United States of America at the court of Verſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, heretofore delegate in Congreſs from the State of Maſſachuſetts-Bay, and Chief Juſtice of the ſaid State; who have agreed and concluded as follows, to wit:</p>
            <p n="1">Art. 1. There ſhall be a firm, inviolable and univerſal peace and ſincere friendſhip between their High Mightineſſes, the Lords, the States General of the United Netherlands, and the United States of America; and between the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and inhabitants of the ſaid parties, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the countries, iſlands, cities and places, ſituated under the juriſdiction of the ſaid United Netherlands and the ſaid United States of Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica, their ſubjects and inhabitants of every de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, without exception of perſons or places.</p>
            <p n="2">Art. 2. The ſaid ſubjects of the States-General of the United Netherlands, ſhall pay in the ports, havens, roads, countries, iſlands, cities or places of the United States of America, or any of them no other nor greater duties or impoſts, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever nature or denomination they may be, than thoſe which the nations the moſt favoured are or ſhall be obliged to pay; and they ſhall enjoy all
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:029760_0027_0FE258F750FC86A8"/>
the rights, liberties, privileges, immunities and exemptions in trade, navigation and commerce which the ſaid nations do, or ſhall enjoy, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in paſſing from one port to another in the ſaid ſtates, or in going from any of thoſe ports to any foreign port of the world, or from any foreign port of the world to any of thoſe ports.</p>
            <p n="3">Art. 3. The ſubjects and inhabitants of the ſaid United States of America, ſhall pay in the ports, havens, roads, countries, iſlands, cities or places of the ſaid United Netherlands, or any of them, no other nor greater duties or impoſts of whatever nature or denomination they may be, than theſe which the nations the moſt favoured are or ſhall be obliged to pay; and they ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy all the rights, liberties, privileges, immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and exemptions in trade, navigation and commerce, which the ſaid nations do or ſhall enjoy, whether in paſſing from one port to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſaid ſtates, or from any one towards any one of thoſe ports, from or to any foreign port of the world: And the United States of America with their ſubjects and inhabitants, ſhall leave to thoſe of their High Mightineſſes, the peaceable enjoyment of their rights in the countries, iſlands and ſeas in the Eaſt and Weſt-Indies, without any hindrance or moleſtation.</p>
            <p n="4">Art. 4. There ſhall be an entire and perfect liberty of conſcience allowed to the ſubjects and inhabitants of each party and to their families, and no one ſhall be moleſted in regard to his worſhip, provided he ſubmits as to the public demonſtration of it, to the laws of the country: There ſhall be given moreover liberty, when any ſubjects or inhabitants of either party ſhall die in the territory of the other to bury them in the uſual burying places, or in decent and convenient
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:029760_0028_0FE25902D387D120"/>
grounds to be appointed for that purpoſe, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſhall require: And the dead bodies of thoſe who are buried, ſhall not in any wiſe be moleſted. And the two contracting parties ſhall provide each one in his juriſdiction, that their reſpective ſubjects and inhabitants may henceforward obtain the requiſite certificates in caſes of deaths in which they ſhall be intereſted.</p>
            <p n="5">Art. 5. Their High Mightineſſes the States-General of the United Netherlands, and the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States of America ſhall endeavour, by all the means in their power, to defend and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect all veſſels and other effects belonging to their ſubjects and inhabitants reſpectively, or to any of them, in their ports, roads, havens, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ſeas, paſſes, rivers, and as far as their ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction extends at ſea, and to recover and cauſe to be reſtored to the true proprietors, their agents or attornies, all ſuch veſſels and effects, which ſhall be taken under their juriſdiction: and their veſſels of war, and convoys, in caſes when they may have a common enemy, ſhall take un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their protection all the veſſels, belonging to the ſubjects and inhabitants of either party, which ſhall not be laden with contraband goods, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the deſcription which ſhall be made of them hereafter, for places with which one of the parties is in the peace, and the other at war, nor deſtined for any place blocked, and which ſhall hold the ſame courſe or follow the ſame route; and they ſhall defend ſuch veſſels as long as they ſhall hold the ſame courſe or follow the ſame route, againſt all attacks, force and violence of the common enemy, in the ſame manner as they ought to protect and defend the veſſels belonging to their own reſpective ſubjects.</p>
            <p n="6">Art. 6. The ſubjects of the contracting par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:029760_0029_0FE259048BC784A8"/>
may on one ſide and on the other, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective countries and ſtates, diſpoſe of their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects by teſtament, donation, or otherwiſe; and their heirs, ſubjects of one of the parties, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding in the country of the other, or elſewhere, ſhall all receive ſuch ſucceſſion even <hi>ab inteſtato,</hi> whether in perſon or by their attorney or ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, even although they ſhall not have obtained <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etters of naturalization, without having the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of ſuch commiſſion conteſted under pretext of any right or prerogatives of any province, city or private perſon; and if the heirs, to whom ſuch ſucceſſion may have fallen, ſhall be minors, the tutors, or curators, eſtabliſhed by the judge domiciliary, of the ſaid minors, may govern, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, adminiſter, ſell, and alienate the effects falling to the ſaid minors, by inheritance, and in general in relation to the ſucceſſions and effects, uſe all the rights and fulfil all the functions, which belong by the diſpoſition of the laws, to guardians, tutors, and curators: Provided never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, that this diſpoſition cannot take place, but in caſes where the teſtator ſhall not have named guardians, tutors, curators by teſtament, codicil, or other legal inſtrument.</p>
            <p n="7">Art. 7. It ſhall be lawful and free for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of each party, to employ ſuch advocates, attornies, notaries, ſolicitors or factors, as they ſhall judge proper.</p>
            <p n="8">Art. 8. Merchants, maſters and owners of ſhips, mariners, men of all kinds, ſhips and veſſels, and all merchandizes, and goods in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, of one of the confederates, or of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects thereof, ſhall not be ſeized or detained in any of the countres, lands, iſlands, cities, places, ports, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or dominations whatever of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confederates, for any military expedition,
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:029760_0030_0FE259061A6A7380"/>
public or private uſe of any one, by arreſts, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or any colour thereof: Much leſs ſhall it be permitted to the ſubjects of either party, to take or extort by force, any thing from the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the other party, without the conſent of the owner: Which however is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of ſeizures, detentions and arreſts, which ſhall be made by the command and authority of juſtice, and by the ordinary methods on account of debts or crimes, in reſpect whereof, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings muſt be, by way of law according to the forms of juſtice.</p>
            <p n="9">Art. 9. It is further agreed and concluded, that it ſhall be who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> free for all merchants, commanders of ſhips and other ſubjects and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the contracting parties, in every place ſubjected to the juriſdiction of the two pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers reſpectively, to manage themſelves, their own buſineſs: And moreover as to the uſe of interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or brokers, as alſo in relation to the load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or unloading of their veſſels, and ever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing which as relation thereto, they ſhall be, on one ſide and on the other, conſidered and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eated up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the footing of natural ſubjects, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at leaſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an equality with the moſt favoured nation.</p>
            <p n="10">Art. 10. The merchant ſhips of either of the parties coming from the port of an enemy, or from their own or a neutral port, may navigate freely towards any port of an enemy of the other ally: They ſhall be nevertheleſs held, whenever it ſhall be required, to exhibit, as well upon the high ſeas as in the ports, their ſea-letters and other documents, deſcribed in the twenty-fifth article, ſtating expreſsly that their effects are not of the number of thoſe, which are prohibited as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traband: and not having any contraband goods, for an enemy's port, they may freely and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:029760_0031_0FE25907A684A050"/>
hindrance, purſue their voyage towards the port of an enemy. Nevertheleſs it ſhall not be required to examine the papers of veſſels convoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by veſſels of war, but credence ſhall be given to the word of the officer, who ſhall conduct the convoy.</p>
            <p n="11">Art. 11. If by exhibiting the ſea-letters, and other documents deſcribed more particularly in the twenty fifth article of this treaty, the other party ſhall diſcover there are any of thoſe ſorts of goods, which are declared prohibited and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and that they are conſigned for a port un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obedience of his enemy, it ſhall not be lawful to break up the hatches of ſuch ſhip, or to open any cheſt, coffers, packs, caſks, or other veſſel found therein, or to remove the ſmalleſt parcel of her goods, whether the ſaid veſſel belongs to the ſubjects of their High Mightineſſes the States General of the United Netherlands, or to the ſubjects or inhabitants of the ſaid United States of America, unleſſ the lading be brought on ſhore, in preſence of the officers of the Court of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty, and an inventory thereof made, but there ſhall be no allowance to ſell, exchange, or alienate the ſame until after that due and lawful proceſs ſhall have been had againſt ſuch prohibited goods or contraband, and the Court of Admiralty by a ſentence pronounced ſhall have confiſcated the ſame, ſaving always as well as the ſhip itſelf as any other good found therein, which are to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed free, and may not be detained on pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of their being infected by the prohibited goods, much leſs ſhall they be confiſcated as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful prize: But on the contrary when by the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation at land, it ſhall be found there are no contraband goods in the veſſel, and it ſhall not appear by the papers that he who has taken and
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:029760_0032_0FE25912871585B8"/>
carried in the veſſel, has been able to diſcover any there, he ought to be condemned in all the charges, damages and intereſt of them, which he ſhall have cauſed both to the owner of ſuch veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and to the owners and freighters of cargoes, with which they ſhall be loaded, by his demerity in taking and carrying them in, declaring moſt expreſsly the free veſſels ſhall aſſure the liberty of the effects with which they ſhall be loaded, and that this liberty ſhall extend itſelf equally to the perſons who ſhall be found in a free veſſel, who may not be taken out of her, unleſs they are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary men, actually in the ſervice of an enemy.</p>
            <p n="12">Art. 12. On the contrary, it is agreed, whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall be found to be laden by the ſubjects and inhabitants of either party, on any ſhip belonging to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e enemies of the other, or to their ſubjects, although it be not comprehended under the ſort of prohibited goods, the whole may be confiſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſame manner as if it belonged to the enemy, except nevertheleſs ſuch effects and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, as were put on board ſuch veſſel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the declaration of war or in the ſpace of ſix months after it, which effects ſhall not be in any manner ſubject to confiſcation, but ſhall be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and without delay reſtored in nature to the owners, who ſhall claim them, or cauſe them to be claimed, before the confiſcation and ſale, as alſo their proceeds, if the claim could not be made but in the ſpace of eight months, after the ſale, which ought to be public; provided never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, that if the ſaid merchandizes are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, it ſhall by no means be lawful to tranſport them afterwards to any port belonging to ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p n="13">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>T. 13. And that more effectual care may be taken for ſecurity of ſubjects and people
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:029760_0033_0FE2591416831790"/>
of either party, that they do not ſuffer moleſtation from the veſſels of war, or privateers of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther party, it ſhall be forbidden to all comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of veſſels of war, and other armed veſſels of the ſaid States-General of the United Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, and the ſaid United States of America, as well as to all their officers, ſubjects and people, to give any offence or do any damage to thoſe of the other party: and if they act to the contrary, they ſhall be upon the firſt complaint which ſhall be made of it, being found guilty after a juſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, puniſhed by their proper judges, andr moreover obliged to make ſatisfaction for all da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages and intereſts thereof, by reparation, unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pain and obligation of their perſons and goods.</p>
            <p n="14">Art. 14. For further determining of what has been ſaid, all captains of privateers, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itters out of veſſels armed for war under commiſſion, and on account of private perſons ſhall be held be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their departure, to give ſufficient caution be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore competent judges, either to be reſponſible for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alverſations which they may commit in their cruizes or voyages, as well as for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traventions of their captains and officers, againſt the preſent treaty, and againſt the ordinances and edicts which ſhal1 be publiſhed in conſequence of, and conformity to it, under pain of forfeiture and nullity of the ſaid commiſſion.</p>
            <p n="15">Art. 15. All veſſels and merchandizes of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever nature, which ſhall be reſcued out of the hands of any pirates or robbers, navigating the high ſeas, without requiſite commiſſions, ſhall be brought into ſome port of one of the two ſtates, and depoſited in the hands of the officers of that port; in order to be reſtored entire to the true proprietor, as ſoon as due and ſufficient proof ſhall be made, concerning the property thereof.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="35" facs="unknown:029760_0034_0FE25915A9CB4B88"/>Art. 16. If any ſhips or veſſels belonging to either of the parties, their ſubjects or people ſhall within the coaſts or dominions of the other, ſtick upon the ſands or be wrecked, or ſuffer any ſea damage, all friendly aſſiſtance and relief ſhall be given to the perſons ſhipwrecked, or ſuch as ſhall be in danger thereof; and the veſſels, effects and merchandizes, or the part of them which ſhall have been ſaved, or the proceeds of them, if being periſhable they ſhall have been ſold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing claimed within a year and a day, by the maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or owners, or their agents or attornies, ſhall be reſtored, paying only the reaſonable charges; and that which muſt be paid in the ſame caſe, for the ſalvage, by the proper ſubjects of the country: there ſhall alſo be delivered them ſafe conducts or paſſports, for their free and ſafe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from thence, and return each one to his own country.</p>
            <p n="17">Art. 17. In caſe the ſubjects or people of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther party with their ſhipping, whether public and of war, or private and of merchants, be forced through ſtreſs of weather, purſuit of pirates or enemies, or any other urgent neceſſity, for ſeeking of ſhelter and harbour to retreat and enter into any of the rivers, creeks, bays, ports, roads or ſhores belonging to the other party, they ſhall be received with all humanity and kindneſs, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy all friendly protection and help, and they ſhall be permitted to refreſh and provide themſelves at reaſonable rates with victuals and all things need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the ſuſtenance of their perſons, or repar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of their ſhips; and they ſhall no ways be detained or hindred from returning out of the ſaid ports or roads, but may remove and depart when and whither they pleaſe, without any let or hindrance.</p>
            <p n="18">
               <pb n="36" facs="unknown:029760_0035_0FE2591737BFD1F0"/>Art. 18. For the better promoting of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce on both ſides, it is agreed, that if a war ſhould break out between their high Mightineſſes the States General of the United Netherlands and the United States of America, there ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be granted to the ſubjects on each ſide, the term of nine months, after the date of the rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the proclamation of war; to the end that they may retire with their effects, and tranſport them where they pleaſe; which it ſhall be lawful for them to do, as well as to ſell or tranſport their effects and goods in all freedom, and without any hindrance, and without being able to proceed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſaid term of nine months, to any arreſt of their effects, much leſs of their perſons; on the contrary; there ſhall be given them, for their veſſels and their effects which they would carry away, paſſports and ſafe conducts, for the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ports of their reſpective countries; and for the time neceſſary for the voyage, and no prize made at ſea, ſhall be adjudged lawful, at leaſt if the declaration of war was not or could not be known, in the laſt port, which the veſſel ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken has quitted. But for whatever may have been taken from the ſubjects and inhabitants of either party, and for the offences which may have been given them, in the interval of the ſaid terms, a complete ſatisfaction ſhall be given them.</p>
            <p n="19">Art. 19. No ſubjects of their High Mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes the States-General of the United Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, ſhall apply for, or take any commiſſions or letters of marque for arming any ſhip or ſhips to act as privateers, againſt the ſaid United States of America or any of them, or the ſubjects and inhabitants of the ſaid United States or any of them, or againſt the property of the inhabitants of any of them, from any prince or ſtate with
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:029760_0036_0FE25922FAC3F9D0"/>
which the ſaid United States of America may happen to be at war; nor ſhall any ſubject or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant of the ſaid United States of America or any of them, apply for or take any commiſſion or letters of marque for arming any ſhip or ſhips, to act as privateers againſt the High and Mighty Lords, the States General of the United Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, or againſt the ſubjects of their high Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſes, or any of them, or againſt the property of any one of them, from any prince or ſtate with which their high mightineſſes may be at war: And if any perſon of either nation ſhall take ſuch commiſſion or letters of marque he ſhall be pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed as a pirate.</p>
            <p n="20">Art. 20. If the veſſels of the ſubjects or in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>habitants of one of the parties, come upon any coaſt belonging to either of the ſaid allies, but not willing to enter into port, or being entered into port and not willing to unload their cargoes or break bulk, or take in any cargo they ſhall not be obliged to pay neither for the veſſels, nor the cargoes, any duties of entry in or out, nor to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any account of their cargoes, at leaſt if there is not juſt cauſe to preſume, that they carry to an enemy merchandizes of contraband.</p>
            <p n="21">Art. 21. The two contracting parties grant to each other mutually, the liberty of having each in the ports of the other, conſuls, vice-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, agents, and commiſſaries, of their own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing, whoſe functions ſhall be regulated by particular agreement, whenever either party chuſe to make ſuch appointments.</p>
            <p n="22">Art. 22. This treaty ſhall not be underſtood in any manner to derogate from the ninth, tenth, nineteenth and twenty-fourth articles of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with France, as they were numbered in the ſame treaty concluded the 6th of February,
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:029760_0037_0FE25924D9737508"/>
1778, and which makes the articles ninth, tenth, ſeventeenth, and twenty-ſecond of the treaty of commerce now ſubſiſting between the United States of America and the crown of France; nor ſhall it hinder his catholic majeſty from acceding to that treaty, and enjoying the advantages of the ſaid four articles.</p>
            <p n="23">Art. 23. If at any time the United States of America, ſhall judge neceſſary to commence ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gociations with the king or emperor of Morocco and Fez, and the Regencies of Algiers, Tunis or Tripoli, or with any of them to obtain paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports for the ſecurity of their navigation in the Mediterranean ſea; their high mightineſſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that upon the requiſition which the United States of America ſhall make of it, they will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſuch negociations in the moſt favorable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by means of their conſuls reſiding near the ſaid king, emperor and regencies.</p>
            <p n="24">Art. 24. The liberty of navigation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce ſhall extend to all ſorts of merchandizes, excepting only thoſe which are diſtinguiſhed under the name of contraband or merchandizes prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited: and under this denomination of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and merchandizes prohibited ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended only warlike ſtores and arms, as mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, artillery with their artifices and appurtenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, fuſils, piſtols, bombs, grenades, gun-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſalt-petre, ſulpher, match, bullets, and balls, pikes, ſabres, lances, halberts, caſques, cutlaſſes, and other ſort of arms, as alſo ſoldiers, horſes ſaddles, and furniture for horſes. All o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther effects and merchandizes, not before ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied expreſsly, and even all ſorts of naval matters, however proper they may be for the conſtruction and equipment of veſſels of war, or for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture of one or another ſort of machines of
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:029760_0038_0FE2592668DF12E0"/>
war, by land or ſea, ſhall not be judged contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, neither by the letter, nor according to any pretended interpretation, whatever, ought they, or can they be comprehended, under the notion of effects prohibited or contraband. So that all effects and merchandizes, which are not expreſs<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly before named, may without any exception, and in perfect liberty be tranſported by the ſubjects and inhabitants of both allies, from and to places belonging to the enemy, excepting only the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which at the ſame time ſhall be beſieged, block<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed or inveſted, and thoſe places only ſhall be held for ſuch, which are ſurrounded nearly by ſome of the belligerent powers.</p>
            <p n="25">Art. 25. To the end that all diſſention and quarrel may be avoided and prevented, it has been agreed, that in caſe one of the two parties happens to be at war, the veſſels belonging to the ſubjects or inhabitants of the other ally, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be provided with ſea letters or paſſports, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the name, the property and the burthen of the veſſel, as alſo the name and the place of abode of the maſter or commander of the ſaid veſſel, to the end, that thereby it may appear, that the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel really and truly belongs to the ſubjects or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of one of the parties; which paſſports ſhall be drawn and diſtributed according to the form anexed to this treaty; each time that the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel ſhall return, ſhe ſhould have ſuch her paſſort renewed, or at leaſt they ought not to be of more ancient date than two years, before the veſſel has been returned to her own country.</p>
            <p>It has alſo been agreed that ſuch veſſels, being loaded ought to be provided not only with the ſaid paſſports or ſea-letters, but alſo with a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral paſſport, or with particular paſſports or mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts, or other public documents, which are ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:029760_0039_0FE25927F8B46B20"/>
given to veſſels outward bound, in the ports from whence the veſſels have ſet ſail in the laſt place, containing a ſpecification of the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, of the place from whence the veſſel departed, and of that of her deſtination; or inſtead of all theſe, with certificates from the magiſtrates or governors, of cities places and colonies, from whence the veſſel came given in the uſual form, to the end that it may be known whether there are any effects prohibited or contraband on board the veſſels, and whether they are deſtined to be carried to an enemy's country or not. And in caſe any one judges proper, to expreſs in the ſaid documents, the perſons to whom the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects on board belong, he may do it freely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out however, being bound to do it; and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſuch expreſſions connot and ought not to cauſe a confiſcation.</p>
            <p n="26">Art. 26. If the veſſels of the ſaid ſubjects, or inhabitants of either of the parties, failing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the coaſt or on the high ſeas, are met by a veſſel of war or privateer, or other armed veſſels of the other party, the ſaid veſſels of war, priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers or armed veſſels for avoiding all diſorder, ſhall remain without the reach of cannon, but may ſend their boats on board the merchant veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel which they ſhall meet in this manner, upon which they may not paſs more than two or three men to whom the maſter or commander ſhall exhibit his paſſport concerning the property of the veſſel according to the form annexed to this treaty; and the veſſel, after having exhibited ſuch a paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, ſea-letter and other documents, ſhall be free to continue her voyage, ſo that it ſhall not be lawful to moleſt her, or ſearch her in any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, nor to give her chaſe, nor to force her to alter her courſe.</p>
            <p n="27">
               <pb n="41" facs="unknown:029760_0040_0FE25930E42C6810"/>Art. 27. It ſhall be lawful for merchants, cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and commanders of veſſels, whether public, and of war, or private and of merchants, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſaid United States of America, or any of them, or to their ſubjects and inhabitants, to take freely into their ſervice, and receive on board their veſſels, in any port or place in the juriſdiction of their High Mightineſſes aforeſaid, ſeamen or others, natives or inhabitants of any of the ſaid ſtates upon ſuch condition as they ſhall agree on, without being ſubject for this to any fine, penalty, puniſhment, proceſs or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion whatever: And reciprocally, all mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, captains and commanders, belonging to the ſaid United Netherlands, ſhall enjoy in all the ports and places under the obedience of the ſaid United States of America, the ſame privilege of engaging and receiving ſeamen, or others natives or inhabitants of any country or the domination of the ſaid States-General; provided, that neither on one ſide nor the other, they may not take in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſervice ſuch of their countrymen who have already engaged in the ſervice of the other party contracting, whether in war or trade, and whether they meet them by land or ſea; at leaſt if the captains or maſters, under the command of whom ſuch perſons may he found, will not of his own conſent, diſcharge them from the ſervice, upon pain of being otherwiſe treated and puniſhed as deſerters.</p>
            <p n="28">Art. 28. The affair of refraction ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated in all equity and juſtice, by the Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates of cities reſpectively, where it ſhall be judged that there is any room to complain in this reſpect.</p>
            <p n="29">Art. 29. The preſent treaty ſhall be ratified and approved of by their High Mightineſſes the
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:029760_0041_0FE25933E21C2D80"/>
States-General of the United Netherlands, and by the United States of America, and the acts of ratification ſhall be delivered in good and due form on one ſide and on the other, in the ſpace of ſix months, or ſooner if poſſible, to be computed from the day of the ſignature.</p>
            <p>In faith of which, we the Deputies and Plenipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiaries of the Lords the States-General of the United Netherlands, and the Miniſter Pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potentiary of the United States of America, in virtue of our reſpective authorities and full pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers have ſigned the preſent Treaty, and oppoſe thereto the ſeals of our arms.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Done at the Hague,
<date>the 8th of October, 1782.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treaty">
            <head>A Treaty of AMITY and COMMERCE conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded between his Majeſty the king of <hi>Sweden</hi> and the <hi>United States of America.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>The King of Sweden, of the Goths and Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, &amp;c. &amp;c. and the Thirteen United States of North America, to wit, New-Hampſhire, Maſſachuſetts-Bay, Rhode-Iſland, Connecticut, New-York, New-Jerſey, Pennſylvania, the Counties of New-Caſtle, Kent, and Suſſex, on Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, North-Carolina, South-Carolina, and Georgia, deſiring to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh in a ſtable and permanent manner, the rules which ought to be obſerved relative to the correſpondence and commerce which the two parties have judged neceſſary to eſtabliſh between their reſpective countries, ſtates and ſubjects; his Majeſty and the United States have thought that they could not better accompliſh that end,
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:029760_0042_0FE259356FED9B88"/>
than by taking for a baſis of their arrangements the mutual intereſts and advantage of both na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, thereby avoiding all thoſe burthenſome preferences, which are uſually ſources of debate, embarraſſment and diſcontent, and by leaving each party at liberty to make, reſpecting naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and commerce, thoſe interior regulations which ſhall be moſt convenient to itſelf.</p>
               <p>With this view, his Majeſty the King of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den has nominated and appointed for his Plenipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiary, Count Guſtavus Philip de Creutz, his Ambaſſador extraordinary to his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, and Knight, Commander of his orders; and the United States, on their part have fully empowered Benjamin Franklin, their miniſter Plenipotentiary to his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty; the ſaid Plenipotentiaries, after exchanging their full powers, and after mature deliberation in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence thereof have agreed upon, concluded and ſigned the following articles:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>ARTICLE 1.</head>
               <p>There ſhall be a firm, inviolable and univerſal peace, and a true and ſincere friendſhip between the king of Sweden, his heirs and ſucceſſors, and the United States of America, and the ſubjects of his Majeſty and thoſe of the ſaid States, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the countries, iſlands, cities, and towns, ſituated under the juriſdiction of the king and of the ſaid United States, without any exception of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or places; and the conditions agreed to in this preſent treaty, ſhall be perpetual and perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent between the king his heirs and ſucceſſors, and the ſaid United States.</p>
               <p n="2">Art. 2. The King and the United States en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage mutually, not to grant hereafter any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular favour to other nations in reſpect to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and navigation, which ſhall not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:029760_0043_0FE2593702F26118"/>
become common to the other party, who ſhall enjoy the ſame favour freely, if the conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was freely made, or on allowing the ſame compenſation, if the conceſſion was conditional.</p>
               <p n="3">Art. 3. The ſubjects of the king of Sweden ſhall not pay in the ports, havens, roads, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, iſlands, cities and towns, of the United States, or any of them, any other nor greater du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or impoſts of what nature ſoever they may be, than thoſe which the moſt favoured nations are or ſhall be obliged to pay; and they ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy all the rights, liberties, privileges, immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and exemptions in trade, navigation and commerce which the ſaid nations do or ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, whether in paſſing from one port to another of the United States, or in going to or from the ſame, from or to any part of the world what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
               <p n="4">Art. 4. The ſubjects and inhabitants of the ſaid United States ſhall not pay in the ports, havens, roads, iſlands, cities and towns under the domin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of the king of Sweden, any other or greater duties or impoſts of what nature ſoever they may be, or by what name ſoever called, than thoſe which the moſt favoured nations are or ſhall be obliged to pay; and they ſhall enjoy all the rights liberties, privileges, immunities and exemptions in trade, navigation and commerce, which the ſaid nations do or ſhall enjoy, whether in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from one port to another of the dominion of his ſaid majeſty, or in going to or from the ſame, from or to any part of the world whatever.</p>
               <p n="5">Art. 5. There ſhall be granted a full, perfect and entire liberty of conſcience to the inhabitants and ſubjects of each party, and no perſon ſhall be moleſted on account of his worſhip, provided <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſubmits ſo far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> regards the public demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations
<pb n="45" facs="unknown:029760_0044_0FE259428DDBD618"/>
of it to the laws of the country: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over liberty ſhal1 be granted, when any of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects or inhabitants of either party die in the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritory of the other, to bury them in convenient and decent places, which ſhall be aſſigned for the purpoſe: And the two contracting parties will provide each in its juriſdiction, that ſubjects and inhabitants reſpectively may obtain certificates of the death in caſe the delivery of them is required.</p>
               <p n="6">Art. 6. The ſubjects of the contracting parties in the reſpective States, may freely diſpoſe of their goods and effects either by teſtament, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or otherwiſe in favour of ſuch perſons as they think proper; and their heirs in whatever place they ſhall reſide, ſhall receive the ſucceſſion even ab inteſtato, either in perſon or by their attorney, without having occaſion to take out let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of naturalization. Theſe inheritances, as well as the capitals and effects, which the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the two parties, in changing their abode, ſhall be deſirous of removing from the place of their abode, ſhall be exempt from all duty, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led "droit de detraction" on the part of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the two States reſpectively. But it is at the ſame time agreed, that nothing contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this article ſhall in any manner derogate from the ordinances publiſhed in Sweden againſt emigrations, or which may hereafter be publiſhed, which ſhall remain in full force and vigour. The United States on their part, or any of them, ſhall be at liberty to make reſpecting this matter, ſuch laws as they think proper.</p>
               <p n="7">Art. 7. All and every the ſubjects inhabitants of the kingdom of Sweden, as well as thoſe of the United States, ſhall be permitted to navigate with their veſſels in all ſafety and freedom, and without any regard to thoſe to whom the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:029760_0045_0FE259453AB04AC0"/>
and cargoes may belong, from any port whatever, and the ſubjects and inhabitants of the two ſtates ſhall likewiſe be permitted to ſail and trade with their veſſels, and with the ſame liberty and ſafety to frequent the places, ports and havens of powers, enemies to both or either of the contracting parties, without being in any wiſe moleſted or troubled, and to carry on a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce not only directly from the ports of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to a neutral port, but even from one port of an enemy, to another of an enemy, whether it be under the juriſdiction of the ſame or of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent princes. And as it is acknowledged by this treaty with reſpect to ſhips and merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes that free ſhips ſhall make the merchandizes free, and that every thing which ſhall be on board of ſhips belonging to ſubjects of the one or the other of the contracting parties, ſhall be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as free, even though the cargo or a part of it ſhould belong to the enemies of one or both; it is nevertheleſs provided that contraband goods ſhall always be excepted; which being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted, ſhall be proceeded againſt according to the ſpirit of the following article. It is likewiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, that the ſame liberty be extended to perſons who may be on board a free ſhip, with this effect that although they be enemies to both or either of the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ies, they ſhall not be taken out of the free ſhip, unleſs they are ſoldiers in the actual ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the ſaid enemies.</p>
               <p n="8">Art. 8. The liberty of navigation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce ſhall extend to all kinds of merchandizes except thoſe only which are expreſſed in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing article and are diſtinguiſhed under the name of contraband goods.</p>
               <p n="9">Art. 9. Under the name of contraband or prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited goods, ſhall be comprehended arms, great
<pb n="47" facs="unknown:029760_0046_0FE25946CD643518"/>
guns, cannon-balls, arquebuſes, muſquets, bombs, petards, grenadoes, ſauciſſes, pitch, balls, carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages for ordinance, muſquet reſts, bandoliers, cannon powder, matches, ſalt petre, ſulpher, bullets, pikes, ſabres, ſwords, morions, helmets, cuiraſſes, halbards, javelins, piſtols, holſters, belts, bayonets, horſes with their harneſs, and other like kind of arms and inſtruments of war for the uſe of troops.</p>
               <p n="10">Art. 10. Theſe which follow ſhall not be reckoned in the number of prohibited goods, that is to ſay all ſorts of cloaths, and all other manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures of wool, flax, ſilk, cotton or any other materials, all kinds of wearing apparel together with the things of which they are commonly made; gold, ſilver coined or uncoined, braſs, iron, lead, copper, latten, coals, wheat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rley, and all ſorts of corn or pulſe, tobacco, all kinds of ſpices, ſalted or ſmoaked fleſh, ſalted fiſh, cheeſe, butter, beer, oil, wines, ſugar, all ſorts of ſalt and proviſions which ſerve for the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſuſtenance of man;—all kinds of cotton, hemp, flax, tar, pitch, ropes, cables, ſails, ſail-cloth, anchors, and any part of anchors, ſhip maſts, planks, boards, beams and all ſorts of trees and other things proper for buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or repairing ſhips; nor ſhall any goods be conſidered as contraband, which have not been worked into the form of any inſtrument or thing for the purpoſe of war by land or by ſea, much leſs ſuch as have been prepared or wrought up for any other uſe. All which ſhall be reckoned free goods, as likewiſe all others which are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenhed and particularly mentioned in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going article; ſo that they ſhall not by any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended interpretation be comprehended among prohibited or contraband goods: on the contrary
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:029760_0047_0FE259485E6CE120"/>
they may freely be tranſported by the ſubjects of the King and of the United States, even to pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces belonging to an enemy, ſuch places only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted as are beſieged, blocked o inveſted, and thoſe places only ſhall be conſidered as ſuch, which are nearly ſurrounded by one of the belli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent powers.</p>
               <p n="11">Art. 11. In order to avoid and prevent on both ſides all diſputes and diſcords, it is agreed that in caſe one of the parties ſhall be engaged in a war, the ſhips and veſſels belonging to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects or inhabitants of the other ſhall be furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſea-letters, or paſſorts expreſſing the name property and port of the veſſel, and alſo the name and place of abode of the maſter or commander of the ſaid veſſel, in order that it may thereby ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that the ſaid veſſel really and truly belongs to the ſubjects of the one or the other party.—Theſe paſſports which ſhall be drawn up in good and due form, ſhall be renewed every time the veſſel returns home in the courſe of the yearr.—It is alſo agreed that the ſaid veſſels when loaded ſhall be provided not only with ſea-letters but alſo with certificates containing a particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the cargo, the place from which the veſſel ſailed and that of her deſtination, in order that it may be known whether they carry any of the prohibited or contraband merchandizes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the ninth article of the present treaty; which certificates ſhall be made out by the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the place from which the veſſel ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part.</p>
               <p n="12">Art. 12. Although the veſſels of the one and the other party may navigate freely and with all ſafety, as is explained in the ſeventh article they ſhall nevertheleſs be bound at all times when required to exhibit as well on the high ſeas as
<pb n="49" facs="unknown:029760_0048_0FE25953A7801368"/>
in port, their paſſports and certificates above mentioned. And not having contraband merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes on board for an enemy's port, they may freely and without hindrance purſue their voyage to the place of their deſtination. Nevertheleſs the exhibition of papers ſhall not be demanded of merchant ſhips under convoy of veſſels of war, but credit ſhall be given to the word of the officeer commanding the convoy.</p>
               <p n="13">Art. 13. If on producing the ſaid certificates it be diſcovered, that the veſſel carries ſome of the goods which are declared to be prohibited or contraband, and which are conſigned to an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my's port, it ſhall not however be lawful to break up the hatches of ſuch ſhips, nor to open any cheſt coffers, packs, caſks or veſſels, nor to remove the ſmalleſt part of the merchandizes, until the cargo has been landed in the preſence of officers appointed for the purpoſe, and until an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventory thereof has been taken; nor ſhall it be lawful to ſell, exchange or alienate the cargo or any part thereof, until legal proceſs ſhall have been made againſt the prohibited merchandizes and ſentences ſhall have paſſed, declaring them liable to confiſcation; ſaving nevertheleſs, as well the ſhips themſelves, as the other merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes, which ſhall have been found therein, which by virtue of this preſent treaty, are to be eſteemed free, and which are not to be detained on pretence of their having been loaded with prohibited mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, and much leſs confiſcated as lawful prize. And in caſe the contraband merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize be only a part of the cargo and the maſter of the veſſel agrees, conſents and offers to deliver them the veſſel, that has diſcovered them, in that caſe the latter, after receiving the merchandizes which are good prize, ſhall immediately let the
<pb n="50" facs="unknown:029760_0049_0FE25955382250C8"/>
veſſel go and ſhall not by any means hinder her from purſuing her voyage to the place of her deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tination. When a veſſel is taken and brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any of the ports of the contracting parties, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>und to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with merchandizes declared to be free, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or he who has made the prize ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nd to pay all coſts and damages to the maſter of the veſſel unjuſtly detained.</p>
               <p n="14">Art. 14. It is likewiſe agreed that whatever ſhall be found to be laden by the ſubjects of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the two contracting parties on a ſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the enemies of the other party, the whole effects, although not of the number of thoſe declared contraband, ſhall be confiſcated as if they belonged to the enemy, excepting never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, ſuch goods and merchandizes as were put on board before the declaration of war, and even ſix months after the declaration, after which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> none ſhall be preju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d to be ignorant of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which merchandizes ſhall not in any manner be ſubject to confiſcation, but ſhall be faithfully and ſpecifically delivered to the owners who ſhall claim, or cauſe them to be claimed before confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and ſale, as alſo their proceeds, if the claim be made within eight months and could not be made ſooner after the ſale, which is to be public: provided nevertheleſs, that if the ſaid merchandizes be contraband, it ſhall not be in any wiſe lawful to carry them afterwards to a port belonging to the enemy.</p>
               <p n="15">Art, 15. And that more effectual care may be taken for the ſecurity of the two contracting parties, that they ſuffer no prejudice by the men of war of the other party, or by privateers; all captains and commanders of ſhips of his Swediſh majeſty, and of the United States, and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="unknown:029760_0050_0FE25956C7D53020"/>
ſubjects ſhall be forbidden to do any injury or da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to thoſe of the other party; and if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the contrary, having been found guilty on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination by their proper judges, they ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bound to make ſatisfaction for all damages, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the intereſt thereof, and make them good, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pain and obligation of their perſons and goods.</p>
               <p n="16">Art. 16. For this cauſe, every individual who is deſirous of fitting out a privateer, ſhall before he receives letters patent or ſpecial commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, be obliged to give bond with ſufficient ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties before a competent judge, for a ſufficient ſum to anſwer all damages and wrongs which the owner of the privateer, his officers or others in his employ may commit during the cruize contrary to the tenor of this treaty, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the edicts publiſhed by either party, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the King of Sweden, or by the United States, in virtue of this ſame treaty, and alſo under the penalty of having the ſaid letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and ſpecial commiſſion revoked and made void.</p>
               <p n="17">Art. 17. One of the contracting parties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at war, and the other remaining neuter, if it ſhould happen that a merchant ſhip of the neutral power be taken by the enemy of the other party and be afterwards retaken by a ſhip of war or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateer of the power at war, alſo ſhips and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes of what nature ſoever they may be when recovered from a pirate or ſea rover, ſhall be brought into a port of one of the two powers, and ſhall be committed to the cuſtody of the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the ſaid port, that they may be reſtored entire to the true proprietor as ſoon as he ſhall have produced full proof of the property. Merchants, maſters and owners of ſhips, ſeamen, people of all ſorts, ſhips and veſſels, and in general, all
<pb n="52" facs="unknown:029760_0051_0FE2595857C651A8"/>
merchandizes and effects of one of the allies or their ſubjects, ſhall not be ſubject to any embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, nor detained in any of the countries, territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, iſlands, cities, towns, ports, rivers or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains whatever of the other ally, on account of any military expedition, or any public or private purpoſe whatever, by ſeizure, by force, or by any ſuch manner; much leſs ſhall it be lawful for the ſubjects of one of the parties to ſeize or take any thing by force from the ſubjects of the other party, without the conſent of the owner. This, however, is not to be underſtood to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend ſeizures, detenſions and arreſts, made by order and by the authority of juſtice, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ordinary courſe for debts or faults of the ſubject, for which proceſs ſhall be had in the way of right according to the forms of juſtice.</p>
               <p n="18">Art. 18. If it ſhould happen that the two contracting parties ſhould be engaged in a war at the ſame time, with a common enemy, the following points ſhall be obſerved on both ſides.</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. If the ſhips of one of the two nations retaken by the privateers of the other, have not been in the power of the enemy more than twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-four hours, they ſhall be reſtored to the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal owner on payment of one third of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the ſhip and cargo. If on the contrary, the veſſel retaken has been more than twenty four hours in the power of the enemy, it ſhall belong wholly to him who has retaken it.</p>
               <p n="2">2d. In caſe during the interval of twenty-four hours a veſſel be retaken by a man of war, of either of the two parties, it ſhall be reſtored to the original owner on payment of a thirtieth part of the value of the veſſel and cargo, and a tenth part of it has been retaken after the twenty four hours, which ſums ſhall be diſtributed as a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification
<pb n="53" facs="unknown:029760_0052_0FE25965407566B0"/>
among the crew of the men of war, that ſhall have made the recapture.</p>
               <p n="3">3d. The prizes made in manner above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, ſhall be reſtored to the owners after proof made of the property, upon giving ſecurity for the part coming to him who has recovered the veſſel from the hands of the enemy.</p>
               <p n="4">4th. The men of war and privateers of the two nations ſhall reciprocally be admitted with their prizes into each others ports; but the prizes ſhall not be unloaded or ſold there until the legality of a prize made by Swediſh ſhips ſhall have been determined according to the laws and regulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons eſtabliſhed in Sweden, as alſo that of the prizes made by American veſſels, ſhall have been determined according to the laws and regulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons eſtabliſhed by the United States of America.</p>
               <p n="5">5th. Moreover the King of Sweden, and the United States of America, ſhall be at liberty to make ſuch regulations as they ſhall judge neceſſary reſpecting the conduct which their men of war and privateers reſpectively ſhall be bound to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve with regard to veſſels which they ſhall take and carry into the ports of the two powers.</p>
               <p n="19">Art. 19. The ſhips of war of his Swediſh Majeſty and thoſe of the United States, and alſo thoſe which their ſubjects ſhall have armed for war may with all freedom conduct the prizes which they ſhall have made from their enemies into the ports which are open in time of war to other friendly nations, and the ſaid prizes upon enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid ports, ſhall not be ſubject to arreſt or ſeizure, nor ſhall the officers of the place take cognizance of the validity of the ſaid prizes which may depart and be conducted freely and with all liberty to the places pointed out in their commiſſions, which the captains of the ſaid veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels ſhall be obliged to ſhow.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <pb n="54" facs="unknown:029760_0053_0FE2596719471D78"/>Art. 20. In caſe any veſſel belonging to either of the two ſtates, or their ſubjects, ſhall be ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſhipwrecked, or ſuffer any other damage on the coaſt or under the dominion of either of the parties all aid and aſſiſtance ſhall be given to the perſons ſhipwrecked, or who may be in danger thereof, and paſſports ſhall be granted to them to ſecure their return to their own country. The ſhips and merchandizes wrecked, or their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, if the effects have been ſold, being clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in a year and a day by the owners or their attorney, ſhall be reſtored, on their paying the coſts of ſalvage, conformable to the laws and cuſtoms of the two nations.</p>
               <p n="21">Art. 21. When the ſubjects and inhabitants of the two parties, with their veſſels, whether they be public and equipped for war, or private, employed in commerce, ſhall be forced by tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, by purſuit of privateers and of enemies, or by any other urgent neceſſity, to retire and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any of the rivers, bays, roads or ports of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the two parties, they ſhall be received and treated with all humanity and politeneſs, and they ſhall enjoy all friendſhip, protection, and aſſiſtance, and they ſhall be at liberty to ſupply themſelves with refreſhments, proviſions, and every thing neceſſity for their ſuſtenance, for the repair of their veſſels, and for continuing their voyage; provided always, that they pay a reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and that they ſhall not in any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner be detained or hindred from ſailing out of the ſaid ports or roads, but they may retire and depart when and as they pleaſe without any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="22">Art. 22. In order to favour commerce on both ſides as much as poſſible, it is agreed, that in caſe a war ſhould break out between the ſaid two
<pb n="55" facs="unknown:029760_0054_0FE25968A89D6278"/>
nations, which God forbid, the term of nine months, after the declaration of war, ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to the merchants and ſubjects reſpectively on one ſide and the other, in order that they may withdraw with their effects and moveables, which they ſhall be at liberty to carry off or to ſell where they pleaſe, without the leaſt obſtacle; nor ſhall any ſeize their effects and much leſe their perſons during the ſaid nine months, but on the contrary; paſſports which ſhall be valid for a time neceſſary for their return, ſhall be given them for their veſſels and the effects which they ſhall be willing to carry with them. And if any thing is taken from them, or if any injury is done to them by one of the parties, their people and ſubjects during the term above preſcribed, full and entire ſatisfaction ſhall be made to them on that account. The abovementioned paſſports ſhall alſo ſerve as a ſafe conduct againſt all inſults or prizes which privateers may attempt againſt their perſons and effects.</p>
               <p n="23">Art. 23. No ſubject of the king of Sweden ſhall take a commiſſion or letters of marque, for arming any veſſel to act as a privateer againſt the United States of America, or any of them, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſubjects, people or inhabitants of the ſaid United States, or any of them, or againſt the property of the inhabitants of the ſaid ſtates, from any prince or State whatever with whom the ſaid United States ſhall be at war<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nor ſhall any citizen, ſubject or inhabitant of the ſaid Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States, or any of them, apply for or take any commiſſion on letters of marque, for arming any veſſel to cruize againſt the ſubjects of his Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Majeſty, or any of them, or their property, from any Prince or State whatever with whom his ſaid Majeſty ſhall be at war. And if any
<pb n="56" facs="unknown:029760_0055_0FE2596A3629EBC8"/>
perſon of either nation ſhall take ſuch commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions or letters of marque, he ſhall be puniſhed as a pirate.</p>
               <p n="24">Art. 24. The veſſels of the ſubjects of either of the parties coming upon any of the coaſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the other, but not willing to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to port, or being entered into port, and not will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to unload their cargoes, or to break bulk, ſhall not be obliged to do it, but on the contrary ſhall enjoy all the franchiſes and exemptions which are granted by the rules ſubſiſting with reſpect to that object.</p>
               <p n="25">Art. 25. When a veſſel belonging to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and inhabitants of either of the parties, ſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the high ſea, ſhall be met by a ſhip of war or privateer of the other, the ſaid ſhip of war or privateer, to avoid all diſorder, ſhall remain out of cannon ſhot, but may always ſend their boat to the merchant ſhip, and cauſe two or three men to go on board of her, to whom the maſter or commander of the ſaid veſſel ſhall exhibit his paſſport, ſtating the property of the veſſel, and when the ſaid veſſel ſhall have exhibited her paſſport ſhe ſhall be at liberty to continue her voyage, and it ſhall not be lawful to moleſt or ſearch her in any manner, or to give her chaſe or force her to quit her intended courſe.</p>
               <p n="26">Art. 26. The two contracting parties grant mutually the liberty of having each in the ports of the other conſuls, vice-conſuls, agents and commiſſaries, whoſe functions ſhall be regulated by a particular agreement.</p>
               <p n="27">Art. 27. The preſent treaty ſhall be ratified on both ſides and the ratifications ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed in the ſpace of eight months, or ſooner if poſſible counting from the day of the ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="unknown:029760_0056_0FE25974EAFD5B18"/>In faith whereof, the <hi>reſpective</hi> Plenipotenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries have ſigned the above articles, and have thereunto affixed their ſeals.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>DONE at Paris, <date>the 3d day of April, in the year of our Lord, One Thouſand Seven Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Eighty-Three.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>(Signed) G. PHILIP, Compte de CREUTZ. L. S.</item>
                        <item>B. FRANKLIN. L. S.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>SEPARATE ARTICLE.</head>
               <p>THE King of Sweden and the United States of North-America, agree that the preſent treaty ſhall have its full effect for the ſpace of fifteen years, counting from the day o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ratification, and the two contracting parties reſerve to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the liberty of renewing it at the end of that term.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>DONE at Paris, <date>the third of April, in the year of our Lord, One Thouſand Seven Hundred and Eighty-Three.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>(Signed) G. PHILIP Compte de CREUTZ. L. S.</item>
                        <item>B. FRANKLIN. L. S.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>SEPARATE ARTICLES.</head>
               <p n="1">Art. 1. His Swediſh Majeſty ſhall uſe all the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ns in his power to protect and defend the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and effects belonging to the citizens or inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the United States of North-America, and every of them which ſhall be in the ports, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, roads, or on the ſeas near the countries, iſlands, cities and towns of his ſaid Majeſty, and ſhall uſe his utmoſt endeavors to recover and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore to the right owners, all ſuch veſſels and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, which ſhall have been taken from them within his juriſdiction.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="58" facs="unknown:029760_0057_0FE259779C41BFD8"/>Art. 2. In like manner, the United States of North America ſhall protect and defend the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els and effects belonging to the ſubjects of his Swediſh Majeſty, which ſhall be in the ports, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens or roads, or on the ſeas near to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, iſlands, cities and towns of the ſaid ſtates, and ſhall uſe their utmoſt efforts to recover and reſtore to the right owners all ſuch veſſels and effects which ſhall be taken from them, within their juriſdiction.</p>
               <p n="3">Art. 3. If in any future war at ſea, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owers reſolve to remain neuter, and as ſuch, to obſerve the ſtricteſt neutrality, then it is agreed, that if the merchant ſhips of either party, ſhould happen to be in a part of the ſea where the ſhips of war of the ſame nation are not ſtationed, or if they are met on the high ſea, without being able to have recourſe to their own convoys, in that caſe the commander of the ſhips of war of the other party, if required, ſhall in good faith and ſincerity give them all neceſſary aſſiſtance, and in ſuch caſe, the ſhips of war and frigates of either of the powers, ſhall protect and ſupport the merchant ſhips of the other, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided nevertheleſs, that the ſhips claiming aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance are not engaged in any illicit commerce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the principles of the neutrality.</p>
               <p n="4">Art. 4. It is agreed and concluded that all merchants, captains of merchant ſhips, or other ſubjects of his Swediſh Majeſty, ſhall have full liberty in all places under the dominion or juriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the United States of America, to manage their own affairs and to employ in the management of them whomſoever they pleaſe; and they ſhall not be obliged to make uſe of any interpreter or broker, nor to pay them any reward unleſs they make uſe of them. Moreover, the maſters of
<pb n="59" facs="unknown:029760_0058_0FE2597929434F08"/>
ſhips ſhall not be obliged in loading or unload<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their veſſels, to employ labourers appointed by public authority for that purpoſe; but they ſhall be at full liberty, themſelves to load or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>load their veſſels, or to employ in loading or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loading them whomſoever they think proper, without paying reward under the tit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of ſalary to any other perſon whatever; and they ſhall not be obliged to turn over any kind of merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes to other veſſels, nor to receive them on board their own, nor to wait for their loading longer than they pleaſe, and all and every of the citizens, and people of the United States of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica, ſhall reciprocall, have and enjoy the ſame privileges and liberties in all places under the juriſdiction of the ſaid realm.</p>
               <p n="5">Art. 5. It is agreed that when merchandizes ſhall have been put on board the ſhips or veſſels of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the contracting parties, they ſhall not be ſubjected to any examination; but all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination and ſearch muſt be before lading, and the prohibited merchandizes muſt be ſtopped on the ſpot before they are embarked, unleſs there is full evidence or proof of fraudulent practice on the part of the owner of the ſhip or of him who has the command of her. In which caſe only he ſhall be reſponſible and ſubject to the laws of the country in which he may be. In all other caſes neither the ſubjects of either of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting parties, who ſhall be with their veſſels in the ports of the other, nor their merchandizes ſhall be ſeized or moleſted on account of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band goods, which they ſhall have wanted to take on board, nor ſhall any kind of embargo be laid on their ſhips, ſubjects or citizens of the ſtate whoſe merchandizes are declared contraband, or the exportation of which is forbidden, thoſe only
<pb n="60" facs="unknown:029760_0059_0FE2597AF45D1338"/>
who ſhall have ſold or intended to ſell or alienate ſuch merchandizes, being liable to puniſhment for ſuch contravention.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Done at Paris, <date>the third day of April, in the year of our Lord, one thouſand ſeven hundred and eighty-three.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>(Signed) G. PHILIP Compte de CREUTZ, L. S.</item>
                        <item>B. FRANKLIN, L. S.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <p>NOW therefore to the end that the ſaid treaty may with all good faith be performed and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on the part of theſe ſtates, all the citizens and inhabitants thereof, and more eſpecially all officers and others in the ſervice of the United States, are hereby enjoined and required to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern themſelves ſtrictly in all things according to the ſtipulations above recited.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Done in Congreſs at Princeton, <date>in the year of our Lord, one thouſand ſeven hundred and eighty-three, and of our Sovereignty and Independence the eighth.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>ELIAS BOUDINOT, Preſident.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Charles Thomſon,</hi> Secretary.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="treaty">
            <pb facs="unknown:029760_0060_0FE25984D21B8B38"/>
            <head>Definitive Treaty of PEACE between America and Great Britain.</head>
            <head type="sub">IN the Name of the Moſt Holy and Undivided Trinity.</head>
            <p>IT Having pleaſed the Divine Providence to diſpoſe the hearts of the Moſt Serene and Moſt Potent Prince George the Third, by the Grace of God, King of Great Britain, France, and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, Duke of Brunſwick and Lunenbourgh, Arch Treaſurer and Prince Elector of the Holy Roman Empire, &amp;c. and of the United States of America, to forget all miſunderſtandings and differences that have unhappily interrupted the good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and friendſhip which they mutually wiſh to reſtore, and to eſtabliſh ſuch a beneficial and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory intercourſe between the two countries, upon the ground of reciprocal advantages and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al convenience, as may promote and ſecure to both perpetual peace and harmony: and having for this deſirable and already laid the foundation of peace and reconciliation, by the Proviſional Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles ſigned at Paris on the 30th November, 1782, by the Commiſſioners empowered on each part, which articles were agreed to be inſerted in, and to conſtitute the Treaty of Peace propoſed to be concluded between the Crown of Great Britain and the ſaid United States, but which Treaty was not to be concluded until the terms of peace ſhould be agreed upon between Great Britain and France, and his Britannic Majeſty ſhould be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to conclude ſuch treaty accordingly; and the treaty between Great Britain and France having ſince been concluded, his Britannic Majeſty and the United States of America, in order to carry into full effect the Proviſional Articles above mentioned according to the tenure thereof, have
<pb n="62" facs="unknown:029760_0061_0FE25986619E8588"/>
conſtituted and appointed, that is to ſay, his Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannic Majeſty on his part, David Hartly, <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Member of the Parliament of Great Britain, and the ſaid United States on their part, John Adams <abbr>Eſq</abbr> late a Commiſſioner of the United States of America at the Court of Verſailles, late Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate in Congreſs from the ſtate of Maſſachuſetts, and Chief Juſtice of the ſaid ſtate, and Miniſter Plenipotentiary of the ſaid United States, to their High Mightineſſes the States-General of the United Netherlands; Benjamin Franklin, <abbr>Eſq</abbr> late derogate in Congreſs from the ſtate of Pennſylvania, Preſident of the convention of the ſaid ſtate, and Miniſter Plenipotentiary from the United States of America, at the Court of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailles; and John Jay, <abbr>Eſq</abbr> late Preſident of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, chief juſtice of the ſtate of New-York, and Miniſter Plenipotentiary from the ſaid United States at the Court of Madrid, to be the Plenipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiaries for the concluding and ſigning the preſent Definitive Treaty: who after having reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procally communicated their reſpective full pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, have agreed upon and confirmed the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing articles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. His Britannic Majeſty acknowledges the ſaid United States, viz. New Hampſhire, Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſachuſetts Bay, Rhode-Iſland and Providence Plantations, Connecticut, New-Jerſey, Pennſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania, Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, North-Carolina, South-Carolina, and Georgia, to be Free, Sovereign and independent States; that he treats with them as ſuch, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or himſelf, his heirs and ſucceſſors, relin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uiſhes all claims to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, property, and territori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l rights of the ſame, and every part thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">Art. 2. And that all diſputes which might ariſe in future, on the ſubject of the boundaries
<pb n="63" facs="unknown:029760_0062_0FE25987EED833E8"/>
of the ſaid United States, may be prevented, it is hereby agreed, and declared, that the following are and ſhall be their boundaries, viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> From the north-weſt angle of Nova-Scotia, viz. that angle which is formed by a line drawn due north from the ſource of St. Croix river to the Highlands, along the ſaid Highlands, which divide thoſe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that empty themſelves into the riv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> St. Lawrence, from thoſe which fall into the Atlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic ocean, to the north-weſtermoſt head of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necticut river: thence down along the middle of that river to the forty-fifth degree of north alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; from thence by a line due weſt on ſaid la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, until it ſtrikes the river <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ois or Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raqui; thence along the middle of the ſaid river into lake Ontario; through the middle of the ſaid lake, until it ſtrikes the communication by water between that lake and lake Erie; thence along the middle of ſaid communication into lake Erie, through the middle of ſaid lake, until it arrives at the water communication between that lake and lake Hur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, thence through the middle of ſaid lake to the water communication between that lake and lake Superior; thence through lake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uper or northward of the Iſles Royal and Philippea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to the long lake; thence through the middle of ſaid long lake and the water communication between it and the lake of the Woods, to the ſaid lake of the Woods; thence through the ſaid lake to the moſt north weſtern point thereof, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om thence on a due weſt courſe to the river Miſſiſſippi; thence by a line to be drawn along the middle of the ſaid River Miſſiſſippi until it ſhall interſect the northernmoſt part of the thirty-firſt degree of north latitude. South by a line to be drawn due eaſt from the determination of the line laſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the latitude of thirty-one degrees north
<pb n="64" facs="unknown:029760_0063_0FE2598983C44390"/>
of the Equator, to the middle of the river A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palachicola or Catahouche; thence along the middle thereof to its junction with the ſaid river; thence ſtrait to the head of St. Mary's river;—and thence down along the middle of St. Mary's river to the Atlantic ocean. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll by a line to be drawn along the middle of the river St. Croix from its mouth in the Bay of Fundy to its ſource and from its ſource directly north to the aforeſaid Highlands, which divide the rivers that fall into the Atlantic ocean from thoſe which fall into the river St. Lawrence, comprehending all iſlands within twenty leagues of any part of the ſhores of the United States, and lying between lines to be drawn due eaſt from the points where the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid boundaries between Nova-Scotia on the one part, and Eaſt Florida on the other, ſhall reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively touch the Bay of Fundy and the Atlantic ocean, excepting ſuch iſlands as now or are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore have been within the limits of the ſaid province of Nova-Scotia.</p>
            <p n="3">Art. 3. It is agreed that the people of the United States ſhall continue to enjoy unmoleſted the right to take fiſh of every kind on the Grand Bank, and on all the other banks of Newfound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, alſo in the Gulph of St. Lawrence, and all other places in the ſea, where the inhabitants of both countries uſed at any time heretofore to fiſh. And alſo that the inhabitants of the United States ſhall have liberty to take fiſh of every kind on ſuch part of the coaſt of Newfoundland, as Britiſh fiſhermen ſhall uſe (but not to dry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſame on that iſland) and alſo on the coaſts, bays and creeks of all others of his Britannic Majeſty's dominions in America; and that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merican fiſhermen ſhall have liberty to dry and cure fiſh in any of the unſettled bays, harbours
<pb n="65" facs="unknown:029760_0064_0FE259949A5662C8"/>
and creeks of Nova-Scotia, Magdalen Iſlands and Labrador ſo long as the ſame ſhall remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettled; but ſo ſoon as the ſame or either of them ſhall be ſettled, it ſhall not be lawful for the ſaid fiſhermen to dry o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cure fiſh at ſuch ſettlement, without a previous agreement for that purpoſe, wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the inhabitants, proprietors or poſſeſſors of the ground.</p>
            <p n="4">Art. 4. It is agreed that the creditors on either ſide ſhall meet with no lawful impediment to the recovery of the full value in ſterling money, of all bona fide debts heretofore contracted.</p>
            <p n="5">Art. 5. It is agreed that Congreſs ſhall ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly recommend it to the legiſlatures of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective ſtates, to provide for the reſtitution of all eſtates rights and properties which have been confiſcated, belonging to the real Britiſh ſubjects—and alſo of the eſtates, rights and properties of perſons reſident in diſtricts in the poſſeſſion of his majeſty's arms, and who have not borne arms againſt the United States; and that perſons of any other deſcription ſhall have free liberty to go to any part or parts of the Thirteen United States, and therein to remain twelve months un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moleſted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their endeavors to obtain the reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch of their eſtates, rights and properties, as may have been confiſcated; and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs ſhall earneſtly recommend to the ſeveral ſtates, a reconſideration and reviſion of all act or laws regarding the premiſes, ſo as to render the ſaid laws or acts perfectly conſiſtent, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with juſtice and equity, but with that ſpirit of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ciliation, which on the return of the bleſſings of peace, ſhould univerſally prevail: And that Congreſs ſhall earneſtly recommend to the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtates, that the eſtates, rights and properties to ſuch laſt mentioned perſons ſhall be reſtored to
<pb n="66" facs="unknown:029760_0065_0FE2599697A5DD10"/>
them, they refunding to any perſons, who may be now in poſſeſſion, the bona fide price (where any has been given) which ſuch perſons may have paid on purchaſing any of the ſaid lands, rights, or properties ſince the confiſcation.</p>
            <p>And it is agreed that all perſons who have any intereſt in confiſcated lands, eiher by debts, marriage ſettlements, or otherwiſe, ſhall meet with no lawful impediment in the proſecution of their juſt rights.</p>
            <p n="6">Art. 6. That there ſhall be no future confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made, nor any proſecutions commenced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any perſon or perſons for, or by reaſon of the part which he or they may have taken in the preſent war; and that no perſon ſhall, on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, ſuffer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> future loſs or damage, either in his perſon, liberty or property; and that thoſe who may be in confinement on ſuch char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, at the time of the ratification of the Treaty in America, ſhall be immediately ſet at liberty, and the proſecutions ſo commenced be diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued.</p>
            <p n="7">Art. 7. There ſhall be a firm and perpetual peace between his Britannic Majeſty and the ſaid ſtates, and between the ſubjects of the one and the citizens of the other; wherefore all hoſtilities both by ſea and land ſhall from henceforth ceaſe; all priſoners on both ſides ſhall be ſet at liberty; and his Britannic majeſty ſhall, with all conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient ſpeed, and without cauſing any deſtruction or carrying away any negroes or other property of the American inhabitants, withdraw all his armies, and fleets from the ſaid United States, and from every poſt, place and harbour within the ſame, leaving in all fortifications the Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can artillery that may be therein, and ſhall alſo order and cauſe all archives, records, deeds, and
<pb n="67" facs="unknown:029760_0066_0FE2599823BBC420"/>
papers belonging to any of the ſaid ſtates, or their citizens, which in the courſe of the war may have fallen into the hands of his officers, to be forewith reſtored, and delivered to the proper ſtate and perſons to whom they belong.</p>
            <p n="8">Art. 8. The navigation of the river Miſſiſſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi, from its ſource to the ocean, ſhall forever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main free and open to the ſubjects of Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and the citizens of the United States.</p>
            <p n="9">Art. 9. In caſe that it ſhould happen that any place or territory belonging to Great Britain, or to the United States ſhould have been conquered by the arms of either from the other, before the arrival of the ſaid Proviſional articles in America, it is agreed that the ſame ſhall be reſtored with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difficulty, and without requiring any compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</p>
            <p n="10">Art. 10. The ſolemn ratifications of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent treaty, expedited in good and due form, ſhall be exchanged between the contracting parties in the ſpace of ſix months, or ſooner if poſſible, to be computed from the day of the ſignature of the preſent treaty. In witneſs whereof we the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, their Miniſters Plenipotentiary, have in their name, and in virtue of our full powers, ſigned with our hands the preſent Definitive trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and cauſed the ſeals of our arms to be affixed thereto.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Done at Paris,</hi> 
                  <date>this <hi>3d day of September in the year of our Lord one thouſand ſeven hundred and eighty-three.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>(L. S.) JOHN ADAMS.</item>
                     <item>(L. S.) DAVID HARTLY.</item>
                     <item>(L. S.) B. FRANKLIN.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treaty">
            <pb facs="unknown:029760_0067_0FE25999AFAA50F8"/>
            <head>TREATY <hi>of</hi> AMITY COMMERCE <hi>and</hi> NAVIGA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, <hi>between his Britannic Majeſty and the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States of America.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>By their Preſident, with the advice and conſent of their Senate.</p>
            <p>HIS Britannic Majeſty and the United States of America, being deſirous by a Treaty of Amity, Commerce and Navigation, to terminate their differences in ſuch a manner, as without refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the merits of their reſpective complaints and pretenſions, may be the beſt calculated to produce mutual ſatisfaction and good underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: And alſo to regulate the Commerce and Navigation between their reſpective countries, territories, and people, in ſuch a manner as to render the ſame reciprocally beneficial and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory: they have, reſpectively, named their Plenipotentiaries, and given them full powers to treat of, and conclude the ſaid Treaty, that is to ſay, his Britannic Majeſty has named for his Plenipotentiary, the Right Hon. Wm. Wynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Baron Grenville of Wotton, one of his Majeſty's Privy Council, and his Majeſty's Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs; and the Preſident of the ſaid United States, by and with the advice and conſent of the Senate thereof, hath appointed for their Plenipotentiary, the Hon. John Jay, Chief Juſtice of the ſaid United States, and their Envoy Extraordinary his Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jeſty, who have agreed on, and concluded the following</p>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>ARTICLES:</head>
               <p n="1">Art 1. There ſhall be a firm inviolable and univerſal Peace, and a true and ſincere friendſhip between his Britannic Majeſty, his heirs and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and the United States of America; and between their reſpective countries, territories, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, towns and people of every degree, without exception of perſons or places.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="69" facs="unknown:029760_0068_0FE259A36A2E5318"/>Art. 2. His Majeſty will withdraw all his troops and garriſons from all poſts and places within the boundary lines aſſigned by the treaty of peace to the United States. This evacuation ſhall take place on or before the firſt day of June, 1796, and all the proper meaſures ſhall in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terval be taken by concert between the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the United States, and his majeſty's go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor General in America, for ſettling the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious arrangements which may be neceſſary reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the delivery of the ſaid poſts: The Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States in the mean time at their diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ton ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending their ſettlements to any part within the ſaid boundary line, except within the precincts or juriſdiction of any of the ſaid poſts. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and traders within the precincts or juriſdiction of the ſaid poſts, ſhall continue to enjoy, unmoleſted, all their property of every kind, and ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected therein. They ſhall be at full liberty to remain there, or to remove with all or any part of their effects; and it ſhall alſo be free to them to ſell their lands, houſes, or effects, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retain the property thereof, at their diſcretion; ſuch of them as ſhall continue to reſide within the ſaid boundary lines ſhall not be compelled to become citizens of the United States, or to take any oath of allegiance to the government thereof, but they ſhall be at full liberty ſo to do, if they think proper, and they ſhall make and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their election within one year after the evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aforeſaid. And all perſons who ſhall continue there after the expiration of the ſaid year, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having declared their intention of remaining ſubjects of his Britannic Majeſty, ſhall be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as having elected to become citizens of the United States.</p>
               <p n="3">Art. 3. It is agreed that it ſhall at all time be
<pb n="70" facs="unknown:029760_0069_0FE259A4F7F8FEA8"/>
free to his Majeſty's ſubjects, and to the citizens of the United States, and alſo to the Indians dwelling on either ſide of the ſaid boundary line, freely to paſs and repaſs by land or inland navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, into the reſpective territories and countries of the two parties on the continent of America [the country within the limits of the Hudſon's Bay Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany only excepted] and to navigate all the Lakes, Rivers, and Waters thereof, and freely to carry on trade and commerce with each other. But it is underſtood, that this Article does not extend to the admiſſion of veſſels of the United States into the ſea ports, harbours, bays or Creeks of his Majeſty's ſaid territories; nor into ſuch parts of the rivers in his Majeſty's ſaid territories as are between the mouth thereof, and the higheſt port of entry from the ſea, except in ſmall veſſels trad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bona fide between Montreal and Quebec, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch regulations as ſhall be eſtabliſhed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the poſſibility of any frauds in this reſpect. Nor to the admiſſion of Britiſh veſſel from the ſea into the rivers of the United States, beyond the higheſt ports of entry for foreign veſſels from the ſea. The river Miſſiſſippi ſhall, however, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the treaty of peace, be entirely open to both parties; and it is further agreed, that all the ports and places on its eaſtern ſide, to whichſoever of the parties belonging, may freely be reſorted to, and uſed by both parties, in as ample a manner is any of the Atlantic ports or places of the United States, or any of the ports or places of his Majeſty in Great-Britain.</p>
               <p>All goods and merchandizes whoſe importation into his Majeſty's ſaid territories in America, ſhall not be entirely prohibited, may freely, for the purpoſes of commerce, be carried into the ſame in the manner aforeſaid by the citizens of the
<pb n="71" facs="unknown:029760_0070_0FE259A6896B77F0"/>
United States, and ſuch goods and merchandize ſhall be ſubject to no higher or other duties than would be payable by his Majeſty's ſubjects on the importation of the ſame from Europe into the ſaid territories. And in like manner, all goods and merchandizes whoſe importation into the United States ſhall not be wholly prohibited, may freely, for the purpoſes of commerce, be carried into the ſame, in the manner aforeſaid, by his Majeſty's ſubjects, and ſuch goods and merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize ſhall be ſubject to no higher or other duties than would be payable by the citizens of the United States on the importation of the ſame, in American veſſels, into the Atlantic ports of the ſaid States. And all goods not prohibited, to be exported from the ſaid territories, reſpectively, may in like manner be carried out of the ſame by the two parties reſpectively, paying duty as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <p>No duty of entry ſhall ever be levied by either party on peltries brought by land, or inland na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation into the ſaid territories reſpectively, nor ſhall the Indians paſſing or re-paſſing with their own proper goods and effects of whatever. But goods in bales, or other large packages unuſual among Indians, ſhall not be conſidered as goods belonging bona fide to Indians.</p>
               <p>No higher or other tolls or rates of ferriage than what are or ſhall be payable by natives, ſhall be demanded on either ſide; and no duties ſhall be payable on any goods which ſhall merely be carried over any of the portages or carrying places on either ſide, for the purpoſe of being immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately re-imbarked and carried to ſome other place or places. But as by this ſtipulation it is only meant to ſecure to each party a free paſſage acroſs the portages on both ſides, it is agreed, that this exemption from duty ſhall extend only to ſuch goods
<pb n="72" facs="unknown:029760_0071_0FE259A81664D190"/>
as are carried in the uſual and direct road acroſs the portage, and are not attempted to be in any manner ſold or exchanged during their paſſage acroſs the ſame, and proper regulations eſtabliſhed to prevent the poſſibility of any frauds in this reſpect.</p>
               <p>As this article is intended to render in a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree the local advantages of each party common to both, and thereby to promote a diſpoſition favora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to friendſhip and good neighborhood, it is agreed, that the reſpective governments will mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally promote this amicable intercourſe, by cauſing ſpeedy and impartial juſtice to be done, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary protection to be extended to all who may be concerned therein.</p>
               <p n="4">Art. 4. Whereas it is uncertain whether the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Miſſiſſippi extends ſo far to the Northward as to be interſected by a line to be drawn due Weſt from the Lake of the Woods in the manner mentioned in the Treaty of Peace between his Majeſty and the United States, it is agreed, that meaſures ſhall be taken in concert with his Majeſty's government in America, and the government of the United States, for making a joint ſurvey of the ſaid river from one degree of latitude below the Falls of St. Anthony to the principal ſource or ſources of the ſaid river, and alſo of the parts adjacent thereto; and that if on the reſult of ſuch ſurvey, it ſhould appear that the ſaid river would not be interſected by ſuch a line as is above mentioned, the two parties will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon proceed by amicable negociation to regulate the boundary line in that quarter, as well as all other points to be adjuſted between the ſaid parties, according to juſtice and mutual convenience, and in conformity to the intent of the ſaid treaty.</p>
               <p n="5">Art. 5. Whereas doubts have ariſen what river was truly intended under the name of the river St. Croix, mentioned in the ſaid treaty of Peace, and forming a part of the boundary therein deſcribed, tha btueſtion ſhall be referred to the final deciſion of Commiſſioners to be appointed in the following man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, viz.</p>
               <p>One Commiſſioner ſhall be named by his Majeſty
<pb n="73" facs="unknown:029760_0072_0FE259B1A89BB0E0"/>
and one by the Preſident of the United States, by and with the advice and conſent of the Senate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and the ſaid two Commiſſioners ſhall agree on the choice of a third; or if they cannot ſo agree, they ſhall each propoſe one perſon, and, of the two names ſo propoſed, one ſhall be drawn by lot in the preſence of the two original Commiſſioners. And the three Commiſſioners ſo appointed, ſhall be ſworn impartially to examine and decide the ſaid queſtion according to ſuch evidence as ſhall reſpectively be laid before them on the part of the Britiſh govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and of the U. States. The ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall meet at Hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fax, and ſhall have power to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ to ſuch other place or places as they ſhall think fit. They ſhall have power to appoint a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary, and to employ ſuch ſurveyors or other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as they ſhall judge neceſſary. The ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſhall by a declaration under their hands and ſeals decide what river is the river S. Croix in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the treaty. The ſaid declaration ſhall contain a deſcription of the ſaid river, and ſhall particularize the latitude and longitude of its mouth of its ſource. Duplicates of this declaration and of and the ſtatements of their accounts and of the journal of their proceeding ſhall be delivered by them to the agent of his Majeſty and to the agent of the United States, who may be reſpectively appointed and authorized <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>age the buſineſs on behalf of the reſpective governments. And both parties agree to conſider ſuch deciſion as final and concluſive, ſo that the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ereafter be called into queſtion, or made the ſubject of diſpute or difference between them</p>
               <p n="6">Art. 6. Whereas it is alledged by divers Britiſh merchants and others his Majeſty's ſubjects, that debts to a conſiderable amount, which were <hi>bona fide</hi> contracted before the peace, ſtill remaining owing to them by citizens or inhabitants of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States, and that by the operation of various lawful impediments ſince the peace, not only the
<pb n="74" facs="unknown:029760_0073_0FE259B382430678"/>
full recovery of the ſaid debts has been delayed, but alſo the value and ſecurity thereof have been, in ſeveral inſtances impaire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and leſſened, ſo that by the ordinary courſe of judicial proceedings, the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh creditors cannot now obtain, and actually have and receive full and adequate compenſation for the loſſes and damages which they have thereby ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: It is agreed, that in all ſuch caſes where full compenſation for ſuch loſſes and damages cannot for whatever reaſon be actually obtained, had and received by the ſaid creditors in the ordinary courſe of juſtice, the United States will make full and complete compenſation for the ſame to the ſaid creditors; But it is diſtinctly underſtood, that this proviſion is to extend to ſuch loſſes only as have been occaſioned by the lawful impediments aforeſaid, and is not to extend to loſſes occaſioned by ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvency of the debtors, or ohter cauſes as would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>equally have operated to produce ſuch loſs, if the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id impediments had not exiſted, nor to ſuch loſſes or damages as have been occaſioned by the manifeſt delay or negligence, or wilful omiſſion of the clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant.</p>
               <p>For the purpoſe of aſcertaining the amount of any ſuch loſſes and damages, five Commiſſioners ſhall be appointed, and authorized to meet and act in manner following, viz. Two of them ſhall be appointed by his Majeſty, two of them by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of the United States, by and with the advice and conſent of the Senate thereof, and the fifth by the unanimous voice of the other four; and if they ſhould not agree in ſuch choice, then the commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners named by the two parties ſhall reſpectively propoſe one perſon, and of the two names ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, one ſhall be drawn by lot in the preſence of the four original commiſſioners. When the five commiſſioners thus appointed ſhall firſt meet, thy eſhall before they proceed to act reſpectively take the following oath or affirmation, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of each other, which oath or affirmation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo taken, and duty atteſted, ſhall be entered on
<pb n="75" facs="unknown:029760_0074_0FE259B511301DB0"/>
the record of their proceedings, viz. I A. B. one of the Commiſſioners appointed in purſuance of the ſixth article of the Treaty of Amity, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and Navigation between his Britannic Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and the United States of America, do ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſwear, or affirm, that I will honeſtly, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, impartially, and carefully examine, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to juſtice and equity, decide all ſuch complaints as under the ſaid article ſhall be preferred to the ſaid Commiſſioners; and that I will forbear to act as a commiſſioner in any caſe in which I may be perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally intereſted.</p>
               <p>Three of the ſaid commiſſioners ſhall conſtitute a board, and ſhall have power to do any act apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the ſaid commiſſion, provided that one of the commiſſioners named on each ſide, and the fifth commiſſioner ſhall be preſent, and all deciſions ſhall be made by the majority of the voices of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners then preſent; 18 months from the day on which the ſaid commiſſioners ſhall form a board, and be ready to proceed to buſineſs, are aſſigned for receiving complaints, and applications; but they are nevertheleſs authorized in any particular caſes in which it ſhall appear to them to be reaſonable and juſt, to extend the ſaid term of eighteen months for any term not exceeding ſix months, after the expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereof. The ſaid commiſſioners ſhall firſt meet at Philadelphia, but they ſhall have power to adjourn from place to place as they ſhall ſee cauſe.</p>
               <p>The ſaid commiſſioners in examining the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints and applications ſo preferred to them, are empowered and required, in purſuance of the true intent and meaning of this article, to take into their conſideration all claims, whether of principal or intereſt, or balances of principal and intereſt, and to determine the ſame reſpectively according to the merits of the ſeveral caſes, due regard being had to all the circumſtances thereof, and as equity and juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice ſhall appear to them to require. And the ſaid commiſſioners ſhall have power to examine all ſuch perſons as ſhall come before them on oath or affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="76" facs="unknown:029760_0075_0FE259B69FFF44D8"/>
or books, or papers, or copies, or extracts thereof, every ſuch depoſition, book, or paper, or extract be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing duly authenticated, either according to the legal forms now reſpectively exiſting in the two countries, or in ſuch other manner as the ſaid commiſſioners ſhall ſee cauſe to require or allow.</p>
               <p>The award of the ſaid commiſſioners or of any three of them as aforeſaid, ſhall in all caſes be final and concluſive, both as to the juſtice of the claim, and to the amount of the ſum to be paid to the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor or claimant: And the United States undertake to cauſe the ſum ſo awarded to be paid in ſpecie to ſuch creditor or claimant with deduction; and at ſuch time or times, and at ſuch place or places as ſhall be awarded by the ſaid commiſſioners; and on condition or ſuch releaſes or aſſignments to be given by the creditor of claimant, as by the ſaid commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners may be directed: Provided always, that no ſuch payment ſhall be fixed by the ſaid commiſſioners to take place ſooner than twelve months from the day of the exchange of the ratifications of this treaty.</p>
               <p n="7">Art. 7. Whereas complaints have been made by divers merchants and others, citizens of the United States, that during the courſe of the war in which his Majeſty is now engaged, they have ſuſtained conſiderable loſſes and damage, by reaſon of irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar or illegal captures or condemnations of their veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and other property under colour of authority or commiſſions from his Majeſty, and that from various circumſtances belonging to the ſaid caſes, adequate compenſation for the loſſes and damages ſo ſuſtained cannot now be actually obtained, had and received by the ordinary courſe of judicial proceedings: it is agreed, that in all ſuch caſes where adequate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation cannot, for whatever reaſon, be now actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally obtained, had and received by ſaid merchants and others in the ordinary courſe of juſtice, full and complete compenſation for the ſame will be made by the Britiſh government to the ſaid complainants. But it is diſtinctly underſtood that this proviſion is
<pb n="77" facs="unknown:029760_0076_0FE259C0CEDB3518"/>
not to extend to ſuch loſſes or damages as have been occaſioned by the manifeſt delay or negligence, or wllful omiſſion of the claimants.</p>
               <p>That for the purpoſe of aſcertaining the amount of any ſuch loſſes and damages, five commiſſioners ſhall be appointed and authorized to act in London, exactly in the manner directed with reſpect to thoſe mentioned in the preceeding article, and after have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken the ſame oath or affirmation <hi>(mutatis mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandis)</hi> the ſame term of eighteen months is alſo aſſigned for the reception of claims, and they are in like manner authorized to extend the ſame in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular caſes. They ſhall receive teſtimony, books, papers and evidence in the ſame latitude, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the like diſcretion and powers reſpecting that ſubject; and ſhall decide the claims in queſtion ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the merits of the ſeveral caſes, and to juſtice, equity, and the laws of nations. The award of the commiſſioners, or any ſuch three of them as aforeſaid, ſhall, in all caſes be final and concluſive, both as to the juſtice of the claim, and the amount of the ſum to be paid to the claimant; and his Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannic Majeſty undertakes to cauſe the ſame to be paid to ſuch claimant in ſpecie, without any deduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at ſuch place or places, and at ſuch time or times as ſhall be awarded by the ſaid commiſſioners, and on condition of ſuch releaſes or aſſignments to be given by the claimants, as by the ſaid commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners may be directed.</p>
               <p>And whereas certain merchants and others his Majeſty's ſubjects complain that in the courſe of the war they have ſuſtained loſs and damage by reaſon of the capture of the veſſels and merchandize taken within the limits and juriſdiction of the ſtates, and brought into the ports of the ſame, or taken by veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels originally armed in ports of the ſaid ſtates.</p>
               <p>It is agreed that in all ſuch caſes where reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall not have been made agreeably to the tenor of the letter from Mr. Jefferſon to Mr. Hammond, dated at Philadelphia, Sept. 5, 1793, a copy of
<pb n="78" facs="unknown:029760_0077_0FE259C25DF7B508"/>
which is annexed to this treaty; the complaints of the parties ſhall be and hereby are referred to the commiſſioners to be appointed by virtue of this arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, who are hereby authorized and required to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the like manner relative to theſe as to the other caſes committed to them: and the United States undertake to pay to the complainants or claimants in ſpecie, without deduction, the amount of ſuch ſums as ſhall be awarded to them reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the ſaid commiſſioners, and at the times and places which in ſuch awards ſhall be ſpecified; and on conditions of ſuch releaſes or aſſignments to be given by the claimants as in the ſaid award may be directed: And it is further agreed that not only the now exiſting caſes of both deſcriptions but alſo all ſuch as ſhall exiſt at the time of exchanging the ratifications of this treaty, ſhall be conſidered within the proviſions, intent and meaning of this article.</p>
               <p n="8">Art. 8. It is further agreed, that the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners mentioned in the two preceding articles ſhall be reſpectively paid in ſuch manner as ſhall be agreed between the two parties; ſuch agreement being to be ſettled at the time of the exchange of the ratification of this treaty. And all other expences attending the ſaid commiſſions ſhall be defrayed jointly by the two parties, the ſame being previouſly aſcertained and allowed by the majority of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners. And in the caſe of death, ſickneſs or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary abſence, the place of every ſuch commiſſioner reſpectively ſhall be ſupplied in the ſame manner as ſuch commiſſioner was appointed, and the new com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner ſhall take the ſame oath or affirmation and do the ſame duties.</p>
               <p n="9">Art. 9. It is agreed that Britiſh ſubjects who now hold lands in the territories of the United States, and American citizens who now hold lands in the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of his Majeſty ſhall continue to hold them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature and tenure of their reſpective ſtates and titles therein; and may grant, ſell, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe the ſame to whom they pleaſe, in like manner as
<pb n="79" facs="unknown:029760_0078_0FE259C3EA2ABD20"/>
if they were natives; and that neither they nor their heirs or aſſigns ſhall ſo far as may reſpect the ſaid lands and the legal remedies incident thereto, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded as aliens.</p>
               <p n="10">Art. 10. Neither the debts due from individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of the one nation, to individuals of the other, nor ſhares nor monies which they may have have in the public funds, or in the public or private banks ſhall ever in any event of war or national dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences be ſequeſtered or confiſcated, it being unjuſt and impolitic that debts and engagements contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made by individuals having confidence in each other, and in their reſpective governments, ſhould ever be deſtroyed or impaired by national au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority on account of national differences and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents.</p>
               <p n="11">Art. 11. It is agreed between his Majeſty and the United States of America, that there ſhall be a reciprocal and entirely perfect liberty of navigation and commerce between their reſpective people, in the manner, under the limitations and on the conditions ſpecified in the following articles.</p>
               <p n="12">Art. 12. His Majeſty conſents that it ſhall and may be lawful during the time herein after limited for the citizens of the United States to carry to any of his Majeſty's iſlands and ports in the Weſt-Indies from the United States, in their own veſſels, not being above the burthen of ſeventy tons, any goods or merchandizes being of the growth, manufacture or produce of the ſaid ſtates, which it is or may be lawful to carry to the ſaid iſlands or ports from the ſaid ſtates in Britiſh veſſels; and that the ſaid American veſſels ſhall be ſubject there to no other other or higher tonnage duties or charges than ſhall be payable by Britiſh veſſels in the ports of the United States; and that the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes of the ſaid American veſſels ſhall be ſubject there to no other or higher duties or charges than ſhall be payable on the like articles if imported there from the ſaid ſtates in Britiſh veſſels.</p>
               <p>And his Majeſty alſo conſents that it ſhall be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the ſaid American citizens to purcaſe, load
<pb n="80" facs="unknown:029760_0079_0FE259C579D1BE18"/>
and carry away in their ſaid veſſels to the U. States from the ſaid iſlands and ports all ſuch articles being of the growth, manufacture or produce of the ſaid iſlands as may now by law be carried from thence to the ſaid ſtates in Britiſh veſſels and ſubject only to the ſame duties and charges on exportation, to which Britiſh veſſels and their cargoes are or ſhall be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in ſimilar circumſtances.</p>
               <p>Provided always that the ſaid American veſſels do carry and land their cargoes in the United States on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it being expreſsly agreed and declared that dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the continuance of this article, the United States will prohibit and reſtrain the carrying any molaſſes, ſugar, coffee, cocoa or cotton in American veſſels, either from his Majeſty's iſlands or from the United States to any part of the world except the United States, reaſonable ſea ſtores excepted. Provided alſo, that it ſhall and may be lawful, during the ſame pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, for Britiſh veſſels to Import from the ſaid iſlands into the United States, and to export from the United States to the ſaid iſlands, all articles whatever being of the growth, produce or manufacture of the ſaid iſlands, or of the United States reſpectively, which now may, by the laws of the ſaid ſtates, be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and exported. And that the cargoes of the ſaid Britiſh veſſels ſhall be ſubject to no other or higher duties or charges, than ſhall be payable on the ſame articles, if ſo imported or exported in American veſſels.</p>
               <p>It is agreed that this article and every matter and thing therein contained ſhall continue to be in force during the continuance of the war, in which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty is now engaged; and alſo for two years from and after the day of the ſignature of the preliminary or other articles of peace by which the ſame may be terminated.</p>
               <p>And it is further agreed, that at the expiration of the ſaid term, the two contracting parties will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour further to regulate their commerce in this reſpect, according to the ſituation in which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="81" facs="unknown:029760_0080_0FE259CF58E496D0"/>may then find himſelf with reſpect to the Weſt-Indies, and with a view to ſuch arrangements as may beſt conduce to the mutual advantage and exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of commerce. And the ſaid parties will then alſo renew their diſcuſſions, and endeavour to agree, whether in any and what caſes, neutral veſſels ſhall protect enemy's property; and in what caſes provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and other articles, not generally contraband, may become ſuch. But in the mean time their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct towards each other in theſe reſpects, ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated by the articles herein after inſerted on thoſe ſubjects.</p>
               <p n="13">Art. 13. His Majeſty conſents that the veſſels belonging to the citizens of the United States of America, ſhall be admitted and hoſpitably received in all the ſea ports and harbours of the Britiſh ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories in the Eaſt Indies. And that the citizens of the ſaid United States may freely carry on a trade between the ſaid territories and the ſaid United States, in all articles, of which the importation or exportation reſpectively to or from the ſaid territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſhall not entirely be prohibited. Provided only that it ſhall not be lawful for them in any time of war between the Britiſh government and any other power or ſtate whatever, to export from the ſaid territories, without the ſpecial permiſſion of the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh government there, any military ſtores or naval ſtores or rice. The citizens of the United States ſhall pay for their veſſels when admitted into the ſaid ports no other or higher tonnage duty than ſhall be payable on Britiſh veſſels when admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ports of the United States. And they ſhall pay no other or higher duties or charges on the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation or exportation of the cargoes of the ſaid veſſels, than ſhall be payable on the ſame articles when imported or exported in Britiſh veſſels. But it is expreſsly agreed, that the veſſels of the United States ſhall not carry any of the articles exported by them from the ſaid Britiſh territories to any port or place except to ſome port or place in America, where
<pb n="82" facs="unknown:029760_0081_0FE259D0EE27FE88"/>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation touching the premiſes; and alſo to receive in evidence according as they may think moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with equity and juſtice, all written depoſitions, where the ſame ſhall be unladen, and ſuch regulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall be adopted by both parties, as ſhall from time to time be found neceſſary to enforce the due and faithful obſervance of this ſtipulation. It alſo underſtood that the permiſſion granted by this arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle is not to extend to allow the veſſels of the Unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed States to carry on any part of the coaſting trade of the ſaid Britiſh territories; but veſſels going with their original cargoes, or part thereof, from one port of diſcharge to another are not to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as carrying on the coaſting trade. Neither is this article to be conſtrued to allow the citizens of the ſaid ſtates to ſettle or reſide within the ſaid territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or to go into the interior parts thereof, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the permiſſion of the Britiſh government eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed there; and if any trangreſſion ſhould be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted againſt the regulations of the Britiſh go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in this reſpect, the obſervance of the ſame ſhall and may be enforced againſt the citizens of America in the ſame manner as againſt Britiſh ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects or others trangreſſing the ſame rule. And the citizens of the United States whenever they arrive in any port or harbor in the ſaid territories, or if they ſhould be permitted in manner aforeſaid, to go to any other place therein, ſhall always be ſubject to the laws, government and juriſdiction of what nature eſtabliſhed in ſuch harbor, port or place, according as the ſame may be: The citizens of the United States, may alſo touch for refreſhment at the iſland of St. Helena, but ſubject in all reſpects to ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulations as the Britiſh government may from time to time eſtabliſh there.</p>
               <p n="14">Art. 14. There ſhall be between all the dominions of his majeſty in Europe and the territories of the United States a reciprocal and perfect liberty of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and navigation. The people and inhabitants of the two countries reſpectively ſhall have liberty freely and ſecurely and without hindrance and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation
<pb n="83" facs="unknown:029760_0082_0FE259D280409B10"/>to come with their ſhips and cargoes to the lands, countries, cities, ports, places and rivers within the dominions and territories aforeſaid, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the ſame, to reſort there and to remain and reſide there, without any limitation of time: And alſo to hire and poſſeſs houſes and warehouſes for the purpoſes of their commerce, and generally the merchants and traders on each ſide ſhall enjoy the moſt complete protection and ſecurity for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce; but ſubject always as to what reſpects this article to the laws and ſtatutes of the two countries reſpectively.</p>
               <p n="15">Art. 15. It is agreed that no other or higher du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhall be paid by the ſhips or merchandize of the one party in the ports of the other, than ſuch as are paid by the like veſſels or merchandize of all other nations. Nor ſhall any other o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her duty be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in one country on the importation of any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles the growth, produce or manufacture of the other than are or ſhall be payable on the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of the like articles being of the growth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce or manufacture of any other foreign country. Nor ſhall any prohibition be impoſed on the expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or importation of any articles to or from the territories of the two parties reſpectively, which ſhall not equally extend to all other nations.</p>
               <p>But the Britiſh government reſerves to itſelf the right of impoſing on American veſſels entering into the Britiſh ports in Europe a tonnage duty equal to that which ſhall be payable by Britiſh veſſels in the ports of America: And alſo ſuch duty as may be adequate to countervail the difference of duty now payable on the importation of European and Aſiatic goods when imported into the United States in Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh or in American veſſels.</p>
               <p>The two parties agree to treat for the more exact equalization of the duties on the reſpective naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their ſubjects and people in ſuch manner as may be moſt beneficial to the two countries. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ments for this purpoſe ſhall be made at the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with thoſe mentioned at the concluſion of the 12th article of this treaty, and are to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb n="84" facs="unknown:029760_0083_0FE259D40D32E418"/>as a part thereof. In the interval it is agreed, that the United States will not impoſe any new or additional tonnage duties on Britiſh veſſels, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the now ſubſiſting difference between the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties payable on the importation of any article in Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh or in American veſſels.</p>
               <p n="16">Art. 16. It ſhall be free for the two contracting parties, reſpectively to appoint conſuls for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of trade, to reſide in the dominions and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories aforeſaid, and the ſaid conſuls ſhall enjoy thoſe liberties and rights which belong to them by reaſon of their function. But before any conſul ſhall act as ſuch he ſhall be in the uſual forms approved and admitted by the party to whom he is ſent; and it is hereby declared to be lawful and proper, that in caſe of illegal or improper conduct towards the laws or government, a council may either be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to law, if the laws will reach the caſe or be diſmiſſed, or even ſent back, the offended go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment aſſigning to the other their reaſons for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Either of the parties may except from the reſidence of conſuls ſuch particular places as ſuch party ſhall judge proper to be ſo excepted.</p>
               <p n="17">Art. 17. It is agreed, that in all caſes where veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels ſhall be captured or detained on juſt ſuſpicion of having on board enemy's property, or of carrying to the enemy any of the articles which are contraband of war: the ſaid veſſel ſhall be brought to the neareſt or moſt convenient port; and if any property of an enemy ſhould be found on board ſuch veſſel, that part only which belongs to the enemy ſhall be made prize, and the veſſel ſhall be at liberty to proceed with the remainder without any impediment. And it is agreed, that all proper meaſures ſhall be taken to prevent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, in deciding the caſes of ſhips or cargoes ſo brought in for adjudication; and in the payment or recovery of any indemnification adjudged or agreed to be paid to the maſters or owners of ſuch ſhips.</p>
               <p n="18">Art. 18. In order to regulate what is in future
<pb n="85" facs="unknown:029760_0084_0FE259DDF7DE0468"/>to be deemed contraband of war, it is agreed, that under the ſaid denomination ſhall be comprized all arms and implements ſerving for the purpoſes of war, by land or ſea, ſuch as cannon, muſkets, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, petards, bombs, grenados, carcaſſes, ſauciſſes, carriages for cannons, muſket reſts, bandoliers, gun powder, match, ſaltpetre, ball, pikes, ſwords, head pieces, cuiraſſes, halberts, lances, javelines, horſe-furniture, holſters, belts, and generally all other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements of war; as alſo timber for ſhip building, tar, or roſin, copper in ſheets, ſails hemp and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and generally whatever may ſerve directly to the equipment of veſſels, unwrought iron and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir planks only excepted; and all the above articles are hereby declared to be juſt objects of confiſcation, whenever they are attempted to be carried to an enemy.</p>
               <p>And whereas the difficulty of agreeing on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe caſes in which alone proviſions and other arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles not generally contraband may be regarded as ſuch, renders it expedient to provide againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies and miſunderſtandings which might thence ariſe: It is further agreed, that whenever any ſuch articles ſo becoming contraband according to the exiſting laws of nations, ſhall for that reaſon be ſeized, the ſame ſhall not be confiſcated, but the own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof ſhall be ſpeedily and completely indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified; and the captors, or in their default the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment under whoſe authority they act, ſhall pay to the maſters or owners of ſuch veſſel the full value of all articles, with a reaſonable mercantile profit thereon, together with the freight, and alſo the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murrage incident to ſuch detention.</p>
               <p>And whereas it frequently happens, that veſſels ſail for a port or place belonging to an enemy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing that the ſame is either beſieged, block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aded or inveſted; it is agreed, that every veſſel ſo circumſtanced may be turned away from ſuch port or place, but ſhe ſhall not be detained nor her cargo, if not contraband, be confiſcated, unleſs after notice
<pb n="86" facs="unknown:029760_0085_0FE24BE8F27DE740"/>ſhe ſhall again attempt to enter; but ſhe ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to go to any port or place ſhe may think pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: Nor ſhall any veſſel or goods of either party, that may have entered into ſuch port or place, before the ſame was beſieged, blockaded or inveſted by the other, and be found therein after the reduction or ſurrender of ſuch place, be liable to confiſcation, but ſhall be reſtored to the owners or proprietors thereof.</p>
               <p n="19">Art. 19. And that more abundant care be taken for the ſecurity of the reſpective ſubjects and citizens of the contracting parties, and to prevent their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering injuries by the men of war, or privateers of either party, all commanders of ſhips of war and privateers and all others the ſaid ſubjects and citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens ſhall forbear to do any damage to thoſe of the other party, or committing any outrage againſt them, and if they act to the contrary, they ſhall be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſhall alſo be bound in their perſons and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates to make ſatisfaction and reparation for all da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and the intereſt thereof, of whatever nature the ſaid damages may be.</p>
               <p>For this cauſe all commanders of privateers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they receive their commiſſions ſhall hereafter be obliged to give before a competent judge, ſufficient ſecurity by at leaſt two reſponſible ſureties, who have no intereſt in the ſaid privateer, each of whom, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſaid commander, ſhall be jointly and ſeverally bound in the ſum of fifteen hundred pounds ſterling, or if ſuch ſhips be provided with above one hundred and fifty ſeamen or ſoldiers, in the ſum of three thouſand pounds ſterling, to ſatisfy all damages and injuries, which the ſaid privateer or officers or men, or any of them may do or commit during their cruiſe, contrary to the tenor of this treaty, or to the laws and inſtructions for regulating their conduct; and further that in all caſes of aggreſſions the ſaid commiſſions ſhall be revoked and annuled.</p>
               <p>It is alſo agreed, that whenever a judge of a court of admiralty of either of the parties, ſhall pronounce ſentence againſt any veſſel of goods or property be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
<pb n="87" facs="unknown:029760_0086_0FE259E240CA9F18"/>to the ſubjects or citizens of the other par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a formal and duly authenticated copy of all the proceedings in the cauſe, and of the ſaid ſentence ſhall if required be delivered to the commander of the ſaid veſſel, without the ſmalleſt delay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e paying all legal fees and demands for the ſame.</p>
               <p n="20">Art. 20. It is further agreed that both the ſaid contracting parties, ſhall not only refuſe to receive any pirates into any of their ports, havens, or towns, or permit any of their inhabitants to receive, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect, harbour, conceal or aſſiſt them in any manner, but will bring to condign puniſhment all ſuch inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants as ſhall be guilty of ſuch acts or offences.</p>
               <p>And all their ſhips with the goods or merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes taken by them and brought into port of either of the ſaid parties, ſhall be ſeized as far as they can be diſcovered, and ſhall be reſtored to the owners or the factors or agents duly deputed and authorized in writing by them (proper evidence being firſt in the court of admiralty for proving the property) even in caſe ſuch effects ſhould have paſſed into other hands by ſale, if it be proved that the buyers knew or had good reaſon to believe, or ſuſpect that they had been piratically taken.</p>
               <p n="21">Art. 21. It is likewiſe agreed, that the ſubjects and citizens of the two nations, ſhall not do any acts of hoſtility or violence againſt each other, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept commiſſions or inſtructions ſo to act from any foreign prince or ſtate, enemies to the other party; nor ſhall the enemies of one of the parties be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to invite, or endeavour to enliſt in the military ſervice any of the ſubjects or citizens of the other party; and the laws againſt all ſuch offences ſhall be punctually executed. And if any ſubject or ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen of the ſaid parties reſpectively ſhall accept any foreign commiſſion, or letters of marque, for arming any veſſel to act as a privateer againſt the other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it is hereby declared to be lawful for the ſaid party to treat and puniſh the ſaid ſubject or citizen, having ſuch commiſſion or letters of marque, as a pirate.</p>
               <p n="22">
                  <pb n="88" facs="unknown:029760_0087_0FE259E4EC382508"/>Art. 22. It is expreſsly ſtipulated that neither of the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d contracting parties will order or authoriſe any acts of repriſal againſt the other, on compl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> of injuries or damages, until the ſaid party <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> firſt have repreſented to the other, a ſtatement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, verified by competent proof and evidence, and demanding juſtice and ſatisfaction, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me ſhall either have been refuſed or unreaſonably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed.</p>
               <p n="23">Art. 23. The ſhips of war of each of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting parties ſhall, at all times, be hoſpitably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the ports of the other, their officers and crews paying due reſpect to the laws and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the country. The officers ſhall be treated with that reſpect which is due to the commiſſions which they bear; and if any inſult ſhould be offered to them by any of the inhabitants, all offenders in this reſpect ſhall be puniſhed as diſturbers of the peace and amity between the two countries. And his majeſty conſents that in caſe an American veſſel, ſhould by ſtreſs of weather, danger from enemies or other misfortunes be reduced to the neceſſity of ſeeking ſhelter in any of his majeſty's ports, into which ſuch veſſel could not in ordinary caſes claim to be admitted, ſhe ſhall, on manifeſting that neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to the ſatisfaction of the government of the place, be hoſpitably received and permitted to refit and to purchaſe at the market price ſuch neceſſaries, as ſhe may ſtand in need of, conformably to ſuch orders and regulations as the government of the place, having reſpect to circumſtances of each caſe ſhall preſcribe. She ſhall not be allowed to break bulk or unload her cargo unleſs the ſame ſhall be bona fide neceſſary to her being refitted. Nor ſhall be permitted to ſell any part of her cargo, unleſs ſo much only as may be neceſſary to defray her expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and then not without the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>preſs permiſſion of the government of the place. Nor ſhall ſhe be obliged to pay any duties whatever except only on ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles as ſhe may be permitted to ſell for the purpoſe aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="24">Art. 24. It ſhall not be lawful for any foreign
<pb n="89" facs="unknown:029760_0088_0FE259ED5F910248"/>privateers (not being ſubjects or citizens of either of the ſaid parties) who have commiſſions from any other prince or ſtate in enmity with either nation, to arm their ſhips in the ports of either of the ſaid parties, nor ſell what they have taken, nor in any other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to exchange the ſame; nor ſhall they be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to purchaſe more proviſions than ſhall be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for their going to the neareſt port of that prince or ſtate from whom they obtained their commiſſion.</p>
               <p n="25">Art. 25. It ſhall be lawful for the ſhips of war and privateers belonging to the ſaid parties reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, to carry whitherſoever they pleaſe the ſhips and goods taken from their enemies, without being obliged to pay any fee to the Officers of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty, or to any Judges whatever; nor ſhall the ſaid prizes when they arrive at, and enter the ports of the ſaid parties be detained or ſeized, neither ſhall the ſearchers or other officers of thoſe places viſit ſuch prizes (except for the purpoſe of preventing the carrying of any part of the cargo thereof on ſhore in any manner contrary to the eſtabliſhed laws of Revenue, Navigation, or Commerce) nor ſhall ſuch officers take cognizance of the validity of ſuch prizes; but they ſhall be at liberty to hoiſt ſail and depart as ſpeedily as may be, and carry their ſaid prizes to the place mentioned in their commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions or patents, which the commanders of the ſaid ſhips of war or privateers ſhall be obliged to ſhew. No ſhelter or refuge ſhall be given in their ports to ſuch as have made a prize upon the ſubjects or citizens of either of the ſaid parties; but if forced by ſtreſs of weather, or the danger of the ſea, to enter therein, particular care ſhall be taken to haſten their departure, and to cauſe them to retire as ſoon as poſſible. Nothing in this Treaty contained ſhall, however, be conſtrued or operate contrary to former and exiſting public treaties with other Sovereigns or States. But the two parties agree, that while they continue in amity neither of them will in future make any treaty that ſhall be inconſiſtent with this or the preceding article.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="unknown:029760_0089_0FE259EEED3A75F0"/>Neither of the ſaid parties ſhall permit the ſhips or goods belonging to the ſubjects or citizens of the other to be taken within cannon ſhot of the coaſt, nor in any of the bays, ports, or rivers of their ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories by ſhips of war, or others having commiſſion from any Prince, Republic, or State whatever. But in caſe it ſhould ſo happen, the party whoſe territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial rights ſhall thus have been violated, ſhall uſe his utmoſt endeavours to obtain from the offending par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, full and ample ſatisfaction for the veſſel or veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels ſo taken, whether the ſame be veſſels of war or merchant veſſels.</p>
               <p n="26">Art. 26. If at any time a rupture ſhould take place (which God forbid) between his Majeſty and the United States, the Merchants and others of each of the two nations reſiding in the dominions of the other ſhall have the privilege of remaining and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing their trade, ſo long as they behave peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and commit no offence againſt the laws; and in caſe their conduct ſhould render them ſuſpected and the reſpective governments ſhould think proper to order them to remove, the term of twelve months from the publication of the order ſhall be allowed them for that purpoſe, to remove with their families, effects, and property, but this favor ſhall not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to thoſe who ſhall act contrary to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed laws, and for greater certainty, it is declared that ſuch rupture ſhall not be deemed to exiſt while negociations for accommodating differences ſhall be depending, nor until the reſpective Ambaſſadors or Miniſters, if ſuch there ſhall be, ſhall be recalled or ſent home on account of ſuch differences, and not on account of perſonal miſconduct according to the nature and degrees of which both parties retain their rights, either to requeſt the recall, or immediately to ſend home the Ambaſſador or Miniſter of the other: and that without prejudice to their mutual friendſhip and good underſtanding.</p>
               <p n="27">Art. 27. It is further agreed that his Majeſty and the United States on mutual requiſitions, by them reſpectively, or by their reſpective Miniſters or
<pb n="91" facs="unknown:029760_0090_0FE259F07B35F198"/>Officers authoriſed to make the ſame, will deliver up to juſtice all perſons who being charged with murder or forgery, committed within the juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of either, ſhall ſeek an aſylum within any of the countries of the other, provided that this ſhall only be done on ſuch evidence of criminality as, according to the laws of the place, where the fugitive or perſon ſo charged ſhall be found, would juſtify his apprehenſion and commitment for trial, if the offence had there be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> committed. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of ſuch apprehenſion and delivery ſhall be borne and defrayed by thoſe who make the requiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and receive the fugitive.</p>
               <p n="28">Art. 28. It is agreed, that the firſt ten articles of this Treaty ſhall be permanent, and that the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent articles, except the twelfth, ſhall be limited in their duration to twelve years, to be computed from the day on which the ratifications of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall be exchanged, but ſubject to this condition—that whereas the ſaid twelfth article will expire by the limitation therein contained, at the end of two years from the ſigning the preliminary or other articles of peace which ſhall terminate the preſent war in which his Majeſty is engaged, it is agreed, that proper meaſures ſhall by concert be taken for bringing the ſubject of that article into amicable treaty and diſcuſſion, ſo early before the expiration of the ſaid term, as that new arrangements on that head, may by that time be perfected and ready to take place. But i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould unfortunately happen, that his Majeſty and the United States ſhould not be able to agree o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch new arrangements, in that caſe all the articles of this treaty, except the firſt ten ſhall then ceaſe and expire together.</p>
               <p>Laſtly. This Treaty, when the ſame ſhall have been ratified by his Majeſty and by the Preſident of the United States, by and with the advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of their Senate, and the reſpective ratifications mutually exchanged, ſhall be binding and obligatory on his Majeſty and on the ſaid States, and ſhall be by them reſpectively executed and obſerved with punctuality and the moſt ſincere regard to good
<pb n="92" facs="unknown:029760_0091_0FE259F20E4CBC70"/>faith; and whereas it will be expedient, in order the better to facilitate intercourſe and obviate difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that other articles be propoſed and added to this Treaty, which articles from want of time and other circumſtances, cannot now be perfected—it is agreed, that the ſaid parties will, from time to time, readily treat of and concerning ſuch articles, and will ſincerely endeavour ſo to form them, as that they may conduce to mutual convenience, and tend to promote mutual ſatisfaction and friendſhip; and that the ſaid articles, after having been duly ratified, ſhall be added to, and make a part of this Treaty. In faith whereof, we, the underſigned Miniſters Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotentiary of his Majeſty the King of Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and the United States of America, have ſigned this preſent Treaty, and have cauſed to be affixed thereto the Seal of our arms.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Done at London, <date>this Nineteenth day of November, One Thouſand Seven Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Ninety Four.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>GRENVILLE, <hi>(Seal)</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>JOHN JAY. <hi>(Seal)</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="ratification">
               <head>CONDITIONAL RATIFICATION, on the Part of the United States, in Senate, June 24, 1795.</head>
               <p>Reſolved, that the Senate do conſent to, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe the Preſident of the United States to ratify the treaty of amity, commerce and navigation, between his Britannic Majeſty and the United States of America, concluded at London, the 19th Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, 1794, on condition that there be added to the ſaid Treaty, an article whereby it ſhall be agreed to ſuſpend ſo much of the 12th article, as reſpects the trade, which his ſaid Majeſty thereby conſents may be carried on between the United States and his Iſlands in the Weſt-Indies, in the manner, and on the terms and conditions therein ſpecified.</p>
               <p>And the Senate recommend to the Preſident to proceed without delay to further friendly negocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with his Majeſty on the ſubject of the ſaid trade, and of the terms and conditions in queſtion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
