<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The defence of Warner Mifflin against aspersions cast on him on account of his endeavors to promote righteousness, mercy and peace, among mankind. [Two lines from Galatians]</title>
            <author>Mifflin, Warner, 1745-1798.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N23288</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N23288</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 30793</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX3352</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">30793</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99020120</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 30793.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N23288)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 30793)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 30793)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The defence of Warner Mifflin against aspersions cast on him on account of his endeavors to promote righteousness, mercy and peace, among mankind. [Two lines from Galatians]</title>
                  <author>Mifflin, Warner, 1745-1798.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30, [2] p. ;  21 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Sansom, Jun. no. 27, Mulberry-Street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1796.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mifflin, Warner, 1745-1798.</term>
               <term>Slavery --  United States --  Controversial literature --  1796.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:030793_0001_0FE92C19F8D85288"/>
            <p>THE DEFENCE OF WARNER MIFFLIN</p>
            <p>Againſt Aſperſions caſt on him on Account of his endeavours To promote RIGHTEOUSNESS, MERCY AND PEACE, <hi>AMONG MANKIND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing <q>It is good to be zealouſly affected with a good thing; and I therefore your Enemy, becauſe I tell you the Truth</q>
               <bibl>GAL. CHAP. IV.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>PHILADELPHIA:</hi> PRINTED BY SAMUEL SANSOM, jun. No. 27, MULBERRY-STREET. 1796</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="unknown:030793_0002_0FE92B39A14096A8"/>
            <head>WARNER MIFFLIN'S DEFENCE.</head>
            <p>I WAS born and chiefly raiſed on the Eaſtern Shore of Virginia; and although my Parents were of the religious Society called Quakers, and exemplary in their Lives, yet I witneſſed great incitements to a departure from the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples held by that People, there being none of the Profeſſion, except our Family within ſixty Miles; and my Aſſociates were of thoſe, who tenaciouſly held the prevailing ſentiments in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Slavery: So that I had no opportunity of having my heart and views enlarged on this intereſting Subject, by converſing with ſuch of my Brethren in Profeſſion, who had come to ſee the neceſſity of an impartial enquiry into the nature and tendency of this atrocious practice.</p>
            <p>Thus ſituated and my Father then poſſeſſing a number of Slaves, I was in great danger of becoming blinded by the influence of Cuſtom,
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:030793_0003_0FE92B3FEF763908"/>
the bias of Education, and the deluſions of ſelf-intereſt; from whence I certainly muſt have become fettered as in the Chains of wrong ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, had not the emanations of divine Light and Grace (which I had been early inſtructed to pay attention to) powerfully prevailed in ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive viſitations, ſo operating as to ſubvert the effects of dangerous prepoſſeſſions, and diſpoſing my mind to yield to the influences of beſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, on this, to my preſent view, one of the worſt of ſins.</p>
            <p>And it is with peculiar ſatisfaction I have to remark, that my Father was not long behind me in eſpouſing the cauſe of Liberty: After ſealing the ſincerity of his profeſſions by the liberation of about an hundred Blacks, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the diſcouragement of a Law then exiſting, he became a zealous Advocate and interceſſor for them with their Maſters, and in many inſtances were his labours ſucceſsful: Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten appearing alone in Courts of Law, amidſt ſurrounding Opponents, to plead the Cauſe of Individuals of the African Race, who had a claim to freedom.</p>
            <p>An occurrence took place about the fourteenth year of my Age, that tended to pave the way for the reception of thoſe impreſſions which have ſince been ſealed with indelible clearneſs on my underſtanding. Being in the Field with my Father's Slaves, a young Man among them queſtioned me <q>
                  <hi>Whether I thought it could be right, that they ſhould be toiling to raiſe me, and I ſent to ſchool, and by and by their children muſt do ſo for mine alſo?</hi>
               </q> Some little irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion took place in my mind at firſt; but his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning finally ſo impreſſed me as never to be
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:030793_0004_0FE92B41C75EB800"/>
eraſed—The idea of loſing ſo much property as what I might probably expect from the great number my Father poſſeſſed, ſeemed hard on firſt view to reconcile: however, before I ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at Manhood I determined never to be a Slave holder—Yet on ſettling in a Married life commenced the proving of my Faith on this head—I became poſeſſed of ſeveral Minor Slaves by my Wife and divers came from my Fathers on different errands, with a concluſion to abide with me, without any move thereto on his part or mine: As alſo ſeveral that never lived with him, that were of my Mothers family of Blacks from Kent County Maryland—Thus all I then had of lawful Age, being Volunteers, I ſat down quiet in the uſe of them, until at length I became almoſt perſuaded I could not do without them—And when the ſubject of freeing Blacks was treated on, the prevailing ſentiment was, that Negroes were ſuch Thieves they would not do to be free; and though this was chiefly the plea of Slave holders, yet I was glad to embrace it as a pretext for keeping mine, but I was not ſuffered long to reſt unreproved in this ſpot; my ſig leaf covering of excuſe was ſtripped off and my ſtate diſcovered to me by the penetrating Rays of that Light which mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth manifeſt <q>
                  <hi>for whatſoever maketh manifeſt is light;</hi>
               </q> from whence conſiderable conflict aroſe in my ſoul; when after continuing for ſome time debating, reſolving and re-reſolving, a period arrived, when he who hath his way in the Clouds, in the Whirlwind, the Earthquake, and thick darkneſs, was pleaſed to arouſe me to greater vigilance by his terrors for Sin, for having omitted what had appeared clearly as my
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:030793_0005_0FE92B4990BF75D8"/>
duty in this buſineſs, when in a time of thunder ſtorm, every flaſh appeared as though it might be the inſtrument to diſpatch me into a ſtate of fixedneſs, and with the meaſure of my duty herein not filled up; what then could I expect if taken in that condition, but an eternal ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from heavenly enjoyment? And though theſe ſenſations may appear ſtrange to ſome, who <hi>neither fear God nor regard Man</hi> yet I ſtill retain a willingneſs, that ſuch ſeaſons of convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the outward Elements, may be impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of ſolid inſtruction to my mind.</p>
            <p>It then ſettled on my underſtanding, that I ſhould indeed be excluded from happineſs if I continued in this breach of the divine Law, written upon my heart as by the finger of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; altho' want and diſgrace to my family had preſented with threatening aſpect, ſhould I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to its dictates. After which, in the Year 1774, I manumited thoſe I had by my Wife, flattering myſelf ſuch who came of their own accord I might retain while they choſe to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue as heretofore, ſtill being viſited with afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, on the preſentation of an awful Eternity, a willingneſs was wrought in me to caſt my care on a merciful Providence, and to reſign up at all events to what I did believe was called for at my hands, that of bearing a faithful Teſtimony againſt the abominable practice of enſlaving fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Men, I therefore let my Father know, he muſt take the Blacks away or authorize me to ſet them free, He readily told me I might do as I would, on which in 1775 I executed another deed of Emancipation for all I held as mine.—</p>
            <p>About the 24th year of my Age I was put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Commiſſion of the Peace, which tended
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:030793_0006_0FE92B4B1E85F318"/>
to excite conſiderable thirſt for preferment in Government, a taſte that had much impeded the progreſs of my Teſtimony againſt Slavery, as it furniſhed an Idea of additional neceſſity for Slaves to ſupport me in that mode of Life. Yet after thoſe reaſons of conflict before hinted at, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came impreſſed with a belief that it was right for me to decline this Office, and with it any fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture advancement to ſtations in Power.—Altho' I revere Magiſtracy, confiding in the Sacred Text, that it is an <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> and believing it a great benefit to mankind when executed under, his holy and preſerving fear—But in the preſent ſtate of Governments, I apprehend my Brethren cannot be active therein conſiſtent with our high profeſſion, of being called to become, thro' a faithful adherence to divine monitions, even as ſome of the firſt fruits of the Nations unto God, in the ſupport of our principle againſt War, with which the various Governments, among Men have ſo much affinity—I was ſolemnly impreſſed with the importance of the truſt when about undertaking the Commiſſion, and reſolved to diſcharge my duty therein fully; yet tho' I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to perform this to the beſt of my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, I never felt that peace of Soul I deſired, during my continuance in Office, this brought me into a ſtrict ſcrutiny, and a confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſucceeded of the Truth of our great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters declaration <q>
                  <hi>My Kingdom is not of this World.</hi>
               </q> My mind hath remained, ſtedfaſtly attached to theſe ſentiments, when at different times ſince I have been ſolicited to accept of any ſtation either in the Legiſlative or Executive de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partments of Government, eſpecially as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably unfits for the promulgation of peace
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:030793_0007_0FE92B52EE7BE318"/>
and good will among Men, when there is an embarkation in human policy, on its floating Sea of party Spirit; that gendereth envy, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, revenge, rents, diviſions and War—And the abundant uſe of Oaths, with frequent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, in what relates to matters of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, appears to me not only a manifeſt violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſts injunction to his followers <q>
                  <hi>Swear not at all,</hi>
               </q> as what exceedeth the ſimple and plain communication of <q>
                  <hi>Yea yea, and nay, nay, cometh of evil</hi>
               </q> but is alſo a profanation of the Sacred Name.</p>
            <p>And indeed I have felt ſcrupulous of taking an active part at Elections, leaſt I ſhould not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come tinctured with a Spirit of party, but alſo contribute by my Vote to the placing thoſe in power who might become oppreſſors of tender Conſciences. If we give no juſt occaſion of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, but are in other reſpects uſeful Members of the Community, we may be admitted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cenſure to the exerciſe of theſe ſcruples: and it would be more to the honour as well as bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the World, if the tender Conſcience was more cheriſhed.</p>
            <p>To reſume the thread of my Narrative—I was concerned with two Eſtates, to which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed many of the African Race: in one they were willed to the Heirs particularly nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and as Executor I conceived I muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the government over them, to enable me to ſettle with the Heirs. But I was turned ſolid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſider, that I ſhould not be juſtified in doing that for another, which I was fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced was a ſin to do on my own Account—The proſpect being clear, a ſolemn impreſſion took place at the time, that I believed to be the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:030793_0008_0FE92B547B806818"/>
of holy certainty, <hi>That neither I nor mine ſhould ever ſuffer by my diſcharging them</hi>; which I believe was never doubted by me. I called them in and let them know, ſo far as I had power they were free; ſome who were hired by their own conſent, I informed they muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the time out and they ſhould have their Wages, and likewiſe all their earnings from their Maſters death; which was fully complied with on my part to the beſt of my knowledge, and according to my faith ſo was the event, the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Heirs as they arrived at age, liberated the Slaves and releaſed me.</p>
            <p>I alſo found an engagement to make reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thoſe I had held in a State of bondage, for the time ſo held, which was done according to the judgment of indifferent Men agreed on by myſelf and the blacks. And on reflection I found I had ſo much hand in ſelling ſome, as to put me under an obligation to releaſe them; which I did to a conſiderable amount, on my own account, my then Wife's, and ſome who belonged to her Father and Grandfather.—</p>
            <p>About this time I was appointed on a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee to labour with the members of our Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty who held Slaves, in order for the convince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their underſtandings, of the inconſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of this practice with Chriſtianity; which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour was ſo far bleſt that in a little time moſt of our Members liberated theirs.—Now great ſtir was made as if the Country was going to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and ruined. It appeared as if the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit had gone forth to deceive the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple—On my ſetting mine free, I thought it beſt to put them from me, to manifeſt they were ſo, it was circulated that Mifflin had ſet free a
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:030793_0009_0FE92B5C519A8BC8"/>
parcel of lazy worthleſs Negroes; he could make nothing by them, therefore ſet them at liberty. This reflection had ſome weight with me, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever unjuſt, and regarding Scripture injunction, not to let <hi>our good be evil ſpoken of,</hi> I thought if expedient to propoſe their having Land and Teams, and in return they ſhould give me half their produce, which was put in execution with thoſe who choſe to accept the Terms. Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately the tune was turned, that Mifflin was mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more Money by his Negroes now than ever, and keeping them in more abject Slavery, under the pretence of their being free. I then deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to do what I did believe to be right, not regarding the unbridled Tongues of Men, and ſo I have endeavoured to act 'till this time, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through both good and evil report.</p>
            <p>Another trial occurred, I felt religiouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in Teſtimony againſt the pernicious uſe of ardent Spirits, ſo generally prevalent, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in time of Harveſt—We had been in the ſuperfluous uſe of it in my family, and laying myſelf out as a candidate for promotion in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as before hinted, when in the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Peace, I frequently kept the Bottle and Bowl on the Table from Morning 'till Night; it being then, and I fear is yet too much, the corrupt manner by which worldly promotion is commonly attained: I now found a ſore conflict was to be experienced, in attempting a practice ſo reverſe to what I had been in, and in which I should ſtand alone. And having diſcharged my Slaves, I feared I might never be able to ſave my Grain or carry on my farm to ſupport my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, but the conviction of its rectitude was ſuch, that I felt impelled to make the attempt, I had
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:030793_0010_0FE92B5DDE8045F8"/>
a number of People in my field, a Maſter Maſon with divers of his hands, among others, I thought if he became reconciled it would tend to ſettle the minds of his Companions, therefore began to diſcourſe with him while he was reaping; when in a moſt ſhocking manner he damned religion and ſaid he would have Rum; this to affected me, I left the field, apprehending I ſhould never be able to ſtem ſuch a torrent;, but ſeriouſly pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering on it, and the ſubject enlarging in my view with increaſing weight, it ſealed on my Spirit, that if I ſhould hand out this Liquor, and any Life by its means be loſt, as I had ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times ſeen a danger of being the caſe, I ſhould not be clear of the blood of ſuch, on which I determined thro' divine aſſiſtance never to uſe it again on any like occaſions, and with thankfulneſs I may acknowledge I have been fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured never to ſuffer damage thro' the diſuſe of it in my fields, and ſo preſerved from the miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of it ſince, that in all my concerns there has not been one pint uſed, except on particular Occaſions as Medicine, and that but little.
The late Revolution now began to make its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance and as I was religiouſly reſtrained from taking any part therein, I had the epithet of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryiſm placed on me by intereſted holders of Slaves, inſinuations were thrown out that my labouring for the freedom of the blacks, was in order to attach them to the Britiſh intereſt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I had liberated mine on the ground of religious conviction, before this revolution<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary period arrived—Added to this, on the iſſue of the Bills of Credit by Congreſs, I felt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricted from receiving them, left I might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, in ſome ſort defile my hands with one of
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:030793_0011_0FE92B65A2ED48C0"/>
the Engines of War; from whence I was fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dipped into ſympathy with the condition of the blacks, in acting ſo as to be declared an Enemy to my Country, and like them, thrown out from the benefit of its Laws, and this for no other Crime, but yielding to the impulſes of divine Grace or Law of God written in my heart, which I ever found the ſafeſt ground to move upon—Abundant threats were poured out, that my houſe ſhould be pulled down over my head, that I ſhould be Shot, Carted  this proved a fiery tryal, my ſoul was almoſt overwhelmed left I ſhould bring my family to want, and it might be through a deception. I left my houſe in the night ſeaſon and walked into a field in the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my ſoul, and without any ſenſible relief returned back, on ſtepping into the door I eſpied a Teſtament, and opening it in the I3th Chap. of Revelations, found mention there made of a time, when none ſhould buy or ſell, but thoſe who received the mark of the Beaſt in the right Hand or forehead: and it fixed in my mind, that if I took that Money after thoſe impreſſions, I ſhould receive a mark of the beſtial ſpirit of War in my right hand; and then the penalty which is annexed in the enſuing Chapter muſt follow—I then reſolved through the Lords aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, which I craved might be afforded, let what would follow, never to deal in any of it, this afforded me ſome relief, and finding my Wife ſo far united with me as to refuſe it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (ſaying though ſhe did not feel the matter as I did, yet through fear of weakening my hands, ſhe was moſt eaſy not to touch it) I became much ſtrengthened and reſigned to ſuffer what might be allotted, feeling at times the prevalence
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:030793_0012_0FE92B67310410B0"/>
of that power, which delivers from all fear of the malice of Men or infernal ſpirits, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces the ſoul into perfect ſubjection to the holy will and ordering.</p>
            <p>Light ſeems to be increaſingly ſpreading on this ſubject, or at leaſt more are diſpoſed to yield to its emanations thereon than heretofore; an inſtance of which is a pamphlet written by a Clergyman in England and lately reprinted by D. Humphreys, in Philadelphia which I would recommend to the peruſal of my Readers, in which he remarks, <q>Such is the dread of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity in diſſenting from opinions ſanctioned by public approbation and applauſe, that but few have courage to forſake the beaten track and think for themſelves, in matters confeſſedly of the higheſt importance: And thus the ſpecious reaſonings and concluſions of men, who have no better claim to infallibility than ourſelves, are ſuffered to divert us from a ſimple attention to the example and unambiguous precepts of him, who has preſented to us, in his own ſacred perſon, celeſtial excellence, and the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete pattern of all moral virtue—On ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects which do not relate to the great truths of Religion, we may be indifferent, and it is doubtleſs, beſt not to be earneſt and tenacious for either ſide of the Queſtion; but when doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, upon the eſtabliſhment and promulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which, the temporal and perhaps the eternal welfare of Millions in ſome meaſure depends, it is the duty and intereſt of every one to ſearch for Truth as for hid treaſure; to be fully perſuaded in his own Mind, that his principles are founded in immutable truth and unerring rectitude—Let ſuch then unfold the ſacred volume, which contains the charter
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:030793_0013_0FE92B6F5629D018"/>
of our eternal ſalvation, and ſay in what part of it they can find any paſſage that will either directly or indirectly, prove war to be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able on Chriſtian principles—that will furniſh one argument in favour of a Chriſtians endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to injure his fellow Creature, even his moſt bitter and inveterate enemy, ſo much as in thought; or what is more; that can juſtify him in diſlodging a human Soul from its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed tabernacle, by deſtroying that life which he neither gave nor can reſtore? Do not the doctrines of the new Teſtament uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formly declare againſt it, and moſt expreſsly and unequivocally prove that War is directly oppoſed to the very aim and end of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which offers reconciliation to the greateſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, and makes our acceptance with God abſolutely to depend on our forgiveneſs of thoſe by whom we ourſelves have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured?</q>—</p>
            <q>Suicide, that lifts his guilty arm againſt his own ſacred perſon, naturally excites ſuch hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in the mind, that he who has impiouſly dared to infringe upon the prerogative of his Maker, by putting a period to his own life, is held to be unworthy the common rites of ſepulture—The Laws of this Country rank dueliſts and their ſeconds in the claſs of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, ſince they impiouſly wanton with their own lives and thoſe of their fellow Creatures (ſee Blackſtones Commentaries.) the gratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of revenge, the darling paſſion of narrow, ſavage, and untutored minds, may, perhaps, be pleaded by ſome, as an excuſe for the encounters of theſe gentlemen-like murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:—But what can be ſaid in extenuation of
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:030793_0014_0FE92B710ED81450"/>
the guilt of thoſe who ſet others on to War, who never ſaw each others faces, nor ever had any poſſible occaſion for hatred or animoſity? Who can ſay that ſuch are more innocent than the dueliſt and ſuicide, or leſs deſerving the puniſhment due to ſuch heinous offences againſt the divine Law, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>The War advancing with increaſing diſtreſs, gloomy proſpects opened, and cloſe provings ſeemed at the door of ſuch who were meaſurably redeemed from the ſpirit of party. Not only our Teſtimony againſt War, in the ſupport of which our religious Society have been oft brought under tryals; but that againſt pulling down or ſetting up of Governments was brought to the Teſt. As there are thoſe, who from full expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience know, that it is not a cunningly deviſed Fable, but the Truth of God revealed in the heart, through his Light and good Spirit, that ſhews us we are called to raiſe the pure Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of the Prince of Peace, above all party rage, ſtrife, contention, rents and diviſions, in the ſpirit of meekneſs and wiſdom; and in quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and confidence, patiently to ſuffer what may ariſe for the promotion of this peaceable Government of the Shiloh; in and through an innocent life and converſation; wherein the language is felt of <q>
                  <hi>Glory to God in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, on Earth peace and good will to Men:</hi>
               </q> And this was the experience of many, I am bold to aſſert it, even during the late cruel War, when thouſands of Men were endeavouring in its fierce and voracious ſpirit to deſtroy one another—Such have been my own ſenſations, when at one view I have beheld both parties, and had to riſk a paſſage through them—I count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:030793_0015_0FE92B78E398A7D8"/>
none my enemy, I felt no fear from any thing on my part in thought, word, or deed; many times concluding, I ſhould have had no objection for the two contending Generals to have known my whole heart and conduct, having at an early period of that Calamity been convinced, it would not do for me, even in idea, to wander without the boundaries of my profeſſed principles; or I could not expect to be ſuſtained by the ſecret aid of the God of the faithful, whoſe everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arm of help, with humble gratitude I may acknowledge, hath been ſtretched out for my ſtrengthening and confirmation in a variety of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: One of which was, when called upon among others for the ſupport of <hi>Truth,</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Aſſembly of Pennſylvania, on behalf of our Friends who were baniſhed from Philadelphia to Virginia, for the well known for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery and unjuſt charge on our Society, dated from Spank Town, reſpecting which, ſome yet undertake to vilify us, though it hath been ſo fully refuted and cleared up. After which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, I queried with an American Officer of high rank, whether he did believe that could have been wrote in any of our Meetings? to which he replied, <q>He believed it was wrote in a Meeting Houſe—</q>I told him it would be hard for us to be anſwerable for all the crimes committed in our Meeting houſes, when they choſe to take them from us by force, but did he believe it was wrote by any of the Society? his anſwer was 'He believed Gen. Sullivan knew who wrote it'—And when on the day of the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Germantown, our Yearly Meeting iſſued a Teſtimony reſpecting our peaceable principles, denying ſaid charge I was one among others, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:030793_0016_0FE92B7AC94473A8"/>
pointed to preſent this to the Commander in Chief of each Army, which was a proving time; to paſs through oppoſing Armies, moſt of whoſe minds were perhaps agitated, and many of them afreſh fired by the Spirit of War, from their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent engagement; and with no paſſport or ſhield to protect us from any mercileſs attack, but our own innocence ſheltered by the wing of divine preſervation: Herein I was brought into renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſympathy with our oppreſſed African Brethren, who are many of them expoſed to the uncontroul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed power of Man, without any tribunal on all the Earth whereunto they can appeal for redreſs of grievances.—</p>
            <p>After many ſimilar exerciſes, with frequent calls for, but little ſeizure of my property, 'till the cloſe of the War (when great ſpoil was made), through a ſteady perſeverance things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to wear a different aſpect, hard ſpeeches, four looks and threats gradually abated ſo that through the whole I had not an inſult offered to me in Perſon.</p>
            <p>Congreſs having publicſhed a declaration, that they <q>hold theſe Truths to be ſelf evident. that all Men are created equal; that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enable rights; that among theſe are life, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and the purſuit of happineſs. That, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure theſe rights, Governments are inſtituted among Men.</q> Seeing it was the very ſubſtance of the doctrine I had been concerned to promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate for years, I became animated with a hope, that if this was ſincere in the Repreſentatives, and by them inculcated among the People gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally; a bleſſing to this Nation would accompany thoſe endeavours. To ſerve my Country by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertions
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:030793_0017_0FE92B82873E89B8"/>
to remove one cauſe of impending Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I was concerned to unite with my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in repreſenting this matter to different Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative bodies—In the Year I782 we appeared before the Aſſembly of Virginia; which was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with great ſatisfaction, having a ſet of Liberal ſpirited Members to deal with, when a Law took place admitting of emancipation; to which Law Judge Tucker ſays in his late pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication, may be attributed the liberation of ſome thouſands of blacks—In I783 we preſented a Memorial to Congreſs reſpecting the Slave Trade and met with encouragement. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in the Aſſemblies of Pennſylvania, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryland, and Delaware, ſome important ſteps were taken. Alſo in our after application to Congreſs it was evident, that a large part of that Body were favourably diſpoſed towards the rights of this People. From theſe encouraging circumſtances I was induced to hope that Divine favour might yet be continued to this Land; though often impreſſed with fears, that our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in this buſineſs was not proportionably great to the light that had ariſen—And indeed it is a mournful conſideration, that this Nation ſhould yet be ſtained with the blood of the African Trade; and that 700,000 Slaves, according to latter calculation, ſhould continue to groan in a Land of boaſted Liberty. My heart has been grieved and ſoul lamented for this afflicted Race, as well as the condition of my Country; having oft felt as I did at the beginning of the Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, apprehenſive, the hand of Judgment was ready to be opened and outſtretched upon a guilty People, if there was not greater reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this point, ſo as to appeaſe offended Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice;
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:030793_0018_0FE92B841569C7F0"/>
as the outrages committed therein againſt humanity, I conſider as alone ſufficient to draw down ſovereign indignation, excluſive of thoſe other evils and vices too prevalent in the Land.</p>
            <p>An occurrence took place which produced re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed exerciſe of mind, and in the hour of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction ſealed further inſtruction on this object. I received a ſevere hurt on my Leg, and whilſt under extreme anguiſh in dreſſing it, was brought into Sympathy with a poor Soldier, whoſe Leg being fractured and he left without help in the field of Battle. The ſenſation was ſo powerful, I told my Wife, that ever ſince arriving to years capable of judging, I had a Teſtimony againſt War, but never ſo powerfully as at that time; feeling ſo, that if every farthing we were poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of, was ſeized for the purpoſe of ſupporting War, and I was informed it ſhould all go, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept I gave voluntarily one ſhilling, that I was ſatisfied I ſhould not ſo redeem it.</p>
            <p>Shortly after which, an account arrived that a Veſſel from the Weſt Indies was run a ſhore at Lewis Town by the Engliſh, and the Militia were called upon to keep them from plundering her, on which this clear preſentation took place—Here is the Channel through which in a Time of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Hoſtility thoſe ſweets I am ſo fond of come; at a manifeſt riſk of the lives of fellow Men. I remember powerfully what were Davids ſenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons when his valiant Men ruſhed through the Philiſtine Army to bring him Water from a Well which he longed for; he was ſtruck with ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy for their ſituation; and becauſe they went in <hi>Jeopardy of their Lives,</hi> was not eaſy to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify his palate therewith, but poured it out in dedication to the Lord. In like manner I felt—
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:030793_0019_0FE92B8BCDB811D8"/>
a prohibition from uſing Foreign imports, and during the continuance of the War, never touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therewith, except what ſeaſoning of Salt might have been in my food when from home—And being brought into a deep feeling for the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the poor Africans in the Weſt Indies; have never been eaſy with indulging in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce of their Labours ſince; leaſt it ſhould even in a ſmall degree contribute towards the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued exiſtence of a Trade, which intereſts the Planters in keeping up the number of their groaning labourers.</p>
            <p>And fully believing that <q>Righteouſneſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth a Nation, but Sin is a ſhame to any Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</q> I am anxiousſly deſirous we may be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered with the wiſe promoters of the Public good. And indeed I am perſuaded, that the growing Sins of America, if perſiſted in, will be finally attended with dreadful conſequences, according to the Teſtimony of the ſacred Records, that <q>Verily there is a reward for the righteous, verily there is a God that judgeth in the Earth;</q> and in the due exerciſe of his Judgment, taking cognizance of the actions of Men, he will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly recompence to all according to the fruit of their doings, to Nations as well as to indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duals, let the Sophiſt 'ſpeculate as he will about ſacred things, in that wiſdom which <hi>darkens counſel by words without</hi> (true) <hi>knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is from a ſenſe of duty both to myfelf and Country that I make theſe obſervations, and ſtate ſome things intereſting to both. It was on this ground I became engaged with others, to urge the ſubject of our concern to different Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; to remove legiſlative obſtacles from thoſe diſpoſed to liberate their Slaves, and to protect
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:030793_0020_0FE92B8D5BBC8E30"/>
thoſe ſet free. And though ſalutary Laws have been enacted in ſome States, for which I believe a bleſſing will or doth deſcend upon them, yet ſtill the evil is continued in other parts of Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca in a moſt glaring degree: Where conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons are diſcouraged from Liberating, as by exiſting Laws the blacks are liable afreſh to be taken into Captivity, by a diſſolute People diſpoſed to avail themſelves of unrighteous Laws; in many inſtances great numbers have been cruelly ſeized and ſold into renewed bondage— Doth not this excite a fearful apprehenſion that the meaſure of their iniquity is filling, up who ſo act, and that they are ripening for that chaſtize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which ſhall be poured forth on the workers of iniquity? and is not the conſideration of it a loud call on that ſtate where ſuch evils prevail, to arouſe, and by a more righteous procedure en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour if poſſible, to avert the impending ſtroke? and what may be expected both in that and other States, where there is an increaſe of cruel and barbarous ſeparation ſuffered between the neareſt Connections in life for gain, even where they have had magnanimity enough to give ſome check to the African Trade! an additional Enormity prevailing, is the frequent kidnapping of free blacks, carrying them off and ſelling them for Slaves, in ſome inſtances of whole families, and in others ſeparating them one from another.</p>
            <p>It is urged as a very great objection to the emancipation of blacks, their diſpoſition to pilfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but is not the worſt of Robbery in depriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them of that moſt valuable Property, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and keeping them under the oppreſſion of Slavery, the very cauſe of this fault? being pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at times for almoſt every neceſſary of life, they
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:030793_0021_0FE92B95293B9E48"/>
naturally put forth a hand to partake of what their labour gives them ſome claim to in equity from their poſſeſſors, where due ſupport is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held; and theſe practices becoming habitual, in their impoveriſhed condition, they diſcriminate not ſufficiently between the property of thoſe they labour for and others; but when oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity preſents frequently ſupply their wants from all alike, except where a principle of religious rectitude reſtrains from all ſuch acts: I attempt not to palliate the crime. I have endeavoured what lies in my power to reprobate ſuch proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, labouring to inculcate the Chriſtian doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of returning good for evil, whereby they may know an overcoming evil with good; and to point out the neceſſity of departing from theſe practices, being objections ſpeciouſly alledged againſt their general liberation: But as Slavery decreaſes and is exploded, we may reaſonably hope its concomitant habits will alſo decreaſe, and a greater nobility of Soul take place. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Almighty hath ariſen to Judgment in this buſineſs, and that his voice will be found to exceed the ſound of many Waters, or all the clamours of the People; overpowering all oppoſition whatſoever.</p>
            <p>If we proved more faithful in the diſcharge of our duty towards God and this People, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they would act differently towards us—But where does Negro crimes exceed the Crimes of White Men? when we view them, ſelling tender Babes from a fond Mother, a beloved Wife from an affectionate Huſband, or an aged Father from his offspring with whom he hath lived from their early years; and although a Slave, capable of the ties of affection and enjoying conſolation in
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:030793_0022_0FE92B970A3E3528"/>
their Society; and now, as to this life, forever parted—Ah! what language can paint in its ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Colours this abominable practice? how rejoicing would it be to me, if with divine allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, I might be placed in an allotment exempt from that continued grief of ſoul, which is almoſt daily renewed, from ſeeing and hearing of thoſe acts of inhumanity committed by my countrymen! could I have believed myſelf authorized by the approbation, of Heaven, I ſhould long 'ere this time have ſought an aſylum in ſome other Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter—but I deſire to be found in my proper allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the little time I may be continued here—faithfully diſcharging my duty towards my Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and my Country.</p>
            <p>And now my fellow Citizens, let me call your ſerious attention to the preſent condition of our Land, you more eſpecially who believe in a God, in the ſuperintendance of his Providence, and in the Sacred Records: Let us ruminate on what is perpetrated within its borders; we who have been ſo highly favoured of the Almighty; and make ſo great profeſſion reſpecting liberty to the World, I believe it can be proved, that ſince the Revolution, even within the ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of the State of Delaware and its adjoining part of Maryland, there hath been more free blacks kidnapped and carried into Slavery, than there has been of American Citizens captured by the Algerines. Where are the feeling Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who ſuffered inexpreſſible grief on ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their darling Children ſtript from them in the late War? are not theſe in any degree brought to feel anothers woe?</p>
            <p>Some advance that Negroes pay no regard to the natural ties of Huſband and Wife, Parent
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:030793_0023_0FE92B9ECE847610"/>
and Child—I know to the contrary; unnatural and hardened characters there are in all Nations, but that ſuch abound more among this People than others, in proportion to their circumſtances, I cannot admit. Where ſuch inſtances have ariſen, to whom muſt we apply the guilt? on the poor tried blacks, or on nominal profeſſors of the bleſſed name of Chriſt? who with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentleſs tyranny can advertize amongſt other ſtock on a farm, a number of theſe Brethren by Creation; and when the afflicted ſufferers are called up for Sale, reluctantly advancing with tears falling from their Eyes—Oh bluſh Americans at this! perhaps a Trader in human fleſh from Georgia, bids off a Mother and her Child, the Maſter of this dreadful Tragedy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding more to be brought forward—an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturer from Kentucky proves the higheſt bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for the Father and another Child—Thus are Families torn aſunder, the Marriage Tie violated and made of no account, and their Cup of human miſery filled up with mingled bitters—And perhaps among the ſpectators, yea in other Lots ſold, of theſe hapleſs victims to Avarice, even among the Speculators, may be found profeſſed Miniſters of the Goſpel, who not only behold without reproof theſe proceedings, but are partakers of this gain of oppreſſion.<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <p>Numerous are the inſtances that might be adduced to ſhew the inhuman cruelties inflicted on theſe helpleſs People, under the public countenance given to the Spirit of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and Tyranny; a few caſes may ſuffice to give the general features of thoſe Enormities, of the certainty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I have no doubt of my Authority.</p>
                  <p>In the County of Kent on Delaware, a Negro man, not long ſince, having petitioned the Court far his freedom and ſecurity being required for his appearance in caſe he ſhould be adjudged a Slave, his ſecurity took him home to his houſe to remain till Trial, the pretended Maſter or his agents went armed to the Houſe when the Maſter of the Family was from home, violently ſeized the black man, much ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified the Family, carried him off, tied a Rope round his Neck, faſtened it to a Horſe, and drove ſo faſt as to keep the poor black on a run, being thus dragged in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and ſo mangled and bruiſed that he died next Morning. No further notice appears to be taken of this brutality, by legal Authority, but the formality of a Warrant iſſued by the chief Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>Two Negro Men at Snow Hill Maryland, being charged with breaking into a Store, whereof on due examination they were found perfectly innocent, but previouſly in order to convict them, they were inhumanly and illegally tortured to make them confeſs, by the application of Thumb-screws, until their Thumbs burſt with the preſſure.—</p>
                  <p>A Negro Man charged with breaking into a Smoke houſe in Northampton County, Virginia, had his Feet put to the Fire to bake till they broiled into Bliſters, to torture him into confeſſion; but he was afterwards acquitted of the Fact by Confeſſion of the Evidence which had been ſuborned againſt him.</p>
                  <p>Of like deteſtable Practices a Volume might be filled; but a more particular enumeration would not comport with the brevity intended in the preſent Repreſentation.</p>
               </note>—Is
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:030793_0024_0FE92BA07553F658"/>
there any ſpirited diſapprobation manifeſted againſt this kind of Traffic where it prevails, is there not too generally a ſilent acquieſcence therewith? and have I advanced ought but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable truths on the ſubject? not ſaying any thing of their hard fare in tyrannical families; though I acknowledge with ſatisfaction their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is much meliorated in a general way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the laſt twenty Years, as to their domeſtic uſage, yet, more diſtreſſing ſeparations have taken place among them within that ſpace of time than heretofore; Let us then my Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men put our Souls in their Souls ſtead, let us
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:030793_0025_0FE92BA8359D6B08"/>
imagine how it would feel, to be groaning under the Iron hand of oppreſſion and no tribunal on Earth whereunto we might apply for relief.</p>
            <p>It hath been infuſed into the minds of the People by the ſpirit of ſeduction, that I have perſuaded the blacks to run from their Maſters, that I gave them paſſes without diſcriminating between thoſe who are free and others, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they apply; and that I keep a large num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of abſconded Slaves in clearing my Swamps; which was recently thrown before the Members of a Legiſlative Body, to counteract any influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence I might poſſibly have there; together with an inſinuation that I had offered a bribe to a connection of one then preſent, on a Negro af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair; all which aſſertions I deny as originating from the Father of Lies; and made I believe to lay waſte any poſſible influence I might have againſt Slavery.</p>
            <p>Added to theſe things are the curſes, threats and hard ſpeeches, that have been thrown out againſt me, for acting only conſonant with the principles of the late Revolution, in peaceably vindicating the natural Rights of Men, on the grounds of Humanity and obligations of the Chriſtian Religion. And I think I may aſſert, that I never violated the Laws of Men in this buſineſs, unleſs feeding the hungry can be term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a violation; to ſome of thoſe poor diſtreſſed People, when abſconding as they have repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, on account of very rigorous treatment, I have indeed pitied and given them food, in which I conſidered myſelf warranted by the Law of God, and principle of human ſympathy, to relieve for a little ſpace a ſuffering fellow Creature, who called for aſſiſtance, hungry and weary.
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:030793_0026_0FE92BA9C8C47220"/>
But it is the reverſe of my judgment of propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, in preſerving the peace of Society, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade theſe People from their Claimers ſervice, and beneath the uprightneſs of my Profeſſion to recommend any as free People who are not ſuch. I believe a cauſe that is ſanctioned by Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, needs no ſuch effort to make it ſucceſsful, but the more pure and upright are its eſpouſers, the more will it be advanced. I am of the faith, the voice of the Spiritual Moſes has been as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligibly ſounded in the Ears of Americans, as ever the voice of Moſes formerly was heard by the Egyptians, even the Lord from Heaven, who is a quickening Spirit and <q>If they eſcap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not who refuſed him that ſpoke on Earth, how much more ſhall not we eſcape, if we turn away from him who ſpeaketh from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</q> who I believe is advancing to lay waſte all oppoſition in this buſineſs; which he will ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in his own time. And it appears by a large part of the Wills latterly made, that many who retain their ſenſes, are unwilling to riſk a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage into an awful eternity and leave fellow Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as Slaves; I marvel there are not many more.</p>
            <p>I am troubled at feeing any run from their Maſters, and generally counſel ſuch, that it is my judgment they had better remain at home in quiet reſignation as much as poſſible to their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotment, and that, if through a good conduct they ſhould obtain favour of their Maker, he could change the hearts of theſe their poſſeſſors and induce them to liberate. On which ground of inward conviction it is, I wiſh to ſee the work carried forward. Some have taken my counſel and returned, others have judged beſt to purſue
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:030793_0027_0FE92BB18CA41580"/>
their own proſpects be the event as it would; and ſome others, who by accounts met with hard treatment at home, I could ſay but little to on the ſubject, only as they were Slaves, it would not do for them to tarry at my houſe, as I could not by that means do them any good, and it would only give offence to their Claimers.</p>
            <p>Is there a White Man among thouſands, who if captured among the Algerines, would not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace his liberty ſhould opportunity preſent: If I were a humane Algerine reſiding in their Land, and an American in eſcaping from his Maſter ventured to call at my houſe, informing he had not eat any thing for ſeveral Days; would my Countrymen judge it criminal in me to feed him! what then ſhould be the conduct of the higher profeſſors of Chriſtianity, in a ſimilar caſe, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a People, who differ from us by a few darker ſhades in the ſkin. Is there any part of our Religion that would authorize us to ſeize ſuch and drag them again into Chains? or would it not be as great a violation of the righteous Law of God, who Scripture teſtifies is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecter of Perſons, but who hath created of one blood all nations of Men, to ſeize on one of a dark complexion as one of a fairer hue?—Is it not through the principles of tyranny and deſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm yet too prevalent in America, in cheriſhing ideas of too much diſtinction among Men on this ſubject, that they are not only yet retained in Slavery, but even, when from a ſenſe of religion and juſtice their Maſters have diſpenſed to them
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:030793_0028_0FE92BB319EE5228"/>
the bleſſing of liberty, they have not an equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble chance to vindicate their right, when it is encroached upon by kidnapping: For even where theſe acts are known in many Neighbourhoods, what a daſtardly Spirit pervades the Minds of the People, leſt they ſhould offend ſome Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, afraid to ſtep forward in a proſecution, and if any are impelled to undertake it from this Sympathy with the ſufferer, they are oft put to great difficulties for want of ſuitable evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; as thoſe Whites who may have due knowledge of the matter, oft evade giving their Teſtimony through fear of making Enemies; and thus in ſeeing the Thief, yet by ſilence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, according to Scripture, they become equally guilty; and if there were thouſands of blacks who could give clear evidence, the Law will not admit it as valid—Is not this arbitrary and very unjuſt?</p>
            <p>I dread the conſequence of a continuance of wrong things in our Land, have we not ſeen evident tokens of divine diſpleaſure? hath not the Sword, the Famine, and Peſtilence made their appearance in various parts? and as a gentle rod ſhaking over us, are calling loudly to greater degrees of humility, repentance and amendment of life; leſt offended Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence ſhould pour forth upon us more abundantly the Vials of his Wrath, and tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, anguiſh and woe, be the complicated por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Inhabitants of America—Let us then by a ſtrict attention to the diſcharge of our duty towards God and Man ſo act as to invite the Lords' bleſſings upon us, who is ever ready
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:030793_0029_0FE92BBADB7D3758"/>
to ſhower down his favours on the Obedient workmanſhip of his hands—Which that it may be our happy experience, is the deſire and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer of a Lover of his Country, and Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, a peaceable Subject to its Laws, and an Univerſal friend to Mankind.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WARNER MIFFLIN</signed>.
<dateline>Kent, on Delaware <date>11 Month 1796</date>.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
