<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The duty of worshipping God in his house, considered in a sermon, delivered December 17th, 1795, on occasion of opening a new meeting-house in the south part of Dennis. / By Nathaniel Stone, A.M. Pastor of the church in that town. ; Published by desire of the hearers.</title>
            <author>Stone, Nathan, 1737-1804.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N23610</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N23610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 31240</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APZ0659</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">31240</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99038278</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 31240.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N23610)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 31240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 31240)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The duty of worshipping God in his house, considered in a sermon, delivered December 17th, 1795, on occasion of opening a new meeting-house in the south part of Dennis. / By Nathaniel Stone, A.M. Pastor of the church in that town. ; Published by desire of the hearers.</title>
                  <author>Stone, Nathan, 1737-1804.</author>
                  <author>Manning, William, 1767-1849.</author>
                  <author>Underwood, Nathan, 1753-1841. Public worship considered and recommended.</author>
                  <author>First Church (Dennis, Mass.).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>17, [1], 14 p. ;  21 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Manning &amp; Loring, Spring-Lane.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Boston, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Feb. 1796.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Mr. Stone's and Mr. Underwood's sermons, at the opening of a new meeting-house in Dennis.</note>
                  <note>"Public worship considered and recommended. A sermon, delivered at Dennis, December 17, 1795, at the opening of a new meeting-house. By Nathan Underwood, A.M. Pastor of the South Church in Harwich. Published by desire of the hearers."--14 p. at end, with separate title page.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Public worship.</term>
               <term>Dedication sermons --  1795.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:031240_0000_0FEB8105B1F083F0"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:031240_0001_0FEAF8F2E616A410"/>
            <p>Mr. STONE'S AND Mr. UNDERWOOD'S SERMONS, AT THE OPENING OF A NEW MEETING-HOUSE IN <hi>DENNIS.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="unknown:031240_0002_0FEAF9104BB96378"
                      rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>The Duty of worſhipping God in his Houſe, conſidered in A SERMON, DELIVERED <hi>DECEMBER</hi> 17<hi>th,</hi> 1795, ON OCCASION OF OPENING A NEW MEETING-HOUSE IN THE SOUTH PART OF DENNIS. BY NATHANIEL STONE, A.M. PASTOR OF THE CHURCH IN THAT TOWN. Publiſhed by deſire of the <hi>HEARERS.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>PRINTED AT BOSTON, BY MANNING &amp; LORING, SPRING-LANE. FEB. 1796.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="unknown:031240_0003_0FEAF91579E7E5F8"/>
                  <head>A SERMON.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the honour of God, and for the benefit of his people, more eſpecially in this part of the town, this houſe, in which we are now met for the firſt time, has lately been erected and completed, for the exerciſe of public worſhip.</p>
                  <p>Let us, with becoming ſeriouſneſs, give our atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to what may be delivered at this time, agreeably to thoſe words of the Pſalmiſt, contained in
<q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>THE 5</hi>th <hi>PSALM, 7</hi>th <hi>VERSE.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>"But as for me, I will come into thy houſe, in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy mercy; and in thy fear will I worſhip toward thy holy temple."</p>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the beginning of this Pſalm we find the Pſalmiſt fervently begging audience of God to his prayer, and urging this from God's relation to him, and his own reſolved choice of him alone as the object of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; as in the following elegant expreſſions, in the 1ſt and 2d verſes. "Give ear to my words, O Lord; conſider my meditation. Hearken unto the voice of
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:031240_0004_0FEAF91898D76000"/>
my cry, my King and my God; for unto thee will I pray." He in the next place expreſſes his hopeful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that God will ſpeedily hear him when calling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him by prayer, and grant an anſwer of peace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Says he, "My voice ſhalt thou hear in the morning, O Lord; in the morning will I direct my prayer unto thee, and will look up." With a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and patient expectation he will wait for relief, under his perplexing troubles: and he encourages himſelf thereunto, it may be, in part, from the charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of his adverſaries, againſt whom he prays; who, through their wickedneſs, are ſo contrary to God, that he cannot chooſe but hear his faithful ſervant's prayers, and will deſtroy the workers of iniquity. "For thou art not a God that hath pleaſure in wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, neither ſhall evil dwell with thee. The fooliſh ſhall not ſtand in thy ſight: thou hateſt all workers of iniquity. Thou ſhalt deſtroy them that ſpeak leaſing; the Lord will abhor the bloody and deceitful man."</p>
                  <p>The text contains his pious reſolution what he would make his conſtant practice. He would come into the houſe of God, and, in his fear, worſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his holy temple. He would, with holy boldneſs and confidence, appear in the preſence of God. "I will come into thy houſe,"—meaning the tabernacle, from which, probably, he might at this time be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the rage and malice of his adverſaries. Yet he had a confident expectation, that, through the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and mercy of God, the obſtacles of hindrance would ſhortly be removed, and the way opened for his worſhipping him according to his appointment, as he heretofore had done in his houſe, or tabernacle. And
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:031240_0005_0FEAF91BB8EEAD30"/>
when thus permitted, he would do it in the fear of God. "In thy fear, ſaith he, will I worſhip toward thy holy temple;" that is, the tabernacle, which in Scripture is ſometimes called by that name; for the temple was not at this time built. Though deprived of the agreeable and delightful ſatisfaction of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in the tabernacle, yet he ſhould ever bear it upon his mind; nay, it could not be eaſily eradicated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from. Though his troubles were many and diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, yet they would not do this. In the fear of God, he would worſhip towards the temple of his holineſs. He was a ſteady ſeeker of God. He maintained a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courſe of ſecret worſhip, as well as made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of attending the public inſtitutions of religion. He frequently prayed by himſelf alone; and in this way he poured out his ſoul before the Lord, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon the continued practice of this important duty; as evidently appears by what he ſays in the context: "My voice ſhalt thou hear in the morning, O Lord; in the morning will I direct my prayer unto thee, and will look up." He made it his buſineſs, as well as his delight, to improve all opportunities of waiting on God in his more public inſtituted worſhip: yea, it was to his great comfort and ſatisfaction, when he was permitted to worſhip God in his ſanctuary, in concert with his people. He was rejoiced at ſuch ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and it was to his great grief when deprived thereof; as appears in divers paſſages in the Pſalms, particularly 122d and 42d. "I was glad when they ſaid unto me, Let us go into the houſe of the Lord." "As the hart panteth after the water-brooks, ſo pant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my ſoul after thee, O God. My ſoul thirſteth
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:031240_0006_0FEB80561A1523A8"/>
for God, for the living God: when ſhall I come and appear before God? My tears have been my meat, day and night, while they continually ſay unto me, Where is thy God? When I remember theſe things, I pour out my ſoul in me: for I had gone with the multitude; I went with them to the houſe of God; with the voice of joy and praiſe, with a multitude that kept holy day." And we have, in the text, his determined reſolution to worſhip God in ſuch ways as Providence might permit, let others do as they would, either by contemning or neglecting the worſhip of the only living and, true God. And this he would do in the fear of God.</p>
                  <p>Hence we may be led, from the pious reſolution of the Pſalmiſt, to conſider, That it is the duty of the people of God, let others do what they will, reſolved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to come into his houſe, in the multitude of his mercy, and in the fear of God, worſhip in his holy temple.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt</hi>—It is the duty of the people of God, reſolved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the multitude of his mercy, to come into his houſe and worſhip him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly</hi>—When they thus do, it is to be done in the fear of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt</hi>—It is the duty of the people of God, reſolved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the multitude, or by the greatneſs of his mercy, to come into his houſe and worſhip him. It is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the people of God, in ſpecial, to worſhip him. Upon this they are to reſolve. Indeed it is the duty of all, indiſcriminately to worſhip him, according to
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:031240_0007_0FEB8057A26CAAF8"/>
their ability, and the knowledge they have of God and their duty. This is what God requires of them. Hence the pſalmiſt, in the 67th pſalm, ſays, "Let the people praiſe thee, O God. Let all the people praiſe thee." All are under obligation to worſhip God. For this end they were made. They were made for the glory and ſervice of God. Were not made for themſelves; to live to, and ſerve themſelves; but were made to ſerve God, to worſhip and glorify him, according to the directions given in his word; to live lives devoted to his fear and to his glory. Though it is far otherwiſe with multitudes of the human race. They bow down to ſtocks and ſtones, pay adoration to them which are no Gods, and acknowledge the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of mercies to thoſe who have no power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow them. What vaſt multitudes are there in a ſtate of heatheniſh darkneſs, idolatry and ſuperſtition, and who are periſhing for lack of viſion! It is obvious that there are none but what are under obligation to worſhip God; ſince he is their Creator from whom they receive their being, and it is he who preſerves and upholds them in life and being. Hence Job ſays, "Thou haſt granted me life and favour, and thy viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation hath preſerved my ſpirit." His hands have made and faſhioned theſe bodies of ours, and they are fearfully and wonderfully made. He breathed into us the breath of life; made us living ſouls; endowed us with rational powers and faculties; teacheth us more than the beaſts of the earth, and maketh us wiſer than the fowls of heaven."</p>
                  <p>Again; He is not only our Creator, but our kind and bountiful Benefactor. All that we have, we pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily receive from him. That which is neceſſary to
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:031240_0008_0FEB805AF385E548"/>
preſerve life, and all the bleſſings, comforts and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of life, that we are made the happy partakers of, come from him, the great Author of all things. All, good and bad, ſaints and ſinners, are dependent on him for the common bounties of his providence, and are all ſharers in them. He maketh his ſun to riſe on the evil and on the good, and ſendeth rain on the juſt and on the unjuſt. So, all ſpiritual bleſſings which any are made to enjoy, flow down to them from the Father of Lights and of Mercies. Hence the apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle James ſays, "Every good gift, and every perfect gift is from above, and cometh down from the Father of Lights, with whom is no variableneſs, neither ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ow of turning." Now, ſurely, He who hath made us, and continues us in life, and furniſhes us with the bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and comforts of life, has a ſpecial right, yea, has the ſole right to us and our ſervices. All religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, homage, adoration and praiſe is to be aſcribed to Him alone, as his due; and this through Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of God. And he is highly diſpleaſed if it be given to another. Says he,—Iſaiah xlii.8. "I am the Lord, that is my name; and my glory will I not give to another, neither my praiſe to graven im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages." Theſe things conſidered, it plainly appears that all are under obligation to worſhip God; to pay all religious worſhip and ſervice to him. And what he requires of them in this, as well as every thing elſe, is juſt and reaſonable; for he requires nothing of any of his intelligent creatures but what is juſt. To do otherwiſe would be inconſiſtent with his holineſs and the purity of his nature; with that juſtice and equity which runs through the whole of the adminiſtration of the divine government.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="unknown:031240_0009_0FEB805C854FB9D8"/>It is the duty of all, indiſcriminately, to worſhip God, who is the ſupreme Ruler and Governor of the univerſe. Much more ſo, then, is it the duty of ſuch as live in a land of Goſpel light and knowledge, that are favoured with the word and ordinances of the Lord, and have the knowledge of his mind and will plainly revealed in the word of truth. The law, word and ordinances of God are the diſtinguiſhing privilege of thoſe who live in a land of Goſpel light. "He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good, and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?" But, more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, God's choſen, covenant people are under pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar obligations, yea, the ſtrongeſt ties, to worſhip him. For they are his, not only by right of creation, but by purchaſe, by right of redemption. All that do or ſhall believe in Chriſt, to the world's end, are the purchaſe of his blood. With this he has bought them: And this is the argument which the apoſtle uſeth with the believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Corinthians, to glorify God with their bodies and their ſpirits which are his. As in 1 Cor. vi.19, 20. "What, know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghoſt, which is in you, which ye have of God, and ye are not your own! For ye are bought with a price; therefore glorify God in your body, and in your ſpirit, which are God's." What this price is, the apoſtle Peter tells us, both negatively and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively. "Foraſmuch as ye know that ye were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, not with corruptible things, as ſilver and gold, from your vain converſation, received by tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from your fathers, but with the precious blood of Chriſt, as of a lamb without blemiſh, and without ſpot." Surely then, ſuch as are thus redeemed, are
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:031240_0010_0FEB806306004528"/>
under peculiar obligations to devote their time, talents and lives to the ſervice of God. Yea, their all is to be devoted to him. They ſhould have an eye to his glory in all they do. Hence that exhortation, 1 Cor. x.31. "Whether therefore ye eat or drink, or whatſoever ye do, do all to the glory of God." They ſhould give unto the Lord the glory due unto his name, according to the exhortation, pſalm xxix.2. "And worſhip the Lord in the beauty of holineſs."</p>
                  <p>It may here be obſerved that reſolution is neceſſary to the worſhip and ſervice of God: and this is eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial in that which is private, ſocial, and public. Reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olution will overcome many, and ſometimes great obſtacles. This we ſee it will often do in the common affairs and concerns of life, eſpecially where ſelf-inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt lies at ſtake: Should it not much more be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed by us, in things of a higher nature, that concern our beſt intereſt, even our ſouls' ſalvation, as the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and kingdom of God moſt certainly does?</p>
                  <p>The honour and glory of God moſt nearly and highly concerns every one: For whatever they do for his glory and honour will finally redound to their own ſaving advantage. Whatever they do for him will not go unnoticed or unrewarded by him. Even he that gives to a diſciple, in the name of a diſciple, a cup of cold water, we are aſſured ſhall not loſe his reward. This is the declaration of our Lord and Maſter. Matt. x.40. and the two laſt verſes. "He that receiveth you, receiveth me; and he that receiveth me, receiveth him that ſent me. He that receiveth a prophet, in the name of a prophet, ſhall receive a prophet's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: And he that receiveth a righteous man, in the
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:031240_0011_0FEB80648BE21570"/>
name of a righteous man, ſhall receive a righteous man's reward. And whoſoever ſhall give to drink unto one of theſe little ones, a cup of cold water only, in the name of a diſciple, verily, I ſay unto you, he ſhall in no wiſe loſe his reward." But then where love is wanting to God and his worſhip, his ſervice will not be delightful, but tedious or irkſome. It is therefore highly neceſſary that we have true love to God; otherwiſe we ſhall not have any real delight or ſatisfaction in his worſhip or ſervice. Love will excite to reſolution and diligence in the duties of Chriſtianity. Want of reſolution is undoubtedly one great reaſon why there is ſuch neglect in the worſhip and ſervice of God. Love to him, and reſolution in his ſervice will have a happy tendency to check ſloth and negligence herein: Yea, it will ſurmount many and great obſtacles. Good reaſon then is there that the worſhip and ſervice of God ſhould be ſeriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon by his people. Thus we find Joſhua re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving, not only for himſelf, but his houſe and family, that they would ſerve the Lord. It is a happy choice they make who ſincerely chooſe the ſervice and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God. Like unto this is the pſalmiſt's reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the text, that he would worſhip God. Though others neglected temple worſhip, yet he would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove all opportunities that preſented for his going into the houſe of the Lord, and worſhipping him in the way of his own appointment. "But as for me, I will come into thy houſe, in the multitude of thy mercy, and in thy fear will I worſhip toward thy holy temple."</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="unknown:031240_0012_0FEB8067B2783E08"/>It is the duty of the people of God to worſhip him publickly; not only in ſecret and in their families, but in his houſe; eſpecially upon his Sabbaths or holy days. Hence God ſays to the children of Iſrael, "Ye ſhall keep my Sabbaths and reverence my ſanctuary: I am the Lord." It is the appointment of God that they ſhould do ſo; and it has been the practice of his people, in all ages of the world. It was David's reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to come into the houſe of the Lord, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip there, with others of his faithful worſhippers. And this he would do in the multitude of God's mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; or <hi>by thy great mercy,</hi> as ſome render it: that is, truſting only to thy great mercy for admittance thith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and acceptance there: or for, or becauſe of thy many mercies to me; for which I will come to pay my thanks and ſervice unto thee. Though frequently it was ſo with him that he was not permitted to enjoy this bleſſed privilege, of meeting with the people of God at his houſe, and worſhipping him there, yet his heart and mind was there; and it was always to his great grief, when deprived of temple worſhip. And it always rejoiced his heart when he was favoured with an opportunity for ſeeing the going of his God and King in his ſanctuary. He could ſay, in the ſincerity of his heart, as in Pſalm xxvi.8. "Lord, I have loved the habitation of thy houſe, and the place where thine honour dwelleth."</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly</hi>—It is the duty of the people of God to worſhip him in fear. We are to attend upon divine inſtitutions with that ſeriouſneſs and ſolemnity that becomes us; are to do it in the manner that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires: And this muſt needs be with reverence and
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:031240_0013_0FEB806ADE486930"/>
with godly fear: with ſuitable apprehenſions of his divine excellence and perfection. We ſhould with becoming ſeriouſneſs conſider, into whoſe preſence it is that we come, when we enter the houſe of God, to worſhip: For it is no leſs than into the preſence of the great heart-ſearching and rein-trying God, before whom we muſt all, in the great day, in the day of judgment, appear, and render up an account, each one for himſelf, of the deeds done in the body. If our minds are duly impreſſed with a ſenſe of this, we ſhall be likely to be awed into a holy fear and reverence of God, when we come into his houſe, and attend upon his public, inſtituted worſhip. Is it the duty of all perſons to worſhip God, not only privately but pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly? let none then allowedly and contentedly live in the neglect of the one or the other. What God requires of us, as duty, is highly reaſonable: And it will be to our own advantage, if we attend hereunto in the manner required. And this muſt be done in ſpirit and in truth, if we would hope to be accepted of God. Thus we read, John iv.24. "God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and truth." And as to the public, inſtituted worſhip of God, it becomes all, but eſpecially Chriſtians, to endeavour after-ſuch a pious diſpoſition and ſpirit as David had. They ſhould, as he did, manifeſt a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere regard for the worſhip of God in his houſe.</p>
                  <p>It is to be hoped, there are many that are really of his diſpoſition, whoſe local ſituation and circumſtances are ſuch as render it impracticable, with frequency, to attend upon the ſtated public worſhip of God, in his houſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="unknown:031240_0014_0FEB806FAB9A2F88"/>This has been the caſe with you, my hearers, in this part of the town, and your anceſtors before you. But the proſpect is now brightening, as to you and yours. You, not long ſince, requeſted of the Congregational Society in this town, of which you are members, that public worſhip might be held, a proportion of the time, in this part of it. They looked upon your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt reaſonable; and, as I doubt not, having in their minds the injunction of our Lord and Maſter, "What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them," have complied with it. Be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the praiſe of the Society, that this affair has been conducted with ſuch brotherly love, and Chriſtian har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. Notwithſtanding what has taken place, we look upon ourſelves to be all brethren, and of one and the ſame Society. Let not Paſtor or People be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their endeavours ſtill to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. As to the erecting of this Edifice, you that have been more particularly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in it, have, with much aſſiduity and unanimity, gone through with it. But, alas! while in the midſt of it, a gloom overſpread you and us of this town, in the ſudden removal by death of a principal proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. ISAIAH BAKER, who died September 25th, Aet. 56. He was juſtly eſteemed as an upright, ſerious and charitable man.</note> and a reſpectable, uſeful member of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity. There is his urn! We would drop a tear over it, for ourſelves, and for the bereaved widow and orphan children.</p>
                  <p>You will now conſider, my friends, that you have an additional price put into your hands. I mean eſpecially, that you will have the privilege, more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently,
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:031240_0015_0FEB807133C8D218"/>
of worſhipping God in his houſe than hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: And many that could not do it at all, may be in circumſtances to do it now. I truſt you will not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs of the privilege. And as to this houſe of worſhip, as well as the other, <hi>may it be ſaid of this and that man, he was born there.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In a word, let us all manifeſt our ſincere regard to the word, worſhip, and ordinances of the Lord, by a ſteady and conſcientious attendance on them:—and may we be ſo happy at laſt, as to meet in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that is above.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="unknown:031240_0016_0FEB807606086730"/>
                  <p>Public Worſhip conſidered and recommended. A SERMON, DELIVERED AT DENNIS, DECEMBER 17, 1795, AT THE OPENING OF A NEW MEETING-HOUSE. BY NATHAN UNDERWOOD, A. M. PASTOR OF THE SOUTH CHURCH IN HARWICH. Publiſhed by deſire of the <hi>HEARERS.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>PRINTED AT BOSTON, BY MANNING &amp; LORING, SPRING-LANE. FEB. 1796.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="unknown:031240_0017_0FEB80778BD22F20"/>
                  <head>A SERMON.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>PSALM xxvii.4.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>One thing have I deſired of the Lord, that will I ſeek after; that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the days of my life, to behold the beauty of the Lord, and to inquire in his temple.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> SENSE of Deity and duty is deeply impreſſed upon the minds of men. The ſtill voice of reaſon, and the more powerful ſuggeſtions of conſcience, with one voice teach us the exiſtence of a God, whoſe being and perfections deſervedly merit the attention of his creatures. There is not a creature which moves, or a plant which grows, but declares the hand which made it to be divine. How much more the intelligent part of creation, who are admoniſhed by all, within and without, to worſhip and venerate their great Creator? The erection of this magnificent Building, and our aſſembling therein to Dedicate it unto God, is a proof alſo that we acknowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edge
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:031240_0018_0FEB807C611E5138"/>
a Being whoſe ſovereignty and dominion it well becomes us to reverence and adore. Theſe truths were too ſtrongly imprinted upon the heart of the pſalmiſt to be eraſed either by the burdens of royalty or the equipage of a ſplendid court. He thought it well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him to regard the great Lord of nature, and on many occaſions, as in the words of the text, expreſſes his affection for public worſhip and deſire to "dwell in the houſe of the Lord, and to inquire in his temple."</p>
                  <p>"One thing have I deſired of the Lord, that will I ſeek after; that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the days of my life, to behold the beauty of the Lord, and to inquire in his temple." It is obvious that the paſſage before us is not (but in part) to be literally underſtood. He does not mean to make his abode in places dedicated to God and ſacred for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic worſhip; but an habitual ſenſe which he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of the great duty and importance of frequently aſſembling there;—at all ſtated ſeaſons and convenient opportunities, not only to have his affections, but his preſence there. To "behold the beauty of the Lord" in order to inflame his devotion, and to "inquire in his temple" that ſo he might learn to do his will. In this view, the words before us are applicable to the preſent occaſion. Well does it become us devoutly to attend and imitate the example of the pious pſalm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt. It will readily be acknowledged that public wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip has been abuſed; that many, it is to be feared, frequent the houſe of God from ſiniſter views; and appear to poſſeſs the form without the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But this can be no apology for others to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw; for certain it is, the example of one ſinner can
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:031240_0019_0FEB807DE6CCDC80"/>
never juſtify another; and that where no form of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion appears, the power is not to be expected. To prove therefore the utility and importance of public worſhip is the deſign of the preſent Diſcourſe: and ſince there is an immediate connexion between the means and the end, it muſt be of conſequence to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the former, in order to obtain the latter.</p>
                  <p>Hence in the firſt place, let us conſider it with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to God. If there be a God who created the world, and ſtill continues his agency and protection, nothing can be more reaſonable and natural than that thoſe who ſubſiſt on his bounty, and are governed by his providence, ſhould ſuitably expreſs their gratitude and praiſe to the Giver of all good. But beſides the private bleſſings we enjoy, and which merit a grateful return, there are numerous favours which we receive in common with others, and which juſtly claim the united thanks of all, and the moſt public expreſſions of gratitude to our common Lord. So conſonant is this to the common ſentiments of mankind, that the moſt uncivilized and barbarous of the human race have ever agreed in eſtabliſhing ſome form of worſhip, and erecting ſome altars, whereunto they might repair in common, and pour forth public expreſſions of grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to their pretended deities. It muſt therefore be evident, that a principle of worſhip is deeply engraven upon the hearts of men. And herein, my friends, conſiſteth the peculiar excellence of the Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, in that it hath inſtructed us in the ſimple and ſpiritual worſhip of our God; which, diſencumbered of rites and unmeaning ceremonies, is worthy its di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Author; its poſitive inſtitutions few and eaſy, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:031240_0020_0FEB808165ABFB60"/>
tending to the good of ſociety and refining the morals and manners of men. How inexcuſeable then ſhall we be, who enjoy ſuperior advantages, if we ſuffer ourſelves to neglect a duty which the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens ſo punctually obſerved!</p>
                  <p>It is true, the refinement of falſe philoſophy has ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted the abſurdity of paying homage to a Being far exalted above all praiſe; whoſe eſſential glory and happineſs can neither be augmented nor diminiſhed by his creatures; yet let me aſk, whether the benefits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from a benefactor in any degree diminiſh the debt of gratitude and praiſe to him, in conſequence of our inability to make an adequate return? or not rather increaſe every ingenuous feeling, and prompt us to embrace every opportunity of publickly expreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the pure emotions of a grateful heart? God is doubtleſs too great to need our homage; yet is he too good not to accept it, when poured forth from a grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful heart, and is the native effuſion of a pure mind? If pride and ſelf-ſufficiency blind all ſentiments of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence upon God, no wonder if we adopt the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of falſe philoſophy; but if we conſider him as he is, our Father and Friend, muſt it not be accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to him to behold his creatures ſuitably affected towards their Benefactor? aſſembling together to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their gratitude in common, and thereby nouriſh and increaſe the general ſtock of benevolence and love? Are not ſuch diſpoſitions and affections as theſe immediately connected with all virtue? naturally tending to impreſs us with a ſenſe of our dependence, increaſe our reverence and gratitude towards God, and charity and good-will towards his creatures?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="7" facs="unknown:031240_0021_0FEB8084A05F3758"/>
                     <hi>Secondly.</hi> If we conſider public worſhip as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects ſociety, we ſhall there alſo doubtleſs find it of great importance. Whereever we turn our eyes, we behold a buſy world; immerſed in the things of time and ſenſe, making proviſion for the preſent life; and were it not for ſtated ſeaſons of worſhipping God, and thus calling off their attention from worldly purſuits, we have reaſon to believe that a ſenſe of duty and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity would be in a meaſure eraſed from the mind. If it be of conſequence to the well-being of ſociety that ſuch a belief ſhould prevail, as an Almighty Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the heavens, who ſurveys and governs all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; from whom none can eſcape, and to whom the moſt ſecret ſins muſt be accounted for; that he is a protector of the righteous, and a revenger of crimes; if it be neceſſary that the thoughts of men be raiſed and carried forward to the day of judgment; ſurely then it muſt enforce the authority of public worſhip, and prove the neceſſity of public inſtruction: Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind being doomed to labour, and ſo early engaged therein, that were it not for thoſe public reſorts where they hear of GOD and CHRIST, of judgment and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, they would doubtleſs fail in moral improvement, ſociability and friendſhip. Shut thoſe temples in which they aſſemble for religious inſtruction and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement, and a declenſion of religion, of morals and manners, would probably ſoon appear. And as a ſenſe of Deity and a future judgment were loſt upon the mind, they would be prone to every outrage which they could commit with impunity.</p>
                  <p>It is well known that in the earlier ages of the world legiſlators were obliged to have recourſe to religion, in order to aſſociate their ſubjects and give a ſanction to
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:031240_0022_0FEB808973324708"/>
their laws. Thus bringing them together at ſtated times to unite in acts of worſhip, gradually tended to civilize the mind, cement the affections, and reduce them to order. And even at the preſent day, excluſive of any effect upon the moral principle, it is not to be doubted but aſſembling together contributes greatly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote order and decency, as well as charity and good affections. At the ſame time it muſt be agreeable to every humane mind to think that one day in ſeven is allotted for reſt, and to join with others of the ſame mortal ſtock in devout meditation, and the reverential worſhip of their common Lord. It is the only time which gives inferiors to feel an equality with the great. When worſhipping in the ſame temple, and acknowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edging the ſame common Parent, then it is that man meets man as a brother; that he is led to realize that as the preſent day is, ſo alſo ſhall be the future; that one day they ſhall ſleep together undiſtinguiſhed in the grave, and alike moulder into duſt; that the ſame Almighty Sovereign ſhall receive their ſpirits, and judge them by their works! Such reflections as theſe tend to humble the pride of man; and thus by reduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to a level with man, he thinks as a man, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts as a Chriſtian, and thereby ſecures and promotes the good of ſociety. But I proceed,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly</hi>—To conſider public worſhip as it reſpects individuals. And here we ſhall find alſo its utility and importance no leſs than in the former caſe. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever be the ſtation of individuals, they are ſtill men, and as ſuch have the duties of a man to perform. Were their attendance on public worſhip of no other ſervice than to give ſanction to a ſalutary inſtitution, this alone would make it their duty. But this is not
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:031240_0023_0FEB808AFB6B0F40"/>
all. If it be neceſſary for man to preſerve and increaſe his own ſtock of virtue, it muſt be of conſequence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own account. It cannot be denied but attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on public ordinances naturally tends to call off men's attention from the world, and to ſolemnize the mind. And ſo far as the impreſſions are good, ſo far its uſe and importance muſt be confeſſed.</p>
                  <p>All Chriſtian inſtitutions have a tendency to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote virtue. They ſerve to give warmth to piety, luſtre to virtue, and dignity to man. Hence theſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional retreats from the cares and anxieties of life give opportunity for better thoughts to ariſe. The body is hereby refreſhed, the faculties of the mind en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livened, and both enabled to perform their functions with greater activity and ſucceſs.</p>
                  <p>But perhaps here it may be urged with too much truth, Are there not many who are punctual in their attendance upon public ordinances, and appear to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive no benefit from them? Are they more improved in their moral conduct, and the diſcharge of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon duties of life, than others who have apparently neglected the ſervices of the church?</p>
                  <p>To which I anſwer; Should this argument be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it can prove no more than that human weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and corruption may defeat the beſt purpoſes and moſt promiſing means for moral improvement. Doubtleſs the greateſt bleſſings conferred upon men may be abuſed, and by perverſeneſs converted into evil. But ſhall we neglect the ſervice of the ſanctuary becauſe we have not diſcovered in others all that good effect which we wiſhed or expected? Shall we refuſe proper nouriſhment to the body becauſe others have indulged to exceſs? But though we cannot diſcover
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:031240_0024_0FEB808E790146E8"/>
every deſired effect, it were preſumption to conclude that no good is effected; ſince it is utterly impoſſible accurately to determine how perverſe they would oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erwiſe have been. It is doubtleſs a juſt remark, that the manners as well as the morals of men keep pace with their religious improvements. Where public worſhip is neglected, factions generally ſpring up; and with great ſimilarity in morals and manners ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit the melancholy picture which Solomon deſcribes by the field of the ſlothful. "I went by the field of the ſlothful, and by the vineyard of the man void of underſtanding, and lo it was all grown over with thorns; and nettles had covered the face thereof, and the ſtone wall thereof was broken down. Then I ſaw and conſidered it well; I looked upon it, and received inſtruction." It is not to be doubted but attention to public worſhip tends to check licentiouſneſs of thought; and that ſome aſſiſtance is always afforded to good diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. Even momentary impreſſions of ſerious med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itation are not without their fruit. They generally leave ſome traces of good behind; and being fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently repeated by religious acts of worſhip, we have reaſon to hope, through divine grace, will make laſting impreſſions upon the mind.</p>
                  <p>But as our aſſembling together in the houſe of God is for the purpoſes of ſocial worſhip, and to hear re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious inſtruction, we ought to remember with what frame of mind it becomes us to attend. It is not the form of worſhip or pretended ſanctity of men which God regards; but the devout worſhipper, the humble mind and ſincere heart. By the inattentive thought and wandering eye we profane the temple of the Lord. And while with irreverence and inattention we join in
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:031240_0025_0FEB8091AA679F10"/>
the ſolemnities of worſhip, we diſhonour God and fruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate the ends for which we ought to aſſemble. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious knowledge then fails, and the conſequence is, we return more guilty than we went. All religious knowledge comes from God. It is a light from heav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, which becomes us with ſeriouſneſs to acknowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edge and regard. When we enter the houſe of God to inquire in his temple, then it is in a more eſpecial manner he expects from us an attentive ear and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right heart; to hear and apply the important truths of the goſpel, as well knowing by the contents thereof we muſt be tried another day. But too often it is to be feared we aſſemble with other views; either in conformity to common cuſtom, or to criticiſe upon the preacher. But theſe diſpoſitions are both deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to man and the ſolemnity of the place. It is with humility and candour, a deſire to apply and improve, which ought to induce us to hear the word of God. Whenever therefore we enter the ſacred temple, let us conſider ourſelves as creatures ſurrounded with darkneſs, ſeeking illumination from the Father of lights; as guilty creatures, imploring forgiveneſs from our Judge; as frail and dying creatures, preparing for that eternal ſtate into which we know not how ſoon we may enter. If with ſuch ſentiments and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions we attend the worſhip and ordinances of God, we may comfortably hope, through the merits of Chriſt, to join hereafter the nobler ſociety of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers in the heavens.</p>
                  <p>But before I conclude, it may not be improper to addreſs the Proprietors and Worſhippers of this place. Your pious zeal for the worſhip of your Maker does you immortal honour! Your union and perſeverance for eſtabliſhing the ordinances of God among you,
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:031240_0026_0FEB8094D9E82BF0"/>
and the erection of this magnificent Temple for that purpoſe, juſtly merit our commendation. And as you have this day Dedicated it unto God, let it alſo be your care to devote yourſelves to his worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. You have heard ſomething of the uſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of public worſhip, as alſo of the frame of mind with which it becomes you to attend; and we would charitably hope, from your laudable exertions, you can cheerfully adopt, with much ſincerity of ſoul, the language of the text: "One thing have I deſired of the Lord, that will I ſeek after; that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the days of my life, to behold the beauty of the Lord, and to inquire in his temple." If this be the language of your hearts, happy are ye; and while you continue it, happy ſhall you be. While you thus attend the worſhip of your God, you have nothing to fear; for he hath never ſaid to any of the children of men, Seek ye me in vain.<note n="*" place="bottom">Iſai. xlv.19.</note> But that he loveth the gates of Zion more than all the dwellings of Jacob;<note n="†" place="bottom">Pſalm lxxxviii.2.</note> and that the prayer of the upright is his delight. Our Saviour alſo hath aſſured us, that where two or three are gathered together in his name, that he is in the midſt of them.<note n="‡" place="bottom">Matt. xviii.20.</note> Let there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the word of God be your comfort and your guide. Enter his gates with thankſgiving, and his courts with praiſe, delighting yourſelves to inquire in his temple.</p>
                  <p>But while we exhort you to the practice of your duty, we cannot forbear to drop with you the friendly tear! The loſs you have ſuſtained by the death of a benefactor you doubtleſs feel.<note n="§" place="bottom">Mr. ISAIAH BAKER, a principal proprietor in the houſe, died before it was finiſhed, and was the firſt buried there. A man of large property, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſive charity and a public ſpirit.</note> His pious zeal for
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:031240_0027_0FEB809A025B4580"/>
the glory of God, and the perfecting of this Houſe, ought to endear him to your memory; and though not permitted to join us here in acts of worſhip and devotion, we humbly truſt he is now on high, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God in purer ſtrains! May his virtues long live, as a comfort and example for ſurviving friends. May his death admoniſh you that you are alſo mortal; cement your union; ſtrengthen the bonds of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and animate you in your Chriſtian courſe.</p>
                  <p>A word to this Aſſembly ſhall finiſh the Diſcourſe. And how ſhall I ſpeak? For to ſome of you I ſhall doubtleſs ſpeak no more! You as well as I, are can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didates for a future exiſtence! travellers for a day to an eternal home, and know not how ſoon you may arrive there. On the rapid wings of time you are now paſſing, and very ſoon with ſome of you the ſcene will be ſhifted! Very ſoon, from worſhipping God here below, you may be ſummoned to meet him in the heav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, to give account of your pilgrimage on the earth! Here you have no continuing city nor ſure abiding place; but are ſeeking one to come, whoſe builder and maker is God. Does not reaſon and revelation admoniſh you of theſe ſolemn truths, and every thing around you ſolemnize the call? Our fathers! where are they? and the prophets, do they live forever? Long ſince have they obeyed the ſummons, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon their reward! And in a little time, as they have done, we alſo muſt quit the ſtage, and leave our places to ſucceeding pilgrims! Does it not therefore concern you, as rational and accountable beings, to meditate upon and apply the truths which have been ſuggeſted? Is it a ſmall thing to diſregard religion, and anſwer it to your Maker? To neglect divine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:031240_0028_0FEB809B88E148F0"/>
and the worſhip of the ſanctuary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when every thing which concerns you as men is built upon it? Succeſs in the preſent world, peace of mind, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in the next, are through Jeſus Chriſt the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral fruit of obedient lives. Means are in order to the end. If then a bleſſed immortality be the object of your purſuit, conſider now in time the part which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes you to act. If with this view you deſire to dwell in the houſe of the Lord and to inquire in his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that ſo you may know his will and your duty, "keep thy foot when thou comeſt thither." Hear as for your life, remembering the omniſcience of God, and the ſolemn account you muſt one day give of your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to him!</p>
                  <p>May the almighty Spirit of God dwell richly in your hearts, and guide you in the way of all truth. And though I muſt now bid you adieu, as probably to join no more in acts of worſhip and devotion upon the earth, yet, guided by light and truth through this wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of life, may we meet again in the heavenly Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, to worſhip our common Lord in nobler ſtrains. And may the day ſoon dawn when "all ſhall worſhip the Father in ſpirit and in truth;" when the kingdoms of the world ſhall become the kingdoms of our Lord, and the whole earth be filled with his glory.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
