<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An oration, on the propriety of introducing the science of jurisprudence into a course of classical education. Pronounced in the Baptist Meeting-House in Providence, at the anniversary commencement of Rhode-Island College, September 6th, A.D. 1797. / By Samuel W. Bridgham, a candidate for the degree of Master in the Arts. ; Published at the request of the students.</title>
            <author>Bridgham, Samuel W. (Samuel Willard), 1774-1840.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N24094</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N24094</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 31865</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX4752</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">31865</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99021531</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 31865.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N24094)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 31865)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 31865)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An oration, on the propriety of introducing the science of jurisprudence into a course of classical education. Pronounced in the Baptist Meeting-House in Providence, at the anniversary commencement of Rhode-Island College, September 6th, A.D. 1797. / By Samuel W. Bridgham, a candidate for the degree of Master in the Arts. ; Published at the request of the students.</title>
                  <author>Bridgham, Samuel W. (Samuel Willard), 1774-1840.</author>
                  <author>Rhode Island College (1764-1804).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p. ;  23 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Carter and Wilkinson.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Providence: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M,DCC,XCVII. [1797]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jurisprudence.</term>
               <term>Law --  Study and teaching.</term>
               <term>Baccalaureate addresses --  1797.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:031865_0000_0FEEF340716566A8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:031865_0001_0FEEF34203061410"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ORATION, ON THE PROPRIETY OF INTRODUCING THE SCIENCE OF JURISPRUDENCE INTO A COURSE OF CLASSICAL EDUCATION. PRONOUNCED IN THE BAPTIST MEETING-HOUSE, IN PROVIDENCE, AT THE ANNIVERSARY COMMENCEMENT OF RHODE-ISLAND COLLEGE, <hi>SEPTEMBER</hi> 6th, <hi>A. D.</hi> 1797.</p>
            <p>BY SAMUEL W. BRIDGHAM, A CANDIDATE FOR THE DEGREE OF MASTER IN THE ARTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PUBLISHED AT THE REQUEST OF THE STUDENTS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>PROVIDENCE:</hi> Printed by <hi>CARTER</hi> and <hi>WILKINSON.</hi> M,DCC,XCVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="unknown:031865_0002_0FEEF344C9863798"/>
            <head>AN ORATION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>That a Science which is univerſal in its uſe and extent, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to each individual, yet comprehending the whole community, ſhould ever have been deemed unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be ſtudied in an Univerſity, is a matter of aſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment and concern.</p>
                  <bibl>BLACKSTONE.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>MAN's knowledge is circumſcribed not only by the limitation of his faculties, but alſo by that of his exiſtence. Perfection being unat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable, a reſolution to arrive at the happy ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of univerſal knowledge, would be as prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous as an attempt to arreſt the ſun in his rapid progreſs through the ſkies. Into what path then is man, that offspring of imperfection, that child of error, to be conducted? Let him, in his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits after knowledge, be allured to thoſe branches only which have moſt for their object his own happineſs, connected with that greater good, the good of ſociety. Learning is the moſt precious jewel; and could I add, without being charged with partiality for a favourite ſtudy, I would ſay, that no learning is ſo excellent for all degrees of
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:031865_0003_0FEEF3475A783308"/>
men as a knowledge of laws, and the principles of legiſlation.</p>
            <p>Univerſal diffuſion of legal information beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies and adorns Juſtice with all her ſplendid ſuit: it preſents her in an attitude ſo divine, that I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the ancients who worſhiped her as a goddeſs. To the honeſt induſtrious yeoman-citizens it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords a ſhield of protection againſt the ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations of fraud, and the bold attacks of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levolence.</p>
            <p>Although eccleſiaſtical and civil authority ſhould never be blended together, yet our <hi>Reverend Teachers of Holy Things</hi> ought not to be unſkilled in the ſcience of juriſprudence. Their duty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in holding up the mirror to the face of man, to reflect his weakneſſes, his follies, his imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and vices; to teach him obedience to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtitutions and civil authority. If the whole duty of man is to be laid before him by his ſpirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual guides, the more extenſive and univerſal their knowledge, the more uſeful will their inſtructions be to all claſſes of hearers.</p>
            <p>To judges and jurors the knowledge of juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence is of ſuperlative concern. Shall man's deareſt intereſts be adjudged by ignorance, by prejudice, and by paſſion? The wiſdom of ages, improved and collected in thoſe maſſy volumes of Engliſh juriſprudence, requires a laborious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtigation, to empower the judges to merit the epithet and maintain the dignity of the fathers of the rights of the people.</p>
            <p>Ill fated and deplorable is the condition of that country, whoſe legiſlators are ignorant. Their duty conſiſts in expounding, modelling and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating laws. To maintain the propoſitions, that man can explain ſtatutes he knows nothing about, can comment upon texts of which he is totally
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:031865_0004_0FEEF34ED9A73ED8"/>
ignorant, or can remedy defects in laws of which he has no knowledge, is prepoſterous in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme. As well might the unſkilled in mechanics undertake to amend the defects in a complicated machine, or the untutored barbarian to enucleate thoſe mighty wonders which decorate and adorn the vaſt amphitheatre of nature. A wiſe legiſlator is therefore a bright luminary to his country, and merits univerſal applauſe. His path is decorated with flowers, and leads to glory. Every man is his enemy, and his country's too, who would rob him of his wreaths, or tarniſh his honour.</p>
            <p>Wherever the principles of legiſlation are well underſtood, political jealouſy and diſcontent are unknown or ſilenced. In every change of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from deſpotiſm to freedom, and in every improvement of law from barbarous rigour to poliſhed mildneſs, ignorant citizens and blind legiſlators revolt againſt meaſures ſuggeſted by wiſdom, and which eventually prove glorious and triumphant.</p>
            <p>At the eſtabliſhment of the federal conſtitution of the United States, ſome ignorant Americans, through blindneſs, felt all the horrors to be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended from internal agitation and civil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion: yet how glorious has that inſtitution proved—and how cordially do they now acquieſce in the ſyſtem they ſo bitterly condemned.</p>
            <p>The feudal ſyſtem in England has been repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as a diſgrace to its hiſtory. But if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the nature of Engliſh juriſprudence, our thoughts will bring home to our minds convic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the feudal ſyſtem is the grand baſis of that ſtupendous fabric: that it is the rock on which the wiſe men of the world have builded, and the ſtorms and tempeſts have beaten upon the ſuperſtructure, and it has not yet fallen. There
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:031865_0005_0FEEF34AB3D082D8"/>
were doubtleſs many evils in this ſyſtem, but they were ſuch as were not to have been prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the early age of the world. A pure Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can-like government could not have been hoped for in that period, when the ſavage foot roamed o'er half creation, and nature bluſhed at the dawn of ſcience. The policy of the times would not admit of that ſpirit of liberty which now ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates the republican. Let us not then be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded: let the natural light which is within us ſhine with its full luſtre: let charity, that celeſtial ſpark, that emanation of divinity, irradiate and ſublime our ſouls: no longer let the dictates of ſound policy be execrated, or magnanimous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits ſtigmatized, by the enemies of man, or by miſguided zealots.</p>
            <p>Let theſe reflections ſerve to convince the mind of the vaſt importance of a general diffuſion of the knowledge of juriſprudence. Permit me now to ſuggeſt, that while the fortunes of our citizens are incompetent for this purpoſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, public good and political neceſſity, plead the cauſe of this ſcience, and ſolicit her introduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the claſſical exerciſes of a collegiate edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. In all countries celebrated for improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this ſcience has been particularly cultivat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and made a branch of claſſical learning. No gentleman in thoſe countries deems his education complete, till he has been indoctrinated in the ſcience of laws. Public inſtitutions for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of literature are the heart and ſeat of life to our government, whence proceed the arteries in tides of health to nouriſh and ſupport the whole ſyſtem. This our ſeminary, though yet in her infancy, has afforded preſages of her riſing great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Already do her ſons contend with thoſe of Oxford and Cambridge for the laurels of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſus.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="unknown:031865_0006_0FEEF3533126DAF0"/>
Let us then give eclat to her riſing glory, till ſhe ſhall be elevated with thoſe bright conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of the Eaſt.</p>
            <p>Thou Seat of Literature, thou <hi>Alma Mater</hi> of Wiſdom, haſten thy progreſs in the career of glory; and let me exhort thy patrons and fathers to venerate and cheriſh in thy boſom the heaven-born ſcience of juriſprudence. May the genius of freedom inſpire your breaſts, ye patrons of ſcience, with the glorious ambition to raiſe up a luminary in the Weſt, which ſhall eclipſe her ſiſter lights. With pleaſing rapture I anticipate the great event. The dawn of truth will burſt the reluctant clouds of night, and her meridian ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine eſtabliſh and perpetuate the glory of Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica. The decrees of wiſdom ſhall afford protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to innocence, and ſecure the rewards of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry. The funeral dirge of injuſtice and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion ſhall be triumphantly ſung o'er anarchy's expiring ruins.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
