<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Treaties of amity and commerce, and of alliance eventual and defensive, between His Most Christian Majesty and the thirteen United States of America; The definitive treaty between Great-Britain and the thirteen United States of America; and The treaty of amity, commerce, and navigation, between His Britannic Majesty and the United States of America.</title>
            <title>Treaties, etc.</title>
            <author>United States.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04">2009-04.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N24940</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N24940</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 33045</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APY1107</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">33045</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99028171</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 33045.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N24940)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 33045)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 33045)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Treaties of amity and commerce, and of alliance eventual and defensive, between His Most Christian Majesty and the thirteen United States of America; The definitive treaty between Great-Britain and the thirteen United States of America; and The treaty of amity, commerce, and navigation, between His Britannic Majesty and the United States of America.</title>
                  <title>Treaties, etc.</title>
                  <author>United States.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>71, [1] p. ;  18 cm. (12mo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Samuel Hall, no. 53, Cornhill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1797.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Treaty of friendship, limits and navigation between the United States of America, and the King of Spain."--p. 49-59; "Treaty of peace and amity between the United States of America and the Dey of Algiers."--p. 61-67; "Treaty of peace and friendship between the United States of America and the Bey and subjects of Tripoli of Barbary."--p. 69-71.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Treaties.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:033045_0000_0FF62F6894CBE210"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:033045_0001_0FF62F4984B133D0"/>
            <p>TREATIES OF AMITY AND COMMERCE, AND OF ALLIANCE EVENTUAL AND DEFENSIVE, BETWEEN His Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty and the Thirteen United States of America; THE DEFINITIVE TREATY BETWEEN Great-Britain and the Thirteen United States of America; AND THE TREATY OF AMITY, COMMERCE, AND NAVIGATION, BETWEEN His Britannic Majeſty and the United States of America.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON:</hi> Printed and ſold by <hi>SAMUEL HALL,</hi> No. 53, Cornhill. 1797.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treaty">
            <pb facs="unknown:033045_0002_0FF62F4B11A44410"/>
            <head>TREATY of Amity and Commerce between his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, and the thirteen United States of America.</head>
            <p>THE Moſt Chriſtian King, and the thirteen United States of North America, <hi>to wit,</hi> New-Hampſhire, Maſſachuſetts-bay, Rhode-Iſland, Connecticut, New-York, New-Jerſey, Pennſylvania, Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, North-Carolina, South-Carolina, and Georgia, willing to fix, in an equitable and permanent manner, the rules which ought to be followed relative to the correſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and commerce which the two parties deſire to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabliſh between their reſpective countries, ſtates, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, and the ſaid United States, have judged, that the ſaid end could not be better obtained, than by taking for the baſis of their agreement, the moſt perfect equality and reciprocity, and by carefully avoiding all thoſe burdenſome preferences, which are uſually ſources of debate, embarraſſment, and diſcontent —by leaving alſo each party at liberty to make, reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commerce and navigation, thoſe interior regulations, which it ſhall find moſt convenient to itſelf—and by found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the advantage of commerce ſolely upon reciprocal utility, and the juſt rules of free intercourſe—reſerving withal, to each party, the liberty of admitting, at its pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure, other nations to a participation of the ſame advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages. It is in the ſpirit of this intention, and to fulfil theſe views, that his ſaid Majeſty having named and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for his Plenipotentiary, Conrod Alexander Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, royal ſyndic of the city of Straſbourg, ſecretary of his Majeſty's council of ſtate—and the United States on their part, having fully empowered Benjamin Franklin, deputy from the ſtate of Pennſylvania to the general
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:033045_0003_0FF62F4DB9D7B188"/>
Congreſs, and preſident to the convention of ſaid ſtate— Silas Deane, late deputy from the ſtate of Connecticut, to the ſaid Congreſs—and Arthur Lee, counſellor at law: the ſaid reſpective plenipotentiaries, after exchanging their powers, and after mature deliberation, have concluded and agreed upon the following articles:</p>
            <p>ART. I. THERE ſhall be a firm, inviolable, and univerſal peace, and a true and ſincere friendſhip, between the Moſt Chriſtian King, his heirs and ſucceſſors, and the United States of America, and the ſubjects of the Moſt Chriſtian King, and of the ſaid ſtates, and between the countries, iſlands, cities, and towns, ſituate under the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Moſt Chriſtian King, and of the ſaid United States, and the people and inhabitants of every degree, without exception of perſons or places, and the terms herein after mentioned, ſhall be perpetual between the Moſt Chriſtian King, his heirs, and ſucceſſors, and the ſaid United States.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Moſt Chriſtian King, and the United States, engage mutually not to grant any particular favour to other nations, in reſpect of commerce and navigation, which ſhall not immediately become common to the other party, who ſhall enjoy the ſame favour freely, if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion was freely made—or on allowing the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, if the conceſſion was conditional.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The ſubjects of the Moſt Chriſtian King, ſhall pay in the ports, havens, roads, countries, iſlands, cities, or towns of the United States, or any of them, no other or greater duties or impoſts, of what nature ſoever they may be, or by what name ſoever called, than thoſe which the nations moſt favoured are or ſhall be obliged to pay: and they ſhall enjoy all the rights, liberties, privileges, immunities, and exemptions in trade, navigation, and commerce, whether in paſſing from one port in the ſaid ſtates to another, or in going to and from the ſame, from and to any part of the world, which the ſaid nations do or ſhall enjoy.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The ſubjects, people, and inhabitants of the ſaid United States, and each of them, ſhall not pay in the ports, havens, roads, iſles, cities, and places, under the domination of his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty in Europe, any other or greater duties or impoſts, of what nature ſoever
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:033045_0004_0FF62F4FB238B850"/>
they may be, or by what name ſoever called, than thoſe which the moſt favoured nations are or ſhall be obliged to pay: and they ſhall enjoy all the rights, liberties, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges, immunities, and exemptions in trade, navigation, and commerce, whether in paſſing from one port in the ſaid dominions in Europe, to another, or in going to and from the ſame, from and to any part of the world, which the ſaid nations do or ſhall enjoy.</p>
            <p n="5">V. In the above exemption is particularly compriſed the impoſition of one hundred ſols per ton, eſtabliſhed in France on foreign ſhips, unleſs when the ſhips of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States ſhall load with the merchandize of France, for another port of the ſame dominion: in which caſe, the ſaid ſhips ſhall pay the duty above mentioned, ſo long as other nations the moſt favoured ſhall be obliged to pay it: but it is underſtood, that the ſaid United States, or any of them, are at liberty, when they ſhall judge it proper, to eſtabliſh a duty equivalent in the ſame caſe.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. The Moſt Chriſtian King ſhall endeavour, by all the means in his power, to protect and defend all veſſels, and the effects, belonging to the ſubjects, people, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the ſaid United States, or any of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his ports, havens, or roads, or on the ſeas near to his countries, iſlands, cities, or towns; and to recover and reſtore to the right owners, their agents, or attornies, all ſuch veſſels and effects, which ſhall be taken within his juriſdiction: and the ſhips of war of his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, or any convoy ſailing under his authority, ſhall upon all occaſions, take under their protection, all veſſels belonging to the ſubjects, people, or inhabitants of the ſaid United States, or any of them, and holding the ſame courſe, or going the ſame way, and ſhall defend ſuch veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels as long as they hold the ſame courſe, or go the ſame way, againſt all attacks, force, and violence, in the ſame manner as they ought to protect and defend the veſſels belonging to the ſubjects of the Moſt Chriſtian King.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. In like manner the ſaid United States, and their ſhips of war ſailing under their authority, ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and defend, conformably to the tenor of the preced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing article, all the veſſels and effects belonging to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the Moſt Chriſtian King, and uſe all their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to recover, and cauſe to be reſtored, the ſaid
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:033045_0005_0FF62F51B3858B70"/>
veſſels and effects that ſhall have been taken within the juriſdiction of the ſaid United States, or any of them.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. The Moſt Chriſtian King will employ his good offices and interpoſition with the King or Emperor of Morocco or Fez—the Regencies of Algiers, Tunis, and Tripoli, or with any of them—and alſo with every other prince, ſtate, or power, of the coaſt of Barbary in Africa —and the ſubjects of the ſaid king, emperor, ſtates, and powers, and each of them, in order to provide, as fully and efficaciouſly as poſſible, for the benefit, conveniency, and ſafety of the United States, and each of them, their ſubjects, people, and inhabitants, and their veſſels and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, againſt all violence, inſult, attacks, or depredations, on the part of the ſaid princes and ſtates of Barbary, or their ſubjects.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. The ſubjects, inhabitants, merchants, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of ſhips, maſters, and mariners of the ſtates, provinces, and dominions of each reſpectively, ſhall abſtain and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to fiſh in all places poſſeſſed, or which ſhall be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by the other party. The Moſt Chriſtian King's ſubjects ſhall not fiſh in the havens, bays, creeks, roads, coaſts, or places, which the ſaid United States hold, or ſhall hereafter hold: and in like manner, the ſubjects, people, and inhabitants of the ſaid United States, ſhall not fiſh in the havens, bays, creeks, roads, coaſts, or places, which the moſt Chriſtian King poſſeſſes, or ſhall hereafter poſſeſs: and if any ſhip or veſſel ſhall be found fiſhing, contrary to the tenor of this treaty, the ſaid ſhip or veſſel with its lading (proof being made thereof) ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated: it is, however, underſtood that the excluſion ſtipulated in the preſent article, ſhall take place only ſo long and ſo far, as the Moſt Chriſtian King or the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States ſhall not, in this reſpect, have granted an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption to ſome other nation.</p>
            <p n="10">X. The United States, their citizens and inhabitants, ſhall never diſturb the ſubjects of the Moſt Chriſtian King, in the enjoyment and exerciſe of the right of fiſhing on the banks of Newfoundland—nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the indefinite and excluſive right which belongs to them on that part of the coaſt of that iſland, which is deſigned by the treaty of Utrecht—nor in the rights relative to all and each of the iſles, which belong to his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, the
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:033045_0006_0FF62F53DA0B8AA0"/>
whole conformable to the true ſenſe of the treaties of Utrecht and Paris.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. The ſubjects and inhabitants of the ſaid United States, or any of them, ſhall not be reputed aubains in France; and conſequently ſhall be exempted from the <hi>droit d'aubaine,</hi> or other ſimilar duty, under what name ſoever. They may, by teſtament, donation, or otherwiſe, diſpoſe of their goods, moveable and immoveable, in fav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of ſuch perſons as to them ſhall ſeem good; and their heirs, ſubjects of the ſaid United States, reſiding whether in France or elſewhere, may ſucceed them, <hi>ab inteſtat,</hi> without being obliged to obtain letters of naturalization, and without having the effect of this conceſſion conteſted or impeded, under pretext of any rights or prerogatives of provinces, cities, or private perſons. And the ſaid heirs, whether ſuch by particular title, or <hi>ab inteſtat,</hi> ſhall be exempt from all duty called <hi>droit de detraction,</hi> or other duty of the ſame kind; ſaving nevertheleſs the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal rights or duties, as much and as long as ſimilar ones are not eſtabliſhed by the United States, or any of them. The ſubjects of the Moſt Chriſtian King ſhall enjoy on their part, in all the dominions of the ſaid States, an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and perfect reciprocity, relative to the ſtipulations contained in the preſent article: but it is at the ſame time agreed, that its contents ſhall not affect the laws made, or that may be made hereafter in France, againſt emigrations, which ſhall remain in all their force and vig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: and the United States on their part, or any of them, ſhall be at liberty to enact ſuch laws, relative to that matter, as to them ſhall ſeem proper.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. The merchant-ſhips of either of the parties, which ſhall be making into a port belonging to the enemy of the other ally, and concerning whoſe voyage, and the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of goods on board her, there ſhall be juſt grounds of ſuſpicion, ſhall be obliged to exhibit, as well upon the high ſeas, as in the ports and havens, not only her paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, but likewiſe certificates, expreſsly ſhewing that her goods are not of the number of thoſe which have been prohibited as contraband.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. If, by the exhibiting of the above-ſaid certificates, the other party diſcover there are any of thoſe ſorts of goods which are prohibited and declared contraband, and
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:033045_0007_0FF62F56348F69F0"/>
conſigned for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> port under the obedience of its enemies, it ſhall not be lawful to break up the hatches of ſuch ſhip, or to open any cheſts, coffers, packs, caſks, or any other veſſele found therein, or to remove the ſmalleſt parcels of her goods, whether ſuch ſhip belongs to the ſubjects of France, or the inhabitants of the ſaid United States, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the lading be brought on ſhore, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the preſence of the officers of the court of admiralty, and an inventory thereof made: but there ſhall be no allowance to ſell, exchange, or alienate the ſame in any manner, until after that due and lawful proceſs ſhall have been had againſt ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited goods, and the court of admiralty ſhall, by a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence pronounced, have confiſcated the ſame; ſaving al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways as well the ſhip itſelf, as any other goods found therein, which by this Treaty are to be eſteemed free: neither may they be detained on pretence of their being as it were infected by the prohibited goods; much leſs ſhall they be confiſcated as lawful prize; but if not the whole cargo, but only part thereof ſhall conſiſt of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited or contraband goods, and the commander of the ſhip ſhall be ready and willing to deliver them to the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who has diſcovered them, in ſuch caſe the captor having received thoſe goods, ſhall forthwith diſcharge the ſhip, and not hinder her by any means freely to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the voyage on which ſhe was bound: but in caſe the contraband merchandizes cannot be all received on board the veſſel of the captor, then the captor may, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the offer of delivering him the contraband goods, carry the veſſel into the neareſt port, agreeable to what is above directed.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. On the contrary, it is agreed, that whatever ſhall be found to be laden by the ſubjects and inhabitants of either party on any ſhip belonging to the enemies of the other, or to their ſubjects, the whole, although it be not of the ſort of prohibited goods, may be confiſcated in the ſame manner as if it belonged to the enemy, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch goods and merchandizes as were put on board ſuch ſhip before the declaration of war, or even after ſuch declaration if ſo be it were done without knowledge of ſuch declaration: ſo that the goods of the ſubjects and people of either party, whether they be of the nature of ſuch as are prohibited or otherwiſe, which, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,
<pb facs="unknown:033045_0008_0FF62F57C9578678"/>
ſaid, were put on board any ſhip belonging to an enemy before the war, or after the declaration of the ſame, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowledge of it, ſhall no ways be liable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation, but ſhall well and truly be reſtored without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay to the proprietors demanding the ſame; but ſo as that if the ſaid merchandizes be contraband, it ſhall not be any-ways lawful to carry them afterwards to any ports belonging to the enemy. The two contracting parties agree, that the term of two months being paſſed after the declaration of war, their reſpective ſubjects, from what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever part of the world they come, ſhall not plead the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance mentioned in this article.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. And that more effectual care may be taken for the ſecurity of the ſubjects and inhabitants of both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that they ſuffer no injury by the men of war or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateers of the other party, all the commanders of the ſhips of his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty and of the ſaid United States, and all their ſubjects and inhabitants, ſhall be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden doing any injury or damage to the other ſide; and if they act to the contrary, they ſhall be puniſhed: and ſhall moreover be bound to make ſatisfaction for all matter of damage, and the intereſt thereof, by reparation, under the pain and obligation of their perſon and goods.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. All ſhips and merchandizes, of what nature ſoever, which ſhall be reſcued out of the hands of any pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates or robbers on the high ſeas, ſhall be brought into ſome port of either ſtate, and ſhall be delivered to the cuſtody of the officers of that port, in order to be reſtored entire to the true proprietor, as ſoon as due and ſufficient proof ſhall be made concerning the property thereof.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. It ſhall be lawful for the ſhips of war of either party, and privateers, freely to carry, whitherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they pleaſe, the ſhips and goods taken from their enemies, without being obliged to pay any duty to the officers of the admiralty, or any other judges: nor ſhall ſuch prizes be arreſted or ſeized, when they come to, and enter the ports of either party: nor ſhall the ſearchers or other officers of thoſe places ſearch the ſame, or make examination concerning the lawfulneſs of the prizes: but they may hoiſt ſail at any time, and depart, and carry their prizes to the places expreſſed in their commiſſions, which the commanders of ſuch ſhips of war ſhall be
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:033045_0009_0FF62F59647298D0"/>
obliged to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: on the contrary, no ſhelter or refuge ſhall be given in their ports to ſuch as ſhall have made prize of the ſubjects, people, or property of either of the parties; but if ſuch ſhall come in, being forced by ſtreſs of weather, or the danger of the ſea, all proper means ſhall be vigorouſly uſed, that they go out and retire from thence as ſoon as poſſible.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. If any ſhip, belonging to either of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, their people, or ſubjects, ſhall, within the coaſts or dominions of the other, ſtick upon the ſands, or be wrecked, or ſuffer any other damage—all friendly aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and relief ſhall be given to the perſons ſhip-wrecked, or ſuch as ſhall be in danger thereof. And letters of ſafe-conduct ſhall likewiſe be given to them, for their free and quiet paſſage from thence, and the return of every one to his own country.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. In caſe the ſubjects and inhabitants of either party, with their ſhipping, whether public and of war, or private and of merchants, be forced through ſtreſs of weather, purſuit of pirates, or enemies, or any other ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent neceſſity for ſeeking of ſhelter and harbour, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat and enter into any of the rivers, bays, roads, or ports belonging to the other party, they ſhall be received and treated with all humanity and kindneſs, and enjoy all friendly protection and help: and they ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to refreſh and provide themſelves, at reaſonable rates, with victuals, and all things needful for the ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of their perſons, or reparation of their ſhips, and conveniency of their voyage: and they ſhall no ways be detained or hindered from returning out of the ſaid ports or roads, but may remove and depart, when, and whither they pleaſe, without any let or hindrance.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. For the better promoting of commerce on both ſides, it is agreed, that if a war ſhall break out between the ſaid two nations, ſix months after the proclamation of war, ſhall be allowed to the merchants, in the cities and towns where they live, for ſelling and tranſporting their goods and merchandizes: and, if any thing be tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en from them, or any injury be done them within that term, by either party, or the people or ſubjects of either, full ſatisfaction ſhall be made for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. No ſubjects of the Moſt Chriſtian King ſhall
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:033045_0010_0FF62F5AEF87A5F8"/>
apply for, or take any commiſſion or letters of marque, for arming any ſhip or ſhips to act as privateers againſt the ſaid United States, or any of them, or againſt the ſubjects, people, or inhabitants of the ſaid United States, or any of them, or againſt the property of any of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of any of them, from any prince or ſtate with which the ſaid United States ſhall be at war: nor ſhall any citizen, ſubject, or inhabitant of the ſaid United States, or any of them, apply for, or take any commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or letters of marque, for arming any ſhip or ſhips, to act as privateers againſt the ſubjects of the Moſt Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian King, or any of them, or the property of any of them, from any prince or ſtate with which the ſaid king ſhall be at war: and if any perſon of either nation ſhall take ſuch commiſſions or letters of marque, he ſhall be puniſhed as a pirate.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. It ſhall not be lawful for any foreign priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers, not belonging to ſubjects of the Moſt Chriſtian King, nor citizens of the ſaid United States, who have commiſſions from any other prince or ſtate in enmity with either nation, to fit their ſhips in the ports of either the one or the other of the aforeſaid parties, to ſell what they have taken, or in any other manner whatſoever, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change their ſhips, merchandizes, or any other lading: neither ſhall they be allowed even to purchaſe victuals, except ſuch as ſhall be neceſſary for their going to the next port of that prince or ſtate from which they have commiſſions.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. It ſhall be lawful for all and ſingular the ſubjects of the Moſt Chriſtian King, and the citizens, people, and inhabitants of the ſaid United States, to ſail with their ſhips with all manner of liberty and ſecurity, no diſtinction being made who are the proprietors of the merchandizes laden thereon, from any port, to the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of thoſe who now are or hereafter ſhall be at enmity with the Moſt Chriſtian King or the United States. It ſhall likewiſe be lawful for the ſubjects and inhabitants aforeſaid, to ſail with the ſhips and merchandizes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, and to trade with the ſame liberty and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from the places, ports and havens of thoſe who are enemies of both or either party, without any oppoſition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diſturbance whatſoever, not only directly from the
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:033045_0011_0FF62F5D9D466280"/>
places of the enemy aforementioned, to neutral places; but alſo from one place belonging to an enemy, to another place belonging to an enemy, whether they be under the juriſdiction of the ſame prince, or under ſeveral. And it is hereby ſtipulated, that free ſhips ſhall alſo give a freedom to goods; and that every thing ſhall be deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be free and exempt, which ſhall be found on board the ſhips belonging to the ſubjects of either of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, although the whole lading or any part thereof ſhould appertain to the enemies of either, contraband goods being always excepted. It is alſo agreed in like manner, that the ſame liberty be extended to perſons who are on board a free ſhip, with this effect, that although they be enemies to both or either party, they are not to be taken out of that free ſhip, unleſs they are ſoldiers and in actual ſervice of the enemy.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIV. This liberty of navigation and commerce ſhall extend to all kinds of merchandizes, excepting thoſe only which are diſtinguiſhed by the name of contraband, and under this name of contraband or prohibited goods ſhall be comprehended arms, great guns, bombs, with the fuſees and other things belonging to them, cannon-ball, gun-powder, match, pikes, ſwords, lances, ſpears, halberds, mortars, petards, grenades, ſaltpetre, muſkets, muſket ball, bucklers, helmets, breaſt-plates, coats of mail, and the like kinds of arms, proper for arming ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, muſket-reſts, belts, horſes with their furniture, and all other warlike inſtruments whatever. Theſe merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes that follow, ſhall not be reckoned among contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band or prohibited goods; that is to ſay, all ſorts of cloths, and all other manufactures woven of any wool, flax, ſilk, cotton, or any other materials whatever; all kinds of wearing apparel, together with the ſpecies where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they are uſed to be made; gold and ſilver, as well coined as uncoined, tin, iron, latten, copper, braſs, coals; as alſo wheat and barley, and any other kind of corn, and pulſe, tobacco, and likewiſe all manner of ſpices, ſalted and ſmoaked fleſh, ſalted fiſh, cheeſe and butter, beer, oils, wines, ſugars, and all ſorts of ſalts, and in general all proviſions which ſerve for the nouriſhment of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind and the ſuſtenance of life; furthermore, all kinds of cotton, hemp, flax, tar, pitch, ropes, cables, ſails, ſail-cloths,
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:033045_0012_0FF62F5F2CBF5668"/>
anchors, and any parts of anchor, alſo ſhips, maſts, planks, boards, and beams of what trees ſoever: and all other things proper either for building or repairing ſhips, and all other goods whatever which have not been work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the form of any inſtrument or thing prepared for war by land or by ſea, ſhall not be reputed contraband, much leſs ſuch as have been already wrought and made up for any other uſe; all which ſhall be wholly reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among free goods; as likewiſe all other merchandiſes and things which are not comprehended and particularly mentioned in the foregoing enumeration of contraband goods, ſo that they may be tranſported and carried in the freeſt manner by the ſubjects of both confederates, even to places belonging to an enemy—ſuch towns or places being only excepted, as are at that time beſieged, blocked up, or inveſted.</p>
            <p n="25">XXV. To the end that all manner of diſſentions and quarrels may be avoided and prevented, on one ſide and the other, it is agreed, that in caſe either of the parties hereto ſhould be engaged in war, the ſhips and veſſels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the ſubjects or people of the other ally, muſt be furniſhed with ſea letters or paſſports, expreſſing the name, property, and bulk of the ſhip, as alſo the name and place of habitation of the commander of the ſaid ſhip, that it may appear thereby that the ſhip really and truly belongs to the ſubjects of one of the parties, which paſſport ſhall be made out and granted according to the form annexed to this treaty. They ſhall likewiſe be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called every year, that is, if the ſhip happens to return home within the ſpace of a year; it is likewiſe agreed, that ſuch ſhips, being laden, are to be provided not only with paſſports as above mentioned, but alſo with certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, containing the ſeveral particulars of the cargo, the place whence the ſhip ſailed, and whither ſhe is bound; that ſo it may be known whether any forbidden or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traband goods be on board the ſame; which certificates ſhall be made out by the officers of the place whence the ſhip ſet ſail, in the accuſtomed form: and if any one ſhall think it fit or adviſeable to expreſs in the ſaid certificates the perſon to whom the goods on board belong, he may freely do ſo.</p>
            <p n="26">XXVI. The ſhips of the ſubjects and inhabitants of
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:033045_0013_0FF62F60E391BA68"/>
either of the parties coming upon any coaſts belonging to either of the ſaid allies, but not willing to enter into port, or being entered into port, and not willing to unload their cargoes or break bulk, they ſhall be treated accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the general rules preſcribed or to be preſcribed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative to the object in queſtion.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. If the ſhips of the ſaid ſubjects, people, or inhabitants of either of the parties, ſhall be met with, either ſailing along the coaſts, or on the high ſeas, by any ſhips of war of the other, or by any privateers, the ſaid ſhips of war or privateers for the avoiding of any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, ſhall remain out of cannon ſhot, and may ſend their boats on board the merchant ſhip, which they ſhall ſo meet with; and may enter her to the number of two or three men only: to whom the maſter or commander of ſuch ſhip or veſſel ſhall exhibit his paſſport, concerning the property of the ſhip, made out according to the form inſerted in this preſent Treaty: and the ſhip, when ſhe ſhall have ſhewed ſuch paſſport, ſhall be free and at liberty to purſue her voyage, ſo as it ſhall not be lawful to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt or ſearch her in any manner, or to give her chaſe, or force her to quit her intended courſe.</p>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. It is alſo agreed, that all goods, when once put on board the ſhips or veſſels of either of the two contracting parties, ſhall be ſubject to no further viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but all viſitation or ſearch ſhall be made before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand; and all prohibited goods ſhall be ſtopped on the ſpot before the ſame be put on board, unleſs there be manifeſt tokens or proofs of fraudulent practice: nor ſhall either the perſons or goods of the ſubjects of his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, or the United States, be put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any arreſt, or moleſted by any other kind of embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go for that cauſe: and only the ſubject of that ſtate to whom the ſaid goods have been or ſhall be prohibited, and who ſhall preſume to ſell or alienate ſuch ſort of goods, ſhall be duly puniſhed for the offence.</p>
            <p n="29">XXIX. The two contracting parties grant mutually the liberty of having each in the ports of the other, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, vice-conſuls, agents and commiſſaries, whoſe func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall be regulated by a particular agreement.</p>
            <p n="30">XXX. And the more to favour and facilitate the commerce which the ſubjects of the United States may
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:033045_0014_0FF62F62D1B8BE40"/>
have with France, the Moſt Chriſtian King will grant them in Europe, one or more free ports, where they may bring and diſpoſe of all the produce and merchandiſe of the thirteen United States: and his Majeſty will alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to the ſubjects of the ſaid States, the free ports which have been and are open in the French iſlands of America; of all which free ports the ſaid ſubjects of the United States ſhall enjoy the uſe, agreeably to the regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations which relate to them.</p>
            <p n="31">XXXI. The preſent Treaty ſhall be ratified on both ſides, and the ratifications ſhall be exchanged in the ſpace of ſix months, or ſooner, if poſſible.</p>
            <p>In faith whereof the reſpective plenipotentiarics have ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the above articles, both in the French and Engliſh languages; declaring nevertheleſs, that the preſent Treaty was originally compoſed and concluded in the French language; and they have hereto affixed their ſeals.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Done at Paris, <date>this ſixth day of February, one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſeven hundred and ſeventy-eight.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>C. A. GERARD, (L. S.)</item>
                     <item>B. FRANKLIN, (L. S.)</item>
                     <item>SILAS DEANE, (L. S.)</item>
                     <item>ARTHUR LEE, (L. S.)</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treaty">
            <pb n="16" facs="unknown:033045_0015_0FF62F6522907708"/>
            <head>TREATY of Alliance Eventual and Defenſive, between his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, and the thirteen United States of America.</head>
            <p>THE Moſt Chriſtian King, and the United States of North-America, to wit, New-Hampſhire, Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chuſetts-bay, Rhode-Iſland, Connecticut, New-York, New-Jerſey, Pennſylvania, Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, North-Carolina, South-Carolina, and Georgia, having this day concluded a Treaty of Amity and Commerce, for the reciprocal advantage of their ſubjects and citizens, have thought it neceſſary to take into conſideration the means of ſtrengthening thoſe engagements, and of render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them uſeful to the ſafety and tranquillity of the two parties; particularly in caſe Great-Britain, in reſentment of that connexion, and of the good correſpondence which is the object of the ſaid treaty, ſhould break the peace with France, either by direct hoſtilities, or by hindering her commerce and navigation in a manner contrary to the rights of nations, and the peace ſubſiſting between the two crowns. And his Majeſty and the ſaid United States, having reſolved in that caſe, to join their councils and efforts againſt the enterpriſes of their common enemy—</p>
            <p>The reſpective Plenipotentiaries, empowered to concert the clauſes and conditions proper to fulfil the ſaid inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, have, after the moſt mature deliberation, concluded and determined on the following articles.</p>
            <p n="1">I. If war ſhould break out between France and Great-Britain, during the continuance of the preſent war be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the United States and England, his Majeſty and the ſaid United States ſhall make it a common cauſe, and aid each other mutually with their good offices, their counſels, and their forces, according to the exigence of conjunctures, as becomes good and faithful allies.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="17" facs="unknown:033045_0016_0FF62F66AE560B98"/>II. The eſſential and direct end of the preſent defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive alliance is, to maintain effectually the liberty, ſover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eignty, and independence, abſolute and unlimited, of the ſaid United States, as well in matters of government, as of commerce.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The two contracting parties ſhall, each on its own part, and in the manner it may judge moſt proper, make all the efforts in its power againſt their common enemy, in order to attain the end propoſed.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The contracting parties agree, that in caſe either of them ſhould form any particular enterpriſe, in which the concurrence of the other may be deſired, the party, whoſe concurrence is deſired, ſhall readily and with good faith join to act in concert for that purpoſe, as far as cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and its own particular ſituation will permit. And in that caſe, they ſhall regulate by a particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, the quantity and kind of ſuccour to be furniſhed, and the time and manner of its being brought into action, as well as the advantages which are to be its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation.</p>
            <p n="5">V. If the United States ſhould think fit to attempt the reduction of the Britiſh power, remaining in the north<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern parts of America, or the iſlands of Bermudas, thoſe countries or iſlands, in caſe of ſucceſs, ſhall be confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated with, or dependent upon the ſaid United States.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. The Moſt Chriſtian King renounces forever, the poſſeſſion of the iſlands of Bermudas, as well as of any part of the continent of North-America, which before the Treaty of Paris, in 1763, or in virtue of that Treaty, were acknowledged to belong to the crown of Great-Britain, or to the United States, heretofore called Britiſh colonies, or which are at this time, or have lately been under the power of the king and crown of Great-Britain.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. If his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty ſhall think proper to attack any of the iſlands ſituated in the gulf of Mexico, or near that gulf, which are at preſent under the power of Great-Britain, all the ſaid iſles, in caſe of ſucceſs, ſhall appertain to the crown of France.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Neither of the two parties ſhall conclude either trace or peace with Great-Britain, without the formal conſent of the other firſt obtained: and they mutually engage not to lay down their arms, until the independ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:033045_0017_0FF62F43781D3FE8"/>
of the United States ſhall have been formally or tacitly aſſured, by the treaty or treaties that ſhall termin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the war.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. The contracting parties declare, that being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to fulfil each on its own part, the clauſes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the preſent Treaty of Alliance, according to its own power and circumſtances, there ſhall be no after-claim of compenſation, on one ſide or the other, whatever may be the event of the war.</p>
            <p n="10">X. The Moſt Chriſtian King and the United States, agree to invite or admit other powers, who may have received injuries from England, to make a common cauſe with them, and to accede to the preſent alliance, under ſuch conditions as ſhall be freely agreed to, and ſettled between all the parties.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. The two parties guarantee mutually from the preſent time and forever, againſt all other powers, to wit, the United States to his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent poſſeſſions of the crown of France in America, as well as thoſe which it may acquire by the future Treaty of Peace: and his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty guarantees on his part to the United States, their liberty, ſovereignty, and independence, abſolute and unlimited, as well in matters of government, as commerce—and alſo their poſſeſſions, and the additions or conqueſts that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federation may obtain during the war, from any of the dominions now or heretofore poſſeſſed by Great-Britain in North-America, conformable to the fifth and ſixth articles above-written; the whole, as their poſſeſſions, ſhall be fixed and aſſured to the ſaid ſtates, at the moment of the ceſſation of their preſent war with England.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. In order to fix more preciſely the ſenſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the preceding article, the contracting parties declare, that in caſe of a rupture between France and England, the reciprocal guarantee declared in the ſaid article, ſhall have its full force and effect, the moment ſuch war ſhall break out: and if ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall not take place, the mutual obligations of the ſaid guarantee ſhall not commence until the momen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>tion of the preſent war, between the United State<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and England, ſhall have aſcertained their poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. The preſent Treaty ſhall be ratified on both
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:033045_0018_0FF62F6BE14EB008"/>
ſides, and the ratification ſhall be exchanged in the ſpace of ſix months, or ſooner, if poſſible.</p>
            <p>In faith whereof the reſpective Plenipotentiaries, to wit, on the part of the Moſt Chriſtian King, Conrad Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Gerard, royal ſyndic of the city of Straſbourg, and ſecretary of his Majeſty's council of ſtate—and on the part of the United States, Benjamin Franklin, deputy to the general Congreſs from the ſtate of Pennſylvania, and preſident of the Convention of ſaid ſtate—Silas Deane, heretofore deputy from the ſtate of Connecticut—and Arthur Lee, counſellor at law, have ſigned the above articles both in the French and Engliſh languages; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, nevertheleſs, that the preſent Treaty was origin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally compoſed and concluded in the French language; and they have hereunto affixed their ſeals.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Done at Paris, <date>this ſixth day of February, one thouſand ſeven hundred and ſeventy-eight.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>C. A. GERARD, (L. S.)</item>
                     <item>B. FRANKLIN, (L. S.)</item>
                     <item>SILAS DEANE, (L. S.)</item>
                     <item>ARTHUR LEE, (L. S.)</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treaty">
            <pb n="20" facs="unknown:033045_0019_0FF62F6D6D193638"/>
            <head>The Definitive Treaty between Great-Britain and the Thirteen United States of America.</head>
            <opener>In the Name of the Moſt Holy and Undivided Trinity.</opener>
            <p>IT having pleaſed the Divine Providence to diſpoſe the hearts of the moſt ſerene and moſt potent prince George the Third, by the grace of God, king of Great-Britain, France, and Ireland, defender of the faith, duke of Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick and Lunenburg, arch treaſurer and prince elector of the holy Roman empire, &amp;c. and of the United States of America, to forget all paſt miſunderſtandings and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, that have unhappily interrupted the good cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence and friendſhip which they mutually wiſh to reſtore—and to eſtabliſh ſuch a beneficial and ſatisfactory intercourſe between the two countries, upon the ground of reciprocal advantages and mutual convenience, as may promote and ſecure to both perpetual peace and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony—and having for this deſireable end already laid the foundation of peace and reconciliation, by the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional articles, ſigned at Paris, on the 30th of November, 1782, by the commiſſioners empowered on each part, which articles were agreed to be inſerted in, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the treaty of peace propoſed to be concluded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the crown of Great-Britain, and the ſaid United States, but which treaty was not to be concluded until terms of peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uld be agreed upon between Great-Britain and France, and his Britannic majeſty ſhould be ready to conclude ſuch treaty accordingly—and the treaty between Great-Britain and France having ſince been concluded, his Britannic majeſty and the United States of America, in order to carry into full effect the proviſional articles above mentioned, according to the tenor thereof, have conſtituted and appointed, that is to ſay, his Britannic majeſty on his part, David Hartley, Eſq. member of the parliament of Great-Britain; and the ſaid United States on their part, John Adams,
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:033045_0020_0FF62F6EF86D1950"/>
Eſq. late a commiſſioner of the United States of Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, at the court of Verſailles, late delegate in Congreſs from the ſtate of Maſſachuſetts, and chief juſtice of the ſaid ſtate, and miniſter plenipotentiary of the ſaid United States, to their high mightineſſes the States General of the United Netherlands; Benjamin Franklin, Eſq. late delegate in Congreſs, from the ſtate of Pennſylvania, preſident of the convention of the ſaid ſtate, and miniſter plenipotentiary from the United States of America, at the court of Verſailles; and John Jay, Eſq. late preſident of Congreſs, chief juſtice of the ſtate of New-York, and miniſter plenipotentiary from the ſaid United States, at the court of Madrid—to be the plenipotentiaries for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding and ſigning the preſent definitive treaty; who, after having reciprocally communicated their reſpective full powers, have agreed upon and confirmed the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing articles.</p>
            <p>ART. I. His Britannic majeſty acknowledges the ſaid United States, viz. New-Hampſhire, Maſſachuſetts-bay, Rhode-Iſland and Providence plantations, Connecticut, New-York, New-Jerſey, Pennſylvania, Delaware, Mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Virginia, North-Carolina, South-Carolina, and Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia, to be free, ſovereign, and independent ſtates; that he treats with them as ſuch, and for himſelf, his heirs and ſucceſſors, relinquiſhes all claims to the government, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, and territorial rights of the ſame, and every part thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">II. And that all diſputes, which might ariſe in future, on the ſubject of the boundaries of the ſaid United States, may be prevented, it is hereby agreed and declared, that the following are and ſhall be their boundaries, viz. from the north-weſt angle of Nova-Scotia, viz. that angle which is formed by a line drawn due north from the ſource of St. Croix river to the highlands, along the ſaid highlands, which divide thoſe rivers that empty them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the river St. Lawrence, from thoſe which fall into the Atlantic ocean, to the north-weſternmoſt head of Connecticut river; thence down along the middle of that river to the forty-fifth degree of north latitude; from thence by a line due weſt on ſaid latitude, until it ſtrikes the river Iriquois or Cataraquy; thence along the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of ſaid river into Lake Ontario; through the middle
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:033045_0021_0FF62F70EEB6D8D8"/>
of ſaid lake until it ſtrikes the communication by water between that lake and Lake Erie; thence along the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of ſaid communication into Lake Erie; through the middle of ſaid lake until it arrives at the water commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication between that lake and Lake Huron; thence along the middle of ſaid water communication into the Lake Huron; thence through the middle of ſaid lake to the water communication between that lake and Lake Superior; thence through Lake Superior northward of the iſles Royal and Philipeaux to the Long Lake; thence thro' the middle of ſaid Long Lake and the water commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication between it and the Lake of the Woods, to the ſaid Lake of the Woods; thence through the ſaid lake to the moſt north-weſtern point thereof, and from thence on a due weſt courſe to the river Miſſiſſippi; thence by a line to be drawn along the middle of the ſaid river Miſſiſſippi until it ſhall interſect the northernmoſt part of the thirty-firſt degree of north latitude. South, by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e to be drawn due eaſt from the determination of the line laſt mentioned in the latitude of thirty-one degrees north of the equator, to the middle of the river Apalachicola, or Catahouche; thence along the middle thereof to its junc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Flint river; thence ſtrait to the head of St. Mary's river; and thence down along the middle of St. Mary's river to the Atlantic ocean. Eaſt, by a line to be drawn along the middle of the river. St. Croix, from its mouth in the bay of Fundy, to its ſource; and from its ſource directly north to the aforeſaid highlands, which divide the rivers that fall into the Atlantic ocean, from thoſe which fall into the river St. Lawrence, comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all iſlands within twenty leagues of any part of the ſhores of the United States, and lying between lines to be drawn due eaſt from the points where the aforeſaid bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries between Nova-Scotia on the one part, and Faſt-Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rida on the other, ſhall reſpectively touch the bay of Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the Atlantic ocean, excepting ſuch iſlands as now are, or heretofore have been within the limits of the ſaid province of Nova-Scotia.</p>
            <p n="3">III. It is agreed, that the people of the United States ſhall continue to enjoy, unmoleſted, the right to take fiſh of every kind on the Grand Bank, and on all the other banks of Newfoundland, alſo in the Gulf of St.
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:033045_0022_0FF62F7342193B40"/>
Lawrence, and at all other places in the ſea, where the inhabitants of both countries uſed at any time heretofore to fiſh. And alſo, that the inhabitants of the United States ſhall have liberty to take fiſh of every kind on ſuch part of the coaſt of Newfoundland, as Britiſh fiſhermen ſhall uſe (but not to dry or cure the ſame on that iſland) and alſo on the coaſts, bays and creeks of all other of his Britannic majeſty's dominions in America; and that the American fiſhermen ſhall have liberty to dry and cure fiſh in any of the unſettled bays, harbours and creeks of Nova-Scotia, Magdalen Iſlands, and Labrador, ſo long as the ſame ſhall remain unſettled; but ſo ſoon as the ſame or either of them ſhall be ſettled, it ſhall not be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the ſaid fiſhermen to dry or cure fiſh at ſuch ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, without a previous agreement for that purpoſe, with the inhabitants, proprietors, or poſſeſſors of the ground.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. It is agreed, that creditors on either ſide, ſhall meet with no lawful impediment to the recovery of the full value, in ſterling money, of all bona fide debts heretofore contracted.</p>
            <p n="5">V. It is agreed, that the Congreſs ſhall earneſtly recommend it to the legiſlatures of the reſpective ſtates, to provide for the reſtitution of all eſtates, rights, and properties, which have been confiſcated, belonging to real Britiſh ſubjects: and alſo of the eſtates, rights, and properties of perſons reſident in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricts in the poſſeſſion of his majeſty's arms, and who have not borne arms againſt the ſaid U. States; and that perſons of any other diſcription, ſhall have free liberty to go to any part or parts of any of the thirteen United States, and therein to remain twelve months unmoleſted in their endeavours to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the reſtitution of ſuch of their eſtates, rights, and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as may have been confiſcated; and that Congreſs ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo earneſtly recommend to the ſeveral ſtates, a re-conſideration and reviſion of all acts or laws regarding the premiſes, ſo as to render the ſaid laws or acts perfectly conſiſtent, not only with juſtice and equity, but with that ſpirit of conciliation, which, on the return of the bleſſings of peace, ſhould univerſally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail: and that Congreſs ſhall alſo earneſtly recommend to the ſeveral ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, that the eſtates, rights, and properties of ſuch laſt mentioned perſons ſhall be reſtored to them, they refunding to any perſons who may be now in poſſeſſion, the bona fide price (where any has been given) which ſuch perſons may have paid, on purchaſing any of the ſaid lands, rights, or proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſince the confiſcation. And it is agreed, that all perſons, who have any intereſt in confiſcated lands, either by debts, marriage ſettlement<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or otherwiſe, ſhall meet with no lawful imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nt at in the proſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion of their juſt rights.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="24" facs="unknown:033045_0023_0FF62F7588243698"/>VI. That there ſhall be no future confiſcations made, nor any proſecutions commenced againſt any perſon or perſons for, or by reaſon of the part which he or they may have taken in the preſent war: and that no perſon ſhall, on that account, ſuffer any future loſs or damage, either in his perſon, liberty, or property: and that thoſe, who may be in confinement on ſuch charges, at the time of the ratification of the treaty in America, ſhall be immediately ſet at liberty, and the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo commenced, be diſcontinued.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. There ſhall be a firm and perpetual peace between his Britannic majeſty and the ſaid ſtates, and between the ſubjects of the one, and the citizens of the other: wherefore, all hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilities, both by ſea and land, ſhall from henceforth ceaſe: all priſoners, on both ſides, ſhall be ſet at liberty: and his Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic majeſty ſhall, with all convenient ſpeed, and without cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any deſtruction, or carrying away any negroes, or other property of the American inhabitants, withdraw all his armies, garriſons, and ſleets from the ſaid United States, and from every poſt, place, and harbour within the ſame, leaving in all fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations the American artillery that may be therein; and ſhall alſo order and cauſe all archives, records, deeds, and papers belonging to any of the ſaid ſtates, or their citizens, which in the courſe of the war may have fallen into the hands of his officers, to be forthwith reſtored, and delivered to the proper ſtates and perſons to whom they belong.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. The navigation of the river Miſſiſſippi, from its ſource to the ocean, ſhall forever remain free and open to the ſubjects of Great-Britain, and the citizens of the United States.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. In caſe it ſhould ſo happen, that any place or territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry belonging to Great-Britain, or to the United States, ſhould have been conquered by the arms of either from the other, before the arrival of the ſaid proviſional articles in America, it is agreed, that the ſame ſhall be reſtored without difficult, and without requiring any compenſation.</p>
            <p n="10">X. The ſolemn ratifications of the preſent treaty, expedit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in good and due form, ſhall be exchanged between the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting parties in the ſpace of ſix months, or ſooner, if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to be computed from the day of the ſignature of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent treaty. In witneſs whereof, we the underſigned, their miniſters plenipotentiary, have, in their name, and in virtue of our full powers, ſigned with our hands, the preſent definitive treaty, and cauſed the ſeals of our arms to be affixed thereto.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Done at Paris, <date>this third day of September, one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, ſeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hundred and eighty-three.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>DAVID HARTLEY, (L. S.)</item>
                     <item>JOHN ADAMS, (L. S.)</item>
                     <item>B. FRANKLIN, (L. S.)</item>
                     <item>JOHN JAY, (L. S.)</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treaty">
            <pb n="25" facs="unknown:033045_0024_0FF62F7713ED7890"/>
            <head>TREATY of Amity, Commerce, and Navigation, between his Britannic Majeſty and the United States of America, conditionally ratified by the Senate of the United States, at Philadelphia, <date>June <hi>24, 1795.</hi>
               </date>
            </head>
            <p>HIS Britannic Majeſty and the United States of America, being deſirous, by a Treaty of Amity, Commerce, and Navigation, to terminate their differences in ſuch a manner, as, without reference to the merits of their reſpective complaints and pretenſions, may be the beſt calculated to produce mutual ſatisfaction and good underſtanding: and alſo to regulate the Commerce and Navigation between their reſpective countries, territories and people, in ſuch a manner as to render the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally beneficial and ſatisfactory; they have, reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, named their Plenipotentiaries, and given them full power to treat of, and conclude, the ſaid Treaty, that is to ſay: his Britannic Majeſty has named for his Plenipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiary, the Right Honorable William Windham, Baron Grenville, of Wotton, one of his Majeſty's Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, and his Majeſty's Principal Secretary of State for Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Affairs; and the Preſident of the ſaid United States, by and with the advice and conſent of the Senate thereof, hath appointed for their Plenipotentiary, the Honorable John Jay, Chief Juſtice of the ſaid United States, and their Envoy Extraordinary to his Majeſty, who have agreed and concluded the following articles:</p>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE I.</head>
               <p>There ſhall be a firm, inviolable, and univerſal peace, and a true and ſincere friendſhip between his Britannic Majeſty, his heirs and ſucceſſors, and the United States of America; and between their reſpective countries, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, cities, towns, and people of every degree, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception of perſons or places.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <pb n="26" facs="unknown:033045_0025_0FF62F78C1C2FD20"/>
               <head>ARTICLE II.</head>
               <p>His Majeſty will withdraw all his troops and garriſons from all poſts and places within the boundary lines aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by the Treaty of Peace to the United States. This evacuation ſhall take place on or before the firſt day of June, one thouſand ſeven hundred and ninety-ſix, and all the proper meaſures ſhall, in the interval, be taken by concert between the government of the United States, and his Majeſty's Governor General in America, for ſettling the previous arrangements, which may be neceſſary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the delivery of the ſaid poſts: The United States, in the mean time, at their diſcretion, extending their ſettlements to any part within the ſaid boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary line, except within the precincts or juriſdiction of any of the ſaid poſts. All ſettlers and traders within the precincts or juriſdiction of the ſaid poſts, ſhall continue to enjoy, unmoleſted, all their property of every kind, and ſhall be protected therein. They ſhall be at full lib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erty to remain there, or to remove with all or any part of their effects; and it ſhall alſo be free to them to ſell their lands, houſes, or effects, or to retain the property thereof, at their diſcretion; ſuch of them as ſhall continue to reſide within the ſaid boundary lines, ſhall not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to become citizens of the United States, or to take any oath of allegiance to the government thereof; but ſhall be at full liberty ſo to do if they think proper; and they ſhall make and declare their election within one year after the evacuation aforeſaid. And all perſons who ſhall continue there after the expiration of the ſaid year, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having declared their intention of remaining ſubjects of his Britannic Majeſty, ſhall be conſidered as having elected to become citizens of the United States.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE III.</head>
               <p>It is agreed, that it ſhall, at all times, be free to his Majeſty's ſubjects, and to the citizens of the United States, and alſo to the Indians dwelling on either ſide of the ſaid boundary line, freely to paſs and repaſs by land or inland navigation, into the reſpective territories and countries of the two parties, on the continent of America (the country within the limits of the Hudſon's bay company only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) and to navigate all the lakes, rivers, and water<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thereof, and freely to carry on trade and commerce with
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:033045_0026_0FF62F7ACCE56FF8"/>
each other. But it is underſtood, that this article does not extend to the admiſſion of veſſels of the United States into the ſea-ports, harbors, bays, or creeks of his Majeſty's ſaid territories; nor into ſuch parts of the rivers in his Majeſty's ſaid territories as are between the mouth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and the higheſt port of entry from the ſea, except in ſmall veſſels trading <hi>bona fide</hi> between Montreal and Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bec, under ſuch regulations as ſhall be eſtabliſhed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the poſſibility of any frauds in this reſpect; nor to the admiſſion of Britiſh veſſels from the ſea into the rivers of the United States, beyond the higheſt ports of entry for veſſels from the ſea. The river Miſſiſippi ſhall, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, according to the Treaty of Peace, be entirely open to both parties; and it is further agreed, that all the ports and places on its eaſtern ſide, to whichſoever of the parties belonging, may freely be reſorted to, and uſed by both parties, in as ample a manner as any of the Atlantic ports or places of the United States, or any of the ports or places of his Majeſty in Great-Britain.</p>
               <p>All goods and merchandize, whoſe importation into his Majeſty's ſaid territories in America ſhall not be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely prohibited, may freely, for the purpoſes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, be carried into the ſame in the manner aforeſaid, by the citizens of the United States, and ſuch goods and merchandize ſhall be ſubject to no higher or other duties, than would be payable by his Majeſty's ſubjects on the importation of the ſame from Europe into the ſaid terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories. And in like manner, all goods and merchandize, whoſe importation into the United States ſhall not be wholly prohibited, may freely, for the purpoſes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, be carried into the ſame, in the manner aforeſaid, by his Majeſty's ſubjects, and ſuch goods and merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize ſhall be ſubject to no higher or other duties, than would be payable by the citizens of the United States on the importation of the ſame in American veſſels into the Atlantic ports of the ſaid States. And all goods not prohibited to be exported from the ſaid territories reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, may, in like manner, be carried out of the ſame by the two parties reſpectively, paying duty as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>No duty of entry ſhall ever be levied by either party on peltries brought by land, or inland navigation, into the ſaid territories reſpectively; nor ſhall the Indians
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:033045_0027_0FF62F7D2A149540"/>
paſſing or repaſſing with their own proper goods and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, of whatever nature, pay for the ſame any impoſt or duty whatever. But goods in bales, or other large pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, unuſual among Indians, ſhall not be conſidered as goods belonging <hi>bona fide</hi> to Indians.</p>
               <p>No higher or other tolls or rates of ferriage than what are or ſhall be payable by natives, ſhall be demanded on either ſide; and no duties ſhall be payable on any goods which ſhall be merely carried over any of the portages or carrying places on either ſide, for the purpoſe of being immediately reimbarked and carried to ſome other place or places. But as by this ſtipulation it is only meant to ſecure to each party a free paſſage acroſs the portages on both ſides; it is agreed, that this exemption from duty ſhall extend only to ſuch goods as are carried in the uſual and direct road acroſs the portage, and are not attempted to be in any manner ſold or exchanged during their paſſage acroſs the ſame; and proper regulations may be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to prevent the poſſibility of any frauds in this reſpect.</p>
               <p>As this article is intended to render in a great degree the local advantages of each party common to both, and thereby to promote a diſpoſition favorable to friendſhip and good neighborhood, it is agreed, that the reſpective gov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ernments will mutually promote this amicable intercourſe, by cauſing ſpeedy and impartial juſtice to be done, and neceſſary protection to be extended to all who may be concerned therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE IV.</head>
               <p>Whereas it is uncertain whether the river Miſſiſippi extends ſo far to the northward as to be interſected by a line to be drawn due weſt from the Lake of the Woods, in the manner mentioned in the Treaty of Peace between his Majeſty and the United States: it is agreed, that meaſures ſhall be taken in concert between his Majeſty's government in America and the government of the Unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed States, for making a joint ſurvey of the ſaid river from one degree of latitude below the falls of St. Anthony, to the principal ſource or ſources of ſaid river, and the parts adjacent thereto; and that if on the reſult of ſuch ſurvey, it ſhould appear that the ſaid river would not be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſected by ſuch a line as is above mentioned, the two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties will thereupon proceed by amicable negociation, to
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:033045_0028_0FF62F7F1DEA7668"/>
regulate the boundary line in that quarter, as well as all other points to be adjuſted between the ſaid parties, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to juſtice and mutual convenience, and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the intent of the ſaid Treaty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE V.</head>
               <p>Whereas doubts have ariſen what river was truly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended under the name of the river St. Croix, mentioned in the ſaid Treaty of Peace, and forming a part of the boundary therein deſcribed; that queſtion ſhall be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the final deciſion of Commiſſioners to be appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the following manner, viz.</p>
               <p>One Commiſſioner ſhall be named by his Majeſty, and one by the Preſident of the United States, by and with the advice and conſent of the Senate thereof, and the ſaid two Commiſſioners ſhall agree on the choice of a third; or if they cannot ſo agree, they ſhall each propoſe one perſon, and of the two names ſo propoſed, one ſhall be drawn by lot in the preſence of the two original Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners. And the three Commiſſioners ſo appointed, ſhall be ſworn, impartially to examine and decide the ſaid queſtion, according to ſuch evidence as ſhall reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively be laid before them on the part of the Britiſh gov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ernment and of the United States. The ſaid Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall meet at Haliſax, and ſhall have power to adjourn to ſuch other place or places as they ſhall think fit. They ſhall have power to appoint a Secretary, and to employ ſuch Surveyors or other perſons as they ſhall judge neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. The ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall, by a declaration under their hands and ſeals, decide what river is the river St. Croix intended by the Treaty. The ſaid declaration ſhall contain a deſcription of the ſaid river, and ſhall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularize the latitude and longitude of its mouth and of its ſource. Duplicates of this declaration and of the ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their accounts, and of the journal of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, ſhall be delivered by them to the agent of his Majeſty, and to the agent of the United States, who may be reſpectively appointed and authorized to manage the buſineſs on behalf of the reſpective governments. And both parties agree to conſider ſuch deciſion as final and concluſive, ſo as that the ſame ſhall never thereafter be called in queſtion, or made the ſubject of diſpute or differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <pb n="30" facs="unknown:033045_0029_0FF62F80D63CA468"/>
               <head>ARTICLE VI.</head>
               <p>Whereas it is alledged by divers Britiſh merchants and others his Majeſty's ſubjects, that debts to a conſiderable amount, which were <hi>bona fide</hi> contracted before the peace, ſtill remain owing to them by citizens or inhabitants of the United States; and that by the operation of various lawful impediments ſince the peace, not only the full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the ſaid debts has been delayed, but alſo the value and ſecurity thereof have been, in ſeveral inſtances, impaired and leſſened, ſo that by the ordinary courſe of judicial proceedings, the Britiſh creditors cannot now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and actually have and receive full and adequate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation for the loſſes and damages which they have thereby ſuſtained. It is agreed, that in all ſuch caſes, where full compenſation for ſuch loſſes and damages can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, for whatever reaſon, be actually obtained, had and received by the ſaid creditors in the ordinary courſe of juſtice, the United States will make full and complete compenſation for the ſame to the ſaid creditors; but it is diſtinctly underſtood, that this proviſion is to extend to ſuch loſſes only as have been occaſioned by the lawful impediments aforeſaid, and is not to extend to loſſes oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by ſuch inſolvency of the debtors, or other cauſes as would equally have operated to produce ſuch a loſs, if the ſame impediments had not exiſted: nor to ſuch loſſes or damages as have been occaſioned by the manifeſt delay or negligence, or wilful omiſſion of the claimant.</p>
               <p>For the purpoſe of aſcertaining the amount of any ſuch loſſes or damages, five Commiſſioners ſhall be appointed, and authorized to meet and act in manner following, viz. two of them ſhall be appointed by his Majeſty, two of them by the Preſident of the United States by and with the advice and conſent of the Senate thereof, and the fifth by the unanimous voice of the other four; and if they ſhould not agree in ſuch choice, then the Commiſſioners named by the two parties ſhall reſpectively propoſe one perſon, and of the two names ſo propoſed, one ſhall be drawn by lot, in the preſence of the four original Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners. When the five Commiſſioners thus appointed ſhall firſt meet, they ſhall, before they proceed to act, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively take the following oath or affirmation, in the preſence of each other, which oath or affirmation, being
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:033045_0030_0FF62F835E9744B0"/>
ſo taken and duly atteſted, ſhall be entered on the record of their proceedings, viz.
<q>I <hi>A. B.</hi> one of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners appointed in purſuance of the ſixth article of the Treaty of Amity, Commerce, and Navigation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his Britannic Majeſty and the United States of America, do ſolemnly ſwear, <hi>or affirm,</hi> that I will hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly, diligently, impartially, and carefully examine, and to the beſt of my judgment, according to juſtice and equity, decide all ſuch complaints, as, under the the ſaid article, ſhall be preferred to the ſaid Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners: and that I will forbear to act as a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner, in any caſe in which I may be perſonally inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſted.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Three of the ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall conſtitute a board, and ſhall have power to do any act appertaining to the ſaid commiſſion, provided that one of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners named on each ſide, and the fifth Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſhall be preſent, and all deciſions ſhall be made by the majority of the voices of the Commiſſioners then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Eighteen months from the day on which the ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall form a board, and be ready to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to buſineſs, are aſſigned for receiving complaints and applications; but they are nevertheleſs authoriſed in any particular caſes in which it ſhall appear to them to be reaſonable and juſt, to extend the ſame term of eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen months for any term not exceeding ſix months, after the expiration thereof. The ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall firſt meet at Philadelphia, but they ſhall have power to adjourn from place to place as they ſhall ſee cauſe.</p>
               <p>The ſaid Commiſſioners in examining the complaints and applications ſo preferred to them, are empowered and required, in purſuance of the true intent and meaning of this article, to take into their conſideration all claims, whether of principal or intereſt, and balances of principal or intereſt, to determine the ſame reſpectively, according to the merits of the ſeveral caſes, due regard being had to all the circumſtances thereof, and as equity and juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice ſhall appear to them to require. And the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſhall have power to examine all ſuch perſons as ſhall come before them, on oath or affirmation, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the premiſes; and alſo to receive in evidence, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as they may think moſt conſiſtent with equity and
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:033045_0031_0FF62F854976DDE8"/>
juſtice, all written depoſitions, or books, or papers, or copies or extracts thereof, every ſuch depoſition, book, or paper, or extract, being duly authenticated, either ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the legal forms now reſpectively exiſting in the two countries, or in ſuch other manner as the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſhall ſee cauſe to require or allow.</p>
               <p>The award of the ſaid Commiſſioners or of any three of them as aforeſaid, ſhall in all caſes be final and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſive, both as to the juſtice of the claim, and to the amount of the ſum to be paid to the creditor or claimant: and the United States undertake to cauſe the ſum ſo awarded to be paid in ſpecie to ſuch creditor or claimant without deduction; and at ſuch time or times, and at ſuch place or places as ſhall be awarded by the ſaid Commiſſioners; and on condition of ſuch releaſes or aſſignments to be given by the creditor or claimant, as by the ſaid Commiſſioners may be directed: Provided always, that no ſuch payment ſhall be fixed by the ſaid Commiſſioners to take place ſooner than twelve months from the day of exchange of the ratification of this Treaty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE VII.</head>
               <p>Whereas complaints have been made by divers mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and others, citizens of the United States, that during the courſe of the war in which his Majeſty is now engaged, they have ſuſtained conſiderable loſſes and damage, by reaſon of irregular or illegal captures or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnations of their veſſels and other property, under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of authority or commiſſions from his Majeſty; and that from various circumſtances belonging to the ſaid caſes, adequate compenſation for the loſſes and damages ſo ſuſtained cannot now be actually obtained, had and received by the ordinary courſe of judicial proceedings; it is agreed, that in all ſuch caſes, where adequate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation cannot, for whatever reaſon, be now actually obtained, had and received by the ſaid merchants and others in the ordinary courſe of juſtice, full and complete compenſation for the ſame will be made by the Britiſh Government to the ſaid complainants. But it is diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood that this proviſion is not to extend to ſuch loſſes or damages as have been occaſioned by the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt delay or negligence, or wilful omiſſion of the claimants.</p>
               <p>That for the purpoſe of aſcertaining the amount of any
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:033045_0032_0FF62F873578B880"/>
ſuch loſſes and damages, five Commiſſioners ſhall be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and authoriſed to act in London, exactly in the manner directed with reſpect to thoſe mentioned in the preceding article, and after having taken the ſame oath or affirmation (<hi>mutatis mutandis</hi>), the ſame term of eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen months is alſo aſſigned for the reception of claims, and they are, in like manner, authoriſed to extend the ſame in particular caſes. They ſhall receive teſtimony, books, papers, and evidence in the ſame latitude, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the like diſcretion and powers reſpecting that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and ſhall decide the claims in queſtion according to the merits of the ſeveral caſes, and to juſtice, equity, and the laws of nations. The award of the ſaid Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or any ſuch three of them as aforeſaid, ſhall, in all caſes, be final and concluſive, both as to the juſtice of the claim and the amount of the ſum to be paid to the claimant; and his Britannic Majeſty undertakes to cauſe the ſame to be paid to ſuch claimant in ſpecie, without any deduction, at ſuch place or places, and at ſuch time or times as ſhall be awarded by the ſaid Commiſſioners, and on condition of ſuch releaſes or aſſignments to be given by the claimants, as by the ſaid Commiſſioners may be directed.</p>
               <p>And whereas certain merchants and others his Majeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty's ſubjects complain, that in the courſe of the war, they have ſuſtained loſs and damage, by reaſon of the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the veſſels and merchandize, taken within the limits and juriſdiction of the ſtates, and brought into the ports of the ſame, or taken by veſſels originally armed in ports of the ſaid ſtates:</p>
               <p>It is agreed, that in all ſuch caſes, where reſtitution ſhall not have been made agreeably to the tenor of the letter from Mr. Jefferſon to Mr. Hammond, dated at Philadelphia, Sept. 5, 1793, a copy of which is annexed to this Treaty; the complaints of the parties ſhall be and hereby are referred to the Commiſſioners to be appointed by virtue of this article, who are hereby authorized and required to proceed in the like manner relative to theſe as to the other caſes committed to them; and the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States undertake to pay to the complainants or claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants in ſpecie, without deduction, the amount of ſuch ſums as ſhall be awarded to them reſpectively by the ſaid
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:033045_0033_0FF62F88E15514C0"/>
Commiſſioners, and at the times and places which in ſuch awards ſhall be ſpecified; and on condition of ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſes or aſſignments to be given by the claimants as in the ſaid awards may be directed: And it is further agreed, that not-only the now exiſting caſes of both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, but alſo all ſuch as ſhall exiſt at the time of exchanging the ratifications of this Treaty, ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as being within the proviſions, intent, and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this article.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE VIII.</head>
               <p>It is further agreed, that the Commiſſioners mentioned in this and the two preceding articles, ſhall be reſpectively paid in ſuch manner as ſhall be agreed upon by the two parties; ſuch agreement being to be ſettled at the time of the exchange of the ratifications of this Treaty. And all other expenſes attending the ſaid commiſſions, ſhall be defrayed jointly by the two parties, the ſame being previouſly aſcertained and allowed by the majority of the Commiſſioners. And in the caſe of death, ſickneſs, or neceſſary abſence, the place of every ſuch Commiſſioner reſpectively, ſhall be ſupplied in ſuch manner as ſuch Commiſſioner was firſt appointed, and the new Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners ſhall take the ſame oath or affirmation, and do the ſame duties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE IX.</head>
               <p>It is agreed, that Britiſh ſubjects who now hold lands in the territories of the United States, and American cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>izens who now hold lands in the dominions of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, ſhall continue to hold them according to the nature and tenure of their reſpective eſtates and titles therein; and may grant, ſell or deviſe the ſame to whom they pleaſe, in like manner as if they were natives; and that neither they nor their heirs or aſſigns ſhall, ſo far as may reſpect the ſaid lands and the legal remedies incident thereto, be regarded as aliens.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE X.</head>
               <p>Neither the debts due from individuals of the one na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to individuals of the other, nor ſhares, nor monies which they may have in the public funds, or in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic or private banks, ſhall ever in any event of war or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional differences, be ſequeſtered or confiſcated, it being unjuſt and impolitic, that debts and engagements con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:033045_0034_0FF62F8B30F589F0"/>
and made by individuals having confidence in each other, and in their reſpective governments, ſhould ever be deſtroyed or impaired by national authority, on account of national differences and diſcontents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XI.</head>
               <p>It is agreed, between his Majeſty and the United States of America, that there ſhall be a reciprocal and entirely perfect liberty of navigation and commerce between their reſpective people, in the manner, under the limitations, and on the conditions ſpecified in the following articles:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XII.</head>
               <p>His Majeſty conſents, that it ſhall and may be lawful during the time herein after limited, for the citizens of the United States to carry to any of his Majeſty's iſlands and ports in the Weſt-Indies from the United States, in their own veſſels, not being above the burthen of ſeventy tons, any goods or merchandiſes, being of the growth, manufacture or produce of the ſaid ſtates, which it is or may be lawful to carry to the ſaid iſlands or ports from the ſaid ſtates in Britiſh veſſels; and that the ſaid Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can veſſels ſhall be ſubject there to no other or higher tonnage duties or charges, than ſhall be payable by Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh veſſels in the ports of the United States; and that the cargoes of the ſaid American veſſels ſhall be ſubject there to no other or higher duties or charges, than ſhall be payable on the like articles if imported there from the ſaid ſtates in Britiſh veſſels.</p>
               <p>And his Majeſty alſo conſents, that it ſhall be lawful for the ſaid American citizens to purchaſe, load, and carry away in their ſaid veſſels to the United States, from the ſaid iſlands and ports, all ſuch articles, being of the growth, manufacture or produce of the ſaid iſlands, as may now by law be carried from thence to the ſaid ſtates in Britiſh veſſels, and ſubject only to the ſame duties and charges on exportation, to which Britiſh veſſels and their cargoes are or ſhall be ſubject in ſimilar circumſtances.</p>
               <p>Provided always, that the ſaid American veſſels do car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and land their cargoes in the United States only, it being expreſsly agreed and declared, that during the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of this article, the United States will prohibit and reſtrain the carrying away any molaſſes, ſugar, coffee, cocoa or cotton in American veſſels, either from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:033045_0035_0FF62F8D1B350AC8"/>
iſlands, or from the United States, to any part of the world except the United States, reaſonable ſea ſtores excepted Provided alſo, that it ſhall and may be lawful, during the ſame period, for Britiſh veſſels to import from the ſaid iſlands into the United States, and to export from the United States to the ſaid iſlands, all articles whatever, being of the growth, produce or manufacture of the ſaid iſlands, or of the United States reſpectively, which now may, by the laws of the ſaid ſtates, be ſo imported and exported. And that the cargoes of the ſaid Britiſh veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels ſhall be ſubject to no other or higher duties or charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, than ſhall be payable on the ſame articles, if ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported or exported in American veſſels.</p>
               <p>It is agreed, that this article and every matter and thing therein contained, ſhall continue to be in force dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the continuance of the war in which his Majeſty is now engaged; and alſo for two years from and after the day of the ſignature of the preliminary or other articles of peace, by which the ſame may be terminated.</p>
               <p>And it is further agreed, that at the expiration of the ſaid term, the two contracting parties will endeavour fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to regulate their commerce in this reſpect according to the ſituation in which his Majeſty may then find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with reſpect to the Weſt-Indies, and with a view to ſuch arrangements as may beſt conduce to the mutual advantage and extenſion of commerce. And the ſaid parties will then alſo renew their diſcuſſions, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to agree, whether in any and what caſes neutral veſſels ſhall protect enemy's property; and in what caſes, proviſions and other articles, not generally contraband, may become ſuch. But in the mean time, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct towards each other in theſe reſpects, ſhall be regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the articles herein after inſerted on thoſe ſubjects.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XIII.</head>
               <p>His Majeſty conſents, that the veſſels belonging to the citizens of the United States of America, ſhall be admitted and hoſpitably received, in all the ſea-ports and harbours of the Britiſh territories in the Eaſt-Indies. And that the citizens of the ſaid United States, may freely carry on a trade between the ſaid territories and the ſaid United States, in all articles of which the importation or expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation reſpectively, to or from the ſaid territories, ſhall
<pb n="37" facs="unknown:033045_0036_0FF62F8EA7926EA0"/>
not be entirely prohibited. Provided only, that it ſhall not be lawful for them in any time of war between the Britiſh government and any other power or ſtate what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to export from the ſaid territories, without the ſpecial permiſſion of the Britiſh government there, any military ſtores, or naval ſtores, or rice. The citizens of the United States ſhall pay for their veſſels, when admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the ſaid ports, no other or higher tonnage duty than ſhall be payable on Britiſh veſſels, when admitted into the ports of the United States. And they ſhall pay no other or higher duties or charges, on the importation or exportation of the cargoes of the ſaid veſſels, than ſhall be payable on the ſame articles when imported or exported in Britiſh veſſels. But it is expreſsly agreed, that the veſſels of the United States ſhall not carry any of the articles exported by them from the ſaid Britiſh territories, to any port or place, except to ſome port or place in America, where the ſame ſhall be unladen, and ſuch regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations ſhall be adopted by both parties, as ſhall from time to time be found neceſſary to enforce the due and faithful obſervance of this ſtipulation. It is alſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that the permiſſion granted by this article, is not to extend to allow the veſſels of the United States to carry on any part of the coaſting trade of the ſaid Britiſh terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories; but veſſels going with their original cargoes, or part thereof, from one port of diſcharge to another, are not to be conſidered as carrying on the coaſting trade. Neither is this article to be conſtrued to allow the citizens of the ſaid ſtates to ſettle or reſide within the ſaid territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or to go into the interior parts thereof, without the permiſſion of the Britiſh government eſtabliſhed there; and if any tranſgreſſion ſhould be attempted againſt the regulations of the Britiſh government in this reſpect, the obſervance of the ſame ſhall and may be enforced againſt the citizens of America in the ſame manner as againſt Britiſh ſubjects, or others tranſgreſſing the ſame rule. And the citizens of the United States, whenever they arrive in any port or harbour in the ſaid territories, or if they ſhould be permitted in manner aforeſaid, to go to any other place therein, ſhall always be ſubject to the laws, government and juriſdiction of what nature eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in ſuch harbour, port or place, according as the
<pb n="38" facs="unknown:033045_0037_0FF62F90B9EBC628"/>
ſame may be. The citizens of the United States may alſo touch for refreſhment at the iſland of St. Helena, but ſubject in all reſpects to ſuch regulations as the Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh government may from time to time eſtabliſh there.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XIV.</head>
               <p>There ſhall be between all the dominions of his Majeſty in Europe and the territories of the United States, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocal and perfect liberty of commerce and navigation. The people and inhabitants of the two countries reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, ſhall have liberty freely and ſecurely, and without hindrance and moleſtation, to come with their ſhips and cargoes to the lands, countries, cities, ports, places, and rivers, within the dominions and territories aforeſaid, to enter into the ſame, to reſort there, and to remain and reſide there, without any limitation of time. Alſo to hire and poſſeſs houſes and warehouſes for the purpoſes of their commerce, and generally the merchants and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders on each ſide, ſhall enjoy the moſt complete protection and ſecurity for their commerce; but ſubject always, as to what reſpects this article, to the laws and ſtatutes of the two countries reſpectively.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XV.</head>
               <p>It is agreed, that no other or higher duties ſhall be paid by the ſhips or merchandiſe of the one party in the ports of the other, than ſuch as are paid by the like veſſels or merchandiſe of all other nations. Nor ſhall any other or higher duty be impoſed, in one country, on the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of any articles of the growth, produce, or manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture of the other, than are or ſhall be payable on the importation of the like articles being of the growth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, or manufacture of any other foreign country. Nor ſhall any prohibition be impoſed on the exportation or importation of any articles to or from the territories of the two parties reſpectively, which ſhall not equally extend to all other nations.</p>
               <p>But the Britiſh government reſerves to itſelf the right of impoſing on American veſſels entering into the Britiſh ports in Europe, a tonnage duty equal to that which ſhall be payable by Britiſh veſſels in the ports of America: and alſo ſuch duty as may be adequate to countervail the difference of duty now payable on the importation of
<pb n="39" facs="unknown:033045_0038_0FF62F932D35C2D0"/>
European and Aſiatic goods, when imported into the United States in Britiſh or in American veſſels.</p>
               <p>The two parties agree to treat for the more exact equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ization of the duties on the reſpective navigation of their ſubjects and people, in ſuch manner as may be moſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial to the two countries. The arrangements for this purpoſe ſhall be made at the ſame time, with thoſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned at the concluſion of the twelfth article of this Treaty, and are to be conſidered as a part thereof. In the interval, it is agreed, that the United States will not impoſe any new or additional tonnage duties on Britiſh veſſels, nor increaſe the now ſubſiſting difference between the duties payable on the importation of any articles in Britiſh or in American veſſels.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XVI.</head>
               <p>It ſhall be free for the two contracting parties, reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively to appoint conſuls for the protection of trade, to reſide in the dominions and territories aforeſaid; and the ſaid conſuls ſhall enjoy thoſe liberties and rights which belong to them by reaſon of their function. But before any conſul ſhall act as ſuch, he ſhall be in the uſual forms approved and admitted by the party to whom he is ſent; and it is hereby declared to be lawful and proper, that in caſe of illegal or improper conduct towards the laws or government, a conſul may either be puniſhed according to law, if the laws will reach the caſe, or be diſmiſſed, or even ſent back, the offended government aſſigning to the other their reaſons for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Either of the parties may except from the reſidence of conſuls ſuch particular places, as ſuch party ſhall judge proper to be ſo excepted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XVII.</head>
               <p>It is agreed, that in all caſes where veſſels ſhall be cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured or detained on juſt ſuſpicion of having on board enemy's property, or of carrying to the enemy any of the articles which are contraband of war; the ſaid veſſel ſhall be brought to the neareſt or moſt convenient port; and if any property of an enemy ſhould be found on board ſuch veſſel, that part only which belongs to the enemy ſhall be made prize, and the veſſel ſhall be at liberty to proceed with the remainder without any impediment. And it is agreed, that all proper meaſures ſhall be taken
<pb n="40" facs="unknown:033045_0039_0FF62F9516CD5760"/>
to prevent delay, in deciding the caſes of ſhips or cargoes ſo brought in for adjudication; and in the payment or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of any indemnification, adjudged or agreed to be paid to the maſter or owner of ſuch ſhips.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XVIII.</head>
               <p>In order to regulate what is in future to be deemed contraband of war, it is agreed, that under the ſaid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination ſhall be compriſed all arms and implements ſerving for the purpoſes of war, by land or ſea, ſuch as cannon, muſkets, mortars, petards, bombs, grenadoes, carcaſſes, ſauciſſes, carriages for cannon, muſkets' reſts, bandoliers, gun powder, match, ſalt-petre, ball, pikes, ſwords, head-pieces, cuiraſſes, halberds, lances, javelins, horſe furniture, holſters, belts, and generally all other implements of war; as alſo timber for ſhip-building, tar or rozin, copper in ſheets, ſails, hemp and cordage, and generally whatever may ſerve directly to the equipment of veſſels, unwrought iron and ſir-planks only excepted; and all the above articles are hereby declared to be juſt objects of confiſcation, whenever they are attempted to be carried to an enemy.</p>
               <p>And whereas the difficulty of agreeing on the preciſe caſes in which alone proviſions and other articles not generally contraband may be regarded as ſuch, renders it expedient to provide againſt the inconveniencies and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtandings which might thence ariſe: It is further agreed, that whenever any ſuch articles ſo becoming con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traband, according to the exiſting laws of nations, ſhall for that reaſon be ſeized, the ſame ſhall not be confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but the owners thereof ſhall be ſpeedily and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletely indemnified; and the captors, or in their default, the government under whoſe authority they act, ſhall pay to the maſters or owners of ſuch veſſels, the full value of all ſuch articles, with a reaſonable mercantile profit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, together with the freight, and alſo the demurrage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to ſuch detention.</p>
               <p>And whereas it frequently happens that veſſels ſail for a port or place belonging to an enemy, without knowing that the ſame is either beſieged, blockaded, or inveſted; it is agreed, that every veſſel ſo circumſtanced, may be turned away from ſuch port or place, but ſhe ſhall not be detained, nor her cargo, if not contraband, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated,
<pb n="41" facs="unknown:033045_0040_0FF62F96A0F689A0"/>
unleſs after notice ſhe ſhall again attempt to enter; but ſhe ſhall be permitted to go to any other port or place ſhe may think proper: Nor ſhall any veſſel or goods of either party, that may have entered into ſuch port or place, before the ſame was beſieged, blockaded or inveſted by the other, and be found therein after the reduction or ſurrender of ſuch place, be liable to confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but ſhall be reſtored to the owners or proprietors thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XIX.</head>
               <p>And that more abundant care may be taken for the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the reſpective ſubjects and citizens of the contracting parties, and to prevent their ſuffering injuries by the men of war, or privateers of either party, all commanders of ſhips of war and privateers, and all others the ſaid ſubjects and citizens, ſhall forbear doing any damage to thoſe of the other party, or committing any outrage againſt them, and if they act to the contrary, they ſhall be puniſhed, and ſhall alſo be bound in their perſons and eſtates to make ſatisfaction and reparation for all damages, and the intereſt thereof, of whatever nature the ſaid damages may be.</p>
               <p>For this cauſe all commanders of privateers, before they receive their commiſſions, ſhall hereafter be obliged to give before a competent judge, ſufficient ſecurity, by at leaſt two reſponſible ſureties, who have no intereſt in the ſaid privateer, each of whom, together with the ſaid commander, ſhall be jointly and ſeverally bound in the ſum of fifteen hundred pounds ſterling, or if ſuch ſhips be provided with above one hundred and fifty ſeamen or ſoldiers, in the ſum of three thouſand pounds ſterling, to ſatisfy all damages and injuries, which the ſaid privateer, or her officers or men, or any of them may do or commit during their cruiſe, contrary to the tenor of this Treaty, or to the laws and inſtructions for regulating their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct; and further, that in all caſes of aggreſſions, the ſaid commiſſions ſhall be revoked and annulled.</p>
               <p>It is alſo agreed, that whenever a judge of a court of admiralty of either of the parties, ſhall pronounce ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt any veſſel, or goods or property belonging to the ſubjects or citizens of the other party, a formal and duly authenticated copy of all the proceedings in the
<pb n="42" facs="unknown:033045_0041_0FF62F9840B0F4C8"/>
cauſe, and of the ſaid ſentence, ſhall, if required, be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the commander of the ſaid veſſel, without the ſmalleſt delay, he paying all legal fees and demands for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XX.</head>
               <p>It is further agreed, that both the ſaid contracting par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſhall not only refuſe to receive any pirates into any of their ports, havens, or towns, or permit any of their inhabitants to receive, protect, harbour, conceal or aſſiſt them in any manner, but will bring to condign puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment all ſuch inhabitants as ſhall be guilty of ſuch acts or offences.</p>
               <p>And all their ſhips, with the goods or merchandiſes taken by them and brought into the port of either of the ſaid parties, ſhall be ſeized as far as they can be diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſhall be reſtored to the owners, or their factors or agents, duly deputed and authorized in writing by them (proper evidence being firſt given in the court of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty for proving the property) even in caſe ſuch effects ſhould have paſſed into other hands by ſale, if it be prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the buyers knew, or had good reaſon to believe, or ſuſpect that they had been piratically taken.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XXI.</head>
               <p>It is likewiſe agreed, that the ſubjects and citizens of the two nations, ſhall not do any acts of hoſtility or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence againſt each other, nor accept commiſſions or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions ſo to act from any foreign prince or ſtate, ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the other party; nor ſhall the enemies of one of the parties be permitted to invite, or endeavor to enliſt in their military ſervice any of the ſubjects or citizens of the other party; and the laws againſt all ſuch offences and aggreſſions, ſhall be punctually executed. And if any ſubject or citizen of the ſaid parties reſpectively, ſhall accept any foreign commiſſion, or letters of marque, for arming any veſſel to act as a privateer againſt the other party, and be taken by the other party, it is hereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be lawful for the ſaid party to treat and puniſh the ſaid ſubject or citizen, having ſuch commiſſion or let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of marque, as a pirate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XXII.</head>
               <p>It is expreſsly ſtipulated, that neither of the ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting parties will order or authorize any acts of reprizal
<pb n="43" facs="unknown:033045_0042_0FF62F9AB10B57F8"/>
againſt the other, on complaint of injuries or damages, until the ſaid party ſhall firſt have preſented to the other a ſtatement thereof, verified by competent proof and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and demanding juſtice and ſatisfaction, and the ſame ſhall either have been refuſed or unreaſonably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XXIII.</head>
               <p>The ſhips of war of each of the contracting parties ſhall at all times be hoſpitably received in the ports of the other, their officers and crews paying due reſpect to the laws and government of the country. The officers ſhall be treated with that reſpect which is due to the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which they bear, and if any inſult ſhould be offered to them by any of the inhabitants, all offenders in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſhall be puniſhed as diſturbers of the peace and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity between the two countries.—And his Majeſty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, that in caſe an American veſſel ſhould, by ſtreſs of weather, danger from enemies, or other misfortune, be reduced to the neceſſity of ſeeking ſhelter in any of his Majeſty's ports, into which ſuch veſſel could not in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary caſes claim to be admitted, ſhe ſhall, on manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that neceſſity to the ſatisfaction of the government of the place, be hoſpitably received and permitted to reſit, and to purchaſe at the market price, ſuch neceſſaries as ſhe may ſtand in need of, conformably to ſuch orders and regulations as the government of the place, having reſpect to the circumſtances of each caſe, ſhall preſcribe. She ſhall not be allowed to break bulk or unload her cargo, unleſs the ſame ſhall be <hi>bona fide</hi> neceſſary to her being reſitted. Nor ſhall ſhe be permitted to ſell any part of her cargo, unleſs ſo much only as may be neceſſary to defray her expenſes, and then not without the expreſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the government of the place. Nor ſhall ſhe be obliged to pay any duties whatever, except only on ſuch articles as ſhe may be permitted to ſell for the purpoſe aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XXIV.</head>
               <p>It ſhall not be lawful for any foreign privateers (not being ſubjects or citizens of either of the ſaid parties) who have commiſſions from any other prince or ſtate in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with either nation, to arm their ſhips in the ports of either of the ſaid parties, nor to ſell what they have tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,
<pb n="44" facs="unknown:033045_0043_0FF62F9CF55A3FB8"/>
nor in any manner to exchange the ſame; nor ſhall they be allowed to purchaſe more proviſions, than ſhall be neceſſary for their going to the neareſt port of that prince or ſtate from whom they obtained their commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XXV.</head>
               <p>It ſhall be lawful for the ſhips of war and privateers belonging to the ſaid parties reſpectively, to carry whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they pleaſe, the ſhips and goods taken from their enemies, without being obliged to pay any ſee to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the admiralty, or to any judges whatever; nor ſhall the ſaid prizes when they arrive at, and enter the ports of the ſaid parties, be detained or ſeized; neither ſhall the ſearchers or other officers of thoſe places viſit ſuch prizes (except for the purpoſe of preventing the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying of any part of the cargo thereof on ſhore in any manner contrary to the eſtabliſhed laws of revenue, navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, or commerce) nor ſhall ſuch officers take cogniz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>once of the validity of ſuch prizes; but they ſhall be at liberty to hoiſt ſail, and depart as ſpeedily as may be, and carry their ſaid prizes to the place mentioned in their commiſſions or patents, which the commanders of the ſaid ſhips of war or privateers ſhall be obliged to ſhew. No ſhelter or refuge ſhall be given in their ports to ſuch as have made a prize upon the ſubjects or citizens of either of the ſaid parties: but if forced by ſtreſs of weather, or the dangers of the ſea, to enter therein, particular care ſhall be taken to haſten their departure, and to cauſe them to retire as ſoon as poſſible. Nothing in this Treaty contained ſhall, however, be conſtrued or operate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to former and exiſting public treaties with other ſovereigns or ſtates. But the two parties agree, that while they continue in amity, neither of them will, in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, make any Treaty that ſhall be inconſiſtent with this or the preceding article.</p>
               <p>Neither of the ſaid parties ſhall permit the ſhips or goods belonging to the ſubjects or citizens of the other, to be taken within cannon ſhot of the coaſt, nor in any of the bays, ports, or rivers of their territories, by ſhips of war, or others having commiſſion from any prince, repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic, or ſtate whatever. But in caſe it ſhould ſo happen, the party whoſe territorial rights ſhall thus have been vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated,
<pb n="45" facs="unknown:033045_0044_0FF62F9E92FEC718"/>
ſhall uſe his utmoſt endeavours to obtain from the offending party, full and ample ſatisfaction for the veſſel or veſſels ſo taken, whether the ſame be veſſels of war or merchant veſſels.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XXVI.</head>
               <p>If, at any time, a rupture ſhould take place (which God forbid!) between his Majeſty and the United States, the merchants and others of each of the two nations, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding in the dominions of the other, ſhall have the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of remaining and continuing their trade, ſo long as they behave peaceably and commit no offence againſt the laws; and in caſe their conduct ſhould render them ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and the reſpective governments ſhould think proper to order them to remove <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he term of twelve mouths from the publication of the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er, ſhall be allowed them for that purpoſe, to remove with their families, effects and property; but this favour ſhall not be extended to thoſe who ſhall act contrary to the eſtabliſhed laws; and for greater certainty, it is declared that ſuch rupture ſhall not be deemed to exiſt while negociations for accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dating differences ſhall be depending, nor until the reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ambaſſadors or miniſters, if ſuch there ſhall be, ſhall be recalled, or ſent home on account of ſuch differences, and not on account of perſonal miſconduct, according to the nature and degrees of which both parties retain their rights, either to requeſt the recal, or immediately to ſend home the ambaſſador or miniſter of the other; and that without prejudice to their mutual friendſhip and good underſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XXVII.</head>
               <p>It is further agreed, that his Majeſty and the United States, on mutual requiſitions, by them reſpectively, or by their reſpective miniſters or officers authorized to make the ſame, will deliver up to juſtice all perſons, who, being charged with murder or forgery, committed within the juriſdiction of either, ſhall ſeek an aſylum within any of the countries of the other, provided that this ſhall only be done on ſuch evidence of criminality as, according to the laws of the place, where the fugitive or perſon ſo charged ſhall be found, would juſtify his apprehenſion and commitment for trial, if the offence had there been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. The expenſe of ſuch apprehenſion and delivery
<pb n="46" facs="unknown:033045_0045_0FF62FA01FBE1558"/>
ſhall be borne and defrayed, by thoſe who make the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition and receive the fugitive.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE XXVIII.</head>
               <p>It is agreed, that the firſt ten articles of this Treaty ſhall be permanent, and that the ſubſequent articles, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the twelfth, ſhall be limitted in their duration to twelve years, to be computed from the day on which the ratifications of this treaty ſhall be exchanged, but ſubject to this condition, That whereas the ſaid twelfth article will expire, by the limitation therein contained, at the end of two years from the ſigning the preliminary or other arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of peace, which ſhall terminate the preſent war in which his Majeſty is engaged, it is agreed, that proper meaſures ſhall by concert be taken, for bringing the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of that article into amicable treaty and diſcuſſion, ſo early before the expiration of the ſaid term, as that new arrangements on that head, may by that time be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ready to take place. But if it ſhould unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately happen, that his Majeſty and the United States, ſhould not be able to agree on ſuch new arrangements, in that caſe, all the articles of this Treaty, except the firſt ten, ſhall then ceaſe and expire together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>LASTLY.</head>
               <p>This Treaty, when the ſame ſhall have been ratified by his Majeſty, and by the Preſident of the United States, by and with the advice and conſent of their Senate, and the reſpective ratifications mutually exchanged, ſhall be bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and obligatory on his Majeſty and on the ſaid States, and ſhall be by them reſpectively executed, and obſerved, with punctuality, and the moſt ſincere regard to good faith; and whereas it will be expedient, in order the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to facilitate intercourſe, and obviate difficulties, that other articles be propoſed and added to this Treaty, which articles, from want of time and other circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, cannot now be perfected—it is agreed, that the ſaid parties will, from time to time, readily treat of and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch articles, and will ſincerely endeavour ſo to form them, as that they may conduce to mutual conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and tend to promote mutual ſatisfaction and friendſhip; and that the ſaid articles, after h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing been only ratified<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall be added to, and make a part of this
<pb n="47" facs="unknown:033045_0046_0FF62FA296281E80"/>
Treaty. In faith whereof, we, the underſigned Miniſters Plenipotentiary of his Majeſty the King of Great-Britain, and the United States of America, have ſigned this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Treaty, and have cauſed to be affixed thereto the ſeal of our arms.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Done at London, <date>this nineteenth day of Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, One thouſand ſeven hundred and ninety-four.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>GRENVILLE. (<hi>Seal.</hi>)</item>
                     <item>JOHN JAY. (<hi>Seal.</hi>)</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>

            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <head>ADDITIONAL ARTICLE.</head>
               <p>It is further agreed between the ſaid contracting par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that the operation of ſo much of the twelfth article of the ſaid treaty as reſpect the trade which his ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty thereby conſents may be carried on between the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States and his Iſlands in the Weſt-Indies, in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and on the terms and conditions therein ſpecified, ſhall be ſuſpended.</p>
            </postscript>
            <postscript>
               <head>EXPLANATORY ARTICLE.</head>
               <p>Whereas by the third article of the Treaty of Amity, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and Navigation, concluded at London on the 19th day of November, 1794, between his Britannic Majeſty and the United States of America, it was agreed, that it ſhould at all times be free to his Majeſty's ſubjects and to the citizens of the United States, and alſo to the Indians dwelling on either ſide of the boundary line aſſigned by the Treaty of Peace to the United States, freely to paſs and repaſs, by land or inland navigation, into the reſpective territories and countries of the two contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parties on the continent of America (the bay company only excepted) and to navigate all the lakes, rivers, and waters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and freely to carry on trade and commerce with each other, ſubject to the proviſions and limitations contained in the firſt article<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and whereas by the 8th article of the treaty of peace and friendſhip concluded at Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ville, on the 3d day of Auguſt. 1795, between the United States and the nations or tribes of Indians called the Wyandots, Delawares, Shawanees, Ottawas, Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppewas, Pattawatunies, Miamies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lkias, it was ſtipulated, that no perſon ſhould be permitted to reſide at any of the towns or having camps of the ſaid Indian tribes as a trader, who is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hed with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for that purpoſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="48" facs="unknown:033045_0047_0FF62FA4DB73E4A0"/>
of the United States, which latter ſtipulation has excited doubts whether in its operation it may not interfere with the due execution of the ſaid article of the Treaty of Amity, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and Navigation; and it being the ſincere deſire of his Britannic Majeſty, and of the United States, that this point ſhould be ſo explained as to remove all doubts, and to promote mutual ſatisfaction and friendſhip; and for this purpoſe his Britannic Majeſty having named for his Commiſſioner, PHINEAS BOND, Eſq. his Majeſty's conſul general for the middle and ſouthern ſtates of America (and his Majeſty's charge d'affairs to the United States) and the Preſident of the United States having named for their Commiſſioner, TIMOTHY PICKERING, Eſq. Secretary of State for the United States, to whom, agreeably to the laws of the United States, he has intruſted this negociation.</p>
               <p>They the ſaid Commiſſioners, having communicated to each other their full powers, have, in virtue of the ſame, and conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to the ſpirit of the laſt article of the ſaid Treaty of Amity, Commerce, and Navigation, entered into this explanatory arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and now, by theſe preſents, explicitly <hi>agree</hi> and <hi>declare,</hi> that no ſtipulations in any treaty ſubſequently concluded by either of the contracting parties within any other ſtate or nation, or with any Indian tribe, can be underſtood to derogate in any manner from the rights and free intercourſe and commerce ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by the aforeſaid third article of the treaty to the ſubjects of his Majeſty, and to the citizens of the United States, and Indians dwelling on either ſide of the boundary line aforeſaid; but that all the ſaid perſons ſhall remain at full liberty freely to paſs and repaſs, by land or inland navigation, into the reſpective territories and countries of the contracting parties, on either ſide of the ſaid boundary line, and freely to carry on trade and commerce with each other, according to the ſtipulations of the ſaid third article of the Treaty of Amity, Commerce, and Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. This explanatory article, when the ſame ſhall have been ratified by his Majeſty, and by the Preſident of the United States, by and with the advice and conſent of the Senate, and the reſpective ratifications mutually exchanged, ſhall be added to make a part of the ſaid Treaty of Amity, Commerce, and Navigation, and ſhall be permanently binding upon his Majeſty and the United States.</p>
               <p>In witneſs whereof, we the ſaid Commiſſioners of his Majeſty the King of Great-Britain and the United States of America, have ſigned this explanatory article, and thereto affixed our ſeals.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Done at Philadelphia, <date>this fourth day of May, in the year of our Lord One thouſand ſeven hundred and ninety-ſix.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>P. BOND, (Seal.)</item>
                        <item>T. PICKERING, (Seal.)</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="treaty">
            <pb n="49" facs="unknown:033045_0048_0FF62FA667DC0E48"/>
            <head>TREATY of Friendſhip, Limits and Navigation between the United States of Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, and the King of Spain.</head>
            <p>HIS Catholic Majeſty and the United States of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica, deſiring to conſolidate, on a permanent baſis, the friendſhip and good correſpondence, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily prevails between the two parties, have determined to eſtabliſh, by a convention, ſeveral points, the ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof will be productive of general advantage and reciprocal utility to both nations.</p>
            <p>With this intention, his Catholic Majeſty has appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the moſt excellent Lord, don Manuel de Godoy, and Alvarez de Faria, Rios, Sanchez, Zarzoſa, Prince de la Paz, duke de la Alcudia, lord of the Soto de Roma and of the ſtate of Albala, Grandee of Spain of the firſt claſs, perpetual regidor of the city of Santiago, knight of the illuſtrious order of the Golden Fleece, and Great Croſs of the Royal and diſtinguiſhed Spaniſh order of Charles the IIId. commander of Valencia, del Ventoſo, Rivera, and Acenchal in that of Santiago; Knight and Great Croſs of the religious order of St. John; Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of ſtate; firſt Secretary of ſtate and deſpacho; Sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retary to the Queen; Superintendant General of the poſts and highways; Protector of the royal Academy of the noble arts, and of the royal ſocieties of natural hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, botany, chemiſtry, and aſtronomy; Gentleman of the King's chamber in employment; Captain General of his armies; Inſpector and Major of the royal corps of body guards, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. and the Preſident of the United States, with the advice and conſent of their Senate, has appointed Thomas Pinckney, a citizen of the United States, and their Envoy Extraordinary to his Catholic Majeſty. And the ſaid Plenipotentiaries have agreed upon and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the following articles:</p>
            <p>
               <label>ARTICLE I.</label>
There ſhall be a firm and inviolable peace and ſincere friendſhip between his Catholic Majeſty, his ſucceſſors and
<pb n="50" facs="unknown:033045_0049_0FF62FA80C2734C0"/>
ſubjects, and the United States, and their citizens, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception of perſons or places.</p>
            <p>ART. II. To prevent all diſputes on the ſubject of the boundaries which ſeparate the territories of the two high contracting parties, it is hereby declared and agreed as follows, to wit. The ſouthern boundary of the United States, which divides their territory from the Spaniſh colonies of Eaſt and Weſt Florida, ſhall be deſignated by a line beginning on the river Miſſiſippi, at the northernmoſt part of the thirty-firſt degree of latitude north of the equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, which from thence ſhall be drawn due eaſt to the middle of the river Apalachicola, or Catahouche, thence along the middle thereof to its junction with the Flint: thence ſtrait to the head of St. Mary's river, and thence down the middle thereof to the Atlantic ocean. And it is agreed, that if there ſhould be any troops, garriſons, or ſettlements of either party, in the territory of the other, according to the abovementioned boundaries, they ſhall be withdrawn from the ſaid territory within the term of ſix months after the ratification of this treaty, or ſooner if it be poſſible; and that they ſhall be permitted to take with them all the goods and effects which they poſſeſs.</p>
            <p>ART. III. In order to carry the preceding article into effect, one commiſſioner and one ſurveyor ſhall be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by each of the contracting parties, who ſhall meet at the Natchez, on the left ſide of the river Miſſiſippi, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the expiration of ſix months from the ratification of this convention, and they ſhall proceed to run and mark this boundary according to the ſtipulations of the ſaid article. They ſhall make plats and keep journals of their proceedings, which ſhall be conſidered as part of this convention, and ſhall have the ſame force as if they were inſerted therein. And if on any account it ſhould be found neceſſary that the ſaid commiſſioners and ſurvey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors ſhould be accompanied by guards, they ſhall be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in equal proportions by the commanding officer of his Majeſty's troops in the two Floridas, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding officer of the troops of the United States in their ſouthweſtern territory, who ſhall act by common conſent, and amicably, as well with reſpect to this point as to the furniſhing of proviſions and inſtruments, and making every other arrangement which may be neceſſary or uſeful for the execution of this article.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="unknown:033045_0050_0FF62FAAAB328860"/>ART. IV. It is likewiſe agreed that the weſtern boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary of the United States which ſeparates them from the Spaniſh colony of Louiſiana, is in the middle of the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel or bed of the river Miſſiſippi, from the northern boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary of the ſaid ſtates to the completion of the thirty-firſt degree of latitude north of the equator. And his Catholic Majeſty has likewiſe agreed that the navigation of the ſaid river, in its whole breadth from its ſource to the ocean, ſhall be free only to his ſubjects and the citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the United States, unleſs he ſhould extend this privilege to the ſubjects of other powers by ſpecial con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention.</p>
            <p>ART. V. The two high contracting parties ſhall, by all the means in their power, maintain peace and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony among the ſeveral Indian nations who inhabit the country adjacent to the lines and rivers, which, by the preceding articles, form the boundaries of the two Flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das. And the better to obtain this effect, both parties oblige themſelves expreſsly to reſtrain by force all hoſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities on the part of the Indian nations living within their boundary: ſo that Spain will not ſuffer her Indians to attack the citizens of the United States, nor the Indians inhabiting their territory; nor will the United States permit theſe laſt-mentioned Indians to commence hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilities againſt the ſubjects of his Catholic Majeſty or his Indians, in any manner whatever.</p>
            <p>And whereas ſeveral treaties of friendſhip exiſt between the two contracting parties and the ſaid nations of Indians, it is hereby agreed that in future no treaty of alliance or other whatever (except treaties of peace) ſhall be made by either party with the Indians living within the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary of the other, but both parties will endeavour to make the advantages of the Indian trade common and mutually beneficial to their reſpective ſubjects and citizens, obſerving in all things the moſt complete reciprocity, ſo that both parties may obtain the advantages ariſing from a good underſtanding with the ſaid nations, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubject to the expence which they have hitherto occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned.</p>
            <p>ART. VI. Each party ſhall endeavour, by all means in their power, to protect and defend all veſſels and other effects belonging to the citizens or ſubjects of the other,
<pb n="52" facs="unknown:033045_0051_0FF62FACEDEFFAB0"/>
which ſhall be within the extent of their juriſdiction by ſea or by land, and ſhall uſe all their efforts to recover and cauſe to be reſtored to the right owners, their veſſels and effects which may have been taken from them within the extent of their ſaid juriſdiction, whether they are at war or not with the power whoſe ſubjects have taken poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſaid effects.</p>
            <p>ART. VII. And it is agreed that the ſubjects or citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of each of the contracting parties, their veſſels or effects, ſhall not be liable to any embargo or detention on the part of the other, for any military expedition or other public or private purpoſe whatever: And in all caſes of ſeizure, detention, or arreſt for debts contracted, or offences committed by any citizen or ſubject of the one party within the juriſdiction of the other, the ſame ſhall be made and proſecuted by order and authority of law only, and according to the regular courſe of proceedings uſual in ſuch caſes. The citizens and ſubjects of both parties ſhall be allowed to employ ſuch advocates, ſolicitors, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, agents and factors, as they may judge proper, in all their affairs, and in all their trials at law, in which they may be concerned, before the tribunals of the other party; and ſuch agents ſhall have free acceſs to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the proceedings in ſuch cauſes, and at the taking of all examinations and evidence which may be exhibited in the ſaid trials.</p>
            <p>ART. VIII. In caſe the ſubjects and inhabitants of either party, with their ſhipping, whether public and of war, or private and of merchants, be forced, through ſtreſs of weather, purſuit of pirates or enemies, or any other urgent neceſſity, for ſeeking of ſhelter and harbour, to retreat and enter into any of the rivers, bays, roads or ports belonging to the other party, they ſhall be received and treated with all humanity, and enjoy all favour, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and help, and they ſhall be permitted to refreſh and provide themſelves, at reaſonable rates, with victuals and all things needful for the ſuſtenance of their perſons, or reparation of their ſhips and proſecution of their voyage; and they ſhall no ways be hindered from returning out of the ſaid ports or roads, but may remove and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part when and whither they pleaſe, without any let or hindrance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="unknown:033045_0052_0FF62FAE8105EAC8"/>ART. IX. All ſhips and merchandize, of what nature ſoever, which ſhall be reſcued out of the hands of any pirates or robbers on the high ſeas, ſhall be brought into ſome port of either ſtate, and ſhall be delivered to the cuſtody of the officers of that port, in order to be taken care of, and reſtored entire to the true proprietor, as ſoon as due and ſufficient proof ſhall be made concerning the property thereof.</p>
            <p>ART. X. When any veſſel of either party ſhall be wrecked, foundered, or otherwiſe damaged, on the coaſts or within the dominion of the other, their reſpective ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects or citizens ſhall receive, as well for themſelves as for their veſſels and effects, the ſame aſſiſtance which would be due to the inhabitants of the country where the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age happens, and ſhall pay the ſame charges and dues only as the ſaid inhabitants would be ſubject to pay in a like caſe: And if the operations of repair ſhould require that the whole or any part of the cargo be unladen, they ſhall pay no duties, charges or fees on the part which they ſhall relade and cary away.</p>
            <p>ART. XI. The citizens and ſubjects of each party ſhall have power to diſpoſe of their perſonal goods with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the juriſdiction of the other, by teſtament, donation or otherwiſe, and their repreſentatives being ſubjects or citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the other party, ſhall ſucceed to their ſaid perſonal goods whether by teſtament or ab inteſtato, and they may take poſſeſſion thereof, either by themſelves or others act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them, and diſpoſe of the ſame at their will, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch dues as the inhabitants of the country wherein the ſaid goods are, ſhall be ſubject to pay in like caſes.</p>
            <p>And in caſe of the abſence of the repreſentatives, ſuch care ſhall be taken of the ſaid goods, as would be taken of the goods of a native in like caſe, until the lawful own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er may take meaſures for receiving them. And if queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall ariſe among ſeveral claimants to which of them the ſaid goods belong, the ſame ſhall be decided finally by the laws and judges of the land wherein the ſaid goods are. And where, on the death of any perſon holding real eſtate within the territories of the one party, ſuch real eſtate would by the laws of the land deſcend on a citizen or ſubject of the other, were he not diſqualified by being an alien, ſuch ſubject ſhall be allowed a reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="54" facs="unknown:033045_0053_0FF62FB034DDEF80"/>
time to ſell the ſame, and to withdraw the proceed, without moleſtation, and exempt from all rights of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction on the part of the government of the reſpective ſtates.</p>
            <p>ART. XII. The merchant-ſhips of either of the parties which ſhall be making into a port belonging to the enemy of the other party, and concerning whoſe voyage, and the ſpecies of goods on board her, there ſhall be juſt grounds of ſuſpicion, ſhall be obliged to exhibit as well upon the high ſeas as in the ports and havens, not only her paſſports, but likewiſe certificates, expreſsly ſhewing that her goods are not of the number of thoſe which have been prohibited as contraband.</p>
            <p>ART. XIII. For the better promoting of commerce on both ſides, it is agreed, that if a war ſhall break out between the ſaid two nations, one year after the procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of war ſhall be allowed to the merchants, in the cities and towns where they ſhall live, for collecting and tranſporting their goods and merchandizes: And if any thing be taken from them or any injury be done them within that term, by either party, or the people or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of either, full ſatisfaction ſhall be made for the ſame by the government.</p>
            <p>ART. XIV. No ſubject of his Catholic Majeſty ſhall apply for, or take any commiſſion or letters of marque, for arming any ſhip or ſhips to act as privateers againſt the ſaid United States, or againſt the citizens, people or inhabitants of the ſaid United States, or againſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of any of the inhabitants of any of them, from any prince or ſtate with which the ſaid United States ſhall be at war.</p>
            <p>Nor ſhall any citizen, ſubject or inhabitant of the ſaid United States apply for or take any commiſſion or let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of marque for arming any ſhip or ſhips to act as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateers againſt the ſubjects of his Catholic Majeſty, or the property of any of them, from any prince or ſtate with which the ſaid king ſhall be at war. And if any perſon of either nation ſhall take ſuch commiſſions or let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of marque, he ſhall be puniſhed as a pirate.</p>
            <p>ART. XV. It ſhall be lawful for all and ſingular the ſubjects of his Catholic Majeſty, and the citizens, people and inhabitants of the ſaid United States, to ſail with
<pb n="55" facs="unknown:033045_0054_0FF62FB2F0408618"/>
their ſhips, with all manner of liberty and ſecurity, no diſtinction being made who are the proprietors of the merchandizes laden thereon, from any port to the places of thoſe who now are, or hereafter ſhall be at enmity with his Catholic Majeſty or the United States. It ſhall be likewiſe lawful for the ſubjects and inhabitants afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, to ſail with the ſhips and merchandizes aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and to trade with the ſame liberty and ſecurity from the places, ports and havens of thoſe who are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of both or either party, without any oppoſition or diſturbance whatſoever, not only directly from the places of the enemy aforementioned, to neutral places, but alſo from one place belonging to an enemy, to another place belonging to an enemy, whether they be under the juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the ſame prince or under ſeveral; and it is hereby ſtipulated, that free ſhips ſhall alſo give freedom to goods, and that every thing ſhall be deemed free and exempt which ſhall be found on board the ſhips belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſubjects of either of the contracting parties, although the whole lading, or any part thereof, ſhould appertain to the enemies of either: Contraband goods being always excepted. It is alſo agreed, that the ſame liberty be extended to perſons who are on board a free ſhip, ſo that although they be enemies to either party, they ſhall not be made priſoners or taken out of that free ſhip, unleſs they are ſoldiers and in actual ſervice of the enemies.</p>
            <p>ART. XVI. This liberty of navigation and commerce ſhall extend to all kinds of merchandizes, excepting thoſe only, which are diſtinguiſhed by the name of contraband: And under this name of contraband or prohibited goods, ſhall be comprehended arms, great guns, bombs, with the fuſees, and the other things belonging to them, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non-ball, gunpowder, match, pikes, ſwords, lances, ſpears, halberds, mortars, petards, grenades, ſaltpetre, muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets, muſquet-ball, bucklers, helmets, breaſt-plates, coats of mail, and the like kinds of arms, proper for arming ſoldiers, muſquet reſts, belts, horſes with their furniture, and all other warlike inſtruments whatever. Theſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes which follow, ſhall not be reckoned among contraband or prohibited goods: That is to ſay, all ſorts of cloths, and all other manufactures woven of any wool,
<pb n="56" facs="unknown:033045_0055_0FF62FB4D9E8A120"/>
flax, ſilk, cotton, or any other materials whatever; all kinds of wearing apparel, together with all ſpecies where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they are uſed to be made; gold and ſilver, as well coined as uncoined, tin, iron, latten, copper, braſs, coals; as alſo wheat, barley and oats, and any other kind of corn and pulſe; tobacco, and likewiſe all manner of ſpices, ſalted and ſmoked fleſh, ſalted fiſh, cheeſe and but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, beer, oils, wines, ſugars, and all ſorts of ſalts: And in general, all proviſions which ſerve for the ſuſtenance of life: Furthermore, all kinds of cotton, hemp, flax, tar, pitch, ropes, cables, ſails, ſail-cloths, anchors, and any parts of anchors, alſo ſhips' maſts, planks and wood of all kind, and all other things proper either for building or repairing ſhips, and all other goods whatever, which have not been worked into the form of any inſtrument prepared for war, by land or by ſea, ſhall not be reputed contraband, much leſs, ſuch as have been already wrought and made up for any other uſe; all which ſhall be wholly reckoned among free goods: As likewiſe all oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er merchandizes and things which are not comprehended and particularly mentioned in the foregoing enumeration of contraband goods: So that they may be tranſported and carried in the freeſt manner by the ſubjects of both parties, even to places belonging to an enemy, ſuch towns or places being only excepted, as are at that time beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, blocked up, or inveſted. And except the caſes in which any ſhip of war, or ſquadron ſhall, in conſequence of ſtorms or other accidents at ſea, be under the neceſſity of taking the cargo of any trading veſſel or veſſels, in which caſe they may ſtop the ſaid veſſel or veſſels, and furniſh themſelves with neceſſaries, giving a receipt, in order that the power to whom the ſaid ſhip of war be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, may pay for the articles ſo taken, according to the price thereof, at the port to which they may appear to have been deſtined by the ſhip's papers; and the two contracting parties engage, that the veſſels ſhall not be detained longer than may be abſolutely neceſſary for their ſaid ſhips to ſupply themſelves with neceſſaries: That they will immediately pay the value of the receipts, and indemnify the proprietor for all loſſes which he may have ſuſtained in conſequence of ſuch tranſaction.</p>
            <p>ART. XVII. To the end, that all manner of diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="57" facs="unknown:033045_0056_0FF62FB676A107F8"/>
and quarrels may be avoided and prevented on one ſide and the other, it is agreed, that in caſe either of the parties hereto, ſhould be engaged in a war, the ſhips and veſſels belonging to the ſubjects or people of the other party muſt be furniſhed with ſea-letters or paſſports, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the name, property, and bulk of the ſhip, as alſo the name and place of habitation of the maſter or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the ſaid ſhip, that it may appear thereby, that the ſhip really and truly belongs to the ſubjects of one of the parties, which paſſport ſhall be made out and granted according to the form annexed to this treaty. They ſhall likewiſe be recalled every year, that is, if the ſhip hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to return home within the ſpace of a year.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe agreed, that ſuch ſhips being laden, are to be provided not only with paſſports as above-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but alſo with certificates, containing the ſeveral par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of the cargo, the place whence the ſhip ſailed, that ſo it may be known whether any forbidden or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traband goods be on board the ſame: which certificates ſhall be made out by the officers of the place whence the ſhip ſailed in the accuſtomed form: And if any one ſhall think it fit or adviſable to expreſs in the ſaid certificates, the perſon to whom the goods on board belong, he may freely do ſo: Without which requiſites they may be ſent to one of the ports of the other contracting party, and adjudged by the competent tribunal, according to what is above ſet forth, that all the circumſtances of this omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion having been well examined, they ſhall be adjudged to be legal prizes, unleſs they ſhall give legal ſatisfaction of their property by teſtimony entirely equivalent.</p>
            <p>ART. XVIII. If the ſhips of the ſaid ſubjects, people, or inhabitants of either of the parties, ſhall be met with, either ſailing along the coaſts or on the high ſeas, by any ſhip of war of the other, or by any privateer, the ſaid ſhip of war or privateer for the avoiding of any diſorder, ſhall remain out of cannon ſhot, and may ſend their boats a-board the merchant ſhip, which they ſhall ſo meet with, and may enter her to the number of two or three men only, to whom the maſter or commander of ſuch ſhip or veſſel ſhall exhibit his paſſports, concerning the property of the ſhip, made out according to the form inſerted in this preſent treaty, and the ſhip when ſhe ſhall have ſhewed
<pb n="58" facs="unknown:033045_0057_0FF62FB80ADC9808"/>
ſuch paſſport, ſhall be free and at liberty to purſue her voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, ſo as it ſhall not be lawful to moleſt or give her chace in any manner, or force her to quit her intended courſe.</p>
            <p>ART. XIX. Conſuls ſhall be reciprocally eſtabliſhed, with the privileges and powers which thoſe of the moſt favoured nations enjoy, in the ports where their conſuls reſide or are permitted to be.</p>
            <p>ART. XX. It is alſo agreed that the inhabitants of the territories of each party ſhall reſpectively have free acceſs to the courts of juſtice of the other, and they ſhall be permitted to proſecute ſuits for the recovery of their properties, the payment of their debts, and for obtaining ſatisfaction for the damages which they may have ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whether the perſons whom they may ſue be ſubjects or citizens of the country in which they may be found, or any other perſons whatſoever, who may have taken refuge therein; and the proceedings and ſentences of the ſaid courts ſhall be the ſame as if the contending parties had been ſubjects or citizens of the ſaid country.</p>
            <p>ART. XXI. In order to terminate all differences on account of the loſſes ſuſtained by the citizens of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States in conſequence of their veſſels and cargoes having been taken by the ſubjects of his Catholic Majeſty, during the late war between Spain and France, it is agreed that all ſuch caſes ſhall be referred to the final de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of commiſſioners to be appointed in the following manner. His Catholic Majeſty ſhall name one commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner, and the Preſident of the United States, by and with the advice and conſent of their Senate, ſhall appoint another, and the ſaid two commiſſioners ſhall agree on the choice of a third, or if they cannot agree ſo, they ſhall each propoſe one perſon, and of the two names ſo propoſed, one ſhall be drawn by lot in the preſence of the two original commiſſioners, and the perſon whoſe name ſhall be ſo drawn, ſhall be the third commiſſioner: And the three commiſſioners ſo appointed, ſhall be ſworn impartially to examine and decide the claims in queſtion, according to the merits of the ſeveral caſes, and to juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, equity, and the laws of nations. The ſaid commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners ſhall meet and ſit at Philadelphia: And in the caſe of the death, ſickneſs, or neceſſary abſence of any ſuch commiſſioner, his place ſhall be ſupplied in the ſame
<pb n="59" facs="unknown:033045_0058_0FF62FBADBAE1EE0"/>
manner as he was firſt appointed, and the new commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner ſhall take the ſame oaths, and do the ſame duties. They ſhall receive all complaints and applications author<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ized by this article, during eighteen months from the day on which they ſhall aſſemble. They ſhall have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to examine all ſuch perſons as come before them on oath or affirmation, touching the complaints in queſtion, and alſo to receive in evidence all written teſtimony, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticated in ſuch manner as they ſhall think proper to require or admit. The award of the ſaid commiſſioners, or any two of them, ſhall be final and concluſive, both as to the juſtice of the claim and the amount of the ſum to be paid to the claimants; and his Catholic Majeſty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to cauſe the ſame to be paid in ſpecie, without deduction, at ſuch times and places, and under ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions as ſhall be awarded by the ſaid commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>ART. XXII. The two high contracting parties, hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the good correſpondence and friendſhip which happily reigns between them, will be further encreaſed by this treaty, and that it will contribute to augment their proſperity and opulence, will in future give to their mutual commerce all the extenſion and favour which the advantages of both countries may require.</p>
            <p>And in conſequence of the ſtipulations contained in the 4th article, his Catholic Majeſty will permit the citizens of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited States, for the ſpace of three years from this time, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit their merchandizes and effects in the port of New-Orleans, and to export them from thence without paying any other duty than a fair price for the hire of the ſtores, and his Majeſty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes either to continue this permiſſion, if he finds during that time that it is not prejudicial to the intereſts of Spain, or if he ſhould not agree to continue it there, he will aſſign to them, on another part of the banks of the Miſſiſippi, an equivalent eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p>ART. XXIII. The preſent treaty ſhall not be in force un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til ratified by the contracting parties, and the ratifications ſhall be exchanged in ſix months from this time, or ſooner if poſſible.</p>
            <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, we, the underwritten plenipotentiaries of his Catholic Majeſty and of the United States of Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica, have ſigned this preſent treaty of friendſhip, limits and navigation, and have thereunto affixed our ſeals reſpectively.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>DONE at San Lorenzo el Real,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>this ſeven and twentieth day of October, one thouſand ſeven hundred and ninety-five.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>THOMAS PINCKNEY, (L. S.)</item>
                     <item>EL PRINCIPE DE LA PAZ, (L. S.)</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treaty">
            <pb n="61" facs="unknown:033045_0059_0FF62FBCC81BED80"/>
            <head>TREATY of Peace and Amity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the United States of America and the Dey of Algiers.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Treaty of Peace and Amity concluded this preſent day I—ima artaſi, the twenty-firſt of the Lunar ſafer, year of the Hegira <hi>1210,</hi> correſponding with Sat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urday, the fifth of September, one thouſand ſeven hundred and ninety-five, between <hi>Haſſan Baſhaw,</hi> Dey of Algiers, his Divan and Subjects, and <hi>George Waſhington,</hi> Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the United States of North-America, and the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the ſaid United States.</head>
            <p>
               <label>ARTICLE I.</label>
FROM the date of the preſent treaty, there ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt a firm and ſincere peace and amity between the Preſident and citizens of the United States of North-America, and Haſſan Baſhaw, Dey of Algiers, his Divan and ſubjects; the veſſels and ſubjects of both nations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally treating each other with civility, honor and reſpect.</p>
            <p>ART. II. All veſſels belonging to the citizens of the United States of North-America, ſhall be permitted to enter the different ports of the Regency, to trade with our ſubjects, or any other perſons reſiding within our ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, on paying the uſual duties at our cuſtom-houſe that is paid by all nations at peace with this Regency; obſerving that all goods diſembarked and not ſold here ſhall be permitted to be reimbarked without paying any
<pb n="62" facs="unknown:033045_0060_0FF62FBE520DFA90"/>
duty whatever, either for diſembarking or embarking. All naval and military ſtores, ſuch as gunpowder, lead, iron, plank, ſulphur, timber for building, tar, pitch, roſin, turpentine, and any other goods denominated naval and military ſtores, ſhall be permitted to be ſold in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency, without paying any duties whatever at the cuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of this Regency.</p>
            <p>ART. III. The veſſels of both nations ſhall paſs each other without any impediment or moleſtation; and all goods, monies or paſſengers, of whatſoever nation, that may be on board of the veſſels belonging to either party, ſhall be conſidered as inviolable, and ſhall be allowed to paſs unmoleſted.</p>
            <p>ART. IV. All ſhips of war belonging to this Regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, on meeting with merchant veſſels belonging to citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the United States, ſhall be allowed to viſit them with two perſons only beſide the rowers; theſe two only permitted to go on board ſaid veſſel, without obtaining expreſs leave from the commander of ſaid veſſel, who ſhall compare the paſſport, and immediately pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>it ſaid veſſel to proceed on her voyage unmoleſted. All ſhips of war belonging to the United States of North-America, on meeting with an Algerine cruiſer, and ſhall have ſeen her paſſport and certificate from the Conſul of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States of North-America, reſident in this Regency, ſhall be permitted to proceed on her cruiſe unmoleſted: No paſſport to be iſſued to any ſhips but ſuch as are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely the property of citizens of the United States: and eighteen months ſhall be the term allowed for furniſhing the ſhips of the United States with paſſports.</p>
            <p>ART. V. No commander of any cruiſer belonging to this Regency, ſhall be allowed to take any perſon, of whatever nation or denomination, out of any veſſel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the United States of North-America, in order to examine them, or under pretence of making them confeſs any thing deſired; neither ſhall they inflict any corporal puniſhment, or any way elſe moleſt them.</p>
            <p>ART. VI. If any veſſel belonging to the United States of North-America, ſhall be ſtranded on the coaſt of this Regency, they ſhall receive every poſſible aſſiſtance from the ſubjects of this Regency: all goods ſaved from the wreck ſhall be permitted to be reimbarked on board of
<pb n="63" facs="unknown:033045_0061_0FF62FC00DFC0078"/>
any other veſſel, without paying any duties at the cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom-houſe.</p>
            <p>ART. VII. The Algerines are not, on any pretence whatever, to give or fell any veſſel of war to any nation at war with the United States of North-America, or any veſſel capable of cruiſing to the detriment of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of the United States.</p>
            <p>ART. VIII. Any citizen of the United States of North-America, having bought any prize condemned by the Algerines, ſhall not be again captured by the cruiſers of the Regency then at ſea, although they have not a paſſport; a certificate from the conſul reſident being deemed ſufficient, until ſuch time as they can procure ſuch paſſport.</p>
            <p>ART. IX. If any of the Barbary ſtates at war with the United States of North-America, ſhall capture any American veſſel and bring her into any of the ports of this Regency, they ſhall not be permitted to ſell her, but ſhall depart the port on procuring the requiſite ſupplies of proviſion.</p>
            <p>ART. X. Any veſſel belonging to the United States of North-America, when at war with any other nation, ſhall be permitted to ſend their prizes into the ports of the Regency, have leave to diſpoſe of them, without pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any duties on ſale thereof. All veſſels wanting pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions or refreſhments, ſhall be permitted to buy them at market price.</p>
            <p>ART. XI. All ſhips of war belonging to the United States of North-America, on anchoring in the ports of the Regency, ſhall receive the uſual preſents of proviſions and refreſhments, gratis. Should any of the ſlaves of this Regency make their eſcape on board ſaid veſſels, they ſhall he immediately returned: No excuſe ſhall be made that they have hid themſelves amongſt the people and cannot be found, or any other equivocation.</p>
            <p>ART. XII. No citizen of the United States of North-America, ſhall be obliged to to redeem any ſlave againſt his will, even ſhould he be his brother: neither ſhall the owner of a ſlave be forced to ſell him againſt his will: but all ſuch agreements muſt be made by conſent of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Should any American citizen be taken on board an enemy-ſhip, by the cruiſers of this Regency, having a
<pb n="64" facs="unknown:033045_0062_0FF62FC325D20D78"/>
regular paſſport, ſpecifying they are citizens of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States, they ſhall be immediately ſet at liberty. On the contrary, they having no paſſport, they and their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty ſhall be conſidered lawful prize; as this Regency know their friends by their paſſports.</p>
            <p>ART. XIII. Should any of the citizens of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States of North-America, die within the limits of this Regency, the Dey and his ſubjects ſhall not interfere with the property of the deceaſed; but it ſhall be under the immediate direction of the conſul: unleſs otherwiſe diſpoſed of by will. Should there be no conſul, the effects ſhall be depoſited in the hands of ſome perſon worthy of truſt, until the party ſhall appear who has a right to demand them; when they ſhall render an account of the property. Neither ſhall the Dey or Divan give hindrance in the execution of any will that may appear.</p>
            <p>ART. XIV. No citizen of the United States of North-America, ſhall be obliged to purchaſe any goods againſt his will; but, on the contrary, ſhall be allowed to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe whatever it pleaſeth him. The conſul of the United States of North-America, or any other citizen, ſhall not be amenable for debts contracted by any one of their own nation; unleſs previouſly they have given a written obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ſo to do. Should the Dey want to freight any American veſſel that may be in the Regency, or Turkey, ſaid veſſel not being engaged, in conſequence of the friendſhip ſubſiſting between the two nations, he expects to have the preference given him, on his paying the ſame freight offered by any other nation.</p>
            <p>ART. XV. Any diſputes or ſuits at law, that may take place between the ſubjects of the Regency and the citizens of the United States of North-America, ſhall be decided by the Dey in perſon, and no other. Any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes that may ariſe between the citizens of the United States, ſhall be decided by the conſul; as they are in ſuch caſes not ſubject to the laws of this Regency.</p>
            <p>ART. XVI. Should any citizen of the United States of North-America, kill, wound, or ſtrike a ſubject of this Regency, he ſhall be puniſhed in the ſame manner as a Turk, and not with more ſeverity. Should any citizen of the United States of North-America, in the above predicament, eſcape priſon, the conſul ſhall not become anſwerable for him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="unknown:033045_0063_0FF62F478BB68CE8"/>ART. XVII. The conſul of the United States of North-America, ſhall have every perſonal ſecurity given him and his houſhold: he ſhall have liberty to exerciſe his religion in his own houſe: all ſlaves of the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſhall not be impeded in going to ſaid conſul's houſe, at hours of prayer. The conſul ſhall have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and perſonal ſecurity given him to travel whenever he pleaſes, within the Regency: he ſhall have free licenſe to go on board any veſſel lying in our roads, whenever he ſhall think fit. The conſul ſhall have leave to appoint his own drogaman and broker.</p>
            <p>ART. XVIII. Should a war break out between the two nations, the conſul of the United States of North-Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica, and all citizens of ſaid ſtates, ſhall have leave to embark themſelves and property unmoleſted, on board of what veſſel or veſſels they ſhall think proper.</p>
            <p>ART. XIX Should the cruiſers of Algiers capture any veſſel having citizens of the United States of North-America on board, they having papers to prove they are really ſo, they and their property ſhall be immediately diſcharged. And ſhould the veſſels of the United States capture any veſſels of nations at war with them, having ſubjects of this Regency on board, they ſhall be treated in like manner.</p>
            <p>ART. XX. On a veſſel of war belonging to the Unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed States of North-America anchoring in our ports, the Conſul is to inform the Dey of her arrival; and ſhe ſhall be ſaluted with twenty-one guns; which ſhe is to return in the ſame quantity or number. And the Dey will ſend freſh proviſions on board, as is cuſtomary, gratis.</p>
            <p>ART. XXI. The Conſul of the United States of North-America ſhall not be required to pay duty for any thing he brings from a foreign country for the uſe of his houſe and family.</p>
            <p>ART. XXII. Should any diſturbance take place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the citizens of the United States and the ſubjects of this Regency, or break any article of this treaty, war ſhall not be declared immediately; but every thing ſhall be ſearched into regularly: the party injured ſhall be made reparation.</p>
            <p>On the 21ſt of the Luna of Safer, 1210, correſponding with the 5th September, 1795, Joſeph Donaldſon, jun. on the
<pb n="66" facs="unknown:033045_0064_0FF62FC512BC3FD8"/>
part of the United States of North-America, agreed with Haſſan Baſhaw, Dey of Algiers, to keep the articles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this treaty ſacred and inviolable; which we the Dey and Divan promiſe to obſerve, on conſideration of the United States paying annually the value of twelve thouſand Algerine ſequins in maritime ſtores. Should the United States forward a larger quantity, the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus ſhall be paid for in money, by the Dey and Regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Any veſſel that may be captured from the date of this treaty of peace and amity, ſhall immediately be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up on her arrival in Algiers.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed,
<list>
                     <item>VIZIR HASSAN BASHAW,</item>
                     <item>JOSEPH DONALDSON, jun.</item>
                  </list>
Seal of Algiers ſtamped at the foot of the original treaty in Arabic.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To all to whom theſe Preſents ſhall come, or be made known.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WHEREAS the under-written David Humphreys, hath been duly appointed Commiſſioner Plenipotentiary, by letters patent under the ſignature of the Preſident, and ſeal of the United States of America, dated the 30th of March 1795, for negotiating and concluding a treaty of peace with the Dey and Governors of Algiers; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by inſtructions given to him on the part of the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, dated the 28th of March and 4th of April, 1795, he hath been further authorized to employ Joſeph Donald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, junior, on an agency in the ſaid buſineſs; whereas, by a writing under his hand and ſeal, dated 21ſt May 1795, he did conſtitute and appoint Joſeph Donaldſon, junior, agent in the buſineſs aforeſaid; and the ſaid Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph
<pb n="67" facs="unknown:033045_0065_0FF62FC6A13BB890"/>
Donaldſon, jun. did, on the 5th of September, 1795. agree with Haſſan Baſhaw, Dey of Algiers, to keep the articles of the preceding treaty ſacred and inviolable:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now know ye,</hi> That I, David Humphreys, Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Plenipotentiary aforeſaid, do approve and conclude the ſaid treaty, and every article and clauſe therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; reſerving the ſame nevertheleſs for the final rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Preſident of the United States of America, by and with the advice and conſent of the Senate of the ſaid United States.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>(Seal) <hi>In Teſtimony whereof, I have ſigned the ſame with my Hand and Seal, at the City of Liſbon,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>this</hi> 28<hi>th of November,</hi> 1795.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>DAVID HUMPHREYS.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="treaty">
            <pb n="69" facs="unknown:033045_0066_0FF62FC82FED2270"/>
            <head>TREATY of Peace and Friendſhip between the United States of America and the Bey and Subjects of Tripoli of Barbary.</head>
            <p>
               <label>ARTICLE I.</label>
THERE is a firm and perpetual peace and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip between the United States of America and the Bey and ſubjects of Tripoli of Barbary, made by the free conſent of both parties, and guarantied by the Moſt Potent Dey and Regency of Algiers.</p>
            <p>
               <label>ART. II.</label> If any goods belonging to any nation with which either of the parties is at war, ſhall be loaded on board of veſſels belonging to the other party, they ſhall paſs free, and no attempt ſhall be made to take or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>ART. III.</label> If any citizens, ſubjects or effects belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to either party, ſhall be found on board a prize veſſel taken from an enemy by the other party, ſuch citizens or ſubjects ſhall be ſet at liberty, and the effects reſtored to the owners.</p>
            <p>
               <label>ART. IV.</label> Proper paſſports are to be given to all veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of both parties, by which they are to be known. And conſidering the diſtance between the two countries, eighteen months from the date of this treaty ſhall be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for procuring ſuch paſſports. During this interval the other papers belonging to ſuch veſſels ſhall be ſufficient for their protection.</p>
            <p>
               <label>ART. V.</label> A citizen or ſubject of either party having bought a prize condemned by the party or by any other nation, the certificate of condemnation and bill of ſale ſhall be a ſufficient paſſport for ſuch veſſels for one year: this being a reaſonable time for her to procure a proper paſſport.</p>
            <p>
               <label>ART. VI.</label> Veſſels of either party putting into the ports of the other, and having need of proviſions or oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="70" facs="unknown:033045_0067_0FF62FCB6111B2C0"/>
ſupplies, they ſhall be furniſhed at the market price. And if any ſuch veſſel ſhall ſo put in from a diſaſter at ſea, and have occaſion to repair, ſhe ſhall be at liberty to land and re-embark her cargo, without paying any duties. But in no caſe ſhall ſhe be compelled to land her cargo.</p>
            <p>
               <label>ART. VII.</label> Should a veſſel of either party be caſt on the ſhore of the other, all proper aſſiſtance ſhall be given to her and her people; no pillage ſhall be allowed, the property ſhall remain at the diſpoſition of the owners, and the crew protected and ſuccoured till they can be ſent to their country.</p>
            <p>
               <label>ART. VIII.</label> If a veſſel of either party ſhould be attacked by an enemy within gun ſhot of the ſorts of the other, ſhe ſhall be defended as much as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. If ſhe be in port, ſhe ſhall not be ſeized or attack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when it is in the power of the other party to protect her; and when ſhe proceeds to ſea no enemy ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to purſue her from the ſame port within twenty-four hours after her departure.</p>
            <p>
               <label>ART. IX.</label> The commerce between the United States and Tripoli—the protection to be given to merchants, maſters of veſſels and ſeamen—the reciprocal right of eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabliſhing conſuls in each country, and the privileges, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities and juriſdictions to be enjoyed by ſuch conſuls, are declared to be on the ſame footing with thoſe of the moſt favoured nations reſpectively.</p>
            <p>
               <label>ART. X.</label> The money and preſents demanded by the Bey of Tripoli as a full and ſatisfactory conſideration on his part, and on the part of his ſubjects, for this treaty of perpetual peace and friendſhip, we acknowledged to have been received by him previous to his ſigning the ſame, according to a receipt which is hereto annexed, except ſuch part as is promiſed on the part of the United States to be delivered and paid by them on the arrival of their conſul in Tripoli, of which part a note is likewiſe hereto annexed. And no pretence of any periodical tribute or farther payment is ever to be made by either party.</p>
            <p>
               <label>ART. XI.</label> As the government of the United States of America is not in any ſenſe founded on the Chriſtian religion, as it has in itſelf no character of enmity againſt the laws, religion or tranquillity of Muſſelmen—and as the ſaid States have never entered into any war or act of
<pb n="71" facs="unknown:033045_0068_0FF62FCD804ED3B0"/>
hoſtility againſt any Mahometan nation, it is declared by the parties, that no pretext ariſing from religious opinions ſhall ever produce an interruption of the harmony exiſting between the two countries.</p>
            <p>
               <label>ART. XII.</label> In caſe of any diſpute ariſing from a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of any of the articles of this treaty, no appeal ſhall be made to arms, nor ſhall war be declared on any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text whatever. But if the conſul reſiding on the place where the diſpute ſhall happen, ſhall not be able to ſettle the ſame, an amicable reference ſhall be made to the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual friend of the parties, the Dey of Algiers, hereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging to abide by his deciſion. And he, by virtue of his ſignature to this treaty, engages for himſelf and his ſucceſſors, to declare the juſtice of the caſe according to the true interpretation of the treaty, and to uſe all the means in his power to enforce the obſervance of the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Signed and ſealed at Tripoli of Barbary, <date>the 3d day of Jumad, in the year of the Hegira 1211—cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponding with the 4th day of November, 1796,</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>by
<list>
                     <item>(L. S.) JUSSUF BASHAW MAHOMET, <hi>Bey.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(L. S.) MAMET. <hi>Treaſurer.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(L. S.) AMET, <hi>Miniſter of Marine.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(L. S.) AMET, <hi>Chamberlain.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(L. S.) ALLY, <hi>Chief of the Divan.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(L. S.) SOLIMAN, KAYA.</item>
                     <item>(L. S.) GALIL, <hi>General of the Troops.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(L. S.) MAHOMET, <hi>Commandant of the City.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(L. S.) MAMET, <hi>Secretary.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Signed and ſealed at Algiers, <date>the 4th day of Argil. 1211, correſponding with the 3d day of January, 1797,</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>by (L. S.) HASSAN BASHAW, <hi>Dey.</hi>
And by the Agent Plenipotentiary of the United States of America. (L. S.) JOEL BARLOW.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
