<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon, delivered at the First Church in Boston, April 6, 1798, at the interment of the Reverend John Clarke, D.D. who expired suddenly, April 2, 1798. Ae. 43. / By Peter Thacher, D.D. Pastor of the church in Brattle-Street, Boston.</title>
            <author>Thacher, Peter, 1752-1802.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N26045</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N26045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 34642</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APY2063</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">34642</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99029138</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 34642.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N26045)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 34642)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 34642)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon, delivered at the First Church in Boston, April 6, 1798, at the interment of the Reverend John Clarke, D.D. who expired suddenly, April 2, 1798. Ae. 43. / By Peter Thacher, D.D. Pastor of the church in Brattle-Street, Boston.</title>
                  <author>Thacher, Peter, 1752-1802.</author>
                  <author>Willard, Joseph, 1738-1804.</author>
                  <author>Belknap, Jeremy, 1744-1798.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27, [1] p. ;  22 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Hall, no. 53, Cornhill, Boston.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Boston] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1798.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Doctor Thacher's sermon, at the interment of the Reverend Doctor Clarke.</note>
                  <note>Includes accounts of the life of Clarke by Joseph Willard and Jeremy Belknap, p. 18-27.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clarke, John, 1755-1798.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  1798.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>AEL Data (Chennai)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:034642_0000_0FFF43668B9B1990"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:034642_0001_0FFF4368111E56E8"/>
            <p>Doctor THACHER'S SERMON, AT The Interment OF THE Reverend Doctor CLARKE.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:034642_0002_0FFF436CA2137AF0"/>
            <p>A SERMON, DELIVERED AT THE FIRST CHURCH IN BOSTON, APRIL 6, 1798, AT THE INTERMENT OF THE Reverend JOHN CLARKE, <hi>D. D.</hi> Who expired ſuddenly, April 2, 1798. Ae. 43.</p>
            <p>BY PETER THACHER, <hi>D. D.</hi> PASTOR OF THE CHURCH in BRATTLE-STREET, BOSTON.</p>
            <p>Printed by SAMUEL HALL, No. 53, Cornhill, Boston. 1798.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="unknown:034642_0003_0FFF436F30B62F30"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 SAMUEL, I. 26.</bibl>
               <q>I AM DISTRESSED FOR THEE, MY BROTHER—VERY PLEASANT HAST THOU BEEN UN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TO ME.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ONCE more, my beloved and mourning friends of this Chriſtian Society, once more <note n="*" place="bottom">In the afternoon of the Lord's-day preceding the delivery of this diſcourſe, Dr. CLARKE was preaching to his people from Pſalm xxii. 3. and in the midſt of his diſcourſe was ſeized with an apoplectic fit, which terminated in his death at three o'clock the next morning. The body was brought into the church on this occaſion.</note> are you called to viſit the houſe of prayer. When laſt you trod its courts, your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions were led and your minds elevated and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by the amiable and excellent man whoſe remains now lie before us. Then too you wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed the arreſt of the king of terrors upon him; and while the pulpit was his dying bed, you ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded it and wept bitterly over him!</p>
            <p>Now—another melancholy duty is to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. We are to commit the ſacred remains to the ſilent grave, and leave them there, not again to return "till the heavens be no more." We have viſited the houſe of prayer in our way to the houſe of death, not merely to ſhew our reſpect to him, but recal to our minds thoſe conſiderations of
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:034642_0004_0FFF4370B48A7080"/>
reaſon and religion which are alone competent to ſupport them under ſuch trying ſcenes. Now, then, recollect how often you have heard him from this ſacred deſk, expatiate with ardor on the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect wiſdom and unbounded goodneſs of the Deity, and ſhew the fitneſs and propriety of an abſolute ſubmiſſion to the divine will, a full confidence in the divine mercy. Recollect theſe things, my brethren, and you will hear him comforting you as it were for his own loſs, charging you not to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend God by complaining of his ways, or indulging to exceſſive grief.</p>
            <p>You ſurely can adopt the language of David in the text, where he laments the death of Jonathan, the friend and brother of his ſoul. Their friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip commenced in early life, and was cemented by numerous inſtances of kind and faithful attention. The cruelty and injuſtice of Saul could not diſſolve it, nor induce Jonathan to forſake the man whom he eſteemed with reaſon and loved with warmth. When therefore he ſuddenly fell by the hands of his enemies, the ſweet Pſalmiſt embalms his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory with tears, and over his untimely grave recites the melancholy but pleaſing ode from which the text is taken. Let us conſider its meaning and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and endeavor to find the conſolation which our preſent circumſtances demand, and religion, the religion of Chriſt alone, can furniſh.</p>
            <p>DEEPLY are we diſtreſſed when it pleaſes God to take from us thoſe whom we highly love and eſteem. Death is at all times awful. God has been pleaſed for wise purpoſes, to implant a dread of it in human nature. When we witneſs its
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:034642_0005_0FFF43723AC62C50"/>
ravages upon ſtrangers, upon thoſe with whom we have no immediate connexion, we feet a ſhud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering horror. But how much more deeply are we affected when it comes near to us, when it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves the tendereſt connexions, when it takes away thoſe who were our guides, our friends, our ſtay and ſtaff; when it cuts down the uſeful, the learned, the wiſe and the good, to whom we were tenderly attached, and from whom we expected that we and our children ſhould derive much ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>efit. This is indeed the moſt diſtreſſing ingredient in the bitter cup.</p>
            <p>SUCH was the virtuous and good character of Jonathan as that David was not diſtreſſed with any anxiety or apprehenſion as to his happineſs in a future ſtate. Of this he could have no doubt. His tears were a tribute to the holy, ardent friendſhip which he bore to this excellent young man. They flowed becauſe his friend fell in battle before his enemies; becauſe "the beauty of Iſrael was ſlain upon the high places;" becauſe he could not viſit and ſupport and miniſter to him in his laſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and becauſe death had put a period to their friendſhip in this world forever.</p>
            <p>Now, we are diſtreſſed for the loſs of our pious friends, not becauſe we have any doubts of their felicity; not becauſe we heſitate in believing that they are far happier than this world can make them, nor becauſe we ſcruple the right which God has to take them away, or his wiſdom and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in doing ſo: But, we mourn becauſe we loved them while they lived, and they are gone away forever; becauſe we have loſt the benefit of their
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:034642_0006_0FFF4373CBABBF48"/>
prayers, their counſels, their ſweet and amiable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; and becauſe a connexion which formed the ſolace of our lives is diſſolved. We do not "weep for them:" We "weep for ourſelves and our children." Their deaths occaſion a loſs to us, but to them they afford unſpeakable gain. They are placed ſafely beyond the reach of all the trials, the temptations and ſorrows of life; while we ſtill navigate its ſtormy ſea and encounter all its dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Their characters are fixed and determined. There is no danger of their forfeiting them; while we are taught to "fear always," and diſtruſt our own reſolutions. Their work is ended. Their warfare is accompliſhed. Their race is run. But we are ſtill toiling in the conflict, and may fall by the hands of our enemies. Surely then, "the day of death is better than the day of one's birth."</p>
            <p>WHEN we are diſtreſſed with the loſs of our dear and reſpected friends, let us "comfort one another with theſe words." Let us remember that they are gone to a glory beyond our conception; that they have aſcended to "their Father and our Father, to their God and our God;" that their triumph is begun, and ſhall endure forever. Let us remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that they have lived ſo long as God ſaw to be beſt for them and for us; that he who cannot err has ordered every event concerning them; and that "though they cannot come to us, yet that we ſhall go to them."</p>
            <p>IN proportion as our friends were pleaſant and agreeable to us in their lives, are we affected and diſtreſſed by their deaths. We can ſee the weak, the wicked and the worthleſs leave the world, and
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:034642_0007_0FFF437A67C95D20"/>
feel ſomething more than reſignation: But when we ſee virtuous and good men, who were tenderly beloved and eminently uſeful, taken away in the midſt of their days, then are "the ways of Heaven dark and intricate," and then are our faith and patience tried.</p>
            <p>THERE are many circumſtances which render men pleaſant to us, or amiable in our view. We may know that every thing excellent in them "comes down from the Father of Lights:" But ſtill we cannot avoid eſteeming and loving them, becauſe what God has given them becomes a part of themſelves, and becauſe they improve well the advantages with which they are favored.</p>
            <p>How natural is it for us to honor and love thoſe who poſſeſs a mild, affectionate and benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent natural temper; who ſeem to have no gall in their conſtitution; who, without ſuppleneſs or cringing ſervility, prove by their deportment that they feel malevolence to none, but wiſh to make all about them happy. When ſuch a temper is joined with ſtrong and vigorous faculties of mind, faculties which render the poſſeſſor ſuperior to the greater part of mankind, and qualify him for emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent uſefulneſs, then we adore the goodneſs of God towards him, and then we take delight in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance.</p>
            <p>IN domeſtic life, where our character appear moſt truly and without diſguiſe, who does not love the dutiful ſon, the tender huſband, the wiſe and affectionate parent, and the kind maſter? When we ſee a man walking through this ſequeſtered path of life, with true goodneſs in his heart, and
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:034642_0008_0FFF437BEC017CD8"/>
"the law of kindneſs on his lips," we "riſe up and call him bleſſed." When he is taken away, the unfeigned grief of thoſe who ſurvive him is a richer teſtimony to his virtues and a greater men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ument of his worth than marble or braſs can erect for him.</p>
            <p>THE friendſhip of David and Jonathan did not ariſe from natural relation. It was founded on eſteem and affection, and eſtabliſhed by that mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual intercourſe of virtuous and affectionate offices which can alone ſupport friendſhip. How ſtrong are the bands of ſuch an attachment! How awful the ſhock when death cruſhes and diſſolves it! Such friends, who were "lovely and pleaſant in their lives," do hardly wiſh "in their deaths to be divided."</p>
            <p>IT is pleaſant to ſee a man diſcharging, with care, fidelity, and diligence, the various duties which he owes to ſociety; increaſing the ſtock of human knowledge and happineſs; mitigating the calamities and relieving the wants of the ſick, the poor, and the needy; contributing his utmoſt aid in furthering every humane inſtitution, and accel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erating every ſcientific purſuit; active in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of mankind, and yet "guiding his affairs with diſcretion." When ſuch a man is taken away, we may ſay, with more propriety than it can be ſaid of any of the heroes and conquerors whom paſt hiſtory or the preſent time make known to us, "A prince and a great man is fallen this day."</p>
            <p>BUT there is nothing which ſo conciliates the affections of good men as goodneſs. The image
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:034642_0009_0FFF437D70374AD0"/>
of Chriſt is dear to his diſciples, let it be inſtamped on whom it may. How delightful is it to ſee the marks of true piety, of chriſtian integrity, of the mild ſpirit and temper of Jeſus Chriſt! When we obſerve a man daily walking with God in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, the cheerful performance of the duties which he owes to his Maker, his fellow-men and his own ſoul: When we ſee him afraid of doing the leaſt thing which may offend God, and deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of diſcovering what is right, in order that he may punctually do it: When we ſee him produc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rich cluſters of the fruits of righteouſneſs; what chriſtian can refrain from loving him?—Although he may differ from us in ſome ſentiments, and may not entertain preciſely the ſame ideas of the doctrines of the goſpel as we do, yet dare we with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from him not only our charity but our eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teem and affection? If we can—we want the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt ourſelves, and prove that our loudeſt religious profeſſions are a "founding braſs and a tinkling cymbal."</p>
            <p>God is pleaſed to give to different men different opportunities of improving the faculties with which he endues them. But he is peculiarly kind to any one, whom by his grace he furniſhes with a pious heart and diſcerning head, a learned edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and a facility in communicating his ideas; and then places him in the work of the miniſtry. This is an employment moſt grateful to a man of piety and learning; and it is excellently calculated to make a good heart better. This employment alſo endears him, who faithfully diſcharges it, to all the wiſe and the good. The miniſter who
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:034642_0010_0FFF438059233DE0"/>
takes pains to find out "the truth as it is in Jeſus," and then clearly delivers what he believes to be ſo, although it may expoſe him to cenſure and inconvenience, proves his integrity and "de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves double honor." If he is diligent in his ſtudies; if he is conſtant in his attention to all the private and public duties of his profeſſion; if his compoſitions diſcover a fund of knowledge, and he is maſter of a chaſte, claſſical and elegant ſtyle; if his public performances are grateful to his people; if in "all their afflictions he is afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed," and under them, like the angel of peace, he pours balm into their wounded ſpirits; then will he be dear and pleaſant, beyond deſcription, to them; and like the Galatians of old, "they will be ready to pluck out their own eyes and give them unto him."</p>
            <p>A MINISTER of this character not only conciliates the eſteem and love of the people with whom he is immediately connected but of all thoſe who know his worth, in the place where he lives, or in more diſtant countries. His brethren, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, will feel themſelves drawn to him with the ſtrongeſt cords of affection, and will rejoice in his gifts, his graces, his uſefulneſs, and his acceptance. Are there any literary honors or diſtinctions to be given? He will receive them, and will have the ſatisfaction of hearing every one agree that they are worthily beſtowed. He will live beloved, and will die univerſally lamented.</p>
            <p>You, my brethren of this ſociety, know that the deſcription, which has now been given of the man and the miniſter who is pleaſant, uſeful and accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:034642_0011_0FFF4383EC3BCAA0"/>
applies exactly to your late excellent Paſtor. The picture was drawn from the life, and it muſt be a likeneſs. I am ſure you will not charge me with flattering his memory when I make this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion. We are not ſurpriſed at your grief on this heavy loſs. You who knew his private and public worth, and who ſat conſtantly under his miniſtrations; you in whoſe welfare, ſpiritual and temporal, he was ſo deeply intereſted, could not but highly prize this precious gift of our aſcended Saviour, and you cannot but weep now he is no more.</p>
            <p>THE manner in which death arreſted him, engag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your ſervice and in your preſence, muſt have deeply wounded your feelings. Yet you ſhould conſole yourſelves with the thought, that this is the beſt mode of dying for one who lives habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally prepared for the coming of his Maſter. He eſcaped the ſevere pangs of diſſolution, and the agony of parting with his friends. From the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate ſervice of his Maſter upon earth, he was tranſlated, we truſt and believe, to the ſublimer ſervices of Heaven.</p>
            <p>IT will be your ſolicitude to make a profitable improvement of this affecting event. You re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the wiſe counſels, the faithful reproofs, the excellent inſtructions, which your miniſter gave you from time to time. You remember in what a ſtriking light he ſet before you the evidences of our holy religion, the excellency of our divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and the neceſſity of virtue, piety, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolence to our happineſs here and hereafter. You cannot forget how he preſſed upon you the
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:034642_0012_0FFF43856FBD8EC0"/>
obſervation of the Sabbath, an attendance upon public worſhip, and eſpecially an obedience to the dying command of Chriſt. "By theſe things, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he is dead before you, he yet ſpeaketh." Let me conjure you, by your regard to him as well as to your own ſouls, to "think on and practiſe theſe things." "Remember how you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and heard," and God grant that "your <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may appear unto all men"!</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> was Dr. CLARKE intereſted in the proſperity of this ſociety, as that nothing could give him more pleaſure than to observe its growth and unanimity. Let this be a motive with you to avoid all diviſion to cultivate a ſpirit of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and condeſcenſion towards each other. You will not "forſake the aſſembling of yourſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether." You will "continue in breaking of bread and in prayer." You will "ſtudy the things which make for peace, and whereby one may edify another," and in due time we truſt that "God will give you another paſtor after his own heart." Let not your feelings be wounded by this ſuggeſtion. You and I are following our dear brother faſt into the world of ſpirits, and it is our duty to provide religious inſtruction as well as other good things for our children. What we can do for them, and for the church of God, we ought to do at once, becauſe "the night cometh, when no man can work." Beſides, <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion paſſeth away and another cometh." The or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſucceſſion muſt not be violated. Could our lamented friend now addreſs you, I doubt not he would urge you to peace and union, and adviſe
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:034642_0013_0FFF43881961AE40"/>
you not to remain "as ſheep without a ſhepherd." We commend you to God and the word of his grace, which is able to build you up, and give you an inheritance among all them that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied"!</p>
            <p>THE grief, the exquiſite grief of the immediate connexions of Dr. CLARKE, renders it improper for me publicly to addreſs them. "God hath taken away the deſire of their eyes with a ſtroke." But, let them bow ſubmiſſively to the divine will, and place their truſt in him who "liveth and abid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for ever," and who will never leave nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them.</p>
            <p>THE church which has for many years been cloſely connected <note n="*" place="bottom">The Firſt Church and the Church in Brattle-ſtreet have been connected in a lecture previous to the communion, for 78 years. When their houſes of worſhip have been building or repairing, they have always met together on Lord's-days.</note> with this, feels ſenſibly an event ſo diſtreſſing. They experienced his kindneſs and attention when they were themſelves vacant, and they "eſteemed him highly in love for his work's ſake." Were it proper to introduce any thing perſonal on this occaſion, I ſhould ſay, that God hath taken away one of the deareſt of my friends, and one of the higheſt enjoyments of my life. But the will of God is done. He is "holy in all his ways, and righteous in all his works."</p>
            <p>WE, my brethren in the miniſtry, have many good leſſons to learn from this ſolemn event. We ſee that neither great talents, real piety, nor the warmeſt affection of thoſe whom we ſerve, can ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us from the lot of all men. We ſee how ſoon
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:034642_0014_0FFF438BC1F09CD0"/>
and how ſuddenly we may be called to our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; and we are taught ſo to perform the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emn offices of religion as that we may not be afraid to be ſummoned from them to the bar of our Judge. Such an idea muſt raiſe us above "the fear of man, which bringeth a ſnare." It muſt render us careful to "deliver the whole counſel of God"; and ſo to "keep our hearts" when we ſerve him in his houſe, as that we may have the bleſſedneſs of the man whom "the Lord, when he cometh, ſhall find ſo doing."</p>
            <p>THE members of the literary and benevolent aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociations, with which Dr. CLARKE was connect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will feel themſelves deeply affected by his loſs. His exertions to promote the important views of their inſtitution were never wanting. While he ſhared the honors of office. <note n="*" place="bottom">Dr. CLARKE was a Counſellor of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, and Correſponding Secretary of the Humans Society of the Commonwealth of Maſſachusetts.</note> in ſome of them, he was careful to perform the duties which were an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to it. It becomes thoſe of us who ſurvive to imitate his induſtry and exertion, ſo that when we ſhall follow our departed brother and aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate to the world of ſpirits, thoſe who ſurvive may "riſe up and call us bleſſed."</p>
            <p>LEARN, my brethren of this great aſſembly, learn all of you, the vanity and uncertainty of life. Here you ſee the end of all fleſh. At this goal, every man, who runs the race of life, muſt, ſooner or later, arrive. Learn, that "in the midſt of life you are in death," and that you "know neither the day nor the hour when the Son of Man ſhall
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:034642_0015_0FFF438D46D88488"/>
come." Liſten to the voice which addreſſes you from the ſable urn of this miniſter of God, and ſpeaks loudly, "Be ye alſo ready." While life and health and reaſon are granted you, improve them to ſecure an intereſt in "the better part which can never be taken from you." We are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing each other rapidly into the world of ſpirits. We ſhall ſoon paſs through the valley of the ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ow of death. "The eye of him that hath ſeen us, ſhall ſee us no more. We ſhall return no more to our houſes, neither ſhall our places know us any more." Let us now then "give diligence to make our calling and election ſure." The bleſſings of the goſpel are offered to us, and urged on our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance. Let us not delay our attention to them, but "ſeek the Lord while he may be found, and call upon him now he is near."</p>
            <p>And now—Farewell! Farewell forever! SWEET SHADE OF OUR DEPARTED FRIEND!—Thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious duſt we will reverendly commit to the "houſe appointed for all living"!—Thy memory we will cultivate with warm and tender affection!—Thy deſolate family, thy widowed wife, and thy fath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erleſs children, we will counſel, aſſiſt, and protect!—Soon ſhall we follow thee where "the wicked ceaſe from troubling, and the weary are at reſt." There will we ſleep in peace till "the trumpet ſhall ſound, and the dead ſhall be raiſed." Then will we ſpring together to a new and eternal life!—"Then this mortal ſhall put on immortality, and this corruptible ſhall put on incorruption, and death ſhall be ſwallowed up of victory!"</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="description_of_person">
            <pb n="18" facs="unknown:034642_0016_0FFF438FD0E98378"/>
            <head>The Reverend DOCTOR WILLARD, PRESIDENT of the Univerſity in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, preached at the FIRST CHURCH on the Lord's-day after the FUNERAL of Doctor CLARKE. The following CHARACTER, delivered by him on that occaſion, is added at the deſire of the Congregation who aſſemble there, <abbr>viz.</abbr>
            </head>
            <p>SO juſt a character of your late excellent Paſtor was drawn by the Gentleman who delivered a diſcourſe from this deſk, on the day of his funeral, that little more can be expected. But as I had a particular opportunity of knowing him, from the commencement of his literary courſe at Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, with little interruption, till the time of his death, it will not, perhaps, be thought improper, ſhould I, on this ſolemn day, offer a few things upon the ſubject.</p>
            <p>BEING a Tutor at the Univerſity when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a member, and the claſs to which he belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed being committed to my particular care, I had an early opportunity of knowing his character, and I was ſoon led to diſtinguiſh in him that genius and application to ſtudy, together with that amiable diſpoſition and excellent ſpirit, which have ever ſince conſpicuouſly ſhone in him. For two years and a quarter I continued with the claſs, and during that his improvements in literature and ſcience were very obſervable; and his conduct
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:034642_0017_0FFF439189ACBEE0"/>
was ſo uniformly good, in every reſpect, that he never merited or received a cenſure or a frown from any one who had the care and inſtruction of the youth; and I found by information, after my leaving the claſs and the Univerſity, that he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the ſame character, through the whole of his. Collegiate courſe. And, perhaps, there never was a ſtudent, who paſſed through the Univerſity and went into the world with a fairer reputation, and few with more ſolid and uſeful acquirements.</p>
            <p>HAPPY is it, when youth improve their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages in ſeats of literature and ſcience to ſo good advantage—Happy when they carry forth with them a character ſo unblemiſhed, into whatever profeſſion or buſiness they enter—Peculiarly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; if they undertake the work of the Goſpel Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>FOR ſome time after Mr. CLARKE left the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, he was engaged in the inſtruction of youth, in which employment he was highly eſteemed and beloved. But whatever his purſuits were, he did not ſuffer his mind to be diverted from the great object he had in view, which was to fit for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred deſk. While he was faithful in performing the buſineſs he undertook, he devoted his leiſure hours to accompliſh himſelf for that profeſſion which lay neareſt his heart; and he purſued his theological ſtudies with great aſſiduity, ſo that when he <hi>firſt entered</hi> the deſk it was not with a ſuperficial knowledge. His natural abilities and literary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirements were ſuch as enabled him to ſearch the
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:034642_0018_0FFF439515098B38"/>
Sacred Oracles with accuracy, eſpecially the Orig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inal of the New-Teſtament, and to attend to every ſubject in Divinity with judgment. And ſuch was the candor and fairneſs of his mind, that few men, perhaps, have been more free from prejudices in their reſearches: He therefore became a Scribe well inſtructed in the Goſpel Syſtem.</p>
            <p>His diſcourſes early diſcovered an elegant taſte in compoſition, a correctneſs, propriety and perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence in thought, and that ſtrain of ſeriouſneſs and piety, which could not but be attractive. You, my Brethren, ſoon heard of his worth; and when you employed him as a Candidate for the Miniſtry among you, your expectations from him were not diſappointed; nay, it will not be beyond the truth to ſay, that they were more than anſwered. After preaching with you a competent time, he was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained over you as a Colleague Paſtor with the venerable, learned and valuable Doctor CHAUNCY, with whom he ſerved as a Son with a Father; and between them there ever exiſted the moſt happy harmony, till the day of the Doctor's death.</p>
            <p>HAVING obtained a ſettlement, he did not grow remiſs about future improvements, but continued the ſame aſſiduity which had been a diſtinguiſhed trait in his character. To the liberal Arts and Sciences, for which he had a true reliſh, and in which he was no <hi>common</hi> proficient, he, at times, paid attention. But theſe he conſidered as noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more than handmaids to Divinity, and of but ſecondary conſideration. Divinity was his profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:034642_0019_0FFF4397A48CFEA0"/>
and to this he directly applied a principal part of his time. He had devoted himſelf to the cauſe of God and the Redeemer, and he would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer other purſuits, however pleaſing to his ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mind, to ſteal him away from his proper func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and rob him of that time which he conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf bound in duty to employ for the inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and edification of his flock, either in prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for his public labors among them, or in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate interviews with the various members.—I have dwelt the more largely on this part of his character, becauſe of ſcholar of Doctor CLARKE'S acquirements, and taſte for literature and ſcience, is under a ſtrong temptation to ſpend more time in ſuch purſuits than is conſiſtent with properly diſcharging the duties of his ſacred profeſſion.</p>
            <p>YOUR Paſtor employed himſelf much in the ſtudy of the Holy Scriptures. To theſe heavenly Oracles he repaired, as the ſources of divine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and endeavoured to gain right apprehenſions of the truths contained in them, both for his own ſake and the ſake of his hearers, whom he inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe, according to his beſt underſtanding, after making uſe of the moſt approved helps he could procure, and which he was conſtantly laying himſelf out to obtain.</p>
            <p>HIS pulpit-performances were always acceptable With thoſe compoſitions of his, which I have either heard or read, I have ever been pleaſed and edified. His Treatiſe in defence of Chriſtianity, entitled, "Why are you a Chriſtian?" is, perhaps, as val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:034642_0020_0FFF439A2EA07660"/>
a piece as has been written within the ſame compaſs. By its conciſeneſs it is well adapted to being diſperſed; and by its perſpicuity and perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence happily calculated to convince and confirm. It is highly eſteemed, not only on this, but on the other ſide of the Atlantic. I have received, but a little while ſince, a letter from a reſpectable Divine in Great-Britain. <note n="*" place="bottom">The Rev. Joſhua Toulmin, D. D. of Taunton.</note> In this letter he ſays, "We have here been greatly pleaſed, inſtructed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by a little piece written by one of your Miniſters, Mr. CLARKE, entitled,—"Why are you a Chriſtian?" And after mentioning that three editions of it had been printed in England, two of which he himſelf had carried through the preſs, he adds,—"The circulation of it cannot fail to give pleaſure to the pious and worthy Author, and to enſure its views of uſefulneſs."</p>
            <p>HIS pleaſing private intercourſe with you, and alſo with the children of the Society, whom he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to inſtruct, you need not be reminded of. The impreſſions made by theſe endearments will not be ſoon, if ever, effaced. Indeed, ſo ſweet was his diſpoſition, and ſo engaging his manners; ſo pleaſing was he in his converſation, and ſo amiable in all his interviews with thoſe he met, that a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eral eſteem of and affection for him was almoſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably excited; and he was beloved by all but the determined foes of virtue and goodneſs.</p>
            <p>I PASS over his domeſtic virtues, in which he was eminent, and which all, who knew him, witneſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="unknown:034642_0021_0FFF439BDDC3E368"/>
WHAT an unſpeakable loſs have you ſuſtained in the death of ſuch a Miniſter and friend! But let the bereaved Relatives—let the Members of this religious Society, conſider the conſolations which offer themſelves in the midſt of their grief. You have all abundant reaſon to conclude that he was a man of habitual piety, and that he lived mindful of his exit; ſo that although he was ſuddenly ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned out of time into eternity, he was prepared for the change, and that "His loins were girded about and his light burning. <note place="bottom">Referring to the text, <abbr>viz.</abbr> Luke xii. 35, 36, 37.</note> He may be ſaid to have been watching when his Maſter knocked. He was even then particularly employed in his ſervice, engaged in the very act of religious teaching, and endeavouring to prepare men for a better world.</p>
            <p>SUCH grounds of comfort have we when we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the character of our dear departed friend. We conſider him as one who had been ſealed with the Holy Spirit of promiſe; <note n="†" place="bottom">A part of the text treated upon by the deceaſed on the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon of the laſt Lord's-day, previous to the Communion. Eph. i. 13.</note> and that having been thus ſealed, he is now aſcended to that "Holy One who inhabiteth the praiſes of Iſrael." <note n="‡" place="bottom">The ſubject upon which he was treating in the afternoon, when he was ſeized with the fatal malady. Pſalm xxii. 3.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="description_of_person">
            <pb n="24" facs="unknown:034642_0022_0FFF125368B4AB68"/>
            <head>The following CHARACTER, by another Hand, was publiſhed in the Columbian Centinel the day after the Interment.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Boſton,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 7, 1798.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>JOHN CLARKE, D. D. Paſtor of the firſt church in Boſton, was born at Portſmouth, in New-Hampſhire, April 13, 1755; graduated at Harvard College in 1774; and ordained July 8, 1778, as colleague with the late Dr. Chauncy, with whom he lived in the moſt intimate and reſpectful friendſhip about 9 years; and afterwards contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, aſſiduouſly and faithfully labouring in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the church, until the Lord's day, April 1, 1798; when, in the midſt of his afternoon ſermon, he was ſuddenly ſeized with an apoplexy, fell down in the pulpit, and expired in leſs than twelve hours; having almoſt completed the 43d year of his age, and the 20th year of his miniſtry.</p>
            <p>DESCENDED from reſpectable parents, who live to lament an only ſon, he diſcovered in early life the ſigns of genius and induſtry. At the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity he was diſtinguiſhed by a cloſe attention to claſſic and philoſophic ſtudies, by a ſtrict obedience to the laws, and by irreproachable morals. In the office of Preceptor, he was gentle and perſuaſive, beloved by his pupils, and eſteemed by their friends. As a public preacher, his compoſitions bore the marks of penetration, judgment, perſpicuity and elegance. Faithful to the intereſt of religion, he
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:034642_0023_0FFF43A400D0C168"/>
deeply examined its foundation and evidence; and perſuaded of the truth and importance of the Chriſtian ſyſtem, he recommended, by his public diſcourſes and private converſation, its ſublime doctrines, its wiſe inſtitutions, and its ſalutary precepts.</p>
            <p>THOUGH fond of polite literature and philoſophic reſearches, yet he conſidered theology as the proper ſcience of a Goſpel Miniſter. To this object he principally devoted his time and ſtudies, and was earneſtly deſirous of inveſtigating every branch of it, not merely to gratify his own ſacred curioſity, but that he might impart to his hearers the whole counſel of God. He was habitually a cloſe ſtudent; and it is not improbable, that the intenſeneſs of his mental application proved too ſevere for the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate fabric of his nerves.</p>
            <p>HIS devotional addreſſes were copious and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent; and his interceſſions ſtrong and affectionate, diſcovering at once the ardor of his piety and the warmth of his benevolence. In the private offices of paſtoral friendſhip, he was truly exemplary and engaging. His temper was mild and cheerful, his manners eaſy and polite; and the ſocial virtues of an honeſt heart gave a glow to his language, and enlivened every circle in which he was converſant.</p>
            <p>IN the relations of a ſon, a brother, a huſband, a father, a guardian, a correſpondent, a maſter, a friend, and a member of ſeveral literary and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itable ſocieties, his deportment was marked with affection, fidelity and carefulneſs. He was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:034642_0024_0FFF43A583C67DE0"/>
for the intereſt, reputation and happineſs of all his connections; and zealouſly devoted to the cauſe of ſcience and humanity.</p>
            <p>BEING ſucceſſor to <hi>ten</hi> eminent luminaries of the church of God, he was ſtudious to emulate them in piety, learning and uſefulneſs. Like three of them, he was ſuddenly called off from his miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial labours, and having happily eſcaped the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful agonies of a lingering death, is gone to receive the reward of a faithful ſervant, and enter into the joy of his Lord.</p>
            <p>THE names of his predeceſſors, the order of their ſucceſſion, and their ages (as far as they are known) are as follow:
<list>
                  <item>A. D. 1632 <hi>John Wilſon,</hi> 1667, <hi>Aet.</hi> 79.</item>
                  <item>1633 <hi>John Cotton,</hi> 1656, <hi>Aet,</hi> 68.</item>
                  <item>1656 <hi>John Norton,</hi> 1663. <hi>Aet.</hi> 57.</item>
                  <item>1668 <hi>John Davenport,</hi> 1670, <hi>Aet.</hi> 72.</item>
                  <item>1668 <hi>James Allen,</hi> 1710, <hi>Aet.</hi> 78.</item>
                  <item>1670 <hi>John Oxenbridge,</hi> 1674, <hi>Aet.</hi> 66.</item>
                  <item>1696 <hi>Benjamin Wadſworth,</hi> removed to the Preſidency of Harvard College. 1725, and died 1737, <hi>Aet.</hi> 68.</item>
                  <item>1705 <hi>Thomas Bridge,</hi> 1715, <hi>Aet.</hi> 58.</item>
                  <item>1717 <hi>Thomas Foxcroft,</hi> 1769, <hi>Aet.</hi> 73.</item>
                  <item>1727 <hi>Charles Chauncy,</hi> D. D. 1787, <hi>Aet.</hi> 83. Beſides two aſſiſtant miniſters, <abbr>viz.</abbr>
                  </item>
                  <item>1684 <hi>Joſhua Moody,</hi> returned to Portſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth, 1692.</item>
                  <item>1693 <hi>John Bailey,</hi> 1697, <hi>Aet.</hi> 54.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>MR. <hi>Norton</hi> died very ſuddenly on the Lord's day, as he was preparing for the afternoon exerciſe.
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:034642_0025_0FFF43A70987F100"/>
Mr. <hi>Oxenbridge</hi> fell down in the pulpit, with an apoplexy, and died in four days. Mr. <hi>Foxcroft</hi> was ſeized with the ſame diſorder on a Saturday, and died the next day.</p>
            <p>DR. CLARKE'S printed works are, four Sermons—one on the death of Dr. <hi>Cooper,</hi> one on the death of Dr. <hi>Chauncy,</hi> one on the death of Dr. <hi>N. W. Appleton,</hi> and one before the Humane Society: An anſwer to the queſtion, Why are you a Chriſtian? (which has had three editions in Boſton, and three in England); and Letters to a Student at the Univerſity of Cambridge.</p>
            <p>HIS remains were yeſterday entombed with every mark of eſteem and affection.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
