<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>War, necessary, just and beneficial: an oration, pronounced on commencement at Rhode-Island College, September 4th, A.D. 1799. / By Tristram Burges, a candidate for the second degree.</title>
            <author>Burges, Tristam, 1770-1853.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N26517</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N26517</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 35255</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW2278</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">35255</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99008132</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 35255.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N26517)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 35255)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 35255)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>War, necessary, just and beneficial: an oration, pronounced on commencement at Rhode-Island College, September 4th, A.D. 1799. / By Tristram Burges, a candidate for the second degree.</title>
                  <author>Burges, Tristam, 1770-1853.</author>
                  <author>Rhode Island College (1764-1804).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p. ;  (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Wheeler.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Providence: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1799.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>War --  Moral aspects.</term>
               <term>Baccalaureate addresses --  1799.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:035255_0000_1001CF6D2F3A1680"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:035255_0001_1001CF758F75CB50"/>
            <p>WAR, Neceſſary, Juſt and Beneficial: AN ORATION, PRONOUNCED ON COMMENCEMENT AT RHODE-ISLAND COLLEGE, SEPTEMBER 4th, A. D. 1799.</p>
            <p>BY TRISTAM BURGES, A CANDIDATE FOR THE SECOND DEGREE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PROVIDENCE:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="oration">
            <pb facs="unknown:035255_0002_1001CF7BD0AE6E78"/>
            <head>AN ORATION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>"BE READY FOR THINE ADVERSARY."</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Mother to her Son,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <bibl>SHAKESPEARE.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS day is conſecrated to academical exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes. The beauties of ſcience, and the charms of philoſophy, are doubtleſs the moſt appoſite themes for claſſical declamation. In this reſpect, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the ſpeakers of to-day have always had their choice. If propriety and decorum be conſulted, they are not confined to any particular deſcription of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. He, who now addreſſes you, would not advance a principle, or anticipate a poſſible juncture of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which might diminiſh the hilarity, or violate the ſolemnities of the preſent occaſion. If his theme, or his ſentiments, ſhould be unpleaſant to a ſingle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual in hearing, that individual may be aſſured, that, neither the one was choſen, nor ſhall the others be exhibited, with any reference to any occaſion, or any deſcription of citizens.</p>
            <p>THIS feſtive anniverſary, this civick and claſſical pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade, the concourſe, the ſplendour, and even the very countenances of this numerous aſſembly, are ſo many teſtimonials of the felicity of our country. But there are truths which tell us all theſe delights of peace may be violated. When we ſee yonder enſign, unfolding its red boſom to the winds of heaven, we feel the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of war. "Steel may glitter in the muſes ſhade."</p>
            <p>The firſt monitions of philoſophy teach us to enjoy with moderation, and hope rationally; to familiarize the idea of probable calamities, and, if poſſible, deduce beneficial conſequences from them. Influenced by this conſideration, I have choſen War for the preſent theme. Let us, for a few moments, contemplate the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, the juſtice, the effects of war; and obſerve what reference they may, now have, to our own country.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="unknown:035255_0003_1001CF86205FC7E0"/>REASONING from analogy, we ſhall be perſuaded that war is inevitable. The two firſt brothers made war; one ſlew the other. Since then, individuals and nations, have conducted in the ſame manner; ſo that the hiſtory of the world is but the narration of war—a ſtory of bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle —ſtratagem—blockade—capitulation—conqueſt—and pillage. War has become an art. Its diſciples are taught its precepts, and initiated into its myſteries; they become ſoldiers by profeſſion, and follow the trade of arms to purchaſe the means of daily ſubſiſtence. If, from the birth of time, till now, war has, very frequently happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will it not, in all probability, very frequently, happen again? We believe rivers will continue to roll towards the ocean, becauſe they have ever rolled that way; and that the dews, and the ſhowers of heaven, will always de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend. For the ſame reaſon, war is juſt as inevitable.— If war be inevitable, it is alſo neceſſary.</p>
            <p>THE neceſſity of it may be illuſtrated and further e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, by a momentary view of our own nature and ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. Men have many relations, and theſe relations o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginate many rights. The eye of reaſon is not, at all times, ſufficiently clear to perceive the line of ſeparation between the rights of one man, and thoſe of another.— Mental viſion is often obſcured, either by paſſion, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, or malevolence. From one or other of theſe cauſes, aggreſſions are conſtantly made. In a ſociety, when one individual violates the rights of another, the arm of law compels remuneration. Among nations, it cannot be ſo. They have no common arbiter in whoſe deciſions they will acquieſce; or whoſe power can force from the aggreſſor a reparation of injury. The wronged nation muſt tamely indure it, or elſe demand redreſs by war. So long, therefore, as nations, either by error, or by malevolence, will infract the laws of reciprocal right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſs, ſo long will war be inevitable, be neceſſary.</p>
            <p>A WAR of <hi>aggreſſion</hi> has not that kind of neceſſity which can render it juſt. It is indeed a polluted ſtream from the fountain of injuſtice. But if a war of <hi>defence</hi> be neceſſary, from that neceſſity, its juſtice is demonſtrated. If one part of mankind will make aggreſſions on the other, why may not thoſe aggreſſions be repelled by arms? If we may not make war, we may not reſiſt injury. If that
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:035255_0004_1001CF8EEFFEAAB8"/>
reſiſtance, which terminates in war, may not be made, no reſtraint will be left on the licentiouſneſs of the profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate. Reſiſtance is the only mound, oppoſed to that ocean of oppreſſion, which, if this were broken down, muſt ruſh in and deluge the moral world. If reſiſtance be not made, where will aggreſſion terminate? "Injuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice muſt ſweep the wide earth, and trample down man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind."</p>
            <p>IF reſiſtance be unjuſt, why do we ſympathize with the injured; or why do we feel the ſame reſentment at our own wrongs? God Almighty, the Omniſcient, the All Good, knew that the felicity of his creatures depended on free-will, and that with free-will, they muſt be liable to tranſgreſſion. To oppoſe this liability, he gave us reſentment, that ſpirit of divinity which ſwells our hearts with indignation, ſparkles in our eye, and nerves our arm againſt the wretch who dares abuſe the freedom beſtowed upon us by our common Creator.</p>
            <p>A CERTAIN equilibrium is the preſervation of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. In the material world this equilibrium is maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by repulſion. By repulſion each particle of matter drives back, and excludes from its own place, all its fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low atoms. If repulſion were deſtroyed, one atom would be conſtantly ruſhing into the habitation of another, and I know not what ceaſeleſs motations might fluctuate the univerſe. Reſentment is the repulſion of the moral world. Take away reſentment, take away reſiſtance its offspring, and not only ſociety would be deſtroyed, but even the human race itſelf would very nigh become ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed. Battle, it is true, would be excluded from the earth; but the good muſt fall a prey to the wicked; and the world be transformed into one wide realm of unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted rapine, pillage and maſſacre.</p>
            <p>IF a war of defence be unjuſt, why have we a principle of ſelf preſervation? Why do we love our country, our friends, our own being, if we are forbidden to raiſe our arm in their defence? Did God warm our hearts with theſe endearing attachments merely to encreaſe our wretchedneſs, and ſharpen our agony at the deſtruction of their objects? He did, unleſs he has commanded us to ſpill our blood in their defence. What, muſt I ſee my country laid waſte, my parents butchered, and the ſword
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:035255_0005_1001CF9D14188FD0"/>
reeking with the blood of my mother, plunged at my own naked boſom, not lift a hand againſt the ruffian aggreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor? I muſt, or a war of defence is a war of juſtice.</p>
            <p>IF I may not reſiſt, he, who would take my life, may, juſtly, take it. I may take it myſelf. For ſurely I, or any other, may juſtly deſtroy what, neither I, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without injuſtice can preſerve. This doctrine of non-reſiſtance goes to the utter deſtruction of all virtue. If we may not defend our friends, our country, our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-men, then friendſhip, and patriotiſm, and philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropy, and benevolence are vices. Nay more, vice is transformed to virtue, parricide becomes piety, the ſtain of guilt is waſhed from the forehead of murder, and ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide itſelf canonized.</p>
            <p>THERE was war in heaven, Michael and his angels fought againſt the ſpirits of perdition. Jeſus, the meek and immaculate friend of humanity, Jeſus ſaid, he who takes the weapons of <hi>aggreſſion,</hi> ſhall periſh by them, but let him who has no ſword of <hi>defence</hi> ſell his coat and buy one.</p>
            <p>THE intention of a juſt war is preſervation. This ever is the effect of it, if the arm of violence be not too power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the arm of juſtice. Tho millions have fallen in battle; tho thouſands of hills have ſmoked with blood; and the flame of many a conflagrant city reddened on the dark boſom of midnight; yet often are nations preſerved by war alone. War has once been the ſalvation of our country. It wreſted us, not from the parental embrace of a mother ſtate, but from the iron arms of tyranny; gave us independence, and in a manner prepared for us the firſt nutriment by which we have grown to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent athletic, national maturity. War demoliſhed the Roman Empire, that ſtupendous fabrick of deſpotiſm, built from the plunder, and trophied with the conqueſts, of a world. The Feudal Syſtem, a complication of ſervitude and domination, more baſe and ferocious, than any known to elder time has been, by the influence of repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wars, meliorated down to the mildneſs of modern Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh juriſprudence.</p>
            <p>WAR has given the world its moſt illuſtrious charact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. It furniſhed Homer a theme for deathleſs verſe; and opened to Achilles a field for immortal atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:035255_0006_1001CFA1D1E36FF0"/>
It raiſed Green, my Fellow-Citizens, your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Green, it raiſed to the glory of the ſecond in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his country. Had War never been, Waſhing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton had never been. The world had forever loſt the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, and the admiration of all ſucceeding time.</p>
            <p>WAR gives men the ineffable delight of defending all that is dear to them. There are thoſe, whom to redeem from danger, we would die with extacy. I, this moment, behold men who have marched barefoot, many a winter midnight, and amidſt the ſtorm of many a battle, wiſhed no greater joy than to throw their naked boſoms between their country and her foes. What then muſt they have felt on that day, when glad millions raiſed loud ſhouts of triumph to the God of armies, who extended his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hand over the fields of Columbia, and frowned the tempeſt of battle from our hemiſphere? When they ſaw their country ſafe? When they beheld parental age, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the hands of benediction, while infancy ſmiled, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conſcious of their kindneſs, and the eye of beauty beamed on them ſuffuſed with tears of gratitude?</p>
            <p>IF, therefore, war be inevitable, if, urged by injuſtice, nations will violate our rights; if a war of defence be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ified by our own feelings the eternal principles of ſelf pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, the example of heaven, and the awful mandates of him who has all power in all worlds; if war ſave na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, demoliſh deſpotiſm, throw open the portals of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal renown, and beſtow the ineffable delight of defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that can endear the poſſeſſion of life; if it do all theſe things, let us baniſh all reluctance, and all temerity at the approach of battle; magnanimoſly give ourſelves up to the voice of our nature, and our God, regarding the tempeſt in which we may be engaged, as we do thoſe el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emental contentions, which, for a while, ſeem to blot out the light and frown the univerſe into convulſions; but, when their fury is exhauſted, paſs off, leaving a ſun bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened with additional luſtre, and young creation laughing with renovated lovelineſs.</p>
            <p>IF at any time, in any region of the earth, any nation might apply theſe principles to themſelves, this is the time, this is the country, we, my fellow-citizens, are that nation. The war between the United States and France is not merely neceſſary, and juſt, and beneficial;
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:035255_0007_1001CFAB36537498"/>
a war not only for our property, our independence and ſovereignty; but for our manners, our morality, our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; for all we enjoy, for all we hope. French ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, ambition, and demoralization aim to encircle in their all devouring, all contaminating embrace, whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of wealth, or liberty, or virtue, may be found under the whole heaven. The war, therefore, is a war of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, moderation, and decency, againſt cruelty, profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy, and impunity; a war of all the virtues againſt all the vices; in a word, a war of the principle of all good againſt the principle of all evil. To the French not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vice itſelf is pleaſant unleſs it be audacious and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el; unleſs it has in it ſomething of perjured treachery, ſome violation of compact, or deſtruction of ancient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, or ſubverſion of liberty and religion. Grown faſtidious by a reiteration of common pillage, nothing can now ſatiate their unhallowed rapacity but ſpoils plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered from the cabinets of the learned, and the altars of the Almighty.</p>
            <p>AMERICANS, you will think on Flanders and Italy. You will not ſuffer Gallick pollution to ſtep over the threſhold of your temples. You have parents and wives, and daughters, and the hallowed tombs of thoſe who ſtood between your infant boſoms and the point of Britiſh ſteel. Round theſe you will form battalions, dark, terrible and reſiſtleſs, as the cloud of the North fraught with the ſpiky artillery of heaven. Let the ſons of Gaul beware. Let them ſtep a hoſtile foot over the laſt wave of the Atlantic—not one ſhall eſcape. Their bones ſhall be left bleaching on our mountains; the ſcattered frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their ſhips ſhall mingle with the ſea-weed that drifts upon our ſhores. What though they graſp at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited domination; what though they have nurtured to a gigantick ſtature a ſoul and fiend-like tyranny; who lifts his bloody forehead towards the ſtars of heaven; who tramples Europe under his feet, lays hold of Africa and Aſia with one hand, and is reaching the other to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards America; yet ſhall the monſter ſoon be proſtrated and the hallelujahs of triumph re-echo from Good-Hope to Nova Zembla, from Miſſiſippi to the Ganges.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
