<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached on the death of George Washington, lieutenant general of the American armies: and late president of the United States of America: delivered in Stonington-Port, Connecticut, on Tuesday evening, January 14th, 1800. / By Clark Brown, A.M. Minister of the Gospel Congregational Church and Society in Brimfield, Massachusetts. ; How are the mighty fallen.</title>
            <author>Brown, Clark, 1771-1817.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N27806</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N27806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 37056</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APV6344</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">37056</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99001818</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 37056.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N27806)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 37056)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 37056)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached on the death of George Washington, lieutenant general of the American armies: and late president of the United States of America: delivered in Stonington-Port, Connecticut, on Tuesday evening, January 14th, 1800. / By Clark Brown, A.M. Minister of the Gospel Congregational Church and Society in Brimfield, Massachusetts. ; How are the mighty fallen.</title>
                  <author>Brown, Clark, 1771-1817.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p. ;  23 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Trumbull, for and by the request of a number of the hearers.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Stonington-Port [Conn.], :</pubPlace>
                  <date>January, 1800.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Washington, George, 1732-1799 --  Death and burial.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:037056_0000_100C3E2286E5BF40"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:037056_0001_100C3E2411903358"/>
            <p>A SERMON, <hi>PREACHED ON THE DEATH OF</hi> George Waſhington, LIEUTENANT GENERAL of the AMERICAN AR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MIES: and LATE PRESIDENT of the UNITED STATES OF AMERICA: DELIVERED in STONINGTON-PORT, CONNECTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CUT, <hi>On Tueſday Evening, January</hi> 14<hi>th,</hi> 1800.</p>
            <p>BY CLARK BROWN, A. M. <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel Congregational Church and Society in Brimfield, Maſſachuſetts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HOW ARE THE MIGHTY FALLEN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>STONINGTON-PORT,</hi> PRINTED BY SAMUEL TRUMBULL, <hi>For and by the requeſt of a number of the Hearers.</hi> January, 1800.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="unknown:037056_0002_100C3E26B913E870"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:037056_0003_100C3E2997C8B6F0"/>
            <head>A SERMON, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>CONVENED for the purpoſe of making ſome ſuitable reflections, upon the death of GENERAL GEORGE WASHINGTON; the Man who, in life, was highly ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erable, amiable and beloved; and who, in his death, is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lamented, and univerſally honored by public and reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ceremonies;—the following pathetic and ejaculatory Aphoriſm of Iſrael's inſpired King, is highly applicable to the occaſion: "HELP, LORD; for the GODLY MAN cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth; for the FAITHFUL fail from among the CHILDREN of MEN."</p>
                  <bibl>PSALMS, CHAP. xii. VERSE 1.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ALL terreſtial things and beings are of a tranſitory and periſhable nature. Even the Sun, that bright emblem of the Deity, which has for ages ſhone with undiſtinguiſhable luſtre upon ſurrounding worlds, muſt at length ceaſe to ſhine, and be removed from its exalted ſtation; among the ſhining worlds in the expanded firmament.—The principles of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay and diſſolution, are inſeperably connected with all the viſible objects of nature.</p>
            <p>THAT all the human race are mortal is a truth which neither the godly, nor the ungodly diſpute. The moſt wiſe and amiable and the moſt godly and eſteemed of men, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be exempted from the ſtroke of death. To death, the rich as well as the poor, the noble as well as the ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, muſt ſubmit and bow. Neither the virtues nor honors of WASHINGTON, could ſecure him from the arreſt of death.—WASHINGTON, the faithful and godly, has fallen; —he is removed from us into the world of ſpirits,—it ſhould therefore be the prayer of United Columbia, Help, or ſave us O Lord, for the godly Man hath ceaſed; for the faithful Man from among us has failed!</p>
            <p>THE death of the wiſe and virtuous in public life, is a juſt cauſe of public lamentation, ſorrow and prayer. Tho' all things and beings are under the wiſe and ſovereign direction
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:037056_0004_100C31EFDFCF1100"/>
of HIM "whoſe kingdom ruleth over all,"—and tho it be the duty of all mankind to ſubmit to the events of his prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idence as juſt and right, yet when perſons of eminent worth and uſefulneſs, of ſingular piety and goodneſs, are taken out of the world, it is lawful to expreſs grief, and to mourn that they are no more. When perſons of this character, in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic life, are taken away by death, it cannot be diſpleaſing to the Holy Governor of the univerſe, to ſee thoſe of the ſame community or nation, noticing with religious ceremonies, ſuch an event of his providence, and reſpecting their virtues by public teſtimonies of veneration. This may be done with all due ſubmiſſion to his holy government, and to the particular inſtance of his providence, by which their ſorrow and mourning are united.</p>
            <p>As the venerable Man, whoſe death we now lament, was poſſeſſed of extraordinary virtues, and was more than uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly uſeful in public life,—it becomes the ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Columbia, to unite in public teſtamonies of grief, and in public ceremonies of reſpect for his memory.</p>
            <p>"THE ILLUSTRIOUS GENERAL GEORGE WASHING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON IS DEAD." Let COLUMBIA be clothed in an HA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BILIMENT of MOURNING. He has died, as expreſſed in the public Papers, "mature in years, covered with glory, and rich in the affection of the American people."</p>
            <p>HOWEVER the Citizens of United America have been, and are yet divided in their political ſentiments,—yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the death of the illuſtrious WASHINGTON, they lay aſide their diviſions and animoſity, and are united in paying a public reſpect to the talents, uſefulneſs, virtues and memory of this their departed Hero.—In all our populous towns, the ſeveral Houſes of public worſhip, have been dreſſed in mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, while the Bells, with ſolemn ſound, have announced that ſome public Calamity has come upon our country: And what is the Calamity? Have either famines, earthquakes, or epidemic diſorders, become the cauſe of theſe public teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſorrow and mourning? No! "The illuſtrious LEADER; the SOLDIERS FRIEND; the FATHER of his COUNTRY," is forever removed from this ſublunary world. Numerous are the Orations, Sermons, and Eulogies, which have been pronounced, in honor to his ſuperior talents and virtues:—And in the commemoration and celebration of which, numerous hymns, pſalms, and dirges, have been ſung in ſolemn ſtrains:—The vocal and inſtrumental muſic, which have been performed on the occaſion, have ſmitten the mind
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:037056_0005_100C3E2D942EF248"/>
with pungent anguiſh, while they have cauſed reflections highly uſeful and important. The ſeveral funeral proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and military honors, which have been formed, as public teſtimonies of ſorrow for the melancholy event of his death, are calculated to teach us the uncertainty and final <hi>End</hi> of all worldly greatneſs and honors.</p>
            <p>AMONG the many public tributes of reſpect with which he has been honored in his death the ſpeaker will now hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly attempt, to ſhew that he was, according to the text, "A Godly and faithful man."</p>
            <p>WITH one voice, all the true Citizens of United Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia, who reſpect the divine government over mankind, muſt readily unite in this ſolemn and pathetic Addreſs to God, "Help, Lord; for the godly man ceaſeth; for the faithful fail from among us."—</p>
            <p>WHATEVER might have cauſed the pious king of Iſrael, to make this addreſs, none of us can be inſenſible of its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the death of Waſhington, the Hero, the Sage, and Patriot of United America.</p>
            <p>HE was a Godly-man, becauſe he always reſpected &amp; vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the character and government of the Supreme Ruler of the Univerſe.—He was never known to trifle with the names by which the Creator and Governor of the world is diſtinguiſhed from other beings. He always reverenced his ſacred names, titles, and attributes; and of things ſacred he always ſpake with ſolemnity and reverence. It has been remarked by thoſe who have had a perſonal acquaintance with him, and who have attended him both in the private and public walks of life, that he never took the name of the Lord God in vain. His countenance indicated a ſolemn mind, and all his private and public actions manifeſted that he was a Godly-man.</p>
            <p>IN his public addreſſes, and in his anſwers to the many thouſand which he has received, and eſpecially in his FARE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WELL ADDRESS to the people when he laſt retired into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate life, his <hi>Piety</hi> is evidently diſcovered. With Godly rev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erence, he always mentioned the Divine government, relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Divine goodneſs and expreſſed the Divine bleſſing, confer'd on the American Nation.</p>
            <p>AMIDST all the honors which his fellow Citizens could confer upon him, and while living in the moſt affluent cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, his heart and affections aſpired to things of a more glorious and duriable nature. He lived as being fully ſenſible of the uncertain and tranſitory nature of all human
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:037056_0006_100C3E2FA2811D58"/>
greatneſs and glory. He lived as one who lived not to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but to the glory of his Creator, and for the good of his fellow creatures. His heart was enlivened by pious affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; his mind enlarged with exalted conceptions of Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah and his providences; and his conduct made amiable by a courſe of uniformity and virtue. Realizing the view and glory of making the people of theſe United States virtuous and happy, under an equitable Conſtitution and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in their National exiſtence and independence; and animated by the hope of leaving virtuous examples of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall heroiſm, and of a juſt adminiſtration in the high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment of Government, both legiſlative and executive, he encounter'd the greateſt dangers, and cheerfully paſſed thro' many trying ſcenes. Endeavouring to promote the honor and kingdom of Jehovah in the world, he has leſt a name, which will be revered by the virtuous of ſucceeding ages. In all the dangers and diſtreſſes with which he has been ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded, he has found abundant conſolation in the applauſe of a good conſcience, and eſpecially in the reaſonable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of having the approbation of the Supreme Ruler of all nations. Such conſolations ſhall ſurvive the wreck of worlds and ages: "they are independent ſolaces" far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the reach of time's deſtroying power. Theſe, in a degree, the Godly of all ranks and ſtations enjoy; and for them, with the moſt ſervent zeal, we ſhould all aſpire.</p>
            <p>PERSUADED that Jehovah governs the world, with the moſt perfect wiſdom and holineſs, juſtice and benignity, and that all his requirements of mankind are perfectly juſt and holy, this godly Man lived ſuperior to all thoſe altercations and diviſions which have been raiſed, and for ages carried on by religious bigots. Senſible that modes of faith and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſentiment were of no importance, only as they tended to promote true benevolence, kindneſs, charity, and virtue among mankind, —his religion, was conſtituted in ſupreme reverence for the character, perfections and government of Jehovah, and of univerſal "good will to man."</p>
            <p>THO' he was a profeſſor of religion in the Church of England, yet it is evident that he was a ſincere believer in the abſolute unity of the Deity, as diſconnected from all human opinions, and inventions, with which the doctrine has long been taught, and handed down from one generation to another.</p>
            <p>BELIEVING that there were virtuous perſons, among the ſev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eral claſſes &amp; different denomination of people in the United
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:037056_0007_100C3E312B41CE88"/>
States, and unwilling to dictate others in their religious ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, he in his Proclamation for a day of public Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving in the year ninety-five, called on the people to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their gratitude to the ONE ONLY SUPREME over all, on account of his wonderful goodneſs manifeſted to them as a nation. He ſaid nothing about any particular ſyſtem of religion, or any of the controverſal doctrines among Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and others: But he fully expreſſed the great funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of all religion; ſuch as the acknowledgement of the exiſtence, perfections, and providence of Jehovah; the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude due to him for all his bleſſings, both of a public and private nature; and our obligations to Him, as alſo our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, in the regulations of our affections and conduct by a faithful obedience to the demands of that religion, which requires repentance and an implicit reliance upon the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine mercy for the pardon of ſin, and for every temporal and ſpiritual favor. He was therefore GODLY by the exerciſe of univerſal CHARITY and "GOODWILL" which are directly oppoſed to the diſpoſition and conduct of thoſe profeſſors of religion, who confine their charity and GOODWILL to thoſe only of their peculiar ſentiments. As ſuch characters are ſo few in the world, eſpecially in public life, we have the higheſt reaſon to mourn for the loſs of the Man of this char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acter, who has lately fallen in death:—With the utmoſt propriety may we pray as in the words of the text, "Help, LORD; for this godly man hath ceaſed; for this faithful Man hath failed from among us."</p>
            <p>THAT WASHINGTON, who is juſtly ſtiled the illuſtrious, was faithful, in the exerciſe of that power and confidence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in him, is a fact too evident to be denied by his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt enemies. In what inſtance, has he ever acted incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with his dignified and exalted ſtation? Did he ever abuſe the power with which he was intruſted? Or, Did he ever betray the high and important TRUST committed to him, by the united ſuffrages of his fellow Citizens? The greateſt error which has ever been attributed to him in his public adminiſtration, was the ſigning the Britiſh treaty. But as we have the higheſt reaſon to ſuppoſe, that he was ſincere in this act, the enemies to the Treaty, ſhould ſpare cenſure, and be candid and charitable, when ſpeaking of this inſtance of his public conduct.</p>
            <p>POSSESSED of all the honors and powers which his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try could beſtow upon him; and poſſeſſed of an Independent fortune, can we conceive of any motive, by which he could
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:037056_0008_100C3E32B7D54620"/>
have been induced, to ſign ſuch a public Inſtrument, either to aggrandize or enrich himſelf:—On the contrary, Have we not every reaſon to ſuppoſe, that he was actuated in this inſtance from a ſincere and diſintereſted regard for the public good? What the conſequences might have been, if the Treaty had not been ratified by his public ſanction, it is <hi>now</hi> impoſſible for us to determine: Perhaps much greater depredations on our commerce, and war devaſtation, and bloodſhed among us. But we will ſpare our conjectures, while we conſider him as having the general good of his country at heart, when to the Treaty he put his public ſanct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion. As the treaty is approbated by a Majority of both branches of Government, and by the Majority of the people, a certain deference is due to their opinion and judgment from the Minority.</p>
            <p>A MAN elevated to the exalted ſtation in which the Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erable MAN, whoſe death we now deplore, was; and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing the power with which he was intruſted, might have been wholly actuated, in his public conduct, from the ſelfiſh principles of avarice and ambition. Hiſtory is filled with unnumbered evils of ſceptered ambition and avarice, abuſed power and domination. Hiſtory teaches us the fatal effects of the ſelfiſhneſs, avarice, and ambition of Rulers both in the cabinet and field. Many of the Kings of Iſrael, ſeveral of the Roman Emperors, ſuch as Nero and Caligula, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable others of almoſt all the kingdoms and nations of the world, have converted their ſupreme magiſtracy and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, into engines of oppreſſion and cruelty, and for the accompliſhment of the moſt tyrannical and ſelfiſh purpoſes. Such characters have ever been the greateſt inſtruments of national profligacy and deſtruction. Jeroboam, King of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, finned, and made his nation to ſin. Hence we find it repeatedly ſaid in the hiſtory of the wicked Kings of Iſrael, He "did like unto Jereboam, King of Iſrael, who made Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael to ſin." This character is applicable to every wicked ruler. Such characters in their public adminiſtration, cauſe oppreſſive laws; burthenſome taxes; injurious promotions; cauſeleſs ejections from office; cruel executions, internal devaſtation; and foreign domination. From the conduct and example of ſuch rulers, profligacy and ruin ſpread through the community, and ſtop the ſtreams of national health and glory. But how very different were the public meaſures and adminiſtration of the illuſtrious Perſonage, whoſe death we now lament. Was he ever known to be cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:037056_0009_100C3E35083D4C78"/>
by the ſplendor of dignity? or wrongly allur'd by the dazzling effects of honnor &amp; influence? Was he ever know to diſtribute juſtice with an uneven balance? Was virtue ever oppoſed by his conduct, or diſcountenanced by his examples? Did he ever deſignedly elevate the vicious to ſtations which claim reſpect and confidence? Are not the whole of this aſſembly, and indeed the millions of confederated America, ready to reply with one voice, No! —Where in our own Country, or indeed in any other Country, can we find anoth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſuch a Character, ſo illuſtrious and uſeful, whom Heaven has ſelected for an inſtrument of ſuch public good? Impel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by ſimilar emotions, the whole American nation are now in mourning for the loſs of a Man <hi>ſo</hi> "godly and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful." He was a Job, for patience, in danger and diſtreſs; a Moſes, for a national Deliverer and Saviour; a Joſhua for a Commander of a numerous and reſpectable Army, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his Country's rights and liberty; and a David for the public adminiſtration of the conſtitution and government of an highly favoured nation. Such an aſſemblage of hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ic and religious virtues, were never found in any human char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acter before. Grecian nor Roman Annals, have never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineated ſuch exalted virtues and talents, in the lines of any of their boaſted and deified heroes, legiſlators or philoſophers. Under the ſuperintending providence of JEHOVAH who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth &amp; humbleth nations, he has done more than any other man, "in founding this our wide ſpreading Empire," and in eſtabliſhing in this weſtern world a grea &amp; independent nation.</p>
            <p>IN a period of the deepeſt calamity, he was appointed Commander in chief of the united army of the <hi>then</hi> thirteen States of America; in which ſtation he always acted with undaunted courage and uniform dignity. With a heroiſm and military wiſdom wholly unprecedented, and in dangers the moſt difficult, trying and diſtreſſing, he has been inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental of eſtabliſhing our national exiſtence, independence and greatneſs. Having accompliſhed the great and highly important OBJECT, for which he was appointed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief of the American armies, he according to the elegant language of prophecy, converted the implements of war, ſuch as the ſword into the ploughſhare and the ſpear in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pruning hook; and with cheerfulneſs, retired into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate life. But as ſoon as it became obvious that it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and highly expedient that there ſhould be a conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion founded, and a general Government eſtabliſhed for the United States, he again, at his country's call, forſook the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirements of domeſtic life, and in a time of political convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:037056_0010_100C3E382943F700"/>
when a National ſtorm had ariſen, came forward into public view; and with virtue and honor, preſided over the confederated States of America, as their firſt and chief Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate. At the cloſe of the laſt term for which he was elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the chief Magiſtracy of the United States, he volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily chooſe to retire again into the private walks of life, even when his unanimous "re-election could not have been doubted."—But as ſoon as his beloved Country, was again in danger, by the threatenings and aſſaults of foreign ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, he was ready to ſtep forward in its defence. He therefore accepted accordingly the appointment and office of Lieutenant General of the American Armies; in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of which office he was faithful unto death.</p>
            <p>HENCE, "by the purity of his character," and by a long ſeries of the moſt important ſervices of a public nature, he has rendered himſelf illuſtrious, not only in this Country, but throughout the World.— He always acted in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as naturally tended to allure others to the practice of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and righteouſneſs, and not to vice and licentiouſneſs. In the ſhade of retirement, in the field, in the cabinet, and in the chair of State, he was reſpectable and virtuous. He was "a Lion in the day of battle, and great and powerful in command." The gentleneſs and ſimplicity of his manners, and his virtuous and amiable conduct, united in forming a character truly grand and illuſtrious: a character which was calculated to command attention and inſpire confidence. His natural genious, acquired talents and virtues; brought him at an uncommon early period of life into public notice and eſteem. In danger, and while others were in diſmay, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways acted with firmneſs and moderation. One inſtance of which, may be noticed in his conduct at the banks of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ongahela: There conſider the youthful Waſhington, in an awful time of Indian victory and triumph, collecting the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains of the defeated Army of Bradock.—and ſaving, by a diſcernment and valor uncommon for his years, the lives of hundreds whoſe hearts had failed for fear, and whoſe lives were in jeopardy every moment by the unrelenting ſavage foe.</p>
            <p>DURING the period of almoſt Fifty Years, he was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the performance of a ſeries of great and important ſervices to his country; the ſplendor and glory of which, eclipſe all the glittering royalty of all the crowns and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified names, of all the Monarchs which ever ſat upon the thrones, of all the Kingdoms and Empires of either Europe, Aſia, or Africa.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="unknown:037056_0011_100C3E3A49508968"/>RELIGION was his "conſtant angelic gueſt," and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine paraclete of his heart.—During the whole of his life, he exhibited a uniform and illuſtrious example of the moſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed virtues. Under his auſpicious protection and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronage, piety and righteouſneſs, as by "kindly rains and temperate ſuns" ſprang up and flouriſhed, and have yielded a profitable harveſt. Like the unclouded Sun, he aroſe into public view; in the meredian and evening of life, attracted the attention and admiration of millions; with refulgent brightneſs, ſat below the horizon of this life, in the ſerene <hi>Eve</hi> of this exiſtence; and has ariſen, with holy ſplendor, in the Horizon of Immortality.</p>
            <p>FROM hence we learn, That, in every inſtance, in which we, in our reſpective ſtations and employments, can imitate his virtues, it is our moſt indiſpenſible duty thus to do.—We all have parts to act upon the theatre of time: and juſtice, goodneſs, and religion are neceſſary for their right perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance: Let it be our conſtant and greateſt concern to live, like the venerable WASHINGTON, godly and faithful in the preſent evil world: And when this world ſhall recede from our mortal view, as it has from his, May we, as he did, have a religious peace in ſuch a ſolemn and awful period:— then we ſhall ſtand firm and ſure at the final Retribution, when the diſſolution of all terreſtial things and ſcenes, ſhall aſtoniſh the thronging MULTITUDE, preſſing forward to the general Judgment.</p>
            <p>FINALLY—My Brethren, by this inſtance of Mortality, we learn, the vanity of all human greatneſs and glory.</p>
            <p>ALASS! WASHINGTON, the Hero, the Friend, and the Father of his Country, is gone, forever gone!!—His ſacred Relics muſt remain under the power of death, until the ſolemn Morn of the general Reſurrection:—And ſhall his unparralled talents, virtues, ſervices, and NAME, be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> No!—For Columbia's Sons and Daughters, ſhall, to the lateſt generation, celebrate them with rapture and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
            <p>"O WASHINGTON, thou HERO, Patriot, Sage," May we not ſay concerning thee, in the ſublime language of the celebrated Bard, to which thy Country has given birth.</p>
            <q>
               <l>"Thy glorious life a volume ſhall compoſe,</l>
               <l>"As Alps immortal; ſpotleſs as it ſnows.</l>
               <l>"The ſtars ſhall be its types; the preſs its age,</l>
               <l>"The Earth its binding, the ſky its page: —</l>
               <l>"In Heaven's high Dome, the Work ſhall ſtand.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="unknown:037056_0012_100C3E3BEAAC02E0"/>"Shine with its Sun's, and with its <hi>Arch</hi> expand;</l>
               <l>"'Till Nature's ſelf, the vandal torch ſhall raiſe,</l>
               <l>"And the vaſt Alcove of Creation blaze."</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>☞ As the Author has not had an opportunity of examining the Proof Sheets, the readers will pleaſe to excuſe all the errors which may be diſcovered.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
