<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The two wealthy farmers; or, The history of Mr. Bragwell. Part IV.</title>
            <author>More, Hannah, 1745-1833.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N27870</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N27870</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 37135</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APY4070</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">37135</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99031198</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 37135.</title>
            <title>Cheap repository. No. 8.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N27870)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 37135)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 37135)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The two wealthy farmers; or, The history of Mr. Bragwell. Part IV.</title>
                  <author>More, Hannah, 1745-1833.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p. ;  15 cm. (18mo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. &amp; J. Johnson, no. 147 High-Street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1800. (Price 4 cents or 2s. 4d. per. doz.)</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head of title: [Cheap repository.] [No. VIII.]</note>
                  <note>This title is included in: The works of Hannah More, New York, 1835.</note>
                  <note>Parentheses substituted for square brackets in imprint transcription.</note>
                  <note>Title vignette.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Juvenile literature --  1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:037135_0000_100C92A87944E380"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:037135_0001_100C92AACC2F4B10"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>[CHEAP RESPOSITORY.] [No. VIII]</p>
            <p>THE Two Wealthy Farmers; Or, the Hiſtory of Mr. BRAGWELL.</p>
            <p>PART IV.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA: PRINTED BY B. &amp; J. JoHNSON, No. 147 HIGH-STREET.</p>
            <p>1800. [Price 4 Cents Or 2s. 4d. per. doz.]</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="story">
            <pb facs="unknown:037135_0002_100C92AD0F3C40D8"/>
            <head>THE Two Wealthy Farmers, &amp;c PART IV.</head>
            <p>AS ſoon as it was ſold, Bragwell again ſaid ſoftly to Worthy, "Five from fifty, and there remain forty-five. The dinner and drink won't coſt me five pounds, and I have got fifty more than the land was worth. Spend a ſhilling to gain a pound, this is what I call practical Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metic, Mr. Worthy."</p>
            <p>Mr. Worthy was glad to get out of this ſcene; and ſeeing that his friend was quite ſober, he reſolved as they rode hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to deal plainly with him. Bragwell had found out among his calculations, that ſome ſins could only be committed by a prudent man one at a time. For inſtance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he knew that a man could not well get rich and get drunk at the ſame mome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> but he had found out that ſome vices made very good company together; ſo, while he had watched himſelf in drinking, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt he ſhould become as unfit to ſell as his gueſts were to buy, he had indulged wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hout meaſure in the good dinner he had provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:037135_0003_100C92AE9C686E30"/>
Mr. Worthy, I ſay, ſeeing him able to bear reaſon, rebuked him for this day's proceedings with ſome ſeverity. Bragwell bore his reproofs with that ſort of patience which ariſes from an opinion of one's own wiſdom, and a recent fluſh of proſperity. He behaved with that good-humour which grows out of vanity and good luck. "You are too ſquemiſh, Mr. Worthy," ſaid he, "I have done nothing diſcreditable. Theſe men came with their eyes open. There is no compulſion uſed. They are free to bid or to let it alone. I make them welcome, and I ſhall not be thought a bit the worſe of to-morrow, when they are ſober. Others do it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides me, and I ſhall never be aſhamed of any thing as long as I have cuſtom on my ſide.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Worthy.</hi> "I am ſorry, Mr. Bragwell, to hear you ſupport ſuch practices by ſuch arguments. There is not perhaps a more dangerous ſnare to the ſouls of men than is to be found in that word CUSTOM. It is a word invented to reconcile corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with credit and ſin with ſafety. But no cuſtom, no faſhion, no combination of men to ſet up a falſe ſtandand can ever
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:037135_0004_100C92B094ED25B0"/>
make a wrong action right. That a thing is often done, is ſo far from a proof of its being right, that it is the very reaſon which will ſet a thinking man to inquire if it be not really wrong, leſt he ſhould be following "a multitude to do evil." Right is right, though only one man in a thouſand purſues it, and wrong will be for ever wrong, though it be the allowed practice of the other nine hundred and ninety-nine. If this ſhameful cuſtom is really common, which I can hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that is a freſh reaſon why a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious man ſhould ſet his face againſt it. And I muſt go ſo far as to ſay (you will excuſe me Mr. Bragwell) that I ſee no great difference in the eye of conſcience, whatever there may be in the eye of law, between your making a man loſe his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and then getting 50 guineas out of his pocket <hi>because</hi> he has loſt it, and your picking the fifty guineas out of his pocket if you had met him dead drunk in his way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome to-night. Nay, he who meets a man already drunk and robs him, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits but one ſin, while he who makes him drunk firſt that he may rob him afterwards, commits two."</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="5" facs="unknown:037135_0005_100C92B30C254890"/>Bragwell gravely replied, "Mr. Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, while I have the practice of people of credit to ſupport me, and the law of the land to protect me, I ſee no reaſon to be aſhamed of any thing I do."—"Mr. Brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, anſwered Worthy, a truly honeſt man is not always looking ſharp about him, to ſee how far cuſtom and the law will bear him out; if he be honeſt on princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple he will conſult the law of his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and if he be a Chriſtian he will conſult the written law of God.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding this rebuff, Mr. Brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well got home in high ſpirits, for no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments could hinder him from feeling that he had the 50 guineas in his purſe. As ſoon as he came in, he threw the money he had received on the table, and deſired his wife to lock it up. Inſtead of receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it with her uſual ſatisfaction, ſhe burſt into a violent fit of paſſion, and threw it back to him. "You may keep your caſh yourſelf, ſaid ſhe. It is all over: we want no more money. You are a ruined man! A wicked creature, ſcraping and working as we have done for her!" Brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l trembled, but durſt not aſk what he dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aded to hear. His wife ſpared him
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:037135_0006_100C92B4F2D04D00"/>
the trouble, by crying out, as ſoon as her rage permitted, "Polly is gone off!" Poor Bragwell's heart ſunk within him; he grew ſick and giddy, and as his wife's rage ſwallowed up her grief, ſo in his grief he almoſt forgot his anger. The purſe fell from his hand, and he caſt a look of anguiſh upon it, finding, for the firſt time, that it could not relieve his miſery.</p>
                  <p>Mr. Worthy, who though much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, was leſs diſcompoſed now, called to mind that the young lady had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with her mother and ſiſter the night before: he begged Mrs. Bragwell to explain the ſad ſtory. She, inſtead of ſoothing her huſband, fell to reproaching him. "It is all your fault, ſaid ſhe, you were a fool for your pains. If I had had my way, the girls never would have kept company with any but men of ſubſtance." "Mrs, Bragwell," ſaid Worthy, "If ſhe has choſen a bad man, it would be ſtill a misfortune, even though he had been rich." "O that would alter the caſe," ſaid ſhe; "a <hi>fat sorrow is better than a lean one.</hi> But to marry a beggar!" Here Miſs Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey who ſtood ſullenly by, put in a word,
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:037135_0007_100C92B6844097B0"/>
and ſaid, "her ſiſter, however, had not diſgraced herſelf by having married a Farmer or a Tradeſman, ſhe had at leaſt made choice of a Gentleman." "What marriage! what Gentleman," cried the afflicted father. "Tell me the worſt!" He was now informed that his darling daughter was gone off with a ſtrolling play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, who had been acting in the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing villages lately. Miſs Betſey again put in, ſaying, "he was no ſtroller, but a gentleman in diſguiſe, who only acted for his own diverſion," "Does he ſo," ſaid the now furious Bragwell, "then he ſhall be tranſported for mine. At this moment a letter was brought him from his new ſon-in-law, who deſired his leave to wait upon him, and implore his forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. He owned he had been ſhopman to a haberdaſher, but thinking his perſon and talents ought not to be thrown away upon trade, and being alſo a little behind hand he had taken to the ſtage with a view of making his fortune. That he had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Miſs Bragwell entirely for love, and was ſorry to mention ſo paltry a thing as money, which he deſpiſed, but that his wants were preſſing, his landlord, to whom he was in debt, having been ſo vulgar as
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:037135_0008_100C92B8137D2A90"/>
to threaten to ſend him to priſon. He ended with ſaying, "I have been obliged to ſhock your daughter's delicacy, by confeſſing my unlucky real name; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve I owe part of my ſucceſs to my ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving aſſumed that of Auguſtus Frederick Theodoſious. She is inconſolable at this confeſſion, which, as you are now my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I muſt alſo make to you, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe myſelf, with many bluſhes, your dutiful ſon,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>TIMOTHY INCLE."</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>"O," cried the afflicted father, as he tore the letter in a rage. "Miſs Bragwell married to a ſtrolling actor! How ſhall I bear it?" "Why, I would not bear it at all," cried the enraged mother. "I would never ſee her, I would never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give her. I would let her ſtarve at one corner of the barn, while that raſcal, with all thoſe Pagan, popiſh names, was rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away at the other." "Nay," ſaid Miſs Betſey, "If he is only a ſhopman, and if his name be really Timothy Incle; I would never forgive her neither. But who would have thought it by his looks, and by his monſtrous genteel behaviour."</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="unknown:037135_0009_100C92BAB49A4348"/>"Come, come," ſaid Mr. Worthy, "were he really an honeſt haberdaſher, I ſhould think there was no other harm done, except the diſobedience of the thing. Mr. Bragwell, this is no time to blame you, or hardly to reaſon with you. I feel for you ſincerely. I ought not perhaps, juſt at preſent, to reproach you for the miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken manner in which you have bred up your daughters. Your error has brought its puniſhment along with it. You now ſee, becauſe you now feel, the evil of a falſe education. It has ruined your daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, your whole plan has led to ſome ſuch end. The large ſums you ſpent to quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy them as you thought for a high ſtation, could do them nothing but harm, while your habits of life properly confined them to company of a lower ſtation. While they were better dreſt than the daughters of the firſt gentry, they were worſe taught than the daughters of your plowmen. Their vanity has been raiſed by exceſſive finery, and kept alive by exceſſive flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Every evil temper has been foſtered by indulgence. Their pride has never been controled. Their ſelf-will has ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been turned. Their idleneſs has laid them open to every temptation, and their
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:037135_0010_100C92BCA566FF38"/>
abundance has enabled them to gratify every deſire. Their time, that precious talent, has been entirely waſted. Every thing they have been taught to do is of no uſe, while they are utterly unacquainted with all which they ought to have known. I deplore Miſs Polly's falſe ſtep. That ſhe ſhould have married a run-away ſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, turned ſtroller, I truly lament. But for what huſband was ſhe qualified? For the wife of a Farmer ſhe was too idle. For the wife of a tradeſman ſhe was too expenſive. For the wife of a Gentleman ſhe was too ignorant. You yourſelf was moſt to blame. You expected her to act wiſely, though you never taught her that <hi>fear of God which is the beginning of wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> I owe it to you, as a friend, and to myſelf as a Chriſtian to declare, that your practices in the common tranſactions of life, as well as your preſent misfortune, are almoſt the natural conſequences of thoſe falſe principles, which I proteſted againſt when you were at my* houſe.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Bragwell attempted ſeveral times to interrupt Mr. Worthy, but her huſband
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:037135_0011_100C92BE3237AEB0"/>
would not permit it. He felt the force of all his friend ſaid and encouraged him to proceed. Mr. Worthy thus went on. "It grieves me to ſay how much your own indiſcretion has contributed even to bring on your preſent misfortune. You gave your countenance to this very company of ſtrollers, though you knew they were acting in defiance to the laws of the land, to ſay no worſe. They go from town to town, and barn to barn, ſtripping the the poor of their money, the young of their innocence, and all of their time. Do you remember with how much pride you told me that you had beſpoke <hi>The bold Stroke for a Wife,</hi> for the benefit of this very Mr. Frederic Theodoſious? To this pernicious ribaldry you not only carried your own family, but waſted I know not how much money in treating your work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's wifes and children, in theſe hard times too, when they have ſcarcely bread to eat or a ſhoe on their feet. And all this only that you might have the abſurd pleaſure of ſeeing thoſe flattering words. <hi>By Desire of Mr. Bragwell,</hi> ſtuck up in Print at the Public-houſe, on the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith's ſhed, at the Turnpike-gate, and on the Barn-door."</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="unknown:037135_0012_100C92C025816120"/>Mr. Bragwell acknowledged, that his friend's rebuke was but too juſt, and he looked ſo very contrite as to raiſe the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Mr. Worthy, who, in a mild voice, thus went on. "What I have ſaid is not ſo much to reproach you with the ruin of one daughter, as from a deſire to ſave the other. Let Miſs Betſey go home with me. I do not undertake to be her gaoler, but I will be her friend. She will find in my daughters, kind companions, and in my wife a prudent guide. I know ſhe will diſlike us at firſt, but I do not deſpair in time of convincing her that a ſober, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, uſeful, pious life is as neceſſary to make us happy on earth, as it is to fit us for heaven."</p>
            <p>Poor Miſs Betſey, though ſhe declared it would be <hi>frightful dull,</hi> and <hi>monstrous vulgar,</hi> and <hi>dismal melancholy,</hi> yet ſhe was ſo terrified at the diſcontent and grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling which ſhe would have to endure at home, that ſhe ſullenly conſented. She had none of that filial tenderneſs which led her to wiſh to ſtay and ſooth and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her afflicted father. All ſhe thought about was to get out of the way of her mother's ill-humour, and to carry ſo much
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:037135_0013_100C92C2121230B0"/>
finery as to fill the Miſs Worthies with envy and reſpect. Poor girl! She did not know that envy was a feeling they never indulged: and that fine cloaths was the laſt thing to draw their reſpect. Mr. Worthy took her home next day. When they reached his houſe, they found there young wilſon, Miſs Betſey's old admirer. She was much pleaſed at this, and reſolved to treat him well. But her good or ill treatment now ſignified but little. This young Grazier reverenced Mr. Worthy's character, and ſince he had met him at the Lion, had been thinking what a happineſs it would be to marry a young woman bred up by ſuch a father. He had heard much of the modeſty a diſcretion of both the daughters, but his inclination now determined him in favour of the elder.</p>
            <p>Mr. Worthy, who knew him to be a young man of good ſenſe and ſound prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, allowed him to become a viſitor at his houſe, but deferred his conſent to the marriage till he knew him more thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Mr. Wilſon, from what he ſaw of the domeſtic piety of this family, impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved daily both in the knowledge and
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:037135_0014_100C92C465461188"/>
practice of religion, and Mr. Worthy ſoon formed him into a moſt valuable character. During this time Miſs Brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well's hopes had revived, but though ſhe appeared in a new dreſs almoſt every day, ſhe had the mortification of being beheld with great indifference by one whom ſhe had always ſecretly liked. Mr. Wilſon married before her face a girl who was greatly her inferior in fortune, perſon and appearance, but who was humble, frugal, meek and pious. Miſs Bragwell now ſtrongly felt the truth of what Mr. Wilſon had once told her, "that a woman may make an excellent partner for a dance, who would make a very bad one for life."</p>
            <p>Mr. Bragwell was ſo much afflicted at the diſgraceful marriage of his daughter, who ran off with Timothy Incle, the ſtrolling-player, that he never fully reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his ſpirits. His chearfulneſs which had ariſen from an high opinion of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, had been confirmed by a conſtant flow of uninterrupted ſucceſs; and that is a ſort of chearfulneſs which is very lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be impaired, becauſe it lies at the mercy of every accident and croſs event in life. But though his pride was now
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:037135_0015_100C92C5F1F99440"/>
diſappointed, his misfortunes had not taught him any humility, becauſe he had not diſcovered that they were cauſed by his own fault; nor had he acquired any patience or ſubmiſſion, becauſe he had not learnt that all afflictions come from the hand of God to awaken us to a deep ſenſe of our ſins, and to draw off our hearts from the periſhing vanities of this life. Beſides, Mr. Bragwell was one of thoſe people, who, even if they would be thought to bear with tolerable ſubmiſſion ſuch trials as appear to be ſent more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from Providence, yet think they have a ſort of right to rebel at every misfortune which befalls them through the fault of a fellow-creature; as if our fellow-creatures were not the agents and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by which Providence often ſees fit to try or to puniſh us.</p>
            <p>This imprudent daughter, Bragwell would not be brought to ſee or forgive, nor was the degrading name of Mrs. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle ever allowed to be pronounced in his hearing. He had loved her with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive and undue affection; and while ſhe gratified his vanity by her beauty and finery, he deemed her faults of little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence;
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:037135_0016_100C92C7DE7FEC20"/>
but when ſhe diſappointed his ambition by a diſgraceful marriage, all his natural affection only ſerved to increaſe his reſentment. Yet, though he regretted her crime leſs than his own mortification, he never ceaſed in ſecret to lament her loſs. She ſoon found out ſhe was undone, and wrote in a ſtrain of bitter repentance to aſk his forgiveneſs. She owned that her huſband, whom ſhe had ſuppoſed to be a man of faſhion in diſguiſe, was a low perſon in diſtreſſed circumſtances. She implored that her father, though he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give her huſband that fortune for which alone it was now too plain he had married her, would at leaſt allow her ſome ſubſiſtence, for that Mr. Incle was much in debt, and ſhe feared in danger of a gaol. The father's heart was half melted at this account, and his affection was for a time awakened. But Mrs. Bragwell oppoſed his ſending her any aſſiſtance. She always made it a point of duty never to forgive; "for ſhe ſaid it only encouraged thoſe who had done wrong once to do worſe next time. For her part ſhe had never yet been guilty of ſo mean and pitiful a weakneſs as to forgive any one; for to pardon an injury always ſhewed either
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:037135_0017_100C92C9936FEBF0"/>
want of ſpirit to feel it, or want of power to reſent it. She was reſolved ſhe would never ſquander the money for which ſhe had worked early and late, on a baggage who had thrown herſelf away on a beggar while ſhe had a daughter ſingle who might raiſe her family by a great match." I am ſorry to ſay that Mrs. Bragwell's anger was not owing to the undutifulneſs of the daughter, or the worthleſſneſs of the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; poverty was in her eyes the grand crime. The doctrine of forgiveneſs, a a religious principle, made no more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part of Mr. Bragwell's ſyſtem than of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> wife's, but in natural feeling, particular<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for this offending daughter, he much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded her.</p>
            <p>In a few months, the youngeſt Miſs Bragwell deſired leave to return home from Mr. Worthy's. She had, indeed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> only conſented to go thither as a leſs ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the two than ſtaying in her father'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> houſe after her ſiſter's elopement. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the ſobriety and ſimplicity of Mr. Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy's family were irkſome to her. Habit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of vanity and idleneſs were become ſo rooted in her mind, that any degree of reſtraint was a burthen; and though ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="unknown:037135_0018_100C92CC460AA180"/>
was outwardly civil, it was eaſy to ſee that ſhe longed to get away. She reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, however, to profit by her ſiſter's faults; and made her parents eaſy by aſſuring them ſhe never would throw her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf away on a <hi>man who was worth nothing.</hi> Encouraged by theſe promiſes, which were all that her parents thought they could in reaſon expect, her father allow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed her to come home.</p>
            <p>Mr. Worthy, who accompanied her, found Mr. Bragwell gloomy and dejected. As his houſe was no longer a ſcene of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and feſtivity, Mr. Bragwell tried to make himſelf and his friend believe that he was grown religious; whereas he was only become diſcontented. As he had always fancied that piety was a melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly gloomy thing, and as he felt his own mind really gloomy, he was willing to think he was growing pious. He had, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, gone more conſtantly to church, and had taken leſs pleaſure in feaſting and cards, and now and then read a chapter in the Bible, but all this was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his ſpirits were low, and not becauſe his heart was changed. The outward actions were more regular, but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:037135_0019_100C92CDD34457B0"/>
man was the ſame. The forms of religion were reſorted to as a painful duty; but this only added to his miſery, while he was utterly ignorant of its ſpirit and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. He ſtill, however, reſerved religion as a loathſome medicine, to which he feared he muſt have recourſe at laſt and of which he even now conſidered every abſtinence from pleaſure, or every exerciſe of piety as a bitter doſe. His health alſo was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, ſo that his friend found him in a pitiable ſtate, neither able to receive pleaſure from the world, which he ſo dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loved, nor from religion which he ſo greatly feared. He expected to have been much commended by Worthy for the change in his way of life; but Worthy, who ſaw that the alteration was only ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the loſs of animal ſpirits, and to the caſual abſence of temptation, was cautious of flattering him too much. "I thought, Mr. Worthy," ſaid he, "to have received more comfort from you. I was told too, that religion was full of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but I do not find much in it." You were told the truth, replied Worthy, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is full of comfort, but you muſt firſt be brought into a ſtate fit to receive it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it can become ſo; you muſt be brought
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:037135_0020_100C92CF6E3B6F18"/>
to a deep and humbling ſenſe of ſin. To give you comfort while you are puffed up with high thoughts of yourſelf, would be to give you a ſtrong cordial in a high fever. Religion keeps back her cordials till the patient is lowered and emptied; emptied of ſelf, Mr. Bragwell. If you had a wound, it muſt be examined and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, aye, and probed too, before it would be ſafe to put on a healing plaiſter. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it to the outward eye, while it was corrupt at bottom, would only bring on a mortification, and you would be a dead man while you truſted that the plaiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was curing you. You muſt be, indeed, a Chriſtian, before you can be entitled to the comforts of Chriſtianity.—I am a Chriſtian, ſaid Bragwell, many of my friends are Chriſtians, but I do not ſee it has done us much good.—Chriſtianity itſelf, anſwered Worthy, cannot make us good unleſs it be applied to our hearts. Chriſtian privileges will not make us Chriſtians unleſs we make uſe of them. On that ſhelf I ſee ſtands your medicine. The doctor orders you to take it. "<hi>Have</hi> you taken it?"—Yes, replied Bragwell. Are you the better for it? ſaid Worthy. —I think I am, he replied.—But, added
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:037135_0021_100C92D21D1DBC40"/>
Worthy, are you the better becauſe the doctor has ordered it merely, or becauſe you have alſo taken it?—What a fooliſh queſtion, cried Bragwell. Why to be ſure the doctor might be the beſt doctor, and his phyſic the beſt phyſic in the world; but if it ſtood forever on the ſhelf, I could not expect to be cured by it. My doctor is not a mountebank. He does not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to cure by a charm. The phyſic is good, and as it ſuits my caſe, though it is bitter, I take it.—You have now, ſaid Worthy, explained undeſignedly the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why Religion does ſo little good in the world. It is not a mountebank; it does not work by a charm; but offers to cure your worſt corruptions by wholeſome, though ſometimes bitter preſcriptions. But you will not take them; you will not apply to God with the ſame earneſt deſire to be healed with which you apply to your doctor; you will not confeſs your ſins to the one as honeſtly as you tell your ſymptoms to the other, nor read your Bible with the ſame faith and ſubmiſſion with which you take your medicine. In reading it, however, you muſt take care not to apply to yourſelf the comforts which are not ſuited to your caſe. You muſt, by
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:037135_0022_100C92D40BA268A8"/>
the grace of God, be brought into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to be entitled to the promiſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you can expect the comfort of them. Conviction is not converſion; that world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcontent which is the effect of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſappointment, is not that <hi>godly sorrow which worketh repentance.</hi> Beſides, while you have been purſuing all the gratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the world, do not complain that you have not all the comforts of Religion too. Could you live in the full enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of both, <hi>the Bible would not be true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bragwell now ſeemed reſolved to ſet about the matter in earneſt, but he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in his own ſtrength; and, unluckily, the very day Mr. Worthy took leave, there happened to be a grand ball at the next town, on account of the aſſizes. An aſſize-ball is a ſcene to which gentleman and ladies periodically reſort to celebrate the crimes and calamities of their fellow-creatures by dancing and muſic, and to divert themſelves with feaſting and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, while unhappy wretches are receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſentence of death.</p>
            <p>To this ball Miſs Bragwell went, dreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out with a double portion of finery,
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:037135_0023_100C92D5978FB530"/>
pouring out on her own head the whole band-box of feathers and flowers her ſiſter had left behind her. While ſhe was at the ball her father formed many plans of religious reformation; he talked of leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſening his buſineſs, that he might have more leiſure for devotion; though not <hi>just now,</hi> while the markets were ſo high; and then he began to think of ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a handſome ſubſcription to the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary; though, on ſecond thoughts, he concluded he need not be <hi>in a hurry,</hi> but leave it in his will, but to give, and repent, and reform, were three things he was bent upon. But when his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter came home at night, ſo happy and ſo fine, and telling how ſhe had danced with Squire Squeeze the great corn contractor, and how many fine things he had ſaid to her, Mr. Bragwell felt the old ſpirit of the world return in its full force. A mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with Mr. Daſhall Squeeze, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractor, was beyond his hopes, for Mr. Squeeze was ſuppoſed from a very low beginning to have got rich during the war. As for Mr. Squeeze he had picked up as much of the hiſtory of his partner between the dances as he deſired, he was convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced there would be no money wanting, for Miſs Bragwell, who was now looked
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:037135_0024_100C92D7C4DA4B58"/>
on as an only child, muſt needs be a great fortune, and he was too much uſed to advantageous contracts to let this ſlip. As he was gaudily dreſſed, and poſſeſſed all the arts of vulgar flattery, Miſs Bragwell eagerly caught at his propoſal to wait on her father next day. Squeeze was quite a man after Bragwell's own heart, a geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us at getting money, a fine daſhing fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low at ſpending it. He told his wife that this was the very ſort of man for his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for he got money like a Jew and ſpent it like a prince; but whether it was fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly got, or wiſely ſpent, he was too much a man of the world to inquire. Mrs. Bragwell was not ſo run away with by appearances, but ſhe deſired her huſband to be careful and quite ſure that it was the right Mr. Squeeze, and no impoſtor. But being aſſured that Betſey would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly keep her carriage, ſhe never gave herſelf one thought with what ſort of a man ſhe was to ride in it. To have one of her daughters drive in her own coach, filled up all her ideas of human happineſs. The marriage was celebrated with great ſplendor, and Mr. and Mrs. Squeeze ſet off for London, where they had a houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="unknown:037135_0025_100C92D9AF25B3C0"/>Mr. Bragwell now tried to forget that he had any other daughter, and if ſome thoughts of the reſolutions he had made of entering on a more religious courſe would ſometimes force themſelves upon him, they were put off, like the repentance of Felix, <hi>to a more convenient season,</hi> and finding he was likely to have a grandchild, he became more worldly and ambitious than ever, thinking this a juſt pretence for adding houſe to houſe, and field to field; and there is no ſtratagem by which men more deceive themſelves than when they make even unborn children a pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence for that rapine, or that hoarding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which their own covetouſneſs is the true motive. Whenever he ventured to write to Mr. Worthy about the Wealth, the gaiety, and the grandeur of Mr. and Mrs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Squeeze, that faithful friend honeſtly re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minded him of the vanity and uncertaint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of worldly greatneſs, and the error h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had been guilty of in marrying his daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter before he had taken time to inquir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into the real character of the man, ſayin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that he could not help foreboding, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the happineſs of a match made at a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> might have an end. Notwithſtandin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mr. Bragwell had paid down a la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="unknown:037135_0026_100C92DBF705B568"/>
fortune than was prudent, for fear Mr. Squeeze ſhould fly of, yet he was ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to receive very ſoon a preſſing letter from him, deſiring him to advance a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſum, as he had the offer of an advantageous purchaſe, which he muſt loſe for want of money. Bragwell was ſtaggered, and refuſed to comply; but his wife told him he muſt not be ſhabby to ſuch a gentleman as Squire Squeeze, for that ſhe heard on all ſides ſuch accounts of their grandeur, their feaſts, their carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, and their liveries, that ſhe and her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſband ought even to deny themſelves comforts to oblige ſuch a generous ſon, who did all this in honour of their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; beſides, if he did not ſend the money ſoon, they might be obliged to lay down their coach, and then ſhe ſhould never be able to ſhew her face again. At length Mr. Bragwell lent him the money on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is bond: he knew Squeeze's income <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as large, for he had carefully enquired <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto this particular, and for the reſt he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ook his word. Mrs. Squeeze alſo got <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat preſents from her mother, by repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enting to her how expenſively they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orced to live to keep up their credit and
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:037135_0027_100C92DD87B20050"/>
what honour ſhe was confering on the family of the Bragwell's by ſpending their money in ſuch grand company. Among many other letters ſhe wrote her the following:—
<floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <head>"To Mrs. Bragwell.</head>
                     <p>"You can't imagine, dear mother, how charmingly we live—I lye a-bed almoſt all day, and am up all night; but it is never dark for all that, for we burn ſuch numbers of candles all at once, that the ſun would be of no uſe at all in London. —Then I am ſo happy; for we are never quiet a moment, Sundays or working-days, nay, I ſhould not know which was which, only that we have moſt pleaſure on a Sunday, becauſe it is the only day in which people have nothing to do but to divert themſelves.—Then the great folks are all ſo kind, and ſo good, that they have not a bit of pride, for they will come and eat and drink, and win my money juſt as if I was their equals; and if I have got but a cold, they are ſo very unhappy that they ſend to know how I do; and though I ſuppoſe they can't reſt till the footman has told them, yet they are ſo
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:037135_0028_100C92DFAFAAF508"/>
polite, that if I have been dying they ſeem to have forgot it next time we meet, and not to know but they have ſeen me the day before. Oh! they are true friends; and for ever ſmiling, and ſo fond of one another, that they like to meet and enjoy one another's company by hundreds, and always think the more the merrier.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your dutiful daughter, BETSEY SQUEEZE."</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>The ſtyle of her letters, however, alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a few months. She owned that though things went on gayer and grander than ever, yet ſhe hardly ever ſaw her huſband, except her houſe was full of company, and cards, or dancing was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on; and that he was often ſo buſy he could not come all night, and that he always borrowed the money her mother ſent her when he was going out on this nightly buſineſs; and that the laſt time ſhe had aſked <hi>him</hi> for money, he curſed, and ſwore, and bid her apply to the old farmer and his rib who were made of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. This letter Mrs. Bragwell conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from her huſband.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="unknown:037135_0029_100C92E19ED0AC00"/>At length on ſome change in public affairs, Mr. Squeeze, who had made an overcharge of ſome thouſand pounds in one article, loſt his contract; he was found to owe a large debt to government, and his accounts muſt be made up imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately. This was impoſſible, he had not only ſpent his large income without making any proviſion for his family, but had contracted heavy debts by gaining and other vices. His creditors poured in upon him. He wrote to Bragwell to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row another ſum; but without hinting at the loſs of his contract. Theſe repeated demands made Bragwell ſo uneaſy, that inſtead of ſending him the money, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to go himſelf ſecretly to London, and judge by his own eyes how things were going on, as his mind ſtrangely miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave him. He got to Mr. Squeeze's houſe about eleven at night, and knocked gently, concluding that they muſt needs be gone to bed. But what was his aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to find the hall was full of men; he puſhed through in ſpite of them, though to his great ſurpriſe they inſiſted on know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his name. This affronted him: he refuſed, ſaying, I am not aſhamed of my name, it will paſs for thouſands in any
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:037135_0030_100C92E3EE8A0C18"/>
market in the weſt of England. Is this your London manners, not to let a man of my credit in without knowing his name indeed! What was his amazement to ſee every room as full of card-tables, and of fine gentleman and ladies as it would hold; all was ſo light, and ſo gay, and ſo feſtive, and ſo grand, that he reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf for his ſuſpicions, thought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing too good for them, and reſolved ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly to give Squeeze another five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds to help to keep up ſo much grandeur and happineſs. At length ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a footman he knew, he aſked him where were his maſter and miſtreſs, for he could not pick them out among the company; or rather his ideas were ſo confuſed with the ſplendour of the ſcene, that he did not know whether they were there or not. The man ſaid that his maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had juſt ſent for his lady up ſtairs, and he believed that he was not well. Mr. Bragwell ſaid he would go up himſelf and look for his daughter, as he could not ſpeak ſo freely to her before all that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. He went up and knocked at the chamber door, and its not being opened; made him puſh it with ſome violence. He heard a buſtling noiſe within, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:037135_0031_100C92E57AB4EE40"/>
made a fruitleſs attempt to open the door. At this the noiſe increaſed, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mr. Bragwell was ſtruck to the heart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſound of a piſtol from within. He n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> kicked ſo violently againſt the door <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it burſt open, when the firſt ſight he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> was his daughter falling to the ground in a fit, and Mr. Squeeze dying b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from a piſtol which was dropping out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his hand. Mr. Bragwell was not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly perſon whom the ſound of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had alarmed. The ſervants, the comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, all heard it, and all ran up to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſcene of horror. Thoſe who had the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the game took care to bring up th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tricks in their hands, having had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> prudence to leave the very few who c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be truſted, to watch the ſtakes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe who had a proſpect of loſing, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fited by the confuſion and threw up, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cards. All was diſmay and terror. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ran for a ſurgeon, others examin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dying man, while ſome remove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Squeeze to her bed, while poor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> could neither ſee nor hear, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thing. One of the company took <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> letter which lay open upon the tabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dreſſed to him, they read it, hoping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> might explain the horrid myſtery. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was as follows:
<floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="32" facs="unknown:037135_0032_100C832E8EC41EF0"/>
                     <head>"To Mr. Bragwell.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>"SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>"Fetch home your daughter, I have ruined her, myſelf, and the child, to which ſhe every hour expects to be a mother. I have loſt my contract. My debts are immenſe. You refuſe me mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>y: I muſt die then; but I will die like man of ſpirit. They wait to take me to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, I have two executions in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>; but I have ten card tables in it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> die as I have lived. I invited all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> company, and have drank hard ſince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to get primed for the dreadful deed. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> refuſes to write to you for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>r thouſand, and ſhe muſt take the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>uence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Vanity</hi> has been my ruin. It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s cauſed all my crimes. Whoever is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ved to live beyond his income is lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> every ſin. He can never ſay to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> thus far ſhalt thou go and no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Vanity led me to commit acts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>, that I might live in ſplendor; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> makes me commit ſelf-murder, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>uſe I will not live in poverty. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> philoſophy ſays, that death is an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> ſleep; but the new philoſophy lies.
<pb n="33" facs="unknown:037135_0033_100C92E996CDD848"/>
Do you take heed: It is too late for me. The dreadful gulph yawns to ſwallow me —I plunge into perdition. There is no repentance in the grave, no hope in hell.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your's DASHALL SQUEEZE."</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>The dead body was removed, and Mr. Bragwell remaining almoſt without ſpeech, or motion, the company began to think of retiring, much out of humour at having their party ſo diſagreeably broken up; they comforted themſelves, however, that as it were <hi>so early,</hi> for it was now ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly twelve, they could finiſh their evening at another party or two; ſo completely do habits of <hi>pleasure,</hi> as it is called, harden the heart, and ſteel it not only againſt virtuous impreſſions, but againſt natural feelings. Now it was, that thoſe who had nightly rioted at the expence of thoſe wretched people were the firſt to abuſe them. Not an offer of aſſiſtance was made to this poor forlorn woman; not a word of kindneſs or of pity, nothing but cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was now heard. Why muſt thoſe upſtarts ape people of quality? though as
<pb n="34" facs="unknown:037135_0034_100C92EC19FB17B0"/>
long as theſe upſtarts could feaſt them, their vulgarity and their bad character had never been produced againſt them. "As long as thou doſt well unto thyſelf, men ſhall ſpeak good of thee." One gueſt who, unluckily, had no other houſe to go to, coolly ſaid, as he walked off, —Squeeze might as well have put off ſhooting himſelf till the morning. It was monſtrous provoking that he could not wait an hour or two.</p>
            <p>As every thing in the houſe was ſeized, Mr. Bragwell prevailed on his miſerable daughter, weak as ſhe was, next morning to ſet out with him for the country. His acquaintance with polite life was ſhort, but he had ſeen a great deal in a little time. They had a ſlow and a ſad jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. In about a week, Mrs. Squeeze lay-in of a dead child, ſhe herſelf languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a few days and then died; and the afflicted parents ſaw the two darling ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of their ambition, for whoſe ſakes they had made <hi>too much haste to be rich,</hi> carried to the land where all things are forgotten. Mrs. Bragwell's grief, like her other paſſions was extravagant; and poor Bragwell's ſorrow was rendered ſo
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:037135_0035_100C92EDA54F1DF0"/>
bitter by ſelf-reproach, that he would quite have ſunk under it, had he not thought of his old expedient in diſtreſs, that of ſending for Mr. Worthy to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him. It was Mr. Worthy's way, to warn people of thoſe misfortunes which he ſaw their faults muſt needs bring on them, but not to reproach, or deſert them when the misfortunes came. He had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been near Bragwell, during the ſhort, but flouriſhing reign of the Squeezes; for he knew that proſperity made the ears deaf, and the heart hard to good counſel; but as ſoon as he heard his friend was in trouble he ſet out to go to him. Bragwell burſt into a violent fit of tears when he ſaw him, and when he could ſpeak, ſaid, This trial is more than I can bear. Mr. Worthy kindly took him by the hand, and when he was a little compoſed, ſaid, I will tell you a ſhort ſtory. There was in ancient times a famous man who was a ſlave. His maſter, who was very good to him, one day gave him a bitter melon, and bade him eat it; he eat it up without one word of complaint. How was it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſaid the maſter, for you to eat ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nauſeous and diſagreeable a fruit? The ſlave replied, My good maſter, I have
<pb n="36" facs="unknown:037135_0036_100C92EF489A06C0"/>
received ſo many favours from your boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that it is no wonder if I ſhould once in my life eat one bitter melon from your hands. This generous anſwer ſo ſtruck the maſter, that the hiſtory, ſays he, gave him his liberty. With ſuch ſubmiſſive ſentiments, my friend, ſhould man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his portion of ſufferings from God, from whom he receives ſo many bleſſings. You in particular have received <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch good at the hand of God, ſhall not you receive evil alſo?</p>
            <trailer>TO BE CONTINUED.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
