<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse, on the dignity and excellence of the human character; illustrated in the life of General George Washington, late commander of the armies, and president of the United States. In commemoration of the afflictive event of his death. Delivered February 22, 1800, in the Benevolent Congregational Church in Providence; and published by request of that society. / By Enos Hitchcock, D.D. member of the Society of the Cincinnati. ; [Two lines of quotations]</title>
            <author>Hitchcock, Enos, 1745-1803.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N28227</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N28227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 37627</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX3429</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">37627</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99020197</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 37627.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N28227)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 37627)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 37627)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse, on the dignity and excellence of the human character; illustrated in the life of General George Washington, late commander of the armies, and president of the United States. In commemoration of the afflictive event of his death. Delivered February 22, 1800, in the Benevolent Congregational Church in Providence; and published by request of that society. / By Enos Hitchcock, D.D. member of the Society of the Cincinnati. ; [Two lines of quotations]</title>
                  <author>Hitchcock, Enos, 1745-1803.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35, [1] p. ;  24 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Carter, Jun.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Providence: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1800.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Dr. Hitchcock's discourse, on the death of General Washington.</note>
                  <note>Appendix, p. [33]-35.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Washington, George, 1732-1799 --  Death and burial.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>AEL Data (Chennai)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Alexis Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="unknown:037627_0000_100EEECA7894E8B8"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:037627_0001_100EEECC556A0E40"/>
            <p>DR. HITCHCOCK's DISCOURSE, ON THE DEATH OF General Waſhington.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:037627_0002_100EEECE2B6037B0"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE, ON THE DIGNITY AND EXCELLENCE OF THE HUMAN CHARACTER; <hi>ILLUSTRATED</hi> IN THE LIFE OF <hi>General George Waſhington,</hi> LATE COMMANDER OF THE ARMIES, AND PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.</p>
            <p>IN <hi>Commemoration</hi> OF THE AFFLICTIVE EVENT OF HIS DEATH.</p>
            <p>DELIVERED FEBRUARY 22, 1800, IN THE BENEVOLENT CONGREGATIONAL CHURCH IN PROVIDENCE; And Publiſhed by Requeſt of that Society.</p>
            <p>BY ENOS HITCHCOCK, D. D. <hi>MEMBER OF THE SOCIETY OF THE CINCINNATI.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>"Know ye not that there is a Prince and a great Man fallen this day in Iſrael?" <bibl>DAVID.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>"Moſes died; and the children of Iſrael wept for Moſes thirty days." <bibl>DEUTERONOMY.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>PROVIDENCE:</hi> PRINTED BY JOHN CARTER, JUN.</p>
            <p>1800.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="unknown:037627_0003_100EEED019B4B810"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2d SAMUEL, i. 19 and 27.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>THE BEAUTY OF ISRAEL IS SLAIN UPON THY HIGH PLACES: HOW ARE THE MIGHTY FALLEN!</p>
                  <p>HOW ARE THE MIGHTY FALLEN, AND THE WEAPONS OF WAR PERISHED!</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE natal day of the FATHER OF HIS COUNTRY has once more occurred; but it no longer brings with it the wonted joy and feſtivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſeaſon. The harps are hung upon the weeping willows; the cheerful ſong converted into a ſolemn dirge. Death, by a ſudden and awful ſtroke, has deprived our nation of its beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and glory, and the world of its greateſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament. Prompted by our own feelings, and a conviction of duty,<note n="‡" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (A) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> we delayed not to lament the eventful criſis of human frailty, by ſuitable tokens and expreſſions of ſenſibility and ſorrow. Our temples were ſhrouded in black, and our pulpits were vocal in his praiſe. Our nation this day aſſembles, in obedience to the procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:037627_0004_100EEED1F91C6450"/>
of his com-patriot, our illuſtrious Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, to pay, in uniſon, the laſt public office of mournful reſpect to the memory of the man ſhe delighted to honour. In Iſrael thirty days of inceſſant mourning were ſolemnly paſſed on the death of Moſes, their lawgiver and leader; and we are told, that in Rome, badges of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were worn<note n="§" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (B) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> a whole year after the death of ſome of their favourite chieftains. The event we have this day aſſembled to deplore is not merely a death—it is the departure of a WASH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>INGTON! The tear of affection and gratitude ſpontaneouſly flows. The involuntary ſigh heaves the patriot breaſt, and pours the full tide of grief at the urn of its father and friend: and in ſuch grief there is a luxury unknown to fordid minds.</p>
            <p>PATRIOTISM mourns the loſs of her firſt-born ſon. Our country laments the loſs of ſo much amiableneſs of diſpoſition and character—of ſo much might and valour, which gave ſtrength and ſtability to the ſtate. But let us not loſe in unavailing ſorrow the rational and moral im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement to be derived from ſo afflictive a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of Divine Providence.</p>
            <p>To this end I have placed David at the head of this diſcourſe, bewailing the fall of Saul and Jonathan.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="unknown:037627_0005_100EEED3889451D0"/>
IT will not be neceſſary to enquire into the connected narrative of tranſactions which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the event he ſo deeply laments, and in ſuch pathetic language calls on the people to memorize. "The beauty of Iſrael is ſlain; how are the mighty fallen!" and dwelling on the amiableneſs of the one, and the valour of the other, he exclaims again and again, "How are the mighty fallen, and the weapons of war periſhed!" The terms, "beauty" and "mighty," may be conſidered as expreſſing the native good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of diſpoſition, and the amiable virtues of the life; great natural energy of mind; a genius ready at acquiring knowledge, and at diſcerning the fitteſt application of it; a ſpirit bold, active and enterprizing; a mind capable of great and benevolent conceptions; a character formed by noble exertions and heroic deeds. To lament fallen greatneſs is but a natural expreſſion of ſympathy at beholding the ſplendid ruins of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man nature in her moſt ennobled ſons; it is a dictate of philanthropy, conſidering the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of ſuch characters to the happineſs of ſociety.</p>
            <p>A FEW thoughts on the true dignity and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence of character will lead us to a juſt eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of its great worth and importance, and to an improved view of the preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="unknown:037627_0006_100EEED5626B5EF0"/>
THE power and influence which characters, formed on the baſis of real worth and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, give the poſſeſſors over the community; the virtue and order which their example ſheds through ſociety; the defence and protection which their exertions afford the ſtate, render them pre-eminent bleſſings to the world, and make them the juſt objects of eſteem and vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration while living, and of ſincere regret, but of grateful memory, when the Supreme Ruler of the world ſees fit to take them out of it. On the theatre of this world there is a field opened wide and extenſive for the exerciſe of genius, and the exertion of all the powers of man, either in the cabinet of national councils, or in the field of national defence; in the advancement of ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and the arts, or in the improvements of civilized and ſecular life; beſides the diſcharge of the more private offices of friendſhip, and of domeſtic obligation.</p>
            <p>As to the public and extenſive ſervices to which men, formed by nature to high elevation of character, are called for the good of their country, we know, and the world knows, their great importance and uſefulneſs. Government, in the preſent ſtate of things, is neceſſary to the exiſtence of ſociety; and military ſkill and prow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs, with "weapons of war," are requiſite for
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:037627_0007_100EEED81A47D438"/>
the eſtabliſhment of civil rights, and defence of civil order. How happy that country, whoſe deſtinies, requiring the wiſdom of patriotic poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and the energy of the intrepid warrior, gives birth to the paragon in whom both completely center! Highly as the circling ſpheres bleſs the natural world, by the regular operation of their eſtabliſhed laws, does the union of theſe qualities reflect their bleſſings on the political ſyſtem. It conſtitutes "the beauty" of our country, on ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of native excellence; and "the mighty," on account of pre-eminence of character among the great.</p>
            <p>CIVIL inſtitutions run parallel to the formation of ſociety. Neither a ſenſe of religion, nor a perception of moral obligation, has been found ſufficiently powerful in any age, to preſerve un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſturbed peace at home; much leſs to check the encroaching ſpirit of ambition or avarice from abroad. Hence ariſes the neceſſity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraines from civil law, to curb the licentious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and unprincipled; and of military force for defence. Hence alſo the neceſſity of great political and military talents, adapted to meet the exigencies of the times. Nor has Divine Providence been unmindful of this. But in every age it has raiſed up thoſe whoſe abilities enabled them to be emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently uſeful in their day. Moſt oppreſſed na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:037627_0008_100EEED9DA4E2950"/>
have been favoured with ſome patriotic de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer. In Iſrael a Moſes was raiſed up to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver, and a Joſhua to lead the people; in Rome a Camillus; in Greece a Leonidas; in Sweden a Guſtavus; and in England a Hampden, a Ruſſel, a Sydney. Theſe were ſucceſsful in preſerving and defending the ſtate. But who of them, like a WASHINGTON, formed and eſtabliſhed an empire?</p>
            <p>THE dignity of the human character does not conſiſt merely in the poſſeſſion or exertion of great talents.</p>
            <p>IT is not the adventitious circumſtance of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil diſtinction, military honours, or opulent conditions, that gives a title to it. There are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, not a few, of commanding genius, of vaſt mental reſource, and of great and brilliant deeds, all ſtained with the moſt peſtiferous crimes: a heart black as midnight darkneſs, with a head luminous as the midday ſun. Deeds that would do honour to the greateſt, and actions that would diſgrace the meaneſt of men, ſometimes conſtitute the mixed ſhades of the ſame character. Can ſuch an unhallowed mixture conſtitute dignity or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence of character? Surely not. We may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the hero, but we deſpiſe the man.</p>
            <p>TRUE worth and greatneſs of character is formed by the union of the head and heart act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:037627_0009_100EEEDC216FC0E0"/>
in concert; in upright principles, directing the judgment and controuling the ſtrong arm of power; in the fear of God, ever guiding to a due regard to man. Actuated by theſe principles, the character will not be ſtained by the aſpirings of unhallowed ambition; but will gather beauty and luſtre from opportunities for great and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent actions; and the more the motives of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are examined, the more cloſely the character is ſcanned, the fairer will they appear.</p>
            <p>THE providence of God calls ſome men to act in high ſtations, and the circumſtances of the public require all their energies, either to form or adminiſter government, or defend the ſtate. Theſe are like a city placed on a hill. The light of their example, or the blackneſs of their charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, becomes conſpicuous in proportion to their elevation; and every private ſtation becomes a poſt of honour, when honourably filled. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of example are great in a private ſtation—more ſo in the domeſtic ſtate. How important then the duty, and how great the bleſſings reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on ſociety, by the good and virtuous example of thoſe who are rendered eminent by high ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the atchievement of glorious deeds! Such ſervices are peculiarly graced, and derive ſupreme worth from that excellence of character which perfumes the moſt amiable, and adds luſtre to the moſt illuſtrious. Not ſo much could the
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:037627_0010_100EEEDE6C680EA8"/>
d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Vernon'</hi>s fertile mount, deſcending on "the elevated lawn,"<note n="§" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (C) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> enrich the plains below; not ſo much could the clear ſhining after rain refreſh the tender graſs, as this moral excellence of character bleſs the land, by extending its influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from north to ſouth.</p>
            <p>WE are here reminded of a circumſtance that damps the uſual joys of this day.</p>
            <p>"THE beauty of Iſrael is ſlain; how are the mighty fallen!" No character ſo good, no man ſo great, but he muſt fall by the hand of death. Proſtrate in the duſt all human glory muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid. Deſcended from the ſame original ſtock, all mankind are deſtined to the ſame end. The ſentence of—"<hi>Duſt to duſt</hi>"—is univerſal upon our race. In this warfare there is no diſcharge; in the grave no diſtinction. In the repoſitory of the dead we behold a mixed multitude, of all ages, conditions and characters; the aged and the young, the rich and the poor, the hero and the coward, the public magiſtrate and the private citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, the pious chriſtian and the impious offender, who have promiſcuouſly fallen before all-conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing death. Such are the ravages death is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly making upon our race!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="unknown:037627_0011_100EEEE024250D40"/>
THE truth of theſe obſervations is verified in the afflicting inſtance of the fall of the glory, ſtrength and boaſt of our country.</p>
            <p>YES, the <hi>princely</hi> ſoul of our beloved WASH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>INGTON has taken its flight! He is no longer diſturbed by the concuſſions of our jarring ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The heavens open wide their huge por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals to receive his pure and ennobled ſpirit; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels hail him welcome to his native ſeat; the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe temple of God becomes the place of his reſidence forever. He has ceaſed from his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, but his works will long live. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription on the lofty marble will for a long time inform the inquiſitive traveller—<hi>Here lies the venerable chief</hi>—"<hi>Firſt in war, firſt in peace, and firſt in the hearts of his countrymen.</hi>" The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numental inſcription ſhall mouldering time ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face; but his heroic and benevolent deeds are recorded on the tablet of the heart. While man lives, they will live; ſo long as virtue has a name, they will be admired. Yea, his juſtly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired fame ſhall ſurvive the wreck of nature; and wreaths of glory crown his head, when time ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p>THE hiſtorian will attempt a diſplay of his virtues by a detail of his great tranſactions; the poet will celebrate his name in poliſhed and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monic periods; he will aſſemble the worthies of
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:037627_0012_100ED3966F8F1450"/>
ancient and modern times, and by all the arts of playful imagination faintly pourtray a WASHING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON. The painter and the ſculptor will employ all their art to eternize his noble form, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtic mein, but can never fully expreſs the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ractereſtic virtues which were enthroned on his brow. The eulogiſt will rack his invention to beſtow merited panegyric on a character whoſe depth it cannot fathom—language will refuſe her aid, and eulogy itſelf grow faint upon his tongue.</p>
            <p>BUT to record his virtues in our hearts, and tranſmit his name, with veneration, to your children, is the claim of gratitude; and by raiſing a ſpirit of emulation, may be uſeful.</p>
            <p>EVERY thing reſpecting this illuſtrious man is now become important. The very name of WASHINGTON is dear to us. The higheſt eulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium we could poſſibly beſtow, would be a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect account of his life and tranſactions. Here again we muſt fail, and ſatisfy ourſelves with a few of the outlines of a portrait which, if filled up with plain facts, would preſent it in a tranſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent attitude.—General WASHINGTON was born of reſpectable parents, in Virginia, on the twenty-ſecond day of February, one thouſand ſeven hundred and thirty-two. His education was not in the academic forums; but his native powers,
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:037627_0013_100EEEE4F1F15AC8"/>
improved by cloſe application under a private tutor, ſoon gave him a reſpectable ſtation among the arts and ſciences; and univerſities of the firſt rank in Europe and America have long deemed it an honour to have his name enrolled in their liſt of literary titles. Indeed, his letters and other compoſitions, both political and military, afford the beſt comment on his literary acquirements. He appears to have early imbibed the principles of religion. That he was nurtured in the habits of virtue, appears from their attending him through all the public and private walks of life. He never loſt the reſpect of the ſon,<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (D) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> in the eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the commander in chief. Nor did patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otiſm diminiſh his connubial and domeſtic affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Amiable in the diſcharge of theſe duties, he never for a moment loſt ſight of thoſe ties that conferred the obligation upon him.</p>
            <p>EARLY habits of a virtuous tendency, an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquaintance with the principles of religion, and the exerciſes of piety, form the ſtrongeſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers againſt vice in youth. They lay the ſureſt foundation for honour and uſefulneſs in life, reſpect in age, and comfort in death. A life com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced with ſuch principles and habits, a youth of ſuch ſobriety, fidelity and filial reſpect, indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates a character to be diſtinguiſhed afterwards by worthy deeds; a career of glory, ſupported and adorned by moral excellence, which ſhall
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:037627_0014_100EEEE678C658F8"/>
end in an age of tranquility and comfort. In this inſtance we are not diſappointed. We behold the happy cloſe of a life, which had been render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed glorious by the union of virtue and talents, ſhining with undiminiſhed luſtre. In whom has the virtue of the youth, the magnanimity of the ſoldier, the pure zeal of the patriot and the chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, ever appeared with ſo much grace and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as in him to whom we this day wiſh to aſſign a juſt tribute of reſpect?</p>
            <p>IN a ſound body dwelt a ſounder mind; the latter improved by cloſe application in youth; the former by athletic exerciſes. His judgment, ever a prominent feature in his character, ripen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at an immature age into the able negociator;<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (E) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> and his bold and enterprizing ſpirit, features no leſs prominent, into the hardihood of the veteran ſoldier; and at the age of twenty he gained the meridian of ordinary life. The weſtern tribes of Indians, the French commander at Fort Du Queſne, and the unfortunate Britiſh army in the gorges of the Monongahela, all experienced in turn his uncommon addreſs in managing a treaty, or in covering the retreat of a ſhattered army in thoſe vaſt wilds, ere twenty-five years had rolled over him. Already had the government of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia committed high betruſtments to him. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready had he given ſtrong proofs of his piety<note n="‡" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (F) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> as
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:037627_0015_100EEEE8755244C0"/>
well as of his patriotiſm and valour. He conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to juſtify their confidence, and they to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their full ſenſe of it. Thus honoured in his own country; thus eſteemed among kindred ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, how clear his title to that honour and eſteem! What then muſt have been their regret, when his health, impaired by the rigour of ſervice and ſevere fatigue, rendered it neceſſary for him to retire from the ſervice, in ſeventeen hundred fifty-nine?</p>
            <p>FROM this time to the year ſeventy-five, we may perhaps moſt properly view him as the American farmer, though employed in various public offices, beſides a ſeat in the Legiſlature. Situated on the ſummit of the very high ground called <hi>Mount-Vernon,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (G) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> he converts that beautiful ſpot into a prolific garden, variegated into a moſt enchanting ſcenery. The arts of peace are leſs ſplendid, but more uſeful than thoſe of war. By agricultural arts and improvements he rendered an extenſive plantation a ſource of wealth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and of inſtruction to others. This favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite ſpot now became more dear than ever, by a happy connubial union with the amiable and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed Mrs. CUSTIS, the aſſiduous ſharer of all his future anxieties, as well as partner of his joys. Domeſtic and agricultural concerns
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:037627_0016_100EEEEACF509010"/>
now unite their friendly beams to ſpeed his way in thoſe delightful purſuits.</p>
            <p>IN ſeventy-four, we find him among the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled worthies and patriots at Philadelphia. The portentous cloud hangs over the land—it is fraught with ire. Soon does the lightening ſlaſh from beneath the dark curdling carr that bears death and deſtruction to all hopes of reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with a parent country. Already poſſeſſed of the metropolis of Maſſachuſetts, they iſſue forth, and on the ever-memorable nineteenth of April, ſeventy-five, Lexington and Concord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the malancholy viſage of ſlaughtered citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens. With eagerneſs our patriotic yeomanry ruſh to the encrimſoned field. But what is a hoſt without a head? Whither, O whither ſhall we turn, to find a leader whoſe powers ſhall juſtify the hope of ſucceſsful reſiſtance? Behold, in the midſt of our patriot band one appears—
<q>"<hi>Toto vertice ſupereſt.</hi>"</q>
               <q>"A whole head above the reſt."</q>
            </p>
            <p>IT is a WASHINGTON! He is unanimouſly elected <hi>Commander in Chief of the armies to be raiſed for the defence of the country.</hi> "It is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps his peculiar glory, that there was not a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle inhabitant of theſe States, except himſelf, who did not approve the choice, and place the firmeſt
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:037627_0017_100EEEECE9CB7680"/>
confidence in his integrity and abilities." But his native modeſty induced him to expreſs deep apprehenſions of his inability to perform the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentous duties which ſuch a truſt devolved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. Obedient to his country's call, he evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the motives of his acceptance to be neither mercenary nor vain, by declining any compenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for perſonal ſervices.</p>
            <p>BIDDING adieu to his compatriots in the great council of the nation, he betakes himſelf to the field, where his abilities are more needed. The reſpectful gratulations of all claſſes<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (H) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> of people, as he paſſed the country; the joy and exultation of the army on his arrival at Cambridge, in July, are evincive of the inſtinctive confidence which his name inſpired. How well qualified he was to take the command of an undiſciplined, unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided army, to reduce them to order, and to withſtand as large and well appointed an army as perhaps was ever ſent out of Europe, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by able and experienced officers, the event has proved. His unimpeached conduct during an eight years war, attended with the moſt trying circumſtances, is an eulogium that can receive no addition, unleſs it be from the uniform and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible attachment of the officers and ſoldiers of his army to his perſon during that period.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="unknown:037627_0018_100EEEEE720EAAB0"/>
THOUGH not verſed in the art military, like his foes, yet they were ſoon taught to reſpect his judgment and fear his power; and what was wanting in force, was ſupplied by policy. His unwearied induſtry, his uncommon method and exactneſs, which gained him the reſpect and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of his own army, rendered him formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to that of his enemies. His ſilent, but eaſy manner of doing buſineſs; his reſerve, void of all haughty ſuperciliouſneſs; his quick diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of every character, and of every ſubject that was preſented to him; his firm and undevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting purpoſe, executed with moderation and humanity, qualified him in the beſt manner for the command of a republican army. How often the above qualities were uſefully diſplayed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſtruggle for freedom, and how much the country is indebted for them, is beſt known to thoſe veterans to whom he often expreſſed his thanks for their eſſential ſervices, becauſe they had the moſt opportunity of obſerving them.</p>
            <p>BESIDES the great and heroic actions that came to public view, thoſe worthy ſons who followed their leader will recollect many of the innumerable virtues of the heart which tranſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the more private tranſactions. They will teſtify to the kind, humane and affectionate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct he always obſerved towards the army;
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:037627_0019_100EEEF07884CBB8"/>
how careful to cheriſh life, where an impoſing policy did not abſolutely require the contrary. They will never forget the deep impreſſion which theſe qualities made on them; while the <hi>irreſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble majeſty</hi> of his preſence<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (I) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> quelled the riotous, and reduced the refractory to order. His coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try's cauſe is now all his own. Never for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did he flinch from danger, or attempt to ſhield himſelf from being a conſpicuous mark for his foes, though expoſed to the ten thouſand inviſible meſſengers of death, from the ſavage am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh which routed one Britiſh army on the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nongahela, to the capture of another at York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town. Amidſt all theſe, and from the aſſaſſin's dagger,<note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (K) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> Divine Providence remarkably preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, till its high purpoſes were accompliſhed in him. On his arrival at Cambridge, he found that the zeal of the country, and not its ſtrength in arms or amunition, held the city beſieged. He applies immediately to organizing the army, and providing military ſtores. Heaven ſmiles.<note n="‡" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (L) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> He ſucceeds in both. An anxious public ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect an aſſault upon Boſton, and grow impatient for the time. But to conquer by delay, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel by circumſcribing his enemies, is a more hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and a ſafer policy. They leave their poſt the enſuing March, to ſeek ſome more favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpot for offenſive operations. New-York is ſelected for the purpoſe. Here again they meet
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:037627_0020_100EEEF285B3BF50"/>
a WASHINGTON with his army. The place is not tenable. A ſcene now opens that brings to the ſevereſt teſt all the feelings of the man, and all the reſources of the general. Succeſs is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally accounted wiſdom, and the ſplendor of character is ſought in the ſucceſsful enterprizes of the warrior. But perhaps we ſhould find the moſt ſplendid rays of General WASHINGTON'S glory beaming from beneath the dark and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful clouds of defeat, misfortune and diſtreſs; at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the ſhattered remains of a retreating army, and unſupported by an inefficient govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. We know not which moſt to admire, his caution or his intrepidity, his moderation or his firmneſs, his penetration in judgment or his promptneſs in deciſion, his patience in ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or his unextinguiſhable zeal and perſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in the cauſe of freedom, through years of deep anxiety, and of unparelleled trials and diſappointments.</p>
            <p>THE ſubject is now too complex to be ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyzed into particulars in a ſingle diſcourſe. Thoſe of you who were then on the ſtage, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the deep ſhades that overſpread the country; and thoſe of you who accompanied him in his hair-breadth eſcapes from Long-Iſland, York-Iſland and its environs, with the loſs of Fort-Waſhington and its garriſon, Fort-Lee and
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:037627_0021_100EEEF40F485A80"/>
its dependencies; in his retreat through the Jer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, purſued like a hunted hare by a large and victorious army, while his own was conſtantly leſſening by loſſes in action, by ſickneſs, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration of enliſtments, and the country too far depreſſed to ſupport him.—Thoſe can beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the true dignity of his invincible ſoul. We are now to view him on the weſtern margin of the Delaware, looking back with indignant eye to his purſuers, at reſt in Trenton. The inhabitants of the country deſponding, ſay, "all is now loſt." But his heroic ſpirit never deſpairs. Oppreſſed with the weight of a ſinking empire, the attic fire of his breaſt enkindles afreſh. He collects his little hardy band, deſtitute of every comfort; the ſame fire flies through the ranks. They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to follow their leader to victory or to death. In vain does the rolling torrent hurry on the maſſy ſheets of ice upon its turbulent bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom; in vain the ſleety tempeſt from the frozen north, adding new horrors to the darkneſs of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember's night, oppoſe the well concerted plan. Ere the morning ſun had enlightened our hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, twelve hundred aſtoniſhed Heſſians yielded to his conquering arms. The main body of the enemy at Princeton, leaving about five hundred, move on with haſty march to retrieve the loſt. The Delaware in his rear, a powerful army fraught with vindictive rage in front, impoſed a
<pb n="24" facs="unknown:037627_0022_100EEEF6CBC7CEE0"/>
woeful dilemma. But he who could inſpire the daring hardihood to reſiſt the force of oppoſing elements, knew how to evade their graſp, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate his faithful adherents from the fatal ſtroke. The ſucceeding night, leaving deceptive fires to lull the enemy, a circuitous rout of ſeventeen miles preſented them in their rear at Princeton. A MERCER nobly dies in the conteſt. A WASH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>INGTON placed himſelf on middle ground be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the conflicting bodies, a mark for both. His example inſpired a general ardour. They ruſh on, and another victory enſues. An inſtant policy covers the handful of invincibles, who had performed ſuch wonders, on the heights of Morriſtown, marking their way thither with blood, for lack of ſhoes: and an army of eight thouſand men are cooped up in New-Brunſwick during the winter, by the ſkeleton of his own.</p>
            <p>AGAIN, committing themſelves to the boſom of the ſwelling ocean, they attempt to elude the penetration of our Argus with his hundred eyes; but in vain. Soon does he meet them at the Head of Elk. Nor does the unfortunate and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal rout of his army on the Brandywine, the vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious diſappointment at Germantown, the loſs of Redbank and Mud-Iſland, after a moſt gallant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; the diſtreſſing failure of ſupplies of men, proviſions and cloathing, nor the faction raiſing its
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:037627_0023_100EEEF88CCA9110"/>
ſerpent head in Congreſs to diſplace him, nor the imbecility of their reſolutions, ſhake the firm purpoſe of his energetic ſoul. With an army ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted by fatigue, reduced by repeated actions, epidemic diſeaſe, and more dreadful ſufferings, he huts them, in the month of December, in a foreſt at Valley-Forge, about twenty miles from Philadelphia, whither the whole Britiſh army had retired for more comfortable winter quarters. The diſtreſſes of the army at this cantonment<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (M) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> had well nigh ſunk his manly, his compaſſionate ſoul. We caſt a mantle over this diſtreſſing ſcene, as too painful for reflection.</p>
            <p>SIR HENRY CLINTON left Philadelphia on the June following; our hero purſued by a circuitous march of near one hundred and fifty miles, and overtook him on the burning plains of Monmouth. A ſevere battle enſued, and his victorious arms obliged him to fly and ſeek ſhelter in New-York. Such was the perilous ſtate of the army, ſo defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in numbers and ſupplies, and Congreſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that their reſolutions did not contain en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ergy ſufficient to draw them forth from the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that they entruſted their faithful General with the power of doing it himſelf. "Maturely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the criſis, and having perfect reliance in his wiſdom, vigour and uprightneſs," they inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with powers bordering on Dictatorſhip,
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:037627_0024_100EEEFA18157F30"/>
on the 27th of December, 1776; and ſimilar reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions were paſſed the two following years. This high betruſtment of power was never abuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but was ever uſed for the beſt purpoſes for which it was given. Such was the confidence of his country in him! Such his integrity in the uſe of it!</p>
            <p>DURING the above gloomy period, when the boldeſt heart needed ſupport from ſome quarter, it was oppreſſed by the reiterated defeats in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nada, with the loſs of Generals MONTGOMERY and THOMAS; the deſtruction of a fleet on Lake Champlain; the poſſeſſion of Rhode-Iſland by the enemy; the evacuation of Ticonderoga, and the wanton devaſtations of VAUGHAN, on the North-River. Preſſed by the fortuitous concuſſion of events on every ſide, he ſends General GATES to retrieve the northern department. He ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, and BURGOYNE with his army ſurrenders. He projects, with indefatigable attention, an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack on Stoney-Point, which, with Verplank's-Point, had yielded to the enemy: the deep laid plan ſucceeds, and the garriſon laid down their arms. General LINCOLN is ſent to protect Charleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, but ſurrenders to a beſieging army vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuperior to his own. He ſends General GREENE to retrieve the diſaſter at Cambden, who performs wonders in the South; and at length goes himſelf for Virginia, leaving the remainder of his army at White-Plains, with ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:037627_0025_100EEEFC46E0B248"/>
as to cover his intentions from the enemy. The capture of Lord CORNWALLIS and his army cloſed the military operations, and peace enſued.</p>
            <p>THE time for diſbanding the army arrived—and now arrived the mighty trial of patriotic vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Talk not of a Caeſar! He was brave, but would have enſlaved his country. Say not that an Alexander conquered from Macedonia to Egypt! He never conquered himſelf. He delug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed countries in blood, but ſaved none; and wept becauſe his ambition was not yet ſatiated with conqueſt.—It is left for a WASHINGTON to give the nobleſt example of virtue, of religion,<note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (N) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> of greatneſs. He conquered for his country. He triumphed in their affections, and at their feet he laid his hard-earned laurels. Like the illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Roman, Lucius Quintus Cincinnatus, he <q>laid-down, in peace, arms aſſumed for public defence.</q>
            </p>
            <p>NOR were the energies of his talents leſs fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to our ſituation in peace, than to our exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies in war: and this ſingular adaptation of talents to circumſtances, proved an eminent bleſſing to the United States.</p>
            <p>THE Hero and Deliverer of his country, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſtored to it that tranquility which he ſo much loved himſelf, returns to enjoy it with a
<pb n="28" facs="unknown:037627_0026_100EEEFE651C55F0"/>
greater reliſh on his own domain. He is every where received with a tribute of applauſe; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heart beats high with admiration, and every tongue is vocal in his praiſe. The peaceful ſhades of domeſtic life were now doubly wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to him. In the cultivation of the earth, and various uſeful improvements, he made rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>id progreſs. Happy would he have been, if the calls of the public had ſuffered the remainder of his days to glide away in this repoſe. But when the preſſure of common danger was at an end, the weakneſs of the federal government was more fully perceived. The rare phaenome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of a political revolution is now to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed by deliberative aſſembly. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the States for framing a new conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of government, place their late Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in Chief in the chair of ſtate. His known and tried patriotiſm, and his eminent ſervices to his country, gave weight to his opinion in their deliberations, and contributed in no ſmall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to the formation and adoption of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable ſyſtem of federal government we now enjoy, and greatly promoted the tranquility and the energy of its operation.</p>
            <p>TWICE called by the unanimous voice of his country to adminiſter the government he had been ſo eſſential an agent in eſtabliſhing, he ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the high ſtation of <hi>Preſident of the United
<pb n="29" facs="unknown:037627_0027_100EEEFFED5CBB60"/>
States,</hi> with unbounded applauſe, during eight years. The conſciouſneſs of his own integrity, like a brazen helmet, warded off the ſhafts of envy; and he remained ſtedfaſt in purſuit of an enlightened and pacific policy,<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (O) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> amidſt the ſurges of diſcontented faction and foreign influence, like a huge rock in the ocean, unmoved by the daſhing of its raging billows. Having ſerved the public forty-five years, and nature claiming repoſe, he expreſſes his earneſt wiſh to retire from public life, in an addreſs, which ought to form the political creed of every ſon and daughter of the land. Americans! how venerable this Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlator, Leader and Commander appears, in this valedictory addreſs, can be perceived only by reading it <hi>again and again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT his repoſe is not long to remain undiſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The will of his country is his own will; her exigencies impoſe an obligation upon him, which he cannot reſiſt. He obeys her call, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the threatening proſpects of war from abroad, and greatly accepts the appointment of Lieuten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant-General of the forces to be raiſed for ſuch emergencies. Happily, no ſuch event has arriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But the morning lowrs, and rapidly brings on the important period that is to terminate his glorious career—Ah me! WASHINGTON is no more! On the 14th of December laſt, he met
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:037627_0028_100EEF022794B890"/>
death with the ſame fortitude that had marked his life, in the ſixty-eighth year of his age.</p>
            <p>MY RESPECTED FRIENDS OF THE CINCINNATI,</p>
            <p>To theſe imperfect lineaments of the character of the illuſtrious man who led you to victory, to glory and freedom, your knowledge can add many more. Often have you braved the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the field, and the hardſhips of the camp, in obedience to his command. Your obedience was always cheerful, becauſe impoſed by duty and affection. Your dangers and ſufferings were always ameliorated by the example of your Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eral voluntarily ſharing them with you. You, Gentlemen, have a double ſhare in the common affliction occaſioned by his death. He was your <hi>beloved commander in Chief.</hi> He was your <hi>vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Preſident-General.</hi> The beſt evidence of your profound reſpect for his memory, and your beſt improvement of this mournful occaſion, will be to preſerve in your minds his amiable and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent virtues as a model for conduct in peace, as you did his example of fortitude in war. May your life, like his, be virtuous; and may its end, like his, be triumphant and happy.</p>
            <p>MY LITTLE CHILDREN, AND YOUNG FRIENDS,</p>
            <p>THOUGH you may never have ſeen the perſon of our beloved WASHINGTON, yet you have often heard his name, and of the good he has
<pb n="31" facs="unknown:037627_0029_100EEF0449395400"/>
done; and you are now enjoying the fruit of his labours, in the opportunity you enjoy for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See note (P) in the Appendix.</hi>
               </note> He was once young, as you now are; and when young he was diligent in learning, and amiable in conduct; and when old he reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the fruits of ſober youth. He was beloved by all; he was virtuous; he was happy. We ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erate his memory now he is gone, becauſe he was as good as he was great. Let his name be ever dear to you, and never ſpeak, never think of him but with gratitude, reſpect and affection.</p>
            <p>MY FRIENDS AND AFFLICTED FELLOW-CITIZENS,</p>
            <p>THIS day has brought with it freſh teſtimonies of our loſs—a nation in tears! It opens new ſources of grief, by preſenting the millions of his ſons aſſembled around the hearſe, to take the laſt look of their parent, to pay one more tribute of reſpect, to drop another tear of gratitude and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for their departed WASHINGTON.</p>
            <p>WHILE we deplore an event that has deprived our country of its greateſt ornament, and of its beſt "weapon of war," let us offer up our moſt unfeigned thanks to the Supreme Diſpoſer of all events, for the continuance of ſo diſtinguiſhed a bleſſing to us for ſo long a time; and that he would be pleaſed to afford divine conſolation and ſupport to his mourning relict. While we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="32" facs="unknown:037627_0030_100EEF05D22D7910"/>
his virtues, let us profit by them; and as we ſee the higheſt and the loweſt, the wiſeſt and the weakeſt of our race, falling with equal fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell ravager of mankind, let us paſs our time uſefully and profitably, that we may leave the favour of a good example behind, and that the morn of eternal day may beam un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clouded upon us.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="unknown:037627_0031_100EEF076FAB7DC0"/>
            <head>APPENDIX.</head>
            <div n="a" type="endnote">
               <head>(A) Page 5. "We delayed not to lament the eventful criſis."</head>
               <p>ON the 23d of December, the afflicting news of General WASHINGTON's death reached this town. The author of the foregoing diſcourſe would have deemed himſelf deficient in duty and in patriotiſm, in omitting the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt opportunity to pay his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſmall tribute of reſpect to the memory of ſo much worth; which he attempted, in an appropriate diſcourſe, on the following ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath; a copy of which was requeſted for the preſs; but the publication was omitted on account of the appointment of the 22d of February for commem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orating that event through the United States. The pulpit, the communion-table and the orcheſtre, ſhrouded with black; the cypreſs bows and feſtoons over the chancel and the Venetian window, and around the columns and the urns, and the emblematical mourning piece in front of the deſk, ſhewed the prompt feelings of the congregation on the occaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="b" type="endnote">
               <head>(B) Page 6. "In Rome, badges of mourning."</head>
               <p>It is related, that on the death of CINCINNATUS, the ladies of Rome wore the cypreſs twelve months; and alſo for BRUTUS the younger.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="c" type="endnote">
               <head>(C) Page 12. "The elevated lawn."</head>
               <p>At the bottom of the elevated lawn, on the banks of the Potomack, is placed the family vault, where the mortal remains of our great WASHING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON were depoſited.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="d" type="endnote">
               <head>(D) Page 15. "He never loſt the reſpect of the ſon."</head>
               <p>Hearing of the dangerous illneſs of his mother, in the ſpring of eighty-ſeven, he immediately repaired to her, and left her not till ſhe expired. His aſſidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and reſpectful attentions, which were the reſult of ſentiment and habit, were ſpoken of much to his honour. He came from her interment to Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the convention for forming the preſent conſtitution, where the author ſaw the lines of ſorrow that deeply marked his countenance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="e" type="endnote">
               <head>(E) Page 16. "The able negociator."</head>
               <p>About the age of 21, he was ſent by the governor of Virginia to treat with the Six Nations and other weſtern Indians, at the diſtance of 400 miles, in the dead of winter, through a pathleſs wilderneſs, inhabited only by ſavages; and to remonſtrate to the French commander on the Ohio againſt their encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. This enterprize he performed on foot, with his proviſion on his back. For the judicious and able management of this buſineſs, he received the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and thanks of his employers; and two years afterwards, he performed that great military exploit of reſcuing the ſhattered remains of General BRAD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOCK's army from the horrid jaws of a ſavage ambuſcade, of the danger of which he had notified that unfortunate General. Though a very conſpicuous mark for the ſavage markſmen, he only received a ball through his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oat.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="f" type="endnote">
               <head>(F) Page 16. "Strong proofs of his piety."</head>
               <p>Though his inviting the <abbr>Rev.</abbr> Mr. DAVIS to perform religious ſervice, and deliver a diſcourſe to the body of men he had the command of as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#AELD" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="unknown:037627_0032_100EEF0959E34DD8"/>
the age of about 22, on a very important expedition, was no certain evidence of piety in itſelf, yet all his other conduct, both in the public and private walks of life, correſponding thereto, affords a ſtrong proof of it; and that gentleman, who permitted the above diſcourſe to be publiſhed, has the following remarkable note, dictated, no doubt, by the remarkable military talents he had already diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered:—"This young man," meaning Major WASHINGTON, "will one day be the ſaviour of his country."</p>
            </div>
            <div n="g" type="endnote">
               <head>(G) Page 17. "Called Mount-Vernon."</head>
               <p>This high and commanding ground, ſituated a few miles below Alexandria, on the Potomack, is called Mount-Vernon, in honour of Admiral Vernon. The area of this beautiful mount is about 200 feet above the ſurface of that richly flowing river; and furniſhing a lawn of about five acres in front, and about the ſame quantity in the rear of his buildings, falls off abruptly on both thoſe quarters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="h" type="endnote">
               <head>(H) Page 19. "The reſpectful gratulations of."</head>
               <p>As though inſpired by one ſoul, all hailed him welcome on the way; public entertainments were made to receive him at every ſtage; and the Maſſachu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetts Convention, then ſitting at Watertown, ſent a large deputation of reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able characters to Springfield, to receive and eſcort him to Cambridge, where he was received with inexpreſſible joy, and where he ſoon gave a new face to things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="i" type="endnote">
               <head>(I) Page 21. "The irreſiſtible majeſty of his preſence."</head>
               <p>Among many other inſtances of the commanding influence of his preſence, and energy of his reproofs, a very noticeable one was at Proſpect-Hill, where a body of riflemen became mutinous. Theſe men had then lately arrived from his own country, which probably increaſed his indignation at their baſe conduct. He rode into the midſt of them, and by the energy of his addreſs quelled and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them to order.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="k" type="endnote">
               <head>(K) Page 21. "And from the aſſaſſin's dagger."</head>
               <p>Among many other dangers out of which he was remarkably delivered, a timely diſcovery was made in New-York, in 1776, of a deſign formed againſt his life, by corrupting one of his own guard.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="l" type="endnote">
               <head>(L) Page 21. "Heaven ſmiles."</head>
               <p>By throwing into our hands the ammunition and military ſtores ſent to ſupply the enemy, which we ſo much needed at that time, and were not in our power to command.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="m" type="endnote">
               <head>(M) Page 25. "The diſtreſſes of the army at this canton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, had well nigh ſunk."</head>
               <p>General WASHINGTON took this poſition in a foreſt, at Valley-Forge, about the 24th of December, 1777, the ſnow being about half-leg deep, with very few axes to build their huts with. This cantonment General HOWE called, by way of ridicule, "the Indian-Town." It was ſufficient, however, to keep him qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et within his own lines, in Philadelphia, though the army was in an extreme ſtate of ſuffering, for want of proviſion and cloathing. So great were their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes, that General WASHINGTON perhaps never felt deeper anxiety than on their account. Being on a viſit at head-quarters, he enquired with great ſolicitude how the ſoldiery fared, and how they ſupported their ſufferings; and when told,
<pb n="35" facs="unknown:037627_0033_100EEF0AE51151A0"/>
"with patience and fortitude," he exclaimed, the tears ſtarting from his eyes, "<hi>what will not theſe brave men endure for the good of their country!</hi>"</p>
            </div>
            <div n="n" type="endnote">
               <head>(N) Page 27. "Example of virtue, of religion."</head>
               <p>In proof of this, many things might be adduced. The frugality and econo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of a table ſupplied by the public; the order, ſobriety and moderation ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved at it, are evincive of virtuous habits, and of the influence of his preſence in reſtraining profanity, intemperance and licentiouſneſs; for theſe never pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted the ſocial repaſt, nor offended the chaſteſt ear. His religious example ſhone in uniformly acknowledging an overruling Providence, aſcribing all his ſucceſſes to that, and in calling on the army "to aſſemble at their reſpective parades, to offer up their unfeigned thanks to Almighty God, for the ſucceſs he had granted them;" beſides his attendance at public worſhip on the ſabbath, whenever the ſtate of the army permitted, with great apparent devotion. To the above may be added, his frequently calling on the officers and ſoldiers, in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral orders, to avoid vice and profanity. Of the many inſtances of this, the two following are offered:</p>
               <div type="extract">
                  <head>EXTRACT from GENERAL ORDERS, May 2d, 1778.</head>
                  <p>"While we are performing the duty of good citizens and ſoldiers, we ought not to be inattentive to the higher duties of religion. To the diſtinguiſhed char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acter of a patriot, it ſhould be our higheſt glory to add the more diſtinguiſhed character of a <hi>chriſtian."</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="extract">
                  <head>EXTRACT from GENERAL ORDERS, July 29th, 1779.</head>
                  <p>"Many and pointed orders have been iſſued againſt that unmeaning and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable cuſtom of ſwearing; notwithſtanding which, with much regret, the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eral obſerves it prevails, if <hi>poſſible,</hi> more than ever; his feelings are continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wounded by the oaths and imprecations of the ſoldiers, whenever he is in hearing of them. The name of that Being, from whoſe bountiful goodneſs we are permitted to exiſt, and enjoy the comforts of life, is conſtantly imprecated and profaned, in a manner as wanton as it is ſhocking. For the ſake, therefore, of religion, decency and order, the General hopes and truſts that officers of every rank will uſe their influence and authority to check a vice which is as unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as it is wicked and ſhameful."</p>
                  <p>He was a ſtranger to religious prejudices, not from an indifference to religion itſelf, but from a conviction of the benevolent deſigns of that ſcheme of religion, which taught him to live and act as a chriſtian, poſſeſſing the feelings of a man, and not of a party. He was educated in the outward profeſſion of the Epiſcopal Church; but his candour towards all religious denominations was manifeſted on all occaſions. His anſwer to the addreſs of the Jews at Newport, will remain a laſting monument of this—"And it is the glory of the United States, that, with the ſtar of empire, fixed therein is the brighter ſun of univerſal toleration."</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="o" type="endnote">
               <head>(O) Page 29. "An enlightened and pacific policy."</head>
               <p>The Preſident of the United States roſe with ſuperior grace when he nobly ſtood forth the independent aſſertor of their independence, and took a neutral poſition among the nations at war. Convinced that juſtice and humanity requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, no apprehenſion of perſonal ſacrifice could ſhake his fixed purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="p" type="endnote">
               <head>(P) Page 31. "The opportunity you enjoy for inſtruction."</head>
               <p>To any one who was preſent, and ſaw the intereſting and affecting exhibition of 180 young maſters and miſſes, with appropriate dreſſes, emblematical of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and of mourning, no apology is neceſſary for this addreſs. Nor will it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear improper to any who conſider the importance of the riſing generation; or the advantages they enjoy from the freedom of their country, through its deceaſed patron.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
