<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nature and importance of Christian worship; considered in a sermon, preached, July 4th, 1800, at the dedication of the new meeting house in the southwest part of Charlton. Erected by a number of inhabitants, belonging to Charlton, Sturbridge and Dudley. / By Erastus Learned, A.M. Pastor of the Congregational Church in Charlton. ; Published by particular request.</title>
            <author>Learned, Erastus, 1775-1824.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N28357</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N28357</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 37789</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW5143</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">37789</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99011231</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 37789.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N28357)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 37789)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 37789)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nature and importance of Christian worship; considered in a sermon, preached, July 4th, 1800, at the dedication of the new meeting house in the southwest part of Charlton. Erected by a number of inhabitants, belonging to Charlton, Sturbridge and Dudley. / By Erastus Learned, A.M. Pastor of the Congregational Church in Charlton. ; Published by particular request.</title>
                  <author>Learned, Erastus, 1775-1824.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>21, [1] p. ;  24 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Isaiah Thomas, Jun.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Worcester [Mass.], :</pubPlace>
                  <date>August--1800.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Second Congregational Church (Charlton, Mass.).</term>
               <term>Worship.</term>
               <term>Dedication sermons --  1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>AEL Data (Chennai)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:037789_0000_100F2794CC6AD928"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:037789_0001_100F51430A195B90"/>
            <p>THE <hi>NATURE</hi> AND <hi>IMPORTANCE</hi> OF CHRISTIAN WORSHIP; CONSIDERED IN A SERMON, PREACHED, JULY 4th, 1800, <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the DEDICATION of the NEW MEETING HOUSE in the Southweſt part of <hi>Charlton.</hi> Erected by a number of<hi> INHABITANTS, </hi>belonging to<hi> CHARLTON, STURBRIDGE </hi>and<hi> DUDLEY.</hi> BY ERASTUS LEARNED, A. M. Paſtor of the Congregational Church in CHARLTON. <hi>Publiſhed by particular Requeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PRINTED AT WORCESTER, BY ISAIAH THOMAS, JUN. <hi>Auguſt</hi>—1800.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="unknown:037789_0002_100F514675E07330"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CONSIDERING the very ſhort time the Author had for preparing the following Diſcourſe, he relies on the candor of thoſe who may read it, to excuſe its imperfections. That it may ſerve to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate the</hi> Nature, <hi>and enforce the</hi> Importance <hi>of Chriſtian Worſhip—eſpecially among thoſe, at whoſe particular requeſt it was delivered and is now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed: And that they may long enjoy unity and peace in</hi> maintaining <hi>Chriſtian Worſhip, in the Houſe they have erected, and dedicated to that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, is the ſincere wiſh of the</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>AUTHOR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="unknown:037789_0003_100F5148D240B6D8"/>
            <head>A DEDICATORY SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>JOHN IV. 23.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in ſpirit and in truth; for the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>TO worſhip God is a <hi>duty,</hi> that hath been generally acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by mankind; and, in all ages and countries, there have been inſtitutions of religion. It is a <hi>duty</hi> enjoined by <hi>reaſon,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced by <hi>divine revelation.</hi> Even thoſe, who were favored with no written revelation of the will of God, might <hi>clearly</hi> ſee, <hi>by the viſible things which were made, his eternal power and godhead,</hi> and be left <hi>without excuſe,</hi> if they neglected to worſhip and adore him. And frequently are we called upon, in the Scriptures, to attend to this important duty. The Pſalmiſt exhorts; <hi>O come, let us worſhip and bow down, let us kneel before the Lord our Maker, for he is our God.</hi> Our Saviour has ſaid; <hi>thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God.</hi> And the Apoſtles have taught us, both by precept and example, <hi>Not to forſake the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:037789_0004_100F512403670478"/>
of ourſelves together,</hi> for divine worſhip, <hi>as the manner of ſome is.</hi> But, notwithſtanding mankind have been in all ages, generally agreed, in conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divine worſhip as an important duty, it is to be lamented that religious inſtitutions have, at the ſame time, been ſo generally abuſed. A ſmall acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the hiſtory of mankind, will ſhew us, that great indeed have been the miſchiefs of miſtaken zeal; of zeal contending, not only about <hi>doctrines,</hi> but <hi>places</hi> and <hi>modes</hi> of religious worſhip. Religious inſtitutions, which were deſigned to promote <hi>love to God, peace on earth,</hi> and <hi>good will to men,</hi> have been perverted, by ſuperſtition and enthuſiaſm, to the purpoſes of diſcord, and bloody perſecution. Our bleſſed Saviour, knowing what was in man, ſeems, in the paſſage here cited from the Goſpel, to have intended totally to prevent theſe evils, by plainly declaring, that neither particular <hi>place</hi> nor <hi>mode</hi> of worſhip, ſhould be of any intrinſic value under the chriſtian diſpenſation; that the local and peculiar worſhip of Judaiſm was to give way to a worſhip of a more exalted nature; that the <hi>hour was now come, when the true worſhippers ſhould worſhip the Father, in ſpirit and in truth:</hi> Not with the painful rites and ceremonies required by the law, which were only <hi>ſhadows of things to come;</hi> but with that more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime and ſpiritual worſhip which ſhould ſuit the genius of Chriſtianity; <hi>for the Father,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The text, conſidered in its connexion, diſcovers to us, not only the <hi>nature</hi> of Chriſtian worſhip, but alſo the <hi>reaſon</hi> of God's various dealings with the children of men; that, "while he ſits enthroned in the glories of unchangeable wiſdom, he condeſcends to the weakneſs of his creatures, and adapts his laws to their various ſituations and capacity."</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="unknown:037789_0005_100F514C90FF74A8"/>
"At the time of the migration of the Jews from Egypt," ſays a learned Divine,<note n="*" place="bottom">See Family Lectures, Vol. II, Serm, LXXXII.</note> "the whole world was ſunk into idolatry. They alone were bleſſed with the knowledge of the true God: Yet even they were perpetually relapſing into the abſurdities of idol worſhip. Hence that load of peculiar ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies was impoſed on them; all tending, by various means, to one great end; that of keeping them pure from idolatry, of ſeparating them from the worſhip of the Pagan nations that ſurrounded them, and of confirming them in that of the true God. To this end, the temple was built and the worſhip eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Jeruſalem. Hither the whole nation was obliged to reſort at ſtated times, to prevent their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe into idolatry. The Samaritans were a ſect, who had divided from the Jews, and for the ſame ends had built a temple on Mount Gerizim, where they likewiſe periodically performed the ceremonies enjoined by the law. Theſe ceremonies, and this ſeparation of the Jews from the Gentiles, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by Providence to be continued till the coming of Chriſt. But now a glorious change was to take place. The world was, by this time, prepared, by higher degrees of knowledge, for the reception of the Goſpel. This was the hour appointed, for the Sun of Righteouſneſs to ariſe, for his light to be ſpread over the face of the whole earth. Every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and ceremony was now to be done away that tended to keep up the former ſeparation; nothing was to be eſtabliſhed, but what tended to the general union of mankind; and the peculiar, the local and periodical worſhip of Jeruſalem, was to be ſwallowed up in that more ſpiritual diſpenſation, which was deſigned to produce univerſal peace and charity."</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="unknown:037789_0006_100F5126DE49B920"/>
This being the deſign of Providence, in its various diſpenſations, we may only attend to the <hi>occaſion</hi> that introduced the words of our text, in order to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover at once its meaning and propriety.</p>
            <p>As our Saviour journeyed from Judea to Galilee, he paſſed through Samaria. Being fatigued with his journey, he ſat down by a well and ſent his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples into the city to procure ſome proviſions for their refreſhment. While they were gone, there came a Samaritan woman to draw water. Our Saviour ſaith unto her, <hi>woman, give me to drink.</hi> Knowing him to be a Jew, by his dreſs, or dialect, ſhe was much ſurpriſed at his requeſt. She thinks it ſtrange that he did not manifeſt the ſame obſtinate temper towards the Samaritans that the Jews had conſtantly done. She wonders that he ſhould condeſcend to aſk this kindneſs of her; for it was the pride of the Jews, "that they would endure any hardſhip and ſuffering, rather than be beholden to a Samaritan." <hi>How is it,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>that thou, being a Jew, aſketh drink of me, which am a woman of Samaria; for the Jews have no dealings with the Samaritans.</hi> Their diſcourſe being thus introduced, our Lord improves the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to inſtruct her in ſpiritual and divine things. He acquaints her of the water of life, that grace of God, which refreſhes the thirſty ſoul and prepares it for eternal felicity. He opens to her memory many of the ſcenes of her paſt life, and convinced her that he was a <hi>Prophet,</hi> or one that was endued with extraordinary communications from the Divine Being. Anxious for further inſtruction, ſhe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly improves the opportunity to inquire concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that diſpute which had ſo long kept up the moſt bitter enmity between the Jews and the Samaritans. <hi>Our fathers,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>worſhipped in this mountain; and ye ſay,</hi> i. e. the Jews ſay, <hi>that in Jeruſalem is the place where
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:037789_0007_100F514E189D6FF8"/>
men ought to worſhip.</hi> It was agreed between the Jews and Samaritans, that <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ought to be worſhipped ſome where, and that <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>gious worſhip was a matter of very great importance. But the ſubject of vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance was, <hi>where,</hi> i. e. in what particular place they ſhould worſhip God. Jeſus ſaith unto her, <hi>woman, believe me, the hour cometh, when ye ſhall neither in this mountain, nor yet at Jeruſalem worſhip the Father:—But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers ſhall worſhip the Father in ſpirit and in truth; for the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Jews and Samaritans were both expecting the hour to come, when, either by ſome divine revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or ſome ſignal providence, this matter ſhould be decided, either in favor of Jeruſalem or of Mount Gerizim. But how differently was it decided from the expectations of either party! The <hi>object</hi> of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is indeed ſtill to continue the ſame. The Jews worſhipped God under the character of a <hi>Father,</hi> and ſo did doubtleſs the Samaritans. This part is ſtill to remain. But a period is now put to all niceneſs and all differences about the place of worſhip. The diſſolution of the Jewiſh economy, and the erecting of the evangelical ſtate, "have ſet this matter at large," as one expreſſes it, ſo that it is a thing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly indifferent in what particular places men wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God. The worſhip of God is not now, under the Goſpel, appropriated to any particular place, as it was under the law; but it is required, <hi>that men pray every where, lifting up holy hands without wrath and doubting.</hi> Our reaſon teaches us to conſult de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and convenience, in the places of worſhip; but our religion gives no preference to one place above another, in reſpect of holineſs and acceptable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="unknown:037789_0008_100F5129A3F49AE8"/>
It is now required of all that worſhip God, that they worſhip him <hi>in ſpirit and in truth.</hi> A change has taken place in the nature of the worſhip. Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians worſhip God, not in the ceremonial obſervances of the Moſaic inſtitution, but in ſpiritual ordinances; conſiſting leſs in external parade, but animated and invigorated with a divine power and energy. The worſhip, which Chriſt has inſtituted, is rational and intellectual, and refined from thoſe external rites with which the worſhip of the Jews was clouded. There is alſo, under the Goſpel, a change in the temper and diſpoſition of the worſhippers. True chriſtians worſhip God <hi>in the ſpirit.</hi> They depend upon the holy ſpirit of God, for ſtrength and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, yielding their ſouls to his influences and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. They devote their own ſpirits to, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them in, the ſervice of God. They worſhip him, with ſteadineſs of mind, with pure affections, and with all the powers of their ſouls. They alſo worſhip him <hi>in truth;</hi> i. e. with ſincerity of heart; without any diſguiſe or hypocriſy. They have <hi>truth in the inward part,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt expreſſes it. They regard the <hi>power</hi> more than the <hi>form</hi> of Godlineſs; they aim at the divine glory, more than to be ſeen of men; and draw near to God with a pure heart.</p>
            <p>Several reaſons may be offered, why mankind ſhould worſhip God <hi>in ſpirit and in truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe, under the Goſpel, they only are the true worſhippers, and they only will be accepted. <hi>The Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him.</hi> This implies that ſuch worſhip is neceſſary in order to meet with the approbation of Heaven. When God comes to judge the world by Jeſus Chriſt, it will not be of any importance, <hi>where</hi> mankind have worſhipped the Father; but in what <hi>manner</hi> they have done it:—Whether they have put on the external ſanctity of
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:037789_0009_100F5150DB67BF40"/>
the hypocrite; or, whether they have worſhipped <hi>in ſpirit and in truth.</hi> Again,</p>
            <p>Our Saviour has obſerved, that <hi>God is a ſpirit,</hi> and offered that as another reaſon, why he ſhould be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped <hi>in ſpirit and in truth.</hi> The ſpirituality of the divine nature is a very good reaſon for the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of divine worſhip. If we do not worſhip God, who is a ſpirit, <hi>in ſpirit and in truth,</hi> we neither give him <hi>the glory due unto his name,</hi> nor can we rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably hope for his favor and acceptance.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee, that the words of our text were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to ſhew, that the time had already come, when men ſhould no longer confine their worſhip of God, to any particular <hi>place,</hi> nor adhere to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>mode,</hi> but ſhould <hi>worſhip the Father in ſpirit and in truth:</hi> That the whole "univerſe is his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and all ſpace his abode;" and that one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar place, in itſelf conſidered, is no more acceptable to him than another; that the ſincerity and purity of the <hi>heart</hi> is what God chiefly requires.</p>
            <p>But as, in avoiding one extreme, it hath too often been the fate of mankind to run into its oppoſite; ſo here, this declaration of our Saviour in the text, which implies only the abolition of the ceremonial law, and the eſtabliſhment of a more pure and ſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itual worſhip, has been frequently miſapprehended, as being an expreſs licence for neglecting all exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ceremonies in religion, and even all public wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. But the examples of the Apoſtles and primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive diſplay of Chriſt, are ſufficient to convince mankind, that our text was never deſigned to deſtroy all public inſtitutions of religion; but to ſhew the purity and ſpirituality of that worſhip, which, under the Goſpel, ſhould ſucceed the pompous and local worſhip of the Jews. We have not only the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the firſt chriſtians aſſembling for public wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:037789_0010_100F512E04C5FC20"/>
but we re poſitively commanded, <hi>not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the aſſembling of ourſelves together as the manner of ſome is.</hi> And indeed, while we are in our preſent imperfect ſtate, it will be found neceſſary, on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial inquiry, to attend to the public inſtitutions of religion, in order to accompliſh that great purpoſe of worſhipping God <hi>in ſpirit and in truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us then inquire into the <hi>neceſſity</hi> and <hi>uſefulneſs</hi> of public worſhip.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The public inſtitutions of religion are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; becauſe without them, mankind in general would relapſe into a ſtate of barbariſm and a total forgetfulneſs of all religion. "I believe," ſays an excellent writer,<note n="*" place="bottom">Rev. JOHN BROWN, Chaplain to the Biſhop of Carliſle.</note> "it is no breach of truth or char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity, to affirm that a great part of mankind are ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſed in buſineſs or pleaſure, that they ſeldom turn their thoughts on God, ſeldom recollect either their obligations to him, or their dependance on him, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only when they are drawn by the ſtated returns of public worſhip. Some indeed are ſo hardened that they are deaf to every call; but much greater numbers are ſwayed by the power of cuſtom, and yield to the rules of decency, when they would ſcorn thoſe of duty." Aſſembling together affords alſo opportunities for moral and religious inſtruction to thoſe who would otherwiſe receive none. "In all Proteſtant countries, the elements of natural religion, and the important parts of the evangelical hiſtory, are familiar to the loweſt of the people. This gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eral diffuſion of knowledge amongſt all orders of chriſtians, which will appear a great thing when compared with the intellectual condition of barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous nations, cannot fairly, I think, be aſcribed to any other cauſe, than the regular eſtabliſhment of
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:037789_0011_100F515293059548"/>
aſſembling for divine worſhip."<note n="*" place="bottom">See PALEY's Moral Philoſophy, Chapter IV.</note> In theſe aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, there are none perhaps, who receive not ſome temporary impreſſions of religion, which, though they work not their entire and full effect, though they be ſoon <hi>choaked</hi> by the cares and pleaſures of the world, yet keep thoſe cares and pleaſures from ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing up the ſoul in a <hi>total degeneracy.</hi> Others, perhaps, are awakened from the deluſion of ſin, to a ſenſe of the importance of piety and religion, are rouſed from their lethargy of ſoul, to liſten to the warning voice, which bids them return to the <hi>right way and walk in it.</hi> Theſe reaſons bind all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of a community to uphold public worſhip by their preſence and example.</p>
            <p>But beſides the direct neceſſity of public worſhip, in order to improve the minds and morals of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, there are other valuable advantages to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the immediate attendance on this duty.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Joining in prayer and praiſes to their common Creator, has a ſenſible tendency to unite mankind together, and to cheriſh and enlarge the generous affections. When they acknowledge themſelves ſprung from the ſame original, "preparing together for the period of all worldly diſtinctions, reminded of their mutual infirmities, and common dependen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, imploring and receiving ſupport from the ſame great ſource of power and bounty, having all one intereſt to ſecure, one Lord to ſerve, one judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſupreme object of all their hopes and fears to look towards, it is hardly poſſible, in this poſition, to behold mankind as ſtrangers or enemies, or not to regard them as children of the ſame family aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled before their common Parent, and with ſome portion of the tenderneſs that belongs to the moſt
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:037789_0012_100F5131E51CB3B0"/>
endearing of our domeſtic relations." It is not to be expected, however, that any ſingle attendance on divine worſhip ſhould produce any conſiderable or laſting effect of this kind; but the frequent return of ſuch ſentiments and feelings as are naturally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited by the preſence of a devout congregation, may ſoften many unkind paſſions, and produce in time, with the bleſſing of God, a moſt extenſive and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent benevolence.</p>
            <p>Again, "Aſſemblies for the purpoſe of divine worſhip, placing men under impreſſions, by which they are taught to conſider their relation to the Deity and to contemplate thoſe around them, with a view to that relation, force upon their thoughts the nat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ural equality of the human ſpecies, and thereby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote humility and condeſcention, in the higheſt orders of the community, and inſpire the loweſt with a ſenſe of their rights." Mankind are apt to make too great diſtinctions with reſpect to the different ſituations of men in the preſent life. Honor, wealth and power are too much the idols of the world.—But all claſſes and diſtinctions of men uniting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to worſhip and adore their common Lord and Maſter has a happy tendency to improve the charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of both high and low, and to impreſs on their minds a ſenſe of their natural equality. Ruler and ſubject, rich and poor are diſtinctions that will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue among men no longer than during the contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance of this ſhort life; and thoſe diſtinctions are almoſt loſt, when mankind are conſidered in a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the great Creator and Governor of the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. <hi>Great</hi> then muſt be the <hi>utility</hi> of public wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, being calculated to produce ſuch happy effects. But beſide theſe great effects, we muſt not forget the powerful influence of <hi>example</hi> in the public worſhip of God. By <hi>example,</hi> I mean, not only that which
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:037789_0013_100F5155A4BBAFC0"/>
excites imitation in the external acts of worſhip; but, "that <hi>ſympathy of ſoul</hi> ſo ſtrongly prevalent in human nature." The paſſions of mankind are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous. Fear, hope, grief and joy, ſhining forth in the countenance of our fellow creatures, ſtrike them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into our hearts, and awaken correſponding feelings in the ſoul. Thus the ſight of a congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſeriouſly united in worſhip, naturally inſpires additional degrees of piety and reverence.</p>
            <p>From this brief diſplay of the ſubject before us, we diſcern the <hi>neceſſity</hi> and <hi>utility</hi> of public worſhip, even in accompliſhing that great purpoſe of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God in <hi>ſpirit and in truth.</hi> And in conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the truths brought to view, in the preced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe, I ſhall now add a few obſervations adapted to the occaſion of our aſſembling together, at this time, and then cloſe. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may obſerve, that as God, under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, has required us to worſhip him in <hi>ſpirit and in truth,</hi> without confining his worſhip to any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>place</hi> or <hi>mode,</hi> we ſhould exerciſe mutual forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and charity towards all chriſtians, though they may not unite with us in the ſame <hi>place</hi> and <hi>mode</hi> of religious worſhip. As we live in a land of civil and religious liberty, all chriſtians have a right to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult their own <hi>convenience</hi> in chooſing their places for religious worſhip; and their <hi>own conſciences</hi> with regard to the mode. Though the convenience of an individual, or of a few, ought, many times, to be ſacrificed to the public good; yet when a number of chriſtians can conſult their own convenience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any injury to others, they have an undoubted <hi>right</hi> ſo to do; and this <hi>right</hi> ought to be ſecured to them by the laws of their country. And if the laws will not permit them to enjoy this right, they are forced to ſuffer, in this particular, an <hi>unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deprivation</hi> of liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="unknown:037789_0014_100F5133DB85B720"/>
Beſides: Too great an attachment to particular <hi>places</hi> and <hi>modes</hi> of worſhip has been often attended with pernicious conſequences. It has cheriſhed a ſpirit of pride and vain glory, and expelled chriſtian charity and all thoſe amiable virtues, which ought ever to reign in the human heart. Different ſects and denominations of chriſtians, who have placed their whole religion in their peculiar <hi>places</hi> and <hi>modes</hi> of worſhip, "have branded each other with the moſt odious names, and conducted towards each other with ſuch mutual hatred and uncharitableneſs, as became a reproach to the pure and holy religion they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed." Churches and ſocieties of different opinions with regard to the externals of religion; and even members of the ſame church and ſociety cannot be happy, without exerciſing mutual forbearance and charity. We are here in an imperfect ſtate, and lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to deception and error. The different capacities and different opportunities of improvement among mankind, render it impoſſible, in the preſent ſtate of things, that there ſhould be an entire uniformity of ſentiment. But I conſider one thing only as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for chriſtian charity; and that is a pure and upright heart. When the <hi>ſerious</hi> and <hi>regular</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of a man, and his attachment to <hi>divine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> evinces his conformity and obedience to God, we ought to grant him the ſame liberty which we are willing to take to ourſelves, of enjoying unmoleſted his own opinions. <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>liberality</hi> are moſt amiable virtues; but <hi>modern liberality</hi> has degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into licentiouſneſs. Many call themſelves lib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eral, becauſe they diſregard all religion themſelves, and wiſh to have others do the ſame. Such perſons are generally the moſt ſevere on the characters of others; eſpecially, of thoſe, who differ from them in their views of religion. A harſher word than
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:037789_0015_100F51572D58A480"/>
               <hi>liberal,</hi> would better deſcribe their temper and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. <hi>True liberality</hi> ſprings from a <hi>generous</hi> and <hi>benevolent</hi> ſoul; and conſiſts in treating every <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>upright</hi> man, with a ſuitable degree of tenderneſs and reſpect. We ought never to condemn a man, <hi>merely</hi> for his particular ſentiments, unleſs they are accompanied with a manifeſt contempt of religion, or a vicious life: But, when this is the caſe, when men advocate licentious <hi>principles</hi> to countenance licentious <hi>practices,</hi> it is perfectly conſiſtent with charity and liberality to conſider and treat them as enemies, both to the private and public happineſs of mankind. But where an upright <hi>conduct</hi> evinces an upright <hi>heart,</hi> charity and tenderneſs towards ſuch a character ſhould be ever kept alive in our breaſts: And when a church or ſociety is compoſed of ſuch characters, though they may not be perfectly uniform in ſentiment, yet, mere difference in opinion is no reaſonable bar againſt <hi>union</hi> and <hi>fellowſhip.</hi> Again,</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. We may here obſerve and admire the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and excellence of the chriſtian inſtitution, in not appointing its proſelytes the obſervance of any particular <hi>place</hi> or <hi>mode</hi> of worſhip. The Jews were commanded to worſhip the Father at Jeruſalem. But the time has long ſince come, when an end was to be put to all diſtinction of place. "The Jewiſh ceremonial law, being appropriated to the uſe of one people, aſſembled in one place, tending only to the purpoſe of a temporary ſeparation, had, in theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, its relative propriety and excellence. On the contrary, the chriſtian religion, being deſigned for the ſervice of all mankind, of every age and nation, hath, with equal wiſdom, left the particular places and modes of worſhip to the conſent, and various circumſtances of different times and people." So that divine worſhip, performed in different <hi>places</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:037789_0016_100F5136F4406F30"/>
under different <hi>forms,</hi> may be equally acceptable to God; if he be worſhipped by them <hi>in ſpirit and in truth.</hi> Again,</p>
            <p n="3">3dly and laſtly: We may obſerve, that the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject we have been conſidering is perfectly conſiſtent with the deſign of this day's ſolemnity. We have aſſembled at this time to ſeparate this houſe from common uſes, by a ſolemn public act, and to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate it to the public worſhip of ALMIGHTY GOD. Although one place in itſelf conſidered, is no more acceptable to God than another; and he regards the diſpoſition of the worſhippers more than any, and every thing elſe; yet we may preſume that dedicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing places deſigned for public worſhip is an accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſervice unto him. It manifeſts our reverence for God and his inſtitutions; and may procure bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings which would not otherwiſe be conferred. For though God dwelleth not in temples made with hands; though his immenſity cannot be confined within conſecrated walls, but is every where preſent to thoſe who worſhip him <hi>in ſpirit and in truth;</hi> yet, the holy ſpirit has thought fit to aſcribe to places, conſecrated to his ſolemn worſhip, the honor of his peculiar <hi>reſidence.</hi> Thus he is ſaid to have <hi>dwelt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the cherubim of the mercy feat. The temple is called his <hi>houſe,</hi> his <hi>court,</hi> the <hi>habitation</hi> of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, the place where his honor <hi>dwelt.</hi> And we find a reſpect, ſuitable to theſe high characters, paid towards the temple at Jeruſalem, by the greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of piety, and enjoined as a religious duty.</p>
            <p>Our bleſſed Lord, the Author of our holy reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, far from diſcouraging ſuch reverence, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted his concern for it, by an act of zeal the moſt extraordinary of any that appeared in his whole life. In the reproof of crimes in general he was meek and lowly. Even the blaſphemies and indignities offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:037789_0017_100F5158B71AB850"/>
to his own ſacred character, he bore without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment or complaint. But when he ſaw the houſe of prayer, his Father's houſe, profaned, his reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enkindled and broke out into a "holy tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of indignation" againſt the offenders. With a ſcourge of ſmall cords, he drove them in haſte from the temple, unwilling to ſee a houſe, dedicated to the ſervice of God, polluted by the iniquities of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And to chriſtian temples we ought to manifeſt a ſuitable degree of reverence. We cannot ſurely ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that <hi>irreverence</hi> ſhewn to the worſhip Chriſt himſelf has inſtituted ſhould be without offence to him, who was ſo highly provoked with <hi>that,</hi> ſhewn to the worſhip of the former diſpenſation. Places ſet apart for religious offices, ſhew that the <hi>honor</hi> of religion is thereby intended. They are calculated to give men an awful ſenſe of the duties they are to perform, and to put them in mind, that, as thoſe places are ſeparated from common uſes and dedicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to God, they ſhould alſo, with becoming ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, dedicate themſelves to his ſervice.</p>
            <p>Beſides: We may hope for peculiar bleſſings to follow in conſequence of this ſacred act. When Solomon dedicated the temple of Jeruſalem, <hi>the glory of the Lord filled the houſe of the Lord.</hi> And may we not hope that in conſequence of the ſame ſolemn act, God may hereafter fill this houſe with the glory of his <hi>power</hi> and <hi>grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As worſhipping God is a duty enjoined by <hi>reaſon,</hi> and enforced by <hi>divine revelation,</hi> may it be ſtrictly attended to, by all who are in connexion with this ſociety; and may they all remember, when they approach him in the duties of his ſanctuary, <hi>to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in ſpirit and in truth; for the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him.</hi> For this ſolemn duty may they always be prepared, by impreſſing on their minds,
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:037789_0018_100F5138835E6570"/>
the moſt reſpectful ideas of that infinite Being, who is the object of their addreſſes. And during their attendance on his ſervice, may they retain an awful ſenſe of his majeſty and preſence. As often as they here aſſemble to preſent themſelves before the Moſt High God, may they leave, as much as poſſible, the world and its concernments behind them, and, on the wings of holy contemplation, elevate their hearts to Heaven. And when they return from the duties of this place, now ſacred to religion, may they retain the religious impreſſions they may here receive.—May they not think themſelves retired from God; but may they hold a ſacred intercourſe with him, by an attention to him in their whole conduct; by acknowledging him in all their ways; by conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his will as their guide, his providence the object of their dependence, his favor the aim of their am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition; and by rendering him continual homage in the uniform <hi>obedience</hi> of a good life. To this <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and the happineſs conſequent upon it, may this houſe of prayer, now dedicated to God, prove hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily ſubſervient. May it be a mean, under divine providence, of uniting many in the worſhip of God, and of recommending and promoting rational piety. May the inſtructions, which may here be delivered, be a mean of reclaiming ſinners; of confirming the righteous; of elucidating the doctrines and enforcing the duties of the Chriſtian ſyſtem; and, of exhibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing religion in its native beauty and excellence, which, when free from ſuperſtition and enthuſiaſm, appears poſſeſſed of every moral excellence; the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of eſteem and veneration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To Conclude:</hi>—May that ſupreme, all propitious Being, to whoſe ſervice we now dedicate this temple, and without whoſe favor and bleſſing <hi>their labor is but loſt that built it;</hi> may he vouchſafe to favor the
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:037789_0019_100F515C99EB8368"/>
hopes of its founders; to proſper this work of their hands upon them, by ſhedding down his bleſſings, and by imparting to every worſhipper within theſe walls the effectual influences of his grace. May the ſeed of true religion, here ſown, ſpring up, and, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with the dew of heaven, be abundantly produc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the fruits of the ſpirit, of love, peace, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and every Chriſtian grace. May the beauty of holineſs appear in the conduct of all who may wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in this place. May they here be directed and find the way that leads to everlaſting life. And may this which is now ſet apart as <hi>the houſe of God</hi> be to thoſe who worſhip in it, <hi>the gate of heaven;</hi> that all who worſhip in this temple made with hands, may be admitted hereafter to that holy temple above, where God unveils his peculiar glory; there to unite with angels and the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, in celebrating the praiſes of God and the Lamb, forev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ever.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
