<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first declaration of His Highness William Henry, by the grace of God Prince of Orang. &amp;c. Of the reasons inducing him to appear in arms in the Kingdom of England, for preserving of the Protestant religion and for restoring the lawes &amp; liberties of England, Scotland, &amp; Ireland.</title>
            <author>William III, King of England, 1650-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N29474</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N29474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Shipton 39251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2332A</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX0774</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">39251</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99017402</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 39251.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N29474)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 39251)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 39251)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first declaration of His Highness William Henry, by the grace of God Prince of Orang. &amp;c. Of the reasons inducing him to appear in arms in the Kingdom of England, for preserving of the Protestant religion and for restoring the lawes &amp; liberties of England, Scotland, &amp; Ireland.</title>
                  <author>William III, King of England, 1650-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p. ;  17 cm. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B. Harrris [sic] at the London Coffee-House.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Dated Oct. 10, 1688. An additional declaration (p. 15-16) is dated Oct. 24, 1688.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  Revolution of 1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="unknown:039251_0000_1013F9DA201662D0"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:039251_0001_1013F9DC868DB430"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The <hi>FIRST</hi> DECLARATION of HIS <hi>HIGHNESS WILLIAM HENRY,</hi> By the <hi>Grace of GOD</hi> PRINCE of ORANG. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of the REASONS inducing Him to <hi>appear in Arms</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> for Preſerving of the <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> and for Reſtoring the Lawes &amp; Liberties of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is both certain and evident to all men, that the Publick Peace &amp; Happineſs of any State or Kingdom cannot be preſerved, where the Laws, Liberties, &amp; Cuſtoms eſtabliſhed by the lawful Authority in it, are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly tranſgreſſed &amp; annulled: More eſpecially where the Alteration of <hi>RELIGION</hi> is endeavoured, and that a Religion which is contrary to <hi>Law</hi> is endeavour'd to be introduced: Upon which thoſe who are moſt imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately concerned in it, are indiſpenſably bound to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to preſerve and maintain the eſtabliſh't Laws, Liberties and Cuſtomes: and above all, the <hi>Religion</hi> &amp; <hi>Worſhip of God</hi> that is eſtabliſhed among them: and to <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> an effectual ca<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that the Inhabitants of the <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tate or Kingdome, may neither be deprived of their Religi<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> nor of their Civil Rights. Which is ſo <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch the more neceſſary, becauſe the Greatneſs and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rity both of Kings, Royal Families, and of all ſuch as <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in Authourity as well as the Happineſs of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s and people, depend in a moſt eſpecial manner, upon <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>act Obſervation and maintenance of theſe their Laws Liberties and Cuſtoms.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe Grounds it is, that we cannot any longer forbear to Declare, that (to our great Regret) we <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that thoſe Councellours who have now the chief Credit with the King, have overturned the <hi>Religion,</hi> Laws, and Liberties of thoſe Realmes: and ſubjected them in all things relating to their Conſciences, Liberties and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, to Arbitrary Government: and that not only by <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; indirect waies, but in an <hi>open</hi> &amp; <hi>undiſguiſed manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="unknown:039251_0002_1013F9DFD4410B18"/>Thoſe evil Counſellours for the advancing and colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this with ſome plauſibe pretexts, did invent and ſet on foot, the Kings <hi>Diſpencing Power,</hi> by virtue of which, they pretend that according to <hi>Law,</hi> he can <hi>ſuſpend</hi> and <hi>diſpenſe</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with the execution of the Laws that have been enacted by the Authority of the King and Parliament for the Security and happineſs of the Subject, and ſo have rendred thoſe Laws of no effect: Tho there is nothing more certain, than that as no Lawes can be made but by the joint Concurrence of King &amp; Parliament, ſo likewiſe, Lawes ſo enacted, which ſecure the publick peace &amp; ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Nation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; the lives &amp; liberties of every Subject in it, cannot be repealed or ſuſpended but by the ſame Authority. For tho the King may pardon the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that a Tranſgreſſour has incurred, and to which he is <hi>condemned,</hi> as in caſes of <hi>Treaſon</hi> or <hi>Fellony</hi>; yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be with any colour of Reaſon, inferr'd from thence, that the King can entirely ſuſpend the <hi>Excution</hi> of thoſe laws relating to <hi>Treaſon</hi> or <hi>Felony:</hi> unleſs it is pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he is clothed with a <hi>deſpotick</hi> or arbitrary Power, and that the lives, liberties, honours &amp; eſtates of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects depend wholly on his good will &amp; pleaſure, and are entirely ſubject to him; which muſt infallibly follow on the King's having power to <hi>ſuſpend</hi> the <hi>Execution</hi> of the <hi>Laws,</hi> and to diſpence with them.</p>
            <p>Thoſe evil <hi>Counſellours,</hi> in order to the giving ſome Credit to this ſtrange &amp; execrable Maxime, have ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted the matter that they have obtain'd a Sentence from the Judges, declaring that this <hi>diſpenſing Power,</hi> is a <hi>Right</hi> belonging to the <hi>Crown</hi>; as if it were in the power of the twelve <hi>Judges</hi> to offer up the Laws, Rights and liberties of the whole Nation to the King, to be diſpoſed of by him arbitrarily &amp; at his pleaſure, and expreſsly contrary to Laws enacted for the ſecurity of the ſubjects. In or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Obtaining this Judgment, thoſe evil Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours did before hand examine <hi>ſecretly</hi> the Opinion of the Judges, and procured ſuch of them as could not in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>concur</hi> in ſo pernicious a Sentence, to be turned <hi>out,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="unknown:039251_0003_1013F9E1623CB988"/>
and others to be ſubſtituted in their rooms, till by the Changes which were made in the Courts of Judicature, they at laſt obtained that Judgment. And they have raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome to thoſe Truſts, who make open Profeſſion of the popiſh Religion, tho thoſe are by law rendred incapable of all ſuch Employments.</p>
            <p>It is alſo manifeſt &amp; <hi>notorious,</hi> that as his Majeſty was upon his coming to the Crown, received &amp; acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all the Subjects of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland,</hi> as their <hi>King,</hi> without the leaſt Oppoſition, tho he made then <hi>open Profeſſion</hi> of the <hi>popiſh Religion</hi>; ſo he did then <hi>promiſe</hi> &amp; ſolemnly <hi>ſwear</hi> at his <hi>Coronation,</hi> that he would maintain his Subjects in the free enjoyment of their laws &amp; liberties, and in particular, that he would maintain the <hi>Church of England as it was eſtabliſhed by Law.</hi> It is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe certain, that there have been at diverſe and ſundry times, ſeveral laws enacted for the preſervation of thoſe Rights &amp; liberties, &amp; of the proteſtant Religion: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other Securities, it has been enacted, that all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever, that are advanced to any Eccleſiaſtical Dignity, or to bear Office in either Univerſity, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all other, that ſhall be put in any Imployment, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil or Military, ſhould declare that they were not <hi>Papiſts</hi> but were of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> (and <hi>that</hi> by their ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> &amp; <hi>Supremacy</hi> and the <hi>Teſt</hi>) yet theſe evil Counſellors have in effect annulled &amp; abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed all thoſe Laws, both with relation to Eccleſiaſtical and Civil Employments. In order to Eccleſiaſtical Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and Offices, they have not only <hi>without</hi> any colour of Law, but <hi>againſt</hi> moſt <hi>expreſs</hi> Laws to the contrary, ſet up a <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> of a certain number of perſons, to whom they have committed the Cogniſance and Direction of all Eccleſiaſtical matters: in the which Commiſſion there has been &amp; ſtill <hi>is,</hi> one of his Majeſties Miniſters of ſtate, who makes now publick Profeſſion of the <hi>popiſh</hi> Religion and who, at the time of his firſt profeſſing it, declared that <hi>for a great while before, he had believed</hi> that <hi>to be the only true Religion.</hi> By all this, the deplorable ſtate to
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:039251_0004_1013F9E33921A410"/>
which the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> is reduced, is apparent, ſince the Affairs of <hi>the Church of England,</hi> are now put into the hands of Perſons who have accepted of a Commiſſion that is manifeſtly <hi>illegal,</hi> and who have executed it contrary to all Law; and that now one of their chief Members has abjured the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> and declared himſelf a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt,</hi> by which he is become incapable of holding an<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Imployment. The ſaid Commiſſioners have hitherto given ſuch proof of their Submiſſion to the directions giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them, that there is no reaſon to doubt, but they will ſtill continue to promote all ſuch deſigns as will be moſt agreable to them. And thoſe <hi>evil Counſellors</hi> take care, to raiſe none to Eccleſiaſtical Dignities, but perſons that have no Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, and that now hide their Unconcernedneſs for it under the ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Moderation.</hi> The ſaid Commiſſioners have ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> only becauſe he refuſed to obey an order, that was ſent him to ſuſpend a Worthy <hi>Divine,</hi> without ſo much as Citing him before him, to make his own Defence, or obſerving the common Forms of Proceſs. They have turned out a Preſident, choſen by the Fellows of <hi>Magdelen Colledge,</hi> and afterwards all the <hi>Fellows</hi> of that Colledge, without ſo much as Citing them before any Court that could take legal Cogniſance of that Affair, or obtaining any Sentence againſt them by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judge: and the only Reaſon that was given for turning them out, was their <hi>Refuſing to chooſe for their Preſident, a perſon that was recommended to them by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of thoſe evil Councellors</hi>: tho the Right of a <hi>Free-Election</hi> belonged undoubtedly to them. But they were turned out of their <hi>Free-holds</hi> contrary to Law, and to that expreſs proviſion in <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> that <hi>no man ſhall loſe life or goods, but by the Laws of the Land.</hi> And now theſe evil <hi>Counſellours</hi> have put the ſaid College wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> tho as is above ſaid, they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of all ſuch Imployments both by the law of the Land and the Statutes of the Colledge. Theſe Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners have alſo cited before them all the Chancellors &amp;
<pb n="5" facs="unknown:039251_0005_1013F9E5AF664318"/>
               <hi>Arch-Deacons</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> requiring them to certify to them, the names of all ſuch Clergy men as have read the Kings <hi>Declaration</hi> for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and of ſuch as have <hi>not</hi> read it: without conſidering that the Reading of it was not enjoined the Clergy by the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> who are their <hi>Ordinaries.</hi> The Illegality and Incompetency of the ſaid Court of the Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> was ſo <hi>notoriouſly</hi> known, &amp; it did ſo evidently appear, that it tended to the <hi>Subverſion</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> that the Moſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in GOD, <hi>William</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Primate &amp; Metropolitan of all <hi>England,</hi> ſeeing that it was raiſed for no other End, but to Oppreſs ſuch Perſons as were of eminent Vertue Learning and Piety, refuſed to fit or concur in it. And tho there are many expreſs Laws againſt all Churches or Chapels for the excerciſe of popiſh Religion, and alſo againſt all <hi>Monaſteries</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents,</hi> and more particularly againſt the Order of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits,</hi> yet thoſe evil Counſellors have procured Orders for the Building of ſeveral Churches and Chapel for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that Religion: they have alſo procured diverſe Monaſteries to be erected; and in contempt of the Law, they have not only ſet up ſeveral Colledges of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> in diverſe places of the Corrupting of Youth, but have raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up one of the <hi>Order</hi> to be a <hi>Privy Councellor</hi> &amp; a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of State. By all which they do evidently ſhew that they are reſtrained by no rules of Law whatſoever; but that they have ſubjected the Honours and Eſtates of the Subjects, and the <hi>Eſtabliſh't Religion</hi> to a deſpotick Power and to arbitrary Government: In all which, they are ſerved &amp; ſeconded by thoſe Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>They have alſo followed the ſame Methods with relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>civil</hi> Affairs: for they have procured Orders to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine all <hi>Lord Lieutenants, deputy Lieutenants, Sherriffs, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the peace,</hi> and all others that were in any publick Imployment, if they would concur with the King in the Repeal of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſts</hi> &amp; <hi>Penal Laws</hi>; and all ſuch, whoſe Conſciences did not ſuffer them, to comply with their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, were turn'd <hi>out,</hi> and <hi>others</hi> were put in their places,
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:039251_0006_1013F9E808BA38F0"/>
who they believed would be more compliant to them, in their deſigns of defeating the Intent &amp; Execution of thoſe laws, which had been made with ſo much <hi>care</hi> &amp; <hi>caution,</hi> for the Security of the Proteſtant Religion. And in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe places they have put <hi>profeſſed</hi> Papiſts, tho the Law has diſabled them, and warranted the Subjects not to have any regard to their Orders.</p>
            <p>They have alſo invaded the Priviledges, and ſeiſed the <hi>Charters</hi> of moſt of thoſe Towns that have a <hi>right</hi> to be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented</hi> by their <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> in Parliament; and have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured <hi>Surrender</hi> to be made of them, by which the Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates in them have deliver'd up all their Rights and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges to be diſpoſed of, at the pleaſure of thoſe Evil <hi>Counſellors,</hi> who have thereupon placed <hi>new</hi> Magiſtrates in thoſe Towns ſuch as <hi>they</hi> can moſt entirely confide in: and in <hi>many</hi> of them they have put <hi>popiſh</hi> Magiſtrates, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>incapacities</hi> under which the <hi>law</hi> has put them.</p>
            <p>And whereas no Nation whatſoever can ſubſiſt without the Adminiſtration of <hi>good</hi> &amp; <hi>impartial Juſtice,</hi> upon which mens <hi>Lives, liberties, honours,</hi> &amp; <hi>eſtates</hi> do depend; thoſe evil <hi>Counſelors</hi> have ſubjected theſe to an <hi>arbitrary</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotick</hi> power. In the moſt important affairs, they have ſtudied to diſcover before hand, the <hi>Opinions</hi> of the <hi>Judges</hi>; and have turned out ſuch, as they found would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelves to their Intentions: and have put <hi>others</hi> in their places, of whom they were more aſſured, without having any regard to their abilities. And they have not ſtuck to raiſe even profeſſed <hi>Papiſts</hi> to Courts of <hi>Judicature</hi> notwithſtanding their incapacity by law, and that no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard is due to an Sentences flowing from them. They have carried this ſo farr, as to deprive ſuch Judges, who in the common <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of Juſtice, ſhewed that they were govern'd by their <hi>conſciences,</hi> and <hi>not</hi> by the <hi>directions</hi> which others gave them: by which it is apparent that they deſign to render themſelves the abſolute Maſters of the <hi>lives, honours</hi> &amp; <hi>eſtates</hi> of the <hi>ſubjects,</hi> of what rank or Dignity ſoever they may be; and that without having any regard to the equity of the cauſe, or to the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:039251_0007_1013F9E9D6B51470"/>
the <hi>Judges,</hi> whom they will have to ſubmit in all things to their own will and pleaſure: hoping by ſuch ways to intimidate thoſe who are yet in imployment, as alſo ſuch others, as they ſhall think fit, to put in the rooms of thoſe whom they have turn'd out; and to make them ſee what they muſt <hi>look for,</hi> if they ſhould at any time, act in the leaſt contrary to their good liking: and that no failings of that kind are pardon'd in any perſons whatſoever. A great deal of <hi>blood</hi> has been ſhed in many places of the Kingdom by Judges guided by thoſe evil Counſellors, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the Rules and Forms of Law, without ſo much as ſuffering the perſons that were accuſed, to plead in their own Defence. They have alſo, by Putting the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Juſtice in the hands of Papiſts, brought all the matters of civil Juſtice into great uncertainties, with how much exactneſs and Juſtice ſoever that theſe Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may have been given. For ſince the Laws of the Land do not only exclude Papiſts from all places of Judicature, but have put them under an incapacity, none are bound to acknowledge or to obey their Judgments, and all Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences given by them, are null and void of themſelves: ſo that all perſons who have been caſt in Trials before ſuch popiſh Judges, may juſtly look on their pretended Sentences as having no more force, than the Sentences of any private &amp; unauthoriſed perſon whatſoever. So de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable is the caſe of the ſubjects who are obliged to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſuch Judges, that muſt in all things ſtick to the Rules which are ſet them by thoſe evil <hi>Counſellours,</hi> who as they <hi>raiſed</hi> them <hi>up</hi> to thoſe Imployments, ſo can <hi>turn</hi> them <hi>out of them</hi> at pleaſure; and who can <hi>never</hi> be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>lawful</hi> Judges; ſo that all their Sentences are, in the Conſtruction of the Law, of <hi>no</hi> force and efficacy. They have likewiſe diſpoſed of all <hi>Military</hi> Imployments in the ſame manner: for tho the Laws have not only excluded Papiſts from all ſuch Imployments, but have in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar provided that they ſhould be diſarmed; yet they in contempt of theſe Laws, have not only armed the Papiſts, but have likewiſe raiſed them up to the greateſt Military
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:039251_0008_1013F9EBACF82178"/>
Truſts both by Sea &amp; Land; and that <hi>ſtrangers</hi> as well as Natives, and <hi>Iriſh</hi> as well as <hi>Engliſh</hi>; that ſo by thoſe meanes, having rendred themſelves Maſters both of the affairs of the Church, of the Government of the Nation, and of the Courſe of Juſtice, and ſubjected them all to a deſpoick and arbitrary power, they might be in a Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to maintain and execute their wicked Deſigns by the Aſſiſtance of the Army, and thereby to enſlave the nation.</p>
            <p>The diſmal effects of this Subverſion of the eſtabliſhed Religion, laws and liberties in <hi>England</hi> appear more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently to us by what we ſee done in <hi>Ireland</hi>; where the <hi>whole</hi> Government is put into the hands of Papiſts, and where are the proteſtant Inhabitants are under the daily fears of what may be juſtly apprehended from the arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry power which is ſet up there, which has made great numbers of them, leave that Kingdom, and abandon their eſtates in it, remembring well that cruel and bloudy Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre, which fell out in that Iſland, in the year 1641.</p>
            <p>Thoſe evil Counſellors have alſo prevailed with the King to declare in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that he is clothed with <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Power,</hi> and that all the Subjects are bound <hi>to obey him without Reſerve</hi>: upon which he has aſſumed an arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry power both over the Religion and Laws of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, from all which, it is apparent, what is to be look't for in <hi>England,</hi> as ſoon as matters are duly prepar'd for it.</p>
            <p>Thoſe great &amp; <hi>inſufferable Oppreſſions</hi> &amp; the open <hi>Contempt</hi> of all Law, together with the Apprehenſions of the ſad Conſequences that muſt certainly follow upon it, have put the Subjects under great and juſt fears, and have made them look after ſuch lawful Remedies, as are allowed of in all Nations, yet all has been without effect. And thoſe evil Counſellors have endeavoured to make all men apprehend, the loſs of their Lives, Liberties, Honours, &amp; Eſtates, if they ſhould go about to preſerve themſelves from this oppreſſion, by <hi>Petitions, Repreſentations,</hi> or other means authouriſed by Law. Thus did they proceed with the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> &amp; the <hi>other</hi> Biſhops who hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offered a moſt humble Petition to the King, in terms
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:039251_0009_1013F9F103E24340"/>
full of Reſpect, and not exceeding the number limited by Law, in which they ſet forth in ſhort the reaſons for which they could not obey that Order, which by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of thoſe evil Counſellors was ſent them, require<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to appoint their Clergy to read in their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, the Declaration for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> were ſent to priſon, and afterwards brought to a Tryal, as if they had been guilty of ſome enormous crime. They were not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obliged to defend themſelves in that purſute, but to appear before profeſſed <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who had not taken the <hi>Teſt,</hi> and by Conſequence were men whoſe Intereſt lead them to condemn them: and the Judges that gave their Opinion in their Favours were thereupon turned out.</p>
            <p>And yet it cannot be pretended that any Kings, how great ſoever there power has been, and how arbitrary &amp; deſpotick ſoever they have bin in the excerciſe of it, have ever reckoned it a Crime for their Subjects to come in all Submiſſion &amp; Reſpect, &amp; in a due number, not exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the limits of the <hi>Law,</hi>) and repreſent to them the Reaſons that made it impoſſible for them to obey their Orders. Thoſe evil Councellors have alſo treated a Peer of the Realm as a <hi>Criminal,</hi> only becauſe he ſaid that the Subjects were not bound to obey the Orders of a popiſh Juſtice of Peace: tho it is evident that (they being by law rendred incapable of all ſuch Truſts) no regard is due to their Orders. This being the ſecurity which the people have by the Law, for their lives, liberties, honours, and eſtates, that they are not to be ſubjected to the arbitrary proceedings of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that are contrary to Law put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any employments Civil or Military.</p>
            <p>Both We our Self, and Our deareſt &amp; moſt entirely beloved Conſort the Princeſs, have endeavour'd to ſignify in terms full of reſpect, to the King, the juſt &amp; deep Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret which all theſe proceeding have given us; and in Compliance with his Majeſty's deſires ſignified to us, We declared both by word of mouth to His Envoy, and in writing, what Our thoughts were touching the <hi>Repealing of the Teſts</hi> &amp; <hi>penal Laws,</hi> which we did in ſuch a manner,
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:039251_0010_1013F9F2A6A1D8C8"/>
that we <hi>hoped</hi> we had <hi>propoſed</hi> an <hi>Expedient,</hi> by which the <hi>peace</hi> of thoſe Kingdoms &amp; a happy <hi>Agreement</hi> among the Subjects of all perſuaſions might have been ſettled: but thoſe evil Counſellors, have put ſuch ill Conſtructions on theſe our good intentions, that they have endeavour'd to alienate the <hi>King</hi> more &amp; more from us, as if we had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to diſturb the Quiet &amp; Happineſs of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The laſt and great Remedy for all thoſe evils, is, <hi>the Calling of</hi> a <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the ſecuring of the Nation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the evil practiſes of thoſe wicked Counſellors: but this could not be yet <hi>compaſſed,</hi> nor can it be eaſily brought about. For thoſe men apprehending, that a lawful Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament being once aſſembled, they would be brought to an account for all their open violations of Law, and for their Plotts and Conſpiracies againſt the proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Lives &amp; Liberties of the Subjects, they have endeavour'd under the ſpecious Pretence of <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> firſt to ſow diviſions among Proteſtants, between thoſe of the <hi>Church of England</hi> and the <hi>Diſſenters</hi>: the deſign being laid to engage Proteſtants, that are all <hi>equally</hi> concerned to preſerve themſelves from popiſh Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into mutual quarrellings; that ſo by theſe, ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages might be given them to bring about their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and that both in the Election of the Members of Parliament, and afterwards in the Parliament it ſelf. For they ſee well that if all proteſtants could enter into a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual good underſtanding one with another, and concur to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the preſerving of their Religion, it would not be poſſible for them to compaſs their wicked ends, They have alſo required all perſons in the ſeveral Counties of <hi>England,</hi> that either were in any imployment, or were in any conſiderable Eſteem to declare before hand, that they would concur in the Repeal of the <hi>Teſts</hi> &amp; <hi>penal Laws</hi>; and that they would give their voices in the Elections to Parliament, only for ſuch as would concur in it: Such as would not thus pre-engage themſelves were turned out of all Employments, and others who entred into thoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements were put in their places, many of them being
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:039251_0011_1013F9F5CCF3F2D0"/>
Papiſts: and contrary to the Charters and Priviledges of thoſe Burroughs that have a Right to ſend Burgeſſes to Parliament, they have Ordered ſuch Regulations to be made, as they thought fit &amp; neceſſary for aſſuring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs of all the Members that are to be choſen by thoſe Corporations: and by this means they hope to avoid that puniſhment which they have deſerved: tho it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that all Acts made by popiſh Magiſtrates are null and void of themſelves; ſo that no Parliament can be lawful, for which the Elections and Returns are made by Popiſh Sheriffs &amp; Ma<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors of Towns: and Therefore as long as the Authority &amp; Magiſtracy is in ſuch hands, it is not poſſible to have any lawful Parliament. And tho ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government &amp; Immemorial Cuſtom, all Elections of Parliament-Men ought to be made with an entire Liberty, without any ſort of Force, or the requiring the Electors to chooſe ſuch perſons as ſhall be named to them: and the perſons thus freely elected, ought to give their Opinions freely upon all matters that are brought before them, having the <hi>good</hi> of the Nation ever before their eyes, and following in all things the dictates of their Conſcience; yet now the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of England cannot expect a Remedy from a free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, legally called and Choſen. But they may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſee one called, in which all Elections will be carried by fraud or force, and which will be compoſed of ſuch perſons, of whom thoſe evil Counſellors hold themſelves well aſſured, in which all things will be carried on accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their direction &amp; Intereſt, without any regard to the <hi>Good</hi> or Happineſs of the Nation. Which may appear evidently from this, that the ſame perſons tried the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the <hi>laſt</hi> Parliament, to gain them to conſent to the Repeal of the <hi>Teſt</hi> &amp; <hi>penal Laws,</hi> and procured that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to be diſſolved, when they found that they could not, neither by Promiſes nor Threatnings, prevail with the Members to comply with their wicked deſigns.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="unknown:039251_0012_1013F9F9F3B13720"/>But to crown all, there are great &amp; violent preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, inducing us to believe that thoſe evil Counſellors in order to the carrying on of their ill deſigns, and to the gaining to themſelves the more time for the effecting of them, for the encouraging of their Complices, and for the diſcouraging of all good Subjects, have publiſhed that the <hi>Queen hath brought forth a Son</hi>: tho there have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared both during the Queen's <hi>pretended</hi> Bigneſs, and in the manner in which the Birth was managed, ſo many juſt &amp; viſible grounds of ſuſpicion, that not only we our ſelves, but all the good Subjects of thoſe Kingdoms, do vehemently ſuſpect that the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> was not born by the <hi>Queen.</hi> And it is notoriouſly known to all the world, that many both doubted of the Queen's <hi>Bigneſs,</hi> &amp; of the Birth of the Child, and yet there was not any <hi>one thing</hi> done to <hi>ſatisfy</hi> them, or to <hi>put an end to their Doubts.</hi> And ſince our <hi>deareſt</hi> &amp; <hi>moſt entirely-beloved Conſort</hi> the <hi>Princeſs</hi> &amp; likewiſe We our ſelvs have ſo great <hi>intereſt</hi> in this Matter, and ſuch a Right, as all the world knows, to the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> to the <hi>Crown</hi>: Since alſo the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did in the year 1672. when the States General of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Provinces</hi> were involved in a moſt unjuſt War, uſe their utmoſt endeavours to put an end to that War, and that in Oppoſition to thoſe who were then in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and by their ſo doing, they run the hazzard of loſing both the favour of the Court and their Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; And ſince the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> has ever teſtified a moſt particular affection and eſteem both to our deareſt Conſort the Princeſs and to Our Selves, We cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe Our Selves from eſpouſing their Intereſts, in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſuch high conſequence, and from contributing all that lies in us for the maintaining both of the Proteſtant Religion, and of the Laws &amp; Liberties of thoſe Kingdoms, &amp; for the ſecuring to them the continual enjoyment of all their juſt Rights. To the doing of which, we are moſt earneſtly ſolicited by a great many Lords both Spiritual &amp; Temporal, and by many <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and other Subjects of all Ranks.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="unknown:039251_0013_1013F9FB78DBBD88"/>THEREFORE it is, that we have thought fit to go over to <hi>England,</hi> and to carry over with us a Force ſufficient, by the Bleſſing of God, to defend us from the violence of thoſe evil Counſellors. And WE being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireous that Our intentions in this may be rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; have for this End prepared this <hi>Declaration,</hi> in which as We have hitherto given a true account of the <hi>reaſons</hi> inducing us to it; So we now think fit to <hi>Declare</hi> that this Our Expedition, is intended for no other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign but to have a Free and Lawful <hi>Parliament</hi> aſſembled as ſoon as is poſſible: And that in Order to this, all the late <hi>Charters</hi> by which the <hi>Elections</hi> of <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> are limited contrary to the ancient Cuſtom, ſhall be conſidered as <hi>null</hi> and of no force, and likewiſe all Magiſtrates who have been injuſtly turned out, ſhall forthwith reſume their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Imployments, as well as all the Burroughs of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhall return again to their ancient Preſcriptions and Charters: And more particularly that the ancient Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the great &amp; famous City of <hi>Lodnon,</hi> ſhall again be in force: and that the Writts for the Members of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſhall be addreſſed to the proper Officers, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law &amp; Cuſtom. That alſo none be ſuffered to <hi>chooſe</hi> or be <hi>choſen</hi> Members of Parliament, but ſuch as are qualified by Law: and that the Members of Parliament being thus lawfully choſen, they ſhall meet and ſit in full Freedom, that ſo the two Houſes may concur in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring of ſuch laws as they, upon full &amp; free debate, ſhall judge neceſſary and convenient, both for the Confirming and Executing the Law concerning the <hi>Teſt,</hi> and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Laws as are neceſſary for the Security and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Proteſtant Religion; as likewiſe for make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch Laws as may eſtabliſh a good agreement between the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and all Proteſtant Diſſenters, as alſo for the covering and ſecuring of all ſuch who will live peaceably under the Government, as becomes good ſubjects, from all perſecution upon the account of their <hi>Religion,</hi> even <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelvs not excepted; and for the doing of all other things which the 2 Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:039251_0014_1013F9FE1449B1F0"/>
ſhall find neceſſary for the Peace Honour &amp; Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Nation, ſo that that there may be no more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Nations falling at any time hereafter under ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Government. To this Parliament we will alſo refer the enquiry into the Birth of the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and all things relating to it, and to the Right of Succeſſion.</p>
            <p>And We, for Our part will concur in every thing, that may procure the peace &amp; Happineſs of the Nation, which a free and lawful Parliament ſhall determine; ſince We have nothing before Our eyes in this Our Undertaking, but the Preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of all men from perſecution for their Conſciences, and the ſecuring to the whole Nation the free enjoyment of all their Laws, Rights &amp; Liberties under a juſt &amp; le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Government.</p>
            <p>This is the deſign that We have propoſed to Our ſevls in appearing upon this occaſion in Arms: in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of which, we will keep the Forces under Our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, under all the Strictneſs of Martial Diſcipline, and take a ſpecial care, that the people of the Countreys thro which We muſt march, ſhall not ſuffer by their means; and as ſoon as the ſtate of the Nation will admit of it, We promiſe that We will ſend back all thoſe forreign Forces, that We have brought along with Us.</p>
            <p>We do therefore hope that all people will judge rightly of us, and approve of theſe our Proceedings: But we cheifly rely on the Bleſſing of God, for the ſucceſs of this our Undertaking, in which we place our whole and only Confidence.</p>
            <p>We do in the laſt place Invite and Require all perſons whatſoever, all the Peers of the Realm, both Spiritual and Temporal, all Lords Lieutenants, Deputy Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and all Gentlemen, Citiſens and other Commons, of all Ranks, to come and aſſiſt Us in order to the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this our deſign, againſt all ſuch as ſhall endeavour to oppoſe us; that ſo we may prevent all thoſe Miſeries which muſt needs follow upon the Nation's being kep't
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:039251_0015_1013FA0174ECF340"/>
under Arbitrary Government &amp; Slavery: and that all the Violences and Diſorders, which have overturned the whole Conſtitution of the Engliſh Government, may be fully redreſſed in a <hi>Free &amp; Legal PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And We do likewiſe reſolve, that as ſoon as the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are brought to a State of Quiet, We will take care that a Parliament ſhall be called in <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring the ancient Conſtitution of that Kingdom, and for bringing the Matters of Religion to ſuch a Settlement, that the people may live eaſie &amp; happy, and for putting an end to all the unjuſt Violences that have been in a Courſe of ſo many years committed there.</p>
            <p>We will alſo ſtudy to bring the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> to ſuch a ſtate, that the Settlement there may be religiouſly obſerved: and that the Proteſtant &amp; Britiſh Intereſt there may be ſecured. And we will endeavour by all poſſible means to procure ſuch an eſtabliſhment in all the Three Kingdoms that they may all live in a happy Union and Correſpondence together; and that the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Peace, Honour, and Happineſs of thoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be eſtabliſhed upon laſting Foundations. Given under our Hand and Seal, at our Court in the Hague, the tenth day of October, in the Year of our Lord, 1688.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>WILLIAM HENRY, PRINCE OF ORANGE.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>By his Highneſſes ſpecial Command.</hi> C. HUYGENS.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>His Highneſs's Additional Declaration</head>
            <p>AFter we had prepared &amp; Printed this our Declaration, we have underſtood, that the ſubverters of the Religion &amp; Law of thoſe Kingdoms, hearing of our preparations to aſſiſt the people againſt them, have begun, to retract ſome of the Arbitrary &amp; Deſpotick powers that they had aſſumed, and to vacate ſome of their Injuſt Judgments and Decrees. The ſenſe of their Guilt, and the diſtruſt of their force, have induced them to offer to the City of <hi>London</hi> ſome ſeeming relief from their Great Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions: hoping thereby to quiet the People, and to divert them from demanding a Re-eſtabliſhment of their Religion and Laws under the ſhelter of our Arms; They do alſo give out, that we
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:039251_0016_1013FA03E13484D0"/>
do intend to conquer &amp; enſlave the Nation, &amp; therefore it is that we have thought fit to add a few words to our Declaration.</p>
            <p>We are confident that no perſons can have ſuch hard thoughts of us, as to imagine that we have any other Deſign in this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, than to procure a ſettlement of the Religion &amp; of the Liberties &amp; Properties of the Subjects upon ſo ſure a Foundation, that there may be no danger of the Nations relapſing into the like miſeries at any time hereafter. And as the forces that we have brought along with us, are utterly diſproportioned to that wicked Deſign of conquering the Nation, if we were capable of Intending it, ſo the great Numbers of the Principal Nobility &amp; Gentry, that are Men of Eminent Quality &amp; Eſtates, &amp; perſons of known Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity &amp; Zeal both for the Religion &amp; Government of <hi>England,</hi> many of them being alſo diſtinguiſh'd by their conſtant fidelity to the Crown, who do both accompany us in this Expedition, &amp; have earneſtly ſolicited us to it, will cover us from all ſuch Malicious Inſinuations: For it is not to be imagined, that either thoſe who have Invited us, or thoſe that are already come to aſſiſt us, can joyn in a wicked attempt of Conqueſt, to make void their own lawful Titles to their Honours, Eſtates &amp; Intereſts, We are alſo confident that all men ſee how little weight there is to be laid, on all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes &amp; Engagements that can be now made: ſince there has been ſo little regard had in time paſt, to the moſt ſolemn Promiſes. And as that imperfect redreſs that is now offered, is a plain Confeſſion of thoſe Violations of the Government, that we have ſet forth, ſo the Defectiveneſs of it is no leſs Apparent: for they lay down nothing which they may not take up at Pleaſure: &amp; they reſerve entire &amp; not ſo much as mentioned, their claims &amp; pretences to an Arbitrary &amp; Deſpotick Power; which has been the root of all their Oppreſſion, &amp; of the total ſubverſion of the Government. And its plain, that there can be no redreſs nor Remedy offered but in Parliament: by a Declaration of the Rights of the Subjects that have been Invad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: &amp; not by any Pretended Acts of Grace, to which the extremity of their affairs has driven them. Therefore it is that we have thought fit to declare, that we will refer all to a free Aſſembly of the Nation, in a lawful Parliament.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under our Hand &amp; Seal, at our Court, in the Hague,
<date>
                     <hi>24 Octob.</hi> in the year of our Lord <hi>1688.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Henry,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>By his Highneſs's ſpecial Command. <hi>C. HUYGENS.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Boſton,</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Harrris</hi> at the <hi>London Coffee-houſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
