<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Hobby's advice to his people from the grave.</title>
            <author>Hobby, William, 1707-1765.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-01">2012-01.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N31427</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N31427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Shipton 41550</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APX9643</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">41550</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99026638</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 41550.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N31427)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 41550)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 41550)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Hobby's advice to his people from the grave.</title>
                  <author>Hobby, William, 1707-1765.</author>
                  <author>Congregational Church (Reading, Mass.).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p. ;  16 cm. (4to) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Z. Fowle, at his printing-office in Back-Street. Price 2d.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1765?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Concerning the selection of a pastor to succeed William Hobby. Hobby was Pastor of the First Church, Reading, Mass., at the time of his death in June of 1765.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Congregational churches --  Massachusetts --  Clergy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:041550_0000_101AB5125E3B3648"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:041550_0001_101AB515E41526F0"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MR. HOBBY's ADVICE TO HIS PEOPLE FROM THE GRAVE.</p>
            <p>BOSTON: Printed and Sold by Z. Fowle, at his Printing-Office in BACK-STREET. Price 2d.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="unknown:041550_0002_101AB43CF7C9C8B8"
                rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>MR. HOOBY's ADVICE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly beloved in Jeſus Chriſt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEFORE theſe lines reach you, the hand that writes them, will be mouldering in the duſt. Receive them, not as from mine houſe upon earth;— but within it, dated from the grave, that houſe appointed for you, and all the living, dead Abel yet ſpeaketh,—he only ſpeaketh, that he may bring you to that precious Blood which ſpeaketh better things than the blood of Abel, crying aloud for pardon, peace, reconciliation and ſalvation. God is my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, you were my paſt concern; God grant you may be my future joy. That concern, and the hope of this joy, is the cauſe of theſe lines, which as they find you now looking towards a reſettlement, ſo are deſigned thro' divine grace, to aſſiſt you therein.</p>
            <p>REALIZE, my dearly beloved, that it is a great work you are entering upon and a great bleſſing that you ſtand in need of. Look upon your families look upon your dear children, that you muſt quickly leave behind you, and, with the moſt importunate concern, realize how greatly their ſafety, welfare, comfort and happineſs, for time and for eternity may turn upon your receiving ſuch a bleſſing. Realize again, the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition you are likely to meet with in your way to it. My death, I doubt not, gives ſatan more life. The ſcythe that cuts down God's miniſters, makes way for the enemy to ſow tares, and furniſhes him
<pb n="3"
                   facs="unknown:041550_0003_101AB51B27263B68"
                   rendition="simple:additions"/>with the proſpect of a large harveſt. Oh! be ſtrongly on your guard againſt a mind prepared to receive them. And therefore put away all pride, anger, envy, headineſs, ſelfiſhneſs and the like, ſuch-like tempers are his hope, and your amazing danger. Yet however greatly concerned, be not diſtreſſed. God liveth God loveth, and Chriſt intercedeth. A proper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for yourſelves is a proof of the divine concern for you; and while the blood of Chriſt is precious to you, fear not that he will leave you deſtitute of a faithful paſtor, the purchaſe of that blood—That you may obtain which, let me ſolemnly charge you to begin with prayer and faſting, and humiliation. God lays his beams in the waters; ſo muſt you too, in the deep waters of repentance, if you would have him dwell with you, in that houſe of his which is the church. From him cometh every good gift, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially that great good, a paſtor after his own heart. But he will be ſought to, for it. Oh go to him, and be glad that you may do ſo. Pour out your tears, and your ſouls into his boſom. Confeſs your ſins before him, particularly whatever has been amiſs in your conduct towards your former paſtors. And eſpecially your careleſneſs to profit by their miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Acknowledge God's juſtice in taking them away, and your own unworthineſs of another. Yet plead with him, his goodneſs, mercy, his promiſe and that how great ſoever is your unworthineſs, the more divinely bright will his grace appear in overcoming it. You muſt ſee your own unworthineſs, of ſuch a bleſſing, if you may expect to receive it; and your acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that unworthineſs is the way to the bleſſing. Not only pray, but continue in prayers; feel your own want, and wreſtle with God for the ſupply of it.
<pb n="4" facs="unknown:041550_0004_101AB51CA8E6B400"/>Wreſtle till you prevail. If you will take no denial, God will give you no refuſal. There is a kind of omnipotency in prayers yea, may I not ſay it overcomes omnipotence itſelf, diſarms God of his anger and extorts that language from him, Commad ye me.</p>
            <p>AND now having ſought to God.—In the next place take council of men; eſpecially of the Minſters of Chriſt round about you: many of whom, bleſſed be God, are of amiable capacity, gracious integrity, and who will naturally care for your ſtate. But beware of poor lowſpirited, ſelfiſh and falſe adviſers. Be well adviſed in yourſelves, in order to your receiving the beſt advice of others.—And now ſuppoſing you to have made application to ſome gentleman with a veiw to ſettle.— Be ye watchful.—Be watchful over yourſelves, againſt all prejudice, one way or another. Eſpecially be watchful over your affections; theſe often blind the underſtanding, and blind the judgment. Don't judge of a miniſter as you do of a bell, by the mere ſound, nor by mere outward appearances; ſuch as air, manner, addreſs, delivery and the like. Theſe, however pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are but the mere work of nature, or the buſineſs of art. It is not all gold that gliſtens. Take heed how ye hear—In the next place be watchful of him. Watch narrowly his preaching. Take heed what you hear. Examine whether his preaching be cloſe, pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and particular; or only large, vague and general; whether by bringing in bad principles, he do not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the truth of Chriſt and endanger your ſouls; or whether he do not cunningly conceal his principles for the preſent, that ſo he and his bad principles may creep in unawares together. Do you hear any thing of the imputation of Adam's ſin, and of Chriſt's righteouſneſs, the depravity of man's nature, and the
<pb n="5"
                   facs="unknown:041550_0005_101AB51E5BD82898"
                   rendition="simple:additions"/>neceſſity of efficacious grace; doth he preach Chriſt, as the all in all of man, his wiſdom, righteouſneſs, ſanctification and redemption; if, not, ſhun him as you would a poſt.—Again be watchful over his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct whether it diſcovers ſincerity and honeſty, wiſdom and prudence, the reaſon of a man, the judgment of a ſcholar, the grace of a chriſtian, and the exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs of a miniſter.—Again, be watchful to know his principles as a divine: here let me charge you, as you will anſwer it at the great day, that you don't ſettle in the dark, and never was greater need of ſuch a charge, than at this day; becauſe never greater dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the goſpel of God's grace; it being perverted into a goſpel without any grace at all. You have a right to know his principles. And if you neglect this right, I fear God is blinding in order to deſtory you. Remember how and what you have received and heard, and hold faſt. Religion, I am confident, will be likely to live, as thoſe doctrines, which, for diſtinction ſake, are called calviniſtic, live, or ſo die, as they die. And if upon examination of the matter you find that the man's principles are not ſettled, I beſeech you ſettle not yet the man.—Once more, be watchful not only that the principles of the man be good, but that he be alſo a good man himſelf; that he have a good heart, as well as a good head.—Endeavour that the man of your choice be alſo one whom the Lord hath choſen to himſelf. God may indeed make uſe of a bad man to bring about good deſigns; but it is not likely that one who is but a veſſel in which he has no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſhould be uſed as a veſſel of honour to bear God's name and grace unto his people: no; ſuch an one is a choſen veſſel; them that honour God, will God honour. However, much caution and modeſty is to
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:041550_0006_101AB51FEBD9BD10"/>be uſed in this matter, and much chriſtian charity; for tho' it would be egregious folly in you to commit the care of your ſouls to one that manifeſted no care of his own; yet there may be much cenſoriouſneſs in determining that he has no ſuch care, or doth not manifeſt it: and where there is this cenſoriouſneſs, there is always pride; and where pride is, there is a demonſtration that you have not taken ſufficient care of your own ſouls. Here therefore let your zeal be accompanied with the meekneſs of wiſdom. Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is profitable to direct. Furthermore, in order to abtain this deſired bleſſing, not only watch and pray, conſult and adviſe, but alſo wait too. Such a mine is not eaſily dug. Such a bleſſing is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently obtained. Guard therefore againſt all precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy. Take time and you will not only do it the better, but do it the ſooner. A few months may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you into anxiety, when a longer time may open your eyes to your full quiet and ſatisfaction. The apoſtle requires that a deacon be firſt proved or tried. Of how much more grand importance is it that a goſpel biſhop ſhould be ſo. How immenſe the riches committed to their truſt. I humbly truſt that the miniſters of Chriſt will be careful that they do not lay hands ſuddenly upon any man. And I ſolemnly charge you as from the world of eternity, that you do not lift up your hands ſuddenly for any man.</p>
            <p>AND now my beloved people, to haſten to a long farewell. Having given you that advice, which my love and concern for you have inſpired, and which I am perſuaded the Spirit of God approves; and in the humble hope that you will obtain the bleſſing I ſo earneſtly deſire for you; let me requeſt and demand in the name of Chriſt my dear Maſter, that you think
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:041550_0007_101AB522F8122BF8"/>nothing too much to do for ſuch a paſtor; and did you know the heart of a miniſter, you would think ſo indeed, and by every method, endeavour to ſooth and eaſe it. Before you receive theſe lines, I ſhall be free from the danger of a ſelfiſh ſpirit myſelf, and the ſuſpicion of it in you. 'Tis your intereſt I am ſeeking, and if you are dear to your paſtor, as you will be if you chooſe ſuch an one as I have pointed out, Oh! let him be dear to you; if he preaches to you the true goſpel, he deſerves to live of the goſpel. Though he can merit nothing of his maſter, yet he in his name merits much of you. If he ſows to you in ſpirtiual thing, don't think it much if he reap of you carnal things—A rich miniſter, I readily grant, has always been the bane of religion; but let me aſſure you, that an impoveriſhed miniſtry always will be ſo. Beware of Jeroboam's prieſts, leſt diſcontented with their condition, they become Jeroboams them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Let your miniſter have enough to keep him choſe in his ſtudy, that he may ſerve God and you without diſtraction; to give honourably to him is to do honour to God and get good to yourſelves,— And now having vented the love of a friend, and the heart of a paſtor, hearken to my laſt words, which ſpeak to you in this wiſe.</p>
            <p>DEARLY <hi>Beloved,</hi> See that you fall not out by the way. Be of one mind as far as poſſible: if not, be of one heart. Put on as the elect of God, bowels of mercies, kindneſs, humbleneſs of mind, meekneſs, long-ſuffering, forbearing one another, forgiving one another; if any man have a quarrel againſt any, even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo do ye; and above all theſe things, put on charity, which is the bond of perfectneſs, and let the peace of God rule in your
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:041550_0008_101AB52539B05F20"/>hearts. To whoſe bleſſing I earneſtly commend you in Chirſt Jeſus, praying that all you, and I, may meet as his right hand, and ſpend an eternity in praiſing him, and God his father for him,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>This is the laſt farewell of your Once affectionate paſtor,</hi> W. HOOBY, <hi>Now no more</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
