<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Narrative of the life, and dying speech, of John Ryer: who was executed at White-Plains, in the county of Westchester, state of New-York, on the second day of October, 1793, for the murder of Dr. Isaac Smith, deputy-sheriff of that county.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N35892</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N35892</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Shipton 46873</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW5266</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">46873</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99011372</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 46873.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N35892)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 46873)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 46873)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Narrative of the life, and dying speech, of John Ryer: who was executed at White-Plains, in the county of Westchester, state of New-York, on the second day of October, 1793, for the murder of Dr. Isaac Smith, deputy-sheriff of that county.</title>
                  <author>A. H.</author>
                  <author>Ryer, Margret.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p. ;  22 cm. (8vo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Nathan Douglas, for the publisher.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Danbury [Conn.], :</pubPlace>
                  <date>--1793.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: A.H.</note>
                  <note>Letter from Ryer's mother, Margret Ryer, p. 4.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ryer, John, 1759-1793.</term>
               <term>Smith, Isaac, d. 1792.</term>
               <term>Executions and executioners --  New York (State) --  White Plains.</term>
               <term>Criminals --  New York (State).</term>
               <term>Murder --  New York (State).</term>
               <term>Crime --  New York (State).</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:046873_0000_102C2F4405380B58"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:046873_0001_102240ADA01CD340"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:046873_0002_10224526273F1E80"/>
            <p>NARRATIVE OF THE LIFE, AND DYING SPEECH, OF John Ryer: WHO WAS EXECUTED AT WHITE-PLAINS, In the county of Weſtcheſter, ſtate of New-York, on the ſecond day of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober, <hi>1793,</hi> for the murder of DR. ISAAC SMITH, DEPUTY-SHERIFF OF THAT COUNTY.</p>
            <p>PRINTED IN DANBURY, BY NATHAN DOUGLAS, FOR THE PUBLISHER.—1793. COPY-RIGHT ſecured according to Law.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb n="2" facs="unknown:046873_0003_10224528A807C5B0"/>
            <head>TO THE PUBLIC.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IF</hi> any one ſhould aſk, why this Speech has not been publiſhed ſooner? I ſtand ready to anſwer, that it was my intention to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured a copy of the endictment, and the minutes of trial, but finding I could not procure them—I offer it to the public without them. The pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſher flatters himſelf that this hindrance, will have no tendency to prove injurious to the publication; but that it will have quite a contrary effect: Seeing there are already two obſtacles which he has to encounter, which might have proved injurious to an early unguard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed publication.—The one is "The laſt Speech and confeſſion of John Ryer," lately ſold in N. York, which contains many falſhoods and is entirely fictious.—The other is, the incredulity of ſome, who do not believe the ſincerity of the profeſſion which he made of meeting with a change of heart.—In order to ſatisfy the minds of thoſe who were in doubt of this, I have taken particular pains to converſe with thoſe who have had oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of informing their judgments reſpecting this matter: who tell me, that his anſwers to the queſtions which they propounded were perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfactory; and when under the Gallows, he being ſtrictly interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated reſpecting the ground of his confidence, gave ſuch anſwers, as I am ſure were ſufficient to remove a doubt of his ſincerity from every unprejudiced mind. I have therefore (in order to guard againſt cenſure) taken particular care, not to inſert a ſingle expreſſion of that nature, but what the amount of which can be proved to have dropped from his own lips.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THE PUBLISHER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE reader is here preſented with not only the tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal diſſolution of one of our fellow mortals, but alſo ſome of the inſtruments made uſe of by the enemy of ſouls, in order to bring about this diſaſtrous event. We frequently hear the people of God pray that he would rule our rulers; and that all our great men might ſpeedily become good men; a terror to evil doers, and a praiſe to them that do well: but an anſwer to thoſe prayers has never yet been fully given: for in peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the following lines, you may be able to make the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of no leſs than three of the magiſtrates of this county<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who have (in the hand of Satan) been (I do not ſay deſignedly) inſtrumental, in bringing about, not only the untimely diſſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lution of our worthy and <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iend Dr. <hi>Iſaac Smith</hi> but alſo in bringing <hi>John</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſituation, that nothin<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhort of d<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> could <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> juſtice, and pay the
<pb n="3" facs="unknown:046873_0004_1022452A844FC280"/>
debt which he juſtly owed to the laws of his country. The firſt thing of this nature which (in the courſe of his ſpeech) comes under our conſideration is the ſeeming kindneſs exerciſed towards him, by one of our magiſtrates, who after taking the piſtols from him (with which he was armed) inſtead of treating him with that degree of contempt, which ſuch conduct loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called for, and which might have detered him and others from any future conduct of ſo diabolical a nature: I ſay, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of dealing with him according to the directions of law, for ſo great a breach of our peace he only deprived him of his arms for five or ſix weeks; and then returned them to him again. The ſecond indulgence of this kind, is ſtill more contemptible than the firſt: For Ryer, being met by a magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, no leſs a perſon than Eſq. J. B—, who, after diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering his arms, inſtead of giving due attention to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his duty, and uſing all lawful means for the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our peace (which peace he was ſolemnly bound to obſerve) he connived at his unlawful conduct, and told him in a very delicate manner, he appeared to be a dangerous man, and paſſed it off with a ſmile.—We will now attend to a diſplay of the groſs ignorance, of another of our magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, in telling John Ryer, that in the diſcharge of his duty as a civil officer, if he crowded upon any perſon, in order to make him a priſoner; and got killed in the attempt, there was no redreſs to be obtained.—From theſe obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, may we not ſuppoſe that there was a notion, inſtilled into the mind of Ryer, that he was almoſt excuſable for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying arms againſt the officers of our country; and that a belief (which he had borrowed from the authority) that it was no great crime for a man to defend himſelf in ſuch a ſituation, was what ſtimulated him to ſtrike the fatal ſtroke, and cauſe a ſeparation to take place between the ſoul and body of our much reſpected friend. He very plainly tells us, that at a certain time, he was ſo countenanced by a perſon in authority, that it impreſſed on his mind an idea, that there was ſome degree of juſtice in his conduct. Let us therefore, inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly offer up our petitions to Heaven; that the Ruler of the Univerſe, might repleniſh the hearts of our rulers with grace and wiſdom; for our land loudly groans, to obtain deliverance, from the burt<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n with which ſhe is oppreſſed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="unknown:046873_0005_1022452DD6ADE880"/>
            <head>A copy of a letter from his Mother to him, a few days pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to his execution.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Manor of Fordom, <date>September 28, 1793.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My Dear Child,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOUR preſent unhappy ſituation does almoſt bring me to death's door; I am the moſt unhappy mother now on earth: The ſting of death could not effect me more, than your ſhort ſtay amonſt us; and the unhappy end, which is now drawing near to you.—I would wiſh to ſee you; but you know, it is impoſſible for me to brook a ſcene ſo cruel as your intended fate; but I hope, through God's mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, we ſhall have a joyful meeting in the world to come; where, neither parting nor ſorrow can affect us; but joy and pleaſure will crown all our labours; and all we have to do, is to get an intereſt in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: For if God grants us the uſe of our tongues, until the laſt moment, we cannot end our lives more comfortably than with ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions as our Saviour made uſe of upon the croſs:— Father into thy hands I commend my ſpirit; and in looking exactly into the death and paſſion of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, we may find how much we are engaged to yield up our ſouls to God, when he is pleaſed to call for them.— David w<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of this mind when he ſaid, into thine hand I commit my ſpirit; thou haſt redeemed me, O Lord God of truth.— Let theſe lines, my dear child, be imprinted on your heart. Think nothing of this world; but fix your whole confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on the Lord Jeſus Chirſt: Lay hold of his croſs, and bathe your ſoul in his precious blood, and he will waſh you whiter than ſnow.—May the God of all mercies be your comfort; and when the ſting of death is gone and paſt, may he be pleaſed to take you to himſelf, to ſing his praiſe forever,— which is the ſincere prayers of your—</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Diſtreſſed and affectionate Mother, MARGRET RYER.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Mr. John Ryer, at White-plains.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="unknown:046873_0006_1022452F6729A668"/>
            <head>NARRATIVE OF THE LIFE, And Dying Speech, of JOHN RYER.</head>
            <p>I JOHN RYER, was born at the Manor of Fordom, in the town and county of Weſtcheſter and ſtate of New-York, the 15th day of February, 1759, of ſober, honeſt, and reputable parents, and was put to ſchool in my youth, but was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued there long; ſo that my education was hardly tolerable. My father being deſtitute of any other help, occaſioned me to be put to labour on the farm; and continued at the farming buſineſs with him, until ſpring of the year 79 or 80, when I left my father; and went to live with my grand mother, at the ſaid Manor of Fordom; where I continued for the ſpace of 9 or 10 months; was then taken a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner by the guides belonging to the continental army, was kept in priſon about one week, when eleven others, with myſelf broke guard made our eſcape, and then went to New-York, where I tarried but a ſhort time, but went to a place called Morriſena; and imbodied in a militia core under Capt. Cuſſer; belonging to a regiment commanded by Col. James De-Lancy, where I fell in with ſuch company, as introduced me to many of the vices of the world; ſuch as exceſs of drinking, card-playing, cock-fighting, curſing, ſwearing, together with almoſt every kind of vice, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and debauchery. But thoſe evils with which I was the moſt delighted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was card-playing and cock-fighting; which (together with every other evil) I would adviſe young people to endeavour to ſhun; for thoſe evils, have a peculiar tendency, to allure the mind; and are the common ſources from whence all evil doth flow; after continuing there a while, and thus miſpending my precious time, I went into the country, with a body of troops which reconnoitred around and returned again to Morriſena: where I continued for ſome conſiderable time. After a while, my father was taken and confined by Col. De-Lancy: I then returned to live with my mother and family, where I continued until my father was reſtored to his liberty. I then went with my father and his family to New-York, in the winter of the year 1781; where I was married to a girl of a reputable family, who was poſſeſſed of thoſe endowments that are neceſſary, to make life contented and happy; with whom I lived about ten years, with all the agreeableneſs that a married life could afford. But ſtill indulged myſelf in my former vices, ſuch as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany-keeping, card-playing, and cock-fighting until my mind got ſo ſtrongly attached to thoſe practices, that I had but little power over my own will; and it ſeemed almoſt beyond my power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain from them.</p>
            <p>After marrying my wife I lived about 9 or 10 months, in a room hired in Prince-ſtreet, (during which time I belonged to the engi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer department) where I continued until the cloſe of the War.— Then moved to my father's, at the aforeſaid Manor of Fordom;
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:046873_0007_102245310F67C960"/>
where I lived about one year, from thence moved with my family, to White Plains, in the ſaid county, on a farm, belonging to one of my uncles where I lived near four years; during which time, there was ſeveral inſtances occured, that are too ruinous to ſociety for me to paſs by, without ſpeaking ſomething to them; hoping thereby that this may be a warning to others; that they may ſhun thoſe evils which has (through inattention) plunged me into one of the moſt deplorable ſituation that can (in this life) befall a poor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy wretch as I am. The firſt, of which was a wrangle with one of my nigheſt neighbours, to wit, Benjamin Lyon: I, by being urged on by others reviled him with unbecoming language and vain reproaches, but did not carry the matter to ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme as to lay myſelf open to the law: This controverſy broke up a communication between us as neighbours: which introduced many inconveniences that commonly attend diſputes of this kind, and prove diſtructive to ſociety.—I ſhall now ſpeak of a very diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable wrangle that took place between Daniel Mertine and myſelf; who (by marriage) was my uncle: he lived in the ſame houſe and occupied a <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rt of the ſame farm, which I did: One day while at work in <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e garden, he came out in a great rage and immediately began a wrangle with me; which continued but a ſhort, time, before he layed hands upon me in order to appeaſe his anger; we were then parted by ſome of the byſtanders and I readily gave up that method of ſeeking revenge and told him I would make application to the authority in order to get redreſs: He made uſe of ſome threats, in order to deter me from putting my deſign into execution; I however, went to a magiſtrate, complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his treatment and had a warrant iſſued againſt him: 'Twas not long before the diſpute broke forth again and his wife engaging in the wrangle, attacked me with a fire-ſhovel, and I retreating from her being armed with a weapon of the ſame kind, by parrying off the blows the ſhovel glanced, ſtruck her forhead and wounded her ſo that the blood guſhed forth: She (together with her huſband) went on with threats in an extreme degree of revengeful language; and I ſcarcely knew what method to take in order to make myſelf ſecure; they immediately went to a juſtice of the peace, in order to get a warrant againſt me: I then to ſecure myſelf from their fury, armed myſelf with piſtols; and within a ſhort time after, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the magiſtrate with them and had my piſtols with me.—Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine informed the juſtice that I carried arms againſt him; the juſtice inquired of me if it was true? I told him yes; whereupon he took them from me; and kept them for five or ſix weeks and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned them to me again. After the diſpute between, Mertine and I was ended, I moved again to the Manor of Fordom, where I lived until the year 1789. when I began to buy beaves, kill and ſell out to my neighbours, which continued for three years together; for ſome of the cattle I was credited, and ſome of the meat I ſold upon credit, and could not collect the money; which was due for the ſame; by which means, I found myſelf unable to make remitance to my
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:046873_0008_10224533A3F36268"/>
creditors; who were continually calling on me for money.— A report was raiſed and circulated abroad, that the place I was in poſſeſſion of, was to be taken from me and ſold; which leſſened my credit among people and which circumſtance ſo inſtantly alarmed my creditors that they thought proper (moſt generally) to preſs me for the collection of the debts due from me to them, and for that purpoſe had recourſe to compulſive means by inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting law ſuits againſt me. At a particular time one of my credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors threatened me with impriſonment unleſs I made him pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſaid many things againſt me, ſpeaking in a reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful language, which had ſuch undue influence on my mind and enraged me in ſuch a manner as to raiſe thoſe paſſions to which human frailty is liable, that I was induced to carry Piſtols in order to keep off the public officers until after the court of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pleas which was in a few days to ſet at Bedford. At the ſame time there was a law-ſuit pending againſt me before a certain juſtice of the peace who was then holding a court at a houſe occupied by Levi Hunt, at Weſtcheſter; I approached within a ſmall diſtance of the houſe, was met there by the ſaid juſtice when he diſcovered me with a piſtol and drawn ſword, and accoſted me with theſe words—Ryer, you appear like a very dangerous perſon — and paſſed it off with a ſmile. I afterwards being much irritated as aforeſaid, and ſtill receiving the threats from the perſon aforeſaid, requeſted him to arm himſelf, and put himſelf in the ſame ſituation I was in, to meet me and decide the quarrel aforementioned. This unfortunate diſpute being countenanced by a perſon in authority impreſſed on my mind an idea that there was ſome degree of juſtice in my conduct, and by degrees I became more and more averſe to the laws of my country. —I was choſen conſtable and collector in the town of Weſtcheſter in the year 1791, and executed that office for that year: During the execution and continuance of the ſame, I had a warrant deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to me to ſerve by a certain magiſtrate, who at the time he handed me the ſame, he aſked me if I knew the duty of a conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I anſwered that for want of longer experience I had not a perfect knowledge of my duty; he then told me that if I had a warrant againſt any perſon I was not obliged to croud upon him or run the riſque of my life, for if I did, and got killed in the attempt, there was no ſatisfaction to be obtained for it. I was induced from the ſituation of my property and the conduct of my creditors (one of whom in particular appeard very preſſing) ſtill to continue carrying arms. On the ſeventeenth of May, 1792, I went from my houſe at the ſaid Manor of Fordom, to Mr. De-Lancy's Mill, to get ſome grain ground, and on my return home, I called at Levi Hunt's Inn, to enquire for ſome perſons I wanted to ſee; when I came there I diſcovered ſeveral people in the houſe playing at cards; I was invited to diſmount my horſe come in and join them to play for ſome liquor, which I very readily aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to, being very fond of that exerciſe: I had not been there long before Williams Hunt, then a conſtable of<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Weſtcheſter, came into the houſe and went <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> any,
<pb n="8" facs="unknown:046873_0009_102245352CE86A08"/>
diſcourſe taking place except my biding him to ſtand off, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered he was coming no nigher, (ſome few words more were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken which I cannot particularly recollect) when ſaid Hunt left the houſe. I went to the door holding a glaſs of liquor in one hand, and a piſtol in the other, and invited him to drink with me, when (after drinking with me) I returned to the table where the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany were ſtill playing cards, and ſeated myſelf between the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and the door leading into the bedroom, oppoſite the front door, being in that ſituation, diſcovered a perſon by the name of Iſaac Smith, a deputy ſheriff, who I did not know upon firſt ſight coming into the houſe and making his way with great ſpeed tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards the place where I was ſeated in order (I ſuppoſed) to make me his priſoner; I being put in great confuſion immediately ſnap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at him one of the piſtols, with which I was armed, having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſly bidden him to ſtand off, he then ſaid I was his priſoner, and demanded aſſiſtance, there being in the room at the ſame time ſeveral perſons who compoſed the company with whom I had been ſpending a part of the afternoon at cards, a young man by the name of John Palmer, who was ſitting by my ſide, ſaid he had not touched me, and Levi Hunt, junr. who was ſitting on the other ſide of me, alſo ſaid, he had only touched his, and Levi Hunt's <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Amidſt the confuſion which took place upon this occaſion, the company all leſt the room except Mr. Smith and myſelf, I then retreated into one corner of the room and Mr. Smith made his way towards the opoſite ſide of the room, he ſtill inſiſted I was his priſoner, and called for aſſiſtance, whereupon I immediately with a piſtol in my left hand, ſhot him through the body, whilſt in confuſion: Smith told me immediately after the diſcharge of the piſtol, that I had done very wrong, for he was a dead man: I anſwered I hoped not, that I was very ſorry, and after this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation between Smith and I, Williams Hunt came in and ſaid to me, Ryer you have killed Smith, I told him to ſtand off, or I would ſerve him the ſame; one of the company then came in and aſked me why I did not go off? and ſaid that Oliver De-Lancy was coming and would take me, I then mounted my horſe and rode off towards home, on my way thither met Oliver De-Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, who charged me with killing Smith, I told him to ſtand off and ſtill continued on my way home, after I got home, went to bed as uſual; ſome time in the night<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Martin MacEvoy, called at my houſe, and enquired for me, whereupon I got up and went to the door; MacEvoy informed me that Smith was dead, and a party of men were collecting together in order to take me, and if I ſtayed there, would certainly be taken, for he expected that in ten minutes the houſe would be ſurrounded, and hurried me away with him; I ſtayed in his barn until the dawn of day, and then betook myſelf to the buſhes where I ſtayed until the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evening when I croſſed Harlem-river, and went to New-York, in order to embark on board of ſome veſſel bound to ſea, but fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of being diſcovered betook myſelf to a houſe near the ſhip <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the upper rooms for two days; while I <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome perſons talking about me under my
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:046873_0010_10224537893CBF00"/>
window, that they ſaw a boat from the Manor of Fordom, bound to New-York, and when ſhe came oppoſite the New Slip lowered her ſails, ſuppoſing from that circumſtance I was not far from that place; finding that I was like to be diſcovered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I left New-York and went towards Kings-bridge, lay there in the buſhes on York-iſland, all the next day, and at night croſſed Kings bridge, and went home; and ſtayed in the neighbourhood about home, (the greater part of the time in the buſhes) until the 12th day of July enſuing; then returned to New-York-iſland by the way of Kings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, where I remained until the night following,—then croſſed the North-river, about a mile below Fort-Waſhington, to the Jer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey ſhore in a came which I tied faſt, and immediately made my way into the country as far as the town of Goſhen, in Orange coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; from thence took my rout to a place called New-Windſor, at the North-river's ſide where I tarried about three days, at which time a veſſel came to an anchor in the river, I hailed her and aſked the Captain if he was bound to Albany, he anſwered he was, I then aſked him if he would take me a paſſenger on board and carry me there, he anſwered he would; whereupon I went on board, and the veſſel carried me to Albany; I then diſembarked and went into the city to take directions which was the righteſt way to Canada; after receiving the ſame, I purſued my rout to Canada by way of Skeenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, from thence croſſed Lake Champlain, to St. Johns, from there to Montreal, and from Montreal to Quebec, where I arrived the 8th day of Auguſt, and was employed by the ſurveyors (who were going to ſurvey the new lands in the ſaid province) to go with them as a chain-bearer and then returned again to St. Johns; I went from thence into the woods again in the ſame employ, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained there a part of the winter; after the winter broke up I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned again to St. Johns, where I remained until the 5th day of April, 1793, when a certain man by the name of John Hutchens, (an acquaintance of mine from the county of Weſtcheſter, being at St. Johns came into the houſe where I boarded. After I diſcovered him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I took him aſide and aſked him what was ſaid of me in the county of Weſtcheſter, he replied the people's wills were good to take me if they could find me, after this I ſaw him paſſing and repaſſing and going from place to place, ſuſpecting from this he had ſome deſign againſt me, I concealed myſelf under the floor of the houſe in which I boarded.—A party then convened together in order to apprehend me, and a ſearch was made for me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the afternoon, but to no purpoſe. About ſunſet (after they had given over ſearching for me) my landlord betrayed me, and for twelve dollars diſcloſed to them the place in which I was concealed. The conſtable who was one of the purſuers, being armed with a ſpear went under the floor in order to make me his priſoner; after he had diſcovered me, he advanced towards me with the ſpear in his hand which I immediately wreſted from him, he then <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and I purſued after him, as I came out of the <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="unknown:046873_0011_1022453A28A87668"/>
the floor received a ſtroke on my head with a club from one of the company which ſettled me almoſt to the ground. After re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering, I attempted to make my eſcape, but being overpowered readily ſubmitted, caſting the ſpear into Lake Champlain; I was then taken priſoner and carried before two magiſtrates who exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined me and after taking my examination committed me to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treal Goal, where I remained until ſome time in the month of May, was then releaſed and delivered over to John Hutchens, and two other perſons who came from the county of Weſtcheſter, in the ſtate of New-York, with a warrant from Chief Juſtice Yates; which was countenanced by, and received a ſupport from the Chief Juſtice of Canada, by delivering me to the perſons aforeſaid; who were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by a ſerjeant, and guard of twelve men, in eſcorting me ſafe within the ſtate of New-York: The guard then returned, and I was brought on (by the ſaid Hutchens and the other two perſons) to the city of Albany, by way of Skeenſburgh; after arriving there, was committed to Albany goal; where I remained near three days, was then taken out, and put on board a veſſel bound to New-York, in order to be brought to the ſaid county of Weſtcheſter. —Was landed at a place called Sing-ſing, a ſmall village, in the ſaid county, contiguous to the North-river, and was put under the care of ſeveral keepers, the keepers falling aſleep in the courſe of the night, I took advantage of that circumſtance, left them and got on board of a ſmall ſkiff, belonging to one of the ſloops, which lay in the harbour: then took a northern courſe, up the ſaid river, and after going near a mile, got out of the ſkiff, went on ſhore, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected together ſome ſtones, and returned again to the ſkiff, which lay floating in the river, ſome diſtance from the ſhore; and after putting the ſtones in her, ſunk her under water, then returned again to the ſhore and after walking thirty or forty yards into the woods, concealed myſelf in a hole under the ſide of a rock; after laying there about two or three hours, was diſcovered and retaken by a party of men who were in purſuit of me, and was then carried back to the ſame place from whence I had eſcaped, and from thence was brought on to the goal at White Plains, in the ſaid county of Weſtcheſter. Being the eleventh day of June, 1793. I was then confined to the dungeon, where I remained until the third day of September enſuing, when a court of oyer and terminer, was open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the White Plains, in and for the county of Weſtcheſter. The next day during the ſitting of the court, I was brought for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and arraigned at the bar, the charge of the grand jury, for the body of the ſaid county was read to me, to which I pleaded not guilty and put myſelf upon God and my country for trial, agreeing that my trial ſhould come on the next day;—was then returned to the dungeon where I remained that night, and the next day (it being on Thurſday the 5th of September) my trial accordingly came <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and was found guilty of the charges contained in the indictment <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> verdict of the following jurors, Peter Lyon, Gilbert Thorn, <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Fowler, Timothy Vanſcoyt, Gilbert Forman,
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:046873_0012_1022453D46321EE0"/>
Thomas Boice, Peter Poſt, Micajah Fuller, ( <gap reason="blank" extent="2 words">
                  <desc> _____ _____ </desc>
               </gap> ) Joſhua Ferris, and John Woolſey, Junr. and the next day in the afternoon the ſentence of death was pronounced againſt me by juſtice Lanſing, and the ſecond day of October aſſigned for carrying the ſolemn ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence into execution.</p>
            <p>I wiſh to ſubjoin this remark in particular, that I had no malice or ill will exiſting in my mind, againſt Dr. Iſaac Smith; that from the moment the fatal event took place, but lamented ſincerely that a man of his temper of mind and goodneſs, ſhould have fallen a vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim to my imprudence.—I alſo wiſh to add, that ſome of the witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes who bore teſtimony againſt me at my trial, carried their evidence further than is within my recollection, but I freely forgive them, and declare that I bear in my mind no envy, malice, or hatred againſt any perſon living.</p>
            <p>Three days before I was to be executed, my father, three of my children, and other friends viſited me, and took their laſt farewell of me in this world; the tears and heart breaking ſorrows I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expreſs; it being propoſed that my wife and friends ſhould make application to the ſheriff and beg my body to be delivered to them for burial, which they did, and the ſheriff being a man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with much humanity, readily complied: it ſo exceedingly gladened them, that I participated with them in their great joy; Early in the morning of the laſt day, that I was doomed to view the dawn thereof; I was viſited by ſeveral preachers, (and other friends) who had frequently viſited me during my confinement; and converſed with me, about the dealings of God with my ſoul. I told them it had been my grief that formerly I had it not in my power to give them any ſatisfaction, by reaſon of my ſtupidity and hardneſs of heart; but at preſent I had great cauſe for thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that God had viſited my ſoul and pardoned my ſins; had bleſt me with a manifeſtation of redeeming love, and repleniſhed my heart with his grace. I was alſo viſited by Mrs. Deborah Smith. I implored her pardon, becauſe I had been the inſtrument of her huſband's death, and had made her a diſconſolate widow; to which ſhe anſwered, I hope God will forgive you, &amp;c.—My wife then took her laſt farewell of me, but Oh, the tears, ſorrows<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and pangs of parting; both overwhelmed with grief, and bowed down with ſorrow beyond expreſſion.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>An Addreſs to his Wife.</head>
                  <p>Oh, my dear and loving wife, may I now part with you in thoſe words that may caſe your bitter ſighs; dry up your flood of tears, and cauſe your heart breaking ſituation, to which you are reduced to be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and prove a bleſſing to your precious ſoul: I am not able to expreſs to you the feelings I have on account of the trouble <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> I have brought upon you. When I take a retroſpective <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the happineſs we enjoyed together, and the <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> afforded each other, and then view my preſent <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> moſt melts my heart. But I am now call <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="12" facs="unknown:046873_0013_1022453F8A695FF0"/>
which I juſtly owe to the laws of my country, and what ſhall I ſay, can I revoke the ſentence which has been paſſed upon me? No—I muſt therefore now fall a victim to juſtice, and ſoon expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience a ſeparation between ſoul and body. I muſt therefore bid you adieu; wiſhing you not to mourn for me for I have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced what the world can neither give nor take away, [to wit] the pardon of my ſins, therefore I ſay weep not for me, but make ſpeedy preparation to follow me; for I expect this day to be in glory. My dear, it will not be long before you will have to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the eternal world; O, ſtrive to make your calling ſure that you may be entitled to a ſeat among the ſpirits of the juſt and not be puniſhed with an expulſion from the preſence of God. I wiſh you to give due attention to the precious ſouls of our ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der offspring, which are now left under your care, ſtrive to bring them up in the inſtruction and diſcipline of the Lord, ſet them good examples, and make earneſt ſupplication to God, that he would fill their tender hearts, with his ſaving grace, and make their minds ſuſceptible of good impreſſions.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>An Addreſs to his Children,</head>
                  <p>And as for you, my dear children, I wiſh you to liſten to the advice of a dying father. I am now about to take my flight into an inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble world; and appear before God. I would therefore wiſh to exerciſe great care in ſpeaking theſe my dying words, and adviſe you to nothing but that which, by being duly attended unto, would have a tendency to promote your preſent, and everlaſting peace. My advice therefore to you is this follow on to know the Lord, and you will then experience the bleſſing of God, both here and here after. You are now travelling in the ſlippery paths of youth, amidſt many ſnares and allurements, but remember if you give way to ſin, you are inexcuſible; for God ſuffers none to be tempted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what they are able to bear. Follow not the example of your unhappy father whoſe youthful days were ſpent in ſin, who lived neglectful of his duty towards God and man; and thereby has brought himſelf to this untimely and diſgraceful end, but remember your creator in the days of your youth, and give your hearts to God. Be not forgetful to diſcharge your duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards your diſconſolate mother; but uſe her with tenderneſs, that thereby you may be entitled to thoſe bleſſings which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to the children which are obedient to their parents.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>An Addreſs to his Parents.</head>
                  <p>Now with what language ſhall I addreſs my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to you, my dear Parents; I confeſs my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at a loſs for words.—O, my dear mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may I not adopt the language of our bleſſed Saviour, and ſay <hi>woman behold thy ſon.</hi>—I truſt, through the aſſiſtance of God I have <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the advice contained in your kind and affectionate letter <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th of September.—But I have filled both your hearts with <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> you are ready to ſpeak in the language of <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> miſchief befall our ſon it will bring down our <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> to the grave.—Ah, my dear pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:046873_0014_102240A942447D78"/>
miſchief, great miſchief has already befallen me; for I can now look back and ſee that I have ſinned againſt God with a high hand; and have been indeed an unprofitable ſervant; that I have neglected my duty towards the King of Kings, and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged myſelf in many practices, which juſtly merited (not only the puniſhment which is about to be inflicted on my poor body) but alſo the frowns of an angry God, and an everlaſting baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the preſence of the Moſt High.—But bleſſed be God, my mourning is juſt now turned into joy;— my conſcience has been filled with remorſe, becauſe I ſaw myſelf a violater of God's law; but I have been bleſt with a removal of guilt—have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced a deliverance from condemnation—am now bleſt with the comforts of religion, and am now able to rejoice in God my ſavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; being confident that I ſhall ſoon be with him in glory.—And now my dear parents (as I truſt my dying words muſt leave a laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impreſſion on your minds) I beſeech you not to weep for me.— One would ſuppoſe that if immoderate mourning was allowable in any caſe whatever, that you might be excuſeable for running in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an extreme on ſuch a melancholy occaſion as this in order to give vent to your grief; but I ſay weep not for me, but weep for yourſelves, if upon a ſtrict examination you ſhould find in you a root of bitterneſs or any thing contrary to the will of God.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>An Addreſs to his Affinity.</head>
                  <p>And as for you unto whom I am related by way of marriage, you have here an opportunity of beholding the conſequences of ſin; it was ſin caſt Adam out of paradiſe, and Angels out of Heaven; it is ſin that has confined me to this dark dungeon and loaded me with irons; and as a conſequence of ſin, the ſeparation is now about to take place between me and one of your family. I am now bound by the ties of nature and gratitude to drop a word of advice to you, that you may no longer ſeek happineſs where it is not to be found, but that your lives may be hid with Chriſt in God—that you may be happy hereafter. You ſee now the doleful ſituation into which I have brought myſelf; and it is nothing but the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of ſin—O, do not ſpend one hour in the devil's ſervice; for his ſervice is drudgery and his wages is death.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>An Addreſs to Dr. Smith's widow.</head>
                  <p>Madam, I have reduced myſelf to the loweſt ebb of wretchedneſs, and am now about to leave this world, and bid adieu to the things of time: I believe it to be my duty, and find it to be my inclination to addreſs myſelf unto you by acknowledging my fault, and publicly aſking your forgiveneſs for what I have done; I have not only deprived the public of a very uſeful man, one who was greatly eſteemed for his humanity, but I have alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived you of your kind companion, and have made <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>conſolate widow: It is a loſs on your part for which I <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> make compenſation.—I am juſt now going to pay the <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> I juſtly owe to the laws of my <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> debt which I owe unto you? Alas <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="14" facs="unknown:046873_0015_10224544035AEAD0"/>
have nothing to pay you, except it be my humble acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be pleaſed therefore to accept of this my laſt offering; for I humbly acknowledge, that I have been guilty of a breach of that law that ſays thou ſhalt not kill; and have gone counter to that command which ſays, that which God hath joined together let not man put aſſunder;—I am therefore not able to furniſh myſelf with any juſtifying excuſe, but wiſh to conclude my addreſs, with referring you to that portion of God's word, which we read in the ſixth chapter of St. Matthew's Goſpel, 14th, and 15th verſes, wherein we find that God will exerciſe the ſame degree of mercy and compaſſion towards us, as we exerciſe towards our offenders.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>An Addreſs to the Doctor's Relatives.</head>
                  <p>And may I not addreſs you in the ſame language, and (after imploring your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs) quote that paſſage which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces a bleſſing to the merciful, promiſſing them that they ſhall obtain mercy, wiſhing you no longer to harbour a ſpirit of enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which perhaps has hitherto juſtly ſubſiſted in your breaſts; but let a reconciliation now take place, and all anger intirely ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>AND let this feeble body fail—</l>
                     <l>And let it faint or die;</l>
                     <l>My ſoul ſhall quit this mournful vale,</l>
                     <l>And ſoar to worlds on high.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O, what hath Jeſus bought for me,</l>
                     <l>Before my raviſh'd eyes;</l>
                     <l>Rivers of Life Divine I ſee</l>
                     <l>And trees of Paradiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ſee a world of ſpirits bright,</l>
                     <l>Who take the pleaſures there;</l>
                     <l>They all are rob'd in ſpotleſs white,</l>
                     <l>And conquering palms they bear.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O, what are all my ſuff'rings here,</l>
                     <l>If, Lord, thou count me meet,</l>
                     <l>With that enraptur'd hoſt t'appear,</l>
                     <l>And worſhip at thy feet.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Give joy or grief, give eaſe or pain,</l>
                     <l>Take life or friends away;</l>
                     <l>But let me find them all again,</l>
                     <l>In that eternal day.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>JOHN RYER.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> morning previous to his execution, he was taken from <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the chamber, Where he ſat and <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Rev. PETER MORIARTY, from
<pb n="15" facs="unknown:046873_0016_102245460C1552A0"/>
Luke 15th chap. and 2d verſe—This man receiveth ſinners.—Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter preaching, the ſacrament of the Lord's Supper was adminiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered to him—He was then taken to the place of execution, attended by ſeveral worthy divines, who aſſiſted him in his laſt exerciſed of devotion. He was then aſked whether he had any thing to offer to the public, he then deſired the People all to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him, and ſee what he had brought himſelf to, ardently wiſhing them all to take warning by him—ſeek the ſalvation of their ſouls, and try to ſerve God the remnant of their days, that they might meet him in glory: And ſaid whereas he had left a ſpeech for the peruſal of the public, he had nothing more to add. The Sheriff then told him he had but fifteen minutes longer to live: he then continued upon his knees by the ſide of his coffin, till again interrupted by the Sheriff, who told him the time was expired. Further preparations were then made for the execution, and after the halter was put around his neck the handkerchief tied over his face he deſired the Sheriff to ſpare him a few minutes longer, which favor being granted: he then appeared to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering up his petitions to Heaven for a ſhort time, and then told the Sheriff he was at his command: returning his unfeigned thanks to Robert Graham the deputy-ſheriff, for the favors which he had ſhewn to him and his family during his impriſonment: He was then launched into eternity! And his remains delivered to his friends for burial.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
