<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The travelling millennarian to the people of America. [Eight lines of Scripture quotations]</title>
            <author>Correy, Molleston.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-05">2011-05.</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">N36533</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">N36533</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Shipton 47760</idno>
            <idno type="NOTIS">APW4707</idno>
            <idno type="IMAGE-SET">47760</idno>
            <idno type="EVANS-CITATION">99010729</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early American Imprints, 1639-1800 ; no. 47760.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(Evans-TCP ; no. N36533)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Readex Archive of Americana ; Early American Imprints, series I ; image set 47760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from Readex microprint and microform: (Early American imprints. First series ; no. 47760)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The travelling millennarian to the people of America. [Eight lines of Scripture quotations]</title>
                  <author>Correy, Molleston.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p. ;  18 cm. (12mo) </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, Molleston Correy,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[United States] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1796.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"On my past life."--p. 27-36, in verse.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Millennium (Eschatology)</term>
               <term>Second Advent.</term>
               <term>Poems --  1796.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global (Manila)</label>Keyed and coded from Readex/Newsbank page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs.</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="unknown:047760_0000_10248E91F7D073C0"/>
            <pb facs="unknown:047760_0001_10248C00EAEDBF00"/>
            <p>Travelling Millennarian TO THE <hi>PEOPLE OF AMERICA.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>REV. i. 3.</bibl>
               <p>For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> me is at hand—Joſeph's corn i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>pt—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>end of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>—The Millennarian of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thouſand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>—Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> dead.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>GEN. xliii. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </bibl>
               <p>And when Joſeph ſaw that Benjamin w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them, he ſaid to the ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r of his houſe, '<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for theſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with me at noon.'</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>REV. xxii. 10.</bibl>
               <p>He which teſtifieth theſe things, ſaith 'Surely I come quietly.' Amen. Even ſo, come Lord Jeſus.</p>
            </q>
            <p>PRINTED FOR THE AUTHOR, <hi>MOLLESTON CORREY,</hi> 1796.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="unknown:047760_0002_10248C03B3C737F0"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IN 1783,</hi> at the Croſs Roads, I made known the coming in of Chriſt's peaceable king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom —a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dover alſo—and next in Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia, and in many places in Pennſylvania and the Jerſeys; and alſo wrote a Letter and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered it to the Congreſs in Princeton College. And in <hi>1784,</hi> I ſent Letters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>me Baptiſt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociations; and travelled through New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, proclaiming the day of the Lord near at hand: which I did alſo in Nova-Scotia, and ever ſince, for twelve years—And now I have written upon the ſubject, to make it known more extenſive as the day approaches more near.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am yours in Chriſt Jeſus, MOLLESTON CORREY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="unknown:047760_0003_10248C0542A9B3A0"/>
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <head>BY the typical repreſentations, in the Old Teſtament teaching of Chriſt's Spiritual kingdom.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> By a great plenty and a famine in Egypt <hi>Page 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2d.</hi> By David's wars againſt the Philiſtines. <hi>Page ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3d.</hi> Solomomon's kingdom and temple <hi>Page 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4th.</hi> God created all things in ſix days <hi>Page 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5th.</hi> By the prieſts ſounding the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'s borns round Jericho <hi>Page 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6th.</hi> The prophet's cleanſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers of Jericho <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7th.</hi> Jacob's ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>de for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>achel <hi>Page 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8th.</hi> The deliverance of Mordecai and Eſther ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained <hi>Page 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9th.</hi> Eliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a's offering: and his deſtroying the falſe prophets <hi>Page 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Promiſes quoted <hi>Page 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CONCLUSION.</hi> Verſes on my paſt ſtate of Life; and on the Antichriſt of falſe worſhip.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="unknown:047760_0004_10248C079DE8C0E8"/>
            <head>BABYLON's DOWNFALL.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Saints' Deliverance.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ARISE ye Saints, look up and view</l>
               <l>The dawning of the Millennium day!</l>
               <l>O come, your courage now renew,</l>
               <l>And drive your riſing fears away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The whore forſaken, mourns her ſtate,</l>
               <l>And haughty Babylon downward bends,</l>
               <l>While Jeſus to avenge your blood,</l>
               <l>In ſtorms of flaming wrath deſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And while he deals his fury round,</l>
               <l>His haughty foes to conſume,</l>
               <l>He with his arm will guard your way,</l>
               <l>And lead you to your heavenly home.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſhall all the heathen lands reſound</l>
               <l>From ſhore to ſhore his fame—</l>
               <l>And thou, America, in ſongs,</l>
               <l>Redeeming love proclaim.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>EXCELLENCY OF WISDOM.</head>
            <p>ALL wiſdom cometh from the Lord, and is with him for ever. Who can number the ſands of the ſea, or the drops of rain and the days of eternity? Who can find out the height of heaven, and the breadth of the
<pb n="6" facs="unknown:047760_0005_10248C0A72F26390"/>earth, and the deep? and wiſdom, wiſdom has been before all things, and the underſtanding of prudence from everlaſting. The word of God moſt high is the fountain of wiſdom. To whom hath the root of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom been made manifeſt, or who hath known her wiſe councils, or underſtood her great experience? There is one wiſe and greatly to be feared; the Lord ſitteth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his throne, he created her, and ſaw her, and poured her out upon all his works. She is with all fleſh, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his gift; he hath given her to them that love him and as God has promiſed, 'Seek and ye ſhall find, aſk and it ſhall be given unto you.' For ſecret things are with him, and none can find out the Almighty to perfection; for there was no man on earth or ſaint in heaven worthy to open the book or unlooſe the ſeals. (Rv. v. 5.) Behold the lion of the tribe of Judah, the root of David has prevailed to open the book and unlooſe the ſeven feals thereof; which doth open unto his ſervants his mind, and will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> he makes them, his inſtruments for the doing of his work, in building his ſpiritual tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of lively ſtones, fitted and prepared by grace, and laid on the corner ſtone, a ſtrong foundation, the rock of eternal ages, Jeſus Chriſt, the ſon of God, as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon's wiſdom and glory, and the magnificency of the houſe he built typified. (1 Kings ii. 45.) And King Solomon ſhall be bleſſed, and the throne of David ſhall be eſtabliſhed before the Lord forever. And we ſee how wonderfully the Lord bleſſed him to make him king inſtead of his father David, to reign in Iſrael, and to bring a change of the times from wars and deſolations, and to eſtabliſh a peaceable kingdom; and for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Lord appeared to him. (1 Kings iii. 5.) In Gibeon the Lord appeared to Solomon in a dream by night; and God ſaid, 'Aſk what I ſhall give thee.' Upon this Solomon begins to expreſs with all his heart filled with thankfulneſs for the great mercies he had given his father, and that he had given him a ſon to ſet on his throne, breaks forth into prayer and praiſe, and acknowledges himſelf unable, being but a little child.
<pb n="7" facs="unknown:047760_0006_10248E33A9DF6FC8"/>I know not how to go out or to come in. Thy people is a great people that cannot be numbered for multitude; give, therefore, thy ſervant an underſtanding heart, that I may judge thy people, and diſcern between good and bad. Here is example for all, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lers both of church and ſtate. O my dear people, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whom God has raiſed up to rule the ſtates, give the people good laws, that you may enjoy a bleſſing and not a curſe; and that your ſpeech may pleaſe the Lord as Solomon's did: for he did not aſk for long life, nor for riches, nor the life of his enemies; but underſtanding to diſcern judgment, and the Lord granted his requeſt; and (1 Kings iii. 12.) ſo, I have given thee an underſtanding heart, and there ſhall be none like unto thee all thy days.</p>
            <p>So King Solomon was king over all Iſrael, and all the princes were under him, and all the officers of his that ruled, every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> according to his charge, that they had over the work and the workmen which were employed in building the temple of the Lord at Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; which typified, in a law diſpenſation, the glories of the goſpel in the converſion of ſinners, 1ſt. By Chriſt's miſſion declared by John the Baptiſt preaching in the wilderneſs, proclaiming liberty to captives, and the opening of the priſon doors to them that are bound: and of the appearing of the promiſed Meſſiah that was foretold by all the prophets—and proclaimed by the wiſe men from the eaſt, directed by a ſtar to Bethle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>m, where the young child was born and laid in a manger; which, in the fulneſs of time, at thirty years of age, he began his public miniſtry in proclaiming the truth of all the prophecies; and by his miracles, which he wrought before their eyes, which plainly teſtified to a ſinful world of ſinners, that he was the Chriſt that ſhould come, and qualify and ſit his workmen to build his temple: 1ſt. His apoſtles, which was ſent through all the corners of the world, with the glorious news of ſalvation for poor miſerable ſinners; and their meſſage was to them as Pharaoh ſaid to the Egyptians, (Gen. xli. 55.) Go unto Joſeph, what he ſaith, do.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="unknown:047760_0007_10248C0C98120C60"/>
And 2dly. By the preaching of his goſpel, by his miniſters that blow the trumpet in Zion, making an alarm in God's holy mountain, in bringing many ſons to glory, by the captain of their ſalvation. And now, my brothers in tribulation, while you are proclaiming the works of faith with earneſt prayer and praiſes, I'll employ my pen and write the glorious declarations of the full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the promiſes for the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ter day, the glory of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem; while you, infant babes of Chriſt, in humble homage, fall proſtrate at his feet, with cries that will pierce through the ſkies, and bring God's mercies down on a wretched world of ſinners.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt <hi>Type</hi>—Gen. xli. 53. 'And the ſeven years of plenty that was in the land of Egypt ended, and the ſeven years of famine began to come, according as Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph had ſaid, for the great dearth was in all lands, for the famine was over all the fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he earth. Then Joſeph opened all-the ſtore-houſes, and ſold unto the Egyptians, and all countries came unto Joſeph to buy corn.' And we have had a glorious day of God's power ſpread abroad; ſo that the north has given up, and the ſouth has not kept back, in bringing ſons from far, and daughters from the uttermoſt part of the earth, as the queen of Sheba came to behold Solomon's glory. But a famine has ſucceeded; the winter has come on the ſeed; there is now but ſmall gathering for the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt men; the church ſeems to be on the looſing hand; the world greatly engroſſes her heart; the love of many are waxing cold; ſhe does not enjoy her firſt love; ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity abounds, and antichriſt riſing and falling away. As the Lord hath ſaid, ſhall I find faith upon earth when I come? 'the man of ſin being revealed, which Chriſt will conſume by the brightneſs of his coming.'</p>
            <p n="2">2d <hi>Type</hi>—Sam. viii. 18. 'And ye ſhall cry out in that day, becauſe of your king, which ye have choſen, for the Lord will not hear you in that day.' For Iſrael reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lord, that he ſhould not reign over them, and deſired Samuel to give them a king to fight their battles; and God gave them Saul in his anger, becauſe they
<pb n="9" facs="unknown:047760_0008_10248E30BB6060E0"/>would not obey the voice of Samuel. And the Lord commanded Samuel to make known unto them the manner of the king that ſhould reign over them, becauſe they rebelled in aſking a king; and which ſhould bring them under tyranny to pay tribute, and made them ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and handmaidens; and he took their fields and vine-yards, and olive-yards, and the tenth of their ſeed, and the tenth of their ſheep; and Saul warred againſt David, and envied him in his heart, fearing that David would poſſeſs his kingdom, which came to paſs; for God raiſed up David to be king, to deliver his church, by deſtroying the Philiſtines. And in the troubleſome times of wars and blood, he made preparation for the building of the temple, and brought in a peaceable king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for his ſon Solomon.</p>
            <p>And ſo God has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iven unto the people of France, King Lewis the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>enth, and the kingdom of Popery which govern the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bjects with laws pernicious both to their ſouls and tyrannical in oppoſition to freedom, like Jeroboam's yoke, chaſtiſes them with whips and ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions. But God will be avenged on ſuch a wicked nation, to chaſtiſe the rebel kingdoms that give their ſtrength to the beaſt; which we ſee is fulfilling by his power ſpread into kingdoms, and is magnifying himſelf againſt the god of armies, and doth not honour the god of forces; and when he ſhall go forth with all his force and craft, to make away many in deſtroying hundreds of thouſands in gaining the conqueſt over large armies, and in pitching his tabernacle between the ſeas in the holy mountain, that is England, he ſhall come to his end without hand: then Babylon ſhall fall, which ruled over all nations; it will be the fall of the tenth part of the city, and ſeven thouſand men ſlain, which is France; and the ruling offices of men will be no more. (Dan. vii. 27.) 'Then the kingdoms of this world ſhall be the Lord's under the whole heaven, and all nations ſhall ſerve and obey him.'</p>
            <p n="3">3d <hi>Type</hi>—Of Solomon's kingdom and Temple.—There was Solomon's peaceable kingdom, when all the
<pb n="10" facs="unknown:047760_0009_10248C0E18F73088"/>wars ceaſed, a time made ready that the work of the Lord was to be done in, building a temple, exceeding magnificial of fame and of glory throughout all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; and it was not to be done without king Hiram's help; for he ſent to Solomon ſhips loaded with gold and ſilver, and cunning workmen for the engraving and running of golden veſſels and ſkilful in all manner of work; but king Solomon was the head, inſpired by God according to the pattern ſhewn him, which repreſented the glory of the gentile church that God would build up of ſpiritual ſtones, made ready from the rocks of ſin, and poliſhed with Chriſt's blood to ſhine in brightneſs like the ſun in the firmament of heaven; and Hiram's kingdom repreſented the Jewiſh nation, which the Lord will join into one people in righteouſneſs, and a nation will be born in a day. (Ezek. 34.) 'Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as a ſhepherd ſeeketh out his flock in the day, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ong them that are ſcattered abroad; ſo I will ſeek my ſheep and deliver them out of all places where they have been ſcattered in the dark and cloudy day.'</p>
            <p n="4">4th <hi>Type</hi>—And as God created the world in ſix days, and reſted the ſeventh from all his labour, and commanded the ſeventh day to be a holy day to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to his ſervice, a day of worſhip, and praiſe, and glory throughout all generations, to glorify God for all his works done for the children of men: ſo God will finiſh all the ſpiritual work of redemption in ſix thouſand years, and the ſeventh thouſand will be a Sabbatical Reſt for the new Jeruſalem Saints upon earth, that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive life from the dead (Levit. xxv. 4.) 'The ſeventh year ſhall be a Sabbath unto the land, a Sabbath for the Lord; (Num. viii. 1.) and when thou lighteſt the lamps, the ſeven lamps ſhall give light over againſt the candleſtick; (Num. xxviii. 25.) and on the ſeventh day ye ſhall have an holy convocation, ye ſhall do no ſervile work; (Num. xxix. 1.) and the ſeventh month, on the firſt day of the month, ye ſhall have a holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, ye ſhall do no ſervile work; it is a day for the blowing of the trumpets, and of an offering; there were
<pb n="11" facs="unknown:047760_0010_10248C0F9BBAFFC0"/>ſeven lambs of the firſt year without blemiſh, and an offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the 7th day of ſeven bullocks. (Dt. xv. 1.) And at the end of ſeven years ye ſhall make a releaſe, and there ſhall be no leavened bread ſeen with thee in all thy coaſts ſeven days. (Deut. xxxi.) They read the law to the people every ſeven years; all which ſhew unto us the ſeventh part of time will be ſet apart for the glory of God.'</p>
            <p n="5">5th <hi>Type</hi>—Joſhua vi. 3, 4. 'And the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Joſhua, that he ſhould compaſs the city of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richo with all his men of war, and go round about the city once; thus ſhall ye do ſix days: and ſeven prieſts ſhall bear before the ark ſeven trumpets of ram's horns; and the ſeventh day ye ſhall compaſs the city ſeven times: and the prieſts ſhall blow with the trumpets; and it ſhall come to paſs that when they make a long blaſt with the ram's horns, and ye ſhall hear the ſound of the trumpet, all the people ſhall ſhout a great ſhout, and the wall of the city ſhall fall down flat, and the people ſhall aſcend up before him.'</p>
            <p>This plainly ſets forth, that our ſpiritual Joſhua has been ſounding the glories of his goſpel by his prophets, apoſtles, and miniſters, almoſt ſix thouſand years; and when the miniſtry ſhall ceaſe, which will end at the full period of ſix thouſand years, this Jericho world ſhall be changed into a new heaven and a new earth, when the pride of nations will be conſumed by the fire of grace, and the antichriſt of ſuperſtition, idolatry, the Antinominian ſecurity, Mahometan and Pagan abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſtandeth in the holy place that maketh deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, will receive the ſickel of God's judgment, which will gather the cluſters of the vine of the earth into the wine-preſs of Almighty God.</p>
            <p n="6">6th <hi>Type</hi>—2 Kings ii. 19. 'The waters of Jericho healed, and the men of the city ſaid unto Eliſha, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I pray thee, the ſituation of the city is pleaſant, as my Lord ſeeth; but the water is naught, and the ground barren: and he ſaid, Bring me a new cruiſe and put ſalt therein; and they brought it to him, and he went forth to the ſpring of waters, and caſt the ſalt in there, and
<pb n="12" facs="unknown:047760_0011_10248C118C2757E8"/>ſaid, thus ſaith the Lord, I have healed theſe waters: there ſhall not be from thence any more death, or bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren land.'</p>
            <p>And ſo God will cleanſe Jeruſalem from her filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when ſhe ſhall ſay, I am no more ſick, and I am freed from death, for her inhabitants will no more die, nor ſee corruption; the grave will no more cover her ſlain, nor death's gorging mouth rage its prey; no more doctor's to ſeparate fleſh and blood apart; no more hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitals of ulcered, noxious bodies of groaning pains; no more lawyers pleading wrong cauſes, robbing the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and widows; no more rich worldlings with hearts ſet on gain; no more falſe teachers that preach for the bag—are like Judas, that fold Chriſt for thirty pieces of ſilver; no more to trade with ſlaves and the ſouls of men. (Rev. xviii. 14.) 'And the fruits of that thy ſoul luſted after, are departed from thee, and all things which were dainty and goodly are departed from thee, and thou ſhalt find them no more at all.'</p>
            <p n="7">7th <hi>Type</hi>—Jacob's ſerving for Rachel. (Gen. xxix. 15.) 'And Laban ſaid unto Jacob, Becauſe thou art my brother, ſhouldſt thou ſerve me for naught? Tell me what ſhall thy wages be? And Jacob loved Rachel, and ſaid, I will ſerve thee ſeven years for Rachel thy younger daughter. And when the time was expired, Jacob expected to enjoy his bride. Laban deceived him, and gave him, and brought in to Jacob his elder daughter Leah; and had to ſerve ſeven years more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he got Rachel, which was a ſorrowful time of trouble to him to be kept from her whom he ſo much delighted in, with all his heart.' But it was ſo deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by God, that Leah repreſented the Jewiſh na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Lord had firſt in the world, ſhe being the elder: and Rachel typified the bringing in of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles in a goſpel diſpenſation, and that their ſpread ſhould be as extenſive as the ſun that runs its journeys round the world. And ſpiritual Jacob, when married to Rachel, the Gentiles' fulneſs come in, which will build Chriſt's Canticle Spouſe, will make the Jews return—As the
<pb n="13" facs="unknown:047760_0012_10248C15DA06CBC8"/>Pſalmiſt prayed, O that the ſalvation of Iſrael was come out of Zion. When God will return to deliver his people from captivity, Jacob will rejoice and Iſrael will be glad, and Jacob's great trouble of labour fourteen years, ſet forth the great troubles that the church ſhould paſs through while in this wilderneſs of ſin and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat time has almoſt run out ſince the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful time God ſent his rod on America, which ſince gave us a goſpel day. And as ſoon as ſhe gained her freedom from England's tyranny, it alſo took wings and flew over the Atlantic ocean to France, and cut off the King and Queen's heads—a beginning for everlaſting fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dom from the world, the fleſh and the devil, the deſtruction of the beaſt, and a glorious righteouſneſs as the drops of the morning dew upon the tender graſs.</p>
            <p n="8">8th <hi>Type</hi>—Eſt. ch. 1. 'Now it came to paſs in the days <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Ahaſuerus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich reigned from India unto Ethiopia, over an hundred and twenty-ſeven provinces; and he ſat on the throne of his kingdom, in a very glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious palace; he made a feaſt unto all his nobles and princes, and ſervants, the power of Media and Perſia of the provinces before him; when he ſhewed the riches of his glorious kingdom, and the honour of his excellent majeſty many days: and his feaſt laſted ſeven days in the garden of the king's palace; and the Queen Vaſhti made a feaſt ſeven days; but ſhe rejected the king's commandment, and was caſt off, and was diſpelled out of his kingdom, and he was wroth againſt her; and Eſther was brought in before the king, and ſhe pleaſed him, and he choſe her inſtead of Queen Vaſhti; and the king made Eſther his queen, and he gave unto her the odours and ointments for purification, and ſeven mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens to wait on her. Now in Shuſhan, the palace, there was a certain Jew, whoſe name was Mordecai, and he brought up Eſther as his own daughter; and alſo there was man whoſe name was Haman, which the king had promoted; and all the ſervants that were in the king's gate bowed and reverenced Haman. But Mordecai bowed not, nor did him reverence; and they ſaid, Why do
<pb n="14" facs="unknown:047760_0013_10248C175DFF7D38"/>you tranſgreſs the king's commandments? and they told Haman, and he was full of wrath, and ſought to deſtroy all the Jews throughout the whole kingdom; and the plot was determined for the Jews' deſtruction in all the provinces. And when Mordecai perceived all that was done, he rent his clothes, and put on ſackcloth with aſhes, and went out into the midſt of the city, and cried with a loud and bitter cry, even before the king's gate, and in every province where the king's letters came, that declared their death, there was a great mourning, faſting, and weeping, and wailing in ſackcloth and aſhes; and Mordecai ſhewed it unto Eſther, and commanded that ſhe ſhould go in unto the king, and make ſupplication unto him, and to make requeſt for her peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and Eſther returned an anſwer to Mordecai, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Gather all the Jews, and faſt for me; neither eat nor drink, three days; and I will go in unto the king, which is not according to the law, and if I periſh I periſh. And ſo the King and Haman came to ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet with Eſther; and when the book of records was read before the king, it was made known of a ſecret of two chamberlains, who ſought to take the king's life, which Mordecai had made known, which gave him favour with the king; and alſo Haman's wickedneſs was revealed by Eſther to the king: and the king granted the queen's petition for the deliverance of her people; and the adverſary, wicked Haman, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and hanged on the gallows of fifty cubits high, that he had erected for Mordecai: ſo the Jews received a great deliverance, and kept the fourteenth day of the month Adar, a day of gladneſs and feaſting and a good day, and of ſending of portions one to another.</p>
            <p>So, the method I take to explain this paſſage—1ſt. As King Ahaſuerus' kingdom was ſo large and extenſive, and his excellent majeſty and riches which he ſhewed to all his nobles and princes; and he received their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence by bowing before the king; ſo God the Father, the Almighty King that rules over all the kingdoms of this world, will make them bow at his footſtool.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="15" facs="unknown:047760_0014_10248C19B6D48B78"/>
2d. Mordecai's great work for the deliverance of his people, ſhews us of Jeſus Chriſt's great and wonderful deliverance of his church; and as Mordecai was in ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth in great diſtreſs for the Jews' calamity and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction which was determined by Haman; ſo Jeſus Chriſt lay in the garden of Gethſemane in the greateſt extremity and pain, ſo as to ſweat great drops of blood; which wrought a glorious ſalvation for his people. And as diſobedient Vaſhti rebelled againſt the king's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, and would not obey his requeſt, he rejected her, and caſt her off, which ſhewed forth the rejection and caſting off the Jews and the rebel kingdoms of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's empire, the whore of Babylon, which ſitteth a queen riding on a ſcarlet beaſt, the abomination of the earth; and as Eſther was received inſtead of Vaſhti, for ſhe pleaſed the king, and he loved her, and granted her requeſt, for a great mercy to the Jews: ſo God was to bring in the gentiles of a goſpel-day, which will make up their fulneſs; then the Jews will return and inherit the promiſes. And as Haman was a wicked, haughty, proud man, filled with envy, hatred, and malice againſt Mordecai and the Jews, which accuſed him to the king for being diſobedient to the king's commandment; Haman ſought to take his life, repreſented the devil's craft and ſubtlety to deſtroy men's ſouls, and make them his ſervants at his will: and as Haman was hanged, and his ten ſons, ſo God will deſtroy the works of ſatan, and ſhew mercy to the ten kingdoms of the beaſt, and as two of the king's chamberlains, Bithan and Tereſh, of thoſe that kept the door, were wroth, and ſought to lay hold on the king Ahaſuerus; and the thing was known to Mordecai, who told it to Eſther the queen; and Eſther certified it to the king in Mordecai's name; ſo Chriſt knows all things; for ſecret things belong to the Lord, and he revealeth his ſecrets to his ſervants the prophets, and they pray to the king in Jeſus' name to deſtroy the wickedneſs of Pope Papal, and Mahomet, which is the two kingdoms that is riſen in wrath againſt
<pb n="16" facs="unknown:047760_0015_10248C8BAD2F8910"/>the king of nations; which theſe two men's rebellion ſhewed forth. (1 Kings xviii.)</p>
            <p n="9">9th <hi>Type</hi>—There was a Jezebel in the days Ahab, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ew and put to death the Lord's prophets, ſo that many hid themſelves in coverts to ſave their lives; and there was a prophet whoſe name was Elijah; and Ahab ſaid unto him, Art thou he that troubleth Iſrael? and he anſwered and ſaid, I have not troubled Iſrael; but thou and thy father's houſe, in that ye have forſaken the commandments of the Lord, and haſt followed Balaam. Now, therefore, ſend and gather me all Iſrael unto Mount Carmel, and the prophets of Baal four hundred and fifty, and the prophets of the groves four hundred, that eat at Jezebel's table; ſo Ahab gathered them all to Mount Carmel, and Elijah came unto all the people and ſaid, How long hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ye between two opinions? If the Lord be God, follow him: but if Baal, then follow him. And the people anſwered him not a word: then ſaid Elijah, I even only remain the Lord's prophet; but the prophets of Baal are four hundred and fifty men; give us two bullocks, and chuſe one for yourſelves, and cut it in pieces, and lay it on wood, and put no fire un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and I will dreſs the other bullock, and lay it on wood, and put no fire under it, and call on your gods, and I will call on the name of the Lord, and the God that anſwereth by fire, let him be God; and they call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed till noon, ſaying, O Baal, hear us; but there was no voice, nor any that anſwered; and they leaped on the altar. And at noon Elijah mocked, and ſaid, Cry aloud, for he is a God; either he is talking, or he is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, or on a journey, or peradventure he ſleepeth, and muſt be awakened; and they cried aloud, and cut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves after their manner, with knives and lancets, until the time of the offering of the evening ſacrifice, and not any regarded. And Elijah ſaid, Come near unto me; and all the people came near, and he repaired the altar that was broken down; and he took twelve ſtones, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the number of the tribes of the ſons of Jacob, unto whom the word of the Lord came, ſaying, Iſrael
<pb n="17" facs="unknown:047760_0016_10248C8D774CA1A8"/>ſhall be thy name; and he made a trench about the altar that would contain two meaſures of ſeed: and he put the wood in order, and cut the bullock in pieces, and filled barrels of water that run round the altar; and it came to paſs at the time of the offering of the evening ſacrifice, and the prophet ſaid, Lord God of Abraham, Iſaac and Jacob, let it be known this day, that thou art God in Iſrael, and that I am thy ſervant, and that I have done all theſe things at thy word. Hear me, O Lord, hear me, that this people may know that thou art the Lord. Then the fire of the Lord fell and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed the burnt ſacrifice, and the wood, and the ſtones, and the duſt, and licked up the water that was in the trench; and when all the people ſaw it, they fell on their faces, and they ſaid, the Lord he is God; the Lord he is the God. And Elijah ſaid, Take the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of Baal and ſlay them; let not one eſcape. So God will 'ere long deſtroy all falſe prophecy; and as Elijah ſent his ſervant to go up to the top of Carmel, and looked towards the ſea, and he ſaw nothing; and he ſent him ſeven times; then he ſaw a little cloud riſing out of the ſea like a man's hand: and the heaven was black with clouds and wind, and there was a great rain. The little cloud is the ſmallneſs of the church; the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, clouds, and wind, is the diſtreſs of her labour and travail. But, when the ſeventh time will commence, it will rain a great rain of righteouſneſs through all the earth; the dry and the thirſty pools will be filled.</p>
            <p>Now I begin to explain the title of my book.</p>
            <p>(Rev. i. 3.) For the time is at hand. There was a wonderful revelation made unto John in the Iſle of Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos, of things that ſhould ſhortly come to paſs, which he was commanded to write. 1ſt. The ſtates of the ſeven churches of Aſia, both of ſuch as were zealous for Chriſt's cauſe, and thoſe that were but idol <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers: and he ſets forth the bleſſings of the Philadelphia church in a goſpel ſtate, and what ſhe ſhould be in a new Jeruſalem glory. (Rev. iii. 8.) I know thy works: behold, I have ſet before thee an open door, and no
<pb n="18" facs="unknown:047760_0017_10248C8FB51FE250"/>man can ſhut it, for thou haſt a little ſtrength, and haſt kept my word, and haſt not denied my name. This is the ſtate of the church that ſhe is now in, Chriſt's true Church of the Gentites; and by the bleſſings of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, fulfilment in bringing in the latter day of glory, it will make up the fullneſs of the Gentile's temple from all nations and kingdoms converted to the knowledge of God, as the waters cover the great deep, which will bring in the falſe Laodicean Church and the Jews—(Rev. iii. 9.) Behold, I will make them of the ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Satan, to come and worſhip before thy feet, and to know that I have loved thee. The falſe church ſays I am rich, and have need of nothing; but the word ſays thou art poor and wretched, blind and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. This is the Antichriſt that believe in their own righteouſneſs, their own goodneſs, their falſe worſhip, ſuperſtition and idolatry, worſhipping idols and images, wood and ſtone, untempered mortar, a daubing work that the fire has not refined; it is droſs and dung, the barren land not dug nor ploughed, nor ſowed with the ſeed of the woman, nor the ſerpent's head bruiſed; it is Prieſts' ſchemes of men's own invention, Popiſh ſchemes of helliſh arts, the ſimple doth betray. But the time is at hand that the Lord will ſend judgment to victory, and deliver Zion univerſally, both Jews and Gentiles, and make them one nation and kingdom in a heavenly ſtate upon earth. Conſider, O wicked ſinners, that the time, is at hand that you muſt die, and if unprepared, you will be damned. Alſo the Day of Judgment is near at hand that Chriſt will judge you according to your works, and receive a reward according to the deeds done in the body, whether good or bad.</p>
            <p>(Gen. xliii. 16.) And when Joſeph ſaw that Benjamin was with them, Joſeph feeding his brethren, typified Jeſus Chriſt feeding ſinners with the bread of his free grace in a goſpel diſpenſation; and we ſee that Joſeph did not dine with them till Benjamin was with them, not till they were all together; for he ſaid to the ruler of his houſe, Bring theſe men home, for theſe men
<pb n="19" facs="unknown:047760_0018_10248C9234E19518"/>ſhall dine with me at noon. So in the fullneſs of the Gentiles, which Benjamin the youngeſt ſon ſhewed forth: Then will be Jeruſalem's feaſting time, the feaſt of tabernacles, the Jew's feaſt of the bread of life, and life from the dead; and Joſeph had a man that ruled his houſe, ſo Chriſt will have a glorified man of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil that will be head and ruler in his ſpiritual kingdom: as God never did any of his work of his temple without an inſtrument, ſo he will ſend his meſſenger before him, that will be the refiner's fire, and the fuller's ſoap, that will burn and purify, and melt hardened hearts, and make them hearts of fleſh, and will turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the children to the fathers, and conſume the earth from the curſe.</p>
            <p>(Rev. xxii. 20.) He which teſtifieth theſe things, ſaith, ſurely, I come quickly. Amen. He which has ſpoken all the promiſes will fulfil them every jot and tittle; for God altereth not: and becauſe God chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, the ſeed of Jacob is not conſumed; he will come quickly, and cut his work ſhort in righteouſneſs, becauſe the Lord will make a ſhort work upon earth: even ſo come Lord Jeſus: this is the churches prayer in her ſtate of this wilderneſs, travail and pain, as a woman with child, and is in pain to be delivered: and the churches birth-pains are not at the greateſt extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; iti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s not midnight yet, that ſhe is ſlumbering and ſleeping with the fooliſh virgins.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ye virgin ſouls ariſe,</l>
               <l>With all the dead awake</l>
               <l>Unto ſalvation wiſe,</l>
               <l>Oil in your veſſels take.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Behold, your bridegroom will come and deliver you; he will ride on a ſwift cloud, and come into Egypt, and deſtroy the idols, and make the hearts to melt in the midſt: but the Egyptian war muſt end firſt, and the cruel Lord and fierce king and kingdom muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and the kingdoms of this world muſt be given, to the ſaints of the moſt high, to live with Chriſt by the glory of his ſpirit one thouſand years, to inherit all the
<pb n="20" facs="unknown:047760_0019_10248C9464776F18"/>glory of all the promiſes, freed from the world, fleſh, and the devil; for Satan will be bound that thouſand years, as you may read in the 20th of Rev. 1. And I ſaw an angel come down from heaven, having they key of the bottomleſs pit, and a great chain in his hand; and he laid hold on the dragon, that old ſerpent, which is the devil and ſatan, and bound him a thouſand years. Perhaps ſome would enquire when this time will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence. I do not ſet forth the certain time; but ſhew forth the events that appear to my underſtanding to be the preparations that God is making for his kingdom's glory. And theſe days are the churches impriſonment and great diſtreſs. But ſo far I determine, that if the ten days of tribulation and impriſonment is ten years, which is in Rev. ii. 10; then, from one thouſand ſeven hundred and ninety, when the wars begun in France for the deſtruction of Popery and all the Antichriſtian powers: Then the fall of the Beaſt will be in the year eighteen hundred of Satan's binding. Then Michael ſhall deliver Iſrael from all their troubles. (Dan. xii. 1.) And at that time ſhall Michael ſtand up, the great prince which ſtandeth for the children of thy people, and there ſhall be a time of trouble, ſuch as never was ſince there was a nation; even to that ſame time, and at that time thy people ſhall be delivered. And it will be by wars and famine, and peſtilence, which will be a great cutting off of nations. (Zach. xiii. 8.) And it ſhall come to paſs, that in all the land, ſaith the Lord, two parts therein ſhall be cut off and die; but the third ſhall be left therein; and I will try them as gold is tried. They ſhall call on my name, and I will hear them ſay, it is my people; and they ſhall ſay, the Lord is my God. This work will be the firſt reſurrection from the dead, as ſpoken by the prophet. (Ezek. xxxvii. 1.) By the reſurrection of dry bones. The dead hope of Iſrael revived by the breath of the Lord. Thus ſaith the Lord, Come from the four winds, O breath, and breathe on theſe ſlain, that they may live. And behold, I will take the children of Iſrael and bring them into
<pb n="21" facs="unknown:047760_0020_10248C95F0D49C40"/>their own land, and will make them one nation upon the mountains of Iſrael, and one king ſhall be king to them all; they ſhall no more be two nations, neither ſhall the be two kingdoms any more, nor defile them with their idols, nor with their tranſgreſſions; but I will ſave them, and will cleanſe them, and they ſhall have one ſhepherd typified by David; and I will make a covenant of peace with them, and will ſet my ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary among them for evermore, and build them, and make their land like unto the garden of Ede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. But, O ye mountains of Iſrael, ye ſhall ſhoot forth your branches, and yield your fruit; for they are at hand to come. And Chriſt's Millennium Saints will live and reign upon the earth one thouſand years in an immortal ſtate of glory; and the dead ſaints that have gone to heaven, and their dead bodies buried in the grave, ſhall ſo continue till the thouſand years are ended: then their ſouls will re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enter their bodies, and experience greater joy of heavenly b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s in Chriſt's holy kingdom of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſs, an endleſs eternity. Then they will aſcend with their glorious king to judgment, when the Millennium Church will be changed to a greater glory to meet their Lord in the air at his ſecond coming. (2 Pet. iii. 10.) But the day of the Lord cometh as a thief in the night, in the which, the heavens ſhall paſs away with a great noiſe, and the elements ſhall melt with fervent he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; the earth alſo, and the works therein ſhall be burnt up. Then the judgment will proceed that the wicked ſhall be judged in their bodies raiſed from death and hell; the ſpiritual war will commence of Gog and Magog, deceived a little ſeaſon, a very ſhort time, not a year nor a day, but an hour or leſs; for there was ſilence in heaven half an hour; ſo as to expect that their t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ted ſouls, that have ſuffered the wrath of God, bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>illed with wrath and malice againſt God and his ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the ſame ſtate as they died, will expect to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a deliverance, as ſome believe, in a hell redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but we ſee what will be their dreadful ſentence (Rev. xx. 9.) And fire came down from God and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
<pb n="22" facs="unknown:047760_0021_10248C997913F428"/>them, and the devil that deceived them, was caſt into a lake of fire and brimſtone, where the Beaſt and the falſe prophet are, and ſhall be tormented for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>Now I return again to ſet forth the glories of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Jeruſalem.</p>
            <p>(Rev. xxi. 1.) I ſaw a new heaven and a new earth, for the firſt heaven and firſt earth were paſſed away— That is, the firſt ſtate of the church will be changed to a larger degree of glory, her former travail of trouble will be ended, all things will be new to her; and poor ſinners, which is earth, earthly, and devliſh and ſenſual will be changed, and made new and living ſaints; the new Jeruſalem will deſcend down out of heaven upon them. The ſpirit, as the dove, was on Chriſt's head when he was baptized in Jordan. Alſo the ſtarry hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens will be a new heaven. No more thundering ſtorms of thunder, and black clouds and hurricane winds and diſmal guſts to lay waſte and break the oaks of the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs; no more floods ruſhing down with rolling waves, nor ſnows nor froſts to freeze the weary labourer or traveller; no more occaſion for the fleecy flocks to put the thick warm woollen cloathing on our trembling bodies. The earth will be a new earth of glory before it is deſtroyed, ſet forth by the prophet, (Iſa. xxxv. 1.) The wilderneſs and the ſolitary places ſhall be glad for them, and the deſart ſhall rejoice and bloſſom as a roſe, it ſhall bloſſom abundantly, and rejoice even with joy and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; the glory of Lebanon ſhall be given unto it; the excellency of Carmel, and Sharon, they ſhall ſee the glory of the Lord, and the excellency of our God. (Iſa. lv. 12.) For ye ſhall go out with joy, and be led forth with peace. The mountains and the hills ſhall break forth into ſinging before you, and all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the field ſhall clap their hands; inſtead of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, there ſhall come up the fir tree; and inſtead of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er, ſhall come up the myrtle tree, and it ſhall be to the Lord for a name, for an everlaſting ſign, that ſhall not be out off. (Iſa. lxv. 25.) The wolf and the lamb ſhall
<pb n="23" facs="unknown:047760_0022_10248E2E719E6C50"/>lie down together, and the lion ſhall eat ſtraw like the bullock, and duſt ſhall be the ſerpent's meat; they ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy mountain, ſaith the Lord. (Iſa. lxvi. 10.) Rejoice with Jeruſalem and be glad all ye that love her; rejoice for joy with her, for thus ſaith the Lord; for behold, I will extend peace to her like a river, and the glory of the Gentiles like a flowing ſtream: then ſhall ye ſuck and be ſatisfied with the breaſts of her conſolations, that ye may milk out and be delighted with the abandance of her glory. So I will comfort you, and ye ſhall be comforted in Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem; and when ye ſee this, your heart ſhall rejoice, and your bones ſhall flouriſh like an herb, and the hand of the Lord ſhall be known towards his ſervants, and his indignation towards his enemies; for, behold, the Lord will come with ſire and his chariot like a whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind, to render his anger with fury, and his rebuke with flames of ſire; for by ſire and by his ſword will the Lord plead with all fleſh, and the ſlain of the Lord ſhall be many; and it ſhall co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, paſs that I will gather all nations and tongues, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y ſhall come and ſee my glory; and this great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k will be done by the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting goſpel preached by an angel in heaven. (Rev. xiv. 6.) And I ſaw another angel fly in the midſt of heaven, having the everlaſting goſpel to preach unto them that dwell on the earth, and to every nation, kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and tongue, and people; and we ſee the glorious work that was wrought in the ſeventh verſe, ſaying, with a loud voice, fear God and give glory to him, for the hour of his judgment is come, and worſhip him that made heaven and earth, and the ſea, and the fountain of waters: this will make Babylon fall—8th verſe— And another angel followed, ſaying, Babylon is fallen, is fallen, that great city; becauſe ſhe made all nations drink of the wine of the wrath of her fornication; then comes the woman out of the wilderneſs. (Iſa. xii. 1.) And there appeared a great wonder in heaven, a woman cloathed with the ſun and the moon under her feet, and upon her head a crown of twelve ſtars.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="unknown:047760_0023_10248C9BD656EEE0"/>
The Churches hard travail will be ended, and the man child caught up to God's throne, which will be the riſing of the two witneſſes which has been ſlaying three years and an half, which has been almoſt twelve hundred and ſixty years ſince the church ſled into the wilderneſs from the face of the dragon that poured out a flood of waters out of his mouth after the woman, that he might cauſe her to be carried away of the flood. But when Michael ſhall deſtroy the devil's war, which is come down upon the ſeat of the beaſt, as in Rev. xii. 12. Woe to the inhabitants of the earth, and of the ſea, for the devil is come down unto you, having great wrath, becauſe he knoweth his time is but ſhort: and when the Dragon ſaw that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as caſt unto the earth, he perſecuted the woman that brought forth the man child. What dreadful perſecutions has ſhe received from the Popiſh nations, in killing thouſands of Chriſt's ſervants, and has executed wrath againſt the remnant of her ſeed, which ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p the commandments of God, and have the teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt. But ſoon we ſhall hear the Lord's voice, ſaying in heaven, Now is come ſalvation and ſtrength, and the kingdom of our God, and the power of his Chriſt, for the accuſer of our brethren is caſt down, which accuſed them before our God day and night; and they overcame him by the blood of the lamb, and by the word of their teſtimony; and they loved not their lives unto the death. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, rejoice ye heavens, and ye that dwell in them; then ſin and ſorrow ſhall ceaſe. (Rev. xxii. 3.) And there ſhall be no more curſe; but the throne of God and the Lamb ſhall be in it, and his ſervants ſhall ſerve him, not in a temple made with ſtones and wood, the work of men's hands; but in the new Jeruſalcm temple, which will be built up of Jew and Gentile, ſtones of grace, which Solomon's houſe typified under the law diſpenſation. This heavenly city is deſcribed in the 21ſt of Rev. deſcending out of heaven, which will be on this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arth as glorious ſtones moſt precious, and as clear as cryſtal, the glory and beauty of every ſaint of
<pb n="25" facs="unknown:047760_0024_10248C9E0B439738"/>that temple, having twelve gates and twelve angels, which are the twelve tribes of Iſrael, which will be brought into it from eaſt, weſt, north, and ſouth, as far as the ſun ſhines or men inhabit; for St. John ſaw no temple therein, for the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb are the temple of it, and the inhabitants is the bride, the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>'s wife, in an everlaſting marriage cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which will never be ſeparated, nor the union diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; but will endure for one thouſand years on earth, and then afterwards in Chriſt's preſence, face to face, an endleſs eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Queſtion aſked, and Reſolved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In what way will the people live when changed into Millennium Saints—will they labour and till the ground, and eat temporal food—and will they marry and be given in marriage, and children born, and mothers ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the pains of labour, and ſome die in child birth, and infants be caught from womb and breaſt?</p>
            <p>My opinion is, that when wars ſhall ceaſe, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall beat their ſwords into plough-ſhares, not to till the ground as formerly; for there will be no black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>hs blowing the bellows, nor beating on anvils; but ſhall receive the plough-ſhare of God's word into their ſtony hearts, which will plow up the fallow ground from ſin, and pruned from bearing thorns that pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a Redeemer's head. The earth ſhall have her Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath of reſt, the ſeventh part of time; and while the church eats temporal food, ſhe will be under affliction of pain and death; but when ſhe will eat nothing but the manna of Chriſt's body, ſhe will enjoy perfect health, and they ſhall marry as they did in the days of Norh, till the flood came and ſwept them all away. So they will while the flood of Antichriſt is ſweeping away ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners into perdition, when his reign ſhall end. They will no more dwell together man and wife, and will love all alike, with all the heart, and the whole temple will be built. Therefore, there will be no infants born after the top-ſtone is brought with ſhoutings, Grace, Grace. (Iſa. lxii. 5.) For as a young man marrieth a virgin, ſo ſhall thy ſons marry thee; and as the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom rejoiceth over the bride, ſo ſhall thy God rejoice
<pb n="26" facs="unknown:047760_0025_10248CA09097F490"/>over thee; for the Lord hath ſworn by his right hand, and by the arm of his ſtrength, ſurely no more will I give thy corn to be meat for thine enemies, and the ſtranger ſhall not drink thy wine; ſinners cannot be partakers of this bread and wine, without they are Chriſt's people; but his ſaints eat it, and they drink in the courts of holineſs. (Iſa. lxi. 11.) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as the earth bringeth forth her bud, and as the garden cauſeth the things that are ſown in it to ſpring forth, ſo the Lord God will cauſe righteouſneſs and praiſe to ſpring forth before all nations.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall ſhew forth of the pouring out of fifth and ſixth vials, and what will be the dreadful, and happy, events that ill enſue. (Rev. xvi. 10.) And the fifth angel poured out his vial upon the ſeat of the Beaſt, and his kingdom was full of darkneſs, and they gnawed their tongues for pain. There will be great commotions of war in this time, and diſmal calamities of death, when they will blaſpheme the God of heaven, becauſe of their ſores and pains, and repented not of their deeds: but when the ſixth angel poured out his vial on the river Euphrates, and the water was dried up; that is, the flood of perſecution is brought to an end. Then the way of the kings of the Eaſt will be prepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; then the glories of the goſpel will take the wings of the morning, and fly unto the uttermoſt parts of the earth. (Iſa. lx. 10.) And the ſons of ſtrangers ſhall build up thy walls, and their kings ſhall miniſter unto thee; and that men may bring unto thee the forces of the Gentiles; and that their kings may be brought; and kings ſhall be nurſing fathers, and queens nurſing mothers, and the church for the nation that will not ſerve thee, ſhall periſh. Yea, thoſe nations ſhall be utterly waſted. (Iſa. lix. 19.) So ſhall they fear the Lord from the weſt, and his glory from the riſing of the ſun, when the enemy ſhall come in like a flood, the ſpirit of the Lord ſhall lift up a ſtandard againſt him. (Song ii. 11, 12.) For ſo, the winter is paſt, the rain is over and gone; the flowers appear on the earth; the time of the ſinging of birds is come, and the voice of the turtle is heard in our land. The churches prayer, O
<pb n="27" facs="unknown:047760_0026_10248CA2415078B8"/>that my winter time-was ended; O that the reign of the Beaſt was over, that I might experience the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the roſe of Sharon in my ſoul. O what glory it will be when wretched ſinners will bloom the flowers of glory; no more to have wrinkled faces, nor cold win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hearts. Then they will ſing the ſong of Moſes and the Lamb. (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> xi. 17.) Saying, we give thee thanks, O Lord God Almighty, which art, and waſt, and art to come; becauſe thou haſt taken to thee thy great power, and haſt reigned: and when the ſecond woe is paſt, and when, behold, the third woe cemeth quickly; then the 7th angel ſounded, and there were great voices in heaven, ſaying, The kingdoms of this world are become the kingdoms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall reign for ever and ever. He which teſtifieth theſe things, ſaith, Surely, I come quickly—Amen. Even ſo, come Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. CORREY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>ON MY PAST LIFE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>HOUSE and land was my paternal lot;</l>
               <l>But ſin and extravagance made me leave my cot.</l>
               <l>When my fields grew in plenty of wheat and corn,</l>
               <l>I like the lark hail'd the ſprightly morn.</l>
               <l>My wife's ſons and daughters, once the comfort of my age,</l>
               <l>Has now left the world's wide buſy ſtage;</l>
               <l>And I twelve years have travel'd from my native home,</l>
               <l>And doom'd in ſcanty poverty to roam:</l>
               <l>And now I am miſerably poor and old,</l>
               <l>Keen winds I've ſuffer'd, hunger, heat and cold,</l>
               <l>And ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> great afflictions. I muſt not repine—</l>
               <l>Be not ſeeure—your lot may be like mine.</l>
               <l>I am a man of ſorrow, grief and miſery:</l>
               <l>We ne'er were born here happineſs for to ſee.</l>
               <l>Was I to tell you the ſource of all my grief,</l>
               <l>Sure you would pray for my relief.</l>
               <l>Still as through life's meandering path I ſtray,</l>
               <l>Lord be the ſweet companion of my way,</l>
               <l>And bring me ſafely to thy bleſt abode,</l>
               <l>Of light and life, and happineſs in God.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="28" facs="unknown:047760_0027_10248CA53005BB50"/>
               <l>Religion's ſacred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Unerring points the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Where happineſs for ever ſhines,</l>
               <l>With unpolluted ray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My fleecy flocks with wool kept me warm,</l>
               <l>And cloth'd my body from the winter ſtorm.</l>
               <l>My cows bags full of milk brought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>door,</l>
               <l>And every day in plenty gave me more.</l>
               <l>Bacon and beef was my daily food;</l>
               <l>The Lord that gave; the Lord is good.</l>
               <l>My negroes toil'd and made me bread,</l>
               <l>The ſinful crime I felt with awful dread;</l>
               <l>I trampled on the mercies of my God,</l>
               <l>And for my ſins, ſmote me with his rod,</l>
               <l>And made me my tranſgreſſions for to ſee,</l>
               <l>And by his free grace and mercy ſet me free.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>[Rom. vii. 9.—For I was alive without the law once, but when the commandment came, ſin revived, and I died.]</p>
            <lg>
               <l>I four years was condemned for my ſin,</l>
               <l>But I, like the dove, my Noah took me in.</l>
               <l>Now I am in his ark from danger free,</l>
               <l>Which will land me on eternity.</l>
               <l>Six months I travel'd in dark deſpair,</l>
               <l>The diſmal burden of temptation for to bear—</l>
               <l>To hang myſelf—to cut my children's throats—</l>
               <l>To drown myſelf—to fall out of boats—</l>
               <l>To burn a wheat field—to deſtroy man's bread—</l>
               <l>Then be damn'd, with wilful curſes on my head—</l>
               <l>To open a mill-dam, and let the water go—</l>
               <l>I might not drown myſelf in eternal woe.</l>
               <l>I went to Philadelphia to be confin'd, that I might not kill my ſon;</l>
               <l>I felt I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as a wretched ſoul undone.</l>
               <l>I fear'd on earth I ſhould not long dwell,</l>
               <l>But ſink down into a diſmal hell:</l>
               <l>Tempted to fall headlong down into wells,</l>
               <l>Terrified by the ringing of court bells.</l>
               <l>I fear'd the priſon and the court of men,</l>
               <l>I ſhould be condemn'd for murder and hang'd; then</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="unknown:047760_0028_10248E2C40A62340"/>
I ran through ſwamps, like a dog mad,</l>
               <l>Driven with horror, my heart ſo bad.</l>
               <l>Lying in the woods, ſatan by my ſide,</l>
               <l>My heart full of curſed pride.</l>
               <l>My wretched ſoul, how<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>guilty and forlorn,</l>
               <l>Wiſhing I was never born,</l>
               <l>To ſuffer ſuch dreadful ſcenes of woe,</l>
               <l>I did not know what to do or where to go.</l>
               <l>The rainy ſtorms and thunders in the ſkies,</l>
               <l>The lightning I fear'd would burn out my eyes,</l>
               <l>And ſend my ſoul into burning fire,</l>
               <l>To be tormented, never to expire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now for a ſong of grateful praiſe,</l>
               <l>With all his ſaints I'll join to raiſe.</l>
               <l>Who pluck'd me from the jaws of hell?</l>
               <l>My JESUS has done all things well.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>[Prov. XXV. 14.—Whoſo boaſteth himſelf of a falſe gift, is like wind and clouds without rain.]</p>
            <lg>
               <l>When infidelity abounds, I employ my pen,</l>
               <l>To ſet forth the characters of deluded men.</l>
               <l>The infidelian PAINE, the Deiſt man,</l>
               <l>Who has written againſt the Goſpel Plan;</l>
               <l>The Arians and Socinians, that deſpiſe the Son of God,</l>
               <l>Set at naught a Redeemer's blood;</l>
               <l>Truſting on a righteouſneſs of their own,</l>
               <l>Rejecting the ſacrifice who did atone.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>[The wicked ſhall be turned into hell, and all nations that forget God. Pſ. xvi. 17.]</p>
            <lg>
               <l>The Murrianites in no hell believe,</l>
               <l>But all a full redemption ſhall receive.</l>
               <l>WINCHESTER the Univerſalian has left the goſpel way,</l>
               <l>Preaching falſe to lead the blind aſtray.</l>
               <l>WORTHLARIAN and COXTERIAN has left the Baptiſt claſs,</l>
               <l>And gone the way of Balaam that ſmote his aſs;</l>
               <l>Believing all that ſinn'd by Adam's fall,</l>
               <l>Will be redeem'd from hell's miſery and thrall.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>[Ezek. xiii. 14.—O Iſrael! thy prophets are like foxes in the deſarts—xxxiv. 3—Woe be to the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds that feed themſelves—Should not the ſhepherds feed the flocks? Ye eat the fat, and ye cloathe you with
<pb n="30" facs="unknown:047760_0029_10248CA767E93960"/>the wool; ye kill them that are fed, but ye feed not the flock. The diſeaſed ye have not ſtrengthened, neither have ye healed that which is ſick, neither have bound up that which was broken, neither have you brought again that which was driven away, neither have ye ſought that which was loſt, but with force and cruelty ye have ruled them.—Song of Solomon ii. 15.— Take us the foxes, the little foxes that ſpoil the vines, for our vines have tender grapes.]</p>
            <lg>
               <l>You blind ſhepherds, that deſtroy men's ſouls,</l>
               <l>Like tinkers of great noiſe to ſtop old holes.</l>
               <l>Seek a pardon from the King Gibba's altar;</l>
               <l>You have riſen againſt his kingdom, muſt have a halter;</l>
               <l>Like Haman plotted that the Jews might die,</l>
               <l>Was hung on a gallows fifty cubits high.</l>
               <l>Hiram ran veſſels in the clayey ground,</l>
               <l>Your metal is filthy droſs, and not the goſpel ſound;</l>
               <l>It will not fit the Scripture-would,</l>
               <l>Nor join together, neither being hot nor cold.</l>
               <l>Don't add nor diminiſh from the word of God.</l>
               <l>Leſt you feel his avenging rod.</l>
               <l>You eat the fat, and don't feed the ſheep,</l>
               <l>You have no ſeed ſown and cannot reap.</l>
               <l>Unbutton, and open your ſleeping eyes,</l>
               <l>Leſt you never ſee a God above the ſkies:</l>
               <l>There is danger, warning take,</l>
               <l>Eſcape eternal death, a burning lake.</l>
               <l>I am in earneſt—be ſo too—</l>
               <l>I am a Gentile—you are like a harden'd Jew—</l>
               <l>You ſtarve the flock, and love the flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Foxes that ſpoil the vines and kill the geeſe—</l>
               <l>You rob hen-rooſts, and kill the pigs,</l>
               <l>The devil's tories, and not true whigs;</l>
               <l>Serpents in a thorn hedge worſe than briers,</l>
               <l>The cruel Prieſts of Monks and Friars,</l>
               <l>Having not a true goſpel hope,</l>
               <l>Get their commiſſions from the Pope;</l>
               <l>By doing penance, believe their ſins are forgiven,</l>
               <l>And think they are going their way to heaven.</l>
               <l>If they go down to hell in ſin's dirt,</l>
               <l>You can't put on you there a hair ſhirt—</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="unknown:047760_0030_10248CA9AC52E0C8"/>
No pardon's diſpens'd to rebels there—</l>
               <l>No, not for any that curſe and ſwear;</l>
               <l>No, not for thieves, no, not for liars;</l>
               <l>No, not for Roman Prieſts, nor Friars:</l>
               <l>But with the rebel crew and helliſh band,</l>
               <l>Before God, rais'd from death and hell, to ſtand,</l>
               <l>With grim horrors falling on your guilty head,</l>
               <l>Before his bar your final ſentence dread,</l>
               <l>Judg'd down to dwell in a burning lake,</l>
               <l>Curſing your helliſh chains, your diſmal ſtate.</l>
               <l>Falſe teachers encourage ſin;</l>
               <l>It is only free grace that takes finners in—</l>
               <l>Into Noah's ark by hammer, blows and pin,</l>
               <l>Built up by grace, new lives of faith begin:</l>
               <l>But Antichriſt brought on the flood—</l>
               <l>The waters on earth fifteen cubits ſtood:</l>
               <l>So now the flooth of Antichriſt has cover'd the land,</l>
               <l>I believe his end is near at hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There is a people call'd the Dancing Quakers,</l>
               <l>They twiſt and turn cruel leg-ſhakers;</l>
               <l>They ſtrip off to ſhift and ſhirt when hot,</l>
               <l>Black and naſty as a ſlut's pot;</l>
               <l>They raiſe a whirling in their tails,</l>
               <l>Worſe than an old ſhip at ſea without ſails.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Juzabel in a coffin put a live man,</l>
               <l>A Captain ſmote it with his ſword, out he ran;</l>
               <l>Men and guns around he would not lie;</l>
               <l>Receiv'd a fright, death ſeem'd ſo nigh:</l>
               <l>So cowards can's ſtand a goſpel-fight,</l>
               <l>Becauſe of ſin of nature's night.</l>
               <l>Such deluders are like Tom Paine,</l>
               <l>And will be till the Beaſt is ſlain.</l>
               <l>O for a glorious Millennium Day,</l>
               <l>To make ſuch deceivers ſing and pray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I have painted the wickedneſs of dark nature,</l>
               <l>Of proud and haughty hearts high in ſtature;</l>
               <l>Like a church-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll, ball, and ſteeple,</l>
               <l>Fine Prieſts in pulpit, in pews the people,</l>
               <l>Only makes a poiſe, calls to the worſhip place,</l>
               <l>With wicked hearts, of prim'd looks of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="unknown:047760_0031_10248CABF1CFE460"/>
At looking-glaſſes on Sunday morning trimming,</l>
               <l>Naſty as ſnakes in mud-bog ſwimming.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Take warning! it is your wickedneſs I do relate,</l>
               <l>Of the city of Philadelphia ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some years ago I remember well,</l>
               <l>A judgment plague, a ſtink inſtead of ſweet ſmell,</l>
               <l>It ſtopt from play-houſe, but again to it you went,</l>
               <l>And regarded not the judgment God had ſent;</l>
               <l>A greater one may be hanging over head,</l>
               <l>Of eternal death that will ſtrike you dead.</l>
               <l>Many families went out of town and left the place;</l>
               <l>Becauſe you had deſpis'd God's grace.</l>
               <l>With powder'd heads, a gaudy ſhow,</l>
               <l>With tinkling feet to church doth go;</l>
               <l>With jeſting tales of gallant life,</l>
               <l>Spending your days in wicked ſtrife.</l>
               <l>Thouſands the Lord's ſword has cut down,</l>
               <l>In mould'ring graves, no more in town.</l>
               <l>Some ſicken and die at dancing ball,</l>
               <l>No more nimble footed at cloven-foot's hall?</l>
               <l>Her vital tuning-ſtrings are broke,</l>
               <l>That twine the heart, receives a ſtroke,</l>
               <l>And gone away on Apollion's hump'd back,</l>
               <l>And left behind their merry fidler Jack.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye Georgic merchants, your horrid negro trade,</l>
               <l>You oppreſs the creatures God has made;</l>
               <l>Like I ſhmaelites 20 ſilver pieces gave t'increaſe their ſtore,</l>
               <l>Traitor Judas ſold Chriſt for ten pieces more.</l>
               <l>You laviſh gold in bag and wrap it up,</l>
               <l>Drunkards love their bottle, and drink a large ſup.</l>
               <l>You that have negroes, Wills, and Jacks,</l>
               <l>Feed their bellies and cloath their backs;</l>
               <l>Clothe their bodies from the winter ſtorm,</l>
               <l>They plough your ground and plant your corn.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>[What God requires of thee, O man, is do juſtice, ſeek peace and love mercy, to walk humbly with thy God.]</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Young fondlings ſleeping in Delilah's lap,</l>
               <l>Is worſe than wolves in a ſteel trap;</l>
               <l>Like Sampſon's wiſhes, the Philiſtines put out his eyes,</l>
               <l>He that loves her charms for ever dies;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="unknown:047760_0032_10248E1D8E0FB758"/>
Her ways lead down to the gates of hell,</l>
               <l>In the dark caverns forever dwell;</l>
               <l>Her wicked heart as black as cripple mud,</l>
               <l>And he is like a dull horſe that has the ſtud,</l>
               <l>That muſt have the ſpur and whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>She giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ip;</l>
               <l>He falls on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> is deck'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> her roling eyes combine;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> barn with threſhing-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ail,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> grimſeſs ribband trail.</l>
               <l>Some for French cuts, of Turks pride, and plaited hair,</l>
               <l>Away they go to galantine fair.</l>
               <l>Some for horn-pipe, ſome for bag-pipe tone;</l>
               <l>Some chufe pound cakes, and ſome Indian pone;</l>
               <l>Some chufe white, ſome brown, ſome take black,</l>
               <l>Some take any, ſo they get a pleaſing ſnack;</l>
               <l>Some at Blue-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, their heads white with cockle,</l>
               <l>Some drinking wine out of glaſſes and bottle;</l>
               <l>Some cry, Landlord! what to pay? dollars ringing,</l>
               <l>Some dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nk f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt aſleep, others ſinging;</l>
               <l>Some curſing and ſome ſwearing,</l>
               <l>Some fighting with bloody noſes, hair tearing—</l>
               <l>Away they get ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and are raving mad,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they went there on pidda-pad.</l>
               <l>Some follow the Prieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, bell under tail ringing,</l>
               <l>Between heaven and hell, of ſins, care-rop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſwinging.</l>
               <l>Hate your pride of Antichriſt and folly,</l>
               <l>Your inticing madam dames of beads, and Polly</l>
               <l>Mind your labouring buſineſs with bended back,</l>
               <l>Miſs Flimſey is more weighty than a pedlar's pack;</l>
               <l>Her deluding arts are ſharper than pointed pins;</l>
               <l>He that runs after her gets ſtinking ſore ſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>And makes them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſick as a dog return'd to his vomit;</l>
               <l>Such worſhip idols, and believe in Mahomet.</l>
               <l>Some hold in hand the ſnuff box at tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ble chats,</l>
               <l>As blind and ſtupid as ſeven ſleeping bats.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This is the wickedneſs of the ten Kings,</l>
               <l>Mammon their god, earth's nothing things;</l>
               <l>Theſe pleaſe their luſts for a night's play,</l>
               <l>Away they trudge home, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>rdly ſee the way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="unknown:047760_0033_10248E1FCB46FE50"/>
So Tom's light breeches and Miſs's ruffled chintz trudge together,</l>
               <l>But he muſt leave his light boots, and ſhe her ſine ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of leath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>And be dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and eyes</l>
               <l>No more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ah <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>No more to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> black <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>He that eats of her dainties gets <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Therefore eſcape her ratling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Or elſe you muſt eat in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſcorpion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>In every mountain and under green trees has pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d the harlot.</l>
               <l>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ck'd with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and cloth'd with ſcarlot.</l>
               <l>Why tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy way to feel earth's love,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eek only the Lord that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and reigns above.</l>
               <l>Bound up right with w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſale <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtays,</l>
               <l>Has taught the wicked o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s thy ways.</l>
               <l>Why gaddeſt ſo much ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> to charge thy way?</l>
               <l>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will make you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed in a coming day.</l>
               <l>My people has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> me, and committed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>They deſpiſe God and worſhip devils.</l>
               <l>Be aſtoniſhed O heavens at this!—</l>
               <l>O! ſinners be horribly afraid of the ſerpent's kiſs;</l>
               <l>For though you waſh with nitre and much ſoap.</l>
               <l>You commit lewdneſs like Francis Pope;</l>
               <l>And ſay'ſt I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot polluted, nor go the way of Bala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</l>
               <l>There's too many ſuch good people in the town of Salem</l>
               <l>See thy way in chimp-foot valley, what haſt thou done?</l>
               <l>Your days are near at end, your thread of life almoſtſpun,</l>
               <l>Your religion is nothing but founding braſs,</l>
               <l>Snuffing in the wind like a wild aſs:</l>
               <l>And as the thief is aſham'd when he is found,</l>
               <l>Taken away to priſon, and within the iron grates is bound,</l>
               <l>To meet the judge, a greater one than is at Dover town;</l>
               <l>When the books will be open'd and you judg'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n</l>
               <l>Into r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lling waves, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>per than Philadelphia ferry,</l>
               <l>To traverse hell ſwifter than a dromedary</l>
               <l>Cruſts and carrion is the food of ravenous dogs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Like bellow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> full-frogs in ſpatter dock bogs.</l>
               <l>But good fiſh are from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he river <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by ſeine,</l>
               <l>So true Chriſtians are drawn from hell and pain.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="unknown:047760_0034_10248E21EF0D0F28"/>
Pride rides in coaches, in grandeur, fame and noiſe</l>
               <l>Of cracking whips, poſtilions, and waiting boys,</l>
               <l>With window'd glaſs to keep them from the ſun;</l>
               <l>If the devil is your driver, you will be undone.</l>
               <l>Away out of town to take the air and pleaſure;</l>
               <l>Perhaps poor creatures are without the richeſt treaſure;</l>
               <l>Without the King's chariot of love that is paved ſo fine,</l>
               <l>They that ride in that, how beautiful they ſhine.</l>
               <l>The ſun ſhines in at the window glaſs,</l>
               <l>The man's glory that rode in Jeruſalem upon an aſs.—</l>
               <l>The huntſman in the morning blows his horn,</l>
               <l>Away the thief runs from cribs of corn;</l>
               <l>He cries hark, plunder, on the foxes drag.</l>
               <l>The miſer runs after gold to ſill his bag.</l>
               <l>Hark! a way in the cover plunder,</l>
               <l>Hark! ſinner, don't you hear law thunder.</l>
               <l>Hark! Drag well, how the valleys ring,</l>
               <l>Hear. ſinner, the voice of Iſrael<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s king.</l>
               <l>Some hunters ſeparate men and wives aſunder,</l>
               <l>O! what a diſmal nights blunder!—</l>
               <l>Some go a hunting, and ſome a gunning,</l>
               <l>And leave their drollys in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> running.</l>
               <l>Some don't kill meat, and will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pork,</l>
               <l>There are ſome nice taſting folks in the town of York.</l>
               <l>Some get bound to pillory to hear cow-ſkin whips,</l>
               <l>Some wretched men curſe and damn aboard of ſhips.</l>
               <l>He that has a ſmoky houſe and a ſcolding wife,</l>
               <l>Lives a very diſtreſs'd life,</l>
               <l>And muſt keep her with hats, fans, and turban ſhawls,</l>
               <l>Still ſhe is ill-natur'd, how loud ſhe bawls.</l>
               <l>With flounce, muſts, camel's hair and Perſian meeds,</l>
               <l>Pick the ſheets with their abominable deeds.</l>
               <l>The poor Indian ſaid, when the old man had ger'd his ſide,</l>
               <l>How do you do broder? but the other ſkinn'd his hide.</l>
               <l>So ſinners that will not fear God, nor death dread,</l>
               <l>Satan will make their wicked ſouls his drum head.</l>
               <l>There are many falſe prophets in this latter day,</l>
               <l>Teaching ſinners down to hell the broad way:</l>
               <l>Blind leading the blind, in this night as dark as pitch;</l>
               <l>All ſuch dehiders muſt fall into the ditch:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="unknown:047760_0035_10248E2945E24578"/>
For they are as dry and hard as cow ſkin whips.</l>
               <l>Apes and peaco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, with gold and ſilver in Hirare's ſhips,</l>
               <l>Falſe profeſſors join'd to churches, neither ſilver nor true gold,</l>
               <l>Self-righteous phariſees, that are not of Chriſt's fold;</l>
               <l>Such cry from morning to evening, O Baal! O Baal!</l>
               <l>Such a god never fill'd the milk maid's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>il.</l>
               <l>They fail on the altar, and cut themſelves with knives.</l>
               <l>Many righteous men have Baalim wives,</l>
               <l>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid to Job, why doſt thou retain thy integrity: curſe God and die,</l>
               <l>Many ſuch are in hell, and muſt for ever lie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>IT is a great bleſſing to have a loving wife;</l>
               <l>But ſome croſs huſbands lead them a wretched life,</l>
               <l>Being as tough and crooked as any limb in woods,</l>
               <l>Such have a naſty piece of houſhold goods;</l>
               <l>Being fill'd with wickedneſs, pride, and ſlander,</l>
               <l>And beats her worſe than wings of fighting ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opping gander.</l>
               <l>I don't repreve you for living in houſes of 2 or 3 ſtory,</l>
               <l>But becauſe you d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> give God the glory.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mers man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> their ground,</l>
               <l>And the wretched without the goſpel ſound.</l>
               <l>Their beaſts draw the burden, a heavy load,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re his croſs, and ſinners deſpiſe his blood.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>well, and end my verſe and thyme,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will employ my thoughts about millennium time.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> how friends and foes are dropping down dead be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> you, and this you have ſeen for a long time, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rning to prepare for death. O let the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forbearance of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead you to repentance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>de you to fly ſpeedily to Chriſt for refuge and prote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wrath. Conſider how terrible death will be if it meets you in an unprepared ſtate, in a Chriſtleſs condition. What a fearful change it will be to be taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om earth to hell, where the worm of a guilty conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will never die, nor be at an end, nor the fire of God's indignation never will be quenched; therefore, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, and give glory to his name, and live forever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
