<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>So shorte a catechisme that whosoeuer cannot,  or wil not learne, are not in any wise to be admitted to the Lords Supper / Edward Fenton.</title>
            <author>Fenton, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-03">2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00652</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10787.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4674</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23727075</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23727075</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26836</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00652)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26836)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1832:52)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>So shorte a catechisme that whosoeuer cannot,  or wil not learne, are not in any wise to be admitted to the Lords Supper / Edward Fenton.</title>
                  <author>Fenton, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Dawson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Catechisms --  English.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26836:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26836:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>So shorte a Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisme, that whosoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer cannot, or wil not learne, are not in any wise to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Lords supper.</p>
            <p>Edward Fenton.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Dawson. 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26836:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26836:2"/>
            <head>So short a Catechisme that whosoeuer cannot or will not learne, are not in any wise to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Lords supper.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho made thee?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answere.</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 44.2. <hi>Psal.</hi> 13.913 14.15.</note> God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He is <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1 <hi>iere.</hi> 32.18 19.</note> Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.4.5 <hi>isa.</hi> 44.24. <hi>Iere.</hi> 16.23. <hi>prou</hi> 21.30.31.</note> maker and <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12. <hi>ioshua</hi> 22.5</note> gouernour of all things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Wherefore did he make thee?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To serue him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How oughtest thou to serue him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.32. <hi>psal.</hi> 119.4</note> As he hath appointed in his lawes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20 <hi>deut.</hi> 6.57.</note> God spake all these wordes, and said, Thou shalt haue none other Gods before me, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Canst thou fulfill all these Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes without breaking anie one of them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, though I doe all that I can, yet I breake them euery daye, in <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 15 19</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:26836:3"/>
thought worde and deede.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 18.19</note>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What punishment is there appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the breach of these commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26. <hi>mat.</hi> 25.41.</note> The curse of God, which is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall destruction both of bodie and soule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> By what meanes then shalt thou escape this punishment?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. <hi>col.</hi> 2.14.15.</note> Onely by Iesus Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is Iesus Christ?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He is the <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.5 <hi>heb.</hi> 1.23.</note> eternall sonne of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What hath he done for thee?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Hee <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8. <hi>heb.</hi> 5.7.8.9</note> suffered the tormentes of death for me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Christ Iesus was God, and how then could he die?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Christ Iesus was both <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5.</note> God and <note n="o" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. 1. <hi>phil.</hi> 2.6.7.</note> man, and in that hee was God, hee could not die: but being man, hee died <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24.</note> for my sinnes, and rose againe to make me righteous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Are all men then saued by his death</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, none are saued, <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.18 36. <hi>acts.</hi> 13 48.</note> but such as lay hold on him by a liuely faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is a liuely faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A liuely faith is a <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.12 <hi>col.</hi> 2.5.7. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3.17.</note> full perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my <hi>s</hi> heart, grounded vppon the
<pb facs="tcp:26836:3"/>
promises of GOD:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.18 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>heb.</hi> 11.11</note> that whatsoeuer Christ hath done for the saluation of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he hath done it as well for mee as for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How commest thou by this faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The holy Ghost doth worke it <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 19.14. <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.45.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in my heart, by the outwarde <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>14.17. <hi>acts</hi> 11.14.</note> preaching of his worde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How is this faith increased &amp; made strong in vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">2. <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.3 <hi>prou.</hi> 4.18</note> By hearing the same worde prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and vsing the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What be Sacraments?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Sacraments be outward <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. <hi>exod.</hi> 12.3.4</note> signes ordeined of God, and are left as <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. 1. <hi>cor.</hi> 10.1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>17.</note> seales and pledges of those benefits of our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation which wee receiue in Christ to strengthen our faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How many Sacraments be there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two, <note n="b" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>1.2.3.4.</note> Baptisme and the Lordes supper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What profite hast thou by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I beleeue that by Baptisme my <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.38.</note> sinnes are forgiuen me: for as the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth wash the filthe of my body: so I beleeue that the <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.7 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> bloud of Christ being
<pb facs="tcp:26836:4"/>
sprinckled vpon my soule by the <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22 <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9.</note> hande of faith, doeth washe mee from all my sinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What profit hast thou by the vse of the Lordes supper?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As I receiue the <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.29.27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23.24 25.</note> bread and wine into my body to become wholy mine: so I beleeue that my soule receiueth with all Christ Iesus with <note n="g" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30 2. <hi>cor.</hi> 5.21</note> his death and righteousnesse to the <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.1. <hi>ephe.</hi> 1.13.</note> sealing vp of my euerlasting saluation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Seeing that they which receiue these mysteries vnworthily, eate and drinke their owne condemnation: how oughtest thou to prepare thy selfe to the right receiuing of them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> First I muste <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13.21. <hi>Thes.</hi> 30 1. <hi>cor.</hi> 16.8. <hi>Mat</hi> 26.15 2. <hi>Cor</hi> 9.70</note> examine my selfe whether I <hi>k</hi> stande strongly in the true faith of Iesus Christ or no.</p>
            <p>Secondly, whether I find my heart <hi>l</hi> inwardly greeued for my sinnes with an <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Psa.</hi> 511, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.2.4.</note> hatred and lothing of the same.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if any offence bee betwixt others and mee, that I <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14.</note> reconcile my selfe vnto them, and <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.22 <hi>colos.</hi> 3.12.13.</note> forgiue them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as Christ hath forgiuen me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Is not praye a speciall meanes to
<pb facs="tcp:26836:4"/>
increase our faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea it is <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4.29.31. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.51.</note> a speciall helpe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How oughtest thou then to pray?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Onely to God in the name of Iesus Christ.<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 19 23. <hi>Iames.</hi> 15</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What forme of prayer vsest thou most?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That which the<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.2.</note> Lorde Iesus taught his Apostles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is that?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Our father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Howe vnderstandest thou this prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This prayer conteyneth sixe peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: whereof the first three are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted onely to Gods glorie: the other three belong vnto vs, wherein wee aske things necessarie both for soule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <p>OPen our eyes (O Lorde) that we may see the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derous things of thy lawe: that by them as by a glasse we may see our owne weaknesse, and by our weaknes our wickednesse, and by them both our accursednesse: then
<pb facs="tcp:26836:5"/>
cause thy sweete comforts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solations conteined in thy Gospel, to shine into our soules, by a true and a liuely faith in Christ Iesus: beseeching thee that our drie and stonie hearts, may by the sweete dewes &amp; showers of thy heauenly spirite, be so moiste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; softned, that as good ground they may euer bee yeelding foorth good fruite to the glorifying of thy name, to the suppressing of sinne, and increasing of vertue, through Christ our Sauiour. Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26836:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26836:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
