<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plaine demonstration of the vnlawful succession of the now emperour Ferdinand the Second, because of the incestuous marriage of his parents Translated out of the Latine printed copie.</title>
            <author>French Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00680</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115032</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850252</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850252</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15441</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00680)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15441)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plaine demonstration of the vnlawful succession of the now emperour Ferdinand the Second, because of the incestuous marriage of his parents Translated out of the Latine printed copie.</title>
                  <author>French Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Stansby for N. Butter],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at the Hage [i.e. London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. D. C. XX [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual place of publication and printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>In 1621? Butter and Stansby were punished for printing this; see Greg, Companion pp. 209-211; the documents are undated and possibly miscalandared in Cal. S.P.D. since the punishemnts seem to have occurred in early 1621; the proclamation referred to by Stansby may be STC 8649. F.S. Ferguson identified other pamphlets on the Bohemian question from the same press, which he thought might be that of W. Jones: STC 3210, 3214, 3215, 10810, 11350, 11351, 11356; 11349 may belong in this group also--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ferdinand --  II, --  Holy Roman Emperor, 1578-1637.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15441:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15441:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PLAINE DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONSTRATION OF THE VNLAWFVL SVCCESSI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON OF THE NOW EMPEROVR <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second, becauſe of the inceſtuous Marriage of his Parents. <hi>Tranſlated out of the Latine printed Copie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at the <hi>Hage. M. D. C. XX.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15441:2"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>Vncle. But, doubtleſſe, they will ſay, that this was with the Diſpenſation, as they terme it, of the Pope Gods Vicar vpon Earth, and therefore in no wiſe to be counted an inceſtuous Marriage. We know it was permitted and that by the Pope, but by what right or authoritie wee ſee not. For ſuppoſe hee bee neuer ſo the Vicar of God, (although they ſhall neuer bee able to proue it, neither from the holy Scriptures, nor authoritie of the Fathers;) yet were it not lawfull for him to doe all things as hee liſt at his pleaſure. For who ſo doth is nothing leſſe then a Vicar, whoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie it is, to frame himſelfe after the mind of his Lord, and to ſee his commands to bee put in execution, and not at his pleaſue, either to change them, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe new.</p>
            <p>God, Leuit. 18. 12. 13. doth expreſly and ſimply forbid Marriage within the third Degree: but the Pope permits this to whom he liſteth. Now if he can doe it lawfully, then he hath right either of himſelfe, or from God: but not of himſelfe, becauſe hee is a Vicar, all whoſe authority depends vpon ſome other not from God, from whoſe nature it is moſt free not to contradict himſelf: now he ſhould contradict him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, if hee ſhould permit that which hee hath moſt ſtraightly forbidden, yea, and that with threatning of death; we ſpeake of morall Precepts, and thoſe which of themſelues are neceſſary to obtayning of eternall Life. Wherefore, ſith the Pope hath this power nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of himſelfe nor from God, it is cleerer then the noone day, that he doth it by no right at all. This
<pb facs="tcp:15441:2"/>
many of the Papiſt them ſelues haue ſeene, they ſaw it, I ſay, &amp; haue profeſſed the ſame: neither need wee to ſeeke any further examples: we haue them at hand. <hi>Iohn Fox</hi> in his Booke of Martyrs, or Engliſh Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Hiſtorie, <hi>pag.</hi> 957, <hi>col.</hi> 2. doth tell vs that the Mariage of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight with <hi>Catharina</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Arthurs</hi> Widow, though permitted by the Pope, was proued to bee ſimply vnlawfull, and not to bee diſpenſed with, by the Theologicall faculties at the leaſt of tenne Vniuerſities; to wit, of Orleans, Paris, Tholous, Erford, Angiew, Bononie, Padua, Oxford, Cambridge. And that the determinations of all theſe faculties, together with the iudgements of other moſt learned, both Diuines and Doctors, not onely of the Ciuill, but of the Canon Law, alſo contayned in one Volume were publiſhed in the yeare 1532. or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about. And that thereupon preſently followed the Diuorce and new Mariage of the King. The ſame is auouched by <hi>Nicholas Sanders</hi> a moſt bitter Papiſt, in his firſt Book of the Engliſh Schiſme, <hi>p.</hi> 58. where he ſaith thus: The King partly ſent certaine men to Pope <hi>Clement,</hi> to vndertake at Rome the cauſe of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce, (amongſt whom was <hi>Thomas Cranmer,</hi> who after was made Archbiſhop of Canterbury) partly he ſought out through all the Kingdome of France, Diuines and Lawyers, which vnder their hands and Seales, affirme that his Mariage with the ſaid <hi>Cathari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> could not poſſible ſtand. And <hi>pag.</hi> 61. This infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (for ſo that foule-mouthed Fellow tearmes it) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſpred) not onely the Vniuerſitie of Paris, Orleans,
<pb facs="tcp:15441:3"/>
Angiew, Tholous, and Erford, but alſo Padua and Bononie: And <hi>p.</hi> 62. he complaines that Oxford and Cambridge adioyned themſelues to the foreſaid Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities. Lo heere we haue the Papiſts themſelues, as it were the guiltie perſons confeſſing: wee haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Popes Vaſſals, and his ſtout Champions, the iudgements of ſo many worthy men, &amp; of whole Vniuerſities; Amongſt which is euen Bononia it ſelfe vnder the Popes Iuriſdiction, which together with vs doe take this power from the Pope.</p>
            <p>Whereupon it is plaine enough, what wee are to thinke of this Marriage of Archduke <hi>Charles</hi> with <hi>Mary,</hi> though iudged to bee lawfull by the Popes Diſpenſation; as alſo concerning their Sonne <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> the Second, now Emperour: to wit, that hee is more then a Baſtard, borne of more then an Illegitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, yea of an execrable Mariage: and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither by the Law of God or man he may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe by Inheritance, ſo much as one foote of Land, See ye Princes of Germany (the honour and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Mankinde) that you haue committed the Chriſtian World which is to be gouerned by Lawes, to him, to whom God hath not vouchſafed a beeing in this World, but contrary to all Lawes.</p>
            <p>Behold ye noble, yea, and meane perſons too, that ye are oppreſſed with his tyranny, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his very Birth hath excluded out of the ſociety of honeſt men. Wey well, ye Souldiers, yee valiant hearts, that you ſpend your liues for the honour and dignity of him whom Nature hath not granted to bee borne, but with the
<pb facs="tcp:15441:3"/>
greateſt diſgrace. Goe to them: rather deliuer your Country the moſt flouriſhing Empire of the World, from this ignominie. Onely bee yee couragious, and the Diuine fauour ſhall be with you. For the Lord is a iealous God which puniſheth the ſinnes of Parents vpon their Children, vnto the third and fourth Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration: And he doth ſo accurſe inceſtuous luſts, that for them, he hath ſubuerted and vtterly defaced the greateſt Cities, whole Countries and Nations: as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe doth witneſſe, Leuit. 18. of the Cananites: ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, withall theſe things (now he ſpeaks of Inceſts) are theſe Nations polluted, which I caſt out before your face. For becauſe the Land is polluted, I will puniſh the iniquitie of it therein, the Earth doth vomit out the Inhabitants. The ſame God (no doubt) in his due time will powre out the Cup of his Wrath vpon this man: and the rather, becauſe to the deteſtable wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Parents, he doth adde moſt horrible cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie, and the very Gouernment of <hi>Phalaris</hi> indeed, which the miſerable people of Auſtria haue felt, and ſtill (alas for wo) do feele, and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e by their iuſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, made knowne to the whole World. Vpon whom the Lord doth now ſeeme to take pitie, and to haue raiſed vp Captaines to tumble downe this Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from his Throne, and together with that whole Family infamous for their monſtrous crueltie, vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to root out, which we craue and beſeech the ſame. One God in three Perſons, ſpeedily to performe: from whom euen to you Readers alſo wee wiſh all good ſucceſſe. Fare ye well.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
