<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles agreed vpon and concluded between the victorious, excellent, high and mighty prince and lord, Frederick Henry, Prince of Orange, Count of Nassaw, &amp;c. on the one part, and the vanquished towne of S'hertogenbosh on the other side And also, how the towne, and the Pettler-Sconce was deliuered, on the fourth of September, into the hands of His said Excellence: and how his garrison entred into the said towne, there to keepe the walles and gates. Worthy of reading.</title>
            <title>Treaties, etc. 'S Hertogenbosh, 1629-09-13</title>
            <author>Frederick Henry, Prince of Orange, 1584-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01247</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11363</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102782</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838545</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838545</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2927</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01247)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2927)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 957:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles agreed vpon and concluded between the victorious, excellent, high and mighty prince and lord, Frederick Henry, Prince of Orange, Count of Nassaw, &amp;c. on the one part, and the vanquished towne of S'hertogenbosh on the other side And also, how the towne, and the Pettler-Sconce was deliuered, on the fourth of September, into the hands of His said Excellence: and how his garrison entred into the said towne, there to keepe the walles and gates. Worthy of reading.</title>
                  <title>Treaties, etc. 'S Hertogenbosh, 1629-09-13</title>
                  <author>Frederick Henry, Prince of Orange, 1584-1647.</author>
                  <author>'s-Hertogenbosch (Netherlands). Treaties, etc. Frederick Henry, Prince of Orange, 1629-09-13. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nicholas Bourne, and are to bee sold at his shop, at the south entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: D⁴ E² .</note>
                  <note>Printed as an addition to "A jornall of certaine principall passages in and before the towne of S'hertogenbosh" (STC 13248.4), but also apparently issued separately and, with gathering D in another setting, with STC 18507.203A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2927:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2927:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES
Agreed vpon and concluded <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
the victorious, excellent, high</hi>
and mighty Prince and Lord, FREDERICK
HENRY, Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Count of
<hi>Naſſaw,</hi> &amp;c. on the one part, and the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed
Towne of <hi>S' hertogenboſh</hi>
on the other ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And alſo,</hi>
How the Towne, and the Pettler-Sconce
was deliuered, on the fourth of <hi>September,
into the hands of His ſaid Excellence: and how</hi>
his Garriſon entred into the ſaid Towne,
there to keepe the Walles and Gates.
Worthy of reading.</p>
            <p>LONDON,
Printed for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and are to bee
ſold at his Shop, at the South entrance of the
Royall Exchange. 1629.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="truce">
            <pb facs="tcp:2927:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2927:2"/>
            <head>Articles agreed vpon, betweene
His Excellence the Prinee of Orange,
and the vanquiſhed Towne of S'Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togenboſh.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince that by the Command of the
Excellent, high, and mighty Prince
of <hi>Orange,</hi> the Towne of <hi>S'hertogen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſh</hi>
hath beene this great while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged,
and daily furiouſly aſſaulted
and battered; chiefly ſince that the
Gallery by the Vucthter gate hath
beene brought ouer the Ditch, whereby his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
endeuoured by all meanes to get the Halfe-moone
without the Vncthter gate, wherein they of
the Towne had all their truſt and confidence; To
which end, his Excellency had already blowne vp a
Mine. And although the Frenchmen hauing giuen an
Aſſault, and attempted vpon the Towne, they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
had beaten them backe, and forced them to retire,
yet the next day after, being betwixt Sunday and
Munday, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> hauing the Watch
there, haue alſo giuen an aſſault vpon the ſaid Halfe-moone,
and haue taken the ſame by force of Armes;
ſo that they within had no more Trenches or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes,
but onely the Walles, into which, by the
continuall battering of the Ordnance, was made ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2927:3"/>
great a breach, that two Waggons together might
well haue paſſed thorow it. And whereas his Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Excellence did for the laſt time ſummon them to
yeeld themſelues and warned the Gouernour, that
if he would not in good time hearken to a Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
that he ſhould take heede to himſelfe, and to all
them that were in the Towne, leſt they might come
in danger of their liues, becauſe his Excellence was
reſolued to aſſault and take the Towne by force, and
way of Armes. The ſaid ſummons cauſed not little
alteration and troubles among the Burgers and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
ſo that they ranne with great fury to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders
Houſe: But becauſe the Gouernour would
not hearken vnto their complaints, whereby the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
of the people did continually increaſe, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the Clergie with the Biſhop, were forced to
come forth themſelues, both to appeaſe the people,
&amp; to moue the Gouernor by their perſwaſions, telling
him, that there reſted no hope for them, of any helpe
or reliefe from abroad, and that within the Towne
there was an infinite number of ſicke and hurt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
and beſides alſo, that they were altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouided
of warlike Amunition, to make ſufficient
reſiſtance againſt the Forces of the Prince: ſo that
they thought it more neceſſary to parley, and make a
Compoſition with the Prince, then to hazzard and
endanger all their liues.</p>
            <p>By this perſwaſion and requeſt the Gouernour was
induced and content to demand of His Excellence
a ceſſation of Armes for three daies, that in the mean
while, there might bee made ſome good agreement
and compoſition on both ſides. Therefore on the 11.
<hi>ſtilo nouo,</hi> and the 1. <hi>ſtilo veteri,</hi> of September, being
Tueſday, there came out of the Towne into the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
Quarter, the Deputies, namely, 2. of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2927:3"/>
of the Town, the Brother-in-law of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour,
and two Monkes, the one a blacke-Frier,
and the other a white-Frier, which did treat, Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
agree and conclude with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi>
and ſome of the Lords States, on the 13. of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
at night, being Thurſday laſt; theſe Articles as
here doe follow.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt, the ſpirituall or Eccleſtaſticall perſons,
as Fryers, Prieſts, Monkes, ſhall depart out of the
Towne within 6. weekes.</p>
            <p>2. Other religious perſons as Nunnes, and ſuch
Women, ſhall keepe their Cloiſters, and there bee
maintained and well entertained during their liues.</p>
            <p>3. The Towne and the Burgers are to keepe and
be maintained in their Priuiledges: But as for ſuch
as will depart, they ſhall haue liberty for two whole
yeeres next enſuing, to ſell their Houſes and goods at
their profit, according to the agreement of <hi>Brede.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. The Papiſts are to haue liberty of conſcience,
but no publike exerciſe of their religion.</p>
            <p>5. The Souldiers ſhall on Munday next (being the
7. of <hi>September)</hi> depart out of the Towne, with their
full Armes, burning Matches, Bullets in the mouth,
and with 4. Peeces of Ordnance.</p>
            <p>6. Vpon Friday laſt, the 4 of <hi>September,</hi> the
Towne was deliuered into the hands and power of
his Excellence, wherefore our Garriſon was receiued
into the Towne, and doe now keepe watch &amp; guard
vpon the Wals, and of the Gates of the Towne: And
on the ſame day there hath alſo beene deliuered into
the hands of his Excellence the Pettler Sconce, and
receiued and kept with his Garriſon.</p>
            <p>7. The Gouernor ſhall be conuoyed to <hi>Breda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>8. Thoſe of the Towne haue required, that they
may haue a Gouernour of the Houſe of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> which
hath beene granted vnto them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2927:4"/>
               <hi>Louing Reader, this is that which in the Treatie, (ſo
much as is deliuered vnto vs) hath beene agreed vpon.
Wherefore we can not enough praiſe and thanke the good
Almighty God, for the great and worthy Victory, which
he hath giuen vs in deſpight of all our Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord God bleſſe and preſerue with all happineſſe,
the Excellent, high and mighty Prince, the Prince of
<hi>Orange,</hi> His Excellencie, Count <hi>Erneſt,</hi> and the high
and mighty Lords, the States, and all true maintainers
of his holy Word. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <argument>
               <p>Theſe former Articles are printed according to the
Dutch Copie, printed at <hi>Delfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This following Copie is tranſlated out of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall.</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="concessions">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2927:4"/>
            <head>Articles, granted by His Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
the Prince of Orange, vnto the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour
of the Towne of the Buſſe, and vnto the
Captaines and Souldiers being in the ſame.</head>
            <div n="1" type="concession">
               <head>1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Gouernour of the <hi>Buſſe,</hi> with all the
Officers of War, and Souldiers, of what
quality and condition ſoeuer they are,
both the Horſe and foote, none excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
yea euen thoſe that haue forſaken
the Seruice of the Lords the States, and
accepted the ſeruice of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> are to march
out of the Towne without any let, trouble, or hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
with their Armes, Bagge and Baggage; the Horſe
with the ſound of Trumpet, flying Colours, armed in
their full Armour, and their Weapons in their hands:
The Foot, Drumme beating, Colours diſplaid, Matches
kindled on both ends, Bullets in their mouths, in ſuch
ſort, forme &amp; order, as they were wont to march in Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell-aray,
hauing all their goods and liues ſafe, from
thence vnto the Towne of <hi>Dieſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="concession">
               <head>2.</head>
               <p>They are to carry with them Six Peeces of Ordnance,
and two Morters, or Murthering-peeces, the which the
Gouernour hath to make choice of; and withall, ſuch
appurtenance and Amunition of Warre, as may ſuffice
to ſhoot off euery Peece twelue times.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="concession">
               <head>3.</head>
               <p>They ſhall be furniſhed and prouided with Horſes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2927:5"/>
and Waggons, with their Waggonmen and conductors,
ſufficient to carry away the ſaid Peeces of Ordnance,
and Murderers, with the ſaid appurtenances, to the
Towne of <hi>Dieſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="concession">
               <head>4</head>
               <p>All the Amunition of Warre and victuals, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> are to bee deliuered without
any fraud or deceit whatſoeuer, into the hands of ſuch as
His Excellency ſhall appoint to that end, except onely
ſuch victuals as haue beene ſold before t<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e 2. of this
preſent moneth when this Treaty was firſt begunne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for
the ſame ſhall ſo remaine ſold, and thoſe that haue
bought the ſame, are not to be ſearched or troubled for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="concession">
               <head>5</head>
               <p>All Officers &amp; Souldiers, both ſicke and hurt, being
in the Hoſpitall, or elſe-where, may ſtay and remaine in
the Towne, vntill their health ſhall giue them leaue to
trauell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and then they are to haue a ſafe conduct and
meanes to carry away their armes and baggage, either
to <hi>Dieſt</hi> or to <hi>Breda.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="concession">
               <head>6</head>
               <p>There is alſo to bee granted aſufficient number of
Waggons, Carts and Horſes, which the Gouernour
ſhall aske for, both for his ſeruice, and all other Officers,
and Souldiers to carry away his ſtuffe, and all ſorts of
bagge and baggage to <hi>Dieſt,</hi> there being comprehended
all Armes, yea even of thoſe Souldiers of the Garriſon, as
are either abſent, dead, ſicke, hurt, fled, or runne away;
and the ſaid Waggons are not to be viſited or ſearched
in any manner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="concession">
               <head>7</head>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall deſire to carry their ſtuffe and
baggage to <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> ſhall be furniſhed without their
pay or charges, ſome Boats to carry the ſame thither by
<hi>Holland,</hi> freed from all taxes, impoſitions or cuſtomes,
with permiſsion to appoint to the ſame perſons to take
care of their ſaid goods: the which are not to be ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
or ſtayed in any place or vnder any colour whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer,
but are to paſſe freely to <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> without ſtay or
vnlading.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="concession">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2927:5"/>
               <head>8</head>
               <p>The Gouernour, Officers, Inginers of Warre, Souldiers, and
other perſons, enioying wages of the King of Spaine, being
Eccleſiaſticall, or ſeculars, none excepted; as likewiſe the
widdowes and children of ſuch Officers, that haue in the ſaid
Towne any houſes, inheritances, reuenues, rents, be it vpon the
States of Braband in this Quarter, or vpon particular houſes
and grounds, or any other goods, moueable and immoueable,
that they are to hauc the ſpace and terme of two yeeres from
the ſignature of this preſent Treaty, according to their owne
will, either to tranſport, ſell, ingage, or otherwiſe diſpoſe of
the ſaid goods: and during the ſaid time, they are to enioy the
ſaid reuenues, rents, fruits, and goods, gotten, or to be gotten,
in ſuch nature and condition as they euer can be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="concession">
               <head>9</head>
               <p>The Officers and Souldiers, of what charge or condition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
they are, may leaue their wiues and children within the
towne; and during the ſaid terme of two yeeres, they may
diſpoſe of their goods, moueables, and immoueables, ſituated
in the ſaid towne, or elſewhere, none excepted, and there ſhall
no confiſcation, or prize, be vſed againſt them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="concession">
               <head>10</head>
               <p>The ſaid Officers and Souldiers, if they forſake and giue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
their Office, charge, or ſeruice, within the ſaid ſpace of two
yeeres, they may freely returne into the ſaid towne, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy
this Treaty, as other Burghers of Inhabitants: But ſo rhat
firſt they doe ſignifie it, and declare themſelues either to his
Excellence, or to the Gouernour that ſhall be in this towne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="concession">
               <head>11</head>
               <p>No Officer or Souldier, nor their baggage can be ſtayd or
areſted for any debts, whether he now march out with the
Garriſon, or being ſicke or hurt, ſtay and come after when he
ſhall be well againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="concession">
               <head>12</head>
               <p>All priſoners on both ſides, of what condition ſoeuer, are
to be put into liberty without any ranſome, ſaue onely they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2927:6"/>
are to pay the expences for their meate and drinke according
to <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he taxe and order of the Quarter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="concession">
               <head>13</head>
               <p>All booties that haue beene taken by thoſe of the towne,
both before and during this ſiege, are not to be taken from
them, but remaine to thoſe that haue them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="concession">
               <head>14</head>
               <p>The Articles of this compoſition being ſigned, the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
of the Buſſe is to haue liberty, and leaſure, to ſend an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
Meſſenger towards the moſt Excellent Infanta of
Spaine, with a ſafe-conduct and aſſurance, to giue her notice
of what hath beene done: But it is vnderſtood, that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour
ſhall ſend him away on the ſame day when the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
ſhall be ſigned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="concession">
               <head>15</head>
               <p>The ſaid conditions being reſolued vpon, and concluded,
there ſhall be granted vnto the ſaid Gouernour and all his men
of warre, and Souldiers, at the leaſt two dayes, to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
ready for their departure: The which terme being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired,
the ſaid Gouernour and Officers of the ſaid garriſon doe
promiſe to be gone, to wit, vpon Munday next very early,
which ſhall be the 7/17. of this month of September.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="concession">
               <head>16</head>
               <p>It is to be vnderſtood, that during the ſaid ſpace of two dayes,
no body at all of the towne may come into the army, nor thoſe
of the army into the ſaid towne, and the ſame to hinder and
preuent all diſorder: But euery one is to remaine in the meane
time within his trenches, or forts; And there ſhall alſo bee
made no approaches, nor done any act of hoſtility: for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
aſſurance wherof, there are to be giuen Hoſtages on the one
and the other part.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="concession">
               <head>17</head>
               <p>Before the Garriſon doth march out, there are to be giuen
two ſufficient Hoſtages on his Excellence's part, the which are
to march with the ſaid Garriſon, armes and baggage, from
hence to Dieſt: As likewiſe on the other ſide, the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
alſo is to giue two Hoſtages, which are to remaine vntill
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2927:6"/>
the ſaid Hoſtages of his Excellence, and the Wagons are come
back: And then preſently his Excellence is to ſend away the
ſaid Hoſtages with a ſafe-conduct and ſecurity vnto the towne
of Dieſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="concession">
               <head>18</head>
               <p>The Officers, Captaines, and other perſons, comprehended
in the firſt Article of this preſent Treaty, hauing any armes,
barges, or boats, or other ſtuffe of warre belonging particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
vnto them, may ſell, or tranſport the ſame, and thoſe that
ſhall buy or tranſport them, are not to be ſearched or troubled
for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="concession">
               <head>19</head>
               <p>There is no reſtitution to be made of horſes, armes, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes,
goods, or other ſtuffes, that haue beene fold, or taken
as booties, and no body is to be moleſted for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="concession">
               <head>20</head>
               <p>Thoſe that are of the Garriſon of Breda, being now in this
ſaid towne, both Officers and particular Souldiers, they may
now returne with their goods and liues ſafe, vnto Breda; And
there ſhall be alſo granted vnto them a ſufficient number of
wagons and horſes for the carriage of bag and baggage, and an
Hoſtage and Conuoy to conduct them thither with all ſafety,
in the like manner as is expreſſed in the firſt Article, as being
comprehended therein.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Giuen in the Campe before Boiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke,
or the Buſſe, <date>this 4/14. of September, 1629.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Signed.
<list>
                        <item>F. Henry de Naſſaw.</item>
                        <item>A. Grobendonke.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <argument>
                  <p>And beneath it was written,                                                                                                                                                                                  <q>By order of his Excellence.</q>
And ſigned <hi>I. Iunius.</hi>
And confirmed by the ſeale of his Excellence.
This agreeth with the Originall.<lb/>
Signed <hi>Corn. Muſch.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
