<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse mathematical on the variation of the magneticall needle Together with its admirable diminution lately discovered. By Henry Gellibrand professor of astronomie in Gresham College.</title>
            <author>Gellibrand, Henry, 1597-1636.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117951</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853160</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853160</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18529</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01586)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18529)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1237:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse mathematical on the variation of the magneticall needle Together with its admirable diminution lately discovered. By Henry Gellibrand professor of astronomie in Gresham College.</title>
                  <author>Gellibrand, Henry, 1597-1636.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones, dwelling in Red-crosse-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Geomagnetism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18529:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18529:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A
DISCOVRSE
MATHEMATICAL
ON THE VARIATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON
OF THE MAGNETICALL
<hi>Needle.</hi>
Together with Its admirable Diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
lately diſcovered.
<hi>By</hi> Henry Gellibrand <hi>Profeſſor of Aſtronomie</hi>
in Greſham College.</p>
            <figure/>
            <q>Veniet tempus, quo ista quae nunc latent, in lucem dies extrahat,
et longioris aevi diligentia.</q>
            <bibl>Sen. Nat: Quaeſt. lib. 7. cap. 25.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>William Iones,</hi> dwelling in
Red-croſſe-ſtreet. 1635.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:18529:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18529:2"/>
            <head>A
DISCOVRSE MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THEMATICALL
on the variation of the
Magneticall Needle.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O write an <hi>Encomiaſtique</hi> of the <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi>
is not my intention; the bold &amp;
confident attempts of Seamen, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough
thoſe hidden paths of the vaſt
Ocean, to all navigable parts of the
earth, will ſpare me the labour; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
will theſe few lines permit me to ſpeake of all
Magneticall qualities, they that liſt may have recourſe
for their ſatisfaction herein, to that moſt learned worke
(admired by all Foreiners) long agoe penned by <hi>Mr.
Dr. Gilbert</hi> our countryman, ſometimes Phyſitian to
that Renowned <hi>Lady</hi> our late <hi>Queene.</hi> That which I
here principally ayme at, is the deflection of the <hi>Needle</hi>
from the Terreſtriall <hi>Meridian,</hi> together with that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſe
and admirable variation of the Variation, lately
diſcovered to the world.</p>
            <p>The Variation then is the deflection of the <hi>Magneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
Meridian</hi> from the <hi>Terreſtriall,</hi> the <hi>Horizon</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining
its Quantitie and Qualitie. Theſe <hi>Meridians</hi>
ſometimes are coincident, and in ſuch places there
can be no Variation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sometimes againe they are diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18529:3"/>
and then that <hi>Hemiſpere</hi> wherein either extremity
of the Needle lyes, denominates its Quality, for if it
be the Eaſterne <hi>Hemiſpere,</hi> it is called Eaſterly variation,
if the weſterne, weſterly. And the Horizon ſuppoſed
(as all great Circles are) to be divided into 360 parts, &amp;
each part ſubdivided into <hi>Centeſmes</hi> or <hi>Milleſmes,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines
the Quantity as 10, 20, 30, &amp;c. parts of variation.</p>
            <p>For our more diſtinct proceeding (and to give ſome
ſatisfaction to thoſe that are not altogether <hi>Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi>)
it will not be impertinent to our preſent purpoſe
to give ſome probable Reaſon for this variation or
ſwarving of the <hi>Needle</hi> from the meridians of moſt
places.</p>
            <p>Take a vigorous <hi>Magnet,</hi> convert it into a <hi>Sphericall</hi>
Body, and having found its <hi>Poles,</hi> delineat the ſame
with <hi>Meridians,</hi> the <hi>Aequinoctiall,</hi> and <hi>Parallells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then take a fine ſowing <hi>Needle,</hi> and applying it to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſection
of a <hi>Meridian</hi> and the <hi>Aequinoctiall,</hi> it will
be found preciſely to point out the <hi>Poles</hi> of the ſtone;
and if the <hi>Needle</hi> be moved towards either Pole, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to its owne direction, it will trace out a Circle o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
the ſaid <hi>Magnetique Pole.</hi> But if this <hi>Sphaericall Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi>
ſhall have a part of it excavated, as admitt about the
forty fift <hi>Paralell,</hi> and forty fift <hi>Meridian</hi> or degree of
longitude, the <hi>Needle</hi> moued forwards from the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid
interſection, aſſoone as it ſhall draw neere to the
limb of this excavation, will forthwith leave its former
poſition, as lying in the plane of the prime meridian, and
incline to the other ſolide ſide, not reſpecting at all the
aforeſaid Poles: and this deflection we call the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation
of the <hi>Needle:</hi> And the greater will this variati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
be, the neerer it approacheth to the <hi>Poles.</hi> For
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18529:3"/>
whereas before the excavation each ſide being a like
potent,<note place="margin">Which may be ſome cauſe of thoſe ſuddaine and exorbitant variations in the Nortweſt and other Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne &amp; South<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erne parts of the Earth.</note> the <hi>Needle</hi> like an upright and indifferent
Arbiter inclined to neither part; after the excava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
it will convert it ſelfe to the more ſolide ſide,
rejecting the imperfect and defective, and ſo much
the more powerfully, by how much the other ſide
ſhall be found to have loſt more of its <hi>Magnetique</hi>
vigorous ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>The like will fall out if the <hi>Needle</hi> be ſo placed, as
that it ſhall biſect the excavated part, for then will it
acurately point out the true Poles of the ſtone former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
found, but ſuddainely ſwarue from them after any
little diſlocation, ſtrongly applying it ſelfe to the
more ſolide ſide.</p>
            <p>As it is with this little, ſo likewiſe with the greater
<hi>Magnet</hi> the Earth, whoſe ſolide magnetique parts are
great Continents, the defective and excavated, the
deepe and vaſt channell of the Sea. For if there were
obſervations made in the midd way betweene the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterly
Coaſt of <hi>China</hi> and this weſterne of Europe, it is
very probable there would be found no variation at all,
the Terreſtriall and <hi>Magneticall Meridians</hi> being congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all;
but if we ſhall incline to either ſide, as admit to
the weſtward, the <hi>Needle</hi> will in like manner move it
ſelfe to the Eaſterne Continent, as the more prevalent
ſide, the channell of the Sea being a part deficient of
the Sphericall Body of the Earth, and the <hi>Needle</hi>
finding no incouragement to apply it ſelfe there
to.</p>
            <p>And ſo likewiſe for the Ocean, which palliates the
imperfect parts of the Earth, it is evident, that if the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18529:4"/>
               <hi>Needle</hi> ſhall equally divide the Marine diſtance between
two continents, there will be found no variation, as
having both the Meridians united, the <hi>Needle</hi> equally
diſpoſing itſelfe to either Continent. But if we ſhall
ſwerue from this mediety, it will preponderate with
the next continent.</p>
            <p>For the evidence of the truth hereof, let a man exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine
generally the variations of our moſt expert Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
(a Catalogue wherof we have annexed to that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate
worke of <hi>Mr. Wright</hi> in his detection and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nection
of errors in <hi>Navigation</hi>) (although by reaſon
of the diverſities of the ſetts of their Compaſſes and
oftentimes unapt handling of their inſtruments, they
very ſeldome concurre) obſerued in the <hi>Atlantique</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean,
from the Equator unto the parts of <hi>Norway,</hi> all
along the Eaſt Coaſt from the <hi>Meridian</hi> of the <hi>Azores,</hi>
as farre North as hath beene diſcovered, and he ſhall
finde the ordinary practiſe to teſtifie the truth hereof.
As alſo after the ſame manner from the <hi>Equator</hi> ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
unto the ſtreights of <hi>Magellan,</hi> and all along the
backe parts of <hi>America</hi> in the South Sea, and on the
Eaſt Coaſt unto the Cape of <hi>Bona Speranza,</hi> and he
ſhall perceive the like agreement; But in fayling from
the aforeſaid Cape further Eaſtward, that ſometime
they doe finde it otherwiſe, the cauſe proceedeth from
the different ſituation of the South Continent hitherto
undiſcovered. And whereas in the <hi>Atlantique</hi> Ocean
about 135 leagues from the Ilands of <hi>Corues</hi> and <hi>Flores</hi>
to the weſtward,<note place="margin">Mr. Iohn Wells.</note> there hath beene found by an able Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt
no variation at all, it is a manifeſt argument, that the
Place is equidiſtant from the <hi>Europaean</hi> or <hi>Affrican</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinents
and the <hi>American:</hi> And as we approach to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18529:4"/>
Continent, ſo ſhall we find the <hi>Needle</hi> praepotent in
its converſion; from whence the variation ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
its denomination.</p>
            <p>Therefore its abſurd for Seamen to touch their
Compaſſes with the allowance of the variation of any
particular place, conſidering this variation is perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
variable according to the ſhipps motion.</p>
            <p>And moreover its abſolutely neceſſary for that Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
who ſailes by his Compaſſe, continually to ſearch
the variatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſo by the <hi>Proſthaphaereticall</hi> application
thereof, the true point of the compaſſe (which is his
principall <hi>Mercurialiſt</hi>) may be rectified.</p>
            <p>And this artifice may be performed by the aſſiſtance
of the Planets or fixed <hi>Starres,</hi> and that either without
or with their Altitudes. I ſhall not need to exemplify
all varieties, as having elſwhere copiouſly and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratively
delivered the ſame. I thinke it only conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient
to touch lightly at one or two, and ſuch as beſt
conduce to our preſent purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And firſt without an <hi>Altitude.</hi> Finde two fixed
Starres of equall right Aſcention, and holding vp a
thread and plummet, obſerve when the thread biſects
them (for that is the exact <hi>Meridian</hi> of the place) and
at that inſtant apply the Compaſſe to them; if the
<hi>Needle</hi> preciſely reſpect them, there is no varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
if not, then is the difference, the variation inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;
and that part of the Horizon to which it inclines,
(alwayes accounting from the ſame interſection of the
Horizon and <hi>Meridian</hi>) claimes it.</p>
            <p>It may likewiſe be performed by the Amplitude <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi>
or <hi>Occiduall</hi> of the Sunne, and as well by night as
by day, by the reſt of the Planets or fixed Starres, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18529:5"/>
onely their declinations and the Latitude of the
places, either <hi>Geometrically</hi> by an <hi>Analemme,</hi> or
<hi>Arithmetically</hi> by the helpe of the <hi>Canon</hi> of <hi>Trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles,</hi>
for the ordinary termes of the proportion runne
thus.</p>
            <p>As the <hi>Sine</hi> complement of the Latitude, is to the
<hi>Radius,</hi> So the <hi>Sine</hi> of the declination, to the Sine of the
Amplitude. Turning therefore the Compaſſe to the
Sunne or Starres, the difference of the Arcs is the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation
inquired. Or by knowing the time of the Sunnes
incidence into the Plane of the Prime verticall, after
the like manner we may obtaine our deſires.</p>
            <p>But in theſe and ſome other wayes, we are confined
to a certaine time: If therefore to the former requiſits
we ſhall add an Altitude, this Artifice may be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
at any convenient appearance of a Planet or Starre,
as we ſhall by and by ſhew.</p>
            <p>And for the more eaſie and certayne obtaining of the
variation at Sea, I would adviſe the Sea-man to extend
or prolong the capitall of his <hi>Needle,</hi> or fix ſome ſtile
on it, ſo that it may cut the Flye at right <hi>Angles,</hi> for
then the Compaſſe coverted to the Sun, this ſtile will
readily ſhadow out the <hi>Azimuth Magneticall,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paring
it with that of the Sunne, he hath the variation
neere enough without any further labour or prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>Thus hitherto (according to the Tenents of all our
<hi>Magneticall</hi> Philoſophers) we have ſuppoſed the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations
of all particular places to continue one and the
ſame: So that when a Seaman ſhall happly returne to
a place where formerly he found the ſame variation,
he may hence conclude, he is in the ſame former <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18529:5"/>
For it is the Aſſertion of <hi>Mr. Dr. Gilberts. Varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio
v<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>icuiuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Loci conſtans eſt,</hi> that is to ſay, the ſame
place doth alwayes retaine the ſame variation. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
hath this Aſſertion (for ought I ever heard) been
queſtioned by any man. But moſt diligent magneticall
obſervations have plainely offred violence to the ſame,
and proved the contrary, namely that the variation is
accompanied with a variation. For whereas in the
yeare 1580 <hi>Mr. Burrows</hi> (a man of unqueſtionable abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities
in the <hi>Mathematiques</hi>) found the variation at <hi>Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe</hi>
neere <hi>London</hi> to be 11 gr. 15 min. or neere one
point of the Compaſſe; In the yeare 1622 <hi>Mr. Gunter</hi>
ſometimes profeſſor of <hi>Astronomie</hi> in <hi>Greſham Colledge,</hi>
found the variation in the ſame place to be but 6 gr. 13
min. And my ſelfe this preſent yeare 1634 with ſome
friends had recourſe to <hi>Dedpford</hi> (where Mr. <hi>Gunter</hi>
had heretofore made the ſame obſervations with thoſe
at <hi>Limehouſe</hi>) and found it not much to exceed 4 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</p>
            <p>For the clearer manifeſtation of this truth, (becauſe
all men have not beene furniſhed with or ſeene the fore
ſaid obſervations, I hold it neceſſary to transferre
theirs hither, and ſubnect thoſe which were lately
made by my ſelfe with the aſſiſtance of ſome friends.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18529:6"/>
               <table>
                  <head>Mr. Burrowes his obſervations made at Lime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe
<date>October. 16. 1580.</date>
                  </head>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="2">Before Noone.</cell>
                     <cell cols="2">After Noone.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Elevation of the ☉</cell>
                     <cell>variation of the ſhadow from the North of the Needle to the weſtwards.</cell>
                     <cell>Elevation of the ☉</cell>
                     <cell>variat: of the ſhadow from the North of the Needle to the Eaſtward</cell>
                     <cell>variat. of the Needle from the Pole or Axis.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gr. Min.</cell>
                     <cell>Gr. Min.</cell>
                     <cell>Gr. Min.</cell>
                     <cell>Gr. Min.</cell>
                     <cell>Gr, Min. Sec.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17: 0</cell>
                     <cell>52, 35</cell>
                     <cell>17: 0</cell>
                     <cell>30: 0</cell>
                     <cell>11: 17, 30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18: 0</cell>
                     <cell>50 8</cell>
                     <cell>18: 0</cell>
                     <cell>27. 45</cell>
                     <cell>11. 11. 30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19: 0</cell>
                     <cell>47 30</cell>
                     <cell>19: 0</cell>
                     <cell>24. 30</cell>
                     <cell>11. 30, 0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>20: 0</cell>
                     <cell>45 0</cell>
                     <cell>20: 0</cell>
                     <cell>22: 15</cell>
                     <cell>11, 22. 30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21: 0</cell>
                     <cell>42 15</cell>
                     <cell>21: 0</cell>
                     <cell>19. 30</cell>
                     <cell>11. 22, 30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22: 0</cell>
                     <cell>38 0</cell>
                     <cell>22: 0</cell>
                     <cell>15: 30</cell>
                     <cell>11. 15. 0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23: 0</cell>
                     <cell>34 40</cell>
                     <cell>23: 0</cell>
                     <cell>12. 0</cell>
                     <cell>11. 20. 0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24: 0</cell>
                     <cell>29 35</cell>
                     <cell>24: 0</cell>
                     <cell>7: 0</cell>
                     <cell>11. 17, 0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25: 0</cell>
                     <cell>22 20</cell>
                     <cell>25: 0</cell>
                     <cell>0: 8</cell>
                     <cell>11. 14. 0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>From N to W</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>The way of finding the variation after this manner
is eaſy to be conceived. A time being choſen when the
Heavens were like to be unmasked for the whole day,
the altitudes of the Sunne were taken by him to each
degree of a Quadrant both forenoone &amp; Afternoone,
from 17 to 25 gr. making nine ſeverall obſervations.
And at every Altitude turning his Needle to the Sunn,
obſerved the degree and parts cut thereby. Then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring
the <hi>Magneticall Azimuthes</hi> made in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone,
with thoſe in the Afternoone anſwerable to
the ſame Solar altitudes, the halfe of the difference is
the variation. Thus at the altitude of 17 gr. in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18529:6"/>
Forenoone, the <hi>Needle</hi> cutting 52 gr. 35 min. and at the
ſame altitude in the Afternoone 30 gr. 0 min: the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
is 22 gr. 35 min: the halfe whereof is 11 gr. 17
min: 30 Sec. the variation inquired.</p>
            <p>Before we proceed to other Obſervations it will be
requiſite we take a review of theſe, and after correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of ſome of the apparent Altitudes, call the Solar
Azimuthes to the Iudicature of a Triangle.</p>
            <p>It is not unknowne that about this time of <hi>Mr. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes</hi>
his obſervations the accurate and corrected ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
of the Sunnes motion were not publiſhed to the
world, Neither the Angles of the Obliquity and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralaxes
of the Sunne ſo truely determined. And as for
the refraction (which inſinuates it ſelfe in every Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
not exceeding 45 degrees) being then in its infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
and a ſtranger to the world it was not called into
the account, no not by the Ancients themſelues, nor
limited before that great Aſtronomer and honorable
<hi>Dane Tyche Brahe</hi> opened the ſame way. If therefore
we ſhall examine theſe Altitudes acording to the late
corrected grounds, we ſhall ſomewhat alter the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations
of Mr. <hi>Burrowes,</hi> but ſo as that we ſhall not much
differ from him, or ſuſpect any great error in his
worke.</p>
            <p>Theſe obſervations then of his, were made the 16
of <hi>October</hi> Anno 1580. And by <hi>Aſtronomicall Calculation</hi>
ſhould begin about 9 ½ in the Morning, and end about
2 ⅓ in the Afternoone. Let us now make choice of the
<hi>Magneticall Azimuthes</hi> anſwerable to the Altitudes of
20 gr. being the fourth obſervation. The true place of
the Sunne about this time correſpondent to this Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
according to the late <hi>Rud<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lphins</hi> Tables, (with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18529:7"/>
conſideration to the difference of <hi>Meridians</hi> and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quation
of Time) is thus found after the Centeſimall
way with the connexion of our <hi>Britiſh Logarithmes,</hi> but
with ſome alteration of the Anomalies</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Motion of the Apog. ☉</cell>
                     <cell>Middle motion of the Sun</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sig. Gr.</cell>
                     <cell>Sig. Gr.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Epoch of Chriſt 2: 83455571829</cell>
                     <cell>9: 88667238532</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>yeares 1579 0: 270303979753</cell>
                     <cell>0: 111927414346</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Month: Biſſ: 9. 0: 00 128419571</cell>
                     <cell>9: 00672704358</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Dayes 14. 0: 000007030268</cell>
                     <cell>0: 137990576119</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Her. 21. Min. 9 0: 00000413028</cell>
                     <cell>0: 08686013944</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sum of the mot. 3: 53895414449</cell>
                     <cell>7: 47943947299</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Motion of the Apogaum ſubſtracted</cell>
                     <cell>3: 53895414449</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The middle <hi>Anomaly.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3: 294048532850</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Our Tabular middle <hi>Anomaly</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3: 29 00000</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The difference of <hi>Anomalies</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>0: 0 40485</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The logarithme whereof is</cell>
                     <cell>0. 6072976</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The diff. of the Coaequated <hi>Anom.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1. 01729167</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The logarithme whereof is</cell>
                     <cell>0: 0074454</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The ſumme of the logarithmes</cell>
                     <cell>0: 6147430</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>To which there anſwers</cell>
                     <cell>04118538</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>which added to the tab: <hi>Coaeq: Anom.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3. 271763527</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gives the inquired <hi>coaeq: Anomaly</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3. 275882065</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>To this the <hi>Apog:</hi> added</cell>
                     <cell>3. 5 3895414</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gives the Sunnes place in ♏</cell>
                     <cell>2 9777479</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The declination whereof is</cell>
                     <cell>12548280</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Whereunto adding a Quadrant</cell>
                     <cell>90000000</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The ſum is the ☉ diſt. from the Pole</cell>
                     <cell>102548280</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe we haue made choice of the apparent
Altitude of 20 gr. the Parallax (<hi>Kepler</hi> admitting lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
or none,) according to <hi>Tycho Brahe</hi> will be
<table>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:18529:7"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>found</cell>
                     <cell>Gr. 0047778</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And the refraction</cell>
                     <cell>0075000</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The difference is</cell>
                     <cell>0027222</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Which ſubſtracted from the appare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Alt.</cell>
                     <cell>20000000</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Giues the true Altitude of the ☉</cell>
                     <cell>19972778</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The complement whereof is the diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>of the ☉ from the <hi>Zenith</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>70027222</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>That the inſuing work may be the better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceived, let
FZB in the annexed ſcheme) be the <hi>Meridian</hi> of <hi>Lime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe;</hi>
Z the zenith or <hi>Pole</hi> of the <hi>Horizon</hi> FOB. The
elevation of the <hi>Pole</hi> PB. ZP the complement thereof.
AE the Equator. The Southerne Parallell of the
<figure/>
Sunne DSO. ZSH a Quadrant of a verticall Circle
interſecting the Sunnes parallell, and paſſing through
his Center in the point S. HS the Sunnes Altitude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue
the Horizon; and ZS the complement or his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
from the zenith. SI the declination. SP the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
of the Sunne from the <hi>Pole</hi> of the world. Alſo
let the obſcure periphery MZG be the <hi>Magneticall Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian</hi>
paſſing through the zenith Z, and deflecting or
<figure>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:18529:8"/>
               </figure>
varying from the Terreſtriall Meridian the Arc MB,
the meaſure of the Angle MZB the variation inquired,
which will be determined by comparing the magneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<hi>Azimuth</hi> CZS with the Solar <hi>Azimuth</hi> PZS, always
greater then the <hi>Magneticall</hi> before Noone, but leſſe
after Noone, where the deflection is Eaſterly as here
with us in England and the adjacent parts. But the
<hi>Magneticall</hi> azimuth is altogether found by inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
obſervation, the Solar by Calculation or the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
of the obliquangular ſphaericall Triangle PZS,
whoſe ſides are already knowne, and therefore the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle
PZS may be obtained by the fourth compend of
the laſt chapter of the Britiſh <hi>Trigonometry</hi> after this
manner.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Logarithmes</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>PS. Diſt of the ☉ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Pale</hi> 10254789</cell>
                     <cell>00269391447</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ZS. Compl. of the ☉ altitude 7002722</cell>
                     <cell>02061682627</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ZP. compl. of the Latitude 3846667</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sum of the ſides 21104178</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The halfe ſumme 10552089</cell>
                     <cell>99838665722</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Diff. of the Baſe and ½ ſumm. 297299</cell>
                     <cell>87148768587</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>189318508383</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:18529:8"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The log. of the ſine of 169996</cell>
                     <cell>94659254191</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The complement 730004</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>The double whereof is 1460008 the Angle inquired
PZS. But the Magnet. Azim. is 1350000 namely the
Angle CZS. The differ. is 110008 MZB the variation
inquired, which converted into ſexageſmes is 11 gr. 0
min, 0 Sec. <hi>Mr, Burrowes</hi> by the helpe of the afternoons
obſervation making it 11. gr. 22 min. 30 ſec. the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
being 0 gr. 22 min. 30 ſec.</p>
            <p>The like may we doe with the ſame Altitude for
the Afternoone, if we ſhall onely rectify the declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
anſwerable to the Sunnes motion for the internall
of time. The Sunnes true place was in 3179445 of ♏ the
declination correſpondent was 1261740. Then in the
adiacent diagram, being the ſame with the former,
ſave onely that the magneticall Azimuth CZS is (as
it ought to be) greater then the Solar PZS, we have
the ſame termes given, and therefore by reſolving the
<figure/>
Triangle PZS, the angle inquired PZS may be found
either by the former or the third variety belonging to
the 11 Probleme of the ſame booke, and agreeing as
<figure>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18529:9"/>
               </figure>
well with the Calculation of a Plane Triangle as of a
Sphaericall, after this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gr.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>PS.</hi> diſt. of the ☉ from the <hi>Pole</hi> 10261740</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ZS. compl. of the ☉ Altitude 700272<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ZP.</hi> compl. of the Latitude 3846667</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The ſum of the ſides 21<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>129</cell>
                     <cell>Logarithmes</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The halfe ſumme 10555564</cell>
                     <cell>00162066869</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Dif. of the half ſum &amp; ſides <hi>PS</hi> 293824</cell>
                     <cell>12902261021</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ZS 3552842</cell>
                     <cell>97642558829</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ZP 6708897</cell>
                     <cell>99643117219</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The ſumme of the logarithmicall ſines</cell>
                     <cell>210350003938</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Logarithmical tang: of half the Angle</cell>
                     <cell>105175001969</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>which found in the cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwereth to</cell>
                     <cell>73104441 the</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>double whereof is the angle ſought</cell>
                     <cell>146208882 PZS</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But the Magneticall Azim: is</cell>
                     <cell>157750000 CZS</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The difference is the variation</cell>
                     <cell>11541118 <hi>CZP.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>which converted into ſexageſmes, is 11 gr. 32 <hi>min.</hi> 28:
ſec. And if with this we compare the morning vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,
(which ſhould have been the ſame with the
afternoones) the difference will be 32 <hi>min: 28 ſec:</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:18529:9"/>
which may eaſily ariſe either from the Inſufficiency or
Fabrique or groſſe handling of the Inſtruments. So
that if we take the Arithmeticall meane, we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably
conclude the variation anſwerable to his time
to be about 11 gr. 16 min: with which very neere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curreth
<hi>Dr. Gilbert,</hi> finding it 11 gr. 20 min.</p>
            <p>From theſe we proceed to <hi>Mr. Gunters</hi> Obſervations,
the Table whereof we have here inſerted, as we finde
them in his mathematicall workes, where we ſee the
variation not to exceede 6 gr. 13 min. His inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
were one Quadrant of three foote Radius for
the Sunnes Altitudes: His Needles were two, the one
of ſix, the other of 10 Inches in length. The Sunnes
Azimuthes were found by calculation, and the Azi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muthes
<hi>Magneticall,</hi> taken off a Horizontall Plane by a
line of Chordes, whoſe Semidiameter was twelue
Inches.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>Mr. Gunters Obſervations made at Limehouſe
<date>Iun: 13 Anno 1622</date> after Noone.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Alt: ☉</cell>
                     <cell>Azim: Mag</cell>
                     <cell>Azim: ☉</cell>
                     <cell>Variation.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gr. Min.</cell>
                     <cell>Gr. Min.</cell>
                     <cell>Gr. Min.</cell>
                     <cell>Gr. Min.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19 0</cell>
                     <cell>82 2</cell>
                     <cell>75 52</cell>
                     <cell>6 10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18 5</cell>
                     <cell>80 50</cell>
                     <cell>74 44</cell>
                     <cell>6 6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17 34</cell>
                     <cell>80 0</cell>
                     <cell>74 6</cell>
                     <cell>5 54</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17 0</cell>
                     <cell>79 15</cell>
                     <cell>73 20</cell>
                     <cell>5 55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16 18</cell>
                     <cell>78 12</cell>
                     <cell>72 32</cell>
                     <cell>5 40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16 0</cell>
                     <cell>77 50</cell>
                     <cell>72 10</cell>
                     <cell>5 40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10 10</cell>
                     <cell>71 2</cell>
                     <cell>64 49</cell>
                     <cell>6 13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>0 52</cell>
                     <cell>70 12</cell>
                     <cell>64 25</cell>
                     <cell>5 47</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Thus haue we prooved that for the Interſtice of 42
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18529:10"/>
yeares, there hath beene an evident diminution of five,
degrees variation. I deny not the Artifice to be very
nice and ſubtle, and that an error may vnawares eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
inſinuate it ſelfe, which together with this great
diſcrepance, moved ſome of us to be overhaſty in
caſting an aſperſion of error on <hi>Mr. Burrows</hi> obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note place="margin">Mr. Iohn Marr.</note>
(though ſince upon noe juſt grounds) till an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance
of ours, lately applying <hi>Mr. Gunters</hi> owne
Needle to the ſide of the Cubicall Stone of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
Diall in White Hall garden, could not finde the
variation ſo great as 6 gr. 15 min: formerly found;
whereupon reſolving with ſome friends to make an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment
hereof, we went to <hi>Diepford</hi> the laſt yeare
1633 the day of the Sunnes entrance into the ſummer
Solſtice, to the very ſame place where <hi>Mr. Gunter</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tofore
had made obſervation, and found it much leſſe
then fiue degrees; And afterwards calling into Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
the Inſufficiency of our Inſtruments, that all
ſcruple might be quite taken away, we had recourſe
this preſent yeare 1634 Ioh. 12. ſtilo vet: to the ſame
Garden of our learned and ingenuous friend <hi>Mr. Iohn
Welles,</hi> with a Quadrant of ſix foote Radius for ſolar
Altitudes, continually rectified with great care, and a
Horizontall Quadrant of two foote Radius, for the
determining of the <hi>Magneticall</hi> Azimuthes, exactly
ſet to the Magneticall meridian, and in paralelliſme
to the Horizon; (otherwiſe great error might enſue)
with two Needles of twelue Inches in length well
touch't with good Magnetts; And for the better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction,
tooke with us alſo the very ſame Needle
wherewith <hi>Mr. Gunter</hi> made the foreſaid obſervations,
in length ten Inches; all three muſt, accurately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18529:10"/>
the ſame Magneticall Meridian as we then pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved.
And leaſt there might ariſe ſome diverſity in the
variation through the touches of ſeverall Stones, I
cauſed the one Needle firſt touch't by a very good
Magnet, to be retouch't by another as good if no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and the ſame wherwith moſt of our zea compaſtes
are touch't, and yet found no difference betweene
them. And ſo Iune the 14. 1634<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we made theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
obſervations, where we found the variation
not to exceed 4 gr. 10 min. as appeareth by the Table
annexed.</p>
            <p>And becauſe in the Reſolutions of theſe obliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
ſphaericall Triangles for the Solar Azimuthes we
have neceſſary uſe of the Latitude of the Place, the
ſame we determine by the Sunnes meridian Altitude
to be 51 gr. 30 min. after this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Gr.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The apparent Altitude of the Sunne</cell>
                     <cell>62: 0: 0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Parallax of the Sunne added</cell>
                     <cell>0: 1: 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Therefore the Sunnes true altitude</cell>
                     <cell>62: 1: 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sunnes declination according to <hi>Tycho</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>23: 31<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hence the Altitude of the Equinoctiall</cell>
                     <cell>38: 30. 0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The compl. wherof is the hight of the <hi>Pole</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>51. 30. 0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>Obſervations made at Diepford An.<note place="margin">Teſtibus ac ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus is D. Welles. Harriſon. Marr. Butler. Ho<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ton. Ho<gap reason="illegible: broken" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>knell.</note> 1634 Iunij 12 before Noone</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Alt: ☉ vera</cell>
                     <cell>Azim. Mag</cell>
                     <cell>Azim. ☉</cell>
                     <cell>variatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gr. Min.</cell>
                     <cell>Gr. M.</cell>
                     <cell>Gr. M,</cell>
                     <cell>Gr. M.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44, 45.</cell>
                     <cell>106, 0</cell>
                     <cell>110 6</cell>
                     <cell>4. 6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>46, 30,</cell>
                     <cell>109, 0</cell>
                     <cell>113 10</cell>
                     <cell>4 10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>48. 31,</cell>
                     <cell>113, 0</cell>
                     <cell>117 1</cell>
                     <cell>4 1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>50, 54,</cell>
                     <cell>118<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 0</cell>
                     <cell>122, 8</cell>
                     <cell>4. 2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>54, 24,</cell>
                     <cell>127. 0</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>30 55</cell>
                     <cell>3 5</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:18529:11"/>

               <table>
                  <head>After Noone the ſame day.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Alt. ☉ vera</cell>
                     <cell>Azi. Mag</cell>
                     <cell>Azim. ☉</cell>
                     <cell>Variation</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gr. Min.</cell>
                     <cell>Gr: M.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>G.</hi> Mn.</cell>
                     <cell>Gr, Min</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44 37</cell>
                     <cell>114: 0</cell>
                     <cell>109. 53.</cell>
                     <cell>4: 7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>40 48</cell>
                     <cell>108: 0</cell>
                     <cell>103, 50</cell>
                     <cell>4: 10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>38 46</cell>
                     <cell>105. 0</cell>
                     <cell>100, 48</cell>
                     <cell>4. 12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>36 43</cell>
                     <cell>102, 0</cell>
                     <cell>97. 56</cell>
                     <cell>4. 4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>34 32</cell>
                     <cell>99, 0</cell>
                     <cell>95, 0</cell>
                     <cell>4: 0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32 10</cell>
                     <cell>96: 0</cell>
                     <cell>91. 55</cell>
                     <cell>4: 5</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Concordant Obſervations can not produce a
variation greater then 4 gr. 12 min. nor leſſe then 3 gr.
55 min. the Arithmeticall meane limiting it to 4 gr.
and about 4 minutes.</p>
            <p>And for a further confirmation herof (though mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
upon no juſt reaſon to ſuſpect theſe obſervations,
being every way as cautelous in them as poſſible we
could) as ſoone as the intermiſſion from my publique
Exerciſe would permit, I cauſed the ſame inſtruments
to be tranſported to <hi>Paules Cray</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> diſtant from
<hi>London</hi> SE and by S about 12 miles, where the fourth
of <hi>Iuly</hi> following (<hi>Fide Aſtronimica</hi>) I made the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
animadverſions, hardly amounting to 4 degrees.</p>
            <p>The Latitude of the Place I finde by the ſame large
Quadrant to be 51 gr. 25 min. which thus I prove.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>o</cell>
                     <cell>i</cell>
                     <cell>ii</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iuly</hi> 21 the ☉ apparent meridian altit. was</cell>
                     <cell>56:</cell>
                     <cell>53:</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Sunnes parallex to be added</cell>
                     <cell>0,</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The ſum is the Sunnes true Altitude</cell>
                     <cell>56,</cell>
                     <cell>54,</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The declination of the Sunne ſubtracted</cell>
                     <cell>18,</cell>
                     <cell>19,</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Relique is the altitude of the equinoc.</cell>
                     <cell>38.</cell>
                     <cell>35.</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The compl: wherof is the hight of the <hi>Pole</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>51.</cell>
                     <cell>25,</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18529:11"/>
               <table>
                  <head>Obſervations made at Pauls Cray in Kent <date>Iuly: 4: 1634:</date>
After Noone.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>vera alt. ☉</cell>
                     <cell>Azim: mag</cell>
                     <cell>Azim: ☉</cell>
                     <cell>variatio</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gr, Min:</cell>
                     <cell>Gr, Min:</cell>
                     <cell>Gr. Min:</cell>
                     <cell>Gr: Min</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>40: 55.</cell>
                     <cell>111 30</cell>
                     <cell>107 30</cell>
                     <cell>4 0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>40: 1</cell>
                     <cell>110 0</cell>
                     <cell>106 5</cell>
                     <cell>3 55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>39: 41.</cell>
                     <cell>109 30</cell>
                     <cell>105 34</cell>
                     <cell>3 56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>38: 42.</cell>
                     <cell>108 0</cell>
                     <cell>104 5</cell>
                     <cell>3 55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>35: 32.</cell>
                     <cell>103 30</cell>
                     <cell>99 32</cell>
                     <cell>3 58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>34. 49.</cell>
                     <cell>102 30</cell>
                     <cell>98 32</cell>
                     <cell>3 58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>33, 41,</cell>
                     <cell>101 0</cell>
                     <cell>97 0</cell>
                     <cell>4 0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32. 57:</cell>
                     <cell>100 0</cell>
                     <cell>96 2</cell>
                     <cell>3 58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32: 9,</cell>
                     <cell>99 0</cell>
                     <cell>94 58</cell>
                     <cell>4 2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>31, 25,</cell>
                     <cell>98 0</cell>
                     <cell>94 0</cell>
                     <cell>4 0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>30: 39:</cell>
                     <cell>97 0</cell>
                     <cell>93 1</cell>
                     <cell>3 59</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>29: 29:</cell>
                     <cell>95 30</cell>
                     <cell>91 31</cell>
                     <cell>3 59</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>27, 51:</cell>
                     <cell>93 30</cell>
                     <cell>89 28</cell>
                     <cell>4 2</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>It were needleſſe having ſo many ſufficient teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes,
to produce any more; one onely obſervation
made with circumſpection being as good as one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth.
So that its plaine, the obſervations made in this
place do all make the variation to fall neere upon 4 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</p>
            <p>Hence therefore we may conclude that for the ſpace
of 54 yeares (the difference of time betweene <hi>Mr. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes</hi>
and theſe laſt obſervations of ours) there hath
beene a ſenſible diminution of 7 degrees and better.</p>
            <p>If any affected with magneticall Philoſophy ſhall
yet deſire to ſee an experiment made for their owne
particular ſatisfaction, where I may prevaile, I would
adviſe them to pitch a faire ſtone parallell to the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18529:12"/>
there to reſt immoveable, and having a Needle
of a convenient length ſtrongly touch't by a vigorous
Magnet to draw a Magneticall Meridian thereby, and
yearely to examine by the application of the ſame (well
preſerved from the ayre and ruſt, its greateſt enemies)
whether time will produce the like alteration.</p>
            <p>I will not here enter into a diſpute concerning the
cauſe of this ſenſible diminution, whether it may be
imputed to the Magnet, or the Earth, or both. It is not
unknowne to the world, how the Greateſt Maſters of
Aſtronomie, which this age hath afforded, for the more
eaſy ſalving the apparent anomalar motions of the fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and erratique caeleſtiall lights, and avoyding that
ſupervacaneous furniture of the Ancients, do with all
alacrity embrace that admirable <hi>Copernicean Hypotheſis</hi>
of the diurnal, Annual, &amp; Secular motions of the earth,
in ſo much as conferring with that Great Aſtronomer
<hi>D. Phil. Lanſberg.</hi> in <hi>Zealand</hi> about Aſtronomicall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
did moſt ſeriouſly affirme unto me, he ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
be diſſwaded from that Truth. This which he was
pleaſed to ſtile a truth, I ſhould readily receive as an <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis,</hi>
and ſo be eaſily led on to the conſideration of
the imbecillity of Mans apprehenſion, as not able right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to conceive of this admirable opifice of God or
frame of the world, without falling foule on ſo great
an abſurdity. Yet ſure I am, it is a probable inducement
to ſhake a wavering underſtanding. And which adds
ſomewhat more, I underſtand by <hi>Galilaeus</hi> a <hi>Florentine,</hi>
and a moſt acute and learned <hi>Mathematician,</hi> that an <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi>
Gentleman of the Family of the <hi>Marſilii</hi> hath late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
found the mutation of the Terreſtriall <hi>Meridians,</hi> and
penned a treatiſe thereof not yet publiſhed, which the
ſaid <hi>Galilaeus</hi> hath ſeene and read <hi>conſtupore,</hi> not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
amazement. His words are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18529:12"/>
Surge di preſente una quinta novita, dalle quale
ſi poſſa arguir mobilita nel globo terreſtre, mediante
quello, che ſottiliſsimamente va ſcoprendo l' illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſsimo
<hi>S.</hi> Caeſare della nobiliſsima famiglia de i Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilij
di Bologna, pur' Academico Linceo, il quale
in una dottiſsima ſcrittura va eſponendo, come ha
oſſervato una continua mutazione, benche tardiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,
nella linea Meridiana; della quale ſcrittura,
da me ultimamente con ſtupore veduta, ſpero che
douera fare coppia a tutti gli ſtudio ſi delle maraviglie
della natura.</p>
            <p>Which in Engliſh runnes thus.</p>
            <p>Now there ariſeth a fift noveltie, from which we
may argue the mobility of the terereſtriall Globe, by the
meanes of that which moſt ſubtllie the moſt muſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Gentleman <hi>Sig: Caeſar</hi> of the moſt noble familie of
the <hi>Marſilij</hi> of Bologna a Lyncean <hi>Academicke</hi> alſo,
hath diſcovered, who in a moſt learned tract plainely
ſheweth how he hath obſerved a continuall mutation,
although very ſlow, in the Meridian line; which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe,
which with wonder I lately ſaw, I hope he
will impart to all thoſe who are Studious of the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
of nature.</p>
            <p>Surely if it be ſo, the due conſideration of the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſes
doth (as I conceive) lay open a faire way for the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18529:13"/>
ſalving of that Irregular Motion imputed to the Axis
of the Earth. I meane the alterable Obliquity of the
Ecliptique, which to deny (as ſome yet doe, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
great violence offred to the Ancients) I ſhall hardly
(without very ſtrong argument) be perſwaded. I preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
likewiſe a ſuppofition which might be made of the
correſpondent motion of the <hi>Pole</hi> of the Magnet with
thoſe of ſome of the Planets, and divers other conceits,
which muſt be all left to future times to diſcover, this
Invention being but newly preſented to the world in
its infancy.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Greſham College <date>5 Cal. Aug. 1634.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata Typographica.</head>
            <p>PAg. 7 lin. 1. for <hi>Gilberts</hi> read <hi>Gilbert.</hi> Pag. 7 lin, 16 for
<hi>D<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ford</hi> read <hi>Diepford.</hi> p. 9 lin 19 for the ſame way, read
the way. p. 9 lin. 27 for 9 ½ read 9 ⅓. p, 13, lin, 12, for internall
reade intervall: pag, 16 lin laſt for muſt reade moſt:</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
