<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true declaration of the happy conuersion, contrition, and Christian preparation of Francis Robinson, gentleman Who for counterfetting the great seale of England, was drawen, hang'd, and quartered at Charing-Crosse, on Friday last, being the thirteenth day of Nouember, 1618. Written by Henry Goodcole preacher of the Word of God, and his daily visiter, during his imprisonment in the gaole of Newgate.</title>
            <author>Goodcole, Henry, 1586-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-07">2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01873</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118282</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853489</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18873</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01873)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18873)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 888:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true declaration of the happy conuersion, contrition, and Christian preparation of Francis Robinson, gentleman Who for counterfetting the great seale of England, was drawen, hang'd, and quartered at Charing-Crosse, on Friday last, being the thirteenth day of Nouember, 1618. Written by Henry Goodcole preacher of the Word of God, and his daily visiter, during his imprisonment in the gaole of Newgate.</title>
                  <author>Goodcole, Henry, 1586-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw: All-de dwelling neere Christ-church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A true declaration of the life and death of Francis Robinson.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Robinson, Francis, d. 1618.</term>
               <term>Executions and executioners --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18873:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18873:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A True Declaration of the happy Conuersion, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Christian preparation of FRANCIS ROBINSON, Gentleman.</p>
            <p>WHO FOR COVNTERFET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Great Seale of England, was drawen, Hang'd, and quartered at <hi>Charing Crosse,</hi> on Friday last, being the Thirteenth day of <hi>Nouember,</hi> 1618.</p>
            <p>Written <hi>By</hi> HENRY GOODCOLE <hi>Preacher of the Word of</hi> God, and his daily visiter, during his impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonment in the Gaole of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Edw: All-de</hi> dwelling neere Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18873:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18873:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Sir <hi>Henry Mountague,</hi> Lord <hi>Chiefe Iustice</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> grace and Honour bee multiplyed here, and by the mercies of Iesus Christ, fruition of his glory, and euerlasting Happinesse <hi>hereafter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable,</hi> I am in a great straite, betwixt hope and dispaire standing, your worthines and wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to trouble with such an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy labour as this is; for which my ambitious and bolde presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I stand at the Barre of your lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Iudgement, and deeme to bee arraigned, conuicted, and adiudged of the same. But my hearty desire of the welfare of our now florishing <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> and her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, which I pray God long it may so continue, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained zeale, thereunto is constrained thus to breake foorth, thus to proclaime vnto all her dwellers therein, your great mercy to distressed soules, desiring to comfort them, &amp; by all meanes possible to saue them, aswel as your Iustice &amp; zeale to punish and cut of offenders: both which to be conioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in your Noble heart, of late are expressed, In sending to a perplexed and distressed soule, when time of neede did greatly require the same (phisicke) by that heauenly Phisiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Messenger of God Mr. <hi>Robert Pricket,</hi> into whose Industrious labour and haruest, I was bolde to intrude my
<pb facs="tcp:18873:3"/>
selfe, and thrust in my sickle. And now further desirous to explaine vnto the world, the good successe and blessing that God in his great mercy gaue to our willing labours: Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly crauing your Honours patronage and acceptance, which if your Hon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vouchsafe to graunt, will incourage vs to be at your Hon: command in the like seruice. And being sheltred vnder your fauourable countenance and acceptance, wil make both the cause &amp; help of our Ministrie, respectiuely regarded and welcome, to whome wee shall be called. And this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour now published, &amp; conuayed, my only ayme &amp; intent by dispersing of it, is to vestigiate your Hon: steps, to wish &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour the generall good of all, &amp; particular hurt of none: The Lord Almighty of his great goodnesse long continue your Hon: amongst his people for their welfare, to be as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer your Religious courses haue explained, to be Noble, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, and Religious, a defence to such as else would be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, and an incourager of the good and vertuous.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all readines, and humilitie, to be commaunded: <hi>HENRY GOODCOLE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18873:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Amentable and perilous, are these times and dayes wherein we now liue, to see the abounding of sinne and iniquity, and pure religion, to the corrupt hearts, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable fantasies of men, to be wrested, as they list, to finde diuersitie of Religions, Sects and Schismes, as the hearts, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and manners of men differ, thereunto they equiuolate their profession and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the which instability, wherein there should not in the least manner be any inconstancie, breedes corrupt liues, and vnrecoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable downfalls, of many hopefull young Gentlemen, worshipfully descended, and carefully tutered, the true meanes of preuenting such horrible wickednesse. Of which duly considering, and ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in my minde, it did in some measure perswade me to a periode of this by mee now published, before I had put penne to paper, to write, being daily experienced, that where one suckes honey, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther followeth, and thence sucketh poyson; for it is a thing most im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible, to please the humours and fantasies of all men. But when I remembred the cause I had to handle, which was for the publique good of my Countrey, to admonish them to take heede by other mens hurts and harmes, and for feare it should slip out of their mindes, This person <hi>Francis Robinson,</hi> his haynous act most remarke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and deplorable downefall, becomes my subiect, to write; insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating mee thereunto, and encouraging mee, not to neglect my intended and good determination to a generality, for feare of the barking and contradicting spirits of our age, but to performe
<pb facs="tcp:18873:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the cause and quarrell which I must write of against God and our enemies, how by a rauening Wolfe, a Romish Catholike, as he was blinded, became a blind guide to this poore Gentleman, to make him fall into the same ditch as he did, whereby like a silly simple inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Lambe by his subtill slie seducings, and inticings, his destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction befell most suddaine and fearefull. I leaue what I shall relate vnto thee to thy construction, desiring (if I may) to haue a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table censure of thee: Concluding with my hearty affection to thee, &amp; Christian admonition, howsoeuer thine is to me-ward. <hi>Stand fast in thy faith, profession, and religion,</hi> and I pray God, that other mens harmes, may make thee and all others, fearefull, carefull, and watchfull, that you fall not in such manner as many before this day haue done: the vndoubted preuention whereof is, daily to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate Gods grace from aboue, to ayde and assist thee, that thou fall not into the same mischiefes, who are as weake, fraile, and subiect to be tempted, as others before thee were. And thus with heartie prayers to God to assist thee to be a conquerour in the day of battell, and constant in the time and day of triall: I rest;</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Iesus, a labourer for thy welfare. HENRY GOODCOLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18873:4"/>
            <head>A true Declaration of the happy conuertion, contrition and godly preparition, of <hi>Francis Robinson</hi> Gentleman.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ying mens wordes are euer remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, &amp; their last déeds memorable for succéeding posterities, by them to be instructed, what vertues or vices they followed and imbraced, and by them to learne to imitate that which was good, and to eschew euill. But such is the depraued and corrupt nature of all Mankinde, and Sathans subtilty (mans mortall enemy) that dayly goeth about, and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by all meanes possible he can, to blindfolde vs, stopping vs out of the way wherein God hath appointed vs to walke, and the example of Gods children that haue trod out the way before vs. Oh how much do these our daies wherin we now liue (shew vs the too true experience of the same) that mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes for company sake, conioyne themselues in all maner of mischiefe, and runne in heapes with delight, to commit most abhominable sins, presuming on Gods patience, because he doth not presently punish, saying in the pride of their hearts, and glory of their wicked sinnes, Doth the Lord sée, marke, or regard the déeds and actions, of the sonnes of men? No, they say tush, He regards them not: And thus the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill by this meanes, gets holde of multitudes, and bringes them in the end, to shame, hell, and destruction; for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and wages of Sinne is death.</p>
            <p>Let me now my worthy Country-men, present vnto your view, the experienced reward of sinfull delights, which latey
<pb facs="tcp:18873:5"/>
befell a Gentleman by name <hi>Francis Robinson,</hi> well descended, educated, and fostred tenderly, who happening into euill company, quickly, by the lewde examples, and dispositions of others, was brought to be as wicked, and as bad as themselues, for the Deuill doth make wicked men to doe, what he cannot doe himselfe (that is) to bring men to sinne and shame, by lewd mens inticings, examples and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, to doe as they doe, to walke in their steps and wayes of wickednes, merrily to passe away their times and dayes whilst here they liue, by which tossing, carousing, and iollitie of life, they become altogether forgetfull of God, and the meanes of their saluation, which to redéeme from the Iawes of Hell, a whole world and to late repentance then small auailes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Remember</hi> O yée youthfull Gallants <hi>now your Creator in the dayes of your youth,</hi> and cast not off the yoke of God from your necke, when you are young, least he reiect you, when your strength and eye-sight faile you; that is, in your olde age: learne to tread now the pathes of his holy wayes, if ye would be assured to come to the place of his euerlasting happines, for the Lord hateth, and vtterly abhorreth all the workes and workers of sinne and iniquitie: but those that loue and feare him he maketh much of them. That you shall see, and say with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> Psalme 58. verse 10. <hi>Doubtlesse there is a God that Iudgeth the Earth, that he is a iust God and loueth righteousnes, and hateth iniquitie, repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vengeance vnto them that delight in the same,</hi> my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing sequell shall declare vnto you: example doth daily testifie, and at this present confirmes the same. I pray God the wanton and roaring Gallants of this our Age, may by them be warned, but much it is to be feared they will not: If they will not, let them take héede as they goe for company, they hang not for company, wherat, for ought I doe perceiue they make a scoffe and scorne, to thinke in that manner of dying they dye valiantly, when that it is indéed most despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, deuillish and damnable, and sauours no whit of the least sparke of Gods grace, but of contempt of God, and the
<pb facs="tcp:18873:5"/>
ripe fruit of Sathans bondslaues, which is to commit sinne, and to boast and bragge of the same, to be the full height of a reprobate soule, from which good Lord deliuer vs all.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now to confirme you how this Gentleman, as he himselfe related to me, fell, obserue what followeth.</head>
               <p>SO soone as euer he was brought into the Gaole of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> he looked round about him, and earnestly entreated those that stoode by him, to take heede of Papists, and euill company, for they were the cause of his destruction. From the Lodge he was conuayed by the Keepers into the common Gaole, where he remained some two houres, on Tuesday the tenth day of Nouember, from which side he was remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to the Maister side by Warrant, from the right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sir <hi>Henry Mountague,</hi> Lord Chiefe Iustice of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who for the same was most hartily and humbly thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and counted it, as well it did deserue, a great fauour from my Lord, there to sequester him, the better to prepare and fit him for his end. And that no meanes might be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to worke that good worke in him of repentance, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and assurance of his saluation, like a good Samaritane that Honourable and religious Iudge, as hée had wounded him by denouncing his iust Iudgement of deserued death, which is to flesh and blood most fearefull and vnwelcome, yet such was his Honorable care towards him, which is worthy of remembrance, what lay in his power hee did to comfort him, and in nothing more appeared the same, then in the sending of my painefull Brother and fellow labourer in Gods worke (Maister <hi>Pricket</hi>) who did most grauely and wisely apply to his distressed soule (such comfort) as that I doe constantly beléeue, the lost sheepe was brought home againe to the folde of Iesus Christ.</p>
               <p>Whereof most constantly <hi>Robinson</hi> said, he was assured: for the spirit of God did inwardly confirme the same to him, vndoubtedly to beléeue it, of which most comfortable words
<pb facs="tcp:18873:6"/>
and effectuall working, we were most glad, and ioyfull, that to our weake meanes, God rich in mercy, had giuen and sent such a blessing and cooperation. Thus séeing our industrie and labour begin to prosper to the glory of God, the sauing and winning to God a sinfull soule, I was bolde to put my Sickle into another mans Haruest, and bestowed likewise my poore willing paines and industry: with what they were I haue here published, and what effect they tooke, I praise God, I laboured not in vaine, but found a hungry and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie soule, apt and ready, to receiue them from my hands, and the fruites thereof, repentance, contrition, and faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A relation how we spent Wednesday Euening, being the eleuenth of Nouember.</head>
               <p>SO soone as euer I came vnto him, he did like a poore, sicke, and wounded Patient, desirous of cure, tell his whole griefe, not mincingly or sparingly, but faithfully and truly, that I might the better apply and endeauour to comfort him, the beginning of his euils he tolde me, and how hée grew worse and worse by degrées, the manner he related, and as néere as I can from his owne mouth spoken, deliuered here the same. Wherein as himselfe obserued we may sée the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note place="margin">Note this.</note> of Sinne, which if it be not preuented in time, how it getteth the masterie of vs, and when we would shake off our olde accustomed and habituall sinnes, we cannot easily doe it, because it cleaueth fast vnto vs, that of our selues, by no meanes we are able, but by the helpe of God, who is willing, and ready at all times to helpe and succour vs therein, if we call and seeke for his sauing health.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Our conference.</head>
               <p>HIs lamentable downefall thus begun, the which, O<note place="margin">Note this.</note> would to God the carelesse and loose liuers, within this Citie of <hi>London,</hi> would take notice of (namely) that he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooke God first, before God forsooke him, at which wordes
<pb facs="tcp:18873:6"/>
he much lamented, that the Deuill had so blinded and deluded him, to forsake and deny the profession (and faith of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) to embrace and cleaue vnto the Hereticall doctrine of Romish Popery, which are but lying vanities, and vaine shaddowes, no way substanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all for the maine ground-worke of a Christian mans salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. An in-sight, whereinto after it pleased God to be so mercifull to grant him, hée from the bottome of his heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, (that false and Antechristian Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) sorrowing nothing more for any thing, then for that time, that in that Church hée had béene a member, and reioycing and ioying in nothing more, then that God had opened his eyes to sée his former errors, and to giue his heart and soule a light, with earnest desiring and thirsting to be accepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, into the company of the true and faithfull beléeuers of the Church of England, which his soule did assure him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly was the true Church of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His Progression.</head>
               <p>VVHen there was warrant out for his apprehension,<note place="margin">Note this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> he then was in <hi>Darby,</hi> and hearing that there was waite laide for him, posted thence some sixe miles, but had not the power any further to trauell, but returned to <hi>Darby,</hi> to goe and Iustifie his foule fact, which by the narrow loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into, and examining of a Lawyer there inhabiting, with whome he was at variance, his designes were discouered.</p>
               <p>When he was thus discouered, and sent vp to <hi>London</hi> to the right Honourable the Lord Chauncellor of England, by whom he was examined, and vrged to confesse, that his foule fact of high Treason: stood stoutly in the deniall of the same. But hée that sitteth in Heauen laughed him to scorne, and most wonderfully disclosed the secret of his heart, and his foule fact, whereof he thought none should haue knowne, for being re-examined by the right Hon: Sir <hi>Henry Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague</hi> Knight, Lord chiefe Iustice of England, to him as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly he did, denyed his foule fact, but behold héere how the
<pb facs="tcp:18873:7"/>
hand of God laide holde on him, and how the eye of God was watching ouer him, and disclosed him, by deliuering a Key to <hi>Humphrey Smith,</hi> to goe to a Truncke, wherein his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Commission was, and diuers other writings.</p>
               <p>It pleased Almighty God, who teacheth all mens hearts wisdome, that the right Hon: the Lord Chiefe Iustice thus bethought himselfe, to know the truth, séeing as yet he could get no knowledge, he set spies to watch those that had accesse vnto him, to finde out by them, this foule fact, which most miraculously by the carefull examination of <hi>Humphrey Smith</hi> (by that graue Iudge Sir <hi>Heury Mountague</hi>) came soone to light thereof, who tolde his Hon: of a Truncke of writings: which so strangely discouered, <hi>Robinson</hi> thereat was greatly amazed, thinking it a thing impossible to be knowne at all to any; who when that he saw he was disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, betooke himselfe (of an obstinate denyer) to become an humble, contrite, and sorrowfull confessor of what he had done, and implored mercy and fauour at honourable persons hands, of whome he little deserued the same. But he out of his most Noble disposition, denyed not any the least of his requests, and humble suites, but buryed all his former vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deseruings, in the bowels of pitty and compassion, grieuing to sée what a most wretched course he had runne, that the Iustice of the King, and his Lawes, did iustly challenge his deserued deoth.</p>
               <p>Nay further note and consider I pray you, for these were the wordes procéeding out of his owne mouth: how God did make his owne wisdome to be foolishnesse, therewith to laugh himselfe to scorne, that presuming he had some sound iudgement and true knowledge in the Law, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which hée too much built and relyed, for his knowledge therein, was but the flash of pride &amp; presumption: for when the right Worshipfull, graue, wise and learned in the Law (Sir <hi>Henry Yeluerton</hi> his Maiesties Atturney Generall) heard, said, that his intention, made the Law to take holde on him, he thereat was silenced, and confessed his blindnes, and ignorance, and that his eyes were shut, and heart infatuated
<pb facs="tcp:18873:7"/>
euen vnto the day of his tryall, in which it pleased God to reueale to him, his grosse mistaking of the Law, and guilt in this his foule fact, which when he well and plainely percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; he then remembred that portion of Scripture which he formerly had read in the 3. Chap. of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> which stroake re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse of conscience in him, and that the whole world might take notice that the Iudgements of God had ouertaken him, aduisedly coated the place recited for memory, that men should feare to offend in the like case, least they come to haue in the end the like reward for their paines.</p>
               <p>Lastly, he confessed the person, and first occasion that drew him to commit his foule fact, which was (Couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) the foundation of all mischiefe. And lodging at the Swan at <hi>Charing Crosse,</hi> there he grew acquainted with one (<hi>Morgan</hi> a Romish Catholicke) whom he tolde of his thirsting after money, who then shewed the fruites of his Religion, to bring by his wicked deuice, the body of this Gentleman to his destruction, and (had not God in his great mercy preuented the same destroyed) his soule also, for he went the right way thereunto, by crafty seducing of him to become a Papist. And thus, he leauing and for saking his God, and Religion, his sodaine downefall afterwards hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, the which he heartily prayed to Almighty God might teach, warne, and terrifie others from the like attempt: and thus spake that morning a little before hée receiued the most holy and blessed Sacrament, of the Supper of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, (said<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) that <hi>Morgan</hi> did seduce him first, from his Religion, and after that, his heart was inclinable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, what <hi>Morgans</hi> poysoned tongue of mischiefe would speake, of which kinde of people and their Religion, hée desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all people to beware and to flye their Doctrine, it tending onely to mischiefe and destruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His great desire of giuing satisfaction so farre as he could, to those whom he had greatly offended.</head>
               <p>HIs God and Creator, hée acknowledged most highly by his foule fact to haue offended, and for attonement
<pb facs="tcp:18873:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18873:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18873:9"/>
he fully relyed on the meritorious death and passion of Iesus Christ.</p>
               <p>The Kings most excellent Maiestie in a most high nature he had offended, for which he was heartily sorrie, and craued pardon, willing to render vp his life, acknowledging his death to be deserued; and further saying, that if he were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so much to be tortured, he deserued the same, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly embraced the same, that so his Maiesties iust wrath might be appeased.</p>
               <p>Of all the people in generall, he heartily craued pardon, that he had beene a Runnagate from their blessed Societie, heartily desiring their prayers vnto Almighty God for him. And those from whom he had, by his deceitfull meanes, and guiles, gotten away any mony, he to his power (of my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) laboured to giue satisfaction, sorrowing that hee altogether was disabled, to doe what his hearts desire was.</p>
               <p>Thus (deare Country-men) I finding a wandring shéepe, and distressed soule, wanting cure, and care, séeking, and earnestly destring to be brought home againe, from whence he had strayed, I set vnto him my helping hand, and now publish vnto thée, how in the sweet Pastures of Gods word, this wandring shéepe, was directed, fed, and comforted, by praying sometimes, and meditating at other times, on these sequent portions of Scripture, out of which, I thanke God, he receiued great comfort, and we Gods Labourers, richly rewarded for the same: That we confidently beléeue, our labour was not in vaine with him, but wee haue brought home againe the lost Shéepe to Gods Church here on earth, and to his triumphant Church in Heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The prayers wherein he was exercised day and night.</head>
               <p>O Lord my God, in thee doe I put my trust, let me neuer be confounded. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>OOmnipotent, and most mercifuil God and Creator, great is thy mercy in mans creation, for thy mercie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedeth
<pb facs="tcp:18873:9"/>
all thy workes, in the mercifull preseruing of man, who without thy blessed ayde, would suddainly come, and quickly slide to vtter confusion, didst not thou in thy great mercy and prouidence daily preuent the same.</p>
               <p>Behold me, I humbly pray thée, the worke of thy own hands, and looke vpon me, with the eye of thy aboundant mercy, that so thereby thy wrath and fury which iustly by my manifolde sinnes and transgressions I haue deserued, may be appeased; the remembrance of the multitudes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of afflicteth me so sorely, that I can finde no peace or rest at, for they are a weight too heauie for me to beare: I am ready to faint, and fall vnder them: O send me Lord Iesus power from aboue, to helpe and support me, that I faint not, and finally fall vnder them. Come vnto mee, O my swéet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, come quickly, and powre in, into this distressed soule of mine, thy blessed baulme of thy mercy, O stablish my vnconstant heart, and wandring thoughts, with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of thy frée spirit: for in my selfe, O Lord my God, I finde no comfort at all, my conscience doth so accuse me, and thy iudgements doe so affright me, that without thou in thy aboundant mercy helpe (O Lord) I vtterly perish. Haue mercy vpon me, O Lord, haue mercy vpon me, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the multitude of thy mercies, doe away mine offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: wash mee, and cleanse mee from all my sinnes, make me a cleane heart I pray thée, and renue a right spirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, and now let my poore distressed soule, with thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly grace be comforted, whose onely stay and refuge O Lord thou art, for whom haue I in heauen (O Lord) but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thée, and nothing here on earth doth my soule more desire, or delight in, then in thee, and in thy sauing health. Forsake mee not therefore, who thus flyeth to thee for succour and comfort, and vnder the shadow of thy wings to be defended. O shelter me vnder the same, for who shall worship thée in the pit or graue, then let my soule liue, and it shall for euer praise thee in the congregation of thy Saints, in the land of the euer-liuing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18873:10"/>
               <head>Certaine deuout inward comforts by him conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually vttered and vsed.</head>
               <p>GRant vnto me (O God) frée pardon of all my sinnes, and remember not the sinnes of my youth: as my Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, pride, wantonnes, and lustes of the flesh.</p>
               <p>Grant vnto me Lord Iesus grace, at no time to dispaire or distrust of thy fauour and mercy towards mée.</p>
               <p>Grant vnto mée O my God, and send into my sad and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed soule, a tast of thy swéete mercy.</p>
               <p>Grant vnto me, O swéete, and gracious Iesus, a willing minde, and heart to loue thee onely, and grace to pray to thée faithfully.</p>
               <p>Grant vnto me Father of mercy, thy gracious assistance, inable me to withstand all the Deuils temptations.</p>
               <p>Grant vnto mée, O thou the wel-spring and fountaine of all good desires, grace, to put out of my minde, all worldly and vaine cogitations, which may now hinder me in thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, or in the meanes of my saluation.</p>
               <p>Grant vnto me, O blessed Bridegroome of my soule, assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance heere, that I shall be with thee this day, in thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory.</p>
               <p>Grant vnto me now, O thou the life of my soule, that though now I am to dye ignomiously, yet that I shall rise againe in the day of Resurrection most gloriously, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde thée in thy perfect glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Prayer wherein hee was exercised.</head>
               <p>O Father of mercy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and God of all consolation, whether shall I flia from thée, oh where shall my poore distressed and sinfull soule féeke for peace, and comfort thus perplexed? to come to thée the fountaine of all goodnes and comfort, I dare not, for I haue sinned against thee onely, and committed many most grieuous offences in thy presence, which maketh
<pb facs="tcp:18873:10"/>
me detestable in thy sight, and to flye the same if that I could for feare of thy heauy displeasure. To approach thy courts O Lord, to pray to thée for mercy, or to praise thée O Lord I cannot tell how, for I haue béene so accustomed to walke in all euill wayes, that now to begin to walke in thy wayes, I am not in the least manner able, for my tongue is still tyed, my heart is still obdurate and rebellious, my thoughts are wandring whilest I am in this Tabernacle of my flesh, after the vanities of this world. Turne me O Lord my God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, and I shall be turned, conuert me vnto thée, and I shall be conuerted, call me home againe vnto thée, and take me to thy mercy: oh teach me thy statutes, and I will kéepe them euen to the end, vnty my tongue to praise thée, mollifie my heart to loue and feare thée, direct and enlighten my will, memory, and vnderstanding to delight and séeke thée, and to loue nothing more then thée, and in thy seruice to be busied. Thy worke O Lord this onely is, fréely thou giuest the same to whom thou pleasest, Oh make me my Lord and God I pray thée in the aboundance of thy mercies, partaker of the same, whose multitude of sinnes makes me thereof vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>This Prayer he saide at the time of his Death.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>His continuall prayer and hearty eiaculation.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>O Lord haue mercy vpon me and saue mee, for in thee doe I onely put my trust.</p>
               <p>O Thou the Sauiour of all Mankinde, and most merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Samaritane, to thée I now flye, in the holes of thy wounds to be sheltred and defended, hearken I most humbly pray thée, and incline thine eares vnto me, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake me not euen for thy mercyes sake, for my soule wholly trusteth in thée and thy sauing health. Thy arrowes O Lord doe sticke fast in me, and of thy terrible Iudgements I
<pb facs="tcp:18873:11"/>
am sore affraid. As thou camest into the world, in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of time to be a Iesus to all Mankinde, come now and be my IESUS for thy ayde I lacke: as thou camest into the world to be an aduocate for all mankinde, become mine now—I pray thée. Pleade thou my cause O Lord, and let not my enemies triumph ouer me, but ridde me and deliuer me out of the handes of my enemies euen for thy mercy sake. Oh plead for my wickednes thy righteousnes; pleade for my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience thy obedience; pleade for my pardon thy meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Death and Passion; plead for my blessednes, thy accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednes; pleade for my life, thy death; pleade for my weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, thy all sufficiencie; pleade for my wretchednes and mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to haue the long white Roabe of thy Innocency to couer me withall, that I being therewith roabed, may beholde the glory of thy Tabernacle and beauty of thy holy Temple, without which I cannot, nor shall not be able to stand but appeare most vile. Thy former mercyes shewed to many of thy seruants, O Lord imboldens me, to approach vnto thee and to lye at thy gates of mercy, expecting thy comfortable answer. O come vnto me my Lord Iesus, come quickly shew vnto me the light of thy countenance, and then I shall be whole, accept now of my teares, and vnfained sorrow and contrition, for that I haue offended so good and gracious a God: abandon and put out of my minde, loue of the world and feare of death, and fixe my heart and thoughts onely on thée, and thy sauing health: swéeten this bitter cup of death vnto me, to make it acceptable and welcome, not fearing or dispairing thereof to taste, but willingly to drinke it vp: O swéeten it with assurance now to my soule, when this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary life of mine is fled away, to inioy thy euerlasting glory which thou hast prepared for me in Iesus Christ, thy alone Sonne and my onely Sauiour. O giue me now and sound into my eares, and assure my heart, of the Théeues paradice, of <hi>Stephens</hi> vision, which is to see thy onely Sonne my Sauiour sitting at thy right hand in glory. And now to thée O Lord, of all Spirits as is most deue, and to thée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone belongeth, I am prepared ioyfully and willingly, to
<pb facs="tcp:18873:11"/>
giue and render vnto thée this body and soule of mine which are thy due, and which of thy blessed mercy, I receiued from thy blessed hands: Lord Iesu receiue them, come Lord Iesus, hast thée vnto me, come O my God and make no long tarrying, but méete me: I expect thy comming, Lord Iesu receiue me in mercy, <hi>Amen.</hi> And these thy mercyes I craue in the mediation of my Sauiour, now faithfully pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and repeating his forme of prayer.</p>
               <p>Our Father which art in Heauen, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The portions of Scriptures whereon hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually meditated, after these Prayers were ended.</head>
               <p>The 8. Chap. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> in that he much delighted to read, in the 5. Chap. 2. Epistle <hi>Cor:</hi> in the 4. Chap. first ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Epistle of Iohn, in the 4. Chap. <hi>Hebrewes. 18</hi> Chap. <hi>St Luke,</hi> the Parable of the poore and humble <hi>Publicane. Plalme 6. 25. 26. 27. 28. 31. 32. 34. 35. 38. 40. 42. 43. 51. 55. 56. 86.</hi> Who so is pleased to peruse these coated Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I hope, as they did yeelde comfort to the dead, they shall no lesse bee thought worthy of the meditation of the liuing.</p>
               <p>I Must pay two Legacies which I promised vnto him I would, one to the right Honourable Sir <hi>Henry Mounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue</hi> Knight, Lord chiefe Iustice of England, his humble thankes and hearty prayers to God, to requite and redouble his blessings here and hereafter, for his Christian and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious care of his distressed soule, to séeke and send meanes, to comfort and saue the same, praysing and attributing to God the glory, who by the weake meanes of our Ministry, hath called and taken home now againe to his most blessed fould, his wandring shéepe, which Honourable care and christian Industry of his, shall remaine memorable in this world, and vndoubtedly rewarded by God in his Kingdoms of glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18873:12"/>Another Legacy bequeathed, to the right worthy, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, graue and Worshipfull Sir <hi>Henry Yeluerton,</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Atturney Generall, to whome Mr. <hi>Francis Robinson</hi> acknowledged himselfe very much bounden, in instructing, and inlightning his vnderstanding in the letter of the Law, wherein he presumed of his owne wit and vnderstanding to make euasion: but by his grauety and wisdome he so confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, that hée to the glory of God being so manifestly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced, and shewed what a haynous fact he had done, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God for the same, and prayed most heartily vnto God, to continue and to increase such happy Guardians to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties peace, and weale publike of this whole Realme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His owne relation of the beginning and proceeding in his foule fact, spoken the same morning a little before he went to his execution.</head>
               <p>NOt long had hee béene acquainted with the fashions or Citie of <hi>London,</hi> for he had not béene in <hi>London</hi> aboue foure times before that time he did put in practise his dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable fact: his suites, places, and persons, were not of meane degrée, such was his ambition: But to the Kings most excellent Maiestie and his Royall Court hee wholy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressed himselfe, and by petition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and helpe of others his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties attendants, moued his Maiestie for a Commission and protection, vnder his Maiesties hand, and great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> concerning the reforming of the diuers abuses, of Uictualers, Maulsters and Usurers, hauing not long before heard, a Petition was preferred for reformation of some such abuses. He thereupon conceiued presently, that this was a fitting subiect for him to worke on, to get thereby money to supply his wants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to satisfie his greedy minde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though he bought it in the end at a most deare price and rate.</p>
               <p>For the better contriuing and effecting of his determina tion and purpose, he got an accomplice by name <hi>Morgan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  </hi> with whom he got first acquainted, at the Swan at <hi>Charing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Crosse,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18873:12"/>
and from thence both of them remoued to the signe of the Mayden-head at Saint <hi>Giles</hi> in the Fields, where hee tolde Morgan his Companion, his Designes were plotted, and resolued of, what should be by him afterward put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, which truly so it happened. And presuming too much vpon that small vnderstanding and knowledge he had in the Law, of himselfe drew the forme of a Commission, and thereinto inserted to make it beare the more validity, the names of diuers worthy Attendants about his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Court and most Royall person, to them from his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie directed, in his Maiesties name to aske, cease, leuie, and receiue in foure seuerall Shieres in this Kingdome, certaine seuerall summes of money, according to the tenure of their Commission, to them from his Maiestie directed.</p>
               <p>This forged Commission being by him alone inuented, and trecherously deuised, brought it to a Scriuener in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> where hee had the same ingrossed, and without the knowledge or priuity of any, did put thereunto a counterfait great Seale, for the true great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> and so by vertue thereof, though none at all there was, did aske, leuie, and receiue at seuerall sittings in Commission, though no lawfull authority he had thereunto, the summe of twenty eight pounds and fiue pence deceitfully, of the Kings liege people. And this he did for the space of a moneth continue and procéede, not thinking of the all séeing eye of Almighty God, that would discouer him, and suddainly confound him, and his most wicked deuice, whereof when he least imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or suspected, euen then bewrayed his treacherous heart and detestable fact.</p>
               <p>After the time of his apprehension for this most detestable and foule fact, behold how stedfastly he stoode in the Iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the same, and vsed the name of a worthy Knight, Sir <hi>Robert Maxwell,</hi> to say he had his priuity and help ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, (of which) he in the least manner was not acquainted; and for which his most false and vniust aspersion on him, at the time of his death, on his knées, and salt teares fast trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe, most humbly, and heartily craued, his frée par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning
<pb facs="tcp:18873:13"/>
of him for the same: and said, it was the Diuels inticing of him, to doe what he did (namely) that foule and filthy treacherous déede of his, and that which did much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict and terrifie his soule, more then Death it selfe, whose grim countenance he did behold so to accuse an innocent guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, worshipfull, and worthy Gentleman, that thereby himselfe who onely was guilty of that foule fact, might be fréed; whereof God in his Iustice would not approue, nor be so deluded, but brought him the plotter, contriuer, and actor of villany, to receiue his iust reward for the same, that the mischiefe by him pretended, to light on others, did at the last fall on his owne pate. And the net and snare which hee had priuily layd, and secretly spread abroade to intrap ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, therein himselfe was ensnared.</p>
               <p>And thus he concluded: Let all take héede, and beware of couetousnes, content themselues with that they haue, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour honestly with their hands for their owne liuing: for the honest and industrious Labourer, God will for euer blesse, but they that doe trust in lying vanities, to get wealth by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull meanes and wiles, let them know, said hee, that though God for a while forbeare them, yet his Iustice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires to render vengeance to them, as iustly on me now he hath done.</p>
               <p>Like a Lambe going to the slaughter so went he vnto his death, prepared before to suffer the same, willingly, patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ioyfully: and our confidence is such of him, that he is receiued into the Fold of that most blessed heauenly Flocke, whereof <hi>Iesus Christ,</hi> the great Shéepheard of vs all is the keeper and defender, and into which number, the Lord Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty in his aboundant mercy giue grace to all, daily so to prepare themselues, that in the end they may be found wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thereof. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb facs="tcp:18873:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The conclusion.</head>
               <p>THus deare Country-men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> haue I exercised your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and boldly presumed to incurre your censures, for the zeale that I beare to the soules of men, destring, and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hartily praying to Almighty God, that his downefall may make all others wary, and carefull to flye sinne, the reward whereof, and to the delighters therein, you haue heard. And although God in his mercy deferres to punish, expecting mens conuersion, which if they doe not in his expected time, hee payes home in the end, such their neglect of him, with most fearefull and vnrecouerable downefalls.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
