<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pauls crovvne of reioycing. Or The maner how to heare the word with profit. By Thomas Granger preacher of the word at Botterwike in Holland, neere Boston in Lincolnshire</title>
            <title>Pauls crowne of rejoycing.</title>
            <author>Granger, Thomas, b. 1578.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02036</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114984</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850204</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850204</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15391</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02036)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15391)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1272:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pauls crovvne of reioycing. Or The maner how to heare the word with profit. By Thomas Granger preacher of the word at Botterwike in Holland, neere Boston in Lincolnshire</title>
                  <title>Pauls crowne of rejoycing.</title>
                  <author>Granger, Thomas, b. 1578.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. S[nodham] for Thomas Pauier, and are to be sold at his shop in Yuie lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>A treatise.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15391:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15391:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PAVLS CROVVNE OF REIOYCING.<hi>OR</hi> The manner how to heare the <hi>Word with profit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By THOMAS GRANGER preacher of the word at <hi>Botterwike </hi>in <hi>Holland,</hi> neere <hi>Boſton</hi> in Lincolnſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>IAMES 1. 12.</bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed is the man that endureth temptation, for when he is tried, hee ſhall receiue the Crowne of life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that loue him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Pauier,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Yuie</hi> lane.
1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15391:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15391:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVL and vertuous Lady, the Lady, IOAN ALTHAM, temporall happineſſe, and eternall bleſſedneſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GOOD MADAME:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AY it pleaſe your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to accept this ſmall treatiſe, of the right hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the word. Small it is, not in reſpect of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect; for to be a good hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer is no leſſe excellent a gift of grace, then to be a good ſpeaker: but in reſpect of the forme, phraſe, and manner of handling thereof, wherein I haue faſhioned my ſelfe to the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of vulgar ignorant people, euen ſuch like as by Gods prouidence I haue heene called vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, who are fitter for milke then ſtrong meates.
<pb facs="tcp:15391:3"/>
Yet whatſoeuer it is, ſuch it ſhall be, as your Ladiſhip ſhall accept it, and to ſpeake ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly without flatterie, which J euer hated, your amiable diſpoſition to Vertue, &amp; Piety, in your yong age, as I well obſerued, when here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore I liued at the houſe of the good Knight Sir <hi>Iohn Leuenthorp</hi> your father; and my often remembrance thereof vpon occaſions, and now vpon this occaſion alſo, as alſo the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular duty that I owe to your ancient, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honoured familie, and to you in ſpeciall, haue moued me, and made me the bolder to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer this vnworthy Preſent vnto you, deſiring you to accept it only as a token of a thankfull minde, and ſincere affection; which remaine euer diſpoſed to the performance of any ſeruice wherein your Ladiſhip by me may be pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips in all <hi>dutie to command</hi> THOMAS GRANGER.</signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>Botterwike</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> neere <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>Lincoln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi> 
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15391:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PAVLS</hi> CROVVNE OF <hi>Reioycing.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 THES. 2. 13.</bibl>
               <q>For this cauſe alſo, thanke we God without ceaſing, that when yee receiued of vs the word of the preaching of God, yee receiued it not as the word of men, but as it is indeed, the word of God, which alſo worketh in you that beleeue.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the former Chapter, at the ſecond verſe, the Apoſtle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth a congratulation, whereby he reioyceth in the behalfe of the Theſſalonians for their effectuall faith, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentloue, and patience in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, wherein they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled, as they became enſamples to all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in <hi>Macedonia</hi> and <hi>Achaia.</hi> Now in this ſecond Chapter from the firſt verſe to the 13. he maketh a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion; wherin he laboreth to confirme them in this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15391:4"/>
effectuall and fruitfull faith, and that by an argument drawne from his true Apoſtleſhip, which by three principall reaſons hee prooueth, and approueth vnto them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By his entrance in vnto them, which was not in outward ſhew and pompe, but in trauaile, and in the feare of God. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. 2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By his preaching, which was not by inſincerity, that is, falſe and corrupt doctrine, impure affections, and guile, but wherein he approueth himſelfe to God. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. 4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By his intire loue and affection towards them, in that hee vſed no flattery, coloured couetouſneſſe, or vaine-glory, but was gentle among them, as a nurſe cheriſheth her children, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. 6. 7.</p>
            <p>Now this his ſincere loue and affection, hee demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrateth by the effects, and tokens thereof, which doe teſtifie the ſincerity, and ſimplicity of his heart.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Effect or token was his readineſſe, to deale not onely the Goſpell vnto them, but euen his owne ſoule, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Was his labour and trauell, becauſe he would not be chargeable vnto them, whereof they had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Was his holy, godly, and righteous conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His faithfulneſſe in executing his office for their good; in exhorting them, comforting them, and intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them (as a father his children) to walke accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their reall calling, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. 12.</p>
            <p>Now taking occaſion at theſe duties of his miniſtery; namely his exhorting of them, his comforting of them, and beſeeching of them: he returneth to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer gratulation in the 13 and 14 <hi>verſes:</hi> wherein hee alſo reioyceth in their behalfe, becauſe they receiued the word, not as his word, but as the word of God,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15391:4"/>
that ſent him; whereof this was a manifeſt token, euen their conuerſion, their faith, and obedience, and daily increaſe therein.</p>
            <p>In this gratulation, two things are to be conſidered, the Manner and the Matter. Firſt, concerning the manner, or forme thereof, it is expounded by way of thankeſgiuing to God, the author of this harmony &amp; concord betweene him the Paſtour teaching them from God, and them his ſtocke receiuing his doctrine as from God.</p>
            <p>In that hee expounds his gratulation by way of thankſgiuing, he teacheth them two things: firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that his preaching, labour, induſtrie, and gifts, wrought not this faith, and obedience in them, but God by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit inwardly, and by his Miniſtery outwardly. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 5. 6. Who is <hi>Paul,</hi> who <hi>Apollos, but Ministers by whom</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 5. 6.</note>
               <hi>ye beleeued, as God hath giuen to euery man? Ego plantaui, Apollos rigauit,</hi> &amp;c. The Apoſtle therefore conſidering how apt we are of our ſelues to attribute too much to the meanes, and to inſiſt on the ſecond cauſe, reuoketh them to God the principall cauſe, that hee alone may be praiſed; and glorified for all thiugs, and in all things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He teacheth them hereby, that their faith is not of themſelues, but of God, and that thereof both he and they by his example ought to glorifie God in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him thanks for this grace.</p>
            <p>Againe, whereas he giueth thanks without ceaſing, he firſt ſheweth his faithfulnes, his loue, earneſt deſire, that hee had of their conuerſion, and now his great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing in their conuerſion: which two things are eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent tokens of a true Apoſtle: great thankes, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall thankes, (you know) do preſuppoſe a great good turne; and ſuch a benefit that one acknowledgeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe euer the better for: ſo the Apoſtle preferres here this benefit, euen the bleſſing of his Miniſtery in their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15391:5"/>
faith and obedience, before the cheifeſt earthly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and in the 19. verſe hee ſaith, they were his hope. <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 1.</note>his ioy, and crowne of reioycing, Likewiſe in <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 1. he calls them his beloued, his longed for, his ioy, and his crowne.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas he giueth thankes without ceaſing, he doth put them in minde, exhort, and warne them, to be continually thankefull for this endleſſe loue, mercy, and grace of God: in calling them out of darkeneſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his meruailous light. Such a benefit as this, whereby we doe not onely eſcape death, but obtaine eternall life, ought we alwaies to remember, and by all meanes to manifeſt our thankfulneſſe for the ſame; both heart, mouth, and hand, ought to be enlarged, euer to praiſe, and thanke him by thought, word and deede, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if wee be not for euer thankefull for this endleſſe benefit, we may iuſtly prouoke the Lord to ſhorten his hand, and to take his graces from vs.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, whereas hee giueth thankes without ceaſing we obſerue what is the greateſt matter of ioy, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing to a faithfull ſhepheard, namely, the faith and obedience of his flock to his doctrine, inſtructions, and exhortations; not as from him, but as from God: as the huſbandman reioyceth in a plentifull harueſt, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting all his labours and trauels in ſeede time; euen ſo the true ſhepheard reioyceth in the fruits of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and ſeeing a plentifull harueſt towards, is glad that God hath made him an inſtrument to gather his wheate, euen the ſoules of men, into his Barne.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter hath cauſe of reioycing, and thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing in the faithfull diſcharge of his calling, when his conſcience doth aſſure him, that he hath kept himſelfe innocent from the bloud of all men, and hath kept no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing back, but to his vtmoſt power and grace giuen him, hath declared all the counſell of God, by word, <note place="margin">Act. 20. 26. 27.</note>and example of life, <hi>Act</hi> 20. 26. 27. he hath I ſay cauſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15391:5"/>
of reioycing herein, though hee ſee no fruits of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, as the Apoſtle ſaith 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 15. <hi>Wee are vnto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 15.</note>
               <hi>God the ſweete ſauour of Chriſt, in them that are ſaued, and in them that periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when his miniſterie is effectual in men to beget and increaſe faith in them, to regeneration, and to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, then is he the ſauour of life vnto life, and there is double matter of reioycing, and thankeſgiuing. <hi>Paul</hi> little reioyced in his owne grace, and conſcionable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his owne dutie, neither eſteemed much all his labours and ſufferings, when he ſaw them not effectuall in the conuerting ſinners vnto God: but when hee had done all that he could, he complaineth that he had run in vaine, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 11. <hi>I am in feare of you, leaſt I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 11.</note>
               <hi>labour on you in vaine. i.</hi> ſeeing no fruit of my labour in your conuerſion.</p>
            <p>The matter of the gratulation, and thankſgiuing, is their Faith, which is not ſimply named, but propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by way of circumlocution, and as it were deſcribed by certaine degrees.</p>
            <p>The firſt degree in this deſcription, or rather definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their faith, is their hearing of the word, <hi>[when yee receiued of vs the word of the preaching of God,]</hi> which words in the greeke are thus, <hi>[becauſe receiuing the word of hearing from vs of God:]</hi> both haue one meaning, but I rather follow the Greeke verbatim, becauſe he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth here eſpecially of their act of beleeuing, the firſt degree whereof is hearing, and emplyeth his act of preaching in theſe words <hi>(from,</hi> or <hi>of vs.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is called the word of the hearing of God, becauſe there is no light or ground of the Goſpell in mans rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; he hath not the leaſt ſparkle of this knowledge of God in Chriſt in him, therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 14. <hi>Faith commeth by hearing, and hearing by the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 14.</note>
               <hi>Adam</hi> was created perfect man in all the faculties of his reaſonable ſoule, yet was hee without this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15391:6"/>
which was hid in God, and reuealed, and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to him by God himſelfe after his fall, Gen. 3. 15. who foreſeeing the fall, foreſaw the remedy alſo. This ſauing knowledge God likewiſe reuealed to Abraham, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 18. and afterward preached the ſame by typicall ceremonies, and by the Prophets, to his church: laſtly, by his owne Sonne, who hath reuealed all the wiſdome of God, concerning mans iuſtification, and ſaluation, and accompliſht the ſame in himſelfe; and the ſonne ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all power and authoritie giuen of his Father in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, hath preached the ſame to vs Gentiles, by his Apoſtles, and Euangeliſts, Paſtours, and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers: Againe, it is called the word of hearing after the imitation of the Hebrew, for the word <hi>heare,</hi> or <hi>which you heard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to heare this word of faith preached, is meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of grace, and is the firſt degree of faith. The grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, <hi>viz.</hi> naturall men, will not patiently heare this word of the preaching of God: it is to them fooliſhnes, and vaine talke, for they make this doctrine and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion groundleſſe, and to no end. Groundleſſe, becauſe they comprehend not the ſame by their carnall reaſon: To no end, becauſe they meaſure euery thing by the worldly vſe, profit, or pleaſure thereof. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 18. <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatio Euang. eſt ijs qui periunt ſtultitia.</hi> In <hi>Act.</hi> 7. 57. 58. The Iewes ſtopped their eares at <hi>Stephens</hi> preaching &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 19 24. The multitude of the <hi>Epheſians</hi> when <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> ſhewed them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of <hi>Paul</hi> and his doctrine, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 23. <hi>Ananias</hi> the high Prieſt cauſed <hi>Paul</hi> to be ſmitten on the mouth, in the very beginning of his Apologie.</p>
            <p>The Turkes, Iewes, and Papiſts are ready to ſtop their eares as ſoone as they heare the truth. Yea, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proteſtant Atheiſts, and Epicures, would at no hand heare the word, if they were at their owne libertie: they hate and deride the very name of a Preacher, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not looke on a blacke coate, (as theſe blacke mouthed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15391:6"/>
hell-hounds terme them) with a patient eye; which ſhewes that they hate our calling, and are the enemies of God, and their owne ſaluation: And that enuious &amp; murtherous heart which ſhewes it ſelfe now in mocks, and taunts, would ſhew it ſelfe in open rage and cruelty, if it were not bound in with chains and bonds of iron.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Degree of their Faith, is in theſe firſt words, <hi>[when ye receiued of vs</hi> &amp;c.] This is the ſecond degree of faith; after we haue heard the word, to giue aſſent in general to the ſame, as true, and to approue of it as good. And this is alſo meerely of grace; for there are many which heare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but their hearing is not mingled with faith, and therefore they profit nothing by hearing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 2. The Goſpell was preached to them, as alſo to vs: but <hi>the word which they heard profited not them, becauſe it was not mixed with faith in thoſe that heard it.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. <hi>The naturall man perceiueth not the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 14.</note>
               <hi>things of the ſpirit of God, for they are fooliſhineſſe vnto him; neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> In <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 18. When <hi>Paul</hi> preached at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> certaine Philoſophers of the Epicures and Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ikes heard him, but ſome counted him a babler, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, a ſetter forth of ſtrange Gods. This generall conſent vnto the word preached in man, is of grace, but this is not ſauing grace, for the Deuills beleeue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo and tremble, <hi>Iames</hi> 2. 19. I ſay it is of grace in man, <note place="margin">Iames 2. 16.</note>becauſe he cannot do this by ſupernaturall light; but the Diuels by light of nature, not by created light, but by obſeruation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Degree of their faith is expreſſed in the middle of the verſe, in theſe words <hi>[ye receiued it,</hi> &amp;c.] This word, <hi>receiued,</hi> is twiſe vſed in the engliſh, but it is of differing ſignifications, as the Greeke, and Latine doe ſhew: The former is in Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>accipere,</hi> the latter is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>excipere:</hi> the former whereof ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth to receiue or take willingly, or vnwillingly, or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15391:7"/>
after any ſort: the latter ſignifieth to entertaine or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue willingly, to welcome: Therefore of this word commeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the right hand. That which we doe vnwillingly, is done as it were with the left hand, ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterly and vntowardly; but that which we do willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is done as it were with the right hand, dexterouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, aptly, and handſomely: to receiue the word, here, therefore ſignifies to welcome, to embrace with wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingnes and liking, and to apply it to themſelues.</p>
            <p>This is then the third degree of Faith, to welcome, entertaine, embrace the word with readineſſe, willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, loue, delight, and to apply the ſame particularly to our owne hearts and conſciences. This is alſo of meere grace, without which grace none can be ſaued. Many heare the word with the outward eare, many do alſo vnderſtand it, and beleeue it to be true, but few receiue the ſame into the heart, to giue it intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">Acts 8. 21.</note>and rooting there. In <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 21. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> beleeued the Goſpell hiſtorically, yet <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith there, that his heart was not vpright in the ſight of God. In <note place="margin">Acts 5. 3.</note>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 3. <hi>Ananias</hi> beleeued the Goſpell, and ſeemed to bring forth fruits thereof, as did the other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but it was not rightly receiued into the heart, for hypocriſie which is is the worke of Satan, and ſauing faith, which is the worke of the ſpirit, cannot dwell together in one heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iudas</hi> vnderſtood, and beleeued the word, and was a Preacher thereof, but it was neuer intertayned and rooted in his heart, but thorny couetouſneſſe was roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therein, which in the end choaked the word. So <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 10.</note>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 10. <hi>Demas</hi> was a follower of <hi>Paul,</hi> but the loue of the world was neuer rooted out of his heart, therefore in time it choaked the word, &amp;c. <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata, giue intertainment to the word, but pride was neuer rooted out of his heart, therefore it choaked the word in him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 11. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of young
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15391:7"/>
widowes, that hauing entertained and profeſſed the word, doe afterward waxe wanton againſt Chriſt, and break their firſt faith, becauſe concupiſcence and fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſt was neuer rooted out of their hearts, therefore it choaked the word in them.</p>
            <p>When as the word is receiued into the heart, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with theſe and ſuch like luſts, which our Sauiour Chriſt calleth thornes, <hi>Math.</hi> 13. 24. the thornes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing naturall to the heart, and therefore hauing ſtrong rooting, muſt needs in time ouergrow and choake the word; euen as weedes being naturall to the earth, doe ouergrow and pine away the corne, that it cannot fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie. And this is the condemnation of the multitude, I meane of the common hypocriticall Proteſtants, which giue entertainment to the word, but expell not their beloued company, or gueſt, their head perſonall ſinne, with the branches and fruits thereof: either muſt Chriſt, and that ſinne dwell together; or elſe muſt Chriſt be expelled, that it may rule.</p>
            <p>But caſt out the bond-woman with her children, for ſhee and her ſonnes cannot be heyre with the free, if <hi>Iſaack</hi> be heyre, then muſt <hi>Iſhmael</hi> be caſt out: and if the birth-right belong to <hi>Iacob, Eſau</hi> cannot haue it. Crucifie the olde man with his children, the luſts of ignorance, and the workes of darkeneſſe: for if the ſonne of God by his word and ſpirit hath taken poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of your hearts, and dwell therein, as owner and heyre, then cannot the bond-womans ſonne be heyre, whether it be pride, or couetouſneſſe, or enuy, or fleſhly luſt, which ſpring out of originall corruption.</p>
            <p>The word of God and naturall luſt cannot both dwell together, they cannot both be heyres, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not both be maiſters, but being contrary one to the other, the one of them will haue the dominion and vpper hand: ſinne and Satan lay claime to all by right of antient inheritance, from many deſcents, but the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15391:8"/>
word is the ſword of the ſpirit, driuing them out of the heart, and cutting them downe. As <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> ſword ſlue all the ancient inhabitants of Canaan, and placed the Iſraelites therein; euen ſo muſt wee caſt out and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due theſe Canaanitiſh luſts and affections, the word muſt be as a ſword, or ſacrificing knife in vs to cut downe theſe ancient in-bred inhabitants, worldly luſts; yea, as the Land of Canaan ſpued forth her Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, ſo muſt we cleare our hearts of this menſtruous filth, that they may be Temples for the holy Ghoſt, euen as Salomons Temple, beautified and adorned with holineſſe, righteouſnes, faith, goodnes, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, loue, truth, continence, temperance, and all vertue.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Degree of Faith, is their intertayning and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing of the word in ſuch ſort as is peculiar, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the word which is propounded: firſt, negatiuely, <hi>[not as the word of Men,]</hi> and then affirmatiuely <hi>(but as the word of God.)</hi> Heerein appeareth euidently the difference betweene hypocrites, and true beleeuers. Infidels heare the word of God altogether as the word of man: Hypocrites receiue the word of God as the word of man, that is, they allow it to be the word of God, ſo farre forth as it is agreeable to their liking, and wherein it differeth from them, they contemne, and put it off from them, as but the word of man: this is therefore the meere and eſpeciall, and ſauing grace of God, to receiue the word as from God, and not from Man.</p>
            <p>The Phariſees heard the pure word of the Goſpell from the mouth of the Sonne of God himſelfe, but becauſe he was in the ſhape and forme of man, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they receiued it but as the word of man, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 13 <note place="margin">Iohn 8. 13. Marke 6. 2.</note>
               <hi>Thou beareſt record of thy ſelfe, &amp;c. Mark</hi> 6. 2. Our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſts Countrymen, friends, &amp; kinsfolks, hearing his wiſedome, and ſeeing his workes, were aſtonied, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15391:8"/>
beleeued not in him: What was the cauſe? <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3. <hi>Is not this the Carpenter, Maryes Sonne, brother of Iames &amp; Ioſes?</hi> &amp;c. They looked with fleſhly eyes on his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance only, and eſteemed his word but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his outward appearance; therefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came vnprofitable to them.</p>
            <p>Such like Phariſees are the heads of the Romiſh Church, the teachers and maintainers of hypocriſie, which auouch that the written word hath no authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but by their approbation, and what is their approbation? Firſt, they wreſt it to ſuch a ſence as may ſerue for the erecting and maintaining of their owne authority, and their <hi>Antichriſtian ſynagogue,</hi> and then hauing adulterated it, and made it their owne word, they giue allowance to it. Heereupon euery Impe of that Church will not heare the word, as the word of God, but as of the Church, that is, of the Pope, and his Cardinals; and in this they reſt ſatisfied, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, thinking it hereſie to receiue the word meerely as the word of God.</p>
            <p>Of this ſort are all prophane <hi>Eſaues</hi> and Epicuriſh Politicians, which count themſelues Proteſtants, but are not: they acknowledge and receiue the olde and new Teſtament, as the word of God, but as for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, Inſtructions, Vſes, and eſpecially Applications thereof, they receiue as but the word of men, and chiefly, when the application thereof concernes their reformation in particular. As the Papiſt counts the true interpretation of Scriptures hereſie, and vnder that name reiects it; ſo the carnall Goſpeller counts the true vſes and applications of the word, preciſenes, and vnder that name or terme contemnes it. So that as the one denyes the truth and embraceth errour; ſo the other confeſſing the truth in generall, doth wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſe it in particular, and liueth after his owne luſt, without the word: and whether of theſe is the better?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15391:9"/>
What is the cauſe that many doe not heare and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the word with that reuerence and obedience as they ought, as their whole life and conuerſation doth ſhew? It is becauſe they receiue it as the word of man: for if they were fully perſwaded and ſeriouſly beleeued that it were the very word of God, they would not ſo lightly regard it, and liue ſo diſſolutely: For who dare be bold to fight againſt God? Who dare contemne him, and deride him to his face, as many doe? If men dare not doe this to an earthly Prince, without feare, yea cold feare troubling their thoughts, and looſing the ioynts of their loynes; how comes it to paſſe, that they dare ſo boldly chalenge God the combate, and with petulant deriſion prouoke him?</p>
            <p>The reaſon is, becauſe they receiue it as the word of man, and thinke they haue to deale with man, and not with God; this is the cauſe of their contempt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience: For if they were touched with any ſence or feeling of the preſence of Gods maieſty, and that they receiued the word as from his owne mouth; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there is no man liuing, that durſt ſo dally and trifle with the word, much leſſe withſtand it, or haue it in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion. It is a maruell therefore to ſee and heare how many take liberty to themſelues to dally with, and to make a ieaſt of the Word, to be touched with no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence or feare of the ſame.</p>
            <p>But indeed, what maruell is it to ſee an infant thruſt his hand into the fire without feare, or doubting? or to ſee a blinde man goe willingly into the pit? or a drunkard inraged with wine, to run deſperately on the ſwords point? or a madde man to kill himſelfe? Did not the rebellious Iſraelites deride the word of the Lord ſent to them by all his Prophets? Did not <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> with their conſorts, wittingly and wilfully rebell againſt the Lord in the perſon of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> whoſe authority they ſaw euen with their owne
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15391:9"/>
eyes, that it was giuen him of God? Did not the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites caſt off the Lord, from being their Gouernour in the perſon of <hi>Samuell? They haue not caſt thee away, but they haue caſt mee away, that I ſhould not raigne ouer them.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8 7. <note place="margin">1 Sam. 8. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Did not the Iewes contemn and caſt off the word of the Lord ſpoken by <hi>Ieremie,</hi> ſaying that it was not the Lords word, but the malicious counſell of <hi>Baruch? Ier.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 43 2. 3.</note>43. 2. 3. Did not the counſel of the Iewes with the high Prieſt, count the Goſpell ſedition, and rebellion, which the Apoſtles taught, as Gods owne ſpirit gaue them vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance? <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 28. Did not <hi>Tertullus</hi> the Orator count <note place="margin">Acts 5. 28.</note>
               <hi>Paul</hi> a peſtilent fellow, a moouer of ſedition, and an heretike? <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 5. Yea if wee recount from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning <note place="margin">Acts 24. 5.</note>of the world, wee ſhall ſee that infidells, and hypocrites haue alwaies heard and receiued the word of the Lord, as the word of man, and vnder that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence haue euer with ſtood the ſame, and caſt it off from them, eſpecially if it were not to their owne liking, or that they could not politickely make ſome vſe of it for their bodily turnes.</p>
            <p>No maruell then is it, if in theſe latter Atheiſticall and Epicuriſh dayes the word of the Lord take no place among many, but be turned lightly off as the word of man, yea, and had in deriſion, as but the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſed, raſh, and indiſcreet ſpeeches of a phantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, ſpleenfull, or preciſe fellow, as <hi>Eli</hi> ſuppoſed the ſober, and feruent prayers of <hi>Anna;</hi> and certaine Iewes termed the gifts of the holy Ghoſt drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>But this were a maruell if that God ſhould come from heauen in the ſhape of a man, (for no mortall man can liue in his glorious preſence) and ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe familiarly with vs, preaching the glad tidings of the Goſpell in all lenity and mildeneſſe, hauing in his perſon, doctrine, and conuerſation matter to prouoke
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15391:10"/>
and allure all men, euen the pooreſt, the meaneſt, the ignoranteſt, the Publicane, the ſinner, the weake-har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the troubled conſcience to follow him, embrace him, loue him, reioyce in him, being meeke &amp; lowly in heart, mercifull, and pittifull, mourning and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing for the hardneſſe of mans heart, weeping for our miſeries, calling all to repentance, refuſing none that in any ſincerity came vnto him; louing all, in whom any token of preſent, or future grace appeared, reprouing onely the enemies of mans ſaluation, pride, enuy, hypocriſie, couetouſneſſe, and threatning iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt hard-hearted and obſtinate rebels, who ſeeke their owne glory in the deſtruction of Gods glory and kingdome, and are enemies to their owne ſaluation, and all other mens; nay, and beſides this, ſhould not onely giue no appearance of euill, but ſhew forth the glory of his God-like maieſty in all his words and workes, publike and priuate. It were a maruell I ſay, if any man receiued not his word, as the word of God, being God himſelfe, and in all humility, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and obedience, followed not him, and yeelded not himſelfe to doe homage vnto him.</p>
            <p>Euen thus was God conuerſant among his owne people the Iewes, in the true ſhape of man; but his owne receiued him not: they heard his word, but as the word of man, and eſteemed his life and holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, but as of an ordinary man: but this is more wonderfull, that God preaching in the forme of man ſhould be reiected as a deceiuer, as a chiefe ſinner, as a worker with euill ſpirits, as not worthy to liue among men. Indeede if that Chriſt had preached ſome new and ſtrange thing neuer heard of before, they might haue had ſome pretence of reiecting his word; but ſeeing that hee taught nothing, but that which <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets foretold, whoſe Diſciples they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt themſelues to be, and whom they beleeued; and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15391:10"/>
yet beleeued not him, but making him contrary to <hi>Moſes, Ioh</hi> 9. 28. who plainely ſet before their eies, put <note place="margin">Iohn 9. 28.</note>into their eares, and euen thruſt into their hands all that they heard, and read in <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets euery day, that they might heare, and ſee euen with bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily eyes and eares, and handle the word of life: It is a wonderfull thing I ſay, that they ſhould not receiue his word as the word of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets, and conſequently of God. What ſottiſh ſtupidity is this? What ſhould thus bewitch them, that being bereft of common ſenſe, as it were, they ſhould deny that eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially which they moſt profeſſed, and reiected that by all meanes as moſt deteſtable, which they moſt glory in, and boaſted of?</p>
            <p>Nay, if we conſider the cauſe hereof, it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull or ſtrange thing, but naturall and common, if wee could but reflect our eyes vpon our ſelues, to ſee the things within vs, as we doe the things without vs, but it is giuen to very few to diſcerne the times, and ſeaſons by application of the true light to the ſame, which maketh euery thing manifeſt as it is.</p>
            <p>The cauſe heereof, was the bewitching hypocriſie of the hart; for howſoeuer they pretended religion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion and zeale, and therein matched the Romiſh Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, yet was not the ſame truly rooted in their harts, but pride, ambition, vaine-glory, couetouſneſſe, and enuy were deepely rooted, and firmely ſetled therein, which ſinnes being coloured with fayre pretences of religion, blinded not onely the eies of the world, but euen their owne eyes, that their religious titles, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, faſtings, almes, and other outward works were but cloaked and coloured pride, vaineglory, couetouſnes, oppreſſion: and this true body, namely, their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion, had not a true ſoule in it, but an euill ſpirit or Deuill, vſing this body deceitfully, and craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily for his owne aduantage. For, this is the nature of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15391:11"/>
the hypocriticall heart, to transforme euen the beſt, and holieſt exerciſes of religion into the nature of it ſelfe, that is, to ſerue it ſelfe of them.</p>
            <p>Theſe holy Deuils of the Iewiſh Church, retayning the bare names, and liueleſſe titles of their Iewiſh pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges, as to be called the Iſraell of God, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp;c. As alſo the outward ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Law, together with their owne ambitious traditions, and gainfull diſpenſations; but being of worldly hearts and ſpirits, were ſo farre from the true knowledge, and ſpirituall meaning of the Law, of the types and ceremonies thereof, as alſo of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, as that they could not abide to heare the ſame, ſounding to their eares as ſtrange and new doctrine; for bare titles, and the outward barke ſerued their turnes, hauing no farther ſauour of religion, nor loue of the truth in them. Therefore when Chriſt preached the Law and the Prophets ſpiritually, which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and wherein they boaſted carnally. It was a <note place="margin">Iohn 6.</note>hard preaching, who could heare it? <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>The Papiſt doth marueile at the ſtupidity, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly condemne the obſtinacy of the Phariſees, and Iewes for their contempt of the Goſpell, and ſhamefull intreatment of the ſonne of God, and for their hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, pride, couetouſneſſe, enuy, &amp;c. And the Friars and Ieſuites in their Sermons worke vpon the paſſions of men, to prouoke and inflame their hearts to an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of them, for hating the Goſpell, and putting our bleſſed Sauiour to death.</p>
            <p>Surely it is a wonderful thing to conſider the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their hard hearts, that they haue no ſight at all in themſelues of theſe things, for which they vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemne the Iewes, being no leſſe enemies of Chriſt then the Iewes.</p>
            <p>The Phariſees holding, and maintayning the true principles of the law, and Prophets, did in their Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15391:11"/>
Expoſitions, and ſpeciall Applications, ſwarue ſo far from the true meaning thereof, through the darkeneſſe of their earthly hearts, as they became vtter enemies of the truth therein contained, for Chriſt was the truth, the end and fulfilling thereof, whom they pointed at, and whom the Phariſees heard and ſaw, ſpeaking and fulfilling the ſame in their eyes, and eares, yet will they not be his Diſciples, but <hi>Moſes</hi> Diſciples, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9. making <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt contrary, <note place="margin">Iohn 9.</note>whereas indeede they themſelues were contrary to themſelues, for if they had knowne and profeſſed <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and the Prophets ſpiritually, and truly, then had they knowne Chriſt, and beene his followers, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carnall profeſſours, they are vtter enemies of the truth which they profeſſed. Let common Proteſtants note this well.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo, in the very ſame manner, the Romiſh Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, with the whole Antichriſtian rout, houlding the true principles of the Goſpell, the olde and new Teſtament, and the abridgements of the ſame, to wit, the Creede, the Commandements, and Lords prayer, doe in their Interpretations, Expoſitions, Gloſſes, and particular Applications of the word, ſo farre and wide run aſtray from the true meaning thereof, as they are vtter enemies of the truth perſecuting the true profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of the ſame, vnder the names of heretickes, as the Iewes perſecuted Chriſt vnder the name of a ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer and deceiuer.</p>
            <p>The Phariſees built their falſe ſect, doctrines and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions vpon the true ground, or principles of the Law and Prophets, ſo doe the Romaniſts build their Antichriſtian Synagogue, their falſe doctrines, workes and deuotions vpon Chriſt, the Prophets, Euangeliſts and Apoſtles. But heere is the cunning of the Deuill, who as he ſees God in his great wiſdome to bring good good out of euill, yea, to turne all his Satanicall poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15391:12"/>
and deuiſes vpon his owne head, and to worke himſelfe glory out of his plot of diſhonour and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion: euen ſo on the contrary he bringeth euill out of good, turning the truth of God into a lye, yea, vpon Gods truth and ordinance builds hee his owne king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but this bay and ſtubble built vpon the true foundation ſhall be burnt by the fire of Gods ſpirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 15. and the plant which he hath not planted ſhall wither away, and be rooted out, <hi>Math.</hi> 15. 13.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing that they haue built a falſe Church vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a true foundation, ſoothing vp themſelues in their outward priuiledges, and liueleſſe titles, making their owne lawes, doctrines, traditions, and innumerable deale of beggarly baggagement the rule of conſcience and holy life, put the caſe, that Ieſus Chriſt the onely truth were to come, or that it ſhould pleaſe his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Maieſty, to come from heauen into the Church of Rome (which profeſſeth it ſelfe to be the onely and holy flocke of Chriſt) in ſuch manner as he came among the Iewes, inſtructing and teaching the people euery where, in truth, ſincerity, and without partiality, prouing his doctrine by the written word, (which themſelues acknowledge and profeſſe) as hee did the Goſpell among the Iewes by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and confirming the Doctrine with miracles; as alſo conuincing and reprouing them for their Idolatry, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, falſe doctrine, vaine ceremonies, traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, godly lies, wicked diſpenſations, ambition, pride, tyranny, cruelty, exceſſiue couetouſneſſe, extortion, bribery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all the heatheniſh abhominations of that holy denne of theeues: If I ſay that Chriſt were at Rome amongſt them at this inſtant, in ſuch appearance life, conuerſation, and doctrine, as he was among the Iewes, I demand what manner of intertainment ſhould be giuen him? And whether his word and doctrine ſhould be receiued as the word of God, or as the word
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15391:12"/>
of man? whether it ſhould be receiued as the trueth of God, or reiected as hereſie?</p>
            <p>Euen as the King of Niniueth, with the Princes, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Nobles and Commons beleeued the word of God ſpoken by <hi>Ionah,</hi> layd his robe from him, couered him with ſackcloath, and ſate in aſhes; and proclaimed that neither man, beaſt, bullocke, nor ſheepe ſhould feede<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or drinke water; that man and beaſt ſhould put on ſackcloth, and cry mightily vnto God, and turne from his euill way, and the wickedneſſe that was in his hands. <hi>Ionah</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>So it may be that the Pope with his Cardinals, Fryers, Monkes, Prieſts, &amp;c. together with the whole Citie of <hi>Rome</hi> would beleeue his word, and receiue it as the word of Chriſt. It may be, they would acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him, reuerence him, and honour him, humbly ſubmitting to his doctrine, confeſſing their errors and ſinnes, and ſuffer themſelues to be rightly enformed, and reformed by him, their guide, gouernour, and chiefe ſhepheard of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>But I rather thinke, that he ſhould haue far worſe intertainment among them, then amongſt the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Iewes, and Heathen, that they would perſecute both his doctrine and perſon with all indignities, that might be deuiſed, and becauſe of his true miracles confounding their lying wonders, would iudge him to be Antichriſt, (of whom they haue already made <hi>Luther</hi> the fore-runner) euen as the Phariſies counted him the greateſt Sorcerer, and to deale with the Prince of the Deuills, by whoſe power he exceeded all other: I ſuppoſe that they which ſo deuoutly worſhip and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the Image of Chriſt, and of the Apoſtles, beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the ſame with ſuch ſumptuous ornaments, and ouerlaying of gold, would by all meanes diſhonour the true Chriſt. And his Apoſtles, not onely contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their perſons, and condemning their doctrines,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15391:13"/>
but alſo putting them to ignominious deaths. I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that <hi>Seruus ſeruorum Dei,</hi> would hardly re-deliuer the chayre, giue the right hand, or wall to <hi>Peter.</hi> For as the Phariſies did to Chriſt the head, ſo doe they to his Apoſtles and members likewiſe. And as <hi>Antichriſt</hi> doth now to the true Miniſters and members, ſo would he doe to the head: For the afflictions of Chriſt are accompliſhed in his members by <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> who ſhould alſo ſuffer the ſame in his owne perſon, if hee were in the ſtate of humiliation vpon the earth, as he was.</p>
            <p>Surely may ſome ſay, it were a maruellous thing, if it ſhould be ſo, I would thinke rather that Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, teaching the ſame doctrines, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſame, or ſuch like miracles, ſhould be heard and receiued of the Pope, his Cardinalls, &amp;c. as hee was of the faithfull in the Iewiſh Church.</p>
            <p>I anſwere, if hee ſhould come indeede, as <hi>Ignatius Loyala</hi> that prophane and bloudy ſouldier, a Spaniard, <note place="margin">Vide Triumphu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Papalem, Haſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulleri. <hi>1539.</hi>
               </note>the Father of the Ieſuites, * came to Pope <hi>Paulus</hi> the third, deuoting himſelfe and his Diſciples to him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing abſolute obedience to him, in all things, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any exception, and binding himſelfe with an inuio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable oath, that hee would, to his vttermoſt power maintaine and vphold the Romiſh Church and See by all meanes poſſible, if (I ſay) both his doctrine and miracles might ſerue for the glorifying of that carnall Idoll-gull, and vpholding of his worldly Synagogue and See; then without doubt hee ſhall haue great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement, and in ſuch ſort alſo might he haue been intertained of the Phariſies, yea of <hi>Herod,</hi> or any worldling.</p>
            <p>But now to come neerer to our ſelues, what if Chriſt were in ſtate of humiliation, and in the very ſame out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance among vs, as hee was among the Iewes; or <hi>Paul, Peter,</hi> or any of the Apoſtles, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15391:13"/>
the ſame Goſpel that is now preached (for none other Goſpell could Chriſt himſelfe preach, than this which is already preached) and expounding the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall texts thereof, as hee did of the Prophets in the Temple, and in the Synagogues, handling the ſame in ſpeciall, and in particular, applying the ſame fitly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all circumſtances, yea, ſpeaking as his and their manner was, to the heart, conſcience, and ſpirit? how ſhould his words be heard? whether as the words of God, or as of man?</p>
            <p>It may be he ſhould be receiued of all men, as hee was of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> of <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> who poured a pound of very coſtly ointment on his head, who wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed his feete with her teares, and wiped them with the hayres of her head. It may be that all men would weep aboundantly, fall on his necke, and kiſſe him, as the Chriſtians did at <hi>Pauls</hi> departure from them; <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 37. It may be that by all meanes poſſible, they would <note place="margin">Acts 20. 37.</note>ſhew their loue to him, by proſtrate obeyſance, and humble obedience, by contemning all worldly things in compariſon of his preſence, yea, and by preferring one word of his mouth before all humane learning and knowledge. It may be that all men from the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the loweſt, from the richeſt to the pooreſt, from the mightieſt to the weakeſt would wholly ſubmit, and ſubiect themſelues to the obedience of his word and doctrine, taking more pleaſure therein, than in all worldly pleaſure and profit, and deuote all their worldly goods, might, wiſedome, and learning to the aduancement thereof, and there is no queſtion, but ſome of all degrees and eſtates would ſincerely and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly, according to the gift of grace and meaſure thereof doe theſe things, yea, many doubtleſſe would loue him, embrace him, reuerence him, for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels ſake, and admiring him would ſay, doubtleſſe the ſpirit of God is plentifull, and very ſtrong in this man,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15391:14"/>
ſo gracious are his words, ſo holy is his conuerſation amongſt vs, as wee may ſee true Chriſtianity perfectly acted, euen as the word teacheth and commandeth.</p>
            <p>But on the other ſide, what entertainment ſhould he finde in the world, I meane among the brutiſh ſinners, the ciuilly honeſt, and the phariſaically religious, for theſe are they that are called the World? In what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner would carnall Goſpellers heare and receiue his pure, ſpirituall, and heauenly Sermons? What man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of taſt and reliſh would his words haue in their eares? What repentance would there be wrought? What confeſſion? Contrition? Satisfaction of wrongs done, with <hi>Zacheus?</hi> What conuerſion? What obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his doctrine? What reformation either of themſelues, or of thoſe, and thoſe things, that are in their power to alter, and order according to his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? How would ſinners and wicked liuers heare him! I meane all ſuch as propound their owne glory and profits, or pleaſures, the end of all their actions, and endeauors, inwardly and outwardly; for they that make theſe and ſuch like things their principall ends, can neither doe good deed, ſpeake good word, nor thinke good thought all their life long.</p>
            <p>How would the greedy churle heare him, that loues to think and meditate of nothing but gaine? to ſpeake nor doe any thing that tends not one way or other to his bodily profit? How would the luſtfull perſon heare him, that makes his whore and wanton woman his Idoll? How would many rauening Lawyers, &amp; ſuch as make authority a cloake of deſtruction &amp; vnhappines, (too many now a daies) heare him, that ſtand conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually waiting and gaping for the bride, whereby the poore is oppreſſed, the hands of reuengeful perſons, &amp; of cruell churles are ſtrengthened againſt their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; and whereby the mouthes of ſuperſtitious and prophane liuers are opened, and hands ſtrengthened
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15391:14"/>
againſt God himſelf, in his Word and Miniſters? How would (I ſay) worldlings of all ſorts heare him? How would they entertaine him? What would they ſay of him?</p>
            <p>Euen as the Iewes did ſay, doe, and Iudge of the Prophets and ſeruants of God then, and as we doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme the faithfull Miniſters and religious profeſſors now; ſo would too many (if authority brideled them not) ſpeake, doe, and Iudge of Chriſt himſelfe, or the Apoſtles being conuerſant among vs, as then they were among them. Some ſayd, <hi>he is a good man;</hi> other ſayd, <hi>nay, but hee ſeduceth the People, Iohn</hi> 7. 12. <note place="margin">Iohn 7. 12.</note>Some would ſay he is too ſtrict, too preciſe, phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall; ſuch kinde of Chriſtianity can no where be acted; of too ſpiced a conſcience, malecontent, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell what he would haue, nothing can pleaſe him, there can be neither loue nor good fellowſhip; but contention and miſlike one of another where ſuch preaching is: hee meddles too far in matters that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne him not: hee thinkes there is none ſo wiſe and godly as himſelfe; his parents and friends are of ſmall reputation among their neighbours, hee is of very meane education, few of the richer or wiſer ſort make any great reckoning of him. If he were of ability, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, friends and learning, as hee is but meane and bare, hee would happily prooue a dangerous fellow; for he is very bold, hee vſes very broad ſpeeches, and takes too much liberty to himſelfe, to ſpeake of ſuch things, as better men then himſelfe will not talke of: he muſt haue an oare in euery mans boate, he makes euery man his text; a melancholy fellow, not of a ſound braine, very malitious, and ſpleenefull; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I and many more be deceiued, ſome thinke that hee hath beene beſide himſelfe: I haue ſeene him chollericke enough for all his mildneſſe, and heard him raile on his betters; hee will be taken vp ere
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15391:15"/>
it be long at one hand or other.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like things would worldlings ſpeake of him, and (I feare) farre worſe: for they that ſticke in the outward letter and bare titles of religion and Chriſtianity, haue beene, are, and alwaies will be, vtter enemies of the life and ſpirit thereof, to the true Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and ſincere profeſſors thereof, being like to the earthly and bloudy Edomites, which vnder the title of circumciſion, and the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> claimed to themſelues the chiefe religion, and hated the true worſhippers of God.</p>
            <p>For the further clearing of this point, I will bring in two interlocutors, or ſpeakers, <hi>Eulalus</hi> and <hi>Mataeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logus,</hi> in which two perſons you may eaſily behold the eſtate and conditions of theſe times, and ſee the common carnall Proteſtant ſet forth in his colours.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeologus.</speaker>
               <p>Au, I pray you iudge charitably of your brethren, you run out now too farre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>A man may be charitable though hee be not fooliſh. Hee may be charitable, though he iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie not <hi>Eſaus,</hi> that preferre their bellies, profits, and pleaſures before Gods kingdome, and mocking <hi>Iſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els,</hi> that being heyres of worldly things, haue the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God in deriſion, becauſe they haue not, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not worſhip the golden Image <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> nor reuerence them, nor count them the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for their Image ſake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeol.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch vnhallowed ſpeeches are too common in the mouthes of many preciſe fellows, there is nothing with them but Scripture, but others that haue not the Scriptures in their mouthes, ſo much <hi>[and therefore neither in their hearts,]</hi> are as good as they, for ought I <hi>[blind Bayard]</hi> ſee. What, doe you thinke, becauſe wee regard not them ſo much, that therefore we would not regard our bleſſed Sauiour, or the holy Apoſtles, if they were in mans appearance
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15391:15"/>
among vs? there is none but they would ſpend goods, body, and life for him: there is none vnleſſe very few <hi>(ſuch as thou art)</hi> but they would leaue all, and follow him, yea we would reſigne all that wee haue, and all that wee are into his hands, to diſpoſe at his gracious will and pleaſure, or elſe we were as ill as the Iewes, as <hi>Pilate</hi> and the Phariſees, and worthy to goe to hell with them: <hi>(I doubt you will proue your ſelfe to be little better in the end.)</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>I would be loath to prouoke you to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, my purpoſe is in friendly manner to reaſon with you, not to offend you. Let vs ſpeake of an other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This queſtion was put forth to me by a friend of mine a while agoe, &amp;c. What if a Lion were changed into a Lambe, whether would the old ſheepe be afraid and run away from him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>Why, common reaſon anſwereth that queſtion, at the firſt hearing, if the Lion were turned into a Lambe, hee ſhould be counted and vſed as a Lambe, and hee might well be afraid of other things, that before were afraid of him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay well, and as the thing is. What iſ a man went to the wars in a far country, and had been forth twenty yeeres, many men ſuppoſing that hee may be aliue, ſome doubting that he is dead, ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouching that he is aliue, and will come ſhortly. Now if this man came in the forme of a poore man, or a ſeruant, to his owne houſe, as <hi>Vliſſes</hi> did, what would his owne family ſay and doe to him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke he ſhould haue <hi>Vliſſes</hi> intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they would mocke and deride him, and thruſt him out by the head and ſhoulders if he troubled them too much, and ſend for the Conſtable to carry him away to the ſtockes if he would not be ruled, and be gone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>What if a King ſhould diſroabe himſelfe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15391:16"/>
of his glory, and come among his ſubiects, in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew of a poore man, or a ſeruant? put the caſe that he ſhould come to dwell in your towne, behauing himſelfe harmeleſly and innocently among you, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying all his owne lawes to the full, and good orders of your pariſh, what would men ſay, and iudge of him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>I think e there is none, but they would count him an honeſt poor man, though there be ſome that is apt to ſpeake badly enough, whem ſmall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is offered, and if he were neuer ſo good, he ſhould neuer pleaſe all parties, for our towne is as the reſt of the world is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>But what if he ſhould begin to meddle in your townes matters, and to finde fault with your rich men for their vniuſt, hard, and vnlawfull dealings, likely enough, all in your pariſh obſerue not law, nor good order, eſpecially if it be not for their profit: ſome are wronged and oppreſſed among you, the ſmall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences of ſome are made heynous crimes, ſome doe manifeſt wrong, and liue in bad and diſhoneſt ſort, and yet no man dare ſpeake of it: I ſay not that there are ſuch in your towne, but put the caſe there were ſuch.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>To tell you the truth (for I haue known their dealings, and their qualities a long time) there were no abiding for him among them, if hee ſpeake but a word againſt ſome of them, though it were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt troth, hee were farre better runne his country than liue there; for the rich would be againſt him, and the poore to pleaſe the rich would doe nothing but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe him, ſome few might happily pitty his caſe, but they durſt ſay naught.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>But what if his kingly maieſty appeared to them in his behauiour, words, geſture, counſells, wiſedome, aduiſe, learning, &amp;c. they might eaſily ſee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15391:16"/>
him to differ from ordinary and common men and to goe beyond themſelues in all things, would they not reuerence him then thinke you, for all his meane eſtate?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>They would euen doe as the Scripture ſaith in one place; when a rich man ſpeakes, euery one muſt hold his tongue, and praiſe him, though he be a foole; but if a poore man ſpeake, they ſay, what fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low is this? and if they get but any aduantage againſt him, they will euen hang him, if they could, ſuch a ſaying there is; and euen ſo would they ſay to him. I may ſay it well enough, and doe them no wrong, for they haue neuer yet beene better; therefore King me heere, King me there, if the King were in ſuch maner among them as you talke of, they would make him a ſubiect, Ile vphold you for all his wiſedome, counſell, &amp;c. for they ſcorne that any meane man ſhould teach or controll them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>But what if the King of Kings, Ieſus Chriſt, ſhould come downe from heauen in ſuch appearance among them, as he was on earth in the ſtate of his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, and ſhould deale plainely with them as hee did with his owne countrimen, <hi>Luke.</hi> 4. and with the <note place="margin">Luke 4.</note>Phariſees, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. would they not be filled with wrath <note place="margin">Math. 23.</note>and indignation? would they not be ready to cling like Bees together, to make him weary of the towne? would they not ſeeke to intangle him in his own ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeol.</speaker>
               <p>It is like enough that if hee once croſſe them, they would deale badly enough, and haue little regard to his Sermons, they are ſo full of pride of heart and couetouſneſſe, as they would turne off eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing with mocking and ieſting, if otherwiſe they could not reuenge themſelues of him. And I thinke there be too many ſuch like euery where.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>How happeneth it that your Miniſter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15391:17"/>
them no better, hee might reforme many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes and diſorders among you, if hee were diligent in preaching and applying the Word as hee ought to doe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>Our Miniſter is more diligent then hee neede to be: hee might take leſſe paynes, and haue the more thankes. There hath beene more diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſince his comming, then euer there was before, but hee gayneth naught by that; for I beleeue hee feeles the ſmart of it in his Tithes payment. His pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor made a pretty liuing of it, becauſe mens harts were more towards him: Againe, he was a good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and neither mak't nor medled with any man, or his doings, as this man doth. And to tell you the truth, I my ſelfe (though he neuer harmed me) cannot fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy him, nor like of his doings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>Why, what are his paynes; you ſpake e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen now as though he were no husband.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>His paines is a deale of lip-labour, all againſt himſelfe; there is nothing but catechizing and preaching with him, if he hold on as he hath begun, hee will catechize all the good ſeruants out of the towne, he makes vs euen all weary of him. Youth muſt not play on the Saboth day, betweene Morning and Euening Prayer: old people muſt not meet together at the Ale-houſe to make merry, as they had wont to doe. A man muſt not doe any ſmall Iobb, nor walke to other townes vpon buſineſſes, nor make bargaines on the Saboth day, and I cannot tell what a hundreth ſuch like prattles (it would make a horſe breake his halter to heare all) but if all men were of my minde, we would giue him the hearing (ſeeing we cannot tell how to remedy it) but wee will doe as our fore-elders haue done before vs, as for him, we know not whence he came, nor what hee would haue: when hee hath made an end, let him doe it, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15391:17"/>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>You ſaid euen now that he bred much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnes among you, tell me wherein he ſo naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behaueth himſelfe, and I will talke with him: it may be I ſhall preuaile with him for a friends ſake of mine that hath beene a Benefactor of his.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>Faith, I cannot ſay that he is of a naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty behauiour; for he neuer ſues nor troubles any man. For indeede the poore pay him all his due, becauſe they dare not withſtand him; neither doth he looke for more then his due, nor all that, as the report go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: And as for the rich, he will not ſtand much with them (they are ſo froward) vnleſſe they too groſſely wrong him; and wrong him they will, doe what hee can, and I thinke in my conſcience, that ſome counts it the beſt and cleereſt gotten goods.</p>
               <p>But heere is the miſchiefe, hee is too bold, and too indiſcreet in his Catechizings and Sermons, he neuer keepes his teske, but is alwaies roauing into Townes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matters, and mens manners, that he hath nought to doe with: We are not ſo ignorant (as it pleaſes him to terme vs ſometimes) but we can ſee when he leaues his teske. What is it for him to ſtand telling vs of ſuch things as are not in the Scripture? We haue ſome in our towne that can read indifferently well marry, and are good ſenſible men, that can finde no ſuch matter in the Bible: Wherefore we thinke that hee is too pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe and curious. It comes ſurely of pride, that hee would haue all men ruled by him (and that our townes men know well enough) and that both his apparell and medling in high matters doth teſtifie; or it comes of malice, for hee hath no good neighbourhood in him: or of enuy, euen as other poore men grudge at, and enuy rich men: or of choller, for he will be angry oft times we know not for what, euen when no man hath wronged him. Well; he thinkes there is no man ſo good as himſelfe, but I thinke there is none ſo bad
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15391:18"/>
as hee, and ſuch like Putricans; but if hee cannot be content to read the Word of God to vs, and to trouble vs with no ſuch bibble babble, ſome of our rich men will ouerpowre him and remoue him; hee had beſt to looke well to himſelfe; <hi>(being among Scorpions,)</hi> you ſhould be greatly his friend if you would adueruſe him of theſe things, but in no caſe tell him, that I ſpeake ſuch things vnto you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſorry to heare you ſay that hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haues himſelfe ſo indiſcreetly among you, eſpecially in the worke of the miniſtery, doe you thinke that he ſpeakes all of pride, enuy, malice, and choler?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>He doth, he doth without doubt, euery man ſees, and ſayes that; for if hee would let them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, they would let him alone, that's a cleare caſe: for I haue heard many ſay ſo, and I fully beleeue it, I know it partly by my ſelfe. Heere is a fine man not farre off (you cannot but heare of him) a very good ſcholler, he is as perfect in his Greeke and Latine as in his Engliſh, it will doe one good to heare him, hee will goe from the Ale-houſe to the Church, and make as good a Sermon, and a better then our Miniſter can doe with all his weekes ſtudy: hee goes not an hare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breadth from his teske, to meddle of any by-matters, as our miniſter doth. The common ſaying is true, the beſt Schollers are the leaſt medlers: hee deales with nothing but with Gods word, and hee hath therefore the good will of all the pariſh, and wants nothing that they can doe for him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>If they loue ſo to heare him, then they are a people of good knowledge; they ſurely know how to order their liues after the rule of Gods word; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he holdes himſelfe ſo to the word of God, and meddles with nothing elſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, I thinke they haue as little to ſay, as wee haue: Wee haue ſome talkatiue (but needy) fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15391:18"/>
in our pariſh that are able to put them all downe in reaſoning, and I doubt the Miniſter to: but neither wee nor they care for them, they might guide their tongues, and keepe their friends if they were wiſe. Such poore men ſhould mind their buſines, and pleaſe their Maſters, and not runne to Sermons, and buſie their heads, they know not about what. We care for no ſuch pratlers that will bee making themſelues bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then other men. But I know what I know, they that carry bookes in their pockets, carry the Deuill in their hearts. And to tell you the truth, wee care for none that followes or fauours our Miniſter: for there is no good neighbourhood, nor good fellowſhip in any of them. I thinke more than I will ſpeake of, but what this world will come to, the Lord knowes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>It ſhould ſeeme by the drift of your ſpeech, that you are in your pariſh, as they are in many more; one man is againſt another, and all againſt the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter for his Preaching and Catechizing, as though Gods word were your common aduerſary, euen as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> was againſt <hi>Pilate,</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> againſt <hi>Herod,</hi> and all againſt Chriſt; or as <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui</hi> brethren in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>What doe you compare vs to <hi>Herod,</hi> that killed S. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> to <hi>Pilate</hi> that condemned our bleſſed Sauiour? And is our Miniſter to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Chriſt, to S. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> or to any of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles? Hee! Whats hee? No body, almoſt none of our ſubſtantiall men care for him, nor any that is wiſe, onely a few ignorant baſe fellowes fauour him. It is more for a dinner, or a pot of beere, then for any good deuotion they haue, more then others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>Be not angry I pray you, I ſpeake not of you, but of them that are ſuch like. I take you to be my friend, and I hope neuer to giue you any iuſt cauſe to thinke hardly of me. I ſuppoſe that if <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:15391:19"/>
                  <hi>Paul, Peter,</hi> &amp;c. or any of the holy men in times paſt, were among you, in the appearance of an ordinary Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter (ſay, it were of your Miniſter) that you would reuerence him, ſuffer your ſelues to be inſtructed, and catechized with all readineſſe and willingnes, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confeſſe your ſinnes, that you would be ſo farre from oppreſſing one another, as you would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſell your poſſeſſions, and caſt the money at his feete, as the Chriſtians did at the Apoſtles feete, <hi>Act.</hi> 4 37. and that you would ſuffer your ſelues to be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ordered in all things by his Sermons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeologus.</speaker>
               <p>I truly, I thinke that I ſhould euen doe ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, and all your neighbours that your Miniſter ſo troubles and diſquiets, with his indiſcreet preaching.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke they would I promiſe you, elſe wee were all euen as ill as <hi>Pilate, Herod</hi> and the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, as you ſaid euen now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke indeede you would bee all alike minded towards <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptist, Paul, Peter</hi> &amp;c. For they would be quiet, not medling with your corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in your townes matters, nor of your euill man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that you complaine of; they would preach lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, in Latine, Greeke and Hebrew, and ſcholler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, as that fine man doth which you told me of, that men might haue a comfort and delight to heare them, as you ſaid of him; they would not raile againſt honeſt men, reprouing them for their couetouſneſſe, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, vſury<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bribery, enuy, lying, ſwearing, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, adulteries &amp;c. but they would preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, letting all ſuch matters paſſe, doing their owne duties, and letting other men alone by them, as your fine man doth: they would keepe company, and goe from the Ale-houſe to the Pulpit: they would reſpect your rich men, and not doe as your Miniſter doth,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15391:19"/>
which makes no difference between the poore and the rich: nor betweene chiefe-charge-bearers, and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly perſons, and thinkes well of none, but ſuch as fauour his Preaching and Catechizing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue now, that all this while you haue mockt mee: you ſeeme to be a fauourer of thoſe hypocrite Putricans, Ile ſtand no longer talking with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>My purpoſe was not to mocke you, but to let you ſee how many men do ſooth and flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the bare title of a Chriſtian, or of a Proteſtant (as the common Papiſt thinkes it enough to haue the bare name of a Catholike) being in the meane time ſo far from the knowlede of God and true Chriſtianity, as they are indeed the vtter enemies of Chriſt and his members, and yet know not ſo much. This is the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt hypocriſie of all, whereby a man blinds not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſo much, as he deceiues his owne heart. As for your ſelfe, I perceiue that you are full of the darkeneſſe of this world; but if it ſhall pleaſe God to haue mercy on you, and to open the eies of your mind, you will be aſhamed of this folly that you haue vttered to mee; though now you thinke that you haue well ſpoken, and the rather becauſe you haue too many abettors in ſuch ignorant Imaginations.</p>
               <p>As concerning your Miniſter, that you ſo contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly ſpeake of; I haue knowne him long, and am well acquainted with him. I am ſure, vnleſſe you ſeeke occaſion, and deuiſe matter againſt him, you cannot iuſtly taxe him for any enormity; whether it be for not obſeruing the Canons, or any temporall, or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Law, or in regard of the faithfull, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable diſcharge of his calling, as the Lawes of God and man enioyne him; or in regard of his life and conuerſation.</p>
               <p>Whereas you ſay that he is more diligent then nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15391:20"/>
that is becauſe you deſire not the knowledge of God nor his waies. Your affections are ſet on the earth and earthly things: Therefore for feare of the Law you come to the Church, but for want of the Loue of God and his Word, you would ſoone be gone againe, to your drinking, gaming, iobs-doing, &amp;c. as the dog returnes to his vomit, and the Sow to her wallowing in the myre.</p>
               <p>Whereas you ſay, hee feeles the ſmart of it in his Tithes paying; this proceedes from your hatred of God, and of Ieſus Chriſt, whoſe children you boaſt your ſelues to be, as the Phariſees boaſted of God their Father, and of <hi>Abraham</hi> their Father. For by your owne confeſſion it is meerely for his preaching, and catechizing ſake, and alſo your good liking to your former idle Paſtour, manifeſteth the ſame. You haue Iewiſh and murtherous hearts by your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, for you diminiſh his liuing by your cunning and crafty ſhifting; you would faine bring him into ſhame and obloquie, and make him a common by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word by your daily miſtaking all his ſayings, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. His Sermons you turne off with raging at euery thing that you thinke is ſpoken againſt you; or elſe with bitter mockings. Yea, you proceed ſo farre in your Iewiſh rebellion, as you can and dare, and as the bribe can giue you libertie. If the Lord had not bound your hands and feete with the chaines of good lawes and gouernment, it is like enough your ciuill ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall men would throw him ouer the Pulpit, and ſtone him out at the townes end, as the Nazarens would haue throwne our Sauiour Chriſt downe headlong <note place="margin">Luke 4.</note>from a rocke, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Whereas you ſo much commend your former mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter for his husbandrie, and nothing elſe; thats your blindneſſe, for the Scripture teacheth you otherwiſe. Our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>He that layeth his hand to the plough,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15391:20"/>
                  <hi>and looketh backe, is vnapt for the kingdome of God.</hi> You are his husbandrie, hee is to worke vpon you, to plow vp the fallowes of your hearts, to deſtroy and kill the vnprofitable weedes of ſinne and wickedneſſe in you, and to make your hearts a pure and cleane ſoule for the Goſpell, that you might bring forth the fruit of holineſſe, and righteouſnes; that you glorifying God vpon earth, he might glorifie you in heauen eternally; and that hee alſo performing this duty which Chriſt (whoſe Steward hee is) hath layed vpon him, might ſhine as the ſtarres in the firmament for euer and euer, by turning you from the waies of death and damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to righteouſneſſe and life.</p>
               <p>Whereas you call his paines a deale of lip-labour, and ſay hee will catechize all the good ſeruants out of the towne, and ſay that it would make a horſe breake his halter to heare all his prittle-prattle: The Lord o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen your heart, that you many know what you ſay, and ſee in what miſerable and fearefull eſtate you are. There is none of theſe things but you heare them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; confirmed plainly by the Scriptures, and many of them are the very words of the Text. How hath Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan blinded and bewitched you, that he cauſeth you to mock God to his face, euen as he would haue brought <hi>Iob</hi> to haue blaſphemed him to his face? <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. 11. The <note place="margin">Iob. 1. 11.</note>Lord conuert you, and baptize you with the fire of his ſpirit, that you may be transformed into a member of Ieſus Chriſt: for truely you ſhow your ſelfe as yet to be but a limbe of the Deuill. What you are in Gods election, the Lord himſelfe knowes, but if you neuer repent, you can neuer be ſaued.</p>
               <p>Whereas you ſay, you will giue him the hearing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you cannot remedy it, but you will doe as you liſt; It would make any Chriſtians heart bleed to heare you. For firſt you ſhew your cruell and reuengefull hearts (as the Iewes did to <hi>Stephen)</hi> in that you would
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15391:21"/>
haue a remedy, if Law would giue liberty, and like e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, ſo farre as it would permit: For the hatred of worldlings againſt Gods Miniſters and children, is as a burning fire kindled by Sathan, and is like the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable fire of hell.</p>
               <p>Againe, whereas you would giue him the hearing, and make no more adoe, you ſhew your reſolution in your obſtinacie: your meaning is, that you would not contend too much with him; that you will come to the Church as late as you can, and when you are come, to while away the time in ſleeping, or thinking on ſome earthly thing; and ſo let both him and the Sabaoth goe; for you thinke he cannot preſent you, and ſo long you care not.</p>
               <p>Againe, you ſay he breedes much diſquietnes among you, through his bold and indiſcreet Sermons: In that you thinke him too bold, that is the pride of your own harts, which thinke that he ſhould be afraid of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <note place="margin">Ierem. 1. 18.</note>contrary to Gods commandement, <hi>Ier.</hi> 1. 18. Is not the Lord able with the breath of his mouth to blow you all in a moment into the riuer of fire &amp; brimſtone, as he cauſed the weſt-winde to blow the graſhoppers of Egypt into the red Sea? Alas ſeely wormes that creep on the earth, and ſauor of nothing but the earth.</p>
               <p>Whereas you taxe him of indiſcreetnes, that is your ignorance and indiſcretion, that know not white from blacke. You ſay he keepes not his text: What, would you haue him to doe nothing but read ouer his text an houre together? You might iuſtly then make him a common by-word. No, but hee roaues into townes matters, and mens manners, that hee hath nought to doe with. Though he hath naught to doe with them, yet God hath to doe with them, that, I hope you will grant. But when your Preacher applies the Word to your towne in particular, and to the hearts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of you and other men in particular, for your
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15391:21"/>
owne inſtruction and reformation, then you ſay, he goeth from his text. Hee meddles of ſuch things as concerne him not. You can finde no ſuch thing in the Bible: what is this but ignorance, and hardneſſe of heart? you thinke becauſe you finde not the name of your towne and townes-matters expreſſed word by word in the text, and becauſe the houſes and names and particular actions of ſuch and ſuch men are not according to euery circumſtance at large expreſſed (as your grounds are butted and bounded in your leaſes) that therefore the text concernes not you, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently none, and ſo would you haue God to haue nought to doe with you, no more than you would haue to doe with him. You thinke enough for you to know what you would haue; but what he would haue you cannot abide to know. Yea, your ſpirits (though not your tongues) doe ſay, depart away from vs, wee will none of thy waies.</p>
               <p>And though you thinke, that you doe but ſpeake and doe againſt your Miniſter: yet the truth is, that you fight like Giants againſt God and Chriſt, whom you call your Father and Redeemer; and not onely you, but Satan by you, who rides you at his pleaſure. But you like the dumb horſe, or mule, that haue none vnderſtanding, know not whether you goe. And thoſe Church-robbers that thinke their miniſters tithes the beſt gotten goods, are the men that caſt lots for Chriſts coate: for Chriſt is crucified, and his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath Lots caſt for it till the worlds end. (I doubt this is a myſtery to you.)</p>
               <p>Whereas you talke of preciſenes, curiouſnes, ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and Putricans (as it pleaſeth your ignorance to terme them) theſe and ſuch like termes are but the froath of an euill and mocking heart, and the ſcumme of a corrupt iudgement, that knowes not what the Miniſter, or what Chriſtian life meaneth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:15391:22"/>
You your ſelfe thinke, that this preciſenes, and too much buſying of himſelfe comes of pride, becauſe he would haue all men ruled by him; whereas the trueth is, (and as his behauiour among you ſhewes it, vnleſſe you be willfully, and ſtarke blinde) that hee wholly and altogether ſet<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth forth God vnto you, in his word, that you might be ruled by him, and that you, (as all men are) being by nature rebels againſt God, might be brought into ſubiection vnder him. And for this cauſe your miniſter doth abaſe himſelfe, that making himſelfe no body, God may be all, among you all, and in you all. And that his rule ouer you, your hearts, conſciences, and liues might the more cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare vnto you, and in you; that he might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you a chaſt and pure Virgin to Chriſt: arrogating nothing to himſelfe, as Reualls and Antichriſts doe, thereby obſcuring Gods glory, but ſending and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering you as it were into the hands of God, and Chriſt, that gathereth and clocketh you to himſelfe, as the hen doth her chickins, by your miniſter. Wherefore euen as the Churle ſaith, Corne is too cheape, becauſe he cannot get ſo much for it as hee would haue, but the poore finde it to be too deare: euen ſo your own hearts are prone, ſtubborne, and rebellious, not his, and therefore diſdaine you to humble your ſelues to walke with your God, and intruding your ſelues into the roome of God, Antichriſtianlike, you as Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants doe in ſpirit ſay, that God is proud, which with the tongue, you as it were father vpon your Miniſter: being like the Libard, which for the hatred he beareth to man, teareth his image in peeces if hee finde it in paper, parchment, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Did not <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> rebell againſt God in the perſon of <hi>Moſes?</hi> Did not the Iſraelites caſt away God from ruling ouer them in the perſon <note place="margin">1 Sam. 8. 7.</note>of <hi>Samuel?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 7. See, if euer any of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15391:22"/>
of God ſpake this of the Prophets, that ſpake to them in the name of the Lord, whether Kings, Nobles, or Commons? But the rebells alwaies, not only Kings and Nobles, but euen the baſeſt miſcreants, tooke oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion at the perſon of the Prophet to deſpiſe and caſt away the Word of the Lord, and to intreat his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers deſpitefully, and as it ſeemes you doe, the Prophet which God hath ſent amongſt you, and to you.</p>
               <p>You ſmile at this particular application, that I call your Miniſter a Prophet of God, but let mee tell you this by the way, that prophane perſons can heare the word of God in generall, I meane, ſo long as they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it not, and know not what vſe to make of it; but when it comes to be applied in particular, they fal eyther to raging, or mocking, as <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. The Nazarens <note place="margin">Luke 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>willingly heard our Sauiour Chriſt read his Text out of <hi>Eſay,</hi> and after he had begun to expound the ſame, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended him, &amp; wondred at his gracious words, but when hee began to reproue their vnbeleefe, and hardnes of heart, (which you call medling of townes matters, &amp; mens manners) they were filled with wrath, and went about to breake his necke: (They lookt for a temporall kingdome without them, and not a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall kingdome within them.) For theſe Nazarens boaſted of Chriſt, and thought it a great honour to their country &amp; city, that a Prophet ſhould ariſe from among them, that could preach ſuch high doctrine, and worke ſuch and ſo many great miracles; yea they imagined alſo that Chriſt ſhould glory in their carnall gracing and honouring of him, as if for that end hee ſhould preach and worke wonders: which thing his owne kinſman alſo imagined, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7. 3. 4. For fleſh and <note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7. 3. 4.</note>bloud can goe no further. But when Chriſt comes to diſcouer their hypocriticall and carnall hearts, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue their infidelity, and that he will not carnally glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15391:23"/>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 5. 44.</note> them, as they would carnally glorifie him. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5. 44. then are they all in a rage, they will to their ability be reuenged of him, as it ſeemes you would be of your miniſter.</p>
               <p>Againe, if they fall not to raging, then they fall to mocking, as the couetous Phariſees mocke Chriſt <note place="margin">Luke 16. 14.</note>
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 14. when they perceiued that he ſpake againſt them: and this is your deuice, by your owne confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you would not ſtriue much with your Miniſter (for want of power to do euill) but you will ſhew your hatred in your mocks, wrye lookes, priuy taunts, nips and girds, incouraging others againſt him, and bringing him and the Goſpell into contempt, by all the ſlie meanes you could, ſo ſhall rude perſons and abiects be actors of your wickedneſſe: but carry your ſelfe as politickely as you can, and couer your ſhame with heatheniſh ciuility, as well as you may (as now a daies many of you are become as cunning as ſtage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>players,) yet you ſhall but dance in a net.</p>
               <p>You ſay hee preacheth of pride, why? becauſe his apparell ſheweth him to be proud. There may be, I hope, a proud heart in a leather doublet, like that of yours, and there may be a meeke ſpirit, and humble heart in a ſtuffe gowne like that of his; you looke on the outward appearance, but God lookes on both your hearts. His apparell is ſuch as his calling requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; and I know that for your cauſe alſo hee weareth ſuch to take away offence, and contempt, you are ſo apt to ſtumble at euery ſtraw; for ſuch as you, iudge onely according to the outward appearance, and would take occaſion at his meane apparell, to diſpoſe the Goſpell, as the <hi>Nazarens</hi> did. <hi>Mark.</hi> 6. 3. 4. and for this purpoſe the Church hath alwaies enioyned decency in apparell to Miniſters.</p>
               <p>You ſay, hee preacheth of malice, becauſe he hath no good neighbourhood in him, becauſe hee goes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15391:23"/>
not to the Ale-houſe with you, and your hang-byes, haile-fellowes well met, to drinke and to game, and to preach ouer the pot (you would then heare him, with great deuotion, and not ſay he preached prittle-prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle) therefore he hath no good neighbourhood in him. If you knew what good neighbourhood were, you ſhould ſee none in any of you, ſo much as in him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeo.</speaker>
               <p>Why, what call you good neighbourhood.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 12.</note> The Apoſtle tells you in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelues one to another in the feare of God.</hi> If your fellowſhip and friendſhip be knit in God, it is good fellowſhip: If your feaſting and meetings be as they were in the Primitiue Church among Chriſtians, vſing your ſelues as in the preſence of God, there is good fellowſhip and neighbourhood. If you be affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctioned to loue one another with brotherly loue, and in giuing honour one going before another, that is good neighbourhood, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 10. If your rich men <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 10.</note>prey not on the poore, by rent-racking, by ſmall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and great prizes, but releeue them before they fall, and helpe them vp when they are fallen, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10. <note place="margin">Luke. 10. 33. 34. 35.</note>33. 34 35. then are you good neighbours.</p>
               <p>But if your good neighbour-hood be acted no where but at the Ale-houſe, in drinking and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ribaldry and ſwearing, in fooliſh iangling, rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and vnſauory ſpeeches. In diſſembling, lying, couſonage in bargayning, inſnarings (called ale-houſe bargaines) waſting your good, like <hi>Eſaus:</hi> then is it ſuch like as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes of, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 3. 4. It's like <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 3. 4.</note>the meeting of ſwine at their trough; and it ſeemes ſtrange to ſuch heatheniſh people, that good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans run not with them to the ſame exceſſe of riot, and therefore ſpeake they euill of them.</p>
               <p>You ſay alſo that he preacheth out of choler, and that hee will be angry when no man hurts him. You thinke belike, no man ſhould be angry for Gods cauſe;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15391:24"/>
you will take your brothers part, your kinſmans part, and your friends part, when you ſee him abuſed: yea, in his abſence, you will anſwer for him, it may be you will not deale onely words, but blowes for him, if you loue him well, and ſhould God haue no friends to take his part, not to ſpeake a word for him, nay, not ſo much as to looke with an angry countenance againſt his enemies. Hath not God beene, and is not God our friend that wee ſhould ſhew no loue at all to him? can a childe with patience ſee his Father wronged? and ſhould the children of God not be diſpleaſed when they heare the name of God blaſphemed? Surely if we loue our Fathers that begat vs, wee cannot but loue God much more which hath made both them and vs, and all the world, and maintaines vs all, and all for vs, of his own goodnes and bounty. If we loue our earthly Mothers, that endured ſome bodily paines in our birth, we cannot but loue Ieſus Chriſt, that endured the curſed death of the Croſſe. For our new birth; Our Mothers bring vs forth Children of wrath; fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands of hell, but Chriſt hath brought vs forth chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and heyres of his glorious kingdome. Surely this loue of God towards vs, which is infinite, and endleſſe, ſhould moue vs to loue him; at the leaſt, to be diſpleaſed with his enemies, and the contemners of him.</p>
               <p>Was not <hi>Moſes</hi> angry with the Iſraelites in Gods <note place="margin">Exod. 32. 19.</note>cauſe? <hi>Exodus</hi> 32. 19. Did not the Leuites out of their zeale of Gods glory ſlay euery man his brother, companion, and neighbour? Was not <hi>Lots</hi> righteous ſoule grieued from day to day, becauſe of the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Sodomites? but you ſay, a man is angry for nought, if it be in Gods cauſe, you ſhew, what knowledge, what faith, what loue of God there is in you. This is farre from louing him with all the heart, ſoule, minde, and ſtrength. There is none ſo ready to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15391:24"/>
anſwere for themſelues as you are, yea, you will be very feruent and zealous in your owne cauſes: but you will hate or mocke them, that ſpeake in Gods behalfe. Whether doe you loue God, or your ſelfe better? whereas you ſay, that ſome of your rich men will ouer power him, and remoue him, vnleſſe he looke well to himſelfe; he knowes that to be the nature of the rich, which ſerue the golden Deuill Mammon, to hate all them that ſeeke to ſet forth Gods glory. Hee knowes that Mammon is now ſtrong in the world, and ſo full of ſophiſtry, that hee can make the Law a noſe of waxe, yea, and the Goſpell alſo, to turne them which way he liſt. Notwithſtanding he feares not the ſouldiers and ſeruants of Mammon, though they come like <hi>Goli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs,</hi> ſtrong men, ſenſible men, ſound cardes, well purſt, cunning vnderminers againſt him; for God hath put a ſtone in his ſling, euen his word in his mouth, and giuen him ſtrength to ſlay a Beare, and a Lion. God hath bidden him not to feare you: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould hee feare? <hi>Ezech.</hi> 2. 6. <hi>Sonne of man feare</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ezech 2. 6.</note>
                  <hi>them not, nor be afraid of their words, although Rebells and thornes be with thee, and thou remaineſt with ſcorpions: feare not their words, nor be afraid at their lookes, for they are a rebellious houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore I would counſell you to looke well to your ſelfe, that Satan and your owne ſins ouer-power not you, and remoue you cleane out of Gods fauour, protection, and kingdome.</p>
               <p>Afterward, you come to tell me of a fine man, of a great Scholler, that vſeth more Greeke and Latine then Engliſh in his Sermons, and that it will doe one good to heare him. What edifying doe you thinke that any of his vnlearned hearers get by ſuch vſing of his Greeke and Latine? You your ſelfe ſay that they profit nothing in knowledge, and I thinke they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit as little in good life. What good is that you ſpeake
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15391:25"/>
of? It is euen nothing but this, that you vſe him, as an inſtrument to diſgrace your Miniſter withall, by your odious compariſons-making. And becauſe heereby you comfort, releeue, and refreſh an accuſing conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whiles that you diſpoſe the plain-dealing of your owne Miniſter, and accounts him the right Preacher, that lets you liue ſecurely in your ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, doe you thinke it a decent thing for a Miniſter to goe from the pot to the pulpit? Should he not rather come from God, I meane from prayer, and Meditation, that he might pray and preach in fear, humility, reuerence, and zeale, as hauing the word put in his mouth from God, and ſpeaking as from God, beeing in the glorious preſence of God and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells?</p>
               <p>You ſay that you haue talkatiue fellows in your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, that can put them all downe in reaſoning, and their miniſter too. It likes you well, and ſuch as you, to call gracious words talkatiueneſſe, and prattle. Marke what the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Coloſſians</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Let the word of God dwell plenteouſly in you, in all wiſedome,</hi> &amp;c. In another place, <hi>Let your ſpeech be ſeaſoned with ſalt;</hi> but you thinke that vaine, fooliſh, rotten, and vnſauory ſpeeches, ſhould rather be plentifull in men mouthes; for with theſe I neuer heare you finde any fault, oaths, lyes, fooliſh ieaſting, ribaldry hath free paſſage with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out checke, or rebuke. And if ſuch perſons doe but humour and pleaſe you, then is all well, taken how bad ſoeuer it be, and with ſuch like perſons you loue to keepe company; but you haue no delight to tarry where there is ſober talke, and Chriſtian communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; as I haue ſeene diuers begin to hem, and to hum, and to hang downe the head, to yawne, raſpe, and ſtretch (as being weary with long ſitting) ſaying that they haue buſineſſe, and therefore muſt away, and ſo ſliuing out of the doores, preſently ſtumble into an
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15391:25"/>
other place, where they will be as merry as cuppe and cann can make them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But heare what the holy man of God, the Prophet</hi> Dauid <hi>ſaith,</hi> Pſal. <hi>26. 4. 5.</hi> I haue not dwelt with vaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <note place="margin">Pſal. 26. 4. 5.</note>neither will I haue fellowſhip with the deceitfull. I haue hated the congregation of the wicked<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and will not ſit among the vngodly, <hi>And</hi> Pſal. <hi>119. 115.</hi> Away from me ye wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 115.</note>for I will keepe the commandement of my God. <hi>And</hi> Pro. <hi>14. 7.</hi> Depart from the fooliſh man, when thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueſt <note place="margin">Prou. 14. 7.</note>not in him the lips of knowledge. <hi>And</hi> Ecclus. <hi>9. 17.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ecclus. 9. 17.</note>Let thy talke be with the wiſe, and all thy communication in the Law of the moſt high. <hi>This is expreſly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> Deut. <hi>11. 19.</hi> We must ſpeake of the Commandements <note place="margin">Deut. 11. 19.</note>continually, when wee ſit at home, when wee walke by the way, when wee riſe vp, and when we lye downe: <hi>but they that do thus, by your confeſſion, ſhall loſe their friends; if they loſe their friendſhip of ſinners, to obtaine the friendſhip of God, and his Angells, it is a gainefull loſſe, for there be more with them then againſt them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas you ſay (a wonted Prouerbe among pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane people) <hi>A booke in the Pocket, a Deuill in the heart;</hi> There be ſome that carry no bookes in their pockets, nor yet good words in their mouthes, which notwithſtanding haue the Deuill in their hearts. All are not bad that carry good bookes with them, nor all good, that haue no bookes. It is a Prouerbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, hee that doth as the Preacher would haue him doe, ſhall die a beggar: but there be ſome which dye beggars, becauſe they will not doe as the Preacher would haue them. And I my ſelfe haue heard ſome ſay, bring not vp your ſonne in learning, for it will make him a bad husband; but there be ſome bad huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands that were neuer brought vp in learning.</p>
               <p>You call your honeſt men needy, in way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. It is as eaſie for the rich man to ſcorne the poore for his pouerty, as it is for the fat Oxe that is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15391:26"/>
ready for the ſhambles to tread the feeble vnder feete. The holy man <hi>Dauid</hi> was peſtered, and puſhed at <note place="margin">Phil. 22. 12.</note>with ſuch fat Bulls of Baſan, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. 12. and bark't at with ſuch dogs, <hi>verſe</hi> 16. ſo was Chriſt alſo, whereof he was a figure; and ſo are, and ſhall all Chriſtians, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the poore, that can leaſt helpe themſelues Marke well, what our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>It is as hard for a rich man to enter into the Kingdome of Heauen, as for a gable rope to paſſe through the eye of a nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle:</hi> The temptations of Mammon preuaile ſo much with them, as that they cannot ſubiect their hearts to the Goſpell; they will not haue Ieſus Chriſt to be King and ruler ouer them, like the murtherous Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the Goſpell, they cannot abide to do homage to Chriſt; ſuch manner of ſeruice is too baſe, with the proud and licentious worldlings. It will not afford ſuch meat, drinke, and cloth, as a man ſhould haue, and there is no liberty but continuall paines-taking. Lewd ſeruants that take no pleaſure in their Maſters profit, nor delight in a well ordered family, loue to ſerue diſſolute and prodigall maſters, where they may haue great wages to maintaine pride, wantonnes, and gaming, and where they may haue full ſcope and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſay and doe what they liſt: Euen ſo, moſt rich men, and all worldlings, haue no pleaſure at all in the profiting of Chriſt by their faithfull ſeruice, neither haue any delight in his gouernment and family, there is ſo much ſtrictneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> curiouſneſſe and baſe work; but they muſt ſerue golden Mammon, that will giue them wage enough, they ſhall want nothing that will doe them good, for there is neither pinching nor ſparing, neither ſhall they be reſtrained of their liberty.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing that theſe worldlings are ſuch bad and froward ſeruants, Chriſt which is a ſtraight and hard man, and therefore lookes to haue his buſineſſe well followed, and to receiue his owne with aduantage, will
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15391:26"/>
haue thoſe that haue not dwelt in wanton and prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall houſes, where there is nothing but eating and drinking, mirth and paſtime; but hee hath choſen the poore and needy to confound the rich; the fooliſh and ſimple, to confound the wiſe and the learned; the weake, and helpleſſe, to bring to naught the mighty and the ſtrong, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 26. 27. 28. This Scripture is <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 26. 27. 28.</note>fulfilled in your owne eyes, in your owne towne, and yet you cannot ſee it, becauſe he lookes on the heart, and hath mercy on whom he will, and you contrarily looke on the outward appearance, and iudge thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. In <hi>Marke</hi> 6. Chriſt preacheth in his owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, <note place="margin">Marke 6.</note>and worketh miracles there alſo, but how do they heare him and receiue him? Whence hath he this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? What wiſedome is this that is giuen him? How doth hee worke ſuch great wonders? Is hee not a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter? are not his Mother, Brethren<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Siſters with vs? But heere was all, and therefore Chriſt maruelled at their vnbeleefe. In the weake and meane outward appearance of Chriſt, they might the more cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue ſeene the power, wiſedome, and glory of God, had they not beheld him with fleſhly and carnall eyes.</p>
               <p>So may you ſee the mercy, grace, and goodnes of God in opening the eyes of your poore men, tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, labouring men, vnlearned men, men of no edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, of no meanes, ſuch as the Diſciples were; not ſo ſenſible and ſo wiſe as ſome of your rich men are, not booke-learned as they are, not at leyſure as they are, but alwaies in ſome labour and trauell, and yet can they put downe all your ſenſible men in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, and your fine Latine Preacher with them. Is not this the power of God inlightning their mindes, mollifying their hearts with the oyle of grace, and ſanctifying the word vnto them which they heare? Heereupon comes this difference betweene them, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15391:27"/>
the rich, and betweene other poore men and them. They hunger and thirſt after the word of God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God ſatisfieth their ſoules with God, and they are fatte and well-liking, the rich haue not this ſpirituall hungar, and thirſt, and therfore they are ſent empty <note place="margin">Luke 1. 53.</note>away. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 53.</p>
               <p>Theſe poore men among you (whom God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued to mercy) you call pratling fellowes, beggarly perſons, Putricans, with other mocking, vngodly, and enuious termes. Our Sauiour Chriſts countrimen ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired his doctrine, wiſedome, miracles, but euer in the end they came in with their (But:) He is but a Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but of meane parentage, but of meane education, &amp;c. Euen ſo doe you come in alwaies with your But: but hee is no Scholler, but he is no linguiſt, but our rich men and great men regard him not; hee is but this, he is but that: ſo you make this But, a ſtumbling blocke, or rather a brazen wall to ſeparate you from Gods Kingdome. The Lord turne your hearts.</p>
               <p>Againe, you ſay ſuch poore men ſhould mind their buſineſſe, and not runne to Sermons: this running to Sermons indeede is a great beame in your eyes: you commonly iudge them vnthrifts, that ſpend an houre in the weeke day at a Sermon: but you neuer ſpeake of them that ſpend many houres in the weeke in idle talke, or at the Ale-houſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nay I haue heard your owne tongue commend a tradeſ-man, for his orderly courſe of life; and among other things, that hee would goe twiſe or thriſe in the weeke to the Ale-houſe; if hee liked the company; but he duely kept his ſtint, hee would not paſſe his houre vnleſſe by great chance. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe I ſimply diſallow this thing in him; but if he beſtowed one of theſe houres in the hearing of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, I ſhould thinke the better of him, and ſo would you to. For I am perſwaded that you your ſelfe thinke the Church better than the Ale-houſe, and the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15391:27"/>
word of God to be as needfull for the ſoule, as Ale for the body. And if they offer not the ſacrifice of fooles, but giue diligent eare, and laying vp that in memory which they heare, ſhall afterward vpon occaſion ſpeak of the ſame, I hope that you for your part will not terme them pratlers, nor hate them for it, but rather commend them, and loue them, preferring them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others that haue that care to know God, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to heare his word.</p>
               <p>Alaſſe, I am ſorry to heare you ſay, that you care for none that followes, and fauors your Miniſter. You ſhould all fauour him, and follow his doctrine: yea, and him alſo, wherein hee followeth Chriſt. You ſhould be his fellow-helpers, and gather with him, and not ſcatter abroad, nor hinder the worke of the Lord in his hands. You rich men ſhould countenance him all that you can, that thereby all ſorts, and euen the worſt people might be moued to reuerence him, which in the contempt of him, contemne the word of God, and God himſelfe, whoſe meſſenger he is. They ſhould couer his faults, and infirmities, that by ſuch things the word of God be not euill ſpoken of among them that ſeeke ſuch occaſions. They ſhould helpe and releeue his wants (as all true Chriſtians euer haue done,) that pouerty hinder not the worke of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery and ſo your ſoules be ſtarued, and famiſhed to death through the pining of his body.</p>
               <p>You will meate your oxen, and keepe your horſes well, that they may be ſtrong to labour, elſe your bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe will lye vndone: ought you not then much more to maintaine your miniſter, that your ſoules may be filled, and ſatisfied with good? Will you withdraw meat from your beaſts, that they might not worke, and yet would haue your worke done? ſurely you would thinke him hardly well in his wits, that would doe ſo: euen ſo, will you ſacrilegiouſly withdraw your
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15391:28"/>
Miniſters maintenance, that he might not preach, and yet would be ſaued, this is ſpirituall madnes, and dead drunkenneſſe.</p>
               <p>Alas for you, I pitty your caſe, I perceiue how the gods of this world, Satan and Mammon, haue blinded the eyes of ſome of your rich men, and hath preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſo much with them, as he hath brought them to be ranke Phariſees, as ill and worſe then they, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Some few of them, it ſhould ſeeme, being fat at the heart, and full in the purſe, are prickt with pride and vaineglory, whereby they ſeeke to ouer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>power all the meaner ſort, to prey vpon them at their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, both to ſay and doe, not what truth and right is, but what they would haue. If any ſubmit themſelues and yeeld to them in all things, magnifying and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them, him they will countenance and fauour and chiefly giue him faire words; but all accompts in the end being caſt, he ſhall finde himſelfe nothing helped, or bettered by them, vnleſſe it be of other mens coſt; but if any diſlike their doings and croſſe them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, yea, when he can doe no other, vnleſſe hee will burthen his conſcience, him they will be reuenged of, diſgracing him, and watching opportunity to thwart him; and as I may ſay, to worrie him if they could. And by thoſe meanes haue they brought, and ſeeke to bring all men into their ſubiection, whereout they ſuck no ſmall aduantage.</p>
               <p>Now theſe men cannot abide your miniſter for his plaine dealing with them, yea like enuious Riualls they cannot abide that any reſpect or reuerence ſhould be had, or giuen to him, for they thinke it great diſgrace to them, that any man ſhould be preferred before them in any thing in your pariſh; yea they make accompt of your miniſter, but as of a bodily ſeruant for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>duties, according to Law, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15391:28"/>
they pay his tithes as his wages. They would not haue him to meddle or make with townes-mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which are ſwayd after their owne luſts, nor of their wickedneſſe, becauſe they would not haue their vglineſſe and ſhame vncouered before the eyes of the world, nor the gnawing worme of their galled conſcience ſtirred and ſet on worke before the time, (the Lord conuert them if it be his gracious pleaſure.) Hence it is that they ſeeke to ſingle out all men from him, that being left alone, and no man daring to ſpeak in his behalſe, no not the manifeſt trueth, they might vpon euery light occaſion vſe him at their pleaſure: but though all men leaue him, yet God will aſſiſt him, in his owne cauſe; and in the end all men ſhall ſee his power in the conuerſion, or in the confuſion of theſe wicked Caitiues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>It is euen as true, that you ſay, as God is in heauen. They are ſo fed as they are like a foole with a full belly, and a bable in his hand. No man can bee in quiet for them: they are euen the moſt venemous people that euer man came amongſt; it is not poſſible to eſcape their hands, but they will one way or other miſchiefe him: I haue had but too much experience of—&amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>How bad ſoeuer they be, let not vs be moued to impatience, but vſe good words; If wee ſee their wickedneſſe, let vs hate it, but let vs loue their perſons, God can make them veſſels of holineſſe and righteouſneſſe at his pleaſure. A ſoft anſwere pacifieth wrath, and good words quench the coales of ſtrife: we muſt not ceaſe to be good becauſe they are euill.</p>
               <p>But to make an end of my former ſpeech vnto you; If you remember, you were angry with me (when vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your owne ſpeeches) I ſaid you were like to <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> one againſt another, and all againſt your Miniſter; doe you not euen now ſay the ſame vpon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15391:29"/>
occaſion) terming them venemous, and full fooles with bables? Whereby it appeares that you are now with them, now againſt them; faine would you haue their fauour, but your owne will withall; but your loue to Gods word, and your miniſter is like theirs. Well, I perceiue that ſinne raignes in a company of you, and that Satan rules you at his pleaſure. When you and they are at ſome variance, and the Miniſter, as his text doth lead him, doth reproue ſome ſinne that you know them guilty of, that ſinne you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber well, and will be rehearſing of it, and curri-fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with the Miniſter, to ſhroud your ſelfe vnder him: this you doe out of a reuengefull heart to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace and defame your neighbours, and that in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king others bad, your ſelfe might ſeeme good. Again, when time ſerues, you will ſide to them againſt your miniſter, and call his reprouing of ſinne rayling againſt honeſt men, and ſay that he hath no neighbourhood, nor loue of his people in him; that hee ſpeakes all out of pride, malice, enuy, choller: Whereby a man may eaſily ſee, that ſome among you are religious, ſome prophane and vnmoueable in their wickedneſſe, ſome crafty ſhifters, ſeruing themſelues of both parties, hating the one, and not louing the other.</p>
               <p>What ſay you now, being in this tune that you are in? Put the caſe that <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp;c. or any of the holy men of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>former times, ſhould come to Preach among you: put the caſe that Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe ſhould come, (I meane not working miracles, nor diſcouering themſelues) but preaching, and teaching in ſuch manner as they did to the Iewes, &amp; to other peoples, when they liued on earth? You ſay you would heare them, follow them, reuerence, and honour them, confeſſe your ſinnes, you would ſpend goods, body, and life for them, you would caſt all that you had at their feete, and ſuffer your ſelues to</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:15391:29"/>
But the manifeſt trueth is, that Chriſt himſelfe ſhould finde no better entertainment, than your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter now doth, nay farre worſe; for Chriſt vſed to ſpeake to the ſpirits of men, ſeeing hee knew the thoughts of their hearts, and their ſecret ſinnes; and therefore would you perſecute him with more deadly hatred. Hee would not preach comfort I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you to obſtinate and hard hearted Phariſees, nor frame his ſpeeches to the liking of their corrupt iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and earthly imaginations, as you would haue your Miniſter to doe.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay hee would be innocent, harme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, ſinneleſſe, giuing none occaſion, no appearance of euill, yea, hee would ſtoppe the mouthes of the worſt, that they could not ſpeake one euill word of him.</p>
               <p>But by your leaue, that is well ſpoken which is well taken, and that is well done, that is well conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If you be of froward diſpoſitions, and euill harts, how would you take that at his hands, which were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to you? how would you being of ignorant and corrupt iudgements interpret his words, and cenſure his doings? It mattereth not onely who is the ſpeaker, and what is ſpoken; but alſo who is the hearer, and how it is heard. The ſerpent can finde poiſon there where the Bee can finde no poyſon but honey. And I haue often heard them ſay that the cunning Alchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt can draw gall out of hony, and hony out of gall: you muſt therefore conſider what heart and eares you haue: I tell you plainely, that vnleſſe Chriſt ſhould put new hearts into your bodies, you would heare him no otherwiſe then you doe your owne Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, that cannot giue you new hearts. And though hee be moſt holy, yet would you eſteeme him a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. What I pray you ſaid the proud and couetous
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15391:30"/>
Phariſees of him? Hee is a glutton, a drinker, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 19. Mat. 27. 63. Mat. 9. 34.</note>companion. <hi>Matthew</hi> 11 19. A deceiuer, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> 27. 63. A Sorcerer, or worker with euill Spirits, <hi>Matthew</hi> 9. 34. Hee hath a Deuill, and is madde, why <note place="margin">Iohn 10. 20.</note>doe you heare him? <hi>Iohn</hi> 10 20. Hee is a Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, <note place="margin">Iohn 8. 48. Iohn 9. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note>and is frantike, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 48. They know that hee is a ſinner, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9. 24. yea, his owne kinſmen layed <note place="margin">Marke 3. 21.</note>hands on him, ſuppoſing that hee was madde. <hi>Mark.</hi> 3. 21.</p>
               <p>How then I pray you would the proud, couetous Phariſees in theſe daies receiue him? How would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane mockers heare him? Euen worſe then they doe your Miniſter, or any other faithfull Paſtor elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. For the more purely that the word of God is preached, the more doth it diſſent from the corrupt heart, and more neerely ſearcheth it, and makes ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners more ſinfull, working more forcibly in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Heereupon the rebellious ſinner preſently ſeekes for falſe releefes, eaſe, and comforts, and that is by returning all vpon the Miniſter, hee is a Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, hee is phantaſticall, preciſe, indiſcreete, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable; now he ſpeakes to himſelfe, for wee are no ſuch men; hee ſpeakes out of pride, malice, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, choller, falſe information, theres none worſe then himſelfe, ſuch Chriſtianity cannot be acted &amp;c. How I pray you, did they cenſure <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt?</hi> Hee hath a Deuill, the Deuill is in him, a grimme dogge, a melancholy fellow, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. How then would you ſpeake of him, and of Chriſt? If new wine be poured into olde veſſells, whoſoeuer poures it in, and howſoeuer it be poured in, the veſſels will burſt. And if a new peece be ſewed to an old garment, how good ſoeuer the peece be, and how cunning ſoeuer the taylor be, it will rent away part of the olde: for the olde veſſell cannot containe the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15391:30"/>
new wine, nor the olde rotten garment retaine the new cloath. If the pure word of God from Chriſts owne mouth were applied to your olde, fleſhly, and rotten hearts, what containing or retaining would there be of it? Againe, ſo long as you are carnall, how can you iudge of thoſe things which are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall?</p>
               <p>The naturall man cannot perceiue the things of the ſpirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſſe to him, nothing ſounds well to his eare, but that which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of fleſh and bloud. And therefore many dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty eared men can away with none but with ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerlike Sermons. The Word muſt ſauor of humane wiſedome and learning, elſe there is no more taſte in it, than in water, hee cannot abide to drinke it; but if it hath ſugar in it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or be mixt with wine, then for the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and wines ſake, hee drinks it off, and commends it not ſimply, but <hi>ſecundum quid.</hi> But the pure word of God hath neither good taſte, nor good farewell, it goeth downe either like water in the ſottiſh, or like wormewood and gall in the hard-hearted and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious.</p>
               <p>Iudge now I pray you, how your froward rich men would heare, receiue, entertaine, and welcome Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, in whom they ſay they beleeue, whom they loue aboue all, and by whom they hope to bee ſaued. I feare that they which ſo greatly commend your fine man, that preacheth more Greeke, Latine, and Hebrew, then Engliſh, and which are ſo delighted and comforted with his languages, if Ieſus Chriſt were preaching to them, in ſuch manner as hee did on the earth, would hardly giue him friendly intertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they would hardly all agree to make him a ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, or contribution, I doubt ſome would giue him neuer a penny, euen of them that are the moſt able.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:15391:31"/>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>I am no Scripture man: I cannot anſwer you to euery thing: but it will not ſinke into my head, but that we ſhould all heare and obey Chriſt. Though wee be bad enough (as there is none good but God) yet wee are not ſo bad, I truſt, whatſoeuer you ſay, I hope you are no Prophet, it is hard for you to iudge what wee are, much leſſe can you tell what you would be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue well that you are no Scripture man; for it appeares by you, that that gift is not yet giuen to you, neither doe you as yet deſire it. For it may be that you are afraid to be termed a Puritane, or to be mocked of your friends &amp; companions, and you loue not to be mocked. Whereas you ſay that I am no Prophet: It is enough for me that you are a Prophet in theſe things. For I haue ſaid nothing but that which you haue ſaid, and I build vpon your reaſon, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reaſon.</p>
               <p>You ſaid euen now that if a Lion were turned into a Lambe, hee would be but regarded and vſed like a Lambe. Euen ſo, when God tooke our nature, euen mans true ſhape vnto him, was hee not regarded and vſed as a man in the world? Yea, and was hee not more deſpitefully and ſhamefully intreated in the world, then euer any man was before him? What if hee were in the ſame appearance now in the world, as then hee was, ſhould hee haue any better entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the world then his brethren haue now, and <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 15.</note>haue had? They that know not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his members. (1 <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> 1. 15. <hi>which diſcerne all things, and are iudged of none:)</hi> How ſhould they know the head, if hee were among them? Surely he that knoweth the head, knoweth the members alſo, and hee that knowes not the members knowes not the head, for they are all <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 11.</note>one. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:15391:31"/>
You ſaide alſo, that if a man were forth twenty yeares in a ſtrange countrey, and ſhould returne home againe in the forme of a ſeruant or poore man, that his owne family would not know him: Euen ſo Saint <note place="margin">Iohn 2. 10.</note>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeakes of Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 10. <hi>Hee came among his owne, and his owne receiued him not.</hi> If they had knowne him in <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, they would ſurely haue receiued him, as ſome beleeuers did. So if you know him not now in his Word preached, you could not poſſibly know him if hee were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you: for you can no way know him but by his voyce.</p>
               <p>You ſaid moreouer that if a King ſhould come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your towne in the forme of a ſeruant, or poore man, that hee would not be heard nor regarded at all, though hee ſhewed forth himſelfe in his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, geſture, behauiour, wiſedome, counſell, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, learning, &amp;c. Euen ſo though Chriſt was the brightneſſe of the glory of God, and the liuely I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and patterne of his perſon in the world, the maieſty, power, greatneſſe, wiſedome, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his God head ſhining in his perſon, face, countenance, words, workes; yet his owne knew him not. And if hee were in ſuch ſort among you, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would you know him nor heare him otherwiſe then now you know him, and heare him by his voyce; if he begin once to meddle with you, and to reforme you, then you would not let him alone. Why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee will not let you alone, as you ſaid of your Miniſter. Alas for you I pitty you, becauſe you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee your owne hypocriſie that you might repent.</p>
               <p>There was a certaine Biſhop, that at a viſitation preached a very godly Sermon, and godlily, euen to the capacity of the meaneſt hearers. I heard him very greatly commended for his graue geſture, for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15391:32"/>
his diſtinct and ſober deliuerie, for his Fatherly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, ſpeaking plainely and familiarly as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to his Children, not ſo earneſt and vehement, and hotte, as young nouices are, &amp;c. And hee was worthy to be a Biſhop. As for their Miniſter, hee was but a youngling, and as good as no body in compariſon of him. If they had ſuch a Preacher, they would giue I know not what (for theſe gaue lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, or nothing towards the maintenance of their owne)</p>
               <p>This great and generall commendation was ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Biſhop in priuate, &amp;c. Now at the next yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viſitation after, the ſame Biſhop came in the attyre and faſhion of an ordinary and poore miniſter, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his beard ſhauen, &amp;c. offering himſelfe to bee their Preacher, for there was a ſpeech in the towne that their owne Preacher would goe away to another place. The Biſhop of ſet purpoſe did chooſe another text differing from his former in words, but not in matter, ſo that in a manner he preached the very ſame Sermon. Now the ſame perſons that did ſo much commend him before, did as muh diſcommend him now, and that in mine owne hearing. They ſaid that hee had no good geſture, but a heauy kinde of moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of his body, that hee bended too much forward, and ſtood not vpright, that hee was nothing ripe, nor ready in his deliuery, that hee could be no ſcholler, becauſe hee was ſo plaine ſpoken, that almoſt any man might make as good a Sermon, that it differed little from ordinary talke, that hee enforſt, nor fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed his exhortations with no vehemencie, nor ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe, and that his words had no life in them, to ſtirre vp attention, or to mooue the affections of the hearers, that none of them would giue a penny to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his maintainance, and that they would haue
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15391:32"/>
an other kinde of Preacher than hee, or they would haue none. Euen ſo if Ieſus Chriſt ſhould come to preach among you in mans appearance, you conceit your ſelfe that you would heare him as Chriſt, but withall; you haue a ſecret confuſed imagination of ſome kinde of worldlie flouriſh, as the Iewes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of him: but the plaine trueth is, that you would ſay and iudge no otherwiſe of him, then of any other faithfull paſtour: for you commend you know not what, and you diſpraiſe you know not what.</p>
               <p>But now to trouble you no longer, let mee coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and exhort you, as a friend, and Chriſtian bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, caſt away all theſe vaine and worldly Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, pray vnto God to enlighten the eyes of your minde, that the glorious light of the Goſpell might ſhine vnto you, which as yet is hidden from you, pray vnto him to take the ſtony heart out of your body, and to giue you an heart of fleſh, a penitent, humble, and ſober heart, leaue that fooliſh ieaſting, and that vaine Ale houſe company keeping, betake your ſelfe to priuate prayer, and reading, and then GOD will heare you, and come vnto you, for hee will not turne away his face from them that deſire to be acquainted with him, giue diligent eare to your Miniſters Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and Catechizings, and meditate ſeriouſly after of that which you haue heard and offer your ſelfe to your Paſtour and Shepheard of your ſoule, be not ſtrange vnto him, as though you cared not for him, but let him ſee your amendment and conuerſion, and be better acquainted with him, but yet in ſinglenes and ſincerity, and if you once be entred into a good way, bee conſtant in it to the end without feare, or wauering, let nothing terrifie or affright you; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer men iudge, ſay, or doe, care not you for that, nor be troubled, be ruled by the aduice of your mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15391:33"/>
before any other, and let your foote weare his threaſhold, for you ſhall finde more comfort, pleaſure, and delight in his company than euer you had in any thing all the daies of your vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yea, you ſhall more and more perceiue in what a moſt miſerable eſtate you were in, and thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels your rich gluttons are in, vnleſſe they repent: You ſhall by Gods grace in time come to a more cleare, and perfect diſcerning of all things. You know the olde Prouerbe commonly vſed, <hi>they that are in Hell thinke there is no other Heauen,</hi> and the Oxe thinkes hee is going to the ſtall, when hee goes to the ſhambles. Bee not deceiued: The men of this world, which you doe call wiſe ſenſible men, are ledde by their ſenſe, and worldly craft to the Deuills Larder-houſe. And as the Apoſtle ſayes, when they thinke themſelues to be wiſe, they become very fooles.</p>
               <p>I haue ſpoken thus boldly vnto you, becauſe I take you to be my friend; for I am ſure that I am yours: if you any way doubt of it, try mee in any thing wherein I can pleaſure you; onely let mee intreat you to conſider well of this point that you and I haue thus reaſoned of. I haue a good hope that howſoeuer you haue beene miſledde a long time, all the Angells in Heauen ſhall reioyce in your conuerſion. And I doe like you a great deale the better, becauſe you haue not left mee, and gone away from mee in a chaſe, eſpeciallie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I haue dealt ſo plainely with you as I haue done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mataeolog.</speaker>
               <p>I can tell you, if you had ſpoken ſo to ſome of our towne, they would ſit on your skirts while they liued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eulalus.</speaker>
               <p>Like enough: for it is the property of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15391:33"/>
fleſh and bloud to be reuengefull, but the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle teacheth vs another leſſon: <hi>Auenge not your ſelues, I will repay ſaith the Lord:</hi> My skirts are as well able to beare a Feather, as it is to ſit on them; I truſt that ſo long as I giue them no other occaſion then I haue done, they ſhall haue no faſt ſitting, for the Lord will not leaue them that feare him, in their enemies hands.</p>
               <p>The Lord grant that I may ſee ſome fruits of this conference in you at our next meeting.</p>
               <p>By this ſhort Dialogue it appeareth how the word of GOD is moſt commonly and generally heard and receiued, , yea, euen of all, that are not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: For they doe either altogether heare it as the word of man, or at leaſt when it is particularly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, for their conuerſion, and reformation, then begin they euer to ſeeke out arguments (for the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſter the Father of lyes is at hand) for their hard hearts, for their luſtfull liuing, for the ſaluing of an euill and corrupt conſcience, drawne from the perſon of the Miniſter; yea, and to ſeeke out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhepheard, (ſome that Satan hath pickt in at the window) whom they may obiect againſt him: who if hee be a good Scholler, politicke and craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for his owne aduantage, and of Gentleman-like fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, then is hee, and ſuch like to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their owne Miniſter, and ſuch like, without all compare. And indeede, to ſay the truth, there is no more compariſon betweene them, then betweene <hi>Paul,</hi> and the learned preachers, that ſo flouriſht at Corinth. A foole will ſeeke out excuſes for his foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhnes.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſeeing that this is the fourth and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree of Faith, whereby a man euen ſteps vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen, the Apoſtle, and all faithfull Shepheards,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15391:34"/>
haue great cauſe of reioycing (as the Angells in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen alſo haue) and of thankſgiuing without ceaſing, when any man heareth the word, not as theirs, but as Gods, ſeeing that they alone, and none but they doe heare, know, and follow Chriſt their chiefe ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard.</p>
               <p>This then is the condemnation of the world, that they heare indeede, but with vnbeleeuing hearts, doubting, and wauering minds, and in a dreaming and ſlumbering manner, being like to <hi>Salomons</hi> ſluggard, <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 10.</note>
                  <hi>Prouerbs</hi> 6. 10. <hi>Yet a little ſleepe, a little ſlumber, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle foulding of the hands to ſleepe; the weather is colde, there is a Beare, or a Lyon in the way;</hi> It is yet early e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, there is no time yet ouerpaſt: many labour and trauell, hauing no reſt night nor day, yet doe they liue and die in pouerty; many lye and ſleepe, yet wealth commeth on them vnlooked for: That which will be, will be: It is but euen happen good, haue good, one good fortune or other will befall mee. I ſhall doe as well as I can, and as others haue done before mee. And thus doth ſlothfulneſſe get the vpper hand, and hold poſſeſſion ſtill, till at the length pouerty come ſodenly, and neceſſity like an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med man.</p>
               <p>This is the common practiſe of dead hearted, and worldly minded men, they are continually called vpon, iogged, and rouzed, yet they heare, and heare not; like dreamers, and are poſſeſt with the ſpirit of ſlumber. Their hearts are fixed, and affections ſet on the earth and earthly things, euen as the tree is fixed, and rooted in the earth. They loue to lye and liue ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely in ſinne, being drunken with the profits, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, delights, pompe and pride of this world, hauing no affection nor fancy to God and godly things, being adulterers, adultereſſes, and fornicators of this world,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15391:34"/>
altogether vnlike and contrary to the ſpouſe of Chriſt in the Canticles.</p>
               <p>Hence it is, that they imagine and reaſon in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues like the ſluggard; yet a little more pleaſure in ſinne, a little more ſolace and delight in fleſhly luſts, a little longer ſpace of liuing after the pleaſant conceits and imaginations of mine owne heart, there is yet no time ouer-paſt, I ſhall repent and amend in my latter dayes, God is mercifull, and will not ſo ſtrictly deale with vs as theſe preciſe Preachers doe beare vs in hand, that would haue vs to be ruled and ordered by their phantaſticall imaginations: they would haue they know not what, and for ought we ſee; they are as ill as others. This preciſe kinde of preaching is come vp but of late yeares, and I thinke there were as good Chriſtians before, as euer there haue beene ſince.</p>
               <p>Theſe and a thouſand ſuch like follies doe they imagine and vtter, tending all to the blinding and hardning of themſelues in their ſinfull and rebellious courſes. That which a man hath a ſpeciall loue, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and inclination to of himſelfe, hee may ſoone be perſwaded vnto by another, for any reaſon, though neuer ſo weake and ſeely feedeth him, and confirmeth him; whereas the ſtrongeſt diſſwaſions that may be ſhall preuaile little or nothing, or but for the time preſent: Againe, on the contrary, if a man out of his owne heart and iudgement haue no liking nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, though hee be neuer ſo earneſtly ſet vpon, and by moſt ſound and ſtrong reaſons be diſſwaded by another; yet can hee be little moued or ſtirred, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer returneth backe againe to his former diſlikes, like the heauy ſtone, that being rouled by great ſtrength vpward, doth of it ſelfe retire backe againe, ſo ſoone as we hold off our hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:15391:35"/>
Thus it is with obſtinate ſinners, whoſe hearts are heauy, and ſtony, the ſtrongeſt reaſons that may be though neuer ſo plaine and euident, yea the very bare word of the text, being the immediate word of God, can preuaile little or nothing with them, they are ſo ſtrongly poſſeſt with contrary imaginations, luſts and deſires: but on the contrary, any weake, ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fooliſh reaſon, any ignorant ſpeech &amp; ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe opinion feedeth them, and confirmeth them in their ſinfull courſes. Any thing will perſwade the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to be idle; ſo any thing will mooue the ſinner to ſpirituall idleneſſe: And thus will thoſe drunken and ſleepy ſinners doe, till death ſummon them to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and till the houſe be fired ouer their heads, and round about them, I meane till the elements melt, and the heauens paſſe away with a noiſe, as our Sauiour <note place="margin">Mat. 24. 38. 39.</note>Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Matthew</hi> 24. 38. 39. <hi>As in the dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the flood, they did eate and drinke, marry, and giue in marriage, vnto the day that Noah entred into the Arke, and knew nothing</hi> (for they little regarded, and leſſe beleeued <hi>Noahs</hi> preaching) <hi>till the flood came, and tooke them all away; ſo ſhall the comming of the Sonne of Man be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore it is no marueile if men commonly caſt away the word of God preached, as but the word of man; but it is a marueile rather that men ſhould heare it as the word of God, taking no offence at the perſon of the Preacher: for this proceedeth of ſupernaturall grace, but the other comes of naturall blindneſſe and corruption. Great cauſe therefore haue we to reioyce and giue thankes to God for them, that receiue the Word from vs, not as our word, but as the Word of GOD; which is an euident token of true conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>In this manner of receiuing the word hee confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15391:35"/>
them, by auouching that the word preached is indeed the word of Gods own mouth: By which briefe aſſeueration, hee preuenteth and cutteth off all obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
               <p>Furthermore hee amplifieth this their manner of receiuing the word, by the efficacy of the word in them <hi>[which worketh in you:]</hi> The word of man worketh on the naturall affections, and moueth them but to that, to which they haue an inclination in themſelues: but the word of God worketh in man by regenerating and ſanctifying him, that denying himſelfe hee might be tranſplanted into Chriſt, and bring forth fruit in him, to the honor of God, not to the profit of himſelfe, which no naturall man can doe. Philoſophy and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall education inſtructeth and ordereth the life and manners, by reſtraining the brutiſhneſſe of ſinne, but it changeth not a man from being a bruit. Heerein then is the euident difference betweene Gods word, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane doctrines, and inſtructions.</p>
               <p>This working of the word he reſtraineth to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers <hi>[in you,]</hi> without faith we are dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 1. And our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 1.</note>
                  <hi>The time ſhall come, and now is, when the dead</hi> (ſinners) <hi>ſhall heare the voice of the Sonne of God, and they that hear it</hi> (with humble, penitent, and obedient hearts) <hi>ſhall liue.</hi> Alſo the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 14. <hi>Awake thou</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 14.</note>
                  <hi>that ſleepeſt</hi> (in worldly and fleſhly affections, &amp; luſts) <hi>and ſtand vp from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall giue thee light.</hi> Now the dead receiue no nouriſhment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they that want faith, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 2.</note>2. <hi>The word which they heard, profited them not, becauſe it was not mingled with faith in them that heard it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the 14 verſe following, hee prooueth that the word of God wrought in them by the outward worke or effect, <hi>[For ye are become followers of the Churches of</hi>

                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:15391:36"/>
                  <hi>Iudaea in Chriſt: For you haue ſuffered the ſame things of your owne countrimen, as they haue of the Iewes.</hi> This, is a ſure and euident argument of true hearing and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, to immitate the godly, and to haue fellowſhip and communion with them. Further, this fellowſhip and imitation is proued and tryed by the fire, namely by their ſuffering with them, this ſuffering is further tryed by the perſons perſecuting <hi>[their owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen, friends, kinsfolkes,</hi> &amp;c.] for that is the greateſt perſecution of all, and which can leaſt be endured, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it trieth a Chriſtian man euen to the heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
