<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The comicall historie of Alphonsus, King of Aragon As it hath bene sundrie times acted. Made by R.G.</title>
            <title>Alphonsus, King of Aragon</title>
            <author>Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02091</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105900</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841625</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841625</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6223</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02091)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6223)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 344:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The comicall historie of Alphonsus, King of Aragon As it hath bene sundrie times acted. Made by R.G.</title>
                  <title>Alphonsus, King of Aragon</title>
                  <author>Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[70] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Brinted [sic] by Thomas Creede,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.G. = Robert Greene.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alfonso --  V, --  King of Aragon, 1396-1458 --  Drama.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-08</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-08</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6223:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6223:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE COMICALL HISTORIE OF Alphonsus, <hi>King of</hi> Aragon. As it hath bene sundrie times Acted. Made by <hi>R. G.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON Brinted by Thomas Creede. 1599.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:6223:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6223:2"/>The Comicall Historie of <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> King of <hi>Arragon.</hi>
         </head>
         <div n="1" type="act">
            <head>Act. I.</head>
            <stage>After you haue sounded thrise, let <hi>Venus</hi> be let downe from the top of the Stage, and when she is downe, say.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>POets are scarce when Goddesses themselues</l>
               <l>Are forst to leaue their high and stately seates</l>
               <l>Placed on the top of high <hi>Olympus</hi> Mount,</l>
               <l>To seeke them out, to pen their Champions praise.</l>
               <l>The time hath bene when <hi>Homers</hi> sugred Muse,</l>
               <l>Did make each Eccho to repeate his verse,</l>
               <l>That euery coward that durst crack a speare,</l>
               <l>And Tilt and Turney for his Ladies sake,</l>
               <l>Was painted out in colours of such price</l>
               <l>As might become the proudest Potentate.</l>
               <l>But now a dayes so yrksome Idels slights,</l>
               <l>And cursed charmes haue witch'd each students mind,</l>
               <l>That death it is to any of them all,</l>
               <l>If that their hands to penning you do call:</l>
               <l>Oh <hi>Virgil, Virgil,</hi> wert thou now aliue,</l>
               <l>Whose painfull pen in stout <hi>Augustus</hi> dayes,</l>
               <l>Did daigne to let the base and silly flea</l>
               <l>To scape away without thy praise of her.</l>
               <l>I do not doubt but long or ere this time,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alphonsus</hi> fame vnto the heauen's should clime:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alphonsus</hi> fame that man of <hi>Ioue</hi> his seed,</l>
               <l>Sprung from the loines of the immortall Gods,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:3"/>
Whose sire although he habit on the earth,</l>
               <l>May claime a portion in the fierie Pole,</l>
               <l>As well as any one what ere he be.</l>
               <l>But setting by <hi>Alphonsus</hi> power diuine,</l>
               <l>What man aliue or now amongst the ghoasts</l>
               <l>Could counteruaile his courage and his strength?</l>
               <l>But thou art dead, yea <hi>Virgil</hi> thou art gon:</l>
               <l>And all his acts drownd in obliuion.</l>
               <l>And all his acts drownd in obliuion?</l>
               <l>No <hi>Venus</hi> no, though Poets proue vnkind,</l>
               <l>And loth to stand in penning of his deeds,</l>
               <l>Yet rather then they shall be cleane forgot,</l>
               <l>I which was wont to sollow <hi>Cupids</hi> games</l>
               <l>Will put in vre <hi>Mineruaes</hi> sacred Art,</l>
               <l>And this my hand which vsed for to pen</l>
               <l>The praise of loue, and <hi>Cupids</hi> peerles power,</l>
               <l>Will now begin to treat of bloudie <hi>Mars,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of doughtie deeds and valiant victories.</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>Enter <hi>Melpomine, Clio, Errato,</hi> with their sisters, playing all vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon sundrie Instruments, <hi>Calliope</hi> onely excepted, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming last, hangeth downe the head, and plaies not of her Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>But see whereas the stately <hi>Muses</hi> come,</l>
               <l>Whose harmony doth very far surpasse</l>
               <l>The heauenly musick of <hi>Appolloes</hi> pipe.</l>
               <l>But what meanes this <hi>Melpomine</hi> her selfe</l>
               <l>With all her sisters sound their Instruments,</l>
               <l>Onely excepted faire <hi>Calliope?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who comming last &amp; hanging downe her head,</l>
               <l>Doth plainly shewe by outward actions</l>
               <l>What secret sorrow doth torment her heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>Stands a side.</stage>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6223:3"/>
               <speaker>Mel.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Calliope</hi> thou which so oft didst crake,</l>
               <l>How that such clients clustred to thy Court</l>
               <l>By thick and threefold, as not any any one</l>
               <l>Of all thy sisters might compare with thee:</l>
               <l>Where be thy schollers now become I troe?</l>
               <l>Where are they vanisht in such suddain sort,</l>
               <l>That while as we do play vpon our strings,</l>
               <l>You stand still lazing, and haue nought to do?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clio.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Melpomine</hi> make you a why of that?</l>
               <l>I know full oft you haue Authors red,</l>
               <l>The higher tree the sooner is his fall,</l>
               <l>And they which first do flourish and beare sway,</l>
               <l>Vpon the sudden vanish cleane away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <l>Mocke on apace, my backe is broad enough</l>
               <l>To beare yout flouts as many as they be.</l>
               <l>That yeare is rare, that nere feeles winters stormes:</l>
               <l>That tree is fertile which nere wanteth frute.</l>
               <l>And that same Muse hath heaped well in store:</l>
               <l>Which neuer wanteth clients at her doore.</l>
               <l>But yet my sisters, when the surgent seas</l>
               <l>Haue ebde their fill, their waues do rise againe</l>
               <l>And fill their bankes vp to the very brimmes:</l>
               <l>And when my pipe hath easd her selfe a while,</l>
               <l>Such store of suters shall my seate frequent,</l>
               <l>That you shall see my schollers be not spent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Errato.</speaker>
               <l>Spent (quoth you) sister, then we were too blame</l>
               <l>If we should say your schollers all were spent:</l>
               <l>But pray now tell me when your painfull pen will rest enough?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mel.</speaker>
               <l>When husbandmen sheere hogs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Melpomine, Errato</hi> and the rest,</l>
               <l>From thickest shrubs dame <hi>Venus</hi> did espie</l>
               <l>The mortall hatred which you ioyntly beare</l>
               <l>Vnto your sister high <hi>Calliope.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What do you thinke if that the tree do bend,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:4"/>
It followes therefore that it needs must breakes</l>
               <l>And since her pipe a litle while doth rest,</l>
               <l>It neuer shall be able for to sound?</l>
               <l>Yes <hi>Muses</hi> yes, if that she wil vouchsafe</l>
               <l>To ente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tain Dame <hi>Venus</hi> in her schoole,</l>
               <l>And further me with her insti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tions,</l>
               <l>She shall haue schollers which wil daine to be</l>
               <l>In any other <hi>Muses</hi> companie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Calliope.</speaker>
               <l>Most sacred <hi>Venus</hi> do you doubt of that?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ope</hi> would thinke her three times blest,</l>
               <l>For to receiue a Goddes in her schoole,</l>
               <l>Especially so high an one as you,</l>
               <l>Which rules the earth, and guides the heauens too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <l>Then sound your pipes, and let vs bend our steps</l>
               <l>Vnto the top of high <hi>Pernassus</hi> hill,</l>
               <l>And there togither do our best deuoyr</l>
               <l>For to describe <hi>Alphonsus</hi> warlike fame:</l>
               <l>And in the maner of a Comedie,</l>
               <l>Set downe his noble valour presently.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Calli.</speaker>
               <l>As <hi>Venus</hi> wils, so bids <hi>Calliope.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Melpo.</speaker>
               <l>And as you bid your sisters do agree.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>Enter <hi>Clarinus</hi> the Father, and <hi>Alphonsus</hi> his sonne.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Carinus.</speaker>
               <l>My noble sonne, since first I did recount</l>
               <l>The noble acts your predecessors did</l>
               <l>In <hi>Aragon,</hi> against their war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ke foes,</l>
               <l>I neuer yet could see thee ioy at all,</l>
               <l>But hanging downe thy head as malcontent:</l>
               <l>Thy youthfull dayes in mourning haue bene spent.</l>
               <l>Tell me <hi>Alphonsus</hi> what might be the cause</l>
               <l>That makes thee thus to pine away with care?</l>
               <l>Hath old <hi>Carinus</hi> done thee any offence</l>
               <l>In reckning vp these stories vnto thee?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:4"/>
What nere a word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mme? <hi>Alphonsus</hi> speake,</l>
               <l>Vnles your Fathers fatall day you seeke.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>Although deare father I haue often vowde</l>
               <l>Nere to vnfold the secrets of my heart</l>
               <l>To any man or woman, who some ere</l>
               <l>Dwels vnderneath the circle of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>kie:</l>
               <l>Yet do your words so coniure me deare sire,</l>
               <l>That needs I must fulfil that you require.</l>
               <l>Then so it is, amongst the famous tales</l>
               <l>Which you rehearst done by our sires in warre,</l>
               <l>When as you came vnto your fathers daies,</l>
               <l>With sobbing notes, with sighs &amp; blubbring teares,</l>
               <l>And much ado, at length you thus began.</l>
               <l>Next to <hi>Alphonsus</hi> should my father come,</l>
               <l>For to possesse the Diadem by right</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Aragon,</hi> but that the wicked wretch</l>
               <l>His yonger brother, with aspiring mind,</l>
               <l>By secret treason robd him of his life,</l>
               <l>And me his sonne, of that which was my due.</l>
               <l>These words my sire, did so torment my mind,</l>
               <l>As had I bene with <hi>Ixion</hi> in hell,</l>
               <l>The rauening bird could neuer plague me worse:</l>
               <l>For euer since my mind hath troubled bene</l>
               <l>Which way I might reuenge this traiterous fact,</l>
               <l>And that recouer which is ours by right.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>Ah my <hi>Alphònsus</hi> neuer thinke on that,</l>
               <l>In vaine it is to sttiue against the streame,</l>
               <l>The Crowne is lost, and now in hucksters hands,</l>
               <l>And all our hope is cast <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>to the dust:</l>
               <l>Bridle these thoughts, and learne the same of me,</l>
               <l>A quiet life doth passe an Emperie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>Yet noble father, ere <hi>Carinus</hi> brood</l>
               <l>Shall brooke his foe for to vsu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> his seate,</l>
               <l>Heele die the death with honour in the field,</l>
               <l>And so his life and sorrowes briefly end.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:5"/>
But did I know my froward fate were such,</l>
               <l>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> I should faile in this my iust attempt:</l>
               <l>This sword deare father should the Author be,</l>
               <l>To make an end of this my Tragedie.</l>
               <l>Therefore sweet sire, remaine you here a while,</l>
               <l>And let me walke my Fortune for to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e:</l>
               <l>I do not doubt but ere the time be long,</l>
               <l>Ile quite his cost, or else my selfe will die.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>My noble sonne, since that thy mind is such</l>
               <l>For to reuenge thy fathers foule abuse,</l>
               <l>As that my words may not a whit preuaile</l>
               <l>To stay thy iourney, go with happie fate,</l>
               <l>And soone returne vnto thy fathers Cell,</l>
               <l>With such a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ne as <hi>Iulius C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ar</hi> came</l>
               <l>To noble <hi>Rome,</hi> when as he had atchiu'd</l>
               <l>The mightie Monarch of the triple wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ld,</l>
               <l>Meane time <hi>Carinus</hi> in this sillie groue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Will spend his daies with praier and horizons,</l>
               <l>To mightie <hi>Ioue,</hi> to further thine intent:</l>
               <l>Farewell deare sonne <hi>Alphonsu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> fare you well.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>And is he gone? then hie <hi>Alphonsus</hi> hie,</l>
               <l>To trie thy fortune where thy fates do call:</l>
               <l>A noble mind disdaines to hide his head,</l>
               <l>And let his foes triumph in his ouerthrow.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Albinius.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Alphonsus</hi> mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> as though thou goest out, <hi>Albi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Albi.</speaker>
               <l>What loytring follow haue we spied here?</l>
               <l>Presume not vill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> her for to go,</l>
               <l>Vnles you do at length the same <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>pent.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Alphonsus</hi> comes towards <hi>Albinius.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>Villain sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t thou, nay vilain in thy throat:</l>
               <l>What knowst <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ou skip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ck whom thou vilain calst?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Albi.</speaker>
               <l>A common vassall I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> villaine call.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6223:5"/>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>That shalt thou soone approoue perswade thy self,</l>
               <l>Or else ile die, or thou shalt die for me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Albi.</speaker>
               <l>What do I dreame, or do my dazeling eies</l>
               <l>Deceiue me? Ist <hi>Alpho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>sus</hi> that I see?</l>
               <l>Doth now <hi>Medea</hi> vse her wonted charmes</l>
               <l>For to delude Albinius fantasie?</l>
               <l>Or doth black Pluto king of darke <hi>Auerne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Seeke to flout m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> with his cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rfait?</l>
               <l>His bodie like to Alphonsus framed is:</l>
               <l>His face resembles much Alphonsus hewe:</l>
               <l>His noble mind declares him for no les.</l>
               <l>Tis he indeed, wo worth Albinius,</l>
               <l>Whose babling tong hath causde his owne annoy.</l>
               <l>Why doth not <hi>Ioue</hi> send from the glittring skies</l>
               <l>His Thunder bolts to chastice this offence?</l>
               <l>Why doth dame <hi>Terra</hi> cease with greedie iawes</l>
               <l>To swallow vp Albinius presently?</l>
               <l>What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ll I flie and hide my trayterous head,</l>
               <l>From <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>out Alphonsus whom I so misusde?</l>
               <l>Or shall I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eld Tush yeelding is in vaine:</l>
               <l>Nor can I flie, but he will follow me.</l>
               <l>Then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ast thy selfe downe at his graces seete,</l>
               <l>Confesse thy fault, and readie make thy brest,</l>
               <l>To entertaine thy well de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ued death.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Albinius</hi> knee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ne.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <l>What newes my friend? why are you so blanke</l>
               <l>That earst before did vau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> it to the skies?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Albi.</speaker>
               <l>Pardon deare Lord, Albinius pardon craues</l>
               <l>For this offence, which by the heaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> I vowe,</l>
               <l>Vnwittingly I did vnto your grace.</l>
               <l>For had I knowne Alphonsus had bene here,</l>
               <l>Ere that my tongue had spoke so trayterously,</l>
               <l>This hand should make my very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>uie to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>Rise vp my f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>end, thy pardon soon is go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>But prithi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ll me what the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>auie might be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>That in such s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t thou e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>st <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>?</l>
               <stage>Albinius <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ses vp.</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:6"/>
Haue compassed the circle of the skie,</l>
               <l>Ile clog their toongs, since nothing else will serue</l>
               <l>To keep those vilde and threatning speeches in.</l>
               <l>Farwell Belinus, loke thou to thy selfe:</l>
               <l>Alphonsus meanes to haue thy Crowne ere night.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Exit</hi> Alphonsus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beli.</speaker>
               <l>What is he gone, the diuel break his necke,</l>
               <l>The fiends of hell torment his traiterous corpes:</l>
               <l>Is this the quittance of Belinus grace,</l>
               <l>Which he did shewe vnto that thankles wre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ch?</l>
               <l>That runnagate, that rachell, yea that theefe,</l>
               <l>For well I wot he hath robd me of a Crowne.</l>
               <l>If euer he had sprung from gentle blood,</l>
               <l>He would not thus misuse his fauourer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Albi.</speaker>
               <l>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nnag, that rachel, yea that theef?</l>
               <l>Stay their sir King, your mouth runnes ouer much,</l>
               <l>It ill becomes the subiect for to vse</l>
               <l>Such trayterous termes against his soueraigne.</l>
               <l>Know thou Belinus, that Carinus sonne,</l>
               <l>Is neither rachel nor runnagate,</l>
               <l>But be thou sure, that ere the darksome night</l>
               <l>Do driue God <hi>Phaebus</hi> to his <hi>Thetis</hi> lap,</l>
               <l>Both thou and all the rest of this thy traine,</l>
               <l>Shall well repent the words which you haue saine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beli.</speaker>
               <l>What traiterous villain dost thou threaten me?</l>
               <l>Lay hold on him, and see he do not scape,</l>
               <l>Ile teach the slaue to know to whom he speakes.</l>
               <l>To thee I speake, and to thy fellowes all:</l>
               <l>And though as now you haue me in your power,</l>
               <l>Yet doubt I not but that in litle space,</l>
               <l>These eyes shall see thy treason recompenst:</l>
               <l>And then I meane to vaunt of our victorie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beli.</speaker>
               <l>Nay proud Albinius, neuer build on that,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:6"/>
For though the Gods do chance for to appoyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Alphonsus victor of <hi>Belinus</hi> land,</l>
               <l>Yet shalt thou neuer liue to see that day,</l>
               <l>And therefore <hi>Fabius</hi> stand not lingring,</l>
               <l>But presently slash off his trayterous head.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Albi.</speaker>
               <l>Slash off his head, as though Albinius head</l>
               <l>Were then so easie to be slashed off.</l>
               <l>In faith sir no, when you are gone and dead,</l>
               <l>I hope to flourish like the pleasant spring.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beli.</speaker>
               <l>Why how now <hi>Fabius,</hi> what do you stand in doubt,</l>
               <l>To do the deed? what feare you? who dares seek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>For to reuenge his death on thee againe,</l>
               <l>Since that <hi>Belinus</hi> did commaund it so?</l>
               <l>Or are you waxt so daintie, that you dare</l>
               <l>Not vse your sword for staining of your hands?</l>
               <l>If it be so, then let me see thy sword,</l>
               <l>And I will be his butcher for this time.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Fabius</hi> giue <hi>Belinus</hi> thy sword drawne, <hi>Belinus</hi> say as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</stage>
               <l>Now sir Albinius, are you of the minde</l>
               <l>That erst you were? what do you looke to see</l>
               <l>And triumph in Belinus ouerthrow?</l>
               <l>I hope the very sight of this my blade,</l>
               <l>Hath chaungde your minde into an other tune.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Albi.</speaker>
               <l>Not so Belin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s, I am constant still,</l>
               <l>My minde is like to the Abeston stone,</l>
               <l>Which if it once be heat in flames of fire,</l>
               <l>Deineth to becommen colde againe.</l>
               <l>Euen so am I, and shall be till I die,</l>
               <l>And though I should see Attropos appeare,</l>
               <l>With knife in hand, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o slit my threed in twaine,</l>
               <l>Yet nere <hi>Albinius</hi> should perswaded be,</l>
               <l>But that Belinus he should vanquisht see.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6223:7"/>
               <speaker>Beli.</speaker>
               <l>Nay then <hi>Albinius,</hi> since that words are vaine</l>
               <l>For to perswade you from this heresie:</l>
               <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> sword shall sure put you out of doubt.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Belinus</hi> offers to strike off <hi>Albinius</hi> head strike vp alarum, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Alphonsus</hi> and his men, flie <hi>Belinus</hi> and <hi>Fabius,</hi> follow <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> and <hi>Albinius.</hi> Enter <hi>Laelius, Milos,</hi> and his seruants.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Laeli.</speaker>
               <l>My noble Lords of <hi>Aragon,</hi> I know</l>
               <l>You wonder much what might the occasion be,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Laelius</hi> which earst did flie the field,</l>
               <l>Doth egge you forwards now vnto the warres,</l>
               <l>But when you heare my reason, out of doubt</l>
               <l>Yowle be content with this my rash attempt.</l>
               <l>When first our King, <hi>Flaminius</hi> I do meane,</l>
               <l>Did set vpon the Neapolitans,</l>
               <l>The worst of you did know and plainly see,</l>
               <l>How farre they were vnable to withstand</l>
               <l>The mightie forces of our royall Campe,</l>
               <l>Vntill such time as froward fates we thought,</l>
               <l>Although the fates ordaind it for our gaine,</l>
               <l>Did send a straunger stout, whose sturdie blowes</l>
               <l>And force alone, did cause our ouerthrow.</l>
               <l>But to our purpose, this same martiall knight</l>
               <l>Did hap to hit vpon <hi>Flaminius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And lent our King then such a friendly blow,</l>
               <l>As that his gasping ghost to Lymbo went:</l>
               <l>Which when I sawe, and seeking to reuenge,</l>
               <l>My noble Lords, did hap on such a prize:</l>
               <l>As neuer King nor <hi>Keisar</hi> got the like.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laelius,</hi> of force we must confesse to thee,</l>
               <l>We wondred all, when as you did perswade</l>
               <l>Vs to returne vnto the warres againe,</l>
               <l>But since our maruell is increased much</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:7"/>
By these your words, which sound of happinesse,</l>
               <l>Therefore good Laelius make no tarrying,</l>
               <l>But soone vnfolde thy happie chaunce to vs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lae.</speaker>
               <l>Then friends and fellow souldiers, hark to me.</l>
               <l>When Laelius thought for to reuenge his king,</l>
               <l>On that same knight, in steed of mortall foe,</l>
               <l>I found him for to be our cheefest friend.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
               <l>Our cheefest friend, I hardly can beleeue,</l>
               <l>That he which made such bloudie massacres</l>
               <l>Of stout Italians, can in any poynt</l>
               <l>Beare friendship to the countrey or the King.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lae.</speaker>
               <l>As for your king <hi>Miles,</hi> I hold with you,</l>
               <l>He beare no friendship to <hi>Flaminius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But hated him as bloudie Attropos,</l>
               <l>But for your countrey, Laelius doth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>owe,</l>
               <l>He loues as well as any other land:</l>
               <l>Yea sure he loues it best of all the world:</l>
               <l>And for because, you shall not thinke that I</l>
               <l>Do say the same without a reason why,</l>
               <l>Know that the knight <hi>Alphonsus</hi> hath to name,</l>
               <l>Both sonne and heire to olde Carinus, whom</l>
               <l>Flaminius sire bereaued of his Crowne:</l>
               <l>Who did not seeke the ruine of our host,</l>
               <l>For any enuie he did beare to vs,</l>
               <l>But to reuenge him on his mortall foe,</l>
               <l>Which by the helpe of high celestiall <hi>Ioue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He hath atchieu'd with honour in the field.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
               <l>Alphonsus man, ile nere perswaded be,</l>
               <l>That ere Alphonsus may suruiue againe,</l>
               <l>Who with <hi>Carinus</hi> many yeares agoe,</l>
               <l>Was said to wander in the stigian fieldes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Laeli.</speaker>
               <l>Truth Noble Miles, these mine eares haue heard,</l>
               <l>For certaintie reported vnto me,</l>
               <l>That olde Carinus with his peerlesse sonne,</l>
               <l>Had felt the sharpnesse of the sisters sheeres,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:8"/>
And had I not of late <hi>Alphonsus</hi> seene</l>
               <l>In good estate, though all the world should say</l>
               <l>He is aliue, I would not credit them:</l>
               <l>But fellow souldiers wend you backe with me,</l>
               <l>And let vs lurke within the secret shade,</l>
               <l>Which he himselfe appointed vnto vs:</l>
               <l>And if you find my words to be vntroth,</l>
               <l>Then let me die to recompence the wrong.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Strike vp alarum, Enter <hi>Albinius</hi> with his sword drawne, and say.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Albi.</speaker>
               <l>Laelius make haste, souldiers of <hi>Aragon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Set lingring by, and come and helpe your King.</l>
               <l>I meane <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> who whilest that he did</l>
               <l>Pursue <hi>Belinus</hi> at the very heeles,</l>
               <l>Was suddenly enuironed about,</l>
               <l>With all the troupes of mightie <hi>Millain</hi> land.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
               <l>What newes is this, and is it very so?</l>
               <l>Is our <hi>Alphonsus</hi> yet in humane state,</l>
               <l>Whom all the world did iudge for to be dead.</l>
               <l>Yet can I scarce giue credit to the same.</l>
               <l>Giue credit, yes, and since the Millain Duke,</l>
               <l>Hath broke his league of friendship, be he sure,</l>
               <l>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e Cynthia, the shining lampe of night,</l>
               <l>Doth scale the heauens with her horned head,</l>
               <l>Both he and his shall very plainly see,</l>
               <l>The league is burst, that caused long the glee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</speaker>
               <l>And could the traytor harbor in his brest</l>
               <l>Such mortall treason gainst his soueraigne,</l>
               <l>As when he should with fire and sword defend</l>
               <l>Him from his foes, he seekes his ouerthrow?</l>
               <l>March on my friends, I nere shall ioy at all,</l>
               <l>Vntill I see that bloudie traytors fall.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>Strike vp alar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, flie <hi>Belinus,</hi> follow <hi>Laelius:</hi> flie <hi>Fabius,</hi> foll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Albinius:</hi> flie the Duke of <hi>Millaine,</hi> follow <hi>Miles.</hi>
            </stage>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:6223:8"/>
            <head>Act. 3.</head>
            <stage>Strike vp alarum, Enter <hi>Venus.</hi>
            </stage>
            <lg>
               <l>NO sooner did <hi>Alphonsus</hi> with his troupe,</l>
               <l>Set on the souldiers of <hi>Belinus</hi> band,</l>
               <l>But that the furie of his sturdie blowes,</l>
               <l>Did strike such terror to their daunted mindes,</l>
               <l>That glad was he which could escape away,</l>
               <l>With life and limme, forth of that bloudie fray.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Belinus</hi> flies vnto the Turkish soyle,</l>
               <l>To craue the aide of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> their King:</l>
               <l>Vnto the which he willingly did consent,</l>
               <l>And sends <hi>Belinus</hi> with two other Kings,</l>
               <l>To know god <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ets</hi> pleasure in the same:</l>
               <l>Meane time the Empresse by <hi>Medeas</hi> helpe,</l>
               <l>Did vse such charmes, that <hi>Amuracke</hi> did see</l>
               <l>In soundest sleepe, what afterward should hap:</l>
               <l>How <hi>Amuracke</hi> did recompence her paine,</l>
               <l>With mickle more, this Act shall shew you plaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>Exit <hi>Venus.</hi>
            </stage>
            <stage>Enter one, carrying two Crownes vpon a Crest, <hi>Alphonsus, Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Laelius</hi> and <hi>Miles, with their souldiers.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <l>Welcome braue youthes of <hi>Aragon</hi> to me.</l>
               <l>Yea welcome <hi>Miles, Lali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> and the rest,</l>
               <l>Whose prowesse alone hath bene the onely cause,</l>
               <l>That we like victors haue subdued our foes.</l>
               <l>Lord what a pleasure was it to my minde,</l>
               <l>To see <hi>Bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> which not long before,</l>
               <l>Did with his threatnings terrefie the Gods,</l>
               <l>Now scudde apace, from warlike <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>lius</hi> blowes:</l>
               <l>The Duke of <hi>Millaine</hi> he increast our sport,</l>
               <l>When doubting that his force was ouerweake,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:9"/>
For to withstand Miles, thy sturdie arme</l>
               <l>Did giue more credence to his frisking skippes</l>
               <l>Then to the sharpnesse of his cutting blade,</l>
               <l>What <hi>Fabius</hi> did to pleasure vs withall,</l>
               <l>Albinius knowes as well as I my selfe:</l>
               <l>For well I wot, if that thy tyred steed</l>
               <l>Had bene as fresh and swift in foote as his,</l>
               <l>He should haue felt, yea knowne for certaintie,</l>
               <l>To checke <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> did deserue to die.</l>
               <l>Breefly my friends and fellow peeres in armes,</l>
               <l>The worst of you doo deserue such mickle praise,</l>
               <l>As that my tongue denies for to set forth</l>
               <l>The demie parcell of your valiant deeds,</l>
               <l>So that perforce, I must by dutie be</l>
               <l>Bound to you all, for this your curtesie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
               <l>Not so my Lord, for if our willing armes</l>
               <l>Haue pleasured you so much, as you do say,</l>
               <l>We haue done nought but that becommeth vs:</l>
               <l>For to defend our mightie soueraigne.</l>
               <l>As for my part, I count my labour small,</l>
               <l>Yea though it had bene twise as much againe,</l>
               <l>Since that Alphonsus doth accept thereof.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>Thankes worthie Miles, least all the world</l>
               <l>Should count Alphonsus thanklesse for to be,</l>
               <l>Laelius sit downe, and Miles sit by him,</l>
               <l>And that receiue, the which your swords haue wonne.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Sit downe</hi> Laelius <hi>and</hi> Miles.</stage>
               <l>First, for because thou Laelius in these broyles,</l>
               <l>By martiall might, didst proude <hi>Belinus</hi> chase,</l>
               <l>From troupe to troupe, from side to side about,</l>
               <l>And neuer ceast from this thy swift pursute,</l>
               <l>Vntill thou hadst obtaind his royall Crowne,</l>
               <l>Therefore I say, ile do thee nought but right,</l>
               <l>And giue thee that which thou well hast wonne.</l>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:9"/>
Set the Crowne on his head.</stage>
               <l>Here doth Alphonsus Crowne thee Laelius, King</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Naples</hi> Towne, with all dominions</l>
               <l>That earst belonged to our trayterous foe,</l>
               <l>That proud Belinus in his regiment.</l>
               <stage>Sound Trumpets and Drummes.</stage>
               <l>Miles, thy share the <hi>Millaine</hi> Dukedome is,</l>
               <l>For well I wot thy sword deseru'd no lesse.</l>
               <stage>Set the Crowne on his head.</stage>
               <l>The which Alphonsus frankly giueth thee,</l>
               <l>In presen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of his warlike men at armes.</l>
               <l>And if that any stomacke this my deed,</l>
               <l>Alphonsus can reuenge thy wrong with speed.</l>
               <stage>Sound Trumpets and Drummes.</stage>
               <l>Now to Albinius which in all my toyles</l>
               <l>I haue both faithfull, yea and friendly found:</l>
               <l>Since that the Gods and friendly Fates assigne</l>
               <l>This present time to me to recompence,</l>
               <l>The sundry pleasures thou hast done to me,</l>
               <l>Sit downe by them, and on thy faithfull head</l>
               <stage>Take the Crowne from thy owne head.</stage>
               <l>Receiue the Crowne of peerlesse <hi>Aragon.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Albi.</speaker>
               <l>Pardon deare Lord Albinius at this time,</l>
               <l>It ill becomes me for to weare a Crowne,</l>
               <l>When as my Lord is destitute himselfe:</l>
               <l>Why high Alphonsus, if I should receiue</l>
               <l>This Crowne of you, the which high <hi>Ioue</hi> forbid,</l>
               <l>Where would your selfe obtaine a Diadem?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Naples</hi> is gone, <hi>Millaine</hi> possessed is,</l>
               <l>And nought is left for you but <hi>Aragon.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>And nought is left for me but <hi>Aragon?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yes surely yes, my Fates haue so decreed,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Aragon</hi> should be too base a thing,</l>
               <l>For to obtaine Alphonsus for her King.</l>
               <l>What heare you not how that our scattered foes,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:10"/>
                  <hi>Belinus, Fabius,</hi> and the Millaine Duke,</l>
               <l>Are fled for succour to the Turkish Court?</l>
               <l>And thinke you not that <hi>Amurack</hi> their King,</l>
               <l>Will with the mightiest power of all his land,</l>
               <l>Seeke to reuenge <hi>Belinus</hi> ouerthrow?</l>
               <l>Then doubt I not but ere these broyles do end,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alphonsus</hi> shall possesse the Diadem</l>
               <l>That <hi>Amurack</hi> now weares vpon his head.</l>
               <l>Sit downe therefore and that receiue of mee:</l>
               <l>The which the Fates appointed vnto thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Albi.</speaker>
               <l>Thou king of heauen, which by thy power diuine,</l>
               <l>Dost see the secrets of each liuers heart,</l>
               <l>Beare record now with what vnwilling mind,</l>
               <l>I do receiue the Crowne of <hi>Aragon.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Albinius</hi> sit downe by <hi>Laelius &amp; Miles, Alphonsus</hi> set the Crowne on his head, and say.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>A rise <hi>Albinius</hi> King of <hi>Aragon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Crowned by me, who till my gasping ghost</l>
               <l>Do part asunder from my breathlesse corpes,</l>
               <l>Will be thy shield against all men aliue:</l>
               <l>That for thy kingdome any way do striue.</l>
               <stage>Sound Trumpets and Drummes.</stage>
               <l>Now since we haue in such an happie houre</l>
               <l>Confirmd three kings, come let vs march with speed</l>
               <l>Into the Citie, for to celebrate</l>
               <l>With mirth and ioy, this blisfull festiuall.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
            <stage>Enter <hi>Amurack</hi> the great Turke, <hi>Belinus, Fabius, Arcastus</hi> King of Moores. <hi>Claramount,</hi> King of <hi>Barbery. Baiazet</hi> a Lord, with their trai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>Welcome <hi>Belinus</hi> to thy cosens Court,</l>
               <l>Whose late arriuall in such posting pace,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:10"/>
Doth bring both ioy and sorrow to vs all:</l>
               <l>Sorrow because the Fates haue bene so false,</l>
               <l>To let <hi>Alphonsus</hi> driue thee from thy land:</l>
               <l>And ioy, since that now mightie <hi>Mahomet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hath giuen me cause to recompence at full,</l>
               <l>The sundry pleasures I receiu'd of thee.</l>
               <l>Therefore <hi>Belinus</hi> do but aske and haue:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Amurack</hi> doth grant what ere you craue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beli.</speaker>
               <l>Thou second sun which with thy glimsing beames</l>
               <l>Doest clarifie each corner of the earth,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Belinus</hi> comes not, as earst <hi>Mydas</hi> did,</l>
               <l>To mightie <hi>Bacchus,</hi> to desire of him,</l>
               <l>That what so ere at any time he toucht,</l>
               <l>Might turned be to gold incontinent.</l>
               <l>Nor do I come as <hi>Iuppiter</hi> did erst</l>
               <l>Vnto the Pallace of <hi>Amphitrion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For any fond or foule concupiscence,</l>
               <l>Which I do beare to <hi>Alcumenaes</hi> hew.</l>
               <l>But as poore <hi>Saturne,</hi> forst by mightie <hi>Ioue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To flie his Countrey, banisht and forlorne,</l>
               <l>Did craue the aide of <hi>Troos,</hi> King of <hi>Troy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So comes <hi>Belinus</hi> to high <hi>Amurack.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And if he can but once your aide obtaine,</l>
               <l>He turnes with speed to <hi>Naples</hi> backe againe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>My aide <hi>Belinus,</hi> do you doubt of that?</l>
               <l>If all the men at armes of <hi>Affrica,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Asia</hi> likewise, will sufficient be,</l>
               <l>To presse the pompe of that vsurping mate:</l>
               <l>Assure thy selfe, thy kingdome shalbe thine,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Mahomet</hi> say I vnto the same:</l>
               <l>For were I sure to vanquish all our foes,</l>
               <l>And find such spoiles in ransacking their Tents,</l>
               <l>As neuer any <hi>Keisar</hi> did obtaine,</l>
               <l>Yet would I not set foote forth of this land:</l>
               <l>If Mahomet our iourney did withstand.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6223:11"/>
               <speaker>Beli.</speaker>
               <l>Nor would Belinus for King <hi>Craesus</hi> trash,</l>
               <l>Wish Amurack to displease the Gods;</l>
               <l>In pleasuring me in such à <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ling toy.</l>
               <l>Then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Monarch, if it be thy will,</l>
               <l>Get the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> consents, and then the act fulfill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>You counsel well, therefore Belinus haste,</l>
               <l>And Claramount go beare him companie,</l>
               <l>With King Arcastus, to the Citie walles.</l>
               <l>Then bend with speed vnto the darksome groue,</l>
               <l>Where Mahomet this many a hundred yeare</l>
               <l>Hath prophesied vnto our auncesters,</l>
               <l>Tell to his Priests, that Amurack your King</l>
               <l>Is now selecting all his men at armes,</l>
               <l>To set vpon that proud Alphonsus troupe.</l>
               <l>The cause you know, and can enforme him well,</l>
               <l>That makes me take these bloudie broyles in hand:</l>
               <l>And say that I desire their sacred God,</l>
               <l>That Mahomet which ruleth all the skies,</l>
               <l>To send me word and that most speedely,</l>
               <l>Which of vs shall obtaine the victory.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt omnes, preter <hi>Baiazet</hi> and <hi>Amurack.</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>You Baiazet go poste away apace,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Siria, Scythia,</hi> and <hi>Albania,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>Babylon,</hi> with <hi>Mesopotamia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Asia, Armenia,</hi> and all other lands</l>
               <l>Which owe their homage to high Amurack.</l>
               <l>Charge all their Kings with expedition</l>
               <l>To gather vp the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>est men at armes</l>
               <l>Which now remaine in their dominions,</l>
               <l>And on the twentie day of the same month,</l>
               <l>To come and wait on Amurack their King,</l>
               <l>At his chiefe Citie <hi>Constantinople.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tell them moreouer, that who so doth faile,</l>
               <l>Nought else but death, from prison shall him baile.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit</hi> Baiazct.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:11"/>
Assoone as he is gone, sound musicke within.</stage>
               <l>What heauenly Musicke soundeth in my eare?</l>
               <l>Peace Amurack and hearken to the same.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Sound musicke, hearken <hi>Amurack,</hi> and fall a sleepe.</stage>
            <stage>Enter <hi>Medea, Fausta</hi> the Empresse, <hi>Iphigina</hi> her daughter.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Medea.</speaker>
               <l>Now haue our charmes fulfild our minds full well,</l>
               <l>High Amurack is lulled fast a sleepe,</l>
               <l>And doubt I not, but ere he wakes againe,</l>
               <l>You shall perceiue Medea did not gibe,</l>
               <l>When as she put this practise in your mind:</l>
               <l>Sit worthie Fausta at thy spowse his feete.</l>
               <stage>Fausta <hi>and</hi> Iphigina, <hi>sit downe at</hi> Amuracks <hi>feete.</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>Iphigina, sit thou on the other side:</l>
               <l>What ere you see be not agast thereat,</l>
               <l>But beare in mind what Amurack doth chat.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Medea</hi> do ceremonies belonging to coniuring, and say.</stage>
               <l>Thou which wert wont in Agamemnons dayes</l>
               <l>To vtter forth <hi>Apolloes</hi> Oracles</l>
               <l>At sacred <hi>Delphos, Calchas</hi> I do meane,</l>
               <l>I charge thee come, all lingring set aside,</l>
               <l>Vnles the pennance you thereof abide.</l>
               <l>I coniure thee by <hi>Plutoes</hi> loathsome lake,</l>
               <l>By all the hags which harbour in the same,</l>
               <l>By stinking <hi>Stix,</hi> and filthie <hi>Flegeton,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To come with speed, and truly to fulfill</l>
               <l>That which <hi>Medea</hi> to thee streight shall will.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:6223:12"/>
Rise <hi>Calehas</hi> vp in a white Cirples and a Cardinals Myter, and say.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <l>Thou wretched witch, when wilt thou make an end</l>
               <l>Of troubling vs with these thy cursed Charmes?</l>
               <l>What meanst thou thus to call me from my graue?</l>
               <l>Shall nere my ghost obtaine his quiet rest?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Me.</speaker>
               <l>Yes <hi>Calchas</hi> yes, your rest doth now approch</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Medea</hi> meanes to trouble thee no more,</l>
               <l>When as thou hast fulfild her mind this once.</l>
               <l>Go get thee hence to <hi>Pluto</hi> backe againe,</l>
               <l>And there enquire of the Destinies,</l>
               <l>How <hi>Amurack</hi> shall speed in these his warres:</l>
               <l>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>use their bookes, and marke what is decreed</l>
               <l>By <hi>Ioue</hi> himselfe, and all his fellow Gods:</l>
               <l>And when thou knowst the certaintie thereof,</l>
               <l>By fleshlesse visions shewe it presently</l>
               <l>To <hi>Amuracke,</hi> in paine of penaltie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <l>Forst by thy charme though with vnwilling minde:</l>
               <l>I hast to hell, the certaintie to finde.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Calchas</hi> sinke downe where you came vp.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Me.</speaker>
               <l>Now peerles Princes I must needs be gon,</l>
               <l>My hast<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> buns<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>esse calls me from this place.</l>
               <l>There resteth nought, but that you beare in minde,</l>
               <l>What <hi>Amuracke</hi> in this his fit doth say.</l>
               <l>For marke what dreaming madam he doth prate:</l>
               <l>Assure your selfe, that that shalbe his fate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>Though very loth to let thee so depart,</l>
               <l>Farewell <hi>Medea,</hi> easer of my hart.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit Medea.</stage>
            <stage>Sound Instruments within, <hi>Amurack</hi> as it were in a dreame, say.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>What <hi>Amurack</hi> doest thou begin to nod?</l>
               <l>Is this the care that thou hast of thy warres?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:12"/>
As when thou shouldst be prancing of thy steed,</l>
               <l>To egge thy souldiers forward in thy warres:</l>
               <l>Thou sittest moping by the fire side?</l>
               <l>See where thy Viceroies grouell on the ground.</l>
               <l>Looke where <hi>Belinus</hi> breatheth forth his ghost.</l>
               <l>Behold by millions how thy men do fall</l>
               <l>Before <hi>Alphonsus</hi> like to sillie sheepe.</l>
               <l>And canst thou stand still lazing in this sort?</l>
               <l>No proud <hi>Alphonsus, Amurack</hi> doth flie</l>
               <l>To quaile thy courage, and that speedilie.</l>
               <stage>Sound Instruments a while within, and then <hi>Amuracke</hi> say.</stage>
               <l>And doest thou think thou proud iniurious God,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mahound</hi> I meane since thy vaine prophesies</l>
               <l>Led <hi>Amurack</hi> into this dolefull case,</l>
               <l>To haue his Princely feete in irons clapt,</l>
               <l>Which erst the proudest kings were fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>st to kisse,</l>
               <l>That thou shalt scape vnpunisht for the same?</l>
               <l>No no, assoone as by the helpe of <hi>Ioue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I scape this bondage, downe go all thy groues.</l>
               <l>Thy alters tumble round about the streets.</l>
               <l>And whereas erst we sacrifisde to thee:</l>
               <l>Now all the Turks thy mortall foes shall bee.</l>
               <stage>Sound Instruments a while within, <hi>Amuracke</hi> say.</stage>
               <l>Behold the Iemme and Iewel of mine age,</l>
               <l>See where she comes, whose heauenly maiestie</l>
               <l>Doth far surpasse the braue and gorgeous pace</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Cytherea</hi> daughter vnto <hi>Ioue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did put in vre when as she had obtaind</l>
               <l>The golden Apple at the shepheards hands.</l>
               <l>See worth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Fausta</hi> where <hi>Alphonsus</hi> stands,</l>
               <l>Whose valiant courage could not daunted be,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:13"/>
Brid'ed my thoughts, and pressed downe my rage,</l>
               <l>In recompence of which my good intent,</l>
               <l>I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ue receiu'd this wofull bamshment.</l>
               <l>Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>l said I? nay happie I did meane,</l>
               <l>If that be happie, which doth set one free:</l>
               <l>For by this meanes, I do not doubt ere long,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Fausta</hi> shall with ease, reuenge her wrong.</l>
               <l>Come daughter come, my minde fore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lleth me:</l>
               <l>That <hi>Amuracke</hi> shall soone requited be.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Make as though you were a going out, <hi>Medea</hi> meete her and say.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Me.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fausta,</hi> what meanes this sudden flight of yours?</l>
               <l>Why do you leaue your husbands princely Court,</l>
               <l>And all alone passe through these thickest groues,</l>
               <l>More fit to harbour brutish sauadge beasts,</l>
               <l>Then to receiue so high a Queene as you?</l>
               <l>Although your credit would not stay your steps,</l>
               <l>From bending them into these daikish dennes,</l>
               <l>Yet should the daunger which is imminent,</l>
               <l>To euery one which passeth by these pathes,</l>
               <l>Keepe you at home with fay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Iphigina.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What fool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h toy hath tickled you to this?</l>
               <l>I greatly feare some hap hath hit amis.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>No toy <hi>Medea,</hi> tickl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>Faustaes</hi> head,</l>
               <l>Nor foolish fancie ledde me to these grou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s,</l>
               <l>But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nest businesse egges my tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>'ing steps,</l>
               <l>To passe all dangers what so ere they be.</l>
               <l>I banisht am <hi>Medea,</hi> I which erst</l>
               <l>Was Empresse ouer all the triple world,</l>
               <l>Am banisht now from pallace and from pompe,</l>
               <l>But if the gods be fauou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ers to me,</l>
               <l>Ere twentie dayes, I will reuenged be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Me.</speaker>
               <l>I thought as much, when first from thickest leaues,</l>
               <l>I saw you trudging in such posting pace.</l>
               <l>But to the purpose, what may be the cause,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:13"/>
Of this strnnge and sudden banishment?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>The cause aske you, a simple cause god wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <l>Twas neither treason, nor yet felonie,</l>
               <l>But for because I blamde his foolishnes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Me.</speaker>
               <l>I heare you say so, but I greatly feare,</l>
               <l>Ere that your tale be brought vnto an end,</l>
               <l>Youle proue your selfe the author of the same:</l>
               <l>But pray be briefe, what follie did your spowse?</l>
               <l>And how will you reuenge your wrong on him?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>What follie quoth you? such as neuer yet</l>
               <l>Was heard or seene, since <hi>Phoebus</hi> first gan shine,</l>
               <l>You know how he was gathering in all haste,</l>
               <l>His men at armes, to set vpon the troupe</l>
               <l>Of proude <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> yea you well do know,</l>
               <l>How you and I did do the best we could,</l>
               <l>To make him shew vs in his drowsie dreame,</l>
               <l>What afterward should happen in his warres:</l>
               <l>Much talke he had, which now I haue forgot.</l>
               <l>But at the length, this surely was decreed,</l>
               <l>How that <hi>Alphonsus</hi> and <hi>Iphigina</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Should be conioynd in <hi>Iunoes</hi> sacred rites,</l>
               <l>Which when I heard, as one that did despise,</l>
               <l>That such a traytor should be sonne to me,</l>
               <l>I did rebuke my husband <hi>Amuracke.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And since my words could take no better place,</l>
               <l>My sword with helpe of all <hi>Amazones,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall make him soone repent his foolishnes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Me.</speaker>
               <l>This is the cause then of your banishment,</l>
               <l>And now you goe vnto <hi>Amazone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To gather all your may dens in array,</l>
               <l>To set vpon the migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ie <hi>Amuracke?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh foolish Queene, what meant you by this talke?</l>
               <l>Those pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ing speeches haue vndone you all.</l>
               <l>Do you disdaine to haue that migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ie Prince,</l>
               <l>I meane <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> counted for your sonne?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:14"/>
I tell you <hi>Fausta,</hi> he is borne to be,</l>
               <l>The ruler of a mightie Monarchie:</l>
               <l>I must confesse the powers of <hi>Amuracke</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Be great, his confines stretch both far and neare,</l>
               <l>Yet are they not the third part of the lands,</l>
               <l>Which shall be ruled by <hi>Alphonsus</hi> hands,</l>
               <l>And yet you daine to call him sonne in law:</l>
               <l>But when you see his sharpe and cutting sword</l>
               <l>Piercing the heart of this your gallant gyrle,</l>
               <l>Youle curse the houre wherein you did denay,</l>
               <l>To ioyne <hi>Alphonsus</hi> with <hi>Iphigina.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>The gods forbid, that ere it happen so.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Me.</speaker>
               <l>Nay neuer pray, for it must happen so.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>And is there then no remedie for it?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Me.</speaker>
               <l>No none but one, &amp; that you haue forsworn,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>As though an oath can bridle so my minde,</l>
               <l>As that I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re not breake a thousand oathes,</l>
               <l>For to eschew the danger imminent.</l>
               <l>Speake good Medea, tell that way to me,</l>
               <l>And I will do it, what so ere it be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Me.</speaker>
               <l>Then as already you haue well decreed,</l>
               <l>Packe to your countrey, and in readinesse,</l>
               <l>Select the armie of <hi>Amazones,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When you haue done, march with your female troupe</l>
               <l>To <hi>Naples</hi> Towne, to succour <hi>Amuracke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And so by marriage of <hi>Iphigina,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You soone shall driue the danger cleane away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iphigi.</speaker>
               <l>So shall we soone eschew <hi>Caribdis</hi> lake,</l>
               <l>And headlong fall to <hi>Syllaes</hi> greedie gulph,</l>
               <l>I vowd before, and now do vow againe:</l>
               <l>Before I wedde <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> Ile be slaine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Me.</speaker>
               <l>In vaine it is, to striue against the streame,</l>
               <l>Fates must be followed, and the gods decree</l>
               <l>Must needs take place in euery kinde of cause.</l>
               <l>Therfore faire maide, bridle these brutish thoughts,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:14"/>
And learne to follow what the fates assigne,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Saturne</hi> heard that <hi>Iuppiter</hi> his sonne</l>
               <l>Should driue him headlong from his heauenly seat,</l>
               <l>Downe to the bottome of the darke <hi>Auarne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He did command his mother presently,</l>
               <l>To do to death, the young and guiltlesse childe:</l>
               <l>But what of that, the mother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oathd in heart,</l>
               <l>For to commit so vile a massacre.</l>
               <l>Yea <hi>Ioue</hi> did liue, and as the fates did say,</l>
               <l>From heauenly seate, draue <hi>Saturne</hi> cleane away.</l>
               <l>What did auaile the Castle all of Steele,</l>
               <l>The which <hi>Acrisius</hi> caused to be made,</l>
               <l>To keepe his daughter <hi>Danae</hi> clogged in?</l>
               <l>She was with childe for all her Castles force,</l>
               <l>And by that child, <hi>Acrisius</hi> her sire,</l>
               <l>Was after slaine, so did the fates require.</l>
               <l>A thousand examples, I could bring hereof.</l>
               <l>But Marble stones needs no colouring,</l>
               <l>And that which euery one doth know for truth,</l>
               <l>Needs no examples to confirme the same.</l>
               <l>That which the fates appoint must happen so,</l>
               <l>Though heauenly <hi>Ioue,</hi> and all the Gods say no.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iphigina,</hi> she sayth nought but truth,</l>
               <l>Fates must be followed in their iust decrees:</l>
               <l>And therefore setting all delayes aside,</l>
               <l>Come let vs wend vnto <hi>Amazone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And gather vp our forces out of hand.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iphi.</speaker>
               <l>Since <hi>Fausta</hi> wils, and fates do so command,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iphigina</hi> will neuer it withstand.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="act">
            <head>Act. 3.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Venus.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>THus haue you seene, how <hi>Amuracke</hi> himselfe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fausta</hi> his wife, and euery other King,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:15"/>
Which holds their seepters at the Turke his hands,</l>
               <l>Are now in armes, entending to destroy</l>
               <l>And bring to nought, the Prince of <hi>Aragon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Charmes haue bene vsde by wise <hi>Medeas</hi> art,</l>
               <l>To know before what afterward shall hap,</l>
               <l>And King <hi>Belinus</hi> with high <hi>Claramount,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ioynd to <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> which with Princely pompe,</l>
               <l>Doth rule and gouerne all the warlike Moores,</l>
               <l>Are sent as Legats to god <hi>Mahomet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To know his counsell in these high affaires.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mahound</hi> proupk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> by <hi>Amurackes</hi> discourse,</l>
               <l>Which as you heard, he in his dreame did vse,</l>
               <l>Denies to play the Prophet any more,</l>
               <l>But by the long in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>atie of his Priests,</l>
               <l>He prophesies in such a craftie sort,</l>
               <l>As that the hearers needs must laugh for sport.</l>
               <l>Yet poore <hi>Belinus</hi> with his fellow Kings,</l>
               <l>Did giue such credence to that forged tale,</l>
               <l>As that they lost their dearest liues thereby,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Amuracke</hi> became a prisoner</l>
               <l>Vnto <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> as straight shall appeare.</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>
               <hi>Exit</hi> Venus.</stage>
            <stage>Let there be a brazen Head set in the middle of the place behind the Stage, out of the which, cast flames of fire, drums rumble within, Enter two Priests.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Pr.</speaker>
               <l>My fellow Priests of <hi>Mahounds</hi> holy house,</l>
               <l>What can you iudge of these strange miracles,</l>
               <l>Which daily happen in this sacred seate?</l>
               <stage>Drums rumble within.</stage>
               <l>Harke what a rumbling ratleth in our cares.</l>
               <stage>Cast flames of fire forth of the brazen Head.</stage>
               <l>See flakes of fire proceeding from the mouth</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:15"/>
Of <hi>Mahomet</hi> that God of peereles power.</l>
               <l>Nor can I tell with all the wit I haue,</l>
               <l>What <hi>Mahomet</hi> by these his signes doth craue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Pr.</speaker>
               <l>Thrise ten times <hi>Phoebus</hi> with his golden beames,</l>
               <l>Hath compassed the circle of the skie,</l>
               <l>Thrise ten times <hi>Ceres,</hi> hath her workemen hir'd,</l>
               <l>And fild her barnes with frutefull crops of corne,</l>
               <l>Since first in Priesthood I did lead my life:</l>
               <l>Yet in this time I neuer heard before,</l>
               <l>Such feareful sounds, nor saw such wondrous sights,</l>
               <l>Nor can I tell, with all the wit I haue,</l>
               <l>What <hi>Mahomet</hi> by these his signes doth craue.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Speake out of the brazen Head.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
               <l>You cannot tell, nor will you seeke to know,</l>
               <l>Oh peruerse Priest, how carelesse are you waxt?</l>
               <l>As when my foes approach vnto my gates,</l>
               <l>You stand still talking of I cannot tell:</l>
               <l>Go packe you hence, and meete the Turkish kings,</l>
               <l>Which now are drawing to my Temple ward:</l>
               <l>Tell them from me, God <hi>Mahomet</hi> is dispos'd</l>
               <l>To prophesie no more to <hi>Amuracke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since that his tongue is waxen now so free,</l>
               <l>As that it needs-must chat and raile at me.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Kneele downe both.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Pr.</speaker>
               <l>Oh <hi>Mahomet,</hi> if all the solemne prayers</l>
               <l>Which from our childhood we haue offered th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Can make thee call this sentence backe againe,</l>
               <l>Bring not thy Priest into this dangerous state:</l>
               <l>For when the Turke doth heare of this repulse,</l>
               <l>We shall be sure to die the death therefore.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
               <l>Thou sayest truth, go call the Princes in,</l>
               <l>Ile prophesie vnto them for this once,</l>
               <l>But in such wise, as they shall neither boast,</l>
               <l>Nor you be hurt in any kinde of wise.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:6223:16"/>
Enter <hi>Belinus, Claramont, Arcastus,</hi> go both the Priests to meet him: the first say.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Pr.</speaker>
               <l>You Kings of <hi>Turkie, Mahomet</hi> our God,</l>
               <l>By sacred science, hauing notice that</l>
               <l>You were sent Legats from high <hi>Amuracke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vnto this place, commaunded vs his Priests,</l>
               <l>That we should cause you make as mickle speed,</l>
               <l>As well you might, to heare for certaintie,</l>
               <l>Of that shall happen to your King and ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beli.</speaker>
               <l>For that intent we came into this place,</l>
               <l>And sithens that, the mightie <hi>Mahomet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is now at leisure for to tell the same,</l>
               <l>Let vs make haste and take time while we may:</l>
               <l>For mickle daunger hapneth through delay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Pri.</speaker>
               <l>Truth worthy king, and therfore you your selfe,</l>
               <l>With your companions, kneele before this place,</l>
               <l>And listen well what <hi>Mahomet</hi> doth say.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Kneele all downe before the brasen Head.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beli.</speaker>
               <l>As you do will, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oyntly will obey.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
               <l>Princes of <hi>Turkie,</hi> and Embassadors</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Amuracke,</hi> to mightie <hi>Mahomet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I needs must muse, that you which e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>st haue bene</l>
               <l>The readiest souldiers of the triple world,</l>
               <l>Are now become so slacke in your affaires,</l>
               <l>As when you should with bloudie blade in hand,</l>
               <l>Be hacking he mes in thickest of your foes,</l>
               <l>You stand still loytering in the Turkish soyle.</l>
               <l>What know you not, how that it is decreed,</l>
               <l>By all the gods, and chiefly by my selfe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>That you with triumph should all Crowned bee:</l>
               <l>Make haste Kings, least when the fates do see,</l>
               <l>How carlesly you do neglect their words,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:16"/>
They call a Counsell, and force <hi>Mahomet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Against his will some other thing to set.</l>
               <l>Send <hi>Fabius</hi> backe to <hi>Amuracke</hi> againe,</l>
               <l>To haste him forwards in his enterprise:</l>
               <l>And march you on with all the troupes you haue,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Naples</hi> ward, to conquer <hi>Aragon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For if you stay, both you and all your men,</l>
               <l>Must needs be sent downe straight to <hi>Lymbo</hi> den.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Pri.</speaker>
               <l>Muse not braue kings at <hi>Mahomets</hi> discourse,</l>
               <l>For marke what he forth of that mouth doth say,</l>
               <l>Assure your selfe it needs must happen so.</l>
               <l>Therefore make hast, go mount you on your steeds,</l>
               <l>And set vpon <hi>Alphonsus</hi> presently.</l>
               <l>So shall you reape great honor for your paine:</l>
               <l>And scape the scourge, which els the Fates ordaine.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Rise allvp.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beli.</speaker>
               <l>Then proud <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> looke thou to thy Crowne,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Belinus</hi> comes in glittring armor clad,</l>
               <l>All readie prest for to reuenge the wrong</l>
               <l>Which not long since, you offred vnto him.</l>
               <l>And since we haue God <hi>Mahound</hi> on our side:</l>
               <l>The victorie must needs to vs betide.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
               <l>Worthie <hi>Belinus,</hi> set such threats away,</l>
               <l>And let vs haste as fast as horse can trot,</l>
               <l>To set vpon presumptuous <hi>Aragon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You <hi>Fabius,</hi> hast as <hi>Mahound</hi> did commaund,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Amuracke,</hi> with all the speed you may.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fabi.</speaker>
               <l>With willing mind I hasten on my way.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Exit</hi> Fabius.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beli.</speaker>
               <l>And thinking long till that we be in fight,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Belinus</hi> hastes to quaile <hi>Alphonsus</hi> might.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
            <stage>Strike vp alarum a while. Enter <hi>Carinus.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>No sooner had God <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>bus</hi> brightsome beames</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:17"/>
Both <hi>Millaine</hi> land, and all the parts thereof.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>Why then I doubt not but you can resolue</l>
               <l>Me of a question that I shall demaund.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
               <l>I that I can, what euer that it be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>Then to be briefe, not twentie winters past</l>
               <l>When these my lims which withered are with age,</l>
               <l>Were in the prime and spring of all their youth,</l>
               <l>I still desirous as voong gallants be,</l>
               <l>To see the fashions of <hi>Arabia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My natiue soyle, and in this pilgrims weed,</l>
               <l>Began to trauell through vnkenned lands,</l>
               <l>Much ground I past, and many soyles I saw,</l>
               <l>But when my feete in <hi>Millain</hi> land I set,</l>
               <l>Such sumptuous triumphs daily there I saw,</l>
               <l>As neuer in my life I found the like.</l>
               <l>I pray good sir, what might the occasion bee:</l>
               <l>That made the <hi>Millains</hi> make such mirth and glee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
               <l>This solemne ioy wherof you now do speak,</l>
               <l>Was not solemnized my friend in vaine.</l>
               <l>For at that time there came into the land,</l>
               <l>The happiest tidings that they ere did heare.</l>
               <l>For newes was brought vpon that solemne day,</l>
               <l>Vnto our Court, that <hi>Ferdinandus</hi> proud</l>
               <l>Was slaine himselfe, <hi>Carinus</hi> and his sonne</l>
               <l>Were banisht both for euer from <hi>Aragon:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And for these happie newes that ioy was made.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>But what I pray did afterward become,</l>
               <l>Of old <hi>Carinus</hi> with his banisht sonne?</l>
               <l>What heare you nothing of them all this while?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Du.</speaker>
               <l>Yes too too much, the <hi>Millain</hi> Duke may say.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alphonsus</hi> first by secret meanes did get</l>
               <l>To be a souldier in <hi>Belinus</hi> warres:</l>
               <l>Wherein he did behaue himselfe so well,</l>
               <l>As that he got the Crowne of <hi>Aragon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which being got, he dispossest also,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:17"/>
The King <hi>Belinus</hi> which had fostered him:</l>
               <l>As for <hi>Carinus</hi> he is dead and gone,</l>
               <l>I would his sonne were his companion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>A blister build vpon that traytors tongue,</l>
               <l>But for thy friendship which thou shewedst me,</l>
               <l>Take that of me, I frankly giue it thee.</l>
               <stage>Stab him.</stage>
               <l>Now will I haste to <hi>Naples</hi> with all speed,</l>
               <l>To see if <hi>Fortune</hi> will so fauour me,</l>
               <l>To view <hi>Alphonsus</hi> in his happie state.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Exit</hi> Carinus.</stage>
            <stage>Enter <hi>Amuracke, Crocon</hi> King of <hi>Arabia, Faustus,</hi> King of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, Fabius,</hi> with the Turkes Ganesaries.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fabius</hi> come hither, what is that thou sayest?</l>
               <l>What did god <hi>Mahound</hi> prophecie to vs?</l>
               <l>Why do our Viceroyes wend vnto the warres,</l>
               <l>Before their king had notice of the same?</l>
               <l>What do they thinke to play bob foole with me?</l>
               <l>Or are they waxt so frolicke now of late,</l>
               <l>Since that they had the leading of our bands,</l>
               <l>As that they thinke that mightie <hi>Amuracke</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Dares do no other then to soothe them vp?</l>
               <l>Why speakest thou not? what fond or franticke fit</l>
               <l>Did make those carelesse Kings to venture it?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
               <l>Pardon deare Lord, no franticke fit at all,</l>
               <l>No frolicke vaine, nor no presumptuous mind,</l>
               <l>Did make your Viceroies take these wars in hand.</l>
               <l>But forst they were by <hi>Mahounds</hi> prophecie,</l>
               <l>To do the same, or else resolue to die.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>So sir, I heare you, but can scare beleeue</l>
               <l>That <hi>Mahomet</hi> would charge them go before</l>
               <l>Against <hi>Alphonsus</hi> with so small a troupe,</l>
               <l>Whose number farre exceeds king <hi>Xerxe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> troupe,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
               <l>Yes Noble Lord, and more then that hee said,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:18"/>
That ere that you with these your warlike men,</l>
               <l>Should come to bring your succour to the field:</l>
               <l>Belinus, Claramount, <hi>and</hi> Arcastus <hi>too,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Should al be crownd with crownes of beaten gold,</l>
               <l>And bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ne with triumphes round about their te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>With triumph man, did <hi>Mahound</hi> tell them so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Prouost go carrie <hi>Fabius</hi> presently,</l>
               <l>Vnto the Marshalsie, there let him rest,</l>
               <l>Clapt sure and safe in fetters all of steele,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Amuracke</hi> discharge him from the same.</l>
               <l>For be he sure, vnles it happen so</l>
               <l>As he did say, <hi>Mahound</hi> did prophesie,</l>
               <l>By this my hand, forthwith the slaue shall die.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Lay hold of <hi>Fabius,</hi> and make as though you carrie him out, Enter a souldier and say.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mess.</speaker>
               <l>Stay Prouost stay, let <hi>Fabius</hi> alone,</l>
               <l>More fitteth now, that euery lustie lad</l>
               <l>Be buckling on his helmet, then to stand</l>
               <l>In carrying souldiers to the Marshalsie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>Why what art thou,</l>
               <l>That darest once presume,</l>
               <l>For to gainsay that <hi>Amuracke</hi> did bid?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Messen.</speaker>
               <l>I am my Lord,</l>
               <l>The wretcheds man aliue:</l>
               <l>Borne vnderneath the Planet of mishap:</l>
               <l>Erewhile, a souldier of <hi>Belinus</hi> band</l>
               <l>But now.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>What now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mess.</speaker>
               <l>The mirror of mishap:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:18"/>
Whose Captaine is slaine, and all his armie dead:</l>
               <l>Onely excepted me vnhappie wretch.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>What newes is this, and is <hi>Belinus</hi> Slaine?</l>
               <l>Is this the Crowne which <hi>Mahomet</hi> did say,</l>
               <l>He should with triumph weare vpon his head?</l>
               <l>Is this the honour which that cursed god</l>
               <l>Did prophesie, should hapen to them all?</l>
               <l>Oh <hi>Dadalus,</hi> and wert thou now aliue,</l>
               <l>To fasten wings vpon high <hi>Amuracke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mahound</hi> should know, and that for certaintie,</l>
               <l>That turkish Kings can brooke no iniurie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fabi.</speaker>
               <l>Tush tush my Lord,</l>
               <l>I wonder what you meane,</l>
               <l>Thus to exclaime against high <hi>Mahomet:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ile lay my life, that ere this day be past,</l>
               <l>You shall perceiue, his tidings all be waste.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>We shall perceiue, accursed <hi>Fabius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Suffice it not that thou hast bene the man,</l>
               <l>That first didst beate those bables in my braine,</l>
               <l>But that to helpe me forward in my greefe,</l>
               <l>Thou seekest to confirme so fowle a lie.</l>
               <stage>Stab him.</stage>
               <l>Go get thee hence, and tell thy trayterous King</l>
               <l>What gift you had, which did such tidings bring.</l>
               <l>And now my Lords, since nothing else will serue,</l>
               <l>Buckle your helmes, clap on your steeled coates,</l>
               <l>Mount on your steeds, take Launces in your hands,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Amuracke</hi> doth meane this very day,</l>
               <l>Proude <hi>Mahomet</hi> with weapons to assay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Messen.</speaker>
               <l>Mercie high Monarch, tis no time now</l>
               <l>To spend the day in such vaine threatnings,</l>
               <l>Against our god, the mightie <hi>Mahomet:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:19"/>
More fitteth thee to place thy men at armes</l>
               <l>In battle ray, for to withstand your foes,</l>
               <l>Which now are drawing towards you with speed.</l>
               <stage>Sound drummes within.</stage>
               <l>Hark how their drummes with dub a dub do come,</l>
               <l>To armes high Lord, and set these trifles by:</l>
               <l>That you may set vpon them valiantly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>And do they come you kings of <hi>Turkie?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now is the time, in which your warlike armes</l>
               <l>Must raise your names aboue the starrie skies:</l>
               <l>Call to your minde your predecessors acts,</l>
               <l>Whose martiall might, this many a hundred yeare,</l>
               <l>Did keepe those fearefull dogs in dread and awe,</l>
               <l>And let your weapons shew <hi>Alphonsus</hi> plaine,</l>
               <l>That though that they be clapped vp in clay,</l>
               <l>Yet there be branches sprung vp from those trees,</l>
               <l>In Turkish land, which brooke no iniuries.</l>
               <l>Besides the same, remember with your selues,</l>
               <l>What foes we haue, not mightie Tamberlaine,</l>
               <l>Nor souldiers trained vp amongst the warres,</l>
               <l>But fearefull bodies, pickt from their rurall flocke,</l>
               <l>Which till this time were wholy ignorant</l>
               <l>What weapons ment, or bloudie <hi>Mars</hi> doth craue.</l>
               <l>More would I say, but horses that be free,</l>
               <l>Do need no spur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and souldiers which themselues</l>
               <l>Long and desire to buckle with the foe,</l>
               <l>Do need no words to egge them to the same.</l>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> with a Canapie carried ouer him by three Lords, hauing ouer each corner a Kings head, crowned with him, <hi>Albinius, Laelius, Miles,</hi> with Crownes on their heads, and their souldiers.</stage>
               <l>Besides the same, behold whereas our foes</l>
               <l>Are marching towards vs most speedilie.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:19"/>
Courage my Lords, ours is the victorie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <l>Thou Pagan dog how darst thou be so bold</l>
               <l>To set thy foote within <hi>Alphonsus</hi> land?</l>
               <l>What art thou come to view thy wretched kings,</l>
               <l>Whose traiterous heads bedeckt my tents so well?</l>
               <l>Or else thou hearing that on top thereof,</l>
               <l>There is a place left vacant, art thou come</l>
               <l>To haue thy head possesse the highest seate?</l>
               <l>If it be so, lie downe, and this my sword</l>
               <l>Shall presently that honor thee affoord.</l>
               <l>If not, pack hence, or by the heauens I vow,</l>
               <l>Both thou and thine shall verie soone perceiue,</l>
               <l>That he that seekes to moue my patience,</l>
               <l>Must yeeld his life to thee for recompence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>Why proud <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> thinkst thou <hi>Amurack</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whose mightie force doth terrefie the Gods,</l>
               <l>Can ere be found to turne his heeles and flie</l>
               <l>Away for feare, from such a boy as thou?</l>
               <l>No no, although that <hi>Mars</hi> this mickle while</l>
               <l>Hath fortified thy weake and feeble arme,</l>
               <l>And Fortune oft hath viewd with friendly face,</l>
               <l>Thy armies marching victors from the field,</l>
               <l>Yet at the presence of high <hi>Amuracke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fortune shall change, and <hi>Mars</hi> that God of might</l>
               <l>Shall succour me, and leaue <hi>Alphonsus</hi> quight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>Pagan I say, thou greatly art deceiu'd,</l>
               <l>I clap vp Fortune in a cage of gold,</l>
               <l>To make her turne her wheele as I thinke best.</l>
               <l>And as for <hi>Mars</hi> whom you do say will change,</l>
               <l>He moping sits behind the kitchin doore,</l>
               <l>Prest at commaund of euery Skullians mouth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Who dares not stir, nor once to moue a whit</l>
               <l>For feare <hi>Alphonsus</hi> then should stomack it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>Blasphemous dog, I wonder that the earth</l>
               <l>Doth cease from renting vnderneath thy feete,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:20"/>
What froward fortune hapned on your side:</l>
               <l>I hope your king in safetie doth abide?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
               <l>I noble madam, <hi>Amurack</hi> doth liue:</l>
               <l>And long I hope he shall enioy his life.</l>
               <l>But yet I feare, vnles more succour come,</l>
               <l>We shall both loose our king and soueraigne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>How so king <hi>Crocon,</hi> dost thou speak in iest?</l>
               <l>To proue if <hi>Fausta</hi> would lament his death?</l>
               <l>Or else hath any thing hapt him amis?</l>
               <l>Speake quickly <hi>Crocon</hi> what the cause might be,</l>
               <l>That thou dost vtter forth these words to me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
               <l>Then worthie <hi>Fausta</hi> know, that <hi>Amuracke</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our mightie king, and your approued spowse,</l>
               <l>Prickt with desire of euerlasting fame,</l>
               <l>As he was pressing in the thickest rankes</l>
               <l>Of Aragonians, was with much adoo</l>
               <l>At length tooke prisoner, by <hi>Alphonsus</hi> hands.</l>
               <l>So that vnles you succour soone do bring,</l>
               <l>You loose your spowse, and we shall want our king.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iphi.</speaker>
               <l>Oh haples hap, oh dire and cruell fate!</l>
               <l>What iniurie hath <hi>Amuracke</hi> my sire</l>
               <l>Done to the Gods, which now I know are wrath?</l>
               <l>Although vniustly and without a cause.</l>
               <l>For well I wot, not any other king</l>
               <l>Which now doth liue, or since the world begun</l>
               <l>Did sway a scepter, had a greater care</l>
               <l>To please the Gods, then mightie <hi>Amuracke.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And for to quite our fathers great good will,</l>
               <l>Seeke they thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> basely all his fame to spill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iphigina,</hi> leaue off these wofull tunes,</l>
               <l>It is not words can cure and ease this wound:</l>
               <l>But warlike swords, not teares, but sturdie speares:</l>
               <l>High <hi>Amuracke</hi> is prisoner to our foes.</l>
               <l>What then? thinke you that our <hi>Amazones</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ioynd with the forces of the Turkish troupe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:20"/>
Are not sufficient for to set him free?</l>
               <l>Yes daughter yes, I meane not for to sleepe,</l>
               <l>Vntill he is free, or we him company keepe.</l>
               <l>March on my mates.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
            <stage>Strike vp alarum, flie <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> follow <hi>Iphigina</hi> and say.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iphi.</speaker>
               <l>How now <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> you which neuer yet</l>
               <l>Could meete your equall in the feates of armes,</l>
               <l>How haps it now that in such sudden sort</l>
               <l>You flie the presence of a sillie maide?</l>
               <l>What haue you found mine arme of such a force,</l>
               <l>As that you thinke your bodie ouerweake</l>
               <l>For to withstand the furie of my blowes?</l>
               <l>Or do you else disdaine to fight with me:</l>
               <l>For staining of your high nobilitie?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
               <l>No daintie dame, I wold not haue thee think</l>
               <l>That euer thou or any other wight,</l>
               <l>Shall liue to see <hi>Alphnosus</hi> flie the field</l>
               <l>From any king or <hi>Keisar</hi> who some ere,</l>
               <l>First will I die in thickest of my fo,</l>
               <l>Before I will disbase mine honour so.</l>
               <l>Nor do I scorne thou goddes for to staine</l>
               <l>My prowes with thee, although it be a shame</l>
               <l>For knights to combat with the female sect.</l>
               <l>But loue sweete mouse hath so benumbd my wit,</l>
               <l>That though I would, I must refraine from it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iphi.</speaker>
               <l>I thought as much when first I came to wars,</l>
               <l>Your noble acts were fitter to be writ</l>
               <l>Within the Tables of dame <hi>Venus</hi> sun,</l>
               <l>Then in God <hi>Mars</hi> his warlike registers.</l>
               <l>When as your Lords are hacking helm es abroad,</l>
               <l>And make their speares to shiuer in the aire,</l>
               <l>Your mind is busied in fond <hi>Cupids</hi> toyes.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:21"/>
Come on I faith, ile teach you for to know</l>
               <l>We came to fight, and not to loue I trow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <l>Nay virgin stay, and if thou wilt vouchsafe</l>
               <l>To entertaine <hi>Alphonsus</hi> simple sute,</l>
               <l>Thou shalt ere long be Monarch of the world:</l>
               <l>All christned kings, with all your Pagan dogs</l>
               <l>Shall bend their knees vnto <hi>Iphigina.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Indian soyle shalbe thine at command,</l>
               <l>Where euery step thou settest on the ground,</l>
               <l>Shall be receiued on the golden mines.</l>
               <l>Rich <hi>Pactolus</hi> that riuer of account,</l>
               <l>Which doth descend from top of <hi>Tiuole</hi> mount,</l>
               <l>Shall be thine owne, and all the world beside:</l>
               <l>If you will graunt to be <hi>Alphonsus</hi> bride.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iphi.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alphonsus</hi> bride? nay villain do not thinke</l>
               <l>That fame or riches can so rule my thoughts,</l>
               <l>As for to make me loue and fancie him</l>
               <l>Whom I do hate, and in such sort despise,</l>
               <l>As if my death could bring to passe his baine:</l>
               <l>I would not long from <hi>Plutoes</hi> port remaine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <l>Nay then proud pecock since thou art so stou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>As that intreatie will not moue thy minde</l>
               <l>For to consent to be my wedded spowse,</l>
               <l>Thou shalt in spite of Gods and Fortune too,</l>
               <l>Serue high. <hi>Alphonsus</hi> as a concubine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iphi.</speaker>
               <l>Ile rather die then euer that shall hap.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>And thou shalt die vnles it come to pas.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Alphonsus</hi> and <hi>Iphigina</hi> fight, <hi>Iphigina</hi> flie, follow <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.</hi> Strike vp alarum. Enter <hi>Alphonsus</hi> with his rapier, <hi>Albinius, Laelius, Miles</hi> with their souldiers. <hi>Amurack, Fausta, Iphigina, Crocon</hi> and <hi>Faustus</hi> all bounde with their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ands behind them, <hi>Amuracke</hi> looke angerly on Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sta.</stage>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:6223:21"/>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Medea, and say.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Med.</speaker>
               <l>Nay <hi>Amurack</hi> this is no time to iarre,</l>
               <l>Although thy wife did in her franticke moode</l>
               <l>Vse speeches which might better haue bene sparde,</l>
               <l>Yet do thou not iudge the same time to be</l>
               <l>A season to requite that iniurie:</l>
               <l>More fitteth thee with all the wit thou hast,</l>
               <l>To call to mind which way thou maist release</l>
               <l>Thy selfe, thy wife, and faire <hi>Iphigina,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Forth of the power of stout <hi>Alphonsus</hi> hands.</l>
               <l>For well I wot, since first you breathed breath,</l>
               <l>You neuer were so nie the snares of death.</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Amurack,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>our high and kingly seate,</l>
               <l>Your ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>all scepter, and your stately Crowne,</l>
               <l>Your mightie Countrey, and your men at armes,</l>
               <l>Be conquered all, and can no succour bring.</l>
               <l>Put then no trust in these same paltrie toyes:</l>
               <l>But call to mind that thou a prisoner art:</l>
               <l>Clapt vp in chaines, whose life and deaths depends</l>
               <l>Vpon the hands of thy most mortall foe.</l>
               <l>Then take thou heed that what some ere he say,</l>
               <l>Thou doest not once presume for to gainsay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>Away you foole, thinke you your cursed-charmes</l>
               <l>Can bridle so the mind of <hi>Amuracke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As that he will stand croaching to his foe?</l>
               <l>No no, be sure that if that beggers brat</l>
               <l>Do dare but once to contrary my will,</l>
               <l>Ile make him soone in heart for to repent,</l>
               <l>That ere such words gainst <hi>Amuracke</hi> he spent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Med.</speaker>
               <l>Then since thou dost disdaine my good aduise,</l>
               <l>Looke to thy selfe, and if you fare amis</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:22"/>
Remember that <hi>Medea</hi> counsell gaue,</l>
               <l>Which might you safe from all those perils saue.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Fausta</hi> you, as well you haue begun,</l>
               <l>Beware you follow still your friends aduise.</l>
               <l>If that <hi>Alphonsus</hi> do desire of thee</l>
               <l>To haue your daughter for his wedded spowse,</l>
               <l>Beware you do not once the same gainsay:</l>
               <l>Vnles with death he do your rashnes pay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>No worthie wight, first <hi>Fausta</hi> means to die,</l>
               <l>Before <hi>Alphonsus</hi> she will contrarie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Med.</speaker>
               <l>Why then farwell, but you <hi>Iphigina,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Beware you do not ouersqueamish wax,</l>
               <l>When as your mother giueth her consent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iphi.</speaker>
               <l>The Gods forbid that ere I should gainsay</l>
               <l>That which <hi>Medea</hi> bids me to obay.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit <hi>Medea.</hi>
            </stage>
            <stage>Rise vp <hi>Alphonsus</hi> out of his chaire, who all this while hath bene talking to <hi>Albinius,</hi> and say.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Al.</speaker>
               <l>Now <hi>Amurack</hi> the proud blasphemous dogs</l>
               <l>(For so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ou termed vs) which did brall and raile</l>
               <l>Against God <hi>Mars,</hi> and fickle Fortunes wheele,</l>
               <l>Haue got the gole for all your solemne praiers:</l>
               <l>Your selfe are prisoner, which as then did thinke</l>
               <l>That all the forces of the triple world,</l>
               <l>Were insufficient to fulfill the same.</l>
               <l>How like you this? is Fortune of such might,</l>
               <l>Or hath God <hi>Mars</hi> such force or power diuine,</l>
               <l>As that he can with all the power he hath,</l>
               <l>Set thee and thine forth of <hi>Alphonsus</hi> hands?</l>
               <l>I do not thinke but that your hopes so small,</l>
               <l>As that you would with verie willing mind,</l>
               <l>Yeeld for my spowse the faire <hi>Iphigina,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>On that condition, that without delay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fausta</hi> and you may scotfree scape away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>What thinkst thou vilain that high <hi>Amurack</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:22"/>
Beares such a minde, as for the feare of death,</l>
               <l>Heele yeeld his daughter, yea his onely ioy,</l>
               <l>Into the hands of such a dunghill Knight?</l>
               <l>No traytor no, for as now I lie</l>
               <l>Clapt vp in Irons, and with bolts of steele:</l>
               <l>Yet do there lurke within the Turkish soyle,</l>
               <l>Such troupes of souldiers, that with small ado,</l>
               <l>Theile set me scotfree from your men and you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
               <l>Villain sayest thou, traitor &amp; dunghil knight,</l>
               <l>Now by the heauens, since that thou dost denie,</l>
               <l>For to fulfill that which in gentle wise</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alphonsus</hi> craues, both thou and all thy traine</l>
               <l>Shall with your liues requite that iniurie.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Albinius</hi> lay holde of <hi>Amuracke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And carrie him to prison presently,</l>
               <l>There to remaine vntill I do returne</l>
               <l>Into my tent, for by high <hi>Ioue</hi> I vowe,</l>
               <l>Vnles he waxe more calmer out of hand,</l>
               <l>His head amongst his fellow Kings shall stand.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Albinius</hi> carrie <hi>Amuracke</hi> forth, who as he is a going, must say.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>No villaine, thinke not that the feare of death</l>
               <l>Shall make me calmer while I draw my breath.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>Now <hi>Laelius,</hi> take you <hi>Iphigina,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her mother <hi>Fausta,</hi> with these other Kings,</l>
               <l>And put them into prisons seuerally:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Amuracks</hi> stout stomacke shall vndo,</l>
               <l>Both he himselfe and all his other crew.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Fausta <hi>kneele</hi> downe.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>Oh sacred Prince, if that the salt-brine teares,</l>
               <l>Distilling downe poore <hi>Faustas</hi> withered cheekes,</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:6223:23"/>
Alphonsus <hi>and</hi> Albinius <hi>go toward</hi> Carinus, Alphonsus <hi>stand looking on</hi> Carinus, Carinus <hi>say.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>What nere a word <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> art thou dumb?</l>
               <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>th my presence so perturbe thy minde,</l>
               <l>That for because I come in Pilgrims weed,</l>
               <l>You thinke each word which you do spend to me</l>
               <l>A great disgrace vnto your name to be?</l>
               <l>Why speakest thou not? if that my place you craue,</l>
               <l>I will be gone and you my place shall haue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <l>Nay father stay, the Gods of heauen forbid,</l>
               <l>That ere <hi>Alphonsus</hi> should desire or wish</l>
               <l>To haue his absence whom he doth account</l>
               <l>To be the Loadstone of his life.</l>
               <l>What though the fates and fortune both in one,</l>
               <l>Haue bene content to call your louing sonne,</l>
               <l>From beggers state, vnto this princely seate,</l>
               <l>Should I therefore disdaine my aged sire?</l>
               <l>No first both Crowne and life I will detest,</l>
               <l>Before such venome breed within my brest.</l>
               <l>What erst I did, the sudden ioy I tooke,</l>
               <l>To see <hi>Carinus</hi> in such happie state,</l>
               <l>Did make me do, and nothing else at all,</l>
               <l>High <hi>Ioue</hi> himselfe do I to witnes call.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>These words are vaine, I knew as much before:</l>
               <l>But yet <hi>Alphonsus</hi> I must wonder needs,</l>
               <l>That you whose yeares are proue to <hi>Cupids</hi> snares,</l>
               <l>Can suffer such a Goddes as this dame,</l>
               <l>Thus for to shead such store of Christall teares.</l>
               <l>Beleeue me sonne, although my yeares be spent,</l>
               <l>Her sighes and sobs in twaine my heart do rent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <l>Like power deare father had she ouer me,</l>
               <l>Vntill for loue, I looking to receiue</l>
               <l>Loue backe againe, not onely was denied,</l>
               <l>But also taunted in most spightfull sort:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:23"/>
Which made me loathe that which I erst did loue,</l>
               <l>As she her selfe, with all her friends shall proue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>How now <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> you which haue so lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</l>
               <l>Bene trained vp in bloudie broyles of <hi>Mars,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What know you not, that Castles are not wonne</l>
               <l>At first assault, and women are not wooed</l>
               <l>When first their suters profer loue to them:</l>
               <l>As for my part, I should account that maide</l>
               <l>A wanton wench, vnconstant lewde and light,</l>
               <l>That yeelds the field, before she venture fight.</l>
               <l>Especially vnto her mortall foe,</l>
               <l>As you were then vnto <hi>Iphigina.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But for because I see you fitter are</l>
               <l>To enter Lists and combat with your foes,</l>
               <l>Then court faire Ladyes in God <hi>Cupids</hi> tents,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Carinus</hi> meanes, your spokesman for to bee,</l>
               <l>And if that she consent, you shall agree.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>What you commaund,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alphonsus</hi> must not flie:</l>
               <l>Though otherwise perhaps he would denie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>Then daintie damsell stint these trickling teares,</l>
               <l>Cease sighes and sobs, yea make a merrie cheare,</l>
               <l>Your pardon is already purchased:</l>
               <l>So that you be not ouer curious</l>
               <l>In granting to <hi>Alphonsus</hi> iust demand.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iphi.</speaker>
               <l>Thankes mightie Prince, no curioser ile bee,</l>
               <l>Then doth become a maide of my degree.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>The Gods forbid that ere <hi>Carinus</hi> tongue</l>
               <l>Should go about to make a mayd consent</l>
               <l>Vnto the thing which modestie denies:</l>
               <l>That which I aske, is neither hurt to thee,</l>
               <l>Danger to parents, nor disgrace to friends,</l>
               <l>But good and honest, and will profit bring,</l>
               <l>To thee and those which leane vnto that thing.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:24"/>
And that is this, since first <hi>Alphonsus</hi> eyes,</l>
               <l>Did hap to glaunce vpon your heauenly hew,</l>
               <l>And saw the rare perfection of the same,</l>
               <l>He hath desired to become your spowse.</l>
               <l>Now if you will vnto the same agree,</l>
               <l>I dare assure you, that you shall be free.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iph.</speaker>
               <l>Pardon deare Lord, the world goes very hard,</l>
               <l>When women kinde are forced for to wooe,</l>
               <l>If that your sonne had loued me so well,</l>
               <l>Why did he not informe me of the same?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
               <l>Why did he not? what haue you clean forgot</l>
               <l>What ample profers he did make to you,</l>
               <l>When hand to hand he did encounter you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iphi.</speaker>
               <l>No worthy sir, I haue not it forgot,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Cupid</hi> cannot enter in the brest,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Mars</hi> before had tooke possession:</l>
               <l>That was no time to talke of <hi>Venus</hi> games,</l>
               <l>When all our fellowes were pressed in the warres.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>Well, let that passe, now canst thou be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</l>
               <l>To loue <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> and become his spowse?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iphi.</speaker>
               <l>I if the high <hi>Alphonsus</hi> could vouchsafe</l>
               <l>To entertaine me as his wedded spowse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>If that he could? what dost thou doubt of that</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iason</hi> did iet when as he had obtaind,</l>
               <l>The golden fleece by wise <hi>Medeas</hi> art,</l>
               <l>The Greekes reioyced when they had subdued</l>
               <l>The famous bulwarkes of most stately <hi>Troy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But all their mirth was nothing in respect</l>
               <l>Of this my ioy, since that I now haue got,</l>
               <l>That which I long desired in my heart.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
               <l>But what sayes <hi>Fausta</hi> to her daughters choice?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fausta</hi> doth say, the Gods haue bin her friends</l>
               <l>To let her liue to see <hi>Iphigina</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Bestowed so vnto her hearts content.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6223:24"/>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>Thankes mightie Empresse for your gentlenes,</l>
               <l>And if <hi>Alphonsus</hi> can at any time</l>
               <l>With all his power requite this curtesie,</l>
               <l>You shall perceiue how kindly he doth take</l>
               <l>Your forwardnesse in this his happie chance.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Albinius</hi> go call forth <hi>Amuracke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Weele see what he doth say vnto this match.</l>
               <stage>Exit <hi>Albinius,</hi> bring forth <hi>Amuracke.</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>Most mightie Turke, I with my warlike sonne</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> loathing that so great a Prince</l>
               <l>As you should liue in such vnseemly sort,</l>
               <l>Haue sent for you to profer life or death:</l>
               <l>Life, if you do consent to our demand,</l>
               <l>And death if that you dare gainsay the same,</l>
               <l>Your wife, high <hi>Fausta,</hi> with <hi>Iphigina,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Haue giuen consent that this my warlike sonne</l>
               <l>Should haue your daughter for his bedfellow,</l>
               <l>Now resteth nought but that you do agree,</l>
               <l>And so to purchase sure tranquilitie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>Now <hi>Amu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ack</hi> aduise thee what thou sayest,</l>
               <l>Bethinke thee well what answere thou wilt make:</l>
               <l>Thy life and death dependeth on thy words,</l>
               <l>If thou denie to be <hi>Alphonsus</hi> sire,</l>
               <l>Death is thy share: but if that thou consent,</l>
               <l>Thy life is sau'd, consent? nay rather die.</l>
               <l>Should I consent to giue <hi>Iphigina</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Into the hands of such a beggers brat?</l>
               <l>What <hi>Amuracke</hi> thou dost deceiue thy selfe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alphonsus</hi> is the sonne vnto a King:</l>
               <l>What then? the worthy of thy daughters loue</l>
               <l>She is agreed, and <hi>Fausta</hi> is content:</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Amuracke</hi> will not be discontent.</l>
               <stage>Take <hi>Iphigina</hi> by the hand, giue her to <hi>Alphonsus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:25"/>
Heere braue <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> take thou at my hand,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iphigina,</hi> I giue her vnto thee:</l>
               <l>And for her dowrie, when her father die,</l>
               <l>Thou shalt possesse the Turkish Emperie.</l>
               <l>Take her I say, and liue King <hi>Nestors</hi> yeeres,</l>
               <l>So would the Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ke and all his Noble Peeres.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
               <l>Immo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tall thanks I giue vnto your grace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cari.</speaker>
               <l>Now worthy Princes, since by helpe of <hi>Ioue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>On either side the wedding is decreed,</l>
               <l>Come let vs wend to <hi>Naples</hi> speedily,</l>
               <l>For to solemnize it with mirth and glee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
               <l>As you do will, we ioyntly do agree.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
            <stage>Enter <hi>Venus</hi> with the Muses, and say.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ve.</speaker>
               <l>Now worthy <hi>Muses</hi> with vnwilling mind,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> is forst to trudge to heauens againe:</l>
               <l>For <hi>luppiter</hi> that God of peerles power,</l>
               <l>Proclaimed hath a solemne festiuall,</l>
               <l>In honour of dame <hi>Danaes</hi> luckles death:</l>
               <l>Vnto the which, in paine of his displeasure</l>
               <l>He hath inuited all the immortall Gods</l>
               <l>And Goddesses, so that I must be there,</l>
               <l>Vnlesse I will his high displeasure beare:</l>
               <l>You see <hi>Alphonsus</hi> hath with much ado,</l>
               <l>At length obtaind fayre <hi>Iphigina</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Amuracke</hi> her father, for his wife.</l>
               <l>Who now are going to the Temple wards,</l>
               <l>For to perfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>me dame <hi>Iunoes</hi> sacred rites,</l>
               <l>Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e we will leaue them till the feast be done:</l>
               <l>Which in the heauens by this time is begun,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6223:25"/>
Meane time deare <hi>Muses,</hi> wander you not farr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Foorth of the path of high <hi>Pernassus</hi> hill:</l>
               <l>That when I come to finish vp his life,</l>
               <l>You may be readie for to succour me.</l>
               <l>Adieu deare dames, farwell <hi>Calltope.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit <hi>Venus.</hi> Or if you can conueniently, let a chaire come downe from the top of the stage, and draw her vp.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Calli.</speaker>
               <l>A dieu you sacred Goddes of the skie.</l>
               <l>Well louing sisters, since that she is gone,</l>
               <l>Come let vs haste vnto <hi>Pernassus</hi> hill,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Citherea</hi> did lately will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Melpom.</speaker>
               <l>Then make you haste her mind for to fulfill.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt omnes, playing on their Instruments.</stage>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
