<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ciceronis amor· = Tullies loue VVherein is discoursed the prime of Ciceroes youth, setting out in liuely portraitures how young gentlemen that ayme at honour should leuell the end of their affections, holding the loue of countrie and friends in more esteeme then those fading blossomes of beautie, that onely feede the curious suruey of the eye. A worke full of pleasure as following Ciceroes vaine, who was as conceipted in his youth as graue in his age, profitable as conteining precepts worthie so famous an orator. By Robert Greene in Artibus magister.</title>
            <author>Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02080</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105897</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841622</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841622</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6220</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02080)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6220)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 344:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ciceronis amor· = Tullies loue VVherein is discoursed the prime of Ciceroes youth, setting out in liuely portraitures how young gentlemen that ayme at honour should leuell the end of their affections, holding the loue of countrie and friends in more esteeme then those fading blossomes of beautie, that onely feede the curious suruey of the eye. A worke full of pleasure as following Ciceroes vaine, who was as conceipted in his youth as graue in his age, profitable as conteining precepts worthie so famous an orator. By Robert Greene in Artibus magister.</title>
                  <author>Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 78, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Robinson, for Thomas Newman and Iohn Winington,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Tullies loue.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cicero, Marcus Tullius.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-10</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-12</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6220:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6220:1"/>
            <p>CICERONIS AMOR.
Tullies Loue. Wherein is discoursed the prime of Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes
youth, setting out in liuely portratures how young
Gentlemen that ayme at honour should leuell
the end of their affections, holding the loue of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie
and friends in more esteeme then those
fading blossomes of beautie, that onely feede
the curious suruey of the eye. A worke full of pleasure as following <hi>Ciceroes</hi> vaine,
who was as conceipted in his youth as graue in his age, profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
as conteining precepts worthie so famous an Orator.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Greene in Artibus magister.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Omne tulit punctum qui miscuit vtile dulci.</q>
            <p>AT LONDON,
Printed by <hi>Robert Robinson,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Newman
and Iohn Winington.</hi> 1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6220:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6220:2"/>
            <head>To the right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Ferdinando Stanley, Lord
Strange, enobled with all titles
that Honor may afforde or ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
challenge, Robert Greene
wisheth encrease of vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
and Lordly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Tripos</hi> (Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable)
ingrauen with <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur
Sapienti,</hi> was by the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle
allotted to <hi>Socrates,
Achilles</hi> shielde maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
with the sword, fel to
<hi>Vlisses</hi> for his wisedome:
<hi>Pallas</hi> had hir library, and
hir launce: and suche as
read <hi>Non vltra,</hi> on <hi>Hercules</hi> pillers, pointed out the
Caracters with their speares. Proportion the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of Geometry, and mistresse of Arts, commands
that <hi>Hector</hi> haue his Honors, <hi>Alcides</hi> his glories, and
that <hi>Olympus</hi> bee neuer without bright glittering ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour,
nor greene wreathed garlands: as well to grace
the souldier, as to glory the Poet. This considered
(Right Honorable) hauing done my indeuor to pen
downe the loues of <hi>Cicero,</hi> which <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius
Nepos,</hi> forgot in their writings: I presumed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
vnto your Honor not high written poemes, as
<hi>Maro</hi> did to <hi>Augustus,</hi> but the fruites of well intended
<pb facs="tcp:6220:3"/>
thoughtes as <hi>Calymachus</hi> scholler did to <hi>Alexander:</hi>
Thinking nothing rare, nor view-worthy, sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
patronaged, vnlesse shrowded vnder the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of so honorable a <hi>Moecenas.</hi> Whatsoeuer was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
in <hi>Rostro</hi> was not pend by <hi>Hortensius,</hi> and yet the
Senatours heard and gaue plausible censures. <hi>Homer</hi>
spent verses as well on <hi>Irus</hi> the beggar, as <hi>Eurymachus</hi>
the wooer. Euery sentence cannot <hi>Cleanthis lucernam
Olere,</hi> and yet men will reade poemes &amp; praise them.
Then (Right Honourable) if my worke treating of
<hi>Cicero,</hi> seeme not fit for <hi>Cicero,</hi> as eclipsing the beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
shew of his eloquence, with a harsh and vnpoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d
stile: yet I craue that your Honour will vouch
of it onely, for that it is written of <hi>Cicero. Ennius</hi> labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
as hard in his rough poesies, as <hi>Virgill</hi> in high po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emes:
<hi>Phidias</hi> pensill in his own conceit was as sharp
pointed, as <hi>Pigmal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons</hi> chasing tooles: meane wits in
their follies, haue equall paines with learned Clarkes
in their fancies. <hi>Apollo</hi> yeelded Oracles as well to
poore men for their praiers, as to Princes for their
presents: Stars haue their lights and hayres their sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
Meane schollers haue hie thoughtes; though
low fortunes. Thus perswaded &amp; imboldened (Right
Honorable I present this pamphlet of <hi>Ciceroes</hi> loues
to your Lordship, resolued vpon your curteous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance
that weighing the minde not the matter,
your Honour will say, if not <hi>Bucephalus,</hi> yet a horse.
And in this hope resting, I wish to your Lordship as
much health and happines as your Honour can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
or I imagine.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships humbly deuoted.
ROBERT GREENE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6220:3"/>
            <head>To the gentle Readers health.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen I haue written of <hi>Tullies</hi>
loue, a worke attempted to win your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours,
but to discouer mine owne igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,
in that coueting to counterfait Tullies phrase,
I haue lost my selfe in vnproper words: but hoping
as euer I haue done of your courtesies, I haue like
bold bayard put my head out of the stable. If my
methode be worse then it was wont to be, think that
skill in musicke marde all, For the cliffe was so disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt
from my note, that wee could not clap a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord
together by fiue marke. <hi>Chiron</hi> the <hi>Sagita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi>
was but a fained conceipt, and men that beare
great shapes, and large shadowes, and haue no good
nor honest minds, are like the portraiture of <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi>
drawne vpon the sands. If I speake mistical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
thinke tis musically, and so desiring that you will
take Tullies loues, as pende for your pleasure, I bid
you farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Robert Greene.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6220:4"/>
            <head>Ad Lectorem Hexasticon.</head>
            <l>In lucem prodit tenebris exuta malignis</l>
            <l>Romulei petula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, vaesana<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> flammula Phoebi:</l>
            <l>Rora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem Authori (Lectores) spargite flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
            <l>Intyba, Narcissos, Latacen, picti<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> roseti</l>
            <l>Dulces diuitias: Illum concingite lauru:</l>
            <l>Emerito solers industria reddat honorem.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Watson. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>Ad Lectorem de Ciceronis
amore, Hexasticon.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Miraris fortasse legens Ciceronis amorem?</l>
               <l>Desine mirari, qui bene scribit, amat.</l>
               <l>Crimen inesse putas? semel insaniuimus omnes,</l>
               <l>Quae faciunt iuuenes, condoluere senes.</l>
               <l>Linguam qui laudat Ciceronis, laudet amorem,</l>
               <l>Greni solus honor, sit Ciceronis amor.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. B. Cantabrigiensis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:6220:4"/>
               <l>VArro and Tucca wrote of Maroes verse,</l>
               <l>And Dares dared to tell of Homers skill,</l>
               <l>Of Ouids workes Latins haue made reherse,</l>
               <l>And Poets haue discourst of Pindars quill,</l>
               <l>Many haue writ Cosmographie of lands,</l>
               <l>And tolde of Gihon and of Tagus sands.</l>
               <l>Of Helens beauty and of Ledas hew,</l>
               <l>The winged fancies of the learnd haue tolde,</l>
               <l>But of the prowdest Poets olde or new,</l>
               <l>Who dard sweete Tullies fancies once vnfolde,</l>
               <l>As far to hie for all that yet hath beene:</l>
               <l>Then giue the palme and glory vnto Greene.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thomas Burneby, Esquire.</signed>
               </closer>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now bloomes the blossomes of faire Adons flower,</l>
               <l>Cupid is stolne from Paphos secrete shrine,</l>
               <l>Diana lurkes, shee and hir nymphes doe lower,</l>
               <l>Bacchus that tempers sacred Loue with wine,</l>
               <l>Ceres and all the gods haue made agree,</l>
               <l>That Loue is god and there is none but hee.</l>
               <l>The Poemes wanton Ouid set in verse</l>
               <l>His art of loue that banisht him from Roome,</l>
               <l>Did neuer such quaint Amorets reherse,</l>
               <l>As are deciphred vnder Tullies doome,</l>
               <l>Whose Romain phrase fetcht from Parnassus hill,</l>
               <l>Saies none but Tully in the depth of skill.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Edward Rainsford, Esquire.</signed>
               </closer>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6220:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6220:5"/>
            <head>Tullies Loue.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here dwelled in the</hi>
Citie of <hi>Rome</hi> being metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politane
of the worlde, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
as well for martiall
Champions, as delicate for
beautiful Ladyes; a Consul
called <hi>Flaminius,</hi> made glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
by fortune, as hauing
twise roade in the trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing
chariot and worne
t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Lawrell wreath, giuen as a Palme to such as haue
béene happie for manie great victories. This consull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
in the common wealth for his martiall exploytes,
Fortune whose conceit rests in extréemes, either too pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal
in her fauors, or preiudicial in her frownes, to make
this man the myracle of her deitie, lent him one onelie
Daughter of such excellent exquisite perfection as Nature
in her seemed to wonder at her owne workes. Hir haire
was like the shine of <hi>Apollo,</hi> when shaking his glorious
tresses he makes the world beauteous with his bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.
The Iuorie of hir face ouer dasht with a vermilion
die, séemed like the blush that lept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Endemions</hi> chéekes
when <hi>Cynthia</hi> courts him on the hilles of <hi>Latmos.</hi> So did
the proportion of her bodie answere to the perfection of
the minde and the honour of hir thoughtes so fitted to the
glory of hir fauors, as it rested doubtfull whether hir out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
beauties or inward vertues helde the supremacie.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6220:6"/>
In so much that as men flocke to <hi>Delphos</hi> to heare the
Oracles of <hi>Apollo,</hi> so diuers resort to <hi>Rome</hi> to take veiw
of the excellencie of <hi>Terentia:</hi> who once delighted with the
sight of hir graces set downe this as an Axiome, that <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi>
the Patronesse of <hi>Troy</hi> for wisedome: or <hi>Venus</hi> the
wonder of Heauen for beautie, might not disgrace the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities
of this gorgious Damosell. <hi>Rome</hi> swelling with
the pride of this matchlesse Uirgin, whose thoughts were
more humble then hir face beautifull: and yet the Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of that time feared to attempt hir portraiture, as fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
the perfection of nature to excéede the proportion of
Art, made hir the Mistresse of their vestals, as one that
counted fancie as vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it for a maide, as <hi>Alexauder</hi> cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize
for a souldier. <hi>Cupid</hi> sitting on his mothers knée by
the fount of <hi>Alcydalion,</hi> séeing howe <hi>Terentia</hi> enemie to
his amarous Philosophie, set loue at so light estéeme, and
for a charme against his magicall inchauntments, carried
the euerburning fire of <hi>Vesta</hi> in hir breast, clasping his
mother wantonly about y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> necke he began thus to prattle.
Séeing mother we haue left the places of our accustomed
reside<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to auoid y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> troups of such sutors as onely end their
loues with their liues, &amp; haue st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ln to this secret fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t here
a while to be solitarie to weare away the time with some
conceited chat, I pray you tell me whereof are womens
hearts made? I aske the question mother for that I finde
the distinction of their fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cies like the difference of their
faces, which as they be distinguisht in proportion, so they
be altogether vnlike in properties. <hi>Venus</hi> hearing hir son
make such a waggish demaunde, beganne thus to reply.
Some say my boy of the liuer of a Camelion, whose nature
is to bee changeable in hues, and women as variable in
their thoughts. Others of a Pyrit stone, which handled
softly is as colde as ice, but pressed betwéene the fingers
burneth like fire: they which inser this comparison, say
that women brooke not fauourable perswasions, nor may
be woone by intreaties, but the readie way to kindle them
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6220:6"/>
to Desire is to crosse them with Disdaine. Some say their
hearts are of Marble which being hard yet drops tears a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
euery storme: Some of waxe that is soft, admiting
euery impression, those women haue their loues in their
lookes, which taken in with a gase is thrust out with a
winke: Some of Adamant, they be hard hearted, and yet
men say the <hi>Lapidaries</hi> haue tooles to pierce them: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
of golde, and they be like <hi>Danae</hi> that will admit no
louer but such as <hi>Iupiter.</hi> To be briefe my boy, so many
fancies so many fictions, euery one censuring of womens
hearts as his owne experience hath found hir froward or
fauorable. <hi>Cupid</hi> hearing his mother discourse thus cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly
demanded amongest all these, whereof was <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias</hi>
heart of <hi>Rome</hi> formed: At this <hi>Venus</hi> fetching a déepe
sigh prosecuted hir former premisses thus. Well wag for
all you play the wanton, hast thou insight so far into thine
enemies thoughts that thou hast coted in thy tables the
resolution of <hi>Terentia,</hi> whom men count more beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
then my selfe, and more chast then <hi>Diana?</hi> Hir heart
my boy is framed of the purest Diamond, which as it is
hard to enterteine loue, so it is cleane, fit for the receit of
vertue: I tell thée <hi>Cupid Terentia</hi> makes Desire hir
drudge, and Disdaine hir Champion: Shée honors all the
Gods but thée, and admits all recreations but loue: Shée
armeth hir youth with Contempt of passions, that shée
may finish hir age with Content of patience: The prime
of hir yeares are graue that the fruits of hir time may be
gracious, and shée striues to be as full of honor in hir life,
as full of fauours in hir lookes. To conclude my boy shée
is <hi>Terentia,</hi> who séekes with labors to auoid loues, &amp; inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours
to be called as vertuous, as other Ladies amarous.
Thus <hi>Venus</hi> ended with a frowne and <hi>Cupid</hi> began with
a smyle, she scorning at hir honors he studying on reuenge.
after a little pause y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> choloricke boy burst foorth into these
tearmes: And shall <hi>Terentia</hi> offer perfumes to <hi>Vesta</hi> and
Hemblocke to <hi>Venus,</hi> shall shee mother strawe <hi>Dianaes</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:6220:7"/>
Lawnes with Roses and your Pallaces with Nettles?
shall shee set Desire in ragges and Disdaine in silkes? No,
<hi>Cupid</hi> hath his boults fethered with the winges of swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes
that flie swift, and his arrowes headed with strong
tempered stéele that pierce déepe, like to <hi>Achilles</hi> launce,
that did wound &amp; heale, my shaftes mother are of sundrie
mettels, the strongest of them all wil I aime at <hi>Terentia,</hi>
and if my fortune fayle me not I will change hir songes
to sighes and hir chast prayers to amorous passions. And
with that leaping from his mothers lappe hee bent his
bowe shott an arrowe and hit <hi>Terentia</hi> on the heart, but
it was of such proofe as the boult rebounded and brake
into a thousand shiuers. At this <hi>Cupid</hi> scorned séeing his
de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tie counterchect with such constant chastitie, &amp; <hi>Venus</hi>
smyled séeing hir sonne in such a rage: which so increased
his chollor that he discharged all his arrowes at randon,
carelesse of his aime so he might any wayes reuenge. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
the rest yong <hi>Lentulus</hi> a Romaine <hi>Caualier,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
whose conduct the consull sent manie legions to make
warre against the <hi>Parthians,</hi> was one of those infortunate
men that <hi>Cupid</hi> had brused with his arrowes. For hauing
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a set battell and bought the victorie with great
l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sse, fresh supplies were sent him from <hi>Rome. Lentulus</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lcoming his newe come souldiers, demaunded what:
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er they had made report of the state of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
wealth, they (then as a thing miraculous and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oursed to him the excellencie of <hi>Terentia,</hi> set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
out hir glories with such Emphaticall discriptions
t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>Lentulus</hi> leaning his head on his hand became a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
audit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r to such pleasa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t philosophie. Smiling thus
in the ouersweete potions that Loue had tempered like
<hi>Circes</hi> to bewitch the warie and warrelike <hi>Vlysses;</hi>
hee caused his Souldiers with often repetitions of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
beau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie to grafte in the syenus of hys newe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
sanci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. In the day his heade was troubled
with thoughts of <hi>Terentia:</hi> in the night conceit presented
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6220:7"/>
the visio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of <hi>Terentia.</hi> Where before he laid plots how to
circumuent the <hi>Parthians,</hi> now he deuised how to compasse
his passions: Loue wisht him to make light estéem of war,
but growing to be carelesse, he gaue his enemies occasion
of incourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Being thus perplexed with vnacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
fits, he began thus souldier like to debate with himself.
Haue not the auncient <hi>Romaines</hi> whose statues and tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phées
hath filled the world with wonder of their Chiualry
made the ende of their honours to consist in armes? haue
they not fetcht Fame from the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with their swords,
and bounde hir to their fortunes with circumscriptions of
bloud: haue not their launces pierst obliuion to the heart,
and their martiall déeds registred their names in the Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles
of memorie? and yet <hi>Lentulus</hi> dost thou make light
estéeme of war, whose very frownes are honor, and whose
fauors immortall glories? Blush at thy thoughts that are
so base, &amp; wéepe with <hi>Caesar</hi> that thou hast not done won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
with <hi>Alexander.</hi> Thou art elected by the Consuls as
a choise man of <hi>Rome,</hi> as high prised for thy valour, as thy
parentage, and yet thy mother was of the great <hi>Aemilij:</hi>
thou art sent against the <hi>Parthians,</hi> a Nation warrelicke
and resolute, either to challenge thy graue with thy sword
or carue out their tombes with thy Courtelax. Darest
thou then <hi>Lentulus</hi> amidst those glorious thoughts of a
souldier admit the least passion of a louer? shall thy polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
too little for the <hi>Parthians,</hi> be imployed in purchasing
<hi>Terentia?</hi> No <hi>Lentulus</hi> draw thy Fauchion, brandish it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<hi>Rome,</hi> and if Loue looke but ouer the walls menace
hir with thy Martiall weapons: and yet <hi>Lentulus</hi> be not
so stoicall as to reiect such a mightie Deitie. Haue not the
<hi>Romaines</hi> erected a Temple néere vnto <hi>Campus Martius?</hi>
Are not Knights dubbed to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Ladies? Make they not
their Helmes proude with their Mistresse fauours? <hi>Mars</hi>
hath his amours as he hath his armours: <hi>Alexander</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
in his loues as he triumpht in his victories? Great
<hi>Pompey</hi> hath his <hi>Iulia, Caesar</hi> his Paramour, Souldiers
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6220:8"/>
haue loued, and so will I. Hauing thus discoursed with
himselfe, the hope of his loues draue such an inuincible
courage into his minde that he past not many daies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
giuing battaile to the <hi>Parthians,</hi> in which getting a
glorious victorie, he sent great treasure and many Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues
home to <hi>Rome,</hi> with great intercession to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
that he might not winter from his owne Countrie.
The Consuls gald to fauour him with any reasonable
graunt, sent <hi>Lepidus</hi> to take his place, and recalled <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus</hi>
home to the Citie: The fame of whose high intended
thoughts, his conquest inlarged with infinite treasures &amp;
rich Captiues, made <hi>Rome</hi> to ring with ecchoes of his
matchlesse excellency: Insomuch that passing through the
stréets to the Capitol, there to be inuested with the honors
due to his victories, multitudes of <hi>Romanes</hi> were placed
on Scaffoldes to take view of so braue and hardie a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
and the gorgeous windowes of the Citie were stuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed
with troupes of beautiful Ladies tickled with an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest
desire to satisfie their sightes with his Personage.
Passing thus in pompe, <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> then being Dictator
after the solemne rites &amp; magnificent triumphs were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
bad him home to dinner, where hee feasted him with
such royaltie as might beséeme the greatnes of the day
and the highnes of his owne thoughts. Thus flewe the
fame of <hi>Lentulus</hi> through <hi>Rome</hi> as the wonder of this
time, but all those triumphant dignities coulde not extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate
the melancholy of this <hi>Romans</hi> thoughts inserted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
his minde by the fond inchantments of loue, but as the
wounded Deare wringeth forth teares, and the Mirtle
pierced yeeldeth Gumme, so <hi>Lentulus</hi> after this déepe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression
of loue, coulde afforde nought but sighes and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes.
The Iemme of <hi>Terentias</hi> excellencie reflected
in his minde like an obiect in a Christall myrrour that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>middest
his most serious affaires hée founde the passions
of loue to be intermedled. Fortune that had tied hir fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours
in the toppe of his Crest halfe perswaded to become
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6220:8"/>
constant to this warlicke Champion séeing <hi>Cupid</hi> wrong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
him without cause thought with a souereign Antidote to
preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> further ensuing preiudices of fancy: forcing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
oportunitie to dance attendance vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this hir darling,
it fell out y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Flaminius,</hi> the father of <hi>Terentia</hi> séeing howe
<hi>Lentulus</hi> was generally feasted of al y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> senators in <hi>Rome,</hi>
thought amongst y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rest, to welcome home y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> warrior with
a ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ket, &amp; therfore méeting him at one <hi>Titus Annius Milos</hi>
house, he solemnely inuited him home to dinner. <hi>Lentulus</hi>
as ful of curtesie as courage, after great thanks, promised
to be his guest, whereupon <hi>Flaminius</hi> passing home made
prouisio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; <hi>Lentulus</hi> stealing to his lodging being solitary,
conceiued such inward ioy at this swéete oportunitie, that
leaning vpon his left hand smiling to himself, he breathed
out these words: <hi>viz.</hi> Such I sée well as <hi>Mars</hi> honours
with fauours <hi>Venus</hi> will not crosse with frownes: those
that conquer in warres shall not perish in loues. <hi>Cupid</hi>
fauours his fathers followers, &amp; such as Fortune smiles
on in ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tail, shée laughs on in fancies. I coueted to beare
charge against the <hi>Parthians,</hi> and the Senate elected me
Lord of their Legions: Desire wisht me to haue a sight of
<hi>Terentia,</hi> and hir father interteines me for a guest: I made
conquest of mine enemies with the sword, and why may
I not win my loue with my loyaltie: Feare not <hi>Lentulus,</hi>
these concluded comparisons are prodigious, bee <hi>Augur</hi>
then to thy selfe, and calculate thy good fortunes by thy
thoughts: Loues and warres craues courage. Feare not
man, for thy intreaties are as mightie as hir denials can
be contrarie. As thus he was debating with himselfe the
Clocke tolde him it was time to goe visite his Host, so
that he made himselfe as sumptuous as might be, and at
the parting from his Chamber-dore hée saide thus. If
<hi>Venus</hi> (quoth hee) thou fauour mee in my loues, I
will become thy vowed seruant in my life: I will strewe
thy Altars with Roses, and set thée vp shrines at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos:</hi>
I wil binde vp my temples with myrtle bowes, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6220:9"/>
for the Martiall garland weare a wreath of flowers. I
wil haue Doues nests in my Pallaces, and what belongs
to thée, shall be some of my delight, onely grace me with
the fauour of <hi>Terentia.</hi> Ending this his vowe hee pased
forward with his traine towards the house of <hi>Flaminius,</hi>
where beeing ariued the graue Senator intertained him
with such magnificence, as <hi>Lentulus</hi> perceiued his wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
by his honours. The board couered and the company
readie to sit, <hi>Lentulus</hi> was placed chiefe at the table, who
all this while hauing no sight of <hi>Terentia,</hi> sat as a man
nipped on the heade, although there were at the table to
grace the feast manie braue &amp; beautifull Damosels. Sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
thus in a dumpe he was cheared vp by all the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,
but at last to set him in his iolitie, <hi>Terentia</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
by hir father to bring him in a cuppe of Gréekish
wine. Shée that little cared to be séene in open bankets as
holding it contrarie to the rites of <hi>Vesta,</hi> durst not yet but
with all diligence signifie hir obedience. Therfore attyred
in a rich roabe of white, spotted with starres of gold; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering
the porphury of hir face with a vermilion blush, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
like <hi>Diana</hi> when shée basht at <hi>Acteons</hi> presence, shée
came into the hall, where humbly saluting all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie,
shée deliuered the wine to hir father. <hi>Lentulus</hi> séeing
Fame had but blemisht hir fauours in being to partiall of
hir praises, sate so amased at the beauteous excellencie of
<hi>Terentia,</hi> as did the <hi>Centaure</hi> enamoured of <hi>Iuno.</hi> His eie
made suruey of hir beauties who posting them ouer to the
contemplation of his thoughts, so set on fire his heart with
hir perfections, as his stomacke shut vp hir Orifice, to giue
his eies leaue to wonder at the serious conceit of natures
cunning: his lookes beganne to sparkle loue as did those of
<hi>Adon</hi> when he pried vpon the face of his Paramour, the
change of his colour bewraied his newe entertained passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
which noted by <hi>Terentia</hi> half angry at loues folly, she
discouered hir collor with such ablush as <hi>Lentulus</hi> letting
fall his knyfe on his trencher saide aloude, <hi>Non fortuna
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6220:9"/>
non Bellum</hi> meaning that neither the highest state of
fortune nor the fatall intent of warre could conquere that
hart y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> her beautie hath made subiect. <hi>Terentia</hi> at this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected
exclamation abashed and the rest of the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
maruelled: but <hi>Flaminius</hi> willing to moue some table
talke demaunded of <hi>Lentulus</hi> what hee ment by this sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine
embleme. <hi>Lentulus,</hi> willing to make flight at the
foule and yet not to haue a bel at his héele, answered thus.
Whilst I lay in legar intrenching the <hi>Parthians</hi> more
hardly with legions of men then with déepe raised conter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mures,
my souldiers discouered a castle which once woone
displaced the strength of the countrie, séeing the <hi>Romanes</hi>
had made mee Uicegerente of their forces although the
place séemed impregnable béeing as well defended by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
situate vpon a mount, as by prowesse stored with
men and munitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet prising honor more déere then bloud,
and countries profite beyonde the content of life, I bent
certaine legions against the castle and following the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
of <hi>Quintus Fabius Maximus</hi> sought by delay to driue
them to composition. For it was said of him,
<q>
                  <l>Vnus homo nobis cunctando restituit rem,</l>
                  <l>Non ponebat enim rumores ante salutem,</l>
                  <l>Ergo post<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> magis<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> viri nunc gloria claret.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Séeking so to get conquest by famine which would haue
béen preiudiciall with the sword, at last séeing their forces
greatly weakened I gaue assault and entred putting the
souldiers to the sword yet willing to saue the Lorde of the
castle for that his valour discouered his thoughtes, sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
him out I found him in his bed chamber his wife
slaine and the blade yet varnished with bloud grasped in
his fist staring me in the face with a gastly looke, that stood
amazed at the stratageme he spake thus. <hi>Romain</hi> report
in the Senate house that where you excell vs in pollicie,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6220:10"/>
we excéede you in resolution, this Ladie which thou séest
here weltring in hir goore is my wife, and for she brokes
not seconde fancies, shee craued to ende hir loue with hir
life: I maried hir a virgine and honourable, shee dies a
wife and honest, as famous in <hi>Parthia</hi> for hir vertues, as
your Romayne Dames for their braue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies. Wee liued
without iarres, for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the desire of the one was the content
of the other, constancie banished ielousie and true loue
helde supition at the launces poynt. Our fortunes Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne
thou hast pulde downe, with thy prowesse warre
hath made wracke of our safeties, but for our loues this
sword shall linke them together by death, so that <hi>Non for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna,
non bellum.</hi> And with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the resolute souldier stabbed
himselfe. Astonied at this peremptorie massacre, although
all stained with the bloud of the <hi>Parthians:</hi> yet I could not
but grieue at the passion of the man, and enter into consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
what that Loue should be, that wrought in mens
mindes such resolued effects: So well liking of his deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
death, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I vowed in my thoughts if euer I obteined
the fauour of some gracious Damosell to write in bloude
with the <hi>Parthian, Non fortuna, non bellum.</hi> The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
(honorable Senatours) of this tragedie made me
to shew my selfe so passionate. <hi>Lentulus</hi> hauing ended his
discourse, the Senatours generally praised the resolution
of the <hi>Parthian,</hi> and the Ladies the constancie of his wife,
all concluding that no impression could be so déepely inser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
into the heart loue. <hi>Terentia</hi> spying the flame by the
smoake, smyled to sée howe couertly <hi>Lentulus</hi> had cloaked
his thoughts, and how in vowing to be constant, he disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
his conceit, so that turning hir backe shée went into
hir Closet, and there blamed <hi>Venus</hi> that had wrapt so
br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue a Champion in hir subtleties: not féeling either the
personage or perfections of <hi>Lentulus</hi> to stirre the staied
continencie of hir minde. Well the Senators not willing
to let this fall to the grounde, talked still of the <hi>Parthian,</hi>
and amongst the rest of those honourable guests that were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6220:10"/>
there feasted, <hi>Archias</hi> the Poet a man of a pleasant dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition,
tooke the tale by the ende, and beganne to prosecute
it thus.</p>
            <p>Graue Senatours I remember I haue heard <hi>Horten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus</hi>
the great Orator say, that in times past the Consuls
for recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would vse light &amp; honest pastimes especially
myrth at meat, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fittest minister for digestio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, alleaging
<hi>Scipio</hi> &amp; <hi>Gracchus,</hi> who coueted to be as iocund at their
banquets, as they were serious in matters of estate. Sée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
then (reuerend fathers) <hi>Lentulus</hi> hath entred into
the discourse of loue, producing the <hi>Parthian,</hi> who amongst
his other singularities, boasted that his fancie had neuer
béene stained with Iealousie a plague that is greatly now
a daies predominant in <hi>Rome,</hi> might it please you to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
vs with your gracious consent, we woulde intreate
<hi>Lentulus</hi> to discourse to vs his opinion of iealousie. The
Senatours graunted, and <hi>Terentia,</hi> being come to giue
attendance on hir father, smyled. <hi>Lentulus</hi> casting his eie
vpon his loue, séeing a dimple in hir chéeke which was to
him <hi>Cos amoris,</hi> made <hi>Archias</hi> this present answere.</p>
            <p>Had the <hi>Thebans</hi> appointed <hi>Zetus</hi> to haue discoursed of
Musicke, or they of <hi>Thessaly, Menalcas</hi> to haue described
the Court: The principles of the one had béene as voide
of art, as the precepts of the other farre from honour: The
one being an enemie to Musicke, the other a swaine and
a shepheard. So (reuerend Senatours and honourable La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
of <hi>Rome) Archias,</hi> how skilfull so euer in Poetrie, yet
hath faild in his pollicie, to request him to discourse of iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie,
that neuer as yet offred incence at the Altars of
Loue. If it had béene to make description of a battaile, to
haue discoursed the order of the Phalaux, or any point of
Martiall discipline, then could I as a souldier haue dilated
such principles, as warrelike Captaines register in the
field with their sword: But of loue whose amarous Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
gréeth not with Drumme and Trumpet, or of iealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie
as the shadowe of fancie, it fitteth me as little to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6220:11"/>
as the shoomaker of <hi>Apelles</hi> portrature. But if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<hi>Venus</hi> shall vouch me that fauour to grace me with a
speciall looke from my Mistresse excellencie, and that mine
eie be allowed as <hi>Paris</hi> was to iudge of beauties, <hi>Archias</hi>
shal commande me as a friend, in the meane time, for Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets
and Painters ought to haue their conceites fethered
with <hi>Mercuries</hi> plumes: I will desire <hi>Archias</hi> to supply
my ignorance, and to describe the effects of iealousie. The
Senators and the rest of the company, hearing how cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly
<hi>Lentulus</hi> retorted the argument vppon <hi>Archias,</hi>
with a resolute consent they inioyned <hi>Archias</hi> to play the
Orator, who being pleasantly disposed began thus.</p>
            <p>The wolues in <hi>Syria</hi> that barke against the Moone suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
small rest and great hunger. Arrowes shot against the
starres pierce downeward: and the <hi>Syrens</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought to
intrappe <hi>Vlisses,</hi> perisht themselues. So gentlemen, I
sought to make experience of <hi>Lentulus</hi> eloquence, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
hath allotted me to discouer mine owne ignorance,
but least I might be counted either too stoicall, or to too full
of sel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e conceit: for iealousie, thus.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="unk">
                  <body>
                     <div type="discourse">
                        <head>Archias discourse of Iealousie.</head>
                        <p>SUch as haue searched into the déepest Aphorismes of
<hi>Anacreon,</hi> or pried into the principles that <hi>Ouid</hi> sette
downe in his volumes, find Loue to be such a pure passion
of the mind, as like y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Christal it admitteth no bruse with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
a cracke: It groweth from the vnion of two minds co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> special liking of some excellent good, consisting
in exteriour beauty, or interiour vertues, or the combining
of them both in one sole, and singular perfection. This
choice of excellencie confirmed by election once imprinted
in the hart is so pretious as the pearls of <hi>Cleopatra.</hi> The
fléece of <hi>Colchos,</hi> the sands of <hi>Tagus</hi> are trash, if brought
into compare with this diuine and metaphysicall passion:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6220:11"/>
man hauing swilled in this nectar of loue is so chary that
he not onely brooketh no corriual of his thoughtes, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth
no partaker of his fauours, and from this feare
procéedeth that furie which men call ielousie, béeing a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete
suspition that others shoulde enioy that excellencie
that he hath chosen sole and singular to him self. This no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Romaines is that f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>end that <hi>Pluto</hi> sent to checke <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid</hi>
in his deitie, this springing from hell bringeth worse
torments to the minde then the stone of <hi>Sysiphus,</hi> vulture
of <hi>Titius</hi> or wheele of <hi>Ixion.</hi> This is the cankar that fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
the quiet of the thoughtes, the moath that secretlie
consumeth the life of man, and the poyson specially oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
against the perfection of loue: after the heart be once
infected with ielousie the slepes are broken, the dreames
disquiet slumbers, the thoughts cares, &amp; sorrowes, the life
woe, &amp; miserie, that lyuing he dies, &amp; dying prolonges out
his life in passions worse then death. None looketh on
his loue but suspition sayes, this is he that couetes to be
corriuall of my fauours: None <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ckes at his doore, but
starting vp he thinkes them messengers of fancie, none
talkes but they whisper of affection: if shée frowne, shée
hates him and loues others, if she smile it is because shée
hath had successe in hir loues, looke she frowardly on any
man she dissembles, if shee fauour him with a gratious
eye, then as a man straught with frensie hee eryeth out
that neither fire in the strawe nor loue in the womens
lookes can be concealed, thus doth he liue restles and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
loue that of it selfe is swéete, to be in taste as bitter
as gall.</p>
                        <p>This discouereth reuerent Senators that loue being of
it selfe a most excellent passion is onely blemisht by this
soule and disgraced staine of ielousie; as hateful and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
to the mind as the Cockatrice to the eye, or hemlocke
to the taste. The purest Chrisolite hath his strakes, the
flowers in <hi>Sydon</hi> as they are pretious in the sight so they
are pestilent in fauour: Loue as it is diuine with loialtie,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6220:12"/>
so it is hellish with ielousie, wherfore by an auncient Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et
were written these verses,
<q>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>When Gods had framd the sweete of womens face,</l>
                                 <l>and lockt mens lookes within their golden haire:</l>
                                 <l>That Phoebus blusht to see their matchles grace,</l>
                                 <l>and heauenly gods on earth did make repaire.</l>
                                 <l>To quippe faire Venus ouerweening pride</l>
                                 <l>Loues happie thoughtes to ielousie were tied.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Then grewe a wrinckle on faire Venus browe,</l>
                                 <l>The amber sweete of loue was turnd to gall:</l>
                                 <l>Gloomie was heauen: bright Phoebus did auowe</l>
                                 <l>He could be coy and would not loue at all,</l>
                                 <l>Swering no greater mischiefe could be wrought</l>
                                 <l>Then loue vnited to a ielous thought.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </q>
                        </p>
                        <p>Had not <hi>Iuno</hi> béen ielous ouer <hi>Iupiter, Io</hi> had not béene
turned into a Heifer: if suspition had not prickt <hi>Menela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,
Helena</hi> had not stolne away with <hi>Paris. Procris</hi> had
beene aliue, had shée not suspected <hi>Cephalus:</hi> Then wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
Romaines we sée what a preiudiciall monster grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
from the fearefull excesse of loue that not onely short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
the life, disquieteth the minde, but oft is the cause of
most strange and vnnatural massacres. If fortune frowne
in loue we flie to patience: If their happen iarres, why
louers braw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es are introductions to delight, If pouertie,
why they hope vpon time thinking that there is <hi>vicissitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do
omnium rerum,</hi> The lowest ebbe may haue his flow,
and the deadest néepe his full tyde, if gréefes, sorrowes,
repulse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, vnkindenes, these bee but <hi>Amantium irae:</hi> And
t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ore <hi>Amoris redintegratio:</hi> but as the pumice stone
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> the paper from spots, and the fire consumeth fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e so
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>is in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ernall plague of iealousi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> rooteth &amp; raceth all true
loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> the heart, that yéelding my censure I conclude
with this Poeme,</p>
                        <lg>
                           <pb n="15" facs="tcp:6220:12"/>
                           <l>Vita quae tandem magis est iucunda,</l>
                           <l>Vel viris doctis magis expetenda,</l>
                           <l>Mente quam pura sociam iugalem,</l>
                           <l>Semper amare?</l>
                           <l>Vita quae tandem magis est dolenda,</l>
                           <l>Vel magis cunctis fugienda, quam quae,</l>
                           <l>(Falso suspecta probitate amicae)</l>
                           <l>Tollit amorem?</l>
                           <l>Nulla eam tollit medicina pestem,</l>
                           <l>Murmur, emplastrum vel imago sagae,</l>
                           <l>Astra nec curant, magicae nec artes,</l>
                           <l>Zelotipiam.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Archias</hi> hauing thus ended his discourse the Senators
greatly praised his description of iealousie, and from that
fell to other pleasant talke as occasion offred. Till dinner
being ended they arose, and after many thankes and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesies
according to the custome of the <hi>Romanes, Flaminius</hi>
to honour <hi>Lentulus</hi> the more, taking him by the hand car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
him into a garden where <hi>Terentia</hi> sate accompanied
with other Uirgins of <hi>Roome:</hi> namely, <hi>Flauia, Cornelia,</hi>
and <hi>Iulia,</hi> all of such exquisite features, as they séemed to
be the choyce Paragons of that time. <hi>Lentulus</hi> amazed at
this gorgious sight wondred not onely at their beauties,
but maruailed why <hi>Flaminius</hi> brought him so friendly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
their presence. At last the old man burst forth into these
words: Lord <hi>Lentulus,</hi> I measure the thoughts of young
gentlemen by the prime of my forepassed youth, not being
so cinicall as with <hi>Chremes</hi> in <hi>Terence</hi> to proportion
young affections by the cynders of olde age, but to thinke
with <hi>Menedemus</hi> that the spring hath flowers and blos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somes,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6220:13"/>
where as winter hath dried braunches and tawnie
leaues: We olde men ouer whom <hi>Saturnus</hi> is predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
hauing infused melancholy in our mindes, couet ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to sit solitarie, or that our talke be serious: you that
are young whose thoughts aime at delight séeke to passe
the time in pleasant discourses. Least therefore the time
might be tedious, I haue brought you amongst these faire
Ladies y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> you may make experience of loues, as you haue
done of warres, <hi>Mars</hi> no sooner puts off his helmet but he
salutes <hi>Venus:</hi> and you come from conquest of the <hi>Parthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
see how you can enter combate with passions: and so
Lord <hi>Lentulus</hi> I leaue you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lentulus</hi> seeing himself thus enuironed with these mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles
of beautie, casting his eye vpon the Goddesse whose
fauourable aspect might be the summe of his fortunes, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
at the first as <hi>Paris</hi> did in the vale of <hi>Ida,</hi> and stoode as
the foes of <hi>Perseus</hi> when hee vncased the head of <hi>Medusa,</hi>
and turned them to marble pictures, so amazed stood <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus</hi>
at the sight of such diuine excellencie, till the Ladies
seeing this Nouice thus in a quandarie beganne to smile,
which reuiuing a kind of amorous choller in the souldiers
minde, he beganne thus to play the Champion.</p>
            <p>Ladies beléeue me, Loue is of more force then warres,
and the lookes of women pierce déeper then the stroke of
Launces, their is no Curtelax so kéene, but armour of
high proofe can withstande, but beauties arrowes are so
sharpe, and the dartes that flie from womens eyes so pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
as the Corslet tempered by <hi>Vulcan</hi> for <hi>Didoes</hi> para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour,
holdes not out the violence of there stroake. The
Gods tremble when <hi>Mars</hi> shaketh his Launce, but he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
when <hi>Venus</hi> casteth a frowne. <hi>Alexander</hi> neuer tooke
notice of the legions of his enemies, but he stoode frighted
at the beauty of the <hi>Amazon.</hi> Then swéet saints of <hi>Rome</hi>
maruell not if I were driuen into a maze at the sight of
such beauteous creatures whose faces are <hi>Venus</hi> wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons,
wherewith shée checketh the pride of ouer daring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6220:13"/>
warriours: I cannot (Ladies) court it as your Romaine
yongsters that tie their wits to their fancies: nor fil your
eares with amarous discourses as <hi>Cupids</hi> Apprentizes,
that spend their time in such louing philosophie: Nor can
I faine conceited supposes of affection to prooue my selfe
louesicke by Poetrie. But as a blunt souldier newe come
from the warres, I offer my selfe a deuoted seruant to
your beauties, swearing to defend your honours against
all men with the hazard of my bloud, and in pawne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
generally to you all, but specially to one (as loue hath
his vnitie) I desire to bee intertained as a duetifull
seruaunt to the Lady <hi>Terentia. Lentulus</hi> hauing thus
boldly boarded these louely Uirgins, the Ladies séeing
with what affection he offred his seruice to <hi>Terentia,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
to byte the lippe, and shée to blush who séeing hir selfe
toucht to the quicke made him this answere.</p>
            <p>I know not Lord <hi>Lentulus</hi> how to answere of loue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
as yet I neuer knew loue: ignorant of his forces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
neuer acquainted with his fortunes. <hi>Vesta</hi> forbids
vs virgins to name <hi>Venus,</hi> as they of <hi>Ephesus</hi> hatefull
<hi>Erostratus. Diana</hi> deals not in <hi>Paphos,</hi> nor suffers shée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of hir maidens to hunt on <hi>Erecynus,</hi> least méeting
with <hi>Venus</hi> mecocks they skippe with <hi>Calisto,</hi> and so séek
after losse. The lesse you are priuate to loues passions, the
more welcome to our presence: for rather had we still our
eares with warres fortunes, then with loues f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llies: and
swéeter are the teares that grows from a constant strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme,
then a smyle from a comike tale of fancie. For your
seruice Lord <hi>Lentu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> finding my self vnworthy, I craue
pardon: Nor can wee by <hi>Vestas</hi> charter admitte such ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts.
But if it please you to bee accepted as a worthy
<hi>Romaine</hi> and my fathers friende, looke for such fauour as
mine honour and virginity can affoord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lentulus</hi> hearing the plausible answere of <hi>Terentia,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
hir first insinuation seemed to answere for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
as preferring the lawnes of <hi>Diana,</hi> and fiers of <hi>Vesta</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:6220:14"/>
before loues holy temples, yet shée concluded so swéetely as
might stand with the modestie of hir honour: he therefore
made thus his reply.</p>
            <p>In that madame we are both nouices in loue, the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler
are our thoughts, and the néerer should be the simpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
of our affections. Doues match <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey are young:
Syenus are grafted when they are sprigs, the one part
not but by death, nor are the other seuered but they perish.
Souldiers are like virgins, the one striuing to liue vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
the other to die valiant: both enemies to loue, while
they wait on those which brooke not loue, I meane warre
and <hi>Vesta:</hi> But both must loue as hauing hearts and
thoughts, eies to sée beautie, and eares to iudge of vertue.
I madame while I thought none greater then <hi>Mars,</hi> was
vowed to <hi>Mars,</hi> but séeing womens wits are worse then
weapons, and that their lookes pierce déeper then launces,
I haue resigned ouer my fortunes at the shrine of warre,
and meane to make proofe of the swéetenesse of loue: Glad
that in my first entrance I haue the patronage of your
gracious fauour, armde with the which <hi>Mars</hi> well may
frowne, but not conquer. But sir, quoth <hi>Terentia,</hi> I graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
my fauor to <hi>Lentulus</hi> the souldier, not to <hi>Lentulus</hi> the
louer. And so madame quoth he I accept of it, for I am a
souldier to doe you honour, and a louer despight of my self.
<hi>Flauia</hi> hearing <hi>Lentulus,</hi> beganne to reason pretily to the
purpose, being a Ladie of passing mirry disposition, whose
witte was as full of wiles as hir face of fauour, second in
the excellencie of beauty to the Lady <hi>Terentia,</hi> thought to
sift hir souldier in this manner.</p>
            <p>I sée well Lord <hi>Lentulus,</hi> that as women haue their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours,
so men haue their sayings: the one prodigall in gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
the other polliticke in deceits, being as cunning to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble
loue, as we chary to discharge loue. We Romaine
Ladies thought to haue founde you a flat souldier, as ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
in loues as we of fancies: but how closely soeuer
you couer the flame, the fire wil be knowne by the smoke:
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6220:14"/>
For your talke so sauours of loues principles, as we iudg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
you are as cunning in faining a passion as in figuring a
battaile, and can assoone deceiue a woman with a pen, as
slaughter an enemie with a launce. This will make vs
to take you for a day friend, and what we like in you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
to disallowe to morrowe, swearing if you bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
vs <hi>Venus</hi> roses, wee will beate you with <hi>Vestas</hi>
nettles: and therefore if you will be admitted as our soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier,
wee either forbidde you the name of loue, or else you
shall be out of our fauours. <hi>Cornelia</hi> willing to breake a
iest with this Champion thwarted <hi>Flauia</hi> thus. And what
of that madame, hath not warre taught him patience: hee
hath past sharper brunts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> womens frownes. But how
your leuell is without aime? If madame <hi>Terentia</hi> smyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
his peny is good siluer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is hir fauour that is the load-star
of his fortunes, and howe can we enter into hir thoughts
but by coniectures: shée ful of beauty, and he a proper yong
gentleman. At this frumpe the Ladies smiled, and <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>
blusht for anger. But <hi>Lentulus</hi> séeing such a broad iest,
pinde on his shoulder willing to make answere for his
Mistresse, although he was sore put to his trumps as half
set at a <hi>Non plus,</hi> yet he followed his fortunes thus.</p>
            <p>Indéede Ladies thinke I haue patience to beare wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens
frumpes that hath incountred an enemies blow, but
if I could as well answere the one, as quit the other, you
shuld neither carry it to hel, nor to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But to reuenge
my selfe as well as I can, thus. First madame to cleare
my cunning in loue, I refer my selfe to the verdict of your
owne conscience: who were you but as fauourable, as you
are frumpish, would soone censure by my talke how déepe I
am reade in loues principles. But women speake by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries,
crying like the lapwing farthest from their nests,
and so I take it being checkt for ouermuch loue, when you
sée I am a nouice in loue. Or perhaps madame <hi>Flauia</hi> you
would haue me loue, if it be so I will become more stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
to satisfie your wish: but your calling mee a day
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6220:15"/>
friend that peremptory punishment were passing sharpe
for one fault to shake me out of seruice, were it not that
for so déepe a wound the Lady <hi>Cornelia</hi> bringeth in a leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue
plaisture alleadging my security if I bee armed with
<hi>Terentias</hi> fauour. Blame mee not swéete goddesses if I
aime at the fairest, souldiers haue eies that can iudge of
beauty, though they haue not weapons to winne beauty:
&amp; eares to déeme of perfections, though they want tongues
to discouer passions. The harmony of loue, I haue hearde
them say, consists in vnities, and nothing is more preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
to fancie then plurality either of thoughtes or of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.
Amongst many then am I charged but to like of one
Mistresse: If I make choice of <hi>Terentia,</hi> and shee vouch to
grace me with hir fauour, <hi>Cornelia</hi> concludes truely, that
armde with the imagination of hir beauty, I thinke my
selfe able to brooke your frumps, and to withstand the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
resolution of <hi>Mars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I maruaile then quoth <hi>Flauia</hi> halfe in choller (if wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens
beauty be like <hi>Delphicus gladius,</hi> of high proofe to
defend, and of sharpe edge to offend) why the Senatours
choose not out legions of Ladies, that with little cost and
great assurance, they may make conquest of the world:
but perhaps all souldiers be not of your temper, for they
vse their weapons and you your lookes.</p>
            <p>No madame quoth <hi>Lentulus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is not the cause, for were
it not that euery woman would be a Captaine, and striue
for supremacie, they had resolued vpon this long agoe, but
fearing a mutiny amongst themselues for superiority: sith
euery one at home wil be counted most wise, &amp; most beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull,
though their wits be meane, and fauours lesse, the
Senate are glad to foresée such an inconuenience. The
Ladies hearing howe cunningly <hi>Lentulus</hi> had gald ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame
<hi>Flauia</hi> on the right side, began all to smyle, and shée
after a blush for very anger began to laugh. <hi>Lentulus</hi> glad
that he had giuen hir a soppe of the same sauce, and paide
hir hir debt in hir owne coine: Calling to his boy to fetch
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6220:15"/>
him a Lute, willing to shew his mistresse he was not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
in musicke, said he would prooue the force of beauty
by a sonet which he heard was made by <hi>Orpheus</hi> when
he fell first in loue with <hi>Euridice,</hi> tuning therefore his
Lute to his voyce he sung this ditty.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Mars in a fury gainst Loues brightest Queene</l>
               <l>Put on his helme, and tooke him to his launce:</l>
               <l>On Erecynus mount was Mauors seene,</l>
               <l>And there his ensignes did the God aduaunce.</l>
               <l>And by heauens greatest gates he stowtly swore,</l>
               <l>Venus should die for shee had wrongd him sore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Cupid heard this and he began to cry,</l>
               <l>And wisht his mothers absence for a while:</l>
               <l>Peace foole quoth Venus, is it I must die?</l>
               <l>Must it be Mars? with that shee coind a smile:</l>
               <l>Shee trimd hir tresses and did curle hir haire,</l>
               <l>And made hir face with beauty passing faire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A fan of siluer feathers in hir hand,</l>
               <l>And in a coach of Ebony shee went:</l>
               <l>Shee past the place where furious Mars did stand,</l>
               <l>And out hir lookes a louely smile she sent.</l>
               <l>Then from hir brow lept out so sharpe a frowne,</l>
               <l>That Mars for feare threw all his armour downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He vowed repentance for his rash misdeede,</l>
               <l>Blaming his choller that had causd his woe:</l>
               <l>Venus grew gratious, and with him agreed,</l>
               <l>But chargd him not to threaten beauty so.</l>
               <l>For womens lookes are such inchaunting charmes,</l>
               <l>As can subdue the greatest god in armes.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Lentulus</hi> hauing sung this ditty, <hi>Terentia</hi> willing a
little to shew hir wit began thus. I remember Lord <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:6220:16"/>
I haue heard my father say that souldiers were
w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt to carry fauours in their helmes, not fancies in
their heart: and made choice of their mistresse to incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
their thoughts, not to inchaunt their affections. But
I see the auncient hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur of the <hi>Romaines</hi> is slipt from
prowesse to passions, and the men couet to be counted ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
amorous wooers, then hardy warriours: gasing <hi>Mars</hi>
in the face with bright armour, but offring Orisons to
<hi>Venus</hi> in secrete conceites. This did not <hi>Quintus Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius
Cincinnatus,</hi> who sette it downe as <hi>Crimen Capitale</hi>
to speake of loue in the Armie. Nor <hi>Scypio Affricanus</hi>
the greate who made lawes that no women shoulde bee
brought prisoners within the Campe, least loue entring
pele mele with war might hazard y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> haughtines of their
houors: And yet madame quoth <hi>Lentulus Cyncinnatus</hi>
ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a wife, and <hi>Scipio</hi> was marrieed. But quoth shée it
was in their age rather chosen for succours then amarous
passions: their youth was wholy spent in warres as ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
to loues, counting fancie as a dishonour to their
martiall dignities: rightly in déede with a déepe insight
entring int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he enormities that growe from following
to precisely the court of <hi>Venus.</hi> For beléeue me gentleman
Poets and Painters erre much that ascribe a dei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y to
<hi>Cupid,</hi> and were worthy to beare some gréeuous punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt
for such a newe inuented heresie, which I will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oue
with a Sonet that one of <hi>Dyanas</hi> nymphes made
w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en <hi>Iupiter</hi> had faulted with <hi>Calipso.</hi> And so <hi>Terentia</hi>
taking the Lute in hir hand beganne to warble out this
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oundelet.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Fond faining Poets make of Loue a God,</l>
               <l>And leaue the Lawrell for the myrtle boughes:</l>
               <l>When Cupid is a childe not past the rod,</l>
               <l>And faire Diana Daphnis most allowes.</l>
               <l>Ile weare the bayes and call the wag a boy,</l>
               <l>And thinke of Loue but as a foolish toy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:6220:16"/>
               <l>Some giue him bowe and quiuer at his backe,</l>
               <l>Some make him blinde to aime without aduise:</l>
               <l>When naked wretch such feathred bolts he lacke,</l>
               <l>And sight he hath but cannot wrong the wise.</l>
               <l>For vse but labours weapon for defence,</l>
               <l>And Cupid like a Coward flieth thence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He is God in Court but cottage cals him childe,</l>
               <l>And Vestas virgins with their holy fires:</l>
               <l>Doe cleanse the thoughts that fancie hath defilde,</l>
               <l>And burnes the pallace of his fond desires.</l>
               <l>With chast disdaine they scorne the foolish god,</l>
               <l>And prooue him but a boy not past the rod.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Terentia</hi> hauing ended hir roundelay, as <hi>Lentulus</hi> was
ready to replie, <hi>Flaminius</hi> came into y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Garden with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rest
of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> senators, whose graue prese<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce brake of their amorous
prattle, so y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he leauing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ladies taking his leaue friendly
of them all, but specially with a pittiful glancing looke of
<hi>Terentia</hi> as crauing some fauour for his farewell, hee
went to the Senatours amongst whom he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>coursed long
of the maner and custome of the <hi>Parthians,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
in warres, and of such serious matters concerning
martiall discipline. Passing thus away part of the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone,
the company at last taking their leaues yeelding
great thankes to <hi>Flaminius</hi> for their good chée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to their seuerall mansions. <hi>Lentulus</hi> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ipping from the
rest of the companie and with a gratious courage tooke
his adue of <hi>Terentia</hi> and the other of the Ladies, vowing
to be theirs euer in any due honourable seruice, and so
staying <hi>Terentia</hi> by the hande he went home with <hi>Titus
Annius Milo:</hi> where he founde <hi>Marcus Tullius Cicero,</hi>
then a youth in <hi>Rome</hi> about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age of twenty yeres &amp; very
priuate and familiar with <hi>Milo.</hi> The fame of this <hi>Tullies</hi>
surpassing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>loquence was so bruted abroade in <hi>Rome</hi> as
they counted him the myrror of that time &amp; as in <hi>Greece</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:6220:17"/>
they wondred at <hi>Demosthenes</hi> for his orations, and the
popular people fedde their eies with his sight, so as <hi>Tully</hi>
past through the stréets they cryed out, <hi>Hic est ille Cicero:</hi>
saying that as <hi>Orpheus</hi> with his musicke made the stones
and trees pliant to his melody: so <hi>Tully</hi> tyed the peoples
cares to his tongue by his eloquence: And that <hi>Plato</hi> who
for his philosophicall sentences was called diuine, in
whose lippes bées rested as presaging his future excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
was inferiour to <hi>Tully</hi> in the musicall concord of his
phrase. <hi>Lentulus</hi> noting his perfections although his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage
was base, yet thinking his eloquence might be
profitable to his loues, grewe to bee very familiar with
<hi>Tully,</hi> insomuch that of vnacquainted citizens they grew
to be deare and priuate friends, that their thoughts were
vnited with a sure league of amity, and their hearts were
receptacles for their mutuall passions, so that their most
secrete affaires were frankely participated without any
doubting suspition. But leauing their familliarity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersing
in <hi>Milos</hi> house: Let vs gentlemen sée how <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>
brookt his departure. <hi>Cornelius Nepos</hi> forgets it in
<hi>Tullies</hi> life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> if you will beléeue me it was thus.</p>
            <p>No sooner were the Senatours and <hi>Lentulus</hi> departed
from <hi>Flaminius</hi> house, but <hi>Flauia</hi> and the rest of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
tooke leaue of <hi>Terentia,</hi> who being solitary by hir selfe
sitting alone in an arbour of roses, began to ruminate on
the <hi>Idaea</hi> of <hi>Lentulus</hi> perfection, and to call to minde his
seueral and singular qualities, his parentage, his person,
honors, and his great possessions, but all in vaine. Loues
poyson was preuented with an antidote, and hir thoughts
sealed vp with an inuincible chastity. For after shée had
long sate: At last with a smyle shée burst foorth into these
tearmes.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Venus</hi> could not infuse more dismall aspects in other
Ladies thoughts then into my minde, they should neither
hold hir as a goddesse, nor honour hir temples with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents:
Fonde are those women that are inquisitiue after
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6220:17"/>
Astrologers, whether <hi>Venus</hi> be retrograde or combust in
their natiuities. Had they but tasted the swéete fauour of
<hi>Vestas</hi> incense, they would abandon hir as a planet care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
in their natiuities: and not trouble the Augurs or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruspices
to censure of their fatall or fortunate fancies. For
had they but insight into the swéete life of virgins, how se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
they liue, if they liue vertuous, they woulde neuer
intangle themselues with the inconstant snares of fancy.
<hi>Vesta</hi> allowes vs frée thoughts, <hi>Venus</hi> disquiet passions<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
at hir Altars we haue swéete s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>éepes, in the others pallace
broken slumbers. <hi>Diana</hi> counteruailes our labours with
myrth and quiet, in <hi>Cipres</hi> we finde toyle tempered with
care and sorrowes. Being virgins we haue liberty: mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
we tie our selues to the variable disposition of a hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
who be he neuer so excellent in perfection, or exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site
in proportion, we shall finde sufficient whereof to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ike. Then <hi>Terentia,</hi> let <hi>Lentulus</hi> passe with his
honors he hath subdued. What though <hi>Alexander</hi> woone
the whole world, his glories are but fortunes fauours. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
him then onely as thou promised, thy fathers friend
and thine as farre as he treats not of weddi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and with
this vpon a sodaine shée start vp, and went to passe away
the time amongst companie, holding <hi>Cupids</hi> deity at dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine,
and accounting of loue as the <hi>Samnites</hi> did of golde:
which they sent as presents to their enemies, but banisht
from their owne common wealth. But <hi>Flauia</hi> poore Lady,
was not pierced with so easie a passion, for shée hauing
more déepely imprinted in hir thoughtes his honours and
vertues, and measuring the man by the height of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes,
fell into these bitter complaints.</p>
            <p>With what little proportion doth iniurious Loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowe
his fauours? With howe small regarde doth blinde
fortune powre out hir treasures? Making in all their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
contrarieties. that so they may triumph in inconstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.
Loue hath brought <hi>Lentulus</hi> from the wars to <hi>Rome,</hi>
onely to sée <hi>Terentia.</hi> Fortune hath brought <hi>Flauia</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:6220:18"/>
to the house of <hi>Flaminius</hi> onely to loue <hi>Lentulus,</hi> shée little
regarding him, he lightly respecting me. Thus hath the
contrariety of loue and fortune made <hi>Lentulus</hi> vnhappy,
and me without hope. Ah but <hi>Terentia</hi> though shée séeme
coy at the first, will bee more curteous at the last, when
shée hath had but a moneths meditating on the excellency
of <hi>Lentulus.</hi> Then, oh then sigh <hi>Flauia,</hi> and say oh then wil
<hi>Terentia</hi> not reiect so honourable a personage: When shée
considers his youth, his beauty, his parentage, his digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<hi>Lentulus</hi> no sooner shall wooe, but shée will be woonne:
This is the coniecture of hir hap, &amp; the dispaire of my hope.
And yet it may be that the destinies haue appointed their
disagrée. For starres are sticklers in loue, and fates are
principall fautors of wedlocke. If my prayers may serue
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>Venus,</hi> if my incense to <hi>Cupid,</hi> if my vowes to <hi>Lucina,</hi>
if my sute to Loue. Let their loue perish in the budde, and
wither in the blossoms. Had I <hi>Medeas</hi> magicke, the drugs
of <hi>Calipso,</hi> the inchauntments of <hi>Cyrces,</hi> the skill of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,</hi>
all these should be imployed to breake the loue of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia,</hi>
and <hi>Lentulus.</hi> Fond <hi>Flauia,</hi> to be so franticke in thy
passions: suppose <hi>Terentia</hi> hated <hi>Lentulus,</hi> can this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
he wil loue thée? No, his thoughts are setled, his rest
set downe, his vowes made, his fancy fixed, &amp; all vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
beautiful <hi>Terentia:</hi> I there <hi>Flauia</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> galleth to
the beautifull <hi>Terentia.</hi> For of such surpassing beauty is
the Lady, that as <hi>Cynthia</hi> brookes no compare with hir
glorious brother: so thou must not enter comparison with
y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> daughter of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Senatour <hi>Flaminius.</hi> But what is this to
<hi>Lentulus.</hi> If shée be faire, yea as faire as euer was <hi>Sulpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia:</hi>
if shée be as coy, and disdainefull as <hi>Caelia,</hi> had he not
better loue homely <hi>Flauia,</hi> who will counteruaile with
loue, what shée wants in beautie, and proportion out in
duety, what shée defects in dignity. But what of this, loue
admits no exceptions, he cannot mis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught in <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi>
Doth not present examples yea instances executed in
<hi>Roome</hi> auerre so much? Is not <hi>Anthonio</hi> enamoured of
the blacke Egyptian <hi>Cleopatra:</hi> Doth not <hi>Caesar</hi> enuy
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6220:18"/>
him in his loues and couets to be corriuall of his fancies.
Affection is oft blinde and déemeth not rightlie, The blac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest
<hi>Ebon</hi> is brighter then the whitest Iuorie: and <hi>Venus</hi>
thought <hi>Vulcan</hi> at the first a proper stripling. Were <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia</hi>
neuer so coy, <hi>Lentulus</hi> will count hir disdaine but
chastitie: yet <hi>Flauia</hi> pray then she may liue in this mislike,
then hast thou yet some cause to hope, otherwise wéepe
thy fill, dispaire and then die, for swéeter is death then to
liue and sée <hi>Lentulus</hi> enioy the loue of <hi>Terentia.</hi> Hauing
at this period breathed awhile readie to goe forwarde in
passions, one of hir waiting women came in who brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
of hir complaintes past away the rest of the day in
prattle. Leauing hir therfore and hir maide at chat, again
to <hi>Lentulus,</hi> who tooke such inwarde griefe at this newe
conceited loue, that his colour began to waxe pale and to
discouer passions his sighes many and often to bewray
his sorrows, his sodayne startes in his sléepes, and his
musinges surcharged with melancholie. These noted by
<hi>Tullie</hi> his priuate friende made him coniecture that some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
was amisse with <hi>Lentulus.</hi> Hauing therefore fit op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie
he began to sift him in this manner.</p>
            <p>The auncient Gréetians swéete <hi>Lentulus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> set downe
principles of friendship, account the secrete conuersi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g of
friendes, and their mutuall participating eyther of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate
sorrows or concealed pleasures, the principall end of
such professed amitie. Therefore did <hi>Theseus</hi> choose <hi>Piri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thous,
Orestes Pylades</hi> &amp; to that end, or else you wronge
me, serues <hi>Tullie</hi> to his <hi>Lentulus.</hi> If then it be requisite in
friendshippe to abandon suspitious secrecie, I cannot but
take it vnkindly that <hi>Tullie</hi> is not made partaker of <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus</hi>
passions. For as the Carbuncle is not hid in the
darke, nor the fire shut vp in strawe, so sorrowes cannot
so couertly be concealed but the countenance will purtray
out the cause by the effectes. Thinke me not then so blind
but I can Iudge of coullors, nor so simple but I can deeme
of affections, what meane these farre fetcht sighes, broken
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6220:19"/>
slumbers, this newe delight to be solitarie, but that <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus</hi>
féeling a passion that pierceth to the quick, yet séekes
to kéepe it secrete from his friend <hi>Tullie.</hi> Knowe this my
good <hi>Lentulus</hi> that smoake depressed stiffleth more deadly.
That the Ouen the closer it is damd vp the greater is
the heate: and passions the more priuate the more preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall.
Stop not then the streame, least it ouerflow. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale
not sorrowes least they ouercharge, and prooue like
woundes, that kepte long from the Chirurgian growe
to be incurable vlcers: If it be a Fathers frowne, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies
wrong, a friendes mishap, reueale it and séeke
remedie. If <hi>Lentulus</hi> gréeues hath left his honours in <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia,</hi>
feare not, <hi>Rome</hi> will haue more warres and <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>
new dignities. If the Senatoures haue delt ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully:
<hi>Solamen miseris socios habuisse doloris.</hi> The most
famous Romaines haue forerunne thée in such hard for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.
<hi>Scipio</hi> subdued <hi>Affrica,</hi> what his rewarde was let
our annualles report. If <hi>Lentulus</hi> misliks ought in <hi>Rome,</hi>
let him abandon <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Tullio</hi> will banishe himselfe
from his countrie too with his friend <hi>Lentulus.</hi> If since
thy comming into this storehouse of natures prodigalitie,
thiue eye hath made suruaie of anie gorgious Damsell,
and so my <hi>Lentulus</hi> be in loue although wisedome wills
to hide amors euen from amitie, and to tie fancie in the
lowest cell of his heart, yet reueale it to thy friende <hi>Tullie,</hi>
and if any way hee may ease his <hi>Lentulus</hi> passions, hee
vowes to salue thy sore, though with the hazarde of his
owne safetie. <hi>Lentulus</hi> hearing his friende leuell so néere
the marke gaue a great grone at the name of loue, and fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
a déepe sighe saide <hi>Actna grauius Amor.</hi> And with
that starting from the place where hee sat taking <hi>Tullie</hi>
by the hande, he began thus.</p>
            <p>Were it my <hi>Tullie</hi> that my passions had any hope of
remedie, or that my wounde were such as might bee cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
by counsell, long ere this had <hi>Lentulus</hi> powred his
plaintes into the bosome of his friende <hi>Cicero:</hi> but my
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6220:19"/>
sorrows, as they are piercing so I haue kept them priuate,
as hoping for no ease and yet delighting in my martire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.
The birde flieth the snare of the fouler, No sooner
doth the woodman bend his bowe, but the Déere trippes
through the lawnes: euerie creature is taught by nature
to feare his fall, and yet wretched <hi>Lentulus</hi> hunteth after
his owne mishappe. So haue I described the furie of my
passions, as I can not but say it is loue that is thus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient.
Loue my <hi>Tullie</hi> that is such a lord as ins<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nuating
his power with fauour he kéeps possession by force. Wars
haue their endes either honors or death, and in battaile
prowesse oft makes constraint of fortune, but in loue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay
is the vnhappie deathsman that holding thée vp nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
saues nor killes. Since my comming to <hi>Rome</hi> (my
<hi>Tullie</hi>) coueting to conuerse with beautifull Ladies as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I had done with martiall souldiers, amongst manie
curious Pearles I founde one Orient Margarite richer
then those which <hi>Caesar</hi> brought from the western shores
of <hi>Europe:</hi> so long I gased at the beautie of this pretious
Iem that I founde my selfe gald with such affection, as
well repeat I might, but recall I coulde not: and for thou
shalt say she is loue worthie. heare how in discribing hir
excellencie I haue plaide the Poet.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <head>Lentulus description of Terentia
in Latin.</head>
                  <l>Qualis in aurora splende scit lumine Titan,</l>
                  <l>Talis in eximio corpore forma fuit:</l>
                  <l>Lumina seu spectes radiantia, siue capillos,</l>
                  <l>Lux Ariadne tua &amp; lux tua Phoebe iacet.</l>
                  <l>Venustata fuit verbis, spirabat odorem,</l>
                  <l>Musica vox, nardus spiritus almus erat:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:6220:20"/>Rubea labra, genae rubrae, faciesque decora,</l>
                  <l>In qua concertant lilius atque rosa.</l>
                  <l>Luxuriant geminae formoso in pectore mammae,</l>
                  <l>Circundant niueae candida colla comae:</l>
                  <l>Denique talis erat diuina Terentia, quales</l>
                  <l>Quondam certantes, Iuno, Minerua, Venus.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <head>Thus in English.</head>
                  <l>BRightsume Apollo in his richest pompe,</l>
                  <l>was not like to the tramels of hir haire:</l>
                  <l>Hir eyes like Ariadnes sparkling starres,</l>
                  <l>shone from the Ebon Arches of hir browes.</l>
                  <l>Hir face was like the blushing of the east,</l>
                  <l>when Titan chardge the mornings Sun to rise:</l>
                  <l>Hir cheekes rich strewd with roses and with whyte,</l>
                  <l>did stayne the glorie of Anchises loue.</l>
                  <l>Hir siluer teates did ebbe and flowe delight,</l>
                  <l>Hir necke colummes of polisht Iuorie.</l>
                  <l>Hir breath was perfumes made of violets,</l>
                  <l>And all this heauen was but Terentia.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>NO sooner had <hi>Lentulus</hi> ended his well written Poem,
and concluded his cunning with the name of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse,
but <hi>Tullie</hi> hearing <hi>Terentia</hi> was the saint at
whose shrine <hi>Lentulus</hi> offred vp his deuotion, entring his
<hi>exordium</hi> with a smyle he began to be thus pleasaut.</p>
            <p>And is there no fruit will serue your taste but such as
growe in the Gardens <hi>Hesperides,</hi> nor no colour content
your eye but such as is stayned by the fish <hi>Murex.</hi> Must
your senses be fed with nothing but that is excellent, nor
your loue haue no meane but to aime at the fairest. What
<hi>Terentia</hi> the beautie of <hi>Rome?</hi> the pride of nature? the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6220:20"/>
wealth of all the fauouring graces, whose excellencies are
spreade throught the triple deuision of the worlde? I see
my <hi>Lentulus</hi> souldiers haue eyes as they haue hands, and
thoughtes as they haue weapons, and that howe bluntlie
so euer brought vp in the warres yet they are curious in
the choises of their loues. Well, be it <hi>Lentulus</hi> loues <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia,</hi>
an honour to set his fancie on hir, but hee kept his
loue secret fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Tullie</hi> a fault to be suspicious of his friend.
But why gréeues <hi>Lentulus?</hi> Is not his parentage grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
then the house of <hi>Flaminius?</hi> Is not his honours suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
to counteruaile hir beauties? Why then is he so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient
in so agreable a passion? <hi>Lentulus</hi> vpon this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursed
vnto <hi>Tullie</hi> from point to point the successe of his
loues, how he gaue his charge ouer to <hi>Lepidus</hi> onely that
he might haue a sight of <hi>Terentia,</hi> and then recounting
what prattle had past betwixt him and hir after dinner:
Hir coy answeres and firmed resolution to remaine chast:
crauing counsell howe he might ease the disquiete of his
thonghts: <hi>Tullie</hi> pittying the extreeme passion of his
friende, deuised sundrie meanes howe to make him lorde
of his desires. But after the discourse of sundry plottes,
it was decreed that <hi>Lentulus</hi> shoulde write vnto <hi>Teren-Terentia.
Lentulus</hi> dispairing of his owne stile and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode,
required <hi>Tully</hi> to write him a letter passionate and
full of familiar eloquence, which at his request <hi>Cicero</hi>
contriued after this manner: where by the way gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
I am to craue you to thinke that <hi>Terentia</hi> kept
the copy secrete, so that neither it can bee founde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
<hi>Lentulus</hi> loose papers, nor in the familiar epistles
of <hi>Cicero.</hi> If the phrase differ from his other excellent
forme of writing, imagine he sought to couer his style, and
in his pen rather to play the blunt souldier, then the curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Orator, neither vsing those <hi>verborum fulmina,</hi> that
<hi>Papyrius</hi> obiects, nor that swéete and musicall cadence of
words, which he vseth to <hi>Atticus,</hi> but howsoeuer or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer,
thus it was.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:6220:21"/>
                  <head>Lentulus, Terentiae salutem.</head>
                  <p>QVod natura in venustatis &amp; formae tuae Idaea forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit
(suauissima Terentia) nullo modo silentio praete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rire
possum: Ne cum nimis cautus amoris ignem ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare
conarer, incautus tanquam Aetna meipsum consumens,
in cineres redigar. Cum inter Parthos versarer, nihil nisi bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum
&amp; arma cogitans, a Roma vsque formae tuae pulchritudo,
morumque integritas à multis saepe nuntiata est. Cuius rei fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma
ca iucunditate aures meas permulsit, vt (syrenum quasi
cantu delectatus) arma abijcere &amp; amorem cogitare coeperim,
meque totum in Terentiae potestatem tradere non erubesce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.
Diuinae autem excellentiae tuae cogitatio, eos mihi pro tempore
in bellicis negotijs addidit animos, vt breui deuictis
&amp; profligatis Parthis, totam hanc Prouinciam Lepido com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miserim,
quem vnum tum honoris, tum fortunae meae partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pem
feci, Parthisque relictis Romam me contuli, vt iucundis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simo
fructu tum aspectus, tum consuetudinis tuae frui liceat.
Formae vero &amp; pulchritudinis tuae dignitas, tanta tamque ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellens
fuit, vt non modo famam, sed expectationem meam
longe superarit. Vnde exquisitam tuam perfectionem oculis
contemplans, &amp; singulares animi dotes auribus accipiens, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentiae
tuae Idaeam in imo pectore collocaui meque totum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mori,
quasi constring endum tradidi. Cum igitur tua vnius
causa (suauissima Terentia) famam fortunasque &amp; arma
proiecerim, verum amantis officium fac praestes, &amp; me non
meritis, sed amore fac metiare, vt in amore tu mihi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondens,
ego in omni officio tibi satisfaciam. Taceo genus &amp;
parentes, quos tamen bonos ciues &amp; senatores fuisse constat;
taceo triumphos, qui quales fuerint Capitolium populusque
Romanus locupletissimi sunt testes; de diuitijs non glorior, quas
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6220:21"/>
t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>men mediocres esse constat, sed virtutis vim &amp; amoris con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
tibi propono, quae nec parui facienda, nec ingratitudine
compensanda sunt. Me igitur fac redames (mea Terentia) &amp;
pulchritudini comitatem coniungens, parentibus honorem, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icis
fidem, Lentulo amorem tribuas, vt parentibus gaudio,
amicis vtilitati, &amp; Lentulo voluptati esse possis. Non disertè,
vt Orator, sed peramanter, vt imperator tibi scribo, quod si
amorinostro consentire digneris, de patris voluntate nihil est
quod dubites: sed si alieno amore non nostro delecteris, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lores
meos &amp; augebo &amp; celabo, &amp; quamcunque in partem te flexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,
tibi tum vitam tranquillam, tum mortem gloriosam, vt
fideliss. amator exoptabo. Vale, plus oculis mihi dilecta Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,
&amp; me tui desiderio iam pene languentem aut ames cito aut
oderis semper, vale &amp; rescribe.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Lentulus to Terentia health.</head>
                  <p>I cannot (swéete soueraigne of my thoughts, and chiefe
myrrour of our <hi>Romaine</hi> excellencie) smother that with
silence which nature hath figured in the portraiture of my
lookes, vnlesse kéeping the flame too secrete, I shoulde like
<hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tna</hi> consume to cinders. When seated amongst the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi>
hauing nothing in my thoughtes but warres and
stratagemes, thy beauty was repeated as speciall newes
from <hi>Roome</hi> amongst the Legions: The melodie séemed
so pleasing to mine eares as if the musicke of the <hi>Syrens</hi>
had inchaunted my senses. I ceased from warres to think
of loue, and from loue to doate on the conceit of <hi>Terentia.</hi>
The thoughtes of thy excellencie doubled such courage in
my attempts, that I conquered the <hi>Parthians,</hi> yéelded vp
my charge to <hi>Lepidus,</hi> made him partaker of my honors,
and fortunes, and came to <hi>Roome</hi> onely to sée <hi>Terentia:</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:6220:22"/>
whose sight was so beauteous, and so farre beyond the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
of fame, that mine eies surueying exquisitely thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
and mine eares censuring of thy wit and vertues
both in league conspired to present the Idea of thy selfe to
the contemplation of my heart, which gréedily intertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
such rare beauties, hath euer since remained a poore
distressed captiue. Sith then <hi>Terentia,</hi> thy <hi>Lentulus</hi> hath
left his fortunes to followe fancy, and hath forsaken the
warres to winne thy loues, holding thée more deare then
country or hono<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r, shewe thy selfe a <hi>Romaine</hi> Lady, that
striuing in minde to be matchlesse, thou mayest bee more
prodigall in fauours, then I worthy in deserts, and yéelde
mée such méede for my loue, as <hi>Lentulus</hi> for his loyaltie
doth merite. I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oast not of my parents, they are Citizens
&amp; of the Senate w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy father. I speak not of mine honors,
the Capitol can witnes what showtes past from the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines</hi>
as victors: what tears from the <hi>Parthians</hi> as van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quished,
both these passions growing from the fortunes of
<hi>Lentulus.</hi> My reuenewes are such as satisfie my desires:
But all these are externall fauours, which though I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearse
yet I bragge not off. But the constancy of my loue,
the loyalty of my thoughts: These <hi>Terentia</hi> are gifts of
the mind, deseruing no light estéem, much lesse to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
with ingratitude. Consider then (swéete goddesse) the
sincerity of mine affections: weigh howe <hi>Lentulus</hi> loues,
and so vse him in loue, measure his fortunes by his fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.
As thou art beautifull, so vse iustice, giue euery one
his due: Honour to the gods, reuerence to thy father, faith
to thy friend, and Loue to <hi>Lentulus,</hi> and if it please thée to
grace me with the title to thy husband <hi>Lentulus:</hi> for I co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet
to like honestly, not to loue wantonly. I write <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>
as a souldier without eloquence, and as a louer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
flattery, if thou satisfie my loue with thy fauours, I
doubt not to seale vp thy content with thy fathers and
friends agrée. If either thou art tied to former loues, or
mislikest of mine, I will close vp my sorrows with silence.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6220:22"/>
Howsoe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er it shall please thée to returne answere: Liue
with content, and die with honour.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Terentias <hi>newe intertained souldier,</hi>
Publius Cornelius Lentulus.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>If gentlemen I haue not translated <hi>Lentulus</hi> letter
verbatim worde for worde, let me in mine owne excuse
yéelde these reasons, that neither the familiar phrase of
the <hi>Romaines</hi> can brooke our harsh cadence of sentences:
nor durst I attempt to wrest <hi>Tullies</hi> eloquence to my rude
and barbarous english: fearing either to wrong so worthy
an Orator in displacing or rather disgracing his phrase: or
in too far presuming purchase your frowne, which I haue
euer in all duty sought to auoid. But howsoeuer my tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation
séemes wrested, I haue kept his. And so to <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi>
who hearing <hi>Tully</hi> reade the epistle, both conceited
the methode, and allowed of the manner: Onely carefull
where to get a fit and conuenient messenger. <hi>Tully</hi> at last
called to remembrance one <hi>Eutrapelus,</hi> an especiall friend
of his, who frequented the house of <hi>Flaminius,</hi> by him did
<hi>Lentulus</hi> sende the letter, and so liuing in hope of a happy
answere, he left <hi>Tully</hi> in his study, and went to the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll.
<hi>Cicero</hi> no sooner was by himselfe, but calling to mind
the description of <hi>Terentia:</hi> set out with such excellency by
<hi>Lentulus</hi> in his new learnd poetrie, and weighing how al
<hi>Roome</hi> woondred at hir beauties: began to féele certaine
sparkes of loue kindling in his young desires, which made
him blush at his owne thoughtes, and smile that fancy
shoulde lie lurking amongst his library to take him at dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couert.
But assoone as he remembred that <hi>Lentulus</hi> was
in loue with hir, the faith to his friend, was a cooling carde
to his affections: and hee quenched those sparkes at the
first, lest suffered they might grow to a greater flame: yet
was he maugre his heade forced to say thus much.</p>
            <p>Hast thou liued fortunate, and fauoured in <hi>Roome?</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:6220:23"/>
hath honour raised thée from a meane cottage to be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion
to the sonnes of Senators? Doe the Consuls make
thee for thy learning one of the <hi>Pret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xtati?</hi> and wilt thou
for the hope of foolish beauty staine all thy fauours and
fortunes with disgrace? Nay rather <hi>Tully</hi> it will be honor
to wooe the daughter of so famous a <hi>Romaine:</hi> but shame
to thee to take the repulse and be denied. Thinkest thou
<hi>Terentia</hi> will looke so lowe? will Eagles catch at flies? wil
the woonder of our time, the paragon of our age, allied to
the noblest houses in <hi>Roome,</hi> make choise of so base and
meane a person? What hast thou to deserue hir loue, any
more then a little babling eloquence. Womens eares are
not their touchstones but their eies: they sée and make
choyse, not heare and fancy. A dramme of honour weighs
downe a pound of wit: and better is it to court with wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
reuenewes, then with swéete lines, or fine coucht po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emes.
Thou hast nothing left but a poore farme called <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum,</hi>
whose rents quits not the charges of thy studies.
But suppose thou couldst winne <hi>Terentia,</hi> suffice shée is
loued by <hi>Lentulus:</hi> and therefore fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this day name hir not
in thy mouth, nor weare hir in thy thoughtes, least thou
violate friendship, which thou ought to prise dearer then
life. Thus <hi>Tully</hi> appeasing his passions went out of his
study and willed <hi>Eutrapelus</hi> to deliuer the letter with se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy:
who being one of <hi>Tullies</hi> chief familiars, went with
all spéede to the house of <hi>Flaminius,</hi> where finding the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<hi>Terentia</hi> sitting with <hi>Flauia</hi> &amp; <hi>Cornelia</hi> at worke, he
being <hi>homo facetus</hi> began merily to commend their hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifery
&amp; after some iests broken betwixt the gentlewome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
&amp; him he craued to speak w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Terentia</hi> about certain serious
affairs y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> greatly imported hir father. Wherupon shée ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
&amp; going with <hi>Eutrapelus</hi> into hir closet he there deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red
vnto hir <hi>Lentulus</hi> letter. <hi>Terentia</hi> abashed at the sight
blushed as half angrie with <hi>Eutrapelus,</hi> that he made him
selfe messenger in so vaine a matter, yet considering it
came from so honourable a personage as <hi>Lentulus,</hi> shée
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6220:23"/>
vouchsafed it &amp; wisht <hi>Eutrapelus</hi> in the euening to come
for an answere. He was no sooner departed, but <hi>Terentia</hi>
vnripped the seales and then red the contentes, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
contrarie to hir resolution, shée determined to returne
with a deniall. But for that she would make hir friends
priuie to hir new loues passions she went smiling in, and
shewed them the letter. Upon poore <hi>Lentulus</hi> plainesong
they all began to descant. <hi>Cornelia</hi> praysing <hi>Terentias</hi>
fortunes that was so enterely beloued of so honourable &amp;
braue a Gentleman, but <hi>Flauia</hi> hung the lippe and saying
little, only askt what a louing answere she would write.
I know not howe to replie quoth <hi>Terentia,</hi> he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
so eloquently and so cunningly. But quoth <hi>Flauia</hi> I
durst pawne my credite it was written by young <hi>Tullie,</hi>
that braue Orator: for I haue red some of his Epistles,
and tis both his methode and his verie phrase. That <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi>
quoth <hi>Terentia</hi> whom I haue heard my Father and
the Senators so highlie commend for his witte, thinking
him to excéede either <hi>Crassus</hi> or <hi>Hortensius?</hi> and with that
sitting downe they began to enter into discourse of <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi>
excellencies, concluding all that he was as singular a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
the <hi>Romaines,</hi> as euer <hi>Demosthenes</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
the <hi>Grecians.</hi> At last <hi>Terentia</hi> remembring hir
selfe, tooke leaue for a whyle of hir two friendes, and stea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
into hir closet stepping to the standish shée was about
to write, but calling to minde the discourse of <hi>Tullies</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
letting fall hir penne she fell into a passion. <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid</hi>
wayting to spie this vestall at aduantage, séeing hir
halfe at discouert vulosde a bolt headed with desire, and
fethered with conceite, which piercing the tender briest
of this young Damosell, he made hir shrinck at the blow,
and so breath out this complaint.</p>
            <p>Hast thou <hi>Terentia</hi> béene wondred at in <hi>Rome</hi> for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spising
loue, and wilt thou now doting gyrle stomble on
desire, shall fancie eclipse all thy former glories<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> shall <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sta</hi>
léese a virgin, and <hi>Venus</hi> winne a wanton? Wilt thou
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6220:24"/>
resemble the buddes of an Elder trée, which young are
swéete and holesome, but blomd foorth are bitter and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall:
thinke with thy selfe that <hi>Dianas</hi> shrubs are
more pleasaunt, than <hi>Cupids</hi> bowers, the one harbours
chast thoughts, the other amorous fancies. Truth, but
<hi>Lucina</hi> is a goddesse, loue is diuine, and marriage hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.
Cedars are fayre, but in yéelding no fruite they
purchase the lesse estéeme. To be a virgin is a glorious
title, but to liue euer so, is to wrong nature in hir fauors.
Well hast thou not then <hi>Terentia</hi> a noble gentleman of
<hi>Rome,</hi> Lord <hi>Lentulus</hi> to bee thy husbande, a man whose
youth is filled with honours and whose spring time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risheth
dignities? hath he not triumpht ouer the <hi>Parthians</hi>
in conquest &amp; bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d fortune to his temples with wreathes
of victorie. Is not his parentage one of the greatest fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies
in <hi>Rome?</hi> Is he not for beautie like the fayre Gréekes
Paramour? For wisedome like wise <hi>Vlisses</hi> that <hi>Cyrces</hi>
could not inchant? For courage <hi>Hector?</hi> Aud of such reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes
as may maintaine thee with the most gorge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
dames of <hi>Italie?</hi> But the chiefe of his graces is he not
enamored of <hi>Terentia</hi> and sues for hir fauour. This I
confesse, <hi>Sed deteriora sequor.</hi> Loue ah that foolish pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
which we tearme loue allowes nothing excellent but
what it likes. It shadowed begarie in <hi>Crates.</hi> For <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sycratea</hi>
thought him rich in that he was vertuous: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie
in <hi>Vulcan,</hi> for <hi>Venus</hi> would not beléeue hee had a
poult foote. Loue hath no lacke, and lesse reason: yet must
I loue, and whome, ah <hi>Tullie</hi> swéete <hi>Tullie,</hi> from whose
mouth flows melodie, more inchaunting then the <hi>Syrens,</hi>
on whose lips the muses make a newe <hi>Parnassus,</hi> in whose
thoughts rest <hi>Platos</hi> diuine spirites, and in whose heade
is contayned the subtil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> witte of <hi>Aristotle.</hi> Is not hee as
glorious in <hi>Rome</hi> for his eloquence, as thou for thy beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties?
Doth not the Senators wounder at his learning,
as at thy perfection? Why should not then both our sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities
be lincked in the vnion of Loue? why shoulde
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6220:24"/>
not <hi>Terentia</hi> liue to <hi>Tullie,</hi> and <hi>Tullie</hi> to <hi>Terentia?</hi> Ah but
he is base, the first of his kyn that tasted of honour, I but
he is vertuous and famous for his eloquence, graces that
counteruaile the meanesse of his parentes. I sée loue hath
reasons béeing out of reason still to argue against reason,
therfore without further <hi>pro &amp; contra</hi> in mine owne pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,
I wil loue <hi>Tullie,</hi> &amp; therfore thus to <hi>Lentulus.</hi> With
that taking vp hir penne she wrote him this aunswere.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Terentia to Lentulus health.</head>
                  <p>WHen I red Lorde <hi>Lentulus</hi> thy letters and spied thy
loues, I blusht at mine owne thoughtes, and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed
at thy fortunes. I serch not the cause of thy loue,
for it sufficeth to me thou doest loue, if it lay in me either
to graunt thy desire, or satisfie thy passions. Thy reasons
are sufficient to moue, were it not my vowe and my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines
direct my minde to contrary thy affections. Thy
honours <hi>Lentulus</hi> knockes at the closet of my heart, thy
victories sue for their lordes libertie, thy loyaltie enters
pele mele with my thoughtes and giueth a sore assault to
my setled resolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, all these put in their pleas to purchase
fauour for young <hi>Lentulus.</hi> But <hi>Vesta</hi> hard harted <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sta</hi>
that makes hir virgings pliant to hir owue proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
commaunds that I shut mine ears against such allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<hi>Syrens.</hi> I count my selfe greatly honoured with the
loue of so worthie a Romayne, and euer will <hi>Terentia</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et
to prooue as thankfull as he affectionate; onely in loue
pardon me, for that either I neuer meane to loue, or if I
doe loue, my thoughtes were fixed before <hi>Lentulus</hi> came
from <hi>Parthia.</hi> Wade not there where the ford hath no foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
barke not with the Wolues of <hi>Syria</hi> against the
Moone, looke not to clim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Olimpus,</hi> way not at impossibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
but pacifie that with patience which thou canst
not obtaine with beeing passionate. If thou suest
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6220:25"/>
to my Father and he graunt to conclude a mariage, yet
shalt thou want a bride, for I will first die before I vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
my resolution. Séeke not then by my preiudice to
aime at thy owne content, which be it euery way, yet it
shall neuer be in my loue: not that I hate <hi>Lentulus,</hi> but
that my fortunes forbides me to loue <hi>Lentulus.</hi> If thou
thinkst these denials be but words of course, and perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest
thy selfe that women will bee first coy and then cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
as the marble that drops of raine do pierce. Thou
shalt déepely deceiue thy selfe and highlie wrong me, but
I challenge thy promise, that howsoeuer I fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>strate thy
expectation thou wilt burie thy conceipte in silence. In
which hope gréeuing that thy showers came in <hi>Autumne,</hi>
I wish quiet to thy thoughts and an ende to thy loues.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine euer but in loue Terentia.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>TErentia</hi> hauing thus ended hir letter and newe begun
hir loues, the one directed to <hi>Lentulus</hi> the other deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to <hi>Tullie,</hi> she went straight to hir two friends <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi>
and <hi>Flauia</hi> shewing them the contentes of the letter.
<hi>Cornelia</hi> saide she was too seuere and stoicall in sending
such a peremptorie aunswere to so braue a gentleman.
<hi>Flauia</hi> ouercharged with ioy praysed the resolution of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia,</hi>
wishing that all maides were of hir minde, mis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
that which shée most loued, thinking by retreating
<hi>Terentia</hi> from the chace, to be mistresse of the game hir
selfe. Well this letter at last was sealed, and deliuered to
<hi>Eutrapelus,</hi> who hying him fast to <hi>Tullies</hi> lodging founde
<hi>Lentulus</hi> and him in secrete and serious discourse, and all
god wot was about <hi>Terentia. Lentulus</hi> hauing receiued
the letter entring with <hi>Tullie</hi> into his study read the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents.
No sooner had he viewed &amp; reuiewed ouer hir cruell
determination but in a great extas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of minde, he cried out
<hi>(Dulcior est mors quam Amor.)</hi> And with that flinging
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6220:25"/>
out of his study he fell into bitter and extreame sorrows.
<hi>Tully</hi> grieuing at his friendes harde fortune sought with
plausible perswasions to appease his furious melancholy,
wishing him whatsoeuer <hi>Terentia</hi> wrote stil to thinke hir
a woman that would one while thrust out fancy with a
finger, and straight interteine loue as a friend: that either
time or his constancy woulde make hir stoope to the lure
of his desires. Thus sought <hi>Tully</hi> to wrest him from his
passions but in vaine, for hir resolution confirmde with
such effectuall and perswasiue determinations so quatted
the conceit of his former hope, that going passing melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly
to his bed, he fell into an extreame feuer, which ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauated
with the inward anguish of his minde grewe to
be so dangerous that <hi>Asclapo</hi> the physit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on excellent at
that time for his facultie, iudged the disease <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be mortall.
The Senatours hearing of <hi>Lentulus</hi> sickenesse sorrowed,
as fearing <hi>Roome</hi> by death shoulde bee depriued of such
high ensuing hope: his friends f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ocked to his lodging to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site
him, who noting, the heate of the ague, and the passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of his minde, his sodaine starts, his gash lookes, and
his abrupt answeres, iudged the extremity of his sickenes
had halfe brought him to a lunacy, all séeking by counsaile
to cure that which neither counsail nor medicine could mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate.
Frustrate of their expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they wished his weal
and returned with grief. Only <hi>Tully</hi> whose setled friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship
no misfortune could remooue, still day and night as a
second <hi>Esculapius,</hi> wayted vpon this perplexed patient.
But as the depth of his passion pierced into the center
of his heart, so the feuer increased, that generally <hi>Roome</hi>
began to sorrow so braue a warriour shoulde bee cut off in
the very prime of his fortunes, insomuch that the report of
his sickenes came to the eares of the thrée Ladies. <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>
made light account as hauing hir heart hardned with
the loue of <hi>Cicero,</hi> but <hi>Flauia</hi> grewe passing passionate, as
being toucht at the quicke with the weake disposition of
<hi>Lentulus,</hi> wishing he might haue cure for his malady, so
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6220:26"/>
it were not by the meanes of <hi>Terentia:</hi> shée frequented the
temples, offred orizons, made vowes and burnt incense to
the gods, that they would be fauourable to hir louer <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus,</hi>
coueting if possible it might be with the preiudice of
hir selfe to haue profited him: but in vaine, <hi>Terentia</hi> was
resolute, and he was resolued: as shée was dainty, so to die
in disp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire. <hi>Flauia</hi> if hir modesty might haue permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
would haue accompanied with other Ladies gone to
his lodging, but the rights of <hi>Vesta</hi> forbidding such fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
conuersing, shée rather was restrained by force then
withhelde by reason. But seeing shée coulde by no meanes
come to his sight, yet to manifest the sincerity of hir loue,
shée sent him a letter to this effect.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Flauia to Lentulus health.</head>
                  <p>IF I could (Lord <hi>Lentulus</hi>) pourtray with outward acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
the secrecy of my passions, or force as many teares
from mine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies as there flie sighes from my heart: The a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomy
of my thoughts would discouer a disquiet minde,
and the source of mine eies a fountaine of bitter laments.
But séeing that barrels the fuller they be the lesse sounde
they yéeld: And where the current is déepest there the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
is most still: and the minde surchargd with extreames,
hath least vtterance of grief: I leaue you to suppose of my
sorrowes which I cannot manifest. But know Lord <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus,</hi>
that when the report of your sickenes came to the
eares of your new intertained friends, <hi>Terentia</hi> sighed as
pitying with a common passion the ill of hir countryman,
but as one that might not relieue being intercepted with
other loues. <hi>Cornelia</hi> chid, as holding your selfe in high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
estéeme, alleaging reasons to hir that admitted no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
but hir owne loue which is without reason. My selfe
sorrowed, as wishing desert shoulde haue his due, where
the honour of the man merites no lesse: we perswaded in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6220:26"/>
vaine, and in séeking to bring <hi>Terentia</hi> to the bay, we inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured
to quench fire with swords. Seeing then your
thoughts leuell at a wrong marke, and that no sutes can
diuert hir from hir froward conceit, in careles extreames
vse patience, wrestle with loue, beeing wrongd by loue:
yéelde not to the arrest of <hi>Cupids</hi> mace, but as he is young
so holde him a boy. Consider as <hi>Terentia</hi> is faire, so shée is
cruel: and as shée is full of fauour, so shée is too too vnkinde.
Fly not with <hi>Apollo</hi> after <hi>Daphnis: Dyana</hi> hath more
nymphes as chast, and yet not so coy: vse loue my <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>
as children doe puppies, which while they are pliant
and gentle they cherish vp with crummes, but when they
waxe churlish they beate away with stroakes. Thinke
<hi>Roome</hi> is the mistresse of the worlde, and hath many faire
dames, if not of such excellencie as <hi>Terentia</hi> yet are they
more curteous, and no lesse vertuous. The curious <hi>Herba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists</hi>
measure not the plants by their colours but by their
properties: the <hi>Lapidaries</hi> make estimate of their stones
not by their outward hue, but by the secrete vertues. Use
then the auncient custome of <hi>Esculapius,</hi> let lillies wither
on the stalke and weare violets in thy hand, the one faire
and vnsauorie, the other blacke but of swéete verdure. Let
these counsailes <hi>Lentulus</hi> confute thée, apply them not as
outward plastures, but as inward potions: which if they
profit, none shall be more glad then <hi>Flauia,</hi> who wisheth
if shée might in this hard extreame to discouer the honour
of hir thoughts, and the resolution of a friende: if ought
rests in me that may pleasure <hi>Lentulus,</hi> commaunde it of
<hi>Flauia,</hi> as one knowing <hi>Lentulus</hi> desires are wholy hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.
Thus praying thou maiest haue ease in thy passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
through end of thy loues: I will offer sacrifice for thy
health as shée that feares hir owne preiudice without thy
recouery.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine, Flauia of Roome.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:6220:27"/>No sooner had <hi>Flauia</hi> ended hir letter, but shée sealed it
and sent it away, and with as much spéede as might be, it
was conueyed to <hi>Lentulus,</hi> who reading the superscripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and perceiuing it came from a woman, supposing it
was sent from <hi>Terentia,</hi> started vp in his bed and rent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ales: when he had read the contents, and saw it
came from <hi>Flauia,</hi> noting the extremity of hir loue by the
plaine discouery of hir passions: he said to himselfe.</p>
            <p>Uniust loue that settles thy delight in crossing with
contraries. Some thou piercest with desire, other with
disdaine: infusing sundry effectes in diuers affects. I couet
<hi>Terentia</hi> and shée is cruell: <hi>Flauia</hi> fauours thée, and thou
art tyed to other loues. What restes in these extreames
but to curse fancy, that maketh such a confused chaos of
hir follyes. Oppose then reason against affection, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte
not of loues conclusions vnlesse they be approoued
principles Thy thoughts are deuoted to <hi>Terentia,</hi> and shée
onely vouchsafes thée the verdict of hir eares. Thou
art more honourable then shée, of richer reuenewes then
hir dowry can satisfie, hauing as many desertes as shée
hath beauties: and yet coy dame as shée is, shée twits thée
with <hi>Vesta</hi> when God wotte <hi>Venus</hi> is the goddesse that
heareth hir orisons. If thou hast this insight into hir
thoughts, why wrongs thou thy selfe with such carelesse
passions? If shée be so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amage let hir fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and séeke for a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that may prooue more gentle: Let hir glory like
<hi>Narcissus</hi> in hir beauties: Loue can chastise if it be but
with selfe loue. Use no phisicke <hi>Lentulus</hi> but the considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of hir frowardnesse, Let the drugs of <hi>Apollo</hi> serue for
others not for thée. Thrust out fancy by force, and setting
<hi>Terentia</hi> at light esteeme, make choice of <hi>Flauia:</hi> Though
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be not so beautifull, yet shée is second to hir in graces,
and farre beyo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d hir in curtesies. Tie not thy selfe <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus</hi>
so strick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly to a wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ans face, beauty is but times
flower, that as it is delicate so it s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e withereth: Like the
colours that <hi>Phidias</hi> drew in his pictures, which shewing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6220:27"/>
most glorious to the eye was yet blemisht with euery
breath. <hi>Venus</hi> was faire and wanton: <hi>Helen</hi> the myracle
of <hi>Greece,</hi> but aske <hi>Troy</hi> of hir qualities. Ah but <hi>Terentia</hi>
is as chast as shée is bautifull. So is <hi>Flauia</hi> to, and farre
more louing. Hir byrth is of higher discent, hir wealth
more, hir virtues no lesse: but hir loue such as may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge
thy affection for debt. Ah but <hi>Lentulus</hi> yet <hi>Terentia</hi>
hir excellency is more then can be shaken off with so slight
reasons: and with that he shrunke downe into his bedde,
falling to his olde complaints: yet did this letter of <hi>Flauia</hi>
somewhat comfort him, that he found it his best physicke.
But leauing him in his bed, againe to <hi>Terentia</hi> who felt
the disquiet of hir minde as restlesse. For the Senatours
daily repairing to hir fathers house, had no other table
talke but of the eloquence of <hi>Tully,</hi> some commending his
witte, other his study, some his vertues, but all his special
gifts of nature, that they put oyle into the flame: and with
these prayses so sette on fire <hi>Terentias</hi> fancy, as nothing
tumbled in hir thoughtes but the excellency of <hi>Cicero:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
so impatient as shée sought by all meanes possible to
come to his sight, and to féede hir eye with that wherwith
shée had inchanted hir eares, finding no ready way to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
the ende of hir desires, vntill loue that like <hi>Mercury</hi>
is full of shifts and subtlety, deuised this plot. <hi>Tully</hi> being
borne in a little village adioyning vnto <hi>Roome</hi> called <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinatum,</hi>
vsed often to make his intercourse betwéene the
towne and the citie for his pleasure: Which <hi>Terentia</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
learned out, thought this the fittest meanes to haue
a sight of hir <hi>Cicero.</hi> So that one day to take the aire ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied
with hir two friends <hi>Flauia</hi> and <hi>Cornelia,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
but a page to attend vpon them, shée walked abroad
into the fields. Passing thus in merry chatte towards <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinatum,</hi>
hauing some glances at the sicknes of <hi>Lentulus,</hi>
they had not walked aboue a mile before <hi>Flauia</hi> spied <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi>
comming from <hi>Arpinatum</hi> to <hi>Roome.</hi> Assoone as shée
had discried him, and for certainety knew that it was he,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6220:28"/>
yonder quoth shée comes that odde man of <hi>Roome,</hi> that
excellent Orator <hi>Marcus Tullius Cicero,</hi> so highly renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
through all our prouinces for his eloquence, now shal
we heare from <hi>Lentulus,</hi> for they are the most familiar
friends and priuate companions in <hi>Roome. Terentia</hi> at
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as one wakened out of a dreame gaue a start, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
vp hir eye espied the Paramour of hir thoughtes,
which driue hir into such an extasie, that surcharged with
ouer much ioy shee felt an vnacquainted trembling in hir
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Being thus perplexed <hi>Tully</hi> drawing nye, and sée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<hi>Terentia</hi> accompanied with his f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iende <hi>Flauia,</hi> gaue
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to oportunity that shee had so highly fauoured his
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lentulus,</hi> as that he might now plead for his safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<hi>Tully</hi> thus incountring those three <hi>Romaine</hi> damosels
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter a curteous <hi>Salue</hi> which made <hi>Terentia</hi> blush, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
thus to board them.</p>
            <p>The place swéete Romaines so aptly agréeing to the
person, this valley resembling <hi>Idas,</hi> and <hi>Rome Troy,</hi> I
cannot but bash with <hi>Paris</hi> at the sight of thrée such god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ses,
whose deitie surpassed those which iudicially y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harde
suruaied with his eye: Humbly therefore saluting
you as <hi>Dianas</hi> darlings and beauties woonder, séeing so
small a trayne for such excellent personages, although my
affaires be serious and of importaunce, yet please it you
to vouche of my seruice, I will attende on your walkes
and conduct you safe to <hi>Rome. Terentia</hi> féeding hir eyes
on the swéete of <hi>Tullies</hi> face, and swilling downe the nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar
of his diuine eloquence, stayning hir chéekes with
such a die, as did the fayre quéene of <hi>Cartharge</hi> cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by <hi>Aeneas,</hi> she made him this aunswere.</p>
            <p>Howe you make compare <hi>Cicero</hi> of this valley with
the plaines of <hi>Troy</hi> as little skilled in Geographie or red
in <hi>Homers</hi> Iliads I leaue without replie. For y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> goddes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
that <hi>Paris</hi> incountred we are equall with them in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er
though far inferiour to them in beautie. For your ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice
we accept it, and for your wages you shall haue gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6220:28"/>
lookes and hartie thankes. Séeing therefore wee are
merilie minded, supposing your selfe to be the shéepeharde
which of vs shall be your <hi>Venus?</hi> Not you madam quoth
<hi>Tullie</hi> aboue all the rest: And why so quoth <hi>Terentia?</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
quoth <hi>Tullie</hi> the least <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lie hath his spleane the smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest
ant her gall, no haire so little but he hath his shadowe,
and no man so meane but he hath his enuie: Why then
quoth <hi>Terentia</hi> I will discarde you from the office of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi>
as a man partiall. But I pray thée <hi>Cicero</hi> wherein
shoulde I offende thée hauing neuer séene thée before? In
this quoth hée that <hi>Lentulus</hi> hath séene you: with that she
blusht, and <hi>Flauia</hi> and <hi>Cornelia</hi> fell into a great laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
that <hi>Tullie</hi> had so roughly crost hir ouer the thumbs.
<hi>Tullie</hi> prosecuting his purpose went forwarde thus. For
knowe madam that <hi>Lentulus</hi> the richest Trophee that
fortune settes vp in the Theator of honour made ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke
of his libertie for the report of your beautie, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
the wars and the great hope of his fortunes to haue
a sight of <hi>Terentia,</hi> who vnkinde not like <hi>Venus</hi> in cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie,
though in fauours; haue counterpoysde his fancie
with mis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike, and for the honie of his amorous thoughts
haue powred him downe heapes of bitter and displeasing
gall. The crueltie of <hi>Cresida</hi> neuer amated so the hardy
<hi>Troilus</hi> as the frowne of <hi>Terentia</hi> hath pierst <hi>Lentulus,</hi>
making so déepe a wound as no phisicke can cure onely
your swéete selfe, whose resolutions are so farre from the
properties of your face, as it séemes the gods wrongd na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
in placing an adamant heart within a christall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerture.
The Ladies hearing <hi>Tully</hi> so sharpe, bitte the lip
and <hi>Terentia</hi> grieued: angry shée coulde not be as one that
was ouer the shooes in affection, but thus shee cutte him
off.</p>
            <p>I cannot iudge <hi>Cicero</hi> by your sharpe and peremptory
inuectiues vpon so small acquaintance, but you professe
your selfe a Cinicke. If your philosophy be such, I will
br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k the blowes as wel as <hi>Alexander,</hi> &amp; think nothing ill
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6220:29"/>
that is spoken from <hi>Diogenes.</hi> Howsoeuer or whatsoeuer
Cynicke or stoicke, I argue thus against <hi>Lentulus,</hi> that
vowes made to <hi>Vesta</hi> are to be holden inuiolated, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions
to liue a virgine are not to be broken with mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.
<hi>Cornelia</hi> and <hi>Flauia</hi> hearing them thus farre in by
the eares, walked a little aside and left <hi>Tully</hi> to schoole <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia:</hi>
who maintained hir arguments thus. Suppose
<hi>Tully</hi> it were not chast thoughts but newe loues that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
me to this refusal: haue not trées their strings &amp; wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
their fancies and affections? If his autum showers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
too late cause not his crops to proue, what is that to
me? Loue consisteth in vnity: the heart hath but one
string, the heauen one sunne, and the Iris one property,
and women but one loue: and that I tell thée <hi>Tully,</hi> is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
on one that is as famous for his vertues as <hi>Lentulus</hi>
for his wealth and dignities. And what then can I giue,
or he rightly challenge? <hi>Tully</hi> although hee conceiued in
his thoughtes that <hi>Terentia</hi> yéelded great reason, yet hée
would not giue ouer the chase so, but made this reply. Ah
but madame haue an insight into the depth of his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
howe he aimes not at your treasures hoping to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched
by your great dowry, For <hi>Lentulus</hi> is of the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiest
family in <hi>Roome:</hi> but leuels at your vertues, the
syrens against whom he could not vse <hi>Vlisses</hi> pollicy. If
affections be but a little past, if loue hath but drawne one
line in your thoughts with his pensell: wrastle with fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie,
blot out loues shadowes, and helpe <hi>Lentulus:</hi> who if
you remaine so cruell shall be no more <hi>Lentulus.</hi> If he dye
for loue, how shall the stréetes swarme with statues of his
constancy? If you be knowen the chiefe actor of the trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
how will the people murmure of your cruelty? Weigh
this madame, I speake as a familiar of <hi>Lentulus,</hi> and no
enemy to <hi>Terentias</hi> honour. If he be a <hi>Romaine</hi> that <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia</hi>
loues, let him either be more honourable, more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant,
more affable, more excellent euery way then <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi>
nay more louing then the poore gentleman, or else dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carde
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6220:29"/>
him for a man insufficient either to tast of <hi>Terentias</hi>
beauty, or to be corriual with <hi>Lentulus</hi> in his loues. <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia</hi>
had yéelded at this fierce assault, had not loue laide
an instance before hir of hir resolution. For the more <hi>Tully</hi>
pleaded for his friend, the more was <hi>Terentia</hi> enamoured:
so that shée made him this answere.</p>
            <p>If I knewe howe to certifie <hi>Lentulus</hi> of this dayes dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course,
he should highly reward you for playing so wel the
Orator. But I maruaile <hi>Cicero</hi> that being young, and of
such eloquence, we heare not of your loues: I feare you
reach so hye, that you thinke no maides in <hi>Roome</hi> hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
inough for your paramour. Were I a man and had
<hi>Tullies</hi> grace, and his tongue, I would plead for my selfe:
and vse one word for my friend, and two for my selfe. So
madame (quoth he) shoulde men account mee a faithlesse
friend, and a flattering louer. But leauing these suppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
madam, how answere you my last reason? With loue
quoth shée and that is without reason, for how might the
gentleman to whom I finde my selfe affectionate, thinke
himselfe wrongd if without cause I should be inconstant.
Graunt I my loue to the meanest citizen, a monarch shall
not make conquest of my thoughts. Suppose syr it were
your selfe, and that <hi>Terentia</hi> loued <hi>Tully,</hi> coulde you brooke
an other to braue you in your affections. I would madame
quoth <hi>Tully</hi> if it were no supposition. And how then quoth
<hi>Terentia</hi> if it were not? Then would I quoth hee become
<hi>Esculapius</hi> to <hi>Lentulus,</hi> and sweare his disease shoulde not
be incurable, for I woulde coniure you by the rightes of
loue, by the sacred lawes of <hi>Venus,</hi> and by the affection
that were imprinted in your thoughtes, to bestowe what
y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u would impart vpon me to my only ioy Lord <hi>Lentulus.</hi>
But women cannot make loue voluntary. Tush madame
what cannot women doe for loue? Any thing quoth <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>
but change loue. Therefore concealing the party that
I loue, I will say and sweare <hi>Tully</hi> is my loue, and so say
to <hi>Lentulus.</hi> With this <hi>Terentia</hi> blusht, and for very griefe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6220:30"/>
that <hi>Tully</hi> woulde not sée into hir thoughtes the teares
stoode in hir eies: which <hi>Tully</hi> spying, it so prickt him to the
heart, that it neuer after was rased out. To smooth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
his rough methode with a fewe fine filed phrases, hee
salued the matter thus. It is madame impossible to driue
fire downeward, or to make heauy things to mount: Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
will not bee wrongd, nor loue drawne out by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint,
therfore I will leaue any more at this time to sue
for <hi>Lentulus:</hi> hoping the consideration of his martirdome
will at length make battery into the bulwarke of your
breast, &amp; whereas you will sweare <hi>Tully</hi> is your l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue: you
knowe madame we haue in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> twelue tables a lawe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
periury, but if you vouch to grace me that title, in
all duty I wil rest your euer bounden seruant. Why then
seruant quoth shée, let vs to yonder two Ladies, that for
want of a companion are faine to make an amarous
knight of my page. <hi>Flauia</hi> séeing they were halfe agréed,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earing <hi>Tully</hi> by his eloquence had perswaded <hi>Terentia,</hi>
waxed pale and incountred them thus. What news quoth
shée, doth <hi>Lentulus</hi> winne or loose? Neither madame quoth
<hi>Tully</hi> but his cause hanges still in suspence, the next court
day I will end my oration, and then the Iudge shall giue
verdict. As they were ready to haue gone forward in some
pleasant prattle they espied a horseman making towards
them with the greatest spéede that might bee. When he
came within ken, <hi>Tully</hi> knew it to be <hi>Lentulus</hi> man, and
before he had leysure to do his message, he demanded how
his master did: passing sicke syr quoth hee, and hath sent
that you be with him presently. <hi>Tully</hi> who was toucht at
the quicke with this newes, put foote in the stirrop and
mounted, yet as one forgetting himselfe hee vsed these
words. Pardon Ladies, if I passe manners and promise,
in leaping vp without leaue, and returning in such post
without your company: It is for <hi>Lentulus</hi> whom you all
loue, and therefore I hope to rest blamelesse. Now madam
<hi>Terentia</hi> what shall I say to <hi>Lentulus?</hi> No more quoth shée
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6220:30"/>
then what I saide to <hi>Tullie,</hi> but how concludes <hi>Tullie</hi> of
his last premisses? that quoth hee, <hi>Terentia</hi> shall frame
the argument, and so with this darke <hi>Aenigma</hi> he tooke
leaue of the Ladies: who after his departure fell in talke
of his perfections. <hi>Terentia</hi> so déepely praysing the man
that hir companions easilie perceiued hir loues, &amp; smilde
that in forsaking a flower shée light vpon a wéede. Well
tracing still amongst the medows they chanced into a val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley
most curiouslie decked with <hi>Floras</hi> delicates, in which
were such varietie of flowers, that nature séemed there
to haue planted the storehouse of hir prodigalitie. Adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
to this valley was a pleasaunt riuer and a groue
that gaue a grace to <hi>Cloris</hi> excellencie: delighted with the
scituation of this place, as they passed along they met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
a shéepheard, who doing reuerence to the dames: <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>
demaunded of this swaine what the name of this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunt
place was. Madam quoth he we shéepehardes here
call it the vale of Loue, And why so quoth <hi>Cornelia?</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
madam quoth he my flocke hath no guide but my
dog, and now in yeaning time the wolues are verie busie,
yet for that I see you are Senators daughters, and with
all passing courteous I will shew the reason, and with
that leaning on his staffe the Ladies sitting downe he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
thus.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="unk">
                  <body>
                     <div type="tale">
                        <head>The Sheepheardes tale.</head>
                        <p>NOt many yeares since here in <hi>Arpynatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           </hi> dwelt a shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdise
called <hi>Phillis,</hi> so famous for hir beauty that the
Senators sonnes which you cal <hi>Pretextati</hi> not only came
to féed their eyes with hir fauours but to satifie their fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
with hir loues: in so much that she was courted of
manie braue <hi>Romaine</hi> Gentlemen. But shee that helde
loue at the staffes end, although hir parentes had left hir
rich, yet to banishe <hi>Cupid</hi> with labour she vouchsaft to be
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6220:31"/>
kéeper of hir owne flockes, fearing the pride of the beautie
(if s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e should marrie with one of <hi>Rome</hi>) would proue an
enimie to hir humble thoughtes: Liuing as chast as shée
was inrouled for a <hi>Vestall,</hi> and quoted by <hi>Diana</hi> for one
of hir speciall followers, hir excellencie was bruted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad
through all <hi>Italie.</hi> But shee who feared to gase at
starres, for stumbling at stones laide hir thoughtes lowe
and made choice of hir companie with countrie maydes,
and homely shepehards: yet was hir attire rich as diuers
that traueled this way tooke hir rather for a Nymphe the
follower of some goddesse, then a maide and daughter of a
poore swaine. While thus she liued ladie of the field, there
was in the same village one <hi>Coridon,</hi> sonne to a simple
shéepeharde who as a Mercinarie man kept shéepe for <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinius</hi>
the Senator, that hath a Farme hard by. This <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridon</hi>
was a man of a pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>fect perfection his haire hung in
tresses and his face was beautifull, wise hee was and
wanted nothing but wealth to make him the chiefe of all
the shéepehardes, being of equal yeares almost with <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi>
in some two yeres elder, he fell extréemely in loue with
<hi>Phillis</hi> Enamored was poore <hi>Coridon</hi> and pensiue by his
flocke sat ruminating of his passions he smothred his loue
in silence for that he was meanest of the swaines and she
mistresse of vs all. He sat and sighed and had none but echo
to pitie his plaintes his flocke left their foode to sée their
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> sorrowe his pipe ceast, the fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es were neuer
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>re partaker of his melodie, and all these thoughts and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>res for <hi>Phillis.</hi> Shée wilie and spying this wanton dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
in the flame, looked narrowly into the perfection of the
man whom she found worthie of loue, if his parentes had
not bene too meane and his wealth none at all, suppres<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ing
this loue with lack<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> and quenching the fire with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>s
she founde in <hi>Coridon.</hi> But <hi>Cupid</hi> that could not
b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ooke such exceptions pittying the passions of the poore
sheepharde, pulled foorth an inuenomed b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ult and pierst
<hi>Phillis</hi> so déepe that <hi>Coridon</hi> began to bee maister of hir
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6220:31"/>
thoughts, now shée praisd his beautie, his behauiour, his
wit, his gestures, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o that nothing was amisse in <hi>Coridon.</hi>
If he pipt, <hi>Apollo</hi> was not like hir <hi>Pan,</hi> if hee sung hys
voyce was without compare, if he tolde tales they were
excellent, if put foorth riddles they were wittie. <hi>Coridon</hi>
was the shéepehard that <hi>Phillis</hi> did fancie, and no flockes
might grase by hirs but those of <hi>Coridon.</hi> This mistris
can loue do, who thought he be choisly honoured in <hi>Rome,</hi>
yet he finds some idle time to dallie amongst shéepehards.
Well at last <hi>Coridon</hi> spyed <hi>Phillis</hi> lookes and got some
hope of fauour, first hee courted with his eyes, and after
natures law fell to prattle with interchange of glaunces,
after from lookes to wordes, which after their homely fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion
was verie faithfully performed with sighs &amp; teares,
such perswasions as shéepehardes vse. Long had they
not wooed, but <hi>Phillis</hi> was willing and she was won, that
after faith and troth as soone as the shéepehards coulde
come together a feast was made we kept holiday and they
were married, and because these louers made this place
the concealer of their passions the shéepehardes for perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
memorie of <hi>Phillis</hi> and <hi>Coridon</hi> call this the vale of
Loue, and in praise thereof we countrie shéephards made
an Ode, which if it please you to stay I will rehearse. The
Ladies passing willing, thus the shephearde gan report.</p>
                        <lg>
                           <head>The Sheepeherds Ode.</head>
                           <l>WAlking in a valley greene,</l>
                           <l>Spred with Flora summer queene:</l>
                           <l>Where shee heaping all hir graces,</l>
                           <l>Niggard seemd in other places.</l>
                           <l>Spring it was and here did spring,</l>
                           <l>All that nature forth can bring:</l>
                           <l>Groues of pleasant trees there grow,</l>
                           <l>Which fruit and shadowe could bestow.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="54" facs="tcp:6220:32"/>Thick leaued boughes small birds couer,</l>
                           <l>Till sweete notes themselues discouer:</l>
                           <l>Tunes for number seemed confounded,</l>
                           <l>Whilst their mixtures musicke sounded.</l>
                           <l>Greeing well, yet not agreed,</l>
                           <l>That one the other should exceede.</l>
                           <l>A sweete streame here silent glides,</l>
                           <l>Whose cleare water no fish hides.</l>
                           <l>Slow it runs which well bewraid,</l>
                           <l>The pleasant shore the current staid:</l>
                           <l>In this streame a rocke was planted,</l>
                           <l>Where nor art nor nature wanted.</l>
                           <l>Each thing so did other grace,</l>
                           <l>As all places may giue place.</l>
                           <l>Onely this the place of pleasure,</l>
                           <l>Where is heaped natures treasure.</l>
                           <l>Here mine eyes with woonder staide.</l>
                           <l>Eies amasd and minde afraide:</l>
                           <l>Rauisht with what was beheld,</l>
                           <l>From departing were withheld.</l>
                           <l>Musing then with sound aduise,</l>
                           <l>On this earthly paradise:</l>
                           <l>Sitting by the riuer side,</l>
                           <l>Louely Phillis was discride;</l>
                           <l>Golde hir haire, bright hir eyen,</l>
                           <l>Like to Phoebus in his shine.</l>
                           <l>White hir brow, hir face was faire,</l>
                           <l>Amber breath perfumde the aire.</l>
                           <l>Rose and Lilly both did seeke,</l>
                           <l>To shew their glories on hir cheeke.</l>
                           <l>Loue did nestle in hir lookes,</l>
                           <l>Baiting there his sharpest hookes.</l>
                           <l>Such a Phillis nere was seene,</l>
                           <l>More beautifull then Loues Queene,</l>
                           <l>Doubt it was whose greater grace,</l>
                           <l>Phillis beauty or the place.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="55" facs="tcp:6220:32"/>Hir coate was of scarlet red,</l>
                           <l>All in pleates a mantle spred:</l>
                           <l>Fringd with gold, a wreath of bowes,</l>
                           <l>To check the sunne from hir browes.</l>
                           <l>In hir hand a shepheards hooke,</l>
                           <l>In hir face Dianas looke:</l>
                           <l>Hir sheepe grased on the plaines,</l>
                           <l>Shee had stolne from the swaines.</l>
                           <l>Vnder a coole silent shade,</l>
                           <l>By the streames shee garlands made.</l>
                           <l>Thus sate Phillis all alone,</l>
                           <l>Mist shee was by Coridon</l>
                           <l>Chiefest swaine of all the rest,</l>
                           <l>Louely Phillis like him best.</l>
                           <l>His face was like Phoebus loue,</l>
                           <l>His necke white as Venus Doue,</l>
                           <l>A ruddy cheeke filde with smiles,</l>
                           <l>Such loue hath when he beguiles.</l>
                           <l>His locks browne, his eies were gray,</l>
                           <l>Like Titan in a sommer day.</l>
                           <l>A russet Iacket sleeues red,</l>
                           <l>A blew bonnet on his hed:</l>
                           <l>A cloake of gray fencst the raine,</l>
                           <l>Thus tyred was this louely swaine.</l>
                           <l>A shepheards hooke his dog tide,</l>
                           <l>Bag and bottle by his side:</l>
                           <l>Such was Paris shepheards say,</l>
                           <l>When with Oenone he did play.</l>
                           <l>From his flocke straid Coridon,</l>
                           <l>Spying Phillis all alone:</l>
                           <l>By the streame he Phillis spide,</l>
                           <l>Brauer then was Floras pride.</l>
                           <l>Downe the valley gan he tracke,</l>
                           <l>Stole behinde his true loues backe:</l>
                           <l>The sunne shone and shadow made,</l>
                           <l>Phillis rose and was afraid.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="56" facs="tcp:6220:33"/>When shee saw hit louer there,</l>
                           <l>Smile shee did and left hir feare:</l>
                           <l>Cupid that disdaine doth loth,</l>
                           <l>With desire strake them both.</l>
                           <l>The swaine did wooe shee was nise,</l>
                           <l>Following fashion nayed him twise:</l>
                           <l>Much adooe he kist hir then,</l>
                           <l>Maidens blush when they kisse men:</l>
                           <l>So did Phillis at that stowre.</l>
                           <l>Hir face was like the rose flowre.</l>
                           <l>Last they greed for loue would so,</l>
                           <l>Faith and troth they would no mo.</l>
                           <l>For shepheards euer held it sin,</l>
                           <l>To false the loue they liued in.</l>
                           <l>The swaine gaue a girdle red,</l>
                           <l>Shee set garlands on his hed.</l>
                           <l>Gifts were giuen they kisse againe,</l>
                           <l>Both did smile for both were faine.</l>
                           <l>Thus was loue mongst shepheards solde,</l>
                           <l>When fancy knew not what was golde:</l>
                           <l>They woed &amp; vowed, &amp; that they keep,</l>
                           <l>And goe contented to their sheep.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <trailer>The ende of the shepheards Ode.</trailer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>ASsoone as the shepeharde repeated his Ode, <hi>Terentia</hi>
delighted with the description of the pastorall loue for
that it touched hir passions gaue him heartie thankes
and so the swaine tooke his leaue and departed. <hi>Terentia</hi>
and the rest hereupon growing into the effectes of loue
that kéepes no proportion of persons, wandring on
talking towardes the groue. And for that the sun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
grewe hote and was risen to the highest zenith of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens,
seeking for shelter they went into the groue which
was seated hard by the pleasant current, finding out there
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6220:33"/>
a place conuenient, these thrée Ladies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it them downe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
the grasse, where delighted with the melodie of the
birdes, and the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lenesse of the shade they fell a sléepe.
Then liued in <hi>Rome Vatinus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Senator which was one
of the most wealthie in possessions of any that had béene
consull in the Citie, fauoured euery way by fortune, had
he not beene thwarted by one gréeuous &amp; dolefull misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.
For this <hi>Vatinius</hi> amongst manie children had his
eldest sonne as first in byrth, so brauest in proportion, of
such exquisite lyneaments touching the outwarde shape,
as nature séemed to haue béene curious in hir workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe:
but otherwise hee was so foolish and of clownish
capacitie that there was no hope of his future conceipt,
his name was after his father <hi>Vatinius.</hi> But for because
neither by the diligence of anie maister, nor the flattery of
his friendes, correction, or anie other industrie he coulde
bee made capable of learning or ciuilitie, vsing fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
and woordes from a harshe and grosse voyce, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resembling
rather a bruite beast then a reasonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
he was in derision called of euery man <hi>Fabius</hi> the
Foole. <hi>Vatinius</hi> gréeuing that the gods had offered him
this wronge for that the presence of <hi>Fabius</hi> was the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall
source of his sorrowes, hée commanded that hee
shoulde goe to his Farme, and there liue amongst his
shepheards. This was no little content to <hi>Fabius</hi> as one
that delighted more in the nature of Clownes and bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slaues
then in the courtly behauior of libertines &amp; gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.
<hi>Fabius</hi> thus being in the countrie applying himselfe
to all principles of husbandrie, one day amongst the rest
walked foorth with a great batte on his necke to ouer-sée
his fathers pastures, at last for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the Sunne was hie and
shone hote, he went into the groue then all ouerclad with
leaues, for it was far spring, and féeling a place wherein
at pleasure to rest himselfe, hee stumbled by fortune on
the fount where <hi>Terentia</hi> lay a sléepe, who when <hi>Fabius</hi>
espied being clad in a robe of Bisse so thinne as the white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6220:34"/>
of hir skinne did appeare, hauing hir two companions
by hir side, he began as one amazed to beholde. Leaning
therefore on his great batte without vttring one worde,
he stood in great admiration what she should be, as though
he had neuer séene so braue a creature before. Nowe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring
into his rusticall and blunt vnderstanding (where
neuer before could be ingrauen any impression of honest
ciuilitie a thought of fancie which made him confesse in
his grosse and materiall spirits that this mayde was the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>airest thing y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> euer could be censured by sight. In this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour
he began to descant of hir seuerall beauties, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
hir hayre to be of gold, hir forehead of Iuorie, hir lips
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oral, &amp; aboue all hir two breasts which then began to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
like pretie tender buddes, in such simple sort so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguishing
of hir fauours that from a grosse clowne hee
became to be a Iudge of Beautie: especially coueting to
sée hir eyes which heauie sléepe had shut vp, determining
often to haue waked hir to haue contented himselfe with
their sight. But séeing hir more faire then any creature
that before he had séene, he thought hir to bee some God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desse.
Hauing thus farre knowledge that things deuine
should be reuerenced more then humaine, and therefore
durst not attempe to wake hir, but (although shée had a
sounde and long sléepe) tooke such pleasure in contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
hir perfections that he would by no delay depart. At
last after a longe space <hi>Terentia</hi> awaked before any of
the rest, lifting vp hir drowsie eyes shee sawe before hir
<hi>Fabius</hi> leaning vpon his staffe, whereof béeing halfe ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed
shée asked of him. <hi>Fabius,</hi> what séekest thou here in
this groue? <hi>Fabius</hi> who as well by his countenance as
clemencie and for the nobilitie of his house, as the riches
of his father, was generally knowne of all the Romains,
made no answere to <hi>Terentia:</hi> but séeng hir eyes open he
began to looke stedfastly vpon them féeling a pleasing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
to issu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from those Lampes which sparkle as the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
flames of loue: insomuch that <hi>Terentia</hi> séeing him gase
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6220:34"/>
so earnestly fearing the sturdie clowne might offer hir
some violence wakened hir companions and starting vp
said <hi>Fabius</hi> farwell. To whome <hi>Fabius</hi> made aunswere
I will goe with you. And although <hi>Terentia</hi> refused as
being surprised with great fear of his rustical disposition,
yet he would not forsake hir till he had brought hir to hir
Fathers house, where bluntly leauing the Ladie he went
home to his Fathers; saying hee woulde not returne ani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
more into the countrie. Although it gréeued his Father to
haue his sorrowe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually before his eies, yet wondring
what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occasio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this strange motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> should mean, he was
content to let him remaine at home in the Citie. Loues
arrowes thus piercing into the heart of <hi>Fabius</hi> wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
neuer before any ciuill thought could enter, made such
a Metamorphosis of his minde that not onely his Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r
&amp; friends, but all <hi>Roome</hi> began to woonder at his sodaine
alteration: for he required to be apparelled as the sonne
of a Senator which his father with all diligence perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
then frequenting the most courteous and honest
young Gentlemen of the Citie, especially such as were
amorous, he to the great astonishig of all not onely lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
his letters, but became verie studious, grew to haue
déepe insight into philosophie, to be skilfull in musicke, to
ride a horse and to be expert in all gentle and manlike ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie,
to conclude in short space he was one of the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest
young men of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here by the way courteous Ladies and braue gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
what shal I say of the transformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Fabius?</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in my opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this: That y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> high vertues of the heauens
infused into his noble brest were imprisoned by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> enuious
wrath of Fortune within some narrowe corner of his
heart, whose bandes went a sunder by loue, as a Lord to
mightie for fortune. <hi>Cupid</hi> the raiser vp of sléepy thoughts
dispersed those vertues into euery part of his mind obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
before with the eclipse of base thoughts. Let vs then
think of loue as of the most purest passion that is inserted
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6220:35"/>
into the heart of man. Well, leauing <hi>Fabius</hi> studious how
to excell in all laudable vertues, againe to <hi>Tullie,</hi> who ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued
in post haste to the lodging of <hi>Lentulus</hi> and founde
him passing sicke, yet somewhat comforted at the sight of
<hi>Cicero,</hi> as of him y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he held most déere in the world. <hi>Tullie</hi>
séeing him so ill &amp; full of passio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s durst not tel him y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he had
seene <hi>Terentia</hi> least hir froward answere should augment
his miserie, concealing therfore his chat y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he had with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
Ladies, at last <hi>Lentulus</hi> shewed him the letter of <hi>Flauia:</hi>
whereupon they fell to discourse of hir beauties and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,
howe she was not much inferiour to <hi>Terentia</hi> in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour,
but farre beyond hir in honours, discoursing so long
from point to point that after a vole of broken sighes tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered
with some teares hée fell a sléepe. <hi>Tullie</hi> glade that
he tooke a nappe stole softly out of the Chamber, and being
by himselfe calling to minde the words of <hi>Terentia</hi> began
to enter into this combate with himselfe.</p>
            <p>So pliant are the aspectes of the foreappointing stars
in some mens natiuitie as they force fortune mauger hir
owne variable nature to bee constant. Amongst all that
haue béene borne in the poore village of <hi>Arpinatum,</hi> thou
maist <hi>Tullie</hi> say that thy planets haue béene pleasing, and
thy desires fauorable, who the son of a poore Fermour art
in hope to make thy house equal with the most in <hi>Roome.</hi>
Measure but thy honour and Iudge of thy fortunes: thy
family base, yet art thou companion with Senators and
men of grauest account in the Citie. Honour treades on
thy héele and dignitie daunceth attendance at thy lookes:
but loue <hi>Cicero,</hi> that deitie, that diuine essence that sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
vp content in al estates he stoopeth at thy frown, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentes
thée wreaths of myrtle that thou maist enter into
<hi>Paphos</hi> without checke. <hi>Terentia</hi> the wonder of <hi>Rome,</hi>
Natures Paragon, the refined beautie of the heauens, she
that seemeth to glaunce on the Pretextati: she that makes
no account of the miracle of our time, Lord <hi>Lentulus:</hi> shée
<hi>Cicero</hi> commaunded by loue, yéelds hir selfe captiue to the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6220:35"/>
sonne of a poore country villager in <hi>Arpinatum.</hi> Then <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi>
strew <hi>Venus</hi> temple with roses, say there is no fount
but <hi>Alcydalion:</hi> no hill but <hi>Erecinus:</hi> no bird but the doue:
no god but <hi>Cupid.</hi> Loose not oportunity, take hir by the
foreheade, let not slip occasion, for shée glydes away like a
shadow, nor loue, for she hangs at the héeles at time. Nowe
<hi>Terentia</hi> hath put the iron in the fire, strike then while it
is hot, pay hir downe poundes of loue for drams of fancy,
for in matching w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the daughter of a senator, think it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sageth
thou shalt be a Senator: so shalt thou gaine at one
time honour, dignity, wealth, and beauty; but with that
loose thy faith <hi>Tully,</hi> thy faith thou hast vowed to <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi>
who shuts vp his secretes in thy heart, and resteth his
thoughts on thy bosome. Wilt thou preferre honour before
thy friend, or wealth before conscience. Ah <hi>Tully</hi> if thou be
the man y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Roome</hi> woondreth at for thy eloquence, be also
the man that they shall canonize for thy vertues. Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
is but a bauins blaze, wealth is but a fickle fauour of
fortune, dignity is haunted by enuy: but friendship that
is the pretious treasure that neither time nor fortune
can violate. Why but <hi>Terentia</hi> will neuer loue <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus,</hi>
then <hi>Tully</hi> hate thou euer <hi>Terentia.</hi> I am
a man and subiect vnto loue as well as <hi>Lentulus:</hi> So art
thou a man and being false to thy friend art vnworthy all
loue. Abandon <hi>Tully</hi> these vaine imaginations, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ount <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia</hi>
foule, deformed, vitious and what not, as long as
one sparke of loue lieth rakt vp in the cynders of thy
thoughts: and as long as <hi>Lentulus</hi> loues hir, hate hir for
thy self, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oue hir for <hi>Lentulus.</hi> Setting downe his rest
at this period, he went into the chamber to sée if <hi>Lentulus</hi>
were awake, but finding him still fast a sléepe, he went to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the Capitoll, where he met with <hi>Flaminius</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of <hi>Terentia</hi> who demaunded very heartily how <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus</hi>
did. <hi>Cicero</hi> with a déepe sigh said passing sick. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
quoth <hi>Flaminius</hi> grows the disease, I heard that <hi>Ascla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po</hi>
iudgeth his sickenes to be mortall. <hi>Tully</hi> thinking to set
all on the dice, not respecting his owne loue but his faith
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6220:36"/>
to his friend, began thus. Graue Senator, I néede not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearse
<hi>Lentulus</hi> byrth, as beeing a citizen, nor his reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes,
his possessions long knowne to euery man, nor his
honours ended in victories, for the <hi>Parthians</hi> are sufficient
euidence of his well discharged dignities and valour. <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus</hi>
graced in the prime of his youth with these fauours,
hearing of the beauty of a <hi>Romaine</hi> Lady, left the warres
and came to <hi>Roome,</hi> where courting his mistresse not
with wanton poemes, but with tearmes of marriage: hee
f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>und hir froward, and his loue dasht in the prime. The
impression of hir beauty grauen with too déepe a caracter
was too fast rooted in his heart to be thrust out with deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all:
yet <hi>Lentulus</hi> to content hir, plaies like the phenix,
burnes in his owne parfumes, rather wishing to die then
to contrary hir resolution. This is the cause that first
brought <hi>Lentulus</hi> to his bedde, and this ere long will bring
him to his graue. And who may it be quoth <hi>Flaminius,</hi> of
what family, of what beauty, of what degrée, that can
or dare deny Lorde <hi>Lentulus?</hi> Is he not mighty and may
commaund by force, what he cannot obtaine by intreaty?
will not the souldiers at his becke rise in armes? Feare not
the Consuls themselues to wrong <hi>Lentulus?</hi> Doth not all
<hi>Roome</hi> hang their thoughts at his lookes? Ah miserable
father that harbours such a daughter, and stubborne hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife
that denies so braue a <hi>Romaine.</hi> In friendship <hi>Tully</hi>
tell me who it is. <hi>Cicero</hi> willing to put a spurre to a frée
horse, and to loose his owne content to winne his friendes
quiet, told him flatly it was his daughter <hi>Terentia:</hi> and for
proofe he shewed him the letters that past betwixt <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>
and hir. Assoone as hir father had read the contents, as
a man half mad he fel into furious and frantick tearmes,
exclaiming against the headstrong humour of foolish <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia.</hi>
After he had breathd out the heat of his choller, he
fell to be somewhat appeased, and bad <hi>Tully</hi> home to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
promising all shoulde sort according vnto <hi>Lentulus</hi>
minde. With that departing from the Capitoll, <hi>Tully</hi> and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6220:36"/>
he went home to his house, where the Cooke being some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
slacke: <hi>Flaminius</hi> hearing his daughter was all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
in the garden, he wished <hi>Tully</hi> to try hir once againe,
and to perswade hir by all possible means to graunt to the
request of <hi>Lentulus.</hi> Upon this <hi>Tully</hi> went into the garden
where finding <hi>Terentia</hi> sitting solitary in an arbour vp to
the hard eares in a dumpe, he wakened hir out of hir muse
thus. <hi>Vestas</hi> chiefe paragon, and <hi>Venus</hi> newe interteined
darling, you madam <hi>Terentia</hi> I meane, that sit in a muse:
are you offring orisons to <hi>Diana</hi> for your chastity, or
thanks to <hi>Cupid</hi> for your loues: or what are you thinking
on when you thinke on nothing? <hi>Terentia</hi> turning hir
head and séeing <hi>Tully</hi> all alone, blusht more then <hi>Cynthia</hi>
did when shée wantond it with hir faire faced shepheard,
yet welcomming hir loue with a smile, shée tooke him by
the hand and made him this answere.</p>
            <p>Your subtile salutation concluding <hi>Vesta</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> in
one <hi>Dilemma</hi> commands me answere that I was dooing
my deuotion to both, offring prayers for my olde thoughts
&amp; thanks for my newe loues: &amp; scarce had I saide gramer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
to the goddesse, but you must come <hi>Cicero</hi> to make my
thanks prodigious: for my thinking when I thought of
nothing it was of mens loues which are lighter then the
flame, and sooner faded then a flash of lightning: But I
pray you say what winde hath driuen you into this coast.</p>
            <p>Marry madame the very sighes that fly from <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>
breast grewe to so great a storme that I was blowne
hither to séeke shelter for the tempest. You haue nothing
quoth <hi>Terentia</hi> but <hi>Lentulus</hi> in your mouth: I pray you say
how fares the gentleman? Ill madame quoth <hi>Tully</hi> euery
way, for his dyet is badde in that his stomacke is nought,
and his health is doubtfull in that his thoughtes are dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet:
and madame it rests in you to saue so honourable a
gentleman not onely from sickenes but from sorrowe: <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi>
was a stragling <hi>Troian</hi> an exile periured and banisht
euen from the ruines of <hi>Troy,</hi> yet <hi>Dydo</hi> the famous <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:6220:37"/>
quéene made him hir paramour. <hi>Demophoon</hi> a py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat
a robber in <hi>Greece</hi> cast vp as shipwrack on the shore,
yet interteind by <hi>Phillis. Phao</hi> a ferryman, a slaue, yet fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured
by <hi>Sapho. Lentulus</hi> the hope of the <hi>Romains,</hi> more
beautifull then <hi>Eneas,</hi> more couragious th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Demophoon,</hi>
more honourable then <hi>Phao,</hi> more louing then them all, is
refused and reiected by <hi>Terentia,</hi> his neighbour and famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar.
Thinke not <hi>Terentia</hi> but loue as hee hath roses so hee
hath nettles, as he hath perfumes so hath hee hemblocke,
and holding fauors the claspeth reuenge, as ready to pierce
as to pacifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. If you procure <hi>Lentulus</hi> death, <hi>Cupid</hi> hath
power to inforce your dispaire, and to cause your loue to be
as fickle to you as you are froward to him. Then madam
let me be the messenger of life, and from your swéete selfe
carry such conserues to <hi>Lentulus</hi> as may recouer his
health and increase your honours. This discourse of <hi>Tully</hi>
did but sette <hi>Terentias</hi> heart more on fire. For hearing the
pleasant harmony of hir <hi>Cicero,</hi> shée likt of the musicke
as of the <hi>Syrens</hi> melody, and so intangled hir selfe with
many newe conceiued fancies, insomuch that forgetting
whose daughter shée was, shée burst foorth into these
tearmes.</p>
            <p>Did I not <hi>Cicero</hi> tell thée twixt <hi>Arpinatum</hi> &amp; <hi>Roome,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
loue hath but one cell wherein to place the <hi>Idaea</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> party
loued: wilt thou haue me like the Camelion to haue many
colours, or like <hi>Helena</hi> to intertain many loues? I know
<hi>Lentulus</hi> dignities are beyond my degrée, that his honors
are more then my fortunes, that his loue is great, and so
I holde him the second in my most secrete thoughtes: first
he cannot be and that he craues. Thou doest wring water
out of the flint, fier forth of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> dry sandes, &amp; immodesty from
hir that hath euer béene honoured for chastily: so that by
wastlesse perswasions for thy friende, I am forst to say
thou art the friend that <hi>Terentia</hi> hath chosen amongst all
the worthy <hi>Romains:</hi> Before I sawe thée <hi>Tully</hi> I loued
thee, and now I haue setled my affection, and thou wrongst
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6220:37"/>
me with discurtesie: but either cease from intreating for
<hi>Lentulus,</hi> or looke to sée me worse then <hi>Lentulus.</hi> And with
this blushing at hir owne ouermuch loues, shée poured
foorth such abundance of teares, as well might bew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay
the sincerity of hir affections. <hi>Tully</hi> gréeuing to sée the
goddesse of his thoughtes in this passion answered hir,
mildly thus. Blame me not <hi>Terentia</hi> if I pleade for <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus,</hi>
séeing his sorrow, and entring into mine owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise.
Then friendship is no swéeter iewell, then howe can
I but labour ere I loose so rich a prize. But séeing <hi>Terentia</hi>
hath vouchsafed of so meane a man as <hi>Tully,</hi> whose ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
onely hanges in his studies: loue béeing the stric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
league of amity and no such friendship as is mariage:
I vowe by the <hi>Romaine</hi> gods, euer to be a duetifull ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant
vnto a <hi>Terentia:</hi> and with my loyalty so to requite hir
fauours, as <hi>Roome</hi> shall more admire my affections then
they haue woondred at my eloquence: yet with this <hi>proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so</hi>
(my swéete <hi>Terentia</hi>) that although I preferre thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours
before mine owne life, yet if thou canst striue to
loue <hi>Lentulus,</hi> which if either the gods, loue, fortune, or thy
selfe can bring to passe, I will with mine owne preiudice
conquer mine owne thoughtes to satisfie the content of
<hi>Lentulus.</hi> As <hi>Terentia</hi> was ready to reply, one of hir fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
seruants came to request <hi>Cicero</hi> to come to supper,
who taking his leaue of <hi>Terentia</hi> went in to hir father
<hi>Flaminius,</hi> who sitting downe to supper, passed away the
time in ordinary talke. Their repast being taken, <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius</hi>
calling <hi>Tully</hi> on the one side, demaunded what his
daughters answere was. Peremptory quoth <hi>Tully</hi> still to
hold <hi>Lentulus</hi> in mislike. Then you shall heare quoth hir
father what I will say, and so report to <hi>Lentulus:</hi> so calling
for <hi>Terentia</hi> they thrée being together, he began thus.</p>
            <p>I knowe not howe <hi>Terentia</hi> to insinuate my exordium,
whether friendly to perswade with a smyle, or fatherly to
admonish with a frowne: thy follies are so great, and my
care so tender. <hi>Roome</hi> hath hitherto admyred thy vertues,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6220:38"/>
and I haue praised thy obedience: thou hast béene counted
honorable and chast, wise to eschew wantonnesse, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
coy to be thought disdainefull: and shall nowe all these
graces ende in disgrace? Then <hi>Terentia</hi> maiest thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
hereafter, and I powre forth present sorrowes. I
speake thus, for that I heare in the city what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
me to grieue, and may force thée to blush. They say
<hi>Terentia</hi> is beautiful and proude, witty and ouerwéening,
hauing coy disdaine crept into the place of curteous desire:
this men say that enuy thy follyes, and grieue at <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>
fortunes. Now daughter thou séest the marke I aime
at, and maiest iudge of my shot by the leuell: <hi>Lentulus</hi> is
fallen into a feuer, which <hi>Asclapo</hi> that famous Phisition
of <hi>Patras</hi> censures to be mortall. Thy frowardnes was
the efficient of the disease, and nowe thou deniest cure of
the maladie. Unaduised gyrle, that neither weighest of
thine owne honours, nor his miseries. <hi>Lentulus</hi> requires
<hi>Terentia</hi> in mariage: let vs make compare of the parties,
and so examine the cause of thy denials. He is descended
from the <hi>Lentuli</hi> and <hi>Aemilij,</hi> two houses that euer haue
béene the props of the <hi>Romaine</hi> dignities. His honours
are great, as proconsul in his youth against the <hi>Parthians:</hi>
His fortunes mighty, doubled with his conquests and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories:
His reuenewes such as he may with <hi>Crassus</hi>
maintaine Legions. If like <hi>Venus</hi> darling thou séekest to
féede thine eie, his fauour is more then his that pleased
<hi>Cynthia.</hi> If thou couetest a souldier, <hi>Lentulus</hi> in <hi>Roome</hi>
is as <hi>Hector</hi> was in <hi>Troy.</hi> If a Courtier, who braues it so
in <hi>Italy?</hi> To conclude if <hi>Terentia</hi> couet to loue, there is
none so fit to loue within the <hi>Romaine</hi> Empire as <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</hi>
Whereas <hi>Terentia</hi> is but the daughter of a meane
Senatour, hir dowry cannot be much, for that hir fathers
wealth is not great: Beautifull shée is, and so are many in
<hi>Roome,</hi> who are of meaner parentage. Hir glories are
but fortunes pelfe, that florishe in the morning, and fade
before night. What then can mooue <hi>Terentia</hi> to oppose hir
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6220:38"/>
selfe against <hi>Lentulus?</hi> vnlesse shée fatally presageth hir
owne discredit, and the ruine of hir fathers house. If then
daughter thou art child to <hi>Flaminius,</hi> I charge thée by the
strickt law of nature, which Philosophers call <hi>Regius a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor</hi>
a kingly loue, if thou be a maide, by the holy fiers of
<hi>Vesta:</hi> if beautifull, by <hi>Venus</hi> deity: if a <hi>Romaine,</hi> by thy
Countryes loue, that thou loue <hi>Lentulus:</hi> which if thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse
to performe, thy father shall curse thée, <hi>Vesta</hi> shall
shut thée from hir temples, <hi>Venus</hi> from hir fauours, and
thy country from inioying the swéete content of honour,
and then make thée outcast of all the <hi>Romaine</hi> virgines.
More are my reasons to alleage, then thy reasons able to
contrary: but omitting all and saying he is onely <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus:</hi>
Daughter what answere?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Terentia</hi> séeing hir father in such a choller, and that hée
was induced vnto it by <hi>Ciceros</hi> perswasio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in a furie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
thus frantike. I not denie but Fathers challenge
loue by nature and obedience by duetie, and both those sir
I hope I haue euer performed, if not I rest sorrowfull &amp;
hartily craue pardon: but in loue parentes haue no priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.
For the liking of the Father is no contract of the
daughter. <hi>Venus</hi> conclusions growe not of parentes pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises,
nor can affection bee like the fire stroken foorth a
flint, for loue is chosen by the eye and confirmed by the
heart, womens thoughtes are not the spoyles of <hi>Mars,</hi>
nor is the battell of fancie fought with the sworde, but
with the Senses, &amp; loues arrowes are pointed by fate and
fortune. Weigh then <hi>Terentia,</hi> who hath not hir loues in
hir hande but in hir heart and thereinto none can make
breach, but such a one as the pleasing constellation of the
stars haue appointed. I not denie the excellencie of <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus</hi>
as well in exterior shewe of honours, wealth, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
and proportion, as in interior vertues &amp; perfections
of the minde, and that he merittes a Ladie of farre more
estéeme then <hi>Terentia,</hi> but I knowe not what contrarie
aspect either of the planets in our natiuities, or of loues
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6220:39"/>
in our thoughtes, or of fortune in our resolution <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o like,
hath crossed his desire and my fancie, but of all the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne
Gentlemen I cannot my Lorde fancie <hi>Lentulus.
Cressida</hi> confest <hi>Troylus</hi> was the better knight, &amp; yet the
Gréeke helde hir louely in his tent. Sith then affection
growes from desire, and desire is tyed to destinie, séeke
not sir to wring water out of the pumex, to couple the
Mouse and the Elephant at one stall, to vnite those loues
that <hi>Venus</hi> in hir Sinod house hath expreslie counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>checkt.
For to aunswere your obiection, <hi>Terentia</hi> cannot
force hir self to loue <hi>Lentulus.</hi> Shée thus concluding with
a few teares, hir father departing from hir with a frown,
tolde <hi>Tullie</hi> that not reason was sufficient to induce his
daughter to be affectionate, and therefore that hee wished
<hi>Lentulus</hi> to appease his passions and to salue such impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibilities
with patience, wherupon they after interchange
of salutations and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon courtesies parted with a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
farewell. <hi>Tullie</hi> at his home comming reuealed
vnto <hi>Lentulus</hi> the whole discourse howe <hi>Flaminius</hi> had
searcht into the depth of <hi>Terentias</hi> thoughtes both with
plawsible perswasions and inforced reasons, and coulde
finde no other conclusion but that shée could not loue <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus.</hi>
Although this newes pierced the verie center of
his heart as mortallie as if hee had béene wounded with
the sting of <hi>Aspis:</hi> yet chéering himselfe a little he sat vp
and in his owne minde hauing aboute or two with fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,
he gaue hir so deepe a reuie that hee held affection at
the swordes point. But <hi>Tullie</hi> who betwéene friendship
and loue felt a furious combate, allured with the beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
perfection of <hi>Terentia,</hi> and forbidden that fauour by
the entyre amitie hee had vowed vnto <hi>Lentulus:</hi> entred
into so déepe a melancholie that not able to master his pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,
he fell sicke and kept his bed. <hi>Lentulus</hi> séeing hys
<hi>Tullie</hi> thus distrest gréeued at his friends misfortune, and
chéered vp himselfe that hee might somewhat comfort his
<hi>Cicero</hi> that newlie was crossed with a distempered sicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6220:39"/>
He sought by physicke to search out the nature of the
disease, but <hi>Asclapo</hi> could not déeme the cause by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes,
he sought by intreaties to wrest out the occasion
of so sodayne a sorrow, but in vayne, <hi>Tullie</hi> was too se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete
and silent to make anie shewe of his loues though he
bought such secresie with death. This gréeued <hi>Lentulus</hi>
who féeling himselfe euery day to amend, perceiued that
<hi>Cicero</hi> daylie waxed worse and worse. Lingring thus in
inward passions, <hi>Terentia</hi> that tooke it discourteously at
<hi>Tullies</hi> hande that hee should force hir Father to inforce
hir to loue <hi>Lentulus,</hi> séeing shée had onely deuoted hirselfe
as his, howsoeuer fortune shoulde oppose hir selfe; to ease
hir mind of some choller that boiled in hir secret thoughts
shée tooke penne and inke and wrote him a letter to this
effect.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Terentia to Marcus Tullius
Cicero health.</head>
                  <p>AS my thoughtes are secrete and my loues extréeme, so
is vnkindenesse bitter and the more vneasie borne.
Thou playest <hi>Tullie</hi> with me, as doe the <hi>Leopards</hi> with
there kéeper; that euer wrong them most that giue them
greatest store of fodder. Are these <hi>Venus</hi> lawes to pay
hunnie with Gall, to make rods of nettles for Garlands
of Roses, to hate them most that loue most. The ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
of <hi>Tullie</hi> hath drawen <hi>Terentia</hi> into this choller, and
if I write sharpely blame me not that am vsed so shrowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.
Before I euer sawe thy face I allowed thy fauour, &amp;
onelie hearing of thy vertues with myne eare, I regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred
them vp déepely in my hearte. <hi>Terentia</hi> hath béene
courted of manie, yet neuer made account of any: sundry
haue sought my loues, but they haue returned with losse.
<hi>Lentulus</hi> the terrour of the <hi>Parthians,</hi> the honour of the
<hi>Romaines</hi> and thy friend hath long woode, but what hath
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6220:40"/>
hee won? onelie <hi>Tullie</hi> hath obtayned that which so many
haue mist, and yet he deales with <hi>Terentia</hi> as crabbedlie
as shee vsed him courteously, doe louers for fishes proffer
scorpions, or doe they like the serpent sting him which
cheerisheth him vp in his bosome. I séeke to fauour <hi>Tullie</hi>
and hee importunate sues for fauour for <hi>Lentulus.</hi> Art
thou so déepe a philosopher, as to déeme friendship aboue
marriage, or faith aboue fancie, or thy <hi>Terentia</hi> lesse then
thy <hi>Lentulus?</hi> If it be so take héede that <hi>Terentia</hi> too much
wronged scornes not both thée and <hi>Lentulus.</hi> Womens
thoughtes consistes oft in extréemes, and they that loue
most, if abused, hate most deadlie, fear this and beware of
my frowne, as yet there is but one wrinckle in my brow,
but if it once proue full of angrie sorrowes it will bee too
late to take holde of occasion behind: Thou art forewarnd
be forearmd and so farewell.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thy Terentia if thou wrong not Terentia.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>AFter shée had written this Letter shée causde it to bee
conueied by <hi>Eutrapelus</hi> to <hi>Tullie,</hi> who reading the
contentes found not a salue to cure his maladie, but that
<hi>Terentia</hi> rubbed the scare a fresh by shaking him vp so
sharpely, yet coueting rather to die with an honourable
minde to <hi>Lentulus,</hi> then with a discredite to enioy beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull
<hi>Terentia,</hi> he laide his heade on his pillowe, and with
manie sighes bewraide the depth of his sorrows. Hauing
laide his letter at his beds heade ouercharged with many
cares poore <hi>Tullie</hi> fell a sléepe and so sodenlie that <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>
by the helpe of <hi>Eutrapelus</hi> got to haue a sight of his
letter. Assoone as the Gentleman saw how déepely <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>
was affected to his friende and perceyued by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances
that he chose rather to die then to falsifie his
faith, such a secrete loue towardes <hi>Tullie</hi> so pierced the
closet of his honourable thoughtes that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell to conceipt
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6220:40"/>
but meanlie of <hi>Terentia</hi> and to wish that his friende <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi>
might both recouer his health and his loue. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
the fancie of <hi>Lentulus</hi> to freze that earst was so great
a flame, and he that like the <hi>Salamander</hi> delighted to liue
in the fire, beganne to feare to <hi>accedere ad ignem,</hi> least he
shoulde <hi>Calescere plus quam satis.</hi> Now he called to mind
the resolution of <hi>Terentia</hi> tempered with frowardnesse,
and with this he did proportion the vertues of <hi>Flauia</hi> mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with courtesie, finding the fauour of the one aunswera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to the beauty of the other. Then the faith of his friend,
his sickenes and extréeme sorrows. These weighed with
depe consideration he vowed to séeke by all meanes howe
to win <hi>Terentia</hi> wholy for his friende <hi>Cicero.</hi> In this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor
he conuaide the letter vnder his beddes heade and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted
silent till occasion might offer him oportunitie to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer
the perfection of his amitie. Thus grewe <hi>Lentulus</hi>
at one time from his sickenes &amp; his loue, walking abroad &amp;
visiting <hi>Flaminius</hi> who entertayned him in all sumptuous
manner. But <hi>Lentulus</hi> séeing the thrée Ladies, made
no showe to <hi>Terentia</hi> nor scarse glaunced a looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
hir beautie, but onely courted the Ladie <hi>Flauia,</hi> who
he founde so agreeable and plyant to his sutes, that <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>
and <hi>Cornelia</hi> might easilie sée howe depely they were
linked in the league of affection. Leauing <hi>Tullie</hi> thus
sicke on his bed and <hi>Lentulus</hi> in swéete content with <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia,</hi>
againe to our newe transformed <hi>Fabius</hi> who in this
time prooued one of the brauest Gentlemen in <hi>Rome,</hi> and
finding a restlesse passion in his mind for the beutie of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia,</hi>
as hauing continually before his eye the <hi>Idaea</hi> of
hir person séeing by hir meanes hee was metamorphosed
&amp; brought to this perfection making the force of his loue
priuie to his Father <hi>Vatinius,</hi> he was not onely praysed
for his good choice, but willed to goe forwarde in the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning
of his affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Whereupon not willing to make
a long haruest to a small crop, to preuent as hee thought
that none shoulde cut the grasse from vnder his féete, hee
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6220:41"/>
went to <hi>Terentias</hi> Father and blunt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> craued his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
in marriage. He knowing him to be of honourable pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage
and of rich reuenewes, séeing shée woulde not
condiscende vnto <hi>Lentulus</hi> gaue him his francke good will
if he could créepe into his daughters fauour, who taking
the aduantage of the time went to find out <hi>Terentia,</hi> who
as then was verie melancholie sitting with <hi>Flauia</hi> &amp; <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelia</hi>
talking of the sickenes of <hi>Tully.</hi> As they were thus
in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat, came in <hi>Fabius</hi> who they streight knew &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
at his strange alteration, he to shewe hee coulde as
well court it as the brauest young gentleman in <hi>Rome,</hi>
began thus curteously to salute the Ladies.</p>
            <p>Maruell not Ladies if a countrie swayne presume to
attempt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> presence of such rare excellencies séeing <hi>Oeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi>
shéephearde durst with his eye suruay the beautie of
diuine goddesses, and they to shewe they were as grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
and full of fauours gaue him the greatest minion that
was counted the swéetest Peragon of the world. Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
creatures you be, fayre Romaynes, but heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
whose looks lighten diuine influence into the thoughts
of such as dare to contemplate your affections. I speake
this as being the man that from the cart liue in the court,
thus metamophosed by your supernaturall beauties. For
which fauour I am come in duetie to rest a bounden vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie
to your swéete selues. <hi>Terentia</hi> was so pensiue for
<hi>Tullyes</hi> passions that shée woulde make no aunswere: but
<hi>Cornelia</hi> whom alreadie <hi>Cupid</hi> had set on fire with <hi>Fabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>
feature she returned him this replie.</p>
            <p>I remember <hi>Fabius</hi> that sitting in the groue by <hi>Arpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum</hi>
a gentle swaine much like your self, in proportion
though not in properties, séeing wee were slenderly gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
with a page conducted vs home to <hi>Rome</hi> with his
friendlie companie, if it be your selfe, had wee as braue a
Ladie as <hi>Helena</hi> was and were shée in our power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowe,
wée woulde make you master and sole possessour of
hir beauties so to rewarde your courtesie. <hi>Fabius</hi> séeing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6220:41"/>
the marke so faire thought not to loose his shoote, but aim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
his leuell thus.</p>
            <p>And for that cause Ladies is <hi>Fabius</hi> come that his mée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
may not want his merite, glad that <hi>Venus</hi> dewes downe
such fauors, and oportunitie such showers of good fortunes
to finde you all here in so fit a time. For knowe honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Romaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that for my grosse and rude nature ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
the ciuill behauiour of the citie. I was surnamed
<hi>Fabius:</hi> in which obscure life I liued hauing my senses
eclipsed with follie, till the gods grudging at natures
spight, sent you thrée to bee ministers of my happines. For
comming into the groue where you lay all a sléepe casting
mine eye on the beautie of <hi>Terentia:</hi> Such a déepe impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
was figured in my mind, that I felt an vnacquainted
motion with a milde reuerence to thinke well of hir per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection:
surueying hir singular beauties, I fell so farre in
loue with hir excellencie, that from the countrie I came to
y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> citie, &amp; how since by hir gratious sight I haue metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phosed
my selfe your owne eares and the wonder of <hi>Rome</hi>
is best ablè to witnesse. Then Ladies I count the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of my life to come from the feature of <hi>Terentia,</hi> and
that she not as <hi>Diana</hi> chaunged mee from a man to bée a
beast, but contrarie full of fauour hath reduced me from a
sensuall beast to a perfect resonable man. Howe déepely
then I ought to bée vowed to hir whose sight is the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring
of my happinesse, let the greatnesse of my benefite
make manifest. In so much as féeding my thoughts with
the contemplation of <hi>Terentias</hi> beautie, I haue béene thus
transformed, but withall so surprised with hir loue that
as I haue gaind a seconde essence by hir swéete selfe, so I
haue lost my selfe within the labyrinth of hir lookes, that I
remayne hir captiue while it pleaseth hir to graunt me li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.
Bee then braue Romaine Dames, impartiall
doomers of my sute, whether my desertes craue not Loue
that thus haue béene chaunged for hir loue. My Parentes
are Senators, my reuenewes inferiour to none, old <hi>Vati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinius</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:6220:42"/>
glad of my choise, and <hi>Terentias</hi> father thrise hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
if his daughter might like of <hi>Vatinius.</hi> Nowe restes it
onely in <hi>Terentias</hi> power to make me blessed or infortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.
At this discourse of <hi>Fabius,</hi> the Ladies were astoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed,
and <hi>Terentia</hi> galled to the quick with this demaund
held hir tongue, till <hi>Cornelia</hi> and <hi>Flauia,</hi> looking earnestly
vpon hir, asked hir what answere shée made to <hi>Fabius.</hi>
Such quoth shée as I returned to <hi>Lentulus,</hi> for know syr if
either the honor of a Souldier, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> dignity of a <hi>Romain,</hi> the
reuenewes of a Senators sonne, or the déepe impression of
fancy might haue drawn <hi>Terentia</hi> to loue, I had beene ere
this the wife &amp; paramour of <hi>Lentulus.</hi> But not y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> courage
of <hi>Hector</hi> that woone <hi>Andromache,</hi> nor the wisedome of
<hi>Vlisses</hi> that intangled <hi>Calipso,</hi> nor the beauty of <hi>Priamus</hi>
sonne that drew <hi>Greece</hi> in armes to <hi>Troy,</hi> these perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
if combined in one man shoulde not mooue <hi>Terentia</hi>
to listen to the allurements of <hi>Venus:</hi> not that I make
light estéeme of <hi>Lentulus,</hi> or that I holde small account of
<hi>Fabius,</hi> as two chiefe myrrours of our <hi>Romaine</hi> gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:
But that either my vowes are resolute to <hi>Vesta,</hi> or
if <hi>Cupid</hi> hath taken me by the héele, it was before <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>
came from <hi>Parthia,</hi> or you from <hi>Arpinatum:</hi> so that
conclude howsoeuer it is I cannot become affectionate to
<hi>Fabius.</hi> At this reply <hi>Fabius</hi> stoode so amated as if hee had
beene an vnwelcome guest at the feast of <hi>Perseus,</hi> which
<hi>Cornelia</hi> noting, déepely in loue with <hi>Fabius</hi> shée told him
thus. Nor may you <hi>Fabius</hi> thinke much at this repulse sith
<hi>Lentulus</hi> and you are in one predicament, nowe both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
gainers in liberty, that haue béene loosers in loue:
and either gette the willowe garlande and so mourne for
your Ladies frowne, or séeke a mistresse that may shewe
you more fauor: For as for <hi>Terentia</hi> shée hath chosen, and
none must please hir but Oratours. If there be <hi>Fabius</hi> but
one Sunne that is thought the beauty of heauen, yet
there be planets that though not in shine, yet in influence
are as vertuous: what there bee Ladies I meane of such
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:6220:42"/>
course die as my selfe and <hi>Flauia,</hi> that when <hi>Terentia</hi> is
once married, looke for husbands. <hi>Fabius</hi> hearing <hi>Cornelia</hi>
thus pleasant, noted this quippe that none must please hir
but Oratours, which made <hi>Terentia</hi> blush for anger, and
<hi>Fabius</hi> to make this answere. I knowe no Oratours in
<hi>Roome</hi> quoth he whose yeares are answerable to <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias</hi>
thoughtes but onely <hi>Marcus Tullius Cicero,</hi> and if it
be he, I sweare by the fitch that gaue him his syrname,
<hi>Terentia</hi> shall be mistresse of a goodly Cottage in <hi>Arpina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.
Terentia</hi> hearing <hi>Fabius</hi> to giue <hi>Tully</hi> the frumpe
answered thus.</p>
            <p>The more his fortune if it be hee whose vertues hath
made him master of his owne desires, for his lands in <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinatum</hi>
as they be little, yet shall his lacke be counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaild
with his loues: and if he hath not one to inrich him
with dowry, yet I may perhaps content him with beauty.
And therefore <hi>Fabius</hi> to take away all suppositions, it is
<hi>Tully,</hi> &amp; none but <hi>Tully</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> shall inioy <hi>Terentia.</hi> And quoth
<hi>Fabius</hi> in great choller, nor <hi>Tully,</hi> nor none besides <hi>Tully,</hi>
but <hi>Fabius</hi> shall inioy <hi>Terentia.</hi> Whereupon departing
without taking his farewell, going vnto hir father and
discoursing vnto him that <hi>Tully</hi> was the man that his
daughter had chosen for hir husband: swearing that his
sword ere it were long should end their loues. Although
<hi>Flaminius</hi> were grieued, yet he sought to pacifie <hi>Fabius,</hi>
but in vaine: for hee flung out of the dores in a rage, and
went to <hi>Milos</hi> house to séeke <hi>Tully.</hi> Where breathing out
many despightfull threats against the Oratour, it came
at last to <hi>Lentulus</hi> eare. Who nowe to make manifest
the déepe affection he bare to <hi>Cicero,</hi> trouping himselfe
with a crue of the <hi>Praetextati,</hi> and chiefe <hi>Romaine</hi> gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
that had béene souldiers and trained vp with him in
the warres, he went to séeke out <hi>Fabius:</hi> and found him
with certaine his companions about the Capitoll. <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>
not brooking the braue of any, as carrying the heart of
a Conquerour, singled out <hi>Fabius,</hi> and after some wordes
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6220:43"/>
they fell to blowes: but <hi>Fabius</hi> part were the weaker, so
that many were wounded, and some slaine. Upon this the
next day parts were taken, the people began to mutiny,
and to fall to intestine and ciuil iarres: that as in the time
of <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Marius,</hi> so the stréets were filled with armed
Souldiers. The Senatours séeing what bloudy strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems
woulde insue of this strife if it were not pacified:
sent for the Consuls, and charged them to raise vp some of
the Legions and to bring <hi>Lentulus, Tully</hi> and <hi>Fabius,</hi> the
next day to the senate house, with <hi>Terentia</hi> and hir father.
They obeying their commaund put this charge in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,
and so qualifiyng somewhat the fury of the people,
brought these thrée wooers with <hi>Terentia</hi> before the
whole state of <hi>Roome.</hi> Where being arriued <hi>Tully</hi> feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
of nature and sicke, yet somewhat strengthened with
the sight of his mistresse, beeing glad <hi>Lentulus</hi> was his
friend in his loues, after due reuerence began thus.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tullies Oration to the Senate.</head>
               <p>COnscript Fathers and graue Senators of <hi>Room,</hi>
I was borne in <hi>Arpinatum</hi> of base parentage, the
first of the <hi>Ciceroes</hi> that euer pleaded in <hi>Rostro,</hi> or
bare title in the city. If then aduanced by your fauours to
these fortunes, I should aspire without proportion to clime
beyonde my degrée, let me be the first and last whose pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption
shall grow to this preiudice. The temple of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
in <hi>Roome</hi> hath hir gates shut, the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reetes are full of
armed men, the stones of the Capitol blusheth at the bloud
of <hi>Romaines</hi> shed against hir walles: and all this mutiny
(cry mine aduersaries) growes from <hi>Tully.</hi> Not that <hi>Tully</hi>
was then out of his bedde, but that men of poore families
lifted vp to honor are soonest bitten with enuy. I appeale
graue Senatours for my life to your owne censures: if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
I haue not béene more carefull to profit my country,
then desirous of preferment for my labours. But what
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6220:43"/>
then say the people is cause of such broy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, <hi>Terentia</hi> the
daughter of <hi>Flaminius,</hi> that firebrand that set <hi>Troy</hi> to cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.
Beauty is like to bring <hi>Roome</hi> to confusion: For the
greatest houses and families are diuided, the <hi>Lentuly</hi> and
<hi>Vatinij,</hi> and this for <hi>Terentia.</hi> Let the cause be examined
before the Senators, and as they heare so let them doome,
<hi>Lentulus</hi> chosen by the Senate, was sent Captaine euer
many Legions against the <hi>Parthians,</hi> where he tyed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
to his thoughtes: and by his great victories and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests
set vp trophées of <hi>Romaine</hi> chiualry. Returning
with glory to <hi>Roome,</hi> hauing set in his place <hi>Lepidus,</hi> he
was enamonred not onely of the beauty but vertues of
<hi>Terentia:</hi> the fame of whose excellency was spred amongst
the <hi>Parthians.</hi> Coueting to match with so honourable a
Lady, he courted hir, but in vaine: not that shée disdained
<hi>Lentulus,</hi> but that shée had fixed hir fancy before shée sawe
<hi>Lentulus:</hi> and the platforme of loue is able to receiue but
one impression. If honours, if conquestes, if parentage, if
reuenewes, if courage, if goods of fortune, body, or minde,
might haue woonne <hi>Terentia,</hi> al this was vnited in young
<hi>Lentulus:</hi> But Loue that liketh without exceptions, had
ouerbard hir heart with such former fancies, as the passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
sute of <hi>Lentulus</hi> coulde haue no entrance. His
thoughtes were extreame, and the disquiet of his minde
brought a disease to his body. But when he knew that <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia</hi>
loued his friend, he appeased his passions, and rested
content with his fortunes. The vnconstant goddesse whose
smyles are ouershadowed frowns, not conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t honor should
spring vp without enuy: sends <hi>Terentia</hi> to walke abroade
towards <hi>Arpinatum</hi> where then <hi>Fabius</hi> liued, as famous
for his rusticke and vnciuile life, as now he is woondred at
for his braue and courtly behauiour. Spying <hi>Terentia</hi> hee
was as <hi>Lentulus</hi> snared in hir beautie, that the Romains
to report a miracle said loue made him of a clowne braue
&amp; resolute gentleman. The excellencie of <hi>Terentia</hi> hauing
newe pollished nature in <hi>Fabius,</hi> hee sues for hir fauour,
but hir thoughtes that were forepointed with other pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6220:44"/>
intreates him to bridle affection and to make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest
of himselfe by subduing the force of fancie, séeing hir
resolution was directed to loue none but one, and that
was <hi>Tullie.</hi> This worde graue Senators and Romaynes
sounding basely in the eares of <hi>Fabius,</hi> caused him take
armes, and <hi>Lentulus</hi> to defende his friend <hi>Cicero,</hi> as for
him before had lost his loue, so he ment to loose his life and
withstoode him in the face. Thus grew this mutinie not
against beautie for it is a cheefe good of it selfe, nor against
<hi>Tullie</hi> for hee is meane and vnworthie to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged
by armes, but against <hi>Terentia</hi> because shee
vouchsafed to loue <hi>Tulllie.</hi> This Romaines is the cause
of this mutinie to suppresse which let <hi>Tullie</hi> die, for rather
had he pacifie this striffe by death then sée the meanest
Romaine fall on the sword. The common people at this
began to murmour, pleased with the plausible Oration
of <hi>Tullie,</hi> which one of the Senators seeing, stoode vp and
saide thus. <hi>Terentia? Cicero</hi> here hath shewed reasons
why thou shouldst loue <hi>Lentulus</hi> and <hi>Fabius,</hi> but what
reason canst thou infer to loue so meane a man as <hi>Tullie.
Terentia</hi> blushing made this answere. Before so honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
an audience as these graue Senators and worthy Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne
Citizens womens reasons would seeme no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
especially in loue which is without reason, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I onely yeld this reason, I loue <hi>Cicero</hi> not able to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefie
my affection with anie strong reason, because loue is
not circumscript within reasons limits, but if it please the
Senate to pacifie this mutinie, let <hi>Terentia</hi> leaue to liue,
because she cannot leaue to loue and onely to loue <hi>Cicero.</hi>
At this she wept and stayned hir face with such a pleasing
vermilion die, that the people shouted none but <hi>Cicero.</hi>
Whereupon before the Senate <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Terentia</hi> were
betrothed, <hi>Lentulus</hi> and <hi>Fabius</hi> made friends, and the
one named <hi>Lentulus</hi> as the <hi>Annales</hi> make mention mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to <hi>Flauia,</hi> and <hi>Fabius</hi> wedded to the worthy <hi>Cornelia.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:6220:44"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
