<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A necessary discourse concerning the right which the house of Guyze pretendeth to the crowne of France. Faithfully translated out of the French</title>
            <title>Discours sur le droit prétendu par ceux de Guise sur la couronne de France. English.</title>
            <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02376</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103547</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839299</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839299</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3707</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02376)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3707)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 511:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A necessary discourse concerning the right which the house of Guyze pretendeth to the crowne of France. Faithfully translated out of the French</title>
                  <title>Discours sur le droit prétendu par ceux de Guise sur la couronne de France. English.</title>
                  <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
                  <author>Aggas, Edward.</author>
                  <author>Rosières, François de, 1534-1607. Stemmatum Lotharingiae ac Barri.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by G. Robinson] for Edward Aggas,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1586.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation (by Edward Aggas?) of: Mornay, Philippe de. Discours sur le droit prétendu par ceux de Guise sur la couronne de France.</note>
                  <note>Based on: Rosières, François de.  Stemmatum Lotharingiae ac Barri.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Guise, House of --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Monarchy --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3707:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3707:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A neceſſary Diſcourſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the right which the houſe of Guyze pretendeth to the Crowne of France.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully tranſlated out of the French</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>AT LONDON, <hi>Imprinted for</hi> Edward Aggas. 1586.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:3707:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3707:2"/>
            <head>A diſcourſe concerning the <hi>pretended right of the houſe of Guyze</hi> to the houſe of <hi>France.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is commonly knowne tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout this Realme that the houſe of Lorraine attributeth to it ſelf the right of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crowne of France, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prouing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſuch Chronickles and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogies as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies of the late King Henry the ſecond they falſified might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be recouered, as alſo the conſultations by them holden concerning their title in the tyme of the late King Frances the ſecond, together with thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances which in the raigne of the late King Charles the ninth, yea and euen vnto this day haue bene ſcattered among the people, ſtill aduancing by ſuch deuiſes their practizes and deuiſes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the ſubuertion of this poore Eſtate doth ſeeme to growe on by meanes of Ciuill Warres where through the lawfull Princes power beeing deminiſhed, the ſinewes weakened and the path to nouelties prepared, they haue promiſed to them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues place in their pretended ſeate, by thruſting forth of thoſe whom they accompt vſurpers. Theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters hauing many tymes bene opened to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties, they haue bene ſo farre from beleeuing them to bee other then ſclanders inuented vpon ſome ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes
<pb facs="tcp:3707:3"/>
of trueth by ſuch as maliced or enuied this famelie, that the ſame notwithſtanding, they haue committed into their hands as well the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons as authoritie royall: yea, and vnder pretence of Romiſh Religion haue permitted them to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize Leagues in this Eſtate, that is, to prepare their factions and partakers to the firſt occaſion, and as it were to make tryall of the Crowne upon their heades, which haue ſo hartened ſome Doctors of Sarbonne that they haue preſumed in argument to graunt that <hi>a Prince or King fayling in his duetie to the Romiſh Church, may by the ſame be diſpoſſeſſed of his Crowne:</hi> yea and ſome Munckes to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the King and derogation of the Princes of his blood, haue preached forth the praiſes of thoſe vndertwigges or borgeons (as they terme them) of Charlemaigne, admoniſhing their auditors to caſt their eyes vpon them, as vpon the perfect reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the Church and Eſtate, all which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, no man hath had regarde thereto, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulled ſuch preſumption, as if the fortune of this Realme were growne fatally to bee diſmembred in theſe our daies, and that properly by this famelie.</p>
            <p>To the ende therefore to cut off all doubtes and manifeſtly to enter into conſideration and notice of this matter, I am moſt humbly to beſeech my Lord the King and all Princes which haue the honor to apperteine vnto him diligently to peruſe a Booke intituled <hi>the Genealogies of Lorrain &amp; Barr</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lately printed at Paris, wherein they ſhall euen
<pb facs="tcp:3707:3"/>
word by word finde the ſame to haue bene publiſhed at this tyme to the onely ende to enſtruct euery one in the pretended right of the houſe of Lorraine to this Crowne, and of ſuch iniurie as they ſuppoſe that the houſe of France doth vnto them, thereby to prepare the people againſt that alteration, which they imagine to bee at hand, ſhall fall out. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the vollume is large, the poyſon diuerſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed through all parts, cloked and couered vnder ſundry fables, I haue thought good herein worde for word to examine and note the principall points and groundes thereof. This Booke is written in Latin by one Frances of Roziers of Bar-le-duc Archdeacon of Thoul in Lorrain, and dedicated to my Lord of Lorrain: which alſo to the ende it may haue the more free paſſage is printed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kings Priuiledge by one William Chaudier a Printer. To come therefore to the matter. It is euidently knowne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſince the Francons firſt inhabited Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by them ſurnamed Gaule, we haue had three ſtocks of Kinges to raigne ouer vs. viz. <hi>Merouingians</hi> diſcended of Merouee, <hi>Carlinghes</hi> proceeding from Charlemaigne, and <hi>Capetz</hi> whoſe poſteritie doth yet raigne in our Kings: as alſo it is not vnknowne that the Lorraines doe pretende to the Crowne as heyres to Charlemaigne, but if this Author may be beleeued the ſame is to them due, euen from the Croyan horſe, whereof Merouee and his poſteritie defrauded them before any of theſe three families had intereſt therein, ſo as by that Lawe which ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:3707:4"/>
               <hi>there is no preſcription againſt the Church or Prince</hi> all our Kings from the firſt to the laſt haue bene v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers, and the true heire to the French Crowne remained in the family of the Dukes of Moſellane from whom the houſe of Lorraine doe fetch their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall. Theſe are the Authors very wordes in the third Booke Capitall ieſt 44. 45. &amp;c. <hi>Pharamond who firſt brought the Francons into France, had by his wife Baſine daughter to the K. of Thuring ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry children of whom the eldeſt was Clodio le Cheue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu or the hearie: This Clodio among the reſt had two ſonnes Ranchair and Alberick. Ranchair had three ſonnes Ranchair the ſecond, Richer and Rainald, who long tyme kept the Countrey of Cambray againſt the Merouingians, but were in the ende ſubdued by the power of Clouis K. of Fran<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, who with his own hands murdered them as before hee had done their father Ranchair the firſt. Thus fell the right of elderſhip to Alberick the ſecond ſonne of Clodio, who notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he was K. of the Eaſt Frenchmen, did not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe ſucceede his father Clodio becauſe Mero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uee had gotten the Crowne. This poore Alberick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his fathers deceaſe retired into the lands of Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſois, Moſelle, and Arden, &amp;c. where ſo well as he might, he kept himſelfe out of the way from their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi> Againe. <hi>Conſider with your ſelues the caſe of this poore Prince, who being of the Royall familie was not onely depriued of his Realme, but alſo through the crueltie of Merouce, who ſought vtterly to roote out the race of Clodio, forced to hide himſelfe: wherefore
<pb facs="tcp:3707:4"/>
he withdrewe himſelfe to Montz in Henault, there to expect the iſſue of the tyrannie of Merouee and his posteritie, after hee had in vaine had recourſe to the armie of Attila for his reestabliſhment.</hi> But if you aſke him of whence this Merouee the vſurper of the Crowne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the predeceſſors of the Lorrains, and the firſt originall of our Kings of France was, <hi>he was</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a bastard to Clodio, or as others af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme a Capteyn or kinſman of his, who by Clodio him ſelfe being made tutor to his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in reſpect of their youth, defrauded the pupilles of their eſtate.</hi> Then he goeth on and ſaith: <hi>Vaubert diſcending from Clodio by this Alberick, was ouerthrowne by Clotaire K. of France, who was in feare leaſt he ſhould obteyne the Crowne, but was forcibly againe restored by Thierry K. of the Ostrogoths.</hi> Likewiſe that <hi>this ofſpring of Merouee, namely the race of Clouis ſeeing Anſbert the ſonne of Vaubert to be a man of great hope, ſeking to establiſh their Kingdome, endeuoured to put him to death, but he being ſecretly conueyed away was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to Roome, where he was brought vp with the Emperour Zeno.</hi> To be brief, <hi>that ſtill they liued in daunger of their liues vntill the mariage of the ſayd Anſbert vnto Blitild K. Clotair the ſeconds daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of whom iſſued Arnold Duke of Moſellane, to whom as well for the ſayd alliance, as alſo that they found their Realm reaſonably eſtabliſhed, they ſhewed themſelues more courteous.</hi> Wherefore now marke after what ſorte hee bringeth the houſe of Lorraine now liuing to the ſucceſſion of this Clodio and his
<pb facs="tcp:3707:5"/>
ſonne Alberick, and ſo conſequently of their rights and titles. From Alberick he leadeth vs as it were by a direct line vnto Arnolph the ſonne of Arnould and Doda the daughter of the K. of Saxonie, who among the reſt had two ſonnes: The firſt Clodulph and Anchiſes the yonger: From the firſt he brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the Dukes of Moſellane and Lorraine, and from the other Charlemaigne and his poſteritie in this maner.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Clodulph Duke of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellane, whoſe Countrey was greater then all Lorraine.</cell>
                     <cell>Anchiſes Clodulphes yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Brother married Begghe Daughter to Pepin of the laundes Duke of Brabant by whom he had.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Martin.</cell>
                     <cell>Pepin Heristell, and ſo ſucceſſiuely.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Eleuthere, dyed without iſſue.</cell>
                     <cell>Charles Martel ſonne to Pepin Heriſtell by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paide his Concubine.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lambert ſonne to Martin &amp; brother to Eleuthere.</cell>
                     <cell>Pepin the Short.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Frederick.</cell>
                     <cell>Charlemaigne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sadigere.</cell>
                     <cell>Lewes the Meeke.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Rainier the firſt Duke of Lorraine, not heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, but inuested by Charles the ſimple in the ſayd Dutchie.</cell>
                     <cell>Charles the Balde.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Lewes the Stammerer.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gilbert, eldeſt ſonne to Rainier.</cell>
                     <cell>Lewes the fourth.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Lothair.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Henry, died without iſſue</cell>
                     <cell>Lewes the 5. dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iſſue.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bona daughter to Ricint ſecond ſonne to Rainier and brother to Gilbert maried to Charles D. of Lorraine.</cell>
                     <cell>Charles D. of Lorraine, brother to Lothaire, &amp; vnkle to Lewes the fifth after his Neuewes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe without iſſue was defrauded of the Crowne by Hugh Capet, maried Bona daughter to Ricint</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3707:5"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="2">
                        <hi>Wherefore.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bona, daughter to Ricint deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of Clodulph the elder ſonne of Clodios fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, who preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them ſelues to bee robbed of the Crowne by Mero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uee and his poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. maried</cell>
                     <cell>Charles D. of Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine diſcended of Anchiſes the yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger familie of Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio, of whome are come Charlemaign and his ofſpring.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Thus doe we by their ſaying ſee the line of the elder houſe of the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dios, which had lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g bene preſerued in the Dukes of Moſellane &amp; Lorraine falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here to the diſtaffe, ſo as at this daye there appeare no other of this ſtock but the ſame which is grafted into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yonger. That is, the ligne of</cell>
                     <cell>To this Charles bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Lothair &amp; the firſt that obteyned the enhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaunce in the Dutchie of Lorrain, after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe of his brother Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes belongd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crowne of France by his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Charlemaigne: Alſo becauſe he married Bona the Daughter of Ricint the two rights do</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3707:6"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Clodio into the houſe of Charlemaigne, by this marriage of Bona vnto Charles Duke of Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine of whom came Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho, Gerberghe and Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingarde. Gerberghe in her firſt mariage was ioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned with Rainier Earle of Montz and in ſecond with Lambert Earle of Louaine, &amp; Hermingard was married firſt to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Earle of Namure, whoſe poſteritie doe yet liue, ſaith he, in the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Lorraine and the Capetz. But becauſe Hugh Capet obteyned the Crowne, the houſe of Lorraine pretende them ſelues to be the onely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertwigges &amp; bourgeons of Charlemaigne and in the right of Charles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd, euen from Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crowne of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Howbeit, ſith they can not deny but this Ottho y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only ſonne to Charles</cell>
                     <cell>ſeme to ioyne in the iſſue of this mariage, viz. the right pretended by the Dukes of Moſellane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Merouingia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, who, as is aforeſaid, ſeme to haue depriued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dios, and the right of the houſe of Charlemaigne, which ſo long tyme and ſo peacealy they had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed: which two rights and titles (to take away all difficulties) doe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comprehende what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer may be required: namely, the proprietie belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging to Bona by the ſucceſſion of Clodulph, the elder of the familie of the Clodios and the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of Charlemaign fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ligne of the ſayd Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maigne, drawne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes the yonger houſe of the Clodios, and thus ſhould theſe two rightes and titles belong to the children begotten of the</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3707:6"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>dyed without iſſue, and ſo conſequently his titles &amp; pretences with him, let vs ſee how in their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogies they patch vp this breach.</cell>
                     <cell>ſayd Charles and Bona, and their poſteritie who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this author faineth thoſe of the houſe of Lorcaine to be.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Ottho then, ſaith he, ſonne to Charles and Bona beeing inueſted in the Dutchie of Lorraine by the Emperour, whoſe parte after his fathers example he tooke, ſeeing himſelfe out of hope of children, did by the ſayd Emperours conſent adopt for his ſonne Geoffrey le Barbu Earle of Arden and brother to his mother Bona daughter to Recinde, or, as others ſay, his brothers ſonne, who ſo reſtored the maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line ligne of Clodio in Lorraine. viz. the ſonne of Recinde the ſonne of Rainier, &amp;c. diſcending from Clodulph the eldeſt ſonne of that familie, as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd: And thus ſhall we finde the two titles vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the perſon of Geoffrey le Barbu: that is, the right and title of the Clodios as beeing from them iſſued, &amp; the right of Carlinghes or iſſue of Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maigne, as being by Ottho Duke of Lorrain adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into that houſe. Whereby in caſe any of the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles be called in queſtion, they may chooſe to which they will cleaue. And thus conſequently they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe on from father to ſonne in this maner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geoffery le Barbu comming of Clodio by Ricinde Rainièr, &amp;c. and adopted by Ottho Duke of Lorrain and ſonne to Charles had iſſue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gothelo, who had</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3707:7"/>
               <hi>Geoffrey the 4. who had</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geoffrey le Boſſue, or with the crouched backe,</hi> who dyed without iſſue, leauing to ſucceed him one one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſiſter named Itte, by whom both the titles afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd of the Clodios and Carlinghes fell to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaffe, who maried (ſay their Chronikles) with Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtace Earle of Boulogne, whom the ſayd Geoffrey adopted into his ſucceſſion.</p>
            <p>Thus againe becauſe here alſo is interruption, they ſupplye their want with an other adoption as before, ſaying that Geoffrey le Boſſue did by the conſent alſo of the Emperour adopt this Euſtace for his ſonne in conſideration of his mariage with his ſiſter Itte, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by this adoption they meane to giue to vnderſtande that the titles and pretences of the houſe of Clodio are into him and his heires grafted and incorporate. And further for auoyding the obiection that might bee propounded: namely, whether the titles and rightes of the Clodios were not in ſo long proceſſe of tyme extinguiſhed, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſith the Popes intermedling and vſing their authoritie haue declared the ſayd Charlemaign and his of ſpring to be lawfull Kings of France, they do againe for the vniting of theſe two families of the Clodios and Carlinges bring in this Euſtace to be of the iſſue of Charlemaigne both by father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in maner following.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3707:7"/>
               <list>
                  <item>By his father Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtace with the cleere ſight by a Daughter to Charles the Bould.</item>
                  <item>Charlemaigne.</item>
                  <item>Lewes the Meeke.</item>
                  <item>Charles the Bould.</item>
                  <item>Judith, Daughter to Charles the Bould and wife to Balduin le fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>réé Earle of Flanders.</item>
                  <item>Baldwin the balde.</item>
                  <item>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ce ſurnamed Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin, brother to Bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win the third Earle of Flanders.</item>
                  <item>Rainier.</item>
                  <item>Guydo.</item>
                  <item>Baldwine.</item>
                  <item>Eustace with the cleere eye.</item>
                  <item>Eustace Earle of Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne huſband to Itte.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>By his mother Mary daughter to Henry Earle of Louayne by Gerbergghe Daughter vnto Charles Duke of Lorrain whom Capet robbed.</item>
                  <item>Charlemaigne.</item>
                  <item>Lewes the Meeke.</item>
                  <item>Charles the balde.</item>
                  <item>Lewes the Stammerer.</item>
                  <item>Charles the Simple.</item>
                  <item>Baldwin the third.</item>
                  <item>Lewes the fourth.</item>
                  <item>Charles D. of Lorrain, as aforeſayd, whom Capet ouercame and defeated of his hope.</item>
                  <item>Gerbergghe Daughter to Bona and Charles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd, and ſister to Otho, which Bona (ſay they) was of the race of Clodio. This Gerbergh maried La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bert le Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bue Earle of Louayne father to Mary mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Eustace Earle of Boulogne.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, by their accoumpt, doe this Euſtace of Boulogne by adoption come to be heire to the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and titles of the Clodios, and both by father and mother is enheritour to the houſe and rightes of Charlemaigne, that is, <hi>to the Crowne of France.</hi> Alſo to the ende we may the more plainly perceiue
<pb facs="tcp:3707:8"/>
the Author doth not in vaine pretende the noting of theſe Genealogies, but hath ſome ſubtile drift, hee ſheweth himſelfe to be often and much offended be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee will not credite this Genealogie of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtace, as in theſe wordes. <hi>This is the Genealogie of Eustace, whereat many doe repine, for in troth both by father and mother he is diſcended from the houſe of Charlemaigne.</hi> Againe, in an other place he ſaith: <hi>Some doe diſſemble this, meaning to inferre that Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtace proceeded not from ſo high a degree, but I would ſuch ſclanderers might bee puniſhed as they deſerue.</hi> Out of this mariage of Euſtace Earle of Boulogne and Itte came fower ſonnes. <hi>Godfrey of Buillon, Baldwin, Eustace and William,</hi> who all each after o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were Dukes of Lorraine, and the firſt at his voyage into the Holy land tooke the armes which yet they beare: Howbeit, the three firſt dying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iſſue (notwithſtanding the annales of Lorraine doe attribute ſome to Baldwin) the ſucceſſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to William Baron of Ioninuille the fourth ſonne and his poſteritie thus.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3707:8"/>
               <hi>In an other place the author bringeth in the matter more <note place="margin">In his ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the 4. tome.</note> plainely. viz. that Geoffrey with the backe dying without iſſue adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Godfrey of Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>illon ſonne to Geof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey the 4. ſonne to Gothelo. &amp;c. that is to ſay, proceeding directly from the ligne of the Clodios and his own father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>Euſtace Earle of Bologne huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to Itte.</item>
                  <item>William his fourth ſonne Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of Ioninuille and heire to his three brethren.</item>
                  <item>Theodoricke his ſonne.</item>
                  <item>Simon the firſt.</item>
                  <item>Mathew the firſt.</item>
                  <item>Simon the ſecond dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iſſue, or made them Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſons.</item>
                  <item>Frederick the firſt, brother to Simon.</item>
                  <item>Thibault the firſt dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iſſue.</item>
                  <item>Matthew the ſecond brother to Thibault &amp; yongeſt ſonne of Fredericke.</item>
                  <item>Fredericke the ſecond.</item>
                  <item>Thibault the ſecond.</item>
                  <item>Fredericke the third.</item>
                  <item>Rodulph.</item>
                  <item>Iohn.</item>
                  <item>Charles the 2. who by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet daughter to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Robert had Iſabell ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to Renee Duke of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieow, Calabre and Prouence.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And here failed the ligne male of Euſtace Earle of Boulogne and his rights doe fall by the Diſtaffe into the houſe of Anieow, by the ſucceſſors of this Renee of the bloud of France, as diſcending from Lewes of Anieow ſonne to King Iohn the ſecond. Then doe followe:</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3707:9"/>
               <list>
                  <item>Antony Duke of Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine and Bar. &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>Frances, ſonne to Antony.</item>
                  <item>Charles the 3. now Duke of Lorraine.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>Renee D. of Anieow huſband to Iſabell heire of Lorraine.</item>
                  <item>Iohn ſonne to Renee.</item>
                  <item>Nicholas ſonne to Iohn who dyed without heires or frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds.</item>
                  <item>Yoland daughter to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Anieow and Iſabell, who the ſayd Renee beeing ouercome in warre and taken by Philip of Burgundy vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony Earle of Vaudemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was aſſociate, for his freer deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie out of priſon permitted to marrie with Fredericke the ſonne of the ſayd Antony.</item>
                  <item>Fredericke Earle of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t huſband to Yoland Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe of Lorraine.</item>
                  <item>Renee their ſonne D. of Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain by his mother &amp; Earle of Vaudemont by his father, whom Charles the 8. forbad to take vppon him the title of King, had 2. wiues, the firſt, daughter to the Earle of Ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>karuill whom for barrenneſſe he forſooke, the ſecond Phillip daughter to Adolph D. of Gelderland by whom he had 12. children: among the reſt.</item>
                  <item>Claude, Earle of Guyze.</item>
                  <item>Frances, Duke of Guyze.</item>
                  <item>Henry now Duke of Guyze.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3707:9"/>
Thus is the Dutchie of Lorraine at this preſent in the houſe of Vaudemont. Now after ſo many al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations of the houſe of the Clodios into the maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine ligne of the Carlinghes by the marriage of of Bona: from the ligne of the Carlinghes to that of the Clodios by the adoption of Geoffrey le Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bu: out of the ligne of le Barbu into y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of the Earles of Boulogne by the mariage of Icte: from the Earles of Boulogne into the houſe of Anieow tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the mariage of Iſabell: Alſo out of that of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieow into the houſe of Vaudemont by Yoland: All theſe beautifull ſhewes and royall pretences might ſeeme to haue benè ſpilled with ſo often powring out of one veſſell into an other, as being, euen long ſince, no further queſtion of the Clodios or Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges by either the father or mothers ſide, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the houſe of Vaudemont. But, to take away theſe difficulties: thoſe of Vaudemont now Dukes of Lorraine and Earles or Dukes of Guyze are yet (ſay they) of the houſe of Charlemaigne: namely, becauſe they ſay themſelues to be come of the houſe of the Earles of Alſatzs, they from the Emperour Conrade, and he of the race of Charlemaigne. That all this is rehearſed to ſome entent. viz. to waken and ſtirre vp the pretences of thoſe of Lorraine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the bloud of our Kings comen from Capet, the author doth in his proceedings ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſhew. For as he hath to his power contemned Merouee the head of the Merouingians, by whome they ſay themſelues to be defrauded of the Realme of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:3707:10"/>
before the ſame was in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hatched <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not likewiſe abſteyne from declayming againſt Hygh Capet, and blemiſhing his whole poſteritie. <hi>This Capet</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>was a Tyrant, who vpon Charles D. of Lorrayn and his iſſue vſurped by force and frande the Crowne of France, and not content with the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning him at Orleans, did miſerably put him to death with his children Lewes and Charles whom he had by his ſecond wife Agnes.</hi> If you aſke him of his original, in liew that he draweth the others rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die crowned out of the bellie of the Troyan horſe, be fetcheth in Ottho great vnckle to Capet from a Witichind baniſhed out of Saxony, and bringeth him into France vppon a Curtall with one onely varlet and a Cloakebagge. Yea, he taketh ſuch feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie in often repeating this ſtorie, that it ſeemeth (if it lay in him) he would ſoone haue brought our Kings to the ſame trayne. Alſo, as in his Epitaphs made vppon pleaſure and added to the eude of his Booke, he bringeth in this Albericke Duke of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellane whom he pretendeth to be robbed by Mero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uee, ſpeaking in theſe verſes.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Quaeres Alberi, Quae fata parant fili</l>
               <l>Tantum diſſidium ne imperio patris,</l>
               <l>Illustratus agas quod rapiunt truces.</l>
               <l>Meruingi?</l>
            </lg>
            <p>So doth he alſo induce Charles Duke of Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine unploring the ayde of all Chriſtian Princes againſt Capet and his of ſpring in theſe wordes.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3707:10"/>
               <l>Huc huc adeste <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ortes quique principes</l>
               <l>Huc aduolate quaeſo, Reges ac Duces.</l>
               <l>Ecquis feret vestrum fati inſolentiam? &amp;c.</l>
               <l>Capetus ille inuaſor Regni Gallici</l>
               <l>Lothario Francorum Rege mortuo</l>
               <l>Heu! me ſatum quidem antiqua proſapia:</l>
               <l>Quondam illius magni ac Inſinis Caroli,</l>
               <l>Armis volens procul expellere. &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The concluſion whereof is</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num mihi ſupereſt vt vindicem Deum,</l>
               <l>Expectem in hiſce a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gustijs.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>As if with <hi>Dido</hi> in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil</hi> he would ſay</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Exoriare aliquis nostris ex oſſibus vltor.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>I will here omit infinite other ſpeeches which he ouerthwarteth to the miſpriſion of the race of the Capets, likewiſe his pretendings to Anieow, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, Naples, &amp;c. preiudicially to this Crowne, which alſo he ſtriueth for ſo much as he may: But the commendations which with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt of our King he attributeth to the Guyzes of our time may not be diſſembled. <hi>The affayres of France</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>had good ſucceſſe vnder the gouernment of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of Lorraine: but after his deceaſe Henry now raigning grew out of fauour with his ſubiects, becauſe that ſoone after the Cardinal of Guyze had anoynted him, giuing himſelf to his pleaſures he ruled all things after his owne fancie, which are the meanes to effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and abaſe a Kings heart, &amp; thus began France to be wrinckled and euery thing to runne into ruyne.</hi> Speaking of the late Lord Prince of Conde, <hi>he did</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3707:11"/>
ſayth he, <hi>all that he might to attaine to the tyrannie.</hi> Alſo, <hi>after the death of King Frances the ſecond be and his aſſociates were ſuffered to depart without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Neither doth he of the Kings late brother or the King of Nauarre ſpeake much more modeſtly. But whereto all this, except to the ende to declare the King through his negligence, and the Princes of his blood for their ſuppoſed Rebellion for euer vnworthy the Crowne: Alſo that as their Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers haue ſufficiently cryed out, euery one may in theſe miſeries, which vnto man are as ſpurres to nouelties, caſt their eyes vppon theſe pretended af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter twigges or bourgeons of Charlemaigne.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, herein I haue onely vndertaken to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Authors purpoſe in his Booke, as alſo the entents of thoſe that procured it to bee printed, and whoſoeuer will take the paine to reade it may finde much more: Neuertheleſſe, leaſt any ſhould deceiue themſelues, I will briefly in fewe wordes examine the groundes of this ſucceſſion.</p>
            <p>He fetcheth his Dukes of Moſellane out of the Troyan horſe with the Francons. In what credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Hiſtorie hath he found it? He maketh Albericke Duke of Moſellane ſonne to Clodio le Cheuelu, and defrauded of the Realme by Merouee: where can he ſhewe that? except in a few ſuppoſed Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies of Lorrain: notwithſtanding toward the end of his fables hee quoteth many Authors to make a ſhewe, who all ſpeake neuer a worde thereof. But what will he ſay to thoſe Hiſtories that make Mero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uee
<pb facs="tcp:3707:11"/>
the ſonne of Clodio? or how could he bee other then the eldeſt, ſith he was of age ſufficient to be tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to Alberick: And which is more, how can Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke complaine that Merouee robbed him of the Crowne of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, when (if we will beleeue the beſt Hiſtorographers) Merouee was the firſt Francon that euer bare title of King in France? But let vs graunt them all their fables from Clodulph Duke of Moſellane vnto Bona wife to Charles Duke of Lorraine, yet how could the mariage of her bring to him Clodulphes right to the Crowne, when the Salick law which was originary Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch and made with the Counſaile of Pharamond excludeth the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſucceſſion thereof? Or admit Charles Duke of Lorraine was wrongfully defrauded of the ſucceſſion of Charlemaign by Hugh Capet and his poſteritie, yet diſcending they will graunt that Ottho his only ſonne dyed without iſſue: but if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Salick law, they will admit daughters to ſucceede, let them ſhewe vs ſome reaſon why the houſe of Lorraine ſhould bee preferred before our Kings, ſith themſelues holde opinion that they all diſcended of one and the ſame daughter? But if they wil hould them to Geoffrey le Barbu Earle of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denne whom Ottho adopted, what neede they bring in theſe daughters? Beſides, where finde they this adoption, or in what Court was it euer exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plefied? yea, or how dare they auowe that it was then pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to extend to the Crowne of France: And as for that of Euſtace of Boulogne, who ſéeth not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:3707:12"/>
manifeſt fraude, ſith themſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> neither author nor title, yea, and are euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> who Godfrey of Buillon was, alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> were he or Euſtace whom Geoffrey le <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. Where alſo they labour to proue that this Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtace was both by father and mother diſcoured of Charlemaigne, to what purpoſe may it ſerue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> was but by daughters, vnleſſe, in ſubuerting the Satick lawe, to habandon this Realme for a pray, not to the Lorraines onely, or to the Ard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s, but alſo to all the families in Europe that haue bene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied to the houſe of Fraunce? Moreouer, although Iſabell maried with Renee of Anieow and Poland with Frederick Earle of Vaudemont, yet who can affirme that therby they tranſported to their heires of Lorraine or Guyze the rights of Clodio and Charlemaigne, which themſelues were not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of, neither did tranſport, although they had had the ſame? Theſe therefore are but fables wherwith in the meane time they feede the people blemiſhing (ſo much as in them lyeth) our Salick law, as falſe and purpoſedly inuented. Moreouer, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all their pretences (which are moſt falſe) were true, yet after that an Eſtate is eſtabliſhed in a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie by lawfull calling and approbation of the Commonwealth and people, and that for ſo many hundred yeeres, it is a manifeſt token that God (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom it is in vaine to ſtriue, and to whoſe decree all people ought to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſcend) hath tranſfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch a Realme or Eſtate into that familie. But
<pb facs="tcp:3707:12"/>
becauſe many an euident right hath decayed for lacke of power, and many a wrong hath preuayled againſt right through default of ſtrength to autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize the ſame, the eſpeciall poynt conſiſteth in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barring them from accompanying their fraud with force, eſpecially with our own, as many tymes haue fallen out through the calamities of Ciuill warres which doe yeeld the people vnpatient of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eſtate and ſtarueth them after nouelties. This diſcourſe haue I thought good to direct to your Maieſtie, not for your ſelf onely, but alſo for others that haue great intereſt therein, and to whoſe lot it will peraduenture fall to haue the deciding of this quarrell, or els to leaue it ouerſtrong for their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, vnleſſe they before take order for the ſame. And I beſeech God to graunt them good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile to his glorie, the preſeruation of their greatneſſe and the benefite of the poore people.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
