<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of golds kingdome, and this vnhelping age Described in sundry poems intermixedly placed after certaine other poems of more speciall respect: and before the same is an oration or speech intended to haue bene deliuered by the author hereof vnto the Kings Maiesty.</title>
            <author>Hake, Edward, fl. 1560-1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-11">2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12607</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841863</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841863</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6478</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02478)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6478)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1025:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of golds kingdome, and this vnhelping age Described in sundry poems intermixedly placed after certaine other poems of more speciall respect: and before the same is an oration or speech intended to haue bene deliuered by the author hereof vnto the Kings Maiesty.</title>
                  <author>Hake, Edward, fl. 1560-1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 57, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Windet dwelling [..,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: E. Hake.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Imprint cropped with loss of date.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6478:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6478:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OF GOLDS KINGDOME, AND THIS VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helping Age.</p>
            <p>Described in sundry Poems inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixedly placed after certaine other Poems of more speciall respect:</p>
            <p>And before the same is an Oration or speech in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to haue bene deliuered by the Author hereof vnto the Kings Maiesty.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Ipse licet venias Musis comitatus <hi>Homere,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Si nihil attuleris, ibis <hi>Homere</hi> foras.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though <hi>Homer,</hi> thou do come thy selfe</l>
               <l>with Muses waiting on thee,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Homer,</hi> if thou nothing bring,</l>
               <l>then <hi>Homer,</hi> God be with thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <q>Animus virtutis studiosus ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nuenit artem Carminum ad la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dandum bona: ad vituperandum vero <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <bibl>Arist. De poet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lib. 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <head>THOV SHALT LABOR FOR</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6478:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6478:2"/>
            <head>A SPEECH INTEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DED TO HAVE BENE MADE VNTO THE KINGS MAIESTIE, in the Towne of Windsore, but not spoken.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Gracious and renowmed King, if we your Highnesse sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of this place, be (for the present) to seeke in what sort to applaud the incomparable bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of your royall presence: we are most humbly to beseech your Highnesse to impute the same vnto two causes: The one, the consideration we haue of our owne imperfections, as the same are now to be exposed vnto the censure of your Princely perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: The other, the abundance of our ioy which hath so possessed euery part of our thoughts, as that thereby we are vnable to retaine in our speaking either Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode or Decorum: For it cannot be told (most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soueraigne) with what insatiable power of our minds we do imbrace &amp; entertaine this ioyfull time of your Maiesties personall repayre into this land, and now particularly to this your Towne and Castell of Windsore: This time I say, most brightsome and cleere, not ouercast with any the least cloud of either trouble present, or danger to come: For it may truly be said of your Maiesty (and that to the glory of God) as it was sometimes said of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the godly Romaine Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: that true piety and felicity haue so met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in your royal person, as that true piety hath forced felicity to be present at a l your royall solemnizations whatsoeuer: And why? surely, because your Maiesty hath not onely couered your head with the Imperiall Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme,
<pb facs="tcp:6478:3"/>
and inue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted your person with the Royall Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Crowne, but hath also adorned your mind with the inestimable Iewels of true Religion and Iustice: But what shall I say? Among all the inexplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blessings which we are now by the goodnesse of God to inioy by your Maiesty, there is one amongst the rest so full of blessednesse, as that it ouerreacheth the measure of common comprehension to dilate it in speech: And what is that? Euen the knitting togither of your two Kingdomes <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> which are now so closed in one Harmony as well of Religion, as of their confining borders and agreeing languages, as that (according to the saying of the Prophet) <hi>Bone</hi> is ioyned to <hi>Bone,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ioynt</hi> to <hi>Ioynt:</hi> Most gracious king, our most beloued Soueraigne, there is one thing that your Maiesty may hold as an vndoubted certainty: namely this, that you are entred into your rule and raigne ouer <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> with as great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formity of harts of English sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects as euer King or Queene within this Realme. Long may your Highnesse liue: Long may the Scepter sway in your Princely hands: And vnto the King of Kings we bow the knees of our hearts, that he will vouchsafe to graunt vnto your Maiesty a long, a peaceable, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed Raigne ouer vs.</p>
            <p>I will not take vpon me to particularize vnto your Maiestie the Nature of <hi>Englands</hi> gouernement, but ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally (vnder your Princely fauour) this thereof may be sayd that by the most ancient vsage of <hi>England,</hi> the king hath bin accounted to be <hi>persona mixta, hoc est, vnita cum Sacerdotibus,</hi> aunswerable to that of <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Aristotle: Suprema potestas antiquitus fuit regia &amp; Sacerdota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</hi> And for that that is holden thereof ciuilly at this day, it is this: we say that our supreme power is <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patus tam regalis quam politicus,</hi> the one respecting times of warre, and the other times of peace. And we say also that <hi>principatus regalis &amp; politicus paris sunt potentiae, sed prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatus regalis difficilioris est exercit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> securitatis.</hi> But of this as also of the Equity of your Maiesties Common
<pb facs="tcp:6478:3"/>
lawes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Equity of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Court of Chauncery with their differences, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall also of Equity in generall as the same is to be vsed in euery humane law, I your Maiesties most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble subiect, a professor of those Common lawes some certaine yeares past did imploy my labours in writing a plaine &amp; open Treatise thereof in English, whichbe ing here contained in this written Volume, if it might <note place="margin">This booke herein mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kings Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, but not by way of dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> stand with your Princely pleasure to vouchsafe your reading of it, I make no doubt but that your Maiestie will find sundry things therein not impertinent, no nor yet vnnecessary for your Princely perusing: The simplicity of the handling alwayes excepted, for the which I must and do most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beseech your Maiesties gracious pardon.</p>
            <p>After this, there should haue followed some priuate and particular matters on the behalfe of the sayd Towne.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6478:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR'SHIPFVLL HIS very kind and curteous friend <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Uaughan Esquire, Deputy</hi> Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of the Office of the Pipe of the Kings Maiesties Eschequer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD Sir, my occasions staying me so long in London this last vacation, as that according to the bill of Certificat there died aboue 19 hundreth of the Plague in one weeke: Although I then thought it not fit to imploy that time in any serious Study, yet I was vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lling to passe it wholly ouer without some exercise of my Pen. Whereupon resor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to a few odde trifles which I had penned about a yeare or two sithens, I added euery day for diuerse dayes together sundry o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vnto them. And causing my man to write them out after me, in the end I found the whole thereof to arise vnto a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a litle Booke: which (thus written as it is) I send vnto you, as a token of my assured goodwill, being ready from time to time to expresse the same by better meanes as I shall be enabled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. And whereas in one or two places of the booke I haue made mention of outragious fees, let that light where it will: As for you, you are knowne to be a giuer of fees: But an extreame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acter of fees I am perswaded in my heart you neuer were, nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will be. And so with my best wishing vnto you, I cease: This First of Ianuarie 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your true and hearty welwiller,
E. Hake.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:6478:4"/>
            <head>The Authors Prologue to such of his Poems in this booke as concerne Golds Kingdome.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ALthough that Gold can closely creepe</l>
               <l>where th'aire could neuer come,</l>
               <l>And cause that vice and vertue be</l>
               <l>of equall poise with some,</l>
               <l>Yet noble and true gentle minds</l>
               <l>with Gold will not be won,</l>
               <l>To do the thing that is vniust</l>
               <l>or leaue good things vndone.</l>
               <l>A proofe hereof me selfe haue seene</l>
               <l>in one that noble is,</l>
               <l>And holdeth place of high respect</l>
               <l>as he well worthy is:</l>
               <l>A poore man with Petition</l>
               <l>annexed to his case</l>
               <l>To him repaires, not hauing helpe</l>
               <l>of any friend in place:</l>
               <l>Which when he had exhibited,</l>
               <l>although that noble man</l>
               <l>Had great imployments of the State</l>
               <l>yet marke what followd than:</l>
               <l>Not full two dayes expyrd, before</l>
               <l>the poore man did receaue</l>
               <l>An Answer to his full content,</l>
               <l>And thence did take his leaue,</l>
               <l>Not rendring gifts to any one</l>
               <l>nor Secretaries fees,</l>
               <l>But hasting home vnto his Hiue,</l>
               <l>reioyced with his Bees.</l>
               <l>A yeare thence after, troubles came</l>
               <l>about that passed gift,</l>
               <l>As that some sought to frustrate it</l>
               <l>by friends or fained shift.</l>
               <l>The poore man for his helpe againe</l>
               <l>preferreth his complaint,</l>
               <l>And by his onely writing doth</l>
               <l>that Lord therewith acquaint,</l>
               <l>Himselfe vnable through disease</l>
               <l>in person to be seene.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6478:5"/>
This noble man, as if the case</l>
               <l>had then like present bene,</l>
               <l>What he had passed earst before,</l>
               <l>Confirmes with greater force:</l>
               <l>Right noble surely was this deed</l>
               <l>and full of true remorse.</l>
               <l>Yea, as before, no peny went</l>
               <l>out of the poore mans purse,</l>
               <l>So now againe, no peny he</l>
               <l>to any did disburse.</l>
               <l>Patron to pupils is that Lord,</l>
               <l>(so doth his office lie)</l>
               <l>Amongst whose vertuous deedes this one,</l>
               <l>the poore mans case did try.</l>
               <l>And sith that I an Actor was</l>
               <l>to pen that poore mans case,</l>
               <l>I therefore write it as a note</l>
               <l>of vertue in that place.</l>
               <l>The rather, for because this Age</l>
               <l>vnhelping is, and why?</l>
               <l>Few men will helpe in cases where</l>
               <l>they see no profit lie.</l>
               <l>So that to speake what I conceiue,</l>
               <l>I feare, no Gold, no Good,</l>
               <l>No, not perhaps for such as haue</l>
               <l>aduentured their bloud.</l>
               <l>And for the man at home, who hath</l>
               <l>of good deseruing bene,</l>
               <l>Nor workes nor worth can him aduance</l>
               <l>if Gold come not betweene:</l>
               <l>For now, as good to beate the ayre</l>
               <l>as fill the eares of some</l>
               <l>Who Sutes preferre: Nay, fill their hands,</l>
               <l>else looke to find them <hi>Mum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet write I not with mind to touch</l>
               <l>men of superiour place:</l>
               <l>Nor do I know particulers</l>
               <l>that any should deface.</l>
               <l>Many complaine and many cry:</l>
               <l>God knoweth where the fault doth lie.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6478:5"/>
            <head>HVMBLE PETITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS OF GOOD SVBIECTS TO THEIR GOOD KING against the Parliament.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onfirme Religion as the Arke of God:</l>
               <l>Preserue the places where the same shall rest:</l>
               <l>Then lawes for life, and maners as the Rod,</l>
               <l>Wherewith offence of Sinne must be supprest,</l>
               <l>So shall the land assuredly be blest.</l>
               <l>But firie Spirits are not for that charge,</l>
               <l>Nor such as seeke their profits to enlarge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Next, for the Common-wealth (as is begun)</l>
               <l>Take off oppressions from the Subiects backe,</l>
               <l>And to the Commons do not alwayes runne</l>
               <l>For euery thing that Common-wealth doth lacke,</l>
               <l>For so poore Subiects still shall go to wracke,</l>
               <l>And yet must Subiects <hi>Caesars</hi> duties pay:</l>
               <l>No faithfull Subiect will thereof say nay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As for the Lawyers faults and griefes thereby,</l>
               <l>The peoples plaints suffice to make them knowne,</l>
               <l>And how huge monstrous fees on Suters lye,</l>
               <l>Which Officers and Clarkes claime as their owne:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:6478:6"/>
But if you aske <hi>quo iure</hi> they are growne,</l>
               <l>The man (say they) must sell who first did buy:</l>
               <l>A case to be redrest as cause shall lie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In briefe, the sores and sicknesses that are</l>
               <l>In <hi>Englands</hi> state, which grieued men will shew</l>
               <l>In <hi>Parliament,</hi> will moue the Princes care</l>
               <l>To finde the fountaines whence the same doe flow,</l>
               <l>And fountaines found, to purge them all arow.</l>
               <l>The God of heauen preserue our blessed King,</l>
               <l>That he to Church and Realme true peace may bring.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Astra Deo nil maius habent, Nil Caesare Terra:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic Caesar Terras, vt Deus Astra regat.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The Subiects loue is the riches and <hi>safety of the King.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>IT is recorded in this wise:</l>
               <l>At <hi>Wormes</hi> aGermaine Towne,</l>
               <l>When all the Princes there were met</l>
               <l>And all were sitten downe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To talke of matters of the State</l>
               <l>At length they tooke in hand,</l>
               <l>Each one to praise and to extoll</l>
               <l>The goodnesse of his land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Baua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia</hi> Dukes their Cities praysde,</l>
               <l>The Saxons praysd their Mines,</l>
               <l>Duke <hi>Palatine</hi> his fertile Soyles</l>
               <l>And fatnesse of his vines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6478:6"/>
               <l>Duke <hi>Eberard</hi> of <hi>Wittenberg,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who likewise was in place,</l>
               <l>And silent sate by <hi>Fredericke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who had the Soueraigne grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As <hi>Saxon</hi> Duke required was</l>
               <l>To tell his Countries praise:</l>
               <l>And he obeying modestly,</l>
               <l>(As loath himselfe to raise)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Lords (sayd he) tis nothing that</l>
               <l>By me can be declarde,</l>
               <l>Who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am the lowest in this place</l>
               <l>And might full well be sparde:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nathlesse this one thing do I know,</l>
               <l>And knowing, do protest</l>
               <l>That I in any Subiects lap</l>
               <l>Of mine can take my rest,</l>
               <l>Although in open fields from prease:</l>
               <l>Whereby our mutuall louesincrease.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="example">
            <head>A notable example of integrity in a <hi>King, betweene himselfe and his Subiects.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>LEwis</hi> King of <hi>Fraunce</hi> was accustomed to sit iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially <note place="margin">Io. Manlius de Magistrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pag. 593.</note> in the hearing of his owne causes: And if he found any to flatter him therein, and to say his cause was good: Let vs heare the same (sayd he) whether Iustice, or your beneuolence hath
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6478:7"/>
swayed most therein: And oftentimes when hee found their Sentence to be with him, he would pronounce the contrary, and would bitterly chide those who had attributed too much to his side.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="example">
            <head>Another notable example of <hi>integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in a Prince.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>FRedericke</hi> Duke of Saxony had certaine woods <note place="margin">10. Manlius de Magistratu pag. 592.</note> neare adioyning vnto <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> which had bene sometimes purchased by his progenitors. <hi>Anhaldine</hi> mother of those Princes of that name, who then liued (being wise &amp; a good Oeconomist) required those woods to be restored vnto her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they had bene at the first but mortgaged. The Duke although it was very hard for him to depart with the woods, insomuch as he had rather haue giuen more mony for them, then to haue forgone them (in respect that the price of woods did then daily increase) yet he would by no meanes vexe or disquiet that most honest Matron, or hold her long in suspence: And therefore albeit he had counsell &amp; pretextes propounded vnto him, how by a shew of right he might retaine them, yet he would by no meanes burthen his conscience, by admitting of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the sayd pretextes for the retaining of them: and such was his integrity, as that he willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored the same to the house of the <hi>Anhaldi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>And hath not <hi>Iames</hi> our Englands King</l>
               <l>Shewd forth like Princely mind,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:6478:7"/>
Who farmes of fines and forfeitures,</l>
               <l>Which Subiects backes did grinde,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With Monopolyes, lycences</l>
               <l>And priuiledges large,</l>
               <l>Whereby he might haue bene enricht</l>
               <l>(Though to his Subiects charge)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hath royally released from</l>
               <l>His English Subiects backes,</l>
               <l>Not minding to enrich himselfe</l>
               <l>By his poore Subiects wrackes?</l>
               <l>What good so great hath earst bene done,</l>
               <l>As by King <hi>Iames</hi> is now begun.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>A Case of Difficultie in the Royall Administration.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>GReat</hi> Difficultie may be found in this</l>
               <l>Vnto the Prince, where Subiects doe complaine</l>
               <l>Of any that in office doth amisse,</l>
               <l>As that percase he should some wrong maintaine:</l>
               <l>For as the Prince is bound to aide the right,</l>
               <l>Without respect of any Subiects might,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So, meete it is that where he giueth power,</l>
               <l>He should support the same, and still vphold</l>
               <l>Th'authorized, for why? Else euery houre</l>
               <l>Th'vprightest men, and men of purest molde</l>
               <l>Might be traduced, and besides, his Grace</l>
               <l>Would be surchargd with plaints in euery place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:6478:8"/>
               <l>Then what to write, or speake in such a case,</l>
               <l>Few men can tell, but fewer will (I feare)</l>
               <l>Th'inferiour once offended, will deface</l>
               <l>Superiours, and such as office beare:</l>
               <l>Againe, the mighty they are full of friends,</l>
               <l>And as friends be, so oft the matter endes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Put case the King vpon complaint preferd</l>
               <l>Against the mighty, by the lower sort,</l>
               <l>Of his great grace should cause to be referd</l>
               <l>The in-sight of such plaints to men of Port:</l>
               <l>Say that the mighty with the mighty hold, <note place="margin">Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erments of cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</note>
               </l>
               <l>So that to aide the poore none durst be bold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What should then here be done, can any tell?</l>
               <l>Th'inferiour he goes downe. But is that all?</l>
               <l>No, no, hee's blamde because he durst to mell</l>
               <l>With such as on the earth men Gods do call.</l>
               <l>O case of cases to be seene into,</l>
               <l>Which doth concerne the Prince what he should do.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And sith a wiser Prince this land nere had,</l>
               <l>Nor better bent to heare the poore mans cry,</l>
               <l>What needes my pen thus moue a case so sad?</l>
               <l>His Highnesse knowes where all the helpe doth lye:</l>
               <l>For least the matter should so go awry,</l>
               <l>His grace himselfe must helpe, or else perhaps</l>
               <l>The poore Complainant shall feele after claps.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Iames</hi> the fift of that name King of Scotland, Graund-father to our most gracious King, was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Poore mans King.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:6478:8"/>
            <head>The infortunate Courtier.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>TWo</hi> Courtiers liuing long at Court,</l>
               <l>The one of good desert,</l>
               <l>The other meanely meriting,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>(vt fortuna fert)</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The meaner had the better lucke,</l>
               <l>By th'emprour well aduanst,</l>
               <l>Which to the other brought great griefe:</l>
               <l>But marke ye how it chanst,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The noble <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gismundus</hi> he</l>
               <l>(So was the Emperour nam'd)</l>
               <l>Enformed of this matter, and</l>
               <l>How he was onely blam'd,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As not to beare an equall hand</l>
               <l>In giuing of reward,</l>
               <l>Aduis'd himselfe thereof, and with</l>
               <l>A Princely due regard</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For answering of the matter, did</l>
               <l>Resolue vpon this course:</l>
               <l>Two ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sts he fild, the one with gold,</l>
               <l>The other, stones or worse.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And calling for the Courtier which</l>
               <l>Had found himselfe so grieu'd,</l>
               <l>Declared vnto him that now</l>
               <l>His case might be relieu'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:6478:9"/>
               <l>If Fortune were not in the fault:</l>
               <l>Choose here (sayd he) of two,</l>
               <l>A chist of gold, or one of stones,</l>
               <l>And thinke well what to do,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For I'le be hence forth quite of blame,</l>
               <l>(The fault thou sayst is mine)</l>
               <l>And if thou choose the stones, then say</l>
               <l>The fault is rather thine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or if not thine, yet Fortunes fault:</l>
               <l>And who can that redresse?</l>
               <l>The Courtier chose, and chose the stones:</l>
               <l>(Alas, vnluckinesse.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But shall I say my mind herein?</l>
               <l>Good Kings will haue respect,</l>
               <l>Whom they aduance, whom they reward,</l>
               <l>And whom they do reiect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For why? All's one to raise the ill,</l>
               <l>And not to helpe the honest still.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Three things very grieuous to good mindes.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THree things there are that breed much griefe,</l>
               <l>And discontent of mind:</l>
               <l>The worlds mishaps, vntrust of friends,</l>
               <l>The third, that Gold doth bind,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:6478:9"/>
               <l>Nay binde and loose, though not with all,</l>
               <l>yet greatly with the most:</l>
               <l>And for the first of these three things,</l>
               <l>what man on earth can boast</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That he hath past his dayes in peace,</l>
               <l>not crost with worlds missehap?</l>
               <l>Not one I thinke, though best men most</l>
               <l>doe taste of sorrowes sap.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The King hath cares to crosse his ioyes,</l>
               <l>home strises to crosse his peace,</l>
               <l>And traytrous harts conspire his hurts,</l>
               <l>while Subiects loues increase.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If pleasures for his health he take,</l>
               <l>what interruptions are</l>
               <l>Vnto his pleasures and disportes</l>
               <l>by suites, that breede his care</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In causes of his Subiects states,</l>
               <l>perhaps their liues and lands:</l>
               <l>The strong doth still oppresse the weake,</l>
               <l>the help's in Princes hands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yea day by day occasions rise</l>
               <l>of common wealthes redresse,</l>
               <l>And day by day abuses grow,</l>
               <l>which Princes should suppresse.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And yet if Princes should not haue</l>
               <l>their pleasures and delight.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:6478:10"/>
Alas, alas, what were their case?</l>
               <l>of all men worst in sight:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Onely the King that feareth God,</l>
               <l>and seekes to spread his prayse</l>
               <l>Shall haue his seat and State securde,</l>
               <l>his soule shall see good daies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then if the King in this worlds course,</l>
               <l>where all men him obay,</l>
               <l>Findes worlds vnrest, of lower States</l>
               <l>how firme can be the stay?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Next for the faith and trust of friends,</l>
               <l>where is the friend whose faith</l>
               <l>As well in hard as happy state</l>
               <l>in friendship firmly stayth?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Swallowes men are, whose Sommers glee</l>
               <l>retaines in friendships band,</l>
               <l>And Winters woes driue cleane away:</l>
               <l>So doth mens friendship stand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Examples here of infinite</l>
               <l>the world doth dayly show,</l>
               <l>And how mens loues are wrongly plac'd</l>
               <l>and from wrong causes grow:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For were true vertue their loues cause,</l>
               <l>then what could it remoue?</l>
               <l>No, no, tis gaine, or vaine respect,</l>
               <l>that most where causeth loue:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:6478:10"/>
               <l>The rich holds friendship with the rich,</l>
               <l>the lecher with his like,</l>
               <l>And pot companions with their mates</l>
               <l>great league of friendship strike.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Blind Zeale also to maintaine Sects,</l>
               <l>and to impugne the truth,</l>
               <l>Doth lincke it selfe in friendships bands:</l>
               <l>but what thereof ensu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Disturbance of the Churches peace,</l>
               <l>contempt of King and law,</l>
               <l>And all that with such friends is found,</l>
               <l>is onely to withdrawe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From vniforme consent of faith,</l>
               <l>and from true seruing God:</l>
               <l>O, out, alas, what loue i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this?</l>
               <l>Such league from loue is od.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The third and last is sway of Gold,</l>
               <l>which so still hinders all</l>
               <l>That to the well deseruing man</l>
               <l>should for his Guerdon fall,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As that no gifts of learning, nor</l>
               <l>of skill which in him are,</l>
               <l>Can do him good, because perhaps</l>
               <l>his state is something bare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fayre speach and sugred words are ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</l>
               <l>but if thy state be poore,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:6478:11"/>
While others prease and come in place,</l>
               <l>looke thou to stand at doore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t office that thou seekest friend?</l>
               <l>why offices are bought:</l>
               <l>An Office is a <hi>Nemo scit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>and should it come for nought?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But be it small or great that thou</l>
               <l>doest labour to obtaine:</l>
               <l>Assure thy selfe that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there be</l>
               <l>therein a sent of gaine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though nere so small, and yet perhaps</l>
               <l>the matter full of toyle,</l>
               <l>Vnlesse with gifts thou get thee friends,</l>
               <l>be sure to catch the foyle:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For if thou stand vpon desert,</l>
               <l>thou maist put vp thy pipes:</l>
               <l>There is a fellow calde <hi>Giffe Gaffe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>that in such cases gripes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And so we see that Gold and gifts</l>
               <l>In suites must doe the deede,</l>
               <l>And how that no man for desert</l>
               <l>of any thing can speede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Audacious, proud, and flattering mates</l>
               <l>I graunt you may doe much;</l>
               <l>And many things of good respect</l>
               <l>are oft bestowd on such.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:6478:11"/>
               <l>Againe, we see that some there are,</l>
               <l>who willingly are led</l>
               <l>By men of slender gifts: And why?</l>
               <l>because by them are fed</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The humors whereunto they be</l>
               <l>enclined, and most what</l>
               <l>For that they please them with delights,</l>
               <l>and seruile are to that.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And sooner will they giue to those,</l>
               <l>Then vnto men of price.</l>
               <l>If such one aske, he straight way speedes,</l>
               <l>and hath it with a trice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But if I should runne ouer all</l>
               <l>that might be said in this,</l>
               <l>How Gold hath Soueraigne power in sutes,</l>
               <l>and chiefe effecter is</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of mens desires, and that desert</l>
               <l>(as of it selfe) shall fayle,</l>
               <l>I might imploy much speech therein,</l>
               <l>And little should preuaile:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For howsoeuer men of place</l>
               <l>and honour are enclinde</l>
               <l>To further and promote a man</l>
               <l>that is of honest mind,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet are the meanes so difficult</l>
               <l>that must be made to such,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:6478:12"/>
And fauorites so many that</l>
               <l>therein doth looke for much,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As that a man farre better were</l>
               <l>to liue with bread and grew,</l>
               <l>Then with a thrid-bare purse to seeke</l>
               <l>or for pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erment sew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And so I end my dolefull song</l>
               <l>of threefold griefe and paine,</l>
               <l>As worlds vnrest, next, friends vntrust,</l>
               <l>the third, that all's for gaine.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Of true Nobilitie.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>OF true Nobilitie doe we enquire?</l>
               <l>Tis that that doth excell the common sort</l>
               <l>In vertuous Actes whereto it doth aspire,</l>
               <l>And shewes it selfe abroad with noble port:</l>
               <l>For noble port must shew the noble State,</l>
               <l>It fits not Noble minds to be at common rate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But what for that? doth Noble therefore wrong?</l>
               <l>Doth he oppresse or seeke a common hurt,</l>
               <l>Whereby to raise himselfe or make him strong?</l>
               <l>No fye, the Noble reckons that as durt:</l>
               <l>For as the world is cheered by the Sunne,</l>
               <l>So from true Noble comforts dailyrunne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Doth Countries seruice call the Noble forth?</l>
               <l>Most what he is prepared for the same,</l>
               <l>For that's a meane to shew his noble worth:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:6478:12"/>
And that accomplisht wins him noble fame.</l>
               <l>To God, to King, and Countrey is he chargde</l>
               <l>To see the Honour of them all enlargde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Is noble neere the King? who else should be?</l>
               <l>Then nobly doth he seruice to his Grace,</l>
               <l>As both his honour and his safety to foresee,</l>
               <l>For which his eyes are open in each place,</l>
               <l>Detracting none that are of good desart,</l>
               <l>But helping all out of a noble hart:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And chiefly vnto suters doth he show</l>
               <l>A noble affabilitie, and why?</l>
               <l>Because from Prince, as from a spring doth flow</l>
               <l>The Subiects helpe, which helples else might lye:</l>
               <l>Then if this Noble keepe poore suters backe,</l>
               <l>Vnnobly doth he cause poore suters wracke,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And to proceede, doth he in Countrey dwell?</l>
               <l>No partie factions doth he there support,</l>
               <l>Much lesse, prepareth plots how to rebell,</l>
               <l>Nor graceth any of suspected sort.</l>
               <l>But honours law, and Iudges doth assist,</l>
               <l>And makes not law to serue him as he list.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>To the most reuerend and right Honourable, the Primate of all England.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>TRue Paterne of pietie, with true hearts good will</l>
               <l>My pen doth presume to speake of thy grace</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:6478:13"/>
Whose vertues and goodnesse right well do fulfill</l>
               <l>The honour and greatnesse that is in thy place,</l>
               <l>Gladnesse of conscience may thee imbrace,</l>
               <l>Whose zeale hath beene peacefull with censures discreet,</l>
               <l>Whose life hath beene blamelesse with doctrine to meete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pride sitting below thee in enuious chayre,</l>
               <l>Doth swell at thy greatnesse, yet faine would be great:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Momus</hi> the wretch that all would impaire,</l>
               <l>His head about mischiefe and malice doth beate,</l>
               <l>But care of the truth shall stablish thy seate.</l>
               <l>Thus vertuesregard hath imployed my pen,</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Monies</hi> reward, nor pleasing of men.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The Iudge must be truthes Patron.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe Iudge that sitteth on the bench</l>
               <l>to iudge of wrong and right,</l>
               <l>Should haue the high Tribunall seate</l>
               <l>prefigur'd in his sight,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Least that the Lawyer with his skill</l>
               <l>and argument preparde</l>
               <l>Well sounding to the sense of man,</l>
               <l>and subtilly declarde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Should haue the hap to harbour in</l>
               <l>his well entending brest,</l>
               <l>Where nought but truth, and truthes defence</l>
               <l>for euermore should rest.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:6478:13"/>
               <l>For this is sure, that some there are</l>
               <l>in this our learned age,</l>
               <l>Whose force is great with witto win</l>
               <l>the iudgement of the sage:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ought this rule be alwayes held</l>
               <l>in all iudiciall things,</l>
               <l>That neither Arte, nor lawes dispute</l>
               <l>which learned Lawyer brings,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Doe draw a present iudgement on</l>
               <l>in question of the law:</l>
               <l>For sudden iudgements of tentimes</l>
               <l>may from the truth withdraw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And (Lord) how grieuous were the case,</l>
               <l>if goods were l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st, or lands</l>
               <l>Vpon a point of lawe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dispute</l>
               <l>which argumentiue stands,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Without well ripping vp the same</l>
               <l>with due and deepe regard,</l>
               <l>Foreseeing that the Princes case</l>
               <l>in iudgement be not sparde?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As (for the purpose) were it thus:</l>
               <l>A Statute law there is</l>
               <l>Of Chauntries (so entituled)</l>
               <l>whereon the case be this:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A man giues lands to one by Will,</l>
               <l>he finding euermore</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:6478:14"/>
A yeerely Obite for the soules</l>
               <l>of some deceast before,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And paying for that Obites charge</l>
               <l>a certaine yerely summe,</l>
               <l>And for default thereof a paine</l>
               <l>out of those lands to come.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Admitting also that the lands</l>
               <l>of greater valew ar,</l>
               <l>Besides Reprises of the same</l>
               <l>then th'Obites charges far,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then say those lands are claymed for</l>
               <l>the King in this degree,</l>
               <l>As that the vse thereof by lawe</l>
               <l>should superstitious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Although I take not on me to</l>
               <l>affyrme how it should go,</l>
               <l>Yet this I say, that if such case</l>
               <l>should into question gro,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For that the wait thereof perhaps <note place="margin">I haue heard of such a case in que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ion at this day, and that it is of no lesse impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the subiect the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant then is here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</note>
               </l>
               <l>vnto the subiect may</l>
               <l>Be such as that those lands in sute</l>
               <l>are his all only stay:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And eke for that the Lawyers s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill</l>
               <l>in case of Lawes dispute,</l>
               <l>Is leuelled to win the cause</l>
               <l>and to obtaine the sute</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:6478:14"/>
               <l>Vpon the side he is retaind,</l>
               <l>and not to bend the same</l>
               <l>For Rights defence (for so perdy</l>
               <l>his Client might him blame)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhat neede then hath this case of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>of Iudges holy aide,</l>
               <l>As by the which full oft and oft</l>
               <l>the Right had neede be swaid?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For howsoeuer counsaile vrge</l>
               <l>the matter for the king,</l>
               <l>The Iudge hath his respect to Right</l>
               <l>as to the chiefest thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as for Coplatiues and Disiunctiues</l>
               <l>in Willes, why should they sway?</l>
               <l>For as the Sunne shines not by night</l>
               <l>as it doth by the day:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So men in sicknes haue not sense</l>
               <l>as in their health they haue:</l>
               <l>Sunne setting bringeth darknes, and</l>
               <l>sense faileth at the graue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Againe, should points or periods</l>
               <l>destroy a Subiects state?</l>
               <l>The King himselfe seekes no mans land</l>
               <l>as such an easie rate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Especially, if there haue bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>like cases formerly</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:6478:15"/>
Adi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dgde for Subiects: but for that</l>
               <l>Let Law such matters try:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My speech is not to preiudice</l>
               <l>The Iudgements of the Graue:</l>
               <l>I, as a meane Professor speake</l>
               <l>The knowledge that I haue,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Submitting all that I haue sayd</l>
               <l>Concerning point of Law</l>
               <l>To such, as from whose learned Breasts</l>
               <l>My learning I must draw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For were the foresayd case mine owne,</l>
               <l>My minds resolue should be</l>
               <l>To take in worth what ere fell out,</l>
               <l>Wer'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good or ill for me,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And to returne where I began:</l>
               <l>The Iudge that hath Gods Seate,</l>
               <l>Protects the Right while Lawyers heads</l>
               <l>Vpon preuailings beate.</l>
               <l>I honour Iudges from my heart,</l>
               <l>And loue all Lawyers of desert,</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>A Caueat to peremptory speaking Lawyers.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ANd dost thou speake (friend <hi>Faber)</hi> for thy fee?</l>
               <l>Speake not with mind to beare the matter downe:</l>
               <l>Thinke not that Law should come from none but thee,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:6478:15"/>
For many a one that weares a thridbare gowne,</l>
               <l>Although his gift be not in speaking well,</l>
               <l>Yet may his iudgement many times excell.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>To Astilius Regius the learned &amp; highly imployed Lawyer.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SVch gifts of skill as few men apprehend,</l>
               <l>Must needes be great to dignifie the man,</l>
               <l>To whom it pleaseth God such gifts to lend,</l>
               <l>Though but one gift: If so, what say we the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Where sundry gifts of equall great degree</l>
               <l>In one selfe person well conioyned be?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lawes knowledge of it selfe withouten more</l>
               <l>Hath made some great, yet not without desart.</l>
               <l>And hath it so? what say we then to store</l>
               <l>Of Lawes great skill, and depth of learned Art?</l>
               <l>I say that he in whom such gifts are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound,</l>
               <l>Is great by Right vpon true Reasons ground:</l>
               <l>Such one are you: O still, then still abound in righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:6478:16"/>
            <head>Of the most commendable and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable gouernement of the City of London, in the late times of the sicknesse and decease of the most gracious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Queene Elizabeth.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>FEare, horror, trembling, and dismay of heart</l>
               <l>Were each where seene vpon reports that went</l>
               <l>That our late Queene lay sicke. O dreadfull smart</l>
               <l>Redoubled still as new reports were sent.</l>
               <l>Most men to flit and chaunge their soiles were bent,</l>
               <l>But where to seate or where to be secure,</l>
               <l>Alas, alas, no casting could procure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The vpland man, thought safest in the Towne,</l>
               <l>The townes man thought him best that was at large,</l>
               <l>And he that earst sate warme in long furd gowne,</l>
               <l>Could well haue brook<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the steering of a barge,</l>
               <l>Not one of other then would take the charge,</l>
               <l>But each suspecting other, all dismayd,</l>
               <l>Not for defence, but for destruction stayd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O London then (to thy still lasting same)</l>
               <l>So prudently thy Gouernement was set,</l>
               <l>As that how euer newes then went and came,</l>
               <l>Nought could thy graue foresight or compasse let</l>
               <l>Wisedome and courage so in thee were met,</l>
               <l>As that the Peacefull had his quiet rest,</l>
               <l>And few men fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd that they should be opprest.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:6478:16"/>
               <l>No troupes by day nor lurkings in the night</l>
               <l>Could gather head, but streight they were descryde:</l>
               <l>Each officer so held his course aright,</l>
               <l>As that no doubtfull person durst abide.</l>
               <l>And for the care that was at water-side,</l>
               <l>It was to all great ioy to vnderstand</l>
               <l>What rules were there for setting men on land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In fine, when certainty of death was knowne</l>
               <l>Of her our Queene, did hurly burly rise?</l>
               <l>No none at all: A bud then straight way blowne</l>
               <l>On selfe same Stalke did London well suffice</l>
               <l>To measure all things with an vpright Size.</l>
               <l>The keyes were kept for him who did succeed,</l>
               <l>And nought was heard that discrepance might breed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then I as one partaker of that Good,</l>
               <l>Who with my wife and family did stay</l>
               <l>Within the City where I vnderstood</l>
               <l>Th'occurrents of those times and Cities sway,</l>
               <l>Found cause of sweete content whereas I lay,</l>
               <l>Obseruing there the orders of that place,</l>
               <l>Which with my heart I highly did imbrace.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>No gold no goodnesse.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>O Gold that goest in and out,</l>
               <l>That rul'st and raignest at thy will,</l>
               <l>O thou that bringest things about,</l>
               <l>Why art thou absent from vs still?</l>
               <l>But O our God, O where art thou</l>
               <l>That suffrest Gold to conquer now?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:6478:17"/>
               <l>You earthly men who vnto men</l>
               <l>Nought giue where you can nothing take,</l>
               <l>I speake to you, regard me then,</l>
               <l>Your Gold and Goods your God you make:</l>
               <l>For whereas Gold is, you are won,</l>
               <l>But where Gold is not, you haue done.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Be honest, learned, skilfull, wise,</l>
               <l>Be what thou canst, if Gold thou want,</l>
               <l>Thou maist lie still, thou shalt not rise,</l>
               <l>For nothing proues where Gold is skant:</l>
               <l>For Gold it is that doth the dead,</l>
               <l>But nothing prospers where is need.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What, shall I then lie downe and die?</l>
               <l>Alas I cannot when I would:</l>
               <l>Or shall I sit me downe and crie</l>
               <l>And with my teares my griefe vnfold?</l>
               <l>Lament and crie, do what thou wilt,</l>
               <l>Thy cause is lost for lacke of Gilt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet say I not that all men looke</l>
               <l>To be rewarded for their deed:</l>
               <l>But this I say, that few men brooke</l>
               <l>To helpe a man that is in need:</l>
               <l>For though he write with <hi>Homers</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke,</l>
               <l>Yet go he shall before he drinke.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:6478:17"/>
            <head>The same of this vnhelp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Age.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHere is the man on whom thou mayst depend</l>
               <l>To worke thy good or to assist thee so,</l>
               <l>As by his helpe thou mayst thy state am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd,</l>
               <l>(Though by thy owne desert?) Not one I tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>In words theile giue thee (yea) In deedes still (No)</l>
               <l>My selfe haue had the proofe with men of choise,</l>
               <l>Who wisht me euer well, but all in voyce:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For when it came to proofe, to write or speake</l>
               <l>In matters which themselues thought good and right,</l>
               <l>Good Lord, how were those friends of mine growne weake</l>
               <l>And how small ioy tooke they of me the sight?</l>
               <l>If twere a matter for me to endite,</l>
               <l>I could report hereof a tedious Tale</l>
               <l>And yet the morall might be worth the sale:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But this (in somme) I say and make it knowne,</l>
               <l>That if my case require more helpe then view,</l>
               <l>Except I giue, or can, I looke for none:</l>
               <l>For if thou stand vpon desert, Adieu:</l>
               <l>Marke well my speech, for thou shalt find it true,</l>
               <l>This age affoordeth naught but words and wind,</l>
               <l>The rich shall be preferd, The poore shall stay behind.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:6478:18"/>
            <head>The same complaining of his want of friends.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVAking in my bed I wept</l>
               <l>And silently complaind,</l>
               <l>The cares that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> crept</l>
               <l>All hope of sleepe restraind,</l>
               <l>I called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my hap,</l>
               <l>I cried on my chaunce,</l>
               <l>Will none stand in the gap?</l>
               <l>Will none my state aduance?</l>
               <l>My woe that neuer ends,</l>
               <l>My w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt that neuer dies,</l>
               <l>My state that neuer mends,</l>
               <l>My soule that euer cries,</l>
               <l>All these are but the loome</l>
               <l>That warpeth vp my death,</l>
               <l>All these presage my doome,</l>
               <l>The losse of later breath.</l>
               <l>But is there not a Ioy</l>
               <l>That worldly Ioy excels,</l>
               <l>That helpeth all annoy</l>
               <l>And worldly woe expels?</l>
               <l>There is no doubt, God graunt it me</l>
               <l>So shall those woes extinguisht be.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:6478:18"/>
            <head>Droupe and die, Looke vp and liue.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BE drouping <hi>N.</hi> and die my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> friend:</l>
               <l>For who regardeth him whose ioyes do end:</l>
               <l>Looke vp and liue, make shew of greatest store:</l>
               <l>If litle thou possesse, make shew of more:</l>
               <l>Be modest, simple, bashfull in thy deed,</l>
               <l>Assure thy selfe of nothing thou shalt speed:</l>
               <l>But stout va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t parler stirring in the State</l>
               <l>Will haue his passage through a Princely Gate.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Answer.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah God my God, and must it needes be thus?</l>
               <l>Will nothing come by plaine and simple course?</l>
               <l>Must Nature change her selfe and loose her I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s?</l>
               <l>Must humble mind be proud? Nay (which is worse)</l>
               <l>Must vertue seruile be to stalcke vpon the Stage?</l>
               <l>Ah Lord my God, how grieuous is this Age?</l>
               <l>Ile neuer liue to make such fained showes:</l>
               <l>Ile rather liue where peace of Conscience growes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Natura pauca, opinio mult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> requiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:6478:19"/>
            <head>Trust to thy selfe and not to thy friends nor kinsfolkes.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe mother L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>sted on the ground</l>
               <l>With all her Brats her litle birds about her,</l>
               <l>Abroad she flew where victuals might be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound,</l>
               <l>But ere she went, because she aid misdoubt her</l>
               <l>That in her absence some thing might be sayd</l>
               <l>For cutting downe the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rne wherein she stayd,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She therefore thus ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> speake vnto them all,</l>
               <l>My birds (quoth she) this crop doth ripe apace</l>
               <l>And in mine eye doth for the reapers call,</l>
               <l>Who when they come will you and me displace,</l>
               <l>And more then that, our liues will they inuade</l>
               <l>Vnlesse in time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> seeke some other glade:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And yet to leaue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> soyle before we need,</l>
               <l>Full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I am: my mind therefore is this,</l>
               <l>That when you heare the owner come, take heed</l>
               <l>What words he speakes and what appointed is</l>
               <l>For felling of this field, the time and maner how,</l>
               <l>Looks well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and so I lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e you now.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No sooner go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, but comes the Farmer thither,</l>
               <l>And thus he spake aloud vnto his man:</l>
               <l>Sirha (sayd he) you see this goodly weather</l>
               <l>Get reapers go, with all the speed you can.</l>
               <l>I t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow my neighbours will not say me nay:</l>
               <l>Request them all and tell me what they say:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:6478:19"/>
               <l>The selfe same night when mother Larke came in,</l>
               <l>The silly birds with low and fearefull voyce</l>
               <l>Related all: Tust, tush (quoth she) a pin,</l>
               <l>If maister Farmer make no better choise</l>
               <l>Then neighbours helpe, this field will not go downe,</l>
               <l>Neighbours will helpe themselues throughout the Towne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Next morning when she was to go againe,</l>
               <l>The like precept and charge she left behind:</l>
               <l>At noone the owner came, but all in vaine,</l>
               <l>His neigbours Sycles no where could he find.</l>
               <l>All cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing then, he cald vnto his man</l>
               <l>Who sayd that they would come, but knew not whan.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well well (quoth she) Ile trust no Neighbours aide,</l>
               <l>Go now to such my Cosins and my Kin:</l>
               <l>I know with them this matter will be waide:</l>
               <l>And here to morrow let them all begin.</l>
               <l>This fearefull Summons when the Dam returnd,</l>
               <l>The litle Larkes declard, and then they mournd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not this (quoth she) as yet shall make vs flie:</l>
               <l>Will kinsfolkes helpe? No no the'yle helpe themselues,</l>
               <l>And therefore yet a while here will we lie.</l>
               <l>Cease therefore cease your moane you whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pring el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</l>
               <l>And marke to morrow when he comes againe</l>
               <l>What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e giues forth and how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e doth complaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The morow came, and (as he did before)</l>
               <l>The owner of the field returnd, and finding none</l>
               <l>About the Corne, Lord how he swet and swore</l>
               <l>For being told of kins excuse, and how each one</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:6478:20"/>
Was faint and cold and stood<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon delay,</l>
               <l>He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>de and fretted, and in fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e did say.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That he no longer neighbours, ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red, nor</l>
               <l>Ought sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> himselfe thenceforth would trust vnto:</l>
               <l>And therefore now (quoth he) to cure this d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</l>
               <l>Do thou therein as I shall bid thee do:</l>
               <l>To morrow morning call my men togither</l>
               <l>And with their Harnest weapons bring them hither.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Those newes at night when Beldam came to neast,</l>
               <l>The birds did tell as they had done before:</l>
               <l>Yea now (quoth she) this matter is increast,</l>
               <l>For after this, delayes must be no more:</l>
               <l>This night with speed we must go change our seate</l>
               <l>And so she did with paines and trauell great.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now to shew the morall of this tale,</l>
               <l>As Larke that neasted in anothers ground,</l>
               <l>Not fenst about with hedge, nor ditch nor pale</l>
               <l>Did yet abide a twise most dolefull sound</l>
               <l>Of kin and neighbours comming to the place,</l>
               <l>But when she saw that altred was the case,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As that the Owner of the field would come,</l>
               <l>Or send his seruants on the morow day,</l>
               <l>Then thought she ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to leaue that borrowd roome</l>
               <l>And with her young ones thence to packe away:</l>
               <l>Such is the case of all men that do lay</l>
               <l>Their hope of helpe in kinred or in frend,</l>
               <l>For such a one lies helples in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:6478:20"/>
            <head>The dolorous man being still cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in his estate bewaileth his mishaps.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>DRooping and dying in depth of dispaire,</l>
               <l>Wasted and wearied with sorrow and smart,</l>
               <l>Pinched and pained in penc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>full chaire,</l>
               <l>Yet dare not discouer the thoughts of my heart.</l>
               <l>To keepe them or shew them brings griefe alike to me,</l>
               <l>To keepe or to shew them alike doth vndo me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O dayes full of dolor, O nights of vnrest,</l>
               <l>O times full of trouble, O seasons vnkind,</l>
               <l>If ought could be added, or ought be decreast,</l>
               <l>Then might th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> be hope some comfort to find:</l>
               <l>But resolute Ruine still standing at doore,</l>
               <l>Death cannot haue entrance nor life be secure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O God if thou dost it to punish my Sinne,</l>
               <l>I am thy poore seruant, the worke of thy hand:</l>
               <l>All fraile and vnstable without and within,</l>
               <l>Vnable without thee one houre to stand,</l>
               <l>But sith thou hast promist to helpe where is need,</l>
               <l>Lord, keepe thou thy promise, and helpe me with speed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou knowst what I lacke, thou knowst what I ail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>O Father of mercy, O Fountaine of Grace,</l>
               <l>Sith none that hath sought thee, did euer yet fail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Lord, let not me onely be thrust out of place:</l>
               <l>But looke thou on me as thou lookest on all,</l>
               <l>And helpe thy poore Seruant that lieth in thrall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:6478:21"/>
               <l>Igraunt, of my merites I may be ashamed:</l>
               <l>Not mercy but iudgement doth fit my des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri</l>
               <l>My life hath bene loose, my thoughts all vntamed,</l>
               <l>And what so was holy, that did I peruert,</l>
               <l>Not therefore for me, but for thy name sake</l>
               <l>Vouchsafe me thy mercy my sorrow to slake.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Of dissembling friends.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WEll spake that chosen of the Lord</l>
               <l>Who viewing friends by proose,</l>
               <l>Compared those that in our woes</l>
               <l>and sorowes stand aloofe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To water brookes, whose moysture Heate</l>
               <l>in Sommer dryes to nought</l>
               <l>And winters Frost likewise suckes vp</l>
               <l>When helpe thereosis sought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Contrariwise, in time of Raine</l>
               <l>When each small pit is full,</l>
               <l>Then flow they fast and send forth store</l>
               <l>each hollow gappe to gull.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>A carefull Debtor.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Liue in debt, yet l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue not to do so,</l>
               <l>I pay no debt, but not because I would not:</l>
               <l>Tis debts disease that breedeth all my woe,</l>
               <l>It kils my heart (alas) because I could not.</l>
               <l>But hence I go to seeke some change of soyle</l>
               <l>Whereby to pay my debt with bodies toyle.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:6478:21"/>
            <head>Of one neere dead through thought.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THought is a secret that doth kill</l>
               <l>And with the dead it selfe doth die</l>
               <l>As with his ruine <hi>Sampson</hi> fill</l>
               <l>Himselfe and all with him perdie,</l>
               <l>And is not my poore case much nye,</l>
               <l>Neere dead through Thought both Thought and I?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I Thought no Thought could haue preuaild</l>
               <l>Against my cheerefull minde,</l>
               <l>But cross with crosse hath so assaild,</l>
               <l>That now not so I finde:</l>
               <l>For Thought is come and ioy is gone,</l>
               <l>The body pines and death drawes on.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The liberall mans Expostula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Golde.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WEre my desier to hoerd thee in my chist,</l>
               <l>Or wisht I thee to feede my lustfull paunch,</l>
               <l>Or that by thee I might do what I list,</l>
               <l>And into seas of banefull pleasures launch,</l>
               <l>Or were my minde to lash thee out in lawe,</l>
               <l>By brabling suites which all good things withdrawe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then hadst thou (Gold) good cause to shunne my sight,</l>
               <l>And keepe thy presence from my longing eye:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:6478:22"/>
But sith in seeking thee my Thoughts goe right,</l>
               <l>Why should'st thou then disdaine my Thoughts to trye?</l>
               <l>Beleeue me as thou list, this is my mind:</l>
               <l>If thou make choyce of me, the poore shall finde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not peny helpe, or slender almes at doore,</l>
               <l>But pounds of aide, if need shall so require:</l>
               <l>A full reliefe Ile giue vnto the poore.</l>
               <l>My needy friend shall haue his harts desire,</l>
               <l>And eu'ry case that helplesse lyes for Golde</l>
               <l>Shall haue my sure support as powre can hold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To Booke-men wanting meanes, both hands shall giue:</l>
               <l>The vnprouided Preacher sound of life</l>
               <l>Shall finde how far my zeale my purse can driue,</l>
               <l>But not to nourish Sects, or maintaine strife.</l>
               <l>In summe, what good so'ere thou Gold canst do,</l>
               <l>My hand shall not withhold my helpe thereto:</l>
               <l>But here I cease, least thou should'st thinke I woo thee with my wordes.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The Golden Swaggerer.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>CRownes, Crownes, cries Swaggerer: Then healthes are had</l>
               <l>Of soundest liquor that those Crownes can finde,</l>
               <l>It bootes not then to tell him he is mad.</l>
               <l>His heads chiese care is how himselfe to blinde,</l>
               <l>Great suppers then so soone as he hath dinde:</l>
               <l>And late at night new banquets are preparde,</l>
               <l>So rundell-wise his Crownes he doth discarde,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not to aduance his state perdy: But how</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:6478:22"/>
To glut himselfe with pleasures long desirde.</l>
               <l>He sowes no seede, though deepe he sets his Plow,</l>
               <l>But downe he sinkes vntill his feete be mirde,</l>
               <l>And fast he stickes when he should be retirde:</l>
               <l>Then Gold, what goodnesse hast thou done hereby</l>
               <l>To make him now crie <hi>Crux,</hi> who Crownes did crye?</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>To all Worthy and well deseruing Souldiers.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>TRue Martial men dispaire not in the times:</l>
               <l>Nobilitie of you must haue a care.</l>
               <l>Liue still vntoucht of infamie and crimes,</l>
               <l>And high Iehoue will helpe you where you are.</l>
               <l>Are you the men who neuer yet would spare</l>
               <l>Nor life, nor lim, for Prince and Countries good?</l>
               <l>You are the men, the men whose losse of blood</l>
               <l>With wounds and skars doth still on you appeare</l>
               <l>Though cloth'd and couer'd with your best aray:</l>
               <l>But is that all? no, this besides I heare</l>
               <l>That what remaines of life or lim, you say,</l>
               <l>You are content to spend it any way</l>
               <l>At Princes pleasure, speake he but the word.</l>
               <l>Ah good sweet harts, what more can breath afford?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Write downe your names, your seruices write downe,</l>
               <l>And say that you deuoutely doe remaine</l>
               <l>Prest for the field, and to forsake the Towne,</l>
               <l>If new imployments call you forth againe.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:6478:23"/>
That being done, then with the same retaine</l>
               <l>Some one that is true Noble for your aide,</l>
               <l>Vpon whose mediation all be laid:</l>
               <l>But let him be like her who sometimes said</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non ignara Mali, miseris succurrere disco</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So help will come from seruice or from <hi>fisco</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Though wit be the woer, Yet gold is the speeder.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Fre <hi>Fibbus,</hi> fye, now fye vpon thee foole,</l>
               <l>What meaning hast thou by thy wooing so?</l>
               <l>Thinkst thou to speed with that thou broughtst fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> schoole,</l>
               <l>Or that by Arte thou canst her ouer go?</l>
               <l>If thou say yea, assure thee ile say no.</l>
               <l>She heares thee speake, but when thy tale is tolde,</l>
               <l>Sheele giue thee loue as thou canst giue her golde,</l>
               <l>Except that flesh for flesh may hap be solde, Then locke to that.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>A Sale of Sinne.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>BVm-braka</hi> Lady of the slimie Snailes,</l>
               <l>Out skowting still, doth seeke where she can win,</l>
               <l>Then in she drawes her bootie by the tailes,</l>
               <l>And puts foule flesh to flesh in filthie sinne:</l>
               <l>Yet gilt sheele haue before they do begin:</l>
               <l>O damned creature clapt in Sathans hold,</l>
               <l>VVho damnes her selfe and many mo for gold if Grace come not betweene.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:6478:23"/>
            <head>A Memoriall of the worthy and Right Worshipfull Gentleman, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Louelace, late of Hurley, in the County of Berke, Esquire, Liefetenant of the Castle and Forrest of Windsor.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Some liue, who neuer louing were</l>
               <l>to kisse nor yet to kin,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Louelace</hi> he by louing all</l>
               <l>vnlouing hearts did win.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I speake of that that I well know,</l>
               <l>who knew him to his end:</l>
               <l>His Countrey did not beare a man</l>
               <l>more louing to his friend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What, to his friend? yea poore as rich</l>
               <l>according to his powre</l>
               <l>His Towne of <hi>Hurley,</hi> where he dwelt</l>
               <l>affirmes it to this houre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His Towne of <hi>Hurley</hi> where he colde</l>
               <l>endure the poore to dwell.</l>
               <l>What dwell? yea oftentimes rent-free</l>
               <l>the Countrey knowes it well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And more then that, for hauing woods</l>
               <l>and wastes that spacious were,</l>
               <l>He could abide the poorer sort</l>
               <l>to plant them dwelling there:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:6478:24"/>
               <l>Not for enlarging of his rentes</l>
               <l>(a thing farre from his mind)</l>
               <l>And yet vnto those Cotagers</l>
               <l>be land ofttimes assignde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as vnto his friends and poore</l>
               <l>he thus exprest his loue,</l>
               <l>So for his seruants, wife, nor childe</l>
               <l>could him from them remoue:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For when his Copy-holds came voyd</l>
               <l>he strake not vp the drum,</l>
               <l>Nor gaue them to his children, as</l>
               <l>I know is vs'd by sum.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But as they fell into his hands,</l>
               <l>he gaue them to his men:</l>
               <l>My selfe haue made them Copies oft,</l>
               <l>was he not louing then?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What should I say? A firmer man</l>
               <l>in kindnesse then was he</l>
               <l>I haue not knowne, nor at this day</l>
               <l>a firmer man can see.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And what I write thus in his prayse,</l>
               <l>I write not for reward,</l>
               <l>But to the end that other of</l>
               <l>his sort might haue regard</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To sample out their deedes by his</l>
               <l>in gentlemanly loue,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:6478:24"/>
Which though it bring no profite here</l>
               <l>shall breede them gaine aboue:</l>
               <l>For they must dye, as he is dead,</l>
               <l>Though neare so high they beare their head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quid sumus (O miseri) nisi puluis motus ab aura,</l>
               <l>Et fragili vitro similes, vmbraeque fugaci?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What are we (O wretches) by nature and kind,</l>
               <l>But ashes and dust blowne about with the winde?</l>
               <l>And sampled by semblance, much like brittle glasse,</l>
               <l>And like to the shadowe that swiftly doth passe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mors tua, mors Christi, fraus mundi gloria coeli,</l>
               <l>Et dolor inferni, sunt meditanda tibi.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy death, Christs death, the worlds deceipt,</l>
               <l>with hels infernall paine,</l>
               <l>And glory of the heauens aboue</l>
               <l>let thy deepe thoughts retaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Viue diu, sed viue Deo, nam viuere Mundo,</l>
               <l>Mortis opus, viua est viuere vita Deo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Liue long, but liue vnto the Lord,</l>
               <l>for to the world to liue</l>
               <l>Is dying life, but life to God</l>
               <l>a liuing life doth giue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quod sibi quisque serit praesentis tempore vitae,</l>
               <l>Hoc sibi messis erit, cum dicitur, ite, venite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:6478:25"/>
               <l>What each one soweth to himselfe</l>
               <l>While he on earth is liuing here,</l>
               <l>That shall he reape, when it is said,</l>
               <l>You had be gone, you good come neere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heu viuunt homines tanquam mors nulla sequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</l>
               <l>Et velut infernus fabula vana foret.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Men liue (alas) as though they should not dye,</l>
               <l>And euen as though hell fier were a lye.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>To a foule and common swearer.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THow swear'st (vile man) as though thou were to pay</l>
               <l>A summe of oathes to Sathan for thy soule,</l>
               <l>Thy tongue and lips that so blaspheme alway,</l>
               <l>In helles blacke booke thy iudgement do enrowle</l>
               <l>To suffer torments there and endlesse dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e:</l>
               <l>For cursed swearing in this mortall life</l>
               <l>Will there haue tearing and eternall strife.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>To a Common Lyer.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THy lyes come from thee by the load,</l>
               <l>The carriage of them easie is.</l>
               <l>Where so thou makest thine abode,</l>
               <l>Of lyes a man shall hardly misse.</l>
               <l>But wilt thou know what comes of this?</l>
               <l>Though thou speake truth, yet men will cry,</l>
               <l>Beleeue him not, he tels a lye.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:6478:25"/>
            <head>To an olde man loosely liuing.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Prauus eras paruus, malus et nunc magnus haberis:</l>
               <l>Esto bonus tandem, non decet esse malum:</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Englished thus.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou lewdly liu'dst a little boy,</l>
               <l>now olde, th'ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cald a knaue:</l>
               <l>Be good at length, tis too too bad</l>
               <l>so vile a name to haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Ad hypocritam.</head>
               <l>Dic mihi, cum Christus tibi sit tam multum in ore</l>
               <l>Cur vita Christum (flagitiose) negas?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come tell me now, sith in thy mouth,</l>
               <l>of Christ thy words are rise,</l>
               <l>Why dost thou still deny him then</l>
               <l>so lewdly in thy life?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Ad Christum.</head>
               <l>Tabesco desiderio tua Regna videndi:</l>
               <l>Hac tu (Christe) tamen da mihi tabe mori,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I waste with longing Lord</l>
               <l>To see thy kingdomes hie,</l>
               <l>Yet grant me (Christ my God)</l>
               <l>Such wasting death to dye.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:6478:26"/>
            <head>A liuely description of Ingratitude by a Fable of a Serpent and a way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring man.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>A Serpent fast enclosed in a Caue,</l>
               <l>Vpon the mouth whereof a stone did lye,</l>
               <l>Did piteously complaine and succour craue</l>
               <l>Of such as then by chaunce were passing by.</l>
               <l>A man there was that did regard his crie,</l>
               <l>And to the Serpents suite this answere gaue:</l>
               <l>Thou wilt inuade my life if thine I saue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Serpent then vnto the man replide,</l>
               <l>O no, not so, but rather if by thee</l>
               <l>My life be sau'd, which else is here destroyde,</l>
               <l>Ile giue thee then the chiefest thing that yee</l>
               <l>Of humane race and kinde accustom'd be</l>
               <l>To giue to those who haue done for you most:</l>
               <l>O saue me man, else here my life is lost.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The man much pitying his distressed case,</l>
               <l>Remou'd the stone and let the Serpent out:</l>
               <l>Who being out, did straight his limmes embrace</l>
               <l>And with his hissing wound his legges about:</l>
               <l>Herewith the man grew into fearefull doubt,</l>
               <l>And asking what his meaning was thereby,</l>
               <l>To kill thee (quoth the Serpent, here to dye:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For such is the reward (quoth he) that men</l>
               <l>On earth do giue and euery where bestow</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:6478:26"/>
On those who vnto them most firme, haue ben:</l>
               <l>Ingratitude from each ones brest doth flow,</l>
               <l>And there is none from whome requitals grow.</l>
               <l>The man denying this, they both agreed</l>
               <l>That Iudges should decide the case: so on they yeede,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as they passe, they meete an aged horse,</l>
               <l>Deathes picture sure was he, whome late before</l>
               <l>The owner had thrust forth without remorse:</l>
               <l>They in this case of theirs his helpe implore</l>
               <l>The feeble horse all galde, which grieu'd him sore,</l>
               <l>Accepted of the charge, and thus began:</l>
               <l>There was a time (quoth he) my selfe know whan,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For many yeeres a maister I did serue,</l>
               <l>Who in my youth was glad to vse me well,</l>
               <l>But being olde, he gaue me leaue to sterne,</l>
               <l>Because that olde, I lame and feeble fell:</l>
               <l>And though in youth I bare away the bell,</l>
               <l>And was esteemde, yet now, my labour past,</l>
               <l>He thrusts me forth an Abiect at the last.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Loe, thus you heare (quoth Serpent) what he saies:</l>
               <l>The like requitall must thou haue of me:</l>
               <l>Not so sir) said the man: This horses prayse</l>
               <l>Is of himselfe: And yet you plainly see</l>
               <l>His ill deserts, not Age the causes be,</l>
               <l>And being now enlargde from former toyle,</l>
               <l>Here may he shift to liue vpon this Soyle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And therefore from his Sentence I appeale,</l>
               <l>And will be tride by one that is vpright:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:6478:27"/>
This idle Iade decideth not of zeale,</l>
               <l>But what he speakes, he speaketh in despight,</l>
               <l>And would much more if malice were of might:</l>
               <l>The next we meete therefore shall hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the strife,</l>
               <l>For why (quoth he) it doth concerne my life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then forward still they passe till at the length</l>
               <l>They meete a dogge, whom also age had worne,</l>
               <l>A sily Curre was he cleane void of strength,</l>
               <l>And one who many miseries had borne,</l>
               <l>An halter lately this poore dogge had torne,</l>
               <l>For why, the end then compassed his necke,</l>
               <l>Whereby it seem'd he had escapte a checke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The matter then vnto this dogge declarde,</l>
               <l>Like doome he gaue, as did the horse before,</l>
               <l>Whereat the Serpent as a victor farde,</l>
               <l>But yet for this the man would not giue ore,</l>
               <l>But tooke exceptions nothing lesse, but more:</l>
               <l>This halters end (quoth he) doth well reueale</l>
               <l>What this dogge is: wherefore I do appeale</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From him as from the horse: that halters end</l>
               <l>Doth shew, that he condemned was to die</l>
               <l>For some offence, though fortune as his friend</l>
               <l>That fate of his hath turned cleane awry,</l>
               <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent him stre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> halters strength to flie.</l>
               <l>The Serpent seeing this to be so plaine,</l>
               <l>Could not reply, but gaue consent againe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That this their cause should once more be referd</l>
               <l>To him whom: next they met. And so content</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:6478:27"/>
They onward walke, and as they then conferd,</l>
               <l>They met a curteous Foxe who grauely went <note place="margin">Referment of a cause to a Foxe, is a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
               </l>
               <l>In long Furd gowne, he to them hearing lent.</l>
               <l>Which done, withdrew himselfe that he thereby</l>
               <l>Might better vse aduise to iudge truly,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And secretly vnto the man meane while thus spake:</l>
               <l>My friend (sayd he) thy life lies in my hand:</l>
               <l>Wilt thou therefore agree if for thy sake <note place="margin">A corrupt Iudge.</note>
               </l>
               <l>I iudge the cause (which doubtfully doth stand)</l>
               <l>Vpon thy side, that I by promise band</l>
               <l>Shall haue the Poultry which thou dost possesse,</l>
               <l>I say thy Poultry be they more or lesse?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Poultry? (quoth the man) how can the same</l>
               <l>Serue as a Guerdon for my liues release?</l>
               <l>There shall not one, not Pertellot by name,</l>
               <l>Be kept from thee, nor euer will I cease</l>
               <l>To yeeld thee yeare by yeare of my increase.</l>
               <l>Sufficeth (sayd the Foxe) thus will I do,</l>
               <l>I will require my selfe to go into</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Caue to see how there the Serpent lay,</l>
               <l>And when the Serpent is come in t'expresse</l>
               <l>The maner how, Ile quickly whip away,</l>
               <l>And being gone, then worke thine owne redresse,</l>
               <l>Roll on the stone before he forward presse.</l>
               <l>The matter thus agreed, the Foxe retires</l>
               <l>Vnto the Serpent, and of him requires</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As is in sort declarde: They go yfeere</l>
               <l>Into the Caue, the Foxe soone skippeth out,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:6478:28"/>
The man who then was standing very neere,</l>
               <l>Rolles on the Stone: So things are brought abowt.</l>
               <l>The Stone once on, not all the learned Rowt</l>
               <l>Of Foxes, nor of Serpents in that feeld</l>
               <l>Could stirre the same or any comfort yeeld</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnto that traitrous worme enclosde againe.</l>
               <l>Then there he lyes. And now I will proceed</l>
               <l>To shewe the rest that hereof doth remaine,</l>
               <l>New dishes oft, new Appetites do breed,</l>
               <l>And many a one of later course doth feed,</l>
               <l>Tis tragicall that refleth to be tolde:</l>
               <l>What then? beet good or bad, our course weele holde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Foxe and man togither thence do go</l>
               <l>In friendly sort vnto the good-mans house</l>
               <l>About the bargaine of the Powltry tho.</l>
               <l>But wilt thou goe poore <hi>Foxe? auisa vous.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy bargaine will be scarcely worth a louse,</l>
               <l>Th'vnthankfulnesse that raigneth in this Age,</l>
               <l>I feare me <hi>Foxe,</hi> must be thy deathes presage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But well, what is foreset, must come to passe:</l>
               <l>Not onely death appointed is to all,</l>
               <l>But eke the maner how, as here it was:</l>
               <l>For nought to man or beast by chaunce doth fall,</l>
               <l>There is none such as men do <hi>Fortune</hi> call.</l>
               <l>Against blacke death no craft nor cunning swayes:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Foxe</hi> for all his craft must ende his daies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The honest man repeates vnto his wife</l>
               <l>The fearefull hazards he had late bene in,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:6478:28"/>
And how the Foxe preserued had his life,</l>
               <l>And while he spake the teares ranne downe his chin,</l>
               <l>Which teares with sobbes and sighes he oft did blin.</l>
               <l>His wife attending all the while his tale,</l>
               <l>At length chaungd colour and waxt wondrous pale:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O man (quoth she) now blessed be that beast</l>
               <l>By whom thou art restorde to me aliue:</l>
               <l>Halfe that we haue is with the very least</l>
               <l>That we vnto that blessed <hi>Foxe</hi> should giue:</l>
               <l>We must make reckning neuer here to thriue,</l>
               <l>If vnrewarded this kinde beast should be:</l>
               <l>O how my soule doth long his face to see.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sweete wife (quoth he) thou speakest nought but truth,</l>
               <l>For what can be too much for lifes great gift?</l>
               <l>And sith I see that thou thereon hast ruth,</l>
               <l>I will disclose to thee an honest stift,</l>
               <l>Not doubting but thou wilt allow my drift.</l>
               <l>Thou knowst the Foxe no riches doth regard,</l>
               <l>Ile shewe thee then what shall be his reward:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Two Cockes and thirteene Hennes I thinke we haue,</l>
               <l>And these thou knowst I count not in our State,</l>
               <l>And if with these a greater gift we saue,</l>
               <l>Then shall we passe it at an easie rate:</l>
               <l>For who that would haue said to me of late,</l>
               <l>What wilt thou giue me if I saue thy life?</l>
               <l>I would haue said, take all except my wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The wife that earst before such Zeale had showde,</l>
               <l>As you haue heard, now when it came to proofe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:6478:29"/>
That words must goe with deeds, Lord how she cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wd,</l>
               <l>Each word she spake flew vp aboue the roofe.</l>
               <l>The husband halfe afeard, began to stand aloofe:</l>
               <l>Why man (quoth she) our goods and gold are thine,</l>
               <l>But for the Cockes and Hennes, they all are mine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Giue what thou wilt, but giue it of thine owne:</l>
               <l>A custome tis that men do neuer mell</l>
               <l>With Cockes and Hennes which in the house haue growne,</l>
               <l>For such small wares the wife doth buy and sell:</l>
               <l>I tell thee man, if thou do wish me well,</l>
               <l>Let no such thought once creepe into thy hart:</l>
               <l>For I will dye before Ile see them smart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas, good man, what should he now replie?</l>
               <l>This peremptory speach hath crossed all:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Foxe</hi> for answere stayes abroad hard by,</l>
               <l>Expecting still what share to him should fall,</l>
               <l>He little thinkes what speech is in the hall.</l>
               <l>Well, yet the man a manly courage tooke,</l>
               <l>And thus he answer'd with a manly looke:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And wilt thou (wife) withstand my willes decr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>?</l>
               <l>I tell thee woman I haue past my word.</l>
               <l>Say what thou wilt, the matter needes must be,</l>
               <l>And if thou caust in kindnesse it affoord,</l>
               <l>I will regard thee both at bed and boord,</l>
               <l>But if thou seeke to thwart my true intent,</l>
               <l>It shall be done, and yet shalt thou repent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which words of his so spoken, had such powre</l>
               <l>To quench the fire of her ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e burning spreete,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:6478:29"/>
As that her speech, which had beene sterne and sowre,</l>
               <l>Grew instantly to be both calme and sweete.</l>
               <l>Well husband then (quoth she) if you thinke meete,</l>
               <l>Let it be done: yet thus much let me craue,</l>
               <l>That he may come by night his pray to haue:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For if I should behold, or heare the crie</l>
               <l>That I am sure the sily fowles will make</l>
               <l>When they shall see themselues drawne forth to dye,</l>
               <l>Full sure I am that hart and ioynts would quake:</l>
               <l>Grant this therefore (sweete husband) for my sake,</l>
               <l>That he may come at midnight, not before,</l>
               <l>And I of purpose will leaue ope the dore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This suite of thine sweete hart (quoth he) is small,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Foxe</hi> I know will readily assent.</l>
               <l>So cheerefully he trudg'd out of the hall,</l>
               <l>And to the <hi>Foxe</hi> that lay hard by he went,</l>
               <l>Fuil soone he found the vermine by the sent,</l>
               <l>And making knowne to him his wiues request,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Foxe</hi> agreed and held it for the best.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But in this while the wife casts by deceipt</l>
               <l>And plots how she her pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lens liues may saue:</l>
               <l>In th'end she doth resolue that at receipt</l>
               <l>His life who sau'd her husbands life sheele haue.</l>
               <l>O cursed wretch whose deede doth so depraue</l>
               <l>The vertue that should be in humane race,</l>
               <l>As that for vertue vice doth come in place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But what ensures? the Stratagem is set,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Foxe</hi> at midnight comes to haue his fee,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:6478:30"/>
And thinking (wretch, that he should haue no let,</l>
               <l>Within the house the mortall Engins be,</l>
               <l>And were so plac'd because he could not see,</l>
               <l>That he was caught, and caught, was put to death,</l>
               <l>So he poore <hi>Foxe</hi> resigned vp his breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And thus we see the <hi>Serpents</hi> saying here</l>
               <l>Is verifide that men to men doe giue</l>
               <l>Ill turnes for good: for so it doth appere,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Foxe</hi> is kild, the man he sau'd doth liue:</l>
               <l>Marke well the <hi>Morall</hi> whereunto we driue,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ingratitude</hi> the <hi>Monster</hi> of our dayes,</l>
               <l>In men more then inbeasts it selfe displayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And also note (as to our purpose fit)</l>
               <l>That as the man was moued much by gift</l>
               <l>To saue the <hi>Serpents</hi> life, and saued it,</l>
               <l>So was the <hi>Foxe</hi> likewise procurde to shift</l>
               <l>To saue the man: which to our former drift</l>
               <l>Is this, that liues reliefe is little waide,</l>
               <l>If for the same be nothing paide.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Mediocria firma, with aduice to Constancie.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IN height beware of peoples hate,</l>
               <l>In welth beware of bitter want,</l>
               <l>To rich may be a doubtfull State,</l>
               <l>To ill is Sate that is to skant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:6478:30"/>
               <l>The two extreames are alwayes hard,</l>
               <l>The meane t'weene both is alwayes best:</l>
               <l>And so each State with truth confard,</l>
               <l>The meane degree still bringeth rest.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But whither bale or blithfull blisse</l>
               <l>Betide vnto thy changing lot,</l>
               <l>The surest way for thee is this</l>
               <l>And by no meanes to be forgot:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not to be proud of sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppry hap,</l>
               <l>Nor to repine at pinching woe,</l>
               <l>But as Dame Fortune ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngeth Sap,</l>
               <l>So let Dame F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtune come and goe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And so though States do chop and change,</l>
               <l>As oft they change and chop indeede,</l>
               <l>Thy mind shall neuer wandring range,</l>
               <l>But constantly in things proceede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fortunam reuerenter habe, quicunque repente</l>
               <l>Diues ab exili progrediere loco.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The same in English.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Who so thou be that suddenly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poore degree art raisde,</l>
               <l>Imbrace thy fortune reu'rently, and see thy God be praysde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>In Scurram pauperem.</head>
               <l>Scurra vbi iam fures totam sibi nocte videret</l>
               <l>Scrutantes magna sedulitate Domum,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:6478:31"/>
Risit, et O, media quid vos hic nocte videtis,</l>
               <l>Miror ait, media nil ego cerno die.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The same in English.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>A scoffing Swayne perceiuing theeues</l>
               <l>to search his house by night,</l>
               <l>Laught lowd, and to the theeues he said,</l>
               <l>O sirs, your braines be light:</l>
               <l>What meane you at this seeld to search,</l>
               <l>as though you could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>spy</l>
               <l>At midnight that, that I at noone</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould neuer yet come by?</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>A returne to Golde.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ANd now to Gold I bend my speech againe:</l>
               <l>Goe packe thee hence, Corrupter of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Enclose thy selfe in Mines, let earth retaine</l>
               <l>Thy tyrant corpes, that so on earth d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st rage,</l>
               <l>That makest great ones serue thee as a Page,</l>
               <l>That what thou wilt, by thee is quickly woon,</l>
               <l>And what thou wilt, in like degree is doon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou setst th'vnlearned in the learned Seate:</l>
               <l>Th'vnfaithfull Shepheard in true Shepheards place,</l>
               <l>Who feedes no flocke, but of the flocke doth eate:</l>
               <l>Thou mak'st the foole the wiseman to disgrace,</l>
               <l>And him that's lewd the honest to deface.</l>
               <l>Woe worth thee wretch, the troubler of our time,</l>
               <l>By whome the vertuous are held backe, and vassals clime.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:6478:31"/>
               <l>And though there be of high and worthy States</l>
               <l>That wey thee not, but wey true vertue more, <note place="margin">I haue heard of some ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, who vpon their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, haue bin most careful in the choise of their seru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nts for feare of bribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Yet through <hi>Gehesi</hi> and his bribing mates,</l>
               <l>There's little had for such as be but poore:</l>
               <l>Where thou set'st foote, the worthy waite at doore,</l>
               <l>While claw-backe Iackes, as brag as body-lowse,</l>
               <l>Are entertaind in euery roome ath'house.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>T'is to be read what was in <hi>Athens</hi> wrought,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Phillippe</hi> king of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who thee</l>
               <l>Imployde to bring that gallant state to nought,</l>
               <l>By bribing those that were of best degree</l>
               <l>Within the same. The like who might not see</l>
               <l>In Englands State, of yeares not many past,</l>
               <l>As also what became of them at last?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It were too long to reckon vp the whole,</l>
               <l>How Golde corrupts by manifolde degrees,</l>
               <l>And how for it full many pill and pole,</l>
               <l>And Lawyers some, do take excessiue fees:</l>
               <l>Thou Golde canst make men flie about like Bees.</l>
               <l>But more then that, (would God that were the wurst)</l>
               <l>Thou mak'st men swell with pride as they would burst.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And yet hereby I touch not Lawyers State,</l>
               <l>Nor haue intent to quippe the learned sorte:</l>
               <l>That were an Office for a scurrile mate,</l>
               <l>For there are Lawyers of most worthy Porte,</l>
               <l>Who still holde out as doth a fensed Forte,</l>
               <l>Well getting Golde, and not enclinde to Pride,</l>
               <l>For which good sort due Honors do abide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:6478:32"/>
               <l>And for the Iudges of our Common lawe,</l>
               <l>I speake it from my heart, and so I holde</l>
               <l>That there are none can say, they euer sawe</l>
               <l>One Iudge that's now aliue corrupt with golde.</l>
               <l>God graunt that they in like sort may be bolde</l>
               <l>To keepe the Ballance tyte twixt small and great, <note place="margin">Grandibus exigu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> sunt pisees pisci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ese<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Least else the small should be the great ones meate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I will conclude. Not eu'ry State of men,</l>
               <l>But some almost in eu'ry State there are,</l>
               <l>Who may be wrought the good with bad to blen,</l>
               <l>If golde, thou golde canst growe vnto their share:</l>
               <l>And though that some of them perhaps haue care</l>
               <l>To do no wrong, yet wrong they will permit,</l>
               <l>As when they should giue helpe, they silent sit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But for as much as many men are led</l>
               <l>By many waies to start aside for Golde,</l>
               <l>And that the mischiefes which are daily bred</l>
               <l>By <hi>Moneys</hi> sway, are great and manifold,</l>
               <l>So great I feare, as hardly can be tolde,</l>
               <l>Therefore I ende my endlesse plaint with this,</l>
               <l>That God must mend what gold hath made amis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quid non mortalia pectora cogis Auri sacrafames.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To what thing is't that Goldene can</l>
               <l>Constraine the thirsting heart of man?</l>
               <l>The heart of man as hard as stone,</l>
               <l>VVhich yeeldeth not to any moue,</l>
               <l>But as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he same with golde is bound,</l>
               <l>So is affection in it found,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:6478:32"/>
To bring about what may be had,</l>
               <l>Let be the matter good or bad.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Omnia venalia Nummo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Seeke gold, seeke gold, (good friend) seeke gold,</l>
               <l>For golde can all things bye,</l>
               <l>Both vertue, vice, (and else what not?)</l>
               <l>To sale for golde do lie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Omnia nummatis loculis sopita quiescunt,</l>
               <l>Cum volet ipse Deus, fiet amaena Dies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To him that hath the golden bagges</l>
               <l>all things in quiet rest,</l>
               <l>But God can giue a golden day</l>
               <l>when he shall thinke it best.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Omnia Diues habet, nam praestat omnia Nummus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The rich hath all that heart can craue,</l>
               <l>For he with golde all things can haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhen vices all waxe olde in man,</l>
               <l>His loue of golde growes youthly than.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:6478:33"/>
            <head>To the Right VVorshipfull and of high deseruing Sir <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> Knight, one of the Maisters of the Requests to the Kings Maiestie.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THough griefes arise in men of troubled harts,</l>
               <l>Yet when the same by skill of penne are plaste,</l>
               <l>Petition-like in writing with the parts,</l>
               <l>Good God, how then such Suters griefes do waste,</l>
               <l>As though that then their helpe would come in haste</l>
               <l>But if their Sutes do happen on delay,</l>
               <l>Faint growes the hope whereon their hearts did stay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If toylesome paine procure dispatch of Sutes,</l>
               <l>What plowman taketh greater paines then yea;</l>
               <l>An open Truth a slaunderous lye confutes,</l>
               <l>So what I write, apparently is true:</l>
               <l>And yet (good sir) this sequele may ensue,</l>
               <l>Vnlesse the Suter do his Sute obta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne,</l>
               <l>Ill words may come for recompence of paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For why it happens oft, that he who sues,</l>
               <l>Because his minde runnes wholly on successe,</l>
               <l>If that he happe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>are contrary newes,</l>
               <l>Then weying no mans trauel more or lesse,</l>
               <l>Away he goes with great vnthankfulnesse.</l>
               <l>So thanklesse thoughts and peeches that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epraue</l>
               <l>Oft Mediators vnto Prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Alphensus</hi> king of Naples was wont to say of <hi>Mediators</hi> of Requests vnto kings and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inces,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6478:33"/>
that they are like vnto those who hauing their dwell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs in the middle roomes of a house, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sprinckled with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rine by those that are aboue them, and annoyed with filth by those that are belowe them.
<q>
                  <p>Sic plerun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Mediatores vtrin<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> leduntur, sicut vespertili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Laceratur a mur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bus &amp; autbus.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The Author.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ANd here my Booke shall haue his end</l>
               <l>with my complaint of Gold;</l>
               <l>God graunt that high and holy thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>in sound estate may hold</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as the seate of Iustice is</l>
               <l>At this day firme and pure,</l>
               <l>So passages vnto the same</l>
               <l>may be both plaine and sure,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not clogd with shifts and falsitie:</l>
               <l>by such as haue to deale</l>
               <l>Inferiourly with Iustice in</l>
               <l>our English common-weale</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That Sut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>before they be opprest</l>
               <l>With bribes and charges in their sute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>and so for all the rest,</l>
               <l>That Gold may neuer beare the sway,</l>
               <l>But that true vertue flourish may.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
