<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A consultorie for all Christians Most godly and ernestly warnyng al people, to beware least they beare the name of christians in vayne. Now first imprinted, the. xxx day of Ianuarie.</title>
            <author>Hart, Henry, fl. 1549.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1549</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12564</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109663</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845310</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845310</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10202</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02432)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10202)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 46:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A consultorie for all Christians Most godly and ernestly warnyng al people, to beware least they beare the name of christians in vayne. Now first imprinted, the. xxx day of Ianuarie.</title>
                  <author>Hart, Henry, fl. 1549.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[120] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Oswen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Anno. M.D.xlix. At Worceter :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1549]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: H.H. =  Henry Hart--Cf. STC and Halkett &amp; Laing.</note>
                  <note>Includes on A2r-A3v Oswen's royal privilege to print service books and religious treatises in Wales and the Marches, dated 6 January 1549.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title: Cum priuilegio Regali ad imprimendum Solum. Per septennium.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10202:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10202:1"/>
            <p>A Conſulto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for all Chriſtians. Moſt godly and erneſtly war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng al people, to beware leaſt they beare the name of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in vayne. Now firſt imprinted, the .xxx day of Ianuarie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno. M.D.xlix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At Worceter by Iohn Oſwen, Cum <hi>priuilegio <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ad im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primendum <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. Per ſeptem</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="biblical_quotation">
            <pb facs="tcp:10202:2"/>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Epheſians the .iiij. ii</bibl>
                  <p>I, beſeche you bretheen, bound in the lorde, that you walke worthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the vocation wherein you be called, with all humylitie and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlenes, with pacience ſupportynge one an other in loue, beyng dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to kepe the vnitie of the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite in the hande of peace, beynge one body and one ſpirite, as you be called in one hope of your voca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion. There is one lorde, one faith, one baptiſme, one god and father of all, which is aboue all, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row all, and in all vs: for to euery one of vs is there grace geuen, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the meaſure of the gyfte of Chriſte.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:10202:2"/>
            <head>¶The copie of the Kynges Maieſties moſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous priuiledge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Dwarde the ſixt by the grace of God, kyng of Englande, Fraunce and Irelande, defender of the faith, and of the churche of England, and alſo of Ireland, in earth the ſupreme head. To all maner of Printers, boke ſellers, and other our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, miniſters and ſubiectes, gretyng: We late you were, that of our eſpecial grace, we renderyng the godly edifiyng and eaſe of our louyng ſubiectes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our Principalitie of Wales, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the ſame, by thaduiſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of our moſt dere vncle Edwarde Duke of Somerſet, Gouernour of our perſon, and Protectòur of all our realmes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions and ſubiectes, and other our counſailours, haue graunted and geuen priuiledge and licence, and by thies pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentes doo graunt and geue priuiledge and lycence, vnto our welbeloued ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect Iohn Oſwen, of our citie of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceter
<pb facs="tcp:10202:3"/>
Printer, and to his factours and aſſignes, to print, reprint, vtter and ſell, or cauſe to be printed, reprinted, vttered, and ſolde, ſo many of euery kynde of boke or bokes, whiche haue or ſhalbe ſet forth by vs, by thaduiſe aforeſaid, for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to be vſed in our Churches, miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Sacramentes, and inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſaid ſubiectes, as ſhall onely ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſe for the Churches and our ſubiectes within our ſaid Principalitie and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, any other licence or priuiledge to the contrary in any wiſe notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>AND alſo, of our eſpeciall grace by thaduiſe and conſent aforeſaid, we haue graunted and geuen priuiledge and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and by thies preſentes do graunt and geue priuilege and licence, vnto the ſaide Iohn Oſwen, and to his factours and aſſignes, to print, vtter and ſell, or cauſe to be printed, vttered and ſold, to all perſon and perſons of whatſoeuer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, degree, or condition they be, al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of bokes conteinyng any ſtorye or expoſition of Gods holy ſcripture, or of any part thereof, beyng not contrary or againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, which at any time hereto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore haue bene, or hereafter ſhalbe made
<pb facs="tcp:10202:3"/>
tranſlated or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>piled, by the ſame Iohn Oſwen, or by his meanes, inſtigatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie or procureme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and at his coſtes &amp; charges, of whatſoeuer qualitie or ſort the ſaide bokes or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the true copies of euery ſuche bokes be firſt diligently ſeen, peruſed and alowed, by ſuche perſon or perſons as we ſhall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time therunto aſſigne and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, before they be put to any ſale or vtteraunce. And further our minde and pleaſure is, &amp; by thies preſentes we doo ſtraightly charge &amp; inhibite, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons of whatſoeuer eſtate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition he or they be, do at any time hereafter print, or reprint, or cauſe to be printed or reprinted priuely or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertly any of the bokes aforeſaid, or any parte or parcell of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, duryng the ſpace of .vii. yeres, next after the printing or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printyng of the ſame bokes by the ſayde Iohn Oſwen, his factours or aſſignes: ſo that the ſame Iohn his factours &amp; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, ſhall and may haue the profitte &amp; aduauntage co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng &amp; growyng of the printyng and reprintyng of ſuche bokes in reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence &amp; alleinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his induſtry paines &amp; charges in that behalfe to bee
<pb facs="tcp:10202:4"/>
ſuſteined. Wherfore we wil &amp; ſtraightly charge &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund al &amp; ſinguler our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, aſwel printers &amp; bokeſellers, as al other perſons within al our dominions, that thei or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do not preſume to print vtter or ſell, or cauſe to be printed vttered or ſolde within any our domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, any of the bokes aforeſaid, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Iohn made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>piled, or tranſlated, or any parcell of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contrary to the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of this our preſent lyce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pain that euery offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der therin ſhal forfait to our vſe al ſuche bokes and euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where ſoeuer they ſhall bee fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Willyng therfore &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundyng all our officers miniſters &amp; ſubiectes as they te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre our fauour &amp; will auoide our high indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they &amp; euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if nede ſhal require, do aide &amp; aſſiſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Iohn Oſwen his factours &amp; aſſignes in the due exerciſyng &amp; executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this our preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; priuiledge with effect ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the true meanyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. In witnes wherof we haue cauſed theſe our letters to be made patentes. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes our ſelf, at Weſtminſter the ſixt day of Ianuary, the ſeconde yere of our Reigne.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10202:4"/>
            <head>A Conſulto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for al Chriſtians.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes paſte,<note place="margin">Heb. i. a</note> diuerſlye &amp; many wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſpake to the fathers by prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, but in theſe laſt daies hath he ſpoken vnto vs, as S. Paule ſayeth, by his ſonne, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath made heyre of al thinges, and by him hath he now declared his moſt godlye will vnto vs, that we might obtain life in him: whoſe moſt excellent cleare brightnes hath long time been darkened,<note place="margin">Apoc. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> and as S. Iohn ſaieth, hid as with a ſackeclothe made with
<pb facs="tcp:10202:5"/>
heare, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay with a fayned ryghtuouſenes grounded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> naturall wyſdome and carnall reaſon, inuented and ſet fourth by man: So that the bright ſhy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng beames of goddes truth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned in the holy ſcriptures might in no wiſe appere (by rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon of that dark vaile or cloud) to the eyes or mynde of men, whiche is not yet wyth all men taken awaye.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>3.</hi> c</note> Neuertheleſſe, when they tourne to the lorde (ſaith Paul) the vayle ſhalbe ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken awaye, for no doute, ſaithe he, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord is a ſpirit, and where the ſpirite of the lorde is, there is lybertie. And ſeyng that god which is ryche in mercy, hathe once againe put downe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great power of the enenemy, broken down his braſen gates, and by
<pb facs="tcp:10202:5"/>
vyolence taken the praye (as a ſpoyle) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the mouth of the Lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea victoryouſly hath he delyuered his truth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> longe time hath of his enemies be hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage &amp; captiuitie, &amp; we haue herd and ſene theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, obeyed &amp; do beleue. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore am I not aſhamed to teſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fye the truthe vnto the worlde becauſe it is the poure of God vnto ſaluation,<note place="margin">Roma. i.</note> to all them that do deleue. And as Sainct Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaythe,<note place="margin">Ihon. i. i. Ihon. i.</note> the onely trewe lyghte whiche lyghteneth all menne that come into the worlde, our handes haue handeled of the worde of lyfe, for lyfe hath ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſaith he, and we haue ſene and beare witnes, &amp; ſhew vnto you lyfe, that is euerlaſtynge whiche was withe the father, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10202:6"/>
hath now apered alſo vnto vs. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tidyngs which we haue heard of him (as Ihon ſaith) de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare we vnto you, that ye may haue felowſhip with vs, &amp; oure felowſhyp may be with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and with his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte &amp;c.</p>
            <p>¶For as moche as, it hathe pleaſed the eternall god, which ſeperated me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my mothers wombe, to lighten the inward eyes of my mynde withe hys grace, and thorowe the knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his word and working of his holy ſpirite, to worke a perfect repentaunce in me, and amendmente of my formoure lyfe, loue conſtraynethe me too wyl you (good bretheren) to be partakers of this greate bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte. And for this cauſe, I haue
<pb facs="tcp:10202:6"/>
thought it neceſſary, as well to declare vnto you the daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe harmes that ſynne bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to ſuche as delyte and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinew therein, as alſo the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable reward of the righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſe whiche god hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thoſe that withe their h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le hartes tourne from theyr ſynnes and walke wyth theyr god in the way of rightuouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I wyll not withhold fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, good brethren, that which god hath wrought in me, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the weake ſtomakes, of them that now waxe faynte herted and ſhrynke backe, that I may ſay wyth the Prophete Dauid.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> Lord I do not hide thy righteouſenes in my herte, but my talkynge is of thy truthe &amp; ſauynge health, all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day long.
<pb facs="tcp:10202:7"/>
Therefore tourn not thou thy mercy from me (o lorde) but let thy louyng kyndnes and truth alwayes preſerue me. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>¶For it is writen, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſpeke vnto the, then open thou thy mouthe, ſaith the lord, and ſay who hereth, let hym here, who ſo wyll not, let hym leaue, for it is a frowarde houſholde. &amp;c</p>
            <p>¶For as moche as I perceyue that the earth maketh haſte to bringe fourth her children, and the tyme draweth faſt toward the end, and all fleſh ſemeth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deſirouſe and as it were gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, to accomplyſhe the thynge with moche haſte, whiche it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in hande, be it good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, my deſyre is alſo to occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie my talente accordynge to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll of the geuer, wherebye I
<pb facs="tcp:10202:7"/>
may pleaſe my lorde, which is my deſire aboue all thynges, &amp; not onely therby to gather tre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure for my ſelfe, but alſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoke as wel my bretheren and naturall contrymenne of thys realme of England / as al other nations and named Chriſtians to bryng fourth their frutes re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyly accordyng to their nature that they may be rype againſt the day of harueſt,<note place="margin">Named criſtians.</note> when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord ſhall rewarde euery man accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng to his deades. Therfore beloued fathers and brethren, ſeyng ye haue taken the name of holynes vpon you, beyng cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led Chriſtians of Chriſt, and do in word profeſſe the ſame, eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge your ſelues the trewe churche and eſpouſe of God vpon earth, as al that lyue god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="tcp:10202:8"/>
doubtles be, See that ye be dilygente to obey to the word of truth which our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther hath now ſente and ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade by his beloued meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, as wel within this reame of England, as in all other regi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons on the earth, as it is wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the eyghtenth Pſalme.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>18</hi> Rom. <hi>16</hi>
               </note> Theyr ſownde is gone owte into all landes: And their wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des into the endes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. If ye accepte the voyce of the ſhepeherde, then wyll he know you for his owne, and lead you in and oute, where ye ſhall all wayes fynde riche paſture. Godde hathe made daye and nyghte,<note place="margin">Ihon. <hi>10</hi>
               </note> lyghte and darkeneſſe, ſommer and wynter, to the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tente that all thynges myght-haue
<pb facs="tcp:10202:8"/>
as well place and time as ſufficient occaſion to ſhew forth &amp; declare theim ſelues, eyther good or euill. Repent &amp; turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your euill waies with your whole hertes, that ye maie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, &amp; ſet your faithe on a ſure ground,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>65</hi> Gala. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> build it on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion of gods holy worde and promiſes, and then will it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies abide the violence of the ſtormes, but yf ye go by groo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng and woorke at auenture, be ye ſure, ye ſhal not go right, for true fayth is liuely, &amp; no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayne thynge, it is ſurelye grounded and ſtabliſhed vpon the ſure rocke of Gods woorde and promiſe, as it is written. Abraham beleued God in hys promiſe,<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> and none opinion of his own imaginacion, &amp; it was
<pb facs="tcp:10202:9"/>
counted to hym for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but yf your faith bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the word, then is it carnall and fleſhely, beyng builte vpon naturall reaſon, and therefore it is vayne and of no valure,<note place="margin">Eccle. i.</note> for trewe faithe is accoumpanyed with godly loue, who hath the wiiſdome of god for her gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſhe teacheth her chyldren (as a right good nourice) know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge and nurture, and leadeth them ſafely in the waye of lyfe,<note place="margin">i. Ihon.</note> and with doctrine ſhe purgeth their hertes from all filthe and corruption, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as god himſelfe is pure. She ſhyneth from and out of the boſome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt, for her clearenes doth farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede the brightnes of the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, whiche lighteth the whole erth with her ſhine. Therfore O ye
<pb facs="tcp:10202:9"/>
ignoraunte, geue a dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eare to the voice of wiſedom, which daily cryeth vnto you in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high places ſtretes, and wayes, and before the holy citie, and in the gates where me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go out and in. It is you, O ye men, ſaieth ſhe, whom I call, vnto you, (O ye children of men, lyfte I vp my voyce: Take hede vnto know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſaieth ſhe, O ye ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, be wyſe in harte. O ye fooles, geue eare, ſayeth ſhe, for I will ſpeake of great matters, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen my lyppes, to tell thynges that be right, for my throte ſhal be talkyng of the truth, my lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes abhorre vngodlines, al the wordes of my mouth are righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, there is no froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes nor falſhode therein. They are all plain, ſayeth ſhe, to ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:10202:10"/>
as wyl vnderſtande, and right to them that fynde knowledge receiue my doctrine, ſaith ſhee, and not ſyluer, and knowledge, more then fyne golde,<note place="margin">Prou. <hi>3.</hi> c</note> for wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is more worth then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſe ſtones, yea all the thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that thou canſt deſyre, are not to be compared vnto it &amp;c.</p>
            <p>¶Wherefore if ye wyll ſeeke wiſdome and dwell with her, ſhee will make you the verye frendes of god, for the higheſt hath geuen her a commaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente, and he that made herre hath apointed her a tabernacle ſaying. Let thy dwellynge be in Iacob, &amp; thyne inheritaunce in Iſrael, rote thy ſelfe among my choſen, for the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the rightuouſe, are the Children of wiſedome, and the
<pb facs="tcp:10202:10"/>
lorde dwelleth amonge them in hys holye Sinay. An vtter enemye to wiſdome is the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſynner, for he hateth to be refourmed, and becauſe he will not refuſe thynges which he knoweth to be euyll; he can come in no good way, brethern conſider this moſt excellent be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefite of god, dayly offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. Refuſe not his worde which teacheth you al wiſdom Come to her brokes, &amp; drinke of her cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duite, for wiſdom hath caſt out floudes, I am,<note place="margin">Eccle. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> ſaith ſhe as a great water broke oute of the ryuer &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And as a water cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duite am I come oute of the gardeine of pleaſure, I ſaide, I wyll water the gardeine of my yonge plan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and fill y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frute of my birth,
<pb facs="tcp:10202:11"/>
ſo my water brooke, became ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceadinge greate ſaith ſhee, and my Ryuer aprocheth vnto the See, for I make doctrine to be to all men as light as the faire morning and I ſhal make it, ſaith ſhe, euer the clearer, I will perſe thorow all the lower partes of the earth, I will loke vpon ſuch as be a ſlepe, &amp; ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten all theym that putte their truſt in the Lorde, I ſhall yet poure oute doctrine lyke a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, and leane vnto ſuche as ſeke after wiſdome, and their generations ſhall I neuer faile vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy euerlaſting world.</p>
            <p>¶Obey vnto the louing voice of God, and accepte this gentle doctrine of wiſedome, ſlumber not to long in thyne owne way (O thou named Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:10202:11"/>
the lorde be angry, leaſte thou fall a ſlepe againe in ſynne, and ſo periſhe vtterly by thine own folly. How can theye be made hole that wyll not knowe they be ſicke, or howe can ſuche ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that refuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right way? Thou thinkeſt thy ſelfe well al redy, becauſe thou haſt a name that thou liueſt. O thou named Chriſtian, therfore thou ſaiſte in thy ſelfe.<note place="margin">Apoca. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Tuſhe I am riche and increſed with goodes, and haue nede of nothynge, &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt not how thou art wretched and myſerable, poore, blynde, &amp; naked: thou haſte a name that thou liueſt, but thou art deade, for by ſynne art thou ſubdued, and thruſt downe by thyne ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies euen to the brinke of hell. O named Chriſtianytie, thou
<pb facs="tcp:10202:12"/>
waft rolde vp in extreme dark<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and myſery, yea ſolde and ſolde again waſt thou for thine offences, to be a bonde ſeruant whereof thou art not yet dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, for ignoraunce holdeth the in captiuitie, and bringeth the a ſlepe, that thou neyther ſeeſt nor feleſt thye harme,<note place="margin">Eſaye <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> but lyke an hongry man dremyng that he is eatyng, &amp; wakynge hath nothinge, or lyke a thyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dreameth that he is drinkyng, but when he waketh he fyndeth nothynge to refreſh hym ſelf, ſo doth ſynne deceiue the, and thou not ware. Awake awake oute of thy heauy ſlepe thou Chriſtianitie, harken to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loud voice and trompe of god which in theſe laſt daies is now blowen amongeſt you. I mean
<pb facs="tcp:10202:12"/>
the preachyng of the gloryouſe goſpell of Chriſt, which is day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preached vnto you, and yet ſoundeth in youre eares. O fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh people, why ſtop you youre eares ſo longe from the truth: and as it were, ſtyll geue youre ſelues to vanitie? Why ſeke ye ſuche frendſhyp of the worlde, whiche hath nothyng to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, but extreame myſerye? Why ſekeſte thou reſte, where none is? Treaſure vp ſuch thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges as are godly, then ſhalte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be recompenſed .vij. folde: but who ſo ſeeketh reſt in worldly thynges, his labour is in vain. Conſider O man, thy lyfe in this worlde, how ſhort, how vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>certeine, and daungerouſe it is it is lyke a vapour or breathe, ſaith the Apoſtle S. Iames,<note place="margin">Iames. <hi>4</hi>
               </note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10202:13"/>
appereth for a lytle ſeaſon, and then vaniſſheth away, therfore truſte not to the worlde, for he is diſceitfull, he promyſeth reſt, but payeth trouble, he promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ioye and paieth ſorowe he promyſeth longe lyfe, and pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſhort, totally, he promyſeth good and payeth euyll, for na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and fortune be muche va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable, &amp; chaunge as the winde and therfore do they ſuffer no thynge here certeine. O folyſh man woldeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> then be thought wiſe, and yet delyteſt and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thy hole hert and pleaſure in this vaine tranſitory world. what frendſhippe woldeſt thou haue of hym that can do you no good, neither careth he lenger for the then thou maiſt do hym pleaſure, for in ſorow pouertie
<pb facs="tcp:10202:13"/>
or payne, will he vtterly diſpiſe the, and laugh the to ſcorne in the anguyſh of thy ſoule. Soo vngodly doth this myſerable worlde recompence his louers that the nighe frende,<note place="margin">O beſtes vngodly &amp; very vnna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turall.</note> ſo called of nature, the wife that lyeth in the boſome, or the Chyldren whom with buſy paine and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy ſome bringe vp, intendynge by them to haue their kindnes after recompenced, do nothing at all regarde them, but flate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryngly from the teth outward thinkyng euery day three, tyll they be gone, that they myght receiue the worldely goodes which their frendes do poſſes. O myſery of all myſeries, thus the worlde which many ſo inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately loue, and ſet ſuch ſtore by, for all his greate bragges,
<pb facs="tcp:10202:14"/>
and flateryng face of frendſhip (if nature withdraw her ſelfe) wyl not onely think hym moch burdened by them, but alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfully abhor &amp; deteſte their preſence. Therefore as Chriſte ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>6.</hi> d</note> ſeke ye firſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of god, &amp; the righteouſenes there of, and all theſe thynges ſhalbe myniſtred vnto you. And alſo Criſt ſaith, geue not ouer your membres to ſerue the fleſh, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beutie thereof fadethe away, for he that ſoweth in the fleſhe,<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> ſhall of the fleſh repe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaith Sainct Paul, but he that ſoweth in the ſpirite, ſhall of the ſpirite reape lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtinge. Againe the apoſtle Iude ſaith. Hate the filthy ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of the fleſſhe, for doubtles it is ſubiect to corruption, it is
<pb facs="tcp:10202:14"/>
alſo, the very gate and meane whereby Sathan oure greate aduerſary, and mortall enemy corrupteth both bodie &amp; ſoule, and draweth man to vtter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Wherfore ſee that ye furniſh the houſe in tyme with an honeſt exerciſe of vertu, that perfecte repentaunce make a ready way, for faith and godly loue with all her noble compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, to dwell with you: for if the enemy finde you vnprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he will buſily ſeke to enter with his ſoudears, for as moch as, man is by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tranſgreſſion of Adam, ſet at lybertie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of good and euyll, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy firſt moueth man by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente, to choſe the euill and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the good, which conſent be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng coupled to the thought of
<pb facs="tcp:10202:15"/>
mans knowledge,<note place="margin">By the fall of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, the inward eye of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the knouledge of good and euyll, Iam. <hi>1</hi> c. Mat. <hi>5.</hi> c Chriſte ſaith, who ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth on a wyfe lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge, hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ultry with her. Exody. <hi>20</hi> Deutro. <hi>5</hi>
               </note> is ſynne. As witneſſeth S. Iames ſaying. When luſt hath conceyued, ſhee bringeth fourth ſynne, by this meanes winneth the enemy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gate or fyrſt ward, then proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge forth in his wicked pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pteth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duryng his life in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of youth, by wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes delectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, pleaſure &amp; redy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of mynd, to ſpend the tyme of this lyfe, either idely or vain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, that he ſhould laboure in no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing that is good, and when nature hathe ſome what done with theſe, he bringeth in place euery carnal concupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, riot, naturall wiſdome, and worldly honoure and riches: and in age he bringeth coueteouſenes, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pacient pouertie, childyſhe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and ſuche lyke. For ſone
<pb facs="tcp:10202:15"/>
after xxx. yeares are ſpent,, as age increaſeth, the thinges of nature dimyniſhe, and begin to fade as a flower, but the ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>my alway duryng the tyme of this lyfe, ceaſeth not to aſſaulte man by ſynne, which is moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing to the nature and age of the perſon ſo tempted. And by ſuche vngodly meanes he ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth to fyll and kepe the mynd of man ſo buſied, that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue no reſpecte to the word &amp; wyll of god, nor ſeke after thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pleaſe hym. But ſeinge the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of theſe is naught els but playne myſery and diſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bothe of bodye and ſoule, what folyſh blyndnes is it, for men to ſet their loue ſo inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natelye vpon ſuche thynges wherein is neuer reſt nor peace?
<pb facs="tcp:10202:16"/>
and to ſeke the ſeruice of ſuche maiſters as be very Aucthors of all trouble and myſery, and the bond ſeruantes of ſynne, and corruption, that ſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherfore, ſtryue daily againſt your luſtes, and mortyfie your affections, compell youre fleſhe to be ruled and ordered, by the rules of Chriſte, preſcrybed in the ſacred worde of god, vnto you. Then doubtles our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye father wyll not onelye loue vs, &amp; take vs for hys dear children, but alſo for Chriſtes ſake (ſo that we yet, continew in faith) beare our imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on durynge the tyme of this lyfe, clearelye forgeue and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get our ſynnes. And make vs partakers with oure ſauioure Chriſte, of hys eternall kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:10202:16"/>
and glorie. Therfore O ye Chriſtined nations call to remembraunce the longe time of your captiuitie &amp; blyndnes of mynde, which hath very far exceded the tyme of the capty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of the Hebrues, the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael, or of any other congregations, profeſſyng the truth before you: neuertheles, the mightie lorde of powers, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely God of Iſrael, hath now remembred his promyſes, and accordyng to hys oulde wonte hath he loked mercyfully vpon vs, for his names ſake, yea, he hath now herd thy mornyngs O Iſrael, &amp; he is come downe to delyuer Iacob his choſen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a myghtie hand, &amp; a ſtretched out arme.<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> But as S. Paul ſaith. I ſpeake not theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10202:17"/>
ceyued not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of the truth, ſaith he, God ſhall ſende them ſtrong deluſion, that they ſhuld beleue lyes, that all they might be dampned (ſaith he) which be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue not the truth but had plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure in vnrighteouſenes. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles, god hath now re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membred Iſrael his electe, for he wyll alway haue compaſſion vpon Iacob his choſen: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is he now mynded to ſhew mercy, and to delyuer his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for our Lordes Ielouſſy is waxen greate, to ſee hys truth dayely thus traiterouſely tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder foote of hys enemy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and cleane defaced vnder a coloure of truthe, and wyth a counterfaicte dyſguiſed holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and outwarde pretence of vertue, whereby the ſymple ig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noraunte
<pb facs="tcp:10202:17"/>
ſynners be diſceiued, for bycauſe the pathes of chriſt be ſo troden out, many can find nothyng of the way. Thus the myſterie of iniquitie, as Paul ſaith, workth in his place, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by the ſynfull man is opened, and the ſonne of perdition, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is an aduerſarie, is exalted aboue all that is called God, or of God, for the vaine glorie of man apereth on earth to haue the vpper hande.<note place="margin">In earthe worldly wiſedome hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the chayre, or vpper ſeat</note> Is not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, or carnal reaſon and world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly wyſedome, moſt hyghlieſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed? Who amongeſte men knoweth anye thynge lyke, or that may be compared vnto it? Where is the wiſdome of God become? Is it not vtterly diſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed of the blynde worlde, and ſet at naughte, and not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
<pb facs="tcp:10202:18"/>
When ye ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abhomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Apoca. <hi>12.</hi> Eſay. <hi>14.</hi> Daniel. <hi>9</hi> Mat. <hi>24,</hi> Mat. <hi>13.</hi> The man of ſinne is exalted, he ſitteth in the eſtima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of men. wheare god ought to ſyt for chief. <hi>2.</hi> Theſſ. <hi>2</hi> Eſay. <hi>11.</hi> Daniel. <hi>8.</hi> God figh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth alwai againſt the man of ſynne to ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e and to ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>due hym. <hi>1.</hi> Corr. <hi>1,</hi> Eſa. <hi>18.37 4.</hi> Reg. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> that betokeneth deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſpoken of, by Danyel the Prophete (ſaith Chriſt) ſtande in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy place, or (as S. Mark ſaith) where it ought not: Let hym that readethe it, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande it. Thus is fleſſhe and bloude, that is to ſaye, the man of ſynne, exalted, extolled, and prayſed, whiche ſheweth hym ſelfe as god, and as thoughe ther were no power aboue him And ſytteth in the holy temple whom the lorde neuettheleſſe ſhall conſume with the ſpiryte and breath of hys mouth. And wythe the apparaunce of hys comynge, euen hym ſaith Paul whoſe comynge that is exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge, or ſettynge vp, is ſaithe he, by the workyng of Sathan
<pb facs="tcp:10202:18"/>
withe all lyinge power, ſignes, and wonders, &amp; in all deceiuea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blenes of vnrighteouſenes &amp;c.</p>
            <p>¶Neuertheles, our god hath taken part againſte fleſſhe and bloud, becauſe it is become his verie enemy, and he hath ſaid. I wyl deſtroy the wiſedome of the wyſe, and caſte awaye the vnderſtandyng of the prudent that no fleſſhe ſhould reioice in hys preſence, for the lorde ſhall ſtep fourth, as he dyd vpon the mounte Pirazim, ſaith Eſaye, and ſhall take on, as he dyd in the dale of Gibion, that he may brynge fourth his deuice, yea, hys ſtronge deuyce, and fulfyll hys worke / therfore make no mockes at it, ſaithe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete, that your captiuytie or blyndenes increaſe not, for I
<pb facs="tcp:10202:19"/>
haue hearde the lord of hoſtes ſay, that there ſhall fall a ſoden diſtruction, and plage, vpon the hole earth (ſaith Eſay) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, take heade, and heare my voice, ponder and marke mye wordes well,<note place="margin">Iere. <hi>13.</hi> c</note> for the lorde ſhall fight againſt all them that mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter them ſelues agaynſte the hyll of Sion,<note place="margin">The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then are ſuche as do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue.</note> ſaith the prophet. And with his myghtie two ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſworde, ſhall he ſmyte the Heathen, they ſhall be at theyr wittes ende, they ſhall be abaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, ſtacker and reele to and froo &amp;c.</p>
            <p>¶Therefore, thus ſaithe the lorde, againſt all them that call them ſelues of the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of god, and yet are not (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they lyue vngodly,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> and are the bond ſeruauntes of ſyn
<pb facs="tcp:10202:19"/>
ye ſhalbe dronken, but not with wine, ye ſhal fal, but not thorow dronkennes, for the Lorde ſhal geue you an harde ſlepyng ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite / and hold doune your eyes namely of your prophetes and heades which ſhoulde ſee, them ſhall he couer, ſo that al viſions ſhalbe vnto you, as the wordes that ſtand in a ſealed lettre &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For, thus ſaith the lorde, for ſo muche as, theſe people draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie me wyth their mouthes, &amp; praiſe me holly with their lyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes (where as their hartes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles be far from me) and the feare that they owe vnto me,<note place="margin">Abdi. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that turne they vnto mens lawes and doctrines: therfore, wyll I ſhew vnto this people, a maruelouſe terryble, &amp; great thing (ſaith the lorde) namelye
<pb facs="tcp:10202:20"/>
this, I wyll deſtroy: the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the wiſe, and the vnder ſtandynge of the learned men ſhal peryſh. Therfore wo be to them that ſeke ſo depe to hyde their ymaginations before the lorde, which reherſe their coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſels in the darknes, &amp; ſay, tuſh, who ſeeth vs,<note place="margin">The chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of god in name, but not in deade, muſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe,</note> or who knoweth vs. Therfore, muſt Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Iuda decay ſaith the lorde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their words &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels are againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde, they prouoke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of his maieſtye vnto anger y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> changyng of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrateth them,<note place="margin">Eſay. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> yea they declare their owne ſynnes theym ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues as the Sodomites, and hide them not. Woo be to their ſoules, for they ſhalbe heauely rewarded, ſaieth the lord, then
<pb facs="tcp:10202:20"/>
ſhall they ſay, O happie are the godly, for they may enioye the frutes of their ſtudies, but wo be vnto the vngodlye and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſe, for they ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded after their workes. O my people, rybauldes oppreſſe thee, and women haue rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thee: O my people thy lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders deceiue thee (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord) and treade out the way of thy fote ſteppes. The lorde is here to common of the matter, ſaith Eſai, and ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to giue iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment with the people, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord ſhall come forth to reaſon with the princes &amp; Senatours, and ſhall ſay thus vnto them, ſaieth Eſay. It is ye that haue bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp my vyneyarde, and the robberye of the poore in youre houſe, wherfore do ye oppreſſe
<pb facs="tcp:10202:21"/>
my people, and marre the faces of the innocentes? And thus ſayeth the prophete, ſhal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord of hoſtes reuile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therefore.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Wo be to thoſe proude boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng ſpirites, which liuing wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedlye, teache their flockes by poure and penaltie, and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by enſamples of vertue &amp; godly lyuyng.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Wo be to thoſe, whoſe hertes are double, whiche with theyr mouthes boaſt proude thinges and flatteryng vertue, theyr wrathe is as the angry Lyon, or as the ſhee beare robbed of her whelpes, whiche euery oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion kendleth, as fire the drie flaxe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Wo be to thoſe falſe prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes whiche vnder the name of gouernours and teachers, doo
<pb facs="tcp:10202:21"/>
the deades of falſe deceyuers, ſeruyng their owne luſtes, and yet ſaye, do as we byd you, and all is forgeuen.</p>
            <p>Wo be to thoſe Ipocrites, &amp; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> wanderyng ſtarres, to whome the myſte of darkenes is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for euer, whiche couloura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly for the bealy, and for lucres ſake, pray for other, and yet nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther forſake ſinne, nor amende their owne lyues.</p>
            <p>Woo be to thoſe deceytefull <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> meſſengers of Sathan, whoſe hertes are exercyſed with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes, hauyng eyes full of adultrye that can not ceaſe to ſynne. And although they goe wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them ſelfes, yet they ſay, thei be ſent of god, to teach and leade other the right way.</p>
            <p>Wo be to thoſe paynted to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:10202:22"/>
and ſtinking ſepulchres ful of all filth and corrupcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which oftentimes ſpake of faythe, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and loue, and yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume the tyme of their lyues in vani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie and idlenes, keepyng theyr belyes from hungre, and theyr throtes from thryſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Wo be to thoſe murtherers of the ſoules of men, which tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough flatterye ſowe pelows,<note place="margin">Ezeche. <hi>13</hi> Eſay. <hi>5.</hi> Miche. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> as the prophete ſayeth, vnder the armeholes of the people, to to the entent they may bryng theim a ſlepe in blindneſſe and ſinne, that they myght ſuſpecte none of their doynges.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Wo be to thoſe blynde guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and moſt wicked generaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by whoſe careleſſe lyuynge, true repentaunce is almoſt ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed and thruſt out of place,
<pb facs="tcp:10202:22"/>
and amendment of lyfe is lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed to ſkorne and not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>Wo be to thoſe filthye ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>/ which haue thus forſaken the right way / &amp; count it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to liue deliciouſly for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whiche as ragyng waues of the Sea / foome oute theyr filthynes and ſhame.</p>
            <p>Woo be to thoſe ſerpentes &amp; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> adders broodes,<note place="margin">Vene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and poyſon is falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and enſamples of naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie liuyng.</note> whiche moſte greuouſly corrupt the inhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the earth with their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem and deadly poyſon, and to mainteyn ambition / pryde / co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſenes, voluptuous and beaſtly liuyng / peruert al thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, and prepoſterouſly tourne it out of frame.</p>
            <p>Wo be to the vngodlye / the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> beaſt &amp; all his warriers, which
<pb facs="tcp:10202:23"/>
maliciouſly do euyll, and fighte continually againſt the lord of powers and all his true ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Woo be to thoſe biſhops, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours / and lawiers / of what name and place ſo euer they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiche boaſt of power and auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie to rule and gouerne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / and yet haue no reſpecte to their owne ſoules: For heui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and miſerably ſhal thei be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded that beare the name of chriſten people, whiche ſeke ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes onely by outward ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and ſignes, not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng what the hert &amp; inwarde conſcience bee / and alſo ſaye in your ſelfes, tuſhe we be well i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the holy lawes, cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies / and Sacramentes of god, are remaining among vs,
<pb facs="tcp:10202:23"/>
and thereby we are knowen to be his people. Neuertheles be thou of good cumfort,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> O thou litle worm Iacob, and thou deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyſed Iſraell, for thy redemer liueth: feare neyther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proude boaſtyng nor threatenynge of thyne ennemies, for the Lorde ſtandeth by thee to defend and deliuer thee,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> for the mightye god of hoſtes wyll now take in hand to conquere the re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>naunt of his people, whiche are left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, from the Aſſirians, Egip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, Arabians, Morians, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamites, Caldees, Antiochia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and Ilandes of the ſea: for the the earth ſhalbe full of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord (ſayth Eſay) Euen as though the water of the ſea flowed ouer the earth:<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>11.</hi> Abac. <hi>2.6.</hi>
               </note> And then ſhall the Gentyles
<pb facs="tcp:10202:24"/>
whiche are vnbeleuers, knowe that our God hath mercifully heard the lamentable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint of the poore oppreſſed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred his couenaunt made with Abraham,<note place="margin">Exody. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Iſaac, and Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob his chooſen. Therefore the Lord commaundeth you to let his people go, ye Heathen naci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ennemies of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, that we may ſacrifice vnto the Lord our god, for the lorde hath now ſeene the heauy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, wherewith ye dailye op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his people, and therefore is he come to deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a mightie hand, and a ſtretched out arme,<note place="margin">Eſai, <hi>11.</hi> Nylus, ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifieth the See of tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie</note> ye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſhal cleaue the tong of the Egipcians. Se ſaith Eſay, and with a mightie wynde ſhall he lyft vp his hand ouer Nylus, and he ſhall ſmyte
<pb facs="tcp:10202:24"/>
his ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtreames, &amp; make men go ouer dry ſhod, and thus ſhal he make a way for his people y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remaineth from the Aſſirians lyke as it happened to the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, what tyme they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted oute of Egipte &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But if you wyll not let hys people goo (O yee enemyes of righteouſenes) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they maye ſerue hym, after his wyll, then wyll he poure hys plages vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, as he did vpon Egipte, and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other nations, among whom he ſcatered hys people for their offences: to the intent they myght teache you righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſenes, that ye myght repent and turne from your euyll wai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, and lerne to know the name of the lorde, which is greate in Iſrael, and myghtie in Sion:
<pb facs="tcp:10202:25"/>
for as touchyng Iſrael and Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>da (thus ſaith the Lorde) they ſhall not be forſaken of their God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 51.50</note> of the Lorde of hooſtes, of the holy one of Iſrael, noo thoughe theye haue fylled all their lande full of ſynne &amp;c. For I wyl not conſume the, but cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſteine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, and correcte the, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with deſcretion, ſaith the lord neither wyl I ſpare the as one that were faultleſſe, for thus ſaith the lorde: O Iacob and Iſrael,<note place="margin">Iere. <hi>46.</hi> and <hi>30.</hi> Eſai. <hi>44.</hi> &amp; <hi>43.</hi> d</note> thou art my ſeruaunte, I haue made the, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſerue me. O Iſrael forgete me not (ſaith the Lorde) as for thyne offences, I driue them a waye lyke the cloudes, and thy ſynnes as the myſte: tourne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> againe vnto me, and I wyl de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer the, ſaith the lorde. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore,
<pb facs="tcp:10202:25"/>
tourne againe O thou diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſed people vnto the lorde, for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſake thy ſyns, leaue thyne own wylful waies, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liuered in the landes of thy cap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyuitie, and be taken as a ſpoile from, and oute of the mouthe of the deuourer, whiche ſeketh to fyll hym alwaye of the. Cry to god from the very herte, to delyuer the from the violente hande of thyne oppreſſer, pour downe thy teares daily before hym, and ſay,<note place="margin">A prayer</note> O euerlaſtynge god and my father, I beſeche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remembre the poore oppreſſed, deale fauourablye with vs, for thyne owne ſake, for thou arte our onely ſurgion. Shew mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy vpon vs O father, for Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake, ſhew mercy vpon vs, the worke of thyne owne han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.
<pb facs="tcp:10202:26"/>
Haue compaſſion vpon thy people, O lorde, that greuouſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly haue ſynned againſt the, for by reaſon of our ſynnes, haue we longe tyme bene thus exy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and kepte from the: and the enemye hath ſore preuayled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs. O be thou mercyfull and take awaye our ſynnes, &amp; let our iniquities no more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe the. O Lorde forget not thyne owne accuſtomed mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes. Is our hurt ſo great that it may no more be heled? Turn our hertes vnto the, that wee maye ſeke thy wyll, praiſe thy name, and walke in thy waies. O lorde, wee knowe that thou only art our god, whoſe nature and propertie is, to ſhewe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, yea, and that thou art alwai readye (O lorde) but oure ſyn
<pb facs="tcp:10202:26"/>
lyeth heauye vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, &amp; preſſeth vs ſore down, quicken vs with thy holy ſpirite (O lorde) and lyft vs vp, we beſeche the with thy holy hande, and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs dayly with thine arme, that we may praiſe the with ioyfull lyppes, and magnifie the, O e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall God, oure onely ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, father, Sonne and holye ghoſte. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Refuſe not thou thy helth, O thou Englyſſhe nation, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng god hath loued the aboue many other, and hath ſent hys worde, the ſonne of god, the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry true patrone and ymage of hys moſte godly ſubſtaunce, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the too call the frome thyne own waies that thou mighteſt be made his owne people, too ſerue hym accordynge to his
<pb facs="tcp:10202:27"/>
wyll, with reuerence and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare.<note place="margin">Apoca. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Say not in thyne hert I am ryche and encreaſed with goodes, and haue neade of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge, leaſt thou be reproued: but anointe thyne eyes with eye ſalue (ſaithe the veritie of God) that thou maiſte ſee, and know how thou art wretched, poore, blynd, and naked. I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell the, ſaith Chriſte, bie of me golde tryed in the fyre, that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> maiſt be ryche, and white ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, that thou maiſt be cloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, that thy filthy nakednes do not apeare &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Therfore, althoughe thou haſte gotten a name that thou liueſt, let it not diſceiue the: but obey to the word of god, turne frome youre Ignorance, and knowledge your ſynnes, caſte
<pb facs="tcp:10202:27"/>
youre ſelues downe,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that the lord may lyft you vp and ſhew mercy vpon you: for he caſteth downe the proud, and exalteth the lowly. If ye thynke youre ſelues heyres with Chriſt and gods chyldren: where is youre loue and readye obedience, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde his will? Where is the victorie which ye haue gotten againſt your fleſſhe, ſynne and the deuyll: the extreame enemi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of vertue and godlynes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the tyme of your profeſſion and baptiſme, ye pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſed manfully to fighte, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge the tyme of your lyues: and to renounce and vtterlye forſake Sathan, &amp; all his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. Boaſt not of the name one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly (O ye chriſtened natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) but ſhew your deades, for that it is
<pb facs="tcp:10202:28"/>
that muſt teſtify with you. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre therfore, from whence thou art fallen, O thou blynde and ignoraunte people, tourne to the lorde that thou maiſt be healed, knowledge thye ſynne which is greate, then ſhall it be forgeuen the. How longe write thou mocke with thy god, and beare a double hert, that goeth two waies: ye pretende in face to haue a greate zeale, and too be very feruent in the waye of the lorde, but youre hertes run after your couetouſe lucre, and daily ye walke in youre owne waies &amp; lyue after your owne luſtes, and yet ye ſay, tuſſhe we be well inou<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>he. When wilte thou leaue of O thou wilful na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion and why wyll ye thus pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe thorow your owne folly.
<pb facs="tcp:10202:28"/>
Truly excepte ye doo repente, and tourn from your euyl wai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es (what name of holynes ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ye haue) ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be made the ſonnes or Children of god, becauſe ye haue refuſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of life, nor yet receiue any inhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritance in his euerlaſting king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome:<note place="margin">Ezec. <hi>44.</hi>
               </note> for this ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord our mercifull god, of all the ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that dwell among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael. No ſtraunger, whoſe herte and fleſſhe is not circumcyſed, ſhall come with in my ſainctuary. Therfore, dear lye beloued and longed for, at my herte, I pray you, cut away your carnall deſires and fighte againſt your fleſhly luſtes, too ſubdu them: that ye dwel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſainctuarye and receiue enheritaunce amonge ſonnes,
<pb facs="tcp:10202:29"/>
and daughtours.<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Againe, this ſaith the lord, waſhe you, make you cleane, put away your euil thoughts out of my ſight, ceaſe from doyng euill and violence, learne to do right, apply your ſelues to equitie, deliuer the op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſed, helpe the fatherles to hys right, let the widowes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint come before you &amp;c. And is it not ſo then ſaith the lorde, though your ſinnes, be as red as ſcarlet, ſhal they not be whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ſnowe. And thoughe they were like purple, ſhal they not be like white wol? Is it ſo? If you belouinge and obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, ye ſhall enioy the beſt thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that growe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land, but if ye be obſtinate and rebelliouſe ye ſhall be deuoured with the ſwerde,<note place="margin">Leuiti. <hi>26</hi>
               </note> for thus the lorde hath
<pb facs="tcp:10202:29"/>
promiſed with his own mouth O ye named chriſtians, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme paſte, preſent &amp; to come loke your owne waies, &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no longer aſtray, refuſe not the lighte of the gloriouſe goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of God, for it is the lyfe of your ſoules. Remembre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> long time of your captiuitie, whiche doubtles happened for your of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fences: ſurely it paſſeth far the bondage and captiuitie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brues, or children of Iſrael in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies of Helyas, Helizeus, &amp; Ieremie, and other prophetes, Ioſias, Ezechias, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinges of Iſrael &amp; Iuda, in whoſe tyme the people with their princes and prieſtes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoke the law of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde, &amp; went a whoringe after ſtraunge god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, &amp; becauſe of their ſins, god
<pb facs="tcp:10202:30"/>
gaue them vp to their own lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, and let them folowe their blynde Imagination, yet was not their fal lyke vnto thine, O Chriſtianitie nor their hurt to be compared w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thine: for thou haſte not onely exceaded in thy fall, but much more in the long tyme of thy myſerable captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and although thou be day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called, yet haſt thou no mind to riſe &amp; come to be made hole: ye hold the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god (as they did) but few do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deedes: ye hold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacramentes ſignes,<note place="margin">The ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes be kepte, but the vertue is gone.</note> and cerimonies appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in the churche of God (as they ſaye) but ye haue loſte the ſtrengthe and vertue of them. For not with ſtandynge, youre daily miniſtration, both youre ſelues and the people, to whom
<pb facs="tcp:10202:30"/>
ye miniſter, yea,<note place="margin">Much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour loſte.</note> bothe ye and they abide ſtyll in youre owne luſtes, which declare playnely that your ſynnes be nother for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geuen, nor taken awaye. Is it not becauſe ye are wicked, that your praiers be not hearde, as perfecte and holye mens haue bene before tyme? For wheare they praied and layde on theyr handes,<note place="margin">Actes. <hi>8</hi>
               </note> god affirmed their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, with his holy ſpirite: ſoo that they receyued knowledge and their vnderſtanſtyng was opened, and their mindes were obediente to the wyll of God. If the doinges of the Apoſtles had bene ſo vncerteine that no thynge thereof hadde appered outewardelye, ſaue onely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, all remayninge as before euery man in his owne waies:
<pb facs="tcp:10202:31"/>
thinke ye they ſhould haue ben ſo well beloued, or if Chriſte at the mariage in Cana of Galile,<note place="margin">Ihon. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> had ſente the gouernoure of the feaſt, water to gyue his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, in the ſteade of wyne (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe he had tolde theym it had bene good wine) and that they muſt vnder paine of damp nation ſo haue beleued, thynke ye it wolde haue beene ſo well accepted at hys hande? Where Chriſte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophetes, or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, or any other in his name, and by his power and ſpirite, did anye miracle, wheather it were outwarde or inwarde, in healynge of the body,<note place="margin">
                  <p>The my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of Chriſt and his apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, were not onely in face and wordes, but were done in ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie: the ſignes be kepte, but the power is gone.</p>
                  <p>The ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly are abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before the lorde. Gene. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> or ſoule: the thynge after appeered, ſoo to be, and it ſhewed it ſelfe that it was doone, as theye ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:10202:31"/>
they ſet neuer the people to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue and woonder at thynges wherof thei heard, felt nor ſaw nothing, ſaue only an outward token or ſigne. But your doyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are vncertayn, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to your ſelues, but much more to other yet would ye haue al men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to beleue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: thus haue your ſinnes (ye your wilful ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) long turned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyes of the Lorde from you, and made all your doynges as the ſacryfice of Cayn. For ye haue forſaken the Lorde, the onelye well and fountaine of lyfe, and haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and dygged you broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that hold no water. In eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſtrete &amp; place, haue ye burnt ſwete odoures, and offered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens before your Idolles, and haue choſen you Goddes after
<pb facs="tcp:10202:32"/>
your owne imaginacion,<note place="margin">Iere. <hi>7.</hi> a.</note> and ſerued theym after youre wyll: yea, as the Iewes and Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nacions, haue ye inuented and ſet vp brothell howſes, to offre in ſacrifice to your Idolles, the vncleane luſtes of your bodyes for many ordinances contrary to the word of God, haue ye ſet vp, whiche may neyther bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted nor ſpoken againſte, but muſt be continewed as thinges lawdable (as ye ſay) &amp; for good purpoſes. Haue ye not alſo as they,<note place="margin">Iere. <hi>32.</hi> ſ.</note> geuen your ſeede to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loch? and burnt your chyldren before Idolles, in that ye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure by power, brybes or flatte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye, or by any other vngodlye meanes, to make theim myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, or common officers, more regardyng the vayne glorye of
<pb facs="tcp:10202:32"/>
thoffice, the dignitie, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly profit of the ſame, then either the health of the ſoules of your ſelues (of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) or of the people, whoſe teachers, leaders, &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours ye make them, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth, or the glory and ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour of god. Thus haue ye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſely forſaken the Lord, for ye are ſick, and your mouthes out of taſte, and therefore ſo that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery rome and place bee fylled, ye thinke it is well, although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſones that be in them haue ſcarce any one poynt of vertue requiſite and nedefull to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and place they be in. Thus haue you ſet &amp; appoynted ſuch to be meanes betwene god and you, and to pray for you, as be voyde of all honeſt poyntes of vertue, whoſe doynges ar hate<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full,
<pb facs="tcp:10202:33"/>
and their prayer execrable and before god an abominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Thus is that wooful plage and great miſerie happened vnto you for your offences, thretned of god by Eſay,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>3.</hi> The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che vpon earth. Sapien. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> who ſayth. The lord of hoſtes ſhall take awaye from Ieruſalem and Iuda, all poſſeſſions and power, al meate and drinke, the captain and the ſouldyer, the iudge and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete, the wyſe &amp; the aged man the worſhipfull of fyftye yeres olde, and the honourable, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>natours and men of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng, the maiſters of craftes &amp; oratours. And I will geue you childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be your princes, ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, &amp; babes ſhall haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of you, one ſhalbe doing viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to an other, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boy ſhall preſume againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elder, and the
<pb facs="tcp:10202:33"/>
vile perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honorable,<note place="margin">What an elder is by the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, loke Sapience <hi>4.</hi> chapter</note> for both Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Iuda muſt decay, becauſe both their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels ar againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, and thei prouoke the preſens of his maieſtie to angre. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And yet neuertheles they ſay tuſhe / we be ſafe, for we bee all chriſtians: we haue gods word and his holye Sacramentes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, and therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great plagues and threatenynges of god (declared by his prophetes and Apoſtles) againſte ſinners, ſhall not touche vs, nor come nigh our dwellyng, &amp; although thou liue more wickedlye then they (O named Chriſtianitie) yet ſaieſt thou, it is ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Iewes, Turkes, Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins and heretikes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diſpiſe our holy religion, and reproue our
<pb facs="tcp:10202:34"/>
dooynges / it is they that ſhall peryſhe (ſaieſt thou) for thei are worthye, but we bee ſafe for we ar gods people. Thinkeſt thou that they ſhalbe preſerued and defended of God that continue and delite in ſtune and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? Or thinke ye to eſcape the puniſhmente of god due to ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, with a face or outewarde apparance of holines? The ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth therof is away then art thou clearely deceiued for as it is right with god to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward the iuſte for well doyng, ſo is it alſo to puniſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked for euill dooynges. God is all good, and no euil may come me hym: and although his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes be vnſearcheable, yet be they al righteouſe and true. He is no reſpecter of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion
<pb facs="tcp:10202:34"/>
/ lande / tyme nor place: but loke who doeth right, hym wil he accept: and he that do the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, hym wyl he puniſh, of what religion, tong, or nacion ſo euer he be: For God is determyned (as he hath plainly declared in his worde) to gather together and choſe out his elect from the foure wyndes, from and out of al nacions vnder heauen: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deceyue not youre ſelues with a name but bryng foorthe the frutes of righteouſnes: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke your old wayes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger in vanitie, but as S. Paul ſaith.<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Let it ſuffiſe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs, that we haue ſpente the tyme of our lyfe paſt in vanitie, as in eatyng, drinkyng, chaum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bryng and wantonnes, and lay from you that olde man which
<pb facs="tcp:10202:35"/>
marreth hymſelf in deceyuable luſtes, and be ye renued, ſayeth he, in the ſpirite of your vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng: obey to the voyce of god, do iuſtice and equitie, hate the euill, &amp; choſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good, ſo ſhal ye lyue for euer, for thei that do theſe thynges are born of god, and are made the belouing ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the higheſt, of what rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, tong or nacion ſoeuer thei be. Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion is nothyng, nor vncircumciſion, ſaith Paul, but the kepyng of the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of god (ſaith he) is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: circumciſion verily auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, ſaith he, if thou kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, but yf thou tranſgreſſe, then is thy circumciſion made vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion. What auayleth then a chriſten name, or baptiſyng and receiuyng of Sacramentes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:10202:35"/>
it be neuer ſo many, yf there folowe not amendement of life / but that the herte delite in euyll as before. Haue ye not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made your baptiſme, which ſignifieth repentaunce, the new regeneracion and amendment of lyfe, toward your helth,<note place="margin">An vntrue profeſſer of Chriſte, is worſe then an infideele.</note> of no value? But it is rather an open witneſſe againſt you, that ye ar falſe diſſembling chriſtians and ſuche as haue mocked god, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendyng one thyng in face / but the contrary in your hertes:<note place="margin">Ezechi. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> yf an infidell turne in his hert fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his infidelitie, and do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge that is equall &amp; right, although he neuer receiue chriſten name nor outward ſacrament, thinke ye that he ſhal not be ſaued? It is the circumciſion and bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of the hert, in that we are
<pb facs="tcp:10202:36"/>
waſhed from an euill conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,<note place="margin">Peter. <hi>3d</hi> Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the fore ſkyn of the hert ſaithe the lorde, and be no mor ſtiffe nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. Deutr. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> and the luſtes of the fleſhe daily foughten againſt by the power of the ſpirite, that is of value be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore god, whoſe prayſe is not of men but of god. The outward face of religion and holines on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excepted: what haue ye to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyce in, aboue other Hethen nacions? So long as ye conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in euill, is there anye kynd of ſinne and wickednes done in any heathen nacion vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that is not in the, thou na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med chriſtianitie? What kind of pryde, vainglory, hipocriſie, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulacion, hatred, malice or en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uye, is there in any other nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that may not be found in thee? Or what kynde of dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, theft, murther, whordom or le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherye, may there be found out
<pb facs="tcp:10202:36"/>
or imagined, of fleſhe and blud / that is not daily done, and moſt ſhamefully committed in thee: although ye compare your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in wiſdom and knowledge to Dauid or Salomon, and yet liue wickedly, &amp; wil not amend when ye are warned: thinke ye to eſcape vnpunyſhed? Nay, ye ſhall ſurely peryſh as other like ſinners haue done beefore you, and drynke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: for thinke ye to eſcape with extollyng of Chriſtes holy religion in name or wordes only, or with ſetting vp of ſacramentes and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, although ye extol them to the cloudes, if ye regard not to leaue ſynne nor to do that they teache you? How can they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit you any thyng at all, for god regardeth not your flatteryng
<pb facs="tcp:10202:37"/>
titles and wordes of holynes (neirher youre ſwete ſonges &amp; pleaſaunt armonie, ſwete ſmel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les,<note place="margin">Deades be acepted for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes ſake that doth them, and not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man for the goodnes of the dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des.</note> nor gloriouſe ſightes: but he loketh vnto the herte, and ſercheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raines, ye, his iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes be, and ſhall be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to equitie, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward thoughtes of the herte, &amp; not after the outward apperance. For the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the herte, the lorde refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the offeringes and ſacrifice of the children of Iſrael, which he hym ſelfe had befoore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded,<note place="margin">Ierem. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> ſaying vnto hym by his prophete Ieremye, ye hepe vp your burnt offeringes with youre ſacrifices,<note place="margin">Deutro, <hi>10</hi> Eſai. <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> and eate the fleſſhe (as though I delyted in youre doynges) but when I brought your fathers out of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipte,
<pb facs="tcp:10202:37"/>
I ſpake no worde vntoo them of burnte offeringes and ſacrifices: but this I commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaying. Herken and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey my voice, &amp; I wyll be your god / &amp; ye ſhall be my people. Al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>though they brought nothyng but that they were commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: yet God vtterly refuſed it at their handes, becauſe they thought to pleaſe him with the worke, &amp; intended not to leaue their ſyns, nor to forſake their owne euill and croked waies. Thinke ye that god wyl accept yours, which are not all groun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded vpon the worde, but partly inuented and ſet vp by natural wiſedom, and carnall reaſon, ye altered and chaunged among your ſelues at youre pleaſure. Or wil ye thinke that god hath
<pb facs="tcp:10202:38"/>
ſuche nede of you,<note place="margin">The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente to be bounde to all that man can ymagyn, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myght haue ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to ſynne, and abyde ſtyl in their owne lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes: the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des that profeſſe Chriſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the faith, and miniſter ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramentes &amp; ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, diuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſlye. Eſai. <hi>1.</hi> b</note> that he wyll accepte you, eyther for youre wiſedome or workes ſake: or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath more loue and fauoure to you, then he had to the Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: in whoſe generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he both made and fulfylled, his many-folde promyſes? yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, when they ſynned againſt hym, he ſaide vnto them by E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay. Heare the word of the lord ye tirauntes of Sodoma, and herke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the law of our god, thou people of Gomorra. Why offer ye ſo many ſacrifices vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, ſaith the lorde? I am diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented for the burnte offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes of wydowes, ſaith he, &amp; with the fatnes of fed beaſtes, I haue no pleſure in the bloud of Bullockes, lambes and goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, when ye appere before me.
<pb facs="tcp:10202:38"/>
who requireth you to tread w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in my porches?<note place="margin">Iere. <hi>6.</hi> Amos. <hi>5.</hi> Mich. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Offer me noo more oblations for it is but loſt laboure (ſaith the lorde) I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre your incence, I maye not awaye with your new incence, youre Sabaothes &amp; ſolempne dayes: your faſtinges are alſo in vayne.<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>58.</hi>
               </note> I hate your new ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye dayes and faſtinges,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> euen from my verie herte, ſaith the lorde &amp;c. If theſe (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge, their offeringes and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfices, holy daies, praiers, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynges, and ſuche lyke obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunces) could not be accepted at the hande of God, becauſe their hertes delyted in ſinne, lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> to be accepted,<note place="margin">God alou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deades of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be euyll.</note> and ſo to eſcape vnpuniſhed, O named Chriſtianitie? Nether except y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> amende and tourne from thine
<pb facs="tcp:10202:39"/>
owne waies, thou ſhalte not eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cape: but ſurely ſhalte thou pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſhe, as they. Wherefore, thus ſaith the lord alſo vnto you. O wicked chriſtians, which conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually delyte in ſynne, heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of the lorde, ye tyrantes of Sodoma, and herken to the lawe of oure god, thou people of Gomorra,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>1.</hi> c</note> whi offer ye ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſacrifices vnto me &amp;c. Lerne obedience in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> landes of youre captiuytie, waſſhe you &amp; make you cleane, put awaye youre e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll thoughtes out of my ſight (ſaith the lorde) ceaſe from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of euyl and violence, lerne to do right, apply youre ſelues to equitie, delyuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oppreſſed, helpe the fatherles to his right and let the widows complaint come before you &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10202:39"/>Prefer the wyll of God aboue and before all thinges, I ſaye, and let that which pleſeth hym be good and beſte, how ſo euer it ſounde or appeere vnto you. Hath there euer anye yet that ſtroue againſt God, and taken in hande to teache hym righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſenes and iudgemente, or to alter or chaunge hys wayes, ſince the beginning,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Pete. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> eſcaped vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>puniſſhed? If y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe thynges may not be ſuffred in Aungell, moche les in fleſhe and bloude, whiche is corrupte, whoſe beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fadeth as a flower, and wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth awaie as hey or graſſe. O thou folyſſhe duſte &amp; aſſhes, dareſt thou preſume againſte thy creator &amp; lord,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>40. 1</hi> Peter. <hi>1.</hi> Pſal. <hi>89.</hi>
               </note> &amp; to reaſon with hym of Iudgemente and righteouſenes? O thou proude
<pb facs="tcp:10202:40"/>
Lucifer,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>14.</hi> Apoca. <hi>12</hi> Carnall wiſedome ſeketh all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to exalte it ſelfe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nſte. god.</note> thou ſaiſt in thy herte: I wyll clyme vp into heauen, &amp; make my ſeate aboue the ſterre of god. I wyll ſyt vpon the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riouſe mount toward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> north: I wyl clyme vp aboue the clou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, and wyll be lyke the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all: yet dare I ſay (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde) thou ſhalt be broughte downe, to the depth of hell &amp;c. your wiſedome canne not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle againſt god and therfore ſhall your glorie haue a greate fall,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>29. 1</hi> Corin. <hi>1. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1.</hi> Eſai. <hi>27.</hi> The lord ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in man, of deſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he and bloud <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> for thus ſaith the lorde. I wyll deſtroy the wiſedome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſe, and caſte away the vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandynge of the prudent: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord with his heauy great long ſwerde, ſhall viſite Leuiathan that vnuiſyble ſerpente (ſaithe Eſai, and ſhall flee the Whale fyſſhe in the See &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10202:40"/>Againe, S. Paul ſaith, where are the wiſe? Where are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes? Where are the diſputers of this worlde, hathe not God made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſedom of this world folyſhnes? For the folyſhnes of god, ſaith he, is wyſer then me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the weakenes of God, is ſtronger then men &amp;c. For god hath choſen the folyſſhe before the worlde, that he myght con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founde the wiſe, and the weake before the world hath god cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, ſaith Paul, that he myghte confounde the mightie, and the vile and diſpiſed befor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world hath god choſen, yea, and that whiche is nothinge ſaythe he,<note place="margin">Nothing of fleſſhe &amp; bloud ſhall reioyce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore god.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he myght deſtroy that whiche is ought, that no fleſſhe ſhould reioyce in his preſence &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Therefore, doo not iuſtifie
<pb facs="tcp:10202:41"/>
your ſelues as phariſees, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exalt any thyng in fleſhe &amp; blud, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinges whiche men highly magnifie,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, be abhomynable in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of god. Lay away your hygh reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; let gods word although it ſeme ſimple &amp; rude, lede you, ſeke not to ioin your wiſdom w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god, leſt in couetyng to clyme ſo high, ye take a gret fall, obedience is an acceptable offering. Therefore, put ſalt on your ſacrifice, that it may be wel accepted at your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des,<note place="margin">Iere. <hi>7.</hi> Exodi. <hi>22.</hi> zacri. <hi>8.</hi> Leuiti. <hi>10</hi>
               </note> for thus hath the lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed with his own mouth. &amp;c. If ye wicked amende your wai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es &amp; counſels, yf ye wyll iudge right betwixte a man and hys neighboure, if ye wyll not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the ſtrannger, the father<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe and the wydow. If ye will
<pb facs="tcp:10202:41"/>
not ſhede inocent bloud in this place: If ye wyll not cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too ſtraunge goddes to youre owne diſtruction, then wyll I let you dwell in thys place for euer &amp;c. If ye bee louynge and righteouſe ye ſhall enioy of the beaſte thynges that dwelle in the lande, ſaith the lorde,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> but if ye be obſtinate and rebellyous ye ſhall be deuoured wyth the ſwearde. Wherefore,<note place="margin">The pols or water of Siloah ſignifyeth repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, or rather y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lauer of regenerati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on. Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>9</hi> Eye ſalue is inward knouledge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth.</note> conuerte and tourne with your hole her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, from your euyll waies, O ye named Chriſtians: waſhe ye vii. tymes in Siloah, that yee maye be clenſed from youre of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences: anointe your eies w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eie ſalue, that ye may ſee: walke in the ſteppes of Chriſt, whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion thou haſte profeſſed, and whoſe name thou ſo well loueſt
<pb facs="tcp:10202:42"/>
O thou Chriſtianitie, brynge forth worthy fruictes of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, as ſobrenes and amend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of lyfe, that the thicke ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les may fall from youre eyes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may ſee the perfecte way of lyfe. For except ye vtterlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce and forſake, at the leaſt in affection, all that is in you of fleſſhe and bloud, yea and your owne lyues whiche ye loue ſoo well, ye can not ſee the glorie of god nether be partakers of his eternall kyngdome. Therefore as Chriſte ſaith, enter in at the ſtrait gate,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> and walke in thys narrow waye, for although the pathe fro the fleſſhe, be nothing pleaſaunte, yet thende leadeth our ſoules vnto reſt. For what is he ſaith the lord, that geueth ouer his hert to come vnto me
<pb facs="tcp:10202:42"/>
ye ſhall be my people, &amp; I wyll be your god. But beholde, on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſyde, ſhall the wrathe of the lorde breake out ſaithe Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remi as a ſtormy weather, as a myghtie whirle wind, and ſhall fall vpon the heades of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, the tetrible diſpleaſure of the Lorde, ſhall not leaue of, tyll he haue done and perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the intente of hys hearte which in the latter daies (ſaith the Prophete) ye ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande &amp;c.<note place="margin">Iere. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>For at that ſame tyme, I ſhal be the god of all the generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Iſrael (ſaithe the lorde) and they ſhall be my people &amp;c.<note place="margin">Iere. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> Neuertheleſſe ſayth he: whom I take in hande to roote oute, to deſtroye, or to waſte awaie, any people or kyngdom, if that
<pb facs="tcp:10202:43"/>
people (againſt whome I haue thus deuyſed) conuerte from their wickednes, ymediately I repente of the plage y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue deuyſed to bringe vpon theym, ſaith the lorde &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Our god is alwaies mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prepare their hertes by obedience and repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunce,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> to receiue his holy ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, for like as rayne and ſnow cometh down from thence and turneth not thyther again, but watereth the earthe &amp; maketh it frutefull and greene, that it may gyue corne and breade to the ſower, ſo the worde whiche cometh out of my mouth, ſaith the lord, ſhall not tourne again voide vnto me, but ſhall accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyſhe my wyll, &amp; proſpere in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing where vnto I ſend it &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:10202:43"/>
Therfore, ſeyng god wyll now repaire the decayed places of his temple, make youre conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence cleane that ye may be lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge ſtones, being faſtened to Chriſte by faith and loue, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the head corner ſtone,<note place="margin">Epheſi. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> in whom euery buildyng, coupled &amp; ioyned togyther, ſaith Paul, is made an holy habitation for god, in the ſpirite &amp;c.<note place="margin">Ezechi. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> For God dwelleth with them that be of an humble ſpirite, and of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite herte, which ſtand in awe of his worde: yea, he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed, to dwel and abide with them for euer,<note place="margin">Ezech. <hi>36.</hi> Ieremi. <hi>31.</hi> Eſai. <hi>51.</hi>
               </note> and to gyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a newe herte, and to write his law therein, ſoo that they ſhall not nede to ſay one to an other, know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, for they ſhal know me from the leſt; to the moſt of
<pb facs="tcp:10202:44"/>
them ſaith the lorde, for I wyll forgeue their myſdeades, and wyl neuer remembre their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes any more,<note place="margin">Ihon. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> for the ſonne of God hathe appered (ſaithe S. Ihon) to take awaye ſynnes, &amp; in hym is no ſynne: and who ſo euer abydethe in hym ſinneth not &amp;c.<note place="margin">Ihon. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> For to as many as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue hym, gyueth he power to be the ſonnes of god, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe that beleue in his name, ſaithe he, which are not born of bloud, nor of the wyll of man, but of god: or here now O Iſrael. Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyce and be glad, for thy rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer lyueth: he hath ſene thyne oppreſſion, and his eyes do py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie the. Therefore, wil he viſite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, and gather y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amonge all nations, where thou art ſca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered &amp; holden in captiuitie, for
<pb facs="tcp:10202:44"/>
thine offences, but yet not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken: for with an euerlaſting loue hath he loued the: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath he raiſed vp for the,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mightie horne of healthe in the houſe of Dauid, of whoſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome there ſhall be none ende:<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>113.</hi>
               </note> neither hath he ſpared his own ſonne, but geuen hym yea, hys lyfe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he loued ſoo well, for thy ſake, to make an euerlaſtyng at tonement betwixte him &amp; the, for thine offences. He hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to leade y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſafe, by his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirite, &amp; daily to defend the fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and oute, of all daungers. Therfore, he calleth euermore gretly vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, ſaying. Come vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to me my beloued, for I am he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for myne own ſake, pardoned thine offences, &amp; caſte thy ſyns into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bottome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſee. Make
<pb facs="tcp:10202:45"/>
none excuſe, neyther prolong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme, but come immediatly my beloued brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; natural cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to this moſt ioyful ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or feaſt, which our merciful father hathe of his owne good wyl prepared &amp; made ready for you: yea, &amp; of long tyme hath he called you by his ſeruauntes &amp; prophetes: ſaiyng. Here &amp; obey my voice, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal ye be my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, &amp; I wil be your god: it appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth he hath not forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, for as a moſt ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle &amp; louing father hath he ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his holy word y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of god, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very true patrone &amp; i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of his moſt godly ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to deliuer you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al captiuitie &amp; blindnes, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oppres the &amp; Iacob, &amp; hold his ſeruant Iſrael in captiuitie, wil he iuge: neuertheles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:10202:45"/>
w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his own mouthe,<note place="margin">Leui, <hi>19.14</hi>
               </note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger wil turne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord with his hole hert, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers ſhal haue inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes &amp; doughters ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord almighty, what can there be more done for vs:<note place="margin">The fore ſkynnes ſignifieth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſtes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh and mind whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che muſte be cutte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye.</note> ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, turne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord with youre hole hertes, circumciſe youre fore ſkynnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may be made right Iſraelites, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſede, &amp; receiue inheritaunce as naturall ſonnes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of Iſrael the faithfull congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: To you wicked people &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licious tirantes,<note place="margin">All y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> religion of Chriſte in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dede, as well as in worde, are heathen &amp; infideles.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeke to ſpoile &amp; deuour Iacob his peple, &amp; to rote out Iſrael his choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord ſendeth word, let Iſrael go, ye heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may do me ſacrifice at my wyl, vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taines: for he is my eldeſt ſon:
<pb facs="tcp:10202:46"/>
perfite is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floweth in righteouſnes,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>13.</hi> The elect muſt be tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed by try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulacion &amp; aduerſitie.</note> &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitely ſhal the lord of hoſtes ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyll the thyng that he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyned in the middes of the world, for I will puniſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of the world, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the vngodlye (ſayeth the lord) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hye ſtomakes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proud wyll I take away, &amp; lay downe the boaſtyng of tyrauntes, ye I wil make a man dearer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fine gold, &amp; a man to be more worth then a golden wedge of Ophir, for I will ſhake the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">All that is of fleſſhe, muſt be do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en awaye.</note> that the earth ſhall remoue oute of her place. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſtaffe is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde wherwith the world is ſmitten.</note>For the Lord ſhall ſmite the world w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſtaffe of his mouth and with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breath of his mouth ſhal he ſlea the wicked: but mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifully wyll he delyuer his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,
<pb facs="tcp:10202:46"/>
and deuide the good fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the euil: for thus ſaieth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord god. Behold I wyll ſeuere the fatte ſhepe from the leane. And for ſo muche as ye haue ſhot y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weake ſhepe vpon the ſides and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and runne vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with your hornes,<note place="margin">Ezech. <hi>34.</hi> Hornes ſignyfyeth ſtrength.</note> ſo long til ye haue vtterly ſcattered them abrode, I will helpe my ſhepe, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall no more be ſpoyled: yea, I will diſcerne one ſhepe from an other, I wyll rayſe vp vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one onely ſhepeheard, euen my ſeruaunte Dauid,<note place="margin">Iere <hi>30.</hi> Miche. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> he ſhall feede them, and he ſhalbe their ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, and I the lord wilbe their god / and my ſeruaunte Dauid ſhalbe their prynce, euen I the lord haue ſpoken it. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Moreouer I will make a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunt of peace with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:10202:47"/>
the lord, and driue all euill bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes out of the land, ſo that they may dwell ſafely in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; ſlepe in the woodes, good fortune and proſperitie wyll I geue them, and vnto all that be round about my hyll, a proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſhower and rayne wyll I ſend them in due ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the trees in the wodde may bryng forth their frintes, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d her encreaſe, they ſhalbe ſafe in their land, and ſhall knowe that I am the lord, which haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their yoke, and delyuered them out of the handes of thoſe that held the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſubiection they ſhall no more bee ſpoyled of the Hethen, nor deuoured with the beaſtes of the lande, but ſafelye ſhall they dwell / and no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal fray them. I wyll ſet vp an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb facs="tcp:10202:47"/>
plant for them, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall ſuffre no more houngre in the lande, neyther beare the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profe of the Heathen any more. Thus ſhal they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that I the Lord their god am with them, and that they (euen the houſe of Iſrael) are my people ſaith the lord god: ye me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ar my flocke, ye are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepe of my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and I am youre God &amp;c.</p>
            <p>O ye people turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your croked wayes, and from youre owne frowarde imaginacions, ceaſſe &amp; leaue of from your own fayned diſſimulacion. Dareſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſo diſſemble with God, and to play the part of an infidel or vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faithfull hypocrit before hym? Thynkeſt thou to hyde thy ſelf vnder thyne owne ſhaddowes from hym that made thee, and
<pb facs="tcp:10202:48"/>
put thy herte in a ſecrete place Or wylte thou thynke to hyde thy ſinnes with deceit, that the higheſt (which ſearcheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> her<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raynes) ſhall not reproue thy wayes? ye come togyther / as god ſayde to the Iewes, by his prophet / after the maner of a greate people,<note place="margin">Ezech. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> to heare his word at the mouth of the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher or prophet, but in no wyſe wyll ye do thereafter. In your mouthes / lykewyſe ye ſhewe youe ſelfes as though ye were feruent, but your heartes goo after youre owne couetous lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, and as a balade that hath a ſwete tune, and is pleaſaunt to ſyng, ſo is the Preacher vnto you his wordes wyll ye heare ſaith the lord / but ye wil not do thereafter. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10202:48"/>For vaine glorie and lucre, ye make croked lawes, wherby ye laye ſnares for the feete of the ſymple: and wolde ye that noo man ſhould reproue your wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es? The mouth of the diſceitful is right well with you alowed, but he that ſpeaketh the truth,<note place="margin">To deale with equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; truth men ſaye playnelye they can not lyue.</note> ſhal not eſcape vnpuniſſhed: for crafte, diſceyte and falſhode, is ſuche an vniuerſall thinge, that to deale with equitie and truth men ſay playnelye they can not lyue, and thus vertue is ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally contempned, that it is nigh a common reproche, for a man to do well. O lord, as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſaith, when wilte thou loke vpon this? O reſtore my ſoule frome the wycked rumoure of them and my darlynge from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lyon, for they are ſtained with
<pb facs="tcp:10202:49"/>
their owne workes, and runne a horinge after their own yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, for daily do they blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme thy name, &amp; ſlaunder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foote ſteps of thyne anointed, &amp; yet wil they be knowen for ſuch as know their god, hold of him, &amp; ar ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in his wais. For thei ſay in their hertes, tuſſhe God ſeeth it not, the higheſt regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth none of theſe thynges, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though god by longe pacience, ſuffer ſuch thinges at their han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des loking and tariyng for thy amendmente (O Chriſtianitie) thinkeſt thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it wyl be forgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten? Hath there euer any nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted like abhomi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nations before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, eſcaped vnpu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſſhed? And doſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> thinke to eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cape? Naye thou ſhalte ſurelye drinke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, thou ſhalt not
<pb facs="tcp:10202:49"/>
be forgote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but thy ſynnes ſhall truly be recompenſed in the (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen into thy boſome) god ſhall tourne thy clothes ouer thye heade (O thou filthy herlot) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy filthynes may many feſtely appere alſo: and ſeyng thou art a people y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> runneſt in thine own wilfull wayes, and ſaieſt, tuſſhe there ſhal no faulte be found in all my doinges: therefore, ſtom bleſt thou in the clere day, &amp; fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſt in the darke, yea, grope do ye as blynde men, after youre own ymagination, but becauſe ye let your handes deale with wickedneſſe, ye can not fynd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right way.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> For as the Pſalme ſaith, your fete are ſwift to ſhed bloud, deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and wretched<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes are in youre waies, but the way of peace haue ye not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen.
<pb facs="tcp:10202:50"/>
O yee frowarde people heare the word of the lord, giue your eares to doctrine, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſe not good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell, ſeke frend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip of god by vertu, &amp; not by fla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terie, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord is alway frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them that put their truſte in hym, but ye call your ſelues chriſtians, and yet commyt wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kednes with your mouthes, ye extolle Chriſtes worde, name, lawes and ſacramentes, but in your deedes ye diſhonour him for as longe verely as ye delite in euyll, your deades are hated of God, and yet ſaye with dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite wyll we eſcape,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> and withe nymblenes wyl we defend our ſelues, therfore are ye curſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> penurie: ye choſe ignorance for your guide, &amp; wylfulnes too be your gouernour, as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges
<pb facs="tcp:10202:50"/>
of the Prophetes,<note place="margin">They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> truſte in their own wiſedom, or in any other thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of fleſſhe &amp; bloud ſhal ſurely erre and be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. Eſai. <hi>19.</hi> Egipte ſignifiethe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of wylfull ſynners.</note> yee take for winde, and the worde of god for a ſcorne, becauſe yee haue no luſte thereto, and thus they go wrong by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wine (ſaith the lorde) they fall &amp; ſtac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker becauſe of ſtronge drinke: yea, the prieſtes &amp; Prophetes them ſelues go amys, they are dronken with wine, and weake brained thorow ſtrong drinke. They erre in ſeing, &amp; in Iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente they faile. For the lorde hath made Egipte dronken w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpirite of errour, ſaith Eſai, and they ſhall vſe it in all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyke as a dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man gooeth ſpewinge aboute. For Egipte ſhall lacke good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell (ſaith he) ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall not know what to do, neither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, nor thend neither vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:10202:51"/>
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land nor water, then ſhall the Egiptians be lyke vnto wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afraide and aſtonied at the lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge vp of the hande, whiche the lorde of hooſtes,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> ſaith Eſai, ſhall lyfte vp ouer them &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Myſerably ſhall the worlde be waſted and cleane deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for the lorde hath ſo deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myned in hym ſelfe &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For the earth is corrupte of her indwellers, for whye they haue offended the lawes chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged their ordinaunces, &amp; made the euerlaſtinge Teſtament of none effects, and therefore ſhal the curſe deuoure the earth: for they that dwell thereon haue ſinned. And although theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces come dayly vpon you from the lorde, for your offences, yet yee ſee it not, nor regarde the
<pb facs="tcp:10202:51"/>
matter noothinge at all: O ye blynde and frowarde nations,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> therefore, though ye holde out your handes, yet tourn I mine eyes from you ſaith the lord, &amp; though ye make many prayers yet here I nothinge at all, for your handes are full of bloude, and ye deale alway with wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, becauſe certeine ſynne hath no outward punyſhment, apointed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rulers, for thoſe that do them: Thinke ye ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foore, that God wyll forgette them?</p>
            <p>The people in Chriſtes tyme (whyle he raygned vppon the earthe) thoughte that thooſe Galathians whoſe bloude Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late myngled with theyr owne ſacrifyce, and the .xviii. perſons vpon whome the towre of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loah<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:10202:52"/>
fell, and ſlewe, had beene moche greater ſynners then the other that ſuffered no ſuch punyſhmente, but our ſauiour Chriſt ſayde playnely, nay and excepte the other repeted, they ſhoulde lyke wyſe periſſhe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe they ſuffered no ſuche punyſhment here, therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre thy ſelfe, O thou na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Chriſtianytie, repente in tyme, and tourne to the Lorde wyth thy hole herte. Too you do I ſpeake, O yee Ignoraunt people, gette ye to moornynge quyckely, and poure oute your teares befoore hym / that hee maye ſhewe mercye and tourn all wayes hys wrathe frome you. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>O tourn you, tourne you,
<pb facs="tcp:10202:52"/>
why will ye dye,<note place="margin">Ezech. <hi>18. 3.</hi> Par. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> ſeyng the lord hath no pleſure in the death of a ſinner, but willeth rather that he conuert and liue. &amp;c. But yf ye withdraw your eares, &amp; will not heare, to turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your euil wayes: then am I ſory for your ſakes. Bee not wilfully blynde, but ſearche the ſcriptures, and ye ſhal ſee, that no people or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion that did ſuche abhominaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and hated to be refourmed ſince the beginnyng eſcaped vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>puniſhed: and would ye eſcape?<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> Then muſt ye refuſe the euill, &amp; chooſe the good: ſeke peace and enſue or folowe it, for the eyes of the lord are ouer the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and his eares are ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their prayers: but the face of the lord beholdeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that do euill, to deſtroy the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance
<pb facs="tcp:10202:53"/>
of them out of the earth. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>yea the curſſe of the lorde is in the houſe of the vngodly, but he bleſſeth the righteous. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe thynges with your ſelues in time, leſt ſinne by long cuſtome blind your vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, ſo that ye iudge derknes for light and good for euill: ye knowe the blynde are eaſye to leade out of the way, wher thei ſone fall and be made a pray for the enemy.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 22.8.</note> Wherefore beloued geue diligent eare vnto wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom whiche hath now agayne opened her flouddes and putte forth her voyce in the ſtreetes, ſhe booeth call before the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion in the open gates, &amp; ſheweth her wordes in the citie O ye chyldren ſayeth ſhe, howe long will ye loue childiſheneſſe?
<pb facs="tcp:10202:53"/>
how long will the ſkorners de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite in ſkorning, and the vnwiſe be enemies to knowledge? O turne ye to my correccion, ſaith ſhe, lo I will expreſſe my minde vnto you, and make you vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtand my wordes. For who ſo herkeneth vnto me ſhal dwelle ſafely, and haue inough w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>oute any feare of euill.<note place="margin">Pro. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> Again ſhe ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, my ſonne: let not theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges departe from thyne eyes, but kepe my lawe &amp; my councel ſo ſhall it be lyfe vnto thy ſoule and grace vnto thy mouth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalte thou walke ſafelye in the way, and thy fote ſhal not ſtum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, if thou ſlepeſt thou ſhalt not nede to be afrayed, but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte take thy reſt and ſlepe ſwetely, thou ſhalt not nede, ſayeth ſhe, to bee afrayed of any ſoodayne
<pb facs="tcp:10202:54"/>
feare, neither for the viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng in of the vngodly whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it cometh, for the lord ſhalbe bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide thee,<note place="margin">Prouer. <hi>1,</hi>
               </note> and kepe thy fote that thou be not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. O ye beloued children, herken vnto wiſdom: Come no more in the pathes of the vngodly, ſaieth ſhe, &amp; walke not in the way of the wicked.</p>
            <p>Take faſt holde of doctrine and let her not go, kepe her, for ſhee is thy life. And again ſhe ſaieth, my ſonne marke my woordes, for the pathe of the rightuouſe ſhineth as the light, and is euer brighter and brighter vnto the perfite day, but the waye of the vngodly is as the darknes, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſhe, wherin men fall or they be aware.<note place="margin">Prouer <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> And moreouer ſhe ſaith, heare ye chyldren the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlye exhortacion, and take
<pb facs="tcp:10202:54"/>
good hede that ye maye learne wiſdom, yea I ſhall geue you a good reward, yf ye wil not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake my lawe, ſaith wiſdom. &amp;c. The chief poynt of wiſedom is to be willing to attain wiſdom. Therefore let thy hert receyue my wordes (ſaith ſhe) and kepe my commaundementes, &amp; thou ſhalt liue. Obey vnto god, and then ſhall ye receiue a good ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of hym, which (as S. Iohn ſaith) wyll looſe the woorkes of ſynne, &amp; geue you a will to loue him, and to kepe his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Io.</hi> 3.</note> for thei that ar born of hym ſynne not (ſaieth he) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue the ſede remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in them,<note place="margin">Where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spirite of god is, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Paule, there is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.</note> the earneſt of our ſaluacion: I meane the ſpyrite of truth, the ioyfull coumforter whiche god hath promiſed that
<pb facs="tcp:10202:55"/>
ſhall alwayes abyde with them that looue hym, euen vnto the ende of the worlde. This is he that loſſeth the workes of ſinne and bringeth a godly deſire vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to righteouſnes and a longing to fulfull the wyl of god: &amp; they that haue opteined a mynde to loue god are begotten &amp; borne of hym and they are knowen &amp; loued of hym. And herby know we ſaith Ihon,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Io.</hi> 1.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god abydeth in vs euen by the ſpirite which he gaue vs as it is write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: To as many as receiue him giueth he power to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſons or children of god,<note place="margin">Io. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> euen thooſe that beleue in his name, which are not born of bloude, nor of the wyll of the fleſh nor of the wyll of man, but of God. The vngodlye are the bonde ſeruauntes of ſynne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:10202:55"/>
they are carnally minded their hertes hate god,<note place="margin">He that is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes hateth god.</note> thoughe theyr lyppes praiſe hym, which is all goodnes, yea, the onelye well and fountayne there of. They lacke true obedience too the word and wyll of god, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore can they not optain to that rightouſnes, which before god, is alowed.<note place="margin">The lorde wyll viſite the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe fore ſki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne is vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyſed.</note> For theire hertes and eares are vncircumciſed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wyl not heare, to learne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, leaſte they ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerte and be healed. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, runne they aſtray and eſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blyſh their own righteouſnes, for vnfaithfully haue they deni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed the lorde in dede, and ſaid, it is not he. Tuſh (ſay they) there ſhal no miſfortune come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs we ſhal ſee neither ſweard nor hunger, as for the warnynges
<pb facs="tcp:10202:56"/>
of the prophetes, thei regard it not: There is almoſt none, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that will tell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes nor geue them warnyng of the plagues that are come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them,<note place="margin">Iere. <hi>6.8.</hi>
               </note> or ſhall happen vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for from the leaſt to the moſte, they hang altogether vpon co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes,<note place="margin">Oſeas. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet to the prieſt, thei go altogether about with falſhod and lies. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For lyke as a net is full of bir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, ſo are theyr houſes full of that whiche they haue gotten with falſehode and diſceit, ſaith the lord.<note place="margin">Ieremi. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Here of cometh theyr great ſubſtaunce and rycheſſe, and hereof are they fatte and welthye, and are runne awaye fro me with ſhamefull blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſayth the lord, they miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre not the lawe, they make no
<pb facs="tcp:10202:56"/>
end of the fatherles cauſe, they iudge not the poore according to equitie: ſhoulde not I pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſh theſe thynges, ſaythe the lorde?<note place="margin">That is not onelye on theſe, but aſwell on al other ſuch lyke.</note> Should I not be auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of all ſuch people as theeſe be? Horrible and greuouſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges are doone in the lande, the Prophetes teache falſely, and the prieſtes folowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and my people hathe pleaſure therein. May ſuch thinges at any time or in anye people be vnpunyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed? Therefore, repente and tourne from your euyll waies, that ye may enter into the reſt of God, and kepe his holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bothes, for they that enter into the reſte of god, do ceaſe frome their owne workes, ſaith Paul as God dyd ceaſe from his, the vii. daye: and excepte ye keepe
<pb facs="tcp:10202:57"/>
the holy feaſte of tabernacles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, ceaſe from your owne wyl, and from doing your own workes: The Lorde wyll con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume you, in his wrath, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroye you, in his ſoore diſpleaſure. For thus ſayth the lorde, I am excedynge gelouſe ouer Ieruſalem and Sion,<note place="margin">zacha. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and am ſoore diſpleaſed at the care<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les heathen, for I was but a ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle angrye, and they dyd theyr beſte, that I might diſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Neuertheleſſe, I wyll tourne me againe in mercy toward Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruſalem, ſo that my houſe ſhall be builded in it, ſaith the lorde of hooſtes. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">zacha. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>Cry and ſpeake, thus ſayth the lorde of hoſtes, my Cities ſhall be in good proſperitie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the Lorde ſhall yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte
<pb facs="tcp:10202:57"/>
Sion, and chooſe Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. yea Hieruſalem ſhalbe in habited with out any wall,<note place="margin">zacha. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> for the multitude of the people &amp; cattell that ſhall be therein, yea I my ſelfe (ſaith the lorde) wyll be vnto her a wal of fyre, round about, and wyl be honoured in her.<note place="margin">Oſeas. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> For although the children of Iſrael ſytte a longe whyle wythout Kyng or Prince, with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oute offeryng, and aulter with out prieſt &amp; reuelacion, yet ſhall the children of Iſrael conuerte ſaith the prophete Oſeas, and ſeke the lorde their god, &amp; Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid their king, and in the latter daies, ſaith he, they ſhal worſhip the lord &amp; his louyng kindnes.</p>
            <p>Therefore, ſeyng that God hath nowe called you by his grace, be not negligent to come,
<pb facs="tcp:10202:58"/>
and ſe that the herte be eſtably<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with grace,<note place="margin">He that both righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſenes is of god,</note> and not with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vain pleaſures of this world, whiche ſhal not profite the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue their pleaſure and felicitie in them. For who ſo dooeth not righteouſnes is not of God: yf we ſay, we haue felowſhip with him,<note place="margin">To walke in darknes is to do ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che deades as wee all did, before we knewe the truthe.</note> and yet walke in derknes / ſaith S. Iohn / we do lye, &amp; doe not the truth. Therfore ſe that ye loue not the world, neyther the thinges that are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world for the world paſſeth away, and the luſtes thereof: but he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filleth the wyll of god, abydeth for euer,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Io.</hi> 3.</note> and hereby knowe we that he abydeth in vs, euen by the ſpirite whiche he hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs.<note place="margin">Apoca. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> And they that ouercome ſhall obtain a croune of glorye, and I wil geue to euery one of
<pb facs="tcp:10202:58"/>
you (ſaith the veritie of god) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to his workes. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Babes, flee from the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng of idols, I meane fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of your owne luſtes, and learne to ſerue the liuyng god in ſpirite, in a cleane hert / waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an euil conſcience, with reuerence and godly feare / for our god (ſaith Paul) is a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fier. To as mani as walk accordyng to this rule, peace, and mercie be vpon them, and vpon Iſrael of god. So be it.</p>
            <trailer type="benediction">
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> The grace of our lord Ieſu Chriſt / be with your ſpirites. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</trailer>
            <closer>Geue praiſe only to god.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>yours as charitie byn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me. H. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:10202:59"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Dieu et mon droit,</head>
                  <p>QVI MAL Y PENS<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> HONY SOYT</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.</bibl>
                  <p>¶Be ye ſubiecte to euery hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayn creature for the Lordes ſake, whether it be to the Kyng as ſupreme head: or to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates which be ſent by him, to the puniſhement of the euyll dooers / but to the prayſe of the well dooers: for ſo is the wyll of God.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10202:59"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
