<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Time is a turne-coate. Or Englands three-fold metamorphosis VVherin is acted the pensiue mans epilogomena, to Londons late lamentable heroicall comi-tragedie. Also a panegyricall pageant-speech or idylion pronounced to the citie of London, vpon the entrance of her long expected comfort. Written by Iohn Hanson.</title>
            <author>Hanson, John, fl. 1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12750</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118582</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853789</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853789</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19185</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02622)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19185)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1206:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Time is a turne-coate. Or Englands three-fold metamorphosis VVherin is acted the pensiue mans epilogomena, to Londons late lamentable heroicall comi-tragedie. Also a panegyricall pageant-speech or idylion pronounced to the citie of London, vpon the entrance of her long expected comfort. Written by Iohn Hanson.</title>
                  <author>Hanson, John, fl. 1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 71, [11] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Field] for I. H[anson?] and are to be sold [by G. Potter?] at the signe of the Bible in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's, publisher's and bookseller's names suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>With perpendicular chainlines--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19185:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19185:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TIME Is a Turne-Coate. OR <hi>Englands three-fold Metamorphoſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherin is acted the Penſiue mans Epilogomena, to Londons late lamentable <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall Comi-Tragedie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALSO</hi> A Panegyricall Pageant-ſpeech or Idylion pronounced to the Citie of London, vpon the entrance of her long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qui color ater erat, nunc eſt contrarius atro.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by IOHN HANSON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for I. H. and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Bible in Paules Church-yard.</p>
            <p>1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19185:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE SIR THOMAS BEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NET KNIGHT, LORD MAIOR OF the famous Citie of London, the right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Sir William Romley, and Sir Thomas Midleton Knights, and Sheriffes of the ſame Citie: increaſe of honor and euer-flouriſhing felicitie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Honorable and right Worſhipfull, I haue long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that ſome men of greater experience and grauer iudgment then my ſelf, ere this ſhould haue bent their ſtudies to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gratulate your proſperous deſignements with their learned Labours: not onely in this regard, that it hath ſeemed gracious in the eyes of Heauen, to turne the time of deſtruction into mirth and exhilaration, to diſpell the cloudes of deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the ſplendant Sun of this Citie, and to ſeale vp the iawes of that ſtarued Tyger, rauening and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging too and fro with inſatiate appetite, to gormandize indefinitely without partialitie: but alſo in reſpect of
<pb facs="tcp:19185:4"/>the proceedings in your general functions and callings; therein manifeſting your ardent zeale to the Church and Commonwealth, in the reformation of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and monſtrous enormities nurced and foſtred vp in the ſame Citie, wounding the hearts of many with the ſting of Securitie, who thereby fall into a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargie of their owne ruination: they being naturally like the Baſilisk, who by ſtinging a man, prouoketh him to conclude his deſtruction with the period of a ſweet ſleepe; which to diſcuſſe vpon more amply, were but to light a torch, when the Sunne boaſteth in his vertical point, or to multiplie leaues to a greene tree. But percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the turne of Times euent to fall out oppoſite to my expectation, and a time of reſpiration exhibited vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me by ſacred Prouidence, (for <hi>Deus nobis haec otiafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit</hi>) I (though moſt vnfit, not ſo much in regard of my litle ſcholerſhip and reading, as in reſpect of my iuue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilitie and leſſe experience, though <hi>Aſsiduè diſcens plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rima, fiam ſenex</hi>) haue thought it not impertinent to my dutie, as alſo conſonant to your dignities, to caſt this poore mite of feruent affection and congratulation, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the rich treaſurie of your honorable and worſhipfull Patronage: being inforced hereupon to vſe the meanes of that poore man, who hauing neither gold nor iewels, preſented both his hands full of running water to <hi>Arta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerxes.</hi> And the rather, for that I behold many preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents and pregnant demonſtrations of a flouriſhing Spring-tide of happineſſe ſubſtituted to your predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb facs="tcp:19185:4"/>and gouernment; in the conſtituting of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie and requiſite lawes for the ſupplanting and depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulating of vice; and being conſtituted, are ſtrictly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued and executed by your importunate induſtrie, (which (as <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaith) is <hi>Fortunae Imperator,</hi> and vrgeth an aſſent <hi>vltra vires rationis</hi>) leading this citie as peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Conductors, (or as <hi>Theodoſius</hi> did <hi>Rome</hi>) to a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Autumne. For <hi>Archidamus</hi> being asked, what made the <hi>Lacedaemonian</hi> kingdome to flouriſh, anſwered: Firſt, the lawes; and next, the Magiſtrates obſeruing the Lawes: and <hi>Aristotle</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Magiſtratus eſt cuſtos legis,</hi> alſo <hi>Xenophon:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Non dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert bonus Princeps à patre bono.</hi> Whereupon may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, that Magiſtrates (as <hi>Patres patriae</hi>) ought ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and with iudiciall precaution, not onely to preſcribe ordinances tending to the generall benefite of a citie or commonwealth; but alſo to be reſpectiue (as the father tendreth the ſucceſſiue fortune of his child with care and vigilancie) that they foreſlow not their progreſſion in the performance of their due execution: for <hi>Non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet principem virum totam noctem dormire, cui populi gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacula commiſſaſunt, &amp; à cuius cura pendent ingentia rerum momenta.</hi> But leſt any man ſhould obiect againſt me, that I pretend by a kind of aemulation and blandilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to adorne your merits like a <hi>Barbarian</hi> image, as <hi>Alexander</hi> was by <hi>Midius:</hi> or on the contrarie, to taxe me of calumniation with this inueterate Axiome: <hi>In medio tutiſsimus ibis:</hi> (which two, proue the Canker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worms
<pb facs="tcp:19185:5"/>of a flouriſhing countrie: for <hi>Diogenes</hi> the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke being asked, what kind of beaſts are moſt deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; he anſwered: that of tame beaſts, the Flatterer, and of wild beaſts, the Back-biter,) therefore ſo to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon the firſt, as not culpable of the laſt, I will cleaue to the golden <hi>Medium,</hi> breaking off that diſcourſe, and ceaſe to diſcuſſe vpon ſuch a Theame. And now to returne to my old taske, I humbly intreate your fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable entertainment to theſe my vnpoliſhed lines, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hewed out and ſquared by one of the meaneſt of <hi>Appolloes</hi> Artificers. And I the more ſeriouſly deſire it, for that I am deeply reſolued, they ſhal find a ſufficient ſhelter vnder the wings of your Honorable and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull names and Patronage, as vnder the receptacle of a ſtrong fortified <hi>Teſtudo,</hi> againſt the yelping chaps of thoſe ſnarling Zoyliſts, <hi>qui potiùs pro conſuetudine, quàm proferocitate latrant,</hi> barking more for cuſtome then curſtneſſe: who by diſgorging their mud-mixed cenſures vpon the ſtudious eſſayes of particulars, (for <hi>Apollo nullos habet inimicos, niſi nimbos</hi>) do reſolue with themſelues by that meanes to win a purchaſe of a lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reall applauſe, and to erect an eternall monument of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to themſelues, vpon the diſgraces of other mens indeauours: but thereby prouing culpable to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of their owne ignorance, and ripping vp the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels of their imperfections and groſſe fatuities, in the calumniating of ingenious enterpriſes, and by brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging backe with impudent arrogance thoſe ſtolne
<pb facs="tcp:19185:5"/>ſparkes which they ſnatched fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Appolloes</hi> ſacred flames, whereby the moiſtned muddie motions of their brains are enforced to euaporate in a ſmoothering heate; do appeare to the world, to ſurpaſſe in immanitie, the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropophagi</hi> or <hi>Canibals;</hi> who, though they gormandize on other mens fleſh, yet will not deuoure themſelues. Thus hoping, that theſe vnlettered lines ſhal paſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſturbance vnder the couert of your worthie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections, I humbly intreat your Honor and Worſhips, to admit this poore pittance into your rich banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-houſe of acceptation and tolleration, with no leſſe willing mind, then by courſe of affectionate congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation it is preſented vnto your hands; which, if it may find free acceſſe, I will turne my ſequele eſſayes with the turne of enſuing Time, more deepely to conuerſe with the <hi>Muſes</hi> thereby to bring foorth a further ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of my ardent affection towards your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie perſonages. In the meane time, Heauens proſper your worthie proceedings.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>26. of <hi>March.</hi> 1604.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honor and Worſhips humbly <hi>deuoted: John Hanſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:19185:6"/>
            <head>The Author, and his Booke.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Book.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HElpe, helpe, alas, elſe am I quite vndone,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O ſhroud me cloſe from ſight of theſe blacke feends,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who wound with Scorpions ſtings: I cannot ſhunne;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alas for ayde, ſome ayde, ſweet gentle friends!</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aut.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why, how now <hi>Booke,</hi> what newes? what, doſt thou dreame?</l>
                  <l>Or art thou quite diſtract, of ſenſe bereaued?</l>
                  <l>Or do thy Thoughts diſcuſſe on dolefull Theame?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yea ſure, I dream'd, yet not by Dreames deceiued:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For in my Dreame, me thought thou badst me poſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Through euery Countrie, Citie, farre and neare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To take my lodging with each erabbed Hoſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And beare the laſh of each lend Cenſurer.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aut.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why, ſo thou muſt: then run, no time delay:</l>
                  <l>Stand not amaz'd at euery carping braine;</l>
                  <l>And if thou meetſt a Cynicke by the way,</l>
                  <l>If he looke grim, looke ſterne on him againe.</l>
                  <l>But if graue <hi>Cato</hi> chance to meete with thee,</l>
                  <l>And deigne on thine his Iudgement to ſuſpend;</l>
                  <l>Do thou him reuerence low, with cap and knee:</l>
                  <l>Tell him, for learn'd aduice to him I ſend.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Book.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What if proud</hi> Argas <hi>meet me in the ſtreet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who robs</hi> Apollo <hi>of that ſacred Fire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which kindleth ardent rage in his cold ſprite,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And driues his muddie-froſt-bit-Braine t'aspire:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He'le turne me ore, and toſſe me in his ſnare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chopping my Subiect in his ſnarling chaps;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And in his turning, turne my coate threed-bare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Within the pocket of his threed-bare ſtops.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:19185:7"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aut.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What, that ſtaru'd hungrie catch-pole-paper knaue,</l>
                  <l>Who ne're durſt looke harſh <hi>Horace</hi> in the face?</l>
                  <l>That ſtealing-Senſe, that Sentence-ſnatching ſlaue,</l>
                  <l>Who feeds on fragments ſcraped from each place?</l>
                  <l>What he, that doth his Braines a begging ſend,</l>
                  <l>For ſome ragg'd Theame to comment on at large,</l>
                  <l>Catching a puddle-wharfe-Diſcourſe by th'end,</l>
                  <l>Chaunts it like whore-houſe tales in weſterne Barge?</l>
                  <l>Who he, that ſtill his Sun-burnt Senſe inclines</l>
                  <l>To turne his ſtate, till faine to turne his purſe;</l>
                  <l>And teares his huing from laſciuious lines,</l>
                  <l>Turnes Good to Naught, and Naught doth turne to worſe?</l>
                  <l>What he, whoſe Wit the whore and ſtrumpet plaies,</l>
                  <l>Got great with child by <hi>Latines</hi> two or three;</l>
                  <l>And then cries out, (for midwife neuer ſtaies)</l>
                  <l>Deliuerd of ſome monſtrous Baſtardie?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Turne him off to the whipping-poſt of <hi>Time;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tell him, his loathſome ſtinking breath infects thee:</l>
                  <l>Then turne his chaps to chop ſome raſcall Rime,</l>
                  <l>To chew ſome hobling doggrell Balladrie.</l>
                  <l>But if he ſweares, he'le turne thy coate with ſpight,</l>
                  <l>And turne thee leafe by leafe, and line by line:</l>
                  <l>Bid him go turne his nap-leſſe coate by night,</l>
                  <l>Who turnes his coate more oft, then thou turn'ſt thine.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Book.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But he that on his Sattins ſeates his Thought,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sinking to hell betweene his Dockeſies armes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Will turne his Fore-top, ſweare by heau'n,</hi> t'is nought,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As though that oath coniur'd, like Magicke charmes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aut.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Turne that word <hi>(Naught)</hi> downe to his heart againe,</l>
                  <l>From whence that viprous terme forc't free acceſſe,</l>
                  <l>Where caues of vgly venim'd Snakes remaine:</l>
                  <l>There let <hi>(naught)</hi> ſting his ſoule without redreſſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:19185:7"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Book.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet will Carnalitie, the vſuring Atheist,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Murtherer, the immane Sodomite:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Cruell man, and terr ene Senſualiſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turne are my leaues and teare them in deſpite:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turne backe with ſcorne my wholeſome Counſell giu'n,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turning me off, my graue aduice expell.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aut.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then turne them vp into the hands of Heau'n,</l>
                  <l>Who'le turne them downe into the chaps of hell.</l>
                  <l>Now get thee hence, poſt on with turning Rime,</l>
                  <l>Turning thy ſenſe to all, thy ſelfe to paine:</l>
                  <l>And turne thy hap to euery turne of <hi>Time,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though to thy ſelfe returnes the ſmalleſt gaine.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Vade, ambula, volens iuſta.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:19185:8"/>
            <head>R. B. De Argumento huius Libri encomium.</head>
            <l>EN tibi depingit Diuúm benè geſta Libellus,</l>
            <l>Funcra Magnatum, lugubria Fota virorum:</l>
            <l>Sicvolat ipſa dies, velox vt ſemita Phoebi,</l>
            <l>Ore vorat tacito, fallitq, volubilis aetas,</l>
            <l>Tabida depellit, cunctus incorpore morbos:</l>
            <l>Inſtruit exemplis inopem; detorquet &amp; aegrum.</l>
            <l>Vis prudens fieri, ſis foelix temporis ipſe</l>
            <l>Filius, vt renouat varios aduertito motus:</l>
            <l>Augeſcunt aliae gentes, aliae minuuntur;</l>
            <l>Mortenigra breuner mutantur ſaecla animantum,</l>
            <l>Et quaſicurſores vitarum Lampada tradunt:</l>
            <l>Fulmine diuino trepidat ſic mundus iniquue.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>Libri &amp; Authoris Encomium.</head>
            <l>COgitur iste Liber (mel tanquam floribus) horte</l>
            <l>Muſaico, nitidis ſplendens lectis<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> coronis.</l>
            <l>Tempore ſis foelix, foelix Genio quoque tempus:</l>
            <l>Lauriferas laudes ſapiens cantabit Apollo.</l>
            <l>Tempure confulges, inſuſus Palladis arte,</l>
            <l>Tu quia Pernaſſimontes renouaſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, ruinas.</l>
            <l>Tempore vireſcis, brumali tempore flores,</l>
            <l>Nectare perlautus, hausliſq, Aganyppidis vndis.</l>
            <l>Tempore, frendit Aper, ringitq, Lupus, Leo rugit,</l>
            <l>Tu tamen in mundo, vt ſplendet, lucebis, Eóus:</l>
            <l>Tempora temporibus tranſuertis tabida firmis:</l>
            <l>Foelici viridis decoret te tempore laurus.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19185:8"/>
            <head>To the iudiciall Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I write not of victorious <hi>Hanniball,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of Romes old murthered ſons, nor <hi>Pompeys</hi> fall,</l>
               <l>Of valiant <hi>Hector,</hi> nor <hi>Achilles</hi> ſhield,</l>
               <l>Burning <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> nor th'<hi>Elyſian field;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor of huge arme-ſtrong <hi>Hercul's Iôle:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of lone-ſicke <hi>Attis,</hi> nor beauteous <hi>Danaë,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To whom (ſhe priſon'd in a mured Tower)</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Saturnes</hi> ſonne rain'd downe the ſiluer ſhower:</l>
               <l>Nor of <hi>Ioues</hi> conquering heire, nor <hi>Pryaps</hi> bed,</l>
               <l>Nor of the ſports of wanton <hi>Ganimed.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But of that <hi>Faire,</hi> the fairest of Earths Faire,</l>
               <l>To whom in troupes ſupernall Nymphs repaire:</l>
               <l>A ſhining Diamond, a radiant Bright,</l>
               <l>Which in earths Center yeeldeth cleareſt Light:</l>
               <l>A precious Pearle, cleare as Aurora's Sun,</l>
               <l>Whoſe hote-reflecting beames will not be done:</l>
               <l>A glorious Starre, to Heau'n and Earth combin'd,</l>
               <l>The brighteſt Gemme that ere in <hi>Albion</hi> ſhin'd.</l>
               <l>Of heighth, of depth, of earth, of heau'n, of hell,</l>
               <l>Of vgly monſters, ſhapes that do excell:</l>
               <l>Ofioy, of wo, of horror, mirth, and feare,</l>
               <l>Of reſtleſſe Motions whirl'd about the Sphare,</l>
               <l>And turn'd circumferent with Typhonian <hi>Time:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Time</hi> hath task't me to a turning Rime.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19185:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Two ardent Paſsions kindled by Deſire,</l>
               <l>VVithin my breast at once began t'aſpire:</l>
               <l>Griefe bad me write, but Ioy ſtraight anſwerd, nay:</l>
               <l>Ioy bad me ſing, then Griefe aduis'd me ſtay:</l>
               <l>Griefe waxed pale, while Ioy more ſterne did ſhow,</l>
               <l>Ioy ſprightly ſtood, Griefe ſcorn'd the ouerthrow.</l>
               <l>Thus Ioy and Griefe, ſtriuing with aduerſe ſpite,</l>
               <l>Twixt Griefe and Ioy, I fram'd my pen to write:</l>
               <l>For turne-coate <hi>Time</hi> perforce directs my quill,</l>
               <l>To vrge it ſing conſorting to his will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſith my <hi>Muſe</hi> wants that Heroicke ſpirit,</l>
               <l>In ſtately ſtraines to eternize their merit;</l>
               <l>Proiects her ſelfe to grauer Iudgements ſight,</l>
               <l>Catching ſwift-winged <hi>Time</hi> on inſtant flight.</l>
               <l>If ſmooth-toung'd <hi>Caliop</hi> theſe lines peruſe,</l>
               <l>The want of <hi>Age</hi> doth want of <hi>Art</hi> excuſe:</l>
               <l>My head's ingirt with iuie, not with baies,</l>
               <l>Ordain'd for deeper wits, that merit praiſe.</l>
               <l>Friendly ſcan all, yet ſcandalize me not,</l>
               <l>VVith the detracting Toung of euery Sot.</l>
               <l>If well, then cenſure well, if ill, diſpraiſe it;</l>
               <l>Yet would I know, if he be wiſe that ſayes it.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Nec Momum nec Mimum metuo.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19185:9"/>
            <head>TIME <hi>Is a Turne-coate:</hi> OR Englands threefold Metamorphoſis. <hi>Post tristia, Leta.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Panàite Pierides vestro ſacra ostia vati.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>YE foule-fac'd Furies which the Stygian keepe,</l>
               <l>Ye grizly Feends of the Cymmerian deepe,</l>
               <l>Ye hel-hounds droupe, and howle in ſulphur'd caues;</l>
               <l>Stand ye amaz'd grim <hi>Plutoes</hi> damned ſlaues;</l>
               <l>Riſe vp from torride lakes, and gaze afarre;</l>
               <l>Loe! Earth preſents to Heau'n a gliſtering <hi>Starre.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye Powers diuine which in the heau'nsare fixed;</l>
               <l>Ye Spirits that with the wandring ſtarres are mixed:</l>
               <l>Conioyne in one ye Sphaeres caeleſtiall:</l>
               <l>Ye Muſes nine, performe this Funerall;</l>
               <l>Condole her death, whoſe glorious life was ſo,</l>
               <l>As by her life, her death was freed from wo:</l>
               <l>Whoſe life repleat with grace, exempt from ſtrife;</l>
               <l>Whoſe death's transformd to neuer-dying life.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19185:10"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cynthia,</hi> faire Siſter to blacke ladie Night,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Gehons</hi> ſtreames with golden <hi>Icons</hi> dight;</l>
               <l>To whom heau'ns ſenior Lights proffer their dutie,</l>
               <l>For thy ſurpaſſing and refulgent Beautie:</l>
               <l>Renounce thy borrowed Shine, reuoke thy race,</l>
               <l>With clouds of Languiſhment remaske thy face.</l>
               <l>Sad <hi>Melpomen</hi> with tragicke Scaenes relent</l>
               <l>Each Marble rocke and obdurated Flint:</l>
               <l>Sigh foorth deepe accents of thy ſacred Loue,</l>
               <l>To cauſe the ſtonie-hearted Sauage moue:</l>
               <l>Straine out <hi>Threnodiae,</hi> thy aſſiduall note,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For Time hath roab'd himſelfe with ſable Cote.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ye ſacred Nymphs hang down your Sun-bright haires</l>
               <l>Bedew your cheekes with penitentiall teares:</l>
               <l>Conduct me to ſome ſolitarie Cell,</l>
               <l>Wherein I may with pale-fac'd Sorrow dwell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas, my Muſe doth faint ere ſhe proceed,</l>
               <l>To tune <hi>Encomions</hi> on a mournfull Reed:</l>
               <l>Wiſe <hi>Caliope,</hi> ſweet Queene of Eloquence,</l>
               <l>Inſpire her Thoughts with ſacred influence.</l>
               <l>Take courage (Muſe) pure Zeale ſhall ſtand thy barre,</l>
               <l>Looke not agaſt on euery frowning Starre:</l>
               <l>Plucke vp thy ſprite from pitchie <hi>Acheron:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Solace amidſt the fields of <hi>Hellicon:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now bath thy ſelfe in the <hi>Pierian</hi> ſpring,</l>
               <l>Where thy ſad Siſters mournfully do ſing:</l>
               <l>Go ſeeke that <hi>Phoenix</hi> mounted in the skie,</l>
               <l>Transform'd to euer-during Dignitie;</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19185:10"/>
               <l>The <hi>Phoenix</hi> of our age, Earths onely Faire,</l>
               <l>Faiths Empreſſe, and heau'ns high glorious Haire:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Englands Phoenix</hi> admir'd for Raritie,</l>
               <l>For Beautie, Vertue, and pure Chaſtitie:</l>
               <l>O ſhee's conſum'd with heau'ns reſplendent Light,</l>
               <l>That from her aſhes <hi>one</hi> might riſe as bright,</l>
               <l>And flouriſh foorth vpon the verdant ground,</l>
               <l>Whoſe paralel in Art is ſcarcely found.</l>
               <l>Why ſtriues my Muſe to ſtellifie her name?</l>
               <l>The bright-eyed-wondring world diuulg'd her fame;</l>
               <l>And Fame it ſelfe flies ſwiftly from her neſt,</l>
               <l>To blaze her honor from the Eaſt to Weſt.</l>
               <l>Sad Sickneſſe, the pale Harbinger of Death,</l>
               <l>Foredoom'd the loſſe of <hi>Syrinx</hi> daughters breath:</l>
               <l>Blacke furious Fate, that wrought ſuch deepe deſpight,</l>
               <l>To locke faire <hi>Phoebe</hi> from <hi>Endimions</hi> ſight;</l>
               <l>I meane <hi>Eliza:</hi> ô write that name againe,</l>
               <l>That with reuoluing Time it may remaine:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eliza,</hi> ſhe who was profound in Art,</l>
               <l>Is now ſtrucke dead with <hi>Thanatos</hi> his dart;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eliza,</hi> who in many dangers ſtood,</l>
               <l>For Gods high glorie, and her ſubiects good:</l>
               <l>By her, th'incarnate Goſpell was poſſeſt;</l>
               <l>Through her, all <hi>Britaines</hi> Ile Iehoua bleſt;</l>
               <l>For her, the heau'ns rain'd down ſuch plenteous ſtore,</l>
               <l>As Natures greedie Sons could wiſh no more.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Honor</hi> imbrac'd her, <hi>Art</hi> by her did ſtand,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Prudence</hi> attended on her genious hand,</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19185:11"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in Mercie with her bare the ſway,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glorie infinite</hi> her laſt Cataſtrophé.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The fatall Siſters ioyntly haue decreed,</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Atropos</hi> ſhould cut that vitall threed,</l>
               <l>Which counites the Subſtance with the Soule;</l>
               <l>Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bing each Senſe with leane-chapt Deaths co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>troule.</l>
               <l>This ſtate is incident to Natures lot;</l>
               <l>Drawne through the world in <hi>Times</hi> ſtill chariot,</l>
               <l>With two vnruly Steedes, and hurl'd along</l>
               <l>By reſtleſſe <hi>Motion</hi> and <hi>Mutation:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At length they leaue her on Deaths diſmall ſtage:</l>
               <l>As being wearie of their cariage:</l>
               <l>Then his grim Sergeant comes without controule,</l>
               <l>T'arreſt her bodie, diſ-unite her ſoule:</l>
               <l>He takes no bribes, but ſtrikes (impartiall)</l>
               <l>The Begger, Baron, Caitiffe, King, and all.</l>
               <l>If Death had fear'd to ſtop <hi>Aſtraeaes</hi> breath,</l>
               <l>Then had he ſpared Queene <hi>Elizabeth:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe ſoule is now enthroniz'd boue the skies,</l>
               <l>Where glorious Cherub's ſing her Exequies:</l>
               <l>Through <hi>Ioues</hi> broad milk-white path now is ſhe gone,</l>
               <l>And ſtately royaliz'd on Angels throne:</l>
               <l>The ſiluer Vault with <hi>Epods</hi> deepe reſounds,</l>
               <l>Of her rare Vertue which on Earth abounds.</l>
               <l>I wiſh <hi>Eliza</hi> from vs could not paſſe,</l>
               <l>Who made each place a heau'n wherein ſhe was.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Th'Almightie <hi>Ioue</hi> ſo lock't Virginitie</l>
               <l>From Antidotes and banefull Trecherie,</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19185:11"/>
               <l>That burning poyſon ne're effected harme,</l>
               <l>Although confected with a Magicke charme.</l>
               <l>How many treaſons, direfull accidents,</l>
               <l>Baſe-bred complots and experiments,</l>
               <l>Conſpir'd her death; yet ſtill preſeru'd was ſhe</l>
               <l>By heau'ns eternall <hi>Triple-Vnitie?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How many ſtriu'd to ſtop <hi>Elizaes</hi> breath?</l>
               <l>Yet (to their ſhame) ſhe died a liuing death;</l>
               <l>For which we laud th'Immortall Deitie,</l>
               <l>Who mixeth ioy with ſad calamitie.</l>
               <l>Her fame on earth is painted by all <hi>Seuen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her corps in Lead, her ſoule a Saint in heauen.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eliza</hi> liu'd, now is <hi>Eliza</hi> dead,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Dauid</hi> rais'd in her Angellike ſtead;</l>
               <l>Shee's quite extinct, yet hath ſhe left behind</l>
               <l>The true <hi>Idaa</hi> of her princely mind;</l>
               <l>Right royall IAMES, the <hi>Britons</hi> gracious King,</l>
               <l>Whoſe honor through the circling Globe doth ring.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Roſe</hi> is cropt which gliſtered in each face,</l>
               <l>And yet as faire ſprung inſtantly in place:</l>
               <l>A <hi>Roſe</hi> moſt ſweet and odoriferous,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Roſe</hi> of grace to cheare and comfort vs;</l>
               <l>A <hi>Roſe</hi> that ſpringeth in a Northerne blaſt,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Roſe</hi> whoſe luſtre doth in Winter laſt.</l>
               <l>O Wonder: that rough <hi>Boreas</hi> dropping wing,</l>
               <l>Should waft ſuch ſhowres to a deſired Spring!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>England,</hi> proſtrate thy ſelfe with folded hands,</l>
               <l>(Whoſe ioyes are numberleſſe euen as the ſands)</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19185:12"/>
               <l>Before the powerfull and almightie Throne,</l>
               <l>Who gaue regard vnto thy grieuous mone,</l>
               <l>Sending to thee ſuch an <hi>Athenian</hi> King,</l>
               <l>Whoſe learning is the round Orbes wondering:</l>
               <l>A ſoueraigne Balme vnto thy Coraſiue;</l>
               <l>Which did thy half-dead-wounded heart reuiue,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Phoebus</hi> Lute tuned his mournfull note,</l>
               <l>To make <hi>Time</hi> turne his gliſtring golden cote.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Couragious <hi>Cato</hi> with his warlike traines,</l>
               <l>While rang'd in rancke vpon the champion plaines,</l>
               <l>Sweet-breathed <hi>Zephyrus</hi> vp ſoftly blew</l>
               <l>The fragrant flowers which in medowes grew,</l>
               <l>Vpon their glittering targets: then they cride:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aglorious Triumph ſhall to vs betide.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Euen ſo the Flowers of fruitfull <hi>Brittanie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Blowne with the wind of zealous Loyaltie)</l>
               <l>Did congregate in troupes, proclaim'd a King,</l>
               <l>Whoſe name once heard, moſt gladſom ioy did bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When glorious <hi>Titan</hi> hath his compaſſe run,</l>
               <l>The foule-maskt gloomie Night enſues thereon;</l>
               <l>Bright <hi>Sol</hi> declin'd, <hi>Luna</hi> skips in the skie,</l>
               <l>Approou'd by Nature in <hi>Philoſophie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Iehoua derogated <hi>Englands</hi> Light,</l>
               <l>And yet purſude no duskie darkſome Night;</l>
               <l>No ſooner <hi>Britaine</hi> had her bright-Eye loſt,</l>
               <l>But ſtraight another gaz'd from Northern coaſt:</l>
               <l>No ſooner did <hi>Eliza</hi> take her flight,</l>
               <l>But inſtantly king IAMES appear'd in ſight:</l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19185:12"/>
               <l>For whom true hearts render immortall praiſe</l>
               <l>To high Iehoua, who this Starre did raiſe</l>
               <l>To yeeld them light, to ſtand their ſoueraigne Lord,</l>
               <l>And Patron pure of the ſoule-ſauing word.</l>
               <l>(O bleſſed Time, when peereleſſe Princes preach,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Dauid</hi> doth his ſonne Gods precepts teach!)</l>
               <l>He is the ſenſe-concluding Period</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Englands</hi> ſolace, charactred by God;</l>
               <l>The pure quinteſſence of her flouriſhing ſtate,</l>
               <l>To whom her life is worthie ſubiugate.</l>
               <l>O what a learned <hi>Varro</hi> hath ſhe gain'd,</l>
               <l>(Who mou'd blith <hi>Gelos</hi> euen when harts complaind)</l>
               <l>A <hi>Cicero</hi> for flowing Eloquence,</l>
               <l>A valiant <hi>Caeſar</hi> for Magnificence.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Don Phoebus</hi> riſing from his ſcarlet bed,</l>
               <l>Out of his eaſterne Cloſet thruſt his head;</l>
               <l>Spreading his flame-hair'd broad vermilion lockes,</l>
               <l>Vpon the earth, the ſea, the trees and rockes;</l>
               <l>Eſpide a fairer ſhining here below,</l>
               <l>Pluckt in his head, no more his face durſt ſhow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now <hi>England, England,</hi> ſhake off ſad annoy,</l>
               <l>Thy forts are full repleniſhed with ioy;</l>
               <l>Let all thy Turrets gliſter in the aire,</l>
               <l>Thy Faire not turn'd to fowle, but Fowle to faire.</l>
               <l>Now boaſt thy ſelfe amidſt thy ſommers Pride,</l>
               <l>Thy Ebbe's transformd into a flowing Tide</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Mirth</hi> and <hi>Gladneſſe:</hi> honor God for ay,</l>
               <l>Who turn'd thy Night into a Sun-ſhine Day.</l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19185:13"/>
               <l>What greater graces to thee could he bring,</l>
               <l>Then grace thy Land with ſuch a gracious King?</l>
               <l>Who lends an eare to euery clients crie,</l>
               <l>Decides his caſe with princely Grauitie.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lycurgus</hi>-like hath he preſcrib'd his lawes,</l>
               <l>To keepe poore <hi>Codrus</hi> out of <hi>Croeſus</hi> iawes;</l>
               <l>He ſuccour ſends to all oppreſt by Might,</l>
               <l>Defends true <hi>Irus,</hi> and maintaines his right.</l>
               <l>By him thou reapſt the wiſhed fruites of peace;</l>
               <l>And for his ſake God giues thee huge increaſe</l>
               <l>Of thy fat harueſt and thy wel-til'd fields,</l>
               <l>Thy withered Plants do bud, and bloſſome yeelds.</l>
               <l>For <hi>Phoebus</hi> Lute deſcants a gladſome note,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whereat Time skips, and turnes his ſable Cote.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What if th' Almightie had ſtretch't out his hand,</l>
               <l>To ſcourge Impietie within thy Land;</l>
               <l>And raz'd thy walles with flat confuſion,</l>
               <l>With ciuill broiles and proud Rebellion.</l>
               <l>Then had thy famous Cities gone to wracke,</l>
               <l>And euery towne bene ſubiect to the ſacke:</l>
               <l>Then Rigor would haue rul'd and borne the ſway,</l>
               <l>Reaſon exil'd and baniſht quite away.</l>
               <l>Then would the mother dread her dreadleſſe child:</l>
               <l>Then ſpotleſſe virgins would haue bene defil'd.</l>
               <l>All theſe (O <hi>London</hi>) to thy extreme paine,</l>
               <l>With preſent ſpoile wert likely to ſuſtaine:</l>
               <l>Then hadſt thou languiſht in th'effuſion</l>
               <l>Of bloudie murther and occiſion:</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19185:13"/>
               <l>Then <hi>Phoebus</hi> Lute a <hi>Threnos</hi> would haue ſtrained;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Time with teares his golden veſtments ſtained.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Me thinke I heare the wailefull weeping cries,</l>
               <l>Of wretched Dames in dreadfull miſeries:</l>
               <l>Me thinke I heare the thundring Canons ſound,</l>
               <l>Whoſe bullets gainſt the battred walles rebound:</l>
               <l>Me thinke I ſee huge troupes of gliſtring ſhields,</l>
               <l>And courſing Palfreys trampling ore the fields:</l>
               <l>Me thinke I ſee how ſouldiers wounded lye</l>
               <l>With gaſping breath, and yet they cannot dye.</l>
               <l>But heau'ns great King to thee propitious,</l>
               <l>In lieu of <hi>Mars</hi> ſent graces wonderous;</l>
               <l>Permitting ſtill his Light to ſhine with thee,</l>
               <l>That thou mightſt walke in perſpicuitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Romes</hi> Minotaure, that monſtrous enemie</l>
               <l>To braue <hi>Britanniaes</hi> peereleſſe Progenie;</l>
               <l>In rancor guzled for his annuall food,</l>
               <l>T'imbrue his throate with <hi>Innocencies</hi> blood;</l>
               <l>Whetting his blacke exacuated fangs,</l>
               <l>To murther ſacred ſoules with tortring pangs:</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Albions Theſeus</hi> with his conquering hand,</l>
               <l>Redeem'd her ſtate from tributarie band;</l>
               <l>And ſlue this Beaſt diſtent with irefull fell,</l>
               <l>Grapling with death in his prodigious cell:</l>
               <l>By <hi>Ioues</hi> decree reduc'd her Babes away,</l>
               <l>So wan the loue of heau'ns <hi>Paſiphaë.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Adopted <hi>England,</hi> ſweet <hi>Elyſian</hi> Ile,</l>
               <l>Obſerue, how God reuiewes with a ſmile;</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19185:14"/>
               <l>Accumulates a ſympathie of ioy,</l>
               <l>To countervaile thy late-ſuſtain'd annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Remember, that twice twentie winters told,</l>
               <l>Thou neuer taſtedſt of that freezing cold,</l>
               <l>And indigence of true Religion,</l>
               <l>To thee oblig'd by perfect vnion:</l>
               <l>Mercie hath ſet a ſuperſedeas free</l>
               <l>On Iuſtice, which conuicts Iniquitie:</l>
               <l>So loth is Heau'n to take reuenge of ſin,</l>
               <l>Grants thee more ſpacious walkes to ſolace in;</l>
               <l>Reuiues thy ſapleſſe Trees which withering dide,</l>
               <l>Thy wals of Grace with Truth reediſide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Euen as the Parent educates his child,</l>
               <l>By obſecrations and corrections mild,</l>
               <l>To fraught his ſoule with filiall reuerence,</l>
               <l>Extenuates Rigor by ſweet Indulgence:</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill if he progreſſe in luſts content,</l>
               <l>Then he inflicts a triple puniſhment.</l>
               <l>So doth th'Almightie powerfully intice</l>
               <l>Thy feet to walke in heau'ns faire Paradiſe,</l>
               <l>And foſters thee with nurcing milke of life,</l>
               <l>Which yeelds an end to endleſſe terrene ſtrife.</l>
               <l>His glorious eye, <hi>Scrutator</hi> of thy hart,</l>
               <l>Delighting not to view thy ruthleſſe ſmart;</l>
               <l>Protracts reuenge to thy affections luſt,</l>
               <l>As though the Iudge forgetteth to be iuſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Numbers of daies haſt thou poſſeſt the light</l>
               <l>Of his pure Goſpell in thee ſhining bright;</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19185:14"/>
               <l>And now t'enrich thee from his treaſures ſtore,</l>
               <l>Hath caus'd it ſhine farre clearer then before.</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill thou lieſt in darke Obſcuritie,</l>
               <l>Wrapt in the depth of Senſualitie;</l>
               <l>Repugnantly, with <hi>Aeſops</hi> frozen Snake,</l>
               <l>Reiects his mercies and his grace forſake:</l>
               <l>Spurning the Clemencie which he hath ſhowne,</l>
               <l>To monſtrous crimes &amp; deepe tranſgreſſions knowne</l>
               <l>And moſt perſpicuous to his piercing Eye,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vindicta's</hi> battering gainſt the loſtie skie.</l>
               <l>Thou ſufferedſt <hi>Vertue</hi> in thine iron age,</l>
               <l>To tread the loneleſſe path to Hermitage:</l>
               <l>For which his heauie Iudgement foorth did flie,</l>
               <l>To counterchecke that great Solemnitie,</l>
               <l>Which thou eſteemedſt at ſo high a rate,</l>
               <l>And conſonant with Kings renowmed ſtate;</l>
               <l>Farre diſſonant to thy expected Fame,</l>
               <l>Who ſtill aſpires to dignifie her name.</l>
               <l>Conſider how he hath ſtretch'd out his hand,</l>
               <l>To ſcourge the Mother-citie of thy land,</l>
               <l>Breaking her ſinewes by diuine Pretence,</l>
               <l>With fierie ſhafts of feuer Peſtilence:</l>
               <l>Withered her Flowers with blaſting-venim'daire,</l>
               <l>Driuing her vp-growne Trees to trembling Feare.</l>
               <l>His arrowes ſharpe in euery corner flie,</l>
               <l>And euery ſtreet did wound outragiouſly;</l>
               <l>In furie ſmiting father, ſonne, andall,</l>
               <l>None could eſchue the ſtroke of ſudden fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19185:15"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Euen as the <hi>Tygreſſe</hi> rauening for her food,</l>
               <l>In furious rage doth range alongſt the wood;</l>
               <l>Who in ſome darkſome denne hath long bene pent</l>
               <l>From meat and ſuſtenance, which makes herrent</l>
               <l>And teare the next ſhee meeteth by the way,</l>
               <l>As nothing partiall, ſo ſhe gaines a pray.</l>
               <l>Euen ſo this Plague, the Tygreſſe fierce of heau'n,</l>
               <l>Such lethall wounds, ſuch large aſſaults haue giu'n;</l>
               <l>Conſuming, ſeuering, midſt the hugeſt throng,</l>
               <l>The youth from age, the aged from the young:</l>
               <l>Inſatiatly deuour'd in euery place;</l>
               <l>None could perſiſt fore her contagious face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O heauie <hi>England,</hi> now behold and ſee,</l>
               <l>Thy Beautie ſtricken with the leproſie</l>
               <l>Of blaſphemies, imbrac'd without regard:</l>
               <l>To whom the Lord hath ſent a iuſt reward.</l>
               <l>Thy grieuous ſins with dreadfull noyſe did crie</l>
               <l>For iuſt Reuenge vnto his Maieſtie;</l>
               <l>Who can both ſtrike and heale, preſerue and wound,</l>
               <l>Erect thy wals, or raze them to the ground.</l>
               <l>How many wonders for thee hath he wrought?</l>
               <l>How many heau'nly Leſſons thee hath taught</l>
               <l>T'aſſwage thy arrogance, ſuppreſſe thy hate?</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill thou ſtandeſt in a fearefull ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As he reduc'd his choſen <hi>Iſraell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From ſauage cruelties of <hi>Egypts</hi> fell;</l>
               <l>When they were plung'd in perils dangerous,</l>
               <l>At his commaund (O wonder maruellous)</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:19185:15"/>
               <l>On either ſide the barking billowes ſtood,</l>
               <l>Whilſt that they marched through the brinie flood,</l>
               <l>When their purſuing foes would them haue ſlaine,</l>
               <l>Were ouerwhelm'd amidſt the troubled Maine:</l>
               <l>Yet did they murmure in the Wilderneſſe,</l>
               <l>As too vngratefull for their rare ſucceſſe.</l>
               <l>But heau'ns iuſt Iudge incens'd with wrathfull ire,</l>
               <l>Powrd foorth his plagues vpon their vaine deſire;</l>
               <l>While they tooke repaſt on their luſtfull will,</l>
               <l>Vile venimous beaſts their grauer age did kill.</l>
               <l>Euen thus (ô <hi>England</hi>) God hath dealt with thee,</l>
               <l>Conducting thee through ſeas of miſerie;</l>
               <l>Redeem'd thy Race from rage of forraine ſpoile,</l>
               <l>Caſting thy foes to baſe-diſhonor'd foile:</l>
               <l>Yet all theſe graces not incite thy hart,</l>
               <l>With humbleneſſe to cure thy cureleſſe ſmart;</l>
               <l>Demurres thy dayes in dilatorie care</l>
               <l>Of worldly luſts, which Heau'n will neuer ſpare:</l>
               <l>But in thy heighth of pompe and iolitie,</l>
               <l>The maſſacring Angell came to viſite thee;</l>
               <l>Slaughtring thy people with reuengefull ſword,</l>
               <l>The Harbinger of Death ſent from the Lord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe ſad euents aroſe and came to paſſe,</l>
               <l>As it befell to old <hi>Diagoras;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who when his ſons th'<hi>Olympian</hi> games had won,</l>
               <l>Caſting their garlands in their Trophees done</l>
               <l>About his necke: the mens applauding voyce,</l>
               <l>And rare delight did make his heart reioyce:</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:19185:16"/>
               <l>But while his ſoule repleat with chearefull grace,</l>
               <l>Was ſtung by Death ere he mou'd from the place.</l>
               <l>Euen ſo whilſt thou in Pleaſures gardens ſtood,</l>
               <l>Thy ſiluer lakes were turn'd to brookes of bloud;</l>
               <l>Thy flouds of ioyes were turn'd to ſeas of teares,</l>
               <l>And lightſome Mirth to interrupting Feares.</l>
               <l>Thus caſt from top of climing Dignitie,</l>
               <l>Into the depth of darkeſt miſerie;</l>
               <l>The hungrie Earth deuour'd thee vp, alas,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> was:</l>
               <l>Thy Anthemes, Trophees, and thy Excellence,</l>
               <l>Were ſwallowed vp by ſtarued Peſtilence:</l>
               <l>Thou wert conſum'd with Death on euery ſide,</l>
               <l>As bold <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> was amidſt his pride.</l>
               <l>Nought but <hi>Threnodiae</hi> danc'd amidſt thy throng,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whereat Time wet his cheekes, and ſlunke along.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Corrupted <hi>London,</hi> Sinke of Surquedrie,</l>
               <l>Thou that ſupports this yoke of miſerie,</l>
               <l>Impos'd vpon thee by th'Almightie Lord,</l>
               <l>For the reiecting of his ſacred word.</l>
               <l>His Minaces brought no remorce to thee;</l>
               <l>But ſleptſt ſecure in beds of Luxurie,</l>
               <l>Feeding thy Will with Pleaſures luſtfull beite,</l>
               <l>Did caſt thy Soule the huskes of ſlie Deceit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Prophet <hi>Ionah,</hi> Troubler of the ſea,</l>
               <l>Sent by heau'ns King to ſinfull <hi>Niniue:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So ſoone as he approch'd her ſtreets ſo wide,</l>
               <l>With vehement ſpeech in vengefull ſpirit cride:</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:19185:16"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>O Niniueh, thy monſtrous facts auoyde,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In fortie dayes elſe ſhalt thou be destroyde.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then King and Commons ioyntly did agree,</l>
               <l>With humbled hearts and zealous feruencie,</l>
               <l>In mourning ſackcloth ſeriouſly to pray</l>
               <l>The worlds chiefe Iudge, his burning wrath to ſtay:</l>
               <l>(The brutiſh <hi>Animals</hi> which harmeleſſe be,</l>
               <l>VVere taxed with this generall penaltie)</l>
               <l>VVith bleeding ſoules and drearie countenance,</l>
               <l>The glorie of the Higheſt did aduance;</l>
               <l>Sincerely turning to Submiſſion,</l>
               <l>That he might turne from them Deſtruction:</l>
               <l>So ſweet attonement Mournings did affoord,</l>
               <l>Reſtrain'd the ſtroke of his two-edged ſword.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not fortie dayes, but fortie yeares and more,</l>
               <l>(Wherein thou mightſt thy grieuous ſinnes deplore)</l>
               <l>Thouſands of <hi>Ionahs</hi> ſent by heau'ns great Lord,</l>
               <l>In thee reſolu'd to preach his ſacred word.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bonarges</hi> thundering in euery ſtreet;</l>
               <l>Thy deafe-charm'd ſins would not his voice regreet;</l>
               <l>But Mole-like plung'd in ſlauiſh Luſts content,</l>
               <l>On which the Lord inflicts a puniſhment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As wiſe <hi>Martha,</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> Propheteſſe,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Marius</hi> caried through his wars ſucceſſe;</l>
               <l>By Necromancie in her Sacrifice,</l>
               <l>Preſag'd the trophees of his victories:</l>
               <l>But once not tolerating her aduice,</l>
               <l>He bought the day (too deare) with bloudie price.</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:19185:17"/>
               <l>So God hath ſent his Angels from aboue,</l>
               <l>Still to be reſident with his ſacred loue;</l>
               <l>Preaching the tidings of celeſtiall Ioy,</l>
               <l>Which warres nor peſtilence can ere deſtroy:</l>
               <l>He conquered Death, and in his conquering brought</l>
               <l>Life in thy death; yet thou ſetſt him at nought:</l>
               <l>Till he in wrath thy ſtubburnneſſe conuicts:</l>
               <l>On grieuous ſins, moſt grieuous plagues inflicts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Foule noyſome crimes in euery corner ſwarme,</l>
               <l>Deadly-infectious wickedneſſe doth harme:</l>
               <l>In euery houſe and looſe-led Families,</l>
               <l>Are foſtred vp theſe dainn'd enormities;</l>
               <l>Theſe take their place as chiefe, commanding all</l>
               <l>Amongſt thy precepts Oeconomicall:</l>
               <l>Pride, Murther, Auarice, Vſurie, Deceipt,</l>
               <l>With ſauage Sodomie, hels alluring baite;</l>
               <l>Blaſting Blaſphemie, Rape and Crueltie:</l>
               <l>Theſe are the Actors in thy Tragedie:</l>
               <l>Shrowding Tractates of viperous Poperie,</l>
               <l>Vnder the ſhades of ciuill Pollicie,</l>
               <l>Reiects the tidings of heau'ns Meſſengers,</l>
               <l>And quite ſubuerts the ſacred Miniſters.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy Widowes mourne oppreſt by cruell might:</l>
               <l>Thy Orphanes weepe, diſ-franchis'd of their right:</l>
               <l>Thy Trades Mechanicall are tax'd ſo hie</l>
               <l>With Rent and Leaſe they fall to penurie:</l>
               <l>With craft thou grindſt the faces of the poore,</l>
               <l>To feed thee fat, while they ſtarue at thy doore.</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:19185:17"/>
               <l>Thou ſitſt in ſilke and coſtly ſoft array,</l>
               <l>And viewes thy brother periſhing in the way,</l>
               <l>With pinching cold lye ſhiuering on the ground;</l>
               <l>To ſow him coates no <hi>Dorcas</hi> can be found.</l>
               <l>When thou perceiu'ſt thy friends Extremitie</l>
               <l>Traduc'd to Want by Fortunes caſualtie:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neſcio,</hi> thou' crieſt, no Mercie canſt thou ſhow,</l>
               <l>No ſtreames of Pitie from thy heart will flow:</l>
               <l>To his penurious Lacke no ſuccours ſends:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When wealth declines, thy flattering friendſhip ends.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Xanthippus</hi> dogge condemnes thy ſauageneſſe,</l>
               <l>Who, when his maſter iourneyed on the ſeas,</l>
               <l>Swam by his ſhip euen from the ſhoarie ſand,</l>
               <l>Till he arriu'd in <hi>Salamina's</hi> land;</l>
               <l>And left him not till he the citie ſpied,</l>
               <l>With wearied lims then laid him downe and died.</l>
               <l>Thy Friend thou leaueſt in his deepe Diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Wrapt in the waues of endleſſe Carefulneſſe:</l>
               <l>Scorning Compaſſion, no Comfort bring;</l>
               <l>But as the <hi>Swallow,</hi> Herald of the Spring,</l>
               <l>Will ſing with vs while Sommers beautie laſts;</l>
               <l>But takes her flight when Winter breath's his blaſts.</l>
               <l>So while his Sommers-flouriſhing wealth doth flow,</l>
               <l>Moſt firme in Friendſhip thou thy ſelfe wilt ſhow;</l>
               <l>And wilt conuerſe in ſmooth-fram'd words each day,</l>
               <l>Thy toung pronounce ſuppos'd <hi>Apocripha:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When Fortunes freezing frownes benum his ſtore,</l>
               <l>Thou art a Stranger, he thy Friend no more.</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19185:18"/>
               <l>Thus weakeſt Wants the ſmalleſt Succors gaine,</l>
               <l>The nakedſt Need the lateſt Helps obtaine:</l>
               <l>How true is that which may be anſwered then?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>More kindneſſe oft is ſhowne by Dogs, the Men.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou ſtudieſt ſtill <hi>Inuention</hi> to ſuffice,</l>
               <l>And deckſt thy ſelfe like <hi>Protean</hi> Prodigies,</l>
               <l>In monſtrous ſhapes, and gariſh rude attire,</l>
               <l>Deuotes thy ſoule to ſwelling <hi>Prides</hi> deſire;</l>
               <l>In worldy ioyes conſumeſt euery day,</l>
               <l>With Zeale affoording ſcarce an houre to pray.</l>
               <l>That chriſtall Ice, which lends my bodie light,</l>
               <l>Hath bene diſſolu'd to teares, depriu'd of ſight;</l>
               <l>My hart-ſtrings broke with dolorous complaint,</l>
               <l>My ſoule hath mourn'd in forcible conſtraint;</l>
               <l>When I haue ambulated longſt the ſtreet,</l>
               <l>And oft this Monſter haue I chanc'd to meet:</l>
               <l>A <hi>Britaine</hi> borne, bedight <hi>Castilian</hi>-wiſe,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Ganle</hi> in ſhape, a <hi>Thuſcane</hi> in diſguiſe;</l>
               <l>His brauerie lin'd with enuious <hi>Pride;</hi> at leaſt</l>
               <l>A Man in forme, in facts a brutiſh Beaſt.</l>
               <l>O that<note n="*" place="margin">Semper la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrimabat.</note> 
                  <hi>Heraclitus</hi> were reſident,</l>
               <l>To powre foorth ſtreames of teares in ſad lament,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Albions</hi> virgins, who from Grace do ſlide,</l>
               <l>Surpaſſing <hi>Sions</hi> Daughters in their pride;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Prides</hi> ſhop it ſelfe full fraught with Fopperie,</l>
               <l>May patterns draw from their Varietie.</l>
               <l>As <hi>Helens</hi> ſhape, (the wofull wracke of <hi>Troy</hi>)</l>
               <l>Was brauely limned by <hi>Apelles</hi> boy,</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19185:18"/>
               <l>In rich attire, and ſumptuous ſhining gold;</l>
               <l>Yet foule in face, not amorous to behold.</l>
               <l>So ſome reſemble <hi>Helens</hi> picture here,</l>
               <l>That bigly brag in gorgeous garments deare;</l>
               <l>But nothing beautifull to <hi>Reaſons</hi> eye,</l>
               <l>Patch the defects of Natures pouertie;</l>
               <l>Adorne with ſilkes, infuſe them with perfumes,</l>
               <l>Like ietting birds bedeckt with others plumes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How canſt thou thinke (thy ſins growne vp ſo hie)</l>
               <l>With hapleſſe hope t'eſcape Impunitie?</l>
               <l>Canſt thou reſolue, that God will ſpare his hand,</l>
               <l>To view ſuch <hi>Hydra's</hi> foſtred in thy Land?</l>
               <l>No, no, his Wrath conſumes like ſmoking fire,</l>
               <l>Thou lieſt as Flaxe before his burning ire;</l>
               <l>He'le crop thee of from full Maturitie,</l>
               <l>And caſt thee foorth to bitter Miſerie.</l>
               <l>At his command, the ſword ſhall ruinate,</l>
               <l>Thy gates ſhall mourne, and ſtreets be deſolate,</l>
               <l>Thy Citie grone, enthral'd with deepe diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iim</hi> howle within thy Pallaces:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Satyres</hi> and <hi>Apes</hi> ſhall dance within thy bowers,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oſtriges</hi> and <hi>Scrich owles</hi> crie in ruinous towers:</l>
               <l>No voyce of <hi>man</hi> on thy wals ſhalt thou heare,</l>
               <l>Nor light of lampe in any houſe appeare.</l>
               <l>Heau'ns grant thy heart t'affect and feare this ſo,</l>
               <l>As that thou neuer feele or taſt this Wo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy children deare in their quotidian ſport,</l>
               <l>Blaſphemouſly the name of <hi>God</hi> extort;</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:19185:19"/>
               <l>Their battring oaths againſt the heau'ns rebound;</l>
               <l>This hideous noiſe in houſe and ſtreet doth ſound.</l>
               <l>They ſcoffe <hi>Eliſha</hi> in decrepit age,</l>
               <l>With arrogance reuile the graue and ſage;</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Ioue</hi> ſent foorth a ſhe-Beare from his wood,</l>
               <l>To gormandize on their decocted bloud.</l>
               <l>How earneſtly thou ſtriu'ſt (for their defence)</l>
               <l>To curbe them from contagious Peſtilence;</l>
               <l>For their ſoules health thou neuer takeſt care:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such as the Parents, ſuch the Children are.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy Trades-men watch to vndermine each other,</l>
               <l>And early riſe to circumuent their brother,</l>
               <l>In buying, ſelling, traffiquing for gaines;</l>
               <l>By which poore <hi>Truth</hi> impoueriſhment ſuſtaines.</l>
               <l>Thy head-ſtrong Seruants impudently ſtray</l>
               <l>From ſin to ſin, vpon the Sabbath day,</l>
               <l>Heaping vp Miſchiefes on themſelues and thee,</l>
               <l>Plucke on their heads earths iuſt Calamitie.</l>
               <l>Theſe are the ſwords of Deſolation,</l>
               <l>Theſe are the Agents in ſubuerſion,</l>
               <l>Theſe are contagious Plagues, diſeaſed, foule;</l>
               <l>Theſe are the ſores and botches of thy ſoule,</l>
               <l>Theſe are ordures which noyſomneſſe affoord</l>
               <l>Vp to the noſthrils of the glorious Lord:</l>
               <l>Theſe are the Scourges of thy leud offence;</l>
               <l>Theſe are th'Inductors of heau'ns Peſtilence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O <hi>London,</hi> then what terror wert to ſee</l>
               <l>Thy ſtreets exempt of popularities?</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:19185:19"/>
               <l>And nought but cries and dolefull horrors yeeld,</l>
               <l>Ore-growne with graſſe as in the verdant field:</l>
               <l>The maſter from his ſeruant ſnatch'd away,</l>
               <l>The ſeruant from his maſter bearing ſway:</l>
               <l>The children fatherleſſe each where were found,</l>
               <l>The fathers childleſſe in deepe Dolor drown'd:</l>
               <l>The husband from his neare-eſpouſed wife,</l>
               <l>The truſtfull friend bereaued of his life:</l>
               <l>No kinſman ſcaping to interre his brother,</l>
               <l>Not one ſcarce left to mourne and weepe for other.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy tender Virgins ſprung from Natures grace,</l>
               <l>(Who once adorn'd and beautifide the face</l>
               <l>Of all thy ſtreets, with roſiall viſage bright,</l>
               <l>As ſplendant Stars, a cleare and glorious Night:)</l>
               <l>Beſmear'd their pure and proper Lineaments,</l>
               <l>With ſcalding Sighs, and pitifull Complaints:</l>
               <l>Their Feature deck't with diffidentall Feares,</l>
               <l>And drown'd in ſalt vnceſſant-flowing Teares.</l>
               <l>Thy Youth howl'd out, amaz'd themſelues to ſee</l>
               <l>Bereft of Vigor and Validitie.</l>
               <l>Thy ramparts mouln'd, thy gates condol'd their ſtate,</l>
               <l>Becauſe no ſtranger ingreſſe ſought thereat,</l>
               <l>To view thy ſtately Towers at ſolemne Feaſts,</l>
               <l>Repleniſh'd then with Owles and lothſome Beaſts.</l>
               <l>Thy paths breath'd ſighes which did vntrampled lie,</l>
               <l>No huge Recourſe or Concourſe walk'd thereby;</l>
               <l>Nor ſcarce one foot-ſtep figured on their face,</l>
               <l>But clinging Brambles did vſurpe their place.</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:19185:20"/>
               <l>Thy ſtreets which once with gloriouſneſſe did ſhow,</l>
               <l>Kneel'd as Homagers to ſolitarie <hi>We;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where noble States obtain'd moſt free acceſſe,</l>
               <l>Reſembled then the vaſt of Wilderneſſe.</l>
               <l>Thy ſelfe diſt weepe, yea weep in mournfull wiſe,</l>
               <l>And faire <hi>Aurora</hi> viſited with thy cries,</l>
               <l>And from thy bitter anguiſh could not ceaſe,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Veſper</hi> drew to his declining eaſe.</l>
               <l>Each bird and beaſt with tranquile ſleepe poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>When Night appear'd, imbrac'd their vſuall reſt:</l>
               <l>But thou conſumdſt the day in deepe Complaints,</l>
               <l>Diſturbdſt the night with loathſome Languiſhments;</l>
               <l>Thy Eyes like two deepe Fountaines ay did run,</l>
               <l>Whoſe brinie ſprings and ſtreames could not be done.</l>
               <l>Thy friends admir'd at thy diſeaſes fowle,</l>
               <l>As fluttring birds flie wondring bout the Owle:</l>
               <l>Amidſt thy griefes thy Louers thee forſake,</l>
               <l>Fled from thy ſight, as from an Aſpe or Snake:</l>
               <l>Thy foes reioyc'd at this confuſion,</l>
               <l>Vſing theſe termes with proud deriſion:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is this that Mirror, reuerenced with dutie?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Surnam'd, The full perfection of BEAVTIE?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then hiſs'd with hate, and clapt their hands to ſee</l>
               <l>Thy Glorie ſpurn'd by pale Perplexitie.</l>
               <l>Thus Wo was drawne thy badge, and Want thy creſt,</l>
               <l>And hungrie Famine did thy skirts inueſt:</l>
               <l>(For ſhee's the hand-maid of Calamitie,</l>
               <l>Attending ſtill on common Miſerie.)</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:19185:20"/>
               <l>Thy tender infants young did gaſpe halfe-dead</l>
               <l>In mothers armes, for indigence of bread:</l>
               <l>Thy worthie Magiſtrates high-growne in age,</l>
               <l>Expected viols of <hi>Ioues</hi> ardent rage,</l>
               <l>To be powr'd foorth vpon them from aboue,</l>
               <l>To notattending on his ſacred loue.</l>
               <l>Grizly <hi>Thanatos</hi> ſlinked through each ſtreet,</l>
               <l>Waiting t'arreſt each perſon he did meet;</l>
               <l>Dragging him headlong to his centred caue,</l>
               <l>Out of whoſe mouth no man himſelfe can ſaue:</l>
               <l>In harſh diſcordant ſound each banefull Bell,</l>
               <l>Rung foorth a <hi>Requiem</hi> with his dolefull knell:</l>
               <l>No Proſpect oppoſite to thy blear'd eyes,</l>
               <l>But horrors, howlings, mournings, weepings, cries.</l>
               <l>Theſe are externall Plagues to ſecret ſin,</l>
               <l>And moſt tranſparant to entrap thee in;</l>
               <l>O theſe will driue each heart to hideous grones,</l>
               <l>Though moſt inflexible, as flintie ſtones.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The conſtellation of the twinkling ſtarres,</l>
               <l>Nor the foure Humors with diſcordant iarres;</l>
               <l>The reuolution of Comets bright,</l>
               <l>Nor corrupt Meteors blaſting in the night;</l>
               <l>Nor yet the welking of a <hi>Pleni-lune,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From whence, <hi>ſome</hi> do the cauſe of death aſſume:</l>
               <l>Nor diſtillations exhal'd by the Sunne,</l>
               <l>Falling in miſts, when <hi>Veſper</hi> hath begunne</l>
               <l>To draw his ſable Curtaines ore the skie,</l>
               <l>Could be th'Efficient of this Miſerie.</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:19185:21"/>
               <l>No ſecundarie Cauſe, nor all of theſe,</l>
               <l>Diſcuſs'd at large in <hi>Ephymerides:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Theſe are but Meanes, manag'd by heau'ns great King,</l>
               <l>Though without meanes <hi>he</hi> comprehends each thing:</l>
               <l>Alas, the venime of thy ſoules offence,</l>
               <l>Poyſon'd thy fleſh with viprous Peſtilence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Phiſitians Skill, nor <hi>Galens</hi> learned Art,</l>
               <l>To whom the Heau'ns deepe Secrecies impart,</l>
               <l>Could rightly cenſure, or diſcerne with eye,</l>
               <l>The nature of this venimous Qualitie.</l>
               <l>Strange are thy plagues, far ſtranger are thy crimes,</l>
               <l>Moſt ſtrangely nouriſhed in theſe moderne Times.</l>
               <l>Therefore the thought of this deuouring Smart,</l>
               <l>With feare may penetrate each Chriſtians heart:</l>
               <l>Deepe ſad Remorſe may aggrauate each one,</l>
               <l>To waile his ſins with ſad Contrition;</l>
               <l>T'admire this Plague with lamention,</l>
               <l>Lament in faith with admiration;</l>
               <l>Deeming his age the length of Natures ſpan,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Monarch now, to morrow not a Man.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou that didſt flie from Heau'ns conſuming ſpoile,</l>
               <l>To ſtand ſecure within the countries ſoile,</l>
               <l>Know, that this Plague deuour'd from Eaſt to Weſt,</l>
               <l>God ſtriketh where, and when he ſeemeth beſt.</l>
               <l>The thirſtie Sword doth watch without the gate,</l>
               <l>Within the wals fierce Peftilence laies waite,</l>
               <l>And boundleſſe Famine which tormenteth all;</l>
               <l>No path lies ſtraight to ſhun their deadly thrall.</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:19185:21"/>
               <l>Thy firme-built walles, thy viands, houſe and ground,</l>
               <l>Wherein thou wertſt inuelloped around;</l>
               <l>Thy purged Aires, and pleaſant Pallaces,</l>
               <l>Could not protect thee from this darke Diſtreſſe.</l>
               <l>If thou ſhouldſt run vp to the mountaines ſteepe,</l>
               <l>Downe to the wilderneſſe and deſerts deepe,</l>
               <l>Reſoluing there to dwell ſecure and free;</l>
               <l>He can purſue thee there with Miſerie:</l>
               <l>His Meſſengers more volatile then <hi>Thought,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fore thou canſt thinke, ſuch Accidents are wrought:</l>
               <l>In <hi>Sions</hi> Songs then <hi>Dauid</hi> ſingeth well:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heau'n can ore-take me if I runne to hell.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When thou reſolud'ſt by flight to ſcape his hand,</l>
               <l>Thy life and ſtate in deepeſt dangers ſtand.</l>
               <l>Like the <hi>Viator</hi> trauelling by the way,</l>
               <l>Who meetes a Beare out-ranging for her prey,</l>
               <l>Through vrgent paſſions ſhifteth from her clawes:</l>
               <l>Then ſtraight a Lion comes with wide-ſtretch'd iawes,</l>
               <l>To lacerate his fleſh, imbrude with gore,</l>
               <l>Which ſtrikes a deeper terror then before.</l>
               <l>Yet by good hap pleuents the Lions rage;</l>
               <l>And then with ioy holds on his pilgrimage:</l>
               <l>But drawing neare to his abiding place,</l>
               <l>(Fore-deeming not the Fates purſude in chace)</l>
               <l>When leaſt he thought of ſuch a timeleſſe ſmart,</l>
               <l>A Serpents ſting doth wound him to the hart.</l>
               <l>So when thou thinkſt to ſleepe in ſafeſt reſt,</l>
               <l>Then art thou by Gods iudgements moſt ſuppreſt:</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:19185:22"/>
               <l>His ſword can wound both woman, child, and man,</l>
               <l>From North to South, from <hi>Berſheba</hi> to <hi>Dan;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>T'is like a Shadow which a man eſchues,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Swifter he runs, the faster it purſues.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou great Soldado, earths Magnifico,</l>
               <l>That conquers ioy by <hi>Lazarello's</hi> wo,</l>
               <l>Heaping vp gold by each deceiptfull way,</l>
               <l>Reſoluing ſtill that thou ſhalt liue for ay;</l>
               <l>At firſt, thou ſprangſt from a ſmall wombe of Sin,</l>
               <l>At laſt, a litle graue ſhall cloſe thee in:</l>
               <l>Thou griping foole, the <hi>Peſtilence</hi> this night,</l>
               <l>Can wound thy corps, and burne thy hearts delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When king <hi>Liſymachus,</hi> through Fortunes hate,</l>
               <l>By thirſt proiected to the <hi>Scythians</hi> ſtate,</l>
               <l>And captiuated with his kingdomes all;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O heau'ns</hi> (quoth he) <hi>how dreadfull is my fall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To yeeld great Prouinces and regall ſeate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For liquide drops to quench my thirſtie heate.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So when thou rifeſt from eternall ſleepe,</l>
               <l>And viewes Heau'ns glorie from the cole-blacke Deep:</l>
               <l>Then wilt thou crie: <hi>O wretched creature I,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To loſe ſuch ioyes for carnall Vanitie;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For momentanie Pleaſures which decay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To miſſe heau'ns Grace, ſo permanent for ay!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then looke to Heau'n, whilſt thou on Earth doſt dwel,</l>
               <l>And not (with <hi>Diues</hi>) when thou lieſt in Hell.</l>
               <l>Too late, alas, to wiſh heau'ns glorious Light,</l>
               <l>When thou art wrapt in blacke eternall Night;</l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:19185:22"/>
               <l>When <hi>Time</hi> turnes off his partie-coloured cote,</l>
               <l>Thy ſoule in hell muſt howle a mournfull note.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou Vſurer, which Penurie doſt racke,</l>
               <l>And ſurfets in thy needfull neighbours lacke;</l>
               <l>Thy Debters watch with care, while thou doſt ſleepe;</l>
               <l>Thy State ſings <hi>Requiem,</hi> while their Senſes weepe:</l>
               <l>In nightly lucubrations ſpend their houres</l>
               <l>To puffe thy Spunge, which all the drops deuoures,</l>
               <l>Diſtilling from their browes with burd'nous griefe;</l>
               <l>Not able ſcarce to miniſter reliefe</l>
               <l>Vnto their children deare and familie:</l>
               <l>Becauſe thou ſuckeſt (with the ſluggiſh Bee)</l>
               <l>That Mel, which they in harbring hiues wold keepe;</l>
               <l>Clothing thy back, with wooll from their poore ſheep.</l>
               <l>What's this, but euen to kill and trucidate?</l>
               <l>And all man-ſlaughtrers, God and Angels hate.</l>
               <l>Thy ſtate is match'd with Lillies in the field,</l>
               <l>Which flouriſh now, and ſtraight to withring yeeld:</l>
               <l>Though thou in terrene Shadowes didſt excell,</l>
               <l>Yet ſhall not Gold redeeme thy ſoule from hell.</l>
               <l>Then let this Sentence in thy ſenſe remaine,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſweeteſt Pleaſures taſt the ſowreſt Paine:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quod<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tibi nolles, aliis feciſſe caueto:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quod<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tibi velles, aliis praeſtare ſtudeto.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou rauening Vultur, gormandizing Kite,</l>
               <l>Thou greedie Wolfe, which builds thy chiefe Delight</l>
               <l>On droſſe, and drinkes the bloud of Periurie,</l>
               <l>Feeding vpon the fleſh of Crueltie:</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19185:23"/>
               <l>Whoſe deep-delv'd throat of Gain deuours more food</l>
               <l>Then do the <hi>Amazons</hi> or <hi>Styrian</hi> brood.</l>
               <l>Thy dropſie-Conſcience ſweld with moiſt Deſire,</l>
               <l>The more it drinkes, the more doth ſtill require:</l>
               <l>Hunger torments thee midſt aboundant ſtore,</l>
               <l>Thou ſtaru'ſt in Wealth, in Riches ſtill art poore:</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Tantalus</hi> which in the <hi>Stygian</hi> lies,</l>
               <l>And ſinkes in water, yet for moiſture dies:</l>
               <l>Like drudging <hi>Indians,</hi> which dig with paine</l>
               <l>The golden Mines, yet others reape the gaine:</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Kine, who gormandiz'd vp cleane</l>
               <l>The fat-fed Beaſts, yet ſtill themſelues were leane.</l>
               <l>The Day thou ſpendeſt in turmoiling paine,</l>
               <l>Selling thy ſoule for temporarie gaine;</l>
               <l>In deepe of Night, thy mind extrauagates,</l>
               <l>And wanders through the perillous gulfes and ſtreits</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Ne're-enough;</hi> when good men take their reſt,</l>
               <l>Thy reſtleſſe Thoughts are toſt, with cares poſſeſt:</l>
               <l>Still pining <hi>Pietie,</hi> ſo leane in thee,</l>
               <l>As is the big-bon'd bare Anatomie.</l>
               <l>Thou planteſt thornes in thy ſoules barren field,</l>
               <l>Which nought but griefes and moleſtations yeeld;</l>
               <l>Whereby not onely <hi>Equitie</hi> is choked,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Vertue</hi> extirpated and reuoked;</l>
               <l>But alſo ſtinging pricks ſpring ſharpe and ſmall,</l>
               <l>That thou thy <hi>ſelfe</hi> art wounded therewithall:</l>
               <l>Yet thou perceiu'ſt not, <hi>All</hi> goes well with thee,</l>
               <l>So thou canſt pleaſe thy hearts Rapacitie,</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19185:23"/>
               <l>Which is inſatiat as Fire and Flood,</l>
               <l>The laſt drinkes Raine, the firſt deuours the Wood:</l>
               <l>Or big-bon'd <hi>Behemoth</hi> with vigour fraught,</l>
               <l>Who thought t'exhale deepe <hi>Iordan</hi> at a draught.</l>
               <l>Thus doſt thou ſing amidſt thy weeping woes,</l>
               <l>As moiles who feed with burdens and with blowes:</l>
               <l>What elſe remaines, thy ſenſes neuer ſee,</l>
               <l>(Profoundly caſt into a Lethargie</l>
               <l>Of <hi>deepe-Deſire</hi>) till Death appeares in ſight,</l>
               <l>Rowzing from ſleepe thy ſolide-ſlumbring ſprite.</l>
               <l>O then how fearefull will it ſeeme to thee,</l>
               <l>To be ſecluded from earths Vanitie!</l>
               <l>Thy death will be farre terribler then hell,</l>
               <l>Becauſe in life, true Life thou didſt diſpell:</l>
               <l>Moſt griping griefes and dolors ſhalt thou find,</l>
               <l>To loſe Earths <hi>Idol,</hi> which thou leau'ft behind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when the Sun-ſet of thy youth drawes neare,</l>
               <l>And occidentall Age begins t'appeare,</l>
               <l>Thoſe ill-got goods, which <hi>Auarice</hi> did intend</l>
               <l>To be preſeru'd, lewd <hi>Luxurie</hi> ſhall ſpend;</l>
               <l>That wealth whereon thy mouth did neuer taſt,</l>
               <l>Vnthriftie <hi>Ganeo</hi> ſhall conſume and waſt.</l>
               <l>Thus doth thy ſin incurre a double ſin,</l>
               <l>Wherto thy ſoule (fore heau'ns great Bar brought in)</l>
               <l>Shall anſwer as a thirſtie Murtherer,</l>
               <l>A ſwallowing Gulfe, a deepe Extortioner.</l>
               <l>Not all that wealth which thou haſt falſly won,</l>
               <l>Can baile thy ſoule from fierie <hi>Phlegeton;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:19185:24"/>
               <l>But will condemne thee in that dreadfull Day,</l>
               <l>And glutinate thy Soule with Hell for ay.</l>
               <l>O damned wretch, then fearefull is thy ſtate:</l>
               <l>Theſe words pronounc'd, Repentance haps too late:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abi, thou curſed to eternall fire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Imbrace the flames of due-deſerued hire.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then know: though ne're ſo ſweet Earths <hi>Syrens</hi> ſing,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An vpright Conſcience is a ſacred Thing.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As wormes cannot corrode the <hi>Laryx</hi> tree,</l>
               <l>Which neuer rots, nor ſcarce can burned be;</l>
               <l>So neither Hell nor Horror, Worme nor Sting,</l>
               <l>Can fret thy Conſcience guarded ſtrong within.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou that in <hi>Sickneſſe</hi> wilt thy ſins deplore,</l>
               <l>That neuer did imbrace good Thought before,</l>
               <l>Orat the obiect of a blazing <hi>Starre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fore-dooming, that ſome Iudgement is not farre,</l>
               <l>Wilt then to mournfull deprecations riſe;</l>
               <l>But being baniſh'd from thy reſtleſſe eyes,</l>
               <l>And nine dayes paſt, thou haſt recourſe amaine,</l>
               <l>With dogs and ſwine, vnto thy filth againe.</l>
               <l>But if thou wilt redeeme thy ſoule from hell,</l>
               <l>Weepe for thy ſins, and mourne whilſt thou art well:</l>
               <l>When Death hath ſtung, there is no time to pray,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But line in Death, or die in Life for ay.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou that ſurmounts in pompous dignitie,</l>
               <l>In Pleaſure, Beautie, Wealth, and Brauerie;</l>
               <l>In Luxurie thy precious Time doſt ſpend;</l>
               <l>Remember, that theſe Shadowes muſt haue end.</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:19185:24"/>
               <l>And that, from whence thou reapedſt chiefe delight,</l>
               <l>With loathſomneſſe ſhall worke thee worſt deſpite.</l>
               <l>Like to <hi>Tarpeia's</hi> bracelets bright of gold,</l>
               <l>For whom, with Guile the <hi>Romaines</hi> caſtell ſold</l>
               <l>Vnto the <hi>Sabines,</hi> won by trecherous Fate:</l>
               <l>But yet theſe bracelets brought her generall hate,</l>
               <l>Wherewith at laſt her ſelfe was preſt to death,</l>
               <l>And quite bereft of vitall ſenſe and breath.</l>
               <l>So Pleaſures preſſe thee downe to gauling Griefe,</l>
               <l>Or glance away, and leaue thee ſans reliefe;</l>
               <l>Like ranging Hawkes that ſoare in loftie skie,</l>
               <l>With ſwift-wing'd flight from Lure of Falkners hie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> that famous <hi>Grecian,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fau'ring faire <hi>Lais, Corinths</hi> Curtiſan;</l>
               <l>Moſt vehemently deſir'd (by Fanciefed)</l>
               <l>To haue acceſſe vnto her brothell bed:</l>
               <l>Whom ſhe deſir'd three hundred crownes to ſend,</l>
               <l>If luſtfull <hi>Will,</hi> her wiſh would apprehend:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>High heau'ns forbid</hi> (quoth he) <hi>that hote Deſire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Should heape ſuch flames to</hi> Pryaps <hi>burning fire:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Though Lust allures, yet doth true Vertue hate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To buy</hi> Repentance <hi>at ſo deare a rate.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This heathen Mole, had Reaſons eyes to ſee,</l>
               <l>That Paine attends on Pleaſures ſurquedrie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The buzzing <hi>Bee</hi> that ſings in Autumnes field,</l>
               <l>Doth from her labour, waxe and honie yeeld,</l>
               <l>Which to mans ſenſes, many comforts bring;</l>
               <l>Yet in her taile there lutkes an angrie ſting.</l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:19185:25"/>
               <l>So Pleaſure hath her hony of Deſire,</l>
               <l>Inflaming waxe diſſolu'd in Follies fire:</l>
               <l>But yet behind a dreadfull ſting remaines,</l>
               <l>Which wounds the heart, enwrapt with Fancies pains:</l>
               <l>Her meager ioynts are tentred on <hi>deepe Cares,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her vigor rack'd on <hi>imbecile Deſpaires:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Times</hi> reuolution frets her pleaſing prancks,</l>
               <l>As waters waſh and weare away their bancks.</l>
               <l>And as the dew from heau'n to earth aſſign'd,</l>
               <l>By heate exhal'd, or ſcattered with the wind:</l>
               <l>Or chriſtall bubbles which on riuers play,</l>
               <l>With agitation vaniſh quite away:</l>
               <l>Or Characters deciphered foorth on ſand,</l>
               <l>Which by Eluuion periſheth out of hand;</l>
               <l>So Earths mask'd Ioyes but for a moment laſt,</l>
               <l>And ſoone extinct by <hi>Times</hi> oft-changing blaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Peruſe the Songs of ſweet-toung'd <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iſraels</hi> great King, faire <hi>Iuda's</hi> Paragon,</l>
               <l>Sions <hi>Melodes,</hi> the ſourſe of Sapience,</l>
               <l>Bedewd with drops of ſacred influence;</l>
               <l>For whom the <hi>Sabian</hi> Queene did iourney farre,</l>
               <l>To view the ſplendor of ſo bright a Starre:</l>
               <l>When he had heaped millions vp of gold,</l>
               <l>Erected buildings glorious to behold;</l>
               <l>And planted trees, fed with ſweet fluent Springs,</l>
               <l>And treaſures won by captiuated Kings;</l>
               <l>And ſingers with harmonious melodie,</l>
               <l>Concording in <hi>Amphyons</hi> ſimphonie;</l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:19185:25"/>
               <l>And all delights which Reaſon could deuiſe,</l>
               <l>Were ſet as Obiects to his reſtleſſe eyes:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O vaine</hi> (quoth he) <hi>is all the Earths delight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But pictur'd Gloſſes, and diſturbe the Sprite:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I now diſcerne by Faiths celeſtiall eye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pleaſure's but vaine, moſt vaine, and Vanitie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For with <hi>Times-turne</hi> their ſemblant Beautie's gone,</l>
               <l>Whirl'd round with Change, as <hi>Syſiphus</hi> rolling ſtone.</l>
               <l>Thus mans Delights, and earths Felicities,</l>
               <l>Are but euen pleaſant-ſeeming <hi>Vanities.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In <hi>Turne</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> all Creatures ſhall decay,</l>
               <l>(For <hi>Time</hi> it ſelfe in time muſt paſſe away)</l>
               <l>The winged-people of the various Skie,</l>
               <l>The ſcalie Troupe which in the Surges lie;</l>
               <l>The heau'ns, the earth, and ſeas ſhall burne to nought:</l>
               <l>(Not to that <hi>Chaos,</hi> whence they firſt were brought)</l>
               <l>The Worlds great Synode formally combin'd,</l>
               <l>With pure celeſtiall <hi>Fire</hi> muſt be refin'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Don Phoebus</hi> Steeds their gliſtering coach muſt ſtay,</l>
               <l>The burniſh'd Gates include heau'ns <hi>Bright</hi> from Day,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Stars,</hi> and <hi>Phoebe's</hi> feuer-ſhaking Light,</l>
               <l>Shall maske their Beauties from the diſmall Night:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Comets, Meteors,</hi> with each <hi>Hemi-ſphaeare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To worke ſtrange Operations ſhall forbeare.</l>
               <l>Old white-hair'd <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> with ſtrikt compas'd pace,</l>
               <l>Muſt ceaſe to courſe his artificiall Race:</l>
               <l>The Sea, the Floud, the Spring, and watrie Lake,</l>
               <l>Muſt by <hi>Times turne</hi> their liquide Caues forſake,</l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:19185:26"/>
               <l>Which from the Ceſternes of the Center deepe,</l>
               <l>Through Earths wide Nerues in curbed maner creepe.</l>
               <l>The flouriſhing <hi>Ver,</hi> and fruitfull <hi>Autumnes</hi> grace,</l>
               <l>The icie Vizard of breme Winters face;</l>
               <l>The Yeare, the Month, the Houre, the Night, the Day,</l>
               <l>Shall ſubiect ſtand to <hi>Heau'ns</hi> Cataſtrophé:</l>
               <l>Heau'ns wondrous Works, which thus in ſtrictneſſe turne,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Pan</hi> appeares, in ſulphur'd flames muſt burne.</l>
               <l>All Wights that wander through this Orbe below,</l>
               <l>Muſt pay that ſumme which they to Nature ow:</l>
               <l>All muſt diſſolue, euen from the Cedar tall,</l>
               <l>Vnto the Hyſope, ſpringing on the wall,</l>
               <l>When heau'ns loud Trump ſhal ſound Earths ſumning note,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Time</hi> turnes off his rain-bow coloured cote.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But <hi>Ates</hi> brood, true Modell of the <hi>Maker,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That Angel-like of ioyes are made partaker;</l>
               <l>Indude with <hi>Reaſon,</hi> Dangers to eſchue,</l>
               <l>Iudicially <hi>Times</hi> Accidents to view:</l>
               <l>Caſting an eye to things paſt and forgone,</l>
               <l>To ſuprauiſe th'Euents enſuing on;</l>
               <l>By retrogredience to <hi>Times</hi> heighth and fall,</l>
               <l>In their progredience can diſcerne them all:</l>
               <l>Theſe that in portraiture all Shapes excell,</l>
               <l>Muſt mount to heau'n, or flutter downe to hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore let <hi>Reaſon</hi> feruently apply</l>
               <l>His ſoule to liue, as ſtill prepar'd to die;</l>
               <l>In all eſſayes his heart vprightly bend,</l>
               <l>As one that ſwiftly marcheth to his end:</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:19185:26"/>
               <l>Though he on Earth all worldly Pleaſures haue,</l>
               <l>Yet let him deeme one foot ſtill in the graue.</l>
               <l>The valiantſouldier marching longſt the plaine,</l>
               <l>Couragiouſly, to his immortall gaine,</l>
               <l>Aſſaults his foes, and neare to them doth come,</l>
               <l>Although moſt neare enſues his banefull doome;</l>
               <l>Swifter he marcheth them with blowes to ſpend,</l>
               <l>The ſwifter ſtill approcheth to his end:</l>
               <l>Deſire of Fame kindles an ardent rage,</l>
               <l>While leane-fac'd <hi>Death</hi> attends him as a Page;</l>
               <l>Yet arm'd in heart, of furniture well ſped,</l>
               <l>Reſolues to die in Honors valorous bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This world's a warfare, thou a ſouldier,</l>
               <l>Wherein thou ſtriu'ſt to ſtand Deaths conquerer,</l>
               <l>Contending with hels Dragons damned hoaſt,</l>
               <l>From woes to ioyes, from ioyes to woes ytoſt.</l>
               <l>Without, the World alluresthee with Delight;</l>
               <l>Within, foule Sin thy intellectuall ſprite</l>
               <l>Suggeſts; and oppoſite to thy darke Eye,</l>
               <l>(T'entangle thee) ſlie Sathans engines lye:</l>
               <l>Behind, a ſtrict-bound Conſcience clogs thy heele;</l>
               <l>On thy right hand, mounts <hi>Fortunes</hi> loftie wheele;</l>
               <l>And on the left, <hi>Aduerſitie</hi> doth waite,</l>
               <l>To feed thy Thoughts with Cares penurious baite:</l>
               <l>Vnder thy feete, the Graue doth gape each houre,</l>
               <l>With wide-ſtretch'd mouth to ſwallow and deuoure;</l>
               <l>And ore thy head, Heau'ns heauie ludgements lie,</l>
               <l>Prepared ſtill to be powr'd foorth on thee.</l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:19185:27"/>
               <l>Then not vnaptly graue learn'd Writers call</l>
               <l>Thee, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Small world of thrall.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy ſtate of life may be compared thus;</l>
               <l>Vnto the Mariner, in ſtormes dangerous:</l>
               <l>(When bluſtring <hi>Aeolus</hi> opes his vented Caues,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Neptunes</hi> rorall beard's bedaſht with waues:)</l>
               <l>He viewes the Heau'ns ore-vail'd with pitchie cloudes,</l>
               <l>Huge tempeſts riſe, each beaſt in ſhelter ſhroudes;</l>
               <l>And foaming billowes beating gainſt his Barke,</l>
               <l>Then waites each houre, to diue in Deluge darke.</l>
               <l>But when <hi>Dan Titan,</hi> with bright golden ray</l>
               <l>Doth guil'd the pale-greene Pallace of the ſea,</l>
               <l>And with his purging Fire refines the skie,</l>
               <l>He skips with ioy for his deliuerie.</l>
               <l>So in this Orbe thou ſail'ſt through ſeas of Woes,</l>
               <l>Againe, with pride ſcornes Fortunes ouerthrowes:</l>
               <l>Oft Fortune ſtormes, and her cleare Sun-ſhine failes,</l>
               <l>Then Ioy retires with wofull-battred ſailes.</l>
               <l>Thus art thou ſubiect to <hi>Times turne,</hi> and <hi>Fate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To be transform'd in Perſon, Life, or State:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Time</hi> can turne to ſet the World on flote,</l>
               <l>And ſtraight can vrge him ſing poore <hi>Niobs</hi> note.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If th' <hi>Embryo</hi> foreknew theſe woes, intomb'd</l>
               <l>Within the wals of his deare Mothers wombe;</l>
               <l>If he could ſee, before he ſees heau'ns Light,</l>
               <l>Earths Languiſhments, as Objects to his ſight;</l>
               <l>Would ne're contend to ope the Matrice wide,</l>
               <l>By Generation naturally to glide</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:19185:27"/>
               <l>From tranquile Calme, to ſurging ſeas of Cares;</l>
               <l>From ſilent Manſion, to a maſſe of Snares:</l>
               <l>But rather wiſh in darke Obliuion caſt</l>
               <l>Without a Being, then on Earth be plac'd,</l>
               <l>To gaze vpon the Suns bright Orient,</l>
               <l>His Beames, Meridian courſe, and Occident;</l>
               <l>The worlds delights would hold in ſpitefull ſcorne,</l>
               <l>Intirely wiſhing he ſhould ne're be borne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This was obſerued by the <hi>Drauſians,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And as an Axiome high decretall ſtands:</l>
               <l>That when a Babe from fruitfull wombe did riſe,</l>
               <l>Would mourne, weepe and lament in wondrous wiſe:</l>
               <l>For that they knew, he was brought foorth to ſtand</l>
               <l>In this fraile Orbe, as on the ſhiuering ſand;</l>
               <l>Readie to ſinke into the depth of Feares,</l>
               <l>Enuiron'd round with intricate Deſpaires.</l>
               <l>But when one died, then gladly they reioyce,</l>
               <l>With rauiſhing Muſicks-ſimphonizing voice:</l>
               <l>In this reſpect, they held him then ſet free,</l>
               <l>From out the vale of cankred Miſerie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus <hi>Man</hi> by Nature is conceiu'd in wo,</l>
               <l>From generatiue Seed continues ſo;</l>
               <l>Still turn'd about with <hi>Times</hi> ſoft motion,</l>
               <l>Diſturbed-wiſe, as <hi>Syſiphus</hi> rolles his ſtone;</l>
               <l>Or boyling <hi>Eurypus,</hi> which hurles along</l>
               <l>With neuer-ceaſſing Agitation:</l>
               <l>Faſt marching forward like a Souldier braue,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtep by ſtep deſcends faſt to his graue,</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:19185:28"/>
               <l>Till the laſt trauell of his mother Earth,</l>
               <l>Shall purge him with regeneratiue Birth.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But in earths warre, prepare heau'ns furniture,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That in thy death, of life thou maiſt be ſure.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As Nauigators firſt forgo the ſight</l>
               <l>Of friends, and next, of cities faire and bright.</l>
               <l>And finally, lanch out from banke and ſhore,</l>
               <l>With reſolution ne're to ſee them more.</l>
               <l>So Man's depriued firſt of Infancie,</l>
               <l>Next, of his Youth and ſtrong Virilitie:</l>
               <l>In fine, out-worne with his vnwealdie Age,</l>
               <l>Loſeth the ſight of this Orbes ſpacious ſtage:</l>
               <l>When hoarie Eld his ſtooping backe doth bend,</l>
               <l>With concau'd eyes viewes then his reſt and end.</l>
               <l>Thus (<hi>pedetentim</hi>) Man exhales his breath,</l>
               <l>If not preuented by immediate Death:</l>
               <l>Euen as the Dials ſhade, depos'd from Reſt,</l>
               <l>In one dayes ſpace doth courſe from Eaſt to Weſt;</l>
               <l>By circumuerſion ſlily paſſeth by</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gradatim</hi> wiſe, yet not diſcern'd with Eye.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Man</hi> craules on twixt earth and heau'ns bright raies,</l>
               <l>Towards the weſt and welking of his daies:</l>
               <l>Yet knowes not when grim Death ſhall ſtop the race</l>
               <l>Of his lifes houres, mouing with gentle pace;</l>
               <l>As nothing is more ſure then loſſe of Breath,</l>
               <l>So nought's vnſurer then the kinds of Death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeterna Lex</hi> hath ſacredly deſcribed,</l>
               <l>(From whence th'euent of Life and Death's deriued)</l>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:19185:28"/>
               <l>A generall vniformall path from Wombe,</l>
               <l>But various by-waies to the graue and tombe.</l>
               <l>As diuers ſhips lanch from one port and deepe,</l>
               <l>Yet ſundrie waies vpon the Surges ſweepe.</l>
               <l>Some bound for Eaſt to froſt-bit <hi>Scythia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Others for Weſt to faire <hi>America,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some ſubiect faile to <hi>Auſters</hi> briefe controules,</l>
               <l>Others range through breeme <hi>Boreas</hi> frozen poles:</l>
               <l>So all atchieuc one entrance from their birth,</l>
               <l>But various paſſage to their grandam Earth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How many plunge to triſtall timeleſſe fall,</l>
               <l>(As may appeare by proofes Authenticall)</l>
               <l>By Murther, Shipwracke, Beaſts, Eluuion,</l>
               <l>By Fire, by Sword, by Wars confuſion:</l>
               <l>By Famine, Peſtilence, (Earths Miſerie)</l>
               <l>By wondrous Accidents throwne downe from hie;</l>
               <l>By Thundring, Lightning, Tempeſts that ariſe,</l>
               <l>By deſperate Sprites and damned Fallacies;</l>
               <l>By Ioy, by Penurie, by Wealth, by Wo,</l>
               <l>Some apprehend vnnaturall ouerthrow:</l>
               <l>By Nonnage, Youth, Old-age, ſome ſtrangely hie</l>
               <l>To the darke Manſion of Obſcuritie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Young <hi>Druſus Pompey, Claudius</hi> lineall heire,</l>
               <l>Amidſt his ſport was choaked with a Peare:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eurypides</hi> was torne with dogs alone,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anacreon</hi> ſtifled with a Raiſins ſtone:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Catulus</hi> purſuing timeleſſe death,</l>
               <l>With ſtinking ſmoke did ſuffocate his breath.</l>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:19185:29"/>
               <l>When <hi>Marius</hi> ſouldiers ſwiftly did purſue,</l>
               <l>Imbrac'd this death, a better to eſchue.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Valerius, Carus,</hi> Emp'rors great through might,</l>
               <l>Periſhed by thunder and celeſtiall Light:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Plinie</hi> was burnt by wondrous fires, that blaz'd</l>
               <l>From mount <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> whereon ſtill he gaz'd,</l>
               <l>To comprehend the nature of that light,</l>
               <l>Wherewith his dayes were conſumated quite:</l>
               <l>And hundreds mo, which might in tragicke verſe</l>
               <l>Be inſtanced, too tedious to rehearſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus various ſtands <hi>Times</hi> imminent turne of Men,</l>
               <l>They know to die, yet know not where, nor when.</l>
               <l>The heau'ns bright Eye knowes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> t'include his raies,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Man</hi> knowes not the <hi>Veſper</hi> of his daies:</l>
               <l>So whether thou incline to Good or Ill,</l>
               <l>Or frame thy heart to Natures wilfull Will;</l>
               <l>Or plant ſuch trees, which bring foorth bitter fruit</l>
               <l>In thy Soules ſoyle, following with hote purſuit</l>
               <l>Earths ſoure-ſweet <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> various in their taſts;</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill thy Lampe combuſts, thy lifes Oyle waſts:</l>
               <l>Wheeling about with blaſts of whirle-wind <hi>Time,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To Deaths darke den of duſt and putride ſlime.</l>
               <l>Admit, thou reapſt Youths flouriſhing verdant flours,</l>
               <l>And ouer-runne the glaſſe of <hi>Neſtors</hi> houres:</l>
               <l>Yet at the laſt, Lifes roote will withered be,</l>
               <l>And ſtocke traduc'd to groſſe Moroſitie:</l>
               <l>The Sap once dried, Life inſtantly is gone,</l>
               <l>Euen as a Dreame, or Apparition.</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:19185:29"/>
               <l>And as greene fruites by ripeneſſe fall from tree,</l>
               <l>Or ſparkes, which of themſelues extinguiſh'd be;</l>
               <l>So <hi>Nature</hi> muſt thy fruitleſſe branches ſend</l>
               <l>To the ſuccincting Period of their end.</l>
               <l>Then let this Diſh be ſeru'd laſt at thy Feaſt:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Memento mori, VIR incertus est.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that his Soule to ſinfulneſſe doth bend,</l>
               <l>Let him recount the Sorrowes of his End;</l>
               <l>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heau'ns ſhril Trump ſhal rowze him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſleep,</l>
               <l>And Goates ſequeſtred from the harmleſſe Sheepe:</l>
               <l>Before the generall ludge ſhall he be brought.</l>
               <l>To plead <hi>Peccaui</hi> for each triuiall Thought:</l>
               <l>Like as his life, ſhall be his Death and end,</l>
               <l>VVhat Death abandons, Iudgements apprehend:</l>
               <l>VVhat Life and Death in Good or Ill defrayes,</l>
               <l>The Iudge in iudgement to his Soule repayes.</l>
               <l>Heau'ns work-men then their wages ſhall be paid,</l>
               <l>VVhen ſlouthfull ſlugs in Dungèon ſhall be laid;</l>
               <l>VVhere <hi>Fire</hi> ſhall burne, yet not conſume them quite,</l>
               <l>Nor to their comfort yeeld them any Light,</l>
               <l>There ſhall they die in life, and liue to die,</l>
               <l>Such Horrors waité on hels Eternitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O <hi>London,</hi> meekely proſtrate on thy knee,</l>
               <l>Fore heau'ns great King with pure Sinceritie;</l>
               <l>Reuolue his praiſe, (Creator of that <hi>Day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVherein the Organs of thy Senſes play)</l>
               <l>VVho hath preſeru'd thee from Sedition,</l>
               <l>From thirſtie Sword, and ſtaru'd Occiſion:</l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:19185:30"/>
               <l>Better it is a thouſand times for Sin,</l>
               <l>To fall into the hands of God then men:</l>
               <l>For brunt of fierie Wars are mercileſſe;</l>
               <l>But God in mercie will thy woes redreſſe:</l>
               <l>This caus'd the princely Prophet wars refuſe,</l>
               <l>By inſpiration <hi>Peſtilence</hi> did chuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou that art poiſoned with this fierce diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>And fierie torments furiouſly increaſe;</l>
               <l>If all externall Remedies were gone,</l>
               <l>Haue thou recourſe to heau'ns Phiſition:</l>
               <l>Perfume the inward roomes of thy Deſites,</l>
               <l>With ſauours ſweet, and holy-heated Fires:</l>
               <l>Moiſten thy couch with reares for thy offence,</l>
               <l>To quench the flames of burning Peſtilence:</l>
               <l>Sing ſadly foorth to Heau'n this ſacred Dittie,</l>
               <l>Thus ſtirre <hi>Iehoua</hi> to ſoules-ſauing pitie:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If thou ſhouldſt ſearch the poyſoned heart of man,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If thou in ludgement ſhouldſt his indgements ſcan:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If thou ſhouldſt view how vile his Nature is,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If thou ſhouldſt notice take what's done amiſſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then would his name be written in the aire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then would Obliuion wrap him in Deſpaire;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then would he ne're atchieue Heau'ns crowning Fame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then would in hell be charactred his ſhame.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O mightie</hi> Ioue, <hi>omnipotent in Might,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O, I Earths-worme craule fore thy gracious ſight:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O God, ô King of kings maiesticall;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O who can ſtand, when thou commandst to fall.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:19185:30"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy Grace ſhines perfect indiniduall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy glorious Power extends it ſelfe to all:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy Mercies paſſe the numbers of the ſand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy Fountaines flow, thy Wel-ſprings neuer ſtand.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Turne downe thine Eye, behold my mournfull griefe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Turne theſe my christall teares to Pearles of life:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Turne backe thy face from my corruptions,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Turne theſe corrections to Inſtructions.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Soule ſurmounts</hi> Aurora's <hi>dew-moist Larke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Senſe is kindled with a ſacred Sparke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Heart is rapt aboue the third Degree,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Sprite with loftie euolence flies to thee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou art that Balne, wherewith my ſoule is cured,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou art that Law, whereto my heart's adiured,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou art that Mount, whereon my ſprite must rest,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou art that Houſe, wherein my Senſe lines bleſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then will thy ſoules Phiſitian come to thee,</l>
               <l>Miniſtring Mercie to thy miſerie,</l>
               <l>And cheare thy Senſes with ſupernall Food,</l>
               <l>Which ſhall redound to thy immortall good;</l>
               <l>Thy heart will then deſire (amongſt the bleſt)</l>
               <l>To be diſſolued, and to ſleepe in reſt:</l>
               <l>And as the Sunne's moſt ſwift at his deſcending,</l>
               <l>So ſhalt thou be moſt bleſſed at thy ending.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>London,</hi> with teares thy grieuous ſins lament,</l>
               <l>Thy flintic heart with humbleneſſe relent.</l>
               <l>With faſtings, mournings, greet him by the way,</l>
               <l>Preuent his plagues with ſpacious <hi>Niniue;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:19185:31"/>
               <l>And purge the inward <hi>Man</hi> of foule Offence,</l>
               <l>That <hi>God</hi> may purge thee of this <hi>Peſtilence:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Imbrace his Loue as ſweet Preferuatiue,</l>
               <l>If in heau'ns <hi>Eden</hi> thou doſt meane to thriue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Diſcute that damn'd-aſpiring Enemie,</l>
               <l>That puft-ſterne-dropſie-ſwelling ſurquedrie</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Selfe-conceit,</hi> which ſuffocates thy Soule,</l>
               <l>And in thy Heart doth <hi>Puritie</hi> controule:</l>
               <l>Leſt thy Selfe-ruine ſo be brought to paſſe,</l>
               <l>As to the <hi>Baſiliske,</hi> which in a glaſſe</l>
               <l>Beholds his beautie long, vntill at length</l>
               <l>He be depriued of his vitall ſtrength;</l>
               <l>And whiles the glaſſe his beautie foorth doth ſend,</l>
               <l>His owne reflecting-poiſon workes his end.</l>
               <l>Or leſt thy Springs be turn'd to Gulfes of blood.</l>
               <l>And Beautie drown'd in faire <hi>Narciſſus</hi> flood.</l>
               <l>To muſe on Heau'n thy Senſes eleuate,</l>
               <l>To walke vpright, thy Spirit animate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let not heau'ns <hi>Light</hi> obſcure thy dazeled eye,</l>
               <l>And be the Deaths-man to Virilitie;</l>
               <l>Let not th' <hi>Ambaſſage</hi> of the glorious Lord,</l>
               <l>And powerfull Eſſence of his ſacred VVord,</l>
               <l>(Lifes pure <hi>Elixer,</hi> Sun-ſhine of thy Day,</l>
               <l>VVhich can with Ioy, Hearts coraſiues allay)</l>
               <l>Harden thy heart, and eke thy ſoule compell,</l>
               <l>To tread the broad-beat-path that leades to hell:</l>
               <l>As ſcorching <hi>Titan</hi> with his ardent ray,</l>
               <l>Diſſolues the waxe, and obdurates the clay,</l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:19185:31"/>
               <l>So doth <hi>Heau'ns voice</hi> the humane heart relent,</l>
               <l>Or workes it harder then the ſparkling Flint.</l>
               <l>Approou'd by <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who would neuer grant</l>
               <l>(His heart being clos'd in tombes of Adamant)</l>
               <l>A free diſmiſment to poore <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Bur did the Legate of heau'ns Lord diſpell;</l>
               <l>And gainſt his Prophet did peruerſly ſtand,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Ione</hi> ſent foorth ſtrange plagues vpon his land.</l>
               <l>So hath thy Toad-ſwel'd proud rebellious hart,</l>
               <l>Increas'd the rigor of thy generall ſmart;</l>
               <l>Which at thy gates hath forc'd Intruſion,</l>
               <l>To thy Conuerſion, or Confuſion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore in Ioue guſh out pure ſtreames of teares,</l>
               <l>Enuiron round thy heart with ſacred Feares;</l>
               <l>And to renounce thy crimes with Zeale intend,</l>
               <l>Leſt <hi>Heau'n</hi> reſerue thee to a fearefull end.</l>
               <l>Shake hands with Sin, and bid him now, Farewell,</l>
               <l>Prepare thy Soule with Godlineſſe to dwell;</l>
               <l>Redeeme that <hi>Time</hi> which thou haft lewdly ſpent;</l>
               <l>In this <hi>Times-turne,</hi> with Faith be penitent:</l>
               <l>For Heau'n hath ſent thee to thy ſoules deſire,</l>
               <l>More bleſſings then earths Nature could require;</l>
               <l>So many Graces to thy hearts Content,</l>
               <l>Which to the World doth argue wonderment.</l>
               <l>But ſith from <hi>him</hi> thou turnedſt backe thy face,</l>
               <l>He turn'd theſe Mercies to thy deepe diſgrace;</l>
               <l>And tedious Taxes faſtned on thy head,</l>
               <l>In that thy Pride was not abandoned:</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:19185:32"/>
               <l>But ſtill relapſe from Grace, and fall from Truth;</l>
               <l>The Nerues of Age, the Complements of Youth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You immane <hi>Atheiſts</hi> who in darkneſſe dwell,</l>
               <l>To horride Diuels the damned Centinell:</l>
               <l>Affoording Nature that ſole high renowne,</l>
               <l>Which natures Author weareth as a crowne:</l>
               <l>Old grandam Earth doth loath your noyſome breath,</l>
               <l>That die in life, and liue, to liue in death:</l>
               <l>Th'inſatiat Gulfe prognoſticates your merits,</l>
               <l>It grieues the Aire to feed your vitall ſpirits.</l>
               <l>Can new-borne Sucklings frame their ſteps to go?</l>
               <l>Can Youth, graue Eld Experiences ſhow?</l>
               <l>Can the Puple, his learned Tutor teach?</l>
               <l>Can the damn'd Reprobate heau'ns Towers reach?</l>
               <l>Can the Pallace direct the Framers hand,</l>
               <l>To build ſo firme, that it for ay might ſtand?</l>
               <l>Or can baſe <hi>Nature,</hi> cauteriz'd with ſhame,</l>
               <l>Abſtract one Iod from <hi>Ioues</hi> great glorious name?</l>
               <l>Can abiect Duſt (by heau'ns predeſtinate,</l>
               <l>Though collocated in Angellike ſtate)</l>
               <l>Aſſume or derogate that Worke diuine,</l>
               <l>Which can to nought but filthineſſe incline?</l>
               <l>With terror muſe, with trembling cogitate;</l>
               <l>To higher Thoughts your ſoules exaſperate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heau'n</hi> is the Iuſticer of Natures hart,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nature's</hi> the workmanſhip of heau'ns great Art,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Art</hi> is the roote of humane natures Skill,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Skill</hi> letteth looſe the reines of Natures Will,</l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:19185:32"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Will</hi> workes th'Effects of Natures owne decay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Decay</hi> muſt Nature, <hi>God</hi> perfiſts for ay.</l>
               <l>How could her power confirme Times Accident,</l>
               <l>Turning ſad woes with ioyes circumferent?</l>
               <l>How could th'Effect without th'Efficient,</l>
               <l>Redound theſe glorious graces imminent,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Albions</hi> comfort, by <hi>Iehoua</hi> wrought,</l>
               <l>When Hope lay fruſtrate of aſpiring thought?</l>
               <l>Then, when the Zodiacke of Earths <hi>Sun</hi> was ended,</l>
               <l>And our Horizon on the <hi>Fates</hi> attended,</l>
               <l>Who rob'd <hi>Apollo</hi> of that faireſt <hi>Faire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe bright Meridian guilded <hi>Albions</hi> Aire:</l>
               <l>Yet of aires benefite it ſelfe depriued,</l>
               <l>From frozen Pole a brighter <hi>Sun</hi> reuiued;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It</hi> led to th' Occident of fatall Reſt,</l>
               <l>A clearer Orient ſtarted out from Weſt.</l>
               <l>Againe, to mixe the poyſon of Annoy,</l>
               <l>With her delightſome cordials of Ioy;</l>
               <l>Amidſt her chearefull wines to mingle in</l>
               <l>The bitter Potion of the dregs of Sin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſearch your hearts, in heart imagine now,</l>
               <l>Hels deepe damnation branded on your brow.</l>
               <l>O gaze to heau'n, grouel not on the ground,</l>
               <l>Earth you corrupts, in Heau'n all ioyes are found:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heau'n</hi> is the hauen of true perfect reſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heau'n</hi> is that place aſſigned to the bleſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heau'n</hi> tendreth all, that do heau'ns Truth auerre,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heau'n</hi> trophees yeelds to Natures Conquerer.</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:19185:33"/>
               <l>Therefore awake from th'Ecſtaſin of Shame,</l>
               <l>By earthly Conqueſt, purchaſe heau'nly Fame:</l>
               <l>Out of your hearts Earths drugs euacuate,</l>
               <l>To heau'ns great <hi>All,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Qui Dro re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant.</note> all praiſes arrogate:</l>
               <l>Accurſt to Hell ſuch as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Do calcitrate againſt the gates of Heau'n.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſith, ô <hi>Albion, Ione</hi> hath full decreed,</l>
               <l>To ſend thee ſuccour at thy extreme need,</l>
               <l>Shrowding thee vnder his Al-couering wing,</l>
               <l>And ſtill protecting thee from Sorrowes ſting;</l>
               <l>Be gratefull therefore to his Soueraigne Might,</l>
               <l>Who alwaies held thee gracious in his ſight.</l>
               <l>In thee no rumors runne of ciuill warres,</l>
               <l>Nor of Sedition and tumultuous iarres;</l>
               <l>But all with joynt applauſe do ſing of Peace,</l>
               <l>Of plenteous Autumnes, and a ſweet Increaſe:</l>
               <l>(O ſacred <hi>Peace,</hi> by thee are onely found</l>
               <l>Th'exceeding ioyes, that euery where abound!</l>
               <l>Thankes, <hi>ſacred Ione,</hi> that hath ſent vs a King,</l>
               <l>Who turnes our Winter, to a gladſome Spring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now <hi>Mars</hi> may drag his Enſignes in the duſt,</l>
               <l>His Adamantine coate may lye and ruſt:</l>
               <l>Brabling <hi>Bellona</hi> now her broyles may ſtay,</l>
               <l>And in her ſacrificing Temple play,</l>
               <l>Turning ſhrill Cries, to tunes of Muſickes ſound;</l>
               <l>Harſh Diſcord now, with Concord ſweet is drown'd.</l>
               <l>For <hi>Phoebus</hi> Lute deſcants a new-found note,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whereat Time skips, and turnes his Protean Cote.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19185:33"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Rippe vp the wombe now of the fertile field,</l>
               <l>And prune thy trees whoſe graffes aboundance yeeld:</l>
               <l>Now may great <hi>Pan</hi> trauerſe the verdant woods,</l>
               <l>To view the ſpringing plants and ſprouting buds.</l>
               <l>Now may the ſhepheards when they chance to meete,</l>
               <l>Trip ore <hi>Narciſſus</hi> with their trampling feete:</l>
               <l>Now may they dance their ruſticke roundelaies,</l>
               <l>Now <hi>philomele</hi> may warble on the ſpraies:</l>
               <l>Now ſweld-cheekt <hi>Thro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bus</hi> midſt his vines may ſwim,</l>
               <l>And fill <hi>Castalian</hi> bowles vp to the brim.</l>
               <l>Now may thy full-fraught ſhips for Merchants gaine,</l>
               <l>Deuide the furrowes of the watrie Plaine;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neptune</hi> who knockes his curl'd-locks gainſt the skie,</l>
               <l>Hath how reſign'd his full Supremacie.</l>
               <l>Now may earths <hi>Load-ſtarres</hi> (ore-vail'd by Night)</l>
               <l>Without diſturbance ſpread their ſparkling <hi>Light:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For <hi>Phoebus</hi> Lute quauereth a heauenly note,</l>
               <l>To make <hi>Time</hi> dance in his <hi>Camelion</hi> cote.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Honor late clos'd in tombes of Infamie,</l>
               <l>Now burne pure lampes of Generoſitie:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Truth</hi> once ore-caft with cloudes of Errors ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Shall now appeare with grace in thickeſt throng.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vertue</hi> reuiue, thou Mirror of thy Race,</l>
               <l>Throwne by malignant Sprites to low Diſgrace,</l>
               <l>And proſtitute to Fates exorbitant,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Shrubs</hi> ore <hi>Cedars</hi> grew predominant.</l>
               <l>Awake <hi>Renowne,</hi> great heire of Chiualrie,</l>
               <l>Spread out thy Name, though in earths womb doſt lie:</l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:19185:34"/>
               <l>Hence old <hi>Obliuion,</hi> claſpe thy black-leau'd Booke,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vertue</hi> diſdaines in thee t'affoord a looke:</l>
               <l>Gainſt hels deſpite, her beames on earth ſhall ſhine,</l>
               <l>Though regiſtred amongſt the Saints diuine:</l>
               <l>While ſolide dromedarie Sprites ſhall be</l>
               <l>Blind Homagers to baſe-bred Progenie;</l>
               <l>Who once ſeem'd bright, ſtamped with Honors mark,</l>
               <l>Like glittring Glow-wormes glimpſing in the darke;</l>
               <l>Fretting their gangren'd ſcars, ſhall lye halfe-drown'd,</l>
               <l>With inundation of Diſgraces found:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Phoebus</hi> fingers ſtrike a ſacred note,</l>
               <l>Conſtraining <hi>Time</hi> to turne his ſable cote.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou worlds-Confuſion, thou ruſt-fretting <hi>Spite,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deflowring Vertue and her Virgins-right,</l>
               <l>With ſtretched Stratagemes, and Forgeries,</l>
               <l>As trecherous Centinels raiſe falſe deſcries:</l>
               <l>To pleaſe thy ſelfe, <hi>Melpomens</hi> muſicke ſings,</l>
               <l>By making Kings poore vaſſals, vaſſals kings.</l>
               <l>Times paſt, thy crue and Machiauellian Race,</l>
               <l>Conſtrain'd the Horſe, to ſerue the ſeruile Aſſe;</l>
               <l>Superficiall ſyllogiſmes propounding ſtill,</l>
               <l>Wreſted <hi>Truths</hi> key to ope thy cankted Will.</l>
               <l>Thy quelling hand ſuppreſſed huge-growne Okes,</l>
               <l>T'abide the brunt of baſe-bred Peſants ſtrokes,</l>
               <l>Poyſoning the fluent ſtreames of Honors <hi>Spring,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With thy infectious venim'd aſpiſh ſting:</l>
               <l>(If <hi>Richard</hi> had not bene by Enuie led,</l>
               <l>Braue <hi>Bucchingham</hi> had neuer loſt his head.)</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:19185:34"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou pale-ſac'd Fate, thou Miniſter of harmes,</l>
               <l>Inueigling <hi>Dian</hi> with ſuppos'd Alarmes:</l>
               <l>Then, when the wide-mouth'd Beaſts purſude in chaſe</l>
               <l>The light-foot <hi>Roe,</hi> tripping with nimble pace,</l>
               <l>T'eſcape the chaps of thoſe <hi>Hart</hi>-ſenting hounds,</l>
               <l>Stript through the Plaines of <hi>Dians</hi> ſporting grounds:</l>
               <l>But yet the yels of their foot-following cries,</l>
               <l>Incens'd the Goddeſſe with a deepe ſurmiſe;</l>
               <l>That, <hi>through her Walkes without reſpect he rones,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spoiling her ſiluer Fountaines, Shades and groues.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whereat ſhe ſtorming, ſnatcht her ſtiffe-ſteel'd bow,</l>
               <l>With quiuer-bearing Might did wound this <hi>Roe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O <hi>Dian</hi> faire, yet foule diſaſtrous Lucke,</l>
               <l>To foile faire-Play in foiling of this <hi>Bucke!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So ſoone as he receiu'd this lethall blow,</l>
               <l>Heart-trembling Feare, and Senſe-appalling Wo,</l>
               <l>Rudely ruſht through the Heard diſturbed-wiſe,</l>
               <l>With vlulations, ſhrikes, and Mandracke-cries:</l>
               <l>Thus woodly ranging, theſe exclaims foorth powred:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Beautie of our beauteous Breed's deflowred!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Syluanes eyes diſtil'd pure chriſtall Teares,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Dians</hi> Nymphs rent their disſheauled haires:</l>
               <l>The Cedar (mal-content) hung downe his head,</l>
               <l>The dwarffie Shrub did quake aſtoniſhed:</l>
               <l>Th'aſpiring hils ſad mournfull murmures ſended,</l>
               <l>The dales cride <hi>(woes)</hi> before their woes were ended;</l>
               <l>Their daughter <hi>Eccho</hi> with her tripled Tong,</l>
               <l>Did Tel-tale-like reduplicate this wrong:</l>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:19185:35"/>
               <l>Through rocks and groues this tatling newes did ſling,</l>
               <l>Which caus'd the concau'd vaſtie anters ring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pan</hi> wakening with theſe vniuerſall cries,</l>
               <l>Began to ſtart, preſaging Tragedies;</l>
               <l>And gazing mongſt his flockes on champion ground,</l>
               <l>Eſpide his <hi>Faire</hi> ſtrucke downe with mortall wound.</l>
               <l>Then bloud-congealing Feare enwrapt his hart,</l>
               <l>Each actuall Senſe forgat to act his part;</l>
               <l>And Natures functions ſlackt their vſuall charge,</l>
               <l>From whence lifes Organs force free paſſage large.</l>
               <l>Thus ouer-quel'd with palſey-quinering Dread,</l>
               <l>Pluckt vp the ſluce and floud-gates of his head,</l>
               <l>From whence guſh'd foorth a Pleni-tide of teares,</l>
               <l>Which trickling down, hurl'd through his ſnow-white hairs.</l>
               <l>But vitall Motions being reduc'd againe,</l>
               <l>Inioyn'd Hearts-bloud to courſe through euery veine;</l>
               <l>Then Sighs and Words (confus'd) did iſſue foorth,</l>
               <l>Like bluſtring ſtormes from cloud-diſpelling North:</l>
               <l>Ech word breath'd ſighs, each ſigh braith'd out a word,</l>
               <l>Euen as the treaſurie of his Thoughts was ſtor'd:</l>
               <l>While blaſting Feare, his branching Nerues did kill,</l>
               <l>Quauered this <hi>Threnos</hi> on his ruſticke Lill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus he began: What Death-preſaging Starre?</l>
               <l>What monſtrous Meteor, or ſphaericall Iarre?</l>
               <l>What blacke diſaſtrous Planet blaſts from skie</l>
               <l>T'infect theſe woods? What enuious Deſtinie</l>
               <l>Hath thus conſpir'd my Paragon to ſlay,</l>
               <l>My flockes chiefe Guide, Conductor of their way?</l>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:19185:35"/>
               <l>Light to mine eyes, Eaſe to my burdened hart,</l>
               <l>Sweet <hi>Delian</hi> Muſicke to aſſwage my ſmart;</l>
               <l>Sap to the Plants, ſweet luſtre to each Flower,</l>
               <l>Faire <hi>Flora's</hi> Ioy ſeated in fragrant bower:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebe</hi> intrail'd him with a loue-ſicke grace,</l>
               <l>And with a ſmile <hi>Titan</hi> adorn'd his face.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ver's</hi> ſweet Bloſſome, <hi>Daphne's</hi> faireſt <hi>Faire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Queene <hi>Clores</hi> Pride, and Natures beſt-fram'd Heire;</l>
               <l>Nay, Natures ſelfe, her ſelfe hath foil'd to frame him:</l>
               <l>But Sighs haue drown'd my Tong, it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not name him:</l>
               <l>Silence ſeares vp my lips they muſt not open,</l>
               <l>While raging Thoughts perforce my brains haue broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>But oh, what foaming flouds beate gainſt my breſt?</l>
               <l>How are the waters of deepe woes increas'd:</l>
               <l>Now, now, per violence their ſtreams burſt out,</l>
               <l>Though with a thouſand floud-gates hem'd about.</l>
               <l>I muſt ſpeake I, though with <hi>Pythagoras</hi> Ring</l>
               <l>My mouth were ſeal'd: <hi>Neceſsitie rules a King.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Miſ-led <hi>Diana,</hi> miſ-informed Queene,</l>
               <l>What furious Nymph did animate thy teene?</l>
               <l>What ouer-ruling Fate, ore-rul'd thy hand,</l>
               <l>To ſtrike the fairſt that tript on ſcorching ſand:</l>
               <l>Ore-ruled <hi>Goddeſſe,</hi> yet ore-ruling All,</l>
               <l>Ore-rul'd, t'approoue this ouer-ruling Thrall.</l>
               <l>O would thy ſinewes had benelooſened ſo,</l>
               <l>As thy ſtiffe armes could not haue bent thy bow;</l>
               <l>O that thine eyes had ſlackt their inſtant ſight,</l>
               <l>That to thy ſhaft gaue iuſt-directed Flight.</l>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:19185:36"/>
               <l>Accurſt that <hi>Bird,</hi> who foorth her plumes did fling</l>
               <l>Next to that Shaft, whoſe roote of whisking wing,</l>
               <l>Sits quaffing Iuice, till Ioy with Sorrow ſingeth;</l>
               <l>Eke rules the Earth, and earths Confuſion bringeth;</l>
               <l>Raiſing vp one, baſely detecting other,</l>
               <l>And ſowing Variance twixt <hi>Man</hi> and his brother:</l>
               <l>I ſay accurſt, who beates her flaggering wing,</l>
               <l>To make it ſing and weepe, to weepe and ſing.</l>
               <l>O that thy nimble fingers wide had ſlipped,</l>
               <l>Til he might through ſome vncouth paths haue skipped</l>
               <l>From dint of Dart, remote a diſtant ſpace</l>
               <l>From plotting Foxe, Wolfe, and abiected Aſſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wiſhes are wind:</hi> ay me, that Darling's ſlaine,</l>
               <l>Whoſe crimſon bloud thy chriſtal brookes doth ſtaine.</l>
               <l>His waxen Shape ſo true proportioned.</l>
               <l>Liues now to <hi>Ioue,</hi> to rurall Syluanes dead;</l>
               <l>Who once was deem'd (before this tragicke part)</l>
               <l>The pure ſubſiſting Eſſence of thy heart.</l>
               <l>The Satyres left their Cels t'affoord him dutie,</l>
               <l>The Faunies leapt, as rauiſhed with his beautie,</l>
               <l>The forreſt gods rude ruſticke Carols chanted,</l>
               <l>The ietting Birds on ſpraies and branches vanted:</l>
               <l>Warbling his praiſe, this ſweet-ſtretcht ſtraine did ſing:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This is the king of Heards, the heards great King.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Once thou didſt grant <hi>him</hi> licence free to roue,</l>
               <l>Through euery valley, mountaine, ſhade and groue;</l>
               <l>As rapt in ſprite to view ſo faire a Creature,</l>
               <l>Of Lineaments diuine and famous Feature:</l>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:19185:36"/>
               <l>To Heau'n adiur'd, in Earth admir'd of all,</l>
               <l>Adorn'd with Vertues Metaphyſicall:</l>
               <l>Vntill the Wolfe, ſlie Foxe, and Aſſe with charmes,</l>
               <l>Rung in thine eares Enuies extent alarmes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oft haue I ſeene the Wolfe of lambes make prey,</l>
               <l>The clamorous Hound hold the ſwift Hart at bey,</l>
               <l>And piercing-ſighted Eagle ſoare aboue,</l>
               <l>To fixe his tallants on the mournfull Doue:</l>
               <l>(Though theſe be Accidents aſſiduall,</l>
               <l>Yet in their kind th'appeare tyrannicall:)</l>
               <l>But neuer ſaw two Gemels wound each other,</l>
               <l>Or ſymbolizing ſhapes deuoure their brother:</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>(Dian)</hi> thou haſt ſpoil'd thy ſelfe in ſpilling</l>
               <l>This guiltleſſe bloud, and kil'd thy ſelfe in killing:</l>
               <l>For Nature in this morall Axiome ſhowes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Precedent Wrongs, hast on purſuing Woes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou mightſt haue aym'd thy deep Hart-wounding ſhaft</l>
               <l>Iuſt at the Wolfe and Foxe, who ſlunke with craft</l>
               <l>Through euery Plaine, to ſpoile the harmleſſe flocks,</l>
               <l>Tearing their lambes, who skipt on craggie rockes:</l>
               <l>This done, came crooching with a courtly grace,</l>
               <l>As masked Homagers with <hi>Ianus</hi> face:</l>
               <l>Fierce <hi>Leopards</hi> in workes, yet <hi>Lambes</hi> in words,</l>
               <l>Their Enterpriſes, enter-piercing ſwords;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vulturs</hi> in thought, yet <hi>Doues</hi> in ſemblant graces,</l>
               <l>Monſters within, without faire-painted Faces,</l>
               <l>Honying their Tongs with Angels proteſtations,</l>
               <l>Poyſon'd their Hearts with diuels diſſimulations;</l>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:19185:37"/>
               <l>Nay <hi>Sphinx</hi> nor <hi>Proteus</hi> (turn'd to colours ſtrange,)</l>
               <l>Could change in time, as they with <hi>Time</hi> wold change.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou mightſt haue rouz'd the burden-bearing <hi>Aſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who ſtriu'd t'immure him ſelfe midſt fatning graſſe,</l>
               <l>Vntill with yeares the <hi>Lion's</hi> ouer-worne,</l>
               <l>Then calcitrates him with inſulting ſcorne:</l>
               <l>Who neigh'd to moue a <hi>Smile,</hi> laden with pride,</l>
               <l>Though loath'd of all thy virgin-Nymphs beſide.</l>
               <l>He ſeeking ſhelter in <hi>Minerua's</hi> Tower,</l>
               <l>From diſtillation of each ſiluer ſhower;</l>
               <l>Lay liſtning Ecchoes, that done, gins to ſnort,</l>
               <l>Carying their tatlings to <hi>Diana's</hi> Court:</l>
               <l>This ſeruile-ſolide-Lumpe plods backe againe,</l>
               <l>To blab what Newes with <hi>Dian</hi> did remaine.</l>
               <l>This fawning Drudge in ponderous gold did ſwim,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Marius</hi> moiles, who toyl'd, yet ſlicke and trim;</l>
               <l>Supporting ay light Courtiers onerous ieaſts,</l>
               <l>As Natures bond-ſlaues, borne to beare like Beaſts.</l>
               <l>For <hi>Pallas</hi> ſpurning him from out her <hi>Hall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cride: <hi>Get thee hence, I know thee not, nor ſhall:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Mars</hi> did ſcorne, that ſuch a dul-pac'd Iade,</l>
               <l>Should be officious to his warlike Trade:</l>
               <l>Yet thou didſt grant him an admitment free,</l>
               <l>To be the Pandar to falſe <hi>Forgerie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe bloud-ſworne Beaſts vnto their Dens ſcarce trudged;</l>
               <l>But ſtill with Enuie this <hi>Harts</hi> ſwiftneſſe grudged:</l>
               <l>(Conſulting with grim<note n="*" place="margin">Midnight.</note> 
                  <hi>Meſonyxion</hi>)</l>
               <l>Obſeru'd his footings, and rang'd tracks each one:</l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:19185:37"/>
               <l>And then purſude with eager hunting cloſe;</l>
               <l>Yet ſmooth'd it vp, not deem'd to be of thoſe</l>
               <l>Who ſteeled their fierce fangs, and tooke their Stand,</l>
               <l>With his hearts-bloud t'imbrue the Forreſts ſand:</l>
               <l>But highly honoured him fore <hi>Dians</hi> face,</l>
               <l>Yet in his abſence drag'd him to Diſgrace.</l>
               <l>Faire-ſeeming Pictures dazeling thus <hi>her</hi> Eye,</l>
               <l>Foule ſeemed Faire, <hi>Truth</hi> ſeemed <hi>Trecherie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Dian</hi> deckt with monſtrous <hi>Semblancie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her ſelfe ſeem'd not <hi>her ſelfe,</hi> ſhe was not <hi>ſhe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But the ſole ſolace of my ſoule, is this,</l>
               <l>Betwixt their Kinds t'oppoſe <hi>Antitheſis:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Albeit, this <hi>Faire</hi> by Deſtinies was chac'd,</l>
               <l>And in bright Splendor by foule Beaſts diſgrac'd:</l>
               <l>Yet in his Occident, (with <hi>Light</hi> repleat)</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Ioue</hi> reſerues him for a daintie meat:</l>
               <l>Whiles they in death ſhall as vile Carion lie,</l>
               <l>Of Heau'n abiected, loath'd of earthly Eye.</l>
               <l>A ſecond <hi>Faire</hi> ſhall ſpring from out his bloud,</l>
               <l>Whoſe branching hornes ſhall beautifie the wood;</l>
               <l>Whom ile range in from Wolfes and Tygers iawes,</l>
               <l>Each Nymph and Satyre lend him their applauſe:</l>
               <l>Whiles their Of-ſpring ſlinke ſlily to their Den,</l>
               <l>Agaſt, to looke on Satyres, Nymphs, or men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus <hi>Pan</hi> ore-wearied with this tasking ſtile,</l>
               <l>With whiſpring <hi>Silence</hi> breaths himſelfe awhile,</l>
               <l>And bids the Nymphs from neighbor-caues ariſe,</l>
               <l>To ſolemnize the <hi>Heards-kings</hi> Exequies.</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:19185:38"/>
               <l>Then that perform'd, runs ſwiftly through the plaine,</l>
               <l>To fetch his flockes vp to their folds againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſoft, ſwift <hi>Muſe,</hi> too faſt thou poſteſt on,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Time</hi> bids, Range in this ſterne <hi>Idilion:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Conclude with Time, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Time cócludes with thee,</l>
               <l>For Times and Motions muſt concluded be:</l>
               <l>Muſicke with Time affoords ſweet harmonie,</l>
               <l>And as vnited natiue Twinnes agree:</l>
               <l>But this was Enuies harſh-diſcordant Song,</l>
               <l>To make <hi>Time</hi> waſh his cheekes and creepe along.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Enuie</hi> go hang, thy viperous word's no Law,</l>
               <l>Thy Toad-like-ſwelling looke's not woorth a ſtraw.</l>
               <l>Thou canſt not now Defame, Depoſe, Depriue;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Truth</hi> ſcales thy wals, thy kingdome cannot thriue:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>She</hi> now diſpels white vizards from thy face,</l>
               <l>And eleuates her Throne by thy diſgrace:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Phoebus</hi> Lute deſcants a new-found note,</l>
               <l>Whereat <hi>Time</hi> skips, and turnes his <hi>Protean</hi> cote.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now may the flocks ſecurely range at large;</l>
               <l>For <hi>Ioue</hi> himſelfe of them hath taken charge.</l>
               <l>Now tender Lambes may skip from out their pens,</l>
               <l>While Romiſh Tygers ſlinke into their dens;</l>
               <l>Like wandring Spirits midſt the drearie Night,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Apparitions do abhorre the light;</l>
               <l>Charming poore Foſters with their Magicke Spels,</l>
               <l>Till the great-<hi>Hunt</hi> ſhal rowze them from their Cels:</l>
               <l>For now <hi>Apollo</hi> takes his Lute in hand,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Time</hi> leapeth on with Ioy, and ſcornes to ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:19185:38"/>
            <lg>
               <l>As Foxes now in anters they remaine,</l>
               <l>Scraping each duſtie concaue of their braine,</l>
               <l>For putride Arguments, to hold diſpute</l>
               <l>Gainſt Heau'n it ſelfe, yet ſtill themſelues confute.</l>
               <l>As ſlipperie Eeles with ſound of dreadfull thunder,</l>
               <l>Scud from their chinkes, and ſeparate aſunder:</l>
               <l>So of they creepe from out their ſlimie caues,</l>
               <l>Plung'd in the mud of deepe-deſpairing waues;</l>
               <l>Fluttring like Schrich-owles on the craggie rockes,</l>
               <l>Yell foorth <hi>Effata's</hi> to their ſenſleſſe Blockes.</l>
               <l>They laſh foorth loathſome libels of Confeſſe,</l>
               <l>With ſoules-ſeducing triuiall Treatiſes;</l>
               <l>So farre vnfit to ſaue a Chriſtian,</l>
               <l>As is the Turkiſh truthleſſe <hi>Alcoran.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The march as Maskers in diſguiſed ſhapes,</l>
               <l>Toſſing their Beads with tricks, like mimicke Apes:</l>
               <l>Or Corniſh chaughs, that in their neſts do chatter,</l>
               <l>Neither to Reaſon, Senſe, or any matter:</l>
               <l>To Seigneur <hi>Crux</hi> ſuch hote-breath'd ſighs they ſend,</l>
               <l>As make him frowne, and vow to be their end:</l>
               <l>An Altar apt for ſuch a Sacrifice,</l>
               <l>For what they craue, his Worſhip ne're denies:</l>
               <l>The place is Shame, through Malefaction,</l>
               <l>And there with Shame they ſhare Deuotion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now hath th'<hi>Italian</hi> Serpent caſt her ſting,</l>
               <l>And wounded lies by IAMES, faire <hi>Albions</hi> King;</l>
               <l>Whom, Heau'ns protect from fawning <hi>Gnato's</hi> crue,</l>
               <l>That turne (with monſtrous <hi>Time</hi>) to <hi>Protean</hi> hue;</l>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:19185:39"/>
               <l>Or as bright Comets, whoſe blaze laſteth pure</l>
               <l>No longer, then their exhal'd Fires endure:</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Hecticke</hi> fits, now hote, now cold within,</l>
               <l>Now burnes the heart, now frigerates the skin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Extirpate Traitors, ô heau'ns expell</l>
               <l>The craftie Counſels of <hi>Achitophell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The ſoothing Humor of each <hi>Midius</hi> braine,</l>
               <l>That by blandiloquence ſeekes his ſtate to ſtaine:</l>
               <l>The damn'd ſtratagemes of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Fauorites,</l>
               <l>And all Spanized bloud-ſworne Ieſuites;</l>
               <l>Who long expected that a day would come,</l>
               <l>Wherin with bloud they might work <hi>Albions</hi> doome:</l>
               <l>Couering their face with vailes of Loyaltie,</l>
               <l>Their poyſoned hearts conſort with Villanie,</l>
               <l>To trucidate and murther <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Peere,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe bloud, both God and man eſteeme moſt deare.</l>
               <l>Theſe are Illuſions ſprung from Poperie,</l>
               <l>Theſe are the fruites of falſe Imagerie.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In Nomine Ieſu,</hi> yet their facts muſt riſe,</l>
               <l>O ſleight <hi>Preludium</hi> to their Tragedies:</l>
               <l>Their actions are exhauſt from Puritie,</l>
               <l>Yet practiſe nought but diueliſh Trecherie.</l>
               <l>Are theſe Deuotions? nay, Deluſions,</l>
               <l>Detractions, and their owne Deſtructions.</l>
               <l>Let no man dread <hi>Romes</hi> Hydra bearing ſway,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Albions Hercul's</hi> crops his heads away:</l>
               <l>One Head entire doth on his ſhoulders ſtand,</l>
               <l>Which will be broke by <hi>Iames</hi> owne royall hand.</l>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:19185:39"/>
               <l>For <hi>Phoebus</hi> hath deuis'd an heau'nly note,</l>
               <l>To make <hi>Time</hi> laugh, and turne his <hi>Sphinx</hi>-like cote.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But harke, <hi>Muſe,</hi> harke, me thinks ſome voice diuine,</l>
               <l>Ecchoes the mountaines of the <hi>Muſes</hi> nine:</l>
               <l>Stay, genious <hi>Muſe,</hi> thy ouer-tired teame,</l>
               <l>Ceaſe to diſcuſſe vpon ſo deepe a Theame:</l>
               <l>Now take repoſe in <hi>Aganyppe's</hi> vale,</l>
               <l>And marke the tenor of this ſequele Tale.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>A Panygericall Idilion pronounced to <hi>the Citie of London before the entrance</hi> of her long-expected Comfort.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NOw <hi>London</hi> riſe from dreadfull Dungeon,</l>
               <l>Of darke diſaſtrous deepe Deſtruction;</l>
               <l>Wherein thou didſt imbrace foule hood-winkt Night,</l>
               <l>Prodigious horror, indigence of light,</l>
               <l>And Senſe-appalling Feare, with ſhort-drawne breath,</l>
               <l>Faſt grip'd betwixt the chaps of rauenous Death:</l>
               <l>Gainſt whom, Heaù'ns wódrous works oppoſed were,</l>
               <l>Each <hi>Planet,</hi> and incomprehended <hi>Sphare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The reſtleſſe <hi>Poles,</hi> and high-remoted <hi>Starres,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Againſt thy Pride conſpired direfull warres:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> mask'd his face with beames of bloud,</l>
               <l>While trembling <hi>Phoeb'</hi> exanimated ſtood:</l>
               <l>With ioyntagree thus adunited all,</l>
               <l>To captiuate thee with perfidious thrall.</l>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:19185:40"/>
               <l>Erect thy bruiſed ſtormie-battred head,</l>
               <l>Baſely deiected like the high-ſprung Reed,</l>
               <l>Or graſſie plaines, where <hi>Ver</hi> bids flowers abound,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſtems are vrg'd to kiſſe the foule-fac'd ground:</l>
               <l>When as the furious <hi>Fire</hi> with diſcontents,</l>
               <l>(Included cloſe midſt liquid Elements,)</l>
               <l>Alongſt the ſphaerie Frame doth range about,</l>
               <l>With burning ire to find ſome paſſage out;</l>
               <l>At laſt breakes through with roarings violent,</l>
               <l>Like to a Lion in ſome dungeon pent;</l>
               <l>And then diſſolues that groſſe-congealed matter,</l>
               <l>To fierce tempeſtuous haile and flouds of water.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Aeolus</hi> ope's his vented anters deepe,</l>
               <l>That curl'd-hair'd <hi>Boreas</hi> through the world may ſweep</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſteele-ſtrong breath doth penetrate the rockes,</l>
               <l>Diſturbes <hi>Damaetas</hi> and confounds his flockes:</l>
               <l>Affrighting Nature with celeſtiall Thunder,</l>
               <l>And ſtoutly ſtrikes the Cedars tops aſunder.</l>
               <l>Whereat huge <hi>Aetna</hi> quakes, proud billowes riſe,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Amphytrite's</hi> Towers confront the skies:</l>
               <l>The ſinewie Oake with feare fals flat to ground,</l>
               <l>Earths Center trembleth at this terrible ſound.</l>
               <l>But when <hi>Latona's</hi> Heire tranſcends his Light,</l>
               <l>From queene <hi>Aurora's</hi> chriſtall Pallace bright,</l>
               <l>Gazing about the World with chearefull Eye,</l>
               <l>Intrailes the Earth with robes of Maieſtie;</l>
               <l>Intreates the vpright-towring <hi>Larke</hi> to ſing,</l>
               <l>The low-laid graſſe to riſe, and plants to ſpring:</l>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:19185:40"/>
               <l>Inſtructing <hi>Man</hi> by courſe from Eaſt to Weſt,</l>
               <l>To riſe with <hi>Labour,</hi> and lie downe with <hi>Reſt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then boaſts queene <hi>Flora</hi> in her fragrant bed,</l>
               <l>Who earſt did droupe with tempeſts ruined.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So thou, ſith Heau'n reſpects thy mournfull mone,</l>
               <l>From the high <hi>Solium</hi> of <hi>Ioues</hi> ſacred Throne;</l>
               <l>Spreading his glorious beames of quickning Grace,</l>
               <l>Vpon thy wofull ſtorm-beat withered face:</l>
               <l>Sucke vigor from his nouriſhing feruent raies,</l>
               <l>He yeelds thee life, yeeld him immortall praiſe.</l>
               <l>Sin as the Load-ſtone, drew this Plague vpon thee,</l>
               <l>And ſins expulſion, muſt expell it from thee;</l>
               <l>Sin grounds the Cauſe, &amp; Iudgment frames th'Effect,</l>
               <l>T'aſſwage th'Efficient, Sin thou muſt reiect:</l>
               <l>Hadſt thou not ſin'd, Heau'n had not cride, Repent;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where raignes no ſin, there needes no puniſhment.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Rig vp thy Barke ſplit through with ſtorms of woes,</l>
               <l>Saile to the port where <hi>Pactolus</hi> ore-flowes;</l>
               <l>Condenſt from <hi>Tmolus</hi> mount in <hi>Lydia</hi> land,</l>
               <l>Where golden grauell guilds the ſiluer ſand:</l>
               <l>Flouriſh in ſpite of interdicting Fate,</l>
               <l>Reduce thine Honor to his auncient ſtate.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lacheſis</hi> now (who earſt ſo ſwiftly ſpun)</l>
               <l>May ſit and reſt, her tedious taske is done:</l>
               <l>For mightie <hi>Ioue</hi> (th'<hi>Olympian</hi> king) foreſhowes</l>
               <l>The calculation of thy by-paſt woes,</l>
               <l>To lie inundate midſt pure founts of Loue,</l>
               <l>Diſtilling from th'<hi>Ambroſian</hi> Springs aboue.</l>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:19185:41"/>
               <l>As flame-hair'd <hi>Phoebus</hi> melteth by degrees,</l>
               <l>Drop after drop the weeping Yſicles,</l>
               <l>And ſo traduc'd to Diſſolution,</l>
               <l>Are by the thirſtie Earth abſorb'd each one:</l>
               <l>So, as he manag'd Iudgement with Increaſe,</l>
               <l>Doth mitigate it with a ſweet Surceaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now bath amidſt <hi>Macenas</hi> ſiluer ſtreames,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Europes</hi> eyes extend thy golden beames.</l>
               <l>And as the Satyres skipping through each ſtreet</l>
               <l>Of auncient <hi>Rome,</hi> with <hi>Orpheus</hi> muſicke ſweet,</l>
               <l>Sounding <hi>Amphyons</hi> quickening ſimphonie,</l>
               <l>Threatned the death of <hi>Marcus Antonie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So let<note n="*" place="margin">The Geddeſſe of Mirth.</note> 
                  <hi>Euterpe</hi> on the aduerſe part,</l>
               <l>Plucke vp her ſprite, and euer-chearefull hart,</l>
               <l>T'infuſe thy ſtreets with heau'nly iocond mirth,</l>
               <l>And ſacred ſolace for thy proſperous Birth.</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Ephori</hi> put on their ſcarlet Die,</l>
               <l>To intertaine his royall Maieſtie;</l>
               <l>Who long'd to view thy face, (from him exil'd)</l>
               <l>Euen as a father doth his long-loſt child.</l>
               <l>Produce thine Ornaments and enſignes faire,</l>
               <l>Let ſhril-toung'd Trumpets penetrate the aire;</l>
               <l>Let bels concord in Muſickes ſimphonie,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Anes</hi> dimme the Meteors of the skie:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iouiſſance</hi> diuine reeccho in each place,</l>
               <l>Each creature cry: <hi>God ſaue king</hi> IAMES <hi>his grace:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eccho,</hi> the tatling Daughter of the hill,</l>
               <l>Shall iterate that Speech thrice-doubled ſtill;</l>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:19185:41"/>
               <l>For <hi>Phoebus</hi> tunes a ſweet celeſtiall note,</l>
               <l>Whereat <hi>Time</hi> skips with Ioy, in golden cote.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When worthie <hi>Pompey,</hi> Lord of <hi>Africa,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was choſen Chiefe to ſcoure the ſurging ſea</l>
               <l>Of Pyrates, brauing with ore-ſwaying might;</l>
               <l>So high his Fame ſoar'd in the <hi>Romaines</hi> ſight,</l>
               <l>That all applauded him with ſhoutes and cries;</l>
               <l>So pierc't the thin vaſt aire beneath the skies,</l>
               <l>That certaine fowles amaz'd fell flat to ground,</l>
               <l>Hearing ſuch clam'rous noiſe, and thundring ſound.</l>
               <l>So let the Steele of pure Affection,</l>
               <l>Strike fire of Zeale and true Subiection</l>
               <l>Vpon thy Vulgars hearts, inflam'd with loue</l>
               <l>Of due Alleigiance, ſparkling from aboue:</l>
               <l>That ſo they may conforme their Loyaltie,</l>
               <l>Conſonant to <hi>Caeſars Solidurij;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who (when they were enrol'd in martiall pay,</l>
               <l>If chanc'd by brunt of fight to loſe the day)</l>
               <l>For griefe would kill themſelues with their own hands,</l>
               <l>So neare ſuccincted with Affections bands:</l>
               <l>Then ſhall thy wals incloſe him plauſibly,</l>
               <l>As to his Throne he entred peaceably.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy <hi>Muſes</hi> flow with <hi>Archimedes</hi> Skill,</l>
               <l>That they thy ſtreets with Rarities may fill.</l>
               <l>For when young <hi>Cato</hi> that braue <hi>Romaine</hi> Peere,</l>
               <l>With his wel-manned ſhips approched neare</l>
               <l>The <hi>Syracuſan</hi> walles ſtrong fortifide;</l>
               <l>By <hi>Archimedes</hi> caution were deſcride:</l>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:19185:42"/>
               <l>They full reſolu'd to raze them flat to ground,</l>
               <l>By him ſuch warlike Engines rare were found,</l>
               <l>(Which from the Tower thereof his Art downe ſent)</l>
               <l>Who turn'd their ſtrong-built Barkes circumferent</l>
               <l>With bottomes vpward, drawne from out the fount,</l>
               <l>And caſt vpon the high confronting mount:</l>
               <l>He fram'd a Doue of wood by Art ſo rate,</l>
               <l>That for ſome ſpace perpended midſt the aire</l>
               <l>Seeming aliue, and counterpois'd ſo right,</l>
               <l>Was thought to flie, moſt ſtrange to humane ſight.</l>
               <l>So ſhall thy <hi>Muſes</hi> from ſweet Sapience,</l>
               <l>Infuſe their Thoughts with powerfull Influence:</l>
               <l>The learn'd <hi>Thalia</hi> that doth on <hi>Pernaſſe</hi> dwell,</l>
               <l>Shall Nectar quaffe from <hi>Aganyppe's</hi> well,</l>
               <l>That they with deepe Deſignes may moue delight,</l>
               <l>Beyond the motions of ſharpe Reaſons ſight:</l>
               <l>From midſt their Rarities ſhall <hi>Caliope</hi> ſing:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Great King of kings, protect king</hi> IAMES <hi>our King.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now genious <hi>Muſe,</hi> drinke of <hi>Castalian</hi> Springs,</l>
               <l>Then ſoare aloft with ſwift <hi>Pegaſian</hi> wings,</l>
               <l>And mounting Euolence to th'ingenious braine;</l>
               <l>There bid thy turret-climing ſprite remaine:</l>
               <l>Suruiue thy Thoughts, ere all the Muſick's done,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Pallas</hi> daunce in this Idilion:</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Phoebus</hi> rauiſhing Lute thy Muſicke be,</l>
               <l>Salute great <hi>Pan</hi> with this <hi>Panygerie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Diuine <hi>Apollo,</hi> Harbinger to <hi>Ioue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To Earth deſcend from mouing ſphaeres aboue,</l>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:19185:42"/>
               <l>With thy bright Chariot, by proud <hi>Eôus</hi> led,</l>
               <l>Where heau'nly Queenes are high enthronized;</l>
               <l>That they as Guards may waite with rare delight,</l>
               <l>On <hi>Albions Caeſars</hi> royalized ſprite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let faire<note n="*" place="margin">Wiſdome.</note> 
                  <hi>Sophia</hi> ſeate the chiefeſt part,</l>
               <l>In the Bed-chamber of his peereleſſe heart;</l>
               <l>That by conuerſe ſhe may pure Motions lend,</l>
               <l>From whence all Motions draw ſucceſſefull end.</l>
               <l>Let louely<note n="*" place="margin">Prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> 
                  <hi>Phroneſis</hi> with cleare Diamonds dight,</l>
               <l>Be euer reſident fore his Princely ſight;</l>
               <l>Feeding with her bright Shine his piercing Eye,</l>
               <l>To ſearch the drifts of wreſting <hi>Sophiſtrie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So ſincere <hi>Truth</hi> ſhall chieue the vpper hand,</l>
               <l>Ore-topping <hi>Vice,</hi> while ſhe amaz'd doth ſtand.</l>
               <l>Let<note n="*" place="margin">Concord.</note> 
                  <hi>Melôs</hi> tune her ſiluer-ſounding Song,</l>
               <l>Within the groues of his minds Motion;</l>
               <l>That Heau'ns <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> ſacred queene of Grace,</l>
               <l>Iuſt meaſures there may tread with loftie trace.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Iuſtice.</note> 
                  <hi>Soter,</hi> vnſheath thy neuer-danted ſword,</l>
               <l>Strike downe-right Blowes, as full-eyes can affoord,</l>
               <l>With ſtrict attendance on his right ſide ſtand,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mercy</hi> on left, t'aſſwage thy rigorous hand,</l>
               <l>And counterpoiſe thy ſcales with Paritie,</l>
               <l>Reiecting ſquint-eyed Partialitie:</l>
               <l>Then ſhall thy Deitie be ador'd of all,</l>
               <l>Congratulated both of great and ſmall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As bright-eyed<note n="*" place="margin">Day-star.</note> 
                  <hi>Eôus Don Phoebus</hi> Page,</l>
               <l>Attends his Maiſters ſweating Pilgrimage,</l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:19185:43"/>
               <l>Sliding vpright with burning flames accrude,</l>
               <l>To his Meridian climing altitude;</l>
               <l>And then deſcends till his hote taske be done,</l>
               <l>Towards the Weſts extracted Horizon.</l>
               <l>So let theſe glorious Empreſſes attend</l>
               <l>Vpon his Acts, from Alpha to the end;</l>
               <l>That by their Conduct he may view the way,</l>
               <l>To dignifie his Throne, and Scepter ſway:</l>
               <l>Purſuing ſtill his princely Thoughts with ſpeed,</l>
               <l>That their rich fruites th'Euent may alwaies feed.</l>
               <l>As' <hi>Numa</hi> was ſuppos'd to ſpend each day</l>
               <l>In deepe conuerſing with <hi>Egeria;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By whoſe aduice he conſtituted Lawes,</l>
               <l>Conſorting to the Vulgar ſorts applauſe:</l>
               <l>So by ſweet Conference with all of theſe,</l>
               <l>Shall he preſcribe his Lawes, Acts, and Decrees;</l>
               <l>Which in their good Succeſſe ſhall ſtand vpright,</l>
               <l>Fore mightie <hi>Ioue,</hi> fore Heau'n and humane ſight.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Albion</hi> thou, abundantly increaſe</l>
               <l>In Wealth, Tranquilitie, and ioy full Peace:</l>
               <l>For that's true Peace, which <hi>Ius</hi> to kingdomes brings,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kings ſubiect to their Lawes, not Lawes to Kings.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now <hi>Mercurie,</hi> ſurnam'd<note n="*" place="margin">Light-ſoot.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Plume thy light wings, make haſt, no time delay;</l>
               <l>Be ſwifter then <hi>Palladius Perſian,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That through the <hi>Romaine</hi> Confines quickly ran</l>
               <l>To <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> where he did remaine,</l>
               <l>Shewing, <hi>The Romaines had the Perſians ſlaine:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:19185:43"/>
               <l>Deſiſt not then (if thou wilt purchaſe name)</l>
               <l>To thruſt this Motto in the chaps of Fame:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Al-ſeeing</hi> Ioue <hi>faire Albions iſle hath blest,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With a renowmed King, and tranguile Rest.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whoſe Vertue gliſtering from his ſtately Throne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Giues ſight vnto his Substitutes each one:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Euen as the Sun with his tranſcendent Light,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tiends all the twinkling Candles of the Night.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Faire <hi>Phoebe</hi> daunce on <hi>Ganges</hi> argent ſtreames;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan Titan</hi> laugh with bright-reflecting Beames;</l>
               <l>Protract thy courſe from burning <hi>Ida's</hi> hill,</l>
               <l>Commaund thy burniſht coach to wander ſtill</l>
               <l>Vnder the ſtarrie Round, and third Degree,</l>
               <l>Till Earth be crown'd with Angels dignitie.</l>
               <l>Great Court of Heau'n thy Synode counite.</l>
               <l>T'adorne his heart with crownes of true Delight,</l>
               <l>That neighbour-kings admiring at his ſtate,</l>
               <l>His Princely ſteps may ſtriue to imitate;</l>
               <l>And that by Soueraigne bliſſe his Raigne may be</l>
               <l>A rare Memoriall to Eternitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O blisfull Concord bred in Heau'ns pure breſt,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Albions</hi> ſacred and aſſured Reſt,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Ioue,</hi> who rules the reſtleſſe ranging skie:</l>
               <l>By thy Decree, that glorious power doth lie,</l>
               <l>With ſweet Accord to keepe the pugnant ſtars,</l>
               <l>And each foule Planet from diſaſtrous wars.</l>
               <l>Celeſtiall <hi>Ens,</hi> that Earths Ens fram'd of nought,</l>
               <l>And by Creation, <hi>Light</hi> from <hi>Darkneſſe brought:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:19185:44"/>
               <l>Thou that refin'd thoſe vitall Elements,</l>
               <l>From the confuſed <hi>Chaos</hi> quinteſſence:</l>
               <l>By whom we liue, reſpire, moue, ſtand, and be;</l>
               <l>Compounded of indifferent Qualitie.</l>
               <l>Thou that commandſt Heau'ns Axletree to moue</l>
               <l>Vpon the diſtant Poles, the Sphaeres aboue</l>
               <l>To turne with meaſured Courſe, and neuer ſtay</l>
               <l>From Agitation neither Night nor Day:</l>
               <l>Yet in the midſt, Earth haſt thou fram'd ſo faſt,</l>
               <l>That ſhall perdure, till Heau'ns huge Frame doth waſt.</l>
               <l>Thou art that <hi>Firſt,</hi> and laſt things doſt pretend;</l>
               <l>Yet ſans Beginning, and without an End:</l>
               <l>Thy glorious Power doth comprehend each one,</l>
               <l>Yet comprehended canſt thou be of none.</l>
               <l>Thou didſt prepare the mountaine <hi>Ararat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(When the wide World in blind-fold Deluge ſate)</l>
               <l>To entertaine the waue-toſt <hi>Arke</hi> with Reſt,</l>
               <l>From whence each Kind abundantly increaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In thee, in thee ſuch powerfull glorie bides;</l>
               <l>From thee ſuch Lenitie and Friendſhip ſlides,</l>
               <l>As may commaund this <hi>Vniuerſe</hi> to bend,</l>
               <l>As mortall <hi>Ens</hi> can neuer comprehend.</l>
               <l>By thy Decree the luſtie Cedars ſpring,</l>
               <l>The bloomie <hi>Ver</hi> abundant fruites doth bring:</l>
               <l>Thou doſt increaſe the grouth of Sommers ſeed,</l>
               <l>For to ſupply the breeme-fac'd Winters need:</l>
               <l>Thou doſt inſpire the hearts of peereleſſe Peeres,</l>
               <l>In ripening Youth to chuſe their flouriſhing Feeres:</l>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:19185:44"/>
               <l>"And looke how faſt to Death <hi>Man</hi> payes his due,</l>
               <l>"So faſt againe doſt thou his Stocke renue.</l>
               <l>As by this Preſident <hi>Albion</hi> now may ſee,</l>
               <l>Who doth inioy IAMES royall Maieſtie:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To whom I wiſh long, long, and happie Raigne,</l>
               <l>Wherein he may the Goſpell pure maintaine;</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Neſtors</hi> yeares (ô Heau'ns) let him excell,</l>
               <l>And be a Father graue in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Grant ſacred <hi>Ioue</hi> his royall Stocke to ſtand,</l>
               <l>His Branch to flouriſh in faire <hi>Albions</hi> Land,</l>
               <l>So long as <hi>Titan</hi> treades Heau'ns ſiluer tracke,</l>
               <l>To analize <hi>Times</hi> compleat Zodiacke:</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Time</hi> himſelfe leaue turning of his cote,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Phoebus</hi> ceaſe to ſtrike <hi>Time</hi> rauiſhing note.</l>
               <l>Thus each true <hi>Engliſh</hi> heart ſincerely pray:</l>
               <l>And he that ſeekes his Perſon to betray,</l>
               <l>Fierce <hi>Proſerpina</hi> with her Daughters three,</l>
               <l>Shall dragge his ſoule to cole-blacke <hi>Tartarie;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To fearefull <hi>Hades,</hi> or the darkeſt Hell,</l>
               <l>Where nought but Diuels and damned Spirits dwell:</l>
               <l>Meane time my genious <hi>Muſe</hi> this Note ſhall ſing:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heau'ns proſper</hi> IAMES, <hi>the Britons lawfull King.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>CECINI.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nuncibo intereà, &amp; Pernaſſi in rupibus altis,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Donec Muſa iterum in beat me exire, latebo.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic_poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:19185:45"/>
            <head>PASTORALL PANEGYRICKS.</head>
            <div type="acrostic_poem">
               <head>Iacobo Regiaeterna Gloria.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>n Winters wracke the torrents rage and flow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>nd ſheapheards forc'd to leaue their pleaſant rockes;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>C</hi>old-wrinkled furrowes ſeated in his brow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi>ut bids them driue their weather-beaten Flockes.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>B</hi>ut mightie <hi>Pan</hi> commannds a <hi>Cedar</hi> ſpring,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi>ut of whoſe roote faire-flouriſhing <hi>Branches</hi> grow;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>iſing in heighth, Heau'ns Quire about him ſing,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>ach loftie <hi>Oake</hi> doth pure Alleigeance ſhow.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>G</hi>raze now ye tender <hi>Lambes,</hi> skip and repast</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>n fruitfull Groues, vnder this <hi>Cedar</hi> ſhroud,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>ſteeme not of fierce <hi>AEolus</hi> bluſtring blast,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>T</hi>urne not from fields when miſts bright <hi>Titan</hi> cloud.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>ager<note n="*" place="margin">Roma</note> 
                  <hi>Phaea,</hi> the wild <hi>Cremonian</hi> Sow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>auening abroad, and ſearching for her prey,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>ought can obtaine but dreadfull ouerthrow;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>s <hi>Flocks</hi> ſuruine, ſhe ſurfets in decay.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>G</hi>reat <hi>Cedar</hi> ſpread, in laſting glorie ſpring,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi>eaues, Viburnes, Flowers, All ſhall ſing thy praiſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi>ur <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>Aſtraea's</hi> King,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>ecrown'd be thou with neuer-fading Baies:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>n <hi>Albions</hi> Groue, flouriſh thy royall Bloud,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>s long as Riuers flow, and Cedars bud.</l>
               <p>Aſtra Deo nil maius habent, nil Caeſare terra: Sic Caeſar terras, vt Deus aſtra, regat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acrostic_poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:19185:46"/>
               <head>Anna valeat Regina.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>ſtraea peeping from the skie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>ymphs and Satyres gaz'd to ſpie</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>ature worke her owne Deſpaire,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>nd foile her ſelfe to frame that <hi>Faire.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>V</hi>p Flockes and dance, pipe ruſticke Swaines,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>ll fragrant flowers adorne the plaines:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi>oe, <hi>Aſtraea</hi> comes at hand,</l>
               <l>(<hi>E</hi>uer <hi>Lucina</hi> by her ſtand:)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſtraea</hi> glideth from the aire</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>T</hi>o guild the Groues; ſhe fairest <hi>Faire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>euiues the Plants, recures the Sprayes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>ternall be her Crowne of Bayes.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>G</hi>aze may the Sun with ſplendant Bright,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>n darke doth ſhe ſurpaſſe his Light:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>ow ſweet <hi>Muſes</hi> ye behold,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſtraea</hi> trip on earthly Mold.</l>
               <p>
                  <hi>Semper vireſcas.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acrostic_poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:19185:47"/>
               <head>Henricus Princeps vivat.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>H</hi>o, Syluanes, Nymphs, leape from your ſiluer lake,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>rect your viols fil'd with golden praiſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>ow <hi>Satyres</hi> ſing, your Cynicke Cels far ſake:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rodanus,</hi> thy madide beard from Riuers raiſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>n ſweet agree,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>C</hi>ome ſing with me,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>V</hi>nto that <hi>Starre</hi> that deignes to glide theſe waies.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi>weet <hi>Flora</hi> now imbelliſh thy faire Bowers;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paris,</hi> thou ſhepheards Ioy, Heau'ns muſicke bring,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>euolue thy Lils, tripping amongſt theſe flowers,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>nfuſe rare Tunes, and rurall <hi>Paeans</hi> ſing:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>ote his bright <hi>Face,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>C</hi>ombin'd with <hi>Grace:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eccho</hi> with <hi>Aues</hi> bid the mountaines ring.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebus</hi> intraile him with thy golden ray,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi>o fragrant <hi>Clores,</hi> Sommers verdant Queene,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>V</hi>nto his Progreſſe, thy vert ſhades diſplay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>nuellop him around with Chaplets greene.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>V</hi>nto this <hi>Shrine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>ll ioyes diuine;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>T</hi>o Heau'n a <hi>Sun,</hi> to earth a <hi>Load-ſtarre</hi> ſeene.</l>
               <p>
                  <hi>Semperſplendeſcas.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19185:48"/>
            <head>ἘΠΙΜΕΛΩΔΕΣ.</head>
            <l>Laeta ſit iſta Dies, totum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> canenda per orbe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
            <l>Qua Princeps nobis Rex<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> IACOBVS erit.</l>
            <l>Plebs pia cum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> pia laetetur plebe Senatus:</l>
            <l>Redde Deo grates ANGLIA tota tuo.</l>
            <l>Attulit illa Dies feſſis miſeriſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Leuamen,</l>
            <l>Et Lumen caecis, attulitilla Dies.</l>
            <l>Tempora temporibus mutantur triſtia laetis,</l>
            <l>Succedunt ſummis Gaudia ſumma Malis.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19185:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
