<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A prophesie of Cadvvallader, last king of the Britaines containing a comparison of the English kings, with many worthy Romanes, from William Rufus, till Henry the fift. Henry the fift, his life and death. Foure battels betweene the two houses of Yorke and Lancaster. The field of Banbery. The losse of Elizabeth. The praise of King Iames. And lastly a poeme to the yong Prince.</title>
            <author>Herbert, William, fl. 1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12752</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103828</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839573</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839573</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4005</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02624)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4005)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1070:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A prophesie of Cadvvallader, last king of the Britaines containing a comparison of the English kings, with many worthy Romanes, from William Rufus, till Henry the fift. Henry the fift, his life and death. Foure battels betweene the two houses of Yorke and Lancaster. The field of Banbery. The losse of Elizabeth. The praise of King Iames. And lastly a poeme to the yong Prince.</title>
                  <author>Herbert, William, fl. 1604.</author>
                  <author>Cadwaladr, Vendigaid, d. 664?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[70] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Creede, for Roger Iackson, and are to be solde at his shop in Fleetstreete, ouer against the Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: William Harbert.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4005:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4005:1"/>
            <p>A
PROPHESIE
of Cadwallader, laſt King
of the Britaines:</p>
            <p>Containing a Compariſon of the Engliſh
Kings, with many worthy Romanes, from
<hi>William Rufus,</hi> till <hi>Henry</hi> the fift.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, his life and death.</p>
            <p>Foure Battels betweene the two Houſes of
<hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancanster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Field of <hi>Baubery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The loſſe of <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The praiſe of King <hi>Iames.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly a Poeme to the yong
<hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi>
Printed by Thomas Creede, for Roger Iackſon, and are to
be ſolde at his ſhop in Fleetſtreete, ouer againſt the
Conduit. 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4005:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4005:2"/>
            <head>TO THE NO LESSE VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
then Honourable Gentleman
Syr Philip Herbert, Knight of the
moſt noble order of the Bathe.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>RIght worthy Sir, the honor which I beare,</l>
               <l>And euer will vnto your worthy line,</l>
               <l>Makes me preſume (preſumption cannot feare)</l>
               <l>To tender you this litle Booke of mine:</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſubſtance if your honor will approue,</l>
               <l>My lines ſhall limits want, ſo doth my loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That man of men whoſe fatall name you beare,<note place="margin">S. P. S.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Of his vnnumbred worthes the chiefe were theſe:</l>
               <l>Three glorious wreathes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his brow to weare,</l>
               <l>Which ſaid he, loued learning, warre, and peace.</l>
               <l>O aemulate this man the ſonne of Fame,<note place="margin">Baye.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Haue all his vertues, though but halfe his name.<note place="margin">Oliue, and Oake.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Purſue thy firſt deſignments (noble Knight)</l>
               <l>Affect thy Country, and admire thy King:</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4005:3"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle Dedicatorie.</head>
            <l>Be as thou art, ſincere in all mens ſight,</l>
            <l>Do this, and I thy praiſe will euer ſing.</l>
            <l>I ſmoothe not I, nor do I hope for gaine,</l>
            <l>Accept my loue, and ſo requite my paine.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>The admirer of your vertues, whoſe
life is deuoted to your loue.
William Harbert.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4005:3"/>
            <head>THE AVTHOR TO HIS
Poeme.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>TRace the wide ſtage of ſpight and proud diſdaine,</l>
               <l>And mount the ſteps of ſcornefull enuies ſtaire,</l>
               <l>Imperfect embrion of an idle braine,</l>
               <l>Soare not aloft, vſe meane, do not deſpaire,</l>
               <l>The beſt way is betweene the ſea and ayre:</l>
               <l>Be like thy ſelfe, be neither proud nor baſe,</l>
               <l>One enuy gets, the other gaynes diſgrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Be not too huge in ſhew, in ſtrength a childe,</l>
               <l>Theſe imateriall Epithites eſchew,</l>
               <l>Be to the ſcornfull proud, the humble milde,</l>
               <l>Put not thy cenſure to an open view,</l>
               <l>Speech enuy oft, but Silence neuer knew.</l>
               <l>When thou ſeeſt good then prayſe, when bad be blinde,</l>
               <l>Then wit will beare with thee, and fooles be kinde.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4005:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Which in ſilence neſt ſo many dayes</l>
               <l>Smoothered the ſlight of my vnfeathered quill,</l>
               <l>Becauſe I knew it could not merit prayſe,</l>
               <l>Here where the Muſes ſang and ſhewd their skill,</l>
               <l>For this did ſeeme to be <hi>Parnaſtus</hi> hill:</l>
               <l>But this amaz'd my minde, and grieu'd mine eye</l>
               <l>To ſee the <hi>Buzards</hi> with the <hi>Eagles</hi> flye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ſee a troupe of Souldiers neuer tride,</l>
               <l>Beſiege a fort by nature fenc'd on high,</l>
               <l>I was aſham'd to ſee the heires of pride,</l>
               <l>Debaſe in vnexperienc'd Poetry,</l>
               <l>The immortall vertues of great Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>I theſe are they that do the Muſes ſtaine,</l>
               <l>One wanton pen makes all be iudged vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I which ſecurely on theſe errours gaz'd,</l>
               <l>And ſafely ſtood vpon the ſilent ſhore,</l>
               <l>When others Ships by enuies rockes were craz'd,</l>
               <l>Loue me conſtrain'd, as pride did them before,</l>
               <l>To truſt the rockes and leaue the ſilent ſhore:</l>
               <l>The loue of friends, not prayſe did me perſwade,</l>
               <l>Againſt my will, against the ſtreames to wade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore to you whoſe iudgement is ſincere,</l>
               <l>If any fault, as many faults there be,</l>
               <l>Seeme harſh and iarring to a tuned eare,</l>
               <l>Impute the blame to thoſe, and not to me,</l>
               <l>Who made my pen ſhew his infirmitie:</l>
               <l>If any good as ſmall there is you ſee,</l>
               <l>Reape you the profit, yeeld but thankes to me.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4005:4"/>
            <head>A PROPHESIE OF
Cadwallader, laſt King of
the Britaines.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SItting with <hi>Clio</hi> by the gliding <hi>Thame,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deſcription of Fortune.</note>
               </l>
               <l>neere to her ſiluer girt the verdant ſtrand,</l>
               <l>I ſaw <hi>Rhamuſis</hi> ſo adornd by fame:</l>
               <l>Dauncing in meaſures, on the farther ſand,</l>
               <l>Holding a Ball of gold within her hand:</l>
               <l>She ſtood on that, that neuer ſtood but went,</l>
               <l>So muſt all thoſe that truſt her gouernment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then did this Queene, her wandring coach aſcend,</l>
               <l>Whoſe wheeles were more inconſtant then the winde,</l>
               <l>A mighty troope this Empreſſe did attend,</l>
               <l>There might you <hi>Caius Marius</hi> caruing find,</l>
               <l>And martiall <hi>Scylla</hi> courting <hi>Venus</hi> kind:</l>
               <l>Times alter, and in times we changed bee,</l>
               <l>Chaunce onely conſtant is in leuitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There might you ſee how <hi>Archimedes</hi> art,<note place="margin">Geometry</note>
               </l>
               <l>As a ſtrong bulwarke guarded <hi>Syracuſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How <hi>Scipio</hi> fought and <hi>Cato</hi> ſtabd his hart,</l>
               <l>How <hi>Anthony</hi> did wrong the ſacred muſe,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Cleopatras</hi> body did abuſe.</l>
               <l>How <hi>Mago</hi> fell in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Hanniball</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did pitch his tents before <hi>Saturnias</hi> wall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4005:5"/>
               <l>His ſtratagems, his ſnares, vnequall fightes,</l>
               <l>Scipio, Sempronius, <hi>and</hi> Flaminius <hi>ſlaine:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aemilius</hi> dead amidſt his wounded knights,</l>
               <l>How chance his youth with praiſe did entertaine,</l>
               <l>And in his age how Fortune wrought this paine:</l>
               <l>All this ſhee did, oh man her fraude perceiue,</l>
               <l>And truſt her not, for ſhee will thee deceiue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How <hi>Alexander</hi> roſe at <hi>Darius</hi> fall,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> within the Lyons den:</l>
               <l>How <hi>Scypio</hi> did beſiedge <hi>Numantias</hi> wall,</l>
               <l>And many thouſands more which ſcape my pen,</l>
               <l>Amongſt this fatall troope of Fortunes men:</l>
               <l>I ſaw an aged king except I erre,</l>
               <l>That cleaped was the high <hi>Cadwallader.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He was the laſt, ſaue three of Fortunes trayne,</l>
               <l>Thoſe were a <hi>Danea, Saxon,</hi> and a <hi>Norman king:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hengist</hi> the firſt, next was <hi>Denmarkes</hi> ſwayne,</l>
               <l>The laſt was <hi>Normanes</hi> baſtard, which did bring</l>
               <l>Plenty of Ioy; whoſe praiſe the Engliſh ſing.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>William,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">William the Conquerour.</note> whoſe valure mixt with happy fate,</l>
               <l>Brought bondage to the <hi>Iuthes</hi> and Augles ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Britaine Monarch ware a ſimple Crowne,<note place="margin">Cadwallader laſt King of the Buranes, his land being vexed with the ſcourge of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, went to Rome, where he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke the habit of a Friar</note>
               </l>
               <l>Hauing ſmall beades of Amber by his ſide:</l>
               <l>A ſiluer Croſſe, a Friers white frize gowne,</l>
               <l>Vpon an humble Aſſe this King did ride,</l>
               <l>As white as ſnow, or as the ſiluer tide.</l>
               <l>One hand a ſtaffe, the other held a booke,</l>
               <l>On which his eyes continually did looke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4005:5"/>
               <l>Wherein were charactred in lines of gold,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Locrinus</hi> warres, and <hi>Humbers</hi> tragedy:</l>
               <l>The King himſelfe by <hi>Gwendoline</hi> controld,</l>
               <l>The Scythians paramour of <hi>Germany</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eſtrilda</hi> drownd, the praiſe of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sabrina</hi> thruſt in <hi>Seuerns</hi> flowing maine,</l>
               <l>Poore <hi>Madan</hi> by the curres of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſlaine.<note place="margin">Wolues.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Britaine Manlius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Madans ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſonne.</note> not the Romane knight,</l>
               <l>Thinking to ſlay <hi>Mempricius Madans</hi> ſonne:</l>
               <l>Himſelfe was by his brother ſlaine in fight,</l>
               <l>And he by wolues (as <hi>Madan</hi> was) vndone,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Sodomes</hi> gilt to luſt his mind had wonne.</l>
               <l>The foremoſt booke did <hi>Britaines</hi> raigne relate,</l>
               <l>The next of <hi>Swayne,</hi> the third of <hi>Saxens</hi> ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The fourth and laſt did write of <hi>Williams</hi> raigne,</l>
               <l>In which there was an ancient propheſie:</l>
               <l>Written of yore, confirmd by <hi>Merlins</hi> twaine,</l>
               <l>What ſhould enſue to <hi>Williams</hi> progeny,</l>
               <l>Was there at large expainde in poetry.</l>
               <l>The warres of <hi>England</hi> for the crowne of <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There many battels with their mournfull chance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ciuill warres of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Cambrian</hi> helmet changde for <hi>Englands</hi> crowne:</l>
               <l>How true diſcent did <hi>Tudors</hi> blood preferre,</l>
               <l>The brow of peace diſpearced <hi>Mars</hi> his frowne,<note place="margin">The helmet was the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient creſt of the Teu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The land of warre is rulde by iuſtice gowne.</l>
               <l>Theſe ſhall haue end, then ſhall ariſe a King</l>
               <l>Which plenty ſhall conduct, in concords ſtring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4005:6"/>
               <l>He with vnnumbred linkes of reaſons chaine,</l>
               <l>Shall three in one, and one in three vnite:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britaine</hi> ſhould be the name, for <hi>Brute</hi> doth raigne,</l>
               <l>A King commands no Princes fauorite,</l>
               <l>This he intreates, for this his penne doth write:</l>
               <l>Ceaſe to command, learne ſubiects to obay,</l>
               <l>Reaſon where iuſtice rules, beares greateſt ſway.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Is it not peerleſſe praiſe with peace to gaine,</l>
               <l>That for the which, our fathers ſpent their blood:</l>
               <l>And neuer age but ours could reobtaine?</l>
               <l>O happy men if that you ſaw ſuch good,</l>
               <l>But will is masked ſtill with errors hood.</l>
               <l>Let ture obeiſans vp this diet breake,</l>
               <l>So <hi>Caeſar</hi> wils, ſo <hi>Cicero</hi> doth ſpeake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The fect was this, the propheſie was ſuch</l>
               <l>Which he had read with carefull induſtry,</l>
               <l>And quoted euery line with iudgments touch,</l>
               <l>A midſt his ſtudy caſting vp his eye,</l>
               <l>Seeing his miſtreſſe Fortune was not nye.</l>
               <l>His booke he ſleightly ſet into his gowne,</l>
               <l>Which on the yellow ſand fell quickly downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thence poſted he on his maieſtique Aſſe,</l>
               <l>Like ſome ſlow rider pacing to the race:</l>
               <l>Than <hi>Iſis</hi> ſiluer channell did I paſſe,</l>
               <l>And thither went, where as mine eyes might gaze</l>
               <l>On that faire booke, clad in a golden caſe.</l>
               <l>I paſt the Annales, for it pleaſde mine eye,</l>
               <l>To muſe vpon that ſacred propheſie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4005:6"/>
               <l>When I had read vnto the latter lyne,</l>
               <l>I ſaw the aged king returne with ſpeede?</l>
               <l>Kind Syr (quoth he) ſaw you a booke of mine?</l>
               <l>I Syr (quoth I) if this be he indeed</l>
               <l>I gaue it him; he gaue me thankes for meed.</l>
               <l>He poſted thence, I to my ſtudy went,</l>
               <l>Where on this matter many houres I ſpent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At laſt I was reſolu'd for to relate</l>
               <l>In Poetry the things mine eyes did ſee:</l>
               <l>Which was the vncertainety of humane ſtate,</l>
               <l>To paint the things a right with equitie,</l>
               <l>I did implore the ayde of memorie.</l>
               <l>Which ſhe denide; Oh worthies pardon mee,</l>
               <l>If ought I write amiſſe which you ſhall ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not <hi>Orpheus</hi> trees, and birds inchanting quill,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Homers</hi> art heere (Reader) ſhalt thou ſee:</l>
               <l>Expect not <hi>Ouids</hi> verſe, nor <hi>Maroes</hi> skill,</l>
               <l>For if you doe, you ſhall deceiued bee:</l>
               <l>If bad it is, pray gentles beare with mee.</l>
               <l>Say it is meane, thou doſt mee much commend,</l>
               <l>I'de haue it meane, becauſe I meane to mend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Miſtake mee not, I liue in hope to pleaſe:</l>
               <l>Diſpraiſe mee not, before thou knoweſt mee well:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Maugre</hi> ſweete, not reuenge, my lines loue peace,</l>
               <l>Doe not my ſhame before thou ſeeſt it tell:</l>
               <l>Marke euery line, and each wordes nature ſpell.</l>
               <l>Ere thou beginſt to reade, looke, beare in minde</l>
               <l>Of whom I write, yea how, and in what kind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4005:7"/>
               <l>Faire <hi>Englands</hi> Peeres with <hi>Romanes</hi> I compare,</l>
               <l>Their warres, their ſpoiles, their fightes and victory,</l>
               <l>Their filthy vices, with their vertues rare:</l>
               <l>Their laud, diſpraiſe, their praiſe and infamy,</l>
               <l>Their conqueſts triumphes with their treachery.</l>
               <l>Then doth our muſe declare inteſtine warres,</l>
               <l>Kings conquering fields, and Princes wounding iarres.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then doth ſhe mount the ayre with <hi>Eagles</hi> winges,</l>
               <l>Then to the North ſhee goes, and paſſeth <hi>Twidet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſings his praiſe, which endles glory bringes,</l>
               <l>Who like a <hi>Pilot</hi> doth this <hi>Iſland</hi> guide,</l>
               <l>Which like a barke, within the Sea doth ride.</l>
               <l>This land is ſeated like to <hi>Venice</hi> ſtate,</l>
               <l>The waues, the walles, and euery ſhip a gate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Leaſt that my Gates be wider then my towne,</l>
               <l>And that <hi>Diogines</hi> my folly ſee:</l>
               <l>My proems prologue Ile ſet quickly downe,</l>
               <l>And bend my muſe vnto the Propheſie:</l>
               <l>Where you may reade art mixt with induſtry.</l>
               <l>Needs muſt I erre, to erre all men are bent,</l>
               <l>To perſeuere, is a bad beaſts intent.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Compariſon.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O What a ſea of blood ſhall <hi>England</hi> ſpill,<note place="margin">So called for aſsiſting Godfrey of Bullion, in his expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daea. Baſsianus and Geta.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When <hi>Normans</hi> Prince, and <hi>Palaſtinas</hi> friend,</l>
                  <l>With burgonets of ſteele our fieldes doth fill,</l>
                  <l>Brothers muſt ſtriue as did <hi>Seuerus</hi> kind,</l>
                  <l>Enuious ambition makes iuſt nature blind.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arunce</hi> and <hi>Brutus</hi> dead, Alarums ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Publicola</hi> doth liue, and loueth peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:7"/>
                  <l>When <hi>Brutus</hi> dide, <hi>Valerius</hi> then did raigne,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Arunce</hi> fell,<note place="margin">Henry the 2. ſonne of Mawd the Empreſſe, and Stephen Earle of Blois, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew to Henry the firſt.</note> the <hi>Tuſcan</hi> Emperour fled:</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Tirrolls</hi> ſhaft ſhall enter <hi>Rufus</hi> braine,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Henries</hi> life with <hi>Roberts</hi> lightes are fled,</l>
                  <l>When all theſe ſleepe in natures earthly bed.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Norfolke</hi> ſhall giue to <hi>Stephen, Henries</hi> due,</l>
                  <l>Peace then ſhall be, but warre ſhall ſoone enſue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flora</hi> is fled, ſtout <hi>Hiems</hi> weares her crowne,</l>
                  <l>Attir'd like <hi>Mars</hi> in furniture of ſteele:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aniow</hi> and <hi>Blois</hi> ſtriue for the Imperiall Crowne,</l>
                  <l>A griefe ſurpaſſing griefe doth <hi>England</hi> feele,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt doubtfull Fortune turns her doubtfull wheele.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Camillus</hi> comes, the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> feare his voice,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alba</hi> is freed, and <hi>Albion</hi> hath her choice.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When <hi>Rome</hi> was ſackt, <hi>Camillus</hi> ended ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>And made <hi>Bellinus</hi> brother to diſpaire:<note place="margin">Brennus.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When <hi>Germanes</hi> Empreſſe <hi>Mawd</hi> ſhall end her life,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> ſhall claime the crowne, as lawfull heire,</l>
                  <l>His Eame in graue, but he in regall chaire</l>
                  <l>Is plac't, and rules his princely Peeres with peace,</l>
                  <l>His ſonnes rebell, and concord gins to ceaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now ſprings the plant,<note place="margin">Henry the 2. the firſt Plantaginet.</note> from hence our ioy ſhall ſpring,</l>
                  <l>Victorious <hi>Aniow</hi> crownd in regall ſtate:</l>
                  <l>Liuing, adopts an heir, inueſts a King,</l>
                  <l>Vagratefull child ſpurd by a womans hate,<note place="margin">Richard 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sturd forraine foes the land to ruinate.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes</hi> ſword is Conſul,<note place="margin">Marcellus, ſo called by Hanniball.</note> foe-men tribute paies,</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>Henries</hi> dead, Chriſts friend the Septer ſwaies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:8"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Marcellus</hi> which did <hi>Syracuſa</hi> burne,</l>
                  <l>Made <hi>Affricks</hi> praiſe,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nniball.</note> to praiſe his matchles minde,</l>
                  <l>And place his aſhes in a golden vrne:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Aibious</hi> lyon ſprung from lyons kinde,</l>
                  <l>When death the king and prince in cords ſhall binde.</l>
                  <l>Heele ſpend his treaſure, for <hi>Iehouas</hi> good:</l>
                  <l>But woe alas, a ſlaue ſhall ſpill his blood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Deſigned <hi>Iohn</hi> diſueſts young <hi>Britaines</hi> Duke,</l>
                  <l>But Antichriſtians prince, our ſauiours foe:</l>
                  <l>Bringes <hi>Lewis</hi> in, and doth him ſtraight rebuke,</l>
                  <l>Egles of England, yeeld to Swans of Poe,</l>
                  <l>A Monarch falles by Monkes,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us Flam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s ſlaine at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e batle of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hraſimenus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>oſe death is by his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>enged in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>iſoning of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>anniball.</note> fates wills it ſo.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Titus</hi> ſuruiues, though flames <hi>Flaminius</hi> burne,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Worſter</hi> is ſafe, and <hi>Lewis</hi> doth returne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>At <hi>Thraſimenus</hi> valiant <hi>Titus</hi> fell,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Pruſias</hi> Court, his ſonne reuengde his death:</l>
                  <l>Form happie heauen, though <hi>Iohn</hi> to haples hell</l>
                  <l>Headlong did ſlide, his ſonne ſhall weare the wreath,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Dolphen</hi> flyes, and <hi>Mars</hi> begins to breath:</l>
                  <l>Tempeſtuous whitle-windes,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>enry the 3.</note> breake the Temple gate</l>
                  <l>Of Peace; the peers the king, the prince the Baron hate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ciuill diſſention and diſlovall armes,</l>
                  <l>Cleerly declares <hi>Clares</hi> hidden enmitie:</l>
                  <l>A fatall ſtarre foretelleth future harmes,</l>
                  <l>The legions meete, each doth the other ſpye,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eccho</hi> reſounds, S. <hi>George,</hi> S. <hi>George,</hi> both cry:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gracchus</hi> is ſtabd, young <hi>Scipio</hi> peace maintaines,</l>
                  <l>The Barrons tam'd, all conquering <hi>Longſhanckes</hi> raignes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:8"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes</hi> enuious <hi>Tribunes</hi> that ignoble Tribe,</l>
                  <l>The vitious iſſue of a vertuous dame:</l>
                  <l>Did the baſe mindes of poore <hi>Plebeians</hi> bribe,</l>
                  <l>To gaine them honour,<note place="margin">Caius and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius Grac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus.</note> with their Countries ſhame:</l>
                  <l>They dead; the world did ring with <hi>Romanes</hi> faine.</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Clare</hi> and <hi>Mountford</hi> ſhall, who being ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> ſhall vanquiſh <hi>Calidonias</hi> plaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Acon</hi> is tane, and <hi>Tunis</hi> feares his ſtroakes,</l>
                  <l>He loued peace,<note place="margin">The ſaying of Leoline him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as Powell hath laid down in his life.</note> yet bare a warriors ſhield:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cambria</hi> diſdain'd to weare her ſiſters yoake,</l>
                  <l>The Enſignes ſpred, both ſtriue to win the field,</l>
                  <l>The bridge is paſt, and <hi>Leoline</hi> muſt yeeld:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Marius</hi> departs, <hi>Proſcriptio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> gin to ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>The Prince of warre ſhall end his dayes in peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Deſtruction graz'd on fertill <hi>Italy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Syllas</hi> legions vanquiſht <hi>Marius</hi> might:</l>
                  <l>So ciuill warres ſhall feed on <hi>Britany,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Leolinus</hi> that all daring Knight,</l>
                  <l>Is tane by <hi>Edward</hi> in vnequall fight:</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Marius</hi> fell, <hi>Concordia</hi> gan to ſmile,</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Wales</hi> will amplify faire <hi>Englands</hi> ſtile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reſplendant <hi>Iuno,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Queens Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel wife to Edward the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. was next heire to Charles king of France whoſe title our preſent king doth enioy</note> leaues her ſacred throne,</l>
                  <l>Young <hi>Gaueſton</hi> bewitcht great <hi>Edwards</hi> hart:</l>
                  <l>The minor Gods bewaile <hi>Saturnias</hi> mone,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bohume</hi> and <hi>Beaumount</hi> takes the <hi>Marchers</hi> part,</l>
                  <l>And falſe <hi>Matreners</hi> ſtabbes <hi>Carnaruans</hi> hart:</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Caeſars</hi> office <hi>Scipio</hi> ſtriues in vaine,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>March</hi> too ſoone retells his triple gaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:9"/>
                  <l>When that the Romane Eagles graſpt of yore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scipio</hi> with auncient <hi>Lentulus</hi> did ſtriue:<note place="margin">Scipio &amp; Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus two wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Ro ſtroue vehemently in the campe of Pomper: for the Biſhoprick of Rome, but the battels ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; Caeſar winning, their ſtrife ended with their liues</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>For <hi>Iulius</hi> prieſthood, whoſe deſerts were more,</l>
                  <l>But when that <hi>Pompeys</hi> legions did not thriue,</l>
                  <l>They taſted gall within the honies hiue.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So Wigmore</hi> ſeekes in vaine to get a Crowne,</l>
                  <l>But by Lord <hi>Mountaoute</hi> is tumbled downe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Terras</hi> proud iſſue tam'd, immortall <hi>Ioue</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Rides in his Chariot, through the azurde skie:</l>
                  <l>Adornd with Valure, Mercy, Peace and Loue,</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Caeſar</hi> rode in <hi>Rome</hi> with maieſty,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scipio</hi> would liue, life <hi>Cato</hi> doth deny.</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Wigmores</hi> honor ſeekes, but muſt not part,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Matreuers</hi> hand, hath ſtabd <hi>Matreuers</hi> hart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Warres thunderbolt,<note place="margin">Ed. the third, maried Phillip daughter to the Earle of Henault.</note> with his Egiptian pearle,</l>
                  <l>Illuſtrious <hi>Venus</hi> and her martiall Bride</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Phillips</hi> faire ſiſter, with great <hi>Mercias</hi> Earle,</l>
                  <l>Submits to <hi>Henaults</hi> mounting-minded bride,</l>
                  <l>Vengeance and Fury ſcourge inhumane pride.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Egipt</hi> is loſt, and <hi>Authony</hi> muſt die,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>March</hi> is immurde, and twiſe he may not flie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When <hi>Anthony</hi> did <hi>Cleopatra</hi> loue,<note place="margin">Lord Roger Mortimer Earle of March and Queene Iſabel, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; Cleopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra:</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And did <hi>Auguſtas</hi> chamber-bed forgoe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bellona Caeſars</hi> irefull minde did moue:</l>
                  <l>To worke reuenge on chaſte <hi>Octauias</hi> foe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Marcus</hi> is ſlaine, he muſt his Loue forgoe.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Anthony</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra</hi> were,</l>
                  <l>So is Queene <hi>Ifabel</hi> and <hi>Mortimer.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:9"/>
                  <l>Depreſſed waters element, ſome thinke,</l>
                  <l>Is downe ſuppreſt by powers moſt diuine:</l>
                  <l>Some iudge that <hi>Terra</hi> doth the moiſture drinke,</l>
                  <l>Yet certes ſhall men ſee with mortall evne,</l>
                  <l>When deadly water ſhall with ayre combine,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Mortimer</hi> whoſe name from waters ſprang,</l>
                  <l>Shall waue in waues of ayre, and there ſhall hang.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vermilion</hi> collour'd clowdes of purple warre,</l>
                  <l>Are by the radiant beames of <hi>Edwards</hi> raigne:</l>
                  <l>Form <hi>Englands</hi> territors exiled farre,</l>
                  <l>But ſtay (me thinkes) <hi>Bellona</hi> ſoundes againe:<note place="margin">Edward the blacke Prince compared to Geranicus.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And calles forth <hi>Mars</hi> to fight in <hi>Aquitaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Stay <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſtay, let valiant <hi>Druſus</hi> goe:</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Arthurs</hi> heire, can vanquiſh <hi>Artois</hi> foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When that <hi>Tiberius</hi> did the Septer ſway,<note place="margin">Edward the blacke Prince ayded the Erle of Artois a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt King Iohn of France.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Albas</hi> Empire, great <hi>Saturnias</hi> king:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Germanicus</hi> whoſe head was deckt with bay,</l>
                  <l>Fought ſtill abroad, and conqueſt home did bring:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Edward</hi> did whoſe praiſe the <hi>Spanyards</hi> ſing,</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Beaumount</hi> witnes fearfull <hi>Phillips</hi> flight.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Iohn</hi> which yeelded to the <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi> knight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The wandring Planets of the burniſht skye,</l>
                  <l>Are by the vncompriſed Spheare of <hi>loue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thruſt here and there, as men condemn'd to dye,</l>
                  <l>Heauen were nought, if Heauen did not moue:</l>
                  <l>So nature taught, ſo natures ſonne did proue.</l>
                  <l>Like vnto theſe,<note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note> or like a Comet bright,</l>
                  <l>Through euery region <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſent his light.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:10"/>
                  <l>The <hi>Zodiaks</hi> lamp in the Eclipticke line,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ermanicus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>peaſed Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>any, but end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d his dayes by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oiſon in Aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Twice vrgd his courſer to a ſwift careere:<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dward prince of Wales re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ored Peter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing of Spaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nto his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ome by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onqueſt of Henry his baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard brother, at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he battle of Nazers.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Hitrurian</hi> ſonne doth in the Eaſt decline,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Europes</hi> Weſt his praiſe did firſt appeere,</l>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Climatericall</hi> diſaſter yeere:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caeſar</hi> thy glory in the Weſt did riſe,</l>
                  <l>The poiſoned Eaſt, thy raine did deuiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So ſiluer ſtreames and topleſſe Apenine,</l>
                  <l>Which doe confront terreſtriall <hi>Paradiſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Muſt not great <hi>Edwards</hi> wandering Fame confine,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ohn Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eaumont, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ooke part with the eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſh againſt the French nation, but afterwards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e fauoured the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iohn, king of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Bellona</hi> ſtratagems deuiſe:</l>
                  <l>That he with Honors wings ſhould mount the skyes.</l>
                  <l>Exiled <hi>Peter</hi> doth implore his ayde,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iberia</hi> quakes, to ſee the croſſe diſplayd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reuolting <hi>Henault,</hi> and relenting <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are terrified at <hi>Bruſe</hi> and <hi>Balliols</hi> fall:</l>
                  <l>No Salike law, can barre bold <hi>Phillips</hi> ſonne,<note place="margin">The lord Aud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley at the battle of Poytiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued himſelfe moſt valiant, as Craſinius did in Pharſalia, who bad Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar be of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and take courage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he fought and that day he ſhould praiſe him aliue or dead, which he performed, for he loſt his l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e in the purſuite of honor, and for the ſafety of Caeſar.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>His matchleſſe valure cauſed a kingdomes thrall:</l>
                  <l>Whilſt ſlothfull <hi>Charles</hi> immur'd him in a wall.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Germanias</hi> terror wan a glorious field,</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Cambrias</hi> monarch made a King to yeeld.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Careleſſe of death, like to a thunder-bolt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Englands Craſinius</hi> with a maſſie lance:</l>
                  <l>And not vnlike a fierce vntamed Colt,</l>
                  <l>Glides like the ſiluer <hi>Rheine</hi> through yeelding <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Blinded with age great <hi>Boheme</hi> falls by chance.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caligula</hi> is borne, the ſinke of ſhame,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Richard</hi> miſled, deſerues an endleſſe blame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:10"/>
                  <l>The worldes faire miſtreſſe, Empreſſe of the earth,</l>
                  <l>Ordaines a triumph for <hi>Auguſtus</hi> heire:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi> triumphes at young <hi>Gaſcoignes</hi> birth,</l>
                  <l>Wonder of Armes ſet in <hi>Victorias</hi> chaire,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Troynouant</hi> with <hi>Tropheys</hi> doth repaire.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes</hi> Senators attended <hi>Albas</hi> ſtarre,</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Albion</hi> Peeres did waite on <hi>Albious</hi> carre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Two glorious ſonnes, rules the celeſtiall Globe,</l>
                  <l>Cheering the world with their tranſpearcing rayes:</l>
                  <l>Garniſht with Saphires, and a Iaſper robe,</l>
                  <l>(Vntimely chaunce) times wonder ends his dayes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aemilius</hi> mournes amidſt his <hi>Tropheys</hi> praiſe.<note place="margin">Ed. the 3. compared to Paulus Aemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> who in his greateſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry loſt his chiefeſt ioy, namely his t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſonnes.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Troies</hi> hope is dead, and <hi>Priams Hector</hi> ſlaine:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> hath loſt his ſonne, his ſonne a raigne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Impartiall death maskt in a ſable weede,</l>
                  <l>Paſſeth the <hi>Romanes</hi> watch and <hi>Praetors</hi> guard:</l>
                  <l>And to <hi>Tiberius</hi> royall tent doth ſpeede,</l>
                  <l>Phiſicke reſiſts, and death by art is bard,</l>
                  <l>But art doth yeeld, for death was too too hard:</l>
                  <l>He laid in graue, his nephewes ſonne doth raigne,</l>
                  <l>The ſcourge of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Europes</hi> Empreſſe ſlaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So when that death of <hi>Edward</hi> made an end,</l>
                  <l>Eſſence of value, ſubſtance of renowne:</l>
                  <l>Whome peace for iuſtice, warres for rule commend,</l>
                  <l>Exalting vertue, putting vices downe,</l>
                  <l>His bones entombd, his worthy ſonnes doe crowne:</l>
                  <l>Their nephew <hi>Richard</hi> ſecond of that name,</l>
                  <l>The firſt, though not the laſt diſgrac't by fame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:11"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>omene</hi> thou diſmal muſe appeare,</l>
                  <l>And moralize the <hi>Anthemes</hi> which I bring;</l>
                  <l>Richard <hi>miſled by</hi> Buſhy, Poole <hi>and</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ere,</l>
                  <l>Ignoble <hi>Scroope</hi> in his new Empires ſpring,</l>
                  <l>Inchaunting charmes vnto his eares did ſing:</l>
                  <l>Flattry corrupteth kings, but good aduiſe</l>
                  <l>Makes Counſellors gratious, and the Princes wiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When <hi>Neroes</hi> ſonne was borne in <hi>Neroes</hi> campe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quirinus</hi> father <hi>Rheas</hi> valiant ſpouſe,</l>
                  <l>In his red Spheare enlightned had his lampe,</l>
                  <l>Leauing his yron roabes and brazen houſe,</l>
                  <l>Did to <hi>Bellona</hi> cups of blood carowſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saturne</hi> then ioynd with <hi>Mars,</hi> which did foretell</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Neroes</hi> ſonne for murther ſhould excell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Brutus</hi> freed by death from <hi>Tarquines</hi> ſtroakes,<note place="margin">Romanes.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Princes of peace, for warres admirde of all:</l>
                  <l>The worlds Arch monarches rent their chained yoakes,</l>
                  <l>Conſulls and Tribunes do a Senate call,</l>
                  <l>Their voice is one <hi>Caligula</hi> muſt fall.</l>
                  <l>Nature doth ſwarue and from her limits paſſe,</l>
                  <l>The Imperious Lyon, got an abiect Aſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So when chaſte <hi>Alice Richard</hi> forth ſhall bring,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Edwards</hi> Campe, <hi>Victorias</hi> ſacred ſeate:</l>
                  <l>Prophets like ſtarres, enſuing harmes ſhall ſing,</l>
                  <l>The Peeres (like <hi>Albas</hi> knights) were all repleate</l>
                  <l>With wrath, diſdain was in a mightie ſweate</l>
                  <l>In working waies, the king for to depoſe,</l>
                  <l>Which being done, the Nobles <hi>Darby</hi> choſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:11"/>
                  <l>The Northerne Planet great <hi>Northumberland,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe peerles iſſue neuer ſhall decaie:</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Nature</hi> doth confound both Sea and land,</l>
                  <l>And ſhapeles <hi>Chaos</hi> comes his part to play,</l>
                  <l>Vertue muſt liue though men be turnd to claye.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This</hi> glorious Moone true badge of Honor bright,<note place="margin">The halfe Moone is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> armes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Percies Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> of Northu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Diſdaynes the Sunne, and did not borow light.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Foreſeeing <hi>Gaunt</hi> like to a carefull fire,</l>
                  <l>Seeing that loſt by Sloth which Labour wonne:</l>
                  <l>Doth contermaund his Soueraignes hot deſire,</l>
                  <l>And like a blaſt doth caulme the ſcorching Sunne,</l>
                  <l>Which by illuding <hi>Sycophantes</hi> is wonne,<note place="margin">Hen. Buſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brooke D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> of Heref. w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> accuſed by Th. Mowb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> Duke of N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>folke of tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> not being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to proue, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> contented t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> maintaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> allegation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> combat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> his aduerſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> did accept. But better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken, they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> both baniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> the land, He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ford for the terme of ten yeares, and Mowbray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the date of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Two <hi>Combatants</hi> on their earth threatning ſteedes,</l>
                  <l>Attend the trumpets ſound in yron weedes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The reuerent Conſulls <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doe conuocate a Senate of the Peeres:</l>
                  <l>And equalizing <hi>Woodſtocke</hi> did preferre,</l>
                  <l>Due baniſhment to thoſe ambitious Peeres,</l>
                  <l>The Barons ioynd to this; the Champions ſweares</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mowbray</hi> for aye, ten yeares muſt <hi>Harford</hi> part,</l>
                  <l>Griefe galles the one, and kills the others hart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The gallant Courſer in the liſted race</l>
                  <l>Diſmounts the Ryder, ſcornes his curbing raine:</l>
                  <l>Stamping with ioy, his freedome doth embrace,</l>
                  <l>And doth his priſtine ſeruitude diſdaine,</l>
                  <l>Leauing his Ryder breathleſſe on the plaine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So</hi> raging <hi>Burdeux</hi> tumbles downe his kinne,</l>
                  <l>And runnes from ſin to vice, from vice to ſinne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:12"/>
                  <l>In his Imperiall Pallace <hi>Pleaſures</hi> Bowre,<note place="margin">Caligula ſlain by his own friends</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes</hi> mightie Monſter did himſelf repoſe:</l>
                  <l>Sacking <hi>Cytheress</hi> fort, faire <hi>Venus</hi> Towre,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The ſtone where the Kings of Englands chaire is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at their Coronatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, is reported to be that ſtone wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Iacob laid his head whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him in his dream</note> The raging multitude their wrath diſcloſe,</l>
                  <l>For his <hi>Praetorian</hi> guard, they did inſcloſe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chaerea</hi> did ſplit his hart; oh happie thing!</l>
                  <l>T'was good he dide, twas bad to kill a King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So Honors ſpurre did pricke the <hi>Percies</hi> blood,</l>
                  <l>To tumble <hi>Richard</hi> from his bloudie Throne:</l>
                  <l>Wiſhing great <hi>Herford</hi> to tranſpaſſe the flood,</l>
                  <l>To come and ſit on <hi>Iocobs</hi> ſacred ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Where he might raigne as King, and rule alone.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Claudius</hi> roſe, ſo <hi>Herford</hi> came to raigne,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Nero</hi> fell, ſo <hi>Edwards</hi> ſonne was ſlaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſ. brought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Scotland by Edward the firſt.</note> Now <hi>Gaunts</hi> great iſſue in his Throne is ſet,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſacred Science this my Muſe ſhould tell:</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Margarets</hi> ſake, that ſprang from <hi>Sommerſet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For her it ſhould, if <hi>Cambria</hi> did not tell,</l>
                  <l>For lawes vnheard, this Monarch did excell.</l>
                  <l>Who gaue him wings to mount,<note place="margin">Henry 4. The extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of his lawes are ſet downe at large in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</note> he threw to ground,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Claudius</hi> who ran ſo faire, is <hi>Claudus</hi> found.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In <hi>Silence</hi> vault my Muſe ſhall hide his fame,</l>
                  <l>Who dide the Grey gooſe wings with purple red:</l>
                  <l>Praiſe he deſeru'd, though he deſerued blame,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sertorius</hi> like his warlike troopes he led,<note place="margin">Owen Gle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to Sertorius.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>For by alluring hope they both were fed.</l>
                  <l>Had men and Fortune equaliz'd his minde,</l>
                  <l>His Conqueſts <hi>Seuernes</hi> neuer had confinde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:12"/>
                  <l>Victorious <hi>Hotspurre</hi> and his valiant ſire,</l>
                  <l>The kings great <hi>Steward, Wosters</hi> reuerent Lord:</l>
                  <l>With neuer daunted <hi>Dowglas</hi> doe conſpire,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe endles praiſe our <hi>Annales</hi> doe record:</l>
                  <l>With theſe doe <hi>Glendowre</hi> ioyne,<note place="margin">Edmund Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>timer Earle o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> March was d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſigned heire apparant in the dayes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard the 2. if the King dye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> without iſſue.</note> and <hi>Wigmors</hi> Lord,</l>
                  <l>To pull the Scepter from the tyrantes hand,</l>
                  <l>And giue it him that ſhould by right command.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dowglas</hi> and <hi>Hotspurre</hi> peerleſſe for their might,</l>
                  <l>Are ouermatcht by <hi>Henries</hi> matchleſſe ſonne:</l>
                  <l>Who like a lyon rowſ'd him in the fight,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Glendowre</hi> himſelfe is by himſelfe vndone,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Northumberland</hi> is ſicke and cannot come:<note place="margin">The battle at Shaftſbury</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Like to a <hi>Tyger</hi> in his eager chaſe,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Monmouthes</hi> praiſe doth run from place to place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tumults appeaſ'd and armor ſet aſide,<note place="margin">Henry the 5. borne at Monmouth ſhire in Wales.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The ſtately Cirty of the higheſt God</l>
                  <l>Diuine <hi>Ieruſalem, Iehouas</hi> bride,</l>
                  <l>Being whipt with warre, and famines pinching rod,</l>
                  <l>Implores the helpe of this all-conquering Lord:</l>
                  <l>His ſoule defilde with ſinne, by merits ſought</l>
                  <l>That to redeeme which <hi>Ieſus</hi> blood had bought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His royall Nauy like a ſea of wood,</l>
                  <l>Attends his princely preſence in the bay:</l>
                  <l>But ſee how meager death ſtill enuying good,</l>
                  <l>With fatall ſtroake his enterpriſe doth ſtay,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Caedar</hi> falles in time, ſo Kings decay.</l>
                  <l>Why ſtay you ſhippes, he treades the ſacred path,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> his ſoule and body hath.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4005:13"/>
               <head>Henry the fift, his lyfe and death.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AVaunt proud <hi>Rome</hi> and bragge not of thy men,<note place="margin">Henr. 5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor thy aetheriall <hi>Caeſars</hi> warres declare:</l>
                  <l>Ceaſe peerleſſe <hi>Plutarch</hi> with thy ſacred pen,</l>
                  <l>The worlds Archmonarches aptly to compare,</l>
                  <l>Reaſon doth vrge, and this alledge I dare,</l>
                  <l>That Englands <hi>Homer</hi> portraid hath his warre,</l>
                  <l>Which doth excell the worthieſt <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſtarre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What telſt thou me of famous <hi>Haſdruball,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Cannas</hi> chance, and <hi>Varros</hi> ouerthrow:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aemiſius</hi> death, and conquering <hi>Hanniball,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Syllas</hi> Legions, and a Parthian bowe,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Titus</hi> valure, <hi>Catos</hi> wrinckled browe,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> and ſtrong <hi>Namantias</hi> wall,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or</hi> Phillip, Perſia, Iugurth Iubas <hi>fall.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of Noble <hi>Druſus</hi> and proud <hi>Saturnine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Scipios</hi> death, and <hi>Gracchus</hi> infamy:</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Marius</hi> trophies, and ſterne <hi>Cataline,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How <hi>Caeſar</hi> vanquiſht <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And twiſe returnd as foild from <hi>Britany.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The world admir;d their victories to ſee,</l>
                  <l>Yet none of theſe muſt be comparde with thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let <hi>Athens</hi> praiſe the lawes which <hi>Solon</hi> gaue,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Marathon</hi> extoll <hi>Miltiades,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Write <hi>Caria</hi> of <hi>Manſolus</hi> ſtately graue,</l>
                  <l>And let <hi>Cycilia</hi> wiſh <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But <hi>Salamina</hi> praiſe <hi>Themiſtocles.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Greece</hi> did admire their tryumphes for to ſee,</l>
                  <l>Yet all of theſe cannot comparewith thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:13"/>
                  <l>Let <hi>Sparta</hi> now conceale <hi>Lycurgus</hi> fame,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Lacedaemon</hi> hide <hi>Lyſanders</hi> praiſe:</l>
                  <l>Ceaſe <hi>Argos</hi> now, to ſhew th'Olimpicke game,</l>
                  <l>Let ſilence cloud or maske thoſe golden dayes,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Epires</hi> Monarch acted Tragicke playes:<note place="margin">Pyrrhus.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But what of him? or what are theſe to thee?</l>
                  <l>For thou alone doeſt farre exceed thoſe three.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though <hi>Alexander</hi> wan <hi>Darius</hi> Crowne,</l>
                  <l>And forc't the Eaſterne Emperour leaue his tent:</l>
                  <l>Burning <hi>Perſopolis</hi> that regall Towne,</l>
                  <l>Seeing thy valure freely giues conſent</l>
                  <l>That two bright ſonnes ſhould rule the Element:</l>
                  <l>With thee great Prince we aptly may compare,</l>
                  <l>Rich <hi>Europes</hi> Paragon, and Phaenix rare.<note place="margin">The Duke of Yorke &amp; Earle of Suffolke, were the onely men of Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie that ended their liues in the battell of Agincourt.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou didſt not want <hi>Parmenios</hi> aiding hand,</l>
                  <l>Nor valiant <hi>Perdicas</hi> aſpiring minde:</l>
                  <l>Which might <hi>Alanſons</hi> quarels fierce withſtand,</l>
                  <l>As long as <hi>Langlies</hi> gallant iſſued minde</l>
                  <l>Had faithfull <hi>Suffolkes</hi> loue to him combinde.</l>
                  <l>They wan, they loſt, they liue though they are dead,</l>
                  <l>They liue in heauen,<note place="margin">Craſsinius was the firſt Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the enemy in the Field, which office of valure, Edward the Duke of Yorke enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Agin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court.</note> and dide in Conqueſts bed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>France</hi> did ten yeares withſtand the Romanes might,</l>
                  <l>Both parties oft with equall courage plaide;</l>
                  <l>Yet that before the Sun ſhewd twice his light,</l>
                  <l>Madſt great <hi>Mompenſier</hi> flye as all diſmaide,</l>
                  <l>To ſee thy kingly Banner forth diſplaide,</l>
                  <l>Like to <hi>Craſſinius Yorke</hi> the yaward led,</l>
                  <l>True valure is by hope of honor bred.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:14"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> two <hi>Diadames</hi> doth now combine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Europes</hi> faire daughters, eldeſt ſiſters twaine:</l>
                  <l>By marriage of a maide a Mimph diuine,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt <hi>Lewis</hi> liues, as Emperour he muſtraigne,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> as heire apparant doth remayne:</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Katherin</hi> is betrothd his beauteous wife,</l>
                  <l>Peace conquers warre, and concord endeth ſtrife.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Immortalized virgin ſacred Queene,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Britaines Aurora</hi> harbinger of day:</l>
                  <l>Fairer then thought could thinke or eye hath ſeene,</l>
                  <l>Rich Vertues port, and Honors cleereſt bay,</l>
                  <l>Thrice bleſſed wombe fram'd of aetheriall clay,</l>
                  <l>Which didſt encloſe that glorious <hi>Theodore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſonne did <hi>Britaines</hi> regalty reſtore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her Amber-treſſes like to wyers of gold,</l>
                  <l>That ſhadowed her white vermilion face:</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Vulcans</hi> chayne did <hi>Venus</hi> champion hold,</l>
                  <l>VVho triumphed erewhile, now ſues for grace,</l>
                  <l>Vndecent action for a Captaines place:</l>
                  <l>Thy eyes are now bewitcht with eyes diuine,</l>
                  <l>Thy heart conſents to honor <hi>Katherine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If I had <hi>Zeuxes</hi> at to paint thy lookes,</l>
                  <l>Did I enioy <hi>Maeonian Homers</hi> quill:</l>
                  <l>To pourtraiture thy praiſe in golden bookes,</l>
                  <l>Thy vertues rare would aequalize my skill:</l>
                  <l>Thy ſacred paps ſweete <hi>Nectar</hi> did diſtill.</l>
                  <l>Hadſt not thou bene, our eyes ſhould neuer view</l>
                  <l>Our preſent peace and pleaſures to enſue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:14"/>
                  <l>Stay ranging <hi>Muſe,</hi> thy wandring courſe reſtraine,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>ioues</hi> all-ſeeing eyes did view this King:</l>
                  <l>He ſent his Harauld to that ſpatious plaine,</l>
                  <l>Where the three fatall Siſters, then did ſpinne:</l>
                  <l>To know when <hi>Henries</hi> life did firſt beginne.</l>
                  <l>And if his thred were not already ſpunne,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Lacheſis</hi> ſhould make it quickly runne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His wiſeſt ſonne did place his golden wings,</l>
                  <l>Holding a ſiluer rodde all-charming wand:</l>
                  <l>VVherewith he could inchant all mortal things,</l>
                  <l>VVith this attire he claue the aetheriall land,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>luno</hi> doth the Gods command:</l>
                  <l>When that he came vnto the appointed place,</l>
                  <l>He told his meſſage with a comely grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Siſters (quoth he) for ſo they were indeed,</l>
                  <l>Th' omnipotent and all-commanding <hi>Ioue:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mercuries Oration.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich doth on <hi>Nactar</hi> and <hi>Ambroſia</hi> feed,</l>
                  <l>Iuno, Apollo, <hi>and</hi> Cythereis <hi>loue:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVith all the Gods that rules the ſphere aboue,</l>
                  <l>Entreats, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands, of you faire ſiſters three,</l>
                  <l>To end his life, though not his dignitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Atlas</hi> you know is old <hi>Alcides</hi> dead,</l>
                  <l>You know the waight of Heauens maſſy throne:<note place="margin">He dyed in a Chamber at the Deane of Weſtmi. lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging named Ieruſalem.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Planets houſes couered all with lead,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioues</hi> pallace varniſht with rich Rubies ſtone,</l>
                  <l>The gates of <hi>Iuory</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> bone:</l>
                  <l>He that doth heauens heauieſt waight ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l>Muſt patience haue to tollerate his paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:15"/>
                  <l>Therefore (quoth he) this is my Fathers will,</l>
                  <l>(For <hi>Ioue</hi> his Father was, or Fame doth lye)</l>
                  <l>That you which power haue great kings to kill,</l>
                  <l>Would ſhorten <hi>Henries</hi> life that he might dye,</l>
                  <l>A heauenly thought deſerues aeternitie.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Atlas</hi> is old, and <hi>Atlas</hi> muſt haue aide,</l>
                  <l>All feare the heft, <hi>Henry</hi> was nere afraide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Siſters ſtood amazde at his requeſt,<note place="margin">The Fates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nſwere.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Each looke at others eyes as in a glaſſe:</l>
                  <l>Whereat ſterne <hi>Clotho</hi> eldeſt of the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Brother quoth ſhee (for <hi>Ioue</hi> their Father was)</l>
                  <l>Shall Fates be rulde by Gods? ahlas, ahlas,</l>
                  <l>They reuell ſtill, but we poore wretches worke,</l>
                  <l>We labour, they in Caues of pleaſure lurke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The worlds poore Impes may iuſtly now complaine</l>
                  <l>Of humane ſorrow, mans ſtill growing griefe:</l>
                  <l>How birds and beaſts a longer life do gaine</l>
                  <l>Then man, poore man; And mans commaunding chiefe</l>
                  <l>If you deny them helpe, where is reliefe:</l>
                  <l>Men ſay that Fates are certaine, now they ſee</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioue</hi> made vs conſtant in inconſtancy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The angry God invelloped with ire,</l>
                  <l>Wrath in his face, and fury in his lookes,</l>
                  <l>His eyes more redde then was the reddeſt fire:</l>
                  <l>Shewes auncient Monuments of ſacred bookes,</l>
                  <l>Which earſt he wrote by the <hi>Idalian</hi> brookes.</l>
                  <l>There might you ſee what Act the Gods did frame,</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the reſt <hi>Ioue</hi> might the Siſters blame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:15"/>
                  <l>Out of this place he drawes his argument,</l>
                  <l>And doth confute their ſugred Sophiſtry:</l>
                  <l>Then reades another Act of Parliament,</l>
                  <l>Which did confirme <hi>Ioues</hi> royall Empery,</l>
                  <l>His great prerogatiue and dignity.</l>
                  <l>Then doth he powre forth ſacred Eloquence,</l>
                  <l>Selected flowers of learnings Quinteſſence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What if proud <hi>Terras</hi> iſſue <hi>Briareus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVould combat with your great aetheriall Sire?<note place="margin">Mercinys reply.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Fntring <hi>Caſtalia,</hi> where the ſacred Muſe</l>
                  <l>Liues ſtill inſpirde with yong <hi>Apollos</hi> fire?</l>
                  <l>VVhat if the Giants could ſo high aſpire,</l>
                  <l>VVould not they touch the chriſtalized sky,</l>
                  <l>Vntuning heauens ſweeteſt harmony?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhat God ſhould then the heauens waight ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt <hi>Bacchus</hi> in his Indian Tygers Carre</l>
                  <l>VVould ſhake the Orbes and that celeſtiall plaine,</l>
                  <l>VVhen faire <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictoria</hi> conquering Queene of warre,</l>
                  <l>Brighter then <hi>Venus,</hi> or the brighteſt ſtarre,</l>
                  <l>Doth giue to <hi>Ioue</hi> a Crowne bedeckt with gold,</l>
                  <l>Could <hi>Atlas</hi> then heauens heauieſt waight vphold?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:16"/>
                  <l>His age is great, and yeares will ſtrength remoue,</l>
                  <l>Therefore faire <hi>Siſters</hi> well aduiſed bee:</l>
                  <l>To anſwere <hi>loue</hi> and all the Gods aboue,</l>
                  <l>Though loth they were, yet all did well agree</l>
                  <l>To cut his thred for meere neceſſitie.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Atlantiades</hi> did ſoone depart,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Atropos</hi> did ſtabbe great <hi>Henries</hi> hart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus dide the <hi>Phaenix</hi> of the vaſtie round,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe worth my Muſe ſhould euer memorize:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Eccho-like</hi> his martiall deeds reſound,</l>
                  <l>Put that he did his Country ſcandalize</l>
                  <l>In following <hi>Henry</hi> which did tyranize.</l>
                  <l>She gaue thee breath to liue and men to fight,</l>
                  <l>Yet thou depriu'ſt her of her cleereſt light.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When noble <hi>Henry</hi> ended hath his daies.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bedford</hi> with conquering ſwords <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ernoi</hi> ſhal fill,</l>
                  <l>And ſpend his blood to gaine immortall praiſe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beauford</hi> and <hi>Beaumount</hi> ſhall good <hi>Humfrey</hi> kill,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Warwicke</hi> gaine the popular good will.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Poole</hi> is exilde from wofull <hi>Margaret,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Yorke</hi> malignes the Duke of <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mars</hi> mounts his Enſigns on our higheſt towers,</l>
                  <l>And decks our helmets with Ambitions plumes:</l>
                  <l>Reuenge ſad maſſacres and ſcarlet ſhowres</l>
                  <l>Diſtills, Cities are burnt, whoſe dankiſh fumes</l>
                  <l>Contaminates the Ayre, now <hi>Yorke</hi> preſumes</l>
                  <l>VVith <hi>Sarums</hi> Earle and <hi>Warwickes</hi> willing hand,</l>
                  <l>To gaine the Crowne, and with the Crowne the land.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4005:16"/>
               <head>The Ciuill Warres.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>PLutonian</hi> Princeſſe ſacred <hi>Proſerpine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Licence <hi>Megaera</hi> and <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſiphone,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich neuer ſaw the <hi>Sunnes</hi> all-pleaſing ſhine</l>
                  <l>Enter this vale of humane miſery,</l>
                  <l>And conſecrate to endles memory</l>
                  <l>Theſe Ciuill broyles in Characters of braſſe,</l>
                  <l>Set forth theſe warres which did all warres ſurpaſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heers <hi>Mars</hi> pauilion, there <hi>Bellonas</hi> tent,</l>
                  <l>The Lanciers here, &amp; there the Carbines ſtands:</l>
                  <l>The Bilmen ſtrikes, the Archers bowes are bent,</l>
                  <l>Here raging Fury flies with burning brands,</l>
                  <l>Diſtorted limmes are pilde on purple ſands:</l>
                  <l>Here <hi>Gaſſamores</hi> are cract, there helmets crazd,</l>
                  <l>Here Gorgets cut, there Vaines of Azure razd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now doth the Courſer neigh, the Clarions ſound,</l>
                  <l>And wrath mounted on a flaming ſteed:</l>
                  <l>Doth both the Legions fortitude confound,</l>
                  <l>The moiſtleſſe earth for very griefe doth bleed,</l>
                  <l>To ſee the Gardner ſpoyle the ſowen ſeed.</l>
                  <l>Heere might you ſee what age could neuer tell,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt Lyons fought, the foreſts Barons fell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heere Ambuſcadoes watch the ſallying Scout,</l>
                  <l>There <hi>Hanniball</hi> entraps <hi>Marcellus</hi> traine:</l>
                  <l>Here wings are plac't and ſquadrons round about,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scipiades</hi> muſt leaue diſloyall <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And like <hi>Anebiſes</hi> clippe the <hi>Elizian</hi> plaine.</l>
                  <l>Nature hath digd for men more kind of graues,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Indian</hi> Ganges hath tranſlucent waues.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:17"/>
                  <l>No valiant <hi>Martius</hi> ſtout <hi>Coriolaene,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did now the raging multitude withſtand:</l>
                  <l>Tumultuous windes haue left the rocky lane,</l>
                  <l>Where ſterne <hi>Hypoaates</hi> with Mace in hand,</l>
                  <l>Their lawleſſe force, by force doth countermaund.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eurus</hi> will blowe and ſhake the <hi>Iſlands</hi> King,</l>
                  <l>Rebells will riſe, and belles of diſcord ring.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vnworthy I, to mount that ſacred hill,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Clodius</hi>-like ſee female ſacrifice:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgill</hi> ſang this, and none but <hi>Virgill</hi> will</l>
                  <l>Aduenture valures worth to memorice;</l>
                  <l>Thrice glorious obiect fit for Princely eyes.</l>
                  <l>Pardon great <hi>Homer,</hi> my all-daring muſe,</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Cherills</hi> folly, <hi>Cherills</hi> fault excuſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The leſſer ſtarres makes <hi>Phoebe</hi> ſhine more bright,</l>
                  <l>So may my infant Muſe comparde to thine,</l>
                  <l>Make thy heroicke Poems ſplendant light,</l>
                  <l>Seeme fairer farre in mens iuditious eyne,</l>
                  <l>Compariſon makes Vertue ſeeme diuine.</l>
                  <l>Yet giue me leaue with my vnworthy pen,</l>
                  <l>To blazon forth the Acts of worthy men.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ceaſe mournfull <hi>Rome</hi> thy ſad enlangoring,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe fatall Fields neere to <hi>Campania</hi> ſought,</l>
                  <l>Wherein the very prime of <hi>Marius</hi> ſpring,<note place="margin">The ciuil wars of Marius and Sylla.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The ſpring of griefe which <hi>Carbo</hi> deerly bought,</l>
                  <l>Ambitious Conqueſt rulde great <hi>Syllas</hi> thought.</l>
                  <l>Speake not of theſe proud <hi>Rome,</hi> nor make thy mone,</l>
                  <l>Or if thou ſpeak'ſt, make not compariſon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:17"/>
                  <l>What of ſtout <hi>Varro,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The battell Spayne, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Caeſar was victor.</note> and <hi>Affranius</hi> loſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Masſilias</hi> ruine <hi>Scaeuas</hi> pierced ſhield:</l>
                  <l>Home by <hi>Brunduſium, Caeſars</hi> ſhippes were toſt,</l>
                  <l>Euer renowm'd <hi>Pharſalias</hi> bloody field,</l>
                  <l>How <hi>Iuba</hi> fell, and <hi>Diator</hi> did yeeld.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pompey</hi> in <hi>Egipt</hi> by <hi>Pothinius</hi> ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>And endles ſhame which <hi>Ptolomy</hi> did gaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caeſar is</hi> ſtabd,<note place="margin">Caeſar ſlaine the Court of Pompey.</note> and <hi>Albas</hi> doth lament,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Antonius</hi> doth the Tyrants plea refute:</l>
                  <l>Irefull <hi>Octauius</hi> to reuenge is bent,</l>
                  <l>Caſcas <hi>and</hi> Casſius,<note place="margin">The battell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Phillippia.</note> Cicero <hi>and</hi> Brute,</l>
                  <l>For Countreys freedome frame a faithleſſe ſuite.</l>
                  <l>Lawes ſilent are when armies rule the towne,<note place="margin">The feelde at Actium.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who conquered Kings, by Kings are tumbled downe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Enuious deſire of honor, loue to raigne,</l>
                  <l>Seuers their mindes whome nature did combine:</l>
                  <l>Two <hi>Romaine</hi> nauyes cut the <hi>Ocean</hi> maine,</l>
                  <l>One brothers loſſe, doth cauſe anothers gaine,</l>
                  <l>Nothing is worſe then Potentates diſdaine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> ſimild with ioy, when ciuill warres did ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>England</hi> admired more at perfect peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In thirteen battells <hi>Englands</hi> ſtrength was tryde,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gauntes</hi> iſſue ſtriues with <hi>Clarence</hi> progenie:</l>
                  <l>Through euery place deſtructions ſteed did ryde,</l>
                  <l>Making debate and endles enmitie,</l>
                  <l>Twixt ſubiects loue,<note place="margin">The firſt of Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Albons barrells.</note> and Princely ſoueraigntie.</l>
                  <l>The Lords conſpire, and at <hi>Saint Atbons</hi> meete,</l>
                  <l>Heres <hi>Warwickes</hi> tent, there <hi>Yorke</hi> doth man the ſtreete.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:18"/>
                  <l>Vnder the Caſtell <hi>Somerſet</hi> is ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>Here <hi>Clsfford</hi> falls, and there <hi>Northumberland,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Buckingham</hi> renewes the fight againe,</l>
                  <l>In vaine the Lion doth the Beare withſtand,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Warwicke</hi> leades his all ſubduing band:<note place="margin">Dayſie in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rench, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>eth Margaret</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Roſe doth wither, and the Dayſie ſpring.</l>
                  <l>The Queene eſcapt, but <hi>Warwicke</hi> hath the king.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O whither ſhall ſhe fly? whoſe ay de expect?</l>
                  <l>Who is encombred with a thouſand woes:</l>
                  <l>VVhat peaſant boore will princes griefes reſpect?</l>
                  <l>By flight ſhe ſcapes the furie of her foes:</l>
                  <l>Thus to the North this <hi>Amazonian</hi> goes.</l>
                  <l>Griefe flies to thoſe, who are oppreſt with griefe,</l>
                  <l>Societie in woe is ſome reliefe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>Romes</hi> two <hi>Scipios</hi> fell, two glorious ſtarres</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Andeluzia</hi> or illuding <hi>Spaine:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>None durſt but <hi>Scipio</hi> vndertake thoſe warres,</l>
                  <l>Euen ſo when <hi>Clifford</hi> was for <hi>England</hi> ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Percies</hi> pride lay breathleſſe on the plaine,<note place="margin">At Wakefield, Rich. Duke of Yorke being taken by the Lord Clifford, in reuenge of his fathers Ideath ſlaine at S. Albons, I crowned the Dukes head with paper.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>None durſt the Ragged Staffe and Beare withſtand,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Cliffords</hi> ſonne and great <hi>Northumberland.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Trumpets wake the Champions to the field,</l>
                  <l>VVho rode in tryumph through <hi>Epaeons</hi> towne</l>
                  <l>To <hi>VVeſtmerland;</hi> and <hi>Margaret</hi> muſt yeeld,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe vertues did deſerue a golden Crowne:</l>
                  <l>His browes are circulizde with paper browne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> doth yeeld to <hi>Xerxes</hi> might,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yorke</hi> ouermatcht, giues place to <hi>Heuries</hi> right.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:18"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Penthiſilea</hi> bends her courſe to <hi>Troy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shewing the ſpoiles of <hi>Lariſſeas</hi> King,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Henry</hi> like to <hi>Priam</hi> ſmiles with ioy,</l>
                  <l>Seeing his <hi>Queene</hi> ſuch <hi>Tropheys</hi> home to bring:</l>
                  <l>And all the <hi>Phrigian</hi> Virgins <hi>Io</hi> ſing.</l>
                  <l>Like vnto this, or like a brauer wight,</l>
                  <l>Couragious <hi>Margret</hi> doth returne from ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Neuer diſcouragde <hi>Warwicks</hi> royall Peere,</l>
                  <l>Vnconſtant <hi>Clarence,</hi> conſtant <hi>Montacute,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Seeing the Southerne coaſt of <hi>Albion</hi> cleere,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Did</hi> Eſſex, Suffolke, Surrey <hi>reſalute,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Norfolke</hi> doth <hi>Mowbray</hi> Captaine conſtitute.</l>
                  <l>Both Armies ioyne,<note place="margin">The ſecon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Battell of S<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Albons.</note> and to <hi>Saint Albons</hi> came,</l>
                  <l>They flye their foes, where firſt they ouercame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mowbray</hi> to <hi>Suffolke, Warwicke</hi> with the reſt,</l>
                  <l>In haſte, poſte haſte, to <hi>Cambrias</hi> borders flye:</l>
                  <l>New riſing <hi>March</hi> doth rowſe his ſpangled Creſt,</l>
                  <l>And vnderſtanding by a ſallying ſpye</l>
                  <l>His Fathers friends, and fauourites were nigh,</l>
                  <l>With decent geſture doth them entertaine,</l>
                  <l>Imploring aide his right to reobtaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Warwicke</hi> who was the ſpeaker for them all,</l>
                  <l>In modeſt ſort, as well became his age:</l>
                  <l>Not Duke of <hi>Yorke</hi> but doth him Soueraigne call,</l>
                  <l>A name ſo great doth vertue equipage,</l>
                  <l>Now each to other doth his honour gage.</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Caeſar</hi> now he ioynes with <hi>Anthony,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And like to him doth foſter enmitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:19"/>
                  <l>When <hi>Brutus</hi> hand had ſtabd great <hi>Caeſars</hi> hart,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Octauius</hi> honour euery where did finde:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Antonius</hi> takes the ſtout <hi>Caeſareans</hi> part,</l>
                  <l>But when reuenge had ſatisfide her minde,</l>
                  <l>Whome mariage chaſte with friendſhip had combinde,</l>
                  <l>Ambition makes them ſtriue for endleſſe raigne,</l>
                  <l>And with their bloud to dye the crimſon mayne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So <hi>Edward</hi> and renowned <hi>Sarums</hi> ſonne</l>
                  <l>Ioyne to reuenge dead <hi>Richards</hi> iniury:<note place="margin">thard Earle Warwicke.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But when that <hi>Gaunts</hi> great iſſue was vndone,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Warwicke</hi> doth enuy <hi>Yorkes</hi> proſperitie,</l>
                  <l>And much diſdaines his peerlſſe Soueraigntie.</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe when <hi>Edward</hi> durſt not here abide,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Barnet</hi> field where noble <hi>Warwicke</hi> dide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henries</hi> faire Queene,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>argret daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>r to Reino <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>rle of Aniow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ho entituled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>mſelf King of Naples, Sycil, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eruſalem, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ioyed none.</note> great Neapolitane,</l>
                  <l>Blinded with masked fate, vnconſtant chance,</l>
                  <l>Did neuer feare her future fatall bane,</l>
                  <l>Like a ſierce coult this Iennet proud did prance,</l>
                  <l>Smiling with ioy to ſee her ſmiling chance.</l>
                  <l>Harke how the Drumme doth ſummon to the field,</l>
                  <l>See how ſhe takes her ill beſeeming ſhield.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Stay <hi>Naples</hi> pride <hi>Sicilian</hi> Empreſſe ſtay,<note place="margin">That day in which Caeſar loſt his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the Court of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ompe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, a poor man tendred him a petition which he light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y regarded, the contents wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of if he had per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vſed, his life might haue bene preſerued</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will <hi>France</hi> for euer ſhowres of vengeance raigne?</l>
                  <l>Thy firſt approch preſage this fatall day,</l>
                  <l>Fire flew from heauen and made our Turrets plaine,</l>
                  <l>When thy Armados cut the Ocean maine.</l>
                  <l>Had <hi>Caeſar</hi> read that which the poore man gaue,</l>
                  <l>Egypt had neuer beene <hi>Antonins</hi> gratre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:19"/>
                  <l>Had but great <hi>Henry,</hi> great in Maieſtie</l>
                  <l>Ioynd with that match which <hi>Bedford</hi> firſt did make,</l>
                  <l>He had not taſted baſe ſeruilitie,</l>
                  <l>But when his minion <hi>Suffolke</hi> did forſake,</l>
                  <l>That Nimph of ioy, great heire to <hi>Arminake,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Yorkes</hi> depreſſed iſſue gan to riſe,</l>
                  <l>An abiect Prince each Subiect will deſpiſe,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clifford</hi> and <hi>Percy</hi> proppes of <hi>Henries</hi> ſtate;</l>
                  <l>(Seeing the Southerne Lords entend to fight,)</l>
                  <l>Doth the fierce Tygers anger inſtigate,</l>
                  <l>Propoſing arguments of <hi>Henries</hi> right,</l>
                  <l>How her decayd, augmented <hi>Edwards</hi> might.</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Hampton</hi> firſt ſhe did our woe begin,<note place="margin">At her firſt c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming, landin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> at Southham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton, ſome pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> of Paules ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. and many other Church<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> in England were ſet on fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Two <hi>Hamptons</hi> cannot end her endleſſe ſin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fury awakes the murthred Lions whelpe,</l>
                  <l>And like poore <hi>Hector</hi> his deceaſed ſire,</l>
                  <l>Craues of his kinſemen their ſupporting helpe,</l>
                  <l>Their ſmotherd hate hath kindled murthers fire,</l>
                  <l>Which none can quench till they haue quencht deſire,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Nemsſis</hi> of late did murther end,</l>
                  <l>There ſhe begins heroicke bloud to ſpend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like the worlds Monarch, <hi>Yorkes</hi> apparant heire</l>
                  <l>Ioynes with his Fathers friend, great <hi>Neuils</hi> race:</l>
                  <l>They to <hi>Northampton</hi> with their troupes repaire,</l>
                  <l>VVhere <hi>Aniowes</hi> Tamiris with martiall grace</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cliffords</hi> triumphant Armes did embrace:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clifford</hi> whoſe name as <hi>Taibot</hi> did in <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Made <hi>Warwicke</hi> feare his Colours to aduance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:20"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Octauius</hi> now,<note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on of Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and Warwicke with Octaui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s &amp; Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</note> and chaſte <hi>Octauias</hi> Bride,</l>
                  <l>Conſpire the death of tyranizing <hi>Brute.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clifford</hi> muſt fall, in top of all his pride,</l>
                  <l>Who did by Armes great <hi>Muuſters</hi> plea refute,</l>
                  <l>Doth pleade his cauſe, but <hi>Warwicke</hi> gaines the ſuite.</l>
                  <l>A headleſſe arrow piercſt his armed throate,</l>
                  <l>Who in his youth did ſaile in Conqueſts boate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If <hi>Homer</hi> liu'd and dwelt in <hi>Caſtalie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And daily taſted of <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> Well,</l>
                  <l>Inſpirde with furious ſacred Poeſie,</l>
                  <l>Yet would he not our <hi>Virgils</hi> worth excell,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>Paeans</hi> did theſe fierce maſſacres tell.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Delia</hi> is praiſd with thy all-prayſing hand:</l>
                  <l>No wonder, for thou dweltſt in <hi>Delos</hi> land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Eight ſeuerall Battels ſhall eſcape my Muſe,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt pride it ſelfe ſhould me eſteeme as proud:</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Maros</hi> quill that ſacred path peruſe,</l>
                  <l>Couer my temples with a ſable cloud,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cimerian</hi> wreathes my head of ſorrow ſhrowd:</l>
                  <l>Giue me a brazen Penſill not a Pen,</l>
                  <l>Some drops of blood to portraiture theſe men.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Field of Banbery.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw warre is mounted on rebellions Steede,</l>
                  <l>And diſcontent perſwadeth willing Pride,</l>
                  <l>His creſt to raiſe, and wears an Iron weede:</l>
                  <l>Long ſmothred Enuy doth the Army guide,</l>
                  <l>Which made firme loue from true obedience ſlide:</l>
                  <l>'T was that great <hi>Neuill</hi> made proud <hi>George</hi> rebell,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe haughty ſpirits <hi>Warwicke</hi> knew too well.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:20"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Warwicke</hi> that raiſde the race of <hi>Mortimer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe eyes did ſee too ſoone, thy death ſaies ſo:</l>
                  <l>The downfall of immortall <hi>Lancaſter,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'T was he that did, what could not <hi>Warwicke</hi> doo?</l>
                  <l>Make Kings and Queenes to loue and feare him too.</l>
                  <l>'T was that great Peere, who with one warlike hand,</l>
                  <l>Crown'd and vncrown'd two kings who rulde the land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus while theſe Royall but diſloyall Peeres,</l>
                  <l>Maugre reuenge to him that knew not feare,</l>
                  <l>Vnnumbred bands of men and ſwarmes appeares</l>
                  <l>In North and South, Eaſt, Weſt, yea euery where</l>
                  <l>They throw away their Coats, and Corſlets weare.</l>
                  <l>Wiues, maides, and Orphants eyes are ſtuft with teares,</l>
                  <l>And cannot ſee the Spades tranſform'd to Speares.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Shepheards hooke is made a ſouldiers pike,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe weather-beaten hands muſt learne aright</l>
                  <l>His ſpeare to traile, and with his ſword to ſtrike</l>
                  <l>Vpon the plumed beauer of a knight,</l>
                  <l>None muſt be ſparde by warres impartiall might.</l>
                  <l>If euery ſouldier were a King, what then?</l>
                  <l>Princes ſhould die as faſt as other men.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Senator muſt leaue his skarlet gowne,</l>
                  <l>And keepe him in ſome Turret of defence:</l>
                  <l>When warres once flouriſh, Iuſtice muſt goe downe,</l>
                  <l>Lawes to correct, is lawleſſe warres pretence,</l>
                  <l>Valure doth greeue to ſee ill gotten pence.</l>
                  <l>To ſee a man without deſerts to riſe,</l>
                  <l>Makes warre ſuch men, not Iuſtice to deſpiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:21"/>
                  <l>You that in peace by vſe of golden hoords</l>
                  <l>Your dunghill race to Barons did erect:</l>
                  <l>You that by Engliſh phraſe and choſen woords</l>
                  <l>Make heauens enuy your topleſle Architeck,</l>
                  <l>Your Angels cannot you from warres protect.</l>
                  <l>The Campe and Court in manners different are,</l>
                  <l>Words may in Peace, but deeds preuaile in Warre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For Robes of honor furr'd with Miniuere</l>
                  <l>You muſt haue breſt-plates of well tempred ſteele,</l>
                  <l>And on your aged heads ſtrong Helmets weare,</l>
                  <l>All ſtates muſt turne when Fortune turnes her wheele,</l>
                  <l>That man which pleaſure taſtes muſt ſorrow feele.</l>
                  <l>Who ſees the wracke of mightie Empery,</l>
                  <l>He loues his life too well that will not dye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When Kings muſt fight, ſhall ſubiects liue in peace?</l>
                  <l>What Coward is of ſuch a crauant race,</l>
                  <l>That loues not honor more than idle eaſe?</l>
                  <l>Great Romane I applaud thy worthy Phraſe,</l>
                  <l>To liue with ſhame, is worſe then dye with praiſe.</l>
                  <l>All which haue being, alwaies cannot bee,</l>
                  <l>For things corrupt muſt die, and ſo muſt wee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Could <hi>Creſſus</hi> mightie mines from <hi>Cyrus</hi> hand,</l>
                  <l>His captiue carkaſſe or his ſtate defend?</l>
                  <l>Wealth cannot warre, nor ſiluer ſpeares withſtand:</l>
                  <l>By ſtrife we ſee the greateſt ſtates haue end,</l>
                  <l>And moſt they marre by warre, who moſt would mend.</l>
                  <l>When old warres ceaſe, then ſtraight their ſprings anew,</l>
                  <l>For harmes ſtill harmes, and euils do ills enſue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:21"/>
                  <l>No ſooner had the gladſome eyes of peace</l>
                  <l>Beheld this warlike ſea inuiron'd Ile,</l>
                  <l>But diſobedience heire to ſluggiſh eaſe,</l>
                  <l>Did weake beleefe ſubdue with ſubtile ſtile,</l>
                  <l>Grace winnes the heart, but words the eares beguile.</l>
                  <l>Twas <hi>Warwicks</hi> tongue, whoſe ſpeech did all men pleaſe</l>
                  <l>Whoſe words were ſuch, or very like to theſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Earle of Warwicks ſpeech.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOu know great Lords, your very eyes did ſee</l>
                  <l>The ſpotleſſe honor which my houſe and I</l>
                  <l>Did euer beare this kingdome; who but wee</l>
                  <l>Did checke the pride of wilfull tyranny:</l>
                  <l>And with our Grandſires we eſteemde it good,</l>
                  <l>For Englands weale to ſpill our deareſt blood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Witneſſe the diſmall fall of <hi>Salisbury</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>Yorke</hi> in <hi>Wakefield</hi> ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>The wracke of my decaied familie,</l>
                  <l>Why did we this, what profit did we gaine?</l>
                  <l>Twas but to ſhew our country our good will,</l>
                  <l>Which now we alſo do, and euer will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How many times haue I in complete ſteele</l>
                  <l>Yea mounted on my ſteed purſude the chaſe?</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe theſe weary limbes, for age muſt feele,</l>
                  <l>If youth hath runn'd aſtray or tedious race.</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe theſe ſiluer haires which now appeares,</l>
                  <l>Cares makes vs old, though we be yong in yeares.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:22"/>
                  <l>When as theſe eyes, impartiall eyes of mine,</l>
                  <l>Beheld my king illuded and miſled</l>
                  <l>By baſer men, true honor did repine</l>
                  <l>To ſee great maieſtie with baſeneſſe wed:</l>
                  <l>For which I waged warre, and warring wan,</l>
                  <l>And winning, choſe a Tyger for a Lambe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Both you and I great Lords, yea all the ſtate</l>
                  <l>With vniuerſall voice adiudg'd him wiſe:</l>
                  <l>Who now hath prou'd a tyrant and vngrate,</l>
                  <l>Humilitie makes time obſeruers riſe.</l>
                  <l>For you I choſe him king and ſpent my blood,</l>
                  <l>But tryall ſaies, good ſeeming is no good,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now therefore friends let <hi>Warwicks</hi> tongue intreate,</l>
                  <l>Since that our hopes of <hi>Edwards</hi> loue diſpaire,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Lancaſter</hi> may repoſſeſſe his ſeate,</l>
                  <l>Whom we vnkindly thruſt from honors chaire,</l>
                  <l>The reaſon is which gouernes our pretents,</l>
                  <l>Tyrants are worſer farre then Innocents.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus this enraged Lord doth inſtigate</l>
                  <l>With ſpurlike words ſwift courſers to the race:</l>
                  <l>Enuy ambition breeds, ambition hate:</l>
                  <l>Hate diſcontent breeds, diſcontent diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>Theſe be warres angry ſounds, pernitious race.</l>
                  <l>Theſe vices by Iniuſtice nouriſht are,</l>
                  <l>Affection in a Iudge is worſe then warre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:22"/>
                  <l>Bleſſed that ſtate, thrice happie is the land</l>
                  <l>VVhere ſacred Iuſtice is eſteemde diuine:</l>
                  <l>And where the Iudge on one eare holds his hand,</l>
                  <l>My pen applaudes that ſentence iuſt of thine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes</hi> holy Prince, peace louing <hi>Antonine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As I am <hi>Marcus,</hi> I am not thy foe,</l>
                  <l>But being Iudge, I muſt be iuſt alſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That lawe deryding Peere, diſdaining Lord,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Warwick</hi> doth his rebellious Enſignes reare:</l>
                  <l>And vowes reuenge on <hi>Edward</hi> with his ſword,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haſtings</hi> and <hi>Stanley</hi> do withſtand the Beare,</l>
                  <l>True honor neuer yeelds to ſeruile feare.</l>
                  <l>He is a friend that loues when Fate doth frowne,</l>
                  <l>He ſhall haue thouſands that doth weare a Crowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus while theſe threatnings like ſome blazing ſtarre,</l>
                  <l>The wracke of ſome great Emperour do portend:</l>
                  <l>Their friends on either ſide addreſſe for warre,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>William</hi> Earle of <hi>Pembrooke</hi> doth entend,</l>
                  <l>Ere warre begin to make of warre an end.</l>
                  <l>And for that purpoſe for his friends he ſent,</l>
                  <l>To whom as thus he ſhewed his right intent.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Earle of Pembrookes Oration.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOu that did euer with your ſwords maintaine,</l>
                  <l>The vndoubted title of the whiter Roſe:</l>
                  <l>By whoſe great ayde great <hi>Edward</hi> did obtaine,</l>
                  <l>The Royall crowne and homage held of thoſe,</l>
                  <l>VVhich now rebell, deere friends correct this ſinne,</l>
                  <l>'Tis as much praiſe to keepe, as praiſe to winne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:23"/>
                  <l>If ſpeech might ſpur you to this glorious race,</l>
                  <l>Where endleſſe honor is the purchaſt fee:</l>
                  <l>Selected words my ruder ſpeech ſhould grace,</l>
                  <l>We pricke in vaine his ſides whoſe feete are free.</l>
                  <l>You euer did the houſe of <hi>Yorke</hi> adore,</l>
                  <l>True loue encreaſeth daily more and more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Giue not occaſion to the enuious pen,</l>
                  <l>To brand you with the badge of infamie:</l>
                  <l>Be firme in reſolution worthy men,</l>
                  <l>And thinke vpon your auncient libertie.</l>
                  <l>Behold why <hi>Warwicke</hi> doth theſe warres entend,</l>
                  <l>A bad beginning hath a worſer end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Looke with indifferent, not reſpecting eyes,</l>
                  <l>Vpon theſe two coriualls in the warre:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> a King, couragious, honeſt, wiſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Warwicke</hi> whoſe name is like a blazing ſtarre,</l>
                  <l>That ſome enſuing harmes doth foretell,</l>
                  <l>Enuy doth ſtill worke ill, but neuer well.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For whom doth he this bloody battell wage?</l>
                  <l>For aged <hi>Henry,</hi> and the Prince his ſonne:</l>
                  <l>Who but for him had led a quiet age,</l>
                  <l>But they poore Princes, were by him vndone.</l>
                  <l>I finde it true which hath bene often ſed,</l>
                  <l>Beares muſt ſometime with humane fleſh be fed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:23"/>
                  <l>It is not loue to either of theſe twaine,</l>
                  <l>That doth enforce this proud ignoble Peere:</l>
                  <l>Theſe wandring troupes of rebells to maintaine,</l>
                  <l>But tis ambition whom he holds moſt deere,</l>
                  <l>That doth compell his willing hands to fight:</l>
                  <l>Vnſetled braines bloud ſtill reſpect, not right.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, what if <hi>Henry</hi> ſhould enioy the wreath,</l>
                  <l>Thinke you by yeelding fauour to enioy?</l>
                  <l>Friends, when warres riſe ſay kings ſhould neuer breath,</l>
                  <l>Princes in neede men of regard imploy.</l>
                  <l>To this iuſt action loyall friends be mou'd,</l>
                  <l>The firmeſt faith in danger great is prou'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>THus hath this Lord as with a touch-ſtone tride,</l>
                  <l>The courage of his countrey-men and loue:</l>
                  <l>The voyce of all is on warres, warres they cride,</l>
                  <l>The Princes vertues do the ſubiectes moue,</l>
                  <l>Dangers and perils eminent to proue.</l>
                  <l>The noble Earle with ſpeede purſues his fate,</l>
                  <l>Delay brings danger to the ſureſt ſtate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When Fame reported this to <hi>Edwards</hi> care,</l>
                  <l>Hope vanquiſht feare and gaue encouragement:</l>
                  <l>To ſee them firme who euer faithfull were.</l>
                  <l>Then to Lord <hi>Stafford, Southwike</hi> Earle he ſent,</l>
                  <l>To muſter all his friends incontinent:</l>
                  <l>Then gaue he ioynt commiſsion to theſe twaine,</l>
                  <l>As equalles when they came in Campe to raigne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:24"/>
                  <l>Thus theſe two Captaines as thoſe two of yore,</l>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>Romes</hi> ſelected youth in <hi>Cannas</hi> bled,</l>
                  <l>Equall in power, but not in Iudgements ſtore,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Varro, Stafford</hi> from the battell fled,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Paulus,</hi> ſo renowmed <hi>Pembrooke</hi> ſped.</l>
                  <l>Thus Lord-like ſtout <hi>Aemilius</hi> forth doth goe,</l>
                  <l>To chaſe the pride of his rebellious foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Stafford</hi> and hee weake ſtaffe to leane vpon,</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Stafford</hi> he, nor ſprung from <hi>Buckingham,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor let that name ſo baſe a man bemoane,</l>
                  <l>His cowardize eſcandalizde his fame.</l>
                  <l>Laſſiuious luſt did explaiten his ſhame.</l>
                  <l>Theſe two to <hi>Banbary</hi> with Armies bend,</l>
                  <l>Thence <hi>Stafford</hi> fled, there <hi>Herberts</hi> life did end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There might you ſee a troope of warlike men,</l>
                  <l>Conducted by the glories of their Clyme:</l>
                  <l>Vnworthy I, with my vnworthy pen,</l>
                  <l>To aeternize in Layes vndecent Rime,</l>
                  <l>Their memories, which liue in ſpight of time.</l>
                  <l>Theſe two as <hi>Fabius</hi> and <hi>Marcellus</hi> weare,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes</hi> guarding target and offending ſpeare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Richard</hi> was valorous, but his brother wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Youth made him forward, age the other ſtayde:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Richard</hi> for action, <hi>Pembrooke</hi> for aduiſe,</l>
                  <l>If both their worths were in a ballance way de,</l>
                  <l>Neither ſhould Fates partiallitie vprayde,</l>
                  <l>The differences betweene theſe brothers are,</l>
                  <l>One peace affected moſt, the other warre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:24"/>
                  <l>There might you ſee the Champions of the Beare,</l>
                  <l>Mounted on Iuſtie Courſers, ſcoure the plaine:</l>
                  <l>There might you ſee the ſonne of <hi>Latimer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With raſhneſſe charge, with feare returne and ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>They neuer feare, who neuer feeled paine.</l>
                  <l>There might you ſee, O I am greeu'd to ſay,</l>
                  <l>What yeares confirm'd, conſumed in a day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There might you ſee that worthy man of men,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Richard</hi> with his victorious ſword in hand,</l>
                  <l>Like a fierce Lyon paſſing from his den,</l>
                  <l>Or ſome ſterne Boare, whoſe anger plowes the land,</l>
                  <l>Securely paſſe through euery conquer'd band.</l>
                  <l>As a round bullet from a Canon ſent,</l>
                  <l>This Knight alone through fortie thouſand went.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And backe return'd to his amazed traine,</l>
                  <l>But more enraged with anger then before:</l>
                  <l>Begins to kill, where he before had ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>Like a cloſe myzer he augments his ſtore,</l>
                  <l>The more he ſlaies, to ſlaie he loues the more.</l>
                  <l>All this thou didſt, what latter age can tell,</l>
                  <l>Of one that better did, or halfe ſo well.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus like <hi>Alcides</hi> all compoſde of ire,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe fiery lights ſhut ſparkes of fortitude:</l>
                  <l>This Champion doth to greater deeds aſpire,</l>
                  <l>Still preſſing on the <hi>Hydra</hi> multitude,</l>
                  <l>Till like to ſheepe they fled in order rude.</l>
                  <l>Then to his Tent with tryumph he doth goe,</l>
                  <l>Valure doth loue to ſpoile, not chaſe the foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:25"/>
                  <l>But ſee vnconſtant chance, and ſeeing weepe,</l>
                  <l>For euery word requires a ſiluer teare:</l>
                  <l>Whiles careleſſe victory did ſweetly ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>And conqueſt by deſert did honour weare,</l>
                  <l>(VVhen moſt we liue ſecure, we moſt ſhould feare)</l>
                  <l>Sixe hundred men conducted by a Squire,</l>
                  <l>Made thoſe that chaſte with praiſe, with ſhame retire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ere that theſe confuſed warriours fled,</l>
                  <l>Whom vnexpected horror did amaze:</l>
                  <l>They ſold their liues for liues ere they were dead,</l>
                  <l>Their conquering blood their honors did emblaze,</l>
                  <l>Bnt all were not deriued from one race.</l>
                  <l>Some Stallions in a field, ſome Aſſes bee,</l>
                  <l>And ſo of men there be, of each degree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Richard</hi> thou canſt not mount thy ſteed and flye,</l>
                  <l>Nor thou great Lord experience makes thee ſtay,</l>
                  <l>To feare the name of death is worſe then dye:</l>
                  <l>But men borne baſe, a baſer word will ſay,</l>
                  <l>I care not how I ſcape ſo liue I may.</l>
                  <l>Ye ſlaues to feare whom I abhorre to ſee,</l>
                  <l>That loue life more, then praiſe or honeſtie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Still do they ſtriue till that vnnumbred preſſe</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Bees</hi> of <hi>Hybla</hi> ſwarmed euery where:</l>
                  <l>Courage in danger doth it ſelfe expreſſe.</l>
                  <l>Submiſsion to a Lyon breeds but feare,</l>
                  <l>But rauenous beaſts their proſtrate ſubiects teare:</l>
                  <l>By ſuch great <hi>Richard</hi> falls, and <hi>Pembrooke</hi> dies,</l>
                  <l>Conquering twiſe twentie thouſand enemies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:25"/>
                  <l>Mount ſacred ſpirits with cleare conſcience wings</l>
                  <l>To the ninth heauen whereas your glorious eye</l>
                  <l>May gaze on the immortall king of kings:</l>
                  <l>Liue you in peace, but we in miſery,</l>
                  <l>Man cannot happie be before he dye.</l>
                  <l>Vnto your glorious tombes I ſacrifice,</l>
                  <l>Theſe diſmall Anthems and ſad Elegies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>CEaſe mournfull Muſe, to chaunt theſe Ciuil broiles,</l>
                  <l>Vnciuill warres, and ſence-amizing times:</l>
                  <l>Brothers by brothers ſpoild, vnnaturall ſpoiles,</l>
                  <l>The guilt whereof to <hi>Ioues</hi> tribunall climes,</l>
                  <l>Oh ſubiect fit for <hi>Thaeban Statius</hi> rimes.</l>
                  <l>All warres are bad, but finall end doth tell,</l>
                  <l>Inteſtine warres all other warres excell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Witneſſe the ſame the Macedinian downe,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Pompey</hi> did the Senates cauſe defend,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſought the worlds Imperiall Crowne:</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe <hi>Philippes</hi> and <hi>Antonius</hi> end,</l>
                  <l>Milde <hi>Othos</hi> death which Authors ſo commend.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Richard</hi> now riſeth at his Nephewes fall,<note place="margin">Richard. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>A conſcience cleare is like a brazen wall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now Englands <hi>Traiane</hi> ſprung from <hi>Troiane</hi> race,</l>
                  <l>Doth <hi>Oxford</hi> helpe and <hi>Darbies</hi> aide implore,</l>
                  <l>Froth-faced <hi>Neptune</hi> with his trident mace</l>
                  <l>Doth guide his Argoſies to <hi>Milfords</hi> ſhoare,</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Boſworth</hi> field he ſlaies the tusked Boare.<note place="margin">The battle o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Boſworth.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Leiceſtrian</hi> Dales their crimſon goare did fill,</l>
                  <l>A ſcarlet ſtreame from <hi>Richard</hi> did diſtill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:26"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cheiney</hi> thy armes and ſinewes are not ſtrong</l>
                  <l>Enough to match with <hi>Albions</hi> martiall king:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Brandon</hi> thou doſt thy youthfull vigor wrong,</l>
                  <l>To combat him who to the field did bring</l>
                  <l>Thoſe cruell parts which <hi>Collingbourne</hi> did ſing.</l>
                  <l>Now conſolations wings doth reare my minde,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew his praiſe, who ſprang from <hi>Priams</hi> kinde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Great Impe of kings,<note place="margin">Henry. 7.</note> heroicke <hi>Theodore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Englands <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> famous Prince of peace,</l>
                  <l>Great Treaſurer of ſacred Vertues ſtore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eden</hi> of pleaſure,<note place="margin">Arthur.</note> which didſt all men pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Comfort of <hi>Albion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Henry.</note> and they Countries eaſe:<note place="margin">Margaret.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>From the foure golden Fountaines did ariſe</l>
                  <l>Like vnto thoſe that ſprang from Paradiſe.<note place="margin">Mary.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh that I had all wittes excelling witte,</l>
                  <l>To eternallize thy deeds immortall king:</l>
                  <l>My pen thy trophies ſhould, and tryumphes writte,</l>
                  <l>The triple lauor of this round ſhould ring</l>
                  <l>VVith thy great name, which my great muſe ſhould ſing.</l>
                  <l>But ſince that Nature did the ſame denie,</l>
                  <l>Accept my will, aetheriall dietie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Elizabeth el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt daughter to Edw. the 4. was maried to Henr. the 7 by which mariage the both hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Yorke and Lancaſter ſo long ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wer vnited</note> O Princely perfect name,</l>
                  <l>Combinde with thee, oh cheerfull cordiall knot:</l>
                  <l>No priuate quarell could white <hi>Albion</hi> fame:</l>
                  <l>VVith blood and rapine fierce diſſention blot,</l>
                  <l>Fury it ſelfe, within it ſelf did rot.</l>
                  <l>Two parted Roſes which ſo long did ſtriue,</l>
                  <l>Grew on one ſtalke, and both began to thriue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:26"/>
                  <l>From that faire ſtalke great <hi>Arthur</hi> firſt did riſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arthur</hi> who matcht with <hi>Caſtiles Katherine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Childleſſe he dide, and death he did deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>His body was intombde in gorgeous ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rine,</l>
                  <l>His ſoule aſcended, for it was diuine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> then Prince and heire apparant was,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> which did all former <hi>Henries</hi> paſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſnow-white <hi>Cliffes</hi> which <hi>Albion</hi> do confine,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſubiect ſands are deckt with <hi>Margarites:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Henry 8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Clearer then is the cleareſt Chriſtaline,</l>
                  <l>The towring waues, which rule the narrow ſtreights,</l>
                  <l>Which do adumbrate ſleepy rockes deceits,</l>
                  <l>Could not debarre his thoughts, but he did goe</l>
                  <l>To conquer <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Englands</hi> greateſt foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wolſey</hi> then liu'd,<note place="margin">Chriſt Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> in Oxford.</note> high minded worthy Clarke,</l>
                  <l>VVhich did erect thoſe glorious Towres of yore:</l>
                  <l>Learnings receptacle, Religions parke,</l>
                  <l>Oh that ſome Eagle-mounting thought would ſo are</l>
                  <l>To finiſh that which he began before.</l>
                  <l>Oh that ſome Prince (for none but Princes can)</l>
                  <l>VVould perfect that, that excellent worke of man.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſiluer <hi>Iſis</hi> and the gliding <hi>Thame,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe billowes reſalute the verdant ſtrand,</l>
                  <l>Should warble <hi>Paans</hi> to his mightie name,</l>
                  <l>The leaden age is paſt which rulde the land,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saturne</hi> is come, and <hi>Saturne</hi> doth command:</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe hopes were dead, rich ſtudents neuer feare,</l>
                  <l>(Moſt rich in hope) ſome will your turrets reare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:27"/>
                  <l>Nurſe of ingenious ſpirits <hi>Athens</hi> praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Chiefe benefactor of what ere is mine:</l>
                  <l>O might I ſee ſome mightie Monarch raiſe</l>
                  <l>Thoſe halfe built walles and parted towres combine,</l>
                  <l>Then Chriſt might yet be iuſtly tearmed thine:</l>
                  <l>As Chriſt is beſt, ſo ſhould his houſes bee,</l>
                  <l>And in perfection haue a ſympathie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henries</hi> triumphant carkaſſe laid in graue,<note place="margin">Edward 6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Couered with gold in <hi>Caeſars</hi> ancient towre:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> ſucceeds, a Prince though yong, yet graue,</l>
                  <l>The ſkye which whilome ſmilde begins to lowre,</l>
                  <l>And ſhowres of ſorrow on the land to powre.</l>
                  <l>He endes his life before it ſcarce began,</l>
                  <l>What is more ſhort then ſhorteſt life of man.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When nature fram'd this Prince, oh goodly creature,</l>
                  <l>Compoſ'd of pure and elementall fire:</l>
                  <l>Turnd in a heauenly mowld diuineſt feature,</l>
                  <l>She ſaw her ſelfe deceiu'd, and wroth with ire,</l>
                  <l>When life began, his end ſhe did deſire.</l>
                  <l>What enuie ſo could thee proud Nature ſting,</l>
                  <l>Nothing ſhould make and marre the ſelfe ſame thing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Gods did enuie mans felicitie,</l>
                  <l>And therfore did to Nature condeſcend:</l>
                  <l>That this yong King, great King of Maieſtie,</l>
                  <l>In ſixteene yeares his vitall courſe ſhould ſpend,</l>
                  <l>His life hath end, and all our ioyes haue end.</l>
                  <l>Nature doth haſten to the houſe of death.</l>
                  <l>And ſhee conſents to ſteale away his breath.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now <hi>Spayne</hi> and <hi>England</hi> ioynes,<note place="margin">Queene Mary married with Phillip Prince of Spayne.</note> that peace I loue,</l>
                  <l>That concord doth augment the common ſtate:</l>
                  <l>Pray God it doth both firme and faithfull proue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4005:27"/>
But for to match with <hi>Spayne,</hi> oh cruell fate,</l>
                  <l>Could <hi>Mary</hi> ſo her countrey ruinate?</l>
                  <l>Guiltleſſe ſhee was, but thoſe that made the match,</l>
                  <l>Vnder their wings did egges of Serpents hatch.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh now me thinkes I could in diſmall blacke</l>
                  <l>Shadow my lookes, and neuer wiſh the light:</l>
                  <l>Writing red lines of blood, more blacke then blacke,</l>
                  <l>The maſſacres of mans amazing ſight,</l>
                  <l>After theſe duskie clouds comes eleareſt light.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> is dead, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> doth raigne,</l>
                  <l>Her conſcience cleare, no coraſiue could ſtaine.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The loſſe of Elizabeth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FAire Virgin, Empreſſe, royall Princely maide,</l>
                  <l>Sprung from the Damaske Roſe the Roſes bud:</l>
                  <l>Tis true as truth it ſelfe which men haue ſaide,</l>
                  <l>The end is beſt, though all the meanes be good,</l>
                  <l>She was the laſt and beſt of <hi>Henries</hi> blood.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> did well in all, excell in this,</l>
                  <l>In getting of this Maide, our greateſt bliſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He vanquiſht <hi>Bolleine,</hi> and ſtrong <hi>Turnus</hi> towne,</l>
                  <l>And rode in tryumph through the Engliſh Pale:</l>
                  <l>Placing the Diademe of <hi>France,</hi> that regall Crowne,</l>
                  <l>Vpon his ſiſters temples; and withall</l>
                  <l>Made the twelue Peeres to feare their finall fall.</l>
                  <l>But what of theſe? if <hi>Bullain</hi> had not bin,</l>
                  <l>We all had liu'd for aye in endles ſin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Aſtronomers did dreame and fondly ſaide,</l>
                  <l>That twelue deſigned ſignes did rule a Spheare:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virgo</hi> did guide the earth, oh heauenly Maide;</l>
                  <l>But now sky-teachers wiſe men neuer feare,</l>
                  <l>To ſay ſhe is in heauen, for ſure ſhees there.</l>
                  <l>Oh ſhe is gone, with her our pleaſures fled,</l>
                  <l>They liu'd in her, they dide when ſhe was dead.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:28"/>
                  <l>Bright Gem of honor, <hi>Albions</hi> glorious ſtarre,</l>
                  <l>The Cynoſure of <hi>Englands</hi> Hemiſpheare:</l>
                  <l>Princeſſſe of peace, <hi>Cytherian</hi> queene of warre;</l>
                  <l>Rides through the cloudes on her caeleſtiall beare,</l>
                  <l>Conquering deathes Ebon dart and ſharpeſt ſpeare.</l>
                  <l>Fathers of peace put on triumphant weedes,</l>
                  <l>A gratious King, a gratious Queene ſucceedes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reaſons firſt founder, Natures eldeſt ſonne,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Stoikes</hi> prince did alſo erre in this:</l>
                  <l>Repugnant natures neuer raigne in one,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ſtotle. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Perfect my griefe, more perfect is my blis,</l>
                  <l>I ſmile with ioy, yet teares my cheekes do kiſſe.</l>
                  <l>A preſent ſalue hath cured a penſiue ſore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Britaine</hi> is now, what <hi>Britaine</hi> was of yore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The wandring <hi>Brute,</hi> who ſprang from <hi>Priams</hi> kinde,</l>
                  <l>Though artleſſe men with their malignant muſe:</l>
                  <l>Still bearing burning enuie in their minde,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Britaines</hi> firſt Monarch warlike <hi>Brute</hi> abuſe,</l>
                  <l>Of all the Northern world, this Iſle did chuſe.</l>
                  <l>With fire and ſword he did obtaine his ſute</l>
                  <l>With peace and ioy we chuſe a ſecond <hi>Brute.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Peace, valure, learning, ſcience hee did bring,</l>
                  <l>Thou feare of God, whom thou doeſt onely feare:</l>
                  <l>Imperiall Monarche, truth and concordes King,</l>
                  <l>No champion then did weild his fruitleſſe ſpeare,</l>
                  <l>No chaine did tye the milde vntamed Beare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saturne</hi> then liued, no <hi>Sinon</hi> did amiſſe,</l>
                  <l>All men were free, (no ſlaue by Nature is.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:28"/>
                  <l>Oh ſacred age, and bleſſed times of yore,</l>
                  <l>When iuſt <hi>Astraea</hi> rul'd this circled plaine:</l>
                  <l>Then each man liu'd alike, and liu'd withſtore,</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Perſian</hi> blood did <hi>Salamina</hi> ſtayne,</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Vandals Rome,</hi> nor <hi>Romane</hi> gouernd <hi>Spayne.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No <hi>Cannas</hi> chaunce did cauſe <hi>Saturnia</hi> mourne,</l>
                  <l>No ſenceleſſe <hi>Nero</hi> wiſht new <hi>Troy</hi> to burne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No <hi>Manlius</hi> ſought a Diademe to gaine,</l>
                  <l>No iuſt <hi>Papirius</hi> ſude for <hi>Fabius</hi> bloud:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Claudius</hi> as then did not <hi>Virginia</hi> ſtayne,</l>
                  <l>No Conſulls fell at <hi>Alias</hi> flaming flood,</l>
                  <l>Red <hi>Charea</hi> was not dewde with <hi>Fabys</hi> blood.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Albans</hi> and <hi>Romanes</hi> knew no ſingle ſight,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saffetius</hi> did not yeeld to <hi>Martius</hi> might.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The vnſpotted ſpowſe of martiall <hi>Collatine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did not conſent to <hi>Sextus</hi> lawleſſe luſt:</l>
                  <l>Each virgin was ybound with <hi>Veſtas</hi> line,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Camillus</hi> needed not the <hi>Ardeans</hi> truſt,</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Sceuola</hi> his hand in flames to thruſt.</l>
                  <l>But ſee, oh ſee how age doth follow age,</l>
                  <l>VVorſe after worſe, as Actors on a ſtage.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thrice happy <hi>Britaine,</hi> ſtrong vnited Ile,</l>
                  <l>Disioynted was by her firſt monarches fall:</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Albanact</hi> was ſlaine by <hi>Humbers</hi> guile,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caeſar</hi> then conquer'd it, who conquered all,</l>
                  <l>Hunes, Pictes and Danes tryumph't in <hi>Britaines</hi> fal.</l>
                  <l>Vaile ſorrowes roabes, <hi>Ioues</hi> father comes againe,</l>
                  <l>The golden age begins with <hi>Iacobs</hi> raigne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:29"/>
                  <l>The Lords great <hi>Stuart, Albions</hi> mightie King,</l>
                  <l>Our ſecond <hi>Brute</hi> like to the morning ſtarre,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Englands</hi> Court doth light of comfort bring,</l>
                  <l>Now Concords boult doth <hi>Ianus</hi> temple barre,</l>
                  <l>Binding in chaines the ſterneſt god of warre.</l>
                  <l>Vertue and valour triumph euermore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Auguſtus</hi> liues adornd with <hi>Craſſus</hi> ſtore.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>TO THE MAIESTIE OF
King Iames, Monarch of all
Britayne.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ALl haile great Monarch of the greateſt Ile,</l>
                  <l>The Northerne worlds vnited lawfull King,<note place="margin">Iames the 1. of England, and 6. of Scotland.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pardon my rudeſt reede vndecent ſtile,</l>
                  <l>Though I want Skill in thy new Empires ſpring,</l>
                  <l>Yet doe I loue, and will thy prayſes ſing.</l>
                  <l>Me thinkes I do on <hi>Clarps</hi> Kingdome ſtand,</l>
                  <l>No maruaile, for <hi>Apollo</hi> rules the land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On true obedience knee I pardon aske</l>
                  <l>Of thy diuine heroicke Maieſtie,</l>
                  <l>It was thy merites great impos'd this taske</l>
                  <l>On my weake pen, badge of infirmitie,</l>
                  <l>Too weake indeede to prayſe thy excellency.</l>
                  <l>Each <hi>Cherrils</hi> muſe doth now ſalute thy grace,</l>
                  <l>Shall I alone be mute and hide my face?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:29"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> extold <hi>Auguſtus</hi> peacefull daies,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Liricke</hi> Poet ſung <hi>Mecenas</hi> fame:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ennius</hi> did <hi>Scipio Affricanus</hi> praiſe,</l>
                  <l>If all they liu'd and ſaw thy ſacred name,</l>
                  <l>Each verſe they made ſhould ſure containethe ſame.</l>
                  <l>But if they reade thy gift,<note place="margin">Baſilicon Doron.</note> oh Princely worke!</l>
                  <l>For ſhame they would in vntrode deſarts lurke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If <hi>Englands</hi> Load-ſtarre pride of Poeſie,<note place="margin">Chaucer, ſo called by M. Camdon.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Could the firme Centers regiment tranſpearſe:</l>
                  <l>And formalize his peerleſſe ingeny,</l>
                  <l>Thy all-ſurpaſſing vertues to rehearſe,</l>
                  <l>A Princely matter fitts a princely verſe:</l>
                  <l>Yet were his wit too weake thy deeds to praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Which brought vs ioyes, in our moſt mournfull daies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Could <hi>Lidgat</hi> paſſe the tower of <hi>Proſerpine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And like to <hi>Virbius</hi> liue a double age,</l>
                  <l>Penning thy Trophies in a golden skrine,</l>
                  <l>Yet could he not thy mertis equipage,</l>
                  <l>Admiring moſt would vſe a tapinage,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bocchas</hi> and <hi>Gowre,</hi> the <hi>Virgils</hi> of their time,</l>
                  <l>Could not vnfold thy prayſe in antique rime.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If theſe foure Poets liu'd like Lions foure,</l>
                  <l>They ſhould thy famous Coach of glory drawe</l>
                  <l>From Vertures temple, to true honours towre,</l>
                  <l>Each ſhould a kingdome haue, thy foes ſhould know</l>
                  <l>Thy might, and feare their finall ouerthrow.</l>
                  <l>But what ſhould muſes ſing? the world doth ſee,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeing, feares vnited <hi>Britany.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:30"/>
                  <l>Still liuing <hi>Sidney, Caeſar</hi> of our land,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe neuer daunted valure princely minde,</l>
                  <l>Imbelliſhed with Art and Conqueſts hand,</l>
                  <l>Did expleiten his high aſpiring kinde,</l>
                  <l>(An Eagles hart in Crowes we cannot finde.)</l>
                  <l>If thou couldſt liue and purchaſe <hi>Orpheus</hi> quill,</l>
                  <l>Our Monarches merits would exceed thy skill</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Albions Maeonian, Homer <hi>natures pride,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Spenſer</hi> the Muſes ſonne and ſole delight:</l>
                  <l>If thou couldſt through <hi>Dianas</hi> kingdome glide,</l>
                  <l>Paſſing the Palace of infernall night,</l>
                  <l>(The Sentinels that keepes thee from the light)</l>
                  <l>Yet couldſt thou not his retchleſe worth compriſe.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe minde containes a thouſand purities.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What fatall chance is this, and luckleſſe fate,</l>
                  <l>That none can aptly ſing thy glorious prayſe,</l>
                  <l>And tell the happineſſe of Englands ſtate,</l>
                  <l>O barren time, and temporizing dayes,</l>
                  <l>Fowle Ignorance on ſacred Learning prayes.</l>
                  <l>But now I doe a Diapazon ſee,</l>
                  <l>None but thy ſelfe (great King) can ſing of thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That <hi>Macedonian</hi> ſtarre, firſt Prince of <hi>Greece,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Philip Ariſtotle</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sent for that wandring learned Stagirite,</l>
                  <l>To teach his Sonne knowledge of knowledges:</l>
                  <l>His ſword was keene, his ſenſe could ill indite:</l>
                  <l>Thy ſworde is ſhape, and who can better write?</l>
                  <l>He had another to inſtruct his ſonne,</l>
                  <l>What he by others did, thy ſelfe hath done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:30"/>
                  <l>Some <hi>Caeſar</hi> deemde the happieſt mortall wight,</l>
                  <l>That breath'd the ayre, or did aſcend the skye,</l>
                  <l>For conquering <hi>Scipios</hi> force, and <hi>Pompeis</hi> might,</l>
                  <l>Some did <hi>Auguſtus</hi> iudge more happy, why?</l>
                  <l>Becauſe the vanquiſht <hi>Aegypts Anhtony,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes</hi> holy Prince, ſaid <hi>Nerua</hi> did ſurpaſſe,</l>
                  <l>For leauing ſuch a ſonne as <hi>Traian</hi> was.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If thoſe olde Wiſards which of yore did ſing,</l>
                  <l>Read with impartiall eyes thy peerleſſe deeds,</l>
                  <l>(Great Prince of warre, of peace thrice happie King)</l>
                  <l>Concord ſhould reconcile their ſtriuing reeds,</l>
                  <l>And ſenſures ioyne, which cenſures enuy breeds.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caeſars</hi> acts, <hi>Auguſtus</hi> peace, good <hi>Neruas</hi> kinde,</l>
                  <l>In thee alone, in non but thee we finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſiluer Moone plac'd in her circle round,</l>
                  <l>At her encreaſe, her equall diſtant hornes</l>
                  <l>Vpwards aſcends, as ſcorning abiect ground,</l>
                  <l>So when the worlds great honour firſt was borne,</l>
                  <l>That fayre ariſing Sunne, cleere faced morne,</l>
                  <l>Her mounting thoughts did to the heauens <hi>Towre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Scorning the earth, or any terrene Bowre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But when that Virgins Goddeſſe doth decreaſe,</l>
                  <l>Her picked forkes their courſe to <hi>Terra</hi> bend:</l>
                  <l>So when our Englands <hi>Lunas</hi> light did ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>The Artike Clime an Vnicorne did ſend,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe radiant Iuſture, night ſhall neuer end:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Phoebes</hi> cleere light ſeemes darke, whilſt he doth ſhine</l>
                  <l>He borrowes perfect light of God diuine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:31"/>
                  <l>Thoſe that do reade the ſecrets of the skie,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe iudgement is in heauen conuerſant:</l>
                  <l>Which portraiture the ſignes in heauenly die</l>
                  <l>Might aſſeuere that <hi>Virgo</hi> was on high,</l>
                  <l>I ſawe a ſtarre of late from heauen flie:</l>
                  <l>Why cannot this ſtarre then faire <hi>Virgo</hi> bee?</l>
                  <l>A ſtarre more chaſte I thinke we cannot ſee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O now my thoughts can diue into the deepe,</l>
                  <l>Our all ſhips guiding ſtarre was fixed there:</l>
                  <l>And when <hi>Eliza</hi> did with honor ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>Mounted vpon her praiſe deſeruing beare,</l>
                  <l>She did obtaine of him ſhe lou'd ſo deare,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe might haue his ſeate, he rule the land</l>
                  <l>Which ſhe of late as Empreſſe did commaund.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Anatomizers of our learned daies,</l>
                  <l>Affirme that <hi>Virgo</hi> do the belly guide:</l>
                  <l>No wonder then that <hi>Albions</hi> wondrous praiſe,</l>
                  <l>That Virgin Queene which here on earth did bide</l>
                  <l>So nouriſht each poore hunger-bitten ſide.</l>
                  <l>Now ſhe is dead, oh who will them reliue?</l>
                  <l>The preſent ſtarre doth preſent comfort giue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I heard an aged woman often ſay,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe did ſee a ſtarre from heauen deſcend:</l>
                  <l>Which was as true me thought, as trees did bray:</l>
                  <l>For ſhe alledg'd the ſame, and did commend</l>
                  <l>A certaine Crowe, whoſe wit ſhe did defend.</l>
                  <l>Pardon me Age, for now mine eyes do ſee</l>
                  <l>A ſtarre on earth, more bright than ſtarre can bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:31"/>
                  <l>To whom ſhall I this Northerne ſtarre compare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>Caeſar</hi> which did firſt ſubdue the ſtate:</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Horſus</hi> who no limbe of Chriſt did ſpare,</l>
                  <l>Damming his ſoule this land to ruinate,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Williams</hi> conqueſt and the Normanes hate.</l>
                  <l>Thus doth my Muſe all wanting art begin,</l>
                  <l>To ſing thy vertues, and to ſhewe their ſin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caeſar</hi> was twice repulſt ere he could ſee</l>
                  <l>This litle world from all the world remote:</l>
                  <l>Before we ſawe thy face we ſent to thee,</l>
                  <l>As to a Pilot for to guide our boate:</l>
                  <l>Which did in Seas of ſuddaine ſorrow floate.</l>
                  <l>He loſt his ſword before he conqueſt wan,</l>
                  <l>We yeeld thee all our hearts, and all we can.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Horſus</hi> by cruell tyrant trechery,</l>
                  <l>Subdude <hi>Ambroſius</hi> that wiſe Prince of peace:</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe the hidden kniues at <hi>Salisbury,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He trauaile brought, but thou doeſt bring vs eaſe,</l>
                  <l>Thy true deſcent makes greedy warres to ceaſe.</l>
                  <l>A Wolfe poſſeſt his heart, a Lyon thine,</l>
                  <l>He worſe then man, thou better more diuine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>William</hi> was fierce in warre, and ſo art thou:</l>
                  <l>In counſell ſage, thou doeſt him aequalize:</l>
                  <l>His ſword forc't foes their trembling knees to bowe,</l>
                  <l>Thou conquerſt hearts, by thy hearts winning eyes</l>
                  <l>By force he wan, by merits thou doeſt riſe.</l>
                  <l>He brought ſubiection, thou doeſt freedome bring.</l>
                  <l>He loued warre, but thou of peace art King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4005:32"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rufus</hi> was rude, thou ciuill, gentle, kinde:</l>
                  <l>He was auſtere, thy browes hath mercies frowne:</l>
                  <l>He had a <hi>Neros</hi> hart, thou <hi>Caeſars</hi> minde:</l>
                  <l>He hunting lou'd, for pleaſure tumbled downe</l>
                  <l>Many a Caſtle fayre, and ſtately Towne:</l>
                  <l>Thou lou'ſt the chaſe, yet Cities doeſt adorne,</l>
                  <l>Thou wert for all the worlds great profit borne,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> was grac't with artes, thou doeſt excell:</l>
                  <l>Children did bleſſe his age but ſoone did dye:</l>
                  <l>Children thou haſt in health and perfect well,</l>
                  <l>(God proſper them with pure proſperitie,)</l>
                  <l>Adorne their harts with louing pietie:</l>
                  <l>He was a worthy King, thou worthier farre,</l>
                  <l>Thou art our Northerne-Pole, harts-guiding ſtarre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Soare humble thoughts, and let my abiect pen</l>
                  <l>Touch the high mounted <hi>Artike</hi> Northerne ſtarre,</l>
                  <l>And there compare this man excelling men:</l>
                  <l>VVe ſhould compare the things that equall are,</l>
                  <l>And who is like this light, this lampe, this ſtarre?</l>
                  <l>Mine eyes diſtill ſweete teares, the teares of ioy,</l>
                  <l>To ſee <hi>Troyes</hi> iſſue raigne in new found <hi>Troy.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let <hi>Barland</hi> ceaſe to write of wiſeſt Kings,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Mellificius</hi> with his tuned voyce,</l>
                  <l>From whoſe ſweet tong ſprang learnings ſweeteſt ſprings?</l>
                  <l>Sing not of <hi>Perſians</hi> prayſe, or <hi>Caldeans</hi> ioyes,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Grecians</hi> Emperour, <hi>Europs</hi> worthieſt choyce.</l>
                  <l>Theſe three combinde, each ſought the others fall,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Britaine</hi> is ioynd, and Concord guides it all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When <hi>Alexander</hi> ſawe that precious ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Vnder whoſe Iſye wings <hi>Achilles</hi> lay,</l>
                  <l>Shedding ambitious teares, he ſaid with mone,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4005:32"/>
Vnhappy I, and ten tunes happy they,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe enſignes prayſe, ſweet <hi>Homer</hi> did diſplay:</l>
                  <l>Then happy art thou King, whoſe raigne wee ſee</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Homer</hi> doth ſing thy prayſe, for thou art hee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Maieſtie of <hi>Marius</hi> fearefull face</l>
                  <l>Did terrifie the <hi>Cymbrians</hi> crauen minde:</l>
                  <l>Though he were armde with <hi>Clothos</hi> fatall mace,</l>
                  <l>And ſolemne oath to murther did him binde,</l>
                  <l>A wandring <hi>Bucke</hi> did feare the <hi>Eagles</hi> kinde:</l>
                  <l>So did thy Princely lookes and grace of God</l>
                  <l>Protect thy iſſue from a Traytors rod.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now doth my Ship in plenties Ocean ſayle,</l>
                  <l>Puſht with a pleaſant gale of pleaſures winde:</l>
                  <l>But ſtay I here an enuious Momiſt rayle,</l>
                  <l>Thy toothleſſe threate doth not amaze my minde,</l>
                  <l>Barke, for thou canſt not bite, I ſcorne thy kinde,</l>
                  <l>That which I write, I reade, and both are true,</l>
                  <l>I dare not, nor I will not tell what will enſue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My hope is good that we ſhall happy bee,</l>
                  <l>Hopeleſſe our foes, they feare, we ſtill ſecure:</l>
                  <l>We peace, they warre: Ye endleſſe peace ſhall ſee,</l>
                  <l>We plenty haue, they pouerty endure,</l>
                  <l>Religion we ſincere, but they impure.</l>
                  <l>They liuing ſeeme to dye, we dying gaine</l>
                  <l>To liue with Saints in <hi>Paradiſus</hi> plaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ſaid the learned, thoſe that learning loue,</l>
                  <l>If cauſes periſh, then effects decay,</l>
                  <l>Pray for the cauſe, yea, pray to God aboue</l>
                  <l>That he may long the <hi>Albion</hi> Scepter ſway,</l>
                  <l>Who ſhinde like <hi>Sol</hi> in our <hi>Cimmerian</hi> day.</l>
                  <l>Liue, and liue long, great King, liue many dayes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vſe that fayre Theame,</hi> Be as thou art alwayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4005:33"/>
            <head>TO THE WORTHY AND
Honourable Gentleman Sir Philip
Harbert, Knight of the moſt
Noble Order of the
Bathe.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe ſecond time doth my unworthy muſe</l>
               <l>Salute thy milde aſpect thriſe noble Knight,</l>
               <l>Let gracious cenſure his defects peruſe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe <hi>Genius</hi> waites on thy heroicke ſpright,</l>
               <l>Whoſe loue and life are bent to honour thee:</l>
               <l>And whileſt breath laſteth vſe both them and mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe Poems which my infant labours ſend</l>
               <l>As meſſengers of dutie to thine eares,</l>
               <l>Are of ſmall value, but if nature lend</l>
               <l>Some perfect dayes to my unripened yeares,</l>
               <l>My pen ſhall vſe a more iudicious vaine,</l>
               <l>And ſing thy glory in a higher ſtraine.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours
at commaund.
William Harbert.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4005:33"/>
            <head>TO THE IVDICIOVS
Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Which in bloudy warres haue ſleep'd my pen,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Muſe the paſſing bell of peace did wring,</l>
               <l>And how the world did looſe a world of men,</l>
               <l>Now chuſe to touch a more concordant ſtring,</l>
               <l>My Prince his prayſe, whoſe prayſe Ile euer ſing.</l>
               <l>Tis no mechanicke hope of hired gaine</l>
               <l>That mou'd my minde theſe labours to ſuſtaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No, that ignoble baſeneſſe I abiure,</l>
               <l>It was the loue I euer bare the place</l>
               <l>Where firſt I breathed life did me allure,</l>
               <l>In pleaſant paines for to conſume a ſpace,</l>
               <l>And her to prayſe, though with mine owne diſgrace:</l>
               <l>With my diſgrace, why? though my verſe be ill,</l>
               <l>I do not doubt to pleaſe the good with will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To thee Iudicious Reader do I ſend</l>
               <l>Theſe fruites of youth, tis thee I hope to pleaſe:</l>
               <l>If that my muſe the ignorant offend,</l>
               <l>No lines of mine their fury ſhall appeaſe,</l>
               <l>I ſet iuſt warre before an vniuſt peace,</l>
               <l>I rayle not I, though I with <hi>Plato</hi> ſay,</l>
               <l>To pleaſe the wiſe, muſt bee the wiſeſt way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4005:34"/>
               <l>THe lotted ſeruant to rhy Infant age,</l>
               <l>Thrice glorious iſſue of a gracious King,</l>
               <l>Leaſt that her twelue-monthes fearefull tapynage,</l>
               <l>Ingratitude ſuſpect to thee ſhould bring,</l>
               <l>Me, though vnworthy, choſe thy prayſe to ſing</l>
               <l>Her mourning garments ſhe hath caſt aſide,</l>
               <l>And hopes ere long to entertaine her Bride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Cleargie with the Barons borrowed light,</l>
               <l>Is now obſcured by thy tranſplendant ſhine:</l>
               <l>The Rochet nor the Border hath no right</l>
               <l>To rule, but that which doth from thee decline,</l>
               <l>She ioyes and glories to be onely thine:</l>
               <l>Shee deemes it honour, count it no diſpraiſe</l>
               <l>For thee with her to ſpend thy yonger dayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No matchles <hi>Machauil,</hi> nor <hi>Arietine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth her plaine meaning breaſt with enuy breede,</l>
               <l>Her wits do moderne ſeeme, and not diuine,</l>
               <l>Loyall her loue though lowly is her weede,</l>
               <l>A ſympathie there is of word and deede:</l>
               <l>Such as theſe are, in <hi>Wales</hi> thine eyes ſhall ſee,</l>
               <l>Thouſands that will both liue and dye with thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O was ſhe euer falſe, vntrue, vnkinde?</l>
               <l>Since her obedience did augment thy ſtile?</l>
               <l>Or ſince the parted Roſes were combinde,</l>
               <l>Did euer rebels blood her breſt defile?</l>
               <l>Or did ſhe euer Englands hopes beguile?</l>
               <l>Witneſſe the world, and thoſe that liue therein,</l>
               <l>Her ſpotleſſe ſoule did neuer taſte that ſin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4005:34"/>
               <l>Search Truthes Records, not times illuding lines,</l>
               <l>Then ſhall thy Princely thoughts and eyes be fed</l>
               <l>With the ſtrange wonders of thoſe warlike times,</l>
               <l>When thy great Grandſyres made our channels red</l>
               <l>With blood of thoſe that on our ſhoares laie dead.</l>
               <l>Teaching great <hi>Caeſar</hi> how to runne away,</l>
               <l>That neuer knew to ſlye before that day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ten yeares did <hi>Rome</hi> and all the world admire,</l>
               <l>For all the world and <hi>Rome</hi> ten yeares did feare</l>
               <l>The luſture of thy Bekons ſet on fire,</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Odoniſis</hi> King, <hi>Character,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe endleſſe worth my worthleſſe Muſe ſhall reare</l>
               <l>To that bright Spheare where honor doth remaine,</l>
               <l>She loues thee dead, thy life her loue did gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhat honor or what glory didſt thou win</l>
               <l>VVith the earthes ſtrength to conquer but an Ile,</l>
               <l>Maiſter of the worlds miſtres, mightie King?</l>
               <l>Only this grac'd the greatnes of thy ſtile,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Claudius</hi> with blood did not his hands defile.</l>
               <l>This triumph <hi>Rome</hi> did thee as highly grace,</l>
               <l>As when by <hi>Scipio Affrique</hi> conquered was.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How many Legions <hi>Caeſar</hi> didſt thou ſend?</l>
               <l>How many Conſuls did returne of thine,</l>
               <l>VVhich ſought what others marr'd, by warres to mend?</l>
               <l>How many Emperours <hi>Britaine</hi> did repine,</l>
               <l>To ſee thy honor riſe, their praiſe decline.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Tacitus</hi> vnto the world declare,</l>
               <l>No land ſaue <hi>Rome</hi> might with this land compare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4005:35"/>
               <l>I know yong Prince, and am agreeu'd to ſee</l>
               <l>The leeuy'd lookes of ſquint-cyde <hi>Theonyn:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who ſaies this ſault is proper vnto mee,</l>
               <l>To iudge all others baſe our ſelues diuine,</l>
               <l>No enuious <hi>Momiſt</hi> tis no fault of mine:</l>
               <l>That ſeme are ſo, I muſt confeſſe tis true,</l>
               <l>All are not bad of vs, nor good of you.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The mellow fields haue tares as well as corne,</l>
               <l>And thiſtles grow amidſt the greeneſt graſſe:</l>
               <l>An <hi>Anacharſe</hi> in <hi>Tartary</hi> was borne,</l>
               <l>Vertue and vice do meete in euery place,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clodius</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> as well as <hi>Milo</hi> was.</l>
               <l>Both good and bad in euery land we ſee,</l>
               <l>And ſo are you, if of a land ye bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Curbe the malignant pride of enuies rage,</l>
               <l>And checke the ſtubborne ſtomackes of diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Theſe penny Poets of our brazen ſtage</l>
               <l>Which alwayes wiſh, O let them wiſh in vaine,</l>
               <l>VVith <hi>Roſſius</hi> gate thy gouernment to ſtaine,</l>
               <l>Make them more milde, or be thou more auſtere,</l>
               <l>Tis veretue, vnto vice to be ſeuere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ſpeake not this vnto the learned wiſe,</l>
               <l>For them I loue, becauſe the truth they loue:</l>
               <l>Tis the bleard iudgement of ſeditious eyes,</l>
               <l>That doth my muſe and my affection moue,</l>
               <l>A moſt vnwilling Satiriſt to proue:</l>
               <l>Nature hath made me milde, but theſe hard men</l>
               <l>Turn'd my ſoft quill into a brazen pen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4005:35"/>
               <l>Play not the Satyr peace affecting muſe,</l>
               <l>I doubt not but their conſcience will prouoke</l>
               <l>Theſe Luciliſts their follies to refuſe,</l>
               <l>And make them ſoft, though they were hard as oke,</l>
               <l>Conſcience makes bad men good, ſo wiſe men ſpoke</l>
               <l>I leaue them to their ſpurres, my muſe ſhall flye</l>
               <l>Vnto that Sphere where enuy dares not prye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnto that Sphere whoſe circuit doth containe</l>
               <l>The neuer ſpotted eſſence of his ſoule,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſacred intellect no worldly ſtaine</l>
               <l>Could with deſires rebelling aide controule:</l>
               <l>This guilded Sphere is like a golden boule,</l>
               <l>Which many leſſer mazers doth containe,</l>
               <l>So many vertues in this one do raigne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why parriall nature ſtepdame to my birth,</l>
               <l>Ye mixed elements affections ſlaues,</l>
               <l>VVhy did ye frame this veſſell but of earth?</l>
               <l>An equall matter to the dead mens graues,</l>
               <l>And ioynd thereto a ſpirt like the waues:</l>
               <l>Low as the earth although my <hi>Genius</hi> be,</l>
               <l>Yet doth it touch skye threatning Maieſtie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O were my wit but equall to my will,</l>
               <l>VVere I as wiſe as I am ignorant,</l>
               <l>Here were a place that would deſerue my skill,</l>
               <l>Had I as great experience as I want,</l>
               <l>Then would I in a booke of Adamant,</l>
               <l>And Inke compoz'd by water made of golde,</l>
               <l>VVith pens of Diamond thy prayſe vnfolde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4005:36"/>
               <l>Let Iuſtice rule the organ of thy ſpeech,</l>
               <l>And Clemency adorne thy Princely browe:</l>
               <l>Vnto thine eares long abſent patience teach,</l>
               <l>By theſe which good men wiſh, let all men knowe,</l>
               <l>None but thy ſelfe, thy ſelfe can ouerthrowe.</l>
               <l>Let pittie check the rod when we offend,</l>
               <l>That makes the good more good, the bad to mend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I witneſſe call the ſeuen hilled Queene,</l>
               <l>How we obey'd, when Lawes obey'd were:</l>
               <l>And ſhall not we be now as we have bene?</l>
               <l>Feare made vs then vnnaturall bondage beare,</l>
               <l>VVe now ſecurely liue, and cannot feare.</l>
               <l>Doubt not thereof,<note place="margin">Cornelius Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus in the life of Agrippa.</note> but come experience haue,</l>
               <l>VVe loue to ſerue, but loathe the name of ſlaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our gazing expectation longes to ſee</l>
               <l>The true admired Image of thy Syre:</l>
               <l>Which Nature hath ſo rightly grau'd in thee:</l>
               <l>As Phiſicke cauſes ſeem'd, they did conſpire</l>
               <l>To ſhape the like to him whom all admire.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Sions</hi> ſacred ſinger <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaies,</l>
               <l>Good trees bring forth good fruit, good fruit alwaies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Do not ſweete Sallets ſpring from ſoundeſt ſeed?</l>
               <l>And is not man like God, which man did make?</l>
               <l>Can bad effects from cauſes good proceed?</l>
               <l>Do we ſee fruite on any withered ſtake?</l>
               <l>Or do we ſee in ſea a buſh or brake?</l>
               <l>How canſt thou then not good and perfect bee,</l>
               <l>That wert engraft on ſuch a goodly tree?</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4005:36"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
