<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new ballad, containing a communication between the carefull wife, and the comfortable husb[and] touching the common cares and charges of house-hold</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1331</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114839</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850062</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850062</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15246</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A03188)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15246)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 871:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new ballad, containing a communication between the carefull wife, and the comfortable husb[and] touching the common cares and charges of house-hold</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for F. Cowles,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>c. 1640]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Verse - "How shall we good husband now live this hard yeare,".</note>
                  <note>Printed on same sheet with STC 13852.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Husband and wife --  Songs and music --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-08</date>
            <label>Jennifer Kietzman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-08</date>
            <label>Jennifer Kietzman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:15246:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A new Ballad, containing a communication between the carefull Wife, and the comfortable Husb touching the common cares and charges of House-hold.
<figure/>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <head type="sub">The carefull Wife.</head>
               <l>HOw shall we good husband now live this hard yeare,</l>
               <l>T<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is world is so queasie and all things so deare:</l>
               <l>And so little taking of money for ware,</l>
               <l>Makes me lye waking with no little care.</l>
               <l>Then had you néed Husband to looke to the Foxe,</l>
               <l>Whose cr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fty conveyance will empty your boxe:</l>
               <l>With faire fawning speeches some credit to crave,</l>
               <l>Or else to bee surety for more then you have.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then Husband bée carefull and not over large,</l>
               <l>For unto Hous-keeping there longeth a charge:</l>
               <l>In wiving and thriving it is an old song,</l>
               <l>More then the bare legs to bed doe belong.</l>
               <l>What you spend on mee, I take for my paine,</l>
               <l>For doing such duties as you would disdaine:</l>
               <l>For dressing your dyet, in washing and wringing,</l>
               <l>And much paines I take man, with faite babies bringing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And what you doe get, Sir that will I save,</l>
               <l>What better good will in a Wife can you have?</l>
               <l>Be sure of my promise, for better, for worse,</l>
               <l>I will be a huswife to husband your purse.</l>
               <l>I must provide, man, for many an odde thing,</l>
               <l>That you ne<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r looke to buy or to bring:</l>
               <l>To welcom<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your neighbours, your Nurse and your friend,</l>
               <l>To furnish a houshold longs many an odde end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What néed, man, such odding betwixt you and me?</l>
               <l>All shall bée even, man, if wée two agree:</l>
               <l>Even you my good husband, and I your good wife,</l>
               <l>Will passe this hard yeere, man without any strife,</l>
               <l>And I for my part will doe what I may,</l>
               <l>With Spinning and Reeling to passe time away,</l>
               <l>Providing and getting to pay for my fla<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e:</l>
               <l>That none shall come chatting to you for such la<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As iust as you will, man, I will be content,</l>
               <l>Pay you the Brewer, and the Landlord his rent.</l>
               <l>The Butcher, the Baker, and the Collier his score,</l>
               <l>And then the Woodmonger and I aske no more,</l>
               <l>Then a good Newyéers gift, good husband give mée,</l>
               <l>And a good Newyéers gift I doe give thée,</l>
               <l>Thou hast a good wife, that a huswife will bee,</l>
               <l>Both this yeare and many to bee merry with thée.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="ballad">
            <lg>
               <head type="sub">The comfortable Husband.</head>
               <l>WIfe, as wee get little, so temper our dyet,</l>
               <l>With any small morsell to live and be quiet,</l>
               <l>Though home be but homely and never so poo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Yet let us keepe warily the Wolfe from the doore,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> there lay a str<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, wife, I am not so mad,</l>
               <l>We<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ard is well sold, wife, a man may be glad,</l>
               <l>With any light gaine to fill up the purse,</l>
               <l>Meane state to maintaine, but not make it worse,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I know it is true, goodwife, that you say,</l>
               <l>He that doth marry, m<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t cast much away:</l>
               <l>For looke wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tsoever I spend upon you,</l>
               <l>Comes never againe (wife) I thinke this is true,</l>
               <l>Loo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e what you would have, Wife, let mée know,</l>
               <l>I grutch not at any thing that you bestow.</l>
               <l>Be content and pleased, lacke shall bée no let:</l>
               <l>Ile see your cares eased as fast as I get.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But looke no more in wife, then I looke without,</l>
               <l>You looke in my purse, wife, too often I doubt,</l>
               <l>But when you looke in would you bring in as fast</l>
               <l>Then though you still look'd, the longer 'twould last,</l>
               <l>Upon the odds, wife, I perceive still you goe,</l>
               <l>With the oddes I have gotten a verry odde shrow:</l>
               <l>The oddes may sometimes, wife, make a faire lay,</l>
               <l>And the oddes may hazard to make all away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A merry new life, makes a merry beginning,</l>
               <l>Let goe this is past, wife, be it losing or winning,</l>
               <l>I will play the good husband the best that I can,</l>
               <l>To live with good credit and pay every man,</l>
               <l>Then shall wee lacke nothing, wife I doe beleeve,</l>
               <l>Nor no man shall take you or me by the sleeve,</l>
               <l>For scoring, or tallying, or taking on trust,</l>
               <l>But cleare quittance making is ioyfull and iust.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That I shall doe, wife, with a very good will,</l>
               <l>To pay that I owe my meaning is still:</l>
               <l>And shall have to pay, I hope while I live,</l>
               <l>What old yeare affords not, the new yeere will give,</l>
               <l>God grant it bee true all this that you say,</l>
               <l>To his onely glory, to whom let us pray,</l>
               <l>That wee in his feare may seeme to amend</l>
               <l>Our former sinnes passed unto our lives end.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
