<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the maior, aldermen, and inhabitants of N. That whiche heretofore I haue propounded to you (right worshipfull and beloued) in teaching, I do now publish to all men by printing, to wit, mine opinion of the vnlawfulnesse of games consisting in chance  ...</title>
            <title>Short and plaine dialogue concerning the unlawfulnes of playing at cards or tables, or any other game consisting in chance</title>
            <author>Balmford, James, b. 1556.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1335.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115732</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850950</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850950</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16192</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A03231)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16192)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1616:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the maior, aldermen, and inhabitants of N. That whiche heretofore I haue propounded to you (right worshipfull and beloued) in teaching, I do now publish to all men by printing, to wit, mine opinion of the vnlawfulnesse of games consisting in chance  ...</title>
                  <title>Short and plaine dialogue concerning the unlawfulnes of playing at cards or tables, or any other game consisting in chance</title>
                  <author>Balmford, James, b. 1556.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By John Harrison 3?] for Richard Boile,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1600?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another edition of: Balmford, James.  A short and plaine dialogue concerning the unlawfulnes of playing at cards or tables, or any other game consisting in chance.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Suggested printer's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 18324.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gambling --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16192:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Maior, Aldermen, and Inhabitants of N.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which heretofore I haue propounded to you (right Worſhipfull and beloued) in teaching, I do now publiſh to all men by printing, to wit,
mine opinion of the vnlawfulneſſe of games conſiſting in chance. My deſire is either information, if I erre in iudgement, or reformation of ſo
leud a practiſe. But whether I erre or no (which yet I would gladly vndeſtand,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 3. 7.</note> for I ought not to teach an vntruth, though to Gods glorie) yet
there is none, zealous indeed againſt ſinne, deſirous from the heart to reclaime ſinners, and who deepely conſidereth the grieuous abuſes, which
accompanie dicing and carding (as horrible ſwearing, dangerous quarelling, loſſe (I ſay not of good houres, but) of nights and dayes, and the
pittifull vndoing of too too manie) but will remembe that<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 12.</note> all things are not expedient, which are lawfull, and therefore abſtaine from ſuch
Heatheniſh paſſe-times, that, if by their example they cannot reforme, they may be ſure<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 8. 9.</note> they do not confirme gameſters in their inordinate walking. Which
reſpect, the 7. Iniunction forbidding Miniſters to vſe theſe vnlawfull games, may be ſuppoſed to haue. Now that which authoritie exacteth of Miniſters, doth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
require of all true Profeſſours. For as the one are to be<note n="*" place="margin">1. Tit. 5. 3.</note> enſamples to the flocke, ſo the other are to be<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 2. 15.</note> lights in the world. And therefore as PAVL ſaith.
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 10. 13</note> If meat offend my brother, I will eate no fleſh while the world ſtandeth. So euerie true Chiſtian ſhould ſay, and that with more reſolution (for Play is not ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie
as meat.) If play offend my brother, who ſeeing me hauing knowledge, play, is boldned to follow gaming, I will not play while the world ſtandeth. Which
care vnto edification if all, who haue the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 50. 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 17.</note> word in their mouthes, and would not be thought to hate to be reformed, would manifeſt in their ſincere conuerſation
and if Magiſtrates, who ſhould not<note n="*" place="margin">Rom 13. 4.</note> carie the ſword in vaine would do what they may by<note n="*" place="margin">33 H. 8. c. 9 5. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 25.</note> law, to baniſh theſe forbidden paſt-times, or rather loſt-times, I doubt
not, but that preaching and writing againſt them would more mightily preuaile, and this good would come of it, manie would applie themſelues to better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes,
there would be leſſe time miſpent in Alehouſes, and God leſſe prouoked to diſpleaſure againſt vs. But theſe things I referre to the conſideration of the wiſe
and this my Dialogue to the iudgement of the Godly, chiefly to you, whoſe good I wiſh eſpecially. Farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <head>A Dialogue againſt playing at Cardes and Tables.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſſor</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir howſoeuer I am perſwaded by that which I reade in the common places of <hi>Peter Martir, Par.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 525. <hi>b.</hi> that Dice (condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
both by the Ciuill lawes, and by the Fathers) are therfore vnlawfull, becauſe they depend vpon thaunce: yet not ſatiſfied with
that which he writeth of Table-playing, <hi>pag.</hi> 526. <hi>b.</hi> I would craue your opinion concerning playing at Tables and Cards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preacher.</speaker>
               <p> Sauing the iudgement of ſo excellent a Diuine, ſo far as I can learne out of Gods word, Cards and Tables ſéeme to
me no more lawfull (though leſſe offenſiue) the dice. For Table playing is no whit the more lawfull becauſe <hi>Plato</hi> compares the
life of man therunto, then a théefe is the more iuſtifiable, becauſe Chriſt compareth his ſecond comming, to Burglarie in the night,
<hi>Matt.</hi> 24. 43. 44. Againe, if Dice be wholly euill, becauſe they wholly depend vpon chance, then Tables and Cards muſt néedes bée
ſomwhat euill, becauſe they ſomwhat depend vpon chance. Therfore conſider well this reaſon, which conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth the one aſwelas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
other: Lots are not to be vſed in ſport, but games co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſting in chance, as dice, cards, Tables, are lots, therfore not to be vſed in ſport.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p> For my better inſtruction, proue that Lots are not to be vſed in ſport.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p> Conſider with regard theſe thrée things: Firſt, that we read not in the Scriptures that Lots were vſed but only in ſerious matters both by the
Iewes.<note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 48. 1. Cor. 11. 16</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 18. 10. and Gentiles <hi>Ion.</hi> 1. 7. Secondly, that a Lot in the nature thereof doth as neceſſarily ſuppoſe the ſpeciall prouidence and determining
preſence of God as an oth in the nature thereof doth ſuppoſe the teſtifying preſence of God. Yea ſo, that (as in an oth) ſo in a Lot prayer is expreſſed or to be
vnderſtood, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. 41 Thirdly, that the proper end of a Lot (as of an oth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 16.) is to end a controuerſie and therefore for your better inſtruction ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine
theſe reaſons. Whatſoeuer directly, or of it ſelfe, or in a ſpeciall maner, tendeth to the aduancing of the name of God, is to be vſed religiouſly, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.
6. 7. and not to be vſed in ſport: as we are not to pray or ſweare in ſport. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20, 7. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 29. 13. <hi>Ier.</hi> 4. 2. but the vſe of Lots, directly of it ſelfe and in a ſpecial
maner tendeth to aduancing of the name of God, in attributing to his ſpeciall prouidence in the whole and immediate diſpoſing of the Lot. and expecting
the euent, <hi>Pro.</hi> 16. 33. <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 24, 26. Therefore the vſe of Lots is not to be in ſport. Againe, we are not to tempt the Almightie by a vaine deſire of manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of his power and ſpeciall prouidence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 18. 19. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 7. 12 <hi>Matt.</hi> 4. 6. 7. But by vſing Lots in ſport we tempt the Almighty, vainly deſiring the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation
of his ſpeciall prouidence in his immediate diſpoſing, Therfore, &amp;c. Laſtly, whatſoeuer God hath ſanctified to a proper end, is not to be peruer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted
to a worſe, <hi>Matt.</hi> 21. 12 13. But God hath ſanctified Lots to a proper end, namely to end controuerſies, <hi>Num.</hi> 26. 55. <hi>Pro.</hi> 18. 18. therefore man is not to
peruert them to a worſe: namely to play, and by playing to get away another mans money, which without controuerſie is his owne. For the common
ſaying is, <hi>Sine lucro friget luſus,</hi> no gaining, cold gaining.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p> God hath ſanctified Pſalmes to the praiſe of his name, and bread and wine to repreſent the body and bloud of our crucified Sauiour, which be
holy ends: and the children of God may ſing Pſalmes to make themſelues merie in the Lord, and feed vpon bread and wine not onely for neceſſity but to
cheare themſelues why then may not Gods Children recreate themſelues by lottery notwithſtanding God hath ſanctified the ſame to end a controuerſie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p> Becauſe we find not in the ſcriptures any diſpenſation for recreation by lotterie as we do for godly mirth by ſinging. <hi>Iam.</hi> 5. 13. and for religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
and ſober chearing our ſelues by eating and drinking, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. 9. 10. And therefore (it being withall conſidered that the ends you ſpeake of, be not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
though holy) it followeth, that God who only diſpoſeth the Lot touching the euent, and is therefor a principall actor, is not to be ſet on worke by lotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
in any caſe but when he diſpenſeth with vs, or giueth vs leaue ſo to do: But diſpenſation for recreation by lottery cannot be ſhewed, Therefore, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p> Lots may be vſed for profit in a matter of right, <hi>Num.</hi> 26. 55. why not for pleaſure?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p> Then others may be vſed for pleaſure, for they may for profite, in a matter of truth, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. 8. 11. But indéed lots (as othes) are not to be vſed
either for profite or pleaſure, but only to end a controuerſie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p> The wit is exerciſed by Tables and Cards, therefore they be no lots.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p> Yet Lotterie is vſed by caſting Dice, and by ſhufling and cutting, before the wit is exerciſed. But how doth this follow? Becauſe Cards &amp; Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
be not naked Lots, conſiſting only in chance (as Dice) they are therefore no lots at all. Although (being vſed without cogging, or packing) they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
principally in chance, from whence they are to receiue denominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In which reſpect a Lot is called in Latin <hi>Sors,</hi> that is, chance or hazard. And <hi>Lyra</hi>
vpon <hi>Prou.</hi> 16. ſaith, To vſe Lots, is, by a variable euent of ſome ſenſible thing, to determine ſome doubtful or vncertaine matter, as to draw cuts, or to caſt
Dice. But whether you will call Cards and Tables Lots, or no, you play with chance or vſe Lotterie. Then conſider whether exerciſe of wit doth ſanctifie
playing with lotterie, or playing with lotterie make ſuch exerciſing of wit a ſin, <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. 13. 14. For as calling God to witnes by vaine ſwearing is a ſinne,
2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 13 ſo making God an vmpier, by playing with lotterie muſt néeds be a ſin: yea, ſuch a ſin as maketh the offender (in ſome reſpects) more blame-worthy. For there be mo occaſions of ſwearing then of lottery. Secondly, vaine othes moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly ſlip out at vnawares, whereas Lots cannot be vſed
but with deliberation. Thirdly, ſwearing is to ſatiſfie other wheras this kind of lottery is altogether to fulfill our own luſts. Therfore take héed, that you
be not guilty of peruerting the ordinance of the Lord, of taking the name of God in vaine, &amp; of tempting the Almighty, by a gameſome putting off things
to hazard, and making play of lottery, except you thinke that God hath no gouernment in vaine actions, or hath diſpenſed with ſuch lewd games.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p> In ſhooting there is a chaunce by a ſodaine blaſt, yet ſhooting is no lottery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p> It is true: for that chance commeth by accident, and not of the nature of the game, to be vſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p> Lots are ſecret, and the whole diſpoſing of them is of God, <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o.</hi> 16. 33. but it is otherwiſe in Tables and Cards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p> Lots are caſt into the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, man, and  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould be ſuſpected: but the diſpoſing of the chance is ſecret, that it may be
chaunce indeed, and wholly of God, who directeth all things, <hi>Pro.</hi> 16. 13. 9. 33. So in Tables, man by faire caſting Dice truly made, and in Cards, by ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling
and cutting, doth openly diſpoſe the Dice and Cards ſo, as whereby a variable euent may follow: but it is onely and immediatly of God that the
Dice be ſo caſt, and the Cards ſo ſhuffled and cut, as that this or that game followeth, except there be cogging and packing. So that in faire play mans
wit is not exerciſed in diſpoſing the chance, but in making the beſt of it being paſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p> The end of our play is recreation and not to make God an vmpire: but recreation (no doubt) is lawfull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p> It may be the ſouldiers had no ſuch end when they caſt lots for Chriſt his coat, <hi>Matt.</hi> 27. 25. but this ſhould be your end when you vſe lottery,
as the end of an oth ſhould be, to call God to witneſſe. Therfore as ſwaring, ſo lottery, without due reſpect is ſinne. Againe, howſoeuer recreation be your
pretended end, yet remember that we muſt not do euill that good may come of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 8. And that therefore we are to recreate our ſelues by lawfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations.
Then ſée how Cards and Tables be lawfull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p> If they be not abuſed by ſwearing or brawling, playing for too long time, or too much money.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p> Though I am perſwaded that it is not lawfull to play for any money, conſidering thanks cannot be giuen in faith for that which is ſo gotten,
<hi>Deut.</hi> 23. 18. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61. 8. Gameſters worke not with their hands the thing that is good, to be frée from ſtealing, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4. 28. and the looſer hath not an anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
benefite for his money ſo loſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29. 15. contrarie to that equitie which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> by the light of nature hath taught long ſince, <hi>Eth. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 4. yet I
grant that Cardes and Tables ſo vſed as you ſpeake, be leſſe ſinfull, but how they be lawfull I ſée not yet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p> Good men and well learned vſe them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p> We muſt liue by precepts, not by examples, except they be vndoubtedly good. Therefore examine whether they be good, and well learned in
ſo doing or no. For euerie man may erre, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 4.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Profeſ.</speaker>
               <p> It is not good to be too iuſt, or too wiſe, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7. 18.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Preach.</speaker>
               <p> It is not good to be too wicked or too fooliſh, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7. 19. in deſpiſing the word of God. <hi>Pro. x.</hi> 22. and not regarding the weakneſſe of other, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14
21. Let vs therefore beware that we loue not pleaſure more then Godlineſſe, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 4.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London for Richard Boile.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
