<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hierons last fare-vvell A sermon preached at Modbury in Devon, at the funerall of that reuerend and faithfull seruant of Iesus Christ, Master Samuel Hieron, sometimes Preacher there. By I. B.</title>
            <author>Barlow, John, b. 1580 or 81.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1438</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850012</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850012</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15195</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A04261)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15195)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 824:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hierons last fare-vvell A sermon preached at Modbury in Devon, at the funerall of that reuerend and faithfull seruant of Iesus Christ, Master Samuel Hieron, sometimes Preacher there. By I. B.</title>
                  <author>Barlow, John, b. 1580 or 81.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 33, [2+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby for William Butler, and are to be sold at his shop in Saint Dunstanes Church-yard in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts.</note>
                  <note>Second sermon has separate title page, reading: "A christian's last day, is his best day" --STC.</note>
                  <note>The first sermon is initialed "Io. B."; the second has "Barlow" in full--STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect as filmed; lacks second sermon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15195:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15195:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Hierons laſt Fare-vvell. A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT MODBVRY in DEVON, at the Funerall of that Reuerend and faithfull Seruant of IESVS CHRIST, Master SAMVEL HIERON, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Preacher there.</p>
            <p>By I. B.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOB 1.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Doeth Iob ſerue God for nought?</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>William Stansby</hi> for <hi>William Butler,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Saint <hi>Dunſtanes</hi> Church-yard in Fleetſtreet. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15195:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15195:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MVCH HONOVRED LADY, AND MY VERY GOOD FRIEND, THE LADY <hi>MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GARET HELE,</hi> of WIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BVRY in DEVON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAME, its well knowne, that Apologies are, (for the moſt) of ſmall praiſe, or profit; being but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excuſes of prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent euill effects; or fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bad accidents likely to follow: yet ſeeing neceſſity is put vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me; I muſt ſay ſomewhat, though, to vſe the Apoſtles phraſe, I ſpeake like a Foole. Your Ladiſhip cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, how Satan and his inſtruments, in all Ages haue indeuoured to hinder both
<pb facs="tcp:15195:3"/>
the libertie, and dignitie of the Word, that it might not runne and be glorified. Hence ſprang theſe bitter ſpeeches: Is not this the Carpenter, the ſonne of <hi>Mary?</hi> Can any good thing come out of Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret? Is <hi>Saul</hi> among the Prophets? How know theſe vnlettered men the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? When went the Spirit of God from me, to thee? Is not this Sect ſpoke euill againſt euery-where? Was not <hi>John</hi> ſaid to haue a Deuill? <hi>Paul</hi> reputed a peſtilent fellow? and Ieſus Chriſt the righteous a notorious ſinner? One cryeth out, He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth the People: another, He is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to <hi>Caeſar:</hi> a third, And hath he not ſpoke blaſphemie? And, let theſe men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, all the world will follow them. And as it hath beene, ſo it is: for as <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes:</hi> ſo doe many in our dayes, reſiſt the truth. And marke their cunning, labouring to bring the Prophets, and Preachers to be contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; that the doctrine might not take effect, and be entertayned. Who then muſt ſtand in this gap, role away this ſtone, and preuent this euill, ſtop thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:15195:3"/>
wide mouthes, plucke the venom from vnder their tongues, and be able to keepe in grace, the Word of Grace, but you and ſuch as be of your Worth, Ranke, and Profeſſion? Therefore I haue made the more bold, to prefixe your Ladiſhips name, in the front of this my weake and pale Infant; as a ſpeciall remedy, to make all his enemies, at the very ſight thereof to fall backward; their tongues to cleaue to the roofes of their mouthes, and their very hearts to tremble: ſo that none dares ſtretch forth a hand, or bend his brow, to hinder him in his pretended iourney, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he haue paſt in peace, and ſaluted his deareſt friends. More reaſons might bee added, for to excuſe this my boldneſſe. The great loue you euer bare to him, for whoſe ſake it was conceiued: Your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall preſence at its birth: And was it not hee that fetcht mee from the Fountayne, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducted me from thence to your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, counted me worthy, and euer gaue me countenance vntill his change? Why then (though moſt vnworthy worke in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of its worth) yet ſhall it not finde
<pb facs="tcp:15195:4"/>
fauour at your hands for his ſake? Let him doubt that liſt, I will not: except change of time giue iuſter occaſion. And thus commending you to the protection of him that ruleth all in all things, theſe my firſt fruits to your Patronage, with my ſelfe to your ſeruice and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure I humbly take my leaue: From my ſtudie at <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth:</hi> euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours to his poore power to be commanded,</hi> Io. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15195:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EADER,</hi> This report hath beene publiſhed: that the abundance of Sermons (by ſome, and of ſome) preached, and printed, haue brought both the Word of God, and his Ordinance to be contemned; either, through the inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of the Authors, or, the corruption of Readers, and Auditors. For when the Word is not diuided aright, men of the beſt apprehenſion will not, cannot, giue approbation. And on the other hand, ſuch as cannot diſcerne betwixt good and euill, ſit at home, with a printed paper, dreaming that will ſuffice to get faith for ſaluation: and ſo abſent themſelues from the more powerfull meanes in the publike Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Doſt thou expect my reply? Shall I take in hand to giue thee ſatisfaction? No: for if I can but cleere my ſelfe from being the iust cauſe of the one (the which (likely) will be hard) Let him that list, and can better iudge, reſolue the other. Now if it be demanded of thee, that knew vs both; why by me, for him, (whoſe ſhoo-latchet, I was not worthy to vnlooſe) this Sermon was first preached; then printed: take one anſwere for all: which is, that a kinde of neceſsity was the cauſe, both of the one, and the other. If thou iudge this darke: Conſider, that God doth not alwayes render (and why may not man then ſometimes conceale?) a reaſon of his proceedings. For the worke it ſelfe, what ſhall I ſay? but as <hi>Naomi</hi> to her Daughters at their departure: It grieueth me much for your ſakes, that I could conceiue no better: yet
<pb facs="tcp:15195:5"/>
as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to the Cripple, ſuch as I haue, ſuch haue I gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. I deny not but thou maiſt finde words, phraſe, matter, and method, that may not content thee: what then? why, try all and keepe that which is good, for he that offends not in tongue, is a perfect man: but where is he?</p>
            <p>In my opinion I haue ſeene this euill vnder the Sunne: Men in hearing, and reading, if they diſlike any thing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſpeech, or perſon, like little children, that haue many things in their hands they like well, yet if their Parents doe but either adde or detract one, contrary to their minds, throw all away in diſpleaſure. Wherefore let me learne thee this leſſon, Get a ſound mind, that thou maiſt be able to iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the perſon, and his ſpeech, doctrine, and doctrine. For it is the perfection of a man in his calling, to know the worth of a commodity, though ſet to ſale by the pooreſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and the baſeneſſe of that which is bad, though proffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and proclaimed for good, by the hands of Princes: ſo is it for a Chriſtian to diſcerne the true Word, from the falſe, whether it come from him that weareth the courſeſt rags, or Kinglyeſt rayment. This is to iudge righteous Iudgement. Furthermore, for doctrine, ſome may be Corne, other Chaffe; therefore thou art to ſeparate the precious from the vile, by the fan of thy vnderſtanding, and hauing winnowed it well, treaſure it vp as good graine in the Garner of thy Memory. This is to haue a mans wit rightly exerciſed, when in the multiplicity of opinions, Truth is elected, error reiected. And thus wiſhing thee no worſe, then willingly I would receiue from thee my ſelfe, I ceaſe and reſt:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The ſame thou takeſt me for toward God, and thy ſelfe: in truth (I hope) though not in meaſure. Io. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15195:5"/>
            <head>HIERONS <hi>laſt Fare-well.</hi> A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT MODBVRY IN DEVON, at the Funerall of that <hi>Reuerend and faithfull Seruant of</hi> Ideſus Chriſt, M. SAMVEL HIERON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. TIMOTH. 4.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>I haue fought a good fight.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words may haue a double conſideration; either Relatiuely, or abſolutely: Relatiuely, hauing dependance on the precedent verſes, and ſo they ſeeme to be a motiue cauſe, or argument to moue <hi>Timothy,</hi> to goe on in the conſtant and ſincere Preaching, and profeſſing of the Goſpell. Abſolutely, and ſo they are a teſtimonie, or confeſſion, which the Apoſtle giueth of himſelfe. Now confeſſions be of two kinds; voluntary
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15195:6"/>
or violent; and this is of the firſt ſort, being free &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any coaction, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pulſion vttered. In the words we may obſerue two things: Firſt, the perſon confeſſing; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the thing confeſſed. The perſon confeſſing, may be conſidered in time paſt, or time future. The thing that he confeſſed, is laid downe firſt generally, then ſpecially. Generally, that he had <hi>fought.</hi> Specially, that (he had not onely <hi>fought,</hi> but) he had <hi>fought a good fight.</hi> If <hi>Paul</hi> had ſaid, I haue fought, &amp; ſtaied there, how many might tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue took vp the ſame ſpeech, and with the yong man in the Goſpell replied: <hi>All this haue I done from my youth vpward?</hi> But if a good fight be added, the anſwere of the Apoſtles to their Lord, concerning the fiue Loaues and few Fiſhes, may (by way of alluſion) ſeeme to bee of force; <hi>What are they among ſo many</hi>? Many fight, few a good fight. In briefe, the cauſe in theſe words, is argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the effect; and the effect, by the kind or qualitie, bountie or goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now would you haue the true ſence? Shall I open the plaine meaning? This it is, for the partie; hee may haue a manifold conſideration. Firſt, for his name, it was twofold, <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi>: for his nature, corrupt, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: for his Profeſſion, both the Righteouſneſſe of the Law, and the Goſpell: for his Function, a Phariſe, and an Apoſtle: for his conuerſation, a deſtroyer of the Saints, and a builder of them: A Murtherer, and a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr: This is the worke of God, and ought to bee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous in our eyes. Thus can the Creator of time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the creature in time, though Time of it ſelfe change nothing.</p>
            <p>For the word fight:] vnderſtand that fights are either <hi>Corporall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. <hi>6.12.</hi>
               </note> or <hi>Spirituall, with fleſh and bloud: or principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers,</hi> the latter heere meant.</p>
            <p>For goodneſſe:] that may be twofold; Naturall, or Morall: Naturall is alſo double. Firſt, the Eſſence of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15195:6"/>
things, by which I vnderſtand, matter, and forme, for whatſoeuer in the beginning was created, of theſe two principles was conſtituted: yea, the very Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, though ſome otherwiſe iudge. For, are they not perfect effects? Why then muſt they not haue all the foure cauſes? Againe, they are finite, therefore ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated in their Eſſence: If terminated in their Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; then by matter and forme; for what elſe doth ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate things? And there is nothing without Limits of Eſſence ſaue only God, the firſt efficient of all things, being one moſt ſimple and pure act.</p>
            <p>The ſecond naturall good, may be ſaid to be the end; that is, the fitneſſe, and aptitude of a thing to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh that for the which it was firſt framed, and wee are to know this, that the end, and goodneſſe of a thing, are one and the ſame. As for example, wee ſay that is a good Ship, that is fitted to ſayle well, a good Knife, made to cut well, or a good Pen, that hath in it ſelfe an aptitude to write well. Now Sayling, Cutting, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, are their ends; and if they haue in them a power, or abilitie to accompliſh theſe ends, they may bee ſaid to bee good, elſe not, in this ſecond ſence,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>1.</hi> vlt.</note> 
               <hi>Thus in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, were all things made good, and very good.</hi> Good for Eſſence, for end; And a thing may remayne good for it Matter, or Subſtance; but not for it qualitie, or end. Satan is ſtill a good ſubſtance; for his materiall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance remayneth; But he wants this ſecond goodneſſe, to doe the will of God: he neyther now hath power, or will to accompliſh that end, for the which he at the firſt was formed. A fine Watch may catch a fall, all the Wheeles by it may bee ſtrooke out of order, yet is it good ſtill, for the matter of it: An Inſtrument, may bee good for ſubſtance, yet, make no ſweet or pleaſant Muſicke, becauſe the ſtrings are not rightly ſet and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; ſo is the condition now with Sathan; And of man
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15195:7"/>
alſo; for vntill the Lord tune the iarring ſtrings of mans heart fit, and frame euery Wheele of the Soule, his beſt Muſicke is not pleaſing to God, and all his Courſe, and Motion, doth but runne to diſcontent his Maker: for <hi>Adam</hi> our father, clyming ſo high into the Tree of Life, and eating of the forbidden fruit, catcht ſuch a fal, (with whom (being in his Loynes) wee fell alſo) that all the Strings, and Wheeles of Soule and Body, were ſtrooke quite out of tune and order.</p>
            <p>Now for a Morall good, it may alſo haue a twofold denomination: Firſt, the act, or ſecondly, the conſequent of the act. That may (I take it) bee called a morall, or diuine act, that is guided by the morall and diuine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, as that may be called a Grammaticall art, that is ruled or done by the art or precept of Grammar.<note place="margin">Mich. <hi>6.8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good; namely, to doe Iuſtice, to loue Mercie, to humble thy ſelfe, and to walke with thy God.</hi> And this muſt needes be good, becauſe the rule is good that guides the action. For euery thing is ſo farre good, as it is anſwerable to its rule: And Diuinitie is the only rule of all Morall and Diuine goodneſſe; ſo farre as a man both in the integritie of his nature, and the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of life anſwereth to this rule, hee is ſo much and no more neerer to all perfection of goodneſſe. <hi>Adam</hi> was very good by Creation, but hee neuer was abſolutely good by action: Becauſe his actions were not guided by the Law of God; the only rule of all ſpirituall good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>The conſequent or ſucceeding good that followeth the Morall act, I vnderſtand to bee, the bleſſing which the Lord hath promiſed to conferre, and beſtow vpon all ſuch as loue him and obey his Commandements; And in this ſenſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>73.</hi> vlt.</note> 
               <hi>It was good for</hi> Dauid <hi>to draw neere vnto God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.37.</note> 
               <hi>For the end of the iuſt man,</hi> (whatſoeuer his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition be) <hi>ſhalbe bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15195:7"/>
               <hi>In a word, this is the ſumme, the true ſence. I</hi> Paul, <hi>who once was a proud Phariſe, called</hi> Rabbi, <hi>in great eſtimation with the High Prieſts, breathing out threatnings againſt the Saints, perſecuting them to ſtrange Cities, making hauocke of the true Church, cauſing ſome to blaſpheme, perſwaded that I ought to doe many contrarie things againſt the Name of</hi> Ieſus <hi>of Nazareth; yet now being extraordinarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, by his powerfull voyce from Heauen, and being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and called, to be his Apoſtle: One that ſaw the Lord</hi> Ieſus <hi>in the fleſh, had the Goſpell by Reuelation, freed from the ſpirit of Error, power to worke Miracles, skill in all Languages, and whoſe Commiſſion was to preach through the World; haue fought, that is, powerfully and plainly prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the glad tydings of Peace, gone on alſo thorow good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and euill report, bonds, impriſonment, and innumerable euils, in the ſincere profeſſing of the ſame, from the verie time of my Conuerſion to this preſent: I would haue thee my Sonne to know this fight, this my courſe is good, for act, for end, and profitable euery manner of way. And further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, let this then, my example, of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alour, and Reſolution, who am thy friend, thy Father, who am now to take my laſt farewell, whoſe face till that laſt day, thou muſt ſee no more, imbolden, encourage, quicken, and ſtirre thee vp to walke, preach and profeſſe, vntill thy changing come alſo. This is that one thing I only would, this is that one thing thou oughtſt and onely ſhouldſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, you ſeeing the plaine meaning of this parcell of Scripture, many things may bee obſerued for our inſtruction: And firſt, from the Relation with the other, we note, that,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> Paul <hi>muſt be imitated of Timothies in preaching, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi> The beſt patternes are beſt worthy our practice. <hi>Hence it is that</hi> Chriſt <hi>left vs an example,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 13.15. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>that wee might tread in his ſteps, And walke</hi> (that is, preach and profeſſe) <hi>as you haue vs for an example, and as we follow Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:15195:8"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> 
               <note place="margin"> Rom. <hi>15.4.</hi>
               </note>Becauſe that this is one reaſon why the liues of good men, are left recorded in Scripture, <hi>For whatſoeuer is written, is written for our Learning: And what a cloud of Witneſſes</hi> hath the Lord to this end committed to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall memory in <hi>the Holy Letters?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label>
               <note place="margin">Heb. <hi>12.1.</hi>
               </note> Againe, if wee doe not this, nature it ſelfe will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs: the very creatures will riſe vp againſt vs: who being yong and weake, imitate their <hi>Seniors</hi> and <hi>Superiors</hi>; No bangling Kite, but with a high flyer will mend his pitch; and ſhall not wee, being Eagles Birds, and borne from aboue, ſoare on high, hauing ſo many fore-runners, and excellent patternes ſet before vs?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> And from hence wee may reprooue the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that denie the people the Booke of God: ſo that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell how <hi>Paul</hi> preached, for matter, or manner, how he behaued himſelfe, either as Preacher or Profeſſor of the <hi>Gospell.</hi> Yea, and it meets with many in our dayes, that be within vs, that though they be <hi>Timothies,</hi> yong Plants, yet they will not learne of <hi>Paul,</hi> either by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept or example: This ſmels of Pride, or Ignorance, or Idleneſſe, or all.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> In the ſecond place, this muſt be to direct the yonger men, that they haue a regard, to bee acquainted with <hi>Pauls</hi> manner of preaching and liuing: and then to walke in his ſteps. Oh that wee would be wiſe, and not be too proud in our owne conceit! then ſhould wee bee ſtrong when wee are weake, and find Gods Wiſdome manifeſted through our fooliſhneſſe. Could we imitate the beſt patternes, we ſhould liue with credit, and dye with comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> And heere we may obſerue, that,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A mans finall eſtate is not to be iudged by the beginning, but by the end.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>6.9.</hi> Titus <hi>3.3. 2.</hi> Chron. <hi>33.11, 12.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> began ſtrangely, yet dyed a Martyr, and though his firſt dayes were bad, yet his latter being better, <hi>hee fought a good fight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15195:8"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> Becauſe all perfection is in the end, not in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: Hence it is that the Scripture runnes ſo much on the end, <hi>O that they were wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.17. <hi>Iames</hi> 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>then they would thinke of their latter end: then I vnderſtood their end: you haue heard of the patience of</hi> Iob, <hi>and of his end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> For, becauſe it often falleth out, that Hypocrites, like <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> may beginne well, and yet prooue Perſecutors, reſiſting the Truth much in the end: And as a man (good only in appearance) may of a truth become naught: ſo may a bad man become verie good. The Sunne may riſe cleere, and ſet vnder a cloud,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</note> ſhine bright in the morning, yet lowre in the euening: ſo may it be with the ſonnes of men?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> This muſt teach vs to iudge righteous Iudgement: Say not that hee is good, who beginnes well, but ends well: he that putteth on the Armour muſt not boaſt, as he that putteth it off.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> This may much make for the comfort of ſuch, as haue miſ-ſpent the time of their youth; that truly repenting, the Lord accepteth of them in their age, and will not lay their former courſes vnto their charge. I can tell you, that if wee were wounded in Spirit, nettled in Conſcience, and tempted by Satan, that God would not accept of our latter dayes ſeruice; then this Truth would be comfortable: But as to a full ſtomacke, euerie ſweet thing is bitter: ſo it is to him, that feeles not his miſerie, a word, a world of comforts.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>3</label> And heere we muſt be exhorted to perſeuere, though we haue begunne well; Beware of imbracing the world with <hi>Demas,</hi> in thy laſt dayes; haue a care to end in the Spirit: for wee muſt ſayle to the ſhore, runne to the end, and ſtrike the Battaile thorow, if wee will bee landed ſafe, winne the Prize, and be crowned.<note place="margin">Reuel. <hi>2.10.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>4</label> And is not here a ſtrong motiue, to mooue impenitent perſons to Repentance? to conſtraine them (as it were
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15195:9"/>
by a forced kind of neceſſitie) with the Prodigall, to returne to their Father: and with <hi>Oneſimus</hi> to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? And truely wee neuer make the right vſe of Gods Mercie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.</note> vntill his bountifulneſſe lead and allure vs to true Repentance.</p>
            <p>And now to come more directly to the words: wee might handle them two wayes, conſidering <hi>Paul</hi> as a Preacher in his particular Charge, or as a Profeſſor, in his generall Calling; but becauſe it is true of him in both, we will the rather inſiſt of the latter; to wit, how that all men are conſidered generally (as Chriſtians) Fighters: yea, and in their particular ranckes, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling alſo. So that the point hence will not to any ſeeme hard, which is,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label>
               <hi>That the faithfull are Fighters, euery Chriſtian is a Souldier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What though there bee many that goe vnarmed, ſtrike not one ſtroke, refuſe their Maſter, and throw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Spirituall Weapons, for this Combat appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? yet the point is plaine, and the proofe of it is at hand. Did not the Lord of old ſet Enmitie, tell vs of a Combat,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32.24.</note> and that the <hi>Seed of the Woman ſhould breake the Serpents head?</hi> This Battaile muſt be of force; this Field is to bee fought: for the purpoſe of God ſhall ſtand. And what did the Wraſtling of <hi>Iſrael</hi> prefigure, but this Fight? <hi>Yea Chriſt playeth vpon Earth, and hath his delights with the ſonnes of men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.31. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.13.</note> 
               <hi>Are not we commaded to ſtand faſt, to quit vs like men, and be ſtrong? And what meaneth all this</hi>;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>if the faithfull were not Fighters? Fight the good Fight of Faith? I fight not as one that beateth the Ayre:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.26. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29.</note> 
               <hi>We wraſtle: You haue the ſame Fight, that you heare to be in mee, and ſaw in me.</hi> And the Author to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.32.</note> 
               <hi>That they, after they had receiued Light, had a great Fight in affliction.</hi> Marke, after Light was receiued, the Combat followed; for it is in ſpirituall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15195:9"/>
things, as in naturall. Firſt, before it thunder, wee ſee a Light, then heare the cracke or noyſe, and after come great ſhowres of wet and water: ſo God (as at the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) ſayth, Let there bee light, in the time of our Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; after, we find a ſtrange working in the Soule, a Quarrell, a Wound, and then commeth the ſweete dew from Heauen to helpe vs, to heale vs. Will you ſee the reaſons of this? ſhall arguments further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> Doe we not read in Scripture of a Prince,<note place="margin">Heb. <hi>2.10.</hi>
               </note> a Chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, or Captaine? And ſhall hee haue no followers? muſt he want his Souldiers? No, for if the one bee, the other is. The Father preſuppoſeth a Child, the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard a Flocke, the cauſe his effect, the ſhaddow a body, and ſo doth a Captaine Souldiers; Souldiers a Combat: for theſe are Relatiue Arguments, and the one depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth neceſſarily on the other.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> Againe, is not mention made of weapons?<note place="margin"> Epheſ. <hi>6.13.</hi>
               </note> are wee not bidden <hi>to take to vs, the whole or complete Armour of God?</hi> If <hi>Dauid</hi> take his Sling, <hi>Peter</hi> his Sword, <hi>Ionathan</hi> his Bow, <hi>Sampſon</hi> his Iawbone, and <hi>Shamgar</hi> his Goad, is it not for an end? Why then, to fight: for the Enemies are in Armes, the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> bee in the Field; <hi>Goliah</hi> is vaunting, and daring to Battaile; and the Combat pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> And haue not the faithfull foes? Doe not the <hi>Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> campe in the Valleys? Are not the <hi>Aramites,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabians</hi> in the Mountaines? What ſhall I ſay? The ſonnes of <hi>Anakim</hi> are not all ſlaine; though their father ſleepe. And theſe foes bee, either forraine, or neerer home: within vs, or without vs: without vs, firſt, <hi>Satan</hi>: ſecondly, <hi>all his Souldiers:</hi> within vs, firſt, <hi>corruption:</hi> ſecondly, <hi>death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt for Satan,<note place="margin">The firſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</note> was hee not a Murtherer from the beginning? doth he not daily goe about, <hi>Like a roaring
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15195:10"/>
Lion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeking whom he may deuoure? Is not this that Red Dragon, that coloureth and choaketh himſelfe with the bloud of the Saints?</hi> Doe you thinke that this <hi>Herod</hi> is dead? Will Time alter his nature? or will the death of many ſatisfie him? No, he groweth worſe, and worſe; and hauing the leſſer time to quarrell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 12.12.</note> the <hi>greater woe ſhall be to the Inhabitants of the Earth.</hi> Wee are commanded to <hi>reſiſt the Deuill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames <hi>4.7.</hi>
               </note> Then ſhall he not oppoſe? Was <hi>Adam,</hi> the firſt, <hi>Iob,</hi> the Iuſt, <hi>Paul</hi> the Prince of the Apoſtles, and <hi>Ieſus Chriſt the Righteous tempted</hi> wounded,<note place="margin">Matth. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> buffet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and mooued from place to place by him? and doſt thou thinke to eſcape his hote, his fierie Darts? Let <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> goe out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to ſerue his God; this <hi>Pharaoh</hi> will be vp in Armes, and purſue: Let the Babe <hi>Ieſus</hi> bee borne; The Infants ſhall be beheaded: Let a little corne and good ſeed bee ſowne in the furrowes of the Soule; This enuious man will be caſting in Tares: or elſe hee ſhall haue his Kingdome weakned, his Scepter remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and not ſo large a Crop of Cockle, at the time of Harueſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond enemie.</note>Againe, his friends will alſo be our foes, and dare vs <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> daily to fight. If this <hi>Iehu</hi> but cry, Who is on my ſide, who? multitudes will follow him: this <hi>Ahab</hi> hath his hundreds of falſe prophets: this Serpent hath brood of his owne bowels, that like the Want, or Mole, can ſwimme the Sea, creepe vnder the Earth, transforme themſelues into Angels of Light, and bee readie to blow vp Prince and Nobles, with fire and Gunpowder. Hee hath <hi>Caine</hi> to kill: <hi>Iſmael,</hi> to ſcoffe: <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> to rayle, eſpecially, if they bee intreated to ſpeake in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Language. At a word, he hath <hi>Sanballats; Tobiahs</hi> Siluer-ſmiths, Copper-ſmiths, and of all kinds of Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, to ſet vp his Kingdome. <hi>Eſau</hi> cryed out, hee was vndone: <hi>Dauid,</hi> Woe is mee: and why? for they dwelt amongſt a people of polluted lips, and that abhorred
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15195:10"/>
peace. Their throats were an open Sepulchre: their Tongues like Razours, hote as the coales of Iuniper, the poyſon of <hi>Aspes</hi> vnder their lips, and their mouthes full of curſing and bitterneſſe;<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> their feete ſwift to ſhead bloud, deſtruction and calamitie in their wayes, and no feare of God before their eyes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 20.10.</note> 
               <hi>Ieremiah</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that his Mother had brought him forth, a man of Contention; he heard the rayling of many, all his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliars watched for his halting; ſaying, It may be that hee is deceiued; ſo ſhall wee preuaile againſt him, and execute our vengeance, vpon him.<note place="margin">Iohn <hi>8.4.</hi>
               </note> For theſe <hi>being of their Father the Deuill, his worke they will doe:</hi> though they goe at the laſt to ruine and deſtruction with him. And thus much for our forraine foes, that ſeeme the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from vs: Our home-bred, and more dangerous ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries follow, being two alſo.</p>
            <p>And the one of them is corruption, ſo called,<note place="margin">The third ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that he rotteth, and corrupteth, as much as in him is, his contrarie. This olde man will ſend out whole ſwarmes of luſts, to deſtroy the new. Hence wee are bidden, <hi>as Strangers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 11.</note> 
               <hi>and Pilgrimes to abſtaine from fleſhly luſts, that fight against the Soule.</hi> This pricke, or ſtab was ſent to buffet <hi>Paul,</hi> and neuer could he be rid of it,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.</note> till death. It is called a pricke in the fleſh: by which I vnderſtand, (omitting all other interpretations) the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie act, or motion of the vnregenerate part, often cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led fleſh, who, by his contrarie luſting, hindreth a man in the performance of all good duties.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17.</note> And the reaſons of this interpretation, are two; firſt, in all probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that which <hi>Paul</hi> complaines the moſt againſt elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, is that, that he moſt praid againſt in this place, <hi>and it was the bodie of death; the Law in his fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23.</note> 
               <hi>rebelling againſt the Law of his minde, and leading him captiue vnto the Law of ſinne, which was in his members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, thus I alſo reaſon, that which doth moſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15195:11"/>
moleſt, and trouble all Gods Children, is it that did the moſt trouble <hi>Paul, (Paul</hi> as a Chriſtian.) But this prick, the act of corruption, the ſtab of the old man, doth moſt moleſt all Gods Children, <hi>Ergo Paul,</hi> why? Aske an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Profeſſor, what doth the moſt trouble him in any good dutie? his anſwere will bee, In Prayer, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering thoughts, carrying the mind from God; ſo that like a man, who maketh a round Circle, fetching a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, wee neuer come neere him, but in the firſt word (Our) and laſt word (Amen) as the two points, in the very period of the Motion, and the Circles perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Alſo, let a man ſpeake, or preach the Word of God, how is a good man grieued that this pricke buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fets him, ſtriking his head awry, that he aimes not at the right end, or marke? weakning the ſpirit, that his ſpeech wants Salt to ſeaſon it, Grace to powder it, cauſing the poore Soule (when ſhe comes to her ſelfe) and viewes her wandering, to cry out, What haue I done? ſo that I had the rather apply it to many, then one particular ſin, or act.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>1</label> But it is called the Meſſenger of Satan?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> True; for Satan was the Authour of it at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; ſinne had his originall from Satan, and is the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed ſeed of a curſed father. Againe, Satan is no more willing to ſend this Meſſenger, but he is as ready to goe his errand, and in theſe and more reſpects, it may bee called the Deuils Meſſenger.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> But it is ſaid to bee in the fleſh, not from the fleſh?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſolut. </seg>
               </label> Wee muſt note, that it is in it, as the forme in the matter, and from it, as the act is from the forme. Againe, in the fleſh, may be read from the fleſh. Compare the 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 8.30. with 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.21.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaeſt. </seg>
               </label> But here a queſtion may bee demanded, <hi>viz.</hi> how grace and corruption,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſolut. </seg>
               </label> being adiuncts, and adiuncts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſentany arguments, can fight, being in the ſame
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15195:11"/>
ſubiect. I anſwere, Firſt, that they may haue a double conſideration, not only as adiuncts, but alſo as owners of the ſame ſubiect, in which they are, and to which they adhere; as two men in the ſame Boat, may diuerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be conſidered, for they are but adiuncts to the Boat in one ſence, and in another, it may bee an adiunct to either of them. The one laying title to it, ſaith it is his, and he wil goe Eaſtward: The other denieth that, and ſaith it is his, and he wil carrie it Weſtward. Thus the arguments being altered, and the one rowing one way, and the other another, comes the Combat.</p>
            <p>So Grace like an Owner, ſaith, that hee hath a true title to the man (for God hath put him into poſſeſſion) and would carrie him to Heauen. <hi>Corruption</hi> denyeth that; (for ſayth he) I haue been owner longer then thee; therefore he is mine, and ſhall to Hell-ward; and hence from their contrary luſting, may grow a quarrell.</p>
            <p>Againe, though they be contraries, yet they may be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in the ſame ſubiect, and more, in the very ſame part of the ſubiect, at the ſame time, but not in the ſame degree or meaſure, but more weake and remiſly; as white and black, heat and cold or diuers colours in varniſh, mixed, and mingled together: but at the ſame time, in the higheſt degree, to bee in the ſelfe-ſame part of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, is impoſſible.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond internall Enemie is Death,<note place="margin">The fourth enemie.</note> againſt whom we are to warre, and combat; as this foe came firſt into the World, ſo muſt he goe the laſt out of it;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.26.</note> 
               <hi>For the laſt Enemie to bee deſtroyed is Death.</hi> This cloſe Aduerſarie comes ſtealing vpon vs at vnawares, and giues vs a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wound with his ſting; And euery man muſt haue a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout and battaile with him, before hee enter into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: except a few that ſhall bee liuing at the laſt Day, yet their change may be called a kind of Combat: and ſtrange is this to thinke: for although this Warriour,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15195:12"/>
with <hi>Dauid,</hi> hath ſlaine his ten thouſand, yet hee neuer hath enough.</p>
            <p>And whatſoeuer the great Gallants of our dayes, in their hot bloud, and height of their valor, may imagine; yet the verie ſight of this foe, will make the ſtouteſt, and ſtrongeſt of their hearts to tremble. PHARAOH, but hearing, (yet hee was a King) that hee was come neere his home, could then cry, Let <hi>Iſrael</hi> bee gone, and ſerue his God, when all other iudgements would not worke effectually with him. Let <hi>Nabal</hi> that drunken Foole, bee come to his wits, and ſober, the tydings of ſuch a Meſſenger to fetch him, will make him as cold as a ſtone, and his liue heart to dye within him. But yet heere is comfort for a Chriſtian; for Chriſt, their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, hath bruiſed this Serpents head, depriued him of his ſting, and remooued that bitter and poyſoned wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from vnder his tongue: he hath changed his nature, put the glorious vayle of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> ouer his vgly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, through which, they that with the eye of Faith behold him, though they may feare at the firſt, as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> to touch his Rod, yet at the laſt, they ſhall haue boldneſſe, and imbrace him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> And laſt of all, Chriſtians muſt be Souldiers: for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they cannot obtaine the Crowne.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>He that ouer-commeth, muſt be clothed in white:</hi> And ſuch as fight man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vnder their Captaine, ſhall haue the Garland of Life. So that you ſee, that the faithfull are fighters: for they haue a Lord <hi>Generall:</hi> Secondly, Weapons and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: Thirdly, Enemies without them, and within them; without them, <hi>Satan, and his Souldiers: within them, Corruption, Death.</hi> And laſt, which is not the leaſt, no Combat, no Crowne: And from this point thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, many profitable <hi>Corrolaries</hi> ſpring, &amp; like ſtreames, from their fountaine, doe flow.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> And firſt of all, heere is confuted that fond opinion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15195:12"/>
of the vulgar, that thinke Heauen may bee had, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out warre, and garments, tumbling in bloud: theſe Dreamers imagine, that the Deuill (to vſe the Worlds Prouerbe) is dead, or that he hath no power to preuaile againſt them; defying, ſpitting, and ſcorning, yet alas, they are tooke captiue of him at his will, and with <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus, in the gall of bitterneſſe and bonds of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> They dreame, that they are borne to a Kingdome, and cannot miſſe of the Crowne; and where is their ground? why, Gods eternall Election. O, ſay ſuch, If I be ordained to life, then ſhall I bee ſaued: if predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated to death; why it is in vaine to fight, for I muſt be damned; But theſe muſt learne, if they haue a luſt to doe it; That Gods Decree excludes not, but includes the meanes, that leade to the end. Iobs <hi>dayes are numbred,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.5.</note> 
               <hi>his bounds he cannot paſſe:</hi> What? ſhall he therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eat, drinke, ſleepe, or vſe lawfull recreation?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>Not a haire ſhall fall from the heads of all the men in the Ship, for the Angell of God hath ſayd it:</hi> ſhall <hi>Paul</hi> therefore let it ſinke or ſwim? no, if theſe abide not in the ſame; yee cannot be ſafe.</p>
            <p>Therefore, bee it knowne, that if God haue choſen thee before eternitie, thou muſt bee created, called,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.</note> iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, ſanctified, and fight manfully, before thou bee ſaued Lay thy hand now vpon thy mouth, ſome out no more ſuch mud, caſt farre this filth from thee, and learne at the length, leſt it prooue too late, That the faithfull are fighters, and all Chriſtians bee Souldiers. It is true that the Lord knoweth who are his, his foundation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth ſure: yet euery one that deſireth to bee ſealed, ſaued, muſt depart from iniquity: for as he hath his ſeale,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19.</note> we muſt haue ours.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> Againe, here is reprehended a ſecond ſort, that thinke it the eaſieſt matter of a thouſand, to go to Heauen. It is a queſtion amongſt ſome, whether it be harder, to enter
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15195:13"/>
into the Kingdome of God, or goe to the Church, and publike Congregation: And too many there bee, that iudge the one as eaſie as the other, making in their ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low concluſion, the like equall proportion.</p>
            <p>To what end then is it, that wee are bidden <hi>to ſtriue, worke, proue, reſiſt, ſtand faſt, fight, quit you like men, let no man take away your Crowne</hi>? If it were ſo eaſie a matter, ſhall we thinke that Satan will not reſiſt, tempt, and caſt his fierie and fierce Darts at vs, if we warre againſt him? Will not the beaſts of <hi>Epheſus</hi> yell, roare, and deuoure ſuch as doe awake them out of the ſleepe of ſinne? Who will, that is wiſe, imagine, that corruption will not ſprawle, like <hi>Eſau</hi>? kicke with the heele, and cuffe vs on the face, as the High Prieſt bid <hi>Paul?</hi> and is it poſſible to liue in <hi>Meſhek,</hi> and <hi>Kedar,</hi> and not to bee oppoſed? breathe in the Ayre, and feed on the Creatures, and not to be mortall? Away then with this fond conceit; for they that thus erre in vanitie, vanitie ſhall bee their change. Theſe Sleepers <hi>Crowne</hi> ſhall, like <hi>Sauls Speare,</hi> be ſtolne from them; their beſt hopes ſhall make them one day aſhamed, their candle muſt bee put out, &amp; their houſe, like the Spyders Web, periſh: for hee that doth not ouercome, ſhall not be crowned; Heauen ſuffereth violence, and the violent take it by force.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>3</label>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And in the third place, I might ſoundly leſſon ſuch, that haue no care at all to bee acquainted with their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; or that thinke all the World is at peace with them; or that like a Child being offended, caſteth downe his weapons, as it doth all things in the hand. Fye, what a multitude of theſe haue wee? of whom we may ſay, that they are like <hi>Laiſh,</hi> a lazie people: ſome haue the eye of the minde put out, and like <hi>Saul</hi> at his Conuerſion goe, they know not whither; others like <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> and <hi>Adonibezech,</hi> are lame both of feete, and fingers: ſome as <hi>Samſon,</hi> when they bee to fight,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15195:13"/>
want their weapons, and ſo like puling boyes, put the finger in the eye, and fall a weeping.</p>
            <p>Alaſſe, alaſſe, how many take <hi>Caine,</hi> for his Keeper, the Wolfe, for the Sheepe, and in ſtead of the true Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, an Hireling! They beleeue euery report, giue credit to each perſon, and ſo like the fooliſh Birds, be inſnared. <hi>Satan</hi> leadeth ſome blind-folded, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet did the people vnto <hi>Samaria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Kings</hi> 6.19, 20</note> vnto the land of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, before their eyes bee opened, and their Enemies be diſcerned; only heares the diſſimilitude; the one found fauour, the other ſhall not be freed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>4</label> And, ſeeing that the Fighters bee faithfull, and the faithfull Fighters; it may make much for the comfort of ſuch as haue oppoſition within them, or without them; for truly, this is a ſure ſigne, that thou art a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier. Doeſt thou imagine, that a man can bee broke out of Satans <hi>Gaole,</hi> and he not make hue and cry after him? ſhall the Sinner be put into the endleſſe Riuer of Gods running Mercies; and ſhall not the Deuill angle for him? Will not the Prince awake, when the Subiects are at warre with him? And therefore the more that thou art tempted by the Deuill, the more cauſe thou haſt to gather comfort: for after remiſſion of ſinne, is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, <hi>Lead vs not into temptation.</hi> Againe, doth the World hate thee, count thee, with <hi>Paul,</hi> a Play-ſellow, runne with <hi>Caine,</hi> and ſeeke to kill thee? Why, know, ſhee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth her owne, cryeth peace vnto them ſhee affecteth, and alwayes lulleth them in her ſoft and lined lap.</p>
            <p>God would haue a wicked one in the <hi>Arke,</hi> that the Church and Truth might neuer be without oppoſition. <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſaid, that in the World wee ſhall haue many perſecutions: the Seruant is not greater then his Maſter: and if they haue done this to a greene Tree, alwayes fruitfull, what will they doe to a dry that is barren and ſeldome beareth? Therefore neuer bee daunted: Satans
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15195:14"/>
ſeede will ſting, although it cannot kill; it will be like <hi>Dan,</hi> and the <hi>Adder</hi> biting vs by the heele: but be thou of good comfort, <hi>The elder ſhall ſerue the younger: for Chriſt hath ouer-come the World.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn <hi>16.</hi> vlt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And what if we finde a ſtrange change in our ſelues, cauſing vs cry with <hi>Rebeccah,</hi> (when the Twins ſtroue in her wombe) Why am I thus? or with <hi>Ieremiah, Is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mans ſorrow like to my ſorrow?</hi> Or with <hi>Manoah, We ſhall die: for haue we not ſeene the Lord?</hi> Yet all this is ground of great ioy, matter of exceeding mirth; for ſaluation is come vnto thy houſe. I know that young Conuerts, in the pangs of regeneration, wonder to ſee ſuch an alteration in themſelues, imagining, that neuer any perſon hath found comfort in that condition. But vſe thou the meanes, and thy feare ſhall be expelled, thy ſpirit healed, thy corruption weakned; and thou, at the laſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.7.</note> ſhalt either be able to ſay with <hi>Dauid, Now, Soule, returne vnto thy reſt:</hi> or elſe with <hi>Paul,</hi> at the laſt, thou ſhalt heare that pleaſant, and ſtill voice, rowning thee in the eare,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9.</note> 
               <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee: for my power is made manifeſt in weakneſſe.</hi> And be thou aſſured, vntill Satan rage, the Fleſh pricke, the World perſecute, and Death terrifie, thou waſt neuer a Chriſtian Souldier, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the liſts of the fight, and in poſſibilitie of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 17.14.</note> 
               <hi>For they that are of the Lambs part, are called, and faithfull, and choſen,</hi> and therefore, muſt vnder-goe in ſome degree, what the Fore-runner, and Finiſher of their Faith hath ſuffered. Let Satan tempt me; corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion like a body lade me; the World deride me; Death looke grim vpon me; Then will I ſay, I either am, or ſhall be <hi>a Chriſtian Souldier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>5</label> The fift vſe, is for our inſtruction; that before we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne the Battaile (for this is Chriſts counſaile) wee would caſt vp our accounts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 14.31.</note> and conſider of our abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, leſt we, ſeeming to beginne in the Spirit, end in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15195:14"/>
Fleſh. Wee muſt take heede, that wee doe not ruſh into the battaile, without mature deliberation, but well weigh with whom, and about what we haue to deale. Many haue ſeemed reſolute at the firſt, that haue runne away at the laſt, and ſo all their labour hath beene loſt. Young Chriſtians are like young Souldiers, ſtrike hard for awhile, lay on lode, and anon retyre. We ſee in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that ſome Gallants ſtanding on the ſhore, and ſeeing a ſhip vnder ſayle, the flags ſpred, hearing the allarum of the Drum, ſound of the Trumpet, and report of the Peeces, lanch out valiantly: But when they, through the ſmell of the Pumpe, or tempeſt and ſtormes of the Sea, haue beene toſſed to and fro, tumbled out of their Cabbin, and Sea-ſicke exceedingly; vow, that if they once come to land, they will be for euer after wiſer: And the very ſame, for want of conſideration, befalleth many, that beginne this ſpirituall combat. We muſt beginne the battell; as men goe into the water to bathe, not too hot, nor too cold: for extremes in all things are full of danger.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> And laſt of all, ſeeing that the faithfull are fighters, we muſt labour for what may further vs in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, and to caſt off what might hinder vs in winning the field: wee muſt take to vs the whole Armour of God: <hi>Our loynes muſt be girded about with Verity:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. <hi>6.13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the plate of Iuſtice vpon our breſts: the Goſpell of peace muſt couer our feete; aboue all, we must take the ſhield of Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Goutch</hi> on this place.</note> 
               <hi>the helmet of Hope, and the ſword of the Spirit.</hi> Who will run into the battell vnarmed? What man is ſo mad, but will haue his weapons with him? elſe, would wee not count ſuch a perſon deſperate? Put on therefore the complete Armour of the Lord: And pray all manner of prayer: for prayer like oyle, and exerciſe, keepeth the furniture, and weapons from ruſting. And take theſe rules for thy further direction.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:15195:15"/>1. Firſt, know thou thy particular place and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: learne in what part of the battell thou art to war <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> vnder thy Captayne; nothing ſooner loſeth the field, but when men preſume aboue their place, and abilitie. Some will command, that are to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded; Others march in the Fore-front, that ſhould be in the Reare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. A third runneth with a Musket, that ſhould on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kindle the match: and ſo brings confuſion, if not death and deſtruction. That may truely be ſaid of the people: that ſometimes the people themſelues vttered: <hi>You take too much vpon you, you Moſes and Aaron.</hi> For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all will either bee Captaynes, or Coronels, or they will none of the Crowne, recoile, like an ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged Cannon, and not fight one ſtroke in the combat.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Againe, he that will ſo fight, as he may not beate the ayre, but winne the field, muſt get ſtrength, and courage: we muſt be ſtrong in the Lord, and the power of his might. How often doth <hi>Dauid</hi> pray for the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of life and power? How doth he preſſe it vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Be ſtrong, &amp;c? For to what end is it to haue wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, to know his ſtanding, if he want ſtrength to wield them, and wound the Aduerſary? Weakeneſſe muſt be remoued, or willingneſſe will bee to no purpoſe. Wee muſt ſtriue therefore for the Spirit of power, as well as for a ſound minde. Knowledge may guide vs, but ſtrength muſt ſupport our ſelues, and wound others.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Beſides, we muſt endeuour alſo for wiſedome: it was Chriſts charge,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>Be wiſe, &amp;c.</hi> Wiſedome muſt not be forgotten. <hi>Paul,</hi> an old beaten Souldier cryes often out,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>Walke wiſely: Be filled with all wiſedome and ſpirituall vnderſtanding.</hi> Want of skill is a great want in a man of any calling, and much to be deſired in this; for our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries are very politike, and ſo muſt we be, if wee would preuaile. Put a ſword into a mans hand that hath
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15195:15"/>
will without skill, and he will either ſmite flat-way, or wound his friend, for his aduerſary. Therefore (I ſay) <hi>Get wiſedome, get vnderſtanding: for when theſe enter into thy heart, they ſhall preſerue thee. Paul</hi> was admirable in this; reade but the <hi>Acts,</hi> and you ſhall ſee, hee killed more by policy, then proweſſe: yet like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui,</hi> theſe muſt goe together to ſlay our <hi>Sychemites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Furthermore, we are to caſt off what will hinder, as to put on what will helpe. We muſt put off ſinne, that hangeth on ſo cloſe, and all other impediments.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that warreth, intangleth not himſelfe with the things of this life, that he may pleaſe his Maſter.</hi> Loue of earthly things out of vs, and corruption cheriſhed within vs,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4.</note> may not be ſuffred to a reſolute ſpirituall Souldier.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.8.</note> As GOD would not haue faint-hearted perſons to fight, no more can he endure ſuch whoſe affections are at home,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.5.</note> with wife, goods, &amp;c. when his perſon is in the field.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. Theſe will faint, and cauſe others, by their cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly examples, to faint alſo. And (thus beloued) when you know your owne Station, keep it, be not like <hi>Iudes</hi> Planets, wandring. Chriſtian Souldiers ſhould not neede, like ſpirits, to be coniured in their Circles. Put on the right armour: <hi>Dauid</hi> cannot walke in <hi>Sauls,</hi> he muſt not ouer-come with ſuch carnall weapons; no, no, they muſt be ſpirituall, that will wound, and kill our <hi>Goliah,</hi> the Philiſtim; and when thou haſt done this, labour for skill, ſtriue for ſtrength: for the one would fight, but without the other cannot, the other can and will, but if he be not guided, hurt will follow.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> The next point to be noted, is, <hi>That a Chriſtians fight is a good fight.</hi> I may ſay of it, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh of wiſedome; <hi>The merchandize thereof is better then ſiluer, and the gaine thereof greater then gold; It is more preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then pearles, and all things that thou canſt deſire, are not to be compared vnto it.</hi> Harken what teſtimony this old
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15195:16"/>
beaten Souldier ſtill giueth of it.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>It was propheſied of Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy, that he ſhould fight a good fight.</hi> And he like a grand Captayne,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.12.</note> or great Commander, <hi>chargeth him to fight this good fight of faith:</hi> in theſe his words the ſame thing is meant.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.7.</note> And what ſaith the Campe elſewhere? <hi>I will goe and returne to my firſt Captayne; for when I fought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Banner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it was better with me, then now. Dauid</hi> (or ſome other worthy Warrior) diſputed the caſe, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth: whether it was better to fight the battailes of the World, or of the Lord? But at the length, he makes this reſolute concluſion:<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>73.</hi> vlt.</note> 
               <hi>Its good for me to draw neere vnto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly (Beloued) it neuer goeth ſo well with a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Souldier, as when he is taking of the Lambs part, warring againſt the Dragon &amp; his followers, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully fighting the battailes of his Lord. And it may be called good, either in reſpect of the fight, or the effects that follow the very act, or the conſequents that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, and enſue, the combat being ended.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reaſons.</note>For firſt: Did not <hi>Elohim,</hi> who created all things of nothing, garniſhed the heauens, framed the crooked Serpent, gathereth the windes into his fiſt, ſpanneth the great Globe with his hand, and that ſaith to the proud waues, Hither ſhalt thou come, and no farther, appoint the ſame? And how can this God doe any thing that is not good? If he appoint the field, we need not to feare but it is a lawfull,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</note> and good fight.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Againe, who is the Lord Generall, and Leader of this Armie? Is it not Chriſt Ieſus, God-Man? Wee may ſay of him, (and more too) as the people did of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that he is worth a thouſand thouſand of vs all. Who euer vnderſtood this, but with admiration? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he neuer ſinned, yet fought this fight: therefore it cannot but be good and very good.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuell.</hi> 17.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Spirit alſo doth ſummon theſe Souldiers, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15195:16"/>
conducteth them into the field,<note place="margin">Matth. <hi>4.1.</hi>
               </note> hee leadeth into euery truth; for he is Truth it ſelfe. And what comfort may this yeeld euery Chriſtian Souldier, that he hath ſuch a Guider, and Conducter vnto the combat!</p>
            <p n="4">4. The new man, and firſt-borne, the part regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, is the Fighter. Theſe are all of the free-womans ſeede,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17.</note> and haue the marke of Chriſt their Captayne in their fore-heads: and theſe Souldiers cannot ſinne.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The weapons for this combat, prepared, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, they are not carnall, but ſpirituall, mightie, from God, and able to ouer-throw the ſtrongeſt holds of Satan, either within vs, or without vs.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.</note> Theſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons are like the ſword of <hi>Saul,</hi> and bow of <hi>Ionathan,</hi> that neuer returned emptie: hee that ſtrikes with theſe, alwayes kils his foe, and wins the field.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And laſt of all; is it not for their owne right,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.32.</note> that they thus warre?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 11.24.</note> I remember what <hi>Iphtah</hi> ſaid to the King of the children of <hi>Ammon:</hi> Wouldeſt not thou poſſeſſe that which <hi>Chemoſh thy god giueth thee to poſſeſſe?</hi> So, ſhall not we fight for that, which our GOD hath commanded vs to fight for? And if it was warrantable for him to doe the one, of a truth its good for vs to doe the other: And thus you ſee, in regard of the act, or fight it ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is good, and none dares (except hee would make God, Chriſt, the holy Ghoſt, the new Man, the Spirituall weapons, and heauens priuiledges, to be ſins, and ſinners) deny it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rea;ſon. </seg>2</label> Againe, the conſequents of this fight confirme it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And they bee either honor or profit. For honor, none greater.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.17.</note> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> wounds that he receiued in this hot skirmiſh, are more honor to him, then if hee had beene adorned with all the ornaments of Nature and the World. <hi>The memoriall of the iuſt ſhall be bleſſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.7.</note> 
               <hi>and euery faithfull Souldier ſhall be had in euerlaſting remembrance; their names ſhall flouriſh on earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.6.</note> 
               <hi>and be foreuer ingrauen in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15195:17"/>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</note>And it is profitable euery manner of way: for <hi>it hath the promiſes of this life, and the life to come.</hi> And is not that a matter of great worth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> of infinite moment? They are called great and precious promiſes: for firſt, they bring food and rayment, fit and conuenient. Secondly, the curſe by Chriſt our Captayne is remoued, the infection is tooke away.</p>
            <p>Our father <hi>Adam</hi> ſteeped all our bread in ſuch a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 10.10.</note> as without this fight, it will bee like <hi>Iohns</hi> little booke, though ſweet in the mouth, yet bitter in the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.25.</note> And our drinke, like the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> if this tree alter not the taſte, rather kill, then cure vs.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8.</note>3. Wee ſhall haue inward peace, that paſſeth all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. A thing often ſpoke of, but ſeldome felt by experience; this ioy is vnvtterable, glorious.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.11, 12.</note>4. The good Angels ſhall pitch their Tents about vs, preſerue vs in their hands: ſo that wee ſhall not ſee death, or daſh our foot againſt a ſtone, vntill wee haue finiſhed our courſe, and our beſt hopes be crowned, neuer making aſhamed:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note> 
               <hi>For all things ſhall worke together (marke that, not apart) for good, to them that loue God, and are choſen of his purpoſe to this combat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</note> Beſides, this fight hath the promiſes of the world to come, and they bee many.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, death ſhall bee to ſuch, aduantage, better then the day wherein they were borne:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>7.3.</hi>
               </note> for Chriſt our Generall hath tooke away her ſting,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55.</note> like a Droane ſhee may feare vs with her humming, but not hurt vs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſoules, at the ſeparation, by the Angels ſhall be apprehended,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 16.22.</note> and inſtantly carryed into heauen, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for our ſafetie and comfort, or in that the ſoules are ignorant of that iourney. God could (we deny not) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately bring them thither, but hee will not: for his Angels are,<note place="margin">Hebr. <hi>1.</hi> vlt.</note> and muſt be miniſtring Spirits, for the good of thoſe elect Souldiers.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15195:17"/>3. They, then ſhall reſt from their labours, ſing glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the Lambe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.17.</note> and with a rauiſhing and ſpirituall longing, expect the finall end of this combat, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of all things.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the day appointed, when this quarrell ſhall be ended, (for it ſhall be finiſhed,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.6.</note> (to allude lawfully to an vnlawfull recreation) when the laſt of theſe men-ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers are borne, and borne againe) then ſhall the Soule deſcend from Heauen into the Graue, bee infuſed into the ſame bodie, where in former time ſhee had her habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: But it ſhall bee farre more glorious,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> for it ſhall be without all corruption, ſpot, or wrinkle: It ſhall be Spirituall, hauing power to aſcend, or deſcend,<note place="margin">Phil. <hi>3.</hi> vlt.</note> immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and abiding glorious for euer: For Chriſt ſhall change our vile bodies, and make them like to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious bodie, by that power whereby he is able to ſubdue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> all things to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But ſome may obiect, What, ſhall that body ryſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? how can this be? For ſuppoſe that a Wolfe eat a Man, a Lion the Wolfe, Birds the Lion, and Men the Birds; how can this be poſſible!</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſolut. </seg>
               </label> I anſwere, that the bodies were at the firſt compoſed, and made of the foure Elements, Fire, Ayre, Water, Earth; and therefore, in the laſt change, they can but be reſolued into their firſt principles; And is it not more eaſie for the Lord, who is infinite in knowledge and power, to recollect this matter, and bring it into forme, then at the firſt, to make all things of nothing? Yes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly; and no art of man can annihilate one graine of Sand, totally ſeparating the forme and the matter; for it is an infinite power. Some hold, a Palingeneſian, or tranſmutation of Elements, but they are deceiued: for the firſt forme can neuer be totally ſeparated from the firſt matter; in part it may; As for example: Caſt water into the fire, the fire will by its act, eate of ſome of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15195:18"/>
matter, and by its owne forme informe it; And then the water contracteth its forme into its owne matter; and ſo in the end, hauing much forme, and little matter, it ſeemeth then to flye away from its oppoſite.</p>
            <p>Therefore this is but a childiſh cauill; for Elements are not annihilated, or wholly tranſmutated, ſo that the ſame bodie may ryſe. What if they were? What, Is any thing impoſſible to God? Shall wee ſo thinke? God forbid, ſo bee it as it doe not (and this doth not) contradict his nature.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> And here a queſtion may ariſe; Whether hee, that wanted a member, as hand, foot, &amp;c. at his birth, ſhall haue it at the Reſurrection reſtored?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> Yes, for it is an imperfection, then a fruit of ſinne; then it came firſtly, from the firſt <hi>Adam:</hi> Then muſt the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> remoue it, (vnderſtand of the Elect only) or hee ſhould not recouer what the firſt loſt: And ſome hold, that the very bodies of the Reprobate ſhall bee made more excellent, that they may vndergoe the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter torment;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.1, 2.</note> but certainly <hi>the Elect ſhall be ſatisfied with Chriſts glorious Image.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But ſome may obiect againſt this, and ſay, Then ſhall more ryſe then was ſowne; if hee that had not a hand, now haue?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> No, for man in his Mothers Wombe, is as much in offence, as when he is of age, but not in quantitie.</p>
            <p>Take a Pecke of Meale; Lay leauen of it, it will bee greater in quantitie, not in eſſence or matter.</p>
            <p>Againe, God can make that deformed maſſe, a well formed man, yet adde no matter; as we ſee a Bell miſt in the caſting, of the ſelfe-ſame matter may bee made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
            <p>So God, the great Bel-founder of all the World, ſhall take out the Soule for a time, and caſt the bodie anew, in the Furnace of the Earth, after put them together; and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15195:18"/>
then <hi>Aarons</hi> Bels in the Sanctuarie neuer rang ſo ſweet a peale, as theſe Bels ſhall, in the eares of the Lord of Hoſts, for euer, and euer.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fiftly, then ſhall not only all their wounds and skars bee cured, but they ſhall tread the Prince of the World, Satan, and all their Enemies, vnder foot, yea,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20.</note> they ſhall ſee their foes ſuffer the vengeance of eternall fire, for troubling them in their flight to Heauen. That ſpirituall <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> with his huge Hoſte,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8, 9.</note> ſhall be ſwallowed vp by the Red Sea of endleſſe deſtruction, without all hope of recouery.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, they haue a promiſe that their Habitation, ſhalbe Heauen; their Companions, Chriſt &amp; his Angels,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Theſ. <hi>4.17.</hi> Pſal. <hi>16.</hi> vlt.</note> all fellow-Souldiers; <hi>their ioy full, and for euer.</hi> What a place is this, where all haue fulneſſe of ioy, fulneſſe with conſtancie, and conſtancie with fulneſſe for all eternitie?</p>
            <p>If theſe things now were laid all together, truely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, ſeriouſly thought vpon, and without doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beleeued, who would not, or could not affirme the propoſition for a truth, that a Chriſtians fight is a good fight? good for act, for euer, for both. The vſes in their order now follow.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> This then in the firſt place, iuſtly reproueth ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that thinke baſely of Religion, reputing it ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther honourable, nor profitable. How many cry out, that gaine is godlineſſe! no profit had in fighting the Lords Battaile. What is that Captaine, that wee ſhould ſerue him, deſiring to learne another good? Haue wee not too many of theſe amongſt vs that foame out their filthy froth, fight againſt Chriſt, and his Souldiers, whoſe tongues walke againſt Heauen and Earth, crying, What get theſe with gadding to Sermons, reading ſo much; (for they allow ſome Scripture:) being ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and ſtrict? Why, I haue told thee in part what they haue in poſſeſſion, and what in poſſibilitie; for no
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15195:19"/>
tongue can ſpeake, or heart fully conceiue the riches of this ſpoile, man, or Angell.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe, that thou haſt rich attire, but it is infected; daintie dyet, but poyſoned; many things, but all in the end ſhall worke for euill; what a miſerie is this? Yet this is the eſtate of Satans Souldiers. Beſides this, hee deales with his Followers, as the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> by <hi>Samſon,</hi> takes away their ſtrength, puls out their eyes, makes them draw in bonds and fetters, and if hee reioyce in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, it is in their bloud-ſhed and endleſſe deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>But we will leaue them, and pittie them, hoping in time they may take the Lambes part, and fight this good Combat.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> This may ſerue to incourage all thoſe Souldiers to go on, with an vndaunted reſolution, and not to ſhrinke or ſhiuer, though they be cruſht and diſgraced: euery one cryeth out,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Who will ſhew vs any good?</hi> as if then had they found it, they would follow it. Why, this is that good thing ſo many haue groped after; wherefore bee yee of good courage, ſtrike hard, ſtand faſt, and bee ſtrong. If thou be out of heart, thinke what an honour it is to be ſlaine in this field, and that all thy wounds againe ſhall be cured, yea the ſooner thou art killed, thou ſhalt bee crowned; for by death we ouercome, get the victorie.</p>
            <p>When I conſider how the children of <hi>Babel,</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, doe ſpill their bloud like water, on the ground, for their Antichriſt, Lord, thinke I then; what ſhould wee doe, that are the ſonnes of <hi>Bethel,</hi> for our Chriſt, that hath bin ſlaine himſelfe, to deliuer vs from the ſting of the firſt, and wound of the ſecond death! But (alas) theſe Meditations come not but like Strangers, to our minds, and what cold, and ſhort entertainment haue they! And this the reaſon, that we are ſo loth to leape, or lanch out, ſhrinke at the ſight of a Ship, cry out at the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15195:19"/>
cracke of a Cannon, and tremble at the report of the narrow mouthed Peece: We (beloued) haue not reſiſted vnto bloud; God hath giuen vs better dayes; fire and faggot haue beene kept afarre, and what a ſhame is it then, that wee are ſo weake, faint, halting, and readie vpon the leaſt aſſault, to be turned out of the way? And therefore if any be giddie-headed in this combat, like a man running through a ſwift water, or ſtreame; let him looke ouer to the ſhoare of Heauen, ſee what a pleaſant landing there is, and thouſands of Angels to giue him entertainment: haue thou reſpect with <hi>Moſes,</hi> to the recompence of reward: thinke of a better Reſurrection, and with thy forerunner ſet before the eye of thy Soule, that glory prepared for thee. What if thy bodie fall in the Wilderneſſe of this World? The Lord hath it in his keeping; Riſe againe it ſhall; therefore be ſtedfaſt, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooueable, <hi>abundant alway in the Worke of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>11.</hi> vlt.</note> 
               <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that you know, that your labor is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when our fellow-ſouldiers fall by vs, let vs thinke that our Captaine is alſo a Surgion, a Phyſician, and will one day cure all our wounds, and <hi>then ſhall we for euer remaine together. Paul</hi> would haue all his fellow-ſouldiers in this caſe, <hi>to comfort one another with theſe words,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>vlt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>3</label> And here may be a vſe of inſtruction, to ſuch as haue not yet regarded to fight in this Field: take knowledge of thy ignorance, and careleſſeneſſe, and now beginne to change thy Captaine, thou muſt bee vnder one of theſe Generals: God, or the Deuill the Lambe, or the Dragon; <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>Belial.</hi> Awake therefore, thou that ſleepeſt; ſtand vp from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall giue thee light; all conuenient furniture, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.14.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But ſome may obiect, it was good for <hi>Paul,</hi> who was an Apoſtle, and excellent in the Church, but not for mee.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:15195:20"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, as good for thee as for him, in ſome reſpects, and in others better.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, thou haſt the ſame Captaine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, the ſame pay; for the promiſes are not made to any perſon, for his greatneſſe, and learning ſake: but as hee is a Chriſtian, and for his goodneſſe: Therefore, <hi>Paul</hi> in the next verſe following my Text, to take away this doubt, addeth, that a Crowne of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is by the righteous Iudge layd vp, not for himſelfe only, but for all them alſo that fight, and loue his appearing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We eſcape many wounds that he had, as <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion:</hi> this made <hi>Zipora call her Huſband, Bloudie Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Exodus</hi> 4.25. How often was hee whipped? <hi>bare in his bodie the markes of the Lord Ieſus?</hi> which laſhes, and ſtripes, we haue eſcaped. And no doubt but they ſet it on for the hatred they bore him, and as doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, by that impreſſion, and skarres, that were to bee ſeene in him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He fought with beaſts at <hi>Epheſus.</hi> Some thinke, after the cuſtome of that Countrey, hee was caſt vnto them: but howeuer, the Fight was fierce, and tart to fleſh and bloud.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We warre a ſhorter time (for the moſt part) then he did; and this is ſome priuiledge, though it were but reſt for a day, or houre; and to the ſpoyle ſo much the ſooner.</p>
            <p>We care not how ſhort a time we ſerue for our free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, how ſpeedily we haue ended, and diſpatched our daily buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>And is not a fauour, in a ſhort time, to winne the Field, and poſſeſſe the <hi>Heauen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. He oft fought alone, and had many Aduerſaries; for he confeſſed that at his being at <hi>Rome</hi> (where then was <hi>Peter</hi>) all <hi>men forſooke him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.</note> not one to aſſiſt him.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15195:20"/>
And a greater griefe muſt it needs be to him; for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in ſuffering is comfortable: And there is a woe pronounced to him, that is (thus) left alone.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And laſt of all, his triall was ſo hot, his foes ſo fierce, that he reſiſted vnto bloud. What ſhould I more ſay? For if wee would ſeriouſly ponder of theſe things, we could not but gather life and ſpirit, and like <hi>Iehu,</hi> march on furiouſly: or, <hi>Deborah,</hi> valiantly. But wee, many of vs, haue the prize in our hands, yet (alas) wee want hearts.</p>
            <p>Well (beloued) I can tell you this, that when death approcheth, and iudgement through her, as through a window lookes vs in the face; then this fight will bee found to be of worth, and a greater good, then all the glorie, and pompe of the world. But if <hi>Pauls</hi> patterne, the goodneſſe of the fight, and the priuiledges, that we aboue many of our Brethren, in time paſt, and at this preſent partake of, will not moue vs to fight, and fight reſolutely; let vs then ſet before vs the fearefull wrath, and dreadfull vengeance, that is prepared for ſuch as ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer began this fight, or if they haue, yet endure not to the end.</p>
            <p>And let that alſo awake vs with <hi>Samſon,</hi> when the Philiſtims were vpon him, and cauſe each of vs to flie for his life: For neceſſitie ſometimes makes the faint and fearefull-hearted Souldier, valiant.</p>
            <p>Conſider therefore what I haue ſaid, and the Lord giue you vnderſtanding in theſe things. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>4</label> And laſt of all, here might Parents be moued to bring vp their children in the feare of the Lord. It were a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thing, that we could trayne vp our ſeed vnder ſuch a Generall, to be Captaynes; then ſhould we haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in them at our latter end. But Parents, for the moſt part, buſie not themſelues with matters of that nature: yet they will that their children receiue the preſſe-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,
<pb facs="tcp:15195:21"/>
weare weapons, goe armed; but neuer teach, or trayne them vp vnder whom, or how to fight, the more is the pitty. But now be yee better aduiſed; make thy ſonnes of Gods Family, of Chriſts Campe, of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Faithfull: ſo ſhalt thou bee a louing Father, and tender Mother. Otherwiſe, thou haſt but made him by nature, the Slaue and Souldier of Satan, child of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. And what an honor will it be to Parents at that laſt Day of appearing, when they can ſay to this great Captayne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.13.</note> as he himſelfe to his Lord Generall, Here am I, and the Souldiers that thou haſt giuen me? For know, that yet a very little while,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.37.</note> and he that will come, ſhall come, and will not tarry.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> Againe, where <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Paul</hi> hath fought a good fight; obſerue, That it is not a ſinne ſimply, to ſpeake the beſt of ones ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That a Murtherer, may dye a Martyr; a Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, an Apoſtle; in a word, a great Sinner, a rare Saint. Here we ſee, that a bloudy Perſecuter, dyed Chriſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Souldier: and the ſame may befall in our dayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Againe note,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That Gods Saints on earth, haue no abiding Citie. Paul</hi> muſt depart; his fight is fought, his courſe is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, calling things that are not, as though (already) they were.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That a well-led life yeelds comfort at the day of death. For <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks this with reioycing.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That a good man in his life, wiſheth the Church might flouriſh after his death. This was the cauſe why <hi>Paul</hi> ſo preſt <hi>Timothy</hi> to preach, hee being ready to depart.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That certaintie of perſeuerance may be had, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rightly ſought for. Beſides others that I omit.</p>
            <p>And now all that I haue to ſay, ſeeing wee are figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and one of our Worthies fallen, is this, Let vs be
<pb facs="tcp:15195:21"/>
the more watchfull ouer our ſelues, and the cloſer knit together.</p>
            <p>Let vs goe vp as one man, hauing our affections vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, like the Leuiathans skales, that no ſword can either pierce them, or diuide them. For a Kingdome diuided againſt it ſelfe, cannot ſtand: and the diuiſions of <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben</hi> will but make great thoughts of heart.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the eye that now ſeeth me (in this place) may ſee me no more; and the eare that now heareth mee (out of this place) may heare me no more; my laſt ſpeech to you (my Brethren) ſhall be that charge <hi>Ioſeph</hi> gaue to his brethren at their parting:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.24.</note> 
               <hi>Fall not out, neither be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> (one againſt another) <hi>by the way. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
