<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epitaph vpon the death of the honorable, syr Edward Saunders Knight, Lorde cheefe Baron of the Exchequer, who dyed the. 19. of Nouember. 1576</title>
            <author>Lloyd, Lodowick, fl. 1573-1610.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1576</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-05">2003-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121800</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856964</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856964</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22620</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A06136)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22620)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 406:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epitaph vpon the death of the honorable, syr Edward Saunders Knight, Lorde cheefe Baron of the Exchequer, who dyed the. 19. of Nouember. 1576</title>
                  <author>Lloyd, Lodowick, fl. 1573-1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By H. S[ingleton] for Henry Disle, dwellyng at the southwest doore of Saint Paules Church, and are there to be solde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>December. 3. [1576]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Lodowick Lloyd.</note>
                  <note>Verse - "You Muses weare your mourning weedes, strike on the fatal drome,".</note>
                  <note>See "The Library, ser. 6, II: 57-58.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Saunders, Edward, --  Sir, d. 1576 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:22620:1"/>
            <head>An Epitaph vpon the death of the honorable, syr Edward Saunders
Knight, Lorde cheefe Baron of the Exchequer, who dyed the .19. of Nouember. 1576.</head>
            <l>YOU Muses weare your mourning weedes, strike on the fatal Drome,</l>
            <l>Sounde <hi>Triton</hi> out the Trumpe of Fame, in spite of <hi>Parcas</hi> dome:</l>
            <l>Distyll <hi>Parnassus</hi> pleasant droppes, possesse <hi>Pierides</hi> plase,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Apollo</hi> helpe with dolefull tune, to wayle this wofull case.</l>
            <l>Wring hard your handes, wayle on your losse, lament the fate that fell,</l>
            <l>With sobbes and sighes to <hi>Saunders</hi> say, oh <hi>Saunders</hi> nowe farewell.</l>
            <l>Whom <hi>Pbaebus</hi> fed with <hi>Pallas</hi> pappe, as one of <hi>Sibils</hi> seede,</l>
            <l>Loe here where Death did rest his corpes, the vermines foule to feede:</l>
            <l>Whom Impes of <hi>Ioue</hi> with <hi>Nectar</hi> sweete, long in <hi>Libetbres</hi> 
               <unclear>noursht</unclear>,</l>
            <l>Behold howe dreadfull Death him brought, to that whence he came first.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Lycurgus</hi> he for learned lawes, <hi>Rhadamanthus</hi> race that ranne,</l>
            <l>Another <hi>Nestor</hi> for aduise, <hi>Zaleucus</hi> fame that wanne.</l>
            <l>A <hi>Damon</hi> deare vnto his freend, in faith like <hi>Phocion</hi> found,</l>
            <l>A <hi>Cato</hi> that could counsell geue, to prince a subiect sound:</l>
            <l>Not <hi>Athens</hi> for their <hi>Solon</hi> sage, not <hi>Rome</hi> for <hi>Numa</hi> waile,</l>
            <l>As we for <hi>Saunders</hi> death haue cause, in flooddes of teares to saile.</l>
            <l>Not <hi>Sparta</hi> card for <hi>Chilos</hi> death, ne proud <hi>Prienna</hi> prest,</l>
            <l>To weepe for <hi>Bias</hi> as we wayle, our <hi>Saunders</hi> late possest.</l>
            <l>His learned pathes his talentes rare, so nowe by Death appeares,</l>
            <l>As he that <hi>Salomon</hi> sought to serue, in prime and youthfull yeares,</l>
            <l>His counsell sadde, his rules, his lawes, in countrey soyle so wrought,</l>
            <l>As though in <hi>Cuma</hi> he had been, of sage <hi>Sibilla</hi> taught:</l>
            <l>His vertuous life was such I say, as Uertue did embrace,</l>
            <l>By Uertue taught in vertuous schoole, to growe in vertuous race:</l>
            <l>Might tender babes, might orphantes weake, might widowes rere the cry,</l>
            <l>The sound thereof should pearce the cloudes, to skale the empire sky:</l>
            <l>To bidde the goddes to battel bend, and to dissend in sight,</l>
            <l>Though farre vnfit, and mates vnmeete, with mortall men to fight.</l>
            <l>Too late (alas) we wyshe his life, to soone deceiued vs Death,</l>
            <l>Too little witte we haue to seeke, the dead agayne to breath.</l>
            <l>What helplesse is, must carelesse be, as Natures course dooth shewe,</l>
            <l>For Death shall reape what life hath sowen, by Nature this we knowe:</l>
            <l>Where is that erce <hi>Achilles</hi> fled, where is king <hi>Turnus</hi> shroude,</l>
            <l>What is become of <hi>Priamus</hi> state, where is <hi>Periander</hi> proude:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Hector, Hanno, Hanibal,</hi> dead, <hi>Pompei, Pirrhus</hi> spild,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Scipio, Cirus, Caesar</hi> slayne, and <hi>Alexander</hi> kild.</l>
            <l>So long there Fortune fast dyd floe, and charged Fame to sound,</l>
            <l>Tyll frowning Fortune foyld by fate, which fawning Fortune found:</l>
            <l>Shun Fortunes feares, shake Fortune of, to none is Fortune sound,</l>
            <l>
               <unclear>Sith</unclear> none may say of Fortune so, I Fortune faithfull found.</l>
            <l>Beholde where Fortune flowed so fast, and fauoured Saunders lure,</l>
            <l>Tyl <hi>fickle</hi> Fortune false agayne, did Saunders death procure.</l>
            <l>Lo clothed could in cloddes of clay, in drossy dust remayne,</l>
            <l>By fate returnd from whence he came, to his mothers wombe agayne.</l>
            <l>Who welnigh thirtie yeeres was Iudge, before a Iudge dyd fast,</l>
            <l>And iudged by that mighty Iudge, which Iudge shall iudge vs all.</l>
            <l>The heauens may of right reioyce, and earth may it bewayle,</l>
            <l>Sith heauen wan, and earth hath lost, the guide and arke of vayle.</l>
            <l>There gayne is much, our losse is great, there myrth our mone is such,</l>
            <l>That they may laugh as cause doo yeelde, and we may weepe as much:</l>
            <l>O happy he, vnhappy we, his happe dooth aye encrease,</l>
            <l>Happy he, and haplesse we, his hap shall neuer cease.</l>
            <l>We liue to dye, he dyed to liue, we want, and he possest,</l>
            <l>We bide in bandes, he bathes in blisse, the gods aboue him blest.</l>
            <l>Being borne to liue, he liued to dye, and dyed to God so plaine,</l>
            <l>That birth, that life, that death, doo shewe, that he shall <unclear>liue</unclear> agayne:</l>
            <l>His youth to age, his age to death, his death to fame applied,</l>
            <l>His fame to tyme, his time to God, thus <hi>Saunders</hi> liued and dyed.</l>
            <l>O happy life, O happier Death, O tenne times happy he,</l>
            <l>Whose happe it was such happe to haue, a Iudge this age to be.</l>
            <l>Oh ioyfull time, oh blessed soyle, where <hi>Pallas</hi> rules with witte,</l>
            <l>O noble state, O sacred seate, where <hi>Saba</hi> sage dooth sitte.</l>
            <l>Like <hi>Susan</hi> sound, like <hi>Sara</hi> sadde, with <hi>Hesters</hi> mace in hande,</l>
            <l>With <hi>Iudiths</hi> sworde <hi>Bellona</hi> like, to rule this <unclear>noble</unclear> lande.</l>
            <l>I had my wyll, you haue your wishe, I laugh, reioy<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you may,</l>
            <l>I wan now much, you gaine no lesse, to see this happy d<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Wherein I died, wherein you liue, Oh treble happy cost,</l>
            <l>Wherein I ioyed in glory greate, wherein you triumph most.</l>
            <l>Kneele on your knees knocke hard your brests, sound forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyful Drome,</l>
            <l>Clappe loude your hands, sounde Eccho say, the golden worlde is come.</l>
            <l>Reioyce you Iudges may of right, your mirth may now be such,</l>
            <l>As neuer earst you Iudges had, in England mirth so much.</l>
            <l>Here <hi>Cuma</hi> is, here <hi>Sibill</hi> raignes, on <hi>Delphos</hi> seate to sitte,</l>
            <l>Here shee like <hi>Phaebus</hi> rules, that can <hi>Gordius</hi> knotte vnknitte.</l>
            <l>I liued to nature long yenough, I liued to honor much,</l>
            <l>I liued at wish, I died at wyll, to see my country such.</l>
            <l>As neither needes it <hi>Numas</hi> lawes nor yet <hi>Apollos</hi> sweard,</l>
            <l>For Mauger Mars, yet Mars shalbe of this our Queene afeard.</l>
            <l>O peerlesse pearle, O Diamond deer, O Queene of Queenes farwell,</l>
            <l>Your royall Maiestie god preserue, in England long to dwell.</l>
            <l>Farwell the <hi>Phaenix</hi> of the woorld, farwell my soueraigne Queene,</l>
            <l>Farwell most noble vertuous prince, <hi>Mineruas</hi> mate I weene.</l>
            <l>No Iuel, Gemme, no Gold to geue, no perles from <hi>Pactolus</hi> lo,</l>
            <l>No Persian Gaze, no Indian stones, no Tagus sandes to show.</l>
            <l>But faith and will to natiue soyle a liue and dead I finde,</l>
            <l>My hart my mind my loue I leaue, vnto my prince behinde.</l>
            <l>Farwell you nobles of this land, farwell you Iudges graue,</l>
            <l>Farwell my felowes freends and mates, your Queene I say God saue.</l>
            <l>What rise in time in time dooth fall, what floweth in time dooth ebbe,</l>
            <l>What liues in time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in time shall die, and yeelde to <hi>Parcas</hi> webbe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>The sunne to darknesse shallbe turnde, the starres from skies shall fall,</l>
            <l>The Moone to blood, the worlde with fire shallbe consumed all.</l>
            <l>As smoke or vapour vanishe streight, as bubbles rise and fall,</l>
            <l>As clowdes doo passe, or shadowe shiftes we liue, we die so all.</l>
            <l>Our pompe our pride, our triumph most, our glory greate herein,</l>
            <l>Like shattering shadowe passe away, as though none <unclear>such</unclear> had bin.</l>
            <l>Earth, water, ayre, and fyre, as they were earst before,</l>
            <l>A lumpe confused, and <hi>Chaos</hi> calld, so shall they once be more.</l>
            <l>And all to earth, that came from earth, <unclear>and</unclear> to the graue descend,</l>
            <l>For earth on earth, to earth shall goe, and earth shalbe the end:</l>
            <l>As Christ descended vp in cloudes, so Christ in cloudes shall come,</l>
            <l>To iudge both good and badde on earth, at dreadfull day of dome.</l>
            <l>From whence our fleshe shall ryse agayne, euen from the drossy dust,</l>
            <l>And so shall passe, I hope vnto, the mansion of the iust.</l>
            <signed>Lodowick LLoyd.</signed>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="printers_device">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>EGO SVM VIA ET VERITAS</head>
                  <q>DVM TEM<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>PVS ABE<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>MVS <unclear>OPE<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>RE<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>MVR</unclear> BO<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>NVM</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>¶Imprinted at London by H. S. for</hi>
Henry Disle, dwellyng at the Southwest doore
of Saint Paules Church, and are there
to be solde</p>
            <p>December. 3.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
