<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A game at chæss as it was acted nine dayes to gether at the Globe on the banks side.</title>
            <author>Middleton, Thomas, d. 1627.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106481</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842196</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842196</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6830</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A07498)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6830)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 658:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A game at chæss as it was acted nine dayes to gether at the Globe on the banks side.</title>
                  <author>Middleton, Thomas, d. 1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Middleton.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Engraved title page with vignette.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, B1r line 4 has "my Disciples"--cf.STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A game at chesse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6830:1"/>
            <p>A Gam<hi rend="sup">e</hi> at Chaess aſ it was Acted <hi>nine days to gether at the Globe on the banks ſide</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:6830:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6830:2"/>
            <head>The Picture plainly explained, after the manner of the Cheſſe-play.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>A Game at Cheſse is here diſplayde,</l>
               <l>Betweene the <hi>Blacke</hi> and <hi>White-Houſe</hi> made,</l>
               <l>Wherein Crowne-thirſting Policy,</l>
               <l>For the <hi>Blacke-Houſe</hi> (by Falacy)</l>
               <l>To the <hi>White-Knight,</hi> checke, often giues,</l>
               <l>And, to ſome ſtraites, him thereby driues;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Fat-Blacke-Biſhop</hi> help's alſo.</l>
               <l>With faithleſſe heart to giue the blow:</l>
               <l>Yet (maugre all their craft) at length,</l>
               <l>The <hi>White Knight,</hi> with wit-wondrous ſtrength;</l>
               <l>And circumſpectiue Prudency,</l>
               <l>Giues Check-mate by Diſcouery</l>
               <l>To the <hi>Blacke Knight;</hi> and ſo at laſt</l>
               <l>The game (thus) won, the <hi>Blacke-Houſe</hi> caſt</l>
               <l>Into the Bagge, and therein ſhut,</l>
               <l>Finde all their plumes and Cockes-combes cut.</l>
               <l>Plaine-dealing (thus) by wiſedomes guide,</l>
               <l>Defeats the cheats of Craft and Pride.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <head>Prologue.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHat of the Game, cald Cheſſe-play can be made</l>
               <l>To make a Stage-Play, ſhall this day be plaid.</l>
               <l>Firſt, you ſhall ſee the men in order ſet,</l>
               <l>States, and their Pawnes, when both the ſides are met:</l>
               <l>The Houſes well diſtinguiſh't: In the Game</l>
               <l>Some men entrapt, and taken to their ſhame,</l>
               <l>Rewarded by their Play: And in the Cloſe</l>
               <l>You ſhall ſee Checque-Mate giuen to Vertues Foes.</l>
               <l>But the fair'ſt Iewell, that our hopes can decke,</l>
               <l>Is, ſo to play our Game, t'auoid your Checke.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:6830:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6830:3"/>
            <head>A Game at Cheſse.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Induction.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Ignatius</hi> Loyola appearing, <hi>Error</hi> at his feete as aſleepe.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ignatius.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>HA? where? what Angle of the world is this;</l>
                  <l>That I can neither ſee the politicke face,</l>
                  <l>Nor with my refined noſtrells taſte the foot-ſteps,</l>
                  <l>Of any of my Diſciples, ſonnes and heires</l>
                  <l>As well of my deſignes, as inſtitutions,</l>
                  <l>I thought they'd ſpread ouer the World by this time,</l>
                  <l>Couered the earths face, and made darke the land,</l>
                  <l>Like the Egyptian Graſſe-hoppers,</l>
                  <l>Here's too much light appeares, ſhot from the eyes</l>
                  <l>Of Truth and Goodneſſe, neuer yet defloured:</l>
                  <l>Sure they were neuer here, then is their Monarchy</l>
                  <l>Vnperfect yet: A iuſt reward I ſee</l>
                  <l>For their ingratitude ſo long to mee,</l>
                  <l>Their father and founder;</l>
                  <l>'Tis not fiue yeares ſince I was ſaluted by'em,</l>
                  <l>Where ſlept my honour all the time before?</l>
                  <l>Could they be ſo forgetfull to cannonize</l>
                  <l>Their proſperous Inſtitutor, when they had ſaluted</l>
                  <l>They found no roome in all their Kallender</l>
                  <l>To place my name, that ſhould haue remoued Princes,</l>
                  <l>Puld the moſt eminent Prelates by the rootes vp,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6830:4"/>For my deare comming, to make way for me,</l>
                  <l>Lets euerie pettie martire, and Saint Homile,</l>
                  <l>Roch, Main, and Pecronel, itch, and Ague curers,</l>
                  <l>Your Abbeſſe Alde-gund, and Cuney-gund;</l>
                  <l>The Widdow Marcell, Perſon <hi>Policary,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Siſlie and Vrſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e, all take place of me;</l>
                  <l>And but for the <hi>Biſſextile,</hi> or Leape-yeare;</l>
                  <l>And that's but one in three, I fall by chance,</l>
                  <l>Into the nine and twenteth day of <hi>February:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There were no roome elſe for me; ſee their loue,</l>
                  <l>Their conſcience too, truſt me a lame Souldier</l>
                  <l>In-to-Leape-yeare: My wrath's vp, and me thinkes</l>
                  <l>I could with the firſt ſyllable of my name,</l>
                  <l>Blow vp their Colledges: vp <hi>Error,</hi> awake</l>
                  <l>Father of Superogation riſe:</l>
                  <l>It is <hi>Ignatius</hi> calls thee, <hi>Loyolla.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Error,</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What haue you done? oh I could ſleep in ignorance</l>
                  <l>Immortality, the ſlumber is ſo pleaſing.</l>
                  <l>I ſaw the braueſt ſetting for a game now,</l>
                  <l>That euer my eie fixt on.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Igna.</speaker>
               <p>Game: what Game?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Error.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>The nobleſt Game of all, <hi>A Game at Cheſse,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Betwixt our ſide, and the <hi>White Houſe,</hi> the men ſet</l>
                  <l>In their iuſt order, ready to goe to it.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Igna.</speaker>
               <p>Were any of my ſonnes plac't for the Game?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Error.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yes: and a daughter too, a ſecular daughter</l>
                  <l>That plaies the <hi>Black<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Queenes pawne,</hi> he the <hi>Black Biſhops.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Igna.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>If euer power cold ſhew a maiſterie in thee,</l>
                  <l>Let it appeare in this,</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Error.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis but a Dreame,</l>
                  <l>A viſion you muſt thinke.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Igna.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I care not what,</l>
                  <l>So I behold the Children of my cuuning,</l>
                  <l>And ſee what ranke they keepe,</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Error.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You haue your wiſh:</l>
                  <l>Behold ther's the full number of the Game,</l>
                  <l>Kings and their Pawnes, Queenes, Biſhops, Kinghts and Dukes.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6830:4"/>
               <speaker>Igna.</speaker>
               <p>Dukes they're cald Rookes by ſome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Error.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Corruptiuely:</l>
                  <l>Le roch, the word cuſtodie de La Rock,</l>
                  <l>The keeper of the forts in whom both Kings</l>
                  <l>Repoſe much confidence, and for their truſt ſake,</l>
                  <l>Courage and worth do well deſerue thoſe titles.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Igna.</speaker>
               <p>Thy anſwer's high, ſee my ſon and daughter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe are two pawnes the <hi>black Queen, &amp; black Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Igna.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pawnes argue but poore ſpirits, and light performents:</l>
                  <l>Nor worthie of the name of my Diſciples:</l>
                  <l>If I had ſtood ſo nigh I would haue cut</l>
                  <l>That Biſhops throat, but I'd haue had his place;</l>
                  <l>And told the Queene a loue tale in her eare,</l>
                  <l>Would haue made her beſt pulce daunce, there's elixar</l>
                  <l>Of braine, and ſpirit amongſt em.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Error.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why? would you haue em play againſt themſelues.</l>
                  <l>That's quite againſt the Game (<hi>Ignatius.</hi>)</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Igna.</speaker>
               <p>Piſh, I would rule my ſelfe, not obſerue rule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Err.</speaker>
               <p>Why you yould play a game all by your ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Igna.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I would do any thing to rule alone,</l>
                  <l>Tis rare to haue the world rulde in by one.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Err.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>See'em anon, and view em in their play,</l>
                  <l>Obſerue as in a dance they glide away.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Igna.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh with what longing will this breſt be toſt,</l>
                  <l>Vntill I ſee this great Game won and loſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="drama">
            <pb facs="tcp:6830:5"/>
            <head>A Game at Cheſse.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Actus Prima,</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scoena Prima<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </head>
                  <stage>Enter from the <hi>Blacke-houſe,</hi> the <hi>Blacke Queenes Pawne.</hi> From the <hi>White-houſe,</hi> the <hi>White Queenes Pawne.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Blacke Queenes pawne.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I Neuer ſee that face, but my pitty riſes,</l>
                        <l>When I behold ſo cleare a Maiſter-peece</l>
                        <l>Of Heauens arte, wrought out of duſt and aſhes,</l>
                        <l>In that not ours, but the Daughter of Hereſie:</l>
                        <l>My ſoule bleeds at mine eyes.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>White Q. pawne.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Where ſhould truth ſpeake</l>
                        <l>If not in ſuch a ſorrow? they're teares plainly:</l>
                        <l>Beſhrew me if ſhe weepe not hartily?</l>
                        <l>What is my peace to her to take ſuch paynes in't?</l>
                        <l>If I wander to loſſe, and with broad eyes</l>
                        <l>Yet miſſe the path ſhe ranne blind-fold in.</l>
                        <l>(Through often exerciſe) why ſhold my ouer-ſight,</l>
                        <l>Though in the game that ere Chriſtian loſt,</l>
                        <l>Rayſe the leaſt ſpring of pitty in her eye,</l>
                        <l>Tis doubtleſſe a great charity, and no vertue,</l>
                        <l>Could winne me ſurer.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Blacke Q. P.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Bleſſed things preuaile with't,</l>
                        <l>If euer goodneſſe made a gracious promiſe,</l>
                        <l>It is in yonder looke, what little paines</l>
                        <l>Would build a Fort for vertue to all memory</l>
                        <l>In that ſweet creature, were the ground-worke firmer.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>White Q. P.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>It has beene all my glory to be firme,</l>
                        <l>In what I haue profeſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Blacke Q. P.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>That is the enemy</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:6830:5"/>That ſteales your ſtrength away, and fights againſt you,</l>
                        <l>Diſarmes your ſoule, euen in that heate of battle:</l>
                        <l>Your firmnes that way, makes you more infirme,</l>
                        <l>For the right Chriſtian conflict<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there I ſpied</l>
                        <l>A zealous primitiue ſparkle, but now ſlew,</l>
                        <l>From your deuoted eyes:</l>
                        <l>Able to blow vp all the Hereſies</l>
                        <l>That euer ſate in Councell with your ſpirit; <stage>Enter the blacke Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops pawne</stage>
                        </l>
                        <l>And here comes he whoſe Sanctimonious breath,</l>
                        <l>Can make that ſparke a flame: liſt to him (virgin)</l>
                        <l>At whoſe firſt entrance Princes will proſtrate:</l>
                        <l>Weomen are weaker Veſſells.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>White Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By my paenitence</l>
                        <l>A comely preſentation, and the habit</l>
                        <l>To admiration reuerend.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But the heart, the heart Lady</l>
                        <l>So meeke, that as you ſee good Charity pictured ſtill</l>
                        <l>With young ones in her armes, ſo will hee cheriſh</l>
                        <l>All his young tractable ſweete obedient daughters</l>
                        <l>E'ene in his armes, in his owne boſome,</l>
                        <l>I am my ſelfe a ſecular Ieſuiteſſe,</l>
                        <l>As many Ladies are of worth and greatneſſe,</l>
                        <l>A ſecond ſort are Ieſuits in <hi>voto,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Giuing their vow into the father generall:</l>
                        <l>That's the Blacke Biſhop of our houſe, whoſe pawne</l>
                        <l>This Gentleman now ſtands, now to receiue</l>
                        <l>The Colledge habit at his holy pleaſure.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But how are theſe in <hi>voto</hi> emploied (Lady)</l>
                        <l>Till they receiue the habit.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Blacke Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>They're not idle,</l>
                        <l>Hee findes 'em all true labourers in the worke</l>
                        <l>Of vniuerſall Monarchy, which hee</l>
                        <l>And his Diſciples princially ayme at.</l>
                        <l>Thoſe are maintayned in many Courts and Pallaces,</l>
                        <l>And are induc'd by noble Perſonages,</l>
                        <l>Into great Princes ſeruices, and prooue</l>
                        <l>Some Counſellers of State, ſome Secretaries:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:6830:6"/>All ſeruing in notes of intelligence:</l>
                        <l>(As Pariſh Clerkes,) their mortuary bills,</l>
                        <l>To the father Generall, ſo are deſignes</l>
                        <l>Often times preuented, and importinant ſecrets</l>
                        <l>Of ſtate diſcouered, yet no author found,</l>
                        <l>But thoſe ſuſpected oft that are moſt ſound:</l>
                        <l>This miſtery is too deepe, yet for your entrance,</l>
                        <l>And I offend to ſet your zeale ſo backe,</l>
                        <l>Checkt by Obedience, with deſire to haſten</l>
                        <l>Your grogreſſe to perfection, I commit you</l>
                        <l>To the great workers hands, to whoſe graue worth</l>
                        <l>I fit my reuerence, as to you my wiſhes.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Blacke B. p.</speaker>
                     <p>Doſt finde her ſupple?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Blacke Q. p.</speaker>
                     <p>There's a little paſſage made.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Blacke B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let me contemplate,</l>
                        <l>With wholy wonder ſeaſon my acceſſe;</l>
                        <l>And by degrees approach the Sanctuary</l>
                        <l>Of vnmatcht beauty, ſet in grace and goodneſſe</l>
                        <l>Amongſt the daughters of men I haue not found</l>
                        <l>A more Cathalecall aſpect, that eye</l>
                        <l>Dos promiſe ſingle life and meeke Obedience.</l>
                        <l>Vpon thoſe lips the ſweete freſh buds of youth,</l>
                        <l>The holy dew of prayer lies like pearle,</l>
                        <l>Dropt from opening eye-lids of the morne,</l>
                        <l>Vppon tht baſhfull Roſe, how beautiouſly</l>
                        <l>A gentle faſt not rigorouſly impoſed,</l>
                        <l>Would looke vpon that cheek, and how delightfull</l>
                        <l>The courteous Phyſicke of a tender pennance,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe vtmoſt cruelty ſhould not exceed</l>
                        <l>The firſt feare of a bride to beate downe frailty,</l>
                        <l>Would worke to ſound health your long feſtred iudgement,</l>
                        <l>And make your merrit well (through erring ignorance</l>
                        <l>Appeares but ſpotted righteouſneſſe to me,</l>
                        <l>Farre clearer then the innocence of Infants.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>White Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To the good worke I bowe and will become,</l>
                        <l>Obedience humbleſt daughter, ſcythence I finde</l>
                        <l>The aſſiſtance of a ſacred ſtrength to ayde me:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:6830:6"/>The labour is as eaſie to ſerue vertue</l>
                        <l>The right way ſince, 'tis ſhe I euer ſerued</l>
                        <l>In my deſire, though I tranſgreſt in Iudgment.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Black B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>It's eaſily abſolued amongſt the reſt,</l>
                        <l>You ſhall not finde the vertue, that you ſerue now</l>
                        <l>A ſharpe and cruell miſtreſſe, her eare's open</l>
                        <l>To all your ſupplications; you may boldly</l>
                        <l>And ſafely let in the moſt ſecret ſinne</l>
                        <l>Into her knowledge, which like vaniſht man</l>
                        <l>Neuer returnes into the World agen:</l>
                        <l>Fate lookes not vp more trulier,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>White Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To the guilty,</l>
                        <l>That may appeare ſome benifit.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Blacke B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Who ſo innocent</l>
                        <l>That neuer ſtands in neede on't in ſome kinde?</l>
                        <l>If euery thought were blabb'd that's ſo confeſt,</l>
                        <l>The very ayre we breath would be imbleſt:</l>
                        <l>Now to the worke indeed, which is to catch</l>
                        <l>Her inclination, that's the ſpeciall vſe</l>
                        <l>We make of all our practiſe in all Kingdomes</l>
                        <l>For my diſcloſing their moſt ſecret frailties,</l>
                        <l>Things which once ours, they muſt not hide from vs</l>
                        <l>That's the firſt article in the Creede we teach 'em,</l>
                        <l>Finding to what poynt their blood moſt inclines,</l>
                        <l>Know beſt to apt them, then to our deſignes:</l>
                        <l>Daughter the ſooner you diſperſe your Errors,</l>
                        <l>The ſooner you make haſte to your diſcouerie,</l>
                        <l>You muſt part with'em, to be nice or modeſt</l>
                        <l>Towards this good action, is to imitate</l>
                        <l>The baſhfulneſſe of one conceales an vlter,</l>
                        <l>For the vncomely parts that tumor vexes,</l>
                        <l>Til't be paſt cure. Reſolue you thus faire (Lady)</l>
                        <l>The priuatſt thought that runnes to hide it ſelfe,</l>
                        <l>In the moſt ſecret corner of your heart, now</l>
                        <l>Muſt be of my acquaintance, ſo familiarlie</l>
                        <l>Neuer ſhe friend of yours might counſell neerer.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>White Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I ſtand not much in feare of any account</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:6830:7"/>Guilty of that blacke crime (moſt noble holineſſe,)</l>
                        <l>I muſt confeſſe as in a ſacred Temple,</l>
                        <l>Throng'd with an auditorie, ſome come rather</l>
                        <l>To feede on humaine obiect, then to taſte</l>
                        <l>Of Angells foode.</l>
                        <l>So in the Congregation of quicke thoughts</l>
                        <l>Which are more infinite, then ſuch aſſemblies,</l>
                        <l>I cannot for truths ſafely ſpeake for all:</l>
                        <l>Some haue bin wandrers, ſome ſinful, ſome ſound:</l>
                        <l>But thoſe found euer poore entertainment.</l>
                        <l>They'd incouragement to come againe,</l>
                        <l>The ſingle life which ſtrongly I profeſſe now:</l>
                        <l>Heauen pardon me, I was about to part from.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Black B. p.</speaker>
                     <p>Then you haue paſt through loue?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>White Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But left no ſtaine</l>
                        <l>In all my paſſage (Sir) no print of wrong;</l>
                        <l>For the moſt chaſt maide that may trace my foot-ſteps.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Black B. p.</speaker>
                     <p>How came you off ſo cleare?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVhite Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I was diſcharged</l>
                        <l>By an inhumaine accident, which modeſty</l>
                        <l>Forbids me to put any language too.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>How you forget your ſelfe? all actions</l>
                        <l>Clad in their proper language, though moſtſorded</l>
                        <l>My eare is bound by duty to let in,</l>
                        <l>And locke vp euerlaſtingly: Shall I helpe you;</l>
                        <l>Hee was not found to anſwere his creation?</l>
                        <l>A veſtall Virgin in a ſlip of prayer,</l>
                        <l>Could noi deliuer mans loſſe modeſtier:</l>
                        <l>T was the White Biſhops pawne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>White Q p</speaker>
                     <p>The ſame (bleſt Sir)</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Blacke B. p.</speaker>
                     <p>An Heriticke well pickled.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>White Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By baſe treachery,</l>
                        <l>And violence prepared by the Competitor:</l>
                        <l>The blacke Knights pawne whom I ſhal euer hate for't.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Black B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>T was of reuenge the moſt vnmanliſt way</l>
                        <l>That euer riualltooke, a villaine</l>
                        <l>That for your ſake ile neuer abſolue him off.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6830:7"/>
                     <speaker>White Q. p.</speaker>
                     <p>I wiſh not ſo heauy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Blacke B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hee muſt feele it,</l>
                        <l>I neuer yet gaue abſolution</l>
                        <l>To any crime of that vnmatring nature:</l>
                        <l>It ſeemes you refuſe him for defect,</l>
                        <l>That other women haue in the ends of marriage:</l>
                        <l>Pardon my boldneſſe, if I ſift your goodneſſe</l>
                        <l>To the laſt gra<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I reuerence your paynes (Sir)</l>
                        <l>And muſt confeſſe, cuſtome to enioy</l>
                        <l>What other women challenge and poſſeſſe,</l>
                        <l>More ruld me then deſire: for my deſires</l>
                        <l>Dwell all in Ignorance, and Ile neuer wiſh</l>
                        <l>To know that fond way, may redeem them thence.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I neuer was ſo taken, beſet dubly</l>
                        <l>Now with her iudgment what a ſtrength it puts forth,</l>
                        <l>I bring worke neerer to you, when you haue ſeene</l>
                        <l>A maiſter-peece of man, compoſed by Heauen</l>
                        <l>For a great Princes fauor, kingdomes loue:</l>
                        <l>So exact Enuy could not finde a place</l>
                        <l>To ſticke a blot on perſon, or on fame:</l>
                        <l>Haue you not found ambition ſwel your wiſhes then?</l>
                        <l>And deſire ſtirre your blood.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By vertue neuer:</l>
                        <l>I haue onely in the dignity of the creature,</l>
                        <l>Admired the workes glory.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>She's impregnable,</l>
                        <l>A ſecond ſiedge muſt not fall off ſo tamely:</l>
                        <l>She's one of thoſe muſt be informed to know</l>
                        <l>A daughters duty which ſome take vntaught;</l>
                        <l>Her modeſty brings her behind hand much,</l>
                        <l>My old meanes I muſt flye too<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yes 'tis it,</l>
                        <l>Pleaſe you pervſe this ſmall tract of Obedience,</l>
                        <l>'Twill helpe you forward well.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>(Sir) that is a vertue:</l>
                        <l>I haue euer thought on with eſpeciall reuerence.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>You will conceiue by that,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:6830:8"/>My power your duty.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter White Biſhops pawne.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>W. B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What makes yond troubler of all Chriſtian water,</l>
                        <l>So neere yon<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> bleſſed ſpring? but I know</l>
                        <l>Her goodneſſe is the rocke from whence it iſſues.</l>
                        <l>Vnmoouable as fate, 'twould more afflict me</l>
                        <l>Then all my ſufferings for her, which ſo long</l>
                        <l>As ſhe holds conſtant to the houſe ſhe come off,</l>
                        <l>The whitneſſe of the cauſe, the ſide, the quality</l>
                        <l>Are ſacrifices to her worth and vertue,</l>
                        <l>And though confined in my religious ioyes,</l>
                        <l>I marry her and poſſeſſe her.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ent. the B. Kt. pawne.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Behold Lady,</l>
                        <l>The two inhuman enemies, the black Knights pawne,</l>
                        <l>And the white Biſhops, the gelder and the gelded.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                     <p>There's my griefe, my hate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What? in the Ieſuites fingers? by this hand,</l>
                        <l>Ile giue my part now for a Parrats feather,</l>
                        <l>Shee neuer returnes vertuous, 'tis impoſſible:</l>
                        <l>Ile vndertake, more wagers will be layd</l>
                        <l>Vpon a Vſurers returne from hell,</l>
                        <l>Then vpon hers from him now: haue I bin guilty</l>
                        <l>Of ſuch baſe malice, that my very conſcience</l>
                        <l>Shakes at the memory of it, and when I looke</l>
                        <l>To gather fruit find nothing but the Sauin tree:</l>
                        <l>Too frequent in Nunnes Orchards, and there planted</l>
                        <l>By all coniecture to deſtroy fruite rather,</l>
                        <l>I wilbe reſolued now moſt noble Virgine.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>W. Q p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ignoble villaine, dare that vnhallowed tongue</l>
                        <l>Lay hold vpon a ſound ſo gracious,</l>
                        <l>What's nobleneſſe to thee, or virgine Chaſtity?</l>
                        <l>They're not of thy acquaintance, talke of violence,</l>
                        <l>That ſhames creation, deeds would make night bluſh</l>
                        <l>That's company for thee, haſt thou the impudence</l>
                        <l>To court me with the Leproſie vpon thee,</l>
                        <l>Able to infect the walls of a great building.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sonne of offence forbeare, go ſet your diuell</l>
                        <l>Before your eyes, a paenitentiall veſture,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:6830:8"/>Would better become yee, ſome ſhirt of haire.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And you a three pound ſmocke, ſteed of an Abbey,</l>
                        <l>An Epicene Caſſible, this holy fellow</l>
                        <l>Robs ſafſt and cloſe, I feele a ſting that's worſe too:</l>
                        <l>White pawne, haſt ſo much Charity to accept</l>
                        <l>A reconcilement, make thy owne conditions,</l>
                        <l>For I begin to be extreamely burthned.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>W. B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No truth, no peace, of that blacke houſe, Proteſt</l>
                        <l>Is to be truſted, but for hope of acquittance,</l>
                        <l>And warned by difference, I may intrap him ſooneſt,</l>
                        <l>I admit conference.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>It is a nobleneſſe</l>
                        <l>That makes confuſion cleaue to all my merrits.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                     <p>That treatiſe will inſtruct you fully.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>So, ſo, <stage>Enter blacke Knight.</stage>
                        </l>
                        <l>The buſineſſe of the Vniuerſall Monarchy</l>
                        <l>Goes forward well now, the Colledge pot</l>
                        <l>That ſhould be alwayes boyling with the fuell,</l>
                        <l>Of all intelligencers poſſible,</l>
                        <l>Through the Chriſtian Kingdome is this fellow</l>
                        <l>Our prime incendiary? one of thoſe</l>
                        <l>That promiſ'd the white Kingdome ſeauen yeares ſince</l>
                        <l>To our blacke-houſe, put a new daughter to him,</l>
                        <l>The great worke-ſlaues, he minds nor Monarchy</l>
                        <l>Nor Hererazie (diuiner principallities) I brag leſſe,</l>
                        <l>But haue done more then all the conclaue on'em</l>
                        <l>Take their aſſiſtant fathers in all parts:</l>
                        <l>I, or their father generall in to boote:</l>
                        <l>And what I haue pone, I haue done factiouſly</l>
                        <l>With pleaſant ſubtilty, and bewitching court-ſhip,</l>
                        <l>Abuſe all my beleeuers with delight,</l>
                        <l>They tooke comfort to be couſned by me,</l>
                        <l>To many a ſoule I haue let in mortall poyſon,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe cheekes haue crackt with laughter to receiue it,</l>
                        <l>I could ſo roule my pills in ſugred ſyllables,</l>
                        <l>And ſtrew ſuch kindly mirth o're all my miſchiefe,</l>
                        <l>They tooke their baine in way of recreation,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:6830:9"/>A pleaſure ſteales corruption into youth,</l>
                        <l>H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ee ſpies me now, I muſt vphold his reuerence,</l>
                        <l>Eſpecially in publique (though I know)</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pryapus</hi> guardianof the cherry Gardens:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> chit is not more vitious.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Bleſſings accumiliation keep with you (ſir.)</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B <hi>Kt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Honors d<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſſimulation be your due (ſir.)</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>W. Q p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>How deep in duty in obſeruance plunge?</l>
                        <l>His charge muſt needes be reuerend.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I am Confeſſor</l>
                        <l>To this <hi>Black Knight</hi> too, you ſee douotion's fruitfull,</l>
                        <l>Sh'as many ſonnes and daughters.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I do this the more,</l>
                        <l>To maze our aduerſaries to behold,</l>
                        <l>The reuerence we giue theſe great ones,</l>
                        <l>And to beget a ſound opinion</l>
                        <l>Of holineſſe in them, and zeale in vs;</l>
                        <l>As alſo to enuite the like obedience</l>
                        <l>In other pupills, by our meeke example:</l>
                        <l>So, is your trifle gone?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>B.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Trifle call you her, it's a good game (ſir)</l>
                        <l>Sure ſhe's the ſecond pawne of the White houſe,</l>
                        <l>And to the opening of the game I hold her.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I you hold well: for that I know your play</l>
                        <l>Of old, if there were more <hi>Queenes pawnes</hi> you'ld plye</l>
                        <l>The game a great deale harder (now ſir we're in priuat)</l>
                        <l>But what for the maine worke, the great exiſtance?</l>
                        <l>The hope Monarchall?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>B</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>It goes on in this.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>In this? I cannot ſee't.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>B.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>So you may deny</l>
                        <l>A Dyalls motion, 'cauſe you cannot ſee</l>
                        <l>The hand mooue, or a wind that rends the Cedars.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Where ſtops the current of the intelligence;</l>
                        <l>Your father generall Biſhop of the blacke-houſe,</l>
                        <l>Complaines for want of worke.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Here's from all parts</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:6830:9"/>Sufficient to to imploy him, I receiu'd</l>
                        <l>A packet from the aſſiſtant fathers lately,</l>
                        <l>Looke you ther's <hi>Anglica,</hi> this <hi>Gallica.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I marry (ſir) ther's ſome quicke fleſh in this.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Germanica.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thinke they'n ſeald this with butter.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>B.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Italica</hi> this</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>They put their pens the hebrew way me thinks,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hiſpanica</hi> there.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hiſpanica,</hi> blinde word this,</l>
                        <l>The Ieſuite hath writ this with iuce of Leamons ſure</l>
                        <l>It muſt be held cloſe to the fire of Purgatory</l>
                        <l>Ere't can be read.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. <hi>B<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>You will not leaue your ieſting (Knight)</l>
                        <l>Though it wound your owne fame.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                     <p>Curanda pecunia.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter the white Kings pawne.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Take heede (Sir) we're intrapt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He's made our owne (man halfe in <hi>Voto</hi> yours,</l>
                        <l>His heart's in the blacke houſe, leaue him to me,</l>
                        <l>Moſt of all friends indeed pretiouſly ſpeciall,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>W. Ki. p.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>You ſee my outſide, but not my heart,</l>
                        <l>Great difference in the colour, there's ſome intelligence,</l>
                        <l>And as more ripeneſſe, ſo your knowledge ſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>l</l>
                        <l>Shall prooue the richer, there ſhall nothing happen</l>
                        <l>(Beleeue't) to extenuate your cauſe.</l>
                        <l>Or to oppreſſe her fr,ends, but I will ſtriue</l>
                        <l>To croſſe it with my counſel, purſe and power</l>
                        <l>Keepe all ſupplies both in meanes and men,</l>
                        <l>That may raiſe againſt you, we muſt part,</l>
                        <l>I dare not longer of this theame diſcuſſe,</l>
                        <l>The eare of State is quicke and iealious.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Excellent eſtemation, thou art valu'd</l>
                        <l>Aboue the fleece of gold, that came ſhort home,</l>
                        <l>Poore Ieſuite, ridden ſoule, how art thou foold</l>
                        <l>Out of thy faith, from thy allegance drawne,</l>
                        <l>Which way ſo ere thou takeſt, thou'rt the loſt Pawne.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <trailer>Finit Actus Primus</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:6830:10"/>
               <head>Incipit Secundus.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>White Queenes Pawne,</hi> with a booke in her hand.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>White Queenes Pawne.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>AND here agen it is the daughters duty</l>
                     <l>To obey her feſſors commaund in all things</l>
                     <l>Without exception, or expoſtulations;</l>
                     <l>Tis the moſt generall rule that ere I heard of:</l>
                     <l>Yet when I thinke how boundleſſe vertue is,</l>
                     <l>Goodneſſe and grace lies gently reconciled,</l>
                     <l>And then it appeares well to haue the power</l>
                     <l>Of the diſpenſor are's vncircumſcrib de'</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ent. b. B. p.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>She's hard vpon't, twas the moſt modeſt key</l>
                     <l>That I could vſe to open my intents,</l>
                     <l>What little, or no paines goes to ſome people:</l>
                     <l>Hah? a ſeald note, whence this,</l>
                     <l>To the blacke Biſhops pawne theſe, how to me</l>
                     <l>Strange, who ſubſcribes it? the blacke King what would he.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The Letter. PAwne</hi> ſufficiently holy; but immeaſurably politicke, Wee had late intelligence from our moſt induſtrious ſernant, famous in all parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> (our Knight of the blacke Houſe) that you haue at this inſtant in chaſe the white Queenes pawne, and very likely by the carriage of your Game to entrap and take her: Theſe are therefore to require you (by the burning affection I beare to the rape of deuotion) that ſpeedily vpon the ſurpriſall of her, by all watchfull aduantage, you make ſome attempt vppon the White Queenes perſon, whoſe fall or proſtitution our <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>moſt violently rages for.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sir after my deſire has tooke a Tulip</l>
                     <l>For it's owne inflamation, that yet ſcorches me,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall haue cooler time to thinke of yours,</l>
                     <l>She's paſt the generall rule of the large extent</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:10"/>Of our preſcription for obedience;</l>
                     <l>And yet with what allacrity of ſoule,</l>
                     <l>Her eye mooues on the Letter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Holy Sir,</l>
                     <l>Too long, I haue miſt you, oh your abſence ſtarues me,</l>
                     <l>Haſten for times redemption (worthy Sir)</l>
                     <l>Lay your commands as thicke and faſt vppon me</l>
                     <l>As you can ſpeake em, how I thirſt to heare em:</l>
                     <l>Set me to worke vpon this ſpacious vertue,</l>
                     <l>Which the poore ſpan of life's, tomorrow for</l>
                     <l>Boundleſſe obedience, the humbleſt, yet mightieſt of all</l>
                     <l>Duties, well ſet her downe a vniuerſall goodneſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By holineſſe of garment, her ſafe innocecne</l>
                     <l>Has frighted the full meaning from it ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>She's farre off from vnderſtanding now</l>
                     <l>The language of my intent, then at firſt meeting</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For vertues ſake, good ſir,</l>
                     <l>Command ſomething,</l>
                     <l>Make triall of my duty in ſome ſmall ſeruice,</l>
                     <l>And as you finde the faith of my obedience there,</l>
                     <l>Then truſt it with a greater.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You ſpeake ſweetely,</l>
                     <l>I do commaund you firſt then.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q.</speaker>
                  <p>With what ioy I do prepare my duty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To meete me,</l>
                     <l>And ſeale a kiſſe of loue vppon my lips,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>VV.</hi> Q. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Hah.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>At firſt diſobedient in ſo little too.</l>
                     <l>How ſhall I truſt you with a greater then?</l>
                     <l>Which was your owne requeſt?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pray ſend not backe</l>
                     <l>My Innocence to wound me, be more courteous,</l>
                     <l>I muſt confeſſe much like a ignorant plaintiffe</l>
                     <l>Who preſuming on the faire path of his meaning</l>
                     <l>Goes raſhly on, till on a ſuddaine brought</l>
                     <l>Into the wilderneſſe of Law, by words</l>
                     <l>Dropt vnaduiſedly, hurts his good cauſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:11"/>And giues the Aduerſary aduantage by it.</l>
                     <l>Apply it you can beſt (ſir) if my obedience</l>
                     <l>And your command can finde no better way,</l>
                     <l>Fond men command, and wantons beſt obey.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B, p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If I can at that diſtance ſend you a bleſſing,</l>
                     <l>Is it not neerer to you in my armes:</l>
                     <l>It flies abroad from theſe li<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s dealt in parcells,</l>
                     <l>And I to honour thee aboue all daughters.</l>
                     <l>Invite thee home to the houſe, where thou mayſt ſurfeit</l>
                     <l>On that, which others miſerably pine for:</l>
                     <l>A fauour which the daughters of great Potentates,</l>
                     <l>Would looke of enuies colour but to heare.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Good men may erre ſometimes, you're miſtaken,</l>
                     <l>Sure if this be vertues path, tis a moſt ſtrange one,</l>
                     <l>I neuer came this way before.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That's your ignorance,</l>
                     <l>And therefore ſhall that edict ſtill conduct you,</l>
                     <l>That knowes no way but one, nor euer ſeekes it,</l>
                     <l>Tis ſtrange if vertue ſhould be put to one,</l>
                     <l>If there be twenty wayes to ſome poore Village.</l>
                     <l>Your feare is wonderous faulty, caſt it from you,</l>
                     <l>T'will gather elſe in time a diſobedience,</l>
                     <l>Too ſtubborne for my pardon.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Haue I lockt my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>At vnawares into ſinnes ſeruitude</l>
                     <l>With more deſire of goodneſſe? is this the tye</l>
                     <l>Of all ſtrict order, and the holieſt</l>
                     <l>Of all ſocieties, the three vowed people</l>
                     <l>For Pouerty, Obedience, Chaſtity:</l>
                     <l>The laſt they moſt forget, when a Virgines raine</l>
                     <l>I ſee the great worke of Obedience,</l>
                     <l>Is better then halfe finiſht.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What a ſtranger,</l>
                     <l>Are you to duty growne, what diſtance keep you,</l>
                     <l>Muſt I bid you come forwards to a happines</l>
                     <l>Your ſelfe ſhould ſue for? 'twas neuer ſo with me</l>
                     <l>I dare not let this ſtubborneſſe be knowne,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:11"/>'Twould bring ſuch fierce hate on you, yet preſume not</l>
                     <l>To make that courteous care a preuiledge</l>
                     <l>For wilfull diſobedience, it turnes then</l>
                     <l>Into the blackneſſe of a curſe vpon you,</l>
                     <l>Come, come, be neerer.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Neerer?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Was that in ſcorne?</l>
                     <l>I would not haue it proued ſo for the hopes</l>
                     <l>Of the great Monarchy, if it were like it,</l>
                     <l>Let it not dare to flye abroad agen,</l>
                     <l>A ſtronger I will coape with't.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Bleſſe me, threatnes me,</l>
                     <l>And quite diſmayes the good ſtrength that ſhould</l>
                     <l>Helpe me. I neuer was ſo doubtfull of my ſafety.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Twas but my iealouſie, forgiue me (ſweetnes)</l>
                     <l>Yours is the houſe of meekneſſe, and no veonome liues</l>
                     <l>Vnder that roofe, be neerer; why ſo fearefull?</l>
                     <l>Neerer the Altar the more ſafe and ſacred.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>But neerer the offerors oft more wicked.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A plaine and moſt inſufferable contempt,</l>
                     <l>My glory I haue loſt vppon this woman,</l>
                     <l>In freely offering that ſhe ſhould haue kneel'd</l>
                     <l>A yeare in vaine for: my reſpect is darkned,</l>
                     <l>Giue me my reuerence agen thou haſt rob'd me off</l>
                     <l>In thy repulſe, thou ſhalt not carry it hence.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>(Sir.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou'rt too great a winner to depart;</l>
                     <l>And I too deepe a looſer to giue way to't.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh Heauen!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Lay me downe reputation,</l>
                     <l>Before thou ſturſt thy nice Virginity</l>
                     <l>Is recompence too little for my loue.</l>
                     <l>'Tis well if I accept of that for both,</l>
                     <l>Thy loſſe is but thine owne, there's arte to helpe thee,</l>
                     <l>And fooles to paſſe thee to; in my diſcouery</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:12"/>The whole ſociety ſuffers and in that,</l>
                     <l>The hope of abſolute Monarchy eclipſt,</l>
                     <l>Aſſurance thou canſt make me none for thy ſecrecy,</l>
                     <l>But by thy honors loſſe, that act muſt awe thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q p</speaker>
                  <p>Oh my diftreſt condition.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Doſt weepe?</l>
                     <l>If thou hadſt any pitty, this neceſſity</l>
                     <l>Would wring it from thee, I muſt elſe deſtroy thee:</l>
                     <l>We muſt not tuſt the policy of <hi>Europe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Vppon a womans tongue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then take my life (Sir)</l>
                     <l>And leaue my honor for to guide me to Heauen.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Take heede I take not both which I haue vowed</l>
                     <l>Since, if longer thou reſiſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Helpe, oh helpe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Art thou ſo cruell for an honors bable:</l>
                     <l>To vndo a whole fraternity, and diſperse</l>
                     <l>The ſecrets of moſt nations lock't in vs?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>For Heauen and vertues ſake</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Anoyſo within</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. W. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Muſt force confound noyſe?</l>
                     <l>Hah, what's that? ſilence (if faire worth be in thee)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile venture my eſcape on all dangers now,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B, p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who comes to take me, let me ſee that pawnes face,</l>
                     <l>Or his proud tympanous Maſ-well with ſtate winde,</l>
                     <l>Which being once prickt in the Convocation houſe,</l>
                     <l>The corrupt ayre puffes out, and he falls ſhriueld.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q p</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I will diſcouer the Arch-hypocrite,</l>
                     <l>To all the kinreds of the earth.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B B p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Confuſion in that voyce,</l>
                     <l>Rings the alarum of my vndooing, <stage>Enter blacks Queenes pawne.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>How, which way ſcapt ſhe from me?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Are you mad?</l>
                     <l>Can luſt infatuate a man ſo hopefull?</l>
                     <l>No patience in your blood: the dog-ſtarre raines ſure,</l>
                     <l>Time, and fire temper would haue wrought her</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:12"/>Pliant: I ſpi'd a Pawne of the white Houſe walke neere vs,</l>
                     <l>And made that noyſe of purpoſe to giue warrant</l>
                     <l>For mine owne turne: which ends in all I worke for.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Methinkes I ſtand ouer a powder vault,</l>
                     <l>And the match now a kindling: what's to be done?</l>
                     <l>'Tis his owne caſe, he will defend you mainely,</l>
                     <l>And happily here he comes with the black Knight too.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Blacke Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>blacke Knight.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh you made noble worke for the white houſe</l>
                     <l>This act will fill the aduerſaryes mouth,</l>
                     <l>And blow the Luthrens cheeks, tilt cracke agen.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This will aduance the ſtate Monarchal buſineſſe</l>
                     <l>In all parts well, and helpe the agents forward,</l>
                     <l>Which I haue ſeauen yeares laboured to accompliſh.</l>
                     <l>One minute ſets back by ſome cod-peece Coledge ſtil.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I dwell not (sir) alone in this default,</l>
                     <l>The blacke houſe yeelds me partners.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B.</speaker>
                  <p>All more cautelous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Qui caute, caſte,</hi> that's my Motto ſtill,</l>
                     <l>Iue trauailed with that word ouer moſt Kingdomes,</l>
                     <l>And laine ſafe with moſt nations on a leaking bottom</l>
                     <l>I haue beene as often toſt on Venus seas</l>
                     <l>As trymer, and freſher barkes, when ſounder veſſels</l>
                     <l>Haue layne at anchor, that is kept the doore.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B.</speaker>
                  <p>She has no witneſſe then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Groſſe witneſſe, when went one of his ſociety?</l>
                     <l>To miſchiefe with a witneſſe?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B,</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I haue don't then,</l>
                     <l>Away vpon the wings of ſpeed, take poſt horſe,</l>
                     <l>Caſt thirty leagues of earth behinde thee ſuddenly,</l>
                     <l>Leaue letters ante-dated at our houſe,</l>
                     <l>Ten dayes at leaſt from this.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Biſhop I taſte thee,</l>
                     <l>Good ſtrong Epiſcopall counſell, take a bottle on't,</l>
                     <l>Twill ſerue thee all thy iourney.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:13"/>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But good (ſir) how,</l>
                     <l>For my getting for the vnſpied?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B.</speaker>
                  <p>There's Checke agen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>No, Ile helpe that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Well ſayd my bouncing Ieſuiteſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>There lies a ſecret valt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Away, make haſt then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Runne for my Cabinet of intelligences,</l>
                     <l>For feare they ſearch the houſe, good Biſhop burn'em,</l>
                     <l>I cannot ſtand to picke 'em now.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Begone the dangers all in you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let me ſee Queenes pawne,</l>
                     <l>How formerly has packt vp his intelligences,</l>
                     <l>H'as laid them all in truckell beds (me thinkes)</l>
                     <l>And like Court harbingers has writ the names</l>
                     <l>In Chalke vpon their Chambers: <hi>Anglica,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oh this is the Engliſh houſe, what newes there trow?</l>
                     <l>Hah by this hand moſt of theſe are bawdy epiſtles,</l>
                     <l>Time they were burnt indeed, whole bundles of 'em:</l>
                     <l>Here's from his daughter <hi>Blanch</hi> &amp; daughter <hi>Bridget:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From the ſafe ſanctuary in the <hi>White-Friers:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thoſe from two tender ſiſters of compaſſion,</l>
                     <l>In the bowels of Blomsbury:</l>
                     <l>Theſe three from the Nonnery in Drury lane:</l>
                     <l>A fire, a fire, (go Ieſuiteſſe) a fire:</l>
                     <l>What haue you there?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A note (ſir) of State policy,</l>
                     <l>And an exceeding ſafe one.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pray let's ſee it (Sir)</l>
                     <l>To ſell away all the powder in the Kingdome,</l>
                     <l>To preuent blowing vp, that's ſafe, ile able it:</l>
                     <l>Here's a factious obſeruation now,</l>
                     <l>That ſuits my humor better, he writes here</l>
                     <l>Some wiues in <hi>England</hi> will commit adultery,</l>
                     <l>And then ſend to Roome for a bull for their husbands.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Haue they thoſe ſhifts?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:13"/>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh no familiarity breathing</l>
                     <l>Sweeter, here wench take thoſe papers,</l>
                     <l>Schorch em ſoundly, burne em to French ruſſet,</l>
                     <l>And put em, in agen.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what's your myſtery?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh (ſir) 'twill mocke the aduerſary ſtrangly,</l>
                     <l>If ere the houſe be ſearcht, 'twas done in <hi>Venis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Vppon the Ieſuiticall expulſe there,</l>
                     <l>Where the Inqueſitors came all ſpecktacl'd</l>
                     <l>To picke out ſyllables out of the dung of treaſon,</l>
                     <l>(As children pick their cherry-ſtones) yet found none;</l>
                     <l>But what they made themſelues with ends of letters.</l>
                     <l>Do as I bid you Pawne.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ent. B. Knights pawne.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Faith not in all,</l>
                     <l>I loue rogarie too well to let it fall:</l>
                     <l>How now, what newes with you?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The ſting of conſcience</l>
                     <l>Afflicts me ſo for that inhumane violence,</l>
                     <l>On the White biſhops Pawne, it takes away</l>
                     <l>My ioy, my reſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This 'tis to make an Eunuch,</l>
                     <l>You made a ſport on't then.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ceaſe agreuation,</l>
                     <l>I come to be obſolu'd for't, where is my Confeſſor,</l>
                     <l>Why do'ſt thou point to the ground?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Cauſe he went that way:</l>
                     <l>Come, come, helpe me in with this Cabinet,</l>
                     <l>Ile tell thee a ſtrange Story.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <p>If't be ſad, tis welcome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Tis not much troubled with mirth, ſir. <hi>Ex.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Fat biſhop, with his Pawne.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fat B.</speaker>
                  <p>Pawne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. p.</speaker>
                  <p>I attend at your great holineſſe ſeruice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For great, I grant you, but greatly holy,</l>
                     <l>There the ſold alters fat Cathedrall bodies,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:14"/>Haue very often leane, little ſoules,</l>
                     <l>Much like the Lady in the Lobſtars head,</l>
                     <l>A great deale of ſhell and garbage of all colours,</l>
                     <l>But for the pure part, that ſhould take wings and mount</l>
                     <l>That's at laſt gaſpe, as if a man ſhould gape,</l>
                     <l>And from a huge bulke let forth a butter-flye,</l>
                     <l>Likethoſe big-bellied mountaines, which the Poet</l>
                     <l>Deliuers, that are brought to bed with mans fleſh,</l>
                     <l>Are my booke Printed pawne, my laſt invictiues againſt</l>
                     <l>Againſt the blacke-houſe?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ready for publication:</l>
                     <l>For I ſaw perfect bookes this morning (ſir.)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Fetch me a few, which I will inſtantly</l>
                     <l>Diſtribute amongſt the White-houſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B. p.</speaker>
                  <p>With all ſpeede (ſir.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tis a moſt Lordly life to rayle at eaſe,</l>
                     <l>See, eate, and drinke vpon the fat of one Kingdome;</l>
                     <l>And rayle vpon an other with the iuce on't:</l>
                     <l>I haue writ this booke out of the ſtrength and marrow</l>
                     <l>Of ſix and thirty diſhes at a meale:</l>
                     <l>But moſt on't out of culliſhe of Cocke ſparrowes,</l>
                     <l>Twill ſticke and glew the faſter to the aduerſary,</l>
                     <l>Twill ſlit the roote of their moſt Caluiſh cauſe,</l>
                     <l>And yet I eate but little butchers meate</l>
                     <l>In the conception:</l>
                     <l>Of all things I commend the White-houſe beſt,</l>
                     <l>For plenty and variety of victualls:</l>
                     <l>When I was one of the blacke-houſe profeſt,</l>
                     <l>My fleſh fell halfe a Cubit, time to revolt,</l>
                     <l>When my owne ribs reuolted; but to ſay truth,</l>
                     <l>I haue no preferment yet, that's ſuteable</l>
                     <l>To the greatneſſe of my perſon and my parts:</l>
                     <l>I grant I liue at eaſe, for I am made</l>
                     <l>The Maiſter of the beds, the long acre of beds:</l>
                     <l>But there's no Marie-gold, that ſhuts and opens,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:14"/>Flower gentlee <hi>Venis</hi> borth, apples of loue,</l>
                     <l>Pinckes, Hyanths, Honie-ſuckles, Daffa-down-dillies,</l>
                     <l>There was a time I'd much more brab then beds,</l>
                     <l>Now I'ue more beds, then drabs:</l>
                     <l>Yet there's no eminent trader deales in whole-ſayle;</l>
                     <l>But ſhe and I haue clap a barging vp,</l>
                     <l>Let in at water-gate, for which I haue rackt</l>
                     <l>My tennants purſe-ſtrings, that then'ue twang'd agen:</l>
                     <l>Yonder blacke Knight, the Fiſtula of <hi>Europe,</hi> 
                        <stage>Enter b. B. with b. Kt.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe diſeaſe once I vndertooke to cure,</l>
                     <l>With a high Holborne halter, when he laſt</l>
                     <l>Vouchſaft to peepe into my priuiledged lodgings</l>
                     <l>He ſaw good ſtore of plate, and rich hangings:</l>
                     <l>He knew I brought none to the White-houſe with me,</l>
                     <l>I haue not loſt the vſe of my profeſſion,</l>
                     <l>Since I turned White-houſe biſhop:</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ent. Pawne with bookes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Looke, more bookes yet?</l>
                     <l>Yonder greaſie gormundizing Prelate</l>
                     <l>Does worke our houſe more miſchiefe by his ſcripts,</l>
                     <l>His fat and fulſome Volumes,</l>
                     <l>Then the whole body of the aduers party.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh 'twere a Maſter-peece of ſerpent ſubtilty</l>
                     <l>To fetch him a this ſide agen.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And then damme him</l>
                     <l>Into the bag for euer, or expoſe him</l>
                     <l>Againſt the aduerſe party, which now he feeds on;</l>
                     <l>And that would double dam him, my reuenge</l>
                     <l>Has prompted me already, ile confound him</l>
                     <l>A both ſides for the phiſicke he prouided,</l>
                     <l>And the baſe Chyrurgion he invented for me,</l>
                     <l>Ile tell you what a moſt vncutholicall ieaſt</l>
                     <l>He put vpon me once when my paine tortur'd me,</l>
                     <l>He told me he had found a preſent cure for me,</l>
                     <l>Which I grew proude on, and obſeru'd him ſeriouſly,</l>
                     <l>What thinke you 'twas, being execution day,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:15"/>He ſhewd the Hangman to me out at window.</l>
                     <l>The common Hangman.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I'le make him the baloom ball,</l>
                     <l>Of the Churches.</l>
                     <l>And both the ſides ſhall toſſe him, he lookes like one,</l>
                     <l>A thing ſweld vp with mingled drinke and wine,</l>
                     <l>And will bound well from one ſide to another.</l>
                     <l>Come, you ſhall write our ſecond biſhops dead</l>
                     <l>Which has yet no imployment in the Game</l>
                     <l>Perhaps nor euer ſhall, it may be wonne</l>
                     <l>Without his motion, it reſt in ours:</l>
                     <l>He ſhall be flattered with <hi>Sede vacant,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Make him beleeue he comes into his place,</l>
                     <l>And that will fetch him with a vengance to vs,</l>
                     <l>For I know powder is not more ambitious,</l>
                     <l>When the match meet it, then his minde for mounting</l>
                     <l>As <hi>Couetous</hi> and <hi>Leacherous.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B.</speaker>
                  <p>No more, now (Sir) both the ſides fill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>This ha's bin look't for long.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The ſtronger ſting it ſhootes into the bloud</l>
                     <l>Of the blacke aduerſary, I'm aſham'd now,</l>
                     <l>I was theirs euer, what a Lumpe was I?</l>
                     <l>When I was led in ignorance and blindneſſe?</l>
                     <l>I muſt confeſſe I'ue all my life time playd</l>
                     <l>The Foole, till now.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>And now he plaies two parts, the foole and knaue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ther's my recantation in the laſt leafe.</l>
                     <l>Wer't like a <hi>Ciceronian</hi> in pure Latain.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Pure honeſty, the better latain ſerues then,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Out of thoſe peſtilent pamphlets thoſe are they</l>
                     <l>That wound our cauſe to the heart.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Heere, more anger yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>But we come well prouided for this ſtorme</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>W.</hi> Q.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Is this my <hi>Pawne?</hi> ſhe that ſhould <stage>Enter both Houſes.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Guard our Perſon,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6830:15"/>
                     <l>Or ſome pale figure of deiection,</l>
                     <l>Her ſhape vſurping, ſorrow and affrightment,</l>
                     <l>Has preuailed ſtrangly with her.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>King of Integrety,</l>
                     <l>Queene of the ſame, and all the houſe profeſſors</l>
                     <l>Of noble Candor, vncorrupted iuſtice,</l>
                     <l>And truth of heart, through my alone diſcouery</l>
                     <l>(My like and honor wondrouſly preſerued)</l>
                     <l>I bring into your knowledge with my ſufferings,</l>
                     <l>Fearefull affrightments, and heart-killing terrors,</l>
                     <l>The great incendiary of all Chriſtendome,</l>
                     <l>The abſolute abuſer of true ſanctity,</l>
                     <l>Fayrer peace, and holy order can be found</l>
                     <l>In any part of th'vniuefſall Globe:</l>
                     <l>Who making meeke deuotion keep the doore,</l>
                     <l>(His lips being full of holy zeale at firſt)</l>
                     <l>Would haue committed a foule rape vppon me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q.</speaker>
                  <p>Hah?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A rape? that's foule indeed, the very ſound</l>
                     <l>To our eare fowler then the offence it ſelfe</l>
                     <l>To ſome Kings of the earth.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sir, to proceede,</l>
                     <l>Gladly I offered life to preſerue honour,</l>
                     <l>Which would not be accepted without both:</l>
                     <l>The chiefe of his ill ayme to be at mine honour,</l>
                     <l>Till heauen was pleaſed by ſome vnlookt for accident,</l>
                     <l>To giue me courage to redeeme my ſelfe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When we finde deſperate ſinnes</l>
                     <l>In ill mens company,</l>
                     <l>We place a charitable ſorrow there;</l>
                     <l>But cuſtome and their leaprous inclination,</l>
                     <l>Quits vs of wonder: for our expectation</l>
                     <l>Is anſwered in their liues, but to finde ſinne</l>
                     <l>Vnder a robe of Sanctity, is able</l>
                     <l>To draw all number to that monſter onely,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:16"/>And leaue created monſters vnadmired,</l>
                     <l>The pride of him that tooke firſt fall fo pride,</l>
                     <l>Is to be Angell ſhapt, and imitate</l>
                     <l>The forme from whence he lell; but this offendor,</l>
                     <l>Farre, baſer then ſinnes maiſter, fix'd by vowe</l>
                     <l>To holy order which is Angells method,</l>
                     <l>It grieues me that my knowledg muſt be tainted,</l>
                     <l>With his infeſted name,</l>
                     <l>Oh rather with thy finger poynt him out.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The place that he ſhould fil is void my L.</l>
                     <l>His guilt has ſcarde him the blacke Biſhops pawne.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hah, mine, my pawne? the glory of his order,</l>
                     <l>The prime and preſident zealot on the earth?</l>
                     <l>Impudent pawne, for thy ſake at this minute</l>
                     <l>Modeſty ſuffers, all that's vertuous bluſhes,</l>
                     <l>And truths ſelfe like the ſunne vext with a miſt,</l>
                     <l>Lookes red with anger.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Be not thou drunke with rage too</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sober ſincerity nor you a cup,</l>
                     <l>Spake with Hypocriſie.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You name their Biſhop,</l>
                     <l>But your own Chriſtmas bole you morning draught</l>
                     <l>Next your Epiſcopall heart all the twelue dayes,</l>
                     <l>Which ſmacke you cannot leaue all the yeare after.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A ſhrewd retorte</l>
                     <l>Has made our Biſhop ſmell of burning too,</l>
                     <l>Would I ſtood farther off, wer't no impeachment</l>
                     <l>To my honor orthe game, would they wold play faſter</l>
                     <l>White Knight, ther's acknowledged from our houſe</l>
                     <l>A reuerence to you and reſpect</l>
                     <l>To that Lord Duke ſtands next you, with the fauour</l>
                     <l>Of the white King, and th'afore-named reſpected,</l>
                     <l>I combate with this cauſe, if with all ſpeed</l>
                     <l>Waſt not one ſyllable, vnfortunate pawne,</l>
                     <l>Of what I ſpeake, thou doſt not plead deſtruction</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:16"/>A plea which will but faintly take thee off neither,</l>
                     <l>From this Leuiathan ſcandall, that lyes rowling</l>
                     <l>Vpon the Chriſtall waters of deuotion,</l>
                     <l>Or what may quit the more (though enough nothing)</l>
                     <l>Fall downe, and foame, and by than pang diſcouer,</l>
                     <l>The vexing ſpirit of falſhood ſtrongly within thee,</l>
                     <l>Make thy ſelfe ready for perdition,</l>
                     <l>Ther's no remoue in all the Game to ſcape it,</l>
                     <l>This pawne or this, the Biſhop, or my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Will take thee in the end, play how you can.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Spite of ſins glorious oſtentatio n;</l>
                     <l>And all blood-threats, that thunder crackes of pride,</l>
                     <l>Vſhering a ſtorme malice houſe of impudence,</l>
                     <l>Truſt and aeqiuocation, my true cauſe</l>
                     <l>Shall keepe the path it treads in.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I play thus then:</l>
                     <l>Now in the hearing of this high aſſembly,</l>
                     <l>Bring forth the time of this attempts conception.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. B.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſeemes blacke Knight you are afraid to touch it</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Well it's eruption, will ſhe haue it ſo then?</l>
                     <l>Or your white Biſhop for her, the more vncleane<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Vile and impious that you vrge the ſtraine to,</l>
                     <l>The greater will her ſhames heape now i'th end,</l>
                     <l>And the wrongs meeke mans glory, the time (pawne)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Yeſterdayes curſed euening.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh the treaſure of my reuenge I cannot ſpend on thee,</l>
                     <l>Ruine enough to ſpare for all thy kinred too,</l>
                     <l>For honors ſake call in more ſlanderers,</l>
                     <l>I haue ſuch plentifull confuſion,</l>
                     <l>I know not how to waſt it, ile bee nobler yet,</l>
                     <l>And put her to her owne houſe: King of meekneſſe</l>
                     <l>Take the cauſe to thee, for our hands are too heauy,</l>
                     <l>Our proofes will fall vpon her like a Tower,</l>
                     <l>And grinde her bones to powder.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:17"/>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What new engine,</l>
                     <l>Ha's the diuell rayſed in him now.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Is it he,</l>
                     <l>And that the time ſtands firme, now to your ſcandall,</l>
                     <l>Pray do not ſhift your ſlander.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Shift your treachery,</l>
                     <l>They'ue worne one ſuit too long.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That holy man,</l>
                     <l>So wrongfully accuſed by this loſt pawne:</l>
                     <l>H'as not beene ſeene theſe ten daies in theſe parts.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>How.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Nay at this inſtant thirty leagues from hence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Fadomleſſe falſhood, will it ſcape vnblaſted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>Can you make this appeare?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Light is not clearer,</l>
                     <l>By his owne letters (moſt impartiall Monarch.)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <p>How wrongfully may ſacred vertue ſuffer, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Biſhop we haue a treaſure of that falſe heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>Step forth and reach thoſe proofes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Amazement couers me,</l>
                     <l>Can I be forſaken of a cauſe</l>
                     <l>So ſtrong in truth and equity, will vertue</l>
                     <l>Send me no ayde in this hard time of friendſhip.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There's an infallible ſtaffe and a red hat</l>
                     <l>Reſerued for you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, ſir, indeede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A ſtaffe</l>
                     <l>That will not eaſily breake, you may truſt to't,</l>
                     <l>And ſuch a one had your corruction need of,</l>
                     <l>There's a ſtate figge for you now,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Behold all,</l>
                     <l>How they were in one:</l>
                     <l>I alwayes held a charity ſo good</l>
                     <l>To holineſſe profeſt I euer beleeued rather,</l>
                     <l>The accuſer falſe you the profeſſor vitious.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:17"/>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A charity like all your vertues elſe,</l>
                     <l>Gracious and glorious.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where ſets the offence,</l>
                     <l>Let the faults puniſhment be deriued from thence:</l>
                     <l>We leaue her to your cenſure.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt iuſt Maieſty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Calamity of vertue, my Queene leaues me too:</l>
                     <l>Am I caſt off as the Oliue caſts her flower?</l>
                     <l>Poore friendleſſe innocence art thou left a prey,</l>
                     <l>To the deuourer?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor thou art not loſt,</l>
                     <l>Let em put on their bloodieſt reſolutions,</l>
                     <l>If the faire policy I ayme at proſpers:</l>
                     <l>Thy counſell (noble Duke.)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. D.</speaker>
                  <p>For that worke chiefely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>A man for ſpeede now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let it be my honor, ſir,</l>
                     <l>Make me that flight that owes my liues ſeruice.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Was not this brought about for our honours:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Piſh, the <hi>Galician</hi> braine can worke out wonders.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let's vſe her, as vpon like diſcouery</l>
                     <l>A mayde was vſed at <hi>Venice,</hi> euery one</l>
                     <l>Be ready with a pennance being maieſty</l>
                     <l>Veſſell of fooliſh ſcandall, take thy fright</l>
                     <l>Had beene in that Cabinet of niceneſſe,</l>
                     <l>Halfe the virginities the earth lockt vp,</l>
                     <l>And all ſweept at one caſt, by the dexterity</l>
                     <l>Of a Ieſuiticall Gamſter t'ad not valu'd</l>
                     <l>The leaſt part of that general worth thou haſt tainted.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt I enioyne thee to a three daies faſt for't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Q.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>You're to penurious, ſir, ill make it foure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <p>I to a twelue houres kneeling at one time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And in a roome fil'd al with Aretines pictures,</l>
                     <l>(More then the twelue labours of Luxurie)</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt not ſo much as the chaſt pummell ſee</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:18"/>Of <hi>Lucrece</hi> dagger peeping: nay Ile puniſh thee</l>
                     <l>For a diſcouerer, ile torment thy modeſty.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. D.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>After that foure dayes laſt, into the inquiſition houſe.</l>
                     <l>Strengthned with bread and water for worſe pennance.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Why well ſaid Duke of our houſe, nobly agriuated.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. <hi>Q p</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Vertue to ſhew her influence more ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>Fits me with patience mightier then my wrong.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <trailer>Finit Actus Secundus.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>Incipit Tertius.</head>
               <stage>Enter Fat <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. Biſhop.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I Know my pen drawes blood of the blacke houſe,</l>
                     <l>Ther's neuer a booke I writ but their cauſe bleedes,</l>
                     <l>It has loſt many an ounce of reputation,</l>
                     <l>Since I came to this ſide, I deepe in,</l>
                     <l>And leaue the Orifex guſhing were I come:</l>
                     <l>But wher's my aduancement all this while I haue got,</l>
                     <l>I'de haue ſome round preferment, corpulent dignity</l>
                     <l>That beares ſome breath and compaſſe in the gulfe on't,</l>
                     <l>I am perſwaded that this fleſh would fit</l>
                     <l>The biggeſt chayre Eccleſiaſticall,</l>
                     <l>If it were put to tryall, to be made Maiſter of an Hoſpitall,</l>
                     <l>Is but a kind of diſeaſe-bred honour:</l>
                     <l>Or dreame of the poore almes Knights that weare badges</l>
                     <l>Ther's but two lazy beggerly preferments,</l>
                     <l>In the white Kingdome, and I'ue got em both,</l>
                     <l>My merrit does begin to be crop-ſicke</l>
                     <l>For want of other Titles.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter blacke Knight.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh here walkes his fulſome holineſſe:</l>
                     <l>Now for the Maiſter-peece</l>
                     <l>To vndo him euerlaſting, that's put home,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:18"/>And make him hang in moſt ſeriouſly,</l>
                     <l>That ieaſted with an halter vpon,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>F.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <p>The blacke Knight? I muſt looke to play then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I bring faire gretings to your reuerend vertues,</l>
                     <l>From Cardinall <hi>Paulus</hi> your moſt princely kinſman.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>F.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our princely kinſman ſaith thou? we accept <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m:</l>
                     <l>Pray keep your ſide and diſtance, I am chary</l>
                     <l>Of my Epiſcopall perſon:</l>
                     <l>I know the Knights walke in this Game too well,</l>
                     <l>He may ſlip ouer me, and where am I then?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There where thou ſhalt be</l>
                     <l>Shortly if arte faile not,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The Letter.</hi> RIght Reuerend and noble (<hi>meaning me</hi>) our true kinſman in affection, but alienated in blood, your vnkind diſobedience to the mother cauſe, prooues the onely cauſe of your ill fortune at this time: My preſent remooue by generall election to the Papall dignity, had now auſpiciouſly ſetled you in my <hi>Sede vacante (how had it ſo)</hi> which at my next remooue, by death might proued, your ſtep to ſupremacy.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>(Hah, all my bodies blood mounts to my face,</l>
                     <l>To looke vpon this letter.)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The pill workes with him,</l>
                     <l>Thinke on't ſeriouſly it is not yet too late then,</l>
                     <l>Through the ſubmiſſe acknowledgment</l>
                     <l>Of your diſobedience`</l>
                     <l>To be brotherly receiued into the louing</l>
                     <l>Boſome of the Conclaue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>F.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This was the chayre of eaſe I euer aymed at,</l>
                     <l>Ile make a bonfire of my bookes immediatly</l>
                     <l>All, that are left againſt that ſide ile ſacrifice:</l>
                     <l>Packe vp my plate and goods, and ſteale away</l>
                     <l>By night at Water-gate: It is but penning</l>
                     <l>An other recantation, and in venting</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:19"/>Two or three bitter bookes againſt the white houſe,</l>
                     <l>And then I'me atother ſide agen,</l>
                     <l>As firme as ere I was, as fat, and flouriſhing:</l>
                     <l>Blacke Knight, expect a wonder ere't belong,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt ſee me one of the blacke-houſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Your holineſſe is merry with the meſſenger,</l>
                     <l>Too happy to be true, you ſpeake what ſhould be.</l>
                     <l>If naturall compunction toucht you truely:</l>
                     <l>Oh you'ue drawn-blood, liue blood, blood of honor</l>
                     <l>From your moſt deare primitiue mothers heart:</l>
                     <l>Your ſharpe inuectiues haue beene points of ſpeares</l>
                     <l>In her ſweet tender ſides, the vnkind wounds</l>
                     <l>Which the ſonne giues, a ſonne of reuerence ſpecially,</l>
                     <l>They rankle ten times more, you the aduerſaries:</l>
                     <l>I tell you, ſir, your reuerend reuolt</l>
                     <l>Did giue the feare-fulleſt blow to adoration</l>
                     <l>Our cauſe ere felt, it ſhooke the very ſtatues,</l>
                     <l>The veines and aſhes of the Sainted ſleepers.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Forbeare, or I ſhall melt i'the place I ſtand,</l>
                     <l>And let forth a fat Biſhop in ſad ſyrrop:</l>
                     <l>Suffice I am yours, when they leaſt dreame on't,</l>
                     <l>Ambitious fooder, power and riches drawes me,</l>
                     <l>When I ſmell honor that's the locke of hay,</l>
                     <l>That lead me throgh the worlds field euery way. <hi>Ex.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>B. Kt.</hi> Here's a ſweet pange to propogate beleefe on,</l>
                     <l>Like the foundation of a Chappell layd</l>
                     <l>Vpon a quagmire, I may number him now</l>
                     <l>Amongſt my inferior policies, and not ſhame em;</l>
                     <l>But let me a little ſolace my deſignes</l>
                     <l>With the remembrance of ſome braue ones paſt,</l>
                     <l>To cherriſh the futerrity of proiect,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe motion muſt be reſtleſſe til that great work,</l>
                     <l>Cald the poſſeſſion of the world be ours:</l>
                     <l>Was it not procured a gallant fleete,</l>
                     <l>From the white Kingdome to ſecure our coaſts,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:19"/>Gainſt th'infidell Pyrats, vnder pretext</l>
                     <l>Of more neceſſities expedition,</l>
                     <l>Who made the Iayles flye open (without miracle)</l>
                     <l>And let the Locuſts out, thoſe dangerous flies.</l>
                     <l>Whoſe properti's to burne corne without touching</l>
                     <l>The Heritique Granaries, feele it to this minute;</l>
                     <l>And now they'ue got amongſt the country Corps,</l>
                     <l>They ſticke ſo faſt to the conuerted eares,</l>
                     <l>The loudeſt tempeſt that authority rowzes,</l>
                     <l>Will hardly ſhake 'em off, they haue their dennes</l>
                     <l>In Ladies coaches, their ſafe groues and fennes:</l>
                     <l>Nay they were followed and found out by th' ſent</l>
                     <l>Palme oyle will make a Purſeuant relent:</l>
                     <l>Whoſe policy was it to put a ſilenc't muzle,</l>
                     <l>On all the barking tong-men of the time:</l>
                     <l>Made pictures that were enough before,</l>
                     <l>Poore ſufferers in that politicke reſtraint?</l>
                     <l>My light ſpleene skips, and ſhakes my ribs to think on't</l>
                     <l>Whilſt our drift walkt vncenſured, but in thought</l>
                     <l>A whifle or a whiſper, would be queſtioned,</l>
                     <l>In the moſt fortunate Angle in the World,</l>
                     <l>The Court has held the City by thy Hornes,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt I haue milkt her: I haue got good ſoups too</l>
                     <l>From Countries for their liberties,</l>
                     <l>From ſome for their moſt vainly hopd for preferments.</l>
                     <l>High offices, in th'ayre, I ſhould no liue</l>
                     <l>But for this <hi>Mellacrim,</hi> this mirth Manna, <stage>Enter blacke Knights pawne.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>My pawne? how now, the new's.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B, Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Expect none very pleaſing</l>
                     <l>That comes (ſir) of my bringing, I'me ſo ſad.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thy conſcience is ſo tender hooft a late,</l>
                     <l>Euery nayle prickes it.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This may pricke yours too,</l>
                     <l>If there be any quicke fleſh in a yard on't.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Mine, miſchiefe muſt finde a deepe nayle and a driuer.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:20"/>Beyond the ſtrength of any Matchauile:</l>
                     <l>The politicke Kingdomes fatten to reach mine,</l>
                     <l>Prithee compunction needle pricke a little,</l>
                     <l>Vnbind this ſore wound.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Sir, your plots diſcouered.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Which of the twenty thouſand, nine hundreth</l>
                     <l>Threeſcore and fiue, canſt tell?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Bleſſe vs, ſo many?</l>
                     <l>How does poore Country men haue but one plot</l>
                     <l>To keepe a Cow o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, yet in law for that,</l>
                     <l>You cannot'em all ſure by their names (Sir)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yes were the number trebled: thou haſt ſeene</l>
                     <l>A Globe ſtand on the table in my Cloſet.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>A thing (ſir) drawne with Countries and hard words.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>True, with lines drawne</l>
                     <l>Some Tropicall, ſome oblique.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſcarce can read, I was brought vp in blindneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Iuſt ſuch a thing (if ere my ſcull be open'd)</l>
                     <l>Will my braines looke like.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Like a Globe of Countries.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I and ſome Maiſter politician,</l>
                     <l>That has ſharpe ſtate eyes will go neere to picke out</l>
                     <l>The plots and euery climate where they faſtned,</l>
                     <l>And will puzle em too.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <p>I'me of your minde for that (ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Th'le finde em too full vpon ſo ne countries,</l>
                     <l>The'd neede vſe ſpectacles; but I turne to you now,</l>
                     <l>What plot is that diſcouered?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Your laſt bruite ſir,</l>
                     <l>Begot 'twixt the blacke Biſhop and your ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>Your ante-dated letters 'bout the Ieſuite.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Diſcouered, how?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The white Knights policy has out ſtript yours it ſeemes:</l>
                     <l>Ioyned with th'aſſiſtant councell of this Duke:</l>
                     <l>The white Biſhops pawne vndertooke the iourney,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:20"/>Who as they ſay, diſcharged it like a flight,</l>
                     <l>I made him for the buſineſſe fit and light.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis but a bawdy pawne out of the way a little,</l>
                     <l>Ther's enough of them in all parts. <stage>Enter both Houſes.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>You haue heard all then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The wonders paſt with me, but ſome</l>
                     <l>Shall downe for't.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Set free that vertuous pawne from all her wrongs,</l>
                     <l>Let her be brought with honor to, the face,</l>
                     <l>Of her malicious Aduerſary.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Good.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Noble chaſt Knight, a title of that Candor,</l>
                     <l>The greateſt Prince on earth without impeachment</l>
                     <l>May haue the dignity of his worth comprized in,</l>
                     <l>This fayre deliuering act vertue will regiſter,</l>
                     <l>In that white booke of the defence of Virgins,</l>
                     <l>Where the cleare fame all preſeruing Knights,</l>
                     <l>Are to eternall memory conſecrated;</l>
                     <l>And wee embrace as partner of that honour,</l>
                     <l>This worthy Duke, the counſell of the act,</l>
                     <l>Whom wee ſhall euer place in our reſpect.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. D.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Moſt bleſſed of Kings, thron'd in al royal graces,</l>
                     <l>Euery good deed ſends backe it's owne rewards,</l>
                     <l>Into the boſome of the enterprizer;</l>
                     <l>But you to expreſſe your ſelfe as well to be</l>
                     <l>King of munificency, as integrity</l>
                     <l>Addes glory to the gift.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thy deſerts clayme it,</l>
                     <l>Zeale and fidelity appeare, thou beauty</l>
                     <l>Of truth and innocence, beſt ornament</l>
                     <l>Of patience, thou that mad'ſt thy ſufferings glorious</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. .Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ile take no knowledg on't what makes ſhe here?</l>
                     <l>How dare you pawne vnpennanc't with a cheeke</l>
                     <l>Freſh as her falſe-hood yet, where caſtigation</l>
                     <l>Has left no pale print of her viſiting anguiſh,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:21"/>Appeare in this aſſembly, let me alone,</l>
                     <l>Sinne muſt be bold, that's all the grace 'tis bound too.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>What's this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>I'me wonder ſtrocke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Aſſiſt me goodneſſe,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall to priſon againe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>At leaſt I'ue maz'd em,</l>
                     <l>Scattered by admiration of her innocence,</l>
                     <l>(As the fir'd ſhips put in, ſeuered the Fleete</l>
                     <l>In eighty eight) Ile on with't, impudence</l>
                     <l>Is miſchiefes patrimony, is his Iuſtice</l>
                     <l>Iniured reuerence no ſharplier righted,</l>
                     <l>I euer held that Maieſty impartiall,</l>
                     <l>That like vnequall, Heauen lookes on the manners,</l>
                     <l>Not on the ſhapes they ſhrowde in.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This blacke Knight</l>
                     <l>Will neuer take any anſwere, 'tis a victory</l>
                     <l>To make him vnderſtand, he does amiſſe,</l>
                     <l>When he knowes in his owne cleare vnderſtanding,</l>
                     <l>That he does nothing elſe, ſhew him the teſtimony</l>
                     <l>Confirmed by good men, how that foule attempter,</l>
                     <l>Got but this morning to the place from whence</l>
                     <l>He dated his forged lines ſix daies paſt,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why may not the corruption ſleep in this,</l>
                     <l>By ſome connivence, as you haue walkt in ours,</l>
                     <l>By too raſh confidence.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. D.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ile vndertake</l>
                     <l>That Knight ſhall teach the diuell how to lye.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If ſinne were halfe ſo wiſe as impudent,</l>
                     <l>She'de neere ſeek father for an aduocate. <stage>En. B. Q. p.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now to act treachery with an angels tong,</l>
                     <l>Since all ours come out, ile bring him in ſtrongly agen,</l>
                     <l>Where is his iniur'd chaſtity? this goodneſſe</l>
                     <l>Whoſe worth no tranſitory prize can equall,</l>
                     <l>This rocke of conſtant, and invinceable vertue</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:21"/>That made ſinnes tempeſt weary of his fury.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q.</speaker>
                  <p>What is my pawne deſtracted?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I thinke rather</l>
                     <l>Ther's ſome notable Maiſter-prize of rogary,</l>
                     <l>This drum ſtrikes vp for.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let me fall downe with reuerence</l>
                     <l>Before this bleſſed Altar.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B Q.</speaker>
                  <p>This is madneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Marke the end, I ſtand for rogery ſtil,</l>
                     <l>I will not change my ſide,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ſhall be tax'd I know</l>
                     <l>I care not what the blacke houſe thinks of me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſay you now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not be vnlayed yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Q. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How euer ſenſure flies, I honor ſanctity,</l>
                     <l>That is my obiect I intend no other,</l>
                     <l>I ſaw this glorious and moſt valiant vertue,</l>
                     <l>Fight the moſt noble combat with the diuell.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Q.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If both the Biſhops had bin there for ſeconds</l>
                     <l>T'ad beene a compleate Diuell.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>Then thou haſt heard the violence intended?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tis a truth, I ioy to iuſtifie I was an agent</l>
                     <l>On vertues part, and rayſ'd that confuſed noyſe,</l>
                     <l>That ſtarted his attempt and gaue her liberty.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh 'tis a righteous ſtory ſhe has told (Sir)</l>
                     <l>My life and ſame ſtands mutually ingaged,</l>
                     <l>Both to the truth and goodneſſe of this pawne.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>Does it appeare to you, yet cleare as the Sun.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Laſſe I beleeued it long before 'twas done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>Degenerate</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Q.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Baſe,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Perfidious.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. D.</speaker>
                  <p>Trayterous pawne</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p,</speaker>
                  <p>What are you al beſides your ſelues?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>But I remember that pawne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:22"/>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>May a fearefull barrenneſſe,</l>
                     <l>Blaſt both my hopes and pleaſures, if I brought not</l>
                     <l>Her ruine in my pitty, a new trap</l>
                     <l>For her more ſure confuſion.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Haue I not wonne now,</l>
                     <l>Did not I ſay 'twas craft, and machination?</l>
                     <l>I ſmell conſpiracie all the way I went,</l>
                     <l>Although the meſſe were couered I'me ſo vſ'd to't.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>That queene would I faine finger.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You are too haſty (ſir)</l>
                     <l>If ſhe were took the game would be ours quickly,</l>
                     <l>My aymes at that white Knight, t'entrap him firſt.</l>
                     <l>The Duke will follow too.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Would that Biſhop were in my Dioceſſe,</l>
                     <l>I'de ſoone change his whiteneſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>(Sir) I could whip you vp a pawne imediatly,</l>
                     <l>I know where my game ſtands.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Do't ſuddainly,</l>
                     <l>Aduantage leaſt muſt not be loſt in this play.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Pawne, thou art ours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hee's taken by default,</l>
                     <l>By wilfull negligence, gard the ſacred perſons,</l>
                     <l>Looke well to the white Biſhop, for that pawne</l>
                     <l>Gaue guard to the queene, and him in the third place.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>See what ſure peece you locke your confidence in,</l>
                     <l>I made this pawne heere by corruption ours,</l>
                     <l>As ſoone as honour by creation yours,</l>
                     <l>The whiteneſſe vpon him is but the leaproſy</l>
                     <l>Of pure diſſemulation: view him now,</l>
                     <l>His heart and his intents are of our colour.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>His vpper garment being taken off, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares blacke vnder.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt dangerous Hypocrite</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. D.</speaker>
                  <p>One made againſt vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. <hi>Q.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>This truth of his complection.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Has my goodneeſſe,</l>
                     <l>Clemency, loue, and fauour gracious rayſ'd thee</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:22"/>From a condition next to popular labour,</l>
                     <l>Tooke thee from all the dublitable hazards</l>
                     <l>Of Fortune? her moſt vnſecure aduentures?</l>
                     <l>And grafted thee into a branch of honour,</l>
                     <l>And doſt thou fal from the top bough by the rottennes</l>
                     <l>Of thy alone corruption, like a fruite</l>
                     <l>That's ouer-ripned by the beames of fauour,</l>
                     <l>Let thy owne weight reward thee, I haue forgot thee,</l>
                     <l>Integrity of life is ſo deare to me,</l>
                     <l>Where I finde falſhood, or a crying treſpaſſe,</l>
                     <l>Be it in any whom our grace ſhines moſt on,</l>
                     <l>I'de teare em from my heart.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Spoke like Heauens ſubſtitute.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You haue him, we can ſpare him, and his ſhame</l>
                     <l>Will make the reſt looke better to their Game.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>(B. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>The more cunning we muſt vſe then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wee ſhall match you,</l>
                     <l>Play how you can) perhaps, and make you too.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Is there ſo much amazement ſpent on him</l>
                     <l>That's but halfe black, there might be hope of that man</l>
                     <l>But how will this houſe wonder, if I ſtand forth</l>
                     <l>And ſhew a whole one, inſtantly diſcouer</l>
                     <l>One that's all blacke, where ther's no hope at all.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ile ſay, thy heart then iuſtifies thy bookes,</l>
                     <l>I long for thy diſcouery.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Looke no farther then,</l>
                     <l>Beare witneſſe all the houſe I am the man,</l>
                     <l>And turne my ſelfe into the blacke houſe freely,</l>
                     <l>I am of this ſide now.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. K.</speaker>
                  <p>Monſter neere matcht him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>This is your noble worke Knight.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Now Ile halter him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Next newes you heare, expect my bookes againſt you,</l>
                     <l>Printed at <hi>Doway, Bruxells,</hi> or <hi>Spallato.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>See his goods ſeaz'd on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:23"/>
                  <speaker>F. R.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Laſſe, they were all conueyed</l>
                     <l>Laſt night by water-gate, to a Taylors houſe:</l>
                     <l>A friend of Blacke houſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>A prepared Hypocrite.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. D.</speaker>
                  <p>Premeditated tuene-coate.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>F.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yes, rayle on,</l>
                     <l>Ile reach you in my writings when I'me gone.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Flatter him a while with honors til we put him</l>
                     <l>Vpon ſome dangerous ſeruice, and then burne him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>This came vnlookt for.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. D.</speaker>
                  <p>How wee reioyce to ſee you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>F.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <p>Now ile diſcouer all the white houſe to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. D.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed that will both reconcile and prayſe you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <p>I reſt vpon you knight for my aduancement.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh for the ſtaffe, the ſtrong ſtaffe that wil hold</l>
                     <l>And the red hat fit for the guilty mazure,</l>
                     <l>Into the empty bagge, know the firſt way,</l>
                     <l>Pawnes that are loſt, are euer out of play.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. K. p.</speaker>
                  <p>How's this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No replication you know me,</l>
                     <l>No doubt e're long you'le haue more company.</l>
                     <l>The bagge is big enough t'wil hold v<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ſue to thee, prethee be one of vs</l>
                     <l>Let my loue winne thee, thou haſt done truth this day,</l>
                     <l>And yeſterday my honor noble ſeruice.</l>
                     <l>The beſt Pawne of our houſe, could tranſcend it not.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My pitty ſtands with zeale eſpecially,</l>
                     <l>When I foreſaw your marriage, then I amounted.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>How? marriage?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That contaminating Art,</l>
                     <l>Would haue ſpoild al our fortunes a rape God bleſſe vs.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou talkſt of marriage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yes, yes, you do marry,</l>
                     <l>I ſaw the man.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>The man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:23"/>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>An abſolute handſome Gentleman, a compleat one,</l>
                     <l>You'de ſay ſo when you ſee him, heire to the three red hats,</l>
                     <l>Beſides his generall hopes in the blacke houſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sure thou art miſtaken, for this man</l>
                     <l>I haue promiſt ſingle life to all my affections.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Promiſe you what you will, or I, or all's one,</l>
                     <l>There's fate rules vs, and ouer rules vs all me thinkes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>How came you to ſee or know this miſtery.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A Magicall glaſſe I bought of an Egyptian,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſtone retaines that ſpeculatiue vertue,</l>
                     <l>Preſented the man to me, your name brings him</l>
                     <l>As often as I vſe it, and me thinkes</l>
                     <l>I neuer haue enough perſon and poſtures:</l>
                     <l>Are all ſo pleaſing.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This is wondrous ſtrange,</l>
                     <l>The faculties of ſoule are ſtill the ſame,</l>
                     <l>I cannot feele one motion tend that way.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Q. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>We do not alwayes ſeeke, the faith we liue by,</l>
                     <l>Nor euer ſee our growth, yet both worke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vpward.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>It was well applied, but may I ſee him too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Surely you may without all doubt or feare,</l>
                     <l>Obſeruing the right vſe as I was taught it,</l>
                     <l>Not looking backe, nor queſtioning the ſpecter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That's no hard obſeruation, truſt it</l>
                     <l>With me, is't poſſible, I long to ſee this man.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pray follow me then,</l>
                     <l>And Ile caſe you inſtantly.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter blacke Ieſting Pawne.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. I. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I would ſo faine take one of theſe white pawnes now.</l>
                     <l>I'de make him do all vnder drudgery,</l>
                     <l>Feede him with aſhes, milke, cromb'd with Goates cheeſe;</l>
                     <l>And all the white meates can be deuiſed for him,</l>
                     <l>So make him my white Iennet when I prance it,</l>
                     <l>After the blacke Knights litter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You'd looke then,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:24"/>Iuſt like the Diuell ſtriding ouer a night mare.</l>
                     <l>Made of a Millers daughter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A pox on you, were you ſo nigh, I'me taken</l>
                     <l>Like a Blacke-bird in the great ſnow, this white</l>
                     <l>Pawne grinning ouer me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And now becauſe I will not foule my clothes</l>
                     <l>Euer hereafter? for white quickly ſoyles you know.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I prethe get thee gone,</l>
                     <l>Then I ſhall ſmut thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ile put that to venture, now I haue</l>
                     <l>Snapt thee, thou ſhalt do all the durty drugery,</l>
                     <l>That ſlauery was euer put too.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ſhall couſen you,</l>
                     <l>You may chance come and finde your worke vndone,</l>
                     <l>For I'me too proud to labour, ile ſtarue firſt,</l>
                     <l>I tell you that before hand.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I will fit you then with a blacke</l>
                     <l>Whip, that ſhall not be behind hand.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. p</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Piſh, I haue beene vſed to whipping,</l>
                     <l>I haue whipt my ſelfe three miles out of Towne</l>
                     <l>In a morning, I can faſt a fortnight, and</l>
                     <l>Make all your meate ſtinke, and lye vpon your hands.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To preuent that, your foode ſhall be</l>
                     <l>Blacke berries, and vpon gaudy daies a pickled</l>
                     <l>Spider cut out like Anchouis: Ime not to</l>
                     <l>Learne a monthes ordinary, come fir, will you firke.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>En. a ſecond blacke pawne</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Soft, ſoft you, you haue no ſuch</l>
                     <l>Bargaine on't, if you looke well about you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I'me ſnapt too, a blacke</l>
                     <l>Pawne in the breech of me:</l>
                     <l>Wee three looke like a bird ſpit, a white Chick</l>
                     <l>Betweene two ruſſet Wood-cockes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. p.</speaker>
                  <p>I'me glad of this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. p.</speaker>
                  <p>But you ſhal haue ſmal cauſe, for ile firke you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>And ile firke you agen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:24"/>
                  <speaker>W. p.</speaker>
                  <p>And Ile firke you againe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Mas here will be old firking, I ſhall</l>
                     <l>Haue the worſt on't, for I can firke no body,</l>
                     <l>Wee draw together now for all the world.</l>
                     <l>Like three flies with one ſtraw throgh their buttocks.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter blacke Q. p. and White Q. p.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This is the roome he did appeare to me in,</l>
                     <l>And looke you, this the Magicall glaſſe, that ſhew'd him.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I finde no motion yet, what ſhould I</l>
                     <l>Thinke on't? a ſuddaine feare inuades me,</l>
                     <l>A faint trembling vnder this omen</l>
                     <l>As oft felt the panting of a Turtle,</l>
                     <l>Vnder a ſtroaking hand.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That boads good lucke ſtill,</l>
                     <l>Signe you ſhall chang ſtate ſpeedily: for that trembling</l>
                     <l>Is alwayes the firſt ſymptome of a bride,</l>
                     <l>For any vaine feares that may accompany</l>
                     <l>His apparitian, by my truth to friendſhip</l>
                     <l>I quite you of the leaſt, neuer was obiect</l>
                     <l>More gracefully preſented, the very ayre</l>
                     <l>Conſpires to do him honor, and treats</l>
                     <l>Sweet vocall ſinne as if a bride-groome enters:</l>
                     <l>Which argues the bieſt harmony of your loues.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W p.</speaker>
                  <p>And will the vſing of my name produce him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nay of yours only, els the wonder halted,</l>
                     <l>To cleare you of that doubt: ile put the difference</l>
                     <l>In practiſe, the firſt thing I do, and make</l>
                     <l>His inuocation in the name of others.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q p.</speaker>
                  <p>That will ſatiſfie me much.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It ſhall be done.</l>
                     <l>Thou with gentle forme and face,</l>
                     <l>Fil'd lately this Egypted Glaſſe,</l>
                     <l>By th'emperious powerfull name,</l>
                     <l>And the Vninerſall fame,</l>
                     <l>Of the mighty blacke Houſe Queene</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:25"/>I coniure thee to be ſeene.</l>
                     <l>What ſee you nothing yet?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Not any part: Pray try another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You ſhall haue your will:</l>
                     <l>I double my commaund and power,</l>
                     <l>And at the inſtant of this houre:</l>
                     <l>Invoke thee in the white queenes name,</l>
                     <l>VVith ſtay for time, and ſhape the ſame.</l>
                     <l>What ſee you yet?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>There's nothing ſhewes at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My truth reflects the clearer.</l>
                     <l>Then now fix and bleſſe your fayre eye,</l>
                     <l>With your owne for euer.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou well compoſ'd by fates hand drawne,</l>
                     <l>To enioy the white Queenes Pawne,</l>
                     <l>Of whom thou ſhalt (by vertue meete)</l>
                     <l>Many gracefull iſſues get:</l>
                     <l>By the beauty of her fame,</l>
                     <l>By the whiteneſſe of her name,</l>
                     <l>By her faire and fruitfull loue,</l>
                     <l>By her truth that mates the Doue,</l>
                     <l>By the meekneſſe of her minde,</l>
                     <l>By the ſoftneſſe of her kinde,</l>
                     <l>By the luſture of her grace,</l>
                     <l>By al theſe thou'rt ſummond to this place.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Harke how the ayre inchanted with your prayſes,</l>
                     <l>And his approach this words to ſweet notes rayſes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>En. b. <hi>B.</hi> p. in rich attire like an Apari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, &amp; ſtands before the glaſſe then Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh let him ſtay a while, a little longer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>That's a good hearing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q p</speaker>
                  <p>If he be mine, why ſhold he part ſo ſoone?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why, this is but the ſhadow of yours:</l>
                     <l>How do you?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh, I did in to giue conſent to ſee it,</l>
                     <l>What certainty is in our bloods our ſtates?</l>
                     <l>What we ſtill write is blotted out by fates:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:25"/>Our wills are like a cauſe that is Law-toſt,</l>
                     <l>What one Court orders, is by another-croſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I find no fit place for this paſſion here,</l>
                     <l>Tis meerely an intruder, he is a Gentleman,</l>
                     <l>Moſt wiſhfully compoſed, honor growes on him,</l>
                     <l>And wealth pil'd vp for him, has youth enough too,</l>
                     <l>And yet in the ſobriety of his Countenance,</l>
                     <l>Graue as a Tetrach, which is gracious</l>
                     <l>Ith'eye of modeſt pleaſure, where's the emptineſſe,</l>
                     <l>What can you more requeſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I do not know</l>
                     <l>What anſwere yet to make, it doth require,</l>
                     <l>A meeting 'twixt my feare and my deſire.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Shee's caught, and which is ſtrong, by her moſt wronger.</p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>Finit Actus Tertius.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>Incipit Quartus.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Blacke Knights Pawne,</hi> and <hi>Blacke Biſhops</hi> Pawne.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. P.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THE Ieſuit in his gallant habit,</l>
                     <l>Tis he my Confeſſor, he might haue paſſ'd me</l>
                     <l>Seauen yeares together, had I not by chance</l>
                     <l>Aduanc'd mine eye vpon that lettered Hat bond:</l>
                     <l>The Ieſuiticall ſymbale to be worne,</l>
                     <l>By the braue Colledgians with conſent,</l>
                     <l>Tis a ſtrange habit for a holy Father,</l>
                     <l>A preſident of pouerty eſpecially:</l>
                     <l>But wee the ſonnes and daughters of Obedience,</l>
                     <l>Dare not once think awry, but muſt confeſſe our ſelues</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:26"/>As humble to the father of that feather,</l>
                     <l>Long ſpeare and ponyard, as to the Abbey and Alter,</l>
                     <l>And happy we are ſo highly grac'd t'attaine to't,</l>
                     <l>Holy and reuerend.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>How has found me out?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh (ſir) put on the ſparlingſt trim of glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Perfection will ſhine for moſt, and I know you</l>
                     <l>By the Catholicall marke you weare about you,</l>
                     <l>The marke aboue your fore-head.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Are you growne</l>
                     <l>So ambitious in your obſeruance: well, your buſineſſe,</l>
                     <l>I haue my Game to follow.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I haue a worme</l>
                     <l>Followes me, ſo that I can follow no game,</l>
                     <l>The moſt faint hearted pawne, if hee could ſee</l>
                     <l>His play, might ſnap me vp at pleaſure:</l>
                     <l>I deſire (ſir) to be abſolued, my conſcience</l>
                     <l>Being at eaſe, I could then with more courage</l>
                     <l>Play my Game.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>'Twas a baſe fact.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <p>'Twas to a Schiſamticke pawne (ſir.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What's that to the ability of reuenge</l>
                     <l>Suffices I haue neither will nor power</l>
                     <l>To giue you abſolution for that violence,</l>
                     <l>Make your petition to the penance Chamber,</l>
                     <l>If the Taxe Regeſter relieue you in't,</l>
                     <l>By the blacke biſhops clemency you hau'wrought out,</l>
                     <l>A ſingle peece of fauour with your money,</l>
                     <l>It's all your refuge now.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>En. w. Q. and b. Q. p.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <p>This ſting ſhootes deeper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yonder's my Game, which like apoletick Cheſſner,</l>
                     <l>I muſt not ſeeme to ſee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh my heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>That 'tis.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The very ſame that the Magicall</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:26"/>Preſented lately vnto me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Aud how like</l>
                     <l>A moſt regardleſſe ſtranger hee walkes by,</l>
                     <l>Meerely ignorant of that ſate, you are not indeede</l>
                     <l>The principall'ſt part of him, what ſtrange miſteries</l>
                     <l>Inſcrutable loue workes by.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The time you ſee,</l>
                     <l>Is not yet come.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But 'tis in our power now</l>
                     <l>To bring time neerer, knowledge is a maſtery,</l>
                     <l>And make it obſerue vs, and not wee it</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I would force nothing</l>
                     <l>From it's proper vertue,</l>
                     <l>Let time haue his full courſe. I'de rather die</l>
                     <l>The modeſt death of vndiſcouered loue,</l>
                     <l>You haue heau'ns leaft and loweſt ſeruant ſuffer,</l>
                     <l>Or in his motion receiue checke for me:</l>
                     <l>How is my ſoules growth altar'd that ſingle life,</l>
                     <l>The fitteſt garment that peace ere made for't</l>
                     <l>Is growne too ſtreight, too ſtubborn on the ſuddain.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Hee comes this way agen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh here's a Traytor</l>
                     <l>Leapt from my heart into my cheeke all ready.</l>
                     <l>That will betray all to his powerfull eye,</l>
                     <l>If it but glance vpon me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By my verity</l>
                     <l>Looke, he's paſt by agen, downe in neglect</l>
                     <l>Without the proſperous hin't of ſo much happines</l>
                     <l>To looke vpon his forrude, how cloſe fate</l>
                     <l>Seales vp the eye of humaine vnderſtanding,</l>
                     <l>Till like the Sunnes flower, time and loue incloſes it,</l>
                     <l>'Tis pitty he ſhould dwell in ignorance longer.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>What will you do?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yes, dye a baſh full death, doe</l>
                     <l>And let the remedy paſſe by vnuſ'd skill,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:27"/>You're chayn'd enough all ready, looke into't,</l>
                     <l>Abſolute (Sir) with your moſt noble pardon,</l>
                     <l>For this my rude intruſion I am bold</l>
                     <l>To bring the knowledge of a ſecret neerer,</l>
                     <l>By many daies (ſir) then would it arriue,</l>
                     <l>In its owne proper reuelation with you,</l>
                     <l>Pray turne and fix, do you know yon'd noble goodnes,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tis the firſt minute my eye bleſt me with her,</l>
                     <l>And clearely ſhews how much my knowledg wanted,</l>
                     <l>Not knowing her till now.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>She's to be lik'd then,</l>
                     <l>Pray view aduiſedly, there's ſtrong reaſon,</l>
                     <l>That I'me ſo bold to vrge it, you muſt gueſſe</l>
                     <l>The worke concernes you neerer then you thinke for.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Her glory and the wonder of this ſecret,</l>
                     <l>Puts a recipicall amazement on me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And tis not without worth,</l>
                     <l>You two muſt be better acquainted.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Is their cauſe affinity,</l>
                     <l>Or any couetous helpe creation ioyes in,</l>
                     <l>To bring that worke forward.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yes, yes, I can ſhew you,</l>
                     <l>The neereſt way to that perfection,</l>
                     <l>Of a moſt vertuous one, that ioy ere found,</l>
                     <l>Pray marke her once agen you follow me,</l>
                     <l>And I will ſhew you her, muſt be your wife (ſir.)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The miſtery exceeds, or elſe creation,</l>
                     <l>Has ſet that admirable peece before vs,</l>
                     <l>To chuſe out chaſte delight by.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Pleaſe you follow (Sir.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What heart haue you to put in on one obiect,</l>
                     <l>And cannot get me off? tis paine to part from't.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If there proue no check in the Magick-glaſſe.</l>
                     <l>But by proportion come as faire, and full</l>
                     <l>Into his eyes as his into mine lately,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:27"/>You I'me confirmed he is mine for euer.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter agen B. B. p.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The very ſelfe ſame that my mirror bleſt me, with</l>
                     <l>From head to foote, the beauty and the habit,</l>
                     <l>Kept you this place? ſtill did not you remooue Lady.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Not a foote (ſir.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Is't poſſible,</l>
                     <l>I would haue ſworne I'de ſeene the ſubſtance yonder,</l>
                     <l>'T was to that luſtre, to that life preſented.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen ſo was yours to me (ſir.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Pawne, ſaw you mine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Perfectly cleare, no</l>
                     <l>Sooner my name vſed, but yours appeared.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Iuſt ſo did yours at mine now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Q. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why ſtand you idle, will you let time</l>
                     <l>Couſen you, (protracting time) of thoſe</l>
                     <l>Delicious benefits, that faith marked to you,</l>
                     <l>You modeſt paire of bluſhing,</l>
                     <l>Gameſters, and you (Sir) the baſhfull</l>
                     <l>I cannot flatter a foule fault in any,</l>
                     <l>Can you be more then man and wife aſſigne,</l>
                     <l>And by a power the moſt irreuocable,</l>
                     <l>Others that be adventurers in delight,</l>
                     <l>May meete with croſſes, ſhame or ſeperation</l>
                     <l>You know the mind of fate, you muſt be coupled.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Shee ſpeakes but truth in this,</l>
                     <l>I ſee no reaſon then,</l>
                     <l>That wee ſhould miſſe the relliſh of this night;</l>
                     <l>But wee are both ſhame-fac't.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How this night (Sir)</l>
                     <l>Did not I know you muſt be mine, and therein</l>
                     <l>Your priuiledge runnes ſtrong, for that looſe motion</l>
                     <l>You neuer ſhould be, is it not by fortune</l>
                     <l>To match with a pure minde, then am I miſerable,</l>
                     <l>The Doues and all chaſt louing, winged creatures</l>
                     <l>Haue their paires fit, their deſires iuſtly</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:28"/>Mated is woman, more infortunate, virgin?</l>
                     <l>The (may of woman) fate has ordayned (Sir)</l>
                     <l>We ſhould be man and wife, has not giuen</l>
                     <l>Warrant for ayme act of knowledge till</l>
                     <l>We are ſo.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tender ey'd modeſty, how it grieues at this,</l>
                     <l>I'me as farre off for all this, ſtrange impoſture,</l>
                     <l>As at firſt enter-view, where lies our game now?</l>
                     <l>You know I cannot marry by my order.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know you cannot (ſir) yet you</l>
                     <l>May venture on a contract.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Hah!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Q. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sure you may (ſir,)</l>
                     <l>Without all queſtion ſo farre, without danger</l>
                     <l>Or any ſtaine to your vow, and that make take her:</l>
                     <l>Nay do't with ſpeede, ſheele thinke you</l>
                     <l>Meane the better too.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Be not ſo lauiſh of that bleſſed ſpring,</l>
                     <l>You'ue waſted that vpon a cold occaſion now,</l>
                     <l>Would waſh a ſinfull ſoule white by our loue ioyes,</l>
                     <l>That motion ſhall neere light vpon my tongue more,</l>
                     <l>Till we're contracted, then I hope your mine.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>In all iuſt duty euer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then doe you queſtion it?</l>
                     <l>Piſh, then you're man and wife,</l>
                     <l>All but Church Ceremonies:</l>
                     <l>Pray let's ſee it done firſt,</l>
                     <l>She ſhall do reaſon then:</l>
                     <l>Now ile enioy the ſport, and couſen you both,</l>
                     <l>My bloods game is the wages I haue</l>
                     <l>Workt for.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exe.</stage>
               <stage>Enter blacke Knight and his pawne.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pawne, I haue ſpoke to the Fat biſhop for thee,</l>
                     <l>Ile get thy abſolution from his owne mouth:</l>
                     <l>Reach me my Chayre of eaſe, my Chaire of couſonage</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:28"/>Seauen thouſand pounds in women, reach me that</l>
                     <l>I loue a life to ſit vppon a banke</l>
                     <l>Of Heretique gold: Oh ſoft and gentle (ſirrah)</l>
                     <l>Ther's a foule flaw i'th bottom of my bum (pawne)</l>
                     <l>I neere ſhall make ſound ſouldier, but ſound treacher</l>
                     <l>With any hee in <hi>Europe,</hi> how now? quality</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt the paultreſt foole that ere I met with,</l>
                     <l>It cannot beare one ſuckling villaine:</l>
                     <l>Mine can digeſt a monſter without credit,</l>
                     <l>A finne as weighty as an Elephant,</l>
                     <l>And neuer wamble for't.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I, you haue beene vſ'd to't (ſir)</l>
                     <l>That's a great helpe, the ſwallow of my conſcience</l>
                     <l>Has but a narrow paſſage, you muſt thinke yet</l>
                     <l>It lyes i'th paenitent pipe, and will not downe,</l>
                     <l>If I had got ſeauen thouſand pounds by Offices</l>
                     <l>And guld downe you, the bore would haue bin bigger.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nay, an thou prou'ſt factious, I ſhall hug thee,</l>
                     <l>Can a poore-pocht-ſoft reare iniquity</l>
                     <l>So rude vpon thy conſcience, I'me aſham'd of thee,</l>
                     <l>Hadſt thou betrayed the witneſſe to the blacke,</l>
                     <l>Beggard a Kingdome by diſſimulation,</l>
                     <l>Vnioynted the faire frame of peace, and trafficke</l>
                     <l>Poyſon'd alleagance, ſet faith backe and wrought</l>
                     <l>Weomens ſoft ſoules euen vp to the maſculine malice,</l>
                     <l>To purſue truth to death if the cauſe rowz'd em,</l>
                     <l>That ſtaires and parets as firſt taught to curſe thee:</l>
                     <l>All theſe and ten times troubled has this braine</l>
                     <l>Bin parent too, they are my off-ſprings all.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <p>A goodly broode.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet I can jeſt as lightly,</l>
                     <l>Laugh and tell ſtrange ſtories to Court Madames,</l>
                     <l>(Daughters of myſeducements) with alacrity,</l>
                     <l>As high and heartily, as youths time of innocence</l>
                     <l>That neuer knew a ſinne, to ſhapea ſorrow by;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:29"/>I feele no tempeſt, not a leafe winde ſtirring,</l>
                     <l>To ſhake a fault, my conſcience is be calm'd rather,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <p>I'me ſure there's a Whirle-winde huffes in mine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sirrah, I ha ſold the Groome ath ſtoole ſix times,</l>
                     <l>And receiued money of ſix ſeuerall Ladies:</l>
                     <l>Ambitious to take place of <hi>Baronets</hi> wiues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>To three old money Matrons I haue promiſ'd,</l>
                     <l>The mother ſhip oth maydes, I'ue taught our friends</l>
                     <l>To conueigh white houſe gold, to our blacke kingdom</l>
                     <l>In cold backt paſties, ſo couſen Searchers:</l>
                     <l>For venting halbow'd oyle, beades, needles, pardons,</l>
                     <l>Pictures, veronices, heads in priuate preſſes,</l>
                     <l>That's done one i'th habit of a Pedler:</l>
                     <l>Letters convaied in roles, Tobaco-roles:</l>
                     <l>When a reſtraint comes, by my politicke counſell;</l>
                     <l>Some of our Ieſuites turne Gentle-men Vſhers:</l>
                     <l>Some Falkners, ſome park-keeper, &amp; ſome huntſ-men:</l>
                     <l>One tooke the ſhape of an old Ladies Cooke once,</l>
                     <l>And diſpatcht two chares in a ſunday morning,</l>
                     <l>The Altar and the Dreſſer: pray what vſe</l>
                     <l>Put I my ſummer recreation too?</l>
                     <l>But more t'enforme my knowledge in the ſtate</l>
                     <l>And ſtrength of the white Kingdome? no fortifications,</l>
                     <l>Hauen, Creeke, landing place, 'bout the white Coaſt,</l>
                     <l>But I got draught, and plot-forme, learn'd the depth</l>
                     <l>Of all the Channels, knowledge of all ſands,</l>
                     <l>Shelues, Rockes and Riuers for invaſion:</l>
                     <l>A Catalogue of all the Nauy Royall:</l>
                     <l>The burthen of each ſhippe, the braſſe murtherers:</l>
                     <l>The number of the men, to what cape bound:</l>
                     <l>Agen for the diſcouery of the Inlands:</l>
                     <l>Neuer a Shire but the State better knowne</l>
                     <l>To me, then to her beſt Inhabitants:</l>
                     <l>What power of men and horſe, gentries, reuenewes,</l>
                     <l>Who well affected to your ſide, how ill,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:29"/>Who neither will nor ill, all the new trality.</l>
                     <l>Thirty eight ſoules haue beene ſeduced (Pawne)</l>
                     <l>Since the Ioales vomited with the Pill I gaue 'em.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure you put oyle of toad into phyſick (ſir)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I'me now about a maiſter-peece of play,</l>
                     <l>To entrap the Wh. Knight, and with falſe alurements,</l>
                     <l>Entice him to our blacke Houſe, more will follow,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt our Fat Biſhop ſets vpon the Queene</l>
                     <l>Then will our game lye ſweetly.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Fat Biſhop.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Hee's come now (ſir.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Heer's <hi>Taxa Penitentiaris</hi> Knight,</l>
                     <l>The booke of generall pardons, of all prizes:</l>
                     <l>I haue bin ſearching for his ſinne this halfe houre,</l>
                     <l>And cannot light vpon it.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>That is ſtrange let me ſee it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wretched as I am, has my rage done that</l>
                     <l>There is no preſident of pardon for?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For wilfull murther 13. pounds, 4. ſhillings</l>
                     <l>and ſixe-pence, that's reaſonable cheape, for killing,</l>
                     <l>killing, killing, killing, killing, killing.</l>
                     <l>Why heer's nothing but killing of this ſide.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>F.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Turne ore the ſheete, you ſhall finde adultery</l>
                     <l>And other triuiall ſinnes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Adultery, oh I'me met now; for Adultery</l>
                     <l>A couple of ſhillings, and for Fornication fiue pence,</l>
                     <l>Mas theſe are the good penny-worths,</l>
                     <l>I cannot ſee how a man can mend himſelfe, for lying</l>
                     <l>With Mother, Siſter, or Daughter, I marry (ſir)</l>
                     <l>Thirty three pounds, three ſhillings and three pence,</l>
                     <l>The ſins gradation right payd all in three too.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You haue read the ſtory of that monſter (ſir)</l>
                     <l>That got his daughter, ſiſter &amp; wife, of his own mother</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Symone nine pounds.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>F.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They may thank me for that, 'twas ninteene,</l>
                     <l>Before I came, I haue mittigated many of the ſumms.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:30"/>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sodomy ſixe pence, you ſhould haue</l>
                     <l>Put that ſumme euer on the back ſide of your booke</l>
                     <l>Biſhop.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Ther's few on's very forward (ſir)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>What's heere? a old preſidents of incouragment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <p>I thoſe are ancient notes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Giuen as a gratitud for the kiling of an Heretical</l>
                     <l>Prince, with a poyſond knife duckats 5 thouſand.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>True (ſir) that was payed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Promis'd to Doctor <hi>Lopus</hi> for poyſoning the Mayden Queene of the Whit Kingdom, ducats twenty thouſand, which ſayd ſum was afterwards giuen as a meritorious almes to the Nunnery at <hi>Lisbone,</hi> hauing at this preſent, ten thouſand pounds more at vſe in the Towne-houſe of <hi>Antwerp.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What's all this to my conſcience (worthy Holineſſe)</l>
                     <l>I ſue for pardon, I haue brought mony with me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You muſt depart, you ſee there is no preſident,</l>
                     <l>Of any price or pardon for that fact.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>K. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Moſt miſerable, are fouler ſinnes remitted?</l>
                     <l>Killing, nay wilfull murder.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>True, there is inſtance:</l>
                     <l>Were you to kill him I'de pardon you:</l>
                     <l>Ther's preſident for that, and price ſet downe,</l>
                     <l>But none for <hi>Gelding.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I haue pickt out vnderſtanding now for euer,</l>
                     <l>Out of the Carbuliſtique bloody ridle,</l>
                     <l>I'le make away all my eſtate and kill him,</l>
                     <l>And by that act obtaine full abſolution.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter the Black King.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why Biſhop, Knight, wher's your remooues?</l>
                     <l>Your troopes? ſtand you now idle in the heart of game?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My life for yours black ſoueraigne the game is ours,</l>
                     <l>I haue wrought vnder-hand for the Whit Knight,</l>
                     <l>And this braue Duke, and finde them very cunning</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:30"/>
                  <speaker>F. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And for their Sanctimonius Queen's ſurprizall,</l>
                     <l>In that State-puzell, and diſtracted hurry,</l>
                     <l>Truſt my <hi>Arch</hi> ſubtilty with.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh Eagle pride,</l>
                     <l>Neuer was Game more hopefull of our ſide.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If Biſhop bul-beife, be not ſnapt at next bout,</l>
                     <l>As the Game ſtands, I'le neuer truſt arte more.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt</stage>
               <stage>Recorder. Dumb ſhew. Enter Blacke Queenes Pawne with a light, conducting the White Queenes Pawne to a Chamber, and fetching in the Blacke Biſhops Pawne conueyes him to an other, puts out the light, and followes. Enter Whit Knight, and White Duke.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>True noble Duke, faire vertues moſt indeer'd one,</l>
                     <l>Let vs preuent their ranke inſinuation,</l>
                     <l>With truth of cauſe, and cunning meet their plots:</l>
                     <l>With confident goodnes, that ſhal ſtrike them grauling.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. D.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>(Sir) all the Gyns, traps, and alluring ſnares,</l>
                     <l>The Diuell ha's bin at worke ſince eighty eight,</l>
                     <l>Are layd for the great hope of this Game onely.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The more noble will Truths triumphs bee,</l>
                     <l>When they haue wound about our conſtant courages,</l>
                     <l>The glittering ſerpent, that e're falſe-hood faſhoned;</l>
                     <l>And glorying moſt, in his reſplendent poyſons,</l>
                     <l>Iuſt Heauen can finde a bolt to bruiſe his head.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. D.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Looke would ſee deſtruction lie a ſunning?</l>
                     <l>In yonder ſmile ſits blood, and treachery basking, <hi>Ent.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In that perfidious modell of face falſehood: <stage>B. <hi>Kt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hell is drawne grinning.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. K.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What a payne it is</l>
                     <l>For Truth to faine alittle?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh faire Knight,</l>
                     <l>The riſing glory of the Houſe of <hi>Candor,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Haue I ſo many protestations loſt?</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:31"/>Loſt, loſt, quite loſt, am I not worth your confidence?</l>
                     <l>I that haue voyed the faculties of Soule,</l>
                     <l>Life, ſpirit, and braine, to your ſweet Game of youth,</l>
                     <l>(Your noble fruitfull Game) can you miſtruſt</l>
                     <l>Any foule play in me? that haue bin euer</l>
                     <l>The moſt ſubmiſſe obſeruers of your vertues,</l>
                     <l>And no way taunted with ambition.</l>
                     <l>(Saue onely to be thought your firſt admirer,</l>
                     <l>How often haue I chang'd (for your delight)</l>
                     <l>The Royall Preſentation of my place?</l>
                     <l>Into a minicke Ieſter, and become</l>
                     <l>(For your ſake, and the expulſion of ſad thoughts)</l>
                     <l>Of a great ſtate ſice, a light ſonne of paſtime,</l>
                     <l>Made three ſcore yeare a Tomboy, a meere wanton,</l>
                     <l>Ile tell you what I told a (<hi>Sauoy</hi>) dame once:</l>
                     <l>New Wed, high, plumph, and luſting for an iſſue,</l>
                     <l>Within the yeare I promis'd her a childe,</l>
                     <l>If ſhe would ſtride ouer (Saint <hi>Rumbants</hi>) breeches,</l>
                     <l>A relique kept at <hi>Methlin,</hi> the next morning</l>
                     <l>One of my followers old hoſe was conueyed</l>
                     <l>Into her chamber, where ſhe tride the feate,</l>
                     <l>By that, and a Court friend, after grew great.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Why who could be without thee)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I will change,</l>
                     <l>To pleaſe you, to any ſhape, and my ayme</l>
                     <l>Has bin to win your loue, in all this game.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou haſt it nobly, and I long to ſee,</l>
                     <l>the <hi>Blacke-houſe</hi> pleaſure, ſtate and dignity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of honor you'le ſo ſurfet and delight,</l>
                     <l>You'le nere deſire agen to ſee the Whit.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Whit Queene.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My loue, my hope, my deereſt, oh he's gon,</l>
                     <l>Entrapt, enſnard, ſurpriſed amongſt the blacke on's,</l>
                     <l>I neuer felt extremity like this,</l>
                     <l>Thicke darkneſſe dwels vpon this houre, Integrity</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:31"/>Like one of Heauens bright Luminaries now,</l>
                     <l>By errors dulleſt element interpoſe,</l>
                     <l>Suffers a blacke ecclipſe, I neuer was</l>
                     <l>More ſicke of loue then now I am of horror:</l>
                     <l>I ſhalbe taken, the games loſt, I'me ſet vppon:</l>
                     <l>Oh tis the turne-coate Biſhop, hauing watched</l>
                     <l>Th'advantage of his play, comes now to ſeize on me:</l>
                     <l>Oh! I'me hard be ſet, diſtreſſed moſt miſerable.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tis in vaine to ſtirre, remooue which way you can:</l>
                     <l>I take you now, this is the time we haue hop'd for,</l>
                     <l>Queene you muſt downe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q.</speaker>
                  <p>No refcue, no deliuerer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>F.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The blacke Kings blood burnes for thy proſtitution,</l>
                     <l>And nothing but the ſpring of thy chaſt vertue</l>
                     <l>Can coole his inflamation: inſtantly</l>
                     <l>He dyes vpon a pluriſie of Luxury,</l>
                     <l>If he deflower thee not.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter white Biſhop.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh ſtreight of miſery.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>VV.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <p>And is your holineſſe his diuine procurer?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>F.</hi> B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The diuells in't, I'me taken by a Ring-doue:</l>
                     <l>VVhere ſtood this Biſhop all this while, that I ſaw him not?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh you were ſo ambitious you lookt ouer me,</l>
                     <l>You aym'd at no leſſe perſon, then the Queene</l>
                     <l>(The glory of the Game) if ſhe were wonne,</l>
                     <l>The way were open to the Maſter-Checque,</l>
                     <l>Which (looke you) he and his, liues to giue you:</l>
                     <l>Honor and vertue guide him in his ſtation.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ent. VV. King.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>W.</hi> Q.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, my ſafe ſanctuary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let Heauens bleſſings</l>
                     <l>Be no longer mine, then I am thy ſure one:</l>
                     <l>The Doues houſe is not ſafer in the Rocke,</l>
                     <l>Then thou in my firme boſome.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. Q.</speaker>
                  <p>I am bleſſ'd in't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Is it that lumpe of ranke ingratitu de,</l>
                     <l>Swell'd with the poyſon of Hypocriſie:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:32"/>Could he be ſo malicious, h'as pertaken</l>
                     <l>Of the ſweet firtile bleſſings of our Kingdome, Biſhop</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt done our White Houſe gracious ſeruice,</l>
                     <l>And worthy the faire reuerence of thy place:</l>
                     <l>For (thee black Holineſſe) that workes out thy death,</l>
                     <l>As the blind Moale the prop'reſt ſonne of earth,</l>
                     <l>Who in caſting his ambitious hills vp,</l>
                     <l>Is often taken and deſtroyed in the midſt</l>
                     <l>Of his aduanc'd worke: 'twere well with thee,</l>
                     <l>If like that verminous labourer, which thou imitateſt</l>
                     <l>In bils of pride and malice, when death puts thee vp,</l>
                     <l>The ſilent graue might prooue the bag for euer:</l>
                     <l>No deeper pit then that for thy vaine ho pe</l>
                     <l>Of the white Knight, and his moſt firme aſſiſtant,</l>
                     <l>Two princely peeces, which I know thy thoughts</l>
                     <l>Giue loſt for euer now, my ſtrong aſſurance</l>
                     <l>Of their fixt vertues, could you let in ſeas</l>
                     <l>Of populous vntruthes againſt that Fort,</l>
                     <l>'Twould burſt the proudeſt billowes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q.</speaker>
                  <p>My feare's paſt then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Feare? you were neuer guilty of an injury</l>
                     <l>To goodneſſe, but in that.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſtayd not with me (ſir.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It was too much, if it vſurp'd a thought,</l>
                     <l>Place a ſtrong guard there.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q.</speaker>
                  <p>Confidence is ſet (ſir.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Take that prize hence (you reuerend of men)</l>
                     <l>Put couetouſnes into the bag againe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Bag had need be ſound, or it goes to wracke,</l>
                     <l>Sinne and my weight will make a ſtrong one cracke.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <trailer>Finit Actus Quartus.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:6830:32"/>
               <head>Incipit Quintus, et Vlimus.</head>
               <stage>Enter the Blacke Knight in his Litter, as paſſing in haſt ouer the Stage.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HOld, hold,</l>
                     <l>Is the blacke Biſhops pawne, the Ieſuite</l>
                     <l>Planted for his conſecration?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Ecce triumphanti, Me fixum Caeſaris Arte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Art there (my holy boy) ſirah, Biſhop</l>
                     <l>Tumbrle is ſnapt ith' Bag by this time.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Heretici pereant ſic.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All Latin: Sure the Oration hath infected him:</l>
                     <l>Away, away make haſt: they are comming.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter B. Ki. Q. D. and B. Kt. with Pawnes, meeting the W. Kt. and Duke: the blacke Biſhops pawne from aboue, entertaines him with this Lattin Oration.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Si quid mortalibus, in vnquam oculis hilarem</l>
                     <l>Et gratum aperuit diem: Si quid permantibus</l>
                     <l>Amicorum Animis gaudium attulit perperitùr</l>
                     <l>Laetitiam (Eques candidiſſime pralucentiſſime,</l>
                     <l>Falic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m profecto tuum a Dome Candoris ad Domum</l>
                     <l>Nigritudinis Acceſſum promiſſsſſe peperiſſe, at tuliſſe fatemur:</l>
                     <l>Omnes aduentus Tui Conflagrantiſſimi, omni qua</l>
                     <l>Poſſumus laetitia, Gaudio, Congratulatione, Acclamations</l>
                     <l>Animis obſeruantiſſimis, Affectibus diuotiſſimis, obſequijs</l>
                     <l>Uenerabundis Te Soſpitim congratulamur?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>(Sir) in this ſhort congratulatory ſpeech,</l>
                     <l>You may conceiue how the whole Houſe affects you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>The Colledges and Sanctimonious ſeed plots.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis cleare and ſo acknowledged royoll (Sir.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:33"/>
                  <speaker>B. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What Honors, Pleaſures, Rarities, Delights</l>
                     <l>Your noble thought can thinke.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Your faire eye fix on</l>
                     <l>That's comprehended in the ſpacious circuit</l>
                     <l>Of our blacke Kingdome, they are your ſeruants all.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>How amply you indeere vs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>WD.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They are fauours that equally inrich the Royall Giuer.</l>
                     <l>As the receiuer in the free donation.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Muſicke: An Altar is diſcoured with Tapers, and Images ſtanding on each ſide.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Harke,</l>
                     <l>To inlarge your welcome: from all parts</l>
                     <l>Is heard ſweet-ſounding aires, abſtruſe things</l>
                     <l>Open of voluntary freenes: And yond Altar,</l>
                     <l>The ſeate of adoration, ſeemes t'adore,</l>
                     <l>The vertues you bring with you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Ther's a taſte of the old veſſell ſtill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. D.</speaker>
                  <p>The erronious relliſh.</p>
               </sp>
               <lg>
                  <head>Song.</head>
                  <l>Wonder worke ſome ſtrange delight</l>
                  <l>(<hi>This place was neuer yet without</hi>)</l>
                  <l>To welcome thee the faire White Houſe Knight,</l>
                  <l>And to bring our hopes about,</l>
                  <l>May from the Altar Flames aſpire,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Tapers ſet themſelues on fire.</l>
                  <l>May ſenſeleſſe things our ioyes approoue, <stage>The Images mooue in a Daunce.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>And thoſe brazen Statues mooue:</l>
                  <l>Quickned by ſome Power aboue,</l>
                  <l>Or what more ſtrange to ſhew our Loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A happy Omen waytes vpon this houre,</l>
                     <l>All moue portentuouſly the Right-hand way.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Ki.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Come let's ſet free all moſt choyſe delights,</l>
                     <l>That euer adorn'd Dayes or quickn'd Nights.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:33"/>Enter White Q. p. and the Blacke <hi>B.</hi> p. the Ieſuit in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Habit meeting them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>W.</hi> Q. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ſee t'was but a triall of my duty now,</l>
                     <l>Has a more modeſt minde, and in that vertue</l>
                     <l>Moſt worthely hath Fate prouided for me,</l>
                     <l>Hah! tis the bad-man in the Reuerend habit,</l>
                     <l>Dares he be ſeene agen? Traytor to Holineſſe,</l>
                     <l>Oh marble fronted Impudence, and knowes,</l>
                     <l>How ill 'has vs'd? I'me aſham'd he bluſhes not,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Are you yet ſtoard with any womans pitty?</l>
                     <l>Are you the Miſtris of ſo much Deuotion?</l>
                     <l>Kindneſſe, and Charity? as to beſtow</l>
                     <l>An Almes of Loue on your poore ſufferer yet</l>
                     <l>For your ſake onely?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>(Sir) for the reuerend reſpect you ought</l>
                     <l>To giue to Sanctity (though none to me)</l>
                     <l>In being her ſeruant vow'd, and weare her liuery,</l>
                     <l>(If I might counſell) you ſhould neuer ſpeake,</l>
                     <l>The language of vnchaſtity in that habit:</l>
                     <l>You will not thinke how ill it do's with you,</l>
                     <l>The world's a ſtage on which all parts are played,</l>
                     <l>You'd thinke it moſt abſurd to ſee a Diuell</l>
                     <l>Preſented there not in a Diuells ſhape,</l>
                     <l>Or wanting one, to ſend him out in yours,</l>
                     <l>You'd rayle at that for an abſurdity,</l>
                     <l>No Colledge ere committed, for Decorum ſake then</l>
                     <l>For pitties cauſe, for ſacred vertues honor,</l>
                     <l>If you'l perſiſt ſtill in your diuliſh part,</l>
                     <l>Preſent him as you ſhould, and let one</l>
                     <l>That carryes vp the goodneſſe of the play,</l>
                     <l>Come in that habit: and Ile ſpeake with him,</l>
                     <l>Then will the parts be fitted, and the ſpectators</l>
                     <l>Know which is which, they muſt haue cunning iudgments,</l>
                     <l>To finde it elſe, for ſuch a one as you</l>
                     <l>Is able to deceiue a mighty Auditory.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:34"/>Nay thoſe you haue ſeduc't (if there be any</l>
                     <l>In the aſſembly) if they ſee what manner</l>
                     <l>You play the Game with me, they cannot loue you.</l>
                     <l>Is there ſo little hope of you to ſmile (ſir)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yes at your feares, at th'ignorance of your power</l>
                     <l>The little vſe you make of time (youths fortune)</l>
                     <l>Knowing you haue a Husband for luſts ſhelter,</l>
                     <l>You dare not yet make bold with a friends comfort:</l>
                     <l>This is the plague of weaknes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. <hi>Q. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So hot burning?</l>
                     <l>The ſiliables of ſinne, flie from his lipps,</l>
                     <l>As if the letter came new caſt from Hell.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Well ſetting aſide the diſh you loue ſo much,</l>
                     <l>(Which hath bin heartily taſted by your betters)</l>
                     <l>I come to marry you to the gentleman</l>
                     <l>That laſt inioyd you, I hope that pleaſeth you.</l>
                     <l>Ther's no immodeſt reliſh in that office.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Strange of all men he ſhould light on him,</l>
                     <l>To tye that holy knote that ſought to vndoe me,</l>
                     <l>Were you requeſted to performe that buſines (ſir)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I name you a ſure toaken.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. <hi>Q. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As for that (ſir)</l>
                     <l>Now you're moſt welcom, and my faire hopes of you</l>
                     <l>You'ld neuer breake the ſacred knote you tyde once,</l>
                     <l>With any lewd ſolicitings hereafter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But all the ctafts in getting of it knit,</l>
                     <l>You are all one fire to make your couſning market,</l>
                     <l>I am the marrier and the man, do you know me?</l>
                     <l>Do you know me nice Iniquity? ſtrict luxurie?</l>
                     <l>And holy whoredome, I would clap on marriage</l>
                     <l>With all hot ſpeede to ſolder vp the Game?</l>
                     <l>So what a ſtrong Fate hath prouided for thee,</l>
                     <l>You were a maid, ſweare ſtill you'r no worſe now:</l>
                     <l>I left you as I found you, haue I ſtartled you?</l>
                     <l>I'me quit with you now for my diſcouery,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:34"/>Your outcries, and your Cunning, farwell brookage.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nay ſtay, and heare me but giue thanks a</l>
                     <l>Little (if your care can endure a worke ſo gracious,</l>
                     <l>Then you may take your pleaſure.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I haue done that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p.</speaker>
                  <p>That power that hath preſerued me from this diuell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>B.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This that may challenge the chiefe chaire in Hell,</l>
                     <l>And ſit aboue his Maſter.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Bring in merrit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That ſuffereſt him through blind luſt to be led,</l>
                     <l>Laſt night to the action of ſome common bed.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ouer common neither.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Black Queens p. within.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Hah! what voice was that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of virgins be thou euer honored.</l>
                     <l>Now you may go, you heare I haue giuen thanks (ſir)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Here is a ſtrangt Game indeed, did not I lie with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>No.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Within.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <p>What a diuell art thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I will not anſwer you (ſir)</l>
                     <l>After thankes-giuing.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You made promiſe to me</l>
                     <l>After the contract.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Within.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Miſchiefe confound thee,</l>
                     <l>I ſpeake not to thee: and you were prepared for't,</l>
                     <l>And ſet your ioyes more heigh.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Then you could reach (ſir)</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Within.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>This is ſome bawdy <hi>P.</hi> i'le ſlit the throat on't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What me your bedfellow, <stage>Enter Black Q. p.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>To one that workes ſo kindly without rape.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <p>My bedfellow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Do you plant your ſcorne againſt me?</l>
                     <l>Why, when I was <hi>Probationer</hi> at <hi>Bruxels.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:35"/>That Engine was not knowne; then Adoration</l>
                     <l>Fild the place, and wonder was in faſhion.</l>
                     <l>Is't turn'd to the wilde ſeede of contempt ſo ſoone?</l>
                     <l>Can 5 yeares ſtamp a baud? pray looke vpon me (ſir)</l>
                     <l>I'me youth enough to take it, 'tis no longer,</l>
                     <l>Since you were chiefe agent for the tranſportation</l>
                     <l>Of Ladies Daughters, if you be remembred,</l>
                     <l>Some of their portions I could name, you purſ'd em too</l>
                     <l>They were ſoone diſpoſſeſt of worldly cares,</l>
                     <l>That came into your fingers.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B p</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Shall I heare her?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Q. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Holy diriſion yes, till thy eares ſwell</l>
                     <l>With thy owne venome, thy prophaine lifes vomit:</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Neice was ſhe you poyſond with child twice,</l>
                     <l>And gaue her out poſſeſs'd with a foule Spirit</l>
                     <l>When t'was indeed your Baſtard?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I am taken <stage>Enter White Biſhops Pawne.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>In mine owne toyles.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>W.</hi> B. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Yes, and tis iuſt you ſhould be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. <hi>Q. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>And thou lewd <hi>Pawne,</hi> the ſhame of Womanhood.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I'me loſt of all hands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I connot feele</l>
                     <l>The weight of my affection: now hee's taken,</l>
                     <l>It hath not the burthen of a Graſſehopper.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter B. Kt. p.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>B. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Thou whore of order, cockatrice in <hi>Voto.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Yonder's the Whit Biſhops pawne, Ile play at's heart now</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh bloody vilain, would'ſt thou heape a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</l>
                     <l>On thy firſt foule offences? O merciles bloodhound</l>
                     <l>'Tis time that thou wert taken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>K. p</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Death preuented.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. <hi>Q. p.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For thy ſake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that partner in thy ſhame,</l>
                     <l>Ile neuer know man further then by Name.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6830:35"/>Enter Blacke King, Queene, Duke and Blacke Knight, white Knight, and white Duke.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You haue enricht my knowledge royall (ſir)</l>
                     <l>And my content together.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Steed of royot,</l>
                     <l>We ſet you onely welcome, ſurfeit is</l>
                     <l>A thing that's ſildom heard of in theſe parts.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>I heare of the more vertue when I miſſe on't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>We do not vſe to bury in our bellies,</l>
                     <l>Two hundred thouſand duckets, and then boaſt on't:</l>
                     <l>Or exerciſe the old Romaine painefull idleneſſe,</l>
                     <l>With care of fetching fiſhes farre from home,</l>
                     <l>The golden headed Coracine out of Egypt:</l>
                     <l>The Salpa from Ebuſis, or the Pelamis,</l>
                     <l>Which ſome call ſummer whiting from Calcedon:</l>
                     <l>Salmons from Aquitayne, Helops from Rhodes:</l>
                     <l>Cockles from Chyos, franckt and ſalted vp,</l>
                     <l>With Far and Sapa flower, and cockted wine,</l>
                     <l>We cram no birds nor Epicurian like,</l>
                     <l>Encloſe ſome creekes oth ſea, as Sergius Crata did,</l>
                     <l>Hee, that inuented the firſt ſtewes for Oyſters,</l>
                     <l>And other ſea fiſh? who beſides the pleaſure of his</l>
                     <l>Owne throate, got large reuenewes by the inuention,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe fat example the nobility followed;</l>
                     <l>Nor do we immitate that Arch Gormandizer,</l>
                     <l>With twenty two courſes at a Dinner;</l>
                     <l>And betwixt euery courſe, hee and gueſſe</l>
                     <l>Waſht, and vſ'd women, then ſat down and ſtrengthn'd:</l>
                     <l>Luſt ſwimming in their diſhes, which no ſooner</l>
                     <l>Was taſted, but was ready to be vented.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt impious Epicures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>We commend rather</l>
                     <l>Of two extreames the parſimonie of Pertinax,</l>
                     <l>Who had halfe Lettices ſet vp to ſerue againe,</l>
                     <l>Or his ſucceſſor Iulian, that would make</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:36"/>Three meales of a leane Hare, and after ſup</l>
                     <l>With a greene fig, and wipe his beard (as we can)</l>
                     <l>The old bewaylers of exceſſe in thoſe dayes</l>
                     <l>Complain'd there were more coyne bid for a</l>
                     <l>Cooke then for a Warre-horſe; but now Cookes are</l>
                     <l>Purchaſed after the rate of Tryumphant, and ſome</l>
                     <l>Diſhes after the rate of Cookes, which muſt needes</l>
                     <l>Make ſome of th'white houſe gormundizers, eſpecially</l>
                     <l>Your wealthy plumpe Plebeans, like the Hogges</l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Scaliger</hi> cites, that could not mooue for fat,</l>
                     <l>So inſenſible of either pricke or goade,</l>
                     <l>That Mice made goles to needle in their buttockes</l>
                     <l>And they nere felt em: There was once a ruler</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cyrenes</hi> Gouernour choakt with his owne paunch,</l>
                     <l>Which death, fat <hi>Sanctius</hi> King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> fearing</l>
                     <l>Through his infinite maſſe of belly, rather choſe</l>
                     <l>To be kild ſuddenly, by a pernicious herbe</l>
                     <l>Taken to make him leane, which old <hi>Cordeba</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>King of <hi>Morocco</hi> counſelled his feare too,</l>
                     <l>Then hee would hazard to be ſtung to death,</l>
                     <l>As that huge Cormorant that was choakt before him.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Well you are as ſound a ſpokes-man for parſimony,</l>
                     <l>And cleare abſtinance, and ſcarce one meale a day</l>
                     <l>As euer ſpake with tongue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Ki.</speaker>
                  <p>Cenſure him mildle (ſir) 'twas but to finde diſcourſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q</speaker>
                  <p>Heele talke of any thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall be halfe a fraide to feede hereafter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. D.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Or I beſhrew my heart: for I feare fatneſſe,</l>
                     <l>The fogge of fatneſſe as I feare a Dragon:</l>
                     <l>The comlineſſe I wiſh for, that's as glorious.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Your courſe is wondrous ſtrict: I ſhould tranſgreſſe (ſir)</l>
                     <l>Were I to change my ſide (as you haue wrought me.)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How you miſprize? tis not ment to you-ward:</l>
                     <l>You that are wound vp to the hight of feedinh,</l>
                     <l>By clime and cuſtome are diſpenc'd withall,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:36"/>You may eate, Cabrito, Calfe, and Ton's:</l>
                     <l>Eate, and eate euery day, twice if you pleaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay, the frank'd hen, fatted with Milke and Corne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>A ryot which the Inhabitants of <hi>Delos</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Were firſt inventers of: or the cramb'd Cockle.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Well for the foode I'me happily reſolued in;</l>
                     <l>But for the dyet of my diſpoſition,</l>
                     <l>There comes a trouble you will hardly finde</l>
                     <l>Food to pleaſe that.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>Kt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It muſt be a ſtrange nature,</l>
                     <l>We cannot finde a diſh for't, hauing <hi>Policy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(The Maiſter Cooke of Chriſtendome) to dreſſe it.</l>
                     <l>Pray name your natures dyet.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>The firſt meſſe, is hot Ambition.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That's but ſeru'd in puff-paſte:</l>
                     <l>Alas, the meaneſt of our Cardinalls Cookes</l>
                     <l>Can dreſſe that dinner: Your Ambition (ſir)</l>
                     <l>Can fetch no further compaſſe then the World?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VV. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Thats certaine (Sir.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wee are about that already,</l>
                     <l>And in the large feaſt of our vaſt Ambition,</l>
                     <l>We count but the white Kingdome (whence you came from)</l>
                     <l>The Garden for our Cooke, to picke his Sallads:</l>
                     <l>The food's leane <hi>France</hi> larded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with <hi>Germany;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Before which comes the the Graue, chaſt Signiory</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Venice,</hi> ſeru'd in (Capon-like) in White-broth:</l>
                     <l>From our chiefe Oven <hi>Italy</hi> the bake-meates:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Savoy</hi> the Salte: <hi>Genena</hi> the chip'd Mancher.</l>
                     <l>Below the Salte, the <hi>Netherlands</hi> are plac'd;</l>
                     <l>A common diſh at lower end a'th table,</l>
                     <l>For meaner pride to fall too. For our ſecond courſe,</l>
                     <l>A ſpit of <hi>Portugals</hi> ſeru'd in for Plouers:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Indians</hi> and <hi>Moores</hi> for blacke-birds: all this while</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Holland</hi> ſtands ready melted to make ſawce,</l>
                     <l>On all occaſions, when the Voyder comes;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:37"/>And with ſuch cheare our full hopes wee ſuffice,</l>
                     <l>Zealand ſaies grace, for faſhion when we riſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Her's meat enough in conſcience for ambition</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If there be any want there is <hi>Swiſſerland,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Polonia,</hi> and ſuch pickled things will ſerue</l>
                     <l>To furniſh out the table.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You ſay well (ſir)</l>
                     <l>Buthere's the miſery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when I ha ſtopt the mouth</l>
                     <l>Of one vice, ther's another ſtands gaping for food.</l>
                     <l>I'me as couetous as a barren wombe,</l>
                     <l>The graue, or what's more rauenous?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wee're for you (ſir)</l>
                     <l>Call you that hanouſneſſe, that is good husbandry?</l>
                     <l>Why when we make mony of our faith, our prayers,</l>
                     <l>We make make the very death bed buy her comforts,</l>
                     <l>Moſt dearely pay for all her pious Counſells,</l>
                     <l>Leaue rich reuennues for a few weake orizons:</l>
                     <l>Or elſe they paſſe vnreconciled without em,</l>
                     <l>Did you but view the vaults within our Moneſteries,</l>
                     <l>You'de ſweare then Pluto (whom the fiction calls)</l>
                     <l>The Lord of riches, were entomb'd there.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Is it poſſible.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. D.</speaker>
                  <p>You cannot walke for Tuns.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. D.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But how ſhall I beſtow the vice I bring, ſir,</l>
                     <l>You quite forget me, I ſhall be ſhut out,</l>
                     <l>By your ſtrickt key of life.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Is yours ſo vild (Sir)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. D.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some that are pleaſ'd to make a wanton on't,</l>
                     <l>Call it infirmity of blood, fleſh frailty;</l>
                     <l>But certaine ther's a worſe name in your booke for't.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The trifle of all vices, the meere innocent,</l>
                     <l>The very nouice of this houſe of clay, verily</l>
                     <l>If I but hug thee hard, I ſhew the worſt on't,</l>
                     <l>Tis all the fruite we haue heere after ſupper:</l>
                     <l>Nay, at the ruines of a Nunnery once,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:37"/>Six thouſand Infants heads found in a fiſh-pond.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. D.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I, how? how came they thither thinke you?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Huldricke</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ausberg</hi> in's Epiſtle</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Nicholas</hi> the firſt, can telly you how,</l>
                     <l>(May be hee was at cleanſing of the pond)</l>
                     <l>I can but ſmile to thinke, how it would puzzle</l>
                     <l>All mother maides that euer liuer in thoſe parts,</l>
                     <l>To know their owne childes head; but is this all?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. D.</speaker>
                  <p>Are you ours yet?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>One more, and I am ſilenc'ſt:</l>
                     <l>But this that comes now will diuide vp queſtionleſſe</l>
                     <l>Tis ten times, ten times, worſe then the fore-runners.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Is it ſo vilde, there is no name ordain'd for't?</l>
                     <l>Toads haue their titles, and creation gaue</l>
                     <l>Serpents, and Adders thoſe names to be knowne by.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This of all others beares the hidden'ſt poyſon,</l>
                     <l>The ſmootheſt venome, I am an Arch-diſſembler.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>How.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tis my natures braine turne from me (ſir,)</l>
                     <l>The time is yet to come, that ere I ſpoake</l>
                     <l>What my heart meant.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And call you that a vice:</l>
                     <l>Auoide all prophanation, I beſeech you;</l>
                     <l>The onely prime-ſtate vertue vppon earth,</l>
                     <l>The policy of Empires, oh take heede (Sir)</l>
                     <l>For feare it take diſpleaſure and forſake you,</l>
                     <l>Tis a Iewell of that precious vallue,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe worth's not known, but to the skilful Lapidary</l>
                     <l>The inſtrument that pickes ope Princes hearts,</l>
                     <l>And lockes vp our from them, with the ſame motion:</l>
                     <l>You neuer came ſo neere our ſoules till now.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. D.</speaker>
                  <p>Now you're a brother to vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>What we haue done, has bin diſſemblance euer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There you lye then:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:38"/>And the Games ours, wee giue the checke mate</l>
                     <l>By diſcouery, King the nobleſt mate of all.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>I'me loſt, I'me taken.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>A great ſhout and flouriſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Ambitious, couetous luxurious falſhood.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. D.</speaker>
                  <p>Diſſembler, that includes all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>All hopes confounded.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q.</speaker>
                  <p>Miſerable condition.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter W. King, W. Queene with their Pawnes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh let my armes be bleſt,</l>
                     <l>With this deare treaſure,</l>
                     <l>Truths glorious Maſter-peece, ſee Queene of ſweetnes</l>
                     <l>He's in my boſome ſafe, and this faire Stucture</l>
                     <l>Of comely honor, his true bleſt aſſiſtant.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>May their Integrities euer poſſeſſe</l>
                     <l>That powerfull Sanctuary.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As 'twas a Game (Sir)</l>
                     <l>Won with much hazard, ſo with much more triumph,</l>
                     <l>I gaue him checke mate by diſcouery (ſir.)</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Obcurity is now the fitteſt fauour</l>
                     <l>Falſhood can ſue for: it well ſnites Perdition,</l>
                     <l>Tis their beſt courſe that ſo hath loſt their fame,</l>
                     <l>To put their heads into the bagge for ſhame;</l>
                     <l>And there behold the bags mouth (like hell) opens <stage>The Bag opens, the B. B. ſlides in it.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>To take her due; and the loſt ſonnes appeare,</l>
                     <l>Greedily gaping for increaſe of fellowſhip</l>
                     <l>In infamy, the laſt deſire of wretches</l>
                     <l>Aduancing their perdition, branded fore-heads</l>
                     <l>Like Envies iſſue, or a bed of Snakes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Tis too apparent the Game's loſt, King taken.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <p>The white Houſe has giuen vs the bag (I thank em.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ieſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They'd neede haue giuen you a whole bag</l>
                     <l>By your ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>Sfoot this blacke biſhop has ſo ouer layd me,</l>
                     <l>So ſquelch'd and ſqueaſde mee, I haue no Verjuce</l>
                     <l>Let in me, you ſhall find all my goodneſſe if you</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6830:38"/>Looke for't in the bottome of the Bagge.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou Male-part Pawne,</l>
                     <l>The Biſhop muſt haue roome, he will haue roome,</l>
                     <l>And roome to lye at pleaſure.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iest. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All the Bagge I thinke</l>
                     <l>Is roome too little for your Spalletto paunch.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. B. p.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Downe viper of our Order, I abhorre thee,</l>
                     <l>Thou't ſhewe thy whoriſh front.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. Q. p.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, monſter Holineſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <p>Contention in the bag? is hell deuided.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You'd neede haue ſome of Maieſty and Power,</l>
                     <l>To keepe good rule amongſt you, make roome Biſhop.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I am not eaſily mooued, when I'me once ſet,</l>
                     <l>I ſcorne to ſtirre for any King on earth.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Q.</speaker>
                  <p>Heere comes the Queene, what ſay you then to her?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeede a Queene may make a Biſhop ſtirre.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Roome for the greateſt Machiauill Polititian,</l>
                     <l>That ere the Diuell hatch'd of a Nuns-egge.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He'le picke a hole in the bagge, and get out ſhortly:</l>
                     <l>I'me ſure to be the laſt man that creepes out;</l>
                     <l>And thats the miſery of greatneſſe euer.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. D.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Roome for a ſun-burn'd, Tanzy fac'd belou'd,</l>
                     <l>An Oliue couloured <hi>Ganimed;</hi> and thats all</l>
                     <l>Thats worth the bagging.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. B.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Crowd in all you can,</l>
                     <l>The Biſhop will be ſtill vppermoſt man</l>
                     <l>Mauger King, Queene, or Polititian.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W. Kt.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So let the Bagge cloſe now (the fitteſt wombe</l>
                     <l>For Treachery, Pride and Falſhoold, whilſt we winner like)</l>
                     <l>Deſtroying through Heauens power, what would deſtroy;</l>
                     <l>Welcome our white Knight with loud peales of Ioy.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:6830:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Epilogue.</head>
            <p>MY Miſtreſſe (the Whit Queene) hath ſent me forth,</p>
            <p>And bad me bow thus low, to all of Worth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>That are true Friends of the White Houſe and Cauſe,</p>
            <p>Which She hopes moſt of this aſſembly drawes:</p>
            <p>For any elſe, by Envies marke deuoted,</p>
            <p>To thoſe night-Glow-wormes in the Bagge denoted;</p>
            <p>Where ere they ſit, ſtand, or in priuate lurke,</p>
            <p>They'le be ſoone knowne by their deprauing worke:</p>
            <p>But She's aſſur'd, what they'le commit to bayne,</p>
            <p>Her white Friends hands will build vp faire againe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6830:39"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
