<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The arrivall and intertainements of the embassador, Alkaid Jaurar Ben Abdella, with his associate, Mr. Robert Blake From the High and Mighty Prince, Mulley Mahamed Sheque, Emperor of Morocco, King of Fesse, and Suss. With the ambassadors good and applauded commendations of his royall and noble entertainments in the court and the city. Also a discription of some rites, customes, and lawes of those Affrican nations. Likewise Gods exceeding mercy, and our Kings especiall grace and favour manifested in the happy redemption of three hundred and two of his Majesties poore subjects, who had beene long in miserable slavery at Salley in Barbary.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07788</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18165</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112908</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848149</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13227</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A07788)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13227)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 996:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The arrivall and intertainements of the embassador, Alkaid Jaurar Ben Abdella, with his associate, Mr. Robert Blake From the High and Mighty Prince, Mulley Mahamed Sheque, Emperor of Morocco, King of Fesse, and Suss. With the ambassadors good and applauded commendations of his royall and noble entertainments in the court and the city. Also a discription of some rites, customes, and lawes of those Affrican nations. Likewise Gods exceeding mercy, and our Kings especiall grace and favour manifested in the happy redemption of three hundred and two of his Majesties poore subjects, who had beene long in miserable slavery at Salley in Barbary.</title>
                  <author>Glover, George, b. ca. 1618, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p. : port. (metal cut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. Okes dwelling in little Saint Bartholmewes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Robert Blake in the title is probably not Robert Blake, 1599-1657--Cf. Michael Baumber, "General-at-Sea" (1989).</note>
                  <note>The portrait is signed: G: Glouer· fe:.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Blake, Robert, d. 1643.</term>
               <term>Jawhar ibn ʻAbd Allāh, --  al-Qāʼid.</term>
               <term>Morocco --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:13227:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>The true Effigies of <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> Alkaid, (or Lord) Jaurar Ben Abdella,
Embaſsador from <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> high and mighty Mully Mahamed
Shegue, Emperourr of Morocco, King of Feſs and Suſs, etc.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G: Glouer fe:</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13227:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
Arrivall and Intertaine<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments
of the Embaſſador,
Alkaid Jaurar Ben Abdella, with
his Aſſociate, Mr. <hi>Robert Blake.</hi>
From the High and Mighty Prince, <hi>Mulley
Mahamed Sheque,</hi> Emperor of <hi>Morocco,</hi>
King of <hi>Feſse,</hi> and <hi>Suſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the Ambaſſadors good and applauded
commendations of his royall and noble enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments
in the Court and the City. Alſo a
Diſcription of ſome Rites, Cuſtomes,
and Lawes of thoſe <hi>Affrican</hi>
Nations.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe Gods exceeding Mercy, and our Kings
eſpeciall grace and favour manifeſted in the happy
Redemption of three hundred and two of his
Majeſties poore ſubjects, who had beene long in
miſerable ſlavery at <hi>Salley</hi> in <hi>Barbary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
Printed by <hi>I. Okes</hi> dwelling in little Saint
<hi>Bartholmewes.</hi> 1637.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2+ pages">
               <desc>〈2… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13227:2"/>
            <p>with the commodities of another: For
though every Countrey doth not yeeld
every commodity, yet by the meanes of
Merchandize and tranſportation, almoſt
every Countrey in particular, enioyes
the fruition of all things needfull in
generall. Thirdly, it conſerves, and
makes peace, love, and amity with Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
and Potentates, though they are far
remote from each other in Religions,
Realmes, Regions, and Territories; yet
they are conioyned in leagues and
friendſhip together, and by the meanes
of Negotiation, may, and doe ſend Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
Ambaſſadors, Meſſuages, and rich
gifts, Magnificent preſents, Aides of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
and Navies, by Land and Sea, for
the expreſsion of their greatneſſe and
ſupportation of peace and unity one
with another. Fourthly, it is the ſtrength
of Kings &amp; Kingdomes, in the encreaſe
of Shipping and Marriners, whereby
either in peace or warre they are furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
upon all occaſions: And what
thing is there more in the World ſo
great, or ſo to be eſteemed, whereunto
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13227:2"/>
love will not ſtirre, and animate the
mindes of mortall men. Laſtly, it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints
each Nation with the Language,
Manners, Behaviour, Cuſtomes, and
carriage of one another; ſo that by
theſe meanes men are made capable of
underſtanding and knowledge; and
therefore preferre knowledge before
wealth and riches, for the one ſoone fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,
the other abideth for ever: for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
all Naturall and Terreſtriall
things, onely wiſedome is immortalll;
and for that maine reaſon knowledge
and underſtanding ought to bee imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
before ignorance; and eſpecially
for that in all other things which are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious,
yet there is ſome profit to bee
found: but ignorance onely is ever noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
and hurtfull to the ignorant, and
doth make them bare the paine of thoſe
offences which they commit, by their
imbecillity and want of knowledge.
Therefore ſtudy for knowledge whilſt
thou haſt time and leiſure to learne, &amp;
and be diligent to give care to thoſe
that are wiſe and learned; for by this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13227:3"/>
meanes thou ſhalt eaſily obtaine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
and knowledge of that,
which others have invented with great
labour and difficulty.</p>
            <p>But to the matter in hand, concerning
this <hi>Alkaid</hi> (or Lord) Ambaſſador; for
the word <hi>Alkaid,</hi> is Lord in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
of the <hi>Morocco,</hi> the <hi>Larbies,</hi> or <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barie.</hi>
I onely meane to relate his ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall
in <hi>England,</hi> his abode and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
with his comming up from
<hi>Graveſend</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> the manner of his
receiving into the City, and how he was
conducted to his houſe, his manner of
riding to the Court at White-Hall,
where he had royall entertainment and
audience; his magnificent and rich Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents,
his returne from the Court, his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate
and condition, and laſtly a ſhort
deſcription of the Emperor of <hi>Morocco</hi>
and his Empire, with his Kingdome of
<hi>Fez,</hi> or <hi>Feſſe,</hi> and his Kingdome of
<hi>Sus,</hi> and other his Dominions, with
ſomething of old and new <hi>Salla,</hi> or
<hi>Sallie,</hi> with the late proceedings
there.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13227:3"/>
The Ambaſsador is by birth a <hi>Portugall,</hi> a
Gentleman borne in a Towne called <hi>Monde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi>
who was taken Captive in his Child-hood at
the age of almoſt eight yeares; he was (as the
miſery and fortune of Captives is) bought and
ſold, and by command (as the manner of thoſe
barbarous Nations is) hee diſteſticled, or Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch'd,
and as he grew in yeares hee by his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
ſervices, was daily more and more in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
with the Emperor of <hi>Morocco,</hi> inſomuch,
that his Maieſty was pleaſed to take him into
his eſpeciall grace, making him his chiefeſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorite,
and truſty councellor of State, dignifi'd
him with the high ſtile or title of <hi>Alkaid,</hi>
or <hi>Lord,</hi> than which, there is not a degree high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
under the Emperor; endowed with Lands
and revenewes fit and correſpondent for ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
a calling, gave him the two moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
places of Lord great Chamberlaine, and
Lord Privy Seale, and to his prudent care and
honourable mature wiſedome was committed the
maine charge and management of the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant
affaires of his whole Empire, and in
ſuffering him to make Lawes and Edicts:
And he which is in an Office or place of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
and maketh Lawes for other men, ought
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13227:4"/>
appointment, Sir <hi>John Finnet</hi> Knight,
Maſter of the Ceremonies, was ſent
downe to <hi>Graveſend,</hi> to conduct the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors
to <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They had no ſooner taken their Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
and were launched, but an expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Welcome</hi> flew in thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
manner out of the mouths of the
great Ordnance, from both the Block-houſes
of <hi>Graveſend,</hi> and on <hi>Eſſex</hi> ſide,
and the Tyde being reaſonable calme,
they pleaſantly paſt to <hi>Woolwich,</hi> where
they ſaw his Maieſties new <hi>great Ship</hi>
(the Eighth Wonder of the World)
with pleaſing and much contenting Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration.
After which they paſt to
<hi>Greenewitch,</hi> where they landed, and
ſtay'd at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crowne</hi> foure
Houres, becauſe the <hi>Kings Barge</hi> with
the Lord <hi>Kenwell,</hi> and 12. Gentlemen of
his Maieſties Privy Chamber, and other
were appointed to come to <hi>Greenewitch,</hi>
to bring them to the <hi>Tower-wharfe</hi> in
State as was fitting and honourable.</p>
            <p>So they tooke Barges at <hi>Greenewitch,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
an houre before Night, with their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13227:4"/>
Trumpets ſounding before them all the
way: And after an Houres Rowing they
landed at the <hi>Tower,</hi> where they were
attended by Thouſands, and ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands
of Spectators, and welcomed and
conveyed with his Maieſties Coach, and
at the leaſt 100. Coaches more, and the
chiefeſt of the Cittizens, and <hi>Barbary-Merchants</hi>
bravely mounted on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe,
all richly apparrelled, every man
having a <hi>Chaine of Gold</hi> about him; with
the <hi>Sheriffes</hi> and <hi>Aldermen</hi> of <hi>London</hi> in
their <hi>Scarlet Gownes,</hi> with ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
of Torches and Links, that
though it were Night, yet the Streetes
were almoſt as light as Day. And in this
brave and noble way the <hi>Embaſſador</hi> with
his Aſſociate Mr. <hi>Blake,</hi> were accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied
from the <hi>Tower-wharfe</hi> to their
Lodgings in <hi>Wood-ſtreete,</hi> at the Houſe
that was Sir <hi>Martin Lumley's,</hi> Knight, and
Alderman of the Citty of <hi>London,</hi> and
where he kept his Honourable Office of
Maioralty in the yeare 1623.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Alkaid,</hi> having reaſonable, well
recovered him of his Health, after
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13227:5"/>
hee had taken reſt fifteene or ſixteene
dayes, till <hi>Sunday</hi> the fift Day of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi>
our Kings Maieſties Phyſitians
all this while (by his Maieſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand)
attending, and uſing their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
beſt skill, whoſe paines and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious
Knowledge tooke ſuch good
effect for his Health, that on the ſaid
fore-named <hi>Sunday,</hi> his Maieſty was gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly
pleaſed to give them Audience,
at his Palace or Mannour of <hi>White-Hall,</hi>
and to that intent theſe preparations
following were ordered for the Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation
of ſo Royall and Honourable
a Deſigne.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Orders that were obſerved upon
Sunday, the 5. of November, 1637. by
ſuch Honourable and Worſhipfull perſons,
and others that were appointed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct
the Embaſsadors to their
Audience.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, the Right Honourable the Earle
of <hi>Shrewſbury</hi> was in the <hi>Privy Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> at one of the Clocke in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13227:5"/>
the After-noone, and twelve Gentlemen
of his Maieſties <hi>Privie Chamber</hi> were
there at the ſame Houre, and according
as it was commanded, it was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the EarIes Coach (with as
many other as was held to be fitting)
waited, and were ready at the <hi>Court-gate,</hi>
to carry his Lordſhip and the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
privately to the <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
or Houſe in <hi>Wood-ſtreete.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Foure Horſes</hi> which were
ſent as <hi>Preſents from the Emperour of</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocco,
to the <hi>King of Great Brittaine,</hi> did
ſtand ready at the <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> Houſe at
the Houre afore-ſaid, and all the Horſes
of thoſe that came from the <hi>Court</hi> for the
ſame Service, were ready at the ſayd
Houſe the ſame houre.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, a good Guard of Officers,
and other men with Halbards, Bills, and
lavelins, were at <hi>Wood-ſtreete</hi> end in
<hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> and the like was in <hi>Wood-ſtreete</hi>
below the <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> Houſe, to
keepe the paſſage cleare from the preſſe
of people.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                     <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13227:6"/>
now it follows, that I relate ſomewhat
of the greatneſſe of the <hi>Emperour</hi> of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocco</hi>
that ſent tham, and ſome Cauſes
why they were ſent, with ſome iuſt
and true Remembrances of the good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices
that Mr. <hi>Robert Blake</hi> (Aſſociate
with the <hi>Alkaid</hi>) hath done for his cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
and diſtreſſed <hi>Countrey-men,</hi> our <hi>Kings</hi>
Subiects, <hi>Engliſh, Scottiſh, Iriſh,</hi> and of
the Iſles of <hi>Garnſey,</hi> and <hi>Jarſey,</hi> and of
other places of his <hi>Maieſties Dominions:</hi>
beſides his goodneſſe in relieving and
helping of many <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of ſundry Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
both with his Word and Purſe,
when they were in miſerable thraldome
and ſlavery; hee never ceaſed to doe his
beſt to comfort them.</p>
               <p>This Mighty and Potent Prince <hi>Mulley
Mahamed Sheque,</hi> is Emperor of <hi>Moroc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co,</hi>
King of <hi>Fez,</hi> or <hi>Feſſe,</hi> or <hi>Sus,</hi> or <hi>Suſa,</hi>
with many other Dominions of large extent;
ſome part of his Territories butting North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
upon the <hi>Mid-land</hi> or <hi>Mediterranean
Sea,</hi> over againſt part of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and ſome
large bounds of hundreds of Leagues South and
VVeſt upon the <hi>Atlantick Ocean:</hi> as alſo his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13227:6"/>
                  <hi>Empire</hi> extends it ſelfe many hundred Miles
upland Southward into <hi>Affrica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Citty of <hi>Morocco,</hi> (which is the
<hi>Metropolis</hi> of his Empire) as <hi>Atlas</hi> relates
in his Hiſtory of <hi>Affrica,</hi> hath beene
one of the greateſt Citties in the world,
being once of that huge circuite, that it
had 100000. houſes within it, moſt
ſtrong and defencibly walled, with 24
Gates to iſſue divers wayes out and in at,
but within theſe 100. yeeres paſt, what
with forraigne Warres and domeſticall
ſeditions, the Citty is much ruined, and
abated of its ancient greatneſſe; yet by
the Maieſtick Valour and Prudency of
this Emperor it begins to re-flouriſh,
and may re-aſſume the former Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
which once it had.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Kingdomes</hi> of <hi>Feſſe</hi> and <hi>Sus</hi> are
vaſte in extention, and rich in divers
Commodities, as <hi>Chamelots, Grograines,</hi>
and many other Stuffes made of the
haire of Cammels, and other Beaſts: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
the beſt <hi>Gold</hi> is found there in
plenty, with <hi>Oyles, Sugars,</hi> and many
other ſorts of <hi>Merchandize,</hi> for which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13227:7"/>
our <hi>Barbary Merchants</hi> doe traffique into
thoſe parts, with our <hi>Iron, Tinne, Lead,</hi>
and other commodities which are ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible
there. As concerning any further
Deſcription of thoſe Countries, I am no
<hi>Geographer,</hi> and whoſoever will know
more of them, let them looke in <hi>Pliny</hi>
his <hi>Naturall Hiſtory,</hi> or in Mr. <hi>Purchaſe</hi>
his <hi>Pilgrimage,</hi> or in <hi>Atlas,</hi> (a compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
Worke, well Tranſlated lately)
or in <hi>Lithgows Travailes,</hi> and there they
may have more ample and ſatisfactory
Relations; there ſhall they finde that in
theſe Dominions of <hi>Mauritania,</hi> the great
Battell of <hi>Alcazer</hi> was fought in the
yeare of our Lord 1578. on the fourth
Day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> when <hi>Don Sebaſtian,</hi>
King of <hi>Portugall,</hi> came into <hi>Barbary</hi>
with a great Army, in a wrong quarrell
to ayde an uſurping Rebell againſt the
true Heire to the Empire of <hi>Morocco,</hi> for
the which Ayde the Rebell had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> to give him the <hi>Kingdome</hi>
of <hi>Feſſe:</hi> But in that fatall Battell King
<hi>Sebaſtian</hi> ſeeking after the ſhadow, loſt
the ſubſtance; and inſtead of obtaining
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13227:7"/>
                  <hi>Feſse,</hi> he was ſlaine that Day, and there
loſt both his Life, and <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall;</hi>
by which meanes the King of
<hi>Spaine</hi> got it, and holds it; and in the
ſame Fight was ſlaine the lawfull King
of <hi>Feſſe,</hi> and the Vſurper, with our
Country-man <hi>Thomas Stukeley,</hi> to whom
the <hi>Pope</hi> had largely promiſed the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>
of <hi>Ireland;</hi> ſo that 3. Kings fell in
that one Battell.</p>
               <p>This Emperor now Reigning, is the
Sonne of <hi>Xeriffe Mulley Cidan, (deceaſed</hi>)
who was a valiant and victorious Prince,
and his <hi>Grandfather</hi> was <hi>Xeriffe Mulley
Hamet,</hi> a Prince that held good League
and Amity with Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (of
bleſſed and moſt famous memory) and
this Emperor as ſoone as he came to the
Crowne, he moſt lovingly deſired the
<hi>Friendſhip</hi> and <hi>Royall Amity</hi> of our Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
King <hi>Charles:</hi> He is a white man, of
a goodly proportion, and a Maieſticall
Aſpect; he is not above 18. yeeres of age,
and yet of ſuch ſurpaſſing ſtrength, that
he hath taken a new Horſe-ſhooe, and
with both his hands hath writhed and
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:13227:8"/>
inforced<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> through extremity and want
to retire the Army, without any deſigne
accompliſhed: And indeed it prooved
no otherwiſe, but ſtill <hi>Laiſhi</hi> held
<hi>Friendſhip</hi> with our <hi>Generall,</hi> and made
many ſhot out of the Towne of <hi>old Sally</hi>
into <hi>new Sally,</hi> ſo that they were ſore
diſtreſt in the Towne, with Famine,
and the battering of our <hi>great Ordnance</hi>
from our Ships by Sea, which did ſink
and teare their Shipping, and beate their
houſes about their eares; as alſo <hi>Laiſhi</hi>
beate upon them on the Land-ſide, that
by Sea and Land they had loſt ſo many
men, that they began to talke of yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p>The Emperor hearing of the perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
dealing of <hi>Laiſhi</hi> towards him, (for
<hi>Laiſhi</hi> ſtill ſtands out, and holds <hi>Old
Sally</hi> from the Emperor) he ſent his <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaid</hi>
and Mr. <hi>Robert Blake</hi> his Aſſociate,
in Commiſſion with him, to command
them of <hi>New Sally</hi> to ſurrender to him
the Towne, and deliver the Captives
that were the King of <hi>Great Brittaines</hi>
Subiects.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13227:8"/>
But before the <hi>Alkaid</hi> and Mr. <hi>Blake</hi>
came, the <hi>Towne,</hi> being unable to hold
out longer againſt the force of our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi>
Ships, that they were in a manner
neere yeelded before the Embaſſadour
came thither: ſo that (under <hi>God</hi>) our
Ships were the meanes to reduce <hi>Sally</hi> to
the obedience of the Emperor, the right
Lord and owner thereof, and alſo to
redeeme all the poore Captives that
were there, <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> So on the 28. day
of <hi>July</hi> the <hi>Alkaid,</hi> with Maſter <hi>Blake,</hi>
went into the <hi>Towne,</hi> and in the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors
name did place there their old Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour,
and all the Captives were ſent
a boord the <hi>King of Englands</hi> ſhips: thoſe
that liſt to have a more ample Relation
of the ſurrendring of this <hi>Towne,</hi> with
the other paſſages that happened there,
they may read a <hi>Journall</hi> written by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<hi>John Duntons</hi> Direction, who was
the Maſter of the <hi>Admirall-ſhip</hi> the <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard,</hi>
who, as it is thought, hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
it truely; but hee is here and
there wrong'd by the Writer, in miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing
ſome things unorderly.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13227:9"/>
were in number 302, <hi>Engliſh, Scottiſh,</hi>
and <hi>Iriſh;</hi> amongſt whom there were 11
Women: Alſo there were 27. <hi>French men,</hi>
which wiſely ran away from their kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers;
and there were likewiſe ſet at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
8. <hi>Dutch-men,</hi> and 11. <hi>Spaniards:</hi>
all theſe <hi>great Mercies of God</hi> to theſe
poore captived <hi>Christians,</hi> ought never
(by them) to be forgotten, but with
<hi>praiſe, Thankeſgiving, and amendment of life
to be had in perpetuall Remembrance:</hi> and we
and they are all bound to love, honour,
and obey <hi>Our moſt Gracious King,</hi> whoſe
<hi>piety</hi> and <hi>pitty</hi> was ſo great, as to take the
Affliction of his poore Subiects ſo farre
into <hi>his moſt Princely conſideration,</hi> as to
ſend his Ships under ſuch wiſe and able
Commanders for their <hi>Redemption.</hi> And
it is a moſt Remarkable Note of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighties
Mercy,</hi> in that hee ſtir'd up and
ordain'd Maſter <hi>Robert Blake</hi> to be the
Agent and Inſtrument to move the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi>
of <hi>Morocco,</hi> to be ſo well affected for
their enlargement.</p>
               <p>Their ſlavery (<hi>for the time</hi>) was
worſe than the <hi>Aegyptian Bondage</hi> under
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13227:9"/>
                  <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> for imagine (<hi>Good Reader</hi>)
what miſery can be more, than for a man
or woman to be bought and ſold like a
Beaſt, for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to be ſervile to an
<hi>Infidell,</hi> in the moſt baſe and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible
drudgeries; to eate the Bread of
<hi>ſorrow,</hi> and drinke the water of <hi>affliction;</hi>
to have the Head ſhaven, the body
pin'd and beaten, to grind in Mills, to
digge and dreſſe Vineyards, to draw
Ploughes, to be labourers dayly, and
all their wages to be hard fare, hard
blowes, hard lodging, and (more
hard than thoſe) never to hope to be
freed till Death; but hardeſt and worſt
of all, to be urged, enforced, and enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<hi>to forſake their Faith, and turne Miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants;</hi>
or (at the beſt) to be ever debar'd
the exerciſe of the Freedome of their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi>
and <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Now the Learned
doe ſay, <hi>That all kind of Servitude is miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
but that especially is intollerable, when
a Man is enforced to ſerve one that is diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
and vicious: And therefore</hi> (as a wiſe
man ſaith) <hi>it is better to live free with a little
feare, than to be in ſervitude with much and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13227:10"/>
great aboundance; for</hi> Liberty <hi>is ſweete, and
worthy to be regarded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe, and more than theſe were the
inſupportable calamities of our poore
diſtreſſed Countrey-men, with 46. of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Nations, who are now <hi>by Gods espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
mercy and providence</hi> at liberty, ſome
of them having endured 30. yeeres ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,
and ſome fewer; but all too
much, and too many.</p>
               <p>In <hi>February</hi> laſt, 1635, Mr. <hi>Robert
Blake</hi> being a Merchant, and trading to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocco,</hi>
by his good converſation and carriage
there, the <hi>Emperor</hi> caſt an eye of Regard
and Favour upon him, inſomuch that he cauſed
him to leave his Merchandiſe and Traffique in
truſt to his ſervants and Factors, and himſelfe
to be neere attendant to his Perſon in the Court,
where his Maieſty taking eſpeciall notice of his
good diligence and Integrity, entertain'd a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
to him and his Services every day more
and more, ſo that in ſhort ſpace hee purchas'd
the Office of <hi>Farmer of all his Ports and
Cuſtomes,</hi> (which place hee ſtill retaines.)
There were then in the <hi>Emperors</hi> Court 33.
<hi>Engliſh Captives,</hi> whom hee and his Father
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13227:10"/>
had formerly bought from <hi>Argeir</hi> and <hi>Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi>
and ſome of them had beene in Captivity
25. yeeres, ſome 20. yeeres, ſome 14, ſome
fewer, but each of them thought that the time
was too long.</p>
               <p>And although theſe mens miſeries
were not altogether ſo great, nor their
Captivity ſo heavy in the Court at <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocco,</hi>
as it was at <hi>Tunnis, Argeir,</hi> or <hi>Sally,</hi>
yet was their Thraldome ſo irkeſome to
them, that they had a deſire to ſee their
owne Countries; their mindes ran upon
their Parents, Kinred, Friends, and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance,
from whom they had beene
long unfortunately ſeparated: ſo that
their beſt mirth was but forc'd, and a
kinde of mourning, and all their ioyes
were too much mixed with care and
ſadneſſe, which Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> (with great
griefe of heart) did note in them dayly;
and his moſt ſorrow for them was, that
he ſuppos'd hee could not helpe them,
and therefore he did often ſee them with
an eye of <hi>Chriſtian compaſſion and pitty,</hi> and
in his minde (like a true <hi>Engliſh-man</hi>)
had a <hi>Sympathy</hi> or <hi>brotherly feeling of his</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                     <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:13227:11"/>
with houſes for ſo large a circuite: It
hath three <hi>Caſtles,</hi> two of them to the
Land-ward, and one to the Sea-ward,
with other ſtrong <hi>Caſſamats</hi> and <hi>Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes,</hi>
well furniſhed with great <hi>Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
From <hi>Sally</hi> to <hi>Saffee</hi> is neere fifty
Leagues more to the <hi>Southward,</hi> and
there the <hi>Embaſſador</hi> tooke ſhipping, as
is before-ſaid.</p>
               <p>And although I have written before in
this Relation, that I have no skill in
<hi>Geography,</hi> or Deſcription of <hi>Countries</hi> and
<hi>Climates,</hi> yet for the ſatisfaction of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
ſuch as will not, or cannot be at the
charge to buy larger Relations, it is not
impertinent that I write ſomewhat of
<hi>Affrica,</hi> and conſequently of <hi>Barbary, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocco,
Feſse, Sus,</hi> and other of thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions,
with their Religions, manners,
Rites, Lawes, and Cermonies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For their</hi> Religion, <hi>they are ſtrict obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
of the Law of</hi> Mahomet; <hi>they ſay</hi>
Chriſt was a great Prophet, borne to bee a
Saviour of the World, (but not incarnate)
that hee was the Breath of God, that hee was
borne of a Virgin, and that the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſhould
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13227:11"/>
have beleev'd in him, but would not; and
therefore becauſe they went about to murder and
crucifie him, he left them, and aſcended from
them into Heaven, and that then they put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
man to Death inſtead of him, whom
they tormented, and cruelly Crucified. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
theſe</hi> Mahometans <hi>doe hold and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme
the</hi> Jewes <hi>as the worſt of men,
and very ſlaves to all Nations of the</hi>
World.</p>
               <p>The one and onely Booke of their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi>
is called their <hi>Alcaron,</hi> deviſed by
their falſe Prophet <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who was
of their <hi>Nation,</hi> (a <hi>Larbee:</hi>) They may
not uſe any other Booke for <hi>Devotion,</hi> nor
on paine of loſſe of life, no part of it doe
they dare to examine or queſtion; but if
any be diffident, or any point or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
be intricate and hard to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
by any of them, then it is lawful
to aske the meaning of the <hi>Talby,</hi> which
is a poore weake learned <hi>Prieſt:</hi> They
are all <hi>Circumciz'd,</hi> and they uſe a kind
of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> but not in their <hi>Churches,</hi> but
at home in their houſes.</p>
               <p>Their <hi>Lent</hi> is much about the time as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13227:12"/>
it is with us, which they doe hold but
30. dayes; and they neither eate nor
drinke all that time on any of thoſe
dayes, betwixt the dawning and the
twi-light, but when once the <hi>Starres</hi>
doe ſhew themſelves, then (for their
Day Faſt) they feed faſt all Night. That
<hi>Prieſt</hi> or <hi>Talby</hi> that cannot Read over
the Booke of the <hi>Alcaron</hi> (or <hi>Mahomets
Law</hi>) all over on their <hi>Good Friday</hi> at
night, is held unworthy of his place and
Function: they ſay their <hi>prayers</hi> ſix times
every day and night, and they doe waſh
themſelves all over very often: they have
no Bells to toll them to <hi>Church,</hi> but he
that is the Clarke, or Sexton, hath a
deepe baſe great voyce, and goes to the
top of the Steeple, and there roares out
a warning for the people to come to
their Devotions. No man doth enter
their Churches with his ſhooes on;
their <hi>Talbies</hi> or <hi>Prieſts</hi> each one of them
are allowed a Wife, or Wives if they
will: The Lay-men may have Captive
women, but they muſt not lye with
them in the night-time, for that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13227:12"/>
to the Wives by turne, and if any
wife be beguiled of her turne, ſhe may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine
for ſatisfaction to the Magiſtrate: he
that hath foure wives muſt be a Rich man; a
poore man is allowed as many, but his
meanes are too ſhort to keepe them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
one or two muſt ſerve his turne. The
<hi>Bride and Bridegroome</hi> doe never ſee each other
before the Wedding-night that they are
going to bed, where if he finde her a Maid,
all is well; if otherwiſe, hee may turne her
away, and give her no part of the portion
ſhe brought him.</p>
               <p>As concerning their <hi>Burials,</hi> if any one
doth dye, they doe waſh the Corps all over,
and (by reaſon the <hi>Countrey</hi> is extreame hot,
they cannot keep them above ground) with
all ſpeed they ſend for the Friends or Kinred
of the party deceaſed, and carry the dead out
of their Townes or Citties, to a place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
for that uſe, (for none are buried in
their <hi>Churches,</hi> or <hi>Synagogues,</hi> or within their
Townes) and there the <hi>Talby</hi> ſayes a ſhort
<hi>Prayer,</hi> and then the <hi>Corps</hi> is interred. They
have a cuſtome to ſpeake in praiſe of <hi>vertuous
perſons</hi> departed, to encourage and animate
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13227:13"/>
taken with falſe weights or meaſures, doth
loſe all his Ware in his houſe to the uſe of
the poore, and is a defamed perſon, and
cruelly whipt. Their Execution for life and
death is, that commonly the perſon adiud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
to die, hath his throat cut by the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner.
And theſe are part of the <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
Lawes, and Manners</hi> of the people of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocco,
Feſſe,</hi> and <hi>Sus,</hi> and I doe wiſh they
were all inſpired with <hi>Holineſſe from God;</hi> for
I am ſure they doe ſurpaſſe <hi>many Chriſtians in
Righteouſneſſe and iuſt dealing towards men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Affrica</hi> there are many <hi>Nations, Kingdoms,</hi>
and <hi>Provinces,</hi> many parts whereof are inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited
by <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Portugalls.
Aethiopia</hi> is a great tract of Land in the South
part of <hi>Affricke,</hi> it hath many Kingdomes in
it, over whom (as Chiefe Ruler) is <hi>Preſter
John:</hi> He is <hi>Emperor</hi> of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> or of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſsines;</hi>
he is a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and ſo are his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
but withall they are all <hi>Circumciſed:</hi> The
<hi>Evnuch</hi> whom <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
was Governour of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> and chiefe
Treaſurer under <hi>Candaces</hi> the Queene then
Reigning there, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Egypt</hi> (now under the <hi>Turke</hi>) is another
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13227:13"/>
part of <hi>Affrica;</hi> in that Land the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>
were in bondage, whom <hi>God</hi> delivered by
the hand of <hi>Moſes:</hi> it is bounded on the
Eaſt with the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> wherein <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and
all his Hoſt were drown'd. Alſo the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
of <hi>Gaogan, Nubia, Dangaly, Doba, Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſila,
Daſila, Barnagaſſo, Doara, Balli, Angola,
Numidia, Guiney</hi> or <hi>Binney, Bizarchus, Trip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toletana,
Mauritaunia Ceſarienſis, Mauritaunia Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiphenſis,
Tingitania, Congo,</hi> (far to the South)
<hi>Carthage,</hi> neare where <hi>Tunis</hi> ſtands, (famous
for <hi>Dido</hi> and <hi>Hanniball) Hippon</hi> more famous
for being the the Biſhops Sea of the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
and bleſſed Lampe of light and <hi>Learning,</hi>
Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and <hi>Utica,</hi> where the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<hi>Roman Cato Uticenſis</hi> did enrich them
with his Venerable bones.</p>
               <p>And in ſome parts of <hi>Affrica</hi> the people doe
uſe to eate three whole daies together, and
are in all things obedient to their Wives or
Concubines: Moreover, they never ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of their Daughters to be married, except
ſhe or they have firſt ſlaine with her owne
hand by <hi>Policy</hi> one of their Enemies: this
they doe obſerve from the <hi>Tartarians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In other parts of this Countrey they doe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13227:14"/>
honour their Women more than their men,
and they take their Sur-names of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and not of their Father: and they leave
their Daughters to be their Heires and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritors
of their Lands, and not their ſons.</p>
               <p>And in ſome places many have beene pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,
and ſome baniſhed, becauſe they
have kiſſed their Wives in the preſence of
their <hi>Children</hi> or <hi>Daughters;</hi> but at the leaſt
they have beene fined to their <hi>Governour</hi>
many Duckets for this offence.</p>
               <p>Their <hi>Lawes</hi> command, that men accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed
to wickedneſſe and viciouſneſſe,
ſhould be cut off, without being ſpared or
concealed: and that they which were attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
and convinced as guilty of any crime,
ſhould never eſcape without ſome puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
or other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Affrica</hi> is that part of the <hi>World</hi> that doth
produce moſt <hi>Wonders, Monſters, ſtrange
Beaſts, Fowles,</hi> and <hi>Serpents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Monſters,</hi> it is ſaid that there are a
people called <hi>Aramaſpians,</hi> with one eye in
the Fore-head; ſome with their Feete natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
growing backward, ſome with heads
like Dogges, ſome with long tailes, ſome
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13227:14"/>
with but one legge, that doe hop very ſwift,
and are called <hi>Sciopedi,</hi> who with the ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
of the foote (as they lye on their
backs) doe defend their whole bodies from
the violent heate of the Sunne; ſome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
Heads, with Eyes in their ſhoulders;
ſome <hi>Satyres,</hi> (halfe men and halfe Goates)
ſome with no Noſes, but flat-fac'd, with
holes to breath at: ſome with legges as lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
and pliable as Lamparnes, (without
bones) who doe creepe and crawle. Some
with eares ſo great that they cover the
whole body; and that in <hi>Aethiopia</hi> there are
ſome men that are 8. Cubits, or 4. Yards
high; let the <hi>Reader</hi> beleeve as much of
this as he liſt: but I am perſwaded, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of theſe things are true, or elſe ſo many
Grave and approved <hi>Authors</hi> would never
have written of them, and divulg'd them
to the World.</p>
               <p>Alſo in <hi>Affrica</hi> are ſtore of <hi>Elephants, Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
Lyons, Buffles, Panthers, Leopards,
Cammells, Rhinoceros, Lynces, Musk kats,
Onces, Elkes, Porcupines, Dragons, Serpents,
Crocodiles, Ichneumons,</hi> the <hi>Hiena Vipers,</hi> the
<hi>Baſiliske,</hi> the <hi>Chamelion,</hi> the <hi>Sallamander, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentalaes,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:13227:15"/>
and <hi>Scollapendraes, Vultures, Eagles,
Oſtriches, Oſprayes,</hi> the Bird of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi>
(that is almoſt all tayle) with many other,
too long to recite: ſo that thoſe parts of the
World doe breed and produce more vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Beaſts and vermine, and ſtrange Rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of Nature, than all <hi>Europe, Aſia,</hi> and
<hi>America.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus having briefly related the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions,
Manners, Rites, Lawes, and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
of ſome of the Dominions of <hi>Affrica,</hi> as
<hi>Barbary, Morocco, Feſſe,</hi> and <hi>Sus,</hi> I hope it
will ſatisfie any indifferent Reader: To
name all were too tedious, and impoſſible;
and therefore thoſe that will have more
ample Deſcription, let them get the credit
to borrow, or the Ability to buy larger
Volumes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sa. Baker,</signed>
               <date>Novemb. 27. 1637.</date>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
