<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true knowledge of a mans owne selfe. Written in French by Monsieur du Plessis, Lord of Plessie Marly. *And truly translated into English by A.M..</title>
            <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 130 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07786</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103514</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">54532267</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 54532267</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3672</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A07786)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3672)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 716:14, 2125:14c)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true knowledge of a mans owne selfe. Written in French by Monsieur du Plessis, Lord of Plessie Marly. *And truly translated into English by A.M..</title>
                  <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
                  <author>Xenophon. Memorabilia.</author>
                  <author>Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 215, [23] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.R. for William Leake, at the signe of the Greyhound in Paules Churchyard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A.M. = Anthony Munday.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L¹² (first and last leaves blank).</note>
                  <note>Printers' device on title page (McK. 341).</note>
                  <note>Includes "A dialogue of the providence of God, written in Xenophon, his firste booke of the deeds and sayings of Socrates" [i.e. the Memorabilia].</note>
                  <note>Bound and filmed following 6832.65.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound; copy at 2125:14c lacks A-B₇, and B₁₁; copy at 716:14 lacks L₁.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Soul --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Man (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Human physiology --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spiritual life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3672:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3672:1"/>
            <p>THE True knowledge of a mans owne ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Written in French by <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur du Pleſsis,</hi> Lord of <hi>Pleſſie Marly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>❀And truly tranſlated into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh by <hi>A. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by I. R. for William Leake, at the ſigne of the Grey-hound in Paules Churchyard. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:3672:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Aduenturez et marchez auant.</head>
                  <figDesc>coat of arms or blazon</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3672:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVorſhipfull, Maiſter <hi>Iohn Swynnerton,</hi> Eſquire: And to the moſt vertuous Gentlewoman his Wife: All happines to them &amp; theyrs in this life, and in the life to come hartilie wiſhed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His excellent Treatiſe, (right Worſhipfull) bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing written in the French tongue, by that honorable and learned Gentleman, <hi>Monſieur du Pleſsis,</hi> appeareth by his owne words, to be doone for the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a mightie Atheist, who stood ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly against the knowledge of God, &amp; verie deepe diſgrace of Religion by him dailie committed. In regard whereof, albeit hee had commended to him his learned labour
<pb facs="tcp:3672:3"/>
of the truth of Christian religion, (able enough to ſtop the impious mouth of any blasphemer whatſoeuer:) yet he was the rather induced this way to deale with him, becauſe by laying open the knowledge of a mans owne ſelfe, and the ſeuerall admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble testimonies hee carrieth about with him, Gods omnipotent glory might the more plainly be approoued, the immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the ſoule no way be able to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, nor the truth of Gods religion &amp; his prouidence be at any time doubted of.</p>
            <p>If wee looke vpon any curious picture drawne to the life: wee immediatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that the ſame was the work of ſome rare and artificiall Painter. If wee gaze vpon the goodly Monuments and ſtately erected Pallaces, full of arte, industry, &amp; many exquiſite perfections: wee preſently apprehend, that ſome ingenious Maister was the contriuer thereof, and that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from a skilfull workman. If diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in cenſuring of theſe and ſuch like things, dooth ſo ſway our oppinions: what
<pb facs="tcp:3672:3"/>
can wee then ſay, when beholding the world, and attayning to the knowledge of wonderful thinges therein contained, but that perforce wee must confeſſe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, an higher cauſe and eſpeciall Creator of them all?</p>
            <p>Let vs come then to <hi>Microcoſmus,</hi> to the little world man, and enter awhile but into this kinde of conſideration. Wee cannot be ſo abſurd and blockiſh, but that we will graunt he had a beginning, a cauſe from whence he came, that it was not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him to make himſelfe, but must needes come into the world by the help &amp; meanes of ſome other.</p>
            <p>This very conſideration, guides vs to acknowledge a Father and Mother, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe loynes we proceeded, &amp; that from them wee had the benefit of life. Ariſing thence by further gradations, wee attaine to intelligence of our prediceſſors, &amp; iudge by them as of our ſelues: that they had an originall as we had, and were not the first men in the worlde, but aſcending vp ſtill
<pb facs="tcp:3672:4"/>
from Father to Father, wee ſhall finde in the end one Father of vs all, &amp; that from him we had our first beginning.</p>
            <p>Concerning that first Father of vs all, hee must alſo deſcend of one, or el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e bee eternall, or come of ſome matter like to God, or at the least be GOD himſelfe. Which becauſe he could not be, hee must needes haue ſome beginning, &amp; be borne after ſome other ſort, then they that did deſcend of him: wherein what can wee otherwiſe ſay, but that the Creator of the whole world must needes be his father? From this beginning wee can climbe no higher, but there of neceſſity must ſtay &amp; conclude: that this first Creator of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was without beginning, and becauſe we ſhall elſe haue no place to rest at, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe him to be infinite and eternall. Thus the creature leades vs to finde out the Creator, and proceeding from one eſſence to another, attaines at last to the first eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, endleſſe &amp; euerlasting, as the ſpring and originall of all in generall, to wit, the
<pb facs="tcp:3672:4"/>
almightie and omnipotent great God.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus attained to the knowledge of God by the creature, let vs nowe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede to learne to know what the creature is: which beeing the whole ſcope and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the Treatiſe following, I will leaue the whole caſe to be reſolued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as beeing therein handled at full and very learnedly.</p>
            <p>Now my humble ſute vnto your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is, that in regarde of ſome breach of promiſe, concerning my <hi>Paradox Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> which long ſince you ſhould haue had, but that the troubles of the time, &amp; miſinterpretation of the worke by ſome in authoritie, was the only cauſe why it went not forward: that you would pleaſe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of this excellent labour, not as in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of that former debt, becauſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againe restored me, ſhall ſhortly come to aunſwer for it ſelfe, but rather to looke with the more fauourable regard on this, first for the honorable Frenchmans ſake, whoſe workes doe carry no meane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation
<pb facs="tcp:3672:5"/>
through the vvorlde: And next, for the vnfained affection I beare you, deuoting my best abilities of ſtudie to your kinde patronage, ſo pleaſe you but to grace them with fauourable acceptance.</p>
            <p>The Treatiſe against Atheiſme, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the ſame Author, to the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and annexed to this learned labour of his, beeing likewiſe ſo lately come to my handes, I will (by Gods aſſistance) finiſh with what expedition I may, and entitle it to the kinde entertayner of this former, as beeing a booke most needfull for theſe times, wherein neuer enough can be ſayde or written of that argument, ſo mightie is the multitude of blasphemous Atheists, and ſo dangerous their proceedings to Gods high diſhonour.</p>
            <p>I am loth to be troubleſome by tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to your Worſhip, becauſe to the wiſe and iuditiall, I know a word is ſufficient: the worke, my ſelfe, and what I can beſide, I prostrate to your gentle interpretation, wiſhing to you, the vertuous Gentlewoman
<pb facs="tcp:3672:5"/>
your wife, &amp; hopefull iſſue, all thoſe hape<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pie bleſſings that this worlde can or may affoord, &amp; after the finiſhing of this frail-terrestriall pilgrimage, a full meaſure of eternall tranquilitie in the Land of the liuing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your VVorſhips in all truneſſe of affection,</hi> An: Mundy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3672:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3672:6"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>BY the iudgement of the beſt and learnedſt Philoſophers, as alſo by ſome apparant proofe in our owne ſelues, wee finde, that our affection or deſire after any thing, is a quality pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per &amp; peculier to the ſoule: for from it onely are our affections deriued, and thereby are we led to the proſecution of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we can moſt couet. Now, all our longings and deſirous ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, are not euermore for the beſt, albeit in our fraile iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments it may carry a wel ſeeming likelyhoode: but too often we
<pb facs="tcp:3672:7"/>
finde it by wofull experience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that we haue no greater enemies then our owne affections, nor fall into heauier daungers, then thoſe we are led to by our owne wilfull follies.</p>
            <p>To runne into particularities of our ſeuerall appetencies, as ſome after honour, others after riches, others after temporarie glory or applauſe, and others af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vaine &amp; friuolous pleaſures: would require a larger diſcourſe then this whereto I am limitted, and I ſhould but follow the olde track of cuſtome, which almoſt is handled in euery tractate. Yet we find the nice natures of ſome to be ſo ſcrupulous, that when the liuer-veine of theyr corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted opinions is but toucht a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
<pb facs="tcp:3672:7"/>
not launced or let blood for the better ſafety of their health: they fall into ſuch extraordinarie fits, or rather frenzies, that no men are more condemned, then they that can ſooneſt cure them, nor worſe entreated, then ſuch as beſt loue them.</p>
            <p>And what is the maine impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment in thoſe teachie humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts, but only a mighty aſſurance and ouer-weening of their own knowledge, and skilfull reach in all thinges whatſouer? whereas if theyr capacity of knowledge were brought to the true touch indeede, it would euidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that they know nothing at all, at leaſt not what they ought to know, and would beſt of all become them to haue knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:3672:8"/>
of. The ambitious man pretends to know what honour &amp; height of dignity is; yet findes his knowledge to be meere ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, vvhen the miſerable downfall from his expectation, teacheth him (too late) that a meane eſtate had beene much better.</p>
            <p>The greedy ſcraping money-monger perſwades himſelfe, that his knowledge in managing of worldly commodities, and bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering for beſt aduantage by bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayning, is as much as is needfull and neceſſarie for him to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted withall, and that, that is the onely reall ſubſtance of knowledge indeede: but when he finds by ſom croſſe &amp; change of the world, as either loſſe at Sea
<pb facs="tcp:3672:8"/>
abroade, rapine of theeues at home, or ſome other caſualtie (vvhereof there vvanteth no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance) that this vvorldlie knowledge is indeede but wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe folly, then hee can cry out with the Philoſopher, that hee had much witte, but no knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>The like might be ſaid of the proude, enuious, wanton, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, &amp;c. all of them coueting no other kinde of knowledge, but what beſt fitteth &amp; agreeth with their ſenſuall appetites; to whom I aunſwer with that learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Saint Ambroſe; <hi>That it had beene much better for them not to haue knowne at all, except they had attayned to true knowledge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3672:9"/>
               <hi>Seneca</hi> tells vs, that the loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Glaſſe was firſt made &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented, for a man to come to the eaſier knovvledge of himſelfe thereby. Nowe albeit we may gather ſomwhat concerning our ſelues, when we view our faces, proportion and the bodies linia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments therein: yet <hi>Socrates</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to a greater matter, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied this beholding of our ſelues in a Glaſſe, to an euident enſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life and good behauiour. For, he would very often aduiſe his Schollers and follovvers, to make a continuall vſe of looking themſelues in a glaſſe, to the end, that he who perceaued his ſhape to be comly and well beautified, might thereby learne to ſhunne all turpitude in manners, which
<pb facs="tcp:3672:9"/>
would much deforme and ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh ſo goodly an appearance. Moreouer, hee gaue them this further admonition, that vvhen any one did diſcern by the glaſſe, ſome want eyther of apt forme or comlines in himſelfe, or any other impediment vvhich hee thought to be defectiue: that his labour and care ſhould be the more induſtriouſly applyed, to recompence the lack of his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward wants and imperfections, with the mindes inward vertues &amp; more ſplendant graces. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, if the outward ſhape appeared Angell-like &amp; goodly: to make the inward part thereto as beautifull in reſemblance, by auoyding all occaſions that may deforme it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3672:10"/>Vpon conſideration (gentle Reader) of that which hath been before alleaged, happening ſo vvell on this excellent Treatiſe, vvritten in French by <hi>Monſieur du Pleſsis,</hi> an honorable Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Kings Counſell, and gouernour of his Crovvne and Kingdome of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The true knowledge of a mans owne ſelfe,</hi> and therfore may the more aptly be compared to a Glaſſe, that guides a man to the knowledge of himſelf: I was the more deſirous to beſtow tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on it, that it might paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade to generall benefit.</p>
            <p>And ſo much the rather was I thereto induced, becauſe this Glaſſe hath a vvonderous diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from the other, which but
<pb facs="tcp:3672:10"/>
deliuer our outward ſhape and ſemblance onely; For this diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers the inward parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, from the very houre of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, to the lateſt minute of life, vvith the manner of nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, encreaſing and grovving to perfection, and how the body naturally liueth by his power &amp; organes, with euery ſence, nerue and faculty thereto belonging; likewiſe how the ſoule hath her being in the body, approouing the dignitie and immortalitie thereof.</p>
            <p>My humble ſute to thee, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall of my labour, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable benefitte thou mayſt gaine heereby: is, that thou wouldſt reade it with reuerence and diſcretion, as a woorke not
<pb facs="tcp:3672:11"/>
meete for euery immodeſt iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Let thy reuerence be to God, who hath ſo miraculouſly wrought for thee, and beſtowed ſo many bleſsings on thee in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Let thy diſcretion guide thee ſtep by ſtep, to a true and perfect knovvledge of thy ſelfe, by ſhunning thoſe corruptions and vices that blemiſh &amp; vvrong Nature, and embracing thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent preſcriptions heerein in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, to preſerue thee in a moſt tranquile &amp; happy condition.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, for him that firſt in French vvrote it, and my ſelfe that haue made it apt for thee in Engliſh: we will refer our ſelues together to thine ovvne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, beeing loath to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue ſo vnkindlie of thee, as for
<pb facs="tcp:3672:11"/>
a good turne to looke for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then kindnes at the leaſt, which if thou canſt affoord vs, it is all we deſire, and in trueth no leſſe then wee haue well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, A. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:3672:12"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <list>
               <label>FOr dogs, read drugs.</label>
               <item>page, 1. line 6.</item>
               <label>For Genues, read Gennes.</label>
               <item>pa. 34. li. 11.</item>
               <label>For inteſtiues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> read inteſtines.</label>
               <item>pa. 52. li. 2.</item>
               <label>For he, read the.</label>
               <item>page 53. line. 20.</item>
               <label>For cerkitude, read certitude.</label>
               <item>page. 96.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3672:12"/>
            <head>The true knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a mans owne ſelfe.</head>
            <p>IF great &amp; excellent ſpirits, tooke delight to know and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the nature of all kindes of Beaſtes, trees, hearbes, dogges, &amp; other things, vvhich God by his power crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by his wiſedom go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernes &amp; maintaineth, and in his liberal boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath ordained to our vſe: ſurely, vvith farre greater reaſon, vvee ought to take ſome
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3672:13"/>
paines to haue knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our own ſelues.</p>
            <p>The knovvledge of a mans owne ſelfe,<note place="margin">The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the knowledge of a mans owne ſelfe.</note> auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, not onely for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the bodies health, but likewiſe to moderate the veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of inordinate affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which hinder and impeach the health of iudgement. And, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bee a matter indeed very hard to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, in regard of the excellencie &amp; inexpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable maieſtie therein conſiſting, agreeing with him that ſaid, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent actions are of great difficultie:</hi> Yet, for the profit and pleaſure
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3672:13"/>
which may be gathered thereby, my good will ſhall ſtretch foorth her vttermoſt abilitie. Our neereſt way then to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this intelligence, is in ſpeaking firſt of our chiefe &amp; principall part, namely the ſoule.</p>
            <p>The ſoule is a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſimple,<note place="margin">What the Soule is.</note> hauing continuall agitation in the naturall bodie, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of parts capable to the actions thereof, and albeit (of herſelfe) ſhee haue powers and perfections: yet it is ſo, that while ſhee abideth within the bodie, ſhee hath no vſe vvithout her organes, and thoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3672:14"/>
parts of the bodie that doe agree with her acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The vertues of the ſoule.</note>It remayneth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to know what ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are in the Soule; in what parts of the body ſhe performes her acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; by vvhat meanes; &amp; how her vertues are extended; with the full effects of her ſtrength.</p>
            <p>The Phyloſopher numbers fiue ſeuerall powers in the ſoule,<note place="margin">The powers in the ſoule.</note> which are diſcerned by offices, organs and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, that is to ſay, thoſe thinges whereon ſhee grounds her action.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers or perfections, is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3672:14"/>
called <hi>vegetatiue,</hi> which by the meanes of ſuch thinges as doe preſerue her, (namely, ayre, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drinking, ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and watching, reſt and motion, euacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuperfluities, and the affections of the hart nouriſhing the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,) doe giue increaſe, and power to beget.</p>
            <p>Nouriſhment is made by the vertue of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heate,<note place="margin">Of nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerts the meat &amp; drink into the ſubſtaunce of him that takes it. The organes &amp; inſtruments which haue vſe of this power in operation, are thoſe parts of the body
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3672:15"/>
appointed to receiue, change, and tranſport our foode: as are the mouth, the pipe or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the throate, the <hi>ventricle,</hi> the liuer, and the veines, which doe conuey the blood.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, all the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies parts doe ſerue to make nouriſhment, &amp; conuert the ſeuerall ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or ſuſtenaunce into their ſubſtaunce: whereupon one vvell ſaith, that each part hath his peculiar pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to receiue, retaine, alter, and expell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the bodies nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment.</note>The maner how the body is nouriſhed, is neceſſary to be known<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3672:15"/>
as well in regarde of health, as alſo behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, which makes mee the more willing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it, for all mens ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier apprehenſion.</p>
            <p>When the ſtomacke or <hi>ventricle</hi> hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the foode, it locks it vp afterward to heate &amp; conuert it into a kind of white matter, which beeing ſo changed (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his qualities) diſcends by degrees in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the guts and bowels, certaine veines wherof doe ſucke and draw the very pureſt &amp; beſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, and ſo do cary it to the Liuer.</p>
            <p>When it is groſſe &amp;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3672:16"/>
ſuperfluous, it diſcends into the nether guttes, but when it is elaborate and refined by the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, then doth it make ſome ample diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Choller.</note>For, the <hi>chollerick hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour,</hi> in the greateſt part is with-drawne, &amp; receiued into a little purſſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called <hi>the purſe of the gaule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Melancholie</note>
               <hi>Mellancholie,</hi> which is the very groſſeſt and moſt earthy bloode, is ſent into the <hi>Spleene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The part cold &amp; dry, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called <hi>fleame,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phlegme.</note> is diſperſed by diuers proportions into the veines, according to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3672:16"/>
oppinion of many, the very beſt whereof the kidneies doe drawe to them for theyr nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the reſt is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by veſſels atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on the bladder, whereof vrine is made in that part.</p>
            <p>What elſe remaineth of this maſſe or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, is tranſported to the hart, where the right <hi>ventricle</hi> thereof receiues and purifies it, to the ende it may bee conuenable and fit for nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>Moreouer,<note place="margin">Of the blood.</note> one part of the bloode ſo recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into the right <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle</hi> of the hart, is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3672:17"/>
vnto the left <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle,</hi> &amp; conuerted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>ſpirits vitall:</hi> So called, becauſe by them the life &amp; natural heate of the bodie is preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and ſo are the <hi>ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall ſpirits</hi> of the braine made, which are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of moouing and vnderſtanding, and of thoſe noble actions that conduct our life.</p>
            <p>Againe, from thys right <hi>ventricle</hi> of the hart, is the blood diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into the veines, and from them an appoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; commutation of them, is conuayed into our ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>There are three ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3672:17"/>
digeſtions made,<note place="margin">Three kinds of digeſtion to perfect nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</note> onely to perfect thys nouriſhment: the firſt is in the <hi>ventricle,</hi> which vulgarly is called the ſtomack, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the food is conuerted into mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dry and white: the ſecond is in the Liuer, where the ſaid matter is altered, &amp; takes a kind of red colour: the third is in the veines, where this matter (already co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted red, and made blood) is purified, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and heated, by the vertue and warmth of thoſe ſpirits which are in the arteries, &amp; (as the nature of ſweat) doe paſſe ouer the heads of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3672:18"/>
thoſe arteries, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly is mingled with the blood of the veines.</p>
            <p>Heerein truly nature gaue vs the lawe &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our graces,<note place="margin">Natures in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction concerning our gifts &amp; graces.</note> gyfts, and perfections, from one to another, for the arteries, which are the pypes appoynted for carriage of the ſpirits, where the fineſt &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteſt blood (regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie placed vnder the veines, by poares &amp; lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle holes almoſt imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible) doe make co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie of their ſpirits with the veines, to the end that the bloode of thoſe veines moſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3672:18"/>
and cold, might be heated, altered, &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiled by the meanes of thoſe ſpirits: in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of which bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, the veines doe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part theyr blood to the arteries, to moiſten and temper theyr ſpyrites, which (without thys helpe) would be verie dry, burning, and too hote.</p>
            <p>The like argument deriued from nature, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth S. Paule, 1, Cor. 12.<note place="margin">1. Cor, 12.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferring the offices of the bodies members, the vtilitie, dignitie and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication of them, with the ſpirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which god hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3672:19"/>
to euerie one perticulerly, to make a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plete body, &amp; an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire church (as it were,) the place is well worth the noting.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience of the firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, not holpen by the other.</note>Wee commonly ſay, that the hurte or defect of the firſt digeſtion, cannot be corrected &amp; repaired by the other: euen ſo, when the <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle</hi> dooth not iuſtlie performe his dutie, the matter which remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ouer-rawe or cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, can neuer ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der good blood.</p>
            <p>Therefore, ſuch as giue not due leyſure to theyr ſtomack to make digeſtion, doe fill their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3672:19"/>
bodies with hurtful hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, abating and weakening the vertue of theyr ſtomacke, and likewiſe of theyr liuer: whence groweth Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, trembling or ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the members, age haſtened ſooner the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be, with bliſters and bleanes, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhape the bodie.</p>
            <p>Yet is not this all the inconuenience &amp; hurt that enſues heereby, for if the blood be impure, the ſpirits made therof, cannot be cleere or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, of which ſpirits, are vapours &amp; fumes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly extracted &amp; drawn
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3672:20"/>
fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the blood, of which ſpirits are begotten and heated the left <hi>ventri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> of the hart, &amp; made like induſtrious &amp; liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſparkles, to giue heat and vertue to the parts of nature, as both prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and produce theyr actions.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſparkles haue been (by reaſon of their dignitie &amp; excellence) in ſo great admiration,<note place="margin">The oppi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſom concerning the ſoule.</note> that diuers entred raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into this errour, that thoſe ſpirits were the ſubſtance of the ſoule: then the impure blood, badly digeſted, groſſe and diſorderly concoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted can neuer be made
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3672:20"/>
ſpirites, nor by ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſe and impure ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, can be doone anie noble actions, neyther can the ſoule be freelie exerciſed in her offices, onely through theyr moſt harmefull hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances.</p>
            <p>For we ſee thoſe men that are giuen to intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perancie,<note place="margin">The hurt of intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancie.</note> be common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſleepie, dull, of ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der capacitie, not able any long while to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template, retaine, well conferre, or vnderſtand the order, diſcourſe, cauſes and effects of thinges, neyther what conuenaunce or diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is among them:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3672:21"/>
nor can they promptly or expeditiouſly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and iudge the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite or harme, which enſueth on any thing taken in hand, ſo great is the intemperance of the mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Herac. Ephe.</note>
               <hi>Heraclitus</hi> the <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> by impuritie of his feeding, became full of the Dropſie.<note place="margin">Salomon.</note> Salomon ſaith, <hi>that more periſh by the intemperance of the mouth, then by the ſword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hipocrates numbers ſixe things,<note place="margin">Sixe things not natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in vs.</note> which hee calls not naturall in vs, becauſe they are no parts at all or members of the body, yet neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie notwithſtanding
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3672:21"/>
to maintain life: which are ayre, eating &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſleep and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, motion &amp; reſt, euacuation of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities, and the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the hart. Hee giues a rule whereby to know thoſe things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the bodie, as alſo the manner &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der howe to vſe them. Firſt (ſaith hee) labour and moderate exerciſe of the body, meat, drink &amp; ſleep, all theſe things are to bee vſed in a meane.</p>
            <p>The benefite of the firſt, is,<note place="margin">The benefit of labour.</note> that by mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate labor, naturall heat is excited and mooued,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3672:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſuperfluities are conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp; expelled, which is a profitable thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore new viands be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. For euen as hot water by the fires ſide becomes coole, when cold water is mingled therewith: ſo is digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hindered, when the ſtomacke is charged vvith freſh receite of foode, not ſtaying till the former haue taken his due courſe. Thys ought wee eſpecially to auoyde, according to the rule which ſayth: that the more vve nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh an impure bodie, the more we do offend &amp; dangerouſly hurt it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3672:22"/>Thoſe labours &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, which do cauſe great agitation of the armes &amp; ſtomacke, are moſt agreeable for health: but care muſt bee had of ouer great ſtirring, as well of the bodie as of the minde, immediatly after refec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is receiued, for then we ſhould reſt, or keep ourſelues from immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate moouing,<note place="margin">The hurt of immoderate exerciſe.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (in that caſe) the ſtomacke beeing too much ſtirred, it cannot intirely and fully make his digeſtion: For the little doore beneath in the ſtomacke, by thys ouer-haſtie ſtirring, is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3672:23"/>
opened, &amp; therethrogh eſcapeth ſome matter vndigeſted, which fault (as already vvee haue ſaid) cannot afterwarde againe repaire it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The qualities, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or quantities, the kindes or ſorts of food, the time, and the place for taking them, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions both of them, and thoſe that receiue them: ought alſo to be diligently co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered &amp; weighed, but them we doe referre to the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, who haue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in preſcribed very lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned rules.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The benefit of ſleepe.</note>Sleepe is neceſſarie for the preſeruation of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3672:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
health, and then it beſt agreeth with the bodie, when the vapours and fumes (both ſweet and profitable) of nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, beeing in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, doe raiſe vp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the braine, ſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſweetly thorowe the <hi>ventricles</hi> of the braine, thickning and mingling them-ſelues vvith the braines natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall coldnes: for, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending, they woulde hinder the courſe of the <hi>motiue</hi> and <hi>ſenſitiue</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and ſtop the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits of vnderſtanding, and thoſe nerues vſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſeruing for motion. Nor doe I without iuſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3672:24"/>
cauſe terme theſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours to be ſweet: for if they bee at any time too clammie, ſharp, dul, or ſlow, they doe then wounde the braine, and engender Apoplexies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How ſleepe profits the powers of the Soule.</note>This reſt ſerues to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create the powers of the ſoule, it moyſtens the braine to beget new ſpirits, and labours for perfecting the offices of the <hi>ventricle</hi> &amp; liuer: all which thinges at full it performeth, becauſe the hart (therby) reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates &amp; drawes his heat to him. For thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers which are farre off from the hart, do wexe cold by ſleeping, as we
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3672:24"/>
may note in the hands, head and feete: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it behoueth to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thoſe parts better in the time of reſt &amp; ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are awake, buſied, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring.</p>
            <p>This reuocation of heate and blood for the hart, works it ſelfe thus,<note place="margin">How heate and blood worke for the hart.</note> the vapors being made cold by the braine, in diſcending, doe meete warme fumes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming from the hart, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon thoſe vapours are chaſed to the exteriour parts, and ſo the heate of the hart more amply is augmented: wherof, the hart, by the arteries,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3672:25"/>
like to a King, (willing to aſſiſt &amp; furniſh tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly the indigences &amp; wants of the liuer, and the ſtomack) makes his prouiſion and ſtore of blood &amp; heate, to help the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſupply in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting their concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and offices of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And aſſuredlie, heerein we haue a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie example, of the well guiding, gouerning, &amp; managing of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth:<note place="margin">An excellent compariſon.</note> for the hart (as Prince and King) enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth &amp; furniſheth him ſelf in the time of peace and reſt, (commonlie called ſleep) to the end he may in needful time
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3672:25"/>
likewiſe, diſtribute to the liuer and ſtomacke, ſuch ſpirits as are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for their working, which ſpirits do helpe, further and fortefie the naturall heate.</p>
            <p>Truely,<note place="margin">Three du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties needfull in a Prince or Ruler.</note> the firſt and chiefeſt office of a Prince or Gouernour of any Country, is, or ought to bee, that his Subiects may liue in quiet, without vexation or trouble of incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and thefts of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>The ſecond office, is, that he take order they haue victuals and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, for their nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3672:26"/>
And the third, is, that they ſhould bee inſtructed in Religion, honeſt actions, &amp; other neceſſary Artes, for maintenaunce of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſocietie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Concluſion concerning ſleepe.</note>Sleepe then is moſt neceſſarie, and ſerueth for euery one of theſe vertues in the ſoul, as in the office <hi>vegetatiue</hi> or nouriſhing, becauſe it perfects digeſtion: and there is nothing more certaine, then that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable crudities doe come thorow lacke of reſt &amp; ſleepe. For not onely by ouer-long watching, the food re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued cannot perfectly
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3672:26"/>
concoct it ſelf, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the vertue of the <hi>ventricle</hi> is feebled and vtterly ouer-throwne: as well through the charge &amp; weight of the foode, as alſo that the nerues are made weake by the feeblenes of the braine, whence they proceede, and this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie is only cauſed by want of reſt. It ſerues alſo in the power <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petente:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The power appetente.</note> for the hart at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts his heate, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genders great aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſpirits, which are alwaies the cleerer, the more the bloode is neate and purified.</p>
            <p>It profits likewiſe the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3672:27"/>
power principal, which is the vertue <hi>Intellectiue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The power Intellectiue.</note> for hee orders his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by meanes of the ſpirits in the braine, which touch &amp; mooue the nerues, as well ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue as motiue.</p>
            <p>Adde wee heereto, that in ſleepe, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the braine is refreſhed and moiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which braine, (by too great drynes,) loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his complexion, &amp; the ſubſtaunce of the nerues cannot then wel performe their offices: iuſtly agreeing with the ſtrings of a muſicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument,<note place="margin">An apt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon.</note> which if they be too dry, or too moiſt,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3672:27"/>
too ſlack, or too much exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, they can yield no ſounde of good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordance.</p>
            <p>This place admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth vs to ſpeake of dreames and fantaſies,<note place="margin">Concerning dreames in ſleepe.</note> which happen in the time of ſleepe, and are nothing elſe but meere imaginations, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelues, vvhen the ſpirits (which are the inſtruments of our cogitations) leaue their orderly courſe, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedly and irregulerly moue themſelues in the braine.</p>
            <p>There are diuers ſorts of dreames,<note place="margin">Diuers kinds of dreames.</note> ſome being called common &amp; vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3672:28"/>
becauſe that the cauſes are euident: as when in our ſleepe, the images and ſhapes of things, which the day before haue exerciſed and frequented our co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, doe make a tender and offer of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues:<note place="margin">Example of dreames, the cauſes being euident.</note> as Iudges do of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reuolue on theyr law-caſes: Scholaſtical Diuines, on theyr rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; vrgent exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations: Carters cal on theyr horſes: Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards on their ſheepe, and ſo of others.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">When the cauſe of dreames is in vs.</note>Sometimes the cauſe of dreames is within vs, as thoſe dreames which agree with the humors
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3672:28"/>
abounding &amp; working in vs, and theſe humors doe induce imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: as ſometimes, by the great aboundance of phlegme beeing in the ſtomacke, a man dreams that he is ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in a water: or by the weight &amp; thicknes of humour in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke or braine, a man thinkes he is crowded, or down-preſſed in his ſleepe.</p>
            <p>There be other ſorts of dreames,<note place="margin">Dreames fore-telling things to enſue.</note> which are many times predictions or fore-runners, of ſuch things as are to enſue: but theſe dreames are not alwaies certaine, &amp;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3672:29"/>
they happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to perſons, by reaſon of ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexion or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prature remaining in them, or elſe by gyft of diuine perfection: as naturally ſome one is more enclined to poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie or muſique, then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Examples concerning dreames.</note>Many eſpeciall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples haue beene no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as namely the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> who dreamed that the Tent belonging to the ſayde Prince, ſhould be ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: whereof he aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed the Emperor, who immediatly did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from thence, and ſoone after it hapned,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3672:29"/>
that the enemy came &amp; ſet vpon it, ſpoyling &amp; deſtroying all that was in it.</p>
            <p>And Cicero, who dreamed of Octauius before hee knewe him, that hee ſhould be the Prince of that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. And a ſouldier at <hi>Genues,</hi> who drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that hee ſhould be deuoured by a Serpent, and therefore, on the day he ſhould haue bin ſhipt away thence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, he hid himſelfe in his houſe: where, by the inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of a tumult, vvhich happened that day in the Citty, he was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3672:30"/>
ſlaine by a bullet, which came from a peece na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a Serpentine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diuine dreames or inſpirations.</note>There are other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of dreames, which diuinely are ſent to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by inſpirations, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounciations of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: ſuch as were the dreames of Iacob, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, Daniell, and ſuch like. Such doe neuer happen vpon light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires or occaſions, but in caſes of importance: as for the gouernment of GODS church in Kingdoms and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weales, for order and obſeruation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be kept: Which kinde of dreames are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3672:30"/>
alwaies certaine. There be others deuiliſh,<note place="margin">Deuilliſh dreames.</note> as the dream of <hi>Caſſius,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius</hi> writeth.</p>
            <p>Wee haue then ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſufficiently (for this time) of the manner how we are nouriſhed, which behooueth the more to be vnderſtood,<note place="margin">The hurt of intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> for our better preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intemperance: for when wee giue no leyſure to Nature, to make her concoctions and tranſmutations, the receptacles of the bodie doe fil themſelues with hurtfull humors, which rotting within vs, doe engender very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous diſeaſes: conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3672:31"/>
that the free and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall courſe of the ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall ſpirits, which are the chiefeſt and verie neereſt inſtruments, or organes of our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, are hindered by the colde fumes of the ſtomack, which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe mount vp into the braine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Encreaſe of nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>The augmentation of nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t differs on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, according to the time &amp; quantitie of the creature, for there is a power, which in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time cauſeth in the creature a iuſt quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, according to his kinde: to wit, when it increaſeth through all
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3672:31"/>
his dime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſions, as length, largenes, and thicknes in al parts, which works it ſelfe about fiue and twenty or thirty yeeres.<note place="margin">When Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth moſt ſubſtance to her ſelfe.</note> In this time nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth moſt ſubſtance by what ſhee takes, which ſhee looſeth not by emptying her fumes &amp; excrements, for then is the heate naturall in greateſt force.</p>
            <p>Galen ſaith, that after this iuſt quantity is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the creature, the action of nature growes to weaken, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the pipes &amp; veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the body, wexe to bee more dry then before: but we ſay that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3672:32"/>
it is the ordenaunce of God, who hath conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and limitted to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery creature a tearme and date, vntill vvhich time hee ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</p>
            <p>Euen as wee behold the flame of a lampe,<note place="margin">Example how the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> to be nouriſhed &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by ſom clammie drines which is in it: in like manner the bodie of any creature, hauing life and vnderſtanding, hath ſom eſpecial good humiditie, fat and ayrie, which commeth of the ſeede and eſſentiall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the body, &amp; diſperſeth it ſelf throgh all the parts, wherein is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3672:32"/>
carried this viuifying &amp; celeſtiall heate, holding together, &amp; ſtill nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing this heate, which humiditie once conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, immediatly that heate is quenched.</p>
            <p>This humidity is (by little and little) vſed &amp; perfected by this heate,<note place="margin">When na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall heate decayeth in vs.</note> and as the meaſure and proportion of this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miditie is diminiſhed in vs, the naturall heate groweth to be the more weakened.</p>
            <p>And albeit that thys beſt and primitiue hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miditie, be ſo maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and nouriſhed, by that which wee take in eating &amp; drinking day
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3672:33"/>
by day, yet whatſoeuer exceedeth, or goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond that iuſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, is held to bee moſt impure. Like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wine, which while his firſt force &amp; nature is intire, he wil very wel beare ſome ſmall quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of water: but if of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, &amp; houre by houre it ſhal be ſo commixed, he will in the end looſe all his ſtrength.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Example conceruing our life.</note>Vpon the like termes ſtandeth our life, for that which we take and receiue daily in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, doth not ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally nouriſh this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uifying heat, as the firſt and originall humidity.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3672:33"/>
For note heereby how naturall death co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth,<note place="margin">Death natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle.</note> which Ariſtotle ſayth to be, when the heat na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall is extinct: that is to ſay, when the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue &amp; originall humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie (pure and intire) is conſumed.</p>
            <p>Death not naturall,<note place="margin">Death vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by many cauſes in our ſelues.</note> hath many other cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to weaken and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueriſh this primitiue humiditie, vvhich is ſweet, pure and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate of it ſelfe: As by drunkennes, gourman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing, immoderate lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricities, and other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of all ſorts.</p>
            <p>Great pitty then is it, that in reſpect our life is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3672:34"/>
but ſhort, and that day by day it attracts &amp; ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſom diminiſhing; that yet through our own barbarouſneſſe &amp; inhumanities, (worthily termed worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe of the <hi>Cyclops</hi>) we ſhold accellerate and haſten our end, onely by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance, and diuers extraordinary kinds of exceſſes. The augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is then made by the ſame organes, &amp; by the ſame naturall heate that our nouriſhment is.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Concerning generation.</note>Generation hath his parts properly orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by nature, &amp; may be thus defined. The
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3672:34"/>
power of engendering, is that wherby the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is (as it were) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molded, and renewed for preſeruation of his kinde: that is to ſay, of the common eſſentiall forme, beeing in manie diſtinct and ſinguler parts.</p>
            <p>The manner how the fruite is formed in the matrixe of a woman,<note place="margin">Howe the fruite is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at the firſt.</note> is thus. When the matrix hath receiued the ſeede of man and woman to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, firſt of all the matrix, like to a little Ouen, (moderatelie made warme) doth dry &amp; ſweetly harden out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly the two ſeedes
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3672:35"/>
together: and makes a thin skin about it, ſuch as wee ſee about the hard ſhell of an Egge, which skinne or mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane, is made to keep and continue the ſayde ſeede, ſoftly and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly boyling within it, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by aboundance of fine and ſubtile ſpirits, which naturally are in the ſame ſeede.</p>
            <p>This me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brane, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſeede is kept and encloſed,<note place="margin">The offices of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane.</note> is principally made of the Womans ſeede, which is more ſoft, and leſſe thicke or maſſie, becauſe it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with more faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie then the other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3672:35"/>And not onely is thys membrane made to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſeede, but it is alſo for other vſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide:<note place="margin">Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veines and arteries of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane.</note> for thereon are placed and impoſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite veines &amp; arteries, to the end that by them the menſtruall bloode might be caried, for the nouriture and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the fruite, which veines &amp; arteries haue their originall, not only of the ſpermaticke veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, that is to ſay, thoſe which draw, prepare &amp; carie this ſeed, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of a great truncke or veine, planted and rooted on the liuer.</p>
            <p>This skinne is (as it
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3672:36"/>
were) folded and wrapt about the matrix, to the end the ſayde matrixe might giue warmth to the fruite round about.</p>
            <p>There is in this wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or membrane, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſmall threds of veins or arteries, which ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and extending themſelues one among another, doe conſtitute and make two veines and two arteries, and in the midſt of them a conduit. Theſe veines and arteries, like rootes of fruite,<note place="margin">Howe the nauill is made, &amp; in what time.</note> beeing plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſeede, doe make the nauil: where, by the firſt ſixe dayes, nature cloatheth theſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3672:36"/>
ſtringes and threds of veines and arteries, and the ſeede ſoftly boyleth in his folder. Then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſeauenth day, when the nauill is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and theſe veines and arteries ioyned, through them is drawn the blood and ſpirits, &amp; caried &amp; mingled with the ſaide ſeede, for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the principall members. For in thys enuellopper there are diuers entries, like the entring into ſome little vault or ſeller, in which entries or concauities, they are conioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, &amp; (thorow thoſe vaultes) the little rootes
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3672:37"/>
doe attract blood and ſpirit. And while the ſeede thus heats &amp; boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,<note place="margin">The places for the liuer, hart, and braine.</note> it is made like three litle bladders or purſes, which are the places for the liuer, the hart, and braine.</p>
            <p>There is then drawn along by a veine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the nauil, ſome thicke bloode, as nouriſhment, vvhich thickens &amp; ſhuts it ſelfe into the ſeede.</p>
            <p>The fore-ſaid veine is forked, and alongſt one of thoſe braunches paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this blood,<note place="margin">How the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and what it is.</note> and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles it ſelfe to a thicke ſubſtance: behold then how the liuer is formed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:3672:37"/>Wee ſee by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that the Liuer is nothing elſe but thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned blood, grown hard together, and this liuer hath many ſmal threds, which ſerue to attract, retaine, change and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, according as vve haue before declared.</p>
            <p>Alongſt the other branch of this veine, is formed a gutte or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, which ſoone after,<note place="margin">How the bowels are faſtned to the backe.</note> carieth, contriueth and faſteneth the bowels or inwards, to the backe of the creature, and it is a veſſell where-with to ſuſtaine the veines, wherin proſpereth the verie pureſt part of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3672:38"/>
blood, in the ſmalleſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines or inwards, and ſo conueies it to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. In like manner, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longſt the ſame bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch, the ſtomack, the ſpleen, and the bowels are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. So whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the liuer is perfected, he makes an aſſembly of the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt veines, as of little rootes, and by their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling is made a great veine on the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per part of the Liuer, which vaine produceth ſome high braunching foorth, whereof is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Diaphragma:</hi>
               <note place="margin">How Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragma is formed.</note> to wit, a ſtrange rounde muſcle, lying ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart the lower part
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3672:38"/>
of the breaſt, ſeperating the hart and lites from the ſtomacke, with the Liuer and the Spleene. And ſo is made a part of the bones belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the backe,<note place="margin">Of the back bones.</note> and there be bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches which ſhoote out ſome-what lower, whereof is alſo formed the reſt of the ſaid back bones.</p>
            <p>The arteries diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the nauill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſeede, doe tende toward the ridge of the back,<note place="margin">The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the hart.</note> &amp; by little and little haue a place deſigned, for forming and engendring of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hart. Theſe arteries doe drawe the hoteſt and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3672:39"/>
moſt ſubtile bloode, whereof in the little purſe (therfore appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) is the hart engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and formed: vvhich hart is a ſolide fleſh, hard and thick, as is moſt conuenable for ſo very hott a member.</p>
            <p>The great plant or veine, extends &amp; goes iuſt to the right <hi>ventri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> of the hart, onely to carry and adminiſter blood for his nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:<note place="margin">The harts nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> and beneath this veine, ariſeth or ſprings vp another vein, which carrieth the purified blood to the lites, made ſubtile and hote, onelie to nouriſh and keepe it
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3672:39"/>
warme.</p>
            <p>At the left <hi>ventricle</hi> of the hart ariſeth a great arterie, which carrieth the <hi>ſpirits vitall,</hi> formed of blood by the heat of the hart,<note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon worth the noting.</note> thorow all the body. And euen as by the braunches of thys great trunck of veines, the blood is conueyed thorowe all the bodies parts for nouriſhment thereof: So by the boughes or armes of this arterie, are the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits likewiſe caried tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe all the bodie, to furniſh it with <hi>vitall heate.</hi> And doubtleſſe,<note place="margin">The hart is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of heat vitall.</note> the hart is the beginner of <hi>vitall heate,</hi> without
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3672:40"/>
which, the other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers can not produce their actions, neither can theyr nouriſhment be dulie made.</p>
            <p>Vnder this artery of the fore-ſaid left <hi>ventri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</hi> ſprings vp another arterie, which ſerues to carry the ſweet ayre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lungs &amp; lites to the hart, to refreſh it: and likewiſe to recarry the ayre, beeing firſt made warme by the hart. So then, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe two <hi>ventricles</hi> of the hart, are thoſe veins brought forth which doe intend to the lites: of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile bloode (vvhich is tranſported by this
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3672:40"/>
veine of the right <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle</hi> of the hart,<note place="margin">Howe the lungs and lites are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the height of the body.</note>) is the lungs and lites formed and made, and ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiuely all the height of the body, is made by theſe arteries &amp; veines, which are conueyers to the ſpirits and bloode, whereby nature fullie makes vp all her buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>Soone after, the brain,<note place="margin">The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the braine.</note> which is the place and ſeate for the very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt functions and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of nature, is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in this manner. A great part of the ſeede with-drawes it ſelf, &amp; is receiued into the third little purſe before ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3672:41"/>
heereof is the braine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is ioyned a couer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, hard and dry by force of naturall heate, like vnto a tile in a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace,<note place="margin">The skul of the head.</note> &amp; that is the skul of the heade. So the braine is onely made of the ſeede, to receiue, conſerue &amp; change the ſpirits, which are the inſtruments and cauſes of voluntary moouing, and of vnderſtanding: it behoueth then that it ſhould not be made of vile or ſimple matter, but of the aboundance of ſeed, fulleſt of ſpirits.</p>
            <p>Novve, euen as the veines are bredde in the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3672:41"/>
liuer, and the arteries in the hart:<note place="margin">The nerues are bred in the braine, as the veines in the liuer.</note> So are the nerues in the braine, which are of the nature of the braine, viſcuous, clammie and hard. Nor are they holow, like the veines and arteries, but ſolid &amp; maſſie: except thoſe two that are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Opticke,</hi> which doe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uey the ſpirits of the braine into the ſight of the eye.</p>
            <p>From the braine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cends the marrowe in the chine of the backe, and there is great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, between the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of the other bones, and this heere ſpoken of: for the marrowe in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3672:42"/>
the other bones is a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluitie of nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, engendred of blood, ordained to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and moiſten the bones,<note place="margin">The mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in the chine bone of the back.</note> but the marrow in the chine bone of the back, is engendered and made of the ſeede, appointed for produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the nerues <hi>ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> and <hi>motiue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVee may (by that which hath been ſaide) in ſome ſort knowe the beginning and faſhion of our humaine bodie. VVhile the fruite is in the wombe,<note place="margin">Howe the fruit is nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the wombe.</note> it is nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by blood, attrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the nauil, becauſe the fluxes ordinarie to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3672:42"/>
women, do ceaſe when they become great, and the infant drawes abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of blood for his nouriſhment. The ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous blood is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into three parts: of the very beſt &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt part,<note place="margin">The deuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the blood into three parts, and to what vſes.</note> is the infant nouriſhed in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers bellie: the other part leſſe pure, is caried to the breaſts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted into milke: the third and laſt part, like ſlime in the bottome of a mariſh, is diſcharged in the birth of the child.</p>
            <p>The times of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants beeing in the wombe, are diſcerned in this ſort: and the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3672:43"/>
of male chyldren,<note place="margin">Male chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren more perfect then female.</note> are euer more perfect then the female, for the ſeede whereof the male is made, is hotter then the other.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſecret, &amp; worthy (w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence) to be regarded.</note>The firſt ſixe dayes after conception, the ſeede boileth, reſolueth, and becommeth as an egge, making three lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle bladders or purſes, as before wee haue decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>Nine dayes follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is the attractions of blood, wherof are made the liuer and the hart: and twelue dayes after the afore-ſaid ſixe and nine dayes, is the liuer, the hart, and the braine
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3672:43"/>
to bee ſeene and diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Then eyghteene dayes after, are the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther members formed: theſe dayes nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, are fortie and fiue, and then when the members are formed &amp; diſcerned, the fruit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to haue life, for it hath ſom feeling: wher vpon it is ſaide, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the fiue and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day, the ſoule is infuſed into the body.</p>
            <p>Hipocrates giues a very good rule, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this manner.<note place="margin">Hipocrates rule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, to deliuerance.</note> The daies from the concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the perfection &amp; intire forming of the members, beeing dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3672:44"/>
doe declare the time of the childs ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: and thoſe dayes trebled, doe ſhewe the day for his deliuerance.</p>
            <p>So then, if the infant haue his members and parts perfect the fiue &amp; fortieth day, he will ſtir at ninetie dayes, &amp; ſhal bee borne the ninth month. This rule is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie in male Chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but the female ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie longer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue, and how it nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth and increaſeth the body, as alſo main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth kind</note>It is as eaſie likewiſe to iudge, howe much the power <hi>vegetatiue</hi> is neceſſary, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues and maintaineth (by his offices) as vvell the whole frame, as the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3672:44"/>
ſinguler parts there-to belonging: that is to ſay, by nouriſhing and augmenting, it main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines the ſeueral parts, and by generation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues and ſupplies the ſtate of kind. Euery one ought to know thys, &amp; reuerence theſe gifts of God in nature, vſing them lawfully, and to the benefit of humaine ſocietie: For it is no light offence, to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue and diſſolute in theſe thinges, wherein likewiſe if we keep not a meane and meaſure, there dooth enſue hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible paines, not onely temporal, but alſo eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3672:45"/>
Indeede Nature admoniſheth vs to bee continent,<note place="margin">How nature admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs to be continent.</note> and if ſhee woulde not bee defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the beginning, ſhee would haue no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther power vſed in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration then is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary:<note place="margin">Our ſelues the greateſt enemies to nature.</note> but we deſtroy al, by vaine lubricities, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant &amp; inordinate meanes, decaying Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in her very ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Ouer and beyonde this, the dilligence, arte and care, which nature appointeth to engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, preſerue and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the infant in the wombe of his mother: aduiſeth vs to preſerue and bee reſpectiue of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3672:45"/>
kind. It is then great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanitie, rage and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, if one part do grow offenſiue to another: for we ſee by the arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecture of nature, the faſhion, the ſeate, the order and vſe of euerie ſeuerall part, that there was an infinite power in the Creator of thys frame and peece of workmanſhippe,<note place="margin">The infinite goodnes of God in our bodies fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</note> by ſo great wiſedome or day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and compaſſed, by vnexpreſſable goodnes liberally furniſhed, and prouided of all thinges for noriſhing &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the ſame.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſees not &amp; vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3672:46"/>
theſe things, hath loſt the light of true ſence, and is more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate to humaine nature, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Nabuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzer when hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a bruite beaſt.</p>
            <p>And in truth, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of theſe powers is worthy conſideration:<note place="margin">Howe the order of the ſeuerall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers is to be conſidered in theyr of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices.</note> for (as hath beene ſaid) the power to nouriſh, maintaines the diſtinct and ſinguler parts: the power of augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, giues them a iuſt quantitie, that is to ſay, greatnes, largenes and thicknes: the power to engender, preſerues &amp; ſupplies kinde. I ſay (in repeating it againe) that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3672:46"/>
this order cleerly ſhews vs, that there is an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall GOD,<note place="margin">An abſolute proofe of God againſt any Atheiſt whatſoeuer.</note> who by his infinite power created theſe natures, &amp; by his inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible vviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom aſſigned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr offices, and ſeperated theyr effects, as we may behold that euery one begetteth a thing like to himſelfe. For theſe kindes are guarded in their cerkitude, and by a certaine law and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner are theſe liuing cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures produced: and not confuſedly (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out counſell) mingled &amp; confounded in their kindes.</p>
            <p>We ſhould conſider
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3672:47"/>
and acknowledge God in nature reuerently,<note place="margin">A note co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning chriſtian du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie in vs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God, in regard of al his diuine gifts beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed on vs in nature.</note> we ſhould eſteeme the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of nouriſhing, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing increaſe, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying by generation, as diuine gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the abuſe whereof is puniſhed by moſt horrible paines. VVe ſee drunkennes, licoriſh feeding, &amp; groſſe gur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandizing, to bee the cauſes of murders, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumuentions in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, trades, traffiques and merchandiſes, of beggeries, and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ruine of goods and lands, of wretched diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes and ſickneſſes, as well corporall as ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3672:47"/>
As for lubricities and immoderate thefts, we ſee the euils and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences enſuing thereby, to be great, &amp; in greater perſons then one woulde wiſh to ſee it: wherat thoſe of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnderſtanding re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue no mean diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment.</p>
            <p>The ſecond power of the ſoule,<note place="margin">Of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer Senſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, being the ſecond power of the ſoule.</note> is called <hi>ſenſitiue,</hi> it is that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee diſcerne our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall actions, and it is an excellent and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie benefite to man: not only to ſearch and ſeeke after his liuing, &amp; a certaine place wherin to confine himſelfe; but
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3672:48"/>
likewiſe for many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offices requiſite in humane ſocietie. Thys power is deuided into ſences exteriour &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, beeing fiue in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</note>The ſences exteriour are fiue, namely Sight, Hearing, Taſting, Sent or Smelling, and Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, &amp; theſe fiue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are diſcerned by theyr offices, ſeates or organes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Sight, &amp; howe the ſame is wrought in vs.</note>Sight is the ſence whereby vvee beholde colours and the light, which things are prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per obiects to the ſayd power: and this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception is wrought by the meanes of certaine
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3672:48"/>
ſpirits, comming from the braine by the <hi>optick nerues,</hi> into the apple of the eye, wherein there is a chriſtaline humour, which receiues (as by a glaſſe or mirrour) the kindes &amp; luſters of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and likewiſe of the light.</p>
            <p>We gather alſo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, the greatnes, figure, number, motion &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of bodies, yet not ſingulerly and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, but likewiſe theſe things are known with and by helpe of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſences.</p>
            <p>Ariſtotle beeing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, conſidering we haue two eyes, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3672:49"/>
all thinges which we behold, do not ſeem double to vs? the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere he made thereto was thus.<note place="margin">Ariſtotles anſwer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our two eyes.</note> That becauſe the nerues of the eye, are ſeated betweene the place of their originall, and the eye, where they meete together like the forke of a tree, therfore the ſpirits vnited there together, doe make the obiect ſeeme but one thing onely.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward organs of the ſight, and what vſe they ſerue vs to.</note>The interiour organs then of this power, are the ſpirits aſſigned to that office, and they are tranſported by the <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke nerues</hi> into the eye, whereof the exteriour
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3672:49"/>
is the eye. This power ſerues vs to knowe the heauens, &amp; they moue vs to vnderſtand, the power and wiſedom of ſo great a GOD: to know alſo the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and them ſeuerallie in their natures, to the end we might make electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the faireſt, and leaue the deformed.<note place="margin">Small diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween life &amp; death, but by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of ſight</note> In ſooth, there would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, no great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene life and death, if we ſhold haue perpetuall darkneſſe: what a wonderful bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe then is it, and more then our frayle thoughts can ſtretch vnto, that GOD hath
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3672:50"/>
giuen vs this gift, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the light?</p>
            <p>Plato ſaith, that our eyes are giuen vs,<note place="margin">Platos oppi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to what end our eyes are giuen vs.</note> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct vs in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we behold the cleerenes of heauen, with his regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and ordinarie moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for this admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth vs (whether wee will or no) of the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and maker of the world, of his great po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, wiſedom, &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and of the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and eternall light, whereof we ſhall haue ioy after this mortall life. This power hath his ſeate in the humour chriſtaline, ſhut vnder
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:3672:50"/>
the bal of the eye, which humour ſhineth of his owne nature:<note place="margin">Where the ſight hath his ſeate and abiding.</note> and the nerues thereto depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, doe carrie the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, which attain to the boule of the cirkle, that ſhewes it ſelf in the eyes to be of diuers colours.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſpirits the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giue life to the eye, and are as a little flame,<note place="margin">Of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that giue life to the eye.</note> reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the Celeſtiall bright beame, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſtrength &amp; power to ſee. The names, the matter, the qualities, &amp; the ſeat of the balls and humours of this mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, wee leaue vnto the Phiſicall Anatomiſts: but properly and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lierly,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3672:51"/>
by this ſence wee apprehend the light &amp; colours, for, as Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſayth,<note place="margin">Ariſtotles iudgment of the eye.</note> the eye can ſee nothing, but onely by his colour, which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour is the qualitie of a commixed body, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipating of the light.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A queſtion concerning the ſight of the eye.</note>One demaunds, how thoſe things offered &amp; apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by the eye, or whether ſo euer it addreſſeth it ſelfe, are thereby perceiued? the common aunſwere is,<note place="margin">The anſwer worth the noting.</note> the light beeing in the colour of the thing ſeene, ſpreads and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends his beames tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the ayre, and thys light formes an image
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3672:51"/>
in the eye, as in a mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, becauſe that the beame when it findes the eye, redoubles if ſelf &amp; gathers together, &amp; ſo the image is made: as wee ſhall ſee the Sun beame,<note place="margin">An excellent compariſon.</note> entring by a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe or crannie into an obſcure place, when it ſettles it ſelfe vpon any hard thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as on a wall, it engroſſeth &amp; redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles it ſelfe, as is very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be noted.</p>
            <p>If the light bee ouer violent, it may hurt and offende the eye,<note place="margin">How eaſilie the eye may be offended</note> as wee may ſee by the flaſh of lightning: and any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour that is too excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, cannot ſuddenlie
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3672:52"/>
and perfectly be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but it raiſeth ſome debilitie in the ſight, as we may ſee likewiſe by ſnowe: but queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, the whole nature of the light is full of meruailes, and can ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be perfectly expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, nor ſufficientlie vnderſtood.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The maner how colours are truly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned.</note>The kinds or images of whatſoeuer colours, are not perceiued at all, but onely by the means of the aire, or the water, as we may note, when one offers a thing too neer vnto the eye, then the beholder doth not plainly ſee it, for aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly, the light which is
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3672:52"/>
in the colour, is very feeble, and a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee or diſcerne it, without ſome diſtance, yea, and very ample meanes of it ſelfe.<note place="margin">The true capacitie of the eye in ſight.</note> And it is alſo to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode, that the eye ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſees any thing, but according to a direct line, and that the ſhapes or images which come into the eye, doe carrie the figure or likenes of a Piramides, which fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure is ſeated in the thing ſeene, and ſo in a direct ſharpneſſe ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it to the eye.</p>
            <p>The commodities of this ſence are euident,<note place="margin">The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which the ſence of ſight yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</note> as well for the knowledge
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3672:53"/>
of God, our ſearch for ſafetie and aſſuraunce, our willing preuention of perrils and inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences: as alſo for our choyſe and election, of thoſe things which are beautiful and fayre, and leauing them, which in themſelues appeare to be ill ſhapte and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, &amp; God knowes what confuſion would happen in our life, if we had not this happie and gracious power of ſight.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, &amp; the organs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note>Hearing is a Sence wherby we apprehend ſounds, which ſence is garniſhed outwardlie with an organe ample
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3672:53"/>
enough for entraunce, but crooked and ful of windinges in deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to the end that by little &amp; little, the ſound might gather it ſelfe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the organe: for otherwiſe, if the ſound entred violentlie, &amp; altogether, it would greatly hurt the power <hi>ſenſuiue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sounde is a qualitie,<note place="margin">What ſound or noyſe is, and howe it makes it ſelfe.</note> onely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming from the fraction of the ayre, which is made whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two bodies large and harde do beat againſt one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. This fraction is made in the ayre, as wee may eaſily ſee, when we throw a litle light ſtone
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:3672:54"/>
vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the water, it makes an appearance like litle circles, in turning and entring into the water: and euen as in ſmall &amp; narrovve Fountaines, thoſe circles beat often againſt the walls, and ſo redouble them-ſelues: euen ſo in places which are cauernie, vaulty, or in forreſts that are well furniſhed with Trees, the ayre comming fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch hollow breakings, doth very audibly and perfectly redouble the ſounds.</p>
            <p>The meanes wherby any ſuch ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or noiſe is apprehended,<note place="margin">Of the means wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by eyther ſounde or noiſe is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended.</note> is the ayre, for thereby is the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3672:54"/>
ſounde carried to the hole or buckole of the eare, and is there enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by another inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ayre, tempered by diuers ſweet ſpirits, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereunto naturallie ordained, vvhich (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a litle thin skinne ſpredde ouer the hole,) renders back againe the ſounde; as wee ſee the skin doth vpon a drum or tabour.</p>
            <p>This ſounde made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaide thinne skin,<note place="margin">Howe all ſounds are conueyed to the ſence common.</note> by the ſpirits tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered of the ſweete na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ayre, is conuayed by the nerues (for that ſeruice deputed) to the <hi>ſence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon,</hi> where only
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3672:55"/>
is made the dijudicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; diſcretion, of the qualities of all kinds of ſoundes: to wit, which are obtuſe or piercing, which are ſweet, rude, wandring or delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, &amp; ſo of al other dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and varieties in the ſounds.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The maner how our voyce or ſpeech is formed.</note>To this purpoſe may wee ſpeake of our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine voyce or ſpeech, which is formed and made on high at the rude, rough, and ſharp arterie, for ſo ſome call the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duit or wezand, vvhere the tongue (at the entraunce of the throat) ſmites &amp; cleaues the ayre, as we may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:3672:55"/>
apparantly beholde in our Flutes, ſo is the voyce made in the we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zand, and ſo is guided right alo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the throat. Therefore Fiſhes doe forme no voyce at all,<note place="margin">An excellent note co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our voyce or ſpeech.</note> for they haue no ſuch conduit, neither lungs or lytes, by the motion whereof, ayre might mount vp into theyr throat: theſe things are euident, but the meanes and cauſes are hidden, beeing an eſpeciall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite granted by God in nature. Nor can the ſaid cauſes be plainlie vnderſtoode, by the weakenes and obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the light of our
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3672:56"/>
capacities: Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, we ought re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently to giue glory to the Creator, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo wiſely created and ordained the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, motions and effects of this ſence, which is ſo profitable and auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, not onely for our health, but likewiſe for directing the affaires of this life: For, by thys ſence vvee haue faith,<note place="margin">By this ſence wee haue fayth.</note> ſaith S. Paule: thereby we alſo make our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions, &amp; in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, it is neceſſary to vnderſtand one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 Of Smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and by what organs it is appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended.</note>The ſence of Smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, is that wherby we
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:3672:56"/>
diſtinguiſh ſents and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours; The organe of this ſence is two little ſpungie teates, and full of ſpirits, which are ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted beneath the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, aboue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duit of the noſtrils, whence the ſubſtaunce of the braine, conuerts to a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle neruie skin, but yet exceeding ſoft and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie tender: by the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing &amp; preſſure where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, all ſents &amp; ſmells are apprehended.</p>
            <p>Nor are the two no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrills the proper ſence, but onely doe ſerue to conuey the odour into this organe: as is verie eaſie to be noated; for,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:3672:57"/>
we perceiue not at al a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie odours or ſmels, but only attract the ayre by the ſaid noſthrils, to the organe ſeated neere the braine, to the end, ſuch gracious ſmells might recreate &amp; cherriſh the braine.</p>
            <p>Odour or ſent,<note place="margin">What o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, ſent or ſmell is.</note> is a certaine qualitie in a ſubtile and inuiſible fume, iſſuing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed bodies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ayrie humidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is mingled in an earthly nature, aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding eyther more or leſſe, and is like a thing burnt, or much dried<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as wee may gather by the wood of Iuniper<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:3672:57"/>
&amp; others: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is ſaid, that the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour or moiſture, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernes in the ſauour, &amp; the drineſſe, in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour.</p>
            <p>Thinges burnt,<note place="margin">Apt compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons of ſents in their moiſt &amp; dry kindes.</note> that are moiſt in a medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie, doe ſauour well, but ſuch as are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dry, haue no odour at all: becauſe in them both cold and drineſſe, are the reaſons that they haue no ſent.</p>
            <p>And albeit that ſome colde things are odori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous, as bee Roſes &amp; Violets: Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, by their odor they doe heate and vvarme ſweetly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:3672:58"/>This is the reaſon, why in the Eaſt partes, things of ſtrong ſauour doe moſt encreaſe,<note place="margin">The ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt things haue leaſt ſauour.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try is hot, and likewiſe things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly ſweete, haue the leſſe ſauour, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they are fulleſt of humiditie.</p>
            <p>Contrariwiſe, thoſe thinges which bee leſſe ſtrong, &amp; yet burning, are of the better ſauour, as Roſemary is good in odoure, but very bitter in the taſte.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween good ſents and hurtfull.</note>The generall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of odours, are thoſe that bee good o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, which comes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſweeteſt parts, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:3672:58"/>
beſt digeſted, hauing an ayrie nature, and is a pleaſing recreation to the braine. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe bad odours, which are thoſe that be called ſtincking, being a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie comming from the corrupt and putrified parts, which is a poyſon and hurt to the braine.</p>
            <p>There be other diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of ſent, taken of ſauours, as is a burning and ſtrong odour, ſuch as the ſent of Garlick or Onions: &amp; the ſower ſauour, drawne from ſharpneſſe, as the ſent of vineger.<note place="margin">The means howe wee iudge of ſmells.</note> The meane vvhereby vvee diſcerne and iudge of theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:3672:59"/>
is the ayre: for Fiſhes do ſauour a ſmel or odour in the water: as we beholde them to be ſooner taken, by the ſent of ſome one baite, then of another.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sent is very neceſſary to our life.</note>It is a thing very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to life, as wel for recreating and deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the braine, by the receiuing and percep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of kindlieſt &amp; beſt pleaſing ſauour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as alſo for freeing and ridding (by the noſthrils) the ſuperfluities of the braine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 Of the ſence of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; his organe.</note>The ſence of Taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is that whereby we diſcerne and relliſh ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours: the organe of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:3672:59"/>
this ſence, is a neruous skinne, ſpred ouer the fleſhe of the tongue, which fleſhe is full of pores, ſlacke, ſlow and ſpungy.<note place="margin">Howe the tongue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues his taſt.</note> The ſelfe ſame skin is extended to the pallate, and hath his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall of thoſe nerues which diſcende by the pallate, to the roote of the tongue, &amp; giues the tongue his power to taſte, &amp; to diſcerne the foure chiefeſt qualities: Now becauſe the ſayd fleſh is full of ſpirit and humour, the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily is therin impreſſed the ſauour of things.</p>
            <p>The meanes of thys powers vſe in his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:3672:60"/>
is the ſaide looſe or ſlack fleſh,<note place="margin">The means of the taſtes vſe in his actions.</note> &amp; the ſpet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or moiſture which is aboue it: and therefore we ſee, that ſuch as haue an Ague, find al things bitter, for their ſpettle is bilious or hot, as much to ſay, as mingled with the chollerick humour.</p>
            <p>The obiect of thys ſence,<note place="margin">Sauour, the onely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of taſte.</note> is ſauour, which is a certaine qualitie in the thing, hauing more humiditie then drines, vvhich is digeſted by the heat naturall.<note place="margin">Many ſorts of ſauours.</note> There be many ſorts of ſauors, which make very much for our further know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: becauſe they ſhewe and teach the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:3672:60"/>
temperature and complexion of things, and for whom they are meeteſt, vvhich is a matter well worth the regarding and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as wel for our ciuill regiment in dyet, as for the remedie of diſeaſes: for, as Galen ſaith, it is neceſſary that our nouriture ſhoulde be ſweet, or prepared, &amp; mingled with things that are pleaſing and ſweet.</p>
            <p>The ſauour that is ſweet, as of honnie,<note place="margin">Of the ſweet ſauour.</note> or of ſweet wine, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light the tongue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch a ſauour is ayrie, &amp; agreeing with
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:3672:61"/>
our fleſhe and bloode, proper alſo to nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, temperate both in heate and drought: for, (as is already ſayd) it is needfull that the nouriſhment be ſweet, or at leaſt tempered with ſweetnes, becauſe ſweet viands &amp; drinks, doe mollifie and fill the parts which are dry &amp; vacant.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour ouer ſweet.</note>But notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſuch things as are exceeding ſweet, as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and honie, doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde in their ayrie heate, and very eaſilie enflame and conuert into choller: therefore ſuch as vſe Suger and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:3672:61"/>
honie too often, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly, it ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrong cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, &amp; putrifactions al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, onely by the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of humours.<note place="margin">Of the fatte &amp; marrowie ſauour.</note> The ſauour which is neereſt to this before named, is the fat and marrovvie, which is not ſo hott as the former: ſuch is the ſauour of butter, oyle, and fleſh.</p>
            <p>A meane in vſage of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is good, for thinges which are ouer fattie, do hurt much: becauſe they will floate vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtomacke, offend and hinder digeſtion, and alſo doe engender op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilations.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:3672:62"/>
               <note place="margin">What ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours beſt agree with nature, and moſt pleaſe the taſte.</note>Theſe two ſauors are moſt agreeable to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and delight the taſt of a healthfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For, euen as the hand glads it ſelfe, at the entrance into luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme water, beeing made temperate in his heate: ſo the taſte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights it ſelfe in thinges ſweet and fatty, becauſe they are indeed tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately hotte, like vnto the blood and fleſh, &amp; alſo doe procure delec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, in that they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in temperature with nature.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the bitter ſauour.</note>The ſauour which wee call bitter, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly contrarie to the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:3672:62"/>
ſweete, and is a ſauour that frets, makes hoarſe and bites the tongue, &amp; is of an earthy nature or complexion, which beeing thick alſo, hath naturally in it an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of heat in drines: as is the taſte of worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood and Aloes, and therefore thinges ouer bitter, doe neuer nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</p>
            <p>The ſauour ſtrong and ardent,<note place="margin">Of the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and hot ſauour.</note> differs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bitter, for not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth it wring, byte, and teare the tongue: but alſo it burnes and chaps it, which pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates &amp; enters by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drying ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely:
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:3672:63"/>
This ſauour exceeds the bitter in hotnes, and ſuch is the taſte of Pepper, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Sneeſing-woorte, Garlick and Onions.</p>
            <p>There is a ſauour cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſower, drawing on ſharpnes,<note place="margin">Of the ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſauour.</note> which in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning backe becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth cold, whereby it flagges &amp; weakens the tongue much: vvhich ſauour is both colde &amp; dry, neuertheleſſe it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth moſt in cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſuch is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of Sorrell.</p>
            <p>The ſauour of vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is not altogether ſo, for, as it retaines ſome obſcure and weak heat,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:3672:63"/>
ſo is it alſo ſome-vvhat ſtrong, and yet therein is coldnes moſt; For, when the ayrie partes thereof are caſt foorth, it remaines earthie in ſome chillie humour.</p>
            <p>Hence is it naturallie receiued,<note place="margin">The ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt ſauours doe moſt vrge appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite.</note> that ſharpeſt thinges doe giue moſt appetite: becauſe they deiect the ſuperfluous humours, gathered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore together at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the <hi>ventricle,</hi> onely by byting, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any burning. So doth Sorrel ſeem good for ſuch as haue a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, not onely becauſe it caſts out &amp; diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the ayrie ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:3672:64"/>
but likewiſe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it moderates the heate chollerick.</p>
            <p>The ſauour called greene,<note place="margin">Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greene ſauour, that edgeth the teeth.</note> which ſetts the teeth an edge, ſhuts vp and drawes backe the tongue: Wherefore it hath the power to col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, thicken, and bind faſt, being of an earthy nature, crude, cold, &amp; dry, therefore it differs from the precedent ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, becauſe the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is of a ſubtile na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and this other is thickning: of ſuch taſt are Medlars and other greene fruites, before they are come to theyr maturitie, for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:3672:64"/>
are ripe, they haue a commixed ſauour, as mingled both vvith ſweetnes &amp; greenenes.<note place="margin">Of the rude and ſharpe ſauour.</note> There are other ſauors beſides theſe, as that which is termed rude, &amp; ſharpe too, that ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dries &amp; hardens the tongue, yet neyther wreſts nor binds it, like the precedent taſte: in nature it is earthy, maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue, cold and dry, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, more hotte and moiſt then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Galen ſaith, that this relliſh is good in wine, for wines of this taſte, doe naturally ſhutte vp and dry the <hi>ventricle,</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:3672:65"/>
caſting fumes of ſmall heat vp to the braine.</p>
            <p>The ſalt ſauor makes not any retyring of the tongue,<note place="margin">Of the ſalt ſauour.</note> but it whets it by waſhing and drying it, for ſalt guardeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> putrifactions, becauſe it thinneth and drieth the parts ſeuerally, perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the humidities; wherfore ſalt hardneth ſoft fleſh, and ſoftneth hard: for, as in the ſoft it conſumeth all ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie of humour, ſo in the harde it attenuates and ſoftens the parts, making the more mild and daintie, beeing of an earthy nature, thick, hotte, and dry.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:3672:65"/>Some things are ſaid to be without ſauour,<note place="margin">Of thinges without ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour.</note> becauſe in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are not to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d any of theſe natures before expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>The ſence of Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,<note place="margin">5. Of the ſence of Touching and his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane.</note> is that whereby we diſcerne the foure chiefeſt qualities, to wit, heat, cold, drought and moiſtnes. The or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane of this, is not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſole or alone part of the body, but is like a thin skinne or neruie caule, which is ſpredde ouer the whole bodie, vnder the vppermoſt skinne, taking his ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall from the braine, and from the mouth of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3672:66"/>
the chine bone in the backe. The moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile nerues, doe make the moſt ſenſible parts, as are thoſe nerues that deſcend into the purſe of the hart, and to the <hi>ventricle.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of this ſence.</note> The benefite of this ſence is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, for a man delights when hee is hotte, to touch coole things, &amp; the coldeſt parts of the body, take pleaſure in touching thinges that are warme.</p>
            <p>The interiour ſence is a power working by organes,<note place="margin">Of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſence, and where it is ſeated.</note> ſeated within the brows or forehead, appointed for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:3672:66"/>
excelling all the exteriour ſences. For if wee ſhould apprehend onely the things, which offer and preſent them ſelues before vs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcerning or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any iudgement of them, it would profite vs but very little: For, what auailes it to looke on black and white, &amp; not to diſcerne or ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally diſtinguiſh them? Therfore the ſence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour is very behoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,<note place="margin">The neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the inward ſence</note> to make diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and dijudication of things, by their ſeuerall cauſes &amp; effects: as the horſe, accuſtomed to paſſe by the way where
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:3672:67"/>
hee hath once falne, growes afraid of falling there againe, this hath the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome power aboue the outwarde ſences, whereof we ſhal come to ſpeake hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, and memory, according to Ariſtotle.</note>Ariſtotle nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers the ſences interiour, to bee two: to wit, the Sence common, and Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Galens addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation.</note>Galen puts another to theſe two, called Cogitation, ſo hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be three.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fiue inward ſences.</note>There be others that name fiue inward Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to wit, the Sence common,<note place="margin">1. Sence common.</note> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues the images and apparitions of thinges
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:3672:67"/>
preſented to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſence.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. Sence i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginatiue.</note> the ſence Imaginatiue, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcernes the actions of each one of the exteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſences.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. Sence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimatiue.</note> the ſence E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimatiue, which by one thing iudgeth another: as a horſe, when one ſtrokes or clapps him, conceiues that he takes pleaſure in him.</p>
            <p>The fourth ſence is called Deliberation or Cogitation,<note place="margin">4. Sence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberatiue.</note> which ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> furtheſt off) the cauſes of thinges: theſe doe conferre and make iudgement, after knowledge is receiued,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:3672:68"/>
what difference and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement hath beene betweene them, which vertues and effects on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they haue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God for his creatures.</note>Our eternall GOD, hath by his (prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) enſtamped in his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, a moouing mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous, to ſearch and ſeeke after thinges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for conſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their liues, and remedies likewiſe for their diſeaſes: as Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents that ſeeke after Fennell, for clearing of theyr eyes, or young Aſſes that ſearch for the hearbe <hi>Ceterach,</hi> to allay theyr melanchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:3672:68"/>The Serpent or Snake,<note place="margin">A ſtrange example of the Snake &amp; the Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prey.</note> beeing willing to meet or company with the Fiſh called a Lamprey, begins to hiſſe or whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, to procure her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and perceiuing that ſhe comes, to meet and bee ſociable vvith him, he caſts his venim on the grauell, as fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to engender (of her) by venim or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: but when he hath ended, he returnes againe to ſeeke his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim, which if hee finde not, he dies with griefe, for hauing loſt his armes or weapons.</p>
            <p>Now, albeit that they doe theſe thinges natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:3672:69"/>
yet wee may not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding iudge,<note place="margin">A kinde of deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in dumb creatures, confirmed by exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples.</note> that they haue herein ſome kinde of deliberation: as we may note for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in a dogge, that knowes his owne mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter amongſt a huge croude of people.</p>
            <p>A Foxe, a Cat, a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and other beaſtes, which haue been ſeene to doe admirable acts: and as for Swallowes &amp; Bees, although they performe very meruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous workes, yet for all that, they haue much leſſe cogitation then they afore-named.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5. Sence is memory.</note>The fift interiour ſence, is Memory. The
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:3672:69"/>
organe of the ſence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,<note place="margin">The organe of the ſence common, &amp; his place.</note> is two <hi>ventricles</hi> at the doore or entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the braine: as much to ſay, as vvhen the nerues of the ſence ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour, doe carry their ſpirits in their concaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or <hi>ventricles,</hi> then afterward do theſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits imprint or ſtampe the ſhapes and images of things in the braine: and thus the ſence inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour workes his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>It is certain that there be many powers in the inward ſences: for,<note place="margin">Many pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſences.</note> a man may looſe memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, without any detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to eſtimation:
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:3672:70"/>
moreouer, when eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is wounded, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> medicine or remedie is applied to the forepart of the heade, but when memory is weakened, then helpe is giuen to the head behind.</p>
            <p>Cogitation hath his organe in the midſt of theſe two ventricles or concauities,<note place="margin">The organe of cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and his ſeate.</note> which are before in the head, and this power is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent to ſome, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, according to the better compoſing of their heads: as wee ſee ſome more ſudden and quick in inuenting any thing, then others are. Some alſo wil diuine &amp;
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:3672:70"/>
iudge more certainly of a propoſed caſe,<note place="margin">Example of this ſences power.</note> then others: as Salomon ſo readily perceiued that the woman lyed, who would haue the infant deuided in twaine, and diſtributed to her and the aduerſe partie by halfes, for he conferred the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeede, with the other parties, vvhich was nothing at all vnto the child.</p>
            <p>The organe of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie is behinde in the brain,<note place="margin">The organe of memorie &amp; his place.</note> which part hath leſſe humiditie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and is more apt to conſerue the images &amp; ſhapes of things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:3672:71"/>
               <note place="margin">Of the brain in his kinds, of diuerſitie.</note>A braine too moyſt, doth eaſily apprehend thinges, but ſuddenly forgets them againe: wheras, the braine that is harder, apprehends more difficultly, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth longer.</p>
            <p>Cold and drineſſe of the brain, is a very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious thing for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie: wherefore it is ſaide, that lubricitie is a plague, which ſpends all humour naturall in a man or woman, and moſt certaine is it, that age then comes, when naturall heate &amp; natiue humiditie do moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline.</p>
            <p>The power <hi>appetente,</hi>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:3672:71"/>
is that wherby we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue or flie thoſe thinges which preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues before vs: This power is called <hi>ſenſitiue appetite,</hi> vvhereby all our affections, do pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue what we haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by the exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ſence.</p>
            <p>There is one kind of appetence or deſiring,<note place="margin">Two kindes of appetence in the ſences</note> which begets it ſelfe by touching, and is one while tearmed griefe, another while delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the other is made without touching: &amp; ſo enſues cogitation, or moouing of the hart, whereby wee followe vvhat is offered, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:3672:72"/>
which cogitation (be it true or falſe) ſhewes what is moſt conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for nature, or makes vs ſhun the things that are not conuenable: ſo that naturally wee may perceiue it cannot bee otherwiſe, but that the thing preſented to the eye, muſt bee from it a ſufficient diſtaunce, or elſe it is not ſeene, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can the Nerues doe theyr delighting functions, but in tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thoſe thinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with nature, vvhereas contrariwiſe, thoſe things which are diſagreeable, breaking and hurting the parts,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:3672:72"/>
muſt needes bee yrke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to them, and very painfull.</p>
            <p>True it is,<note place="margin">Of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer Motiue.</note> that the motiue power may be reſtrained by the will, for, if wee pleaſe, vvee may ſhut our eyes, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vve can behold no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all: but vvhile the eye is open, and at libertie, diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his obiect by a ſufficient ſpace, it cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the image there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; therefore ſuch as haue ſaide, that griefes are oppinions,<note place="margin">Of greefes.</note> which come and goe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to imagination, haue ſpoken againſt manifeſt and vniuerſall
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:3672:73"/>
experience.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Foure prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Ioy.</item>
                     <item>2. Feare.</item>
                     <item>3. Hope.</item>
                     <item>4. Hate.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites foure.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Loue.</item>
                     <item>2. Greefe.</item>
                     <item>3. Enuie.</item>
                     <item>4. Iealoſie.</item>
                  </list>
               </note>There be foure prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall affections, to wit, ioy, feare, hope, and hate, whereunto are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced loue, greefe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, iealoſie and others. And ſurely it is a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous thing, that ſo ſoone as a man hath knowledge of a thing pleaſing or offenſiue: the hart moues it ſelfe, and likewiſe the ſpirits and humors of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of anger, &amp; the hurt it doth the braine.</note>As in anger, the hart (as riſing to reuendge himſelfe) labours and beates, &amp; then the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits beeing chafed, doe heat the blood, and the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:3672:73"/>
actions of the members are troubled, by the ſuddaine moouing of the ſpirits and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the blood: but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in rage or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the braine is hurt by the bloode, and the ſpirits inflamed or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-heated, doe mount thether, by fiering the nerues and ſubſtaunce of the braine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vvhich cauſeth a ſhaking or trembling in the heade, by vehement and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine mouing, as alſo a preſent fiering of the eyes, &amp; all the face be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth as burning: therefore, by ouer ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement anger, are fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zies
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:3672:74"/>
ingendered, &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes Apoplexies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Homers op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note>Homer ſaith, that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is ſweeter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> milk, as meaning, that a man takes great pleaſure, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may reuendge himſelf, as he that loues ardently, is buried (as it were) in ioy, when hee hath the iouiſſaunce of the thing by him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued.<note place="margin">Of feare, and how it hurts the hart.</note> Feare is a moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the hart or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, vvhereby the hart ſhuttes vp it ſelfe, as flying and ſhunning euill to happen, and this affection agrees with greefe: for albeit the harme or euil is not yet preſent, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:3672:74"/>
it is wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as if it were inſtant. In like maner,<note place="margin">The hurt of greefe and ſadneſſe.</note> in griefe or ſadnes, the hart (as beeing preſſed downe &amp; cloſe ſhut) is weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by drying &amp; lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing, for not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the libertie of the ſpirits: wherefore, if it continue long in this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, it prepares the death of the body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſpirits, by their long pining and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, can giue no further help or ſuccour to it: beholde vvhat great hurt enſues by greefe and ſadnes.</p>
            <p>Loue is a mouing of the hart,<note place="margin">Of loue, and how it helps the hart.</note> whereby wee
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:3672:75"/>
deſire ſome thing, be it truly good, or but in apparance only. In this mouing, the hart doth (as it were) leap &amp; flie, ſtriuing to attract that thing vnto it, onelie to enioy it: Hope dooth beſt of all agree vvith this affection, but yet ſhe is more vehement.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of hate and his hurt.</note>Hate is a kind of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant &amp; permanent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: and anger &amp; hate are contrary to loue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Shame.</note>Shame is a motion, whereby a man deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and growes agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at himſelfe, for ſom faulte or turpitude by him committed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of mercy.</note>Mercie is a greefe
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:3672:75"/>
which a man takes for the paines, miſeries or aduerſities of another.</p>
            <p>Enuie is a ſorrowe of one man, at the good,<note place="margin">Of Enuie.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, or aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of another.</p>
            <p>Iealoſie is a mouing,<note place="margin">Of Iealoſie.</note> mingled with loue and anger, to wit, vvhen a man loues ſome thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and growes diſpleaſed againſt ſuch, as doe harme, diſhonor, or ill to the thing he loueth: as the prophet Helias, louing the honor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to God, grewe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at the misbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers.<note place="margin">How a king ought to be iealous.</note> So ſhould a king or gouernour of a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, bee inflamed with
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:3672:76"/>
the loue of iuſtice, the profit, honour and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of honeſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: contrariwiſe, hee ought to deſpiſe the wicked, vngracious, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, and diſturbers of peace, loyalty, and publique truth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more hurtful then the reſt.</note>There is another af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which hath no name neither in Latine nor French, &amp; it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to iealoſie: that is, when one deſires the loſſe and ouerthrow of the good, and the exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of hypocrites, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſuch as were Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, Tymon, &amp; (it may be) others of like qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:3672:76"/>
now in theſe times.</p>
            <p>Ioy is a moouing,<note place="margin">Of ioy, and how it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth the hart.</note> wherby the hart dilates it ſelfe, &amp; ſweetly takes pleaſure at preſent good: it diſpoſeth it ſelfe in hope, to receiue a future good.</p>
            <p>Some of theſe affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are good and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to GOD:<note place="margin">Of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons pleaſing to God.</note> as are honeſt loue of thy neighbour, of thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, thy wife and thy country: iealoſie of the honour and glorie of God: deſire for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people: feare of the anger and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God: hatred of Tyrants, ſeditious &amp;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:3672:77"/>
diſſolute diſturbers of publique peace: hope and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in God in all afflictions what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, beeing aſſured that he ſees vs, and that he will ſtill haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What the contrary are.</note>The other are vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as enuie, hate, and thoſe beſide, vvhich trouble the peace of humaine communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and are the paines or penalties of the firſt fault, diſperſed ouer all mankinde: the meane or moderation of them is very neceſſary, for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeruation of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſocietie, beeing the onely butte &amp; aime
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:3672:77"/>
of morall phyloſophie, and of all ciuill lawes in generall.</p>
            <p>And certainly,<note place="margin">The hurt of humane ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie.</note> ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can this ſocietie or religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be maintained, except we refraine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auarice, hate, and other ſuch like vicious affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which horriblie doe deforme nature in this part, it remaines then to ſupport thys part with all diligence and reſpect.</p>
            <p>The organe or ſeat of thys power, is the hart,<note place="margin">The organe of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er appete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te.</note> &amp; not any part of the braine at all, for often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a man ſhal deſire what hee knowes to be ill: as Ouid ſaide of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:3672:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Medea: <hi>I ſee &amp; approue the good, but I doe the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi> And S. Paule: <hi>I ſee another lawe in my members</hi>: that is to ſay, the hart, <hi>repugnant to the lawe of my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, &amp; it holdeth me in captiuitie, vnder the law of ſin and death:</hi> and many other things (to like effect) in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Romanies. In briefe, very often is iudgement reprooued by affection, whereby then it is moſt cleere &amp; euident, that our affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are not in the braine, where indeede is the certaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thinges.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:3672:78"/>In this ſort diſputes Galen,<note place="margin">Galen, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our affections.</note> and by the ſame reaſon it is apparant, that affections are not oppinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as the <hi>Stoicks</hi> held and eſteemed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be.</p>
            <p>That the affections are not of the liuer nor the other parts,<note place="margin">Affections are not of the liuer nor the other parts.</note> where the naturall appetenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are, of eating and drinking, it is manifeſt: for, the affections can eaſilie appeaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelus, or vſe ſome kinde of moderation, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the ſame by reaſon, and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations: but the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall appetites, as to eate or drinke, will not
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:3672:79"/>
be guided by any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: for, as <hi>Homer</hi> ſaith, there is nothing more impreſſing or continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vrging,<note place="margin">Homers ſaying of the belly.</note> then the belly, eſpecially when it is hungry: for it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pells vs to be mindfull thereof, although vve had no care thereof at all, and albeit wee had neuer ſo many other things to doe.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that our affections haue theyr ſeate, neyther in the braine, nor in thoſe parts where the organe is of the power <hi>vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue:</hi> we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they are in the hart, for the hart is io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:3672:79"/>
and merry in ioy, mirth, loue, and hope, but in greefe, anger, feare, hate, &amp; ſuch like, it is wearie, and much troubled.</p>
            <p>The holie Scripture ſaith,<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning our loue to GOD.</note> that a man ought to loue God with al his hart, as much to ſay, as by the affection to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the fruition: to purſue this loue in cheerefulneſſe of hart, deſiring to pleaſe him, and in truth (without feigning) to embrace, franckly entertaine, &amp; fulfill his Lawes, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in him, &amp; expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting health onely from him: heereto are redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:3672:80"/>
the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.<note place="margin">The degrees of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, in the firſt Table.</note> Now becauſe thoſe works &amp; labors which God commaundes vs, ought to be done of vs in cleannes of hart, not hipocritically, or vvith diſſembling: wee will ſpeake a little thereof heere in this place.</p>
            <p>The firſt commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement dooth ſtrictlie charge vs,<note place="margin">Of the firſt commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> to ſtande in awe and feare of God: wherby we may aſſure our ſelues without any doubting, that hee is a God, to whom we owe obedience, and that he puniſheth the faultes, offences, exceſſes and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:3672:80"/>
malices of men.</p>
            <p>The ſecond expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,<note place="margin">Of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> how iealous hee is of his honour, that hee will haue no partner or competitour in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, much leſſe anie attribute at all to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to ſtocks or ſtones, images, or inuentions of mens idle braines: the penalties of ſuch offences are therin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, &amp; to what ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations it in iuſtice extendeth, vvee ought then to be moſt careful of his honour &amp; glory.</p>
            <p>The third,<note place="margin">Of the third commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> chargeth vs to doe all honor and reuerence to the Name of God, &amp; it is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:3672:81"/>
honor which is contained in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, wherby we are enioyned: that with great heede, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and feare, wee ſhould take care of an oath, for affirmation of any thing, becauſe it is moſt certain, that God hath an eye on all our dooings, and that hee wil ſeuerely puniſh our iniquities.</p>
            <p>So then wee ſhoulde affirme truth in an oths taking, and deſire him to puniſh vs iuſtly, if we ſweare not truly, or if wee doe beguile and deceiue any one: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo wee are taught,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:3672:81"/>
to deteſt and holde as horrid, all blaſphemies &amp; ſpeeches, which are contrary to Chriſtian religion, and ſo it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded in the inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation on God.</p>
            <p>The fourth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,<note place="margin">Of the 4. commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> conſiſteth in the obſeruation of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and duties, thereto belonging, as alſo in their diligent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding: according to our entraunce into the knowledge of God, of which knowledge they are viſible ſignes, exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs to obſeruaunce of true religion. Then the true performing of the commaundements
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:3672:82"/>
in the firſt Table, is true feare of God,<note place="margin">The ſum of the firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, well worthy to be regarded.</note> certaine truſt in his mercy, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and publication of his doctrine, inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for his ayde and propitiation, giuing of thankes, praiſe of his Name &amp; glory, for the creation, conſeruation, &amp; manutention of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, beeing his ovvne worke, created, conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, furniſhed, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and maintained by him: behold heere the lawes of the firſt table.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond table.</note>In the ſecond Table, is contained neceſſarie precepts for our owne
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:3672:82"/>
pollitique ſocietie: for, firſt of all, ſuch a ſtate cannot be rightly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, except there be a kinde of degree and order obſerued among men.</p>
            <p>It is that whereof A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle ſpeakes in his Pollitiques,<note place="margin">Ariſtotle in his Polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> there are ſome naturally free, &amp; others as ſeruaunts: as much to ſay, as that ſome haue (by the gift of GOD beſtowed on nature) more light of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, &amp; more purity of affections, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others can reach vnto, to the end, that they may guide and guarde by edicts, lawes &amp; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:3672:83"/>
the affaires &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations of thys lyfe. Such were the ancient law-makers, Pretors, &amp; Iuriſconſults, who left vnto vs ſo many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident lawes, gathered by certaine demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of the cleereneſſe and light, which God had infuſed and placed in their vnderſtanding, as alſo theyr ſincere loue &amp; iealoſie, for the tranquility of publique peace:<note place="margin">S. Paules af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of lawes &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</note> 
               <hi>Which Lawes,</hi> (ſaith S. Paule) <hi>beeing written in our harts and conſciences, woulde giue vs testimonie of them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">What men are to bee honoured.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Such perſonages the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to be honoured,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:3672:83"/>
as, holding the bridle of authority, do tame rude ſeruaunts, that is to ſay, ſuch as cannot cleerelie iudge of thinges: or (thorowe their inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate affections) do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrate crimes, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit offence to the ciuil bodie, or to the honors or goods of others.</p>
            <p>There are two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of gouernments,<note place="margin">Two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernments, the firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſiue.</note> one is, to force &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the rebellious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of honeſtie: like vnto a maiſter, who conſtraines his ſeruant (willing or vnwilling) to doe his dutie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any refuſall or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:3672:84"/>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond, ciuill and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient.</note>The other manner of gouernment, is polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique and ciuil, as when without compulſion, a man freely dooth the acts of honeſtie, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in horrour and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination, all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes and turpitude: namelie, when a man in reaſon is perſwaded, that it ought to be ſo: as Pericles,<note place="margin">Pericles ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Athenians.</note> who by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt reaſon &amp; ſpeeches guided the Athenian Common-wealth: or as a holy &amp; wiſe Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher gouerneth his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation and church.<note place="margin">Seuerall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note> In this multitude, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one haue their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affections, ſome,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:3672:84"/>
ſudden inordinate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, and directlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to vertue: but then by perſwaſion, which a man perceiues to be vſed, of the hurt &amp; inconuenience that may thereon enſue, as well publiquely as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately; they are made more moderate, and faultes remitted.</p>
            <p>God hath ſtamped in vs,<note place="margin">Reaſon and iudgement giuen vs of God.</note> the image and forme of either of theſe maners of gouerment. Reaſon &amp; iudgement well and truly concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thinges, fore-ſees the commodities and diſprofit of al enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes whatſoeuer, exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:3672:85"/>
or reſtraining, and accordingly moderates the affections of the hart: and this manner will hold out very well, if daily our affections be managed by ſound iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt offence, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures maine impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note>But becauſe (in thys caſe) nature being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancked and made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulie, by the firſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence caſt generallie on all, the affections are not moderated by iudgement, deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">The wil, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> or honeſt councell: the will, as miſtreſſe of the affections, forbids the <hi>motiue power,</hi> that ſhee tranſport not the members, to perpetrate
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:3672:85"/>
vnreaſonable or perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious things. As a man hauing a Feuer, affects to drinke inordinately: but yet the will checks the hande, that it ſhall not approche to the cup or glaſſe.</p>
            <p>Thus ſee we two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect formes of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">The appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the two gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> the one (to hold back the rebellious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulters) in theyr office: and the other, by ſweet exhortations and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, drawne from the rule of vnderſtanding, to guide the obedient, and ſway their actions to publique profit and honour.</p>
            <p>Concerning the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:3672:86"/>
we owe by dutie to our parents,<note place="margin">Of the dutie we owe to our Parents, exampled.</note> we haue a moſt cleere example in nature: as we may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee in the young Storkes, who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they attaine to ſtrength and age, doe nouriſh &amp; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt their fathers &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>The following com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, forbid to doe iniury or harme to the bodies of one an other.<note place="margin">Of the other commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</note> Man is created to be ſociable &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatiue, as is ſhewe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs by our procreation, carefull nouriſhment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and dilligent regard of our propagation: but the principall ende of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:3672:86"/>
this ſocietie, is for our ioynt inſtruction, and erudition together in the lawe of God, and al laudible actions what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>And becauſe impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident and ill aduiſed men,<note place="margin">The reaſon why lawes &amp; penalties were inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted.</note> haue neede of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectours, therefore, to the end our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitie might continue ſound &amp; intire: the obſtinate &amp; ſtifnecked are to be exempted, &amp; for that cauſe were paines and corrections by lawes inſtituted.</p>
            <p>Againe,<note place="margin">Why the deuiſion of poſſeſsions was thought behouefull.</note> in this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brideled communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and nature, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarice and greedines of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:3672:87"/>
the wicked, negligent and ſlothful is ſo great, as they will not permit any one to liue in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitie or proportion: and therefore the deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of poſſeſsions was thought neceſſarie for, if all ſhoulde bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, then the idle, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and careleſſe wretches, woulde in ſhort while deuoure all the riches of the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious and dilligent:<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning theft.</note> for this cauſe therefore was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting of theft forbidden.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that men ſhould haue dealings one with another, it behooued
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:3672:87"/>
that the communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theyr goods and labors, ſhould be made by certaine meaſure &amp; reaſons: for, an vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall communication, that is to ſay, when the price or recompence ſhalbe ouer-exceeding, or elſe of too light or little value; ſuch enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe among men,<note place="margin">The reaſon of iuſtice in our contrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> cannot be long main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: heereupon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued iuſtice, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to euery one his rightfull proportion, in dealing &amp; contracting thus one with another.</p>
            <p>More-ouer, our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, contracts, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>federations,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:3672:88"/>
&amp; appointments made by voluntarie agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">Without truth, no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie can be obſerued.</note> are to be kept: for, without truth, fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie &amp; loyaltie of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in our contracts, humaine conuerſation can neuer be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued. Marke then howe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deſires conſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Natures co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of herſelfe: &amp; our iniury to her and our ſelues.</note>In eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, temperance muſt be obſerued: for, inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce corrupts na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and inordinate lubricitie ſpoyles the ſanctified combination of marriage, troubles titles of ſucceſsion, wardſhippes, caſes of dowrie, &amp; al pollitique
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:3672:88"/>
order, all which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede moſt pernitious woundes to pollitique and diſcreete ſocietie.</p>
            <p>Thus ſee we the law to agree with nature,<note place="margin">The lawe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nature, and in what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</note> which firſt of all eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Religion, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward conſtituted Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed to ordaine lawes, for defence of ſuch as were oppreſſed either in goods or bodie: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding honor to be giuen to men of worth and deſert, and they to be committed to al po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique functions, by certaine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> formes and lawes. So grew eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of mariages, and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:3672:89"/>
perfect diſcerning of poſſeſsions, as alſo iuſt orders and degrees of correction for all looſe wantons, ouer-daring reſiſters, and wilful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of the lawes.</p>
            <p>Aſſuredly, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and chiefeſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of theſe lawes,<note place="margin">The lawes them ſelues the voice of nature, by their cauſes.</note> are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues the voice and ſentence of nature reſtored, &amp; reformed, that is to ſay: the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the light of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, ordered by the very pureſt: and ſincereſt braines, illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and renued by the grace of God; doe declare in what eſtate this life is guided and
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:3672:89"/>
gouerned, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions in the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue apointed, which expreſſe to the very life, the forme of liuing according to the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie of nature.</p>
            <p>Nowe to returne to the poynt of the harts moouing,<note place="margin">Two kindes of mouing in the hart, firſt by the pulſe.</note> there are two ſorts of moouing: one is called the pulſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpirits engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at the hart, moue the ſame, by meanes of the organes thereto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted by nature, and likewiſe when by dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traction of his <hi>ventricles,</hi> the arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries driuen forward by the ſubtile ſpirits with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:3672:90"/>
them, doe conuay &amp; adminiſter heate tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row all the body.</p>
            <p>Novve, albeit theſe thinges are very admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the affections, which are the mouers of the hart, (as we haue heeretofore ſaide,) are worthy of farre greater and much more admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The hart mooueth likewiſe by contrarietie of humours, ſeuerally by each one of them.</note>The hart dilated or ſhut vp, mooueth alſo by diuerſitie of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours: as in anger, it is mooued by the cholle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick humour: in ioy it is mooued by the verie ſweeteſt blood, and ſends the ſame (as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe)
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:3672:90"/>
to the exteriour parts. In feare, it calls it ſelfe backward, &amp; in griefe it is trobled with the humour of mellan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chollie.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe, in theſe motions of diuers hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, are fumes and riſings vp of diuers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions: nor is it anie eaſie matter to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the cauſes of theſe moouings, or the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell of God in theſe their natural functions.<note place="margin">Of the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſes (inwardly &amp; outwardly) of the harts moouing.</note> The efficient cauſes of theſe affections, are in vs interiourly the hart, and exteriourly the things which offer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto vs, eyther
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:3672:91"/>
pleaſing or offenſiue: but it is neceſſarie that knowledge ſhold pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede affection, for, as one ſaith: no man euer deſired, what hee had not firſt knowledge of.</p>
            <p>Ye haue the very like combination betweene the powers of nature,<note place="margin">Of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of nature anſwerable to the harts affections, &amp; their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</note> and that the motions of the hart, doe iuſtly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the knowledge which a man hath of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing: but there is a difference in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plections or tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the hart, &amp; the ſpirits, and the bloods preſent beeing, for, the hart beeing hotte and dry, is the ſooner kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:3672:91"/>
whereon wee ſee ſome more ſuddenly to bee enflamed with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, then others are, &amp; the moouings of the hart &amp; the ſpirits, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the blood (not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-more) after one kinde, but diuerſly, and according to the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of the affections.</p>
            <p>Therefore in griefe or ſadneſſe,<note place="margin">Of the hart in greefe &amp; ſadnes, and the bloods office in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice then.</note> the hart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhruncke vp and crowded together, the blood runnes to him, as willing to helpe him: and this is the reaſon, why men or vvomen (being ſad, agreeued, or fearefull) are pale, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ill complexio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:3672:92"/>
or colloured.</p>
            <p>In ioy or anger, the hart dilates it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Of the hart, in ioy &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, &amp; how the blood works then.</note> and ſends his bloode to the parts exteriour: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe in anger the hart is enflamed, it mooueth redd choller, which ſpreading it ſelfe ouerprodigally abroad, infecteth all the reſt of the blood.</p>
            <p>And if it continue long in that heat, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth blacke, and ſeething ſtrongly, dries vp and burnes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by oftentimes it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens that ſome becom frantique, mad and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate.</p>
            <p>Thoſe men that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:3672:92"/>
in mellancholy,<note place="margin">Of mellan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chollie and chollericke men, &amp; their conditions.</note> mingled with red chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler: are enuious, full of ill will, and of verie ſtrange and hard con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</p>
            <p>Sanguine men are ioyous,<note place="margin">Of ſanguine men.</note> delightfull and pleaſant, by the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and cleerenes of their blood, for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in them are pure &amp; full of rich ſplendour.</p>
            <p>The phlegmatick are dull, remiſſe,<note place="margin">Of phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> ſleepie &amp; heauie: becauſe theyr blood is thin, &amp; theyr ſpirits ſcant warme.</p>
            <p>The mellancholick, are properly ſadde and fearefull, becauſe theyr blood is troubled, thick
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:3672:93"/>
and colde, their ſpirits likewiſe impure, groſſe, and (as it were) full of darknes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules ſocietie with the body, anſwerable to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</note>The very ſame ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie is there of the body with the ſoule, and her effects doe aunſwer to theſe humours.</p>
            <p>In griefe or ſadneſſe, the hart ſhuts it ſelfe, &amp; drawing backward (as it were) attracts the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of mellanchollie to the ſpleene, vvhich ſpreading it ſelfe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times on either ſide the body, engenders diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the ſides, as plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies, and other verie dangerous obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: which wee ſee to
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:3672:93"/>
happen to ſuch as are long time in ſadneſſe, meditating on nothing but matter of griefe &amp; offence: I haue heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to-fore experimented this hurtfull humour in my owne ſelfe, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can the better ſpeake it.</p>
            <p>The proper cauſes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe affections,<note place="margin">Of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cauſes of our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and whence they receiue their originall.</note> are the things whereto a man finds himſelfe &amp; his cogitation moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied: and the hart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuddenly mooued, ioyning and following the knowledge of thoſe thinges, dooth in like maner apprehend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It is very cleere concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:3672:94"/>
anger and griefe, that they haue theyr cauſe inwardlie in the hart, and the exteriour is the knowledge of ſome outward offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue thine.</p>
            <p>So of loue in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for all ſuch as are of right iudgement, loue vertue and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie: as Scipio loued honour grounded on vertue, and the beautie thereof in others, moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him to attempt deedes of high pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſſe, and (oftentimes) very difficult enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Euen ſo, people ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling in vertue, doe deerely loue together,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:3672:94"/>
for the conuenaunce and naturall ſimilitude that is between them:<note place="margin">Ariſtotles oppinion of good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple &amp; good affections.</note> For euery one (ſayth Ariſtotle) loueth his like; &amp; truly good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections (ſaith hee) are cauſes of great profit &amp; commoditie, and are as pricks and ſpurres en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing to vertue.</p>
            <p>Plato ſaith,<note place="margin">Platos iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is as the nerue of the ſoule, by looſing or with-drawing wherof, vertue is exerciſed.</p>
            <p>Seeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that there is in nature, certaine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganes and parts proper to her actions, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine humours vvhich ſerue neceſſarily to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:3672:95"/>
it behoueth, that ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be voide of vice or offence: for euen as the light in the eye, is the gift of God to nature,<note place="margin">Our good affections are diuinely inſpired.</note> euen ſo are good affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s diuinely inſpired, vvhich pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke and incite vs to what-ſoeuer is good &amp; honeſt: as to loue our children, hate ſin, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, tirannie, force, violence and all turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ariſtotles ſaying of anger in a vertuous man.</note>The ſaying of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle is very good, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, that a vertuous man vſeth anger, as a Captaine doth a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour: for it is moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, that our actions
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:3672:95"/>
would be cold and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, if loue of hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, &amp; hate of vice did not ſeuerallie incite &amp; moue vs. In al reſpects like vnto a ſhip, which hauing no winde, goes ſlowly and ſoftly: euen ſo were we, if wee had no good affections, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our actions would be lame, ſlowe, and of ſlender effect.<note place="margin">The cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of nature in vs, the cauſe of euill moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> If na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture were not corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in vs, wee ſhould haue very good &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent moouings, and no vices at all remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in vs: but the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; harmonie of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture beeing troubled, makes bad affections
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:3672:96"/>
to ariſe in vs, and ſuch as are repugnant to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, which boldly do ſurmount, &amp; ouer-goe thoſe that are good, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtardizing, and quite ouer-throwing them.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, in all times, and in all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, in changes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weales, there hath euer-more beene reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſome heroyick na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, exceeding thoſe of common courſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing motions farre pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and of much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter excellence then the vulgare.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in our Sauiour.</note>The repairer of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, had in him moſt
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:3672:96"/>
true &amp; pure affections: as when he threwe the Merchants out of the Temple,<note place="margin">His zeale of his Fathers glory.</note> onely for iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſie hee had of the place, as alſo the honor and worſhip of God, contemning the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers, vvho had polluted the place of veneration, inuocation and holy ſacrifice.<note place="margin">His heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus.</note> In the reſurrection of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus, he ſhewed great heauines, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wept, as beeing greatly moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in ſpirit: In loue, wherby he commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,<note place="margin">His loue to little chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> that they ſhoulde permit little children to come vnto him: In compaſſion, which he
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:3672:97"/>
had of the people, that had followed him in the deſert and vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full places:<note place="margin">His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion of them in the deſert.</note> And how many times is the word of mercie vſed, repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; inculqued in the Scripture?</p>
            <p>There is great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce between the good affections of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,<note place="margin">The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in Chriſtians &amp; Infidells.</note> and thoſe in Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels: for Chriſtians ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this puritie of motion, to be repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, onely by the grace of God, &amp; cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully (for loue of him, and dreade of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure) do ordaine in their gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, good and honeſt lawes, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:3672:97"/>
theyr actions to the glory of GOD: as did the Prophets Eſay &amp; Ieremie, who knew that God would haue Common-weales to be gouerned by holy laws, and all wicked confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be caſt out. The other,<note place="margin">The wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Heathen.</note> (as Cicero) acknowledge not at al, that Magiſtrates are ordained of God, but doe build vppon their owne wiſedome &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, not attributing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny honour to God, but onely to them-ſelues: wherefore theſe moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may bee thought good, yet are (by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent) euill to vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:3672:98"/>
becauſe they are not ordered, nor ruled by the knowledge and loue of God.</p>
            <p>In this place, after our paſſed ſpeech of the affections, vvhich are actions and moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings of the hart, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the knowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges comming to it by the ſences: me thinkes it ſhoulde not differ much fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our purpoſe, to ſpeak ſome-what of concupiſcence remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in vs,<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in vs.</note> whereby we may vnderſtand many diſputations of Saint Paule, the eſtate of our owne nature, and the great domage or detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:3672:98"/>
that comes to vs by originall tranſgreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>The worde Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence,<note place="margin">Of the word Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, and how it may be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</note> according as it ſeemes to mee (yet yeelding ſtill to better iudgement) ſignifies, not onely a mouing of the hart, wherby a man deſires earneſtly &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond meaſure, ſome thing that may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for profit or pleſure, as to eat, drink, or commit follie: but likewiſe it is a priuation &amp; defect of light in the vnderſtanding, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of enſueth ignoraunce of God and his wil, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trueths, boldnes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:3672:99"/>
with any of his inhibitions, fayling in fayth and loue towards him, as alſo diffidence in his gracious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in the will.</note>Likewiſe, the ſame word imports an error in the will, as diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and contempt of the commaundements of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The wills boldneſſe in his owne pride.</note>In theſe obſcurities, our vnderſtanding lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and conceiueth great admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him ſelfe, and of his ovvne wiſedom, wexing bold to feigne oppinions of God, &amp; to apprehend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after his own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, wherby afterward
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:3672:99"/>
it falls into ſome nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row diſtreſſe, where it is girded vp with feare &amp; terrour, inſulting of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes beyond all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</p>
            <p>Of theſe euills com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained S. Paule, when hee ſaide:<note place="margin">Rom. 7, 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Miſerable wretch that J am, who ſhall deliuer me from this bodie, ſo ſubiect to dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and death?</hi> After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he aunſwers,<note place="margin">Rom. 7, 25,</note> 
               <hi>The grace of GOD by Jeſus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word then ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies not onely an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſenſuall, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a vice &amp; defect in the vnderſtanding and will, by which inſueth
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:3672:100"/>
infinite multitudes of miſhaps. So dooth the Scripture call the harts endeuours,<note place="margin">The harts moouings ioyned with the will.</note> becauſe the mouing and agitation of the hart, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioyned with the will.</p>
            <p>Aſſuredly, if nature had continued in her puritie,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of nature.</note> the knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of GOD would haue been cleere in our vnderſtanding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the will had franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obeyed, but nowe is hindered only through her obſcurity.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings of the hart &amp; will.</note>The hart &amp; wil haue moouings diſtort, and contrarie to God: for the will (without the feare of God and truſt
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:3672:100"/>
in him) loues himſelfe, ſeeks ſafety in himſelfe, truſts in his owne dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, delights in his owne wiſedome: for a man would be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and eſteemed, and feares more the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or blames of the world, then of GOD his Creator.</p>
            <p>The very like agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doe ſway the hart, the ſenſuall motions draw the will vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as much to ſay, as when the hart loues the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous pleaſures of the ſences, which are prohibited, or when a man hates his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, flatly againſt the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:3672:101"/>
lawe of God.</p>
            <p>To this effect ſpake our Sauiour;<note place="margin">Mark, 7, 21,</note> 
               <hi>That out of the hart proceeded e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill cogitations, thefts, blaſphemies, murders, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulteries, lies,</hi> and ſuch like other crimes.</p>
            <p>In this then it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares moſt certainely,<note place="margin">The hart ſignifies the will and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</note> that by the hart is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and will: as vvhen the hart takes pleaſure in falſe oppinions, and ſuch imaginations as are contrary to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; glory of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Howe to come to the knowledge of our ſelues</note>The conſideration of theſe thinges, ſhoulde check the pride &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption reigning in
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:3672:101"/>
vs, and induce vs to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, by often and feruent prayer to God, that he would renue in vs the cleere, pure and ſincere light of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: that hee woulde likewiſe make cleane our harts, and plant therein none but good affections.</p>
            <p>As Dauid deſired of God, <hi>A cleane hart, &amp; a right ſpirit.</hi> And Saint Paule, who ſaid: <hi>That Ieſus Christ onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes the cleereneſſe of our vnderſtanding, and conformes the body to his brightneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Motiue power,<note place="margin">Of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue power, carying the body from place to place, and what are his organes.</note> is that whereby the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:3672:102"/>
and his parts, are tranſported from one place to another: the organes, are the nerues, the muſcles, and the cords of the members.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſoule, the cauſe of the bodies moouing.</note>Alexander Aphro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſianus ſaith, that the ſoule is the cauſe of the bodies moouing, as weight is the cauſe why a ſtone falls downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Two kindes of mouing, naturall and voluntarie, and the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note>This moouing is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into two kindes, naturall, and volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
            <p>The naturall, neyther beginnes or ceaſſeth, according to our ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination and pleaſure, nor can it be otherwiſe,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:3672:102"/>
but as when an obiect is preſented, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward purſued: as the <hi>ventricle,</hi> vvhich drawes the receiued foode to it, &amp; the hart attracts the ſpirits, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuddenly, or ſoftly.</p>
            <p>The voluntary moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, both begins and ends at our owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, &amp; that is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of this power: as is the ſeuerall mouings of our parts, going, ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſwimming, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>There is another co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed moouing,<note place="margin">Of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing partly natural, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly voluntary.</note> bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing partly naturall, and partly voluntary: as is the moouing of the
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:3672:103"/>
breſt or ſtomack. The benefit of this power is eaſily diſcerned: For thereby we ſeeke what is neceſſary for our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, and ſhunne what we imagine ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to contrary.</p>
            <p>It remaines to ſpeak of the intellectuall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,<note place="margin">Of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer intellec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to S. Auguſtines oppinion.</note> whereof S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine makes an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation to the Trinitie.</p>
            <p>The memorie, (ſaith hee) forming the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, repreſents the Father: the intellection repreſents the Sonne: and the will, the holie Ghoſt. For the Father, conſidering &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:3672:103"/>
himſelfe, begot the Sonne; and the holie Ghoſt is the agitation proceeding of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Son.</p>
            <p>This is the povver whereby wee know,<note place="margin">How action becoms ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate to intellection.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, iudge and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, hauing in it the beginning of Artes: heereto likewiſe is acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on riciprocall for ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our actions are ſeen and iudged.</p>
            <p>This power differs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſenſitiue:<note place="margin">How it dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſenſitiue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.</note> for the ſenſitiue takes knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge but of things pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiare and ſingulerly, but this other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiues, and apprehends both ſinguler &amp; vniuerſallie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:3672:104"/>
               <note place="margin">Of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellection.</note>The obiect of thys power, is God, and the whole vniuerſalitie of things, as well celeſtiall as elementarie.</p>
            <p>The offices of thys power,<note place="margin">The offices of intellec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> are to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand &amp; forme in him ſelfe, the images &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations of things, to retaine, and conferre them together: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, to ſee, what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement &amp; what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is between the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>The organes of this power,<note place="margin">The organs of intellec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> are the interior ſences, wherof we haue diſcourſed already. Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſaith, that as the ſeale imprinteth on the wax, ſo (by meanes of the
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:3672:104"/>
ſpirits) are the ſhapes of thinges imprinted in the braine. But this is the matter moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous of all, that we ſhould retaine ſo great a multitude, and ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral diuerſities of things, &amp; likewiſe for ſo long a time: but the reaſon thereof can neuer bee well or ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</p>
            <p>Wherfore,<note place="margin">Our life is guided by our actions.</note> ſeeing by our actions our life is guided, we ſhould pray vnto GOD, that hee would take pittie vpon our weake nature: and that hee would renewe his image in vs, to the end we may more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:3672:105"/>
know his workes in vs, and ſhewe our ſelues more reuerent and obedient to him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ariſtotles deuiſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the two vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, actiue and paſsiue.</note>Ariſtotle makes a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, between the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding actiue, and that which is tearmed paſſiue: mary hee calls the actiue vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing elſe, but that which inuenteth any thing, as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes, did inuent the Compaſſe.</p>
            <p>The paſſiue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, is that which inuenteth not of it ſelf, but makes approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an others inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: as he that appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:3672:105"/>
the inuention of Gunpowder, or that of the Compaſſe, or the Aſtralabe. The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, are deuided into actions and habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. The knowledge which is called action,<note place="margin">Actions and habitude, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledges of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</note> is that part of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth ſomthing, by forming the image thereof.</p>
            <p>Habitude, is as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant &amp; reſident light in the vnderſtanding, whereof wee make vſe whenſoeuer we pleaſe.</p>
            <p>The vnderſtanding ſomtimes buſies it ſelfe, and conſiders thoſe
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:3672:106"/>
thinges, whereof it can but hardly reach to the knowledge: as the changes of the ayre,<note place="margin">Of ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue &amp; prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> the reuolutions ordinarie of the heauens, &amp; thoſe are termed ſpeculatiue. Sometimes it meditates on thinges that it can eaſily exerciſe, and then it is called practiue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of reaſon, &amp; the wills co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction there-with.</note>The word reaſon, is that which compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends, and then the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiuing things, conferreth and makes iudgement of them, where-upon the wil makes his coniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">The defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the will.</note> Then may the wil be thus very well defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it is a part or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:3672:106"/>
of the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which is called reaſon: working free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, after that the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hath tried, &amp; iudged the thing to be good or bad.</p>
            <p>If nature had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in her firſt inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie,<note place="margin">The hurt of natures lack of her firſt condition.</note> we ſhould neuer haue willed, but what of it ſelf had been good &amp; honeſt: but the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of nature beeing perturbed, makes ſuch an alteration, that there is a diſcord among the powers, &amp; that the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times deceued in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of things. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit it can eaſilie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:3672:107"/>
the hurtfulnes of things, yet many impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments doe happen to croſſe it:<note place="margin">The impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments or hinderances of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</note> as ſelfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceit, or ouer-great weening in our owne ſelues, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, and other ſuch like harmes, which drawes vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit enormous crimes, and to trouble (ſometimes) the quiet eſtate of the publique weale.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How Gods image be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth miſhapen in vs.</note>Thus becomes the image of GGD defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in vs, &amp; keeps not the true Idea of his firſt excellence. Wherfore it behoueth vs,<note place="margin">What wee ought to deſire of God, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of our wants &amp; defects.</note> earneſtlie to deſire (with S. Paul) <hi>that GOD would make perfect his image in vs,</hi>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:3672:107"/>
&amp; that by vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding &amp; knowing aright the cauſe &amp; authour of all things, we may attaine to more noble &amp; purer actions, as well in our vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, as in our will. Likewiſe, that our memorie may euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more retaine good and holy cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of god, and of commendable actions, whereby reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is preſerued &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed: that he would purifie our affections, &amp; in ſted of ſuch as are euill and corrupt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite (by his holy ſpirite working in his Word) honeſt and vertuous motions in our harts.
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:3672:108"/>
Moreouer, to worke ſo graciouſly in vs, that the inferiour powers may be obedient to the ſuperiour, beeing euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more guided, by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred direction in his word contained: to the end, that by this accord and conſonance of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in our ſoule, the honor of God may be exalted and reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in vs, and publique tranquilitie kept and maintained, vntil it ſhal pleaſe him to receiue vs, and giue vs eternall reſt in his high &amp; hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie dwellings.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:3672:108"/>
               <head>Of the immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the ſoule.</head>
               <p>NOW, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of the ſoule, ſome doe diſpute in this ſort, by arguments taken and deriued from nature.<note place="margin">Naturall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, concerning the ſoules immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</note> It is impoſſible (ſay they) that all the honeſt and vvell diſpoſed people, which are borne and brought vppe in thys worlde, ſhoulde euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more be vexed or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with miſeries. Yet is it euident,<note place="margin">1. Of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this life.</note> that the greater part of good people, are moſt of all, and oftneſt afflicted greeuouſly, yea, many
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:3672:109"/>
times ſlaine by the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſeditious and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants. It is then neceſsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to think and ſay, that GOD hath reſerued ſome port or hauen of ſafetie for them, where (after all troubles) they may arriue to perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. Of paines reſerued for the wicked, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theyr felicitie in this life.</note>Some likewiſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute on the contrarie part, of the paines re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued for the wicked, for, naturally we iudge and ſay, that euil deeds doe iuſtly deſerue pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. Yet often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wee ſee, that they which are oppreſſours of others, both in body and goods, are neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:3672:109"/>
happy in theyr worldlie enterpriſes: why then it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that a place is alſo afterward reſerued for them, and paines like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, where-with they are to be puniſhed.</p>
               <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Platos rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſoule.</note> Plato giueth this reaſon: thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that bee not of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary nature, are not ſubiect at all to corup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion nor death: The ſoule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth no way of the elements, it is then cleere, that ſhee is not mortall, nor any way corruptible.</p>
               <p>That the ſoule is no way co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſting or made of any part of the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">The ſoule no way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of the elements.</note>
                  <pb n="196" facs="tcp:3672:110"/>
is apparant and manifeſt by this reaſon. It is impoſſible, that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture being corruptible, ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend and conceiue thinges vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall and incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: as to conceiue and apprehend God, with the vniuerſality of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: the numbers, the differences of thinges honeſt and diſhoneſt:<note place="margin">What na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding her corruption.</note> yet naturally, and euen without teaching, men doe apprehend theſe things.</p>
               <p>It is then to bee iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that the ſeates of theſe apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſions, are not natures elementa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but much more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:3672:110"/>
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corruptible things, &amp; likewiſe that they are perpetual: ſee heere what natural rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are yeelded, for the immortalitie of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>But we,<note place="margin">Of Gods great loue and kindnes to vs, farre beyond o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> whom God hath ſo much looued, and endued with ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall a fauour, as to make the beams of the glory of his Goſpell ſhine vpon our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, taking &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the teſtimonies of true examples, and ſayinges of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, which we know to be diuinely beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on them, &amp; confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the words and
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:3672:111"/>
works of our Lord <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ</hi>: aſſuredlie, mee thinkes it is verie meruailous, ſeeing that this epithite of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie is ſo apparant, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed in vs by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſayings and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,<note place="margin">Mens care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe regard of the ſoules immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</note> why men doe not better prepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this iudgement aright, and that they haue no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter feare or horrour of the paines eternall.</p>
               <p>It remaineth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that men of good and vertuous diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ought to reſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by the examples of Enoch, Elias, &amp; our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:3672:111"/>
liuing already in life perpetuall.</p>
               <p>And if wee will take notice from the verie firſt age of the worlde,<note place="margin">Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the ſoules immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, from the originall of the world.</note> we ſhall find, that God declared, how he wold one day hold his iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to puniſh the wicked, and reward the good, according to their ſeuerall workes, as when he ſaid to Caine: <hi>If thou hast well doone,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>thou ſhalt finde it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue like reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence: but if thou hast doone euill, thy ſinne ſhall be hidden, vntill ſuch time as it ſhall be declared and diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The reaſon of wicked mens neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the ſoules im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie.</note> This deferring &amp; dilatation of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:3672:112"/>
makes the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked more bolde &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in theyr ſinning, and begetteth likewiſe contempt of God: but albeit wee ſee not ſuch tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s puniſhed in this world, let vs not therefore thinke, that they ſhall ſo eſcape without correction.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gods delay of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment agra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uates the chaſtiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note>For, as the wiſe man of Greece ſaid: <hi>GOD deferreth his chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but hee recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth that delaying with greater meaſure of pains.</hi> And let vs likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his own holie words, to wit, that <hi>ſinne ſhalbe diſcouered,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene, 4, 7,</note> which let vs not thinke to bee
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:3672:112"/>
ſpoken in vaine, or that the words are of no ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: for, although wee beholde not heere the pittifull end of tyrants, or others that depart this life vnpuniſhed, let vs yet remaine aſſured, that the meaſure of their ſcourging will be the greater afterward.</p>
               <p>Enoch, who in his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing body was rapt vp,<note place="margin">An eſpeciall proofe of the life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> and tranſlated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys world, giues vs thereby to vnderſtand, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth a better: then is it not to be doubted, but that Enoch, Elias, and thoſe other holie perſons, taught and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:3672:113"/>
others in the happineſſe of this lyfe perpetuall, and that it alſo remained after this preſent eſtate.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of the Apoſtle S. Iude, there is a part of the ſermon of Enoch, which ſpeaketh in this manner:<note place="margin">Iude. 1, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Beholde, the Lord ſhall come with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite company of Saints, onely to doe iustice, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke and puniſh all thoſe that haue doone euill and vngodly deedes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Helie &amp; Eliſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, who did raiſe vp, &amp; make to liue againe ſome that were dead: and Elias, who was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:3672:113"/>
vp in the preſence of his friendes, &amp; carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to heauen in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire bodie, both in a whirle-wind &amp; a flame of fire.</p>
               <p>Many other exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,<note place="margin">Infinite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme the immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſoule.</note> and namely the moſt euident example of our Sauiour, vvho roſe againe, and to him excited the companie of the prophets &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Fathers, to liue with him perpetually, &amp; to enioy the fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the company of God.</p>
               <p>By diuine Scripture then it is moſt cleere,<note place="margin">That our ſoules are ſpirits, not to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by death.</note> that our ſoules are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, which are not to be extinct in death like the
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:3672:114"/>
body: but doe remaine ſeperated afterward, &amp; liue perpetually.</p>
               <p>God ſaide, <hi>that wee neede not to feare ſuch as kill the body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math, 10.28</note> 
                  <hi>and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward can doe nothing els.</hi> He ſaid likewiſe to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted theefe:<note place="margin">Luke. 23, 43</note> 
                  <hi>This day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the ſoule could be extinct and diſsipated like ſmoke in death,<note place="margin">That the ſoule is to liue with Chriſt after death.</note> it would not then follow, that ſhe ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſe and liue afterward with Ieſus Chriſt: it is then a ſpirit, which continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after death, and in regard it is a ſpirit, it cannot be idle.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="205" facs="tcp:3672:114"/>As concerning the word <hi>Paradiſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of Paradiſe, and what it ſignifieth.</note> it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the place of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie and eternall life: there where ioy, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and iuſtice are in all aboundance.</p>
               <p>It is neceſſary to note the ſermon of the good theefe,<note place="margin">The good theefes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on the Croſſe.</note> which he made hanging aloft on the Croſſe, euen when he was at the inſtant of death, and when all the Apoſtles were aſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, and had left off theyr office of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, &amp; did forget the mercies of God.</p>
               <p>Vndoubtedly, thys ſpectacle was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great ſignification,
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:3672:115"/>
for, there was to bee ſeen two theeues hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the bleſſed Sonne of God, which ſignified, that the world was condemned to death for moſt gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous offences And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſhould be ſo, that the Son of God, was to appeaſe his Fathers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure,<note place="margin">One part of the world refuſed the benefit of Chriſtes death, figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the bad theefe.</note> and by his death onely: that yet one part of the worlde would ſtill contemne this benefit, &amp; deſpiſe the kindnes of thys Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, as may be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the bad theefe, hauing no hope at all of ſaluation, and in whoſe perſon is figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:3672:115"/>
forth to vs, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſeditious, and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, enemies againſt the Goſpell of GOD, who ought aſſuredlie to know, that their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation is alreadie doone, for theyr wilful contemning the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God.</p>
               <p>But the other part of the worlde,<note place="margin">The conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the wicked, and aſſurance of the elects ſaluation, in Ieſus Chriſt.</note> which are ſuch as (with reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) acknowledge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this bleſſing of God, knowing &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing (with the good theefe) that they haue deſerued nothing but conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation &amp; death: yet truſting onelie in God, doe inuoke his
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:3672:116"/>
mercy and propitiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, acknowledging al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that they are deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from ſin &amp; death, onely by the bleſſed &amp; innocent death of their Redeemer.</p>
               <p>The good thiefe, who deſired his deliuerance of God, acknowledged him therein, and albeit he ſaw him there to die with him; yet he helde it for moſt certaine &amp; aſſured, that this was he who could giue him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life: wherefore he heard the ſweet an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of GOD, who promiſed him, <hi>that that very day, hee ſhoulde bee with him in the place of
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:3672:116"/>
reſt, life, and ioy perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall.</hi> By this voyce hee vnderſtood, that his ſinnes were forgiuen him, and that life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal was (in mercie) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon him.</p>
               <p>Then, though hee was hanged, broken, &amp; halfe deade, yet (for all that) he did honour &amp; gaue reuerence to the Sonne of God:<note place="margin">When the vvhole church was ſilent, &amp; the Apoſtles dumbe, yet the good theefe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, in his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus.</note> euen then when the whole Church was ſilent, and when the Apoſtles were amazed and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed, yet hee confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he who was there hanged, and readie to die, ſhoulde (neuertheleſſe) raigne
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:3672:117"/>
and giue eternall life to men: he called on him, as the onely maiſter &amp; authour of life: Nay more, he defended the glory of GOD againſt the other euill ſpeaker.</p>
               <p>This ſpectacle then admoniſheth vs of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, and all good mindes doe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, their tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to bee fixed to his croſſe: for wee are all (by our ſinnes) ſubiect to death and calamities of all ſorts, and can no way bee deliuered but by the Sonne of God only. It remaines then, that wee call on him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>, that wee declare to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:3672:117"/>
theſe great bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,<note place="margin">How much wee ſtand bounde to defend the glory of God, againſt all Atheiſts &amp; misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers.</note> &amp; that we main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his honor &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, againſt all miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants and euill ſpeakers: whatſoeuer afflictions, torments or deaths we endure in the cauſe, to the end, that hee may giue to euery one of vs, that which hee did to the happy conuerted theefe, ſaying: <hi>This day thou ſhalt be with mee in Paradiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing then ſo great a matter is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in this ſpeech and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, of our Sauiour Chriſt with the good theefe, let vs confirme and fixe in our harts,
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:3672:118"/>
this ſaying and moſt powerfull ſentence: which manifeſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth,<note place="margin">The ſoule is a liuing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, after the bodies death, and conſiſteth no way of the bodies temper.</note> that the ſoule is a ſeperable ſpirit, liuing after it hath left the bodie, according as Chriſt himſelfe ſayde, that the ſpirit of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted theefe, ſhould conuerſe and bee with him in Paradiſe.</p>
               <p>Aſſuredly, it coulde not conuerſe nor liue after death, if it vvere onely of the bodies te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or if it were ſome ſmoke, neyther coulde it likewiſe bee in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, but would be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed abroade in the ayre.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="213" facs="tcp:3672:118"/>In Saint Mathewe,<note place="margin">Math, 17, 3.</note> Moiſes ſpake and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred with our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the Mountaine, although it be plainelie written in the Booke of the repetition of the law, commonly called Deuteronomie, that Moyſes was deade and buried: our Sauiour then ſpake with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated ſoule of him. Saint Paule ſaide,<note place="margin">Philip, 1, 23,</note> 
                  <hi>that he deſired to be deliuered from his body, and to bee with Ieſus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians hee ſaid:<note place="margin">2. Cor, 5, 6,</note> 
                  <hi>While we remaine in this bodie, we are far off from our Lord. But we haue this
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:3672:119"/>
confidence, that after we ſhall haue finiſhed this long voyage, we ſhall then abide with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And S. Peter ſayth, that the Spirit of our Lord, while his bodie was in the Tombe, <hi>preached vnto the ſpirits of them that were in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1, Pet, 3, 19,</note> which then aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs, that our ſoules are ſeparable ſpirits. In Saint Luke, the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is recited of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked rich man that was in hell torments, &amp; the poore begger,<note place="margin">Luke. 16, 19</note> whoſe ſpirit was in Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams boſome.</p>
               <p>In another place, GOD ſayth, <hi>that hee
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:3672:119"/>
is the God of Abraham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math, 22, 32</note> 
                  <hi>and the God of Iſaac, and the God of Iacob: and that he is not the God of the deade, but of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</hi> Let vs then end vvith this concluſion, that Abraham, Iſaac &amp; Iacob are liuing.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:3672:120"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:3672:120"/>
               <speaker>Socr.</speaker>
               <p>Tell me, which dooſt thou iudge to be workes of Fortune, or of reaſon and delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? as much to ſay, as thoſe workes that haue no certaine end, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are knowne wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be made? and what thinkeſt thou of ſuch, as manifeſtly doe appeare, that they are made for the benefite of men?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aristo.</speaker>
               <p>Doubtleſſe, thoſe which are made for the profit of men, are queſtionles workes made by reaſon &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Socr.</speaker>
               <p>Doth it not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appeare to thee, that
<pb facs="tcp:3672:121"/>
hee that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning made men, and gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſhoulde haue knowledge of euerie thing, did it not for their benefit? as eyes to behold thinges viſible: eares to heare ſoundes: &amp; ſo likewiſe of things that are apprehended by ſent, whereof no profit woulde bee had except we had noſtrils: nor knew wee howe to perceiue or diſtinguiſh which taſte is ſweet, &amp; vvhich is ſower or ſharpe, except we had a tongue and pallate to taſt them? Moreouer, dooth it not likewiſe
<pb facs="tcp:3672:121"/>
ſeeme to thee, to bee a worke of Gods high prouidence, to encloſe (within lidds) the weak and feeble eyes, which when need requires to ſee, doe open, &amp; cloſe againe when deſire of ſleepe vrgeth?</p>
               <p>And to the end no angry windes may bee offenſiue to them, hee hath placed the browes ouer the eyes, as alſo to defend them from the ſweat, deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding down the head, yet kept ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by out of the eyes. As in like maner the eares, that receiue all ſounds, and yet are neuer full: the teeth alſo in order
<pb facs="tcp:3672:122"/>
made and placed, that thoſe before do cut the meat, and thoſe behind chewe &amp; prepare it for the paſſage: ſo may we ſay of the mouth, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the foode hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoy to the ſtomack, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeated vnder the eyes and noſtrills: but the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duit of offenſiue ſuperfluities, is placed behinde, and far from the ſeueral ſeates of the ſences, leaſt it ſhoulde be any way hurtful vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</p>
               <p>Theſe things which thou diſcerneſt to bee made by ſo great a prouidence, whether dooſt thou attribute
<pb facs="tcp:3672:122"/>
them to Fortune, or to counſell and delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aristo.</speaker>
               <p>Aſſuredlie, theſe thinges ſeeme to mee, to bee the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of a moſt wiſe Creator.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Socr.</speaker>
               <p>And the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall great deſire vvee haue to beget a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of linage, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of mothers to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh their young chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, &amp; when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come great, a care for theyr liuing, and then the mightie feare they haue of theyr death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ari.</speaker>
               <p>In ſooth, al theſe thinges are the workes of him, who had a will,
<pb facs="tcp:3672:123"/>
that by counſel, reaſon, and deliberation, his creatures ſhoulde bee made liuing, hauing both ſence and moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Socra.</speaker>
               <p>Dooth it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to thee that thou haſt any diſcretion, whereby thou makeſt apprehenſion or iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe thinges?</p>
               <p>Thou haſt in thee a little portion of thys earth, which thou ſeeſt to be ſo great, &amp; a ſmall quantitie of humour, which is of ſo large a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance in the world: nowe, conſidering ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe thinges to be ſo great, &amp; yet thou
<pb facs="tcp:3672:123"/>
haſt of eyther ſome ſmal portion, and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether being ſo aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in thy body, as thou couldeſt haue no vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding at all, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they were in this ſort ordered: Theſe thinges (I ſay) being ſo great, and in multitude infinite, howe dooſt thou imagine, but that they ſhould be well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arist.</speaker>
               <p>I can no way perceiue their ordena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as I behold the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of other workme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s labours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Socr.</speaker>
               <p>Why euen ſo thou canſt no way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde thy ſoule, which
<pb facs="tcp:3672:124"/>
directs and gouerns (at her pleaſure,) all thy whole bodie: yea, and in ſuch ſort, as thou mighteſt elſe ſay, thou dooſt all thinges with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out counſell; reaſon, or deliberation, but that onely raiſeth regard of feare and trembling.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arist.</speaker>
               <p>I vvoulde be lothe to neglect the Gods, but doe holde and eſteeme them ſo great, as wee ſhoulde haue nothing els to do, but to be reuerent one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie toward them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Socra.</speaker>
               <p>The greater then thou eſteemeſt them to bee, the more thou oughteſt to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="tcp:3672:124"/>
them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arist.</speaker>
               <p>If I wiſt that they had any care of men, I woulde adore them, and neuer neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Socra.</speaker>
               <p>VVhy howe canſt thou thinke, but that they haue care and regarde of vs, ſeeing man is made onely (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue and beyond al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures) to goe vpright? to fore-ſee many thinges intended to him, and to gouerne all other creatures vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him? hauing eyes, eares, and a mouth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon him?</p>
               <p>And though to ſome he haue giuen but feet,
<pb facs="tcp:3672:125"/>
as to Serpents: yet to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hands, to garde himſelfe from many outrages, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are more happy then other creatures.</p>
               <p>And albeit other beaſtes haue tongues, yet to man onely it is giuen, to turne his tongue from one ſide of his mouth to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thereby to forme an intelligible voyce, to diſpoſe and make known his thoughts to others.</p>
               <p>Now not onely is this care taken of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but much more of our inward ſpirits. For where or when did any
<pb facs="tcp:3672:125"/>
other creature euer thinke or conſider, that God was the Creator of the very beſt and greateſt thinges? Or what kinde elſe, (one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man excepted) dyd euer, or can giue honor to God? or keep him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from cold, heate, famine, thirſt, &amp; other inconueniences? Or ſhun diuerſitie of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes? Or by exerciſe gather ſtrength, ability, and learning? or retain longer and more faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully what-ſoeuer is to be vnderſtood?</p>
               <p>Seemes it not then to thee, that man onely is (as a God) amongſt all
<pb facs="tcp:3672:126"/>
other creatures? more excellent, and out-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them both in body and minde?</p>
               <p>Vndoubtedly, if man had had the body of an Oxe, hee coulde not haue doone what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he would<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; ſuch as haue hands (without any other part of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpirit) haue ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to bee reckoned of much more, then they that haue no hands at all.</p>
               <p>But thou that haſt handes and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, canſt thou think that God hath not care and reſpect of thee? Dooſt thou not think,
<pb facs="tcp:3672:126"/>
that the moſt auncient and wiſeſt Citties, are thoſe that moſt dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently &amp; carefully doe honour the Gods?</p>
               <p>Learne, learne my friend, that thy ſoule gouerns thy body: like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that the good ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which containeth all thinges, directeth all thinges at his good pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Thinkeſt thou that thine owne eye can ſee many thinges farre off, &amp; that Gods eye doth not diſcerne them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together? Or that thy minde may conceite at one inſtant, what is doone in Athens, Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilie,
<pb facs="tcp:3672:127"/>
Egypt, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and the Diuine Spirit or minde, dooth not know all things di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly together? Yes, hold and beleeue it for moſt certaine: that God ſees, heares, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards, and hath care of thee, me, &amp; all thinges elſe whatſoeuer toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:3672:127"/>
            <head>A Directorie, for the Readers more eaſie and ſpeedie apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, of the ſpeciall matters handled in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>WHat benefit a man gaines by the knowledge of himſelfe. page, 2.</item>
               <item>What the Soule is. page 3,</item>
               <item>Of the vertues and powers in the ſoule. page 4,</item>
               <item>Of nouriſhment, and the manner of the bodies nouriſhment. page 5, 6.</item>
               <item>Of Choller, Mellancholie, &amp; phlegme. page<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8,</item>
               <item>Of the blood, and how it is receiued, page 9,</item>
               <item>Of three kindes of digeſtion, to perfect nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment. page, 11,</item>
               <item>That the inconvenience of the firſt digeſtion, is not holpen by the other. page 14,</item>
               <item>Some mens oppinion concerning the Soule. 16</item>
               <item>The hurt of intemperancie. page 17,</item>
               <item>Sixe things not naturally in vs. page 18,</item>
               <item>The benefit of labour to the body. page 19</item>
               <item>The hurt of immoderat exerciſe to the body. 21</item>
               <item>Of ſleepe, how it benefits the body, and helpes the powers of the ſoule. page, 22, 24,</item>
               <item>How heat &amp; blood do work for the hart. 24.</item>
               <item>Of dreames in ſleepe, their kindes, cauſes &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples. page 31, 32, 33, 34, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Of the increaſe of nouriſhment, &amp; when nature receiueth moſt ſubſtaunce to her ſelfe. 38, 39</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3672:128"/>How naturall heat groweth or decaieth in vs, 41<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </item>
               <item>Of death naturall, and vnnaturall. page 43</item>
               <item>Of generation, &amp; how the fruite is formed, 44,</item>
               <item>Of the offices, veines, and arteries of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane. page 46, 47,</item>
               <item>How the nauill is made, and in what time. 48,</item>
               <item>Of the places for the liuer, hart and braine, 50</item>
               <item>How the liuer is formed, and what it is. 50</item>
               <item>How the bowels are faſtened to the back, 51</item>
               <item>How Diaphragma is formed. page 52</item>
               <item>Of the back bones, and forming of the hart, 53</item>
               <item>Of the harts nouriſhment. page 54</item>
               <item>That the hart is the beginner of vitall heat, 55</item>
               <item>How the lungs and lites are formed, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the bodies height. page 57</item>
               <item>Of the forming of the braine, and skull of the head. page 57, 58,</item>
               <item>Of the marrow in the chine bone of the backe, page 60</item>
               <item>How the fruite is nouriſhed in the wombe, and the bloods deuiſion into 3. parts. 60, 61, 62,</item>
               <item>How the power Vegetatiue nouriſheth the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and maintaineth kind. page 64</item>
               <item>Howe the order of the ſeuerall powers ſupplie theyr offices, page 68</item>
               <item>Of the ſenſitiue power, beeing the ſoules ſecond power. page, 71</item>
               <item>Of the fiue exteriour ſences, and firſt how ſight is wrought in vs. page, 72</item>
               <item>Of the inwarde organes of ſight, and what vſe
<pb facs="tcp:3672:128"/>
they ſerue vs to. page 74</item>
               <item>How ſight hath his ſeate, and what ſpirits giue life to the eye. page, 77</item>
               <item>The maner how colours are truly diſcerned, 80,</item>
               <item>The true capacitie of the eye in ſight, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of that ſence. page 81,</item>
               <item>Of hearing and his organe, page 82</item>
               <item>What ſound or noyſe is, &amp; of the meanes of apprehending it, page 83, 84</item>
               <item>How our ſpeech or voyce is formed. 86</item>
               <item>Of ſmelling, &amp; by what organe it is apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. page 89</item>
               <item>What odour, ſent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or ſmell is, 90,</item>
               <item>Of taſting, and his organe, &amp; howe the tongue taſtes with his meanes, vſe and obiect. 94, 95</item>
               <item>Of the ſeuerall kindes of ſauour; what ſauours beſt pleaſe the taſte: what moſt vrgeth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite: and of thinges without ſauour. page 96, 97, 98, 99, &amp;c</item>
               <item>Of Touching &amp; his organe, &amp; benefit. 107, 108</item>
               <item>Of the inwarde ſence, his ſeate, and neceſſarie vſe. page 108, 109</item>
               <item>Of the fiue inwarde ſences, their organes what they are, &amp; how they help each other, 110, &amp;c</item>
               <item>Of the braine in his diuerſity of kindes. 118</item>
               <item>Of two kindes of appetence in the ſences. 119</item>
               <item>Of the foure principall affections, and theyr op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites: both helping and hurting. 122. &amp;c</item>
               <item>The organe of the appetente power, and what it is. page 133</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3672:129"/>Of the commaundements in both the Tables. page, 136, 137, 138, &amp;c</item>
               <item>Of the contrarietie &amp; difference amongſt men. page 41,</item>
               <item>Of two kindes of gouernment: compulſion &amp; obedience. page 143, 144,</item>
               <item>That the will is the commaunder of the affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. page 146</item>
               <item>The reaſon of lawes, deuiſion of poſſeſsions, &amp; iuſtice in our dealings. 149, 150, 151</item>
               <item>How the lawe agrees with nature, and in vvhat manner. page 153, 154</item>
               <item>Of two kindes of moouing in the hart: and the efficient cauſes thereof, 155, 156, 157</item>
               <item>Of the powers of nature, anſwerable to the harts affections, and their difference. page 158,</item>
               <item>Of the hart, with his helps and hurts. 159, 160.</item>
               <item>Of the ſoules ſocietie with the body, aunſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the humours. page, 162,</item>
               <item>Of the proper cauſes of our affections, &amp; whence they take originall. page 163</item>
               <item>That natures corruption is the cauſe of our euill affections. page, 167</item>
               <item>Of the diuine affections in our Sauiour, page, 168, 169, 170,</item>
               <item>The contrarietie of affections in Chriſtians and Infidels. page 170, 171</item>
               <item>Of Concupiſcence, and how it may bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. page 173, 174, 175.</item>
               <item>Of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary mouings of the hart &amp; wil. 176.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3672:129"/>Howe to come to the true knowledge of our ſelues. page 178.</item>
               <item>Of the motiue power, carrying the bodie from place to place. page, 180</item>
               <item>That the ſoule is the cauſe of the bodies moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. eodem</item>
               <item>Two kinds of moouing, and the power of ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them. eodem</item>
               <item>Of a commixed power, partly naturall, &amp; partly voluntary. page 181</item>
               <item>Of the intellectuall power. page 182</item>
               <item>Howe action becoms appropriate to intellecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and differs from the power ſenſitiue. 183</item>
               <item>Of the obiect of intellection: his offices &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganes. page 184</item>
               <item>Of the two vnderſtandings, actiue and paſsiue. page 186</item>
               <item>The action and habitude, guide the vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. page 187</item>
               <item>Of the ſpeculatiue &amp; practiue knowledge. 188</item>
               <item>Of Reaſon, &amp; the wills coniunction therewith. page eodem,</item>
               <item>Of the wills definition. eodem.</item>
               <item>Of the hurt of natures lacke of her primatiue condition. page 189</item>
               <item>Of the impediment and hinderances in our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. 190.</item>
               <item>How Gods image becommeth deformed in vs, and what we ought to deſire of him in repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of our wants &amp; defects<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 190, 191, 192,</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3672:130"/>Of the ſoules immortalitie, and naturall reaſons therefore alleaged. page 193, 194</item>
               <item>That the ſoule conſiſteth no way of the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. page 195</item>
               <item>What nature can doe, notwithſtanding her cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. page, 196</item>
               <item>Of mens careleſſe regard of their ſoules immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie. page 198,</item>
               <item>How God inſtructed the ſoules immortality fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worlds beginning. page 199</item>
               <item>That our ſoules are ſpirits, not to be ouer-come by death. page 203.</item>
               <item>That the ſoule is to liue with Chriſt after death. page 204</item>
               <item>Of Paradiſe, and what it ſignifieth. page 205</item>
               <item>Of the good Theefes ſermon on the Croſſe. page, eodem</item>
               <item>One part of the worlde refuſed the benefite of Chriſtes death. page 206,</item>
               <item>The condemnation of the wicked, &amp; aſſurance of the elects ſaluation. page 207,</item>
               <item>That the good theefe preached Gods glorie, when the whole Church was ſilent, and the Apoſtles ſtood dumbe. 209</item>
               <item>That the ſoule is a liuing ſpirit after the bodies death, and no way conſiſteth of the bodyes temper. page 212.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3672:130" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
